<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Tutu-Harvard     02-04 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tutu-Harvard,0437</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop Desmond Tutu Appeals To Harvard to Divest</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-South Africa</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON> urged fellow
members of a <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION> governing board <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to back
divestment in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> until changes promised by that country's
president become reality.
   In a news conference following a closed-door meeting of the
<ORGANIZATION>Board of Overseers</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said that much of what <ORGANIZATION>South African
President F.W. de Klerk</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>last week</DATE> was a declaration of purpose.
   ``Sanctions should remain in place until certain conditions are
met,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said.
   In last week's speech, de Klerk promised to free jailed <ORGANIZATION>African
30 outlawed opposition groups.
   Tutu, who won the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel Peace Prize for his anti-apartheid
efforts, welcomed the announcement but tempered his response with
pragmatism.
   ``We'd like to see these things immediately but let's be
realistic. The parliamentary session has just begun,'' the Anglican
archbishop said.
   Tutu said he had asked colleagues on the 30-member <ORGANIZATION>Board of
Overseers</ORGANIZATION> to press <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> to withdraw <MONEY>$139 million</MONEY> in investments
in South African companies until <ORGANIZATION>Mandela</ORGANIZATION> is freed, all exiled
political activists are granted amnesty and the government's policy
of segregation is dismantled.
   The board planned to further consider the divestment issue at a
future meeting.
   The board is less powerful than the university's main governing
body, the <ORGANIZATION>Harvard Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, but is the only alumni-elected panel with
an influence on school policy. The board plays no role in
day-to-day business, but must give formal consent to major
initiaitves and appointments.
   Tutu, who ran for the board on an anti-apartheid slate, was
elected last <DATE>June</DATE> along with <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Labor Secretary <PERSON>Elizabeth Dole</PERSON>
and actor <PERSON>John Lithgow</PERSON>.
   The archbishop said de Klerk's action last week was sparked by
the growing number of countries that had placed sanctions on <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>, a position <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said seemed to be catching on among fellow
board members.
   He said he was encouraged by the attention <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> had
received in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> amid the historic changes in the
Soviet bloc.
   ``The kind of coverage and response is indicative that, in spite
of what has happened in <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION>, which pushed our case to
the back burner, people here do want to see our situation
resolved,'' he said.
   Asked why he was in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> rather than <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> at
such a critical time, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> replied, ``Harvard is Harvard. The
things that <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> does and does not do have an impact far beyond
what you would expect from an educational institution.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900203-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-03-90 1645EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SouthAfrica-Tutu     02-03 0620</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa-Tutu,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anglican Archbishop Desmond Tutu Makes Surprise Visit to Boston</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLISON J. PUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jubilation over the pending release of <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>'s imprisoned black leader <PERSON>Nelson Mandela</PERSON> must be tempered
with the realization that apartheid is far from ended, <ORGANIZATION>Archbishop
Desmond Tutu</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Tutu, visiting to confer with other opposition leaders and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
officials, said the fight for equality is not over and urged
continued political and economic pressure on the South African
government to dismantle apartheid.
   ``We have not yet the complete dismantling of apartheid and this
is the pinpoint of the sanction program. We want apartheid totally
dismantled,'' said <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON>, the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel Peace Prize laureate.
   The Anglican archbishop said his initial joy over the lifting of
some political restrictions against blacks <DATE>Friday</DATE> was tempered
later by the realization that apartheid still is far from over.
   He said his change of heart came after ``having pinched myself
and convinced myself it wasn't a dream and it was real. ... Of
course you see apartheid is still in place.''
   Tutu said he is looking forward to relinquishing his position as
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s pre-eminent opponent of apartheid now that <ORGANIZATION>Mandela</ORGANIZATION>
is to be released from prison.
   ``I said long ago I was just an interim leader until he
(<ORGANIZATION>Mandela</ORGANIZATION>) comes out,'' he said. ``He's been making us work too
hard.''
   Tutu was accompanied by <PERSON>Patrick Lekota</PERSON>, publicity secretary for
the <ORGANIZATION>United Democratic Front</ORGANIZATION>. They were met at <LOCATION>Logan International
Airport</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Themba Vilakazi</PERSON>, head of the Boston-based Fund for a
Free <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, just returned from <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION> where the <ORGANIZATION>African
National Congress</ORGANIZATION> is based.
   The group was met by <PERSON>Zenani Mandela Dlamini</PERSON>, 30, eldest daughter
of <ORGANIZATION>Nelson</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Winnie Mandela</PERSON> and a political science student at
<ORGANIZATION>Boston University</ORGANIZATION>.
   Their arrival came less than 24 hours after <ORGANIZATION>South African
President F.W. de Klerk</ORGANIZATION> announced in a speech to Parliament that
<ORGANIZATION>Mandela</ORGANIZATION> would be released unconditionally, although he set no date.
   De Klerk also lifted bans on more than 30 opposition groups
after three decades of underground activity against white rule,
including the <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION>, outlawed in <DATE>1960</DATE>.
   The announcements appeared to clear the way for talks on a new
constitution that would end the black majority's exclusion from
national politics.
   Tutu, a member of <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University's Board of Overseers</ORGANIZATION>, was
here to attend a meeting at the school. <PERSON>Lekota</PERSON> said he planned to
attend a meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>Albert Einstein Institute</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>
think tank that advocates the use of non-violent sanctions to solve
political unrest.
   Mandela's daughter, greeted fondly by <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION>, told reporters she
was skeptical of the recent changes in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, despite the
news her father would be released.
   ``This has been going on for 300 years,'' she said. ``What
happened <DATE>Friday</DATE>, I'm not overly excited about it. Release some
political prisoners, to me, that's nothing. We want total majority
voting in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. Until that happens, I will not be
satisfied.''
   Her husband, <PERSON>Thumbumuzi Dlamini</PERSON>, 39, is a prince from <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION>,
one of the sons of the late king Sobhuza II. His brother is now the
king of <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION>, an independent country almost completely
surrounded by <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. They live in the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> area with their
three children.
   <PERSON>Lekota</PERSON>, who was recently released from prison, was more positive
about the changes. He predicted members of the white minority in
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> who resist change will eventually be forced to accept
the idea of equality with blacks.
   ``They cannot stop us,' he said. ``We are unstoppable now.''
   <PERSON>Lekota</PERSON> said he also planned to meet with <PERSON>Sen. Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> officials to give the South African
black perspective on the recent turn of events.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900205-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-05-90 0800EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Tutu-Harvard     02-05 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tutu-Harvard,0301</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu: Havard Should Divest Until South African Changes Are Made</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON>, who is a member
of <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION>'s governing board, urged the school to
withdraw its money from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> until promised changes are
made there.
   Tutu told reporters <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that he had asked the 30-member <ORGANIZATION>Board
of Overseers</ORGANIZATION> to sell off <MONEY>$139 million</MONEY> in investments in companies
that do business in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. The money could be reinvested
once it becomes clear that reforms promised by President <ORGANIZATION>F.W. de
Klerk</ORGANIZATION> will take place, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Board of Overseers</ORGANIZATION>, to which the Anglican archbishop was
elected last <DATE>June</DATE>, had met earlier in the day in a closed session.
The board planned to further consider the divestment issue at a
later meeting.
   Last week, <ORGANIZATION>de Klerk</ORGANIZATION> said he would release jailed <ORGANIZATION>African
30 outlawed opposition groups.
   Tutu, who won the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel Peace Prize for his anti-apartheid
efforts, praised de Klerk for his announcement, but said actual
advancements would be decided by the <ORGANIZATION>South African Parliament</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We'd like to see these things immediately, but let's be
realistic. The parliamentary session has just begun,'' he said.
``If (de Klerk) is playing games, they would be very odd games and
the world would know how to act.''
   When asked why he was in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> rather than in <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION> at such a critical time, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said, ``Harvard is Harvard.
The things that <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> does and does not do have an impact far
beyond what you would expect from an educational institution.''
   Tutu ran for the <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> board on an anti-apartheid slate and
was elected last <DATE>June</DATE>, along with <ORGANIZATION>Labor</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Elizabeth Dole</PERSON>
and actor <PERSON>John Lithgow</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890608-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-08-89 2118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Harvard-Tutu 1stLd-Writethru a0678 06-08 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Harvard-Tutu, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0678,0457</SECOND>
<HEAD>Desmond Tutu Wins Seat on Harvard Governing Board</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 7th graf, `Actor John...,' with one graf to CORRECT that
Elizabeth Dole's title to Labor Secretary.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE DREYFOUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON> won a seat
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> on a <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION> governing board, striking a blow
for forces opposed to the school's <MONEY>$163.8 million</MONEY> investment in
   ``I ... pray God I will do justice to the honor that has been
given me,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said, speaking from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   The <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel Prize-winner, who promised a year ago to return
honorary degrees to any schools that had not divested such holdings
by <DATE>May 1989</DATE>, said he would not return the diploma <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> conferred
on him 10 years ago.
   Instead, the South African Anglican prelate will use his new spot
on the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Overseers</ORGANIZATION> to lobby against apartheid and for
divestment, said Tutu spokesman <PERSON>John Allen</PERSON>.
   ``This is really big news,'' said <PERSON>Robert Wolff</PERSON>, director of
<ORGANIZATION>Harvard-Radcliffe Alumni Against Apartheid</ORGANIZATION>. ``I feel very confident
that once (Tutu) arrives there will be enormous pressure on <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>
to divest.''
   Tutu's victory was the only one claimed by the pro-divestment
coalition, which ran four other candidates against an official slate
of 10 people backed by the <ORGANIZATION>Harvard Alumni Association</ORGANIZATION>.
   Actor <PERSON>John Lithgow</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Labor</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Elizabeth Dole</PERSON>, both
endorsed by the alumni assocation, were the top vote-getters in the
write-in election open to all <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> degree holders.
   Tutu came in fourth with 14,226 of the votes cast by 39,897
people, who elected five officials to serve six-year terms on the
30-member board. The panel monitors the university's academic
policies and advises the <ORGANIZATION>Harvard Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, which manages the
school's business affairs.
   Since <DATE>1986</DATE>, the Harvard-Radcliffe anti-apartheid group has
nominated candidates to the 30-member overseers panel by petition
and has succeeded in placing three members on the board.
   The campaign was more heated than any in recent years, with the
alumni association and university officials speaking out against
electing ``single issue'' candidates.
Massachusetts</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Amherst</LOCATION>, said he was optimistic Tutu's presence on
the panel would encourage other ``progressive'' board members to
join the push for divestment in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   ``There are a large number of progressive board members who would
feel comfortable rallying to Tutu's standard,'' <PERSON>Wolff</PERSON> said. ``In his
presence he will be the moral center of the board on this issue.''
   <PERSON>Wolff</PERSON> said it was not immediately clear when Tutu would come to
<LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> to meet with the board, but predicted that ``when he
comes, thousands of people will turn out support him.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 0121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TutuVisit     12-09 0239</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tutu Visit,0257</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop Tutu Urges Iraq, U.S. to Talk, Not Fight</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEN IWANSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION> should avert war
in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> by talking out their differences, <ORGANIZATION>South African
Archbishop Desmond Tutu</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   ``People must make it more and more clear that we are
peacemongers, because peace is so sensible. It's so much more
sensible than war,'' said the Anglican prelate, who won the <DATE>1984</DATE>
Nobel Peace Prize for his opposition to South African apartheid.
   At a news conference, <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION> also urged the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to
continue its economic sanctions against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> ``until the
process of dismantling apartheid is irreversible.''
   Apartheid is <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s official police of racial
segregation and discrimination against non-whites.
   Although <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s President F.W. de Klerk deserves credit
for some reform, ``the pillars of apartheid still stand firmly in
place,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said.
   Tutu came to this ity of 24,000 people to help raise
scholarship money for South African students abroad and for
American Indian students in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
   Tutu heads the 2.6 million-member <ORGANIZATION>Anglican Church of Southern
Africa</ORGANIZATION>. This was his only scheduled stop in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> while en
route to a convocation in <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>.
   The visit was arranged by the <LOCATION>Montana Logging</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ballet
Company</ORGANIZATION>, a Helena-based quartet that mixes music, comedy and satire
to promote political and social causes.
   Tutu wrote liner notes for the group's latest album after
hearing it perform an anti-apartheid song, ``Take the Barriers
Down,'' in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051990-0137 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 221601 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 19, 1990, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
817 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TUTU TO VISIT DISNEYLAND TODAY AT CHILD'S URGING 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LANIE JONES and TONY MARCANO, TIMES STAFF WRITERS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ANAHEIM 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Acting on a grandchild's request, <ORGANIZATION>Anglican Archbishop Desmond Tutu</ORGANIZATION> will be 
making an unscheduled stop today at <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION>, where he and his party of 17 
plan to tour the world-famous amusement park. 
</P>
<P>
The South African cleric, a <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION> winner and leader of the struggle 
against apartheid, had planned a weeklong series of speeches and sermons in 
<LOCATION>Orange</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> counties. But on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> an aide told <ORGANIZATION>Disneyland</ORGANIZATION> 
officials that Tutu's party -- and especially his 3-year-old grandson, Xabiso 
Tutu -- wanted to visit the park. 
</P>
<P>
The aide did not specify what attractions the little boy wanted to see, but, 
according to <ORGANIZATION>Disneyland</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Bob Roth</PERSON>, the aide did make one request: "The 
Rev. <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> wants the little boy to have the time of his life." 
</P>
<P>
Tutu, <LOCATION>Xabiso</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON>'s wife, <PERSON>Leah</PERSON>, daughters <PERSON>Mpho Tutu</PERSON>, <PERSON>Thandi Tutu</PERSON> and <PERSON>Naomi 
Tutu</PERSON> as well as family friends and <ORGANIZATION>Episcopal Church</ORGANIZATION> officials are expected to 
arrive at the park's main gate at <TIME>12:30 p.m</TIME>. They will sign the <ORGANIZATION>VIP</ORGANIZATION> guest book, 
meet <PERSON>Mickey Mouse</PERSON> and spend part of the day touring Fantasyland, which offers a 
carousel as well as attractions based on fairy-tales. 
</P>
<P>
At <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION>'s request, most of the nearly six-hour visit will be private -- away 
from reporters and photographers, <PERSON>Roth</PERSON> said, so the archbishop and his 
17-member entourage "can be like everyone else when they're in the park." 
</P>
<P>
Well, not quite like everyone else, he conceded. As guests of <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION>, 
<PERSON>Bishop Tutu</PERSON> and his party will not have to pay the admission of <MONEY>$25.50</MONEY> for 
adults, <MONEY>$20.50</MONEY> for children ages 3 to 11. Also, the Tutu group will be treated 
to lunch and probably escorted to the front of all lines. 
</P>
<P>
Also arriving at the park <TIME>this morning</TIME> will be another dignitary -- <PERSON>Zhu 
Quizhen</PERSON>, the Chinese ambassador to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, and his wife. An official 
of the <ORGANIZATION>People's Republic of China Consulate</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> said the couple, who 
live in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, would spend the entire day at <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION>. They also will 
get <ORGANIZATION>VIP</ORGANIZATION> treatment -- a free and very private tour, <PERSON>Roth</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Tutu is making his first visit to <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> with his trip to <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION>, 
but he plans to return here <DATE>Monday</DATE> at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> when he speaks at <ORGANIZATION>Santa Ana 
High School</ORGANIZATION>. That visit is being hosted by the <ORGANIZATION>Episcopal Church of the Messiah</ORGANIZATION> 
in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
He is also scheduled to deliver two sermons in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> and will 
appear at <LOCATION>Cal State Long Beach</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> before his arrival in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>. Tutu 
also has appearances scheduled at <ORGANIZATION>Caltech</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> and at <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Tutu, who was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in <DATE>1984</DATE> for his anti-apartheid 
efforts, is expected to discuss the recent dramatic turn of events in <LOCATION>South 
Africa</LOCATION>, including the release of <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> leader <PERSON>Nelson 
Mandela</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Tutu and Zhu are the latest in a long line of luminaries who have visited 
<ORGANIZATION>Disneyland</ORGANIZATION> in the past 30 years. Park records show there have been cosmonauts 
and astronauts, princesses and prime ministers, presidents and would-be 
presidents -- not to mention a couple of kings. 
</P>
<P>
Almost every famous visitor has taken in the Matterhorn roller coaster and 
several other rides, he said. But there have been exceptions. 
</P>
<P>
"When (Japanese) <PERSON>Emperor Hirohito</PERSON> was here in <DATE>October, 1975</DATE>, for a very brief 
time, he spent the majority of his time watching our bicentennial parade," <PERSON>Roth</PERSON> 
said. <PERSON>Roth</PERSON> noted that a child of about 7 or 8 got into the <ORGANIZATION>VIP</ORGANIZATION> seating area and 
climbed into the Emperor's lap, and <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> "treated him as if he were his own 
child," letting him stay through the rest of the parade. 
</P>
<P>
Each time a celebrity comes to <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION>, "I think we're honored," <PERSON>Roth</PERSON> said. 
"It's a feather in our cap. It says what this place is all about . . . that 
people want to see a real piece of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
When Tutu returns to <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the program at <ORGANIZATION>Santa Ana High 
School</ORGANIZATION> will also include an appearance by the <PERSON>Saint Joseph</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ballet Company</ORGANIZATION>, 
accompanied by the <ORGANIZATION>Biola University Gospel Choir</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Parishioners from the program's organizer, the <ORGANIZATION>Episcopal Church</ORGANIZATION> of the Messiah, 
were granted the first opportunity to buy tickets for the speech. They and 
other local leaders and residents snapped up the 1,500 available tickets within 
10 days and are "very excited" about the visit, said <PERSON>Leonora Will</PERSON>, an organizer 
of the event. 
</P>
<P>
"The Anglican Church in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> has played an important role in the 
struggle," Will said. "We're very proud and excited that he's coming." 
</P>
<P>
While Tutu's <DATE>Monday</DATE> visit to <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> is expected to be peaceful, Will 
noted that "there are security concerns wherever the archbishop goes because he 
and his family have received death threats in the past." She added that 
organizers of the visit have taken security measures that are required by the 
county and that <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> police will be on hand, but no unusual security 
arrangements are planned. 
</P>
<P>
At <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Roth</PERSON> declined to comment on the park's security plans for today. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Archbishop Desmond Tutu is on Southland speaking circuit. JOE KENNEDY / 
Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
DISNEYLAND; TUTU, DESMOND; CLERGY; APARTHEID; RACIAL RELATIONS -- SOUTH AFRICA; 
TOURISM -- ORANGE COUNTY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880517-0215 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-17-88 2204EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfricaTutu     05-17 0376</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica Tutu,0388</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Broadcast Attacks Tutu's Pro-Sanctions Stance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government-run
broadcasting network assailed the pro-sanctions position of
<ORGANIZATION>Archbishop Desmond Tutu</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and challenged the Anglican
Church to say if it supports or rejects Tutu's stance.
   Tutu, the first black to head the Anglican Church in <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>, was completing a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> tour where he appealed for additional
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> economic sanctions to protest <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s apartheid
policies.
   ``Archbishop Tutu has never been voted into a public office that
gives him the right to claim a significant constituency,'' the
<ORGANIZATION>South African Broadcasting Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said in a commentary.
   The statement failed to note that Tutu, like all of the nation's
26 million blacks, is ineligible to vote or be elected to national
political office.
   The <ORGANIZATION>SABC</ORGANIZATION> also said, without elaborating, that the Anglican
Church ``is deeply divided as a result of his (Tutu's) political
utterances.''
   ``What is the church's stand on the widely held view that
sanctions will bring deprivation and hardship in increasing numbers
to black South Africans?'' the <ORGANIZATION>SABC</ORGANIZATION> asked.
   ``The church owes it not only to parishoners but to all <LOCATION>South
Africans</LOCATION> to state unequivocally where the church stands on
sanctions, disinvestments, and their consequences.''
despite repeated telephone calls to their offices.
   The government has attacked Tutu in harsh tones on a number of
issues. In <DATE>March</DATE>, President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON> sent a letter to <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION> and
other church leaders saying they ``love and embrace'' the outlawed
<ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> guerrilla group.
   ``You embrace and participate in their call for violence,
hatred, sanctions, insurrection and revolution,'' <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> said.
   Tutu, winner of the <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION>, has continued to
call for sanctions and other forms of international pressure as the
most likely ways to bring about race reform in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Congress</ORGANIZATION> imposed limited sanctions against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>
in <DATE>1986</DATE>, banning the import of selected goods and stopping direct
air links between the two countries. <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> now is considering
much tougher legislation that would ban almost all bilateral
economic activity.
   Under apartheid, a racially segregated society is established by
law and custom, with the 5 million whites controlling the economy
and maintaining separate districts, schools and health services.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880320-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-20-88 1347EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Bishops     03-20 0264</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Bishops,0269</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release 6 p.m. EST, Time set by source</NOTE>
<HEAD>Bishops To Meet About Government Threat Against Tutu</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Anglican bishops from
throughout southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> plan an emergency meeting this week to
discuss the threat of government action against <ORGANIZATION>Archbishop Desmond
Tutu</ORGANIZATION>, the church said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Tutu, the first black to lead the Anglican Church in <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>, has been engaged in increasingly bitter confrontations with
the white-led government since <DATE>last month</DATE>, when it banned political
activity by leading black anti-apartheid groups.
   Tutu, winner of the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel Peace Prize for his fight against
apartheid, was briefly detained three weeks ago when he and other
church leaders tried to march to Parliament with a petition
protesting the crackdown on opposition activity.
   He and other clergymen, including the Rev. <PERSON>Allan Boesak</PERSON>,
subsequently vowed to continue challenging the government. Boesak
is president of the <ORGANIZATION>World Alliance of Reformed Churches</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s Anglican bishops, in a statement <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, said the
government has ``launched a carefully planned attack'' on Tutu and
<PERSON>Boesak</PERSON> ``aimed at portraying them as Marxists and isolating them
from their churches as a prelude to state action against them.''
   President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON> met with Tutu last week and suggested that
the archbishop had aligned himself with the outlawed <ORGANIZATION>African
National Congress</ORGANIZATION> guerrilla movement.
   The bishops' meeting on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> is to take place at <LOCATION>Jan Smuts
Airport</LOCATION> outside <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>. The Right Rev. <PERSON>Keith Sutton</PERSON>, a bishop
from <LOCATION>Litchfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, is to join African bishops at the meeting
as the representative of the <ORGANIZATION>Archbishop of Canterbury</ORGANIZATION>, the Right
Rev. <PERSON>Robert Runcie</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA052090-0218 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 221872 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 20, 1990, Sunday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
924 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BISHOP TUTU MEETS DISNEYLAND, AND THRILL IS MUTUAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LYNN SMITH and TAMMERLIN DRUMMOND, TIMES STAFF WRITERS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ANAHEIM 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When the "the happiest place on earth" greeted the world's jolliest cleric 
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the result was mutual glee. 
</P>
<P>
Anglican Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON>, the moral leader of the anti-apartheid 
movement in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, thrilled <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION> visitors who recognized him as he 
smiled and chuckled his way through the park, hugging <PERSON>Mickey Mouse</PERSON>, riding a 
carousel with his grandson and dancing in a conga line. 
</P>
<P>
His visit resulted partly from a promise to his grandson, <PERSON>Xabiso Tutu</PERSON>, 3, who 
is learning English while living in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, where his mother is studying 
medicine. Wearing the traditional black-eared hat with his name sewn on, Xabiso 
solemnly and politely shook hands with <PERSON>Mickey Mouse</PERSON>. But <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said he was 
actually "using the child as an excuse." 
</P>
<P>
"I've always wanted to come. Now I can say I have been," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Tutu's wife, <PERSON>Leah</PERSON>, who had toured the park once before, said she thought Tutu 
would enjoy the park as much as his grandson, especially the faster rides. 
</P>
<P>
Xabiso sucked his thumb while Tutu held a brief press interview in Fantasyland 
under the watchful gaze of security guards in suits and ties. 
</P>
<P>
"It's great fun being here," said the diminutive cleric who won the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel 
Peace Prize for his nonviolent opposition to apartheid and white rule in <LOCATION>South 
Africa</LOCATION>. "We're all children at heart." 
</P>
<P>
If more people could recapture the childlike innocence represented by 
<LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION>, he said in his lilting accent, "We wouldn't have all these problems 
in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and everywhere else. People would know we're all part of the 
same family." 
</P>
<P>
Upon his arrival, Tutu was greeted by Rep. <PERSON>Robert K. Dornan</PERSON>, who described 
himself as "<PERSON>Mickey Mouse</PERSON>'s congressman." Dornan (R-Garden Grove) said he had 
voted for economic sanctions against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, despite his Republican 
conservatism. He told <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION> that he had cried during one of the archbishop's 
speeches, in which <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION> said he would resign if bloodshed in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> did 
not stop. 
</P>
<P>
Tutu, 58, wearing his characteristic dark glasses, a Greek fisherman's cap, 
Reeboks and an <ORGANIZATION>Occidental College</ORGANIZATION> sweat shirt, posed happily for publicity 
photographs and rode down Main Street USA in a fire truck before joining his 
grandson on the carousel. 
</P>
<P>
Next, they watched the Party Gras parade with 50-foot balloon characters. At 
the end of the parade, a line of conga dancers approached Tutu, his wife and 
grandson and drew them into a serpentine dance around a circle in front of 
Sleeping Beauty's castle. Smiling broadly, Tutu appeared to enjoy the dance. 
</P>
<P>
Tutu was taking a break from a 10-day preaching tour in the <ORGANIZATION>Southland</ORGANIZATION>, where he 
is also raising funds for South African refugees. He spoke earlier this week at 
<ORGANIZATION>Occidental College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Tutu is scheduled to speak at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Santa Ana High School</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Park officials said they were advised that Tutu likes rum and <ORGANIZATION>Coke</ORGANIZATION>, favors 
raisin ice cream and dislikes salads. But as they have with other VIPS, they 
provided the entourage a special tour guide, lunch at the <ORGANIZATION>Blue Bayou</ORGANIZATION> restaurant 
-- which serves no alcohol -- and cuts to the front of the lines. 
</P>
<P>
"It didn't seem proper to have him wait," said <PERSON>Mary Anne Mang</PERSON>, public relations 
manager. 
</P>
<P>
Park-goers who recognized Tutu most often used the word "wonderful" to describe 
their feelings toward him. 
</P>
<P>
"I've got to shake his hand!" said <ORGANIZATION>Paula Monarz of North Hollywood</ORGANIZATION>. "People get 
excited about movie stars, but here's someone who's made a difference." 
</P>
<P>
"There he is! Desmond Tutu!" shouted a middle-aged man in a red coat, who 
raised his hand in a fist. "Free South Africa!" 
</P>
<P>
"I'm a fan!" said <PERSON>Richard Mathews</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, who videotaped his 
14-year-old son with the world-famous leader. "We've got historic film here!" 
he said, shaking his camera. 
</P>
<P>
But some had no idea who the cleric was. A clerk at the tobacco shop, asked 
about Tutu, replied: "Is that a kind of cigarette? We don't carry it." 
</P>
<P>
At one point, a toddler ran toward Tutu and the accompanying Disneyland 
characters, but he was more interested in the world-famous mouse and yelled 
"Mickey!" 
</P>
<P>
"I'm peeved," the archbishop joked about the youngster's slight. 
</P>
<P>
"But I shouldn't be," he said. "Mickey's older." 
</P>
<P>
The day ended for Tutu and his entourage at <TIME>7:45 p.m</TIME>. They were all given 
<ORGANIZATION>Mickey Mouse</ORGANIZATION> hats as they left the <ORGANIZATION>Magic Kingdom</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I think all world leaders should come here and recover their childlike 
qualities," <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
But what, specifically, captured this world figure's fancy? 
</P>
<P>
"We went on everything -- Space Mountain, <PERSON>Peter Pan</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Circle Vision</ORGANIZATION>, the train 
and Splash Mountain," he said. "Splash Mountain was awful. Once was enough and 
I'll never go on it again." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
VIP VISITS 
</P>
<P>
Some of the dignitaries who have visited <ORGANIZATION>Disneyland</ORGANIZATION> since it opened in <DATE>1955</DATE>: 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1955</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. Gov. <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1955</DATE> -- Vice President <PERSON>Richard M. Nixon</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1956</DATE> -- President <PERSON>Sukarno</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1956</DATE> -- Chief Justice <PERSON>Earl Warren</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1959</DATE> -- <PERSON>King Hussein</PERSON> of Jordan 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1961</DATE> -- Prime Minister Nehru of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
1961 -- Gen. <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1962</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. Gov. <PERSON>Edmund G. Brown Jr</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
1963 -- Astronaut <PERSON>John Glenn</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1968</DATE> -- <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Robert F. Kennedy</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1969</DATE> -- Russian cosmonauts <LOCATION>G.T. Bergeovoi</LOCATION> and <PERSON>K.P. Feoktistov</PERSON> and families 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1970</DATE> -- <PERSON>Nicolae Ceausescu</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
1971 -- <PERSON>Dr. Henry A. Kissinger</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1976</DATE> -- <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Brian Muldoon</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1977</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Pierre Trudeau</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1979</DATE> -- <PERSON>Fang Yi</PERSON>, Vice Premier of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1979</DATE> -- <PERSON>Sidi Mohamad</PERSON>, Prince of <LOCATION>Morocco</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1982</DATE> -- Former President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1984</DATE> -- <ORGANIZATION>Princess Anne of Great Britain</ORGANIZATION> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1988</DATE> -- Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1988</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. Gov. <PERSON>George Deukmejian</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Tutu Turns Tourist: Anglican Archbishop Desmond Tutu of South 
Africa and his grandson Xabiso Tutu, 3, are accompanied by Mickey and Minnie 
Mouse characters during a tour of Disneyland on Saturday. ; Photo, Tutu Visits 
Magic Kingdom: Anglican Archbishop Desmond Tutu signs the guest register 
Saturday at Disneyland, where he and family members, including his 3-year-old 
grandson, rubbed elbows with Mickey Mouse, rode a carousel and danced in a 
conga line parade. The moral leader of the anti-apartheid movement in South 
Africa will speak in Santa Ana Monday. LACY ATKINS / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
TUTU, DESMOND; DISNEYLAND; TOURISM -- ORANGE COUNTY; APARTHEID; RACIAL 
RELATIONS -- SOUTH AFRICA; CLERGY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880410-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-10-88 1137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Namibia-Tutu     04-10 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Namibia-Tutu,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu Denounces Namibian Government as Sham</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>KATUTURA</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South-West Africa</LOCATION> (AP) _ Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON>
preached <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in the territory's largest black township, derided
its multiracial government and renewed his call for independence
from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   Tutu gave his sermon to about 1,500 people, many in the red,
green and blue colors of the <ORGANIZATION>South-West Africa People's
Organization</ORGANIZATION>, a guerrilla group fighting for independence.
   The congregation had gathered to hear Tutu, the first black
leader of the Anglican church in southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, in a church near
<LOCATION>Windhoek</LOCATION>, capital of the territory commonly known as <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>.
   ``God is here with you in <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>. He suffers with you,'' said
Tutu. ``He says, `It is going to be all right, because I am the God
of justice, I am the God of liberation.'''
   Tutu, winner of the <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION>, lamented last week's
moves by South African President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON> to broaden power of his
country's chief representative in <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> said <PERSON>Administrator-General Louis Pienaar</PERSON> will be empowered
to act against ``subversive'' media, arrange for regional or
racially based elections and refer certain major court rulings to
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s appellate court.
   The archbishop spurned the territory's multiracial interim
government as ``echoes of their master's voice.''
   He was joined at the church <DATE>Sunday</DATE> by 18 Anglican bishops who
serve under him. They included the bishop of <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, who wore a
leopard-skin mitre, and bishops from nearby <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Lesotho</LOCATION> and
neighboring <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   Women ululated and held their children above their heads for a
glimpse of Tutu. The service was held at a Roman Catholic church,
the largest place of worship in the township of 60,000 people.
   <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s 1.3 million people are <PERCENT>88 percent</PERCENT> black. The rest are
divided about equally between whites, who dominate the economy, and
people of mixed race.
   The rebels in the territory have waged a 22-year-old, largely
ineffectual war of independence.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, Tutu blamed <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s apartheid system for the
violence.
   Tutu won his Nobel prize for his fight against apartheid, which
establishes a racially segregated society in which <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s
26 million blacks have no vote in national affairs. The 5 million
whites control the economy and maintain separate districts, schools
and health services.
   ``We are opposed to all violence, especially the violence of the
evil system of apartheid, however it may be disguised by cosmetic
adjustments,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. ``It can survive only because it
uses evil and immoral methods to defend it.''
   A sheet of hymns distributed at the church <DATE>Sunday</DATE> showed
pictures of detained activists.
   But <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said he opposed violence by both guerrillas and the
military, and he rejected communism as a goal for <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>.
   ``The best defense against communism is a free and contented
people,'' he said. ``<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> does not want <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION> to be
free.''
   Tutu appealed for <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION> to observe a <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> resolution calling
for a South African withdrawal and U.N.-supervised independence
elections in <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>.
   But <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> says it will stay as long as Cuban troops
remain in neighboring <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>, where they are helping the Marxist
government battle combined forces of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and a rebel
movement.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880611-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-11-88 1415EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SouthAfrica-Tutu     06-11 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa-Tutu,0570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scuffle At Airport Between Tutu's Backers And Critics</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mandela Concert, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Supporters and critics of
<ORGANIZATION>Archbishop Desmond Tutu</ORGANIZATION> scuffled <DATE>Saturday</DATE> during rival
demonstrations before the black Anglican leader embarked on a trip
to <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
   At least one black man, a supporter of <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION>, was taken into
custody, and police ordered all members of the public to leave the
main hall at <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Jan Smuts Airport</LOCATION>.
   About 100 of <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION>'s supporters remained in the hall and chanted
the archbishop's name when he arrived on a connecting flight from
<LOCATION>Cape Town</LOCATION>.
   Police and clergymen escorted <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> and his wife, <PERSON>Leah</PERSON>, through
the hall as his supporters, most of them black, cheered. Many white
onlookers stared in amazement.
   He gave a final wave to the crowd before entering the
international departure area to catch a flight to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. He is to
fly to <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to join ecumenical celebrations of the
1,000th anniversary of the <ORGANIZATION>Russian Orthodox Church</ORGANIZATION>.
   About 15 anti-Tutu protesters _ including a few blacks and a
white woman with charcoal on her face and wearing a bishop's
costume _ assembled at <LOCATION>Jan Smuts</LOCATION> with placards denouncing the
archbishop's support for sanctions against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. One poster
termed Tutu ``<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s Puppet,'' while another said: ``Red Carpet
for Tutu _ Red Bombs for Us.''
   It was the fourth airport protest against Tutu since he returned
three weeks ago from a trip to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. During
that trip, he repeatedly called for tougher sanctions against <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION> as a means of promoting racial reform.
   <DATE>Saturday</DATE> marked the first time during the series of protests
that anti-Tutu demonstrators were outnumbered by supporters of the
archbishop, who won the Nobel Peace Prize in <DATE>1984</DATE> for his fight
against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s policy of white domination.
   The altercation began after some of the supporters grabbed an
anti-Tutu poster and tore it. Police announced over the public
address system that the arrival hall should be vacated, but many
people _ including members of the rival protest groups _ remained.
   When Tutu arrived, about 45 minutes after the scuffle, one woman
cursed him but few of his other critics were visible.
   Participants in the earlier anti-Tutu protests have included
whites from right-wing organizations and jobless blacks recruited
by conservative black politicians. All the protests have been
filmed and shown on the national television news by the state-run
<ORGANIZATION>South African Broadcasting Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which frequently denounces Tutu.
   Tutu has described sanctions as one of the few non-violent means
of pressuring the government to end apartheid, under which <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>'s 26 million blacks have no voice in national affairs.
Sanctions could be avoided, he says, if the government dismantled
apartheid and moved to grant the black majority full political
rights.
   Tutu's critics contend that sanctions will result in higher
black unemployment while hardening the attitudes of pro-apartheid
whites.
   These critics also claim most blacks oppose sanctions, but there
is no means of verifying this. Endorsement of sanctions is illegal
under emergency regulations, and blacks are not allowed to vote in
national elections or referendums.
   The Rev. <PERSON>Frank Chikane</PERSON>, secretary general of the <ORGANIZATION>South African
Council of Churches</ORGANIZATION>, said this week that the anti-Tutu protests
were being ``orchestrated ... to give the impression that there was
mounting protest against anti-apartheid groups.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890606-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-06-89 0949EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-HarvardDivestment     06-06 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Harvard Divestment,0234</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bishop Tutu Heads Anti-Apartheid Slate In Contested Harvard Election</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON> was among five
anti-apartheid candidates for <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION>'s governing board
awaiting word on whether alumni supported their stand against the
school's investments in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   ``It has been a vituperative campaign. Things have heated up,''
said <PERSON>Robert Wolff</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>Harvard-Radcliffe Alumnae Against
Apartheid</ORGANIZATION>.
   The group, which has three members on the 30-member <ORGANIZATION>Board of
Overseers</ORGANIZATION>, ran five candidates against a <ORGANIZATION>Harvard Alumni
Association-backed</ORGANIZATION> slate of 10, including <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Transportation
Secretary <PERSON>Elizabeth Dole</PERSON>, former <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Paul
Kirk</PERSON> and actor <PERSON>John Lithgow</PERSON>.
   Results of the election, which was open to all <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> degree
holders and conducted by mail, will be made public <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at
<ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>'s commencement.
   The anti-apartheid group has pressured the university to
withdraw its <MONEY>$162.8 million</MONEY> in investments in companies doing
business in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   Tutu, a black leader of the Anglican church in southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>
and a <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize-winner</ORGANIZATION>, has threatened to return the
honorary degree <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> gave him in <DATE>1979</DATE> unless the university
backs away from its South Africa-related holdings.
Massachusetts</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Amherst</LOCATION>, charged that <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> had campaigned
against the anti-apartheid slate.
   <PERSON>Fred Glimp</PERSON>, vice president of alumni affairs, denied that but
said voters should be wary of one-issue candidates.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880322-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-22-88 1138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SAfrica-Bishops     03-22 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SAfrica-Bishops,0486</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anglican Bishops Pledge Backing For Tutu In Showdown With Botha</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Anglican bishops, including an
envoy sent by the <ORGANIZATION>Archbishop of Canterbury</ORGANIZATION>, today pledged support
for <ORGANIZATION>Archbishop Desmond Tutu</ORGANIZATION> in his confrontation with the
government.
   Tutu, the first black to lead the Anglican church in southern
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, has angered President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON> by declaring that he and
other church leaders will carry on the work of anti-apartheid
groups which last month were banned from operating.
   Nineteen bishops, after an emergency meeting with <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION>, issued a
statement warning that the government ``is driving this beloved
country closer to civil war.''
   ``We offer Archbishop Tutu our loyalty and support,'' the
bishops said. ``We shall not allow the government to isolate him.''
   Tutu, who declared that the government would ``bite the dust,''
said it was important that <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> and other white <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION>
``know that I am not just spouting forth things that come into my
head.''
   ``These are responsible people,'' said <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON>, gesturing to the
bishops. ``They would have knocked me down if they believed that
what I am saying is inconsistent with the gospel.''
   Botha met with <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION>, the winner of the <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION>,
last week and suggested that the archbishop had aligned himself
with the outlawed <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> guerrilla movement.
   Referring to this, the bishops said they ``take grave offense at
the cavalier way'' in which <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> treated Tutu.
   Among those attending today's meeting was Bishop <PERSON>Keith Sutton</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Lichfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, who was sent as representative of the
<ORGANIZATION>Archbishop of Canterbury</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Robert Runcie</PERSON>.
   Runcie is spiritual leader of the 70-million-member worldwide
Anglican communion.
   ``He is a Christian leader,'' <PERSON>Sutton</PERSON> said of Tutu. ``His
objections to apartheid grow directly out of his pastoral work.''
   At a news conference <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> dared <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> to take action
against him.
   ``If they try to restrict me or ban me, they are just wasting
their time, because I will not obey their orders,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said.
``They will have to put me in jail.''
   ``I can't keep looking over my shoulder to see if God has got
the approval or disapproval of the government,'' he added.
   Three weeks ago, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> and 24 other church leaders were arrested
and briefly detained after they tried to march to <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>Cape Town</LOCATION> with a petition protesting the latest crackdown on
opposition.
   Last month, the government banned 17 other organizations from
participating in any activity not approved by the government.
   Since then Tutu and other church representatives have taken up
the struggle against apartheid, which by law and custom establishes
a racially segregated society in which the 26 million blacks have
no vote in national affairs.
   <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s 5 million whites control the economy and maintain
separate districts, schools and health services.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880422-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-22-88 1144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Tutu-Botha     04-22 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tutu-Botha,0269</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu Rejects Botha Reform Proposal As ``Crumbs of Conscience''</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BIRMINGHAM, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON> today
rejected as ``crumbs of conscience'' President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON>'s
proposal for giving blacks more political clout in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   The black South African cleric accused <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> of making ``slight
adjustments to the evil system'' of apartheid, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s
official policy of separation of the races. Tutu, an outspoken
opponent of apartheid, won the <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   It won't help if the white-led government merely ``moved
furniture around, because the room would remain the same,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON>
said on the <DATE>last day</DATE> of a four-day visit to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
   Botha told <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that he would move for black
participation in the electoral college and possibly in the Cabinet
as part of the <ORGANIZATION>National Party</ORGANIZATION>'s program of gradual reform.
   Blacks have demanded full voting rights and abolition of
residential and school segregation.
   Tutu, leader of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Anglican Church</ORGANIZATION>, dismissed
<PERSON>Botha</PERSON>'s policy of gradually introducing apartheid reforms.
   ``Reform will not come by `big master' throwing to us crumbs of
conscience that fall from his table,'' the archbishop said. ``It
will happen when all the people in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> are able to
determine the menu together when they sit at the same table.''
   Tutu was speaking at ceremony opening a primary school in this
central <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> industrial city.
   The school is named after <PERSON>Nelson Mandela</PERSON>, the jailed black
activist, prompting protests from local Conservative politicians.
They denounced <ORGANIZATION>Mandela</ORGANIZATION> as a terrorist and said Tutu had not been
forthright in his condemnation of violence.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880412-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-12-88 0920EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SouthAfrica-Tutu     04-12 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-South Africa-Tutu,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop Defends His Activism Against Criticism From Botha</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>WINDHOEK</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>South-West Africa</ORGANIZATION> (AP) _ In a stinging rebuke to
President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON>, <PERSON>Archbishop Desmond Tutu</PERSON> today denied that he
endorsed Marxism and said his fight against apartheid was deeply
rooted in Christian tradition.
   Tutu, the first black to lead the Anglican Church in southern
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, released the text of a letter to <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> defending his
challenges of government policy in a church-state confrontation
that has intensified over the past two months.
   The Nobel Peace Prize laureate was responding to a <DATE>March</DATE> letter
from <LOCATION>Botha</LOCATION> in which the South African president suggested Tutu was
furthering the cause of the <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> guerrilla
movement and promoting a Marxist dictatorship.
   Botha, whose letter was quoted at length on South African
television, asked whether Tutu was acting ``on behalf of the
kingdom of God or the kingdom promised by the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION>.''
   Replied Tutu: ``I work for God's kingdom. For whose kingdom,
with your apartheid policy, do you work for?''
   ``I reject atheistic Marxism and I reject apartheid, which I
find equally abhorrent,'' said Tutu. He cited numerous scriptural
passages to support his contention that <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s policy of
racial separation is ``unbiblical, un-Christian, immoral and evil.''
   Referring to insinuations in <LOCATION>Botha</LOCATION>'s letter, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said he had
never listened to the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION>'s radio broadcasts or read its magazine.
   ``My theological position derives from the <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION> and the
teachings of the Church,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> wrote. ``The Bible and the Church
predate Marxism and the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION> by several centuries.''
   Tutu is presiding this week over a synod of Anglican bishops in
<LOCATION>South-West Africa</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> administers the territory, also
known as <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, in violation of a <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> resolution.
   Tutu also offered to debate the morality of apartheid with a
theologian from <PERSON>Botha</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Dutch Reformed Church</ORGANIZATION>. Apartheid
establishes a racially segregated society in which the 26.5 million
blacks have no vote in national affairs, but the 5 million whites
control the economy and maintain separate districts, schools and
health services.
   ``My position in this is not one of which I am ashamed ... I
know that I stand in the mainline Christian tradition,'' he added.
   Botha had chided Tutu for getting arrested, along with 25 other
church leaders, when they tried to march on Parliament six weeks
ago to protest the bannings of 17 major anti-apartheid
organizations and more than a dozen individuals.
   The clergymen have been trying to fill the political void
created by the crackdown.
   Tutu, who leaves <DATE>Saturday</DATE> on a five-week trip to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, asked <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> to ensure that his reply to the
president was covered as prominently by state television as <PERSON>Botha</PERSON>'s
<DATE>March 16</DATE> letter to Tutu. He also accused the president of falsely
claiming that Tutu once preached under a communist banner.
   ``I pray for you, as I do for your ministerial colleagues, every
day by name,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON>'s letter concluded. ``God bless you.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880824-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-24-88 2056EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Simon 1stLd-Writethru a0605 08-24 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Simon, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0605,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Illinois Senator Visits Soweto, Meets Tutu</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with Simon meeting Bishop Desmond Tutu,
edits to conform, raises identification of Simon as key subcommitte
chairman.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. <PERSON>Paul Simon</PERSON> visited black
squatters <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Soweto</LOCATION>, met with <PERSON>Archbishop Desmond Tutu</PERSON> and
renewed his clemency appeal for the <ORGANIZATION>Sharpeville Six</ORGANIZATION>, a group of
blacks facing execution.
   The Illinois Democrat, on a five-day trip to <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>,
conferred briefly with <PERSON>Prakash Diar</PERSON>, lawyer for the <LOCATION>Sharpeville</LOCATION>
Six. The five men and one woman have been sentenced to hang for
involvement in a mob that killed a black town councilor in <DATE>1984</DATE> in
<LOCATION>Sharpeville</LOCATION>, a township south of <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>.
   Later, <PERSON>Simon</PERSON> spent about 30 minutes with <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION>, leader of the
Anglican church in southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and winner of the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel
Peace Prize for his campaign against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s apartheid
   Speaking to reporters after the meeting, <PERSON>Simon</PERSON> predicted that
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will toughen sanctions against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. As chairman
<PERSON>Simon</PERSON> will have a major role in that decision.
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> ``would be eager to avoid sanctions if we got a good
strong clear signal from the government here that they were going
to do away with apartheid,'' <PERSON>Simon</PERSON> said. ``But I'm not getting that
signal.''
   He contends that sanctions could push the white authorities
toward reform.
   Before meeting Tutu, <PERSON>Simon</PERSON> toured <LOCATION>Soweto</LOCATION>, the black township of
2.5 million people outside <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>. He also visited two
squatter camps and an all-male hostel for migrant workers.
   ``I've just spoken with a man with five children who sees his
family only once a year,'' <PERSON>Simon</PERSON> said after emerging from the
hostel. ``This is an illustration of what happens under a system of
injustice based on racial separation.''
   Simon also met with <PERSON>Albertina Sisulu</PERSON>, a prominent anti-apartheid
activist whose husband, <PERSON>Walter</PERSON>, is serving life in prison with
   Simon is leading a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> campaign seeking clemency for the
<LOCATION>Sharpeville</LOCATION> Six, whose case has drawn worldwide attention.
President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON> has refused to intervene. They were granted a
reprieve in <DATE>March</DATE> hours before they were to be executed.
   Diar will argue the case before the <ORGANIZATION>Appeal Court</ORGANIZATION> next month.
   His clients did not physically contribute to the death of the
councilor, according to court testimony. They were convicted under
the doctrine of ``common purpose,'' which holds them responsible
for being an active part of the mob that carried out the killing.
   ``There is a feeling that the system has not provided justice
for a great many people, and to some extent the <LOCATION>Sharpeville</LOCATION> Six are
a symbol of that,'' <PERSON>Simon</PERSON> said.
   He said his request to visit with the <LOCATION>Sharpeville</LOCATION> Six was turned
down but he planned to mention the case in a scheduled meeting
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> with Foreign Minister <PERSON>Roelof F. Botha</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06116118 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06116118 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO:; Bishop Desmond Tutu had spent a week in the hospital in March.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  RELIGION; LEADER; SOUTH-AFRICA; HOSPITAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Anglican Archbisop Desmond Tutu was hospitalized Wednesday for tests related
to an earlier urinary tract infection, his press officer said.;    Tutu, 59,
spent a week in the hospital in March because of the infection.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TUTU IN HOSPITAL AFTER INFECTION  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     He returned <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from a 17-day trip to <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, where he
attended the enthronement of the 103rd Archbishop of <LOCATION>Canterbury</LOCATION>, <PERSON>George
Carey.</PERSON>;    "He's gone to hospital for tests which were arranged to help the
doctors locate the source of the previous infection," said press officer <PERSON>John
Allen</PERSON>. "We don't know how long he'll be there. There is no indication at this
stage that there is anything seriously wrong.";    Test results were expected
in a few days, <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> said.;    The head of the Anglican church in southern
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tutu</LOCATION> is the religious leader of 2.6 million people. He won the <ORGANIZATION>Nobel
Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE> for anti-apartheid activities.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Cape Town, South Africa  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910425  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  159  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday April 25, 1991
00116118,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1621EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Christmas-Israel     12-25 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas-Israel,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu Condemns Israeli Treatment of Palestinians</HEAD>
<HEAD>With-AM-World Christmas, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS MEIXLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop Desmond Tutu of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Monday</DATE> compared his country's suppression of blacks to <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s
treatment of Palestinians in the occupied lands, where Christmas
celebrations were subdued because of the Arab uprising.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION> laureate came under increased criticism
from Jews and also Christians sympathetic to <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>, who accused
him of taking a one-sided approach to the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> conflict
during his five-day trip.
   ``Members of our team have remarked on the similarities between
the situation in the occupied territories and that in <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>,'' Tutu told reporters.
   ``In the methods of resistance used by Palestinians, and in the
ways the Israeli government deals with the resistance, we
experienced an extraordinary sense of being at home,'' he said.
   In the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION> city of <LOCATION>Bethlehem</LOCATION>, hundreds of Christian
pilgrims marked Christmas with a visit to <ORGANIZATION>St. Catherine</ORGANIZATION>'s basilica
in <LOCATION>Manger Square</LOCATION>, the legendary site of Jesus' birth.
   Israeli soldiers removed barricades and metal detectors from
<LOCATION>Manger Square</LOCATION> after <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION> passed without incident. But the
military presence was heavy, and at least 50 paratroopers and
soldiers from the elite <ORGANIZATION>Givati</ORGANIZATION> brigade patrolled the square.
   ``I don't like it, but I guess it's for security,'' said <PERSON>Sara
Paredes</PERSON>, 20, of <LOCATION>Fort Leavenworth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION> as she stood outside the
Church of the <LOCATION>Nativity</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Paredes</PERSON> said making a pilgrimage to <LOCATION>Bethlehem</LOCATION> was a ``dream''
for her, but added that she would like to return in the future when
tensions and security are lessened and ``when I can find a better
Christmas.''
   Twenty Palestinians were wounded after troops opened fire on
stone-throwing demonstrators in the <LOCATION>Gaza Strip</LOCATION>, Arab reports said.
   The army said it was investigating the reports.
   Tutu drew harsh criticism after he refused to meet with a
delegation of Ethiopian Jews, saying their visit to the <ORGANIZATION>St. George
Anglican Church</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>East Jerusalem</LOCATION> was not on his schedule.
   ``He did not have time to sit with us, even for two or three
minutes,'' <PERSON>Yitzhak Rahamim</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Ethiopian
Immigrants Association</ORGANIZATION> told a reporter outside the church. ``I
heard he had time to meet with Palestinians, but not with Jews,
even with us from <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.''
   Tutu met <DATE>Monday</DATE> with a group of prominent Palestinian leaders to
discuss the situation in the occupied territories, where
Palestinians began their revolt against Israeli rule in <DATE>December
1987</DATE>.
   The Jerusalem-based <ORGANIZATION>International Christian Embassy</ORGANIZATION>, headed by
<PERSON>Willem van der Hoeven</PERSON>, a Dutch Evangelist cleric, published a
statement denouncing Tutu's repeated expressions of support for
Palestinians.
   In the statement that was also sent to Israeli leaders, Van der
Hoeven wrote: ``we specifically apologize for the remarks made by
the visiting Anglican Archbishop Desmond Tutu...we bow our heads in
shame.''
   Tutu's endorsement of a Palestinian state has alienated many
Israelis, and <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s two chief rabbis refused to meet with the
Anglican human rights leader.
   When asked to comment on criticisms of his visit, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> replied:
``The bible...speaks about <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> as being an agent of God for
establishing justice and peace, and there is no way I am going to
say the way <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> is treating Palestinians is just. And if they
revile me for that, tough luck.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890103-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-03-89 2132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Tutu'sSon 2ndLd-Writethru   01-03 0511</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tutu's Son, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0673,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu's Son Says He Engineered Arrest as a Publicity Stunt</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 2nd graf CORRECTING name to Trevor, sted Travor. Picks
up 3rd graf pvs, ``We're in ...</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto JOH1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The son of <ORGANIZATION>Archbishop Desmond
Tutu</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he engineered his own arrest at an airport to
promote an advertising agency he heads.
   <PERSON>Trevor Tutu</PERSON> made the declaration to reporters after going to
court <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> first to face charges stemming from the airport
incident and then to answer minor traffic violations.
   ``We're in the business of playing with people's minds,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON>,
32, told reporters at his news conference. He said he tricked police
into arresting him mainly ``to tell people that TuMult had arrived.''
   He serves as chairman of <ORGANIZATION>TuMult</ORGANIZATION>, a black-oriented advertising
agency formed a few months ago. He said the name was chosen to sound
like his last name, which gained international fame in <DATE>1984</DATE> when his
father won the <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION>.
   Earlier <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> and a former girlfriend appeared in a
suburban magistrate's court to face charges of violating civil
aviation laws.
   The charges relate to an incident over <LOCATION>Tutu</LOCATION>'s luggage <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at
<LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Jan Smuts Airport</LOCATION>. The case against <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Joan
Rhodes</PERSON> was postponed until <DATE>Feb. 15</DATE>.
   But Tutu was taken into custody by <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION> police as he left
the <LOCATION>Kempton Park</LOCATION> courthouse, driven to police headquarters, and
fined <MONEY>$160</MONEY> for failing to answer three traffic summonses.
   He pleaded guilty to operating an unlicensed vehicle and parking
twice in a loading zone.
   At the news conference, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said he and colleagues planned the
airport incident as a promotion stunt.
   Tutu said he changed into dirty, old clothes while heading into
<LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION> on a flight from <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION>. He said he then placed
luggage near some policemen at the airport and told them he was a
servant acting on instructions of his white employer.
   He said the police did nothing until he came back later to remove
the bags and told them the parcels could have contained bombs.
   At that point, he said, many policemen converged, and he was
arrested, <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said.
   ``I tied down 5,000 guys,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said of security personnel. He
repeatedly mocked police, saying at one point: ``They don't know
what they're doing.''
   Police have warned <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION> not to leave parcels and
luggage unattended in public places because of a bombing campaign by
anti-government guerrillas.
   Tutu is the eldest of four children of <ORGANIZATION>Desmond Tutu</ORGANIZATION>, who leads
the <ORGANIZATION>Anglican Church</ORGANIZATION> in southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. The father won the Nobel
Prize for his campaigning against the country's system of racial
discrimination.
   <PERSON>Trevor Tutu</PERSON> said his father did not know in advance of his recent
activities but added: ``As long as I'm using peaceful means, he
doesn't mind.''
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, <PERSON>Trevor Tutu</PERSON> was held by police for three days before he
was cleared of a charge of drunken driving.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, he was briefly detained after arguing with police at a
courthouse about the detention of black children.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900502-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-02-90 2129EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Tutu     05-02 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tutu,0365</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop Tutu Calls Pretoria-ANC Talks `Mind Boggling'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-South Africa, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EXETER, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON> called
``mind-boggling'' <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s first talks between the South African
government and the <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> and said too much was
at stake for either side to be ``bloody-minded.''
   The black Anglican archbishop of <LOCATION>Cape Town</LOCATION>, an anti-apartheid
campaigner and <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel Peace laureate, said he didn't expect
important agreements to emerge from the preliminary talks in <LOCATION>Cape
Town</LOCATION> which end <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   ``I just think what most of the people in our community would
like to hear is a real commitment on all sides to talks,'' he told
a news conference at <ORGANIZATION>Exeter University</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``And that we want to go in to substantive negotiations, that
would be important and give hope to people who are tired of the
violence of apartheid and the counterviolence of those who oppose
apartheid.''
   Tutu came to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for a three-day visit shortly
before the talks began. He lectured <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in this
university city in <LOCATION>southwest England</LOCATION>.
   Asked by reporters at <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Heathrow Airport</LOCATION> if he believed
much could be achieved in the first round, he said:
   ``I am very hopeful. I don't think that any of those people, on
both sides, are going into those talks bloody-minded. We've got too
much at stake. Too many people have already died, too many people
have suffered.''
   Tutu said <ORGANIZATION>South African President F.W. de Klerk</ORGANIZATION> knew that unless
he settled with the black majority ``the whole question of
sanctions and apartheid economy will be exacerbated.''
   Tutu commented, ``It's actually almost mind-boggling to think
that they are now sitting across the table with the people they
tried to demonize.''
   ``On the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION> side, they know that most of their supporters would
like to see an end to violence,'' the prelate said.
   He called <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s racial-segregation system ``one of the
most vicious the world has seen.''
   Tutu criticized British Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> for
opposing sanctions on <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   ``We admire her eloquency in condemning apartheid. We just wish
there was a matching consistency in action,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880905-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-05-88 0153EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SouthAfrica     09-05 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-South Africa,0603</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu: Voters Should Boycott Municipal Elections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON>,
saying he was ``obeying God'' in defying the government, urged
blacks and whites to boycott next month's nationwide but segregated
municipal elections.
   Elsewhere on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, black activist <PERSON>Winnie Mandela</PERSON> also violated
state of emergency rules by calling for increased international
economic sanctions against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   Tutu, in a service at <ORGANIZATION>St. George's Cathedral</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cape Town</LOCATION>,
described the elections as ``ludicrous'' and ``unjust'' and said
the government was attempting to ``force participation.''
   ``I urge black people in this diocese not to vote in the <DATE>October</DATE>
elections and I hope that white Anglicans would join their black
fellow Anglicans in that action,'' said <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON>, winner of the <DATE>1984</DATE>
<ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I am aware of the penalties attached to this call. I am not
defying the government, I am obeying God,'' the black churchman
said.
   Whites, blacks, Asians and people of mixed-race will hold
separate elections <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> to choose local officials. The black
majority has no vote in national affairs, although the nation's 26
million blacks make up about <PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s
population.
   Under the 26-month-old state of emergency it is illegal to call
for an election boycott in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. If convicted, violators
may be fined or imprisoned.
   In the <DATE>1984</DATE> municipal elections, anti-apartheid groups promoted
election boycotts and only about <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> of eligible black
voters went to the polls.
   Many black activists view black elected officials as
collaborators with the white-dominated government and its apartheid
policies of racial separation.
   Tutu said calling for an election boycott was a legitimate
``non-violent way of expressing our opposition to the evil and
injustice of apartheid.''
   ``You cannot get security through the barrel of a gun, nor
through the draconian and oppressive state of emergency,'' he said.
   Tutu spoke at a special service to install <PERSON>Canon Colin Jones</PERSON> as
dean of <ORGANIZATION>St. George's Cathedral</ORGANIZATION>. Jones, 37, becomes the first black
to serve in the post. He spent last year in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, and
most recently was the chaplin at the <ORGANIZATION>University of the Western
Cape</ORGANIZATION>, a mixed-race school.
   Minister of <ORGANIZATION>Law and Order Adriaan Vlok</ORGANIZATION> has threatened to clamp
down on anti-apartheid clergymen.
   ``We must clip their wings _ as we clipped those of the 19
revolutionary and activist organizations,'' <PERSON>Vlok</PERSON> said on <DATE>Friday</DATE> in
reference to the government's <DATE>February</DATE> decision banning most
leading anti-apartheid groups.
   Anti-government church leaders were among the few prominent
resistence figures spared in the crackdown, and they now are the
most visible domestic opponents of the government.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Mandela</PERSON> called for increased economic sanctions in a speech
   ``When we call for sanctions, when we call for disinvestment
from this country, it is because we are looking for those peaceful
measures as an alternative to the structural violence of the state
we see <DATE>today</DATE>,'' she said.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Mandela</PERSON> spoke to 400 people gathered to mark the
publication of a biography on her husband, jailed <ORGANIZATION>African National
Congress</ORGANIZATION> leader <PERSON>Nelson Mandela</PERSON>. The book, entitled ``Higher Than
Hope,'' was written by South African academic <PERSON>Fatima Meer</PERSON>, who also
was present.
   The 70-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Mandela</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s best known black leader,
is in a <LOCATION>Cape Town</LOCATION> clinic recuperating from tuberculosis.
   He has been imprisoned for 26 years and is serving a life
sentence for sabotage and attempting to overthrow the government.
The <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION> is the major guerrilla group fighting white minority rule.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901105-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-05-90 1736EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Churches     11-05 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Churches,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>Black, White Church Leaders Meet to Discuss South Africa's Future</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TINA SUSMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON> urged
churches once divided over apartheid to work together for a
peaceful future as he opened a church conference <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   About 300 delegates from 90 churches are meeting in hopes of
reaching agreement on how to help <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> move peacefully to a
non-discriminatory democracy. They will spend five days at the
<ORGANIZATION>National Conference of Churches</ORGANIZATION>, billed as the largest such meeting
to be held in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   The conference in <LOCATION>Rustenburg</LOCATION>, 62 miles northwest of
<LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>, has brought together the white branch of the <ORGANIZATION>Dutch
Reformed Church</ORGANIZATION> with its black and mixed-race branches.
   The white <ORGANIZATION>Dutch Reformed Church</ORGANIZATION>, the main church of the
Dutch-descended Afrikaners who dominate the government, argued for
decades that the <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION> supported apartheid. It has changed that
view and says it wants to merge with the other branches.
   The black and mixed-race branches have staunchly opposed
apartheid.
   Tutu, the Anglican archbishop who won the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel Peace Prize
for his anti-apartheid activism, called for reconciliation. ``We
come here not to engage in recrimination,'' he said in the opening
speech.
   ``In this land we are bound together by common humanity, by
having one God. The only way we will ever be able to survive, to be
free, to be human, is together, black and white,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Khoza Mgogo</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>South African Council of Churches</ORGANIZATION>,
urged delegates to adopt strategies for redistribution of wealth,
most of which is in the hands of the white minority.
   ``The beauty of the meeting is that we are bringing the whole
Christian community of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> together - the establishment
Afrikans churches and their anti-apartheid counterparts,'' the Rev.
<PERSON>Frank Chikane</PERSON>, a conference organizer, told the <ORGANIZATION>Sunday Times</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``For the first time there is the distinct possibility that the
can speak with one voice on apartheid and the country's future,''
he said.
   Two relatively small white churches that still support apartheid
- the <ORGANIZATION>Afrikaans Protestant Church</ORGANIZATION> and the Reformed Church - are not
attending.
   Many of the churches represented belong to the <ORGANIZATION>South African
Council of Churches</ORGANIZATION>, which often has been at the forefront of the
anti-apartheid movement. Chikane is the general secretary of the
council.
   The nation's church leaders met 30 years ago in an attempt to
forge a united front to challenge apartheid, but the agreement
collapsed when the <ORGANIZATION>Dutch Reformed Church</ORGANIZATION> rejected it.
   The current conference was organized after President F.W. de
Klerk urged church leaders to develop a common position on the role
they envision for the church in the future.
   De Klerk has said he wants to dismantle the apartheid system and
negotiate a new constitution that would allow the country's 5
million whites and 30 million blacks to share power.
   <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> is predominantly Christian, with large numbers of
Catholics, Anglicans, Methodists, Zionists and Pentecostalists.
There also are many Jews and Moslems in the nation.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880302-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-02-88 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SouthAfrica     03-02 0417</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-South Africa,0428</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu Says West Should Sever South Africa Diplomatic Ties</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY GRAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Anglican Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON> said
today he would try to persuade Western governments to break all
diplomatic ties with <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> until it eased restrictions on
anti-apartheid groups.
   ``We want to tell the South African government that they do not
deserve to be part of a decent society,'' he said at a news
conference.
   Tutu said Western nations should cut any diplomatic links with
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and expel South African diplomats from their countries.
   ``<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> have kept saying that
sanctions hurt blacks and sanctions are not effective,'' he said.
``While not withdrawing my support for economic sanctions, I am
saying to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and other Western countries, `Here
is your chance.'''
   Tutu was in the Kenyan capital for a meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>All-African
Conference of Churches</ORGANIZATION>, which he heads.
   He said he has called in the past for Western governments to
break relations with <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>. But he said this time he intended to
actively campaign for such a move.
   ``My own intention now is to challenge the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> to break off
diplomatic relations with <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, to expel South African
diplomats from their countries until certain conditions are met,''
the churchman said.
   Those conditions are a lifting of the state of emergency,
reversal of a <DATE>Feb. 25</DATE> ruling that outlawed political activity by 18
opposition groups, and the release of political detainees,
especially children.
   Tutu, winner of the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel Peace Prize, and other churchmen
were arrested <DATE>Monday</DATE> when they attempted to march on the <LOCATION>South
African Parliament</LOCATION> at <LOCATION>Cape Town</LOCATION> to protest the crackdown on black
opposition groups.
   The Rev. <PERSON>Allan Boesak</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>World Alliance of
Reformed Churches</ORGANIZATION>, also was arrested. In an interview with ``CBS
This Morning'' from <LOCATION>Harare</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, he said it is clear that the
government now is outlawing ``all legitimate peaceful activity,''
and that apartheid opponents have no choice but to resist.
   ``And if that means confrontation, if that means disobedience to
your unjust laws then I think that is exactly what we mean,'' he
said. ``We are talking about the possibility of civil
disobedience.''
   He said non-violent protests have ended in deaths in the past
but won't be a deterrent to civil disobedience.
   ``We will have to take the risks that go with it and we will
have to take the consequences that follow these actions of ours,''
he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881104-0220 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-04-88 2317EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Tutu-Election     11-04 0280</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tutu-Election,0291</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu Says South African Blacks Prefer Dukakis</HEAD>
<HEAD>with AM-Political Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHEGE MBITIRU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that
black <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION> would be disappointed by a Republican victory
in next week's presidential election.
   ``We would rather see a Democrat in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> than a
Republican,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said. ``We have suffered a great deal from the
<PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration's policy of constructive engagement.''
   Tutu, leader of the <ORGANIZATION>Anglican Church</ORGANIZATION> in southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and winner
of the <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION>, made the comments in <LOCATION>Nairobi</LOCATION> while
attending the annual conference of the <ORGANIZATION>All-Africa Council of
Churches</ORGANIZATION>.
   He is council president and chairman.
   Tutu did not mention either Democrat <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> or
Republican <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> by name. He also did not single out policies
advocated by either candidate that would be harmful or helpful to
blacks in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   The <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration preferred a policy on <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> that
became known as constructive engagement _ dialogue with the
white-led <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION> government rather than the diplomatic and
economic confrontational tactics pursued by former Democratic
President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>.
   Tutu said President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s policy had failed.
   ``We are now virtually being ruled by martial law,'' he said.
   The archbishop said South African authorities had declared a
state of emergency three times during <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s tenure at the <ORGANIZATION>White
House</ORGANIZATION>. During that period, he said, more than 2,000 people were
killed, many by security forces.
   Tutu is a key activist against apartheid, the policy of racial
segregation under which <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s 26 million blacks have no
vote in national affairs. The 5 million whites control the economy
and maintain separate districts, schools and health services.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880316-0249 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-16-88 2338EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica-Churches     03-16 0653</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa-Churches,0673</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu Cancels Meeting With Dutch Reformed Church Leaders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURINDA KEYS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Black <ORGANIZATION>Anglican Archbishop
Desmond Tutu</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> canceled a meeting with leaders of the
white <ORGANIZATION>Dutch Reformed Church</ORGANIZATION> after they described his challenge of
government policy as ``impious.''
   Tutu, a prominent foe of apartheid and winner of the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel
Peace Prize, had planned to meet the leaders in <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
for the first formal talks between the two churches since <DATE>1960</DATE>.
President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON> and most other government officials belong to
the <ORGANIZATION>Dutch Reformed Church</ORGANIZATION>, the largest denomination of the dominant
Afrikaner white minority.
   Tutu said he canceled the meeting because of an ``abusive
attack'' on his church in a statement issued <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by Dutch
Reformed leaders and published <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. He said the leaders
``deliberately sabotaged the talks.''
   Later <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> issued a statement asking Tutu to
repudiate the outlawed <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> guerrilla
movement. Tutu says he does not endorse the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION>'s use of violence
but shares its professed goal of a non-racial democracy.
   ``The question must be posed whether you are acting on behalf of
the kingdom of God or the kingdom promised by the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>SACP</ORGANIZATION>
(South African Communist Party),'' <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> said.
   ``Are you in favor of the establishment of a Marxist
dictatorship in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> under the rule of the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION> and the
<ORGANIZATION>SACP</ORGANIZATION>, to the detriment of the church?''
   Tutu later met with <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> to urge clemency for the ``Sharpeville
Six'' _ a group of blacks scheduled to hang <DATE>Friday</DATE> for complicity
in a <DATE>1984</DATE> mob killing during anti-apartheid unrest.
   Tutu said <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> scolded him for taking a confrontational stance
toward the government.
   The archbishop said his decision to cancel the church meeting
was influenced by a ``background of unease'' related to the
scheduled hangings. He urged Dutch Reformed leaders to join
Anglican clergy in prayers for condemned prisoners.
   The Dutch Reformed leaders' statement referred to comments by
<PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> and the Rev. <PERSON>Allan Boesak</PERSON>, a mixed-race minister, at a church
service <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Cape Town</LOCATION>.
   Tutu and <PERSON>Boesak</PERSON> were protesting a recent government ban on
political activity by 19 organizations.
   Boesak, president of the <ORGANIZATION>World Alliance of Reformed Churches</ORGANIZATION>,
and Tutu used strong language in responding to Law and Order
Minister <PERSON>Adriaan Vlok</PERSON>'s warnings that he will act against the
clergymen if they did not stop ``preaching revolution.''
   <PERSON>Boesak</PERSON> said the government ``signed its own death warrant. ...
No government can challenge the living God and survive.''
   Tutu said, ``If it is revolution to say I work for a <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION> that is truly democratic ... I am for that.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Dutch Reformed Church</ORGANIZATION> objected to the clergymen's
``language, convictions and veiled threats that do not breathe the
spirit of the Gospel.''
   It said it was ``not unsympathetic to the problems that churches
in this country have to contend with.'' But the statement called on
<PERSON>Boesak</PERSON> and Tutu ``to divorce themselves from this impious road and
to discuss their problems openly'' with Vlok and <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> ``who are
both avowed Christians.''
   Botha issued a statement <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> through the <ORGANIZATION>South African
Broadcasting Corp.</ORGANIZATION> saying the churches had to recognize ``certain
limitations in the execution of their prophetic task outside the
ecclesiastical field.''
   One major point of <PERSON>Boesak</PERSON>'s and <ORGANIZATION>Tutu</ORGANIZATION>'s sermons was to dispute
Vlok's statement that they were preaching revolution instead of the
Christian message.
   The Dutch Reformed statement appeared to agree with Vlok and
<PERSON>Botha</PERSON>.
   ``In exceeding these limits they have confronted the state, and
cannot equate themselves with the church in the face of state
retaliation,'' it said. ``The Church of Jesus Christ cannot be used
as a means for a revolutionary change of government.''
   By law and custom, apartheid establishes a racially segregated
society in which the 26 million blacks have no vote in national
affairs. The 5 million whites control the economy and maintain
separate districts, schools and health services.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890131-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-31-89 0938EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-People-Tutu 1stLd-Writethru a0524 01-31 0220</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-People-Tutu, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0524,0222</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bishop Calls On Wiesel To Join Him In Mediating Palestinian Conflict</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs lede to CORRECT title to archbishop, sted bishop. Subs
2nd graf to CORRECT typo in name of synagogue. Inserts in 4th graf, `He
said ...,' that Wiesel was not at ceremony.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON>, who won the <DATE>1984</DATE> Nobel
Peace Prize for his struggle against apartheid in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, has
called on a fellow Nobel laureate to join him in mediating the
Israeli-Palestinian conflict.
   Tutu made the offer to <DATE>1986</DATE> Nobel Peace Prize recipient <PERSON>Elie
Wiesel</PERSON> as he accepted an award <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> from the <ORGANIZATION>Stephen Wise
Free Synagogue</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>.
   ``The idea, I must say, did not come to me `cerebrally,' but in a
vision, because of its symbolic significance, as two men who have
been honored with the Nobel Peace Prize,'' <PERSON>Tutu</PERSON> said at the award
ceremony.
   He said he had not consulted with <PERSON>Wiesel</PERSON>, the author and
Holocaust survivor, before making his proposal. Wiesel was not in
the audience.
   Tutu said he supported <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s right to territorial integrity
and condemned terrorism, ``But <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> is not infallible,
mercifully.''
   Tutu was honored by the synagogue ``for his leadership in the
struggle against apartheid and for the entire spectrum of civil and
human rights for all peoples.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880507-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-07-88 0546EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-UN-SouthAfrica     05-07 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-UN-South Africa,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu Says U.S., British, West German Votes Protect South Africa</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICTORIA GRAHAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop <PERSON>Desmond Tutu</PERSON> denounced the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> for voting to block <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION>
resolutions calling for sanctions against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> because it
