<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030390-0047 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 184033 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 3, 1990, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 13A; Column 4; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
339 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GIRLS' BASKETBALL DIVISION IV; 
</P>
<P>
HOLTVILLE SENIORS COMPLETE WARDROBE, ROLL PAST CORONADO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LAURA PALMER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Holtville senior <PERSON>Teresa Ibarra</PERSON> just wanted one more basketball championship 
patch to sew on her letterman jacket. 
</P>
<P>
"I needed a third patch to fill up my sleeve," she said. 
</P>
<P>
She got it <DATE>Friday</DATE> when <LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> defeated <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>, 57-31, in the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 
Section Division IV girls' basketball final at Golden <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> went into the game as two-time Division IV defending champion, having 
defeated Coronado by 24 and 13 points in previous finals. But <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s game was 
expected to be closer. In the second game of the season, <LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> (18-9) 
defeated Coronado (14-11) by just five after <PERSON>Coronado</PERSON> had built a 10-point 
lead. 
</P>
<P>
"I thought it would be a two- or three-point ball game either way," <LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> 
Coach <PERSON>Mike Pacheco</PERSON> said. "It was great to have a game like this. It makes my 
job easier." 
</P>
<P>
Coronado trailed by 18, 41-23, at the <DATE>end of the third quarter</DATE> and did not 
score again until three minutes remained. The Islanders were outscored, 16-8, 
in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>. Their leading scorer, <PERSON>Kris Skaalan</PERSON>, managed just eight 
points. 
</P>
<P>
"He (<ORGANIZATION>Coronado Coach Ernie Dickerson</ORGANIZATION>) has seen our press," <PERSON>Pacheco</PERSON> said. "We 
pressed them the last time, and that's how we won. They didn't look as ready or 
prepared for the press as I thought they would be. Maybe he was prepared, and 
it just didn't work. We tried to throw them with a two-three zone and never 
went to a man-to-man." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> took a 12-6 <DATE>first-quarter</DATE> lead and then broke the game open, making 
it 31-11 by halftime. Senior <PERSON>Denise Gaddis</PERSON> scored nine of her 11 points in the 
first half. 
</P>
<P>
Ibarra, a 5-1 guard, worked hard for her patch. She scored 21 points, including 
two three-pointers in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE> and two more, on consecutive shots, in 
the fourth. Ibarra said she doesn't concentrate on shooting from that range. 
</P>
<P>
"Whenever I have an open shot I shoot," she said. "He (Pacheco) always tells me 
I never shoot enough and to shoot more." 
</P>
<P>
Said Pacheco: "Teresa delivered like a senior should. It didn't surprise me 
that she led the team today. Too bad she's not 6-1." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030290-0038 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 183512 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 2, 1990, Friday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 7A; Column 5; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
211 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DIVISION IV BASKETBALL PREVIEWS; 
</P>
<P>
GIRLS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LAURA PALMER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When <LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> meet at noon for the girls' Division IV 
championship, they will be much different teams than those that met in 
<DATE>November</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
In the second game of the season in the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Tournament</ORGANIZATION>, Coronado (14-10) 
held as much as a 10-point lead before losing by five. 
</P>
<P>
"I start three different kids than I did then, and he starts two," Coronado 
Coach <PERSON>Ernie Dickerson</PERSON> said. "Looking back on that game, it doesn't mean a whole 
lot." 
</P>
<P>
The teams played for the Division IV championship in each of the past two 
years, with <LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> (17-9) winning both. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Mike Pacheco</PERSON> said the change to <ORGANIZATION>Golden Hall</ORGANIZATION> from the Sports 
Arena -- where his team has played in section finals the past four years -- 
could be a "key factor" for <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"His kids are so young that if we were playing in the Sports Arena, it could 
make a difference," <PERSON>Pacheco</PERSON> said. "Nobody's been at <LOCATION>Golden Hall</LOCATION>, so there's no 
home-court advantage." 
</P>
<P>
The two only varsity returners for <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> are <PERSON>Mary Strasser</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kelly Kaye</PERSON>. 
Strasser, a left-handed shooter who started as a freshman last year, has a 
15.5-point average but has averaged 18 the past six games. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> is led by <PERSON>Teresa Ibarra</PERSON>, a 5-1 senior point guard who is averaging 12 
points a game. LAURA <LOCATION>PALMER</LOCATION> 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011490-0142 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 162024 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 14, 1990, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
449 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ON THE BRIDGE TOLL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
On <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>, you carried a commentary written by the mayor of <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mary 
Herron</PERSON>, which dealt with the problems of the <LOCATION>San Diego-Coronado Bay Bridge</LOCATION>. I 
want you to know that the message by <PERSON>Mary Herron</PERSON> does not speak for all the 
residents of Coronado. 
</P>
<P>
The mayor talks of reducing the traffic in Coronado by the use of any mode of 
transportation except the single-occupancy auto. She also speaks of the tourist 
industry preference for discounting the present toll. What was not said was 
that, for several months, there has been a "car pool" lane on the bridge that 
allows cars with two or more persons, buses and motorcycles to cross the bridge 
without paying any toll. Therefore, most tourist traffic can use this benefit. 
</P>
<P>
Many of the Coronado residents must still make their way to the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> side 
in order to make their daily wage. In many cases, this involves the use of 
single-occupancy cars because car-pooling is difficult, if not impossible, to 
arrange. 
</P>
<P>
It should be noted that these residents are for the most part traveling in the 
opposite direction of the heaviest traffic. Yet we must pay the toll each and 
every day. It seems that the mayor is most interested in ensuring that the toll 
continue to provide bridge maintenance and for the ever-illusive alternative 
transportation system. 
</P>
<P>
I submit that the car-pool lane is an excellent means of moving the vast number 
of cars through the toll plaza, but is a poor way to reduce the number of cars 
on <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s streets. Therefore, I would propose that the car-pool lane be 
limited to the high-traffic periods (for the most part, early morning) and all 
vehicles pay a reduced toll at other times. In this manner, the monies 
necessary for bridge maintenance could be generated by all travelers, not just 
the people who cannot find another person to transport. 
</P>
<P>
I would also hope that some of the revenue generated would provide some measure 
of control of the traffic along the few streets that carry such a high 
percentage of the commuter traffic. During much of the day, it is difficult and 
dangerous to cross such streets as 3rd and 4th. I would also hope that the 
mayor would instruct the <ORGANIZATION>Police Department</ORGANIZATION> to enforce the speed limit on all 
vehicles. This would include buses and trucks. Mayor <PERSON>Herron</PERSON> observe the speed 
that some of these vehicles use on these streets. It is frightening. 
</P>
<P>
The headline, "Coronado Is Still Willing to Pay the Toll" is misleading. It 
leaves the impression that <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> wants the toll the way it is. The toll 
needs to be rethought and the residents of Coronado allowed to fully express 
themselves on the way it is applied, or, I should say, misapplied. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>JACK A. VAUGHAN 
</P>
<P>
Coronado</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Letter to the Editor 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030289-0037 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 25151 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 2, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 9A; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
429 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SOMETHING OLD, SOMETHING NEW AT FINALS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KIM Q. BERKSHIRE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
For some, it's the thrill of a lifetime. For others, it's a steppingstone to 
the next stop, the Southern Regionals. 
</P>
<P>
Eight teams -- five making return engagements, three celebrating their coming 
of age -- vie for <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Section Division IV and V girls' and boys' 
basketball titles today and tonight at the Sports Arena. 
</P>
<P>
"This is a good opportunity for us," Christian Coach <PERSON>Randy Wright</PERSON> said. "Not 
too many kids have the opportunity to play in the Sports Arena." Wright's 
Patriots (13-11) will take a measure of experience -- they defeated <ORGANIZATION>Mountain 
Empire</ORGANIZATION> for the Division IV title last year -- into their 8:30 game against 
Coronado (11-13), first-time visitors to the arena. 
</P>
<P>
Top-ranked Christian also has the distinction of coming from the <ORGANIZATION>City Central</ORGANIZATION> 
league, joining Lincoln (Division III) and <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> (Division I) also in the 
Section finals. 
</P>
<P>
"We've been through the war with a lot of these teams," <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Coronado, picked to finished last in the 10-team 3-A Metro Conference, finished 
a surprising fourth. 
</P>
<P>
But Coronado Coach <PERSON>Bob Stanton</PERSON> knows what kind of competition his team will 
face. "Christian is going to be tough," <PERSON>Stanton</PERSON> said. "We have to get on 
(<PERSON>David</PERSON>) <PERSON>Jeremiah</PERSON> and work to break their press." 
</P>
<P>
Jeremiah is averaging 23 points and <PERSON>Darrell White</PERSON> 18. <PERSON>Tim Barkett</PERSON> has come on 
late in the season and has averaged 18 points in the last eight games. Coronado 
will rely on co-captains <PERSON>Jesse MacNeill</PERSON> (18-point average) and <PERSON>Derek Wastila</PERSON> 
(14). 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wright</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Christian</ORGANIZATION>'s success will depend on "executing our offense and 
playing with poise and intensity on defense." 
</P>
<P>
At <TIME>4:30</TIME>, <ORGANIZATION>Desert League</ORGANIZATION> rivals <LOCATION>Calipatria</LOCATION> (16-7) -- the defending Division V 
champion -- and Imperial (13-9) -- the <LOCATION>Desert League</LOCATION> champion -- meet for the 
sixth time this season, with <LOCATION>Calipatria</LOCATION> winning four out of the five played. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mike Moss</PERSON> is <LOCATION>Calipatria</LOCATION>'s only returning starter, but <PERSON>Javier Vega</PERSON> and <PERSON>Vince 
Coleman</PERSON>, who came off the bench last year, add experience. Fourth-seeded 
<LOCATION>Calipatria</LOCATION> knocked off top-ranked Bishop's to advance to the championship 
round. 
</P>
<P>
For Imperial, <PERSON>Brian Williams</PERSON> is the player to stop, but the Tigers are hurt by 
the absence of <PERSON>Fabian Diaz</PERSON>, out with a badly sprained ankle. 
</P>
<P>
In the girls' Division IV final, defending champion and top-ranked <LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> 
will play third-seeded Coronado at <TIME>6:30</TIME>, a rematch of last's year's 
championship, which <LOCATION>Holtville</LOCATION> won. 
</P>
<P>
In the <ORGANIZATION>Division V</ORGANIZATION> game at <TIME>2:30</TIME>, top-seeded <PERSON>Calvin Christian</PERSON> (23-1) will try to 
defeat second-seeded La Jolla Country Day (16-5) -- the defending Division V 
champion -- for the third time this season. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101290-0056 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 291281 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 12, 1990, Friday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
612 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TOLL TO REMAIN FOR CORONADO BRIDGE UNTIL '95; 
</P>
<P>
TRANSPORTATION: STATE DECISION IS A VICTORY FOR CORONADO, WHICH WANTS TOLL FEES 
TO HELP PAY FOR SOLUTIONS TO TRAFFIC PROBLEMS IN THE CITY. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PATRICK McDONNELL, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <MONEY>$1</MONEY> toll on the San Diego-Coronado Bay Bridge will remain in place until at 
least mid-1995, the <ORGANIZATION>California Transportation Commission</ORGANIZATION> decided <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, 
ending months of speculation about the future of the fee. 
</P>
<P>
In a meeting in <LOCATION>San Luis Obispo</LOCATION>, the commission voted 5-0 to retain the toll 
until <DATE>June, 1995</DATE>, and use the funds for improvements on the bridge and along 
<ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s congested roadways, said <PERSON>Mariana Mejia</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman. The 
commission sets state transportation policy. 
</P>
<P>
The toll question will be reviewed again in <DATE>January, 1995</DATE>, <PERSON>Mejia</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The toll already has provided sufficient funds to cover the construction costs 
of the 21-year-old bridge, one of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>'s most recognizable landmarks, 
which stretches from near downtown across <LOCATION>San Diego Bay</LOCATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Some critics had wanted the toll scrapped, contending that it was too 
burdensome. 
</P>
<P>
But Coronado city officials and others feared that rescinding the toll would 
prompt more people to use the bridge, thus worsening the city's already 
substantial traffic problem. Pro-toll advocates backed retaining the fee and 
using the proceeds for road and bridge improvements -- the precise option 
chosen <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by the state commission. 
</P>
<P>
The tolls are expected to generate <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> in gross revenues between now 
and <DATE>1995</DATE>, <PERSON>Mejia</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"Mostly we hope it (the toll) will help with some of the traffic issues," said 
<PERSON>Jacqueline Wilson</PERSON>, deputy Coronado city clerk. "Traffic seems to be Coronado's 
biggest problem. What are we going to do with all those cars on the roads?" 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Barrio Logan</LOCATION>, the low-income <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> community most impacted by the 
bridge, many favor using toll funds for improvements in their inner-city 
neighborhood. 
</P>
<P>
Councilman <PERSON>Bob Filner</PERSON>, whose district includes <PERSON>Barrio Logan</PERSON>, said he planned to 
approach state officials about directing toll monies toward community projects. 
Among the possible options: Use the funds to help alleviate bridge-related 
neighborhood traffic congestion or for the upkeep and expansion of the 
acclaimed murals painted on the bridge columns in <LOCATION>Chicano Park</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"If they're going to keep the toll, we should pay what's due to a community 
that has has suffered from it," <PERSON>Filner</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
To this day, construction of the bridge is remembered bitterly by many in 
<LOCATION>Barrio Logan</LOCATION>, who say that the structure split one of southern <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s 
oldest Chicano communities, displacing many families. Chicano Park was born 
amid that controversy, symbolizing to many the determination of area residents 
to fight back after the devastation inflicted by the bridge construction. 
</P>
<P>
The decision is a victory for <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> Mayor <PERSON>Mary Herron</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado City 
Council</ORGANIZATION>, who have gone on record in support of a continued toll. Mayor <PERSON>Herron</PERSON> 
testified <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in favor of retaining the fee, as did councilman <PERSON>Michel 
Napolitano</PERSON>, according to <PERSON>Mejia</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman. 
</P>
<P>
The elegant, 2.23-mile long, 246-feet high bridge, which was was officially 
opened on <DATE>Aug. 2, 1969</DATE>, was financed through the sale of almost <MONEY>$48 million</MONEY> in 
construction bonds. The accumulated tolls paid off the bond bill by <DATE>1986</DATE>, some 
17 years ahead of schedule. 
</P>
<P>
The <MONEY>$1</MONEY> bridge toll is charged only to westbound vehicles. (The toll had been 
<MONEY>$1.20</MONEY> until it was reduced in <DATE>1988</DATE>.) Car-pool vehicles are exempt. Commuters 
may purchase books of 20 tickets for <MONEY>$12</MONEY>, or <MONEY>60 cents</MONEY> per round trip. 
</P>
<P>
Bridge traffic has been increasing by <PERCENT>2%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> per year, according to <ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION>. 
The numbers of vehicles using the bridge in both directions rose from almost 
50,000 during the 1984-85 fiscal year to 62,000 during the 1988-89 fiscal year, 
the most recent year for which data are available, <ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111289-0096 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 133682 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 12, 1989, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
316 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CORONADO GANG 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
I am writing in response to an article titled "Coronado Question: Does It Have 
a Gang Problem?" (<DATE>Oct. 19</DATE>) I find the so-called Coronado White Boys a revolting 
and ill-humored joke. Any form of respect (or humor, for that matter) cannot be 
dug up for these kids who make a feeble attempt at imitating those serious 
gangs on the mainland. Just calling themselves a "gang" already has invited a 
lot of dispute. Inevitably, so will it invite the serious gangs of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Such easy prey as a group of <ORGANIZATION>Coronado White Boys</ORGANIZATION> would be a pleasure for those 
gangs that dispute violently over colors and territory. Besides, any gang could 
just hop in a car with two or more members, and drive over the bay for free. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Bay Bridge</ORGANIZATION> begins in the <LOCATION>Barrio Logan</LOCATION> area of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, a prime 
hangout for local gangs. It would only be a five- to 10-minute commute over to 
the island. 
</P>
<P>
I suggest that these white boys be exposed to what gangs really are all about. 
I suggest that they be taken away from their secure and untouched homes in 
<LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION> and placed in the middle of a gang-infested neighborhood. I'd like to 
see their shocked faces as an innocent 10-year-old boy gets hit by gang 
cross-fire at a public park. I'd like them to attend a high school where they 
couldn't wear a certain color for fear of being terrorized by a gang. Would 
these teens still mock and imitate a gang with humorous intent after seeing the 
corruption and evil of a typical <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> gang? Would they still have the 
nerve to form a gang in their community after seeing the fear gangs create in 
communities? 
</P>
<P>
And the answer to the Coronado question? Yes, <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> has a gang problem. If 
these teens succeeded in forming a gang, with innocent intentions or not, then 
<ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> should be shuddering with fear of the possibility that it too can be 
infected with the widespread disease of gangs. 
</P>
<P>
ERNESTO ANDRADE 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Letter to the Editor 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022589-0031 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 23123 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 25, 1989, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 9B; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
373 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CORONADO GIRLS RALLY, REACH DIVISION IV FINAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Coronado advanced to the final of the section Division IV girls' basketball 
playoffs with a 39-38 victory over <LOCATION>Christian</LOCATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Granite Hills High 
School</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Coronado will play the winner of tonight's Mountain Empire-Holtville game for 
the title. 
</P>
<P>
Christian (11-11) led, 26-13, at halftime. 
</P>
<P>
"It's exciting going to the finals," Coronado Coach <PERSON>Ernie Dickerson</PERSON> said. "I 
wasn't especially pleased with our play. We fought back at the end and made 
it." 
</P>
<P>
The only time Coronado (13-12) led was with 7 seconds left, after a basket by 
<PERSON>Ijnanya Roberts</PERSON>. <PERSON>Julie Lochte</PERSON> scored 20 points for <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Our press worked well the first half but they beat us on the boards. It was 
the second shot off of their rebounding that beat us tonight," Christian Coach 
<PERSON>Rod Bell</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Erika Jonte</PERSON> scored 18 points for Christian and <PERSON>Stacy Patsko</PERSON> had 11 rebounds. 
</P>
<P>
Division I quarterfinals 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> 65, <LOCATION>Bonita Vista</LOCATION> 45 -- <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> (19-9) jumped to 17-4 <DATE>first-quarter</DATE> lead en 
route to a 65-45 victory over <LOCATION>Bonita Vista</LOCATION> (21-6). The key to <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION>'s victory, 
Coach <PERSON>Jay Trousdale</PERSON> said, was the man-to-man pressure defense that forced 27 
turnovers. <PERSON>Laura Nugent</PERSON> led <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> with nine rebounds and seven blocked shots. 
</P>
<P>
The Titans shot <PERCENT>54%</PERCENT> from the field, led by <PERSON>Christy Fortney</PERSON> (19 points) and Dawn 
Gigstad (15). Torril Purvis scored 16 points and <PERSON>Colleen Gannon</PERSON> added 15 for 
<ORGANIZATION>Bonita Vista</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Division II quarterfinals 
</P>
<P>
Mission Bay 53, <LOCATION>Torrey Pines</LOCATION> 48 -- Trailing, 14-8, after the <DATE>first quarter</DATE>, 
Mission Bay rallied to outscore visiting <LOCATION>Torrey Pines</LOCATION>, 16-2, in the second and 
then held on for the victory. <PERSON>Cristina Willis</PERSON> scored 23 points, and <PERSON>Bonnie 
Martin</PERSON> added 15 for Mission Bay (20-7). Torrey Pines (16-10) tied the game with 
3 minutes remaining, but <LOCATION>Mission Bay</LOCATION> again pulled away. Tiffany Booth led 
<LOCATION>Torrey Pines</LOCATION> with 19 points. 
</P>
<P>
Oceanside 49, Castle Park 42 -- Castle Park led by seven with just over 3 
minutes to play, but multiple turnovers down the stretch held the Trojans to 
just one more point, while <LOCATION>Oceanside</LOCATION> rallied for 14 points to advance. 
</P>
<P>
In the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>, <PERSON>Tonya Lee</PERSON> scored six of her 17 points, and <PERSON>Keche Fowlkes</PERSON> 
six of her 10 for <LOCATION>Oceanside</LOCATION> (20-8). Mildred <ORGANIZATION>Conston</ORGANIZATION> added 11 points and 15 
rebounds. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Christina Murguia</PERSON> had 21 points and 26 rebounds. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032890-0026 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 195822 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 28, 1990, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 4; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
158 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO COUNTY DIGEST: CORONADO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Coronado police pursued two car thieves across the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Bridge</ORGANIZATION> and into the 
streets of <LOCATION>Logan Heights</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Police got the car, but the thieves got away. 
</P>
<P>
Witnesses told police that they saw a car being stolen near Star Park Circle 
and <LOCATION>Loma Avenue</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION> about <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>, officials said. 
</P>
<P>
A patrol car and unmarked police car spotted the stolen car as it was going 
through the bridge toll plaza and followed it to the Crosby Street exit in 
<LOCATION>Logan Heights</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
According to a press release issued by <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Police</ORGANIZATION> Chief <PERSON>Jerry Boyd</PERSON>, the 
officers chased the car through "several side streets and alleys." The car 
finally hit a tree in the <DATE>2100</DATE> block of <LOCATION>Newtown Avenue</LOCATION>. The two men in the car 
ran away, and police impounded the vehicle. A stereo was stolen from the car. 
</P>
<P>
Witnesses who saw the two running said one had a handgun and may have also cut 
his head in the crash. The second man was bitten by a dog as he jumped over a 
fence. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110889-0003 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 131573 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 8, 1989, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
608 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CORONADO COOL TO PROPOSAL THAT IT TAKE OVER TROUBLED IMPERIAL BEACH; 
</P>
<P>
BROKE: MAYOR OF NEARLY BANKRUPT CITY GETS LITTLE ENCOURAGEMENT IN VISIT TO 
RICHER NEIGHBOR. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By H.G. REZA, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Coronado Mayor <PERSON>Mary Herron</PERSON> reacted coolly <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to an idea by Imperial Beach 
Mayor <PERSON>Henry Smith</PERSON> that <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> take over nearly bankrupt <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Beach</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It is time for us to seriously investigate our future options. One of the 
options is the city of Coronado," <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said in a letter he read to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Coronado City Council</ORGANIZATION>. "All that I would like to do today is to begin the 
process of our staff looking at the city of Coronado and assessing whether it 
is a viable option to consider our consolidation with your city." 
</P>
<P>
Imperial Beach officials have warned that the city will not be able to pay its 
bills in <DATE>January</DATE>, unless new revenue sources are found. To that end, a measure 
to raise <MONEY>$450,000</MONEY> annually with a <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> tax on each utility bill was put to 
voters, but was defeated, <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
But even that wouldn't have guaranteed financial viability for the ailing beach 
town, <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said, and officials would still seek to merge with <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
If Imperial Beach goes bankrupt, it might be forced to disincorporate, thereby 
coming under county control. <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> have also discussed 
consolidating with <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Herron</PERSON> made it clear that Coronado officials are not enthusiastic 
about annexing <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Beach</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"We would feel very cautious," <PERSON>Herron</PERSON> said. "Coronado has worked long and hard 
to be where we are. It may be more of an undertaking than we can envision." 
</P>
<P>
Imperial Beach, a city of about 25,000 residents, is the only beach city in the 
county that has not developed its beachfront. Many of its residents are 
apartment dwellers, and it has a limited tax base. For almost a decade, the 
city was forced to dip into its reserves to continue providing services, and 
the reserve is now exhausted. 
</P>
<P>
In contrast, <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>, with its upper-middle-class community, has long 
cherished its exclusiveness and is well-known for the many <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> admirals who 
have retired there. The average cost of a home is <MONEY>$406,000</MONEY> in <LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION>, which 
has a population of about 20,000; the average cost of a home is <MONEY>$174,000</MONEY> in 
<LOCATION>Imperial Beach</LOCATION>. The two cities are joined by the Silver Strand. 
</P>
<P>
Herron expressed concern that <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s resources would be strained if it were 
required to provide services such as police and fire protection to <LOCATION>Imperial 
Beach</LOCATION>, which is served by the sheriff and has a tiny fire department. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't know what the outcome will be. But no mayor will want to be faced with 
the condition you find yourself in," <PERSON>Herron</PERSON> said to <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> requested that <PERSON>Herron</PERSON> allow <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s city manager to meet with 
<ORGANIZATION>Imperial Beach</ORGANIZATION>'s city manager to discuss the proposed merger, <PERSON>Herron</PERSON> did not 
make a commitment to the talks. 
</P>
<P>
"They're not going to jump into this, are they? All I ask for is exactly what 
the letter said," <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said after his brief appearance before the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado 
City Council</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In an interview with The Times last month, <ORGANIZATION>Coronado City</ORGANIZATION> Manager <PERSON>Homer Bludau</PERSON> 
said there is no incentive for <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> to consolidate with <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Beach</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Diego City</LOCATION> Manager <PERSON>John Lockwood</PERSON> said that <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> city officials would 
be willing to discuss consolidation with Imperial Beach, but he added that 
there were no immediate plans by <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to annex <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Beach</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Diego County</LOCATION> Supervisor <PERSON>Brian Bilbray</PERSON> has argued that the best alternative 
available to <LOCATION>Imperial Beach</LOCATION> is to consolidate with the county. <PERSON>Bilbray</PERSON>, a 
former <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Beach</ORGANIZATION> mayor, said the county would become <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Beach</ORGANIZATION>'s 
trustee for three years, then voters would have an opportunity to vote on 
incorporation again. 
</P>
<P>
However, <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> and the majority of the <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Beach City Council</ORGANIZATION> favor 
consolidating with either Coronado or <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102090-0065 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 295201 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 20, 1990, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
577 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CITY URGED TO USE CORONADO BRIDGE TOLLS FOR BARRIO LOGAN PROJECTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PATRICK McDONNELL, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> city officials were asked <DATE>Friday</DATE> to examine ways to use tolls from 
the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Bridge</ORGANIZATION> to improve <PERSON>Barrio Logan</PERSON>, the historic Chicano neighborhood 
that was devastated by bridge and highway construction two decades ago. 
</P>
<P>
Last week, the <ORGANIZATION>California Transportation Commission</ORGANIZATION> decided to retain the <MONEY>$1</MONEY> 
round-trip toll until at least mid-1995, but authorities earmarked the 
estimated <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> in tolls until mid-1995 for bridge upkeep and for traffic 
projects along bridge approaches in <LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION>. The tolls have already paid for 
bridge construction costs. 
</P>
<P>
By statute, the toll funds -- which are state, not city revenues -- can now 
only be used for maintenance, rehabilitation and traffic improvements on the 
bridge and its approaches, said <PERSON>Mariana Mejia</PERSON>, a spokeswoman in <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> with 
</P>
<P>
Whether that requirement can be met and the funds directed toward 
bridge-related projects in <LOCATION>Barrio Logan</LOCATION> remains an open question. "They (<LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION> officials) will have to work around it creatively," said <PERSON>Mejia</PERSON>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <PERSON>Councilman Bob Filner</PERSON> formally requested that City Manager <PERSON>John 
Lockwood</PERSON> investigate the use of tolls for a variety of Barrio Logan projects, 
including traffic improvements on city streets leading to the bridge and the 
upkeep and expansion of <LOCATION>Chicano Park</LOCATION>. The park, which is situated in the shadow 
of the bridge's eastern terminus, features widely acclaimed murals depicting 
Chicano, indigenous American and other themes emblazoned on the bridge's 
concrete support pillars. 
</P>
<P>
"Both the construction of the bridge and the ongoing operations have had a 
really negative impact on the community of <LOCATION>Barrio Logan</LOCATION>, and there ought to be 
some recognition of that impact," said <PERSON>Filner</PERSON>, whose district includes the 
barrio, a low-income area. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Barrio Logan</LOCATION>, where the bridge remains a sore point and where bridge traffic 
contributes to traffic bottlenecks, a still-nascent movement has emerged 
seeking to redirect some of the toll funds to community needs, particularly the 
care of <ORGANIZATION>Chicano Park</ORGANIZATION> and its much-lauded murals. Some of the murals are 
deteriorating and badly in need of care, activists say. There have also been 
few additions in recent years, although the mural project is considered ongoing 
and open to expansion. 
</P>
<P>
"I think we should get our fair share," said <PERSON>Salvador Roberto Torres</PERSON>, a 
neighborhood resident, artist and assistant professor at <ORGANIZATION>San Diego State 
University</ORGANIZATION> who has long been active in promoting the park murals. 
"Traditionally, we have been the stepchild in this whole drama of events that 
has unfolded and impacted our community." 
</P>
<P>
The bridge opened in <DATE>August, 1969</DATE>. Its erection, along with the somewhat 
earlier construction of the Interstate 5 freeway, displaced thousands of 
residents of <LOCATION>Barrio Logan</LOCATION>, one of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s oldest Chicano communities. 
Neighborhood outrage over the displacements and a perceived city neglect of the 
area sparked a series of events and confrontations that led directly to the 
founding of <LOCATION>Chicano Park</LOCATION> and the painting of the murals. 
</P>
<P>
In <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>, Mayor <PERSON>Mary Herron</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that she expects no objection from 
her constituents if bridge toll revenues are redirected to improvements in 
<LOCATION>Barrio Logan</LOCATION>. However, she noted that the city could face difficulty in 
complying with the state guidelines restricting the use of toll money. 
</P>
<P>
"I think there would be a pretty stiff legal battle," Mayor <PERSON>Herron</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030789-0118 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 27704 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 7, 1989, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 6; Column 4; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
365 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE PREPS; 
</P>
<P>
SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA BASKETBALL REGIONALS; 
</P>
<P>
DIVISION IV BOYS; 
</P>
<P>
WHITTIER CHRISTIAN TO PLAY SAN DIEGO CORONADO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BARBIE LUDOVISE, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Whittier Christian High School</ORGANIZATION>, after winning the Southern Section 2-AA 
basketball championship <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, enters the <ORGANIZATION>Southern California Regionals</ORGANIZATION> 
today as the third-seeded team in Division IV. 
</P>
<P>
Whittier Christian (22-6) will play <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Coronado (11-14) at <ORGANIZATION>La Habra High 
School</ORGANIZATION> in a first-round game tonight at <TIME>7:30</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
Whittier Christian, led by 6-foot-7 center <PERSON>Scott Ferguson</PERSON> (19 points and 11 
rebounds a game) and 6-4 forward <PERSON>Paul McKinley</PERSON> (21 points, 9 rebounds), may not 
have too great a challenge in <LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION>, the only team in the division playoffs 
with a losing record. <PERSON>Derek Wastila</PERSON>, a 6-5 junior center, leads Coronado with 
14 points a game. 
</P>
<P>
Wastila is supported by 5-6 guard <PERSON>Tim DeWitt</PERSON>, 6-3 forward <PERSON>Jesse MacNeill</PERSON> and 
6-2 guard <PERSON>Tom Mitchell</PERSON>, who was the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Section player of the year in 
water polo last fall. 
</P>
<P>
"When you're facing these unknown teams, you are always a little hesitant in 
what to say to the kids," Whittier Christian Coach <PERSON>Bob Brown</PERSON> said. "But I feel 
good. I feel we got a real good seeding for the first round." 
</P>
<P>
In other Division IV play: 
</P>
<P>
Orange Lutheran (23-4) vs. El Cajon Christian (14-11) at Granite Hills High: 
Orange Lutheran, which defeated <ORGANIZATION>Whittier Christian</ORGANIZATION> twice en route to the 
Olympic League title this season, qualified for the regionals as an at-large 
entry after losing, 78-54, to 2-A champion <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Orange Lutheran, coming off its worse performance of the season <DATE>Saturday</DATE> when 
it shot just <PERCENT>32%</PERCENT> from the field after averaging <PERCENT>55%</PERCENT> all season, will meet a 
good shooting team. 
</P>
<P>
 <ORGANIZATION>El Cajon Christian</ORGANIZATION>, which defeated <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>, 70-60, <DATE>Saturday</DATE> for the section 
Division IV title, is especially capable at the free throw line. Saturday it 
converted 21 of 22 free throws. 
</P>
<P>
Its top player, 6-1 guard <PERSON>David Jeremiah</PERSON>, is a three-year starter who averages 
21.6 points. In one game this season, he made 10 three-point shots. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Darrell White</PERSON>, a 6-5 senior forward, averages 20 points for <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>. Other 
starters are 6-3 forward <PERSON>Tim Barkett</PERSON>, 6-foot junior guard <PERSON>Brad Fox</PERSON> and 6-10, 
215-pound center <PERSON>Dan Tate</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Tate, though intimidating in size, rarely scores in double figures. He scored 
just two points in <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s victory. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030889-0033 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 27862 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 8, 1989, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 4; Column 4; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
189 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
KEITH EDGES WALKER TO WIN CORONADO VOTE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Susan Keith</PERSON>, chairwoman of the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Planning Commission</ORGANIZATION>, appeared to have 
won a narrow victory <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> over three other candidates in a race for a 
vacant <ORGANIZATION>Coronado City Council</ORGANIZATION> seat, according to unofficial results released by 
the <LOCATION>San Diego County</LOCATION> registrar of voters. 
</P>
<P>
With <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> of the votes counted, <PERSON>Keith</PERSON> led <PERSON>Greg Walker</PERSON>, a jewelry store owner, 
by 29 votes, or 2,217 to 2,188. However, an official at the registrar's office 
said 27 absentee and 14 provisional ballots remained to be counted. A 
provisional ballot is one that needs to be validated by making sure that a 
voter is properly registered. 
</P>
<P>
Two other candidates, <PERSON>Donald Zub</PERSON>, a former <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> SEAL and construction worker, 
and <LOCATION>Louis</LOCATION> de Beer, an engineer and computer consultant, trailed badly with 172 
and 153 votes, respectively. 
</P>
<P>
Keith is expected to fill the seat left vacant when Councilwoman <PERSON>Mary Herron</PERSON> 
was elected mayor in <DATE>November</DATE>. Herron defeated incumbent <PERSON>R.H. Dorman</PERSON>. Keith 
will serve for the remaining two years of <ORGANIZATION>Herron</ORGANIZATION>'s council term. 
</P>
<P>
The registrar's spokesman said <PERCENT>42.8%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s 11,190 registered voters 
turned out in the special election. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030390-0045 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 184031 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 3, 1990, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 13A; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
458 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BOYS' BASKETBALL DIVISION IV; 
</P>
<P>
CORONADO TITLE DEFEATS IMPERIAL, STEREOTYPE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DON PATTERSON 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Hey, all you water polo and tennis players, listen up. The Coronado boys' 
basketball team won the Division IV <LOCATION>San Diego Section</LOCATION> championship <DATE>Friday</DATE> with 
a 63-53 victory over Imperial at <LOCATION>Golden Hall</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Nyah-nyah nyah nyah-nyah nyah. 
</P>
<P>
"We're stereotyped as a tennis and water polo school," said 6-foot-3 center 
<PERSON>Derek Wastila</PERSON>, who scored 19 points. "Little do they know we have some talent 
out here." 
</P>
<P>
Enough, in fact, to win the school's first section basketball championship. 
This team also won <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s first league championship since <DATE>1963</DATE>, finishing 
atop the newly formed <ORGANIZATION>City Harbor League</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"All they hear is tennis and water polo," <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Coach</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>Bob Stanton</PERSON> said. "But 
we've beaten some pretty good teams this year. This wasn't a fluke." 
</P>
<P>
Still, people have been telling guard <PERSON>Paul Carter</PERSON> for years that he should 
transfer to a real basketball school. He didn't listen. 
</P>
<P>
"I stuck it out for four years," he said. "And I'm pretty satisfied with my 
career here." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Carter</PERSON> ended it with an exclamation point, scoring nine points and assisting 
his teammates on a rather amazing accomplishment in the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>, when 
Coronado (19-8) outscored Imperial 18-2. Imperial, which used a balanced 
offense to build a 33-29 halftime lead, managed only a pair of free throws in 
the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>. Forward <PERSON>Brian Williams</PERSON>' half-court prayer at the conclusion 
of the period, which bounced around the rim and out, was the closest thing 
Imperial had to a field goal. 
</P>
<P>
"I think their size and strength wore us down a little," Imperial Coach <PERSON>Kerry 
Legarra</PERSON> said. "We just quit moving and maybe that was because of fatigue." 
</P>
<P>
If Imperial (16-8) was tired, it wasn't extinct. Trailing, 47-35, at the end of 
the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Tigers</ORGANIZATION> trimmed <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s lead to eight with less than 
three minutes remaining. Then, when Imperial forward <PERSON>Erik Mellas</PERSON> drove for a 
layup, Wastila swatted <PERSON>Mellas</PERSON>' shot halfway to <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> wound 
up with a layup on the other end. 
</P>
<P>
"I do tend to feast on the smaller teams," <PERSON>Wastila</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
A basket and three free throws down the stretch by forward <PERSON>Adam Smith</PERSON>, who 
scored 19 points to share game-high honors with <LOCATION>Wastila</LOCATION>, helped preserve the 
victory, <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s second over Imperial this season. 
</P>
<P>
One key to this victory was <PERSON>Stanton</PERSON>'s decision to change the defense in the 
<DATE>third quarter</DATE> from a box-and-one, designed to shut down forward/center <PERSON>Brian 
Williams</PERSON>, to a two-three zone. Williams managed just nine points, and the 
defensive switch threw Imperial's offense out of kilter. 
</P>
<P>
"A lot of their shots came easy," <PERSON>Legarra</PERSON> said. "And a lot of ours came very, 
very hard." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Legarra</PERSON> wasn't completely dissatisfied. 
</P>
<P>
"How many teams," he asked, "score two points in one quarter and are still in 
the ball game?" 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Paul Carter eluded Eddie Johnston here, helped ignite 18-2 third quarter 
for Coronado. SEAN M. HAFFEY / For The Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121090-0076 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 320243 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 10, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
979 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CORONADO'S BID TO BAR TOUR BUSES GETS STRANDED ON THE BEACH 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY WALLACE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CORONADO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
If diesel smoke was all that tour buses spewed, <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> residents might 
consider backing down. It's the annoying patter that they say they're sick to 
death of -- the running commentary, blared over the buses' public address 
systems, lecturing paying passengers about one of <LOCATION>San Diego County</LOCATION>'s most 
exclusive communities. 
</P>
<P>
"They slow down and they say, 'Now look. This is where all the rich folks live. 
Well, now this is where the Duchess of <LOCATION>Windsor</LOCATION> lived. Now you see in the 
driveway the Jaguars or the Mercedeses or the BMWs,' " said <PERSON>Doris Pray</PERSON>, a 
grandmother whose 27 years in Coronado have made her an expert on tour bus 
prattle. 
</P>
<P>
Such gawking is harassment, Pray and other Coronadans say. And these days -- at 
least since <DATE>September</DATE>, when the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado City Council</ORGANIZATION> passed an ordinance to 
bar tour buses from most streets except state highways -- it is against the 
law. At least, technically. 
</P>
<P>
Other cities, like <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION>, for example, have laws limiting tour bus 
routes. But <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s attempt has a peculiar wrinkle. 
</P>
<P>
The state <ORGANIZATION>Coastal Commission</ORGANIZATION> is concerned that in limiting tour bus routes the 
city also has inadvertently limited coastal access in violation of the state 
Coastal Act. Until a ruling is obtained on that question, the <ORGANIZATION>Coastal 
Commission</ORGANIZATION> has stopped Coronado from enforcing its law. 
</P>
<P>
But Coastal Commissioner <PERSON>David Malcolm</PERSON> says he already has made up his mind. 
</P>
<P>
"You have a basically white community saying, Stay out!" said <PERSON>Malcolm</PERSON>, who has 
earned the enmity of some Coronadans by opposing several proposals he finds 
"exclusionary." Malcolm, who is also a councilman in the largely Latino city of 
<LOCATION>Chula Vista</LOCATION>, says the Coronado sensibility goes something like this: "God 
forbid someone from out of town and from a minority race would come into our 
city." 
</P>
<P>
Coronado's civic leaders deny that racism has tainted their policy-making. But 
they admit that ever since the tiny 6-square-mile island city seceded from <LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION> in <DATE>1891</DATE>, it has struggled to keep its distance from its larger mainland 
neighbor. Especially since <DATE>1969</DATE>, when the elegant 2.23-mile San Diego-Coronado 
Bay Bridge linked the two cities for the first time, residents have chafed at 
the resulting surge in traffic -- and, some say, crime -- on their orderly, 
tree-lined streets. 
</P>
<P>
In recent months, <PERSON>Malcolm</PERSON> says, city leaders seem to be working harder than 
ever to keep out-of-towners at bay. 
</P>
<P>
This <DATE>fall</DATE>, when the <ORGANIZATION>California Transportation Commission</ORGANIZATION> considered scrapping 
the <MONEY>$1</MONEY> toll on the <LOCATION>San Diego-Coronado Bay Bridge</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> Mayor <PERSON>Mary Herron</PERSON> 
successfully lobbied to extend the toll until <DATE>1995</DATE>. While it had more than met 
its original goal -- paying back nearly <MONEY>$48 million</MONEY> in construction bonds -- 
the toll had other merits, <PERSON>Herron</PERSON> argued. By discouraging sightseers, she said, 
it kept <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s traffic in check. 
</P>
<P>
Then the city came up with a plan to create residents-only decal parking zones 
on a section of shoreline near the <LOCATION>North Island Naval Air Station</LOCATION>. The city 
said it needed the zones because <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> employees' vehicles often block residents 
from parking near their homes. But <PERSON>Malcolm</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Coastal Commission</ORGANIZATION> Chairman 
<PERSON>Thomas W. Gwyn</PERSON> cried foul and are appealing the ordinance on the basis that it 
limits beach access. 
</P>
<P>
Then came the tour bus ordinance, which would keep most commercial buses from 
traveling the city's most scenic coastal routes. In addition, the ordinance 
would force buses that drop passengers at the area's biggest tourist 
attraction, the historic Hotel del Coronado, to travel five extra miles down 
the Silver Strand peninsula simply to turn around. 
</P>
<P>
Coronado is not the first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> city to try to regulate tour bus traffic. 
In <DATE>1976</DATE>, sick of being overrun by star-gazers, <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> banned commercial 
sightseeing vehicles weighing three tons or more from traveling on most 
residential streets. 
</P>
<P>
The ordinance, which withstood challenges in the <ORGANIZATION>state Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>, sought to 
eliminate what it called "all nature of nuisances . . . such as trespassing, 
knocking on doors, littering, trampling on shrubbery and flower beds, using the 
shrubbery for toilet purposes, making loud and raucous noises, removing items 
as souvenirs and generally disturbing the peace and privacy of the residents, 
most of whom are not celebrities." 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Malcolm</PERSON> heard that <PERSON>Coronado</PERSON> was going to follow suit, he says he could 
only wonder what would come next. "A wall around the city? A drawbridge?" 
</P>
<P>
"What gives Coronado the right to say people can't go up and down the 
waterfront?" he asked, rejecting as absurd the charge, leveled by some 
Coronadans, that he is a shill for the tour bus industry. 
</P>
<P>
Pray, who has made the anti-bus fight a personal crusade, says it is a matter 
of human decency. Given the buses' long history of wrongdoing, she said, 
something has to change. 
</P>
<P>
At a public hearing last week, tour bus operators said the ordinance will 
create an economic hardship, adding 15 minutes to their routes and forcing 
passengers to endure repetitive views. But when <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s mayor suggested to 
her constituents that they increase their chances of winning <ORGANIZATION>Coastal Commission</ORGANIZATION> 
approval by considering alternatives to the ordinance, 11 residents rose, one 
by one, to say no. 
</P>
<P>
For now, the buses continue to roll unrestricted through town, gushing 
well-rehearsed flackery as they go. Among the highlights: a church with <ORGANIZATION>Tiffany</ORGANIZATION> 
windows, the house where <PERSON>Wallace Simpson</PERSON> lived before she married the duke, and 
the spot where <PERSON>Marilyn Monroe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jack Lemmon</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tony Curtis</PERSON> filmed "Some Like It 
Hot" at the grand <ORGANIZATION>Hotel Del</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It was the inspiration for the <LOCATION>Emerald City</LOCATION> in the Wizard of Oz," said Old 
Town Trolley tour bus driver <PERSON>Midge Crockett</PERSON> as she turned off the highway, 
hurtled down a quiet residential street and parked at a shorefront bus stop 
that the ordinance would abolish. 
</P>
<P>
"And this," she said, "is the most beautiful beach in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, CORONADO, Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CORONADO (CA) -- ORDINANCES; TOURISM -- SAN DIEGO COUNTY; CALIFORNIA -- LAWS; 
COASTAL AREAS -- SAN DIEGO COUNTY; BUSES; NEIGHBORHOODS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA040689-0007 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 40163 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 6, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
227 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
'CORONADO COMPANY' FIGURE ARRESTED IN NEW DRUG CASE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Another member of a former drug-smuggling ring known as the "Coronado Company" 
has been arrested on new drug charges, authorities said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>John Edward Wade</PERSON>, 47, of <ORGANIZATION>Del Mar</ORGANIZATION> was arrested <DATE>Monday</DATE> in the <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> 
town of <LOCATION>Leggett</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego County Integrated Narcotic Task Force</ORGANIZATION> announced. 
He is the third former "Coronado Company" member to be arrested in the task 
force investigations since <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Wade was arrested on suspicion of conspiracy to import marijuana. He was 
described by authorities as an "alleged partner and financier" in a plan to 
smuggle 10 tons of marijuana into the country by boat. Agents seized about 
<MONEY>$55,000</MONEY> when <PERSON>Wade</PERSON> was taken into custody. 
</P>
<P>
Among the nine other people arrested in connection with the smuggling plot was 
<PERSON>Edward R. Otero</PERSON>, 34, of <ORGANIZATION>Del Mar</ORGANIZATION>, another member of the "Coronado Company," a 
drug-trafficking ring that so named because it had its start among classmates 
at <ORGANIZATION>Coronado High School</ORGANIZATION> in the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Otero was taken into custody <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Rockport</LOCATION>, along the <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> 
coast. Authorities said <PERSON>Otero</PERSON> was the leader of a group that had gone to 
<LOCATION>Rockport</LOCATION> to rendezvous with a boat off the coast. 
</P>
<P>
A third <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Company</ORGANIZATION> member, <PERSON>Robert Kent Lahodny</PERSON>, 39, of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, was 
arrested <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> by <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> agents in connection with an alleged plot 
to sell 11 pounds of cocaine. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA050290-0033 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 212661 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 2, 1990, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 5B; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
402 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HIGH SCHOOL ROUNDUP; 
</P>
<P>
CORONADO BEATS ST. AUGUSTINE, CLOSES ON FIRST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KIM Q. BERKSHIRE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>St. Augustine High</ORGANIZATION> is still in the driver's seat, but <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> just forced the 
driver to take a closer look in the rear-view mirror. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>City Harbor League</ORGANIZATION> teams were already familiar with one another before 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, having met twice in league and once in the Lion's Tournament, with <ORGANIZATION>St. 
Augustine</ORGANIZATION> winning twice. But Coronado evened the series, scoring three runs in 
the seventh inning to break a 3-3 tie and give the Islanders a clutch, 6-3 
victory that kept them in the league race. 
</P>
<P>
Coronado jumped to a 3-0 lead in the top of the first, then watched <LOCATION>St. 
Augustine</LOCATION>'s creep back into the game with single runs in the second, third and 
sixth. 
</P>
<P>
"I told them before the game that three (runs) wouldn't win it," <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Coach 
Ron Smock</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
By winning, <PERSON>Coronado</PERSON> (14-7-1, 6-3) bought some time in its attempt to catch <LOCATION>St. 
Augustine</LOCATION> (13-0, 7-2). There are three games left. 
</P>
<P>
"This gives us some momentum," <PERSON>Smock</PERSON> said. "This was a big win for us. We could 
have folded, but we hung in there." 
</P>
<P>
No one hung tighter than <ORGANIZATION>Smock</ORGANIZATION>'s son, <PERSON>Kyle</PERSON>, a freshman who had struck out twice 
and popped to second in his first three at-bats. With one out in the seventh, 
<ORGANIZATION>Smock</ORGANIZATION>, the first batter to face reliever <PERSON>George Inzunza</PERSON>, hit a ball hard to 
left field, and it took a Coronado drop for a double. <PERSON>Jason Fledderjohn</PERSON> was 
intentionally walked, and <PERSON>Joel Franklin</PERSON> hit a triple to right, scoring Smock 
and <ORGANIZATION>Fledderjohn</ORGANIZATION>. Franklin scored the final run on a wild pitch. 
</P>
<P>
"When the little guy can come in and get a double like that, that tells the 
other guys something," said <PERSON>Ron Smock</PERSON>, whose son is 5-feet-4. 
</P>
<P>
Mike (Buck) <PERSON>Bryant</PERSON> pitched 6 1/3 innings for the Saints and gave up three runs 
on five hits before <PERSON>Inzunza</PERSON>, who shut out <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>, 2-0, the last time they 
played, came in. 
</P>
<P>
"We got some clutch hitting. We didn't let up," said <PERSON>Fledderjohn</PERSON>, who pitched 
an eight-hitter, singled twice, walked twice and scored twice. 
</P>
<P>
Coronado's other league losses were to <PERSON>Marian Catholic</PERSON> and Clairemont, both 
teams they must meet again. 
</P>
<P>
"We can't panic," said <PERSON>Mike Stephenson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>St. Augustine</LOCATION> coach. "We just need to 
execute a little better." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>St. Augustine</ORGANIZATION> still has the enviable league-leading record, something 
<PERSON>Stephenson</PERSON> finds relief in. 
</P>
<P>
"I'd rather be in our position than theirs," he said. "We don't have to depend 
on anyone but ourselves, and they need help from someone else. We don't have to 
worry about that." KIM Q. BERKSHIRE 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, St. Augustine shortstop Eric Dent makes the tag to end unsuccessful 
steal attempt by Coronado's Paul Carter in the second inning. BRUCE K. HUFF / 
Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011890-0122 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 163623 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 18, 1990, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 11B; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
348 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAINTS WIN A GAME THEY NEED; 
</P>
<P>
HIGH SCHOOLS: THEY DOMINATE SHOWDOWN WITH CORONADO, 74-61, TO STAY IN HARBOR 
LEAGUE RACE. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LAURA PALMER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CORONADO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It was supposed to be a game matching equal talent, between two teams that were 
favorites to battle for the <ORGANIZATION>Harbor League</ORGANIZATION> boys' basketball title. 
</P>
<P>
But <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s game between Coronado and <LOCATION>St. Augustine</LOCATION> was instead a mismatch, 
and <ORGANIZATION>St. Augustine</ORGANIZATION> won, 74-61. 
</P>
<P>
"They are the best team in the league," <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Coach</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>Bob Stanton</PERSON> said. "Our 
kids underestimated them, and they beat us up out there." 
</P>
<P>
Coming off a loss to Christian last week, <LOCATION>St. Augustine</LOCATION> (1-1, 11-6) needed the 
victory to stay in the running for the league title. 
</P>
<P>
"This was a must-win situation for us," Coach <PERSON>Jeff Armstrong</PERSON> said. "You can't 
go down 0-2 in league and expect to win it. We talked about it all week. Now 
we're back in the hunt." 
</P>
<P>
Even though the victory was assured with a 10-point lead and a minute 
remaining, <ORGANIZATION>St. Augustine</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Bryan Cantwell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Paul Mossuto</PERSON> kept shooting and 
scoring until the final buzzer. Cantwell finished with season-high 31 points, 
14 in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>. Mossuto scored 19. 
</P>
<P>
"I have to stay intense all the time," <PERSON>Cantwell</PERSON> said. "We had three intense 
practices this week. We came in thinking we were the underdog, and <PERSON>Wastila</PERSON> was 
the man." 
</P>
<P>
The Saint' defense held <PERSON>Derek Wastila</PERSON>, who has been averaging 18.7 points a 
game, to seven. 
</P>
<P>
After a sluggish first five minutes, <LOCATION>St. Augustine</LOCATION> trailed, 12-10. But the 
Saints then turned it into a running game and five minutes later had a 27-16 
lead. 
</P>
<P>
"We wanted to create an up tempo and run against <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>," <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> said. "We 
went up by 10, then wanted to play a deliberate game with high-percentage 
scoring." 
</P>
<P>
Coronado (0-1, 10-7) trailed, 38-33, at halftime and never got closer than that 
in the <DATE>second half</DATE>. The Islanders had a number of opportunities, but missed 
shots from long range prevented them from challenging. 
</P>
<P>
"It wasn't their press that hurt us," <PERSON>Stanton</PERSON> said. "Our kids were trying too 
many outside shots. When we came down the middle of court and got inside, we 
were scoring, but the kids just weren't doing it enough." 
</P>
<P>
James Stark led Coronado with 19 points, <PERSON>Adam Smith</PERSON> scored 17 and <PERSON>Paul Carter</PERSON> 
scored 11. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Nobody's having much luck getting a handle on the ball as St. Augustine 
and Coronado scramble during Wednesday afternoon's game. VINCE COMPAGNONE / Los 
Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111890-0228 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 310174 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 18, 1990, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 22; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
253 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CORONADO WINS FOURTH WATER POLO TITLE IN ROW 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LAURA PALMER, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Coronado water polo team wasn't quite sure if its coach, <PERSON>Randy Burgess</PERSON>, 
would make it in time to see the Islanders play <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> for the 3-A Section title 
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
As it turned out, it didn't matter. 
</P>
<P>
Coronado (28-4) claimed its fourth consecutive Section title by defeating 
<LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION>, 14-9, at the <ORGANIZATION>Jewish Community Center</ORGANIZATION>. And <PERSON>Burgess</PERSON>, who did arrive 30 
minutes before the game, praised his team's play even though the Islanders had 
to play catchup a couple of times. 
</P>
<P>
"They played us tough, but I felt our kids weren't really focused on the game," 
<PERSON>Burgess</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
After a 3-3 <DATE>first-quarter</DATE> tie, <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> forced Coronado to play catchup in the 
<DATE>second quarter</DATE>. At halftime, the score was again tied, 5-5. 
</P>
<P>
In the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>, <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> (23-1) took an 8-6 lead. But with three minutes 
remaining in the quarter, <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> went on a scoring spree and led, 10-8, 
entering the fourth. 
</P>
<P>
"After it was 8-6 I thought we were in control of the game," <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Greg 
Ormsby</PERSON> said. "They just went on a rampage. They're a very balanced field and 
(they have) the best qoalie in the county (<PERSON>Jack Bowen</PERSON>)." 
</P>
<P>
Earlier in the day, <LOCATION>Valhalla</LOCATION> defeated USDHS, 17-10, to win the 2-A 
championship. 
</P>
<P>
In the 2-A game, USDHS tried, but couldn't stop <PERSON>Mike Nalu</PERSON>, who scored nine 
goals for <LOCATION>Valhalla</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Eric Nielsen</PERSON> added four for the Norsemen. USDHS was led by 
<PERSON>Doug Munz</PERSON>, who scored six goals. 
</P>
<P>
"We wanted to try to have two people on <PERSON>Mike</PERSON> when he gets the ball," USDHS 
Coach <PERSON>Dan Crane</PERSON> said. "He's so quick that he turns and make things happen." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121489-0157 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 148441 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 14, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 11A; Column 5; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
505 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HIGH SCHOOL BASKETBALL ROUNDUP; 
</P>
<P>
GONZALES POWERS HILLTOP IN VICTORY OVER MAR VISTA 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Carlos Gonzales</PERSON> scored 11 of his game-high 24 points in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>, and 
Hilltop scored the last nine points of the game to pull away from <LOCATION>Mar Vista</LOCATION>, 
69-56, in a <ORGANIZATION>Metro Conference</ORGANIZATION> opener <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at Hilltop. 
</P>
<P>
Gonzales, a 6-foot-1 senior transfer from <LOCATION>Sierra</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>, made 10 of 15 shots 
from the field, including two three-pointers. <PERSON>Chris White</PERSON> had eight points, 
eight rebounds and six assists for Hilltop (4-2, 1-0). <PERSON>Tim O'Neal</PERSON> led Mar Vista 
(0-4, 0-1) with 15 points. 
</P>
<P>
Hilltop led by three at the half, one at the end of three quarters and four 
with less than two minutes left before scoring nine in a row. 
</P>
<P>
In another <ORGANIZATION>Metro Conference</ORGANIZATION> game: 
</P>
<P>
Bonita Vista 82, <PERSON>Montgomery</PERSON> 52 -- <PERSON>Allen McNamee</PERSON> scored 19 to lead Bonita Vista 
(5-0, 1-0) over <PERSON>Montgomery</PERSON> (1-5, 0-1). Rope <PERSON>Perry</PERSON> added 15 points and <PERSON>Matt 
Gibbs</PERSON> 12 for the Barons. 
</P>
<P>
Nonleague 
</P>
<P>
Coronado 65, <LOCATION>Mt. Miguel</LOCATION> 60 -- Coronado trailed, 52-48, in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>, 
but rallied behind the scoring of <PERSON>Derek Wastilia</PERSON>, who had 10 of his game-high 
26 points in the final eight minutes. <PERSON>Paul Carter</PERSON> had 11 assists for <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> 
(6-2). <PERSON>Shannon Lafever</PERSON> scored 16 of his 21 points in the first half for Mt. 
Miguel (3-2). 
</P>
<P>
Mira <LOCATION>Mesa</LOCATION> 73, <ORGANIZATION>Grossmont</ORGANIZATION> 49 -- No. 10 <PERSON>Mira Mesa</PERSON> (4-3) outscored <LOCATION>Grossmont</LOCATION>, 21-2, 
in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Grossmont</ORGANIZATION> to take a 23-point halftime lead. <PERSON>Marc 
Ziegler</PERSON> scored 22 points, six coming on a variety of spectacular dunks, to lead 
the Marauders. <PERSON>Todd Cady</PERSON> had a game-high 24 points for <ORGANIZATION>Grossmont</ORGANIZATION> (4-2). 
</P>
<P>
Clairemont 113, <LOCATION>West Hills</LOCATION> 25 -- No Clairemont team had ever scored more than a 
100 points in a game before the Chieftains (2-4) met <LOCATION>West Hills</LOCATION>, which suited 
up only seven players because of the flu. Alex Love (23 points and a school 
record 17 assists) led six Clairemont players in double-figure scoring. <PERSON>Odis 
Ayers</PERSON> added 20 points, <PERSON>James Gerstenslager 16</PERSON>, <PERSON>Issac Wasserteil 16</PERSON>, <PERSON>Clarence 
Hunt</PERSON> 15 and <PERSON>Brian Sorenson</PERSON> 13. 
</P>
<P>
Lincoln 85, <ORGANIZATION>Central</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>El Centro</LOCATION>) 68 -- <PERSON>Darryl McMillan</PERSON> led No. 4 Lincoln with 23 
points, and <PERSON>Victor Dean</PERSON> added 22 in the Hornets annual game in <LOCATION>El Centro</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
La Jolla 68, <PERSON>Hoover</PERSON> 64 -- <PERSON>Justin Chaitin</PERSON> had 21 points to lead La Jolla. <PERSON>Roger 
Blake</PERSON> (16 points) and <PERSON>Alex Davis</PERSON> (14) led <LOCATION>Hoover</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Girls' basketball 
</P>
<P>
Mt. <LOCATION>Carmel</LOCATION> tournament 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Poway 75</LOCATION>, Madison 18 -- <PERSON>Dawn Gigstad</PERSON> had 14, <PERSON>Allison Brady</PERSON> 13 and <PERSON>Christy 
Fortney 12</PERSON> as the No. 2 Titans routed <PERSON>Madison</PERSON> in the first round.. 
</P>
<P>
Serra 52, La Jolla 37 -- <PERSON>Pam Ross</PERSON>, <PERSON>Loni Clark</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lynn Riordan</PERSON> each had 12 
points for Serra (4-2). 
</P>
<P>
Nonleague 
</P>
<P>
La Jolla Country Day 59, <LOCATION>Valhalla</LOCATION> 33 -- <PERSON>Isabel Schoepflin</PERSON> had 19 and <PERSON>Nancy 
Dickerson</PERSON> 12 for La Jolla Country Day (6-1). <LOCATION>Valhalla</LOCATION> fell to 0-3. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>University City 51</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Crawford</PERSON> 49 -- <PERSON>Tamika Edwards</PERSON> (game-high 19 points) made 
two free throws with less than 10 seconds left to pace the Centurions. 
Charlotte Kornik added 17 for <ORGANIZATION>University City</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Myra Knowles</PERSON> scored 13 for 
<ORGANIZATION>Crawford</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Helix 41, <PERSON>Patrick Henry 29</PERSON> -- <PERSON>Deisha Patterson</PERSON> had 15 points and <PERSON>Andrea 
McTrusty</PERSON> 12 for Helix (1-2). 
</P>
<P>
Coronado 71, <ORGANIZATION>Mtn</ORGANIZATION>. Empire 34 -- <PERSON>Donna Lukenbill</PERSON> scored 25 for Coronado (7-4). 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031489-0036 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 30584 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 14, 1989, Tuesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 8; Column 3; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
341 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HIGH SCHOOL BASEBALL ROUNDUP; 
</P>
<P>
SAN DIEGO HIGH SCORES 10 RUNS IN FIRST TO DEFEAT CORONADO, 16-3 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>San Diego High School</ORGANIZATION> baseball team wasn't fazed when a line drive double 
play in the first inning wasted a leadoff triple. The Cavers, who trailed by a 
run, went on to score 10 runs in the inning and routed visiting <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>, 16-3, 
<DATE>Monday</DATE> in pool play of the <ORGANIZATION>Grossmont Metro City</ORGANIZATION> tournament. 
</P>
<P>
San Diego (3-1) used six hits, four walks and three Coronado errors to send 14 
players to the plate in the first. <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> scored in each of the first five 
innings. The game was called after the fifth because of darkness. Coronado is 
2-2. 
</P>
<P>
Kian Sly had a two-run homer in the fourth and finished three for three with a 
triple and four RBIs. <PERSON>Josh Stepner</PERSON> went the distance for the victory, allowing 
three hits. 
</P>
<P>
In another tournament game: 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>El Cajon Valley 6</ORGANIZATION>, La Jolla Country Day 3 -- <PERSON>Fred Earnst</PERSON> went two for three 
with a double and an <ORGANIZATION>RBI</ORGANIZATION> triple and <PERSON>Donny Frost</PERSON> was two for three to lead <ORGANIZATION>El 
Cajon Valley</ORGANIZATION> (2-2). <PERSON>John Hayward</PERSON> (1-1) pitched six innings for the victory. 
</P>
<P>
Pirate tournament 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Fallbrook</LOCATION> 7, Grossmont 2 -- <PERSON>Wade Pearson</PERSON> hit a grand slam as <LOCATION>Fallbrook</LOCATION> won at 
home. Pearson was two for three for <LOCATION>Fallbrook</LOCATION> (3-1) and is nine for 14 with 
nine RBIs this season. <PERSON>David Michaelian</PERSON> was three for three with two RBIs for 
<LOCATION>Fallbrook</LOCATION>. Left-hander <PERSON>Mike Gainesborough</PERSON> (1-1) allowed two hits in 4 1/3 
innings for the victory. Grossmont is 3-1. 
</P>
<P>
Madison Warhawk tournament 
</P>
<P>
Sweetwater 4, Point Loma 2 -- Two errors led to a run and <PERSON>Juan Lopez</PERSON>'s 
sacrifice fly to right in the fifth inning broke a 2-2 tie for <LOCATION>Sweetwater</LOCATION> (4-2) 
at home. Reliever <PERSON>Issac Bruce</PERSON> (2-1) struck out six in five innings for the 
victory. Point Loma led, 2-0, with two runs in the top of the second, but 
<LOCATION>Sweetwater</LOCATION> rallied to tie the score in the bottom of the inning. 
</P>
<P>
Orange <PERSON>Glen 13</PERSON>, Mt. Miguel 5 -- <PERSON>Matt Taylor</PERSON> hit a three-run homer as <ORGANIZATION>Orange 
Glen</ORGANIZATION> trailed, 3-1, after two innings. Orange <PERSON>Glen</PERSON> (4-2), however, scored four 
runs in the third and five in the fifth for the victory at <ORGANIZATION>Mt. Miguel</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Scott 
Coleman</PERSON> and winning pitcher <PERSON>Jim Roby</PERSON> (1-1) had two-run singles in the fifth. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102289-0189 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 124351 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 22, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 49; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1071 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CORONADO AWAKENS -- MAYBE -- TO A NEW THREAT; 
</P>
<P>
GANGS: THE POLICE CHIEF SAYS THE CORONADO WHITE BOYS, OR CWBS, ARE THE ISLAND'S 
FIRST GANG, BUT SOME RESIDENTS -- AND CWB MEMBERS -- CONTEND IT'S ALL AN 
OVERREACTION. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY WALLACE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CORONADO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The police chief of <LOCATION>Coronado Island</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jerry Boyd</PERSON>, has no doubt that there are 
dangerous forces at work on his orderly, tree-lined streets across the bay from 
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. They are the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado White Boys</ORGANIZATION>, the island's first gang, he says, 
and their message is "Crips, get out of town." 
</P>
<P>
Coronado parents aren't so sure. Yes, some have begun hearing about a new club, 
the CWBs. And yes, it's been hard to ignore the new teen-age fashion trend: 
white baseball caps worn askew. But, don't kids always dress funny? 
</P>
<P>
Self-proclaimed CWBs, a bunch of skateboard-riding adolescents with a penchant 
for video games, say they are the victims of gang hysteria. They have no 
intention, they say, of doing harm to anyone, especially street gangs. They say 
they're being harassed by the law, and recently they have won support from the 
island newspaper. 
</P>
<P>
"Police Chief <PERSON>Jerry Boyd</PERSON> has taken what may have been a student's private joke 
and made it into something terrifying," an editorial proclaimed two weeks ago 
in the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Journal</ORGANIZATION>. "Minors need to be protected from themselves and 
outside influences. Let us hope they do not need to be protected from the 
police." 
</P>
<P>
Local residents, many of whom settled on the six square miles of manicured 
lawns to escape big-city problems, say the furor surrounding the White Boys is 
just not Coronado's style. The exclusive community enjoys the lowest crime rate 
in <LOCATION>San Diego County</LOCATION>. Its phone book is littered with retired admirals and 
colonels, and more of its high school students try out for water polo than for 
football. When school lets out on a sunny day, the fresh faces of local 
teen-agers look capable of nothing more ominous than under-tipping. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> says that, although most CWBs are law-abiding boys and girls looking 
for the social prestige of an in crowd, about eight members are out to protect 
their beach from outsiders -- and to use force if necessary. Lately, <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON>, a 
tough-talking veteran of the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> police force, has been warning parents 
that inner-city gangs may retaliate if they feel threatened by the CWBs. 
</P>
<P>
"They'll go looking for the ones who did them. If they can't find them, they'll 
go after anyone in a white baseball cap. Or worse yet, at noon, at lunchtime, 
when there's 150 kids out in the park, they'll open fire," <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> told 45 parents 
at a meeting last week. "People say that's sensationalism, but it happens 2 1/2 
miles from here every night of the week. It's just a matter of geography." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>CWB</ORGANIZATION> members who agreed to talk last week said <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> is grandstanding. 
</P>
<P>
"We're just a group of friends, not a gang," said <PERSON>Jamie Johnson</PERSON>, an articulate 
17-year-old who helped found the CWBs. "The first we heard of trying to reclaim 
the beach was what we read in the paper." 
</P>
<P>
Instead of a negative influence, he said, the group has helped some of its 
members get off drugs. The <ORGANIZATION>CWB</ORGANIZATION> name, he said, was a joke, coined as an 
alternative to what other students called them: Grits, or cigarette smokers. 
</P>
<P>
"White is a neutral color, and we were trying to be neutral," said <PERSON>Aaron 
Renshaw</PERSON>, a 15-year-old sophomore with a skateboard under his arm, who said the 
name was never intended to provoke minority gangs. "We have black kids and 
Mexicans in the group, too." 
</P>
<P>
The controversy began about a month ago, when <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> says he first heard from his 
officers that the CWBs were mixing with the 16 out-of-town gangs -- "bona fide, 
righteous gangs" -- that frequent the sparkling waters of <LOCATION>North Beach</LOCATION>. Then, a 
few <DATE>Saturdays ago</DATE>, <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> said, there was a "push-and-shove confrontation" 
between the CWBs and the <LOCATION>Crips</LOCATION>, a black street gang -- a confrontation CWBs 
deny. On several nights afterward, <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> claims, police identified cars of Crips 
cruising the beaches. 
</P>
<P>
"We'd ask, 'Hey, there's no party tonight. Why are you over here?' They said, 
'We're here looking for the white boys,' " <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
So <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> wrote a letter to the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Journal</ORGANIZATION> cautioning residents to keep an 
eye out for gang activity. The <ORGANIZATION>Coronado School District</ORGANIZATION> responded with both 
barrels: a gang expert was brought in to address a joint faculty meeting of the 
middle and high schools; parents of "known" CWBs received phone calls from 
school administrators; the superintendent of schools sent a letter to parents 
warning that <PERSON>Coronado</PERSON> gang activity was in the "formative" stage. 
</P>
<P>
Then came the weekly newspaper's edition two weeks ago, which suggested that 
<PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> was blowing things out of proportion. 
</P>
<P>
In a letter to the editor, <PERSON>Suzanne K. Larsen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Aaron Renshaw</PERSON>'s mother, urged her 
neighbors to "dispel the myth" surrounding the CWBs. Writing on behalf of 12 
CWBs, she made what many CWBs say is their first actual challenge: They invited 
the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Police Department</ORGANIZATION> to a friendly game of flag football. 
</P>
<P>
Boyd says that about 15 of his officers have agreed to play in early <DATE>November</DATE>. 
Around the same time, however, <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> is scheduling a gang symposium for parents 
and students. In addition to photos of <LOCATION>Crips</LOCATION>, Bloods, B-Down Boys and other 
gangs, <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> plans to exhibit a collection of weapons confiscated in <LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION> 
and to invite a special guest -- "a real gang member." 
</P>
<P>
"We're going to open some eyes. We'll have weapons on display. And I promise 
you, we didn't go across the bridge, seize them and bring them back over here," 
<PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Boyd says there are 50 CWBs, while the teen-agers put the number at less than 
20. 
</P>
<P>
Judging by attendance at last <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> parents' meeting, the public debate has 
only made some parents more curious -- and frightened. 
</P>
<P>
"If I have spray paint on my garage in a symbol, should I be worried?" one 
woman asked <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> after hearing about the placas, or graffiti symbols, that 
gangs often leave behind. 
</P>
<P>
A concerned father wondered if it would help to publish identifying information 
about the CWBs in community watch newsletters. "Like when you go to <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, 
(there are signs) that say, 'This is an alligator. Don't pet it.' " 
</P>
<P>
And another parent asked if the free car-pool lane on the <LOCATION>San Diego-Coronado 
Bay Toll Bridge</LOCATION> is to blame for increased gang activity. "I'd go back to paying 
if it means keeping people like that out of here," she said. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, the CWBs have responded to the outcry by taking off their white 
hats, and they are considering dropping their name. 
</P>
<P>
"If we break the mold, it's because they're trying to mold us into trendy 
little people who wear slacks and play tennis," said <PERSON>Brian Wentz</PERSON>, 16. "But we 
aren't naive. We know gangs have guns." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Police Chief Jerry Boyd addresses parents on threat posed by Coronado 
White Boys, a group that he contends is the island's first gang. BOB GRIESER / 
Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CORONADO (CA); GANGS -- SAN DIEGO COUNTY; CRIME -- SAN DIEGO COUNTY; CLUBS; 
HYSTERIA; TRENDS; FEAR 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122190-0111 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 325551 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 21, 1990, Friday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 8; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
690 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CORONADO'S SOMETIMES-CRITICIZED POLICE CHIEF RESIGNS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARK PLATTE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Nearly a decade ago, <PERSON>Jerry Boyd</PERSON> rode into Coronado a flamboyant figure, a 
lawman who nabbed suspects in high-speed chases, responded to late-night police 
calls and made many of his own arrests. 
</P>
<P>
Pretty unusual for the chief of police. 
</P>
<P>
His aggressiveness brought criticism, especially from the police union that was 
battling management in the mid-1980s. But <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> continued to pull on the uniform 
and steer a patrol car through town when he felt like it. 
</P>
<P>
Come <DATE>Jan. 11</DATE>, he will cross the San Diego-Coronado Bay Bridge and leave for a 
new job as chief of police in the <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> town of <ORGANIZATION>Martinez</ORGANIZATION>, in 
<LOCATION>Contra Costa County</LOCATION>. The two cities share similarities: population, department 
size and a low crime rate. 
</P>
<P>
Boyd, 44, said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> he believed he had accomplished just about all he could 
in upscale <LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION>, where, in the chief's 10-year tenure, two people have been 
slain. 
</P>
<P>
The most pressing order of the day is getting a new police station for the 
force of 43 uniformed officers and 17 civilian officers and staff members. 
Plans have been approved, and construction is scheduled to begin next <DATE>summer</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> got to town in <DATE>1981</DATE>, he already had spent eight years as a <LOCATION>Los 
Angeles County</LOCATION> sheriff's deputy and sergeant and six years as a lieutenant and 
captain for the <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Police Department</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
While captain, <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> said, he got into a run-in with <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>'s police chief, who 
had tried to destroy a police report on an <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> city councilwoman, which led 
to <ORGANIZATION>Boyd</ORGANIZATION> being assigned a 4 p.m.-to-midnight shift with no command 
responsibility. 
</P>
<P>
In <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> was branded a frustrated cop by police critics when, in his 
first year, he went undercover and helped rescue a 3-year-old girl from a 
kidnaper after negotiating for nearly an hour. The incident brought <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> 
fleeting fame in the national media. 
</P>
<P>
Some officers believed <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> would have better served the department sitting 
behind a desk, instead of leading the troops into battle, making his own 
arrests and even using physical force, by his own count, on at least a half a 
dozen occasions. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Nearly four years ago</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Police Officers Assn.</ORGANIZATION> asked for either the 
<LOCATION>San Diego County Sheriff</LOCATION>'s Department or the state attorney general to 
investigate allegations that <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> used excessive force and profanity during a 
<DATE>1987</DATE> arrest of a robbery suspect and that he improperly used police video 
equipment. 
</P>
<P>
Dist. Atty. <PERSON>Edwin Miller</PERSON> reviewed the matter, called the allegations 
"frivolous" and said no investigation was warranted. 
</P>
<P>
A television videotape of the suspect's arrest showed <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> holding a revolver 
and twice shouting, "Shut your . . . mouth" while police held the suspect. <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> 
said he was justified in using profanity at the time because he was dealing 
with "an ex-con." Boyd also defended punching the suspect in the stomach 
because the suspect was about to kick an officer. 
</P>
<P>
In an interview <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <PERSON>Boyd</PERSON> described the criticism in the mid-<DATE>'80s</DATE> as the 
low point of his career in <LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION> and said it was raised only because of 
labor disputes with the city's police union. Despite the second-guessing, he 
said he wouldn't change his tactics. 
</P>
<P>
"I will continue to put on a uniform and go out and ride in <LOCATION>Martinez</LOCATION>," he said. 
"I contend that the chief should have firsthand knowledge of what his people 
are doing. I need to know that city and I won't get to know it sitting behind a 
desk." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Martinez</PERSON> has a population of 30,332, and 45 sworn officers, compared to 
<ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION>'s 23,681 population and 43 sworn officers. 
</P>
<P>
According to <DATE>1989</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> statistics, <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> had no murders, eight rapes, 12 
robberies, 26 aggravated assaults, 166 burglaries, 551 thefts and 151 auto 
thefts. During the same time frame, <PERSON>Martinez</PERSON> had one murder, six rapes, 24 
robberies, 36 aggravated assaults, 336 burglaries, 912 thefts and 146 auto 
thefts. 
</P>
<P>
Detective <PERSON>Keith James</PERSON>, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Coronado Police Officers Assn.</ORGANIZATION>, said 
<PERSON>Boyd</PERSON>'s years in the city were positive. 
</P>
<P>
"On one hand, we're losing a good chief," <PERSON>James</PERSON> said. "On the other hand, we're 
excited by the change. But the chief's going to be missed. He's done a lot. 
He's just up for a different challenge now." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, CHIEF RESIGNS: Jerry Boyd, Coronado's sometimes controversial police 
chief, has resigned after holding the job for nearly a decade. Boyd is leaving 
to become chief of police in Martinez, a small city in Contra Costa County. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06182146 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06182146 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROBE; ORGANIZED-CRIME; PRISON; SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  When a member of a rival prison gang slipped up behind Gabriel Coronado two
years ago in the Santa Clara County Jail and slit his throat, the stoic gang
leader survived but refused to talk to prosecutors. No one was charged in the
attack.;    But after virtually the same thing happened on May 23, at the
hands of a different assailant, Coronado decided he'd had enough and told his
story to a grand jury.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GANGS CITED AS INMATE INDICTED  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Last week, the courts unsealed an indictment charging attempted murder and
related weapons violations against <PERSON>Leonel Jose Cano</PERSON>, 30, the reputed prison
gang member accused of attacking Coronado with a homemade weapon fashioned
from a toothbrush and the blades of jail-issued razors.;    "With this
indictment, the <LOCATION>D.A.</LOCATION>'s office wants to send a message to gang members that if
they commit a crime in <LOCATION>Santa Clara County</LOCATION>, it will be taken seriously. It will
be prosecuted," said Assistant District Attorney <PERSON>Jim Shore</PERSON>, who is handling
the case.;    <PERSON>Both Cano</PERSON>, who is reputed to be a member of the prison gang
<ORGANIZATION>Nuestra Familia</ORGANIZATION>, and Coronado -- an admitted leader of the Fresno-based prison
gang F-14 -- are in protective custody in the main county jail and could not
be reached for comment.;    But episodes such as the hit on Coronado were
predicted last <DATE>October</DATE> in a controversial memo from a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> parole
officer to officials of the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara County Department of Correction</ORGANIZATION>. The
memo warned that members of state prison gangs being held in the local jail
were recruiting county inmates, who are being taught to make weapons and run
errands for gang members.;    Capt. <PERSON>Roy Froom</PERSON>, who wrote the memo after
consulting with state parole gang officer <PERSON>E.J. Allen</PERSON>, said the situation in
<LOCATION>Santa Clara County</LOCATION> was not an emergency but would "certainly become violent"
if gang activity was not controlled.;    Froom blamed the problem on a county
policy that allows minimum-security state prisoners to be kept at the local
jail in exchange for money. County jail officials have said repeatedly there
is no serious problem with prison gangs in the jails.;    <LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION>, 30, was
first attacked in the <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Jail</LOCATION> in <DATE>February 1989.</DATE>;    He now
says a soldier of the rival gang, <ORGANIZATION>Nuestra Familia</ORGANIZATION>, carried out the assault.;  
 The two gangs have clashed since <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> and several others broke from
<ORGANIZATION>Nuestra Familia</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> and formed F-14, Shore said.;    He said the most
recent attack occurred about <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>May 23</DATE>, soon after <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> received
word that he would be moved to a different part of the jail to join a drug
abuse program he had hoped to enter.;    Shore said <PERSON>Coronado</PERSON> indicated to
<ORGANIZATION>Cano</ORGANIZATION>, who had befriended him in the jail, that he might be moved soon. Minutes
later, after talking to his wife on the telephone, <ORGANIZATION>Coronado</ORGANIZATION> walked to the
lower tier of his jail dorm.;    When Coronado reached the bottom step, Shore
said, Cano allegedly grabbed him around the mouth and chin. The F-14 leader
felt a long slash across the right side of his neck. Cano then allegedly
walked casually to the telephone and placed a call, the prosecutor said.;   
The makeshift weapon was later recovered from the scene.;    Coronado
initially told correction officers he injured himself falling against a hinge
of his cell door.;    But somewhere between <ORGANIZATION>Valley Medical Center</ORGANIZATION>, where
doctors closed his wound with 14 stitches, and his return to the <TIME>jail later
that night</TIME>, <PERSON>Gabriel Coronado</PERSON> decided he'd had enough. He told the authorities
he had something he wanted to say.;    Last week, <PERSON>Leonel Cano</PERSON> discovered what
it was.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JACK FISCHER, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910630  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  599  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday June 30, 1991
00182146,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021590-0122 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 176721 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 15, 1990, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 11B; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
397 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CHRISTIAN CELEBRATES CLARK MARK; 
</P>
<P>
HIGH SCHOOLS: THE NUMBERS ARE A LITTLE FUZZY, BUT IF BILL WALTON'S SEASON 
SCORING RECORD ISN'T OFFICIALLY GONE YET, IT ALMOST CERTAINLY WILL BE FRIDAY. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LAURA PALMER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
With 10 seconds remaining in the Christian High boys' basketball game at 
<LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, Christian's <PERSON>Tony Clark</PERSON> was taken out of the game, 
given a standing ovation and congratulated for breaking <PERSON>Bill Walton</PERSON>'s 
20-year-old section season scoring record. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Clark</PERSON> had made two free throws with 24 seconds left to bring his game total to 
36 points, which by most accounts had taken him past <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>'s 960 for a season. 
</P>
<P>
Following Christian's 66-50 victory, which tied Coronado for first place (at 
5-2) in the <ORGANIZATION>Harbor League</ORGANIZATION> with a game to play, the celebration of <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s 
accomplishment continued. 
</P>
<P>
Kids were asking him to sign their tennis shoes, pictures were being taken, and 
people were chanting "Tony, Tony." 
</P>
<P>
There's a slight catch, but one <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> should take care of easily in his final 
regular-season game against Clairemont <DATE>Friday</DATE>. In the statistics kept by 
Christian, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> had 925 entering the game, needing 36 to break <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>'s 
record. Statistics kept by <ORGANIZATION>The Times</ORGANIZATION> had him needing just 35 to break. But one 
other statistical source had him needing 37, saying that Christian had wrongly 
credited him with a basket not included in the home scorebook for a game at 
<LOCATION>Santana</LOCATION> way back on <DATE>Dec. 13</DATE>; the home book is official for record purposes. 
</P>
<P>
Whatever. Christian (12-10 overall) decided to celebrate <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s accomplishment 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, and the first few minutes of <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s game will almost certainly 
eliminate any doubt. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, who is averaging 44.1 points a game, had only scored 22 points in the 
first three quarters but added 14 in the fourth. 
</P>
<P>
"Coronado had to give up something," Christian Coach <PERSON>Randy Wright</PERSON> said. "When 
the score got spread out eight to 10 points, they had to play more straight up. 
When people play straight up, the worst he's done is 49 points." 
</P>
<P>
Coronado used a box-and-one defense, but when <PERSON>Adam Smith</PERSON> collected his fourth 
foul in the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> was able to take avantage of the situation. 
</P>
<P>
"The kids did a good job on defense but then kept thowing the ball away," 
<ORGANIZATION>Coronado Coach</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>Bob Stanton</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Clark</PERSON> said his main concern was winning the game, not <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>'s record. 
</P>
<P>
"I never had any idea how many points I had," <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> said. "If I did it, I did 
it. It didn't make any difference. I was more interested in the 'W' " 
</P>
<P>
Christian took a <DATE>20-14</DATE> lead after a quarter and never trailed. Coronado fell to 
15-8, 5-2 in the league. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Tony Clark fades away from basket on shot attempt against Coronado. ; 
Photo, Recording Artist -- Christian's Tony Clark looks for room to maneuver 
during his team's game at Coronado Wednesday. Christian celebrated both a 
victory and Clark's surpassing Bill Walton's section season scoring mark of 960 
points. ROBERT FAABORG / For The Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111989-0194 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 137242 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 19, 1989, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 17B; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
274 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HIGH SCHOOL WATER POLO; 
</P>
<P>
CHAMPIONSHIP; 
</P>
<P>
CORONADO GOALIE SURFACES TO DEFEAT POWAY FOR TITLE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVE McKIBBEN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
LA JOLLA 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Coronado High water polo coach <PERSON>Randy Burgess</PERSON> said he'd been waiting for his 
junior goalie, <PERSON>Jack Bowen</PERSON>, to have a game of the spectacular variety for two 
years. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Burgess</PERSON>' wait ended <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> as <PERSON>Bowen</PERSON> put on a rejection show <PERSON>Mark Eaton</PERSON> 
would have proud of in <LOCATION>Coronado</LOCATION>'s 13-8 victory over <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>San Diego 
Section</LOCATION> title game at the <ORGANIZATION>Jewish Community Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Bowen personally turned back any hopes <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> had of dethroning the two-time 
champs by holding the Titans scoreless with four <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> saves. 
</P>
<P>
"He's just an incredible player," said <PERSON>Bowen</PERSON>'s teammate <PERSON>Pat Mitchell</PERSON>, who 
scored three third-period goals. "What you saw in the second half was the <PERSON>Jack 
Bowen</PERSON> show." 
</P>
<P>
The show's highlight came with three minutes remaining in the game and Coronado 
ahead, 12-8. With <PERSON>Bowen</PERSON> one-one with <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> junior <PERSON>Chad Aronen</PERSON> at point-blank 
range, <PERSON>Bowen</PERSON> leaped up out of the water and swatted away <ORGANIZATION>Aronen</ORGANIZATION>'s rifle shot. 
</P>
<P>
"That was leg strength," <PERSON>Bowen</PERSON> said. "That's what lifting in the <DATE>summer</DATE> is all 
about. I visualized those kind of blocks in my room <TIME>last night</TIME> when I was 
listening to music." 
</P>
<P>
The music stopped for <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> (22-3) after they grabbed a 7-5 lead early in the 
third period. After the Titans led, they continually self-destructed with 
turnovers and missed opportunities. 
</P>
<P>
And while <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> was self-destructing, <PERSON>Coronado</PERSON> (23-3) was taking advantage of 
nearly every scoring opportunity it had. After trailing 7-5, <LOCATION>Poway</LOCATION> scored four 
consecutive goals, including long-range bullets from <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Chris Cote</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I was not concerned when we fell behind," <PERSON>Burgess</PERSON> said. "Everybody was in good 
condition and we stayed with our game plan." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051389-0059 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 56452 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 13, 1989, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 4; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
132 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO COUNTY DIGEST: CORONADO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Coronado police are seeking a man in connection with a series of sexual attacks 
