<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900226-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-26-90 0832EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv10   02-26 0415</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv10,0431</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv10</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Saturday, March 10</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <DATE>March 10</DATE>, the <DATE>69th day of 1990</DATE>. There are 296
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <DATE>March 10</DATE>, the <DATE>69th day of 1990</DATE>. There are 296
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880229-0238 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-29-88 0834EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv10   02-29 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv10,0440</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv10</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thursday, March 10</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Today in History</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>March 10</DATE>, the <DATE>70th day of 1988</DATE>. There are 296
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>March 10, 1876</DATE>, <PERSON>Alexander Graham Bell</PERSON> made the first
telephone call, telling his assistant in an adjoining room in
<LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, ``<PERSON>Mr. Watson</PERSON>, come here. I want you.''
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1496</DATE>, <PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON> concluded his second visit to the
<LOCATION>New World</LOCATION> as he left <LOCATION>Hispaniola</LOCATION> for <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1629</DATE>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>King Charles</LOCATION> the First dissolved parliament.
He would not call it back for 11 years.
   In <DATE>1785</DATE>, <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON> was appointed minister to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,
succeeding <PERSON>Benjamin Franklin</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1848</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> ratified the Treaty of <LOCATION>Guadalupe Hidalgo</LOCATION>,
ending the war with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1864</DATE>, <PERSON>Ulysses S. Grant</PERSON> became commander of the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> armies
in the Civil War.
   In <DATE>1880</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Salvation Army</ORGANIZATION> arrived in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> from
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1949</DATE>, <PERSON>Mildred E. Gillars</PERSON>, who had made wartime broadcasts for
the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION> under the name ``<PERSON>Axis Sally</PERSON>,'' was convicted of treason
in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
later repudiated that plea.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, the author of the ``Scarsdale Diet,'' <PERSON>Dr. Herman
Tarnower</PERSON>, was shot to death at his home in <LOCATION>Purchase</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Jean
Harris</PERSON> was arrested and later convicted of the crime.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, Soviet leader <PERSON>Konstantin U. Chernenko</PERSON> died of emphysema
as well as heart and liver complications at the age of 73.
   Ten years ago: The government reported the nation's jobless rate
fell in <DATE>February</DATE>, to a seasonally adjusted <PERCENT>6.1 percent</PERCENT>, compared to
<PERCENT>6.3 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   Five years ago: Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> returned to the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> from
an eight-day tour of <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>, telling reporters aboard his
special jet that his tour had been a ``great experience.''
   One year ago: The <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> issued a 40-page document stating the
Roman Catholic church's position on scientific techniques involving
procreation. The document condemned such things as surrogate
motherhood, test-tube births and cloning.
   Today's Birthdays: Playwright <PERSON>David Rabe</PERSON> is 48. Newspaper
columnist <PERSON>Bob Greene</PERSON> is 41. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Prince Edward</ORGANIZATION> is 24.
   Thought for Today: ``Journalism largely consists in saying `<PERSON>Lord
Jones</PERSON> is dead' to people who never knew <PERSON>Lord Jones</PERSON> was alive.'' _
<ORGANIZATION>G.K. Chesterton</ORGANIZATION>, English writer (1874-1936).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance for Thursday, March 10</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890227-0230 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-27-89 0751EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv10   02-27 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv10,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv10</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday, March 10</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <DATE>March 10</DATE>, the <DATE>69th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 296
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>March 10, 1876</DATE>, <PERSON>Alexander Graham Bell</PERSON> made the first telephone
call, telling his assistant in an adjoining room in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, ``<PERSON>Mr.
Watson</PERSON>, come here. I want you.''
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1496</DATE>, <PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON> concluded his second visit to the
<LOCATION>New World</LOCATION> as he left <LOCATION>Hispaniola</LOCATION> for <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1629</DATE>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s King Charles I dissolved parliament. He would
not call it back for 11 years.
   In <DATE>1785</DATE>, <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON> was appointed minister to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,
succeeding <PERSON>Benjamin Franklin</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1848</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> ratified the Treaty of <LOCATION>Guadalupe Hidalgo</LOCATION>,
ending the war with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1864</DATE>, <PERSON>Ulysses S. Grant</PERSON> became commander of the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> armies in
the Civil War.
   In <DATE>1880</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Salvation Army</ORGANIZATION> arrived in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> from
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1949</DATE>, <PERSON>Mildred E. Gillars</PERSON>, who had made wartime broadcasts for
the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION> under the name ``<PERSON>Axis Sally</PERSON>,'' was convicted of treason in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. She ended up serving 12 years in prison.
later repudiated that plea.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, the author of the ``Scarsdale Diet,'' <PERSON>Dr. Herman
Tarnower</PERSON>, was shot to death at his home in <LOCATION>Purchase</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Jean
Harris</PERSON> was arrested and later convicted of the crime.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, Soviet leader <PERSON>Konstantin U. Chernenko</PERSON> died at age 73.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> issued a 40-page document on scientific
techniques involving procreation, condemning such practices as
surrogate motherhood, test-tube births and cloning.
   Ten years ago: President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> arrived in <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> after
three days of talks in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> with President <PERSON>Anwar Sadat</PERSON>. Earlier
that same day, <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> had spoken to the Egyptian parliament,
becoming the first American president to address that body.
   Five years ago: In his fourth victory over <PERSON>Walter F. Mondale</PERSON>,
Democratic presidential hopeful <PERSON>Gary Hart</PERSON> won the <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> caucuses,
following his victories in <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>.
   One year ago: <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Congressman <PERSON>Jack Kemp</PERSON> dropped out of the
have not failed, because our ideas are winning.''
   Today's birthdays: Playwright <PERSON>David Rabe</PERSON> is 49. Newspaper
columnist <PERSON>Bob Greene</PERSON> is 42. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Prince Edward</ORGANIZATION> is 25.
   Thought for Today: ``History is more or less bunk. It's
tradition. We don't want tradition. We want to live in the present
and the only history that is worth a tinker's damn is the history we
make today.'' _ <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION>, American automaker, 1863-1947.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance for Friday, March 10</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880815-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-15-88 0746EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv22   08-15 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv22,0524</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv22</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday, Aug. 22</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 22</DATE>, the 235th day of <DATE>1988</DATE>. There are 131
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Aug. 22, 1787</DATE>, inventor <PERSON>John Fitch</PERSON> demonstrated his steamboat
on the <LOCATION>Delaware River</LOCATION> to delegates of the <ORGANIZATION>Continental Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
(Although Fitch deserves credit for inventing the first practical
steamboat, it was <PERSON>Robert Fulton</PERSON> who developed the first
commercially successful one. Fitch died in poverty in <DATE>1798</DATE>.)
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1485</DATE>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>King Richard III</PERSON> was killed in the Battle of
<ORGANIZATION>Bosworth Field</ORGANIZATION>, ending the War of the Roses. Richard was succeeded
to the throne by <ORGANIZATION>Henry VII</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1762</DATE>, <PERSON>Ann Franklin</PERSON> became the first female editor for an
American newspaper, the <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1775</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>England's King George III</ORGANIZATION> proclaimed the American
colonies to be in a state of open rebellion.
   In <DATE>1846</DATE>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> annexed <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1851</DATE>, the schooner <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> outraced the <LOCATION>Aurora</LOCATION> off the
English coast to win a silver trophy that came to be known as the
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s Cup.
   In <DATE>1902</DATE>, President <PERSON>Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON> became the first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
chief executive to ride in an automobile, in <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1911</DATE>, it was announced in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> that <PERSON>Leonardo da Vinci</PERSON>'s
``Mona Lisa'' had been stolen from the <LOCATION>Louvre Museum</LOCATION> sometime
during the night. (The painting turned up two years later in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.)
   In <DATE>1956</DATE>, President <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> and Vice President
<PERSON>Richard M. Nixon</PERSON> were nominated for second terms in office by the
Republican national convention in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>Paul VI</PERSON> arrived in <LOCATION>Bogota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, for the start
of the first papal visit to <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, the Republican national convention in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> nominated
President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and Vice President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> for a second term in
office. (In a break with tradition, both renominations were
approved in a single roll-call vote.)
   Ten years ago: President <PERSON>Jomo Kenyatta</PERSON>, a leading figure in
<LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s struggle for independence, died in the city of <LOCATION>Mombasa</LOCATION>;
Vice President <PERSON>Daniel Arap Moi</PERSON> was sworn in as acting president. In
<LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>, leftist guerrillas seized the <ORGANIZATION>National Palace</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Managua</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: In a move applauded by feminists, <ORGANIZATION>Justice
Department</ORGANIZATION> employee <PERSON>Barbara Honegger</PERSON> resigned her post, charging
that President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s program to end sex discrimination in
federal laws and regulations was a ``sham.''
   One year ago: The supertanker <LOCATION>Bridgeton</LOCATION> and three other
reflagged Kuwaiti tankers left <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION> under <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> escort and safely
cleared <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> waters where the <LOCATION>Bridgeton</LOCATION> had hit a mine the
month before.
   Today's birthdays: Chinese leader <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON> is 84. Author
<PERSON>Ray Bradbury</PERSON> is 68. Heart surgeon <PERSON>Dr. Denton Cooley</PERSON> is 68. TV
newscaster <ORGANIZATION>Morton Dean</ORGANIZATION> is 53. Baseball great <PERSON>Carl Yastrzemski</PERSON> is
49. Actress <PERSON>Valerie Harper</PERSON> is 48. Actress <PERSON>Cindy Williams</PERSON> is 40.
Tennis player <PERSON>Mats Wilander</PERSON> is 24.
   Thought for today: ``Next to the originator of a good sentence
is the first quoter of it.'' _ <PERSON>Ralph Waldo Emerson</PERSON>, American
essayist, poet and philosopher (1803-1882).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890814-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-14-89 1019EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv22   08-14 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv22,0561</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tuesday, Aug. 22</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 22</DATE>, the 234th day of <DATE>1989</DATE>. There are 131
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Aug. 22, 1485</DATE>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>King Richard III</PERSON> was killed in the
Battle of <ORGANIZATION>Bosworth Field</ORGANIZATION>, ending the War of the Roses. Richard was
succeeded to the throne by <ORGANIZATION>Henry VII</ORGANIZATION>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1762</DATE>, <PERSON>Ann Franklin</PERSON> became the first female editor for an
American newspaper, the <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1775</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>England's King George III</ORGANIZATION> proclaimed the American
colonies to be in a state of open rebellion.
   In <DATE>1787</DATE>, inventor <PERSON>John Fitch</PERSON> demonstrated his steamboat on the
<LOCATION>Delaware River</LOCATION> to delegates of the <ORGANIZATION>Continental Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1846</DATE>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> annexed <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1851</DATE>, the schooner <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> outraced the <LOCATION>Aurora</LOCATION> off the
English coast to win a silver trophy that came to be known as the
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s Cup.
   In <DATE>1902</DATE>, President <PERSON>Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON> became the first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
chief executive to ride in an automobile, in <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1911</DATE>, it was announced in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> that <PERSON>Leonardo da Vinci</PERSON>'s
``Mona Lisa'' had been stolen from the <LOCATION>Louvre Museum</LOCATION> sometime
during the night. (The painting turned up two years later, in
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.)
   In <DATE>1950</DATE>, <PERSON>Althea Gibson</PERSON> became the first black tennis player to
be accepted in competition for the national championship.
   In <DATE>1956</DATE>, President <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> and Vice President
<PERSON>Richard M. Nixon</PERSON> were nominated for second terms in office by the
Republican national convention in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1965</DATE>, a 14-minute brawl broke out during a game between the
pitcher <PERSON>Juan Marichal</PERSON> hit <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> catcher <PERSON>John Roseboro</PERSON> with his
bat, accusing <PERSON>Roseboro</PERSON> of throwing too close to his head.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>Paul VI</PERSON> arrived in <LOCATION>Bogota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, for the start
of the first papal visit to <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1978</DATE>, President <PERSON>Jomo Kenyatta</PERSON>, a leading figure in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s
struggle for independence, died in the city of <LOCATION>Mombasa</LOCATION>; Vice
President <PERSON>Daniel Arap Moi</PERSON> was sworn in as acting president.
   Ten years ago: <ORGANIZATION>The United Auto Workers</ORGANIZATION> union said more than <MONEY>1
million</MONEY> of its members stopped work across the nation for up to six
minutes to sign postcards aimed at pressuring <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to enact an
energy policy.
   Five years ago: The Republican national convention in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>
nominated President <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> and Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>
for second terms in office, breaking with tradition by approving
both nominations with a single roll-call vote.
   One year ago: Appearing before the <ORGANIZATION>Veterans of Foreign Wars</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, Vice President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> defended the <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> service of
his running mate, <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, during the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War, saying, ``He
did not go to <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, he did not burn his draft card and he damn
sure didn't burn the American flag.''
   Today's birthdays: Chinese leader <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON> is 85. Author
<PERSON>Ray Bradbury</PERSON> is 69. Heart surgeon <PERSON>Dr. Denton Cooley</PERSON> is 69. TV
newscaster <PERSON>Morton Dean</PERSON> is 54. Baseball hall-of-famer <PERSON>Carl
Yastrzemski</PERSON> is 50. Actress <PERSON>Valerie Harper</PERSON> is 49. Actress <PERSON>Cindy
Williams</PERSON> is 41. Tennis player <PERSON>Mats Wilander</PERSON> is 25.
   Thought for today: ``The history of the world is only the
opinion of the world.'' _ German proverb.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-2275</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEABLABGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910501
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 MAY 91 / Arts: Edward II - The Pit, Barbican
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MALCOLM RUTHERFORD
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Simon Russell Beale</PERSON>
If you want to see a play wrecked by a wrong choice of costume, go to the
<ORGANIZATION>Royal Shakespeare Company</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Edward II</ORGANIZATION>, which has arrived at The Pit from
<LOCATION>Stratford</LOCATION>. To be fair to the designers, there are a lot more faults in this
production than the wardrobe, but the clothes do set a tone. If you dress
the characters in black and white leather jackets, trousers to go with them,
and heaven knows what the Queen is wearing, you are at a disadvantage from
the start.
For a number of reasons, the production never quite recovers from this
self-inflicted wound. <PERSON>Simon Russell Beale</PERSON> is an actor of great versatility;
he is not, however, one of nature's Edward IIs. The point about the part is
that he has a strong homosexual attraction to his favourites. He is also the
<LOCATION>King of England</LOCATION> with wars to fight, civil and foreign. To carry this off, in
the court and on the stage, requires a certain style. Beale plays the role
as someone short, fat and stupid who hops about like a bloated frog.
The message may be that you do not have to be beautiful to have homosexual
passions. Yet it would help if there were a certain style. Beale is simply
gross. He never rises to the part. Moreover, he shouts - repeatedly and
unnecessarily. So do much of the rest of the cast. This is not a production
of light and shade.
<PERSON>Edward II</PERSON>, admittedly, is not <PERSON>Christopher Marlowe</PERSON>'s best play: not a patch
on Tamburlaine the Great or Dr Faustus. But it does have its moments as well
as unmistakeable affinities with <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s Richard II. Its greatest
attraction is <PERSON>Piers Gaveston</PERSON>, the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s first favourite. The <ORGANIZATION>RSC</ORGANIZATION>'s
<LOCATION>Gaveston</LOCATION>, played by <PERSON>Grant Thatcher</PERSON>, comes into his own only when he has been
beaten up and his mouth is covered in blood - like lipstick. By then, he has
little left to say. Before that, he is dressed in his ridiculous white
leather clothes with sequins. The only surprise is that he does not wear an
earring. That is left to the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s next favourite, <PERSON>Spencer</PERSON>, whom we first
see under a sheet with a curate.
The nobles and the clerics are wooden. This may be deliberate. For if the
<PERSON>King</PERSON> does not behave like a king, even a deviant king, the court can hardly
be expected to behave like a court. The general entourage is more like that
of a rotary club faced with unseemly goings on, which cannot have been what
<PERSON>Marlowe</PERSON> intended. There ought also to be room for some humour, since most of
the characters go through a remarkable number of changes of mind. That is
not there either.
The best performance is by <PERSON>Ciaran Hands</PERSON> as the young <PERSON>Mortimer</PERSON>. By the time
he has become an accomplice to murder, his black jacket is decked with
phosphorescent green. For the rest, it is a pretty grim evening. The
direction is by <PERSON>Gerard Murphy</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-2129</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEABLAFIFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910501
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 MAY 91 / Arts: Edward II - The Pit, Barbican
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MALCOLM RUTHERFORD
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
If you want to see a play wrecked by a wrong choice of costume, go to the
<ORGANIZATION>Royal Shakespeare Company</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Edward II</ORGANIZATION>, which has arrived at The Pit from
<LOCATION>Stratford</LOCATION>. To be fair to the designers, there are a lot more faults in this
production than the wardrobe, but the clothes do set a tone. If you dress
the characters in black and white leather jackets, trousers to go with them,
and heaven knows what the Queen is wearing, you are at a disadvantage from
the start.
For a number of reasons, the production never quite recovers from this
self-inflicted wound. <PERSON>Simon Russell Beale</PERSON> is an actor of great versatility;
he is not, however, one of nature's Edward IIs. The point about the part is
that he has a strong homosexual attraction to his favourites. He is also the
<LOCATION>King of England</LOCATION> with wars to fight, civil and foreign. To carry this off, in
the court and on the stage, requires a certain style. Beale plays the role
as someone short, fat and stupid who hops about like a bloated frog.
The message may be that you do not have to be beautiful to have homosexual
passions. Yet it would help if there were a certain style. Beale is simply
gross. He never rises to the part. Moreover, he shouts - repeatedly and
unnecessarily. So do much of the rest of the cast. This is not a production
of light and shade.
<PERSON>Edward II</PERSON>, admittedly, is not <PERSON>Christopher Marlowe</PERSON>'s best play: not a patch
on Tamburlaine the Great or Dr Faustus. But it does have its moments as well
as unmistakeable affinities with <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s Richard II. Its greatest
attraction is <PERSON>Piers Gaveston</PERSON>, the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s first favourite. The <ORGANIZATION>RSC</ORGANIZATION>'s
<LOCATION>Gaveston</LOCATION>, played by <PERSON>Grant Thatcher</PERSON>, comes into his own only when he has been
beaten up and his mouth is covered in blood - like lipstick. By then, he has
little left to say. Before that, he is dressed in his ridiculous white
leather clothes with sequins. The only surprise is that he does not wear an
earring. That is left to the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s next favourite, <PERSON>Spencer</PERSON>, whom we first
see under a sheet with a curate.
The nobles and the clerics are wooden. This may be deliberate. For if the
<PERSON>King</PERSON> does not behave like a king, even a deviant king, the court can hardly
be expected to behave like a court. The general entourage is more like that
of a rotary club faced with unseemly goings on, which cannot have been what
<PERSON>Marlowe</PERSON> intended. There ought also to be room for some humour, since most of
the characters go through a remarkable number of changes of mind. That is
not there either.
The best performance is by <PERSON>Ciaran Hands</PERSON> as the young <PERSON>Mortimer</PERSON>. By the time
he has become an accomplice to murder, his black jacket is decked with
phosphorescent green. For the rest, it is a pretty grim evening. The
direction is by <PERSON>Gerard Murphy</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881017-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-17-88 0819EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   10-17 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv 24,0504</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday, Oct. 24</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<HEAD>By The Associated Press</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>Oct. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>298th day of 1988</DATE>. There are 68
   Today's highlight in history:
   In <DATE>1945</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> officially came into existence as
its charter took effect. The world body began with 51 members in
<DATE>1945</DATE>, a figure that has more than tripled since then.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1537</DATE>, <PERSON>Jane Seymour</PERSON>, the third wife of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>King Henry
VIII</PERSON>, died 12 days after giving birth to <LOCATION>Prince Edward</LOCATION>, later <ORGANIZATION>King
Edward VI</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1648</DATE>, the Peace of <LOCATION>Westphalia</LOCATION> ended the <ORGANIZATION>Thirty Years</ORGANIZATION>' War and
effectively destroyed the <ORGANIZATION>Holy Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1861</DATE>, the first transcontinental telegraph message was sent
as Justice <PERSON>Stephen J. Field</PERSON> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> transmitted a telegram to
President <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1901</DATE>, <PERSON>Anna Edson Taylor</PERSON>, a 43-year-old widow, became the
first person to go over <LOCATION>Niagara Falls</LOCATION> in a barrel and live to tell
about it. <PERSON>Mrs. Taylor</PERSON>'s dreams of fame and fortune failed to
materialize, however, and she died in poverty in <DATE>1921</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1931</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>George Washington Bridge</ORGANIZATION>, connecting <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, opened to traffic.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, the first nylon stockings went on sale, in <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Del</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, the 40-hour work week went into effect under the Fair
Labor Standards Act of <DATE>1938</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1952</DATE>, in a speech in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, Republican presidential
candidate <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> declared, ``I shall go to <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>'' as
he promised to end the war.
   In <DATE>1962</DATE>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> blockade of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> during the missile crisis
officially began under a proclamation signed by President <PERSON>John F.
Kennedy</PERSON> the day before.
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, 25 people were killed when a fire set by an arsonist
broke out at a social club in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>South Bronx</LOCATION> section.
   Ten years ago: A jury in <LOCATION>Hackensack</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, found <PERSON>Dr. Mario
Jascalevich</PERSON> innocent of charges he had murdered three hospital
patients with the muscle relaxant curare in the mid-1960s. The
judge also freed <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> reporter <PERSON>Myron Farber</PERSON>, who was
jailed 40 days for his refusal to turn over notes on the case.
   Five years ago: President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> told a news conference he was
determined to keep <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Marines stationed in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>, despite a
truck-bomb attack in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> the day before that claimed the lives
of 241 servicemen.
   One year ago: Thirty years after it was expelled for refusing to
answer allegations of corruption, the <ORGANIZATION>Teamsters</ORGANIZATION> union was welcomed
back into the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION> by a vote of the labor federation's executive
council in <LOCATION>Miami Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   Today's birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Bobby Brown</PERSON> is 63.
Football hall-of-famer <PERSON>Y.A. Tittle</PERSON> is 62. Actor-producer <PERSON>David
Nelson</PERSON> is 52. Rock musician <PERSON>Bill Wyman</PERSON> is 47. Actor <PERSON>Kevin Kline</PERSON> is
41.
   Thought for today: ``There has never been any 30-hour week for
men who had anything to do.'' _ <PERSON>Charles F. Kettering</PERSON>, American
inventor (1876-1958).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891122-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-22-89 1447EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CountryLawsuit     11-22 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Country Lawsuit,0344</SECOND>
<HEAD>Colorado Man Seeks Ownership Of Northern U.S.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHEYENNE, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man who claims his family was given most
of the northern <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> by the king of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> during
colonial times has sued to get it back.
   <PERSON>Robert Brewster</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Longmont</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>, said in his <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District
Court</ORGANIZATION> lawsuit, filed in <LOCATION>Cheyenne</LOCATION>, that he wants the land to set up
his own country for blue- and green-eyed people.
   <PERSON>Brewster</PERSON> claimed his family was given the land between the 40th
and 48th north latitudes from ocean to ocean. The 48th parallel is
approximately at the Canadian border and the 40th parallel
stretches approximately from <LOCATION>Eureka</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, across the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>.
   ``It is now necessary for the Brewsters to reclaim their land
before the federal government loses its ability to return the
land,'' the lawsuit said. ``The <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> has lost its vision and is
collapsing every day with newspapers reporting each morning of
massive land purchases by <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> or <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION>.''
   The lawsuit filed <DATE>Monday</DATE> said <PERSON>Brewster</PERSON> is a descendant of
<PERSON>William Brewster</PERSON>, a founder of the <ORGANIZATION>Plymouth Colony</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1620</DATE> in what
is now <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
   The lawsuit said <PERSON>William Brewster</PERSON> and his companions were given
the land by the <LOCATION>King of England</LOCATION> when they left that country to move
to the ``New World.''
   <PERSON>Brewster</PERSON> said he wants the land back so he can ``form an area
where only green-eyed and blue-eyed persons will be permitted.''
People with green and blue eyes are superior to those with brown
eyes, <PERSON>Brewster</PERSON> said, but will soon be extinct unless they are
protected.
   Brewster also asked the court for permission to establish a
standing army to protect the borders of his country.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, as represented by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney's office
in <LOCATION>Cheyenne</LOCATION>, has 30 days to respond to <PERSON>Brewster</PERSON>'s lawsuit,
according to a woman in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> clerk's office. She
said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that the case has been assigned to <PERSON>Judge Alan B.
Johnson</PERSON>, but no hearing date has been set.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900618-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-18-90 0755EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   06-18 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0551</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, June 24</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <DATE>June 24</DATE>, the <DATE>175th day of 1990</DATE>. There are 190
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>June 24, 1948</DATE>, Communist forces cut off all land and water
routes between <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>, prompting the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> to organize a massive airlift of supplies into the city's
western sector to counter the blockade.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1314</DATE>, the forces of <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>'s King Robert I defeated the
English in the Battle of <LOCATION>Bannockburn</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1497</DATE>, the first recorded discovery of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> by a
European took place as explorer <PERSON>John Cabot</PERSON>, on a voyage for
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, sighted land, probably in present-day <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1509</DATE>, <PERSON>Henry VIII</PERSON> was crowned king of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1647</DATE>, <PERSON>Margaret Brent</PERSON>, a niece of <LOCATION>Lord Baltimore</LOCATION>, was ejected
from the <ORGANIZATION>Maryland Assembly</ORGANIZATION> after demanding a place and vote in that
governing body.
   In <DATE>1793</DATE>, the first republican constitution in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> was adopted.
   In <DATE>1842</DATE>, author-journalist <PERSON>Ambrose Bierce</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>Meigs
County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Grover Cleveland</PERSON>, died in <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, at the age of 71.
   In <DATE>1915</DATE>, more than 800 people died when the excursion steamer
<LOCATION>Eastland</LOCATION> capsized at <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Clark Street dock.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> signed an armistice with <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> during World War
II.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Republican National Convention</ORGANIZATION>, meeting in
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, nominated <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Thomas E. Dewey</PERSON> for president.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, ``Resurrection City,'' a shantytown constructed as part
of the Poor People's <DATE>March</DATE> on <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, was closed by authorities
one day after the permit for the campsite expired.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, 113 people were killed when an <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines Boeing</ORGANIZATION>
727 crashed while attempting to land during a thunderstorm at <LOCATION>New
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, the space shuttle Challenger _ carrying <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first
woman in space, <PERSON>Sally K. Ride</PERSON> _ coasted to a safe landing at
<ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, comedian-actor <PERSON>Jackie Gleason</PERSON> died at his home in <LOCATION>Fort
Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, at age 71.
   Ten years ago: President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> left <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, where he had
attended a summit, and flew to <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>, where he met with the
collective leadership that took charge following the death of <PERSON>Josip
Broz Tito</PERSON>.
   Five years ago: A federal judge in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> found former Wall
Street Journal reporter <PERSON>R. Foster Winans</PERSON> guilty of illegally using
his position at the paper in an insider-trading scheme.
   One year ago: Following the crackdown on <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s pro-democracy
movement, <PERSON>Zhao Ziyang</PERSON> was deposed as <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> general
secretary, and was replaced by <PERSON>Jiang Zemin</PERSON>.
   Today's birthdays: Actor <PERSON>Al Molinaro</PERSON> is 71. Comedian <PERSON>Jack Carter</PERSON>
is 67. Movie director <PERSON>Claude Chabrol</PERSON> is 60. Actress <PERSON>Michele Lee</PERSON> is
48. Actress <PERSON>Nancy Allen</PERSON> is 40.
   Thought for today: ``No idea is so antiquated that it was not
once modern. No idea is so modern that it will not some day be
antiquated. ... To seize the flying thought before it escapes us is
our only touch with reality.'' _ <PERSON>Ellen Glasgow</PERSON>, American author
(1874-1945).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, June 24.</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890612-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-12-89 0817EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   06-12 0540</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0563</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Saturday, June 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Saturday, June 24</DATE>, the <DATE>175th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 190
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>June 24, 1948</DATE>, Communist forces cut off all land and water
routes between <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>, prompting the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> to organize a massive airlift of supplies into the city's
western sector to counter the blockade.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1314</DATE>, the forces of <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>'s King Robert I defeated the
English in the Battle of <LOCATION>Bannockburn</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1497</DATE>, the first recorded discovery of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> took place
as explorer <PERSON>John Cabot</PERSON>, on a voyage for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, sighted land,
probably in present-day <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1509</DATE>, <PERSON>Henry VIII</PERSON> was crowned king of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1647</DATE>, <PERSON>Margaret Brent</PERSON>, a niece of <LOCATION>Lord Baltimore</LOCATION>, was ejected
from the <ORGANIZATION>Maryland Assembly</ORGANIZATION> after demanding a place and vote in that
governing body.
   In <DATE>1793</DATE>, the first republican constitution in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> was adopted.
   In <DATE>1842</DATE>, author-journalist <PERSON>Ambrose Bierce</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>Meigs
County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
Cleveland</PERSON>, died in <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, at the age of 71.
   In <DATE>1915</DATE>, more than 800 people died when the excursion steamer
<LOCATION>Eastland</LOCATION> capsized at <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Clark Street dock.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> signed an armistice with <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> during World War
II.
   In <DATE>1947</DATE>, <PERSON>Kenneth Arnold</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, reported seeing flying
saucers over <LOCATION>Mount Rainier</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Republican National Convention</ORGANIZATION>, meeting in
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, nominated <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Thomas E. Dewey</PERSON> for president.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, ``Resurrection City,'' a shantytown constructed as part
of the Poor People's <DATE>March</DATE> on <LOCATION>Washington D.C.</LOCATION>, was closed down by
authorities one day after the permit for the campsite expired.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, 113 people were killed when an <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines Boeing</ORGANIZATION>
727 crashed while attempting to land during a thunderstorm at <LOCATION>New
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, proponents of the proposed Equal Rights Amendment to the
Constitution officially conceded defeat, but vowed to continue
efforts to fight for equal rights for women.
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, the space shuttle Challenger _ carrying <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first
woman in space, <PERSON>Sally K. Ride</PERSON> _ coasted to a safe landing at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards
Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, comedian-actor <PERSON>Jackie Gleason</PERSON>, perhaps best known for
his TV series ``The Honeymooners,'' died at his home in <LOCATION>Fort
Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, at age 71.
   Ten years ago: President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> arrived in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> to begin a
12-day Asian tour that included a two-day summit conference in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: Black Muslim leader <PERSON>Louis Farrakhan</PERSON> delivered a
speech in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> in which he seemed to refer to Judaism as a
``gutter religion,'' although he later insisted he'd said ``dirty
religion.''
   One year ago: Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON>, on a visit to <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, condemned
Nazism during a stopover at the <LOCATION>Mauthausen</LOCATION> death camp where 110,000
World War II prisoners died.
   Today's birthdays: Actor <PERSON>Al Molinaro</PERSON> is 70. Comedian <PERSON>Jack Carter</PERSON>
is 66. Movie director <PERSON>Claude Chabrol</PERSON> is 59. Actress <PERSON>Michele Lee</PERSON> is
47. Actress <PERSON>Nancy Allen</PERSON> is 39.
   Thought for today: ``There is nothing more frightful than
ignorance in action.'' _ <PERSON>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</PERSON>, German poet,
dramatist and author (1749-1832).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890615-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-15-89 1236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24 1stLd-Writethru 06-15 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24, 1st Ld - Writethru, b0285,0558</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Saturday, June 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Eliminates 12th graf pvs reference to Eastland sinking; sinking
was on July 24.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Saturday, June 24</DATE>, the <DATE>175th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 190
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>June 24, 1948</DATE>, Communist forces cut off all land and water
routes between <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>, prompting the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> to organize a massive airlift of supplies into the city's
western sector to counter the blockade.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1314</DATE>, the forces of <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>'s King Robert I defeated the
English in the Battle of <LOCATION>Bannockburn</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1497</DATE>, the first recorded discovery of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> took place
as explorer <PERSON>John Cabot</PERSON>, on a voyage for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, sighted land,
probably in present-day <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1509</DATE>, <PERSON>Henry VIII</PERSON> was crowned king of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1647</DATE>, <PERSON>Margaret Brent</PERSON>, a niece of <LOCATION>Lord Baltimore</LOCATION>, was ejected
from the <ORGANIZATION>Maryland Assembly</ORGANIZATION> after demanding a place and vote in that
governing body.
   In <DATE>1793</DATE>, the first republican constitution in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> was adopted.
   In <DATE>1842</DATE>, author-journalist <PERSON>Ambrose Bierce</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>Meigs
County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
Cleveland</PERSON>, died in <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, at the age of 71.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> signed an armistice with <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> during World War
II.
   In <DATE>1947</DATE>, <PERSON>Kenneth Arnold</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, reported seeing flying
saucers over <LOCATION>Mount Rainier</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Republican National Convention</ORGANIZATION>, meeting in
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, nominated <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Thomas E. Dewey</PERSON> for president.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, ``Resurrection City,'' a shantytown constructed as part
of the Poor People's <DATE>March</DATE> on <LOCATION>Washington D.C.</LOCATION>, was closed down by
authorities one day after the permit for the campsite expired.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, 113 people were killed when an <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines Boeing</ORGANIZATION>
727 crashed while attempting to land during a thunderstorm at <LOCATION>New
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, proponents of the proposed Equal Rights Amendment to the
Constitution officially conceded defeat, but vowed to continue
efforts to fight for equal rights for women.
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, the space shuttle Challenger _ carrying <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first
woman in space, <PERSON>Sally K. Ride</PERSON> _ coasted to a safe landing at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards
Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, comedian-actor <PERSON>Jackie Gleason</PERSON>, perhaps best known for
his TV series ``The Honeymooners,'' died at his home in <LOCATION>Fort
Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, at age 71.
   Ten years ago: President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> arrived in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> to begin a
12-day Asian tour that included a two-day summit conference in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: Black Muslim leader <PERSON>Louis Farrakhan</PERSON> delivered a
speech in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> in which he seemed to refer to Judaism as a
``gutter religion,'' although he later insisted he'd said ``dirty
religion.''
   One year ago: Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON>, on a visit to <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, condemned
Nazism during a stopover at the <LOCATION>Mauthausen</LOCATION> death camp where 110,000
World War II prisoners died.
   Today's birthdays: Actor <PERSON>Al Molinaro</PERSON> is 70. Comedian <PERSON>Jack Carter</PERSON>
is 66. Movie director <PERSON>Claude Chabrol</PERSON> is 59. Actress <PERSON>Michele Lee</PERSON> is
47. Actress <PERSON>Nancy Allen</PERSON> is 39.
   Thought for today: ``There is nothing more frightful than
ignorance in action.'' _ <PERSON>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</PERSON>, German poet,
dramatist and author (1749-1832).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880705-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-05-88 0752EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv11   07-05 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv11,0441</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv11</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday, July 11</NOTE>
<HEAD>Retransmitting to fix header</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   Today is <DATE>Monday, July 11</DATE>, the <DATE>193rd day of 1988</DATE>. There are 173
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>July 11, 1804</DATE>, Vice President <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON> mortally wounded
former <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton</PERSON> in a pistol duel near
<LOCATION>Weehawken</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1533</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Pope Clement VII</ORGANIZATION> excommunicated <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>King Henry
VIII</ORGANIZATION>.
States</LOCATION>, was born in <LOCATION>Braintree</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1798</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Marine Corps</ORGANIZATION> was created by an act of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1864</DATE>, Confederate forces led by Gen. <PERSON>Jubal Early</PERSON> began their
invasion of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> D.C.
   In <DATE>1934</DATE>, President <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> became the first chief
executive to travel through the <LOCATION>Panama Canal</LOCATION>, aboard the cruiser
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1955</DATE>, the new <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force Academy</ORGANIZATION> was dedicated at <ORGANIZATION>Lowry
Air Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1974</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>House Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION> released volumes of
evidence it had gathered in its Watergate inquiry.
   In <DATE>1977</DATE>, the Medal of Freedom was awarded posthumously to the
Rev. <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> in a <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> ceremony.
   In <DATE>1979</DATE>, the abandoned <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space station Skylab made a
spectacular return to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, burning up in the atmosphere and
showering debris over the <LOCATION>Indian Ocean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, American hostage <PERSON>Richard I. Queen</PERSON>, freed by <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> after
eight months of captivity because of poor health, left <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> for
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <PERSON>Nolan Ryan</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Houston Astros</ORGANIZATION> became the first
pitcher in major league baseball to strike out 4,000 batters as he
fanned <PERSON>Danny Heep</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mets.
   Ten years ago: A tanker truck overfilled with propylene gas
exploded on a coastal highway south of <LOCATION>Tarragona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, setting
off a fireball that devastated a nearby campsite, killing 215
tourists as well as the driver. The <ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> downed the
<ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION>, 7-3, in baseball's 49th annual All-Star Game.
   Five years ago: The <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration filed its first school
desegregation suit, charging that <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>'s public colleges and
universities were practicing racial segregation.
   One year ago: Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON> won a third
consecutive term, becoming the first Labor Party leader in the
country's history to be elected to three straight terms in office.
   Today's Birthdays: Actor <PERSON>Tab Hunter</PERSON> is 57. Singer <PERSON>Bonnie Pointer</PERSON>
is 37. Boxer <PERSON>Leon Spinks</PERSON> is 35.
   Thought for Today: ``History is written by the winners.'' _ <PERSON>Alex
Haley</PERSON>, American author.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv July 11</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880613-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-88 0951EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   06-13 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0601</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Friday, June 24</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   Today is <DATE>Friday, June 24</DATE>, the <DATE>176th day of 1988</DATE>. There are 190
   Today's Highlight in History:
   <DATE>Forty years ago</DATE>, on <DATE>June 24, 1948</DATE>, Communist forces cut off all
land and water routes between <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>,
prompting the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to organize a massive airlift of
supplies into the city's western sector to counter the blockade.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1314</DATE>, the forces of <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>'s King Robert I defeated the
English in the Battle of <LOCATION>Bannockburn</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1497</DATE>, the first recorded discovery of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> took
place as explorer <PERSON>John Cabot</PERSON>, on a voyage for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, sighted
land, probably in present-day <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1509</DATE>, <PERSON>Henry VIII</PERSON> was crowned king of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1647</DATE>, <PERSON>Margaret Brent</PERSON>, a niece of <LOCATION>Lord Baltimore</LOCATION>, was ejected
from the <ORGANIZATION>Maryland Assembly</ORGANIZATION> after demanding a place and vote in that
governing body.
   In <DATE>1793</DATE>, the first republican constitution in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> was adopted.
   In <DATE>1842</DATE>, author-journalist <PERSON>Ambrose Bierce</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>Meigs
County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Grover Cleveland</PERSON>, died in <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, at the age of 71.
   In <DATE>1915</DATE>, more than 800 people died when the excursion steamer
<LOCATION>Eastland</LOCATION> capsized at <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Clark Street dock.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> signed an armistice with <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> during World War
II.
   In <DATE>1947</DATE>, <PERSON>Kenneth Arnold</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, reported seeing flying
saucers over <LOCATION>Mount Rainier</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Republican National Convention</ORGANIZATION>, meeting in
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, nominated <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Thomas E. Dewey</PERSON> for president.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Resurrection City</ORGANIZATION>, a shantytown constructed as part of
the Poor People's <DATE>March</DATE> on <LOCATION>Washington D.C.</LOCATION>, was closed down by
authorities one day after the permit for the campsite expired.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, 113 people were killed when an <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines Boeing</ORGANIZATION>
727 crashed while attempting to land during a thunderstorm at <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>John F. Kennedy Airport</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, proponents of a proposed equal rights amendment to the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Constitution officially conceded defeat, but vowed to continue
efforts to fight for equal rights for women.
   Ten years ago: A group of about two dozen neo-Nazis who had won,
but declined, the legal right to march in predominantly <LOCATION>Jewish
Skokie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, held a rally in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Marquette Park</LOCATION>, where they
were drowned out by more than 2,000 counter-demonstrators.
   Five years ago: The space shuttle Challenger _ carrying
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first woman in space, <PERSON>Sally K. Ride</PERSON> _ coasted to a safe
landing at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, wet weather having
scrubbed a planned landing at <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION>.
   One year ago: Comedian-actor <PERSON>Jackie Gleason</PERSON>, perhaps best known
for his television series ``The Honeymooners,'' died at his home in
<LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, at age 71.
   Today's Birthdays: Actor <PERSON>Al Molinaro</PERSON> is 69. Comedian <PERSON>Jack Carter</PERSON>
is 65. Movie director <PERSON>Claude Chabrol</PERSON> is 58. Actress <PERSON>Michele Lee</PERSON> isre is
nothing else to live in. To live in the present is like proposing
to sit on a pin. It is too minute, it is too slight a support, it
is too uncomfortable a posture. ... To live in the future is a
contradiction in terms. The future is dead, in the perfectly
definite sense that it is not alive.'' _ <ORGANIZATION>G.K. Chesterton</ORGANIZATION>, English
poet, critic, essayist (1874-1936).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890731-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-31-89 1145EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv09   07-31 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv09,0507</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv09</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday, Aug. 9</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 9</DATE>, the 221st day of <DATE>1989</DATE>. There are 144
   <DATE>Twenty years ago</DATE>, on <DATE>Aug. 9, 1969</DATE>, actress <PERSON>Sharon Tate</PERSON>, hair
stylist <PERSON>Jay Sebring</PERSON>, coffee heiress <PERSON>Abigail Folger</PERSON>, movie director
<PERSON>Voityck Frykowski</PERSON> and high school graduate <PERSON>Steven Parent</PERSON> were found
brutally murdered in the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> home Tate shared with her
husband, movie director <ORGANIZATION>Roman Polanski</ORGANIZATION>. Cult leader <PERSON>Charles Manson</PERSON>
and a group of his young disciples were later convicted of the
murders.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1842</DATE>, a border dispute between the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>
was resolved with the signing of the Webster-Ashburton Treaty.
   In <DATE>1848</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Free-Soil Party</ORGANIZATION> nominated <PERSON>Martin Van Buren</PERSON> for
president at its convention in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   In <DATE>1854</DATE>, <PERSON>Henry David Thoreau</PERSON> published ``Walden,'' in which he
described his experiences while living in a small cabin near <LOCATION>Walden
Pond</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1902</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Edward VII</ORGANIZATION> was crowed King of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> following the
death of his mother, <PERSON>Queen Victoria</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1930</DATE>, a forerunner of the cartoon character ``<PERSON>Betty Boop</PERSON>''
made her debut in <PERSON>Max Fleischer</PERSON>'s animated short ``Dizzy Dishes.''
   In <DATE>1936</DATE>, <PERSON>Jesse Owens</PERSON> won his fourth gold medal at the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>
Olympics as the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> took first place in the 400-meter
relay.
   In <DATE>1942</DATE>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> arrested Indian nationalist <PERSON>Mohandas K. Gandhi</PERSON>;
he was not released until <DATE>1944</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1945</DATE>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> dropped a second atomic bomb on
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, destroying part of the city of <LOCATION>Nagasaki</LOCATION>. An estimated 74,000
people died from the blast or its after-effects.
   In <DATE>1974</DATE>, President <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON>'s resignation took effect. Vice
President <PERSON>Gerald R. Ford</PERSON> became the nation's 38th chief executive.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, a federal judge in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> ordered <PERSON>John W. Hinckley
Jr.</PERSON>, who had been acquitted of shooting President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and three
others by reason of insanity, committed to a mental hospital.
   Ten years ago: The <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> administration expressed support for
federal loan guarantees for <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, but not the <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>
in tax credits sought by the financially troubled automaker.
   Five years ago: At the <DATE>1984</DATE> Summer Olympics, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Daley
Thompson</PERSON> won his second successive Olympic decathlon, falling short
of breaking the world record.
   One year ago: President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> nominated <PERSON>Lauro Cavazos</PERSON> to be
secretary of education, the first Hispanic ever to serve in the
Cabinet. Hockey star <PERSON>Wayne Gretzky</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Edmonton Oilers</ORGANIZATION> was
traded to the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Kings</LOCATION>.
   Today's Birthdays: Former <PERSON>Georgia Sen. Herman Talmadge</PERSON> is 76.
Former baseball manager <PERSON>Ralph Houk</PERSON> is 70. Senator <PERSON>J. James Exon</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Neb.</LOCATION>, is 68. Comedian-director <PERSON>David Steinberg</PERSON> is 47. Actor <PERSON>Sam
Elliott</PERSON> is 45. Boxer <PERSON>Ken Norton</PERSON> is 44. Football quarterback <PERSON>Doug
Williams</PERSON> is 34. Actress <PERSON>Melanie Griffith</PERSON> is 32. Singer <LOCATION>Whitney
Houston</LOCATION> is 26.
   Thought for Today: ``Civilization is a race between education
and catastrophe.'' _ <PERSON>H.G. Wells</PERSON>, English autor (1866-1946).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance Wednesday, Aug. 9</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890626-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-26-89 0834EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv06   06-26 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv06,0507</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv06</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thursday, July 6</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>July 6</DATE>, the <DATE>187th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 178
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>July 6, 1885</DATE>, French scientist <PERSON>Louis Pasteur</PERSON> successfully
tested an anti-rabies vaccine on a boy who had been bitten by an
infected dog.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1483</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>England's King Richard III</ORGANIZATION> was crowned.
   In <DATE>1535</DATE>, Sir <PERSON>Thomas More</PERSON> was executed in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> for treason.
   In <DATE>1777</DATE>, during the <ORGANIZATION>American Revolution</ORGANIZATION>, British forces led by
Gen. <PERSON>John Burgoyne</PERSON> captured <LOCATION>Fort Ticonderoga</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1854</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Republican Party</ORGANIZATION> came into being at a convention in
<LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1917</DATE>, during World War I, Arab forces led by <ORGANIZATION>British Capt.
T.E. Lawrence</ORGANIZATION> captured the port of <LOCATION>Aqaba</LOCATION> from the Turks.
   In <DATE>1923</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</ORGANIZATION> was formed.
   In <DATE>1928</DATE>, a preview was held in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> of the first all-talking
feature, ``The Lights of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.''
   In <DATE>1933</DATE>, the first All Star baseball game was played, at
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Comiskey Park</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> defeated the <ORGANIZATION>National
League</ORGANIZATION> 4-2.
   In <DATE>1944</DATE>, nearly 170 people died when fire broke out in the main
tent of the <ORGANIZATION>Ringling Brothers</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Barnum</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bailey Circus</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Conn</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1945</DATE>, President <PERSON>Harry S. Truman</PERSON> signed an executive order
establishing the Medal of Freedom.
   In <DATE>1945</DATE>, <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> became the first nation to formally accept the
<ORGANIZATION>United Nations Charter</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1957</DATE>, <PERSON>Althea Gibson</PERSON> became the first black tennis player to
win a Wimbledon singles title, defeating fellow American Darlene
Hard 6-3, 6-2.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, the Biafran War erupted as Nigerian forces invaded an
eastern region which had declared its independence <DATE>May 30</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, <PERSON>Fred Lynn</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Angels hit the first grand
slam in an All Star game as the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> zoomed to a 13-3
victory over the <ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   Ten years ago: President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> launched a ten-day summit
on domestic issues at his Camp <PERSON>David</PERSON> retreat in <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> renewed its invitation to the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to hold talks on banning space weapons, but said the
Americans had to agree first to limit the agenda to that issue.
   One year ago: Medical waste and other debris began washing up on
<LOCATION>New York City-area</LOCATION> seashores, forcing the closing down of several
popular beaches.
   Today's birthdays: Former first lady <PERSON>Nancy Reagan</PERSON> is 68. Actor
<PERSON>William Schallert</PERSON> is 67. Former talk show host <PERSON>Merv Griffin</PERSON> is 64.
Actress <PERSON>Janet Leigh</PERSON> is 62. Comedian <PERSON>Pat Paulsen</PERSON> is 62.
Singer-actress <ORGANIZATION>Della Reese</ORGANIZATION> is 57. Actor <PERSON>Ned Beatty</PERSON> is 52.
Actor-director <PERSON>Sylvester Stallone</PERSON> is 43. Football
player-turned-actor <PERSON>Fred Dryer</PERSON> is 43. Actress <PERSON>Shelley Hack</PERSON> is 37.
Hockey player <PERSON>Ron Duguay</PERSON> is 32.
   Thought for today: ``The difference between intelligence and
education is this: Intelligence will make you a good living.'' _
<PERSON>Charles F. Kettering</PERSON>, American engineer (1876-1958).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891016-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-16-89 0843EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   10-16 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0516</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tuesday, Oct. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>Oct. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>297th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 68
   Today's highlight in history:
   <DATE>Fifty years ago</DATE>, on <DATE>Oct. 24, 1939</DATE>, nylon stockings went on sale
for the first time as several stores in <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Del.</LOCATION>, began
offering the much-awaited hosiery made with <ORGANIZATION>Du Pont</ORGANIZATION>'s new synthetic
yarn. The day's shipment of 4,000 pairs of nylon stockings, ranging
in price from <MONEY>$1.15</MONEY> to <MONEY>$1.35</MONEY> a pair, sold out quickly.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1537</DATE>, <PERSON>Jane Seymour</PERSON>, the third wife of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>King Henry
VII</ORGANIZATION>, died 12 days after giving birth to <LOCATION>Prince Edward</LOCATION>, later <ORGANIZATION>King
Edward VI</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1648</DATE>, the Peace of <LOCATION>Westphalia</LOCATION> ended the Thirty Years War and
effectively destroyed the <ORGANIZATION>Holy Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1861</DATE>, the first transcontinental telegraph message was sent
as Justice <PERSON>Stephen J. Field</PERSON> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> sent a telegram to
President <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1901</DATE>, <PERSON>Anna Edson Taylor</PERSON>, a 43-year-old widow, became the
first person to go over <LOCATION>Niagara Falls</LOCATION> in a barrel and live to tell
about it. <PERSON>Mrs. Taylor</PERSON>'s dreams of fame and fortune failed to
materialize, however, and she died in poverty in <DATE>1921</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1931</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>George Washington Bridge</ORGANIZATION>, connecting <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, opened to traffic.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, <PERSON>Benny Goodman</PERSON> and his orchestra recorded their
signature theme, ``Let's Dance,'' for <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Records</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, the 40-hour work week went into effect under the Fair
Labor Standards Act of <DATE>1938</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1945</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> officially came into existence as
its charter took effect.
   In <DATE>1952</DATE>, in a speech in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, Republican presidential
candidate <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> declared, ``I shall go to <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>'' as
he promised to end the war.
   In <DATE>1962</DATE>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> blockade of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> during the missile crisis
officially began under a proclamation signed by President <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>
the day before.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, thirty years after it was expelled for refusing to
answer allegations of corruption, the <ORGANIZATION>Teamsters</ORGANIZATION> union was welcomed
back into the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION>.
   Ten years ago: President <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> announced the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was
prepared to furnish <MONEY>$70 million</MONEY> in emergency food aid to <LOCATION>Cambodia</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: A visit to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> by French President <PERSON>Francois
Mitterrand</PERSON> was marred by a diplomatic flap as <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> Yard
announced that a French bodyguard had planted unarmed explosives on
the grounds of the French ambassador's residence to test British
security.
   One year ago: The crew of the <LOCATION>U.S.S. Vincennes</LOCATION> received an
emotional homecoming in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, nearly four months after the
cruiser shot down an Iranian jetliner in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, killing
all 290 people aboard.
   Today's Birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> president <PERSON>Dr. Bobby Brown</PERSON> is
64. Football hall-of-famer <PERSON>Y.A. Tittle</PERSON> is 63. Actor-producer <PERSON>David
Nelson</PERSON> is 53. Actor <PERSON>Kevin Kline</PERSON> is 42.
   Thought for Today: ``Vanity, vanity, all is vanity, that's any
fun at all for humanity.'' _<PERSON>Ogden Nash</PERSON>, American poet (1902-1971).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Tuesday, Oct. 24</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901015-0217 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-15-90 0822EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   10-15 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0523</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Wednesday, Oct. 24</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Oct. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>297th day of 1990</DATE>. There are 68
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>Oct. 24, 1901</DATE>, <PERSON>Anna Edson Taylor</PERSON>, a 43-year-old widow, became
the first person to go over <LOCATION>Niagara Falls</LOCATION> in a barrel and live to
tell about it. (<PERSON>Mrs. Taylor</PERSON>'s dreams of fame and fortune failed to
materialize, however, and she died in poverty in <DATE>1921</DATE>.)
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1537</DATE>, <PERSON>Jane Seymour</PERSON>, the third wife of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>King Henry
VIII</PERSON>, died 12 days after giving birth to <LOCATION>Prince Edward</LOCATION>, later <ORGANIZATION>King
Edward VI</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1648</DATE>, the Peace of <LOCATION>Westphalia</LOCATION> ended the 30 Years War and
effectively destroyed the <ORGANIZATION>Holy Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1861</DATE>, the first transcontinental telegraph message was sent
as Justice <PERSON>Stephen J. Field</PERSON> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> transmitted a telegram to
President <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1931</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>George Washington Bridge</ORGANIZATION>, connecting <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, opened to traffic.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, nylon stockings went on sale for the first time as
several stores in <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Del.</LOCATION>, began offering the much-awaited
hosiery made from <ORGANIZATION>Du Pont</ORGANIZATION>'s new synthetic yarn.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, <PERSON>Benny Goodman</PERSON> and his orchestra recorded their
signature theme, ``Let's Dance,'' for <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Records</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, 50 years ago, the 40-hour work week went into effect
under the Fair Labor Standards Act of <DATE>1938</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1945</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> officially came into existence as
its charter took effect.
   In <DATE>1952</DATE>, in a speech in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, Republican presidential
candidate <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> declared, ``I shall go to <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>'' as
he promised to end the war.
   In <DATE>1962</DATE>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> blockade of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> during the missile crisis
officially began under a proclamation signed by President <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>
the day before.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, 30 years after it was expelled for refusing to answer
allegations of corruption, the <ORGANIZATION>Teamsters</ORGANIZATION> union was welcomed back
into the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION>.
   Ten years ago: The merchant freighter <LOCATION>S.S.</LOCATION> Poet departed
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> bound for Port Said, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, with a crew of 34 and a
cargo of grain; it was never heard from again. (The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION>
believes the Poet sank in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> too quickly for any distress
call to be sent.)
   Five years ago: President <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> committed the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> to a ``fresh start'' in U.S.-Soviet relations during a
speech to the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>. Ines <PERSON>Guadalupe Duarte Duran</PERSON>,
the daughter of <ORGANIZATION>El Salvador</ORGANIZATION>'s president, <PERSON>Jose Napoleon Duarte</PERSON>, was
released by leftist rebels as part of a prisoner exchange.
   One year ago: Former television evangelist <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> was
sentenced by a judge in <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, to 45 years in prison for
fraud and conspiracy.
   Today's Birthdays: Football Hall-of-Famer <PERSON>Y.A. Tittle</PERSON> is 64.
Actor-producer <PERSON>David Nelson</PERSON> is 54. Actor <PERSON>Kevin Kline</PERSON> is 43.
   Thought for Today: ``History must always be taken with a grain
of salt. It is, after all, not a science but an art.'' - <PERSON>Phyllis
McGinley</PERSON>, American poet and author (1905-1978).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wednesday, Oct. 24</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Oct. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>297th day of 1990</DATE>. There are 68
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>Oct. 24, 1901</DATE>, <PERSON>Anna Edson Taylor</PERSON>, a 43-year-old widow, became
the first person to go over <LOCATION>Niagara Falls</LOCATION> in a barrel and live to
tell about it. (<PERSON>Mrs. Taylor</PERSON>'s dreams of fame and fortune failed to
materialize, however, and she died in poverty in <DATE>1921</DATE>.)
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1537</DATE>, <PERSON>Jane Seymour</PERSON>, the third wife of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>King Henry
VIII</PERSON>, died 12 days after giving birth to <LOCATION>Prince Edward</LOCATION>, later <ORGANIZATION>King
Edward VI</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1648</DATE>, the Peace of <LOCATION>Westphalia</LOCATION> ended the 30 Years War and
effectively destroyed the <ORGANIZATION>Holy Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1861</DATE>, the first transcontinental telegraph message was sent
as Justice <PERSON>Stephen J. Field</PERSON> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> transmitted a telegram to
President <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1931</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>George Washington Bridge</ORGANIZATION>, connecting <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, opened to traffic.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, nylon stockings went on sale for the first time as
several stores in <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Del.</LOCATION>, began offering the much-awaited
hosiery made from <ORGANIZATION>Du Pont</ORGANIZATION>'s new synthetic yarn.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, <PERSON>Benny Goodman</PERSON> and his orchestra recorded their
signature theme, ``Let's Dance,'' for <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Records</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, 50 years ago, the 40-hour work week went into effect
under the Fair Labor Standards Act of <DATE>1938</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1945</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> officially came into existence as
its charter took effect.
   In <DATE>1952</DATE>, in a speech in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, Republican presidential
candidate <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> declared, ``I shall go to <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>'' as
he promised to end the war.
   In <DATE>1962</DATE>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> blockade of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> during the missile crisis
officially began under a proclamation signed by President <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>
the day before.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, 30 years after it was expelled for refusing to answer
allegations of corruption, the <ORGANIZATION>Teamsters</ORGANIZATION> union was welcomed back
into the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION>.
   Ten years ago: The merchant freighter <LOCATION>S.S.</LOCATION> Poet departed
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> bound for Port Said, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, with a crew of 34 and a
cargo of grain; it was never heard from again. (The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION>
believes the Poet sank in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> too quickly for any distress
call to be sent.)
   Five years ago: President <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> committed the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> to a ``fresh start'' in U.S.-Soviet relations during a
speech to the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>. Ines <PERSON>Guadalupe Duarte Duran</PERSON>,
the daughter of <ORGANIZATION>El Salvador</ORGANIZATION>'s president, <PERSON>Jose Napoleon Duarte</PERSON>, was
released by leftist rebels as part of a prisoner exchange.
   One year ago: Former television evangelist <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> was
sentenced by a judge in <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, to 45 years in prison for
fraud and conspiracy.
   Today's Birthdays: Football Hall-of-Famer <PERSON>Y.A. Tittle</PERSON> is 64.
Actor-producer <PERSON>David Nelson</PERSON> is 54. Actor <PERSON>Kevin Kline</PERSON> is 43.
   Thought for Today: ``History must always be taken with a grain
of salt. It is, after all, not a science but an art.'' - <PERSON>Phyllis
McGinley</PERSON>, American poet and author (1905-1978).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900827-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-27-90 0818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv03   08-27 0495</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv03,0521</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv03</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday, Sept. 3</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 3</DATE>, the 246th day of <DATE>1990</DATE>. There are 119
   
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Sept. 3, 1783</DATE>, the Treaty of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> between the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> officially ended the Revolutionary War.
   
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1189</DATE>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s King Richard I (the Lion-Hearted) was crowned
in <LOCATION>Westminster</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1658</DATE>, <PERSON>Oliver Cromwell</PERSON>, the Lord Protector of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, died.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> declared war on <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, two days
after the Nazi invasion of <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, 50 years ago, <PERSON>Artie Shaw</PERSON> and his Gramercy Five recorded
``Summit Ridge Drive,'' ``Special Delivery Stomp,'' ``Keepin'
Myself for You'' and ``Cross Your Heart'' for RCA Victor in
<LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1943</DATE>, Allied forces invaded <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> in World War II.
   In <DATE>1951</DATE>, the television soap opera ``Search for Tomorrow'' made
its debut on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Nguyen Van Thieu</ORGANIZATION> was elected president of <LOCATION>South Vietnam</LOCATION>
under a new constitution.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, motorists in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> began driving on the right-hand
side of the road.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, the original version of the television game show
``What's My Line?,'' hosted by <PERSON>John Charles Daly</PERSON>, broadcast its
final episode after more than 17 years on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, football coach <PERSON>Vince Lombardi</PERSON> died in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, the unmanned <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> spacecraft Viking II landed on Mars
to take the first close-up, color photographs of the planet's
surface.
   In <DATE>1978</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>John Paul</PERSON> I was installed as the 264th supreme
pontiff of the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1979</DATE>, Hurricane David smashed trailers and beachfront
condominiums along the central <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> coast, leaving several
people dead and <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in damage.
   
   Ten years ago: Most workers in <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> who had gone on strike
were reported back on the job after major concessions by the
government, including the right to form independent trade unions.
   Five years ago: The space shuttle Discovery landed at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards
Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, ending a seven-day mission that
included the retrieval, repair and redeployment of a malfunctioning
satellite.
   One year ago: The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> began shipping a <MONEY>$65 million</MONEY>
package of military aircraft and weapons to help <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> fight its
war against drug lords.
   
   Today's Birthdays: Actress <PERSON>Kitty Carlisle Hart</PERSON> is 76. Cartoonist
<PERSON>Mort Walker</PERSON> is 67. Actress <PERSON>Anne Jackson</PERSON> is 64. Actress <PERSON>Irene Papas</PERSON>
is 64. Time magazine contributing editor <PERSON>Hugh Sidey</PERSON> is 63. Actress
<PERSON>Eileen Brennan</PERSON> is 55. Actress <PERSON>Pauline Collins</PERSON> is 50. Beach Boy <PERSON>Al
Jardine</PERSON> is 48. Actress <PERSON>Valerie Perrine</PERSON> is 47. Actor <PERSON>Charlie Sheen</PERSON>
is 25.
   
   Thought for Today: ``Labor is prior to, and independent of,
capital. Capital is only the fruit of labor, and could never have
existed if labor had not first existed. Labor is the superior of
capital, and deserves much the higher consideration.'' _<PERSON>Abraham
Lincoln</PERSON>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> president (1809-1865).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday, Sept. 3</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890703-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-03-89 1020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv11   07-03 0441</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv 11,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv11 ^For Release Tuesday, July 11</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>July 11</DATE>, the <DATE>192nd day of 1989</DATE>. There are 173
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>July 11</DATE>, the <DATE>192nd day of 1989</DATE>. There are 173
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for July 11</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880822-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-22-88 0722EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv03   08-22 0439</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv03,0459</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv03</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Saturday, Sept. 3</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 3</DATE>, the 247th day of <DATE>1988</DATE>. There are 119
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Sept. 3, 1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> declared war on <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>,
two days after the Nazi invasion of <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1189</DATE>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s King Richard I (the Lion-Hearted) was crowned
in <LOCATION>Westminster</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1658</DATE>, <PERSON>Oliver Cromwell</PERSON>, the Lord Protector of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, died.
   In <DATE>1783</DATE>, the Treaty of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> between the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great
Britain</LOCATION> officially ended the Revolutionary War.
   In <DATE>1943</DATE>, Allied forces invaded <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> in World War II.
   In <DATE>1951</DATE>, the television soap opera ``Search for Tomorrow'' made
its debut on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Nguyen Van Thieu</ORGANIZATION> was elected president of <LOCATION>South Vietnam</LOCATION>
under a new constitution.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, motorists in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> began driving on the right-hand
side of the road, instead of the left.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, the original version of the television game show
``What's My Line?,'' hosted by <PERSON>John Charles Daly</PERSON>, broadcast its
final episode after more than 17 years on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1969</DATE>, North Vietnamese president <PERSON>Ho Chi Minh</PERSON> died.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, football coach <PERSON>Vince Lombardi</PERSON> died in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, the unmanned <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> spacecraft Viking II landed on Mars
to take the first close-up, color photographs of the planet's
surface.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, the space shuttle Discovery made a safe landing at
<ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>, concluding a seven-day mission described by
one space agency official as ``near-perfect.''
   Ten years ago: Pope <PERSON>John Paul</PERSON> I was officially installed as the
264th supreme pontiff of the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> with a simple
yet colorful service in <LOCATION>St. Peter's Square</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: Demonstrators rallied from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, burning effigies of Soviet leaders and praying for the 269
people aboard a <ORGANIZATION>Korean Air Lines</ORGANIZATION> shot down by the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>. The
Soviet news agency <ORGANIZATION>TASS</ORGANIZATION>, without conceding the plane had been shot
down, accused the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> of waging an anti-Soviet campaign.
   One year ago: A Soviet prosecutor accused West German pilot
<PERSON>Mathias Rust</PERSON> of seeking ``cheap popularity'' by landing a private
plane in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Red Square</LOCATION>, and demanded Rust be sentenced to
eight years at hard labor. (Rust was freed by the Soviets <DATE>Aug. 3,
1988</DATE>.)
   Today's birthdays: Actress <PERSON>Kitty Carlisle Hart</PERSON> is 74. Cartoonist
<PERSON>Mort Walker</PERSON> is 65. Actress <PERSON>Anne Jackson</PERSON> is 62. Actress <PERSON>Irene Papas</PERSON>
is 62. Actress <PERSON>Eileen Brennan</PERSON> is 53. Actress <PERSON>Valerie Perrine</PERSON> is 45.
Actor <PERSON>Charlie Sheen</PERSON> is 23.
   Thought for today: ``Integrity needs no rules.'' _ <PERSON>Albert Camus</PERSON>,
French author and philosohper (1913-1960).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-16026</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJHCKADKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931008
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 OCT 93 / Arts: The Wilton Diptych remains enigmatic
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By SUSAN MOORE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
In an age which has seen blockbuster exhibitions swell to ever more
monstrous proportions, the <ORGANIZATION>National Gallery</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> has pioneered series
of modest shows which recognise how rewarding it can be to look hard and
think about a single work. For the first in a new series, Making and
Meaning, which again focuses on major works in its own collection, the
spotlight is directed towards the <PERSON>Wilton Diptych</PERSON> in the aftermath of its
recent cleaning and technical examination.
This small, portable altarpiece is one of the most refined and sumptuous
products of the late medieval world. It is also one of the most enigmatic.
Generations of scholars have debated who painted it, and why, and what it
meant to those who first saw it. The purpose of this exhibition, which is
supplemented by a small number of judicious loans of panels, manuscripts,
sculpture, metalwork and jewellery, is to offer visitors the possibility of
understanding a private and complex image. The temptation to tell them how
to interpret it is scrupulously resisted.
Although the <PERSON>Wilton Diptych</PERSON> has the inevitability of a dream, its two halves
make for a distinctly odd couple. On the barren earth of the left wing
kneels <PERSON>Richard II</PERSON> of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, identified as such by his personal emblems of
the white hart on his breast and the broomcods, or pods of the broom plant -
the planta genista from which the Plantagenets took their name - laced
around his neck. The three figures standing behind him - <PERSON>Edmund</PERSON>, king and
martyr, <PERSON>Edward</PERSON> the Confessor and <PERSON>John</PERSON> the <LOCATION>Baptist</LOCATION> - act as intercessors and
have been carefully chosen for their personal significance for the monarch.
The frieze of saints is remarkable for its evenly distributed verticality
while the profile portrait of the king has all the depth of a playing card.
The crowded panoply of the right wing could hardly be more different. Here
the Virgin stands cradling the <ORGANIZATION>Christ Child</ORGANIZATION> in a paradise garden, supported
by a company of angels who, wearing broomcods and white harts, seem to have
been liveried by the <ORGANIZATION>King of England</ORGANIZATION> rather than the <ORGANIZATION>Queen of Heaven</ORGANIZATION>. Arms
crossed, wings fluttering, seven of them form a backdrop to her, while four
more ring her round. This image is the epitome of a manner of painting that
was swept away by the Renaissance and the discovery of perspective, but here
too there is pictorial space.
The narrative link between the two is provided by the white banner
emblazoned by the red cross of <ORGANIZATION>Christ</ORGANIZATION>'s Resurrection which is also the
banner of <ORGANIZATION>St George</ORGANIZATION>. Its pinnacle is a silvered orb and that too alludes to
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. Recent cleaning has revealed that it contains a minute
representation of a green island, a white tower with two turrets, and a boat
in full sail. It is hard not to read it as 'this sceptred isle . . . and
precious stone set in the silver sea' of <ORGANIZATION>John of Gaunt</ORGANIZATION>'s speech in
<ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s Richard II.
This is no standard image of a donor being presented to the Virgin by his
patrons. Rather, it appears a carefully orchestrated expression of <PERSON>Richard</PERSON>'s
notion of the divine nature of his kingship and his hopes for salvation. As
such, the altarpiece is likely to have been made for the private devotions
of the king, a few years before his untimely death in <DATE>1399</DATE>.
The <PERSON>Wilton Diptych</PERSON> is one of the high points of the so-called <ORGANIZATION>International
Style</ORGANIZATION>, that phase of late Gothic art when painters and sculptors all over
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> seemed to be marching to the same drum. Such is the extent of
cross-fertilisation that no agreement has been reached about whether its
creator was English, French, Italian or Bohemian. The recent technical
examination has only confirmed that while the preparation of the ground of
the oak panels is typically Northern, the technique adopted for binding the
pigments and for the green undermodelling of the flesh tones is
characteristically Italian. The use of egg white allowed the painter to
exploit the full purity of the precious lapis lazuli which he ground to
produce the brilliant ultramarine.
Wherever he came from, the anonymous master of the <PERSON>Wilton Diptych</PERSON> was a
great painter. This is his (or her?) only surviving work. We have no idea
whether it belongs to his youth, maturity or old age. One thing is certain,
however: if it had not survived, no one would have felt the lack of it. The
picture stands as a poignant reminder of how much of our past has been lost.
That, and not just its quality, is part of its enchantment.
Sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>Esso UK plc</ORGANIZATION>, at the <ORGANIZATION>National Gallery</ORGANIZATION> until <DATE>December 12</DATE>,
admission free.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8412 Museums and Art Galleries.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890828-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-28-89 0935EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv03   08-28 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv03,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Sept. 3</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <DATE>September 3</DATE>, the <DATE>246th day of 1989</DATE>. There are
   Today's highlight in history:
   <DATE>Fifty years ago</DATE>, on <DATE>September 3, 1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>
declared war on <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, two days after the Nazi invasion of <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1189</DATE>, 800 years ago, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s King Richard I (The
Lionhearted) was crowned in <LOCATION>Westminster</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1658</DATE>, <PERSON>Oliver Cromwell</PERSON>, the Lord Protector of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, died.
   In <DATE>1783</DATE>, the Treaty of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> between the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great
Britain</LOCATION> officially ended the Revolutionary War.
   In <DATE>1943</DATE>, Allied forces invaded <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> in World War II.
   In <DATE>1951</DATE>, the television soap opera ``Search for Tomorrow'' made
its debut on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Nguyen Van Thieu</ORGANIZATION> was elected president of <LOCATION>South Vietnam</LOCATION>
under a new constitution.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, motorists in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> began driving on the right-hand side
of the road, instead of the left.
   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, the original version of the television game show
``What's My Line?,'' hosted by <PERSON>John Charles Daly</PERSON>, broadcast its
final episode after more than 17 years on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1969, 20 years ago</DATE>, <LOCATION>North Vietnamese</LOCATION> president <PERSON>Ho Chi Minh</PERSON>
died.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, football coach <PERSON>Vince Lombardi</PERSON> died in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, the unmanned <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> spacecraft Viking 2 landed on Mars to
take the first close-up, color photographs of the planet's surface.
   In <DATE>1978</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>John Paul</PERSON> I was installed as the 264th supreme
pontiff of the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, the space shuttle Discovery made a safe landing at
<ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>, concluding a seven-day mission.
   Ten years ago: Hurricane David smashed trailers and beachfront
condominiums along the central <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> coast, leaving several people
dead and <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in damage.
   Five years ago: Three French tourists were killed when a pipe
bomb exploded at <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>'s main train station, less than a week
before the start of a Canadian tour by Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON>. (A
<LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, man was later convicted of the bombing.)
   One year ago: On the presidential campaign trail, Democrat
<PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> paid a visit to <LOCATION>Ellis Island</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, while
Republican <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> met reporters at his official residence in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Today's Birthdays: Actress <PERSON>Kitty Carlisle Hart</PERSON> is 75. Cartoonist
<PERSON>Mort Walker</PERSON> is 66. Actress <PERSON>Anne Jackson</PERSON> is 63. Actress <PERSON>Irene Papas</PERSON>
is 63. Time contributing editor <PERSON>Hugh Sidey</PERSON> is 62. Actress <PERSON>Eileen
Brennan</PERSON> is 54. Beach Boy <PERSON>Al Jardine</PERSON> is 47. Actress <PERSON>Valerie Perrine</PERSON>
is 46. Actor <PERSON>Charlie Sheen</PERSON> is 24.
   Thought for Today: ``The die is cast.'' _ Attributed to <PERSON>Julius
Caesar</PERSON> by the Greek biographer <PERSON>Plutarch</PERSON> (A.D.46-A.D.120).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Use Sunday, September 3</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890902-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-89 1154EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-History Adv03   09-02 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv03,0496</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Sept. 3</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: DELETES 13th graf, `In 1969...,' to delete Ho Chi Minh death
on that date. Communique from Hanoi Thursday revealed he really died on
Sept. 2, 1969, sted Sept. 3. See story slugged AM-Ho Chi Minh.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 3</DATE>, the <DATE>246th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 119
   Today's highlight in history:
   Fifty years ago, on <DATE>Sept. 3, 1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> declared
war on <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, two days after the Nazi invasion of <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1189</DATE>, 800 years ago, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s King Richard I (The
Lionhearted) was crowned in <LOCATION>Westminster</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1658</DATE>, <PERSON>Oliver Cromwell</PERSON>, the Lord Protector of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, died.
   In <DATE>1783</DATE>, the Treaty of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> between the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great
Britain</LOCATION> officially ended the Revolutionary War.
   In <DATE>1943</DATE>, Allied forces invaded <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> in World War II.
   In <DATE>1951</DATE>, the television soap opera ``Search for Tomorrow'' made
its debut on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>.
