<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-EastGermany 3rdLd-Writethru a0577 12-22 0860</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0577,0882</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Surge Through as Berlin Wall Opens at Brandenburg Gate</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 9 grafs to ADD quotes from revelers. Pickup 8th pvs,
`The crowd...' Delete 19th graf pvs, `Others held...' to remove reference
to Ceausescu.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BER19</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of jubilant <ORGANIZATION>Berliners</ORGANIZATION> surged
through new openings in the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall at the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION>
<DATE>today</DATE> for the first time in 28 years.
   The celebrants braved an intermittent rain as they filled the
square in front of the towering symbol of the postwar division of
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> that is becoming a monument to the rapprochement of <LOCATION>East
Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>.
   East German Premier <PERSON>Hans Modrow</PERSON> met <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> Chancellor
<PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> at the border for the <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME> (<TIME>9 a.m. EST</TIME>) ceremony,
then they walked together into <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>. They were nearly
mobbed by the crowd as they walked to a platform in front of the
gate to address the exulting Berliners.
   Kohl called the occasion ``a fantastic thing.''
   Thousands drenched by the rain uncorked champagne and danced
atop the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall, the once impregnable concrete barrier that is
quickly crumbling.
   The opening was televised live in both countries. ``This is
where the heart of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> pounds,'' said a commentator for <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION>'s ZDF network.
   Two banners were unfurled near the new crossings to protest the
killings of demonstrators in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>.
   ``The last time I was here was as a kid when I used to play on
this very spot. I never thought I'd come here again, it's really
wonderful,'' said <PERSON>Peter Rebachmann</PERSON>, 42, of <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>.
   ``What a beautiful Christmas present. I am so elated that I can
experience this,'' said a middle-aged woman.
   The crowd cheered and set off firecrackers when East German
workers started dismantling the wall <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. The workers
used a crane to remove the rounded top of the wall.
   ``This is an experience that will go down in history. The gate
was a symbol of division of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Jozef Polak</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>West
Berlin</LOCATION> mechanic.
   More than 10,000 people had jammed the western side for the two
sections of the wall to fall down. Some climbed on trees to get a
better view. More people kept arriving throughout the <TIME>night</TIME>.
   A loud cheer sounded through the <TIME>night</TIME> air as the East German
crane lifted a 3{-foot-wide segment of the concrete to make the
first hole in that part of the wall shortly after <TIME>midnight</TIME>.
   The two new crossing points are 15 feet wide each. One is for
Westerners going into <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>, the other for East Germans going
to <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>.
   Although more than 20 border crossings have been made at the
wall since <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> opened its borders to the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> on <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> has the most symbolic meaning for <ORGANIZATION>Berliners</ORGANIZATION>.
   The 200-year-old gate, <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>'s most famous landmark, remained
on the eastern side when <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s Communist authorities built
the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall in <DATE>1961</DATE>.
   Graffiti on the western side at one of the segments to be
removed said, ``One day every wall must fall down.''
   <PERSON>Friedhelm Brinkman</PERSON>, a salesman from <LOCATION>Dortmund</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, said
he drove 360 miles to see the event.
   ``This was the central place in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> where everything happened
(before the war). I always thought this place would be opened again
and that's why I came tonight,'' he said <DATE>late Thursday</DATE>.
   Some people in the crowd shouted, ``<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>United
Fatherland</ORGANIZATION>,'' _ the rallying call of East German supporters of
German unification.
   
   The crowd was kept well away from the wall by barricades and
cordons of <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> police to prevent them from possibly trying
to cross the wall.
   After <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s dramatic opening of the borders, thousands
of people danced on the section of the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall at <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg
Gate</ORGANIZATION>.
   Crowds pulled down one segment of the wall in unforgettable
scenes seen on television worldwide. Thousands of people had waited
in vain for the gate to be opened in the first few days after the
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall started crumbling down in the wake of <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s
peaceful revolution.
   Kohl and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> announced the agreement to open the two
crossings when <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> visited <LOCATION>Dresden</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The gate, the size of a five-story building on top of which is a
bronze chariot with the goddess <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON>, was the backdrop for
<PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>'s rise to power and his last stand. It was also where East
German workers began a <DATE>1953</DATE> uprising that was crushed by Soviet
tanks.
   In <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>, the famous Unter den <PERSON>Linden</PERSON> boulevard ends at
the gate. On the Western side, the sprawling avenue that leads to
the gate was renamed <DATE>June 17</DATE> Street, after the date of the uprising.
   Nazi brown shirts staged a triumphant torch parade through the
gate when <PERSON>Adolf Hitler</PERSON> was named chancellor on <DATE>Jan. 30, 1933</DATE>.
   In the final days of World War II, the six-column sandstone gate
was heavily damaged as Soviet tanks closed in on Hitler's bunker in
the chancellory. It marked the border between the Soviet and
British sectors when the victorious allies divided conquered <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>
into four sectors.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0645 12-22 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0645,0780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brandenburg Gate Opened in Emotional Ceremony</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to include estimate of crowd; picks up 6th
graf ``More than ...''</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BER19</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of people surged through
two new <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall openings <DATE>Friday</DATE> and celebrated at the
<ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>, a monument to German unity that became a symbol
of division when the wall went up in <DATE>1961</DATE>.
   The new passages, immediately north and south of the towering
gate, were opened at <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME> in a ceremony attended by Chancellor
<PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> of <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and the East German premier, <PERSON>Hans
Modrow</PERSON>.
   Berliners rushed through them, back and forth, then uncorked of
champagne and drank to the famous landmark that was sealed inside
<LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> for 28 years.
   Security on both sides collapsed as the vast crowd broke through
metal barriers and rushed to the gate, filling the vast <LOCATION>Paris
Square</LOCATION>, where people hugged each other and danced together.
   A sea of people who had waited patiently for hours in
intermittent rain surrounded the 200-year-old sandstone monument.
   <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> police said about 30,000 people gathered on the
Western side before the gate was opened. The crowd on the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>
side appeared much larger, but there were no official estimates of
its size.
   More than 20 crossings have been cut through the wall since <LOCATION>East
Germany</LOCATION> opened its borders <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>, but the freeing of the
<ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> was the emotional climax of the coming together of
a people divided since the end of World War II.
   In addition to being cut off from <LOCATION>West Berliners</LOCATION>, the gate also
was inaccessible to East Berliners until <DATE>Friday</DATE> because it lay in
the off-limits East German border zone.
   Flags of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> flew above the
huge crowd. Several people who climbed the wall held up a sign
saying ``Come Together.''
   Hundreds of people climbed atop the thick section of wall that
remains directly in front of the gate, dancing and hugging in
chaotic scenes reminiscent of <DATE>November</DATE>.
   Kohl called the opening of the gate a ``fantastic thing.''
   He and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> met at <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME> on the border, shook hands and
walked together to a platform to address the crowd. They were
nearly mobbed by the exultant crowd.
   National television of both countries broadcast the event.
``This is where the heart of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> pounds,'' said a commentator
for the <ORGANIZATION>ZDF</ORGANIZATION> network of <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> said the historic Brandenburg Gate's new function should
be ``to serve the peace.''
   The speeches were drowned out by the mass of people, many with
tears in their eyes, shouting with joy.
   <PERSON>Peter Rebachmann</PERSON>, a 42-year-old <PERSON>East Berliner</PERSON>, said: ``The last
time I was here was as a kid, when I used to play on this very
spot. I never thought I'd come here again; it's really wonderful.''
   ``It's great, but it's too bad my father didn't live to see
it,'' said <PERSON>Hans Achtzehnig</PERSON>, another resident of <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>.
   ``What a beautiful Christmas present!'' said a middle-aged woman
who did not give her name.
   Several signs carried by the crowd called for German unity, a
demand made by a growing number of participants in East German
demonstrations.
   ``<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, One city, One Nation,'' said one sign.
   People on the eastern side of the wall greeted Kohl with shouts
of ``Helmut! Helmut!'' He and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> announced the agreement to
open the gate during a visit Kohl made to <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
and <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Thousands of people cheered and set off firecrackers earlier
when East German workers began knocking the new holes in the wall.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>, its battle-scarred columns are topped with
a bronze chariot of the goddess Victory in a chariot, was the
backdrop for <PERSON>Adolf Hitler</PERSON>'s rise to power and his last stand. It
also was where East German workers began an uprising in <DATE>1953</DATE> that
was crushed by Soviet tanks.
   In <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>, the Unter den <PERSON>Linden</PERSON> boulevard ends at the gate.
On the Western side, the avenue that leads to the gate was renamed
<DATE>June 17</DATE>, for the date of the uprising.
   Nazi ``brown shirts'' made a triumphant torchlit parade through
the gate when <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON> was named chancellor on <DATE>Jan. 30, 1933</DATE>.
   In the final days of World War II, the six-column gate, five
stories high, was badly damaged when Soviet tanks closed in on
Hitler's bunker in the chancellery. It marked the border between
the Soviet and British sectors when the victorious allies divided
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> into four sectors.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0826EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0492 12-23 0710</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0492,0727</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Pour Through Newly Opened Brandenburg Gate</HEAD>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING to indicate 1st Ld-Writethru</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 6 grafs to UPDATE thousands pouring into West Berlin
for last-minute Christmas shopping. Pickup 7th, `West German Chancellor...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of East Berliners poured through
new <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall border crossings at the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>today</DATE> for
a final, frantic day of Christmas shopping in the well-stocked
stores of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   Other Berliners headed for home after singing and dancing late
into the night at the newly opened gate, which has been transformed
from a symbol of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s divisions into one of East-West
rapprochement.
   Although visa-free travel for West Germans to <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>
technically does not take effect until <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, there were few
formalities at the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION>, opened only <DATE>Friday</DATE>, for those
who headed East today.
   Throughout the night <DATE>Friday</DATE>, a steady clink of metal against
stone accompanied the merrymakers as hundreds of souvenir seekers
chipped away at the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall near the gate in the 28-year-old
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall.
   At other crossing points, East German shoppers laden with
purchases from <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> carried Christmas presents, cases of
beer and bags of oranges.
   West German television periodically carried live coverage of the
festivities <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, showing the crowd dancing on top of the
wall, popping champagne corks and waving sparklers.
   West German Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> and East German Premier <PERSON>Hans
Modrow</PERSON> met <DATE>Friday</DATE> for the second time in a week at a ceremony
formally opening two border crossings in the wall just north and
south of the towering gate.
   Security collapsed as soon as the two crossings were opened.
Thousands of people pushed down metal barriers erected to control
the crowd and swept through the vast <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> square, snaking through
the gate and climbing the wall.
   West <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> police estimated that more than 30,000 people had
gathered on the Western side for the ceremony. The crowd on the
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> side appeared to be much larger, but there were no official
estimates.
   Although more than 20 border crossings have been cut through the
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall since <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> opened its borders to the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>, the opening of the Brandenburg Gate was the emotional
climax of the rapid merger of the people divided since the end of
World War II.
   The openings resulted from a popular uprising in <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>
that drove out its hard-line Communist leaders.
   When the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall was built in <DATE>1961</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>'s most famous landmark that straddled a main prewar
thoroughfare, remained in the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>. It was also inaccessible to
East Berliners until <DATE>Friday</DATE> because it was part of the off-limit
East German border zone.
   The crowd carried <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, West German and East German flags. One
large sign saying in English ``Come Together'' was held aloft by
several people who climbed atop the wall.
   The thick section of the wall directly in front of the gate
remains, but hundreds climbed on top to dance and hug in joyful
scenes reminiscent of the time when the borders were first opened
in <DATE>November</DATE>.
   Kohl said the opening of the gate was a ``fantastic thing.''
   He and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> met <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> on the border line, shook
hands and then walked together to a platform to address the crowd.
   The two leaders were nearly mobbed by the exultant crowd as
security officials tried in vain to establish some control.
   The ceremony was broadcast live on both countries' national
television.
   ``This is where the heart of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> pounds,'' said a commentator
for <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s ZDF network.
   Modrow reminded the crowd of the role the gate has played in
German history, then said its new function should be ``to serve the
peace.''
   Kohl said, ``This is the happiest day in my life, because I feel
that here in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> I am standing in the middle of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.''
   ``We need the sympathy, the support and the approval of our
neighbors'' as the two Germanys move closer together, he said. ``We
want peace and freedom.''
   The speeches were drowned out by the noisy crowd. Many people
had tears in their eyes as they mingled together.
   ``<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, have fun now,'' <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> mayor <PERSON>Walter Momper</PERSON> told
the crowd.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891115-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-15-89 1537EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Gate     11-15 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Gate,0619</SECOND>
<HEAD>200-Year-Old Gate Again a Stage for History</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The battle-scarred sandstone columns of the
<ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>, which were the backdrop for Hitler's last stand
and a workers' uprising against Communism in <DATE>1953</DATE>, once again tower
over the stage of history.
   The 200-year-old gate, <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>'s most famous landmark, has stood
as the symbol of German division for 28 years.
   With the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall quickly crumbling, the gate is being called
the symbol of German unity. It also has been the backdrop for much
of the television coverage beamed around the world in the past week
of fast-moving developments.
   <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> has said it is considering opening a <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall
border crossing at the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>. There was wide speculation
in <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> that an opening would be knocked through the wall
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>, although there was no official confirmation.
   The gate _ the size of a five-story building _ remained on the
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> side when the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall was built in <DATE>1961</DATE>. The famous
Unten den <PERSON>Linden</PERSON> boulevard ends at the gate.
   On the Western side, the sprawling avenue that leads to the gate
was renamed <DATE>June 17</DATE> Street, after the date of the workers' uprising
in <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> in <DATE>1953</DATE> that was bloodily crushed by Soviet tanks.
   East <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> workers, angered by the nationalization and
collectivization policies of the Communist government, began their
street demonstrations at the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> and tore down the red
flag from the top of the gate.
   In the closing days of World War II, Soviet tanks rumbled by the
gate as they closed in on <PERSON>Adolf Hitler</PERSON>'s bunker in the chancellery.
Only a few hundred yards away was the heart of Hitler's government
in a small complex on <LOCATION>Wilhelmstrasse</LOCATION>, which also served as the seat
of the imperial government. The Reichstag also is not far away.
   The Brandenburg Gate also marked <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>'s rise to power. Nazi
brown shirts staged a triumphant torch parade through the gate when
<PERSON>Hitler</PERSON> was named chancellor on <DATE>Jan. 30, 1933</DATE>.
   Built from <DATE>1788</DATE> to <DATE>1791</DATE> by <PERSON>Carl Gotthard Langhans</PERSON>, the
six-column gate was commissioned by Prussian King <PERSON>Frederick Wilhelm
II</PERSON>. When it was built, it opened the road to the region of
<LOCATION>Brandenburg</LOCATION>, getting its name.
   The gate was modeled after the <LOCATION>Acropolis</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION> to reflect
the king's intention to make <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> a city of learning and arts.
   On top of the gate is a bronze chariot with the goddess
<PERSON>Victoria</PERSON>. It was hauled away to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> when <PERSON>Napoleon</PERSON> defeated the
Prussians at <ORGANIZATION>Jena</ORGANIZATION> and Auerstadt on <DATE>Oct. 27, 1806</DATE>. He marched into
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> through the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION>.
   The chariot was brought back to <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> after <PERSON>Napoleon</PERSON>'s defeat
in <DATE>1814</DATE>. After the Franco-German war in 1870-71, the victorious
Prussians made a triumphal return to <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, the new imperial
capital, again through the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>.
   The gate was heavily damaged in the last days of World War II
and marked the border between the Soviet and British sectors of
conquered <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>.
   It was restored between <DATE>1956</DATE> and <DATE>1958</DATE>. The chariot was repaired
and paid for by <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> under Mayor <PERSON>Willy Brandt</PERSON>, but <LOCATION>East
Berlin</LOCATION> authorities removed the Prussian eagle and the iron cross
from <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION>'s staff before mounting it again.
   In <DATE>1963</DATE>, Communist soldiers dropped huge red drapes over the
gate to prevent President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> from looking into <LOCATION>East
Berlin</LOCATION> when he visited <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> and delivered his ``Ich bin ein
Berliner'' speech.
   The gate, the last of the 20 gates to <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> still standing, is
66 feet high, 215 feet wide and 36 feet deep.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122389-0073 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 152644 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 23, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 24; Column 1; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
726 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BERLIN'S HISTORIC BRANDENBURG GATE REOPENS; 
</P>
<P>
GERMANY: RAIN FAILS TO DAMPEN THE CROWD'S ENTHUSIASM AS THE SYMBOL OF A DIVIDED 
LAND GETS TWO NEW BORDER OPENINGS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By WILLIAM TUOHY, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WEST BERLIN 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Brandenburg Gate, the Cold War symbol of a divided <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, a divided 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and a divided <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, was reopened <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> amid joyous scenes 
undampened by gray skies, relentless rain and the quickly gathering darkness. 
</P>
<P>
The historic, six-columned Grecian-style monument in the heart of the sprawling 
former capital of the German Empire was overwhelmed by East and West Berliners 
who swarmed around it, reveling in this long-awaited Christmas gift. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall was breached in two places at either side of the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg 
Gate</ORGANIZATION>, leaving a staunch, thick portion of the wall in place. But the wall 
itself seemed almost superfluous, as young people climbed over it, posing for 
pictures and waving champagne bottles, then jumped down on the other side. 
</P>
<P>
The two new border crossings, which had been prepared by East German engineers 
all night <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, were formally opened at <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> by West German 
Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> and East German Prime Minister <PERSON>Hans Modrow</PERSON> on the east 
side of the wall. 
</P>
<P>
As <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> walked through the central arch of the 200-year-old gate, 
originally built to separate old <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> from the fields to the west, <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> 
declared: "This is where the German <PERSON>Reich</PERSON> went down in flames lit by German war 
criminals. The burning stench of war must never again be smelled here. It must 
be a gate of peace." 
</P>
<P>
As he spoke, many East Germans in the crowd chanted: "Helmut, Helmut!" 
</P>
<P>
Kohl seemed purposely to avoid sounding the German reunification issue in his 
brief speech when he said: "Let us be patient and prudent in the steps we have 
to take to walk forward into our common future." 
</P>
<P>
But a banner said it for <ORGANIZATION>Kohl</ORGANIZATION> in English: "<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Is One Town -- <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> Is One 
Nation." 
</P>
<P>
West <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Walter Momper</PERSON> told the crowd: "<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> is still divided but 
the people are no longer separated." 
</P>
<P>
East and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> police officers made no attempt to interfere with 
celebrants atop the wall, nor with others who for the first time began banging 
away at the wall from the east side to chip off pieces. 
</P>
<P>
As the wine corks popped, the <ORGANIZATION>British Royal Welch Fusiliers</ORGANIZATION> band -- the gate 
stands in the British sector of <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> -- played marches, but then broke, 
incongruously, into "Deep in the Heart of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
Inspired by a trumpet player standing with thousands of other revelers on top 
of the wall, the crowd sang everything from "Amazing Grace" to "Such a Day as 
Wonderful as <DATE>Today</DATE>," an old <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> folk favorite. 
</P>
<P>
Fireworks lent the occasion a festive atmosphere. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall has been opened at various checkpoints since <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>, but the 
<ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> had never served as a border crossing since the wall went up 
in <DATE>1961</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Before the wall was erected, the gate had been the entryway between the two 
sides of the divided city. Under it passed the <ORGANIZATION>Unter Den Linden</ORGANIZATION>, once the most 
famous and elegant thoroughfare in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In earlier times, the gate was the center arch for promenades by Prussian 
aristocrats, Nazi parades with Hitler in an open car and, in the end, for 
Soviet tanks marauding through it during the apocalyptic Battle for <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> in 
<DATE>1945</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
So for many Germans, the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>'s opening <DATE>Friday</DATE> has been the 
ultimate test of the East German government's decision to liberalize relations 
between East and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> -- and the two Germanys. 
</P>
<P>
As <PERSON>Franz Bertele</PERSON>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s chief emissary to <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, put it as he 
wandered on the east side: "It's a great feeling to be able to walk under the 
gate after 28 years. We never thought we would live long enough to see this 
day. 
</P>
<P>
"My only problem is that I lost my wife in all the excitement. I'm trying to 
find her." 
</P>
<P>
One couple who were married in <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> decided to come through 
the new Brandenburg opening to have a ceremonial dinner in <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Dietrich</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sybile Schumann</PERSON>, she wearing a white hat and veil and carrying a 
bouquet of flowers, both said "wunderbar" -- wonderful. 
</P>
<P>
"My own parents met at the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION> in <DATE>1958</DATE>," said <PERSON>Sybile</PERSON>. "So walking 
through on my wedding day is lovely -- even though it is raining." 
</P>
<P>
And under the tall columns, three generations of one <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> family were 
heading west -- for the moment. 
</P>
<P>
Grandfather <PERSON>Willi Szeszrat</PERSON>, son <PERSON>Juergen</PERSON>, and 8-year-old grandson, <PERSON>Mario</PERSON>, walked 
together toward the new opening. 
</P>
<P>
"We just wanted to be part of it all," said <PERSON>Juergen</PERSON>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Officials at the reopening of Berlin's Brandenburg Gate. Agence 
France-Presse; Photo, Crowds gather at Brandenburg Gate for opening of Berlin 
Wall there. Reuters; Photo, (Orange County Edition) COLOR, Crowds gather at 
Brandenburg Gate for opening of Berlin Wall. Reuters 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BERLIN WALL; EAST BERLIN; WEST BERLIN; EAST GERMANY -- BORDERS -- WEST GERMANY; 
REUNIFICATION; EAST GERMANY -- TRAVEL RESTRICTIONS -- WEST GERMANY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900429-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-29-90 2356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BerlinWall     04-29 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Berlin Wall,0572</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wall's Most Famous Section Falls to Wrecking Crew</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The big arm of the crane smashed into the
stacked slabs of concrete like a fist through a window, scattering
enough bits of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall to fill a dozen souvenir stands.
   A small crowd lingered close to <TIME>midnight</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to watch the
floodlit scene, wincing as a screeching, scraping array of machines
began clearing away the most famous section of the battered barrier.
   From this spot _ the gigantic <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> serving as a
breathtaking backdrop _ came the most vivid image of the collapse
of <LOCATION>Communist East Germany</LOCATION>.
   Thousands climbed the section of wall when the country's borders
were opened on <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>, chipping away at the stretch of stone that
that was once an art gallery of political graffiti.
   ``I remember walking with my old mother here on <DATE>Nov. 5</DATE> and
telling her that it won't be long before this wall is gone,'' said
<PERSON>West Berliner Hans Ulrich</PERSON>, 42, as he leaned on a guardrail and
watched the destruction.
   ``Of course, I'd been saying that for years.''
   When they built the wall around <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> nearly three decades
ago, Communist authorities put the most effort into the 575-foot
section that loops around the Brandenburg Gate. It was by far the
most heavily reinforced, a semi-circle of concrete slabs cemented
together and woven with heavy cable.
   With the 18th-century <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> the symbol of old <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>,
this section of wall was the symbol of its division, splitting the
wide avenue that was once a main thoroughfare.
   After the wall was opened, a border crossing was cut into it at
<ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> and the area became a major tourist attraction.
   Makeshift souvenir stands hawk everything from <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall
keychains to membership pins worn by <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s notorious
former secret police.
   Much of the imaginative graffiti has been chiseled away by
souvenir hunters who place great value on paint-splashed pieces of
wall. New, post-revolution graffiti has taken its place.
   ``The wall is on its way to your hometown,'' read one comment.
   The new East German government has said it will remove all of
the 100-mile barrier that encircles <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>. A few weeks ago,
long sections adjacent the Brandenburg Gate were demolished.
   Late <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, after most of the tourists had gone home, a
West German construction crew and East German soldiers began taking
down the section of wall directly in front of the gate.
   They planned to work only at night, completing the removal
within a week. Officials say they hope to restore auto traffic down
the divided street.
   About 400 people watched <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> as a giant jackhammer
hooked to the end of a crane continued the slow battle against the
wall's most formidable stretch.
   ``It is a symbol, but it kept people apart,'' said <PERSON>East Berliner
Fabian Evers</PERSON>, 18, as he sold chunks of wall on a blanket near the
gate. ``It is an ideological statement to tear it down.''
   Ulricht, a school teacher, said he has no desire to see this
part of the wall remain as a memorial.
   ``This section was a symbol not only of the division of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, but of East and <LOCATION>West Europe</LOCATION>,'' he said. ``I enjoy very
much that this wall is coming down.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 2ndLd-Writethru a0718 12-19 0993</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0718,1024</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl, Modrow Meet; Brandenburg Gate to Reopen by Christmas</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with two grafs to CORRECT that reopening is by Christmas
Day, that news was misread on state TV. Picks up 3rd `Modrow, Kohl ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DRE3,5,29</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DRESDEN, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>, a towering
monument to unity that became a symbol of discord, will reopen by
Christmas after being closed by the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall for a generation,
the government said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   State television reported the date after Premier <PERSON>Hans Modrow</PERSON> and
Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> of <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> held a summit and said the
gate would be opened on <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION> but its editors late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
said the announcer had misread his text and that the date for
reopening was by Christmas Day.
   <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> and the mayors of East and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> will preside
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the television report said.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> police began setting up crowd-control
barriers in front of the wall at the gate, which is in <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>.
   At their summit, <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> and Kohl agreed to negotiate closer ties
between the two <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s created at the end of World War II. The
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall was built in <DATE>1961</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> said that visa-free travel between East and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>
will begin Christmas Eve and his government will free all political
prisoners.
   In a joint statement, the German leaders said ``a
good-neighborly relationship between the two states ... is of great
importance for stability in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and represents a contribution to
the new European architecture.''
   At a news conference after their meeting, <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> would not be
specific about the Brandenburg Gate pedestrian crossing, but <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON>
said: ``We will all be able to take a walk across to the
Brandenburg Gate before <DATE>Christmas</DATE>.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> was built 200 years ago and opened the road
to the region of <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Prussia</LOCATION>, but its six battle-scarred
sandstone columns became a symbol of division after the wall was
built in <DATE>1961</DATE>. The gate, the size of a five-story building,
remained on the eastern side.
   In <DATE>1963</DATE>, Communist soldiers dropped huge red drapes over the
gate to prevent President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> from looking into <LOCATION>East
Berlin</LOCATION> when he visited <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>.
   With the political upheaval that has ended Communist domination
in <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> and opened the country's once-locked borders, the
gate is viewed by millions as the symbol of German unity.
   The issue of how to bring the nations closer dominated the first
meeting of Kohl and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON>, and the public reaction highlighted the
debate raging over possible reunification after more than four
decades.
   Workers in hard hats left their jobs and joined thousands of
others to catch a glimpse of Kohl as he rode to the meeting in his
motorcade of black Mercedes limousines.
   ``Helmut! Helmut!'' and ``<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, united fatherland!'' they
shouted.
   But posters in the city center read ``Kohl Go Home.''
   ``A Fourth <PERSON>Reich</PERSON> _ Is that why you stayed behind?'' said one,
referring to East Germans who have declined to emigrate to wealthy
<LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, choosing instead to stay behind and help rebuild
their troubled socialist state.
   East German TV reported 5,000 people demonstrated against
reunification in <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>, shouting ``Nazis out!''
   Modrow opposes reunification, and Soviet Foreign Minister <PERSON>Eduard
A. Shevadrdnadze</PERSON> reiterated the <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION>'s opposition to
reunification during a speech <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>European Parliament</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It is necessary to proceed on the basis of the postwar
realities, namely, the existence of two sovereign German states.
... A retreat from that is fraught with destabilization in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>,'' he said.
   Elsewhere in <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION>:
   _ Shooting and fires were reported in western <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, where
there were reports that security forces have killed hundreds of
people who protested the harsh Communist regime of President
<PERSON>Nicolae Ceausescu</PERSON>.
   _ Former Czechoslovak dissident <PERSON>Vaclav Havel</PERSON> received an
endorsement for the presidency from the Communist premier, <PERSON>Marian
Calfa</PERSON>, who urged that he be elected before the end of the year.
   _ The Soviet Parliament pushed through an economic reform plan
that retains heavy central planning, in a no-confidence vote that
Premier <PERSON>Nikolai I. Ryzhkov</PERSON> and his ministers easily survived.
   _ <LOCATION>Lithuania</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> leader urged a united political
front with other parties to press for sovereignty and protect the
<LOCATION>Baltic</LOCATION> republic from <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION> pressure. Algirdis Brazauskas avoided
calling for an immediate, direct break with the Soviet Communist
Party or for Lithuanian indepenence, but he left open both
possibilities.
   The German summit began with the signing of an economic
cooperation agreement and pacts to boost cultural and travel ties.
   A significant development is the planned treaty to improve
cooperation and relations. Negotiations will start immediately,
<PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> said, with Kohl saying he hoped the treaty could be signed
by <DATE>spring</DATE>.
   The leaders planned a second summit in late <DATE>January</DATE> or early
<DATE>February</DATE>.
   Perhaps the most striking aspect of the summit was the welcome
Kohl received.
   Later, at an <TIME>evening</TIME> rally, a crowd of 20,000 burst into rounds
of wild cheers and applause as the West German leader addressed
them as his ``countrymen'' and promised not to abandon them.
   ``God bless our German fatherland,'' he said.
   Some, however, carried signs supporting East German sovereignty.
   Kohl spoke near the ruins of the Frauenkirche (Church of Our
Lady), destroyed during World War II. There Kohl laid a bouquet in
memory of war victims before addressing the flag-waving crowd.
   ``Unity! Unity! Unity!'' they shouted as he began to speak.
   Kohl promised West German aid for the economic recovery,
assuring the crowd: ``We will not desert our countrymen.''
   But mindful of warnings from East German leaders, the
superpowers and European neighbors that a reunited <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> could
threaten peace, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> promised East Germans: ``We will respect what
you decide for the future.''
   The last such summit was <DATE>Sept. 7-8, 1987</DATE>, in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, when Kohl met
<PERSON>Honecker</PERSON>. The last time a West German chancellor visited <LOCATION>East
Germany</LOCATION> was in <DATE>December 1981</DATE>, when <PERSON>Helmut Schmidt</PERSON> met with <PERSON>Honecker</PERSON>
in <LOCATION>Werbellinsee</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1257EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BerlinWall     01-07 0367</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Berlin Wall,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Move to Protect Crumbling Berlin Wall</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY CZUCZKA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tourists have chiseled so many souvenirs out
of the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall that some sections are in danger of collapsing,
and police have had to cordon off one especially hard-hit area near
the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION>.
   The East German government plans eventually to tear down the
entire wall and replace it with normal border markings, President
<PERSON>Manfred Gerlach</PERSON> disclosed in an interview last week. But free-lance
demolition work has already proceeded on the 100-mile border
barrier, especially on the <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> side.
   East German border guards on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> welded steel bars over a
gaping hole near the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION> to shore up the reinforced
concrete structure.
   West <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> police put up crowd control barriers <DATE>Saturday</DATE> around
the most damaged sections to keep adults and children from climbing
inside giant holes carved out of a double-walled segment. Police
cited a danger of collapse.
   Once covered by graffiti, the wall has been chipped bare at the
<ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>, the 18th-century arch that now symbolizes German
unity.
   The wall has also taken a beating at <ORGANIZATION>Checkpoint Charlie</ORGANIZATION>, the
famed intra-Berlin crossing, but police said they do not fear a
collapse there.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, onlookers and chippers on the <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> side booed
when East German border guards welded steel bars over a 7-foot-high
hole at the <LOCATION>Reichstag</LOCATION>, the former seat of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s parliament near
the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION>.
   Enterprising vendors have been selling pieces of the wall for up
<MONEY>$30</MONEY> and even rent hammers and chisels for do-it-yourself chipping.
   But each wall chunk removed means lost business for <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>.
   An East German company said <DATE>last month</DATE> it plans to raise Western
currency by selling sections of the wall removed from the
<ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Potsdamer Platz</LOCATION>, a square that was the hub of
1920s <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>.
   Profits from sales are to go to humanitarian causes.
   Communist East German authorities have punched dozens of
crossings into the wall since their decision <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> to open borders
to the West, The action was the result of a sudden and peaceful
popular revolution that drummed hard-line Communist leaders out of
power.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900101-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-01-90 0714EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-BerlinNewYear 1stLd-Writethru a0437 01-01 0559</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Berlin New Year, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0437,0569</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drums, Saxophones And Fireworks At Berlin Wall</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 5-6 `After midnight...rescue workers' with 3 grafs
to UPDATE with 135 injured in screen collapse, 68 neo-Nazis
arrested. Picks up 7th pvs, `A West ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With PM-World New Year, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cacophony of drums, saxophones and
firecrackers pierced the air <DATE>early today</DATE> and fireworks illuminated
the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall as tens of thousands of people from <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> and West
celebrated New Year's together.
   Tens of thousands poured in both directions through the newly
opened Brandenburg Gate each hour, and thousands more scaled the
wall and tumbled into the other <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> as border guards watched
with amusement.
   In a revival of the city-wide street party that erupted when the
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall opened <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>, young people scrambled atop the divide
to take in the scene on both sides, bobbing and rocking to the
erratic rhythm of the concert without conductor at <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hammers clanged against chisels as hundreds mined the wall for
souvenirs.
   After midnight, some scaffolding supporting an outdoor
projection screen near <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION> collapsed under the weight
of revelers, killing a man and injuring 135 people, <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s
official ADN news agency reported. Seventy-seven of them were
hospitalized, it said.
   ADN said drunks and a carpet of broken glass from champagne
bottles hindered rescue workers.
   In other border areas, police police arrested 68 neo-Nazi
activists overnight after they tried to stage illegal
demonstrations. Authorities in both German states had formed joint
patrols to prevent disturbances threatened by right-wing radicals.
   A <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> counter-culture group had appealed to Berliners on
both sides of the crumbling divide to bring musical instruments and
inspiration to the battle-scarred gate, for a concert to fete the
first New Year's in four decades that Germans have celebrated
together.
   ``We just wanted to be here for it. It's fantastic,'' said
21-year-old <PERSON>Kerry Bundgaard</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> as her father videotaped the
scene.
   ``The wall is open for the first time in my life. We want to
celebrate along with everyone else,'' said <PERSON>Hans-Juergen Witfeld</PERSON>,
who traveled from the <LOCATION>Ruhr Valley</LOCATION> city of Dortmund with eight
friends to spend the holiday in cold and misty <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>.
   At <TIME>midnight</TIME>, fireworks filled the <TIME>midnight</TIME> sky over <LOCATION>Brandenburg
Gate</LOCATION>. The soot-stained monument was swathed in smoke as young
people from around the world clamored atop the surrounding wall and
scaled even the tarnished bronze chariot that crowns the columned
gate.
   Since East German authorities began punching holes in the
graffiti-splattered concrete that had severed <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> since <DATE>1961</DATE>,
the wall has become more a bridge than a barrier.
   Tour buses from throughout <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> shuttled thousands to the
heart of the party, a stretch of pock-marked wall between the
<LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> and a towering Christmas tree on
the west side.
   Tourists filled every hotel and restaurant to capacity on both
sides of the wall and jammed streets and parking lots with
impromptu parties.
   Enterprising youth like 15-year-old <PERSON>Salim Mussa</PERSON> hawked chips of
the wall for up to <MONEY>$30</MONEY>, <LOCATION>West Berliners</LOCATION> rented out hammers and
chisels, and the West German government operated a mobile
information booth for any East German visitors considering
relocation in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   Border police said they had no estimate of the numbers crossing
between the two Germanys.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900217-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-17-90 0302EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BerlinWall     02-17 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Berlin Wall,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>East Germans to Allow Unchecked Travel Through Brandenburg Gate</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> will tear down a 600-foot
section of the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall near the Brandenburg Gate and allow
completely unhindered passage between the two sides of the city
there, West German television said.
   Since <DATE>November</DATE>, the East Germans have created numerous passage
points through the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall but have retained nominal checks of
passports or identity cards.
   The section at the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> will be the first section
without any official controls.
   ``The <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall at the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> will be torn down,''
the <ORGANIZATION>ZDF</ORGANIZATION> television network said <DATE>Friday</DATE>. ``East German border troops
will start the work on <DATE>Monday</DATE>.''
   ``There will then be unhindered passage between East and West
from the <LOCATION>Reichstag</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION>. There will not be a
fence there as originally planned.''
   The wall, for years a symbol of the division of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, was
built in <DATE>1961</DATE> to prevent East German laborers from leaving. A
popular uprising in <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> <DATE>last fall</DATE> toppled the hard-line
leadership and forced the opening of the wall in <DATE>November</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891110-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-10-89 2229EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Landmarks     11-10 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Landmarks,0419</SECOND>
<HEAD>Berlin Landmarks Tell History of Divided City</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A solitary building stands on the far corner of
the once teeming and elegant Potsdamer Platz, now a desolate no
man's land overlooking a jagged corner of the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall.
   Potsdamer Platz will soon regain at least a semblance of its
former prominence after 28 years as a Cold War curiosity, East
German officials said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Devastated during World War II and long a lonely tourist
attraction for a glimpse over the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall, <ORGANIZATION>Potsdamer Platz</ORGANIZATION> will
shortly become another major transit checkpoint between East and
<LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>.
   Its opening comes as part of <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>'s decision to open its
borders to the West, officials say.
   Since the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall was built in <DATE>1961</DATE>, <LOCATION>Potsdamer Platz</LOCATION> and
similar landmarks have been sober reminders of the brutal division
of the city and the two Germanys.
   For many Berliners, the blockaded <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Potsdamer
Platz</PERSON> are the starkest symbols of that division. In both cases, two
main thoroughfares end abrubtly at the concrete base of the
imposing, graffiti-smeared Wall.
   When Foreign Minister <PERSON>Hans-Dietrich Genscher</PERSON> of <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>
told a rally in <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> that the East Germans had decided to
punch a hole through the Wall at <LOCATION>Potsdamer Platz</LOCATION>, the crowd roared
with applause and cheers.
   Another famous crossing has also taken on new tasks.
   <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Glienicke Bridge</ORGANIZATION>, a frequent site of <ORGANIZATION>East-West</ORGANIZATION> swaps of
spies and political prisoners, has since been opened to accommodate
more travelers.
   Another notorious stretch of the Wall is also to be opened _
<ORGANIZATION>Bernauer Strasse</ORGANIZATION>, where scenes of dramatic escape attempts stunned
the world 28 years ago.
   A house near the new checkpoint still stands with its
westward-facing windows boarded and sealed with bricks, testimony
to the first desperate attempts to jump to freedom as the Wall was
going up.
   Nearby, others died later in escape attempts that ended in a
hail of bullets. Eighty people died trying to cross the Wall.
   The Wall's most famous crossing, <ORGANIZATION>Checkpoint Charlie</ORGANIZATION>, will remain
in use for foreign visitors, although East German border guards
have allowed scores of East Berliners to use the crossing since
travel restrictions were lifted on <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   No plans have surfaced so far to tear down the concrete barriers
that stand in front of the massive, 18th-century <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>,
which for decades has been a rallying point of protest against the
city's partition.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891112-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-12-89 0345EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-EastGermany     11-12 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-East Germany,0542</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mayors of Divided City Meet at Berlin Wall's Newest Breach</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The mayors of East and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> shook hands
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> at a new <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall crossing point in a historic meeting
symbolizing the crumbling of the Cold War relic that divided the
city since <DATE>1961</DATE>.
   Their meeting came after more than 1 million East Germans poured
into <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, taking advantage of their
government's opening of Western borders. The vast majority intended
to make a brief visit and then return to the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Walter Momper</PERSON> and his <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>
counterpart, <PERSON>Erhard Krack</PERSON>, met at the <LOCATION>Potsdamer Platz</LOCATION>, a bleak,
virtual no-man's land bisected by the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall.
   Hours before their morning session, East German workers drilled
a hole through the wall with jackhammers at <LOCATION>Potsdamer Platz</LOCATION>,
creating the third new border crossing point since <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s
Communist leaders announced the end of travel restrictions late
last week.
   Momper and <PERSON>Krack</PERSON> later left the area for breakfast and talks in
a <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> hotel.
   The new freedom to travel and other reforms in <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> have
touched off a wave of enthusiam about the possibility of reuniting
the two German states divided at the end of World War II.
   However, East German Communist leader <PERSON>Egon Krenz</PERSON> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
dismissed such talk.
   The new wave of visitors to <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> was expected to exceed <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s estimated 1.3 million
visitors, almost <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT> of East German's 16.6 million population.
   Most of <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s exuberant visitors returned home overnight,
West German border police said.
   A core of East German and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> revelers kept a joyful
vigil in front of the <LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION> on the western side of the
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall.
   However, <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> riot police vans lined up in front of the
wall at the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>early Sunday</DATE> to try to fend off
revelers who lit torches and candles in memory of East Germans
killed trying to escape over the wall.
   At the Friederichstrasse crossing point, known as <ORGANIZATION>Checkpoint
Charlie</ORGANIZATION>, renowned cellist <PERSON>Mstislav Rostropovich</PERSON> gave an impromptu
concert <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in front of a section of the wall covered with
graffiti.
   Police said a 24-year-old visitor from <LOCATION>Potsdam</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>,
went into labor on bustling <ORGANIZATION>Wuerttembergische Strasse</ORGANIZATION> and gave
birth to a girl on the sidewalk, to the delight of a surrounding
crowd.
   Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> of <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> said he would meet with
<ORGANIZATION>Krenz</ORGANIZATION>, whose three weeks in office have brought a whirlwind of
change, to discuss ways of cooperating in the new age.
   However, <ORGANIZATION>Krenz</ORGANIZATION> told <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> to forget any ideas of making the two
nations that rose from the rubble of World War II into a single
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> again.
   East <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s Communist authorities built the 14-foot-high
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall beginning <DATE>Aug. 13, 1961</DATE>, to stem a flow of workers to
the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. Ironically, it was another flight this year, of more than
200,000 East Germans, that forced them to open it.
   East German leaders lifted travel regulations and pledged
greater democratic freedoms after both the exodus and weeks of
street protests.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122289-0042 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 152101 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 22, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 16; Column 6; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
174 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WORKERS START WALL TUMBLING AT BRANDENBURG 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Reuters 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
EAST BERLIN 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
East German border workers began dismantling the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall at the historic 
<ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> to make a new crossing point between East 
and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Shortly after <TIME>10 p.m.</TIME>, a crane began lifting the cylindrical concrete sections 
from the top of the wall and a worker with a pneumatic drill started 
demolishing part of it. 
</P>
<P>
An East German border guard estimated that the work would only take about 90 
minutes as two teams of 10 border guard engineers cut openings to the left and 
right of the massive <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
West German Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> and East German Prime Minister <PERSON>Hans Modrow</PERSON> 
are due to inaugurate the new crossing with the mayors of East and <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> 
today. 
</P>
<P>
Crowds cheered on the western side of the wall and some climbed trees to get a 
better view of the work. The scene was brightly lit by the floodlights that 
have illuminated the 12 columned-gate since it was walled off 28 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
The crossing point -- two gates for one-way movement in each direction -- will 
be for pedestrians only. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BERLIN WALL; EAST BERLIN; WEST BERLIN; EAST GERMANY -- BORDERS -- WEST GERMANY; 
DEMOLITION 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1106EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-EastGermany 2ndLd-Writethru   12-20 0707</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0595,0731</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Says No Need to Fear Reunification</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with Kohl news conference. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DRESDEN, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> of <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION> tried to reassure opponents of German reunification <DATE>today</DATE>
and said their fears of an evil German empire based on past horrors
are ``absurd.''
   Kohl, during a news conference closing a triumphant two-day
visit, also said he expects a treaty expanding East and West German
ties to be completed by <DATE>May</DATE>.
   Kohl met with Communist Premier <PERSON>Hans Modrow</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, and the
two later announced plans for the treaty and a number of other
changes:
   _The famed Brandenburg Gate, isolated in <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> since the
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall was built in <DATE>1961</DATE>, will be reopened by <DATE>Christmas</DATE>.
   _Germans will be allowed to travel without visas between the two
states beginning <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION>.
   _<LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> will free all political prisoners, with many to be
released before <DATE>Christmas</DATE>.
   Kohl pledged to take into account the concerns of other European
countries as the two German states, created after World War II,
move closer together.
   ``It's the most natural thing that Germans want to live
together,'' <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> said.
   Kohl pledged to avoid ``destabilization,'' a reference to the
power vacuum in <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> that has followed the virtual collapse
of <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> control here since a popular revolution began in
the <DATE>fall</DATE>.
   Kohl added: ``Fears based in the past are understandable, but
there is nothing to be feared from the future. It's absurd to talk
about a Fourth <PERSON>Reich</PERSON>.''
   East German Communists and other opponents of reunification have
said joining the two states could create a ``Fourth <PERSON>Reich</PERSON>,'' and
have reminded people of the atrocities of Nazi dictator <PERSON>Adolf
Hitler</PERSON>'s Third <PERSON>Reich</PERSON>.
   In meeting with several opposition groups, including New Forum,
Democratic Awakening, and others, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> said he heard none of them
voice opposition to eventual reunification.
   New Forum representative <PERSON>Arnold Vaatz</PERSON> told the official news
agency ADN he found ``broad agreement'' with <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> and that his
group was ``thankful'' for the results of the summit.
   Earlier today, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> met with the Roman Catholic bishops of
<LOCATION>Dresden</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Joachim Reinelt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Georg Sterzinsky</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Sterzinsky</PERSON> said he and <PERSON>Reinelt</PERSON> explained their views on future
cooperation with <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> in the meeting with Kohl.
   <PERSON>Sterzinsky</PERSON> said he expects <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> to ``treat us as a
partner and help with our renewal.'' He viewed the visit by <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON>, a
conservative Christian Democrat, as ``entirely positive,'' the
official news agency <ORGANIZATION>ADN</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s Bild newspaper quoted unidentified officials in
<LOCATION>Dresden</LOCATION> as saying <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>'s Brandenburg Gate will be open to
pedestrians <DATE>Friday</DATE>. The newspaper said its report would appear in
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s editions. It was sent in advance to other news media
today.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> is a symbol of German unity to millions and
was a centerpiece of a major <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> thoroughfare before the wall
was built 28 years ago.
   Under the pressure of massive pro-democracy demonstrations
starting in <DATE>October</DATE>, openings have been made in the wall, two sets
of Communist leaders have been ousted, and free elections are
scheduled in <DATE>May</DATE>. At the same time, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> has warmly
accepted all East German refugees and offered to help revive its
neighbor's struggling economy.
   At a joint news conference after their summit, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON>
said their talks had made progress toward what the two nations
refer to as a ``treaty community.'' Such an arrangement would
safeguard the sovereignty of both states.
   Talks leading up to the planned bilateral treaty could focus on
improving traffic connections, telecommunications and pollution
problems, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> said.
   Both leaders agreed to meet again in late <DATE>January</DATE> or early
<DATE>February</DATE> in <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>.
   While <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> stressed the ``right of self-determination'' for
citizens in both <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> on the issue of reunification, <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON>
called for the continued existence of two German states.
   Kohl joined his host in counseling caution and patience.
   Later, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> received an emotional welcome from a crowd of about
20,000 at an outdoor evening rally.
   People repeatedly burst into wild cheers, applause and chants of
``Unity!'' ``Unity!'' as <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> addressed them as his ``countrymen.''
   Many waved West German flags, outnumbering those carrying signs
insisting on East German sovereignty or attacking Kohl.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111589-0012 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 134784 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 15, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 8; Column 1; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
990 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
EAST GERMAN PARTY SEEKS COALITION; 
</P>
<P>
EUROPE: WEST GERMANY RENEWS ITS OFFER OF AID KEYED TO ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL 
REFORMS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By WILLIAM TUOHY, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
EAST BERLIN 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The newly elected East German prime minister, <PERSON>Hans Modrow</PERSON>, opened talks with 
non-Communist Party leaders <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in an effort to form what he called a 
"genuine coalition government." 
</P>
<P>
He and Communist leader <PERSON>Egon Krenz</PERSON> conferred with the heads of four small 
parties that have suddenly displayed independence after years of serving as 
<ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> satellites. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, West German officials again offered massive financial aid to <LOCATION>East 
Germany</LOCATION> -- providing that the government introduces stringent economic and 
political reforms. 
</P>
<P>
The East German regime is also considering opening up the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall near the 
<LOCATION>Brandenburg Gate</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>'s best-known monument and symbol, according to 
the official news agency ADN. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> was quoted in <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s editions of the West German newspaper Bild 
as saying that while the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall can remain open to travel, it must remain 
standing. 
</P>
<P>
"In our country, there is little criminal activity . . . cases of AIDS 
(acquired immune deficiency syndrome) and drugs are virtually unknown. Our 
people are asking themselves why they shouldn't just leave that as it is," Bild 
quoted him as saying. 
</P>
<P>
The number of people crossing the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was estimated at 
180,000. 
</P>
<P>
At the same time, West German Red Cross officials reported that the number of 
East German refugees approaching them about returning home has reached 10,000. 
Counseling services for potential returnees have been set up at West German 
relocation camps to advise East Germans whether they will be penalized if they 
go back. 
</P>
<P>
In trying to form a coalition regime, <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> sought out the leaders of the four 
small parties: the Democratic Farmers' Party, the <ORGANIZATION>Christian Democratic Union</ORGANIZATION>, 
the <ORGANIZATION>Liberal Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>National Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
These smaller parties, which in the past rubber-stamped Communist orders, have 
seats in the Parliament and have been increasingly critical of government 
policies and the Communists. 
</P>
<P>
Communists occupy 39 of the 43 Cabinet posts, and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> is expected to reduce 
the size of the Cabinet as well as make it more of a coalition. ADN gave no 
details of the meeting, and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> did not say whether the opposition would 
join his conception of a coalition government. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Guenter Schabowski</PERSON>, a prominent member of the Politburo, resigned as party 
chief for <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>ADN</ORGANIZATION> reported. Political analysts say <PERSON>Schabowski</PERSON>, 
considered to be a leading reform-minded politician, may receive an important 
post in <LOCATION>Modrow</LOCATION>'s Cabinet. 
</P>
<P>
He earlier had indicated he might surrender the city post because of a heavy 
workload. He remains in the Politburo and as the party's propaganda chief. He 
was replaced as party chief for the capital by <PERSON>Hans Albrecht</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, the new, non-Communist Speaker of the <ORGANIZATION>East German Parliament</ORGANIZATION> said he 
will seek to change the first article of the country's constitution, which 
defines the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>'s leading role in society. The party has used the 
provision to justify its monopoly on power. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Guenther Maleuda</PERSON> told a meeting of his Democratic Farmers' Party faction in 
<LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> that the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> is to blame for <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s economic, 
social and political problems. 
</P>
<P>
The West German pledge of massive financial aid to help rebuild <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s 
economy had been made before and was conditional on political and economic 
reforms that the Communists have so far rejected. 
</P>
<P>
a six-point plan that would include investments and joint ventures, as well as 
revamping the nation's dilapidated communications and transport systems. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Haussmann</PERSON> did not specify a figure for the aid and said the plan would be 
useless if <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> fails to carry out a "thorough change" in its centrally 
directed economy. East German authorities have rejected the idea of adopting a 
complete free-market system. 
</P>
<P>
Haussmann compared his proposal to the <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> Plan, brainchild of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
Secretary of State <PERSON>George C. Marshall</PERSON>, which sent more than <MONEY>$12 billion</MONEY> in U.S 
aid from 1948-51 to help war-devastated <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> return to prosperity. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>, the rumors that a new border crossing would be punched through 
the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall near the historic Brandenburg Gate drew about 200 West 
Berliners to a chilly vigil <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
Police chiefs from both sides of the wall conferred by phone, and it was 
understood afterward that "nothing will happen tonight," a <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> police 
spokesman said. 
</P>
<P>
"We don't know if and when it will go down," he added. 
</P>
<P>
Ten East German guards stood almost casually atop the wall, gazing down at the 
throngs of <LOCATION>West Berliners</LOCATION> and reporters, some of whom had staked out their 
spots with pup tents. Television lights cast a bright glow on the 
graffiti-covered western face of the wall. 
</P>
<P>
Behind the barricade, floodlights illuminated the gate itself, which came to 
separate the city into Allied and Soviet zones after World War II, also 
severing <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>'s busiest boulevard -- <ORGANIZATION>Unter Den Linden</ORGANIZATION>. West German police 
kept the crowd about 20 feet back from the wall, which some Berliners danced 
atop last week. 
</P>
<P>
People waited in line to climb the two viewing platforms erected by the West 
years ago to allow tourists a peak over the forbidden wall and the gate behind 
it. 
</P>
<P>
Times staff writer <PERSON>Tamara Jones</PERSON> contributed to this story. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
BACKGROUND 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>, the site where <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> is considering creating a new 
opening in the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall, has for decades served as a mocking reminder of 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s defeat in World War II. Lying in <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> just beyond the wall in 
the heart of the divided city, the monument, topped with a bronze statue of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Goddess of Victory</ORGANIZATION> in a chariot, was erected in 1788-91 to celebrate military 
victories and was named after the German state that later became <LOCATION>Prussia</LOCATION>. 
Modeled on the <LOCATION>Propylaea</LOCATION>, the entrance to the <LOCATION>Acropolis</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>, it was 
severely damaged in World War II and has been completely rebuilt. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Infobox 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MODROW, HANS; EAST GERMANY -- GOVERNMENT; GOVERNMENT REFORM; EAST GERMANY -- 
POLITICS; EAST GERMANY -- FOREIGN AID -- WEST GERMANY; REFUGEES -- EAST 
GERMANY; REFUGEES -- WEST GERMANY; EAST GERMANY -- FOREIGN RELATIONS -- WEST 
GERMANY; BERLIN WALL; EAST GERMANY -- TRAVEL RESTRICTIONS -- WEST GERMANY; EAST 
GERMANY -- BORDERS -- WEST GERMANY; EAST GERMANY -- EMIGRATION 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900428-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-28-90 1436EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BerlinWall     04-28 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Berlin Wall,0297</SECOND>
<HEAD>Workers Begin Removing Famous Section of Berlin Wall</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Workers on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> began tearing down the
thickest and perhaps most famous part of the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall, a stretch
of graffiti-covered concrete in front of the historic <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg
Gate</ORGANIZATION>.
   Crowds of tourists and souvenir peddlers watched as East German
soldiers and West German construction workers with heavy tools
began knocking away at the section ofwall that curves around the
18th-century gate.
   The huge, colonnaded gate represents the grandeur of old <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>
just as the section of wall in front of it symbolized its division.
   The wall provided some of the most memorable images of the
revolution last <DATE>autumn</DATE> that ended four decades of Communist
oppression, opened the wall, and began the process of reunifying
the two Germanys. With the giant gate as a backdrop, protesters
with chisels climbed on the wall last year to demonstrate their new
freedom when <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s borders were finally opened.
   Much of the surrounding sections of the 100-mile wall already
have been removed, but the section in front of the gate is
considered the sturdiest. It is 10 feet high and equally as thick.
   The area around the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION> has become a heavily
visited tourist area. Makeshift souvenir stands hawk everything
from postcards depicting the revolt to key chains made of wall
fragments.
   The work <DATE>Saturday</DATE> was part of an ongoing process of removing
certain sections of the wall. The East German government says the
entire wall will eventually be removed, except for one section that
will stand as a monument.
   The East German news agency <ORGANIZATION>ADN</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Saturday</DATE> that 70
segments of the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall will be auctioned off on <DATE>June 23</DATE> in the
principality of <LOCATION>Monaco</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010290-0106 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 156631 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 2, 1990, Tuesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 2; Column 5; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
654 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BERLIN WALL WILL BE PULLED DOWN, EAST GERMAN TELLS HAVEL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall, which symbolized the schism between <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Western Europe</LOCATION> 
for 28 years, will be pulled down, an East German official said <DATE>today</DATE> in a 
dramatic demonstration of the liberalization of the <LOCATION>East Bloc</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
East German head of state <PERSON>Manfred Gerlach</PERSON> told visiting Czechoslovak President 
<PERSON>Vaclav Havel</PERSON> that the wall will be torn down. 
</P>
<P>
"We are pulling down the wall. It has become superfluous. It will be replaced 
by normal border markings," <PERSON>Gerlach</PERSON> said in the interview with the West German 
daily, Bild. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Gerlach</PERSON> said that no date has been set for the wall's removal but that the East 
German government would discuss it soon. 
</P>
<P>
Bild said it interviewed him after he had taken Havel to see the wall and the 
historic Brandenburg Gate today. 
</P>
<P>
Havel told reporters that he was amazed that the wall, built in <DATE>1961</DATE> and a 
symbol of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s division until <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> opened its borders 
in <DATE>November</DATE>, is still standing. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Gerlach</PERSON> told me work would soon start to tear it down. I told him if he had 
any problems we could send some independent Czechoslovak workers to help free 
of charge," he said to loud applause. 
</P>
<P>
Havel also told journalists he would like to say "Ich bin ein Berliner" -- "I 
am a Berliner" -- as did President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> during his visit to <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> 
in <DATE>June, 1963</DATE>, two years after the wall was built. 
</P>
<P>
"I would like to take the liberty to repeat this sentence at a new time and in 
a new context," <PERSON>Havel</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
He said all walls and barriers in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> must fall. 
</P>
<P>
Built by Soviet-backed East German troops <DATE>Aug. 13, 1961</DATE>, the wall was first 
breached last <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> as East German authorities were moving away from the 
Stalinist policies that had been their trademark for 40 years. 
</P>
<P>
Havel visited the East German capital briefly before seeing West German 
Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Munich</LOCATION>, his first official visits since he was 
elected president <DATE>Friday</DATE> as part of an agreement among the Czechoslovak 
government, opposition groups and the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
His trips to the Germanys ahead of one to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> reflected a shift in 
<LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION>'s foreign policy. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Havel</PERSON> said his visits originally were to be symbolic but turned out to be 
"working visits." 
</P>
<P>
"We managed to discuss many concrete issues," he said. 
</P>
<P>
In response to a question, <PERSON>Havel</PERSON> said he is opposed to the death penalty but he 
said last week's execution of Romanian leader <PERSON>Nicolae Ceausescu</PERSON> and his wife 
may have saved many lives. 
</P>
<P>
After talks with <PERSON>Gerlach</PERSON> and Prime Minister <PERSON>Hans Modrow</PERSON>, <PERSON>Havel</PERSON> praised recent 
developments in <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, which has moved away from the Stalinist policies 
it had adhered to since its founding 40 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
"All of us Europeans must thank the GDR (<LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>) for having started 
pulling down one of the worst walls," said <PERSON>Havel</PERSON>, a playwright and essayist, 
who gained prominence during the <DATE>spring 1968</DATE> uprising in <LOCATION>Prague</LOCATION> that was 
crushed by <ORGANIZATION>Warsaw Pact</ORGANIZATION> tanks. 
</P>
<P>
"This decade must become the decade of Europeans," said <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> after meeting with 
Havel in <LOCATION>Munich</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Czechoslovakian leader also met with West German Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Hans-Dietrich Genscher</PERSON>, President <PERSON>Richard von Weizsaecker</PERSON> and opposition leader 
<PERSON>Hans-Jochen Vogel</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Havel, who was jailed for five years for his opposition to the Communist 
authorities, was awarded the annual Peace Prize of the <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> Book Fair last 
year. The Czechoslovakian government had prevented his traveling to <LOCATION>West 
Germany</LOCATION> to collect the award. 
</P>
<P>
Earlier, <PERSON>Havel</PERSON> declared a New Year's amnesty for common criminals and said his 
biggest task is to lead <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION> toward free elections without violence. 
</P>
<P>
Czechoslovak Justice Minister <PERSON>Dagmar Buresova</PERSON> said in a radio address that the 
amnesty will be extensive because many prisoners are serving excessively harsh 
sentences. But she said corrupt public officials will be excluded from the 
amnesty. 
</P>
<P>
It was not immediately clear how many prisoners will be affected by the 
amnesty. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Czechoslovak President Vaclav Havel, surrounded by officials and 
security, visits the East Berlin side of the Brandenburg Gate today. Associated 
Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-EastGermany 5thLd-Writethru a0530 12-19 0898</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 5th Ld - Writethru, a0530,0922</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wall To Be Opened At Brandenburg Gate; Summit Puts Focus On Reunification</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS dateline to East Germany, sted West; SUBS grafs 9-30,
`Kohl was...financial ties' with 17 to add comments from Kohl and Modrow,
color from scene. Trims and deletes outdated material. Pickup 31st graf,
`Kohl has...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DRESDEN, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall will be opened
before <DATE>Christmas</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Brandenburg Gate</ORGANIZATION>, the towering monument
viewed by many as a symbol of German unity, East German Premier
<PERSON>Hans Modrow</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   The announcement followed a meeting between <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> and West
German Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, during which the two leaders
discussed the thorny issue of how to bring the long-divided nations
closer together.
   Since the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall started crumbling early last month,
Germans in both East and West have demanded an opening at the gate
to demonstrate the new era of improved relations between the
countries.
   Modrow told reporters the new opening for pedestrians will be
created before <DATE>Monday</DATE>. And the date for visa-free travel by West
Germans and <LOCATION>West Berliners</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> will be moved up from
<DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> to <DATE>Dec. 24</DATE>, in time for <DATE>Christmas</DATE> and New Year.
   Elsewhere in <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION> today:
   _Former Czechoslovak dissident <PERSON>Vaclav Havel</PERSON> received an
endorsement for president from the Communist premier, <PERSON>Marian Calfa</PERSON>.
   _Hungarian radio reported that gunfire rang out early today in
the streets of the Romanian city of <LOCATION>Timisoara</LOCATION>, where bloody clashes
between security forces and anti-government protesters reportedly
left dozens dead <DATE>last weekend</DATE>.
   _<LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>'s premier suffered a blow after the nation's largest
republic, <LOCATION>Serbia</LOCATION>, flatly rejected his key reform program that would
introduce market mechanisms into the ailing economy.
   The summit highlighted the debate raging over German
reunification, which <ORGANIZATION>Kohl</ORGANIZATION> supports and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> opposes.
   Chants of ``Helmut! Helmut!'' and ``<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, united
fatherland!'' rose from the crowd of at least 5,000 that lined the
streets as <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON>'s motorcade of black Mercedes limousines carried
him to the meeting at the <LOCATION>Hotel Bellevue</LOCATION>.
   Workers in hard hats left work to catch a glimpse of the
chancellor, and West German flags and banners calling for German
unity formed a sea of red, black and gold.
   But there were signs of opposition to <ORGANIZATION>Kohl</ORGANIZATION>'s pro-reunification
stance.
   ``A Fourth <PERSON>Reich</PERSON> _ Is that why you stayed behind?'' said one
poster on a fence in the city center. It referred to those East
Germans who have declined to emigrate to wealthy <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>,
choosing instead to stay behind and help rebuild their troubled
socialist state.
   With the ruins of war-ravaged buildings visible in the distance,
<PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> told reporters his first talks with Kohl marked a ``new
beginning'' in relations between the countries. Kohl accepted an
offer to start negotiations on a treaty to improve relations, and
negotiations will start ``immediately,'' <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> said.
   Kohl told reporters he hopes such a treaty can be signed by late
<DATE>spring</DATE>.
   He later walked through a crowd of several thousand people.
Several signs called for German reunification, with one saying
``Helmut and <PERSON>Hans</PERSON>, make us into one <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.''
   At an outdoor rally, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> drew wild cheers when he referred to
the crowd as ``compatriots'' and said, ``We will not abandon you.''
   ``The emotions are nice, but we have to see what the reality
is,'' he said on <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s ZDF television.
   Kohl said he and <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> would meet again at the end of <DATE>January</DATE>
or the beginning of <DATE>February</DATE>.
   He said the two sides ``got closer on some issues,'' citing the
East German push for a more formal relationship between the two
states.
   The summit was held in <LOCATION>Dresden</LOCATION> because <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> refuses to
acknowledge <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> as the capital of a separate and sovereign
East German state.
   <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> has been seeking a ``Treaty Community,''
establishing fuller ties between East and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, rather than
working to join them.
   Kohl has proposed a 10-point plan aimed at eventual German
reunification.
   Soviet Foreign Minister <PERSON>Eduard A. Shevardnadze</PERSON> today reiterated
Soviet concerns about reunification during a speech to members of
the <ORGANIZATION>European Parliament</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, saying there are two good
reasons to oppose it:
   ``We (the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>) paid the price of 20 million lives for
the existing European stability,'' he said of World War II.
``Furthermore, can the German people themselves forget the national
tragedy brought onto them by Hitlerism?''
   Kohl has made clear that his conservative-led government seeks
eventual reunification of the two German states that have been
divided since <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   But <PERSON>Modrow</PERSON> and many other East Germans active in the
increasingly fragmented political arena have said joining the two
states would be destabilizing for <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and would result in a
``sellout'' of East German land and industry.
   Reunification has become a major topic of public debate and a
political football in both Germanies ever since a massive popular
uprising forced <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> to open its borders <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> and led to
a crumbling of Communist control.
   East <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s first free elections are now set for <DATE>May 6</DATE>.
   Chants of ``<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, united fatherland'' occasionally disrupted
a candlelight vigil in <LOCATION>Leipzig</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. The silent march
was called by church and reform leaders in memory of the victims of
Stalinism.
   The words ``<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, united fatherland'' were originally part of
the East German national anthem but have been excised since the
early <DATE>1970s</DATE> when Communist officials dropped reunification as a
goal.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111089-0127 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 132901 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 10, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 6; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1431 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
EAST GERMANY OPENS BORDERS; WALL HAS 'NO MORE MEANING'; 
</P>
<P>
EAST BLOC: THOUSANDS TEST THE NEW POLICY BY CROSSING TO WEST BERLIN. THEY'RE 
WELCOMED WITH CHEERS AND SONG. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By WILLIAM TUOHY, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
EAST BERLIN 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The East German government threw open its borders <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and announced that 
its citizens now may travel freely to <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>. Thousands of jubilant East 
Germans quickly tested the new policy by flocking to the crossing points in 
divided <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
At <ORGANIZATION>Checkpoint Charlie</ORGANIZATION>, a major crossing point, a huge crowd gathered. As East 
Berliners in small groups made their way through the last barrier to <LOCATION>West 
Berlin</LOCATION>, the crowds on that side welcomed them with cheers and songs. 
</P>
<P>
East German border guards, who obviously had no instructions on the new border 
policy, generally waved them through with puzzled smiles. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm watching history being made," said one <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> bystander. 
</P>
<P>
It was like New Year's Eve or a World Series victory celebration at this and 
other border crossings along the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall. Late <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and <DATE>early today</DATE>, 
hundreds of people climbed atop the grim, grafitti-marred structure, long the 
symbol of the Iron Curtain dividing East and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. Some of them danced for joy 
there. 
</P>
<P>
The new border policy was explained by Politburo member <PERSON>Guenter Schabowski</PERSON>, who 
told a news conference here that East Germans would "promptly" be given permits 
to go to <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>. He said they could stay there if they wish, or return to 
<LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"This means that the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall has no more meaning," an East German official 
said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
"The long-awaited day has arrived," declared <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Walter Momper</PERSON>. 
"The <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall no longer divides <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
Crowds swarmed through the streets long after <TIME>midnight</TIME>, auto horns blared, 
police sirens pierced the air, couples walked hand in hand toward the wall and 
people laughed and smiled, offering each other open wine and beer bottles. 
</P>
<P>
Some East Germans arriving at border crossings at Invalidenstrasse and 
Prinzstrasse in their small, sputtering Trabant autos were almost prevented 
from entering by the crowds gathered to greet them. But they made their way 
through to <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>'s bright lights. 
</P>
<P>
Remarkably, many of the <LOCATION>East Berliners</LOCATION> returned later today to the drab, gray 
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> half of the city after sampling the bright lights of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I just wanted to take a look at the <LOCATION>Kurfuerstendamm</LOCATION>," said one young man in 
his 20s, as he returned from <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION>'s famous shopping district and headed 
back through the wall to <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
From their side, hundreds of West Berliners crossed into <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>, shouting, 
"The wall is gone, the wall is gone!" 
</P>
<P>
A huge crowd gathered next to the Reichstag building at the Brandenburg Gate -- 
the traditional scene of anti-wall demonstrations by <LOCATION>West Berliners</LOCATION> and the 
place where President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> uttered his famous line, "Ich bin ein 
Berliner." 
</P>
<P>
Many people climbed atop the wall there. At <TIME>3 a.m.</TIME>, lights at the gate were 
still blazing as the crowd called out: "Open the gate!" 
</P>
<P>
Beyond <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, as one analyst here put it: "This news is deeply significant. It 
changes the whole shape of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. It will take a while for the import of this 
to sink in." 
</P>
<P>
In the euphoria of <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, there were few formalities for those surging 
through the checkpoints in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But beginning <TIME>this morning</TIME>, East Germans will be expected under the new open 
policy to get exit visas for travel abroad, whether permanent emigration or 
just a visit. 
</P>
<P>
They will be allowed to go through any crossing point in the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall except 
<PERSON>Checkpoint Charlie</PERSON>, which is reserved for foreigners and military personnel. 
</P>
<P>
Whether emigrating or just visiting, they also may enter <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> through 
the various crossings along the fortified inner-German frontier. 
</P>
<P>
West Germans long have been free to travel to <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> by simply arriving 
at the border, paying a small fee and exchanging some West German money for 
East German currency. 
</P>
<P>
Schabowski, the spokesman for <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s Politburo, was asked about tearing 
down the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall. 
</P>
<P>
"The opening of the wall does not answer its real purpose," he said. "There is 
still a whole complex of questions that will have to be discussed." 
</P>
<P>
He mentioned the state of the opposing military alliances in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> -- the 
control as factors bearing on the ultimate fate of the Wall. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, officials said that though East German emigrants are inundating the 
country, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> will accept all East Germans arriving there. 
</P>
<P>
"No one will be turned back," Interior Minister <PERSON>Wolfgang Schaeuble</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Schaeuble warned that new arrivals can expect poor housing for a long time to 
come -- in what was seen as an effort to discourage the flood of immigrants. 
</P>
<P>
"For this reason," he said, and because of the cold season, every German from 
<LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> should think carefully before they come here." 
</P>
<P>
A session of the West German Parliament broke into the national anthem on 
hearing the news from <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> about opening the borders. 
</P>
<P>
Bundestag member <PERSON>Willy Brandt</PERSON>, the former chancellor who was mayor of <LOCATION>West 
Berlin</LOCATION> in <DATE>1961</DATE> when the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall went up, wept openly. 
</P>
<P>
The stunning news came after another tumultuous day in <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> during the 
three-day meeting of the policy-making <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party Central Committee</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Central Committee</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that there will be a special 
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> meeting <DATE>Monday</DATE> to approve the newly appointed reformist Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Hans Modrow</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Central Committee</ORGANIZATION> also called a rare meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party 
Conference</ORGANIZATION> for <DATE>Dec. 15-17</DATE> to discuss the economic, political and social crises 
swamping the country. 
</P>
<P>
An economic slowdown has been compounded by the flight of about 225,000 East 
Germans so far this year. 
</P>
<P>
West German estimates of those East Germans wishing to depart range from 
400,000 to 1.2 million -- in a nation of 16.6 million. 
</P>
<P>
Travel restrictions helped spark the massive demonstrations that brought East 
Germans out in unprecedented numbers onto the streets of <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Leipzig</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Dresden</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Halle</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Schwerin</LOCATION> and other cities. 
</P>
<P>
In his briefing on the lifting of travel restrictions, <PERSON>Schabowski</PERSON> said, "The 
decision was taken that makes it possible for all citizens to leave the country 
through East German crossing points." 
</P>
<P>
Schabowski's announcement seemed almost impromptu: He did not read from the 
prepared text he was given shortly before the briefing and seemed vague about 
some details. 
</P>
<P>
But he indicated that East Germans can take their identity cards to their local 
police station and apply for exit visas. Thus, they would not need passports, 
which not many East Germans have. 
</P>
<P>
The exit visas, <PERSON>Schabowski</PERSON> said, will be issued without red tape or demanding a 
reason for the travel. 
</P>
<P>
Similarly, he said those wishing to emigrate would be treated with dispatch. 
</P>
<P>
The decision, <PERSON>Schabowski</PERSON> said, will ease East German relations with Communist 
neighbor <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION> because emigrants no longer will be forced to pass 
through that country en route to the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Curiously, some opposition elements in <LOCATION>East Berlin</LOCATION> did not applaud the 
Communist leaders' decision to open up travel to the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hans-Peter Schneider</PERSON>, a leader of the small opposition group Democratic 
Awakening, declared: "I doubt that it is a step that will keep the people here. 
I would have preferred it if they had said take your passport and get a visa 
and come back to us. 
</P>
<P>
"I think this step is a sign of the helplessness of our leaders." 
</P>
<P>
But for thousands of Germans, it was a sign of hope. 
</P>
<P>
About <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME>, an animal trainer walked through <PERSON>Checkpoint Charlie</PERSON> with a big, 
brown muzzled bear on a leash. 
</P>
<P>
"The bear is a symbol of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>," he said, "A united <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>. We are now one 
city." 
</P>
<P>
"We couldn't believe we could get out," said one man who crossed with his wife. 
"We just wanted to try it. But we will return." 
</P>
<P>
Most people on foot and in cars appeared to have little baggage with them, 
indicating they planned to go back to the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> -- in contrast to those who fled 
through <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION> carrying all their family belongings. 
</P>
<P>
One woman who had been watching the drama for two hours said: "The Vopos (East 
German police) don't know what to do. So they have just been waving people 
through." 
</P>
<P>
Another man said: "A Vopo gave me a cigarette. I am keeping it as a souvenir. 
Ordinarily they would take your picture to put you on the blacklist." 
</P>
<P>
A bearded <LOCATION>West Berliner</LOCATION>, watching the amazing sight of East Berliners coming 
