<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890722-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-89 1731EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Apollo-Houston     07-22 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Apollo-Houston,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>Apollo Week Draws to Close at Johnson Space Center, Houston</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Covering</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF AWALT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SPACE CENTER, Houston (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Apollo 11 astronaut <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> led
a parade <DATE>Saturday</DATE> through <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION> in the city whose
name was the first word ever spoken on the <DATE>moon two decades ago</DATE>.
   ``On <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>, men first stepped on the moon and made more
than footprints in history,'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> told space fans at a rally
beside what would have been Apollo 18, the giant <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> 5 rocket
whose mission was scuttled by an expensive war in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>.
   Aldrin, minus his fellow moon-walker of 20 years ago, <PERSON>Neil
Armstrong</PERSON>, was one of 14 Apollo astronauts who attended the
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> events commemorating the successful <DATE>1969</DATE> mission
and other past accomplishments and looking ahead to an expanded
program of space exploration.
   When men first landed on the moon <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> had
said: ``<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Tranquillity Base</ORGANIZATION> here. The <ORGANIZATION>Eagle</ORGANIZATION> has landed.''
   ``Since then, we've seen many triumphs and tragedies in our
quest in space,'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> said, stopping for applause from the large
crowds surrounding Rocket Park. ``And now, thanks to President
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, we continue to reach for the stars.''
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, in his speech <DATE>Thursday</DATE> on the 20th anniversary of the
lunar landing, called for a continuing commitment to space
exploration.
   Several thousand people attended the parade and rally at <ORGANIZATION>Johnson
Space Center</ORGANIZATION>, where <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and others thanked <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> and the
surrounding cities for their support of the space program.
   Crowds that lined streets for the space center's first public
parade waved American flags and cheered the astronauts who have
lived and worked in the <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> area, where the astronaut corps is
based.
   Hot air balloons lifted into the air and T-38 training jets flew
in formation over the festivities.
   Aldrin received a plaque with a footprint like the ones left on
the moon, and a child's handprint. It was enscribed, ``When we
touch the moon again.''
   ``Not unlike earthbound explorers and adventurers before us, we
search for yet-unknown treasures and try to unlock and understand
the mysteries of nature,'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> said. ``It is inherent in our
kind to strive for a better understanding of life and a richer
source of understanding.''
   Aldrin joined <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s current chief astronaut, Capt. <PERSON>Dan
Brandenstein</PERSON>, in recognizing other astronauts and space program
contributors before and after the historic moon mission.
   On stage with <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Brandenstein</PERSON> were astronauts
representing missions Apollo 9 _ the first to reach lunar distance
_ through Apollo 17.
   ``The Apollo landing, as you're all well aware, was probably the
premier event in the <DATE>last 20 years</DATE> or better and we are proud to
have these men back with us today,'' <PERSON>Brandenstein</PERSON> said. ``However,
a program like the Apollo program takes a great deal of teamwork,
as do many of the other (<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>) programs.''
   Just as the <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> and Gemini programs laid the groundwork for
Apollo and the trip to the moon, Apollo helped lay the base for the
shuttle era and the work on the space station, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890717-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-17-89 0209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ApolloAnniversary Bjt   07-17 0576</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Apollo Anniversary, Bjt,0594</SECOND>
<HEAD>Apollo Astronauts Celebrate 20th Anniversary of Moon Landing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty years after the first moon
walk, the Apollo 11 crew called for further exploration of the lunar
surface and Mars, but another astronaut said a bold new program is
unlikely soon.
   <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON>, <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mike Collins</PERSON>, at a ceremony
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> commemorating the anniversary of their spectacular liftoff on
<DATE>July 16, 1969</DATE>, expressed their hopes for a rejuvenated space program.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the anniversary of the landing, they will join with
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> for a celebration outside the <ORGANIZATION>National Air and Space
Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   There, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> will deliver a speech on space policy. Some are
pressing him to announce a return to the moon, while others are
pushing for an exploration to Mars. Many scientists are suggesting a
joint U.S.-Soviet exploration for either option.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> he was weighing different ideas.
   At <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>, told 6,000 flag-waving space
workers and their families <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that they should ``allow ourselves
just a touch of pride, a touch of satisfaction, that we were
participants and witnesses to the birth of a new human era.''
   He said historians in future centuries will identify the <DATE>20th
century</DATE> ``as the time when the human species broke the bonds of
gravity that had heretofore bound them to this planet.''
   In brief remarks, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>, who walked on the moon with <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>,
and <PERSON>Collins</PERSON>, who remained in lunar orbit in the command ship, looked
to future space exploration.
   ``One of these years, and I hope it won't be too long, this
country will decide to press on again far out into space, perhaps to
the planet Mars,'' <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> said.
   Aldrin said <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Freedom space station, to be assembled in
orbit in the mid-1990s, should serve as a stepping stone to a manned
lunar base and human flights to Mars.
   He called President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON>'s commitment to the moon
landing goal 28 years ago ``a starter's gun for our pioneering giant
leap for mankind.''
   ``We're not yet ready for that go again. But perhaps we are at
the starting line, prepared to take our marks or get set,'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
said.
   Following the ceremony, the astronauts rode in a
20-mile-motorcade from the space center to <LOCATION>Cocoa Beach</LOCATION>, where they
attended a luncheon in their honor. An estimated 10,000 people lined
the route to cheer the spacemen and to take pictures.
   For <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Collins</PERSON>, the ceremony was the second
stop on a week-long sentimental journey that began <DATE>Saturday</DATE> with a
their <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> 5 rocket was designed.
   In <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, Apollo 12 astronaut Alan Bean had a more
pessimistic view of space exploration in the near future.
   Bean, the fourth man to walk on the moon, said that until the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> decides to put a man on the moon or take some other
such step, Americans will be complacent about their space
achievements.
   ``Sometime something will happen where we'll say maybe we'd
better catch up. But that won't happen today,'' Bean said.
   Bean, who walked on the moon on <DATE>Nov. 19, 1969</DATE>, and later flew
aboard Skylab 3 for 59 days in <DATE>1973</DATE>, said he didn't want to see
another 1960s-style space race.
   ``I'd rather have space cooperation. I'd think that would be much
better for the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890714-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-14-89 0430EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MoonAnniversary     07-14 0447</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Moon Anniversary,0459</SECOND>
<HEAD>Apollo 11 Astronauts Will Commemorate Moon-Landing Anniversary</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Space Goals, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Apollo 11 astronauts kick off a
man's landing on the moon, beginning at the site where their lunar
rocket was designed.
   They will take part in ceremonies and parties at three <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> space
centers and with President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> in the nation's capital.
   <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> left the first footprints on the
lunar surface on <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>, while <PERSON>Mike Collins</PERSON> circled overhead
in the command ship.
   The three will start their anniversary trip <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the
<ORGANIZATION>Marshall Space Flight Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, where the giant
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> 5 rocket that propelled them to the moon was designed and
tested.
   There they will meet with rocket pioneers and attend a reception
and an open house concert where the landing on the moon's <ORGANIZATION>Sea of
Tranquillity</ORGANIZATION> will be re-created by actors on a stage.
   The astronauts will be at the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Cape
Canaveral</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the launch's anniversary. Against a backdrop of
an unused <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> 5, now a museum piece, they will make brief remarks
and listen to a tape recording of the launch commentary in the
minutes before the Apollo 11 liftoff.
   The ``taped liftoff'' will occur at <TIME>9:32 a.m. EDT</TIME>, precisely the
time they left <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   After the ceremony the spacemen will ride in a motorcade that
will travel 20 miles to <LOCATION>Cocoa Beach</LOCATION>, where they will be honored at a
luncheon.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, they will be in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> for an evening reception
at the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution's National Air and Space Museum</ORGANIZATION>.
   The next day, the anniversary of the moon landing, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> will be joined by President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> for a ceremony
on the <ORGANIZATION>Mall</ORGANIZATION> in front of the museum.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is expected to unveil a long-term space plan that could
include strong endorsement of a permanent space station and
proposals for building a lunar research base and sending Americans
to Mars early in the <DATE>21st century</DATE>.
   The astronauts then will fly to the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, site of their Apollo training base and home for the <ORGANIZATION>Mission
Control Center</ORGANIZATION> that directs all <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> manned spaceflights.
   There they will attend a giant reception on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>
attended by 5,000 or more people who will re-create the infamous
``splashdown parties'' that went on all night after each successful
Apollo mission.
   Next <DATE>Friday</DATE>, they will attend a black tie gala at a <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>
hotel. The master of ceremonies will be <PERSON>Walter Cronkite</PERSON>, the former
<ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> anchorman who reported on the mission for his network.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900301-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-01-90 0122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Shuttle-LastMission     03-01 0862</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shuttle-Last Mission,0883</SECOND>
<HEAD>Silent Orbit, A Final Mission</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The writer began covering <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s space
program for <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>May 1959</DATE>. He has covered more
than 2,300 rocket or missile launches, including every <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> manned
mission. On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, he retired, but not before covering his 65th
manned space flight.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The writer began covering <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s space
program for <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>May 1959</DATE>. He has covered more
than 2,300 rocket or missile launches, including every <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> manned
mission. On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, he retired, but not before covering his 65th
manned space flight.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072389-0079 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 85713 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 23, 1989, Sunday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 2; Column 5; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
140 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE NATION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Apollo 11 astronaut <PERSON>Edwin E.</PERSON> (Buzz) <PERSON>Aldrin Jr.</PERSON> led a parade through the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson 
Space Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, the city whose name was the first word ever spoken on 
the <DATE>moon two decades ago</DATE>. "On <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>, men first stepped on the moon and 
made more than footprints in history," <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> told space fans at a rally beside 
what would have been Apollo 18, the giant <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> 5 rocket whose mission was 
scuttled because of the costs of the war in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. Aldrin, minus his fellow 
moon walker of 20 years ago, <PERSON>Neil A. Armstrong</PERSON>, was one of 14 Apollo astronauts 
who attended the events commemorating the successful <DATE>1969</DATE> mission and other 
past accomplishments and looking ahead to an expanded program of space 
exploration. When the Apollo 11 crew first landed on the moon, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> had 
said: "<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Tranquillity Base</ORGANIZATION> here. The <ORGANIZATION>Eagle</ORGANIZATION> has landed." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890628-0217 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-28-89 1437EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Apollo-12ontheMoon Adv09   06-28 1074</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Apollo-12 on the Moon, Adv 09,1089</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv09</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, July 9, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Capsules of 12 Who Walked on Moon</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Part of an eight-story package for use at will or on successful
Sundays in July.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twelve men, all Americans, walked on
the moon in those heady days of Apollo exploration. Their fame was
fleeting and their names today are mostly dim memories.
   <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> earned a place in history 20 years ago when he
became the first human to leave his footprints in the ancient lunar
dust.
   The rest, in order: <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Charles Conrad Jr.</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alan L.
Bean</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alan B. Shepard Jr.</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edgar D. Mitchell</PERSON>, <PERSON>David R. Scott</PERSON>, <PERSON>James
B. Irwin</PERSON>, <PERSON>John W. Young</PERSON>, <PERSON>Charles M. Duke Jr.</PERSON>, <PERSON>Eugene A. Cernan</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Harrison H. Schmitt</PERSON>.
   Each was affected profoundly by his stay on the moon and the
perspective it gave them of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ``My impression was of the importance of that small, fragile,
remote blue planet,'' <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> reported. ``People everywhere have,
by television and photographs, shared that perspective and shared
our concern for the security of our globe.''
   Nine of the moon-walkers are business executives, one is an
artist, one is an evangelist, and one remains with <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>, an
engineering trouble-shooter.
   Here is a glance:
   _ <PERSON>Neil A. Armstrong</PERSON>, 58 ... aeronautical engineering degree from
Purdue ... flew 78 combat missions in <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> ... X-15 test pilot ...
commanded Gemini 8, aborted shortly after the first docking of two
vehicles in space ... first man to walk on the moon ... shunned the
spotlight and became a professor of aerospace engineering at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Cincinnati</ORGANIZATION> for nine years ... chairman <ORGANIZATION>CTA Inc.</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, a computer systems company.
   _ <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON>, 59 ... born <PERSON>Edwin E. Aldrin Jr.</PERSON>, but legally
changed name ... son of a general ... West Point honor graduate ...
fighter pilot in <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> ... Gemini 12 space walker ... landed on the
moon with <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> on Apollo 11 ... commander of the <ORGANIZATION>Aerospace
Research Pilots School</ORGANIZATION> ... passed over for promotion to brigadier
general by the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> ... suffered mental depression and bouts
with alcoholism and recovered from both ... now president of his own
Los Angeles-based firm, <ORGANIZATION>Research &amp; Engineering Consultants</ORGANIZATION>.
   _ <PERSON>Charles Conrad Jr.</PERSON>, 59 ... engineering degree from <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>
... <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> test pilot ... eight days in space aboard Gemini 5 ...
commanded Gemini 11 ... commanded Apollo 12 moon landing ... daring
space walks helped save crippled Skylab station ... now a senior
vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Douglas Aircraft Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   _ <PERSON>Alan L. Bean</PERSON>, 57 ... aeronautical engineering degree from
<ORGANIZATION>University of Texas ... Navy</ORGANIZATION> test pilot ... holder of 11 world
records in space and aeronautics ... landed on the moon with Conrad
... commanded 56-day Skylab 2 flight ... resigned from <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE>
to devote time to his hobby, painting, and now turns out expensive
canvases of the moon and other space scenes in his <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> studio.
   _ <PERSON>Alan B. Shepard Jr.</PERSON>, 65 ... <ORGANIZATION>Naval Academy</ORGANIZATION> graduate ... carrier
and test pilot ... only one of the seven original Mercury astronauts
to walk on the moon ... first American in space, a 15-minute
suborbital flight in <DATE>1961</DATE> ... grounded for several years by an ear
disorder ... commanded Apollo 14 moon landing ... several banking,
real estate and other business interests have made him a <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>
millionaire.
   _ <PERSON>Edgar D. Mitchell</PERSON>, 58 ... doctorate of science from MIT ...
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> carrier and test pilot ... landed on the moon with <PERSON>Shepard</PERSON> ...
en route to moon he conducted extrasensory perception experiments
with a friend in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> ... on return he concentrated on research
into psychic phenomena and wrote a book about it ... now chairman of
<ORGANIZATION>Forecast Systems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>West Palm Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   _ <PERSON>David R. Scott</PERSON>, 57 ... fifth in <LOCATION>West Point</LOCATION> class ... master of
science from <ORGANIZATION>MIT ... Air Force</ORGANIZATION> test pilot ... flew with <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> on
the aborted Gemini 8 flight ... commander of Apollo 9 Earth-orbiting
mission that tested the Lunar Module ... commanded Apollo 15 moon
landing ... <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> and crewmates <PERSON>James B. Irwin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Alfred P. Worden</PERSON>
admitted carrying 400 unauthorized stamps to the moon which they
planned to sell; all three were removed from astronaut status ...
<PERSON>Scott</PERSON> became director of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Flight Research School</ORGANIZATION> and now is
president of <ORGANIZATION>Scott Science and Technology</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Lancaster</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   _ <PERSON>James B. Irwin</PERSON>, 59 ... <ORGANIZATION>Naval Academy</ORGANIZATION> graduate ... <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
test pilot ... with <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>, drove first lunar car on the moon ...
viewed his Apollo 15 moon journey as an overwhelming religious
experience ... founded High Flight, an interdenominational
evangelistic foundation, headquartered in <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>
... slowed by three heart attacks, but continues his religious work
... made six expeditions to Mount Ararat in <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION> in search for
<ORGANIZATION>Noah</ORGANIZATION>'s ark.
   _ <PERSON>John W. Young</PERSON>, 58 ... aeronautical engineering graduate of
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> ... piloted Gemini 3, the first manned <ORGANIZATION>Gemini</ORGANIZATION> flight,
and commanded Gemini 10 ... orbited moon on Apollo 10 and landed as
commander of Apollo 16 ... only moonwalker to fly on the space
shuttle, commanding the first and ninth missions ... has made a
record six space flights ... served as chief of the astronaut office
and now is special assistant for engineering operations and safety
at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>.
   _ <PERSON>Charles M. Duke Jr.</PERSON>, 53 ... <ORGANIZATION>Naval Academy</ORGANIZATION> graduate ... master
of science from <ORGANIZATION>MIT ... Air Force</ORGANIZATION> test pilot ... landed on the moon
with Young ... now a partner in <ORGANIZATION>Duke Investments</ORGANIZATION> and president of
<ORGANIZATION>Southwest Wilderness Art</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   _ <PERSON>Eugene A. Cernan</PERSON>, 55 ... degree in electrical engineering from
<LOCATION>Purdue</LOCATION> ... <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> fighter pilot ... Gemini 9 spacewalker ... flew
within 10 miles of the moon on Apollo 10 ... commanded Apollo 17,
last Apollo moon-landing mission ... helped plan <DATE>1975</DATE> U.S.-Soviet
manned flight ... now president of the <ORGANIZATION>Houston-based Cernan
Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, which consults on aerospace, energy and related
industries.
   _ <PERSON>Harrison H. Schmitt</PERSON>, 54 ... doctorate in geology from <LOCATION>Harvard</LOCATION>
... served with <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>'s Astrogeology Branch ...
trained astronauts in geology before joining the corps ... first
geologist on the moon, on Apollo 17 ... served one term as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
senator from <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> ... now a business consultant in <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, July 9</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890720-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-07-20-89 2325EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Apollo-HoustonCelebration 1stLd-Writethru a0751 07-20
0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Apollo-Houston Celebration, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0751,0394</SECOND>
<HEAD>``Splashdown'' Party Celebrates Apollo 11 Lunar Landing</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with color from party; picks up
4th graf pvs, `On July...</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ;ADDS byline.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush-Space, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HT2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH RENDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SPACE CENTER, Houston (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ;ADDS byline.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA052689-0183 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 62464 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 26, 1989, Friday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 2; Column 3; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
314 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
1ST MAN ON MOON BACKS PLANNED SPACE STATION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From United Press International 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Neil A. Armstrong</PERSON>, who walked into history <DATE>20 years ago July</DATE> as the first man 
on the moon, made a rare public appearance today with his two Apollo 11 crew 
mates and endorsed <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s planned space station. 
</P>
<P>
At a news conference to commemorate the <DATE>20th anniversary</DATE> of their historic 
flight, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>, 58, <PERSON>Edwin E.</PERSON> (Buzz) <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>, 59, and <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, 58, 
reminisced about their <DATE>July 16, 1969</DATE>, blastoff atop a mighty <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> 5 rocket 
and the mission that fulfilled President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON>'s promise to land men 
on the moon before the end of the <DATE>1960s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"Ten years ago, I did make a statement endorsing the concept of a permanent 
presence in space," <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> said. "I guess I still feel that's a worthy 
objective. I hope that space station Freedom becomes a reality before we have 
another 10 years go by." 
</P>
<P>
Armstrong was referring to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s plans to build a permanently manned space 
station in the <DATE>late 1990s</DATE>, a project that is threatened by budget cuts and a 
lack of political support. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Mars Mission Endorsed 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> called for an evolutionary approach to exploring the solar system while 
<PERSON>Collins</PERSON> strongly endorsed a mission to Mars. 
</P>
<P>
"I think this country should set a goal of exploring and setting up on Mars," 
<PERSON>Collins</PERSON> said. "That is the one goal that . . . I think would have a unifying 
and perhaps even an electrifying effect on <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> and our space program." 
</P>
<P>
Armstrong and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> touched down in the <ORGANIZATION>Sea of Tranquility</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>, 
in a spider-like lunar module spacecraft called <ORGANIZATION>Eagle</ORGANIZATION> while <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> orbited 69 
miles overhead in the gumdrop-shaped Apollo command module, <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"That's one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind," <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> said as 
he stepped onto the moon's surface. 
</P>
<P>
While <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> have granted interviews and written books, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>, 
a very private man, has routinely refused to meet the press or make public 
appearances. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Moon Flight Reunion Former lunar astronaut Michael Collins picks up a 
lunar module at news conference in Washington to mark upcoming 20th anniversary 
of lunar landing July 20, 1969. With him are fellow moon voyagers Buzz Aldrin, 
left, and Neil Armstrong. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890721-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-21-89 0536EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Apollo-HoustonCelebration     07-21 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Apollo-Houston Celebration,0550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Gather to Celebrate 20th Anniversary of Apollo 11 Lunar
Landing</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Space-What's Needed, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH RENDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SPACE CENTER, Houston (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bash for 10,000 past and present
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> employees had the same open bar and mob scene as the parties
that followed Apollo missions 20 years ago.
   The only thing missing was the splashdown.
   ``Then, they threw everybody in the pool,'' said <PERSON>Cookie
employee who was trying to take pictures of the honored guests at
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s party at the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION> _ Apollo 11 astronauts
<PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, who
marked the 20th anniversary of the first moonwalk.
   Leisenring recalled with pleasure the informal parties that
followed the Apollo splashdowns of the 60s and 70s.
   ``You knew everybody, the cars were parked on the medians and
you had to work to get up to the bar,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Leisenring</PERSON> said. ``All
the contractors had open bars at the hotels and you just walked up
and tried to make your way to get a drink. The parties were
everywhere.''
   One big party activity _ throwing others into the hotel swimming
pools _ wasn't possible <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Robert R. Gilruth Recreation
Facility</ORGANIZATION> has no pool.
   Separate outdoor areas of the party were designated for
different departments such as engineering and development and
recovery crew. Inside, a band played in a gym-sized room decorated
with star-shaped ballons and blue balloons with the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> flag on
them.
   Beer and soft drinks were free, but partygoers had to pay for
hot dogs.
   The crowds were so dense when the astronauts arrived at the
party that <ORGANIZATION>Space Center</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>Aaron Cohen</PERSON> had to board a van
carrying the astronauts to officially greet them. <PERSON>Hans Mark</PERSON>, a
former director, also greeted the astronauts.
   ``Twenty years ago, I sat in mission control when these guys
came down and I wouldn't miss this for the world,'' said <PERSON>Mark</PERSON>, now
the chancellor for the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION> system.
   Collins, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>, who earlier <DATE>Thursday</DATE> ate a
barbecue lunch with President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, exited the
van to loud cheers and then went separate ways to mingle with the
crowd.
   ``It is exciting to get to see all these guys that figured out
how to go to the moon in the first place,'' said <PERSON>Ken Schultz</PERSON>, an
engineer for <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Engineering &amp; Science Co</ORGANIZATION>. Inc. ``I'm just
sitting here and going `Wow.'''
   On <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> planted their footsteps
on the moon while <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> circled above in the spacecraft that
carried the three back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> proposed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to establish a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> moon base
early in the next century and then mount a manned Mars mission. His
proposal is likely to ignite a national debate in a budget-minded
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and among those who believe federal dollars should not be
spent on costly space endeavors but on solving more earthly
problems.
   After the splashdown party, the three former astronauts attended
a private party at a nearby hotel where they watched a fireworks
display that began at <TIME>9:56 p.m.</TIME> _ the moment <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> stepped on
the moon <DATE>two decades ago</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890720-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-20-89 1438EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush-Space-Scene     07-20 0719</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Space-Scene,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Astronauts Share Memories With Bush</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush-Space, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly half the American astronauts who flew in
space shared a day of memories <DATE>Thursday</DATE> with the president. It was
one small ceremony for man, recalling one giant leap for mankind.
   ``It's hard to believe that 20 years have passed,'' said
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> of man's first landing on the moon. ``Three days and
three nights they journeyed. It was a perilous, unprecedented,
breathtaking voyage. And each of us remember the night.''
   ``They'' were the men of Apollo 11, which set down on the <ORGANIZATION>Sea of
Tranquillity</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>: <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>.
   On that day, they were the only human beings away from their
world; on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, they bathed in the glow of reminiscence outside
the <ORGANIZATION>National Air</ORGANIZATION> and Space Museum only a few feet from the command
module <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> which carried them to the moon and into the history
books.
   Behind them at the ceremony were models of the 36-story rocket
that lifted them from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and the spindly legged lander that took
<ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> to the airless moon.
   Eagle, the lander, still is on the moon, a souvenir of the brief
visit that will remain for all eternity, along with the American
flag they planted and the footprints they left.
   <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>, the first of 12 Americans who walked the moon, said
the space effort in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> had ``a nobility of purpose ... not to
conquer enemies, but to conquer ignorance.''
   Buzz Aldrin, No. 2 on the moon and now a strong advocate of
proceeding onward to <PERSON>Mars</PERSON> said ``the time for seizing the initiative
in space is upon us.''
   And <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, who orbited overhead as a lonely lifeguard
while <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> pirouetted on the moon, said ``we have
rested on our Apollo laurels long enough; it's time to get moving
again.''
   The president had words for <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>:
   ``For those old enough to remember that historic night 20 years
ago, step outside tonight with your children or your grandchildren.
Lift your eyes skyward, and tell them of the flag _ the American
flag _ that still flies proudly in the ancient lunar soil ...
   ``Project Apollo. The first men on the moon. Some called it
quixotic, impossible _ had never been done. But <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> dreamed it.
And <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> did it.''
   Among the 700 guests at the ceremony were 66 of the 126 Americans
who have gone into space, including 21 of the 30 who flew on Apollo.
   They went for the most part unrecognized: <PERSON>Pete Conrad</PERSON> and <PERSON>Alan
Bean</PERSON>, second on the moon on Apollo 12; <PERSON>Jim Lovell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Fred Haise</PERSON>,
who were going there but didn't make it because of an explosion _
the third man on their Apollo 13 voyage, <PERSON>John Swigert</PERSON> has died.
   There were also <PERSON>Eugene Cernan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Harrison Schmitt</PERSON>, the last on
the moon _ more than 16 years ago.
   In the crowd was <PERSON>Thomas Paine</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> administrator then and
more recently the architect of the plans for <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s future in
space that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> enunciated <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``That was first rate,'' he said of the president's speech. ``A
good beginning.''
   <PERSON>John Young</PERSON>, who made two Apollo flights, called it a great speech
and said he wasn't disturbed that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was not specific about time
and costs for the program he envisioned. ``Nobody knows what it will
cost,'' said <PERSON>Young</PERSON>, who also has flown the space shuttle four times,
``if anybody tells you the cost <DATE>today</DATE>, don't believe it.''
   <PERSON>Rusty Schweickart</PERSON>, who was on Apollo 9 _ a moon flight rehearsal
_ said ``Part of the problem of Apollo was it had a single,
wonderful goal but nothing to sustain the momentum.''
   Richard Truly, twice a shuttle astronaut and now head of the
space agency, saw <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s speech as ``dynamite ... a clear road map.''
   In his speech, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said he is asking ``my right hand man'', Vice
President <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> _ chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>National Space Council</ORGANIZATION> _ to
develop realistic timetables and milestones for future exploration
and to report back.
   Quayle, who has been out making pro-space speeches, said that
``when Americans set their minds to acomplish something, we always
exceed our expectations.''
   He addressed the crowd as ``My fellow astronauts.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890715-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-89 2322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpaceCelebration 2ndLd-Writethru a0633 07-15 0771</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Celebration, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0633,0784</SECOND>
<HEAD>20th Anniversary of Lunar Landing Brings Call for New Adventures</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Apollo-Footprints on Moon, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `Four days...,' with 2 grafs to UPDATE with description
of celebration. Picks up 6th graf pvs, `Aldrin, who...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WHUN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PHILLIP RAWLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty years after man walked on the
moon, those responsible for that ``one giant leap for mankind'' said
the space program needs another bold challenge to recapture
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s imagination.
   And with <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s imagination, they said, will come the
financial support needed for a daring project, such as landing
astronauts on Mars.
   On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, a soldout crowd of more than 4,000 people joined the
Apollo 11 crew _ <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael
Collins</PERSON> _ at the <LOCATION>Alabama Space</LOCATION> and Rocket Center for the first of
four celebrations around the country to commemorate the lunar
landing on <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>.
   Huntsville's celebration focuses on the role this northern
<LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> city and the <PERSON>Wernher von Braun</PERSON> rocket team at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Marshall Space Flight Center</ORGANIZATION> played in developing the <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> V
rocket to propel Apollo 11 on its journey to the moon.
   The celebration was like a high-tech rock concert without the
music. Lasers bounced off rockets exhibited throughout the center,
sound effects simulated the takeoff of the <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> V rocket to the
moon, and actors portrayed <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>'s and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>'s walk on the
rugged lunar landscape four days after blasting off from <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy
Space Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   It climaxed with the Apollo 11 crew rising from a cloud of smoke
20 feet into the air to the front of a giant movie screen showing
footage of their travels. The crew was surrounded by a cacophony of
fireworks and dozens of dancing laser beams.
   Aldrin, who spent much of his time in <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION> autographing his
new book ``Men from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' describes the 20th anniversary as
``bittersweet.'' That's because he worries that <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> ``will sink
to second-rate status'' in space if it continues on its present
course.
   The 59-year-old former astronaut said <DATE>Saturday</DATE> he hoped the
anniversary would help <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> set well-defined space objectives
instead of having each space shuttle flight ``being an entity into
itself.''
   ``There is an excitement about the past but there is not an
awareness of where we want to go,'' he said in an interview.
   He envisions the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> working with the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> on space research projects, with a goal of developing
spaceships that will take advantage of planetary movements to
slingshot between Mars and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on five-month cycles.
   <PERSON>Collins</PERSON>, 58, also called for greater direction in the space
program.
   ``One of these days, and I hope it's not too long, this country
is going to decide it wants to go to Mars,'' he told a gathering of
engineers who worked on the Apollo project.
   Armstrong, 58, told the same group, ``A machine is man-made and
hence imperfect. No one has ever made a perfect machine. Those of
you who made the <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> V came about as close as history ever
recorded.''
   <PERSON>Jack Lee</PERSON>, director at <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Space Flight Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION>
and a former member of the von <PERSON>Braun</PERSON> team, vividly remembers
President <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>'s seemingly impossible challenge to land a man on
the moon by the end of the <DATE>1960s</DATE>.
   No president has issued an equally bold challenge since then, but
he hopes President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> will in a 20th anniversary speech <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``We must continue what <PERSON>Wernher von Braun</PERSON> and Apollo 11 started
many years ago, that is to reach out and touch another world,'' he
said. ``This time our launching pad is going to be the space
station.''
   <PERSON>Konrad Dannenberg</PERSON>, a German rocket scientist who came to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>
with <PERSON>Von Braun</PERSON> after World War II and later supervised engineering
and testing of the <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> rocket, said the moon landing ``was the
biggest step for mankind that has ever taken place. I hope this
(anniversary) is the first step toward an even bigger achievement.''
   <PERSON>Ed Buckbee</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Space and Rocket Center</ORGANIZATION>, a tourist
attraction focused on space achievements, and a former member of <PERSON>Von
Braun</PERSON>'s staff, said he hopes ``President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> gives us a goal. I've
heard everything from a moon colony to a man on <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, with a space
plane in there.''
   Buckbee said he sees only one way for <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> to recapture <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s
imagination and pocketbook.
   ``It's got to be a man on Mars landing,'' he said. ``I don't
think a space station is going to capture American imagination. It's
got to be something that puts man and machine against the hazards of
space.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA071789-0022 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 83122 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 17, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part 6; Page 2; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
168 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MORNING REPORT: TELEVISION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Claudia Puig, Arts and entertainment reports from The Times, national and 
international news services and the nation's press. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The executive producer of a <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> documentary on man's first walk on the moon in 
<DATE>1969</DATE> said the program mistakenly showed clips taken on the moon during a <DATE>1972</DATE> 
flight. The program said the <DATE>1972</DATE> footage was of the historic first moon walk 
by American astronauts. "It was an honest mistake," <PERSON>Perry Wolff</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> of 
the error in "The Moon Above, the Earth Below," a two-hour special that aired 
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> and saluted the 20th anniversary of the historic Apollo 11 moon 
flight. The program was co-anchored by <PERSON>Dan Rather</PERSON> and <PERSON>Charles Kuralt</PERSON>. Two 
scenes showed two astronauts -- ostensibly <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> -- 
bouncing on the moon's surface, and then their lunar orbiter blasting off from 
the moon. In a brief interview, <PERSON>Wolff</PERSON> said he had just learned that they 
actually were from the Apollo 17 flight in <DATE>December, 1972</DATE>. No deception was 
intended, he emphasized. He blamed the error on a "mislabeled tape" taken from 
a box of more than 100 tapes of footage of moon flights and landings. <PERSON>Claudia 
Puig</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890720-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-20-89 1230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Moon     07-20 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Moon,0273</SECOND>
<HEAD>20 Years Later, Soviet TV Shows U.S. Moon Landing</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Space, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet TV viewers finally got a chance <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to
see what the rest of the world saw 20 years ago: the first steps by
a man on the moon.
   State-run TV featured a lengthy documentary on the Apollo 11
lunar landing by astronauts <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON>,
including interviews with <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> scientists.
   On <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>, Soviet television ignored the historic landing
that millions around the world witnessed live, and instead broadcast
a musical variety show.
   <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s 20th anniversary documentary showed footage from the
moonwalk by <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>, with the astronauts gathering
samples of moon rocks. The American flag was clearly visible.
   The narrator of the documentary, former Soviet cosmonaut <PERSON>Vitaly
Sevastyanov</PERSON>, translated <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>'s famous first words on the moon
into Russian: ``Eto malyenky shag cheloveka, i bolshoi skochok
vsyevo chelovechestva'' _ ``That's one small step for a man, one
giant leap for mankind.''
   <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s broadcast _ shown on a weekday morning that hardly
guaranteed a wide audience _ followed a <DATE>July 10</DATE> article in Ogonyok
magazine that said it was wrong to hide the moon landing from the
Soviet people. The article also gave a detailed description of the
lunar landing.
   Under President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>'s policy of glasnost, or
greater openness, Soviet media have reported on many topics they
once did not cover.
   Soviet TV carried extensive coverage of the linkup of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Apollo and Soviet Soyez capsules in <DATE>1975</DATE>, but largely ignored the
American program to land a man on the moon.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890701-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-89 1057EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Apollo-NASAatCrossroads     07-01 1217</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Apollo-NASA at Crossroads,1249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hopes for New Space Ventures Tempered by High Cost</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Part of an eight-story package for use at will or on successful
Sundays in July. Also moved in advance June 28 as b0730.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY314-315, LaserGraphics, Logo</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> laments that ``the
promise of Apollo was never fulfilled,'' that the American space
program languished after he and <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> left the first human
footprints on the <DATE>moon two decades ago</DATE>.
   He says he hopes the 20th anniversary of Apollo 11 will ``become
a catalyst for the country to chart a bold course for human
expansion outward.''
   But given today's political and tight budgetary climate, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
is not too hopeful.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is expected to voice continuing support for a
permanent manned space station and say other nice things about
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s program when he meets with <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and their
command module pilot, <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, on <DATE>July 20</DATE>, the anniversary
of the moon landing.
   But no matter how many nice things the president says about
space, the political truth is that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> must approve the money.
And with the space station already facing a sharp funding cut,
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is not expected to give much support to new projects.
is at a crossroads, as it was when the glory days of Apollo ended.
   President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> had committed this nation to landing a
man on the moon in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>. The goal was to gain space superiority
over the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, whose early feats had earned the Russians
worldwide respect and shocked Americans.
   When the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> won the race to the moon, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> laid out
bold plans for the future.
   To a presidential panel, agency head <PERSON>Thomas Paine</PERSON> in <DATE>1969</DATE>
proposed a 12-man space station and a reusable space shuttle in
operation as early as <DATE>1976</DATE>, followed by a station in moon orbit, a
base on the moon, a 50-man space station in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit and a manned
mission to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   But in a period of unrest due to domestic racial problems and
involvement in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, costly plans to explore space were given low
priority.
   Only the reuseable space shuttle survived, and its proposed
funding was cut deeply.
   ``Those were tough times,'' said <PERSON>Paine</PERSON>, who resigned in
frustration a year after Apollo 11.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> administrations were lukewarm toward the
space program, but the shuttle was built. It performed capably as a
space truck for 24 missions until <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>, when the Challenger
exploded, killing its seven crew members and grounding the program
for 32 months.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> had gained some hope from President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s endorsement of
a strong space program and from his <DATE>1984</DATE> State of the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> message,
in which he backed building the space station Freedom.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> created a commission to define long-term space
goals. Its chief was <PERSON>Thomas Paine</PERSON>, the former <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> administrator.
   Six months after Challenger, <PERSON>Paine</PERSON> stood in the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> and
gave <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> a slick leather-bound volume that recommended the space
station, a lunar base and manned trips to Mars _ essentially an
update of <ORGANIZATION>Paine</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1969</DATE> plan.
   Reagan <DATE>two years later</DATE> signed a Presidential Directive on
<ORGANIZATION>National Space Policy</ORGANIZATION> that stated space leadership was a fundamental
objective. It endorsed the space station and, without being
specific, set a long-range goal ``to expand human presence and
activity beyond <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit into the solar system.''
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s policy set in motion a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> program named Pathfinder
whose goal is to test technologies for manned and robotic
exploration of the moon and planets, advanced missions in orbit and
on planetary surfaces, extended human presence in space, and space
transportation to the moon and planets.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has not disclosed his thinking beyond saying he supports a
space station. He established the <ORGANIZATION>National Space Council</ORGANIZATION>, headed by
Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, to recommend a comprehensive space policy.
   Quayle is expected to have a preliminary outline ready for <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s
anniversary meeting with the Apollo 11 astronauts.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> needs a decision from <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> soon on how much money it can
spend next year on space station Freedom. A permanent orbiting space
station is essential to those ambitious Pathfinder dreams and would
serve as a training base and launch pad for flights deeper into
space.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has requested <MONEY>$2.05 billion</MONEY> in the budget for fiscal <DATE>1990</DATE> to
continue work on the station. Predictions are that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will
trim that by <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY>, amounts that space
officials say could further delay or even kill the project.
   The space station project has gone through five tumultuous years.
Reagan wanted it built in cooperation with <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s major allies,
but there were stormy sessions over access to the station before 10
European nations, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> agreed to invest nearly <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY> to build sections of it.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said in <DATE>1984</DATE> it could begin launching segments of the
orbiting laboratory in <DATE>1992</DATE> and estimated the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cost at <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY>. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, agency officials revised the pricetag to <MONEY>$14.6
billion</MONEY>. The new figure covered a suddenly scaled-down Phase One,
which left off two of the external struts to which experiment
modules would be attached. The struts would be added in orbit under
Phase Two.
   Shortly after that, a <ORGANIZATION>National Research Council</ORGANIZATION> panel reviewing
station costs and technical issues for the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> said the
total cost to develop and deploy the first phase would be <MONEY>$25.02
billion</MONEY>, with Phase Two raising the cost to <MONEY>$32.8 billion</MONEY>.
   The schedule began slipping. And <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> now says if it receives the
proper funding, it could begin assembling the station in <DATE>1995</DATE>.
   Some in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> believe <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> should alter its plans and build a
less complex station and, instead of relying totally on the space
shuttle, develop a large unmanned rocket to do much of the lifting
job.
   Orbiting at 250 miles, Freedom would be home to a crew of eight,
with astronauts rotating back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> after four to six months.
   The station would allow humans to study the stars and planets
from the pollution-free environment of space. The weightless
interior would permit manufacture of new, contamination-free
medicines and other products impossible to create on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
Astronauts would assemble, service and repair satellites and send
them out into space. And the station could eventually be the staging
point for man's return to the moon or a journey to Mars.
   No one can predict whether these grand plans will come about, but
the three astronauts who made that extraordinary Apollo 11 flight to
the <DATE>moon 20 years ago</DATE> think they should.
   ``A permanent presence in space is a worthy objective, and I hope
that space station Freedom becomes a reality,'' <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> said
recently.
   ``I strongly endorse the station, a scientific base on the moon
and eventually manned flights to Mars,'' said <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, who orbited the moon while <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
walked its surface, envisioned setting up a colony on Mars.
   ``We're a nation of explorers,'' he said. ``We started on the
<LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>, we went to the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>, and then vertically. Starting
with the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers, <PERSON>Chuck Yeager</PERSON> through the sound barrier,
<ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and Aldrin on the moon.
   ``It's in our tradition, it's in our culture.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890628-0215 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-28-89 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Apollo-NASAatCrossroads Adv02   06-28 1224</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Apollo-NASA at Crossroads, Adv 02,1256</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv02</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, July 2, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Hopes for New Space Ventures Tempered by High Cost</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphics, Logo</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Part of an eight-story package for use at will or on successful
Sundays in July.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> laments that ``the
promise of Apollo was never fulfilled,'' that the American space
program languished after he and <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> left the first human
footprints on the <DATE>moon two decades ago</DATE>.
   He says he hopes the 20th anniversary of Apollo 11 will ``become
a catalyst for the country to chart a bold course for human
expansion outward.''
   But given today's political and tight budgetary climate, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
is not too hopeful.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is expected to voice continuing support for a
permanent manned space station and say other nice things about
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s program when he meets with <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and their
command module pilot, <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, on <DATE>July 20</DATE>, the anniversary
of the moon landing.
   But no matter how many nice things the president says about
space, the political truth is that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> must approve the money.
And with the space station already facing a sharp funding cut,
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is not expected to give much support to new projects.
is at a crossroads, as it was when the glory days of Apollo ended.
   President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> had committed this nation to landing a
man on the moon in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>. The goal was to gain space superiority
over the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, whose early feats had earned the Russians
worldwide respect and shocked Americans.
   When the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> won the race to the moon, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> laid out
bold plans for the future.
   To a presidential panel, agency head <PERSON>Thomas Paine</PERSON> in <DATE>1969</DATE>
proposed a 12-man space station and a reusable space shuttle in
operation as early as <DATE>1976</DATE>, followed by a station in moon orbit, a
base on the moon, a 50-man space station in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit and a manned
mission to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   But in a period of unrest due to domestic racial problems and
involvement in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, costly plans to explore space were given low
priority.
   Only the reuseable space shuttle survived, and its proposed
funding was cut deeply.
   ``Those were tough times,'' said <PERSON>Paine</PERSON>, who resigned in
frustration a year after Apollo 11.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> administrations were lukewarm toward the
space program, but the shuttle was built. It performed capably as a
space truck for 24 missions until <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>, when the Challenger
exploded, killing its seven crew members and grounding the program
for 32 months.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> had gained some hope from President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s endorsement of
a strong space program and from his <DATE>1984</DATE> State of the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> message,
in which he backed building the space station Freedom.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> created a commission to define long-term space
goals. Its chief was <PERSON>Thomas Paine</PERSON>, the former <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> administrator.
   Six months after Challenger, <PERSON>Paine</PERSON> stood in the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> and
gave <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> a slick leather-bound volume that recommended the space
station, a lunar base and manned trips to Mars _ essentially an
update of <ORGANIZATION>Paine</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1969</DATE> plan.
   Reagan <DATE>two years later</DATE> signed a Presidential Directive on
<ORGANIZATION>National Space Policy</ORGANIZATION> that stated space leadership was a fundamental
objective. It endorsed the space station and, without being
specific, set a long-range goal ``to expand human presence and
activity beyond <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit into the solar system.''
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s policy set in motion a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> program named Pathfinder
whose goal is to test technologies for manned and robotic
exploration of the moon and planets, advanced missions in orbit and
on planetary surfaces, extended human presence in space, and space
transportation to the moon and planets.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has not disclosed his thinking beyond saying he supports a
space station. He established the <ORGANIZATION>National Space Council</ORGANIZATION>, headed by
Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, to recommend a comprehensive space policy.
   Quayle is expected to have a preliminary outline ready for <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s
anniversary meeting with the Apollo 11 astronauts.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> needs a decision from <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> soon on how much money it can
spend next year on space station Freedom. A permanent orbiting space
station is essential to those ambitious Pathfinder dreams and would
serve as a training base and launch pad for flights deeper into
space.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has requested <MONEY>$2.05 billion</MONEY> in the budget for fiscal <DATE>1990</DATE> to
continue work on the station. Predictions are that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will
trim that by <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY>, amounts that space
officials say could further delay or even kill the project.
   The space station project has gone through five tumultuous years.
Reagan wanted it built in cooperation with <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s major allies,
but there were stormy sessions over access to the station before 10
European nations, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> agreed to invest nearly <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY> to build sections of it.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said in <DATE>1984</DATE> it could begin launching segments of the
orbiting laboratory in <DATE>1992</DATE> and estimated the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cost at <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY>. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, agency officials revised the pricetag to <MONEY>$14.6
billion</MONEY>. The new figure covered a suddenly scaled-down Phase One,
which left off two of the external struts to which experiment
modules would be attached. The struts would be added in orbit under
Phase Two.
   Shortly after that, a <ORGANIZATION>National Research Council</ORGANIZATION> panel reviewing
station costs and technical issues for the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> said the
total cost to develop and deploy the first phase would be <MONEY>$25.02
billion</MONEY>, with Phase Two raising the cost to <MONEY>$32.8 billion</MONEY>.
   The schedule began slipping. And <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> now says if it receives the
proper funding, it could begin assembling the station in <DATE>1995</DATE>.
   Some in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> believe <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> should alter its plans and build a
less complex station and, instead of relying totally on the space
shuttle, develop a large unmanned rocket to do much of the lifting
job.
   Orbiting at 250 miles, Freedom would be home to a crew of eight,
with astronauts rotating back to <ORGANIZATION>Earh</ORGANIZATION> after four to six months.
   The station would allow humans to study the stars and planets
from the pollution-free environment of space. The weightless
interior would permit manufacture of new, contamination-free
medicines and other products impossible to create on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
Astronauts would assemble, service and repair satellites and send
them out into space. And the station could eventually be the staging
point for man's return to the moon or a journey to Mars.
   No one can predict whether these grand plans will come about, but
the three astronauts who made that extraordinary Apollo 11 flight to
the <DATE>moon 20 years ago</DATE> think they should.
   ``A permanent presence in space is a worthy objective, and I hope
that space station Freedom becomes a reality,'' <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> said
recently.
   ``I strongly endorse the station, a scientific base on the moon
and eventually manned flights to Mars,'' said <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, who orbited the moon while <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
walked its surface, envisioned setting up a colony on Mars.
   ``We're a nation of explorers,'' he said. ``We started on the
<LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>, we went to the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>, and then vertically. Starting
with the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers, <PERSON>Chuck Yeager</PERSON> through the sound barrier,
<ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and Aldrin on the moon.
   ``It's in our tradition, it's in our culture.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, July 2</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890718-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-18-89 0136EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Apollo-20YearsAgo     07-18 0177</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Apollo-20 Years Ago,0177</SECOND>
<HEAD>What Happened 20 Years Ago During Moon Flight</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are highlights of events on the
Apollo 11 moon flight <DATE>20 years ago today</DATE>:
   As Apollo 11 coasted smoothly toward the moon, astronauts <PERSON>Neil
Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> left <PERSON>Mike Collins</PERSON> alone in the command
module <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> and crawled through a connecting tunnel to enter the
lunar module <ORGANIZATION>Eagle</ORGANIZATION>. With earthlings watching on television,
<ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> inspected the craft and checked switch settings
to make certain nothing had been disturbed or damaged by buffeting
at the time of launch. They reported the lunar ship was in good
shape.
   At <TIME>11:32 p.m. EDT</TIME>, the astronauts passed through an area called
the equigravisphere, a ``twilight zone'' in which the gravitational
influence of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and moon is about equal. Once through this
zone, the moon won the gravitational tug-of-war and Apollo 11 was in
the grip of lunar gravity. The ship passed through this invisible
barrier when it was 43,495 miles from the moon and 214,402 miles
from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890717-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-17-89 0250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SpaceCelebration-Bean     07-17 0356</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Space Celebration-Bean,0366</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronaut Says America Satisfied Being No. 2 in Space</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Apollo Anniversary, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PHILLIP RAWLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The fourth man to walk on the moon
doesn't expect more moon walks soon because of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s complacency
toward space discovery.
   Apollo 12 astronaut <PERSON>Alan Bean</PERSON>, 57, said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> he doubted that
bold space initiatives would arise out of the 20th anniversary of
the Apollo 11 mission, which put the first man on the moon.
   But Bean, speaking at <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION>'s Space Celebration <DATE>'89</DATE>, said
that doesn't bother him.
   ``It's Americans' way to go hard at a goal, then stand back and
savor that and not go hard at it all the time,'' he said. ``Back in
the days of Apollo, I thought we would have done much more by now.
But I didn't stop and think _ that is not the American way.''
   Bean, who walked on the moon on <DATE>Nov. 19, 1969</DATE>, flew aboard Skylab
3 for 59 days in <DATE>1973</DATE> and has trained astronauts, spoke a day after
Apollo 11 astronaut <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> addressed the <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION>
celebration.
   Aldrin had called for putting men on Mars within 20 years.
   ``I hope it's as fast as <ORGANIZATION>Buzz</ORGANIZATION> is talking about it,'' Bean said.
But he doubts it.
   ``People feel right now, that even though we are not No. 1 in the
world in space .. that if we really wanted to be and really made an
all-out effort like we did with Apollo, we could be No. 1,'' said
Bean, who noted specifically that Soviet endurance experiments in
space had far outstripped <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> efforts.
   Until the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> decides to put a man on the moon or take
some other pride-threatening step, Bean expects little change in
Americans' attitudes.
   ``Sometime something will happen where we'll say maybe we'd
better catch up. But that won't happen today,'' Bean said.
   When that day comes, Bean hopes for space cooperation between the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   ``I'd think that would be much better for the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' said Bean,
who is retired in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> and spends his time painting space scenes.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890628-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-28-89 1605EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Apollo-FootprintsonMoon Adv16-2Takes   06-28 1267</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Apollo-Footprints on Moon, Adv 16-2 Takes,1295</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv16</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, July 16, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>20 Years Since Armstrong's `Small Step for a Man'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Part of an eight-story package for use at will or on successful
Sundays in July.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhotos, LaserGraphics, Logo</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
one giant leap for mankind.''
   Twenty years have passed, nearly a generation, since <PERSON>Neil
Armstrong</PERSON> called those momentous words down from the moon.
   Two decades since Earthlings watched those flickering television
images, saw that tentative first step on the dusty surface and
looked on in wonder as two Americans hopped about in weak gravity,
planted and saluted their flag, picked up bits of lunar treasure and
spoke with their president a quarter million miles away.
   Most people living then can tell you today where they were when
astronauts <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> took those first steps on
the moon <DATE>Sunday, July 20, 1969</DATE>.
   They were realizing a goal that <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> had set in
frustration and desperation.
   Kennedy came to office in <DATE>January 1961</DATE> with a pledge to ``get
this country moving again.'' The economy was sluggish, <PERSON>Fidel Castro</PERSON>
had taken over <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> trailed the Soviets in
the highly visible arena of space.
   The space chasm widened <DATE>April 12, 1961</DATE>, when Soviet cosmonaut
<PERSON>Yuri A. Gagarin</PERSON> blasted into orbit, the first man to fly in space.
   American prestige was rocked again <DATE>five days later</DATE>. On <DATE>April 17</DATE>,
a brigade of Cuban exiles, sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Central Intelligence
Agency</ORGANIZATION>, stormed the beach at <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Bay of Pigs</LOCATION> in an effort to
overthrow <PERSON>Castro</PERSON>. His forces routed the ill-equipped exiles, leaving
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and its young president in shame and disarray.
   Kennedy accepted the blame and decided bold action was needed to
restore <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s honor. Space was the answer, he concluded, and he
gave Vice President <PERSON>Lyndon Johnson</PERSON> the task of determining what
could be done.
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> chaired, submitted a preliminary report to the president.
``The moon is a good target for us,'' it said.
   Even as the president and his advisers were discussing moon
trips, some in the administration were concerned about the first
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> man-in-space flight, now set for <DATE>May 2</DATE>. With everything going
wrong for the nation, the impact of a failure could be devastating.
   But <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> let the launch date stand, and, on <DATE>May 5</DATE>, after a
three-day weather delay, astronaut <PERSON>Alan Shepard</PERSON> rode a slender
Redstone rocket and a cramped Mercury capsule 115 miles up and 302
miles down the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> tracking range on a 15-minute suborbital
flight.
   America heaved a sigh of relief. The Soviets were still ahead,
but the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was on the move.
   On <DATE>May 25</DATE>, four months after taking office, <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> delivered a
special <ORGANIZATION>State of the Union</ORGANIZATION> message on urgent national needs. It
covered many subjects, from the economy to disarmament. It also
dealt with space.
   ``I believe this nation should commit itself to achieving the
goal, before the decade is out, of landing a man on the moon and
returning him safely to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. No single space project in this
period will be more impressive to mankind, or more important to the
long-range exploration of space; and none will be so difficult or
expensive to accomplish.''
   The project was called Apollo _ after the Greek archer-god, the
god of light and truth, bright-shining, far-shooting.
   <PERSON>Christopher C. Kraft Jr.</PERSON>, who would become flight operations
director for Apollo, was a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineer working on the Mercury
project.
   ``I thought he had lost his mind,'' <PERSON>Kraft</PERSON> said of <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> and his
bold commitment. ``We had a total of 15 minutes of manned
spaceflight experience, we hadn't flown <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> in orbit yet, and
here's a guy telling me we're going to fly to the moon. ... Doing it
was one thing, but doing it in this decade was to me too risky.''
   Despite the doubts of <PERSON>Kraft</PERSON> and others within <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s
biggest, costliest and most ambitious technological effort began
with virtually no dissent. Before it was achieved, more than 20,000
industrial contractors and 420,000 technicians, engineers and other
skilled persons would be involved.
   While the hardware of Apollo was being developed and tested,
Americans and Russians were learning to live and work in space and
to perfect the rockets, spaceships and techniques for going to the
moon.
   To a watching world, it was like a relay race in space. The
Russians, with their larger booster rockets and larger manned
spacecraft, held the early lead.
   <PERSON>John Glenn</PERSON> in <DATE>1962</DATE> was hailed as <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first orbital
champion. Three more Mercury orbital flights proved man could
survive and function for at least a short time in weightless space.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> moved on in <DATE>1965</DATE> to the two-man Gemini program, and 10
exciting flights in 20 months tested and proved all the rendezvous
and docking and space walking procedures needed to travel to the
moon.
   The Russians, too, were perfecting these techniques. But by early
<DATE>1967</DATE>, as the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was ready to move into manned Apollo
flights, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> seemed to have a slight lead, based on superior
computer and other technologies.
   Then, tragedy.
   In a countdown test on <DATE>Jan. 27, 1967</DATE>, a month before the planned
launch, faulty wiring released a spark that touched off an inferno
inside the Apollo 1 cabin. The flames, intensified by the 100
percent oxygen environment, incinerated the three-man crew, <PERSON>Gus
Grissom</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ed White</PERSON> and <PERSON>Roger Chaffee</PERSON>.
   Three months after the Apollo fire, cosmonaut <PERSON>Vladimir Komarov</PERSON>
rode into orbit in a new spacecraft named Soyuz, believed to be a
test model for a lunar command ship. After a day in orbit, as he
returned to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Soyuz 1 tumbled, became tangled in its parachute
straps and crashed. Komarov became the world's first in-flight space
casualty.
   In both countries, critics brought their guns to bear on both
space programs. Each was halted for nearly two years while repairs
were made.
   Apollo was reexamined, rewired, redesigned and finally flew.
Apollo 7 orbited the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> for 11 days in <DATE>October 1968</DATE>, and then, in
a bold move, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> officials decided to fly the three-man Apollo 8
crew into orbit about the moon on <DATE>Christmas Eve 1968</DATE>.
   They reasoned the flight would provide vital information about
navigating to and around the moon, buy time while the lagging lunar
landing module was readied, and rob the Soviets of any glory they
might reap by looping one man once around the backside of the moon
on a translunar trajectory; there was a widely reported rumor that
the Soviets were ready to do just that.
   The mission was a huge, uplifting success, and two more flights,
one in which two astronauts swooped to within 10 miles of the lunar
surface, set the stage for the main event, Apollo 11.
   More than 1 million people _ tourists, congressmen, diplomats,
business people, reporters and movie stars _ came to watch the
launch at the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>July 16, 1969</DATE>. All eyes stared
at the sheet of flame as the mighty <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> 5 rose ponderously from
Launch Pad 39A, precisely on schedule at <TIME>9:32 a.m.</TIME>, and sent a
thunderclap across the scrubland.
   In the spaceship on the tip of the rocket were <PERSON>Neil Alden
Armstrong</PERSON>, 38, a civilian, the commander; <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Edwin
Eugene Aldrin Jr.</PERSON>, 39, the lunar module pilot, and <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Lt.
Col. <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, 38, the command module pilot _ ambassadors
from planet <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> headed for a target 250,801 miles away.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890715-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-89 1306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpaceShuttle     07-15 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle,0585</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shuttle Columbia At Launch Pad 20 Years After Another Columbia Left
For Moon</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Space shuttle <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> moved to the
launch pad <DATE>Saturday</DATE> as workers got set to celebrate the <DATE>20th
anniversary</DATE> of the liftoff of another spaceship with the same name,
the one that carried the first men to the moon.
   The shuttle completed a seven-hour trip to launch pad 39B shortly
before <TIME>5 a.m.</TIME>, and engineers and technicians began readying it for
an early <DATE>August</DATE> flight with five astronauts who are to release a
secret military spy satellite. Meanwhile, others made preparations
for <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s commemoration of the flight of the first <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>.
   It was <DATE>July 16, 1969</DATE>, that an Apollo command module <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>
blasted away from the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION> here with astronauts <PERSON>Neil
Armstrong</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>. Four days
later, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and Aldrin climbed into the lunar landing vehicle
Eagle and descended to the moon.
   After an historic 22 hours on the surface, the moonwalkers
rejoined <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> in mother ship <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> for the three-day trip home.
<LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> for a ceremony there before coming here here to
join with thousands <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in remembering the launch of the Apollo
11 mission.
   Outside the giant shuttle assembly building, where Apollo's
Saturn 5 rockets once were put together, the former astronauts will
make brief remarks and listen to a tape recording of the final
minutes of their countdown.
   The ``taped liftoff'' will occur at <TIME>9:32 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, precisely
the time they left <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   As the shuttle <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> moved to the pad, shuttle launch director
<PERSON>Bob Sieck</PERSON> looked back at its namesake.
   ``Twenty years ago there was another spaceship, also called
<ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, and it was out at the pad,'' he said. ``It had an
important mission and an important payload. This parallels it.
Shuttle <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> also has an important mission and an important
payload.
   ``It also will prove we have three orbiters, and that is
significant,'' <PERSON>Sieck</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> will be making its first flight since the Challenger
explosion 3{ years ago. The other two shuttles, Discovery and
Atlantis, each have been launched twice since flights resumed <DATE>last
September</DATE>.
   After the ceremony here <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Collins</PERSON> will ride 20 miles in a motorcade to <LOCATION>Cocoa Beach</LOCATION>, where they
will be honored at a luncheon. On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the 20th anniversary of
the moon landing, the trio will join President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> for a ceremony
at the <ORGANIZATION>National Air and Space Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> earlier had set <DATE>July 31</DATE> as the date for launching shuttle
<ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>. But agency officials said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that preparations were
behind schedule and that a liftoff now is expected during the first
week in <DATE>August</DATE>. A firm launch date will be set <DATE>July 26</DATE> following a
two-day meeting called a flight readiness review.
   <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s all-military crew is to deploy a classified <ORGANIZATION>Defense
Department</ORGANIZATION> payload believed to be an advanced reconnaissance
satellite.
   While the counterparts from <DATE>1969</DATE> are being honored, the shuttle
astronauts will fly here <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, in preparation for
some practice sessions <DATE>Monday</DATE> and <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The crew is commanded by <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Brewster H. Shaw Jr</PERSON>. The
others are <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Cmdr. <PERSON>Richard N. Richards</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Cmdr. <PERSON>David C.
Leestma</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Lt. Col. <PERSON>James C. Adamson</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Maj. <PERSON>Mark
N. Brown</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890719-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-19-89 0030EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Apollo-20YearsAgo     07-19 0764</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Apollo-20 Years Ago,0787</SECOND>
<HEAD>What Happened 20 Years Ago During Moon Flight</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are day-to-day highlights of
events on the Apollo 11 moon flight <DATE>20 years ago this week</DATE>:
   
   <DATE>Saturday, July 19, 1969</DATE>:
   Apollo 11 raced into the shadow of the moon and the astronauts
reported a spectacular first sighting of their destination.
Armstrong described a brilliant solar corona as the moon eclipsed
all but the halo of gases surrounding the sun. ``It looks like an
eerie sight,'' he reported.
   The spaceship slipped behind the backside of the moon, and
<PERSON>Collins</PERSON> fired the main engine for 5 minutes, 57 seconds to slow
their speed from 5,465 mph to 3,726 mph, settling into an orbit
ranging from 70 to 196 miles above the surface. Later, they
triggered the engine again to achieve a more circular path with a
low point of 62 miles and high point of 75 miles.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are day-to-day highlights of
events on the Apollo 11 moon flight <DATE>20 years ago this week</DATE>:
   
   <DATE>Saturday, July 19, 1969</DATE>:
   Apollo 11 raced into the shadow of the moon and the astronauts
reported a spectacular first sighting of their destination.
Armstrong described a brilliant solar corona as the moon eclipsed
all but the halo of gases surrounding the sun. ``It looks like an
eerie sight,'' he reported.
   The spaceship slipped behind the backside of the moon, and
<PERSON>Collins</PERSON> fired the main engine for 5 minutes, 57 seconds to slow
their speed from 5,465 mph to 3,726 mph, settling into an orbit
ranging from 70 to 196 miles above the surface. Later, they
triggered the engine again to achieve a more circular path with a
low point of 62 miles and high point of 75 miles.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are day-to-day highlights of
events on the Apollo 11 moon flight <DATE>20 years ago this week</DATE>:
   
   <DATE>Saturday, July 19, 1969</DATE>:
   Apollo 11 raced into the shadow of the moon and the astronauts
reported a spectacular first sighting of their destination.
Armstrong described a brilliant solar corona as the moon eclipsed
all but the halo of gases surrounding the sun. ``It looks like an
eerie sight,'' he reported.
   The spaceship slipped behind the backside of the moon, and
<PERSON>Collins</PERSON> fired the main engine for 5 minutes, 57 seconds to slow
their speed from 5,465 mph to 3,726 mph, settling into an orbit
ranging from 70 to 196 miles above the surface. Later, they
triggered the engine again to achieve a more circular path with a
low point of 62 miles and high point of 75 miles.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are day-to-day highlights of
events on the Apollo 11 moon flight <DATE>20 years ago this week</DATE>:
   
   <DATE>Saturday, July 19, 1969</DATE>:
   Apollo 11 raced into the shadow of the moon and the astronauts
reported a spectacular first sighting of their destination.
Armstrong described a brilliant solar corona as the moon eclipsed
all but the halo of gases surrounding the sun. ``It looks like an
eerie sight,'' he reported.
   The spaceship slipped behind the backside of the moon, and
<PERSON>Collins</PERSON> fired the main engine for 5 minutes, 57 seconds to slow
their speed from 5,465 mph to 3,726 mph, settling into an orbit
ranging from 70 to 196 miles above the surface. Later, they
triggered the engine again to achieve a more circular path with a
low point of 62 miles and high point of 75 miles.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are day-to-day highlights of
events on the Apollo 11 moon flight <DATE>20 years ago this week</DATE>:
   
   <DATE>Saturday, July 19, 1969</DATE>:
   Apollo 11 raced into the shadow of the moon and the astronauts
reported a spectacular first sighting of their destination.
Armstrong described a brilliant solar corona as the moon eclipsed
all but the halo of gases surrounding the sun. ``It looks like an
eerie sight,'' he reported.
   The spaceship slipped behind the backside of the moon, and
<PERSON>Collins</PERSON> fired the main engine for 5 minutes, 57 seconds to slow
their speed from 5,465 mph to 3,726 mph, settling into an orbit
ranging from 70 to 196 miles above the surface. Later, they
triggered the engine again to achieve a more circular path with a
low point of 62 miles and high point of 75 miles.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are day-to-day highlights of
events on the Apollo 11 moon flight <DATE>20 years ago this week</DATE>:
   
   <DATE>Saturday, July 19, 1969</DATE>:
   Apollo 11 raced into the shadow of the moon and the astronauts
reported a spectacular first sighting of their destination.
Armstrong described a brilliant solar corona as the moon eclipsed
all but the halo of gases surrounding the sun. ``It looks like an
eerie sight,'' he reported.
   The spaceship slipped behind the backside of the moon, and
<PERSON>Collins</PERSON> fired the main engine for 5 minutes, 57 seconds to slow
their speed from 5,465 mph to 3,726 mph, settling into an orbit
ranging from 70 to 196 miles above the surface. Later, they
triggered the engine again to achieve a more circular path with a
low point of 62 miles and high point of 75 miles.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890609-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-09-89 1544EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-ParisAirShow     06-09 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Paris Air Show,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Neil Armstrong Disappointed No Man Has Walked on Mars</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty years after <PERSON>Neil A. Armstrong</PERSON> made his
``giant leap for mankind'' on the moon, he and his fellow Apollo 11
astronauts said <DATE>Friday</DATE> they are disappointed man has not taken even
one small step on Mars.
   ``I thought the moon would lead immediately and logically to
Mars,'' said <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, the astronaut who remained in the
spacecraft <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> circling the moon while <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON>
``Buzz'' <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> set down on the <ORGANIZATION>Sea of Tranquility</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>July 20, 1969</DATE>.
   Millions of television viewers watched the heady culmination of a
bold challenge issued in <DATE>1961</DATE> by President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> to land
an American on the moon by the end of the decade.
   Speaking to a jammed news conference at the <ORGANIZATION>Paris Air Show</ORGANIZATION>, the
three gray-haired astronauts used the anniversary to renew the
challenge for Americans to expand the human presence in the solar
system.
   Also on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, Soviet pilot <PERSON>Anatoly Kvochur</PERSON> was discharged from
the hospital after being treated for injuries he suffered on
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> when he ejected from his MiG-29 fighter seconds before it
exploded at the air show.
   No one else was injured when the jet stalled during a performance
before reporters and exhibitors, and crashed in the center of the
field at Le Bourget airport. The cause was being investigated.
   At the news conference, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> said it was competition from the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> in the early <DATE>1960s</DATE> that spawned the leap into space,
and that no similar urgency exists today.
   Armstrong, who commanded the Apollo 11 mission, said: ``We all
started much before <DATE>1969</DATE> and at the time, most people did not
believe there would ever be people in space in our lifetime. In that
sense I'm very encouraged that we did more than most people,
including myself, would have guessed 30 years ago.''
   ``Having said that and knowing now that we were able to break the
chains of gravity, those of us who are involved are always
disappointed that we are not doing more and doing more faster.''
   Collins added: ``I think of the moon not so much as a place these
days than as of a direction, a direction out there, a small way
station on the way to Mars or the outer planets beyond our solar
system.''
   In an interview earlier, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> planners only recently
considered seriously a proposal he made in <DATE>1985</DATE> for a ``cycling
spaceship.''
   Two spaceships would orbit the sun in a two-year cycle, passing
Mars on the outbound leg and then circling back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The spaceships could serve as permanent transport to and from
Mars with ``stripped-down space ferries shuttling men and materials
back and forth to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>, whose book ``Men From
Earth'' was published in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <DATE>last month</DATE>.
   ``I hope the spaceships will become an increasingly pursued means
of getting to Mars,'' said <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>, who lives in <LOCATION>Laguna Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   ``I expect we'll be back on the moon by <DATE>2005</DATE> and then by <DATE>2010</DATE> we
should be sending people to Mars,'' he said.
   The three astronauts said they did not expect to set foot on
Mars, but that the moon still holds allure.
   ``I look forward to the day when there is commercial service and
I have a chance to go back,'' <PERSON>Armstrong</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890720-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-20-89 1252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpaceMilestones 1stLd-Writethru a0629 07-20 0548</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Milestones, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0629,0565</SECOND>
<HEAD>Highlights of Manned Space Travel</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 22nd graf to CORRECT length of Challenger flight to 73
seconds sted 72; SUBS last graf to CLARIFY that year-long flight was on
space station.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush-Space, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some notable dates in the history of manned space flight:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some notable dates in the history of manned space flight:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890721-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-21-89 0436EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     07-21 0646</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0676</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<HEAD>Astronauts Put Moon, Va., On The Map</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOON, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The city that <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz''
<PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> put on the map 20 years ago planned no official festivities
to mark the 20th anniversary of the astronauts' moon walk.
   Residents there are still trying to explain where they live.
   Before the moon walk, <PERSON>Moon</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, was little more than a post
office and a bump in the road in <LOCATION>Mathews County</LOCATION> near the <LOCATION>Chesapeake
Bay</LOCATION>.
   You couldn't even find Moon on a <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> road map.
   Today, the community of about 100 families isn't much bigger,
but at least it's on the map. The attention <PERSON>Moon</PERSON> attracted in <DATE>1969</DATE>
when the Eagle landed on its celestial cousin apparently encouraged
the <ORGANIZATION>Virginia Department of Transportation</ORGANIZATION> to put it on the official
state map.
   Sometimes, even maps don't help.
   <PERSON>Pat Chalkley</PERSON>, a former <LOCATION>Mechanicsville</LOCATION> resident and relative
newcomer to <PERSON>Moon</PERSON>, said she sent her new address to a friend, who
replied with a note: ``Where in the hell is Moon?''
   Almost heaven, to hear <PERSON>Mrs. Chalkley</PERSON> and others describe their
community.
   ``I've heard people say that once you've seen a full moon over
the <LOCATION>Chesapeake Bay</LOCATION>, you never want to leave,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Chalkley</PERSON>,
whose husband, <PERSON>Blanton</PERSON>, commutes 90 minutes to <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> to work.
``I was sitting there the other night, looked up and saw this
absolutely gorgeous big ol' orange moon.''
 
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MOONVILLE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The city that <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz''
<PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> put on the map 20 years ago planned no official festivities
to mark the 20th anniversary of the astronauts' moon walk.
   Residents there are still trying to explain where they live.
   Before the moon walk, <PERSON>Moon</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, was little more than a post
office and a bump in the road in <LOCATION>Mathews County</LOCATION> near the <LOCATION>Chesapeake
Bay</LOCATION>.
   You couldn't even find Moon on a <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> road map.
   Today, the community of about 100 families isn't much bigger,
but at least it's on the map. The attention <PERSON>Moon</PERSON> attracted in <DATE>1969</DATE>
when the Eagle landed on its celestial cousin apparently encouraged
the <ORGANIZATION>Virginia Department of Transportation</ORGANIZATION> to put it on the official
state map.
   Sometimes, even maps don't help.
   <PERSON>Pat Chalkley</PERSON>, a former <LOCATION>Mechanicsville</LOCATION> resident and relative
newcomer to <PERSON>Moon</PERSON>, said she sent her new address to a friend, who
replied with a note: ``Where in the hell is Moon?''
   Almost heaven, to hear <PERSON>Mrs. Chalkley</PERSON> and others describe their
community.
   ``I've heard people say that once you've seen a full moon over
the <LOCATION>Chesapeake Bay</LOCATION>, you never want to leave,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Chalkley</PERSON>,
whose husband, <PERSON>Blanton</PERSON>, commutes 90 minutes to <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> to work.
``I was sitting there the other night, looked up and saw this
absolutely gorgeous big ol' orange moon.''
 
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The city that <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz''
<PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON> put on the map 20 years ago planned no official festivities
to mark the 20th anniversary of the astronauts' moon walk.
   Residents there are still trying to explain where they live.
   Before the moon walk, <PERSON>Moon</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, was little more than a post
office and a bump in the road in <LOCATION>Mathews County</LOCATION> near the <LOCATION>Chesapeake
Bay</LOCATION>.
   You couldn't even find Moon on a <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> road map.
   Today, the community of about 100 families isn't much bigger,
but at least it's on the map. The attention <PERSON>Moon</PERSON> attracted in <DATE>1969</DATE>
when the Eagle landed on its celestial cousin apparently encouraged
the <ORGANIZATION>Virginia Department of Transportation</ORGANIZATION> to put it on the official
state map.
   Sometimes, even maps don't help.
   <PERSON>Pat Chalkley</PERSON>, a former <LOCATION>Mechanicsville</LOCATION> resident and relative
newcomer to <PERSON>Moon</PERSON>, said she sent her new address to a friend, who
replied with a note: ``Where in the hell is Moon?''
   Almost heaven, to hear <PERSON>Mrs. Chalkley</PERSON> and others describe their
community.
   ``I've heard people say that once you've seen a full moon over
