<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901129-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-29-90 0953EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DinosaurFind     11-29 0455</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dinosaur Find,0535</SECOND>
<HEAD>University Team Discovers `Whale Dinosaur' And Late-Surviving
Brontosaurus</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DX8</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOULDER, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An expedition has discovered remains of a
gigantic ``whale dinosaur'' and a brontosaurus that lived more
recently than other known dinosaurs of its type, scientists
announced.
   <ORGANIZATION>University of Colorado Paleontologist Robert Bakker</ORGANIZATION> said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that the two finds in the fertile dinosaur fields of
southern <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> are providing important clues about dinosaur
extinction.
   <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said the remains of a 70-foot-long Haplocanthosaurus, a
member of the cetiosaur or ``whale dinosaur'' family, were found in
the Como Bluffs area near <PERSON>McFadden</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, last <DATE>July</DATE>.
   The team also is excavating a brontosaurus that is the only one
of its kind known to have survived the Cretaceous Period that began
about 135 million years ago. The excavation is under way near <LOCATION>Rock
River</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, in a fossil deposit known as the <ORGANIZATION>Breakfast Bench</ORGANIZATION>. Rock
River is just a few miles north of <ORGANIZATION>Como Bluff</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said that before this discovery, no brontosaurus had ever
been unearthed that was less than about 137 million years old.
   ``This means the <ORGANIZATION>Golden Book of Dinosaurs</ORGANIZATION> will need a slight
footnote, since this particular animal apparently managed to slide
just under the tag into the Cretaceous,'' he said.
   The brontosaurus bones were found last <DATE>May</DATE> by <PERSON>Don Kralis</PERSON>, a high
school science teacher from <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> who has been assisting <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>
with his <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> fieldwork.
   ``Finding this brontosaurus was a big surprise,'' <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
``Our initial reaction was that the animal was stuck in the wrong
time zone.''
   The whale dinosaur or cetiosaur, dubbed the ``<PERSON>Carlin Giant</PERSON>,''
was found by <PERSON>James Filla</PERSON>, an expedition volunteer and physicist at
find included a shoulder, thigh, tailbone, hand, forearm, shin and
several vertebrae from both the <ORGANIZATION>Carlin Giant</ORGANIZATION> and another small
specimen.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Carlin Giant</ORGANIZATION> is the largest member of cetiosaur family ever
unearthed, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
   ``It's not surprising that this particular animal was so big
because it appears to be the last in its line,'' <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. ``As
a rule, the large dinosaurs tended to get larger before they went
extinct, and we seem to have caught the last gasp of the
cetiosaur.''
   Cetiosaurs, large plant-eaters that were common during the late
<ORGANIZATION>Jurassic Period</ORGANIZATION> about 150 million years ago, apparently were the
victim of a worldwide catastrophe that struck about that time, said
<PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>.
   ``One after another, the giant dinosaur families died out, and
the cetiosaurs were the first to go,'' <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. ``As far as we
know, this was the first major extinction of a large dinosaur
family during the late Jurassic.''
   He said his paleontology team's work at <ORGANIZATION>Como Bluff</ORGANIZATION> has
determined the cetiosaurs were the first dinosaur family to die off
in a one-by-one, ``stepwise'' extinction sequence. It spanned a
period beginning 150 million years ago and ending 66 million years
ago.
   ``Stepwise patterns just don't agree with the popular theory
that a cataclysmic disaster suddenly wiped out the dinosaurs,''
<PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. ``The fossil record clearly indicates that these mass
extinctions were not the result of one <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> of cosmic
mayhem.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891010-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-10-89 1444EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-DinosaurName     10-10 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dinosaur Name,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Provoked Paleontologists Pursue Postal Precision</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's paleontologists, who know a
dinosaur when they see one, are upset over the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Postal
Service</ORGANIZATION>'s latest block of dinosaur stamps.
   One of the stamps uses an out-of-date name and another actually
shows a flying reptile, complain the scientists who study ancient
forms of life.
   In its own defense the <ORGANIZATION>Postal Service</ORGANIZATION> produced a letter from a
<LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> seven-year-old to whom the identity of the animals was
perfectly clear.
   And as for calling the set ``dinosaur'' stamps, officials say
that term is simply the easiest for people to understand.
   The stamps were selected in an effort to join in the current
interest in dinosaurs among young people, and they are being
featured as part of the <ORGANIZATION>Postal Service</ORGANIZATION>'s annual ``Stamp Collecting
Month'' promotion.
   The four 25-cent stamps include a tyrannosaurus, a large fierce
reptile, and a stegosaurus, or plated lizard, with a row of large
plates on its back. Neither of those raised any complaints from the
paleontologists.
   But the other two show a brontosaurus, a large-bodied lizard
with long neck and tiny head, and a pteranodon, a flying reptile,
   That means that one of the stamps, the pteranodon, doesn't
picture a dinosaur at all, complained the paleontologists.
   And the brontosaurus actually is an apatosaurus, they said.
   While promoting the dinosaur stamps in their advertising, postal
officials admit that the pteranodon isn't technically a dinosaur.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Postal Service</ORGANIZATION>'s book ``Introduction to Stamp Collecting,''
which is being used in the stamp promotion, refers to the stamps as
the ``prehistoric animals series'' and notes that the group of
stamps portrays ``three dinosaurs and a pteranodon, a winged
creature that ruled the skies while dinosaurs ruled the land.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Paleontological Society</ORGANIZATION> is more upset about the brontosaurus
stamp, however, having gone so far as to issue a statement
detailing the correct name for the animal.
   The brontosaurus never existed, having actually been the result
of a <DATE>19th century</DATE> researcher mixing up the skull of one prehistoric
animal with the body bones of another, the paleontologists say. The
body skeleton had already been named apatosaurus, the scientists
noted.
   In the past 15 years or so museums have corrected the problem,
joined the correct skulls with the skeletons of the animals, and
changed the designation to apatosaurus.
   By scientific convention, the paleontologists state, ``when more
than one name is given to a species only the oldest name is
scientifically valid. As a consequence, use of the name
brontosaurus must be discontinued.''
   In its defense, the <ORGANIZATION>Postal Service</ORGANIZATION> noted that its booklet on
stamps uses both names, and the agency produced a letter from
7-year-old <PERSON>Brandon Dennis</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Laurel</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, who had read about the
controversy in a <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> newspaper.
   ``I like the name brontosaurus because it means thunder lizard,
not deceptive lizard like apatosaurus,'' wrote <PERSON>Brandon</PERSON>.
   After citing a several books using the term brontosaurus, he
concluded that ``it's all right to use brontosaurus because most
kids, including my sister, know that brontosaurus and apatosaurus
are the same creature.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901129-0148 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-29-90 1838EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DinosaurFind     11-29 0462</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dinosaur Find,0535</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dinosaur Remains Stir More Debate Over Cause of Dinosaur
Extinction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PEGGY LOWE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The discovery of two giant dinosaurs in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> is
reigniting debate over why the huge beasts became extinct.
   <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> paleontologist <PERSON>Robert Bakker</PERSON>, who led the team that
found the dinosaur remains, said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the discoveries reinforce
his theory that dinosaurs became extinct gradually.
   A scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian</ORGANIZATION> Institution who supports the
theory that dinosaurs met their end suddenly, in a cosmic
collision, says the latest finds prove nothing of the sort.
   The extinction of dinosaurs is ``a big area of controversy right
now in science,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Richard Stucky</PERSON>, paleontologist at the
<ORGANIZATION>Denver Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION>.
   Scientists offer dozens of theories about the mysterious mass
extinctions, including a change in the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s motion, famine,
parasites, poisons, climatic changes, meteorites and even
extraterrestrial hunters.
   The debate is on again since <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>'s team of <ORGANIZATION>University of
Colorado</ORGANIZATION> scientists unearthed a 70-foot-long, 25-foot-high
Haplocanthosaurus. A member of the cetiosaur or ``whale dinosaur''
family. The ``Carlin Giant'' found near <PERSON>McFadden</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, was the
largest cetiosaur ever located, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
   The second find is the only brontosaurus scientists have placed
in the <LOCATION>Cretaceous Period</LOCATION>, which began 135 million years ago.
   Before that discovery, near <LOCATION>Rock River</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, in a fossil
deposit known as <ORGANIZATION>Breakfast Bench</ORGANIZATION>, no brontosaur had been found that
was less than 137 million years old.
   Bakker announced the discoveries <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. The remains were
found last <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   ``The fossil record clearly indicates that these mass
extinctions were not the result of a <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> of cosmic
mayhem,'' <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. ``The last remains of different (dinosaur)
families are strewn through millions of years of rock,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Nicholaus Hotton</PERSON>, a curator of paleobiology at the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian
Institution</ORGANIZATION>, disagrees. He still subscribes to a collision theory,
which he said is evidenced by iridium-rich sediments in the
deposits marking the end of the <ORGANIZATION>Cretaceous Period</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Iridium</ORGANIZATION> is a
heavy metal found in platinum ores.
   ``The crustal rocks in the top kilometers of the earth are very
poor in iridium, but meteors and things are very rich in iridium.
So why do you find that in that zone?'' <PERSON>Hotton</PERSON> said.
   ``The argument is that they were brought in from the outside ...
an asteroid, comet, or one hell of a big meteorite that struck the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. And in doing so it disrupted the ecology,'' he said.
   Bakker believes extensive migration and subsequent disease
epidemics may have wiped out dinosaurs. He said <PERSON>Hotton</PERSON> is missing
the ``frog facts.''
   ``If a comet or asteroid hit the earth and killed all the
dinosaurs, how then were the deaths so selective?'' he asked. ``The
fact (is) that the little delicate animals - like frogs - survived
and the large aggressive animals didn't.''
   According to <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>, dinosaurs became extinct because of
worldwide diseases.
   ``Dinosaurs didn't go out with a bang, they went out with
worldwide diarrhea,'' he said.
   The cetiosaur bones eventually will be displayed at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Wyoming</ORGANIZATION> and at <ORGANIZATION>North Carolina State University</ORGANIZATION>, which
assisted the fieldwork. The brontosaurus is still being unearthed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900503-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-03-90 0250EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DinosaurExtinction     05-03 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dinosaur Extinction,0615</SECOND>
<HEAD>Paleontologist Searching For `Serial Killer' of Dinosaurs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PEGGY LOWE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOULDER, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Small land animals _ including the
ferocious 6-ounce ``Mutant Ninja Chipmunk'' _ thrived while an
environmental crisis killed off most giant dinosaurs more than 100
million years ago, a researcher found.
   Dr. <PERSON>Robert Bakker</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Colorado</ORGANIZATION> paleontologist, said
fossils recently unearthed from a 130-million-year-old deposit in a
rock quarry in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> showed small dinosaurs, mammals, turtles and
other animals flourished in the early Cretaceous period a few
million years after the giant dinosaurs that lived in the <LOCATION>Jurassic</LOCATION>
period became extinct.
   ``The new fossils are the remains of animals that lived in a
crisis interval during the early Cretaceous Period, and this is the
first rock layer that seems to record just what happened and why,''
<PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   His preliminary findings were published <DATE>April 15</DATE> in the
proceedings of the <ORGANIZATION>Fourth North American Paleontological Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   With several colleagues, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>, who first identified the fossil
beds in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, unearthed a wide array of ``fossil miniatures''
from the 10- to 12-foot thick deposit known as ``Breakfast Bench''
near the town of Rock River.
   The specimens date to the earliest part of the Cretaceous
period, a transitional period following the demise of long-necked,
giant dinosaurs such as brontosaurus, supersaurus and diplodocus.
   <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said the deposit provides evidence of a classic case of
``<PERSON>David</PERSON> and Goliath'' _ a variety of diminutive creatures
overshadowed the great dinosaurs for a time.
   After the dinosaurs evolved into a new line of giants, again
eclipsing small animals, the same scenario apparently was played
out about 65 million years later at the end of the Cretaceous
period, when another catastrophe of some kind killed off all
dinosaurs.
   New species unearthed at the site include a 20-pound herbivorous
dinosaur, a pair of fierce rodent-like mammals weighing less than a
pound each and a neurologically sophisticated turtle, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
Numerous crocodilian remains also were found, he said.
   The sudden appearance of Zofiabaatar, a 6-ounce furry meat-eater
that <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> nicknamed the ``Mutant Ninja Chipmunk,'' illustrates
small mammals were taking evolutionary advantage of the swampy
environment during the crisis, he said.
   Scientists have long been puzzled by the mass extinctions at the
end of the Jurassic period, and theories focus on such factors as
movements of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, starvation, parasites, poisons, changes in
climate and meteorites.
   But according to <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>, dinosaurs became extinct because of
worldwide diseases that turned into an ``epidemiological
nightmare.''
   ``Dinosaurs didn't go out with a bang, they went out with
worldwide diarrhea,'' he said.
   Big animals travel and are extremely vulnerable to disease,
<PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. As land bridges formed throughout the globe, the
animals spread hundreds of diseases throughout all continents _
eventually killing the lot.
   ``If you're a species one of the most dangerous things you can
do is to invade a continent or have a foreign species move in,'' he
said. ``So the stay-at-homes have an automatic immunity to this
tourist trap of exotic disease.''
   The newly identified creatures apparently thrived in the swampy,
fern-choked environment that marked the end of the Jurassic and the
beginning of the Cretaceous periods, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
   Since fern-choked swamps also were present at the end of the
Cretaceous and during times of other mass die-offs, they may help
explain why dinosaurs and other large land animals suffered
repeated extinctions.
   ``Scientists studying mass extinction are like criminologists
tracking a serial killer _ the clues that finally catch the killer
usually come from the repeated pattern in the way the crimes were
committed,'' <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA050390-0172 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 213502 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 3, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
<P>
Correction Appended 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 4; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1103 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FOSSILS OF NEW SPECIES ADD TO MYSTERY OF DEMISE OF DINOSAURS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By THOMAS H. MAUGH II, TIMES SCIENCE WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Fossils of at least four new species of animals discovered in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> cast 
doubt on the theory that comets colliding with the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> killed off some 
dinosaurs 130 million years ago and all dinosaurs 65 million years later, a 
<LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> paleontologist said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The new species include a 20-pound herbivorous dinosaur, a bizarre mammal that 
the researchers have nicknamed a "mutant ninja chipmunk" and a "high-tech" 
turtle. They flourished after the large dinosaurs that preceded them were 
exterminated 130 million years ago by an unknown environmental catastrophe, 
said <PERSON>Robert Bakker</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Colorado</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Many researchers believe that cometary collisions produced highly acidic 
rainfall and cold temperatures that led to the dinosaurs' decline. But 
discoveries at the new site cast doubt on that proposal because other reptiles 
and fish, which should have been affected by the cold and acid, proliferated 
while the dinosaurs died out. 
</P>
<P>
"The mechanism (of extinction) obviously needs to be rethought," said <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>, 
who is considered by many paleontologists to be a maverick in the profession. 
</P>
<P>
It is not widely appreciated that dinosaurs went through two distinct periods 
of dominance. During the late <ORGANIZATION>Jurassic Period</ORGANIZATION>, which extended up to 130 million 
years ago, the largest dinosaurs were well-known varieties such as the 
long-necked brontosaurus, the spike-backed stegosaurus and the fierce, 
carnivorous allosaurus. 
</P>
<P>
These species died off at the end of the <LOCATION>Jurassic</LOCATION>, to be replaced by small 
dinosaurs that evolved into the iguana-like iguanodons, the dome-headed 
dinosaurs and the largest land-based predator ever to exist, Tyrannosaurus rex 
-- all of which were wiped out at the end of the Cretaceous period 65 million 
years ago. 
</P>
<P>
"This dramatic change in the evolutionary cast of characters (between the 
<LOCATION>Jurassic</LOCATION> and Cretaceous) is one of the most profound crises in dinosaur 
development," <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. "The new fossils are the remains of animals that 
lived in a crisis interval during the early Cretaceous period, and this is the 
first rock layer (containing the fossils) that seems to record just what 
happened and why." 
</P>
<P>
That rock layer, known as the <ORGANIZATION>Breakfast Bench</ORGANIZATION>, lies in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Albany County</LOCATION>, 
near the town of <LOCATION>Rock River</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> has been studying the site since <DATE>1974</DATE>, but 
the bones obtained there, he said, "are so small that I misidentified them at 
first." It was only when he and his colleagues found an almost complete 
skeleton of a 20-pound dinosaur now called Drinker nisti "that I realized what 
we had been getting and the new species kind of jelled." 
</P>
<P>
The fossil bed indicates that the region was swampy and fern-choked at the end 
of the <LOCATION>Jurassic</LOCATION>. Similar conditions prevailed at the end of the Cretaceous and 
at the end of the Permian period 250 million years ago, when another extinction 
occurred before dinosaurs existed. Swamps have also been associated with other, 
smaller extinctions, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"It looks like we have a 'serial killer' here that has something to do with 
swamps," he said. "We're not ready for convictions yet, but we certainly have 
enough evidence for an indictment." He speculates that the dinosaurs were 
killed by disease as they moved into new environments in response to climate 
change. 
</P>
<P>
But, noted geologist <PERSON>Walter Alvarez</PERSON> of UC <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, there is "overwhelming 
evidence" that a cometary impact did occur at the end of the Cretaceous period. 
"We may never know precisely what the killing mechanisms were, but it would 
require a breathtaking coincidence to say that a gigantic impact had nothing to 
do with a gigantic extinction," said <PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON>, a long-time proponent of the 
impact theory of extinction. 
</P>
<P>
Natural History</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> called <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>'s claim about a serial killer 
"wild," but noted that <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> "does have a very interesting new dinosaur and 
little animals there." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> has been criticized in the past for making strong claims in the media 
and for not publishing his results in refereed journals. The current findings 
were published recently in the Proceedings of the <ORGANIZATION>Fourth North American 
Paleontological Congress</ORGANIZATION>, a non-refereed journal. The fact that a paper is 
unrefereed means that other scientists have not subjected it to critical 
review. 
</P>
<P>
The fossil strata also show that while large land animals died off, smaller 
aquatic species and reptiles did not. "If a meteorite hit, it would cause a 
sudden chill and acid rain that would kill off turtles and frogs right away," 
<PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. "But the frogs didn't disappear. Neither did the turtles. In fact, 
the whole aquatic ecosystem bloomed and did fine. That's a very powerful clue 
about what happened." Bakker is not sure, however, what caused the swamps to 
form. 
</P>
<P>
The most common dinosaur to be found at <ORGANIZATION>Breakfast Bench</ORGANIZATION> was the new D. nisti, 
he said. It was equipped with the most complicated leaf-cutting teeth ever to 
evolve among dinosaurs. The animal's large, spreadable hind feet were adapted 
to walking on soggy ground. 
</P>
<P>
Baby D. nisti specimens, with body and leg bones as small as pigeons', are 
among the smallest dinosaurs ever found, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. "You can put a pile of 
their bones on a dime." 
</P>
<P>
Zofiabaatar, a ferocious eight-ounce mammal, has been nicknamed the "mutant 
ninja chipmunk" by <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>. The animal apparently killed lizards and other small 
prey with its mouse-like front teeth, then sliced up the bodies with its long, 
saw-edged rear teeth. 
</P>
<P>
It was a member of a group of mammals known as multituberculates -- primarily 
insect eaters and herbivores that have no relatives living today. "The mutant 
ninja chipmunk apparently made an evolutionary hard right turn" to become a 
carnivore, he said. 
</P>
<P>
Foxraptor was a furry, even smaller animal with a bulldog snout designed for 
attacking large bugs and small vertebrates. The fourth new species, <PERSON>Uluops</PERSON>, was 
a "high-tech" turtle boasting a skull architecture far more advanced that its 
contemporary cousins. 
</P>
<P>
The largest common animal in the Breakfast Bench strata was the "giant 
crushing-tooth lungfish," a half-ton predator with huge, flat teeth shaped like 
mittens for cracking hard-shelled prey. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
NEW SPECIES FOUND 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> paleontologist <PERSON>Robert Bakker</PERSON> has discovered four new species that date 
from 130 million years ago. Two -- the Foxraptor and the Zofiabaatar -- are 
small but ferocious mammals. One -- the Uluops -- is a neurologically 
sophisticated turtle. The fourth -- the Drinker -- is a 20-pound plant-eating 
dinosaur. 
</P>
<P>
Illustrations: <ORGANIZATION>University of Colorado</ORGANIZATION> 
</P></TEXT>
<CORRECTION-DATE>
<P>
May 8, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</CORRECTION-DATE>
<CORRECTION>
<P>
FOR THE RECORD 
</P>
<P>
Dinosaur fossils -- In a May 3 article about the discovery of new dinosaur 
fossils, it was incorrectly stated that the Proceedings of the Fourth North 
American Paleontological Conference were not subject to peer review. They are. 
</P>
</CORRECTION>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, Dinosaur fossils found, Los Angeles Times ; Drawing, Foxraptor ; Drawing, 
Zofiabaatar ; Drawing, Uluops ; Drawing, Drinker 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
DINOSAURS; MAMMALS; FOSSILS; PALEONTOLOGY; EVOLUTION; EXTINCTION; COMETS; 
RESEARCH; MYSTERIES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880811-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-11-88 0716EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-DinosaurGrave     08-11 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dinosaur Grave,0526</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Find Mass Grave of Baby Dinosaurs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists from <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> said <DATE>today</DATE> that
they unearthed a mass grave of sheep-sized baby dinosaurs who were
apparently buried during a sandstorm 75 million years ago.
   Dr. <PERSON>Philip Currie</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>Tyrrell Museum of Paleontology</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Alberta</LOCATION>, said the joint team excavated the skulls of five baby
Pinacosaurus in the wastelands of southern Inner <LOCATION>Mongolia</LOCATION>.
   He said they found a sixth baby on the last day of their <DATE>summer</DATE>
expedition, ``and it appears likely there are a number of other
specimens.''
   One adult, which in life was ``about the size of an extremely
heavy bull,'' was also discovered nearby, he said.
   ``We feel that the five babies were congregating together behind
a sand dune in a sandstorm,'' <PERSON>Currie</PERSON> said. Either they were buried
by sand or killed by the collapsing dune, he said.
   <PERSON>Currie</PERSON> said it was first time the plant-eating reptile had been
found to be ``gregarious,'' or living and moving in groups.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Canada-China Dinosaur Project</ORGANIZATION>, working together for the
second straight <DATE>summer</DATE> in the fertile and largely untouched
dinosaur fields of Inner <LOCATION>Mongolia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Xinjiang</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s far west,
found the remains of about 50 other dinosaurs and their nests, and
40 other mammals, turtles and lizards.
   The <PERSON>Bayan Manduhau</PERSON> area of southern Inner <LOCATION>Mongolia</LOCATION> where the
babies were dug up was first explored by American and Swedish
paleontologists in <DATE>1928</DATE> and <DATE>1931</DATE>. This year's find was in a spot
that was inaccessible at that time because of lack of roads.
   Hou Lianhai of the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese Academy of Science's Institute of
<LOCATION>Xinjiang</LOCATION> had excavated a meat-eating theropod but needed another
year to dig up a brontosaurus-like sauropod.
   Both beasts were discovered in <LOCATION>Xinjiang</LOCATION> during the first
expedition last year. The sauropod, about 160 million years old and
estimated to have been 100 feet long, is one of the largest of its
kind to have been found in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hou</PERSON> said.
   At a news conference, <PERSON>Currie</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Hou</ORGANIZATION> also revealed one nearly
intact oblong-shaped egg, about eight inches long, and several
broken egg shells of the Protoceratops, a pig-sized horned dinosaur.
   <PERSON>Currie</PERSON> said the year's finds will help understand the histories
of dinosaurs in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>. He said the fossils
discovered in <LOCATION>Inner Mongolia</LOCATION> were the same age as those found in
<LOCATION>Alberta</LOCATION>, another great repository of dinosaurs, and that many of
the same kinds of reptiles were turning up.
   He said it was still not clear whether the dinosaurs migrated
from either the dry, dune-coursed Asian deserts or the wetter lands
of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, or whether they may have developed independently.
   The dinosaur project is to return to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> again next year and
in the future may carry out further research in either <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> or
northern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. Noble said there are also plans to stage a world
tour of dinosaur fossils from around <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   The project is coordinated by the <ORGANIZATION>Ex-Terra Foundation</ORGANIZATION> and
supported by the Canadian government.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880906-0200 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-06-88 1220EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--BasementDiscoveries Adv08   09-06 0669</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Basement Discoveries, Adv 08,0685</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv08</NOTE>
<HEAD>For use Thursday, Sept. 8, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Museum Basements, Warehouses Treasure Troves Of Discovery</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOE McDONALD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 70-foot dinosaur known as ``Happy'' stood
prominently on display at the <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION>
for nearly 25 years before researchers discovered it was a new
species.
   Four months before it announced that finding in <DATE>July</DATE>, the museum
said it had discovered a new dinosaur, Nanotyrannus _ based on a
skull that had been in the basement for decades.
   This <DATE>spring</DATE>, a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> researcher found the fossil remains of
a marine reptile called a Masasaur, so well-preserved that the 75
million-year-old animal still had scales on its skin and food in
its stomach. It was in a <ORGANIZATION>Natural History Museum of Los Angeles
County</ORGANIZATION> warehouse.
   Paleontologists say the finds aren't surprising. Museum
storerooms have become rich hunting grounds for new species because
a lack of money and staff has delayed the identification of bones
excavated up to 60 years ago.
   ``In general, paleontologists can collect stuff faster than it
can be prepared,'' said <PERSON>Michael E. Williams</PERSON>, who helped identify
``Happy,'' a 140-million-year-old relative of the Brontosaurus.
``There are museums ... which have skeletons still in plaster
jackets going back to the turn of the century.''
   Researchers at the <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> museum had determined that
``Happy'' was a Haplocanthosaurus, but didn't realize it
represented a new and larger species _ and named it ``delfsi''
after the researcher who found the bones 30 years ago _ until they
recently had time to study it more closely.
   ``Literally there is so much material to collect and save from
weathering and erosion that we are just decades behind,'' said
<PERSON>Lawrence G. Barnes</PERSON>, curator of vertebrate paleontology at the
<ORGANIZATION>Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County</ORGANIZATION>. ``I could walk in to
the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian</ORGANIZATION> or any museum and find 80 or 90 new species of
whales or dolphins, which is my specialty.''
   Barnes estimated that the museum had 300 to 400 plaster jackets
in storage, encasing everything from dinosaurs to mammoths, and
that <PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> of the museum's collection has not been examined
closely.
   Even at the well-funded <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution</ORGANIZATION>, it took half a
century to study and identify fossils excavated by <DATE>19th century</DATE>
dinosaur researcher <PERSON>O.C. Marsh</PERSON> that form the bulk of the museum's
collection, according to research curator <PERSON>Nicholas Hotton</PERSON>.
   ``When <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON> died, we got seven big, big train carloads of
dinosaur bones,'' <PERSON>Hotton</PERSON> said. Researcher <PERSON>C.W. Gilmor</PERSON> worked on
<PERSON>Marsh</PERSON>'s fossils for nearly 50 years, and ``there is a bunch of
stuff <PERSON>Gilmor</PERSON> didn't get to.''
   Fossils stored at the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian</ORGANIZATION> have almost all been
identified, he said. ``We don't anticipate any surprises, but
that's silly because we can always get surprised.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Field Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION> researchers in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> have
spent 10 years working through the collection of unstudied fossils,
some of them in storage for decades, said <PERSON>John Bolt</PERSON>, chairman of
the geology department.
   ``We've made quite a bit of progress at reducing that backlog,''
<PERSON>Bolt</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Mary Dawson</PERSON>, curator of the <ORGANIZATION>Carnegie Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, said some of the fossils still stored in plaster
jackets at the museum date to <DATE>1922</DATE>. With only five paleontologists
on the staff, many of those blocks will have to remain in storage.
   Four years ago, a <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> grant let <ORGANIZATION>Carnegie</ORGANIZATION>
researchers open an old plaster block. They found the only known
complete hind foot of a stegosaurus.
   ``We liken our collection to an iceberg, with one-tenth above
the surface and the rest waiting for study,'' <PERSON>Miss Dawson</PERSON> said.
   Most of the work done at the museum is based on specimens the
researchers collect themselves, so much of the collection in
storage will remain unstudied, she said. ``We know we should stay
home and study the collections we already have, but it's such a
challenge to get out in the field.
   ``We're really putting apples back on the tree when we do this.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sept. 8</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880920-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-20-88 0953EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Obit-Bell     09-20 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Bell,0298</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Who Put Up Famed Roadside Dinosaurs Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANAHEIM, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Claude K. Bell</PERSON>, whose dinosaur creations
became a landmark to millions of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> desert
travelers, has died at 91, but his family vowed that his fanciful
``dinosaur garden'' would live on.
   Bell died <DATE>Monday</DATE> of pneumonia at <ORGANIZATION>Humana Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION>.
   Bell and his dinosaurs have been featured in People magazine,
the film ``Pee-Wee's Big Adventure'' and a book titled ``The
Well-Built Elephant and Other Roadside Attractions _ A Tribute to
American Eccentricity.''
   The retired amusement park sculptor spent more than two decades
and <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> creating the giant creatures _ a 150-ton, concrete
brontosaurus named Dinney and a 100-ton tyrannosaurus named Rex _
on an otherwise desolate stretch of Interstate 10 near <LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION>.
   The towering dinosaurs can be seen for miles by travelers
approaching the tiny community of Cabazon on the desert route
between <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   ``The dinosaurs aren't dead and they never will be,'' <PERSON>Bell</PERSON>'s
daughter, <PERSON>Wendy Murphy</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Costa Mesa</LOCATION>, said. ``He wanted to build a
monument that would withstand the sands of time, and he has done
that.''
   Bell, a retired sculptor for <ORGANIZATION>Orange County</ORGANIZATION>'s popular <PERSON>Knott</PERSON>'s
<PERSON>Berry</PERSON> Farm amusement park, was in his mid-60s when he first began
building the steel-framed, 150-foot-long brontosaurus on 60 acres
of desert land he owned at Cabazon.
   It was meant to be the first of several figures in his Dinosaur
Garden theme park. Plans to add a giant mastodon and a sabre-tooth
tiger are on the drawing board.
   The park, which includes a museum and gift shop, is run by
<PERSON>Bell</PERSON>'s son-in-law, <PERSON>Denny Rowing</PERSON>.
   Bell is survived by his wife, <PERSON>Anna Marie</PERSON>, a son, five daughters,
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900402-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-02-90 2325EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--DinosaurFossils-Species Adv15   04-02 0271</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Dinosaur Fossils-Species, Adv 15,0274</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv15</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, April 15</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-APN--Dinosaur Fossils, b0524</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fossils of some of the dinosaurs that have been
found in the <ORGANIZATION>Morrison Formation</ORGANIZATION> include:
   _Apatosaurus: Popularly known as the brontosaurus, one of the
best-known dinosaurs. The 70-foot-long creature had a heavy body
and legs and a long neck and tail.
   _Diplodocus: Ninety feet long with most of the length from the
long, thin neck and long, whip-like tail. Its name, which means
``double beam,'' describes a special feature of the backbone, a
piece of small bone that pointed forward as well as the normal
piece that pointed back.
   _Stegosaurus: Had a tiny, tubular skull with a brain the size of
a walnut. It had small, flat plates on its neck and bigger
diamond-shaped plates on its back and the first part of its tail.
It grew up to 30 feet long.
   _Allosaurus: The largest carnivore in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> in the late
<LOCATION>Jurassic Period</LOCATION>. It may have fed on other well-known dinosaurs. It
was different from other meat-eating dinosaurs in the shape of its
skull, which had a ridge along the top that ran from between the
eyes to the tip of the snout. It was 35 feet long.
   _Camarasaurus: A heavily built suaropod with a shorter tail and
neck than the apatosaurus or diplodocus. Its head was short with a
blunt snout, and its nostrils were on the top of its head. Those
features have led scientists to believe it could have lived in
water. It generally grew to 60 feet long.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06041047 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06041047 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawing; DRAWING: King Kong fights off a pesky pterodactyl in NOVA's 'The Case
of the Flying Dinosaur.'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ANIMAL; REPTILE; BIRD; TELEVISION; HISTORY; PROGRAM; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  WHAT if the dinosaurs really didn't mysteriously die out but just continued
evolving until they turned into something else, such as ostriches or swans?;  
 Goofy as it may sound, that's a broad interpretation of a popular scientific
theory that says birds and reptiles have a common ancestor. The notion has
been around at least 200 years and still has wide currency.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  TV Magazine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DOES DINOSAUR THEORY FLY?  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Public Television  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The possible link between the dinosaurs of 140 million years ago and
today's birds is explored on PBS <DATE>this week</DATE> in a fascinating edition of the
"Nova" series called "The Case of the Flying Dinosaur." The show, second of
three "Nova" episodes about dinosaurs, plays <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> on Channel 9.; 
  The dinosaur/bird theories <DATE>spring</DATE> from scientific attempts to search out the
origin of birds by studying fossils from the Mesozoic Era.;    Scientists can
see links between existing birds and reptiles -- such as the presence of
scales and births from hard-shelled eggs -- but there are many differences,
too, between cold-blooded reptiles and warm-blooded birds.;    Yet
well-preserved fossils of bird-like reptiles first found in German limestone
quarries in the 18th century inspired some renowned scientists, including
<PERSON>Thomas Huxley</PERSON>, to believe they were evidence of an evolutionary turn taken by
dinosaurs.;    Most of the "flying dinosaur" partisans believe that
prehistoric reptiles that ran or leaped to grab prey gradually acquired the
ability to fly. Others think it's more likely the dinosaur ancestors of birds
were tree-climbing reptiles that developed wings to "sail" after prey.;    The
fossils that were central to the theory were those of creatures known as
archaeopteryx -- small, bird-like reptiles with wings. They promised to be the
"missing link" between dinosaurs and birds.;    Debate over the theory has
divided the scientific world for years, and the "Nova" episode explores both
sides of the controversy.;    "It's an enormously attractive idea," said bird
fossil expert <PERSON>Larry Martin</PERSON> about the dinosaur theory. "If I have a cage with a
parakeet in it, it's certainly a lot more fun to think that it's a small
tyrannosaurus." Martin is among those who believe birds originated
independently and probably existed side by side with dinosaurs. He thinks the
"flying dinosaur" theory is the result of inadequate study of the fossil
records.;    Latest challenge to the theory is the <DATE>1985</DATE> discovery of a new
bird-like fossil creature, tentatively dubbed "protoavis," which predates
archaeopteryx by millions of years, making it a contemporary of the dinosaurs
from which birds are supposed to have evolved. The first scientific papers
describing this creature are due this spring.;    Still, "Nova" stirs the
imagination with some carefully photographed scenes of contemporary birds that
do resemble dinosaurs when seen from the proper angle. Example: ostriches
browsing on a plain, looking like brontosauruses with feathers.;    This
edition of "Nova" replays the scene in "King Kong" where Kong beats up a
pterodactyl trying to make off with <PERSON>Fay Wray</PERSON>. But it warns against any leap to
the conclusion that pterodactyls were related to modern birds. The world of
science is unanimously of the opinion that birds didn't evolve from those
particular bat-winged reptiles. So when <PERSON>Steven Spielberg</PERSON> starts filming
<PERSON>Michael Crichton</PERSON>'s novel "Jurassic Park," a fanciful story about dinosaurs
being cloned on an island off the coast of <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>, he probably should
omit the part about pterodactyls being kept in a giant aviary. (box)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RON MILLER, Mercury News Television Editor  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910210  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  579  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday February 10, 1991
00041047,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891208-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-08-89 0443EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Dinobusters     12-08 0594</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dinobusters,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Use `Dinobusting' Method to Help Dig Up Huge Dinosaur</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A method developed to find buried toxic
waste is helping scientists dig up what may be the longest
fossilized dinosaur ever found, a 120-foot seismosaurus who died in
a river 145 million years ago.
   ``Something big in your neighborhood? Who ya gonna call?
Dinobusters!'' is the slogan inscribed on the T-shirt of <ORGANIZATION>Oak Ridge
National Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> researcher <PERSON>Alan Witten</PERSON>, who developed the
``dinobusting'' technique with about <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Energy</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> excavation is under way at a secret site
northwest of <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Witten</PERSON>'s technique is used to
locate buried bones by making fuzzy pictures of them with sound
waves.
   ``What Alan is going to do is bring paleontology out of the <DATE>19th
century</DATE>'' by making it faster, easier and cheaper to excavate large
fossils, said <PERSON>J. Wilson Bechtel</PERSON>, who supervises the dig with his
wife, <PERSON>Peggy</PERSON>. They direct the <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Paleontology Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>.
   The Tennessee-based <PERSON>Witten</PERSON> discussed the dig and his technique
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> during the <ORGANIZATION>American Geophysical Union</ORGANIZATION>'s fall meeting.
   <PERSON>Witten</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Energy Department</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s toxic materials
agency paid to develop the method so it could be used to find
buried toxic waste for cleanup, check the integrity of potential
toxic or nuclear waste dumps, and perhaps explore for coal seams.
   The method is similar to medical CT scans, which use X-rays and
detectors to make images of internal organs.
   To make images of buried seismosaurus bones, <PERSON>Witten</PERSON> said he
sends sound waves through the ground using ``an 8-gauge shotgun on
wheels, pointed down. It fires a soft metal slug that hits the
ground and flattens.''
   The sound waves are detected by a set of 29 microphones in a
nearby hole. The sound travels at different rates through rock and
bone. To make an image of one part of the dinosaur, the gun is
moved around and fired repeatedly, producing a two-dimensional
image of a bone's ``sound shadows.''
   The method is similar to that used to make holographs, <PERSON>Witten</PERSON>
said. The sound gun is a commercial kind used to search for oil by
studying the speed of sound waves bouncing off various underground
rocks, not by making an image, he added.
   Several tail vertebrae from the seismosaurus, a relative of
brontosaurus and diplodocus, were discovered by two hikers in <DATE>1979</DATE>.
The exposed bones were excavated in <DATE>June 1985</DATE> by <PERSON>David Gillette</PERSON>,
then paleontology curator at the <ORGANIZATION>New Mexico Museum of Natural
History</ORGANIZATION> and now <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>'s state paleontologist.
   <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> announced the find in <DATE>August 1986</DATE>, coining the name
seismosaurus, or ``earth shaker.''
   The seismosaurus lived in a hot, humid river <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> much like
today's <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, and ``probably laid down on a river sandbar
and was covered by sand rather rapidly'' after damming water
upstream, <ORGANIZATION>Bechtel</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The dinosaur's bones are still in the position where they were
when the animal died.
   Debate continues over whether the seismosaurus or a fossil
dinosaur found near <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>, is the biggest ever discovered.
<ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> said seismosaurus was at least 120 feet long and probably
longer, and <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young University</ORGANIZATION> scientists have said their
dinosaur was at least 100 feet long and possibly 130 feet.
   Until the dinosaurs are excavated, ``it's all speculation,''
said <PERSON>Witten</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Bechtel</PERSON> said it will take at least one more year to
excavate the seismosaurus. So far, the team has removed the base of
the tail, vertebrae, pelvis and several ribs from beneath 8 feet of
sandstone.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102289-0049 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 124001 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 22, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 13; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
567 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE COUSTEAU WATCH: PREHISTORIC DREAM IN NEW ZEALAND 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JACQUES-YVES COUSTEAU 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>'s Breaksea Sound, one of the longest fjords in the world, the 
coasts are steep, covered with forests and dripping with water. Calypso's stern 
dug into the bushy tree branches. It was raining, unrelentingly. Halfway to the 
top of the high mountains above us, patches of fog clung to the slopes. 
Vertiginous waterfalls cascaded down drenched mountain peaks that merged with 
the sky. Water was everywhere. 
</P>
<P>
It fell in raindrops. It hung in layers of fog. It soaked the forest, oozing 
out of the moss-covered ground, swallowing sap and rot. Then over the surface 
of the sound, it regurgitated a layer of yellowish and murky vegetal freshwater 
goo that floated on top of the deep and crystalline salt water. 
</P>
<P>
I took our small seaplane to land and walked through the deep, vertical forest. 
I maneuvered through the mud, proceeding with caution in a silence broken only 
by the patter of rain, the crackling of rotting branches and the melodic songs 
of bellbirds. 
</P>
<P>
There were evergreen beeches, shrubs with clustered leaves, and ferns 
everywhere -- the dwarf kind, the creeping kind, but also the very tall and 
arborescent kind. Networks of moss covered the ground, the tree trunks and the 
rocks. Everything was spongy. 
</P>
<P>
This welcoming forest, mild and soft to the touch, was defenseless against such 
animals as goats and deer. But scarcely two centuries have passed since humans 
brought goats, sheep, deer, rats and other mammals to <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, that had 
otherwise evolved free of all mammalian life, free of the need of defense. 
</P>
<P>
I removed my gloves and found that, in contrast to the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> forest, here 
nothing prickled, nothing stung, nothing irritated the skin. There were no 
scorpions, no snakes, no tarantulas, no biting ants. And, except for perhaps an 
occasional tiny white orchid, obviously of recent date, even as I searched, all 
around me, I saw no flowers. 
</P>
<P>
I leaned on a forked tree limb and fell under the spell, escaping from the 
present world and traveling back in time, relying on daydreams as fragile as 
the half-rotten branch that supported me. Mystery, like the water, flowed 
everywhere. 
</P>
<P>
I traveled back some 70 million years, when <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> broke away from the 
supercontinent of <LOCATION>Gondwanaland</LOCATION> that eventually divided into the continents of 
our time. I pictured <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> as a ship that broke loose from its parent, 
drifting, lashed by tremendous volcanic storms, constantly reshaped by the whim 
of shifting tectonic plates. The dinosaurs never invaded the region that would 
become this vessel, and so the castaway forests had not developed defenses 
against the formidable plant-eaters that most dinosaurs were. 
</P>
<P>
Then I travel back perhaps 130 million years, just before the appearance of the 
first flowers. This time I set foot on <LOCATION>Gondwanaland</LOCATION> itself to witness the havoc 
the dinosaurs wreaked on plants of all kinds. The vegetation had armed itself 
to no avail with ridiculous prickles to ward off the teeth of the 
brontosauruses and other diplodocuses. When the flowering plants did appear, 
they managed to survive because of their rapid reproduction. And these plants 
not only produced perfumes, but alkaloids and tannins -- odors and bitter 
chemicals capable of discouraging most herbivores. 
</P>
<P>
With that, I then fantasize that flowers could have caused dinosaurs to starve 
and vanish. I picture, with a smile, a giant brontosaurus spitting out a tender 
flower. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900402-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-02-90 2324EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--DinosaurFossils Adv15   04-02 0980</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Dinosaur Fossils, Adv 15,1007</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv15</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, April 15</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w
photo, 1 graphic.)</NOTE>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   As dinosaurs go, they were the biggest of the
big. They lived in a region that is now the <LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION>, no
dwarfs themselves when it comes to hills. And it's in those
mountains that their bones are interred, offering today's
scientists valuable clues to the history of life.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By PEGGY LOWE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As dinosaurs go, they were the biggest of the
big. They lived in a region that is now the <LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION>, no
dwarfs themselves when it comes to hills. And it's in those
mountains that their bones are interred, offering today's
scientists valuable clues to the history of life.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900411-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-11-90 1425EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--DinosaurFossils ADV15 1stLd-Writethru 04-11 0997</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Dinosaur Fossils, ADV 15, 1st Ld-Writethru,1022</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv15</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, April 15, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 19th graf beginning ``Bakker believes...'' to CORRECT
spelling of epidemiological.''
^(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w
photo, 1 graphic.)</NOTE>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   As dinosaurs go, they were the biggest of the
big. They lived in a region that is now the <LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION>, no
dwarfs themselves when it comes to hills. And it's in those
mountains that their bones are interred, offering today's
scientists valuable clues to the history of life.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By PEGGY LOWE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As dinosaurs go, they were the biggest of the
big. They lived in a region that is now the <LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION>, no
dwarfs themselves when it comes to hills. And it's in those
mountains that their bones are interred, offering today's
scientists valuable clues to the history of life.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890816-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-16-89 0316EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     08-16 0632</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0658</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>American Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION> has
decided that three heads are better than one when it comes to
dinosaurs.
   The museum has revised its opinion of what the head of an
apatosaurus _ commonly known as a brontosaurus _ looked like.
   But because the museum's 17-foot-tall, 66-foot-long apatosaurus
skeleton was assembled in <DATE>1905</DATE> and contains bones that are 140
million years old, it was too fragile to withstand a head transplant.
   So the museum has created an exhibit featuring three heads. One
is a copy of the head now on the apatosaurus skeleton, another is a
model that scientists now believe more closely resembles the
apatosaurus' real head, and the third is the head of a close
relative of the extinct beast.
   ``We may have to change our minds again once we find a skeleton
with a skull attached, but we think this is the most likely guess
based on the available evidence until we actually find a complete
skeleton with a skull attached,'' said <PERSON>Lowell Dingus</PERSON>, exhibit
coordinator.
   No one has ever found an apatosaurus skeleton with a skull
attached. The skull created for the <DATE>1905</DATE> model skeleton was based on
that of a dinosaur believed to be close kin, a camarasaurus.
   Since then, paleontologists have changed their minds about the
apatosaurus' likely relatives. A paper published in <DATE>1978</DATE> argued that
the diplodocus was a closer kin than the camarasaurus, implying the
apatosaurus had a longer, sleeker head than had been believed.
   When the museum tried to behead its apatosaurus in preparation
for a new skull, ``it sent vibrations down the skeleton and a couple
of the ribs fell off and broke,'' <PERSON>Dingus</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PEORIA, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>American Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION> has
decided that three heads are better than one when it comes to
dinosaurs.
   The museum has revised its opinion of what the head of an
apatosaurus _ commonly known as a brontosaurus _ looked like.
   But because the museum's 17-foot-tall, 66-foot-long apatosaurus
skeleton was assembled in <DATE>1905</DATE> and contains bones that are 140
million years old, it was too fragile to withstand a head transplant.
   So the museum has created an exhibit featuring three heads. One
is a copy of the head now on the apatosaurus skeleton, another is a
model that scientists now believe more closely resembles the
apatosaurus' real head, and the third is the head of a close
relative of the extinct beast.
   ``We may have to change our minds again once we find a skeleton
with a skull attached, but we think this is the most likely guess
based on the available evidence until we actually find a complete
skeleton with a skull attached,'' said <PERSON>Lowell Dingus</PERSON>, exhibit
coordinator.
   No one has ever found an apatosaurus skeleton with a skull
attached. The skull created for the <DATE>1905</DATE> model skeleton was based on
that of a dinosaur believed to be close kin, a camarasaurus.
   Since then, paleontologists have changed their minds about the
apatosaurus' likely relatives. A paper published in <DATE>1978</DATE> argued that
the diplodocus was a closer kin than the camarasaurus, implying the
apatosaurus had a longer, sleeker head than had been believed.
   When the museum tried to behead its apatosaurus in preparation
for a new skull, ``it sent vibrations down the skeleton and a couple
of the ribs fell off and broke,'' <PERSON>Dingus</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PARKER, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>American Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION> has
decided that three heads are better than one when it comes to
dinosaurs.
   The museum has revised its opinion of what the head of an
apatosaurus _ commonly known as a brontosaurus _ looked like.
   But because the museum's 17-foot-tall, 66-foot-long apatosaurus
skeleton was assembled in <DATE>1905</DATE> and contains bones that are 140
million years old, it was too fragile to withstand a head transplant.
   So the museum has created an exhibit featuring three heads. One
is a copy of the head now on the apatosaurus skeleton, another is a
model that scientists now believe more closely resembles the
apatosaurus' real head, and the third is the head of a close
relative of the extinct beast.
   ``We may have to change our minds again once we find a skeleton
with a skull attached, but we think this is the most likely guess
based on the available evidence until we actually find a complete
skeleton with a skull attached,'' said <PERSON>Lowell Dingus</PERSON>, exhibit
coordinator.
   No one has ever found an apatosaurus skeleton with a skull
attached. The skull created for the <DATE>1905</DATE> model skeleton was based on
that of a dinosaur believed to be close kin, a camarasaurus.
   Since then, paleontologists have changed their minds about the
apatosaurus' likely relatives. A paper published in <DATE>1978</DATE> argued that
the diplodocus was a closer kin than the camarasaurus, implying the
apatosaurus had a longer, sleeker head than had been believed.
   When the museum tried to behead its apatosaurus in preparation
for a new skull, ``it sent vibrations down the skeleton and a couple
of the ribs fell off and broke,'' <PERSON>Dingus</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890927-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-27-89 1201EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r k BC-EditorialRdp 1stAdd   09-27 0898</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Editorial Rdp, 1st Add,0941</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: is character.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Sept. 21
   <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>) Monitor on IRAs' tax advantage:
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>'s presidential aspirations could mean
tax breaks for millions of Americans.
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s plan restores part of the <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION>'s tax advantage. It
would allow anyone to put up to <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> per year in an <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> while
paying taxes on half that amount. Taxes would have to be paid on
withdrawals from IRAs to pay for a first home or college expenses,
but no penalty for early withdrawal would be incurred.
   For financial reasons alone, <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s expansion of IRAs is far
preferable to (President) <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s cut in the capital gains tax.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Sept. 21
   <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>) Monitor on IRAs' tax advantage:
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>'s presidential aspirations could mean
tax breaks for millions of Americans.
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s plan restores part of the <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION>'s tax advantage. It
would allow anyone to put up to <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> per year in an <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> while
paying taxes on half that amount. Taxes would have to be paid on
withdrawals from IRAs to pay for a first home or college expenses,
but no penalty for early withdrawal would be incurred.
   For financial reasons alone, <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s expansion of IRAs is far
preferable to (President) <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s cut in the capital gains tax.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Sept. 21
   <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>) Monitor on IRAs' tax advantage:
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>'s presidential aspirations could mean
tax breaks for millions of Americans.
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s plan restores part of the <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION>'s tax advantage. It
would allow anyone to put up to <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> per year in an <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> while
paying taxes on half that amount. Taxes would have to be paid on
withdrawals from IRAs to pay for a first home or college expenses,
but no penalty for early withdrawal would be incurred.
   For financial reasons alone, <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s expansion of IRAs is far
preferable to (President) <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s cut in the capital gains tax.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Sept. 21
   <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>) Monitor on IRAs' tax advantage:
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>'s presidential aspirations could mean
tax breaks for millions of Americans.
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s plan restores part of the <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION>'s tax advantage. It
would allow anyone to put up to <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> per year in an <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> while
paying taxes on half that amount. Taxes would have to be paid on
withdrawals from IRAs to pay for a first home or college expenses,
but no penalty for early withdrawal would be incurred.
   For financial reasons alone, <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s expansion of IRAs is far
preferable to (President) <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s cut in the capital gains tax.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Sept. 21
   <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>) Monitor on IRAs' tax advantage:
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>'s presidential aspirations could mean
tax breaks for millions of Americans.
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s plan restores part of the <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION>'s tax advantage. It
would allow anyone to put up to <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> per year in an <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> while
paying taxes on half that amount. Taxes would have to be paid on
withdrawals from IRAs to pay for a first home or college expenses,
but no penalty for early withdrawal would be incurred.
   For financial reasons alone, <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s expansion of IRAs is far
preferable to (President) <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s cut in the capital gains tax.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Sept. 21
   <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>) Monitor on IRAs' tax advantage:
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>'s presidential aspirations could mean
tax breaks for millions of Americans.
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s plan restores part of the <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION>'s tax advantage. It
would allow anyone to put up to <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> per year in an <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> while
paying taxes on half that amount. Taxes would have to be paid on
withdrawals from IRAs to pay for a first home or college expenses,
but no penalty for early withdrawal would be incurred.
   For financial reasons alone, <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s expansion of IRAs is far
preferable to (President) <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s cut in the capital gains tax.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920120-0126
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920120-0126.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   This Paleontologist
   Is Breathing Life
   Into Dinosaurs
   ---
   Robert Bakker, on Extinction,
   Distresses His Profession;
   The Perils of Wanderlust
   ----
   By Marj Charlier
</HL>
<DATE>
01/20/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<NS>
SCIENCE &amp; TECHNOLOGY (SCN)
</NS>
<RE>
COLORADO (CO)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   COMO BLUFF, WYO. -- According to Robert Bakker, much of
what you think you know about dinosaurs is wrong. And he has
devoted his life to setting it right.
   Dinosaurs, insists the 46-year-old paleontologist and
museum curator at the University of Colorado, weren't
coldblooded, lizard-like behemoths that lumbered across the
land and wallowed in swamps. Contrary to popular belief, many
were warm-blooded creatures with colorful skins, and they ran
like cheetahs.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   If that isn't radical enough for you, consider <PERSON>Mr.
Bakker</PERSON>'s reason for crawling around on a wind-swept, treeless
bluff here in the high plains of southern <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>: He is
searching for clues to disprove one of science's most
currently popular theories -- that dinosaurs were wiped out
en masse after an asteroid fell, suddenly changing the
earth's climate for the colder.
   <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON>'s theory? They were done in because they liked
to travel too much.
   It's just another day at the office for the enfant
terrible of paleontology, whose whole life seems bent on
irking the scientific establishment. Most scientists speak
cautiously, in terms like "the evidence suggests." The brash
<PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> proclaims his theories with an air of certainty.
Other archaeological expeditions are larded with Ph.D.s and
graduate students from prestigious institutions; <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON>
mans his with amateurs he refers to as "Mesozoic
bird-watchers." (<PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON>, himself, is equipped with all
the usual, impressive credentials, including a <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>
doctorate.) While most paleontologists ship their discoveries
to far-off <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> universities for study and storage, <PERSON>Mr.
Bakker</PERSON> helps local towns build museums to house fossils found
close at hand.
   But though some of his peers dismiss his theories -- and
many abhor his style -- few deny that he is roiling the
prehistoric waters. <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON>'s theories are discussed in
college classes, in textbooks and encyclopedias as
alternative views of Mesozoic life. "Before <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> came
along, dinosaurs looked like extinct old bones," says <PERSON>Sankar
Chatterjee</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Tech University</ORGANIZATION>. "With <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>, dinosaurs
became vibrant, living beings." Well, in a manner of
speaking.
   How he accomplished that is a sore subject in the science
-- so sore, in fact, that some of his peers won't talk about
him. Others complain that he is a showboat, promoting his
notions in the popular press and on TV, not just before they
have been accepted by the paleontology establishment, but, in
some cases, even before they have been published in a
scientific journal.
   <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> is clearly annoyed by the criticism. "If I seem
aggressive," he says, "it's because sometimes one gets
impatient with orthodoxy."
   But <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> doesn't spend all his time romancing the
media. Mostly, he spends it trying to prove his extinction
theory, which means long hours painstakingly combing the dirt
here on <ORGANIZATION>Como Bluff</ORGANIZATION> for bones.
   On a current dig, the paleontologist is pushing dirt
around a gray mound with his fingers as his long, kinky hair
drags in the dust and his jeans get dirtier. A few hundred
yards away, <PERSON>James Siegwarth</PERSON>, a physicist with the
is digging out the vertebra of a huge allosaur, a two-ton
meat-eater of the Jurassic era, after two days of carefully
prodding the dirt with tiny ice picks and paintbrushes. His
work isn't over: It can take up to 200 hours in the lab just
to clean the big bone. "I don't mind," he says. "I guess I
like playing in the dirt."
   In the <DATE>summer of 1990</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Siegwarth</PERSON> and another dinosaur
buff, <PERSON>Jim Filla</PERSON>, spotted some tiny bones sticking out of the
mudstone here. And, though at least one paleontologist they
approached wasn't interested, when they took the bones to <PERSON>Mr.
Bakker</PERSON>, he promptly declared the find a new species of
dinosaur, named it Drinker (after the early paleontologist
<ORGANIZATION>Edward Drinker Cope</ORGANIZATION>), and recruited Messrs. <PERSON>Siegwarth</PERSON> and
Filla for a new dig at <ORGANIZATION>Como</ORGANIZATION>, which had been considered a
played-out site. Since then, the "Como Irregulars," as <PERSON>Mr.
Bakker</PERSON> calls them, have unearthed more than half a dozen
heretofore-undiscovered dinosaurs, with, he hopes, more to
come. "I want to find a voracious, small-minded predator and
name it after the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>," <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> says.
   <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> wishes more amateurs would join the hunt. "We
need 10 times, 100 times more weekenders," he says. "The
reason the world knows so much about birds is because there
are thousands of amateur bird-watchers. The reason we know so
little about dinosaurs is there are too few people looking
for them."
   He blames the shortage on pretentious paleontologists who
insist on calling an eye socket "the fossa orbital" and who
generally look down at enthusiastic amateurs. "My science is
low-tech, and it requires sharp eyes and delicate fingers,"
not a knowledge of Latin, says <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON>. "Ph.D.s are a dead
loss," he adds. "They break things."
   With his weekenders, <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> hopes to prove that
dinosaurs didn't die from an asteroid collision. Supporters
of the much-in-vogue asteroid theory argue that a layer of
iridium separating rocks of the Cretaceous and Tertiary
periods was left by an asteroid whose impact created a
nuclear winter-like climatic disaster. That wiped out many
species, including the dinosaurs, says physicist <PERSON>Walter
Alvarez</PERSON>, whose theory this is. His argument: Dinosaurs are
found in rocks laid down before the iridium was deposited,
but not afterward.
   But that doesn't make sense to <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON>, who contends
that bones would have been found on top of the iridium if the
dinosaurs died after the asteroid collision. And why did the
small and delicate frogs and toads survive the cold and
drought while bigger beasts didn't? Frogs should have bit the
dust first, he says.
   <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON>'s theory is based on the ebb and flow of early
seas. Paleontologists have documented several dinosaur
extinctions in the Mesozoic Era that coincide with periods of
shrinking seas. When the seas ebbed between the <LOCATION>Jurassic</LOCATION> and
Cretaceous periods, for example, most dinosaurs, including
the brontosaurs, were wiped out. <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> calls that
extinction the "dinosaur midlife crisis."
   <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> points out that each time the seas receded,
land bridges appeared. Over those bridges, the largest and
most mobile dinosaurs wandered into new territory searching
for food. They also found exotic and deadly new diseases, <PERSON>Mr.
Bakker</PERSON> argues. Itinerant dinosaurs carried new diseases to
alien lands, causing epidemics.
   The bones of the Drinker dinosaur in the rocks at <ORGANIZATION>Como
Bluff</ORGANIZATION> helped him form this theory. The Drinker apparently was
one of the few species to survive the <LOCATION>Jurassic</LOCATION>. "The old
money crowd, the brontosaurs, are damn rare here," says <PERSON>Mr.
Bakker</PERSON>, waving his arm over the layer where Drinker bones
have been found. Drinker survived, he believes, because it
was small -- about the size of a turkey -- and thus couldn't
wander far. Neither could frogs and toads.
   In an effort to win skeptical colleagues over to his
notions, <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> plans a blitz of papers, which he
illustrates himself. But no matter how his extinction theory
is received, he plans to continue his quest to alter the
world's vision of the prehistoric world. Dinosaur orthodoxy,
he says, was "<PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> wrong when I was growing up. Now it's only
half wrong."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111190-0072 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 306224 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 11, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Book Review; Page 4; Book Review Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1053 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE THING FROM THE TAR PITS; 
</P>
<P>
JURASSIC PARK BY MICHAEL CRICHTON (ALFRED A. KNOPF: $19.95; 413 PP.) 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Andrew Ferguson, Ferguson is an editorial writer with Scripps Howard News 
Service. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Michael Crichton</PERSON>, the doctor (<ORGANIZATION>Harvard Medical</ORGANIZATION>) turned novelist ("The Andromeda 
Strain") turned moviemaker ("Coma"), is a worry wart, and like most excessively 
anxious people he feels duty-bound to make the rest of us as edgy as he is. His 
many novels and movies form an extended brief explaining why we, as a nation, 
race and planet, should have a serious case of the willies. 
</P>
<P>
The theme that preoccupies him is nothing less than the hubris of man and the 
heedlessness of science. Our capacity for technological innovation, in his 
view, has outstripped our capacity to deal maturely with the power it affords, 
carrying us inexorably to the yawning abyss of annihilation. Crichton's first 
novel, "The Andromeda Strain," told the story of a 
life-as-we-know-it-destroying bacterium uncorked by money-grubbing scientists; 
likewise, his movie "Westworld" featured a rampaging amusement-park automaton 
(played by <ORGANIZATION>Yul Brynner</ORGANIZATION>) who turns on his feckless human creators and, Yul 
Brynner-like, pumps them full of hot lead. 
</P>
<P>
Only time will tell whether <PERSON>Crichton</PERSON>'s worries about rampaging bacilli and 
deranged automatons are justified -- even now, after all, an irritable Third 
World dictator is hoarding untold stashes of bacteria, and you never can tell 
when the talking <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON> at <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION> might go berserk during some 
matinee, lifting skirts and making rude noises with his armpits. But so far the 
<PERSON>Crichton</PERSON> prognostication average has not been good -- zero, in fact. We should 
hope it stays that way. Otherwise, having read <PERSON>Crichton</PERSON>'s fat new novel, 
"Jurassic Park," I have a word of advice for anyone owning real estate within 
10 miles of La Brea tar pits: Sell. 
</P>
<P>
What sets <PERSON>Crichton</PERSON>'s teeth to chattering these days is biotechnology, the 
manipulation of DNA to create new forms of life or -- the premise of "Jurassic 
Park" -- re-create old ones. The novel opens with a documentary-like sketch of 
how this new technology has come to be corrupted by slithery commerce. Once 
scientists were pure, disinterested; now they -- unlike, say, the directors of 
sci-fi movies and the authors of pulp fiction -- have lowered themselves to 
making a buck. "Suddenly," <PERSON>Mr. Crichton</PERSON> writes, "it seemed as if everyone 
wanted to become rich." 
</P>
<P>
"Jurassic Park" is the story of how this ignoble ambition, married to 
biotechnology, results in the beginning of the end of the world as we know it, 
or at least of <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION>. That hapless Central American country is the site of 
the eponymous park, developed by one <PERSON>John Hammond</PERSON>, a money-grubbing and devious 
American entrepreneur, on an island off the coast. There money-grubbing 
scientists, working in secret, have managed to cull dinosaur DNA from ancient 
amber and re-construct living versions of the beasts, so that they might serve 
as tourist attractions for wonder-struck Americanos. 
</P>
<P>
Things, as you can imagine, quickly go awry. A few months before the park is to 
open, an unspecified number of the smaller dinosaurs escape to the mainland, 
where, on a deserted beach, they maul the vacationing family of a <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> 
real-estate developer -- a tragedy all the more horrifying because the 
real-estate developer escapes unharmed. The authorities remain unaware of the 
danger through a series of amazingly convenient botches, giving <PERSON>Hammond</PERSON> the 
chance to summon a handful of experts to set matters in order. 
</P>
<P>
This is a risky plot device for <PERSON>Mr. Crichton</PERSON>, since it requires him to 
introduce characters into his elaborate fictional architecture, and the 
creation of plausible characters is not, to speak generously, his strength. Our 
hero is a paleontologist called Grant; we are signalled his hero status early 
on when <PERSON>Mr. Crichton</PERSON> informs us that <ORGANIZATION>Grant</ORGANIZATION> eschews the stuffy tweeds of the 
common prof in favor of jeans and sneakers -- even when he lectures! He is 
joined on the island by a mathematician named <PERSON>Malcolm</PERSON>; a sexy assistant called 
<PERSON>Sattler</PERSON>; a candy-bar-scarfing computer jockey, Nedry by name, who designed the 
island's labyrinthine security systems, and two insufferably precocious 
grandchildren of the evil <PERSON>Hammond</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The mutilations begin in earnest not long after this group arrives at <LOCATION>Jurassic 
Park</LOCATION>. The computer expert (note that a single letter's transposition makes 
Nedry nerdy -- a typical <PERSON>Crichton</PERSON> subtlety) neutralizes the island's electronic 
fences for his own devious purposes, mostly of the money-grubbing kind. His 
comeuppance follows shortly after, for with the fences down the dinosaurs roam 
freely, and before long they've put on the old feed bag and are dining on 
<ORGANIZATION>Nedry</ORGANIZATION>'s innards. Hungry creatures, dinosaurs. 
</P>
<P>
Nedry's intestines are neither the first nor the last to be spilled and gnawed 
in <LOCATION>Jurassic Park</LOCATION>. In these scenes, <PERSON>Crichton</PERSON>'s prose, usually rough-hewn and 
business-like, takes on an almost sensual vividness. "Nedry stumbled, reaching 
blindly down to touch the ragged edge of his shirt, and then a thick, slippery 
mass that was surprisingly warm, and with horror he suddenly knew . . . his 
guts had fallen out." The vividness increases when you remember that <PERSON>Nedry</PERSON> has 
spent the afternoon eating Mars Bars. 
</P>
<P>
As unattractive as these passages are, they're almost Johnsonian compared with 
the dithering of the mathematician <PERSON>Malcolm</PERSON>, who serves as <PERSON>Crichton</PERSON>'s Greek 
chorus. Hubris-of-man and heedlessness-of-science soliloquys flow from him like 
intestines from a computer nerd. Our "Western training" saps our appreciation 
of nature, Crichton-Malcolm announces ponderously, and encourages us to conquer 
nature rather than live harmoniously with it -- a tired if once again 
fashionable idea that has been far more cogently expressed elsewhere. 
</P>
<P>
My pre-publication copy of "Jurassic Park" bears the ominous phrase "Soon to be 
a major motion picture," raising the suspicion that this fat novel is really a 
screenplay larded up with a few tons of exposition. A movie would have the 
advantage of being without <PERSON>Malcolm</PERSON>'s dime-store philosophizing, but it would 
lack too the book's only real virtue: its genuinely interesting discussions of 
dinosaurs, DNA research, paleontology and chaos theory. 
</P>
<P>
Crichton could have performed a service by using this material to write books 
of popular science. Instead, he's written a ponderous novel soon to be a major, 
and undoubtedly trashy, motion picture. Suddenly it seems as if everybody wants 
to become rich. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, The brontosaurus and the stegosaurus are part of The Great Dinosaur 
Mural in the Peabody Museum, Yale University. The mural is illustrated in 12 
accordion-folded pages in "The Age of Reptiles" (Abrams: $19.95; 48 pp.). 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Book Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880408-0009 </DOCNO>
<HL> Cousin of Feared Dinosaur Was a Runt, Scientists Say </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> CLEVELAND (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The skull of a prehistoric animal has been identified as part of a previously unknown species of compact, meat-eating dinosaur, scientists announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 

   The skull was misidentified after its discovery in <DATE>1942</DATE> in eastern <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> by an expedition from the <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION>, officials said. 
It was in storage in the museum's basement when it was noticed by a visiting paleontologist last year. 

   The museum said the skull is from a previously unknown member of the ferocious Tyrannosaurus rex family of dinosaurs that roamed the earth some 60 million years ago. 
Because of its relatively small size, the new dinosaur has been named Nanotyrannus or "pygmy tyrant" by the identifying scientists. 

   <PERSON>Robert T. Bakker</PERSON>, adjunct curator of paleontology at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Colorado</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION>, grew suspicious of the skull's initial identification as a Gorgosaurus, a primitive and very common meat-eater, during a visit to the <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> museum last <DATE>spring</DATE>. 
He worked with two other scientists in determining its identity and their discovery was reported this month in a paleontology publication. 

   The Nanotyrannus resembled the giant Tyrannosaurus rex but was only about one-third as large and one-tenth as heavy, the scientists said. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Bakker</PERSON> blamed the 40-year misidentification on a lack of scientists. 

   "There are never enough scientists to study dinosaurs, or crocodiles or beetles or whatever kind of critter you're talking about," he said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880408-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-88 0126EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewDinosaur 1stLd-Writethru a0819 04-08 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Dinosaur, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0819,0514</SECOND>
<HEAD>Researchers Identify Previously Unknown Species</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4th graf to CORRECT spelling of pygmy.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By STEPHANIE NANO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The skull of a prehistoric animal has been
identified as part of a previously unknown species of compact,
meat-eating dinosaur, scientists announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The skull was misidentified after its discovery in <DATE>1942</DATE> in
eastern <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> by an expedition from the <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Museum of
Natural History</ORGANIZATION>, officials said. It was in storage in the museum's
basement when it was noticed by a visiting paleontologist last year.
   The museum said the skull is from a previously unknown member of
the Tyrannosaurus rex family of dinosaurs, a ferocious meat-eating
animal that roamed the earth some 60 million years ago.
   Because of its relatively small size, the new dinosaur has been
named Nanotyrannus or ``pygmy tyrant'' by the scientists who
identified it. The <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> skull is believed to be the only such
specimen of the Nanotyrannus, although teeth have been found in
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>.
   ``This animal is so different from any other meat-eater that it
merits its own branch of the tyrannosaur family tree,'' said <PERSON>Robert
T. Bakker</PERSON>, adjunct curator of paleontology at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Colorado</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> grew suspicious of the skull's initial identification as
a Gorgosaurus, a primitive and very common meat-eater, during a
visit to the <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> museum last <DATE>spring</DATE>. He worked with two other
scientists in determining its identity and their discovery was
disclosed in a paleontology publication this month.
   The Nanotyrannus resembled the giant Tyrannosaurus rex but was
only about one-third as large and one-tenth as heavy, the
scientists said. <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said the Nanotyrannus probably weighed less
than 1,000 pounds, stood about 10 feet tall, walked on its hind
legs and measured about 17 feet from nose to tail.
   Bakker compared the skull, which is about 22 inches long and 10
inches high, to the size of a brown bear's head.
   He said the Nanotyrannus had the same level of advancement in
anatomical features as the Tyrannosaurus rex, including eye sockets
that faced forward instead of sideways, a wider skull base and a
neck joint that bent downwards.
   The Nanotyrannus head was discovered during a museum field trip
to a farm in <LOCATION>Carter County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>. The expedition yielded other
dinosaur skeletons in the museum's collection but no other parts of
the Nanotyrannus.
   ``It's very rare to find just the head, very rare. And I hope
the rest of it is out there,'' <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said after a news conference
to announce the discovery.
   <PERSON>Michael E. Williams</PERSON>, curator of vertebrate paleontology at the
museum, said there are no plans to excavate the site again.
   Bakker blamed the 40-year misidentification on a lack of
scientists.
   ``There are never enough scientists to study dinosaurs, or
crocodiles or beetles or whatever kind of critter you're talking
about,'' he said.
   The third scientist involved in the discovery with <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Williams</PERSON> was <PERSON>Philip Currie</PERSON>, assistant direector of the <ORGANIZATION>Tyrrell
Museum of Paleontology</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Alberta</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900104-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-04-90 1617EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BigDinosaur     01-04 0484</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Big Dinosaur,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dinosaur Discovery Strengthens Theory Of Rapid Evolution</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Stands for item slugged AM-Epanterias on news advisory.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>LaserPhoto DX2
^By WARD MARCHANT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The discovery of the fossilized bones of a giant
meat-eating dinosaur predating the fearsome tyrannosaurus rex
strengthens the theory that dinosaurs evolved rapidly before
becoming extinct, a scientist said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The bones of an Epanterias were found at the top of the <ORGANIZATION>Morrison
Formation</ORGANIZATION> deposit, an ancient saline lakebed near <LOCATION>Fort Collins</LOCATION>, by
a paleontology team from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Colorado Museum</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION>.
   The discovery a year and a half ago was only the third of an
Epanterias, according to <PERSON>Robert Bakker</PERSON>, a research associate at the
museum, who announced the find <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Bakker identified the giant member of the allosaur family from a
jawbone and parts of the neck and tail vertebrate.
   <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said the discover strengthens the theory that dinosaurs
entombed in the <ORGANIZATION>Morrison Formation</ORGANIZATION>, which dates to 130 million
years ago, and elsewhere in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> evolved rapidly.
   ``On average, the rule is that big animals tend to get bigger
until they go extinct. The incredible size of Epanterias indicates
there was some sort of an evolutionary arms race going on,'' <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON>
said in a telephone interview from <LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION>.
   The Epanterias, which weighed about four tons and was 50 feet
long, could have eaten about 40 tons of meat annually, and its
ability to expand its enormous jaws _ much like modern-day snakes _
would have allowed Epanterias to gulp huge bites of prey easily.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Morrison Formation</ORGANIZATION>, about 50 miles north of <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, contains
up to six distinct dinosaur fauna from successive time periods,
<PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
   The formation is only about 300 feet deep, he said, ``but every
50 feet or so you have a different species. This one was only in
the last 20 feet and the earlier ones also were short-lived. Things
were really moving at that time.''
   The other two discoveries of Epanterias fossils were in <DATE>1877</DATE>
near <LOCATION>Canon City</LOCATION>, 80 miles south of <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, and in <DATE>1934</DATE> in the
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> panhandle.
   Epanterias apparently was the last and largest species in the
evolutionary line of allosaurs, carnivorous dinosaurs that walked
on their hind legs, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
   Epanterias' great size confused early paleontologists, he said.
The bones of the <ORGANIZATION>Canon City</ORGANIZATION> specimen were so large they were
initially misidentified as brontosaur bones.
   <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> speculated the size increase of many dinosaur species
over time may have been due to sexual selection, predation success
or disease resistance.
   He subscribes to the theory that dinosaurs were warm-blooded
like modern birds and that dinosaur mass extinctions about 66
million years ago may have been brought on by extensive migrations
and outbreaks of disease.
   <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said he and other researchers will study all three
Epanterias specimens and they hope to assemble a complete model
pieced together from portions of each dinosaur.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890519-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-19-89 0732EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DinosaurTeeth     05-19 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dinosaur Teeth,0351</SECOND>
<UNK>Fossils 220 Million Years Old, Researcher Says</UNK>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 30 fossilized dinosaur teeth
found near <LOCATION>Tucumcari</LOCATION> are estimated to be 220 million years old,
meaning the creature was one of the first of its kind to inhabit
the earth.
   ``This is of worldwide importance because it is so rare,'' said
<PERSON>Adrian Hunt</PERSON>, a doctoral candidate at the <ORGANIZATION>University of New Mexico</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hunt, who made the discoveries during four years of explorations
for the <ORGANIZATION>New Mexico Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the
shape of the animal's teeth indicate it was one of the first
dinosaurs on earth.
   He named the animal Revueltosaurus callenderi, after the <LOCATION>New
Mexico</LOCATION> museum's director, <PERSON>Jon Callender</PERSON>. The first part of the name
referred to a Spanish word for revolution, `revuelta.'
   The discoveries are discussed in a book published this week
titled ``Dawn of the Age of Dinosaurs in the <ORGANIZATION>American Southwest</ORGANIZATION>,''
edited by Hunt and museum paleontologist <PERSON>Spencer Lucas</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Lucas</PERSON> said it was the first new genus of dinosaur discovered in
<LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> since <DATE>1923</DATE> and the first new dinosaur species found in
the state in nearly 30 years. ``We're breaking a lot of new ground
after a long dry spell,'' he said.
   Found with the teeth were fossils of many early ancestors to
mammals, turtles, crocodiles, flying reptiles and birds, several of
which have yet to be identified, <PERSON>Hunt</PERSON> said.
   <LOCATION>Tucumcari</LOCATION> is in eastern <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> about 30 miles from the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
border.
   ``The area is an incredible graveyard of ancient animals,''
<PERSON>Lucas</PERSON> said.
   The authors' conclusions have yet to be reviewed by scientific
peers.
   Their theory is that <PERSON>Revueltosaurus</PERSON> was the ancestor of all the
plant-eating dinosaurs, including stegosaurus. It resembles a
10-foot-long lizard with 3-foot hind legs that permitted it to walk
nearly upright. It had much smaller forelegs.
   The oldest previous <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> fossil, also dating back some
220 million years, was unearthed several years ago in west <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Dinosaur fossils from the same period have been found in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>
and the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA080690-0069 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 257851 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 6, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
156 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IN BRIEF: SCIENCE / MEDICINE; 
</P>
<P>
PREHISTORIC LIZARD FOSSIL DISCOVERED IN GOBI DESERT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Scientists have found fossil remains of a previously unknown eight-foot lizard 
that may have attacked baby dinosaurs, a researcher reported last week. A 
well-preserved skull and a forelimb of the beast, about 80 million years old, 
were unearthed in <LOCATION>Mongolia</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Gobi Desert</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Michael Novacek</PERSON>, vice president 
</P>
<P>
The creature apparently resembled today's Komodo dragon -- the largest living 
lizard, reaching lengths of more than 11 feet in Southeast Asian jungles, 
<PERSON>Novacek</PERSON> said. The present-day animal has been known to attack and consume human 
adults. 
</P>
<P>
The ancient lizard, perhaps a juvenile, may have eaten young dinosaurs or 
dinosaur eggs. Its bones were found near a dinosaur nesting site that contained 
eight eggs, <PERSON>Novacek</PERSON> said. The find occurred during an expedition Novacek called 
the first to <LOCATION>Mongolia</LOCATION> by Western paleontologists in 65 years. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
LIZARDS; REPTILES; DINOSAURS; FOSSILS; PALEONTOLOGY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880408-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-88 0611EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-NewDinosaur     04-08 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-New Dinosaur,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Researchers Discover New Dinosaur In Old Skull</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEPHANIE NANO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A misidentified dinosaur skull found in the
<ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION>'s basement came from a
previously unknown meat-eating reptile that was a pygmy cousin of
Tyrannosaurus rex, scientists say.
   The skull was found on a southeast <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> farm 46 years ago by
a museum expedition, but was misidentified as a gorgosaur, a
relatively primitive, common carnivore, scientists said at a news
conference <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The new genus has been named Nanotyrannus, or ``pygmy tyrant,''
by the three scientists who discovered it.
   ``This animal is so different from any other meat-eater that it
merits its own branch of the tyrannosaur family tree,'' said <PERSON>Robert
T. Bakker</PERSON>, adjunct curator of paleontology at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Colorado</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said he found the skull, believed to be the only
Nanotyrannus specimen, while rummaging around the museum's basement
last <DATE>spring</DATE>.
   ``The best place in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> to find new (kinds) of
dinosaurs ...is to look in basements, he said. ``There are never
enough scientists to study specimens as soon as they come out of
the crate. This came out of the crate in <DATE>1942</DATE>. But no one did a
detailed study.''
   Tyrannosaurus rex roamed the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> some 60 million years ago.
Nanotyrannus resembled the bigger dinosaur, but was only about
one-third as large and one-tenth as heavy. It probably weighed less
than 1,000 pounds, stood about 10 feet tall, walked on its hind
legs and measured about 17 feet from nose to tail, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
   The skull, about 22 inches long and 10 inches high, is about the
size of a brown bear's head, <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said.
   Nanotyrannus had the same advanced anatomical features as
Tyrannosaurus rex, including eye sockets that faced forward instead
of sideways and a neck joint that bent downwards.
   The expedition that found the skull yielded other dinosaur
skeletons in the musuem's collection, but no other Nanotyrannus
parts.
   ``It's very rare to find a perfect head and no backbone or no
hind leg or tail or ribs,'' <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said. ``It's not impossible that
the body is still out there entombed in very hard sandstone.''
   There are no plans to excavate the site again, said <PERSON>Michael
Williams</PERSON>, curator of vertebrate paleontology at the musuem. The
third scientist involved in the discovery was <PERSON>Philip Currie</PERSON>,
assistant director of the <ORGANIZATION>Tyrrell Museum of Paleontology</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Alberta</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said the skull had been on display, but not for at
least the <DATE>last 10 years</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> said Tyrannosaurus rex is the most popular dinosaur among
children he gives talks to.
   ``I think Tyrannosaurus rex wil continue to be the favorite
dinosaur, but I bet you the pygmy tyrant becomes the second most
popular,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900731-0005 </DOCNO>
