<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA012190-0050 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 164892 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 21, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 5; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
971 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GREECE'S NEW 'SEA WOLVES' OPT FOR PRACTICALITY OVER GLAMOUR; 
</P>
<P>
SHIPPING: DESPITE THE FLASHY LEGACY OF ONASSIS AND NIARCHOS, TODAY'S TYCOONS 
ARE MAKING THEIR FORTUNES WITH CAUTION AND COMPUTER SENSE. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARY BETH SHERIDAN, ASSOCIATED PRESS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
PIRAEUS, Greece 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
They were the Golden Greeks, fiercely independent men who controlled the 
world's shipping, built lush island paradises and married society's most 
glamorous women. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Aristotle Onassis</PERSON>, <PERSON>Stavros Niarchos</PERSON> and their contemporaries are still revered 
in <LOCATION>Piraeus</LOCATION>, base of the powerful Greek shipping industry. But today a new 
tycoon is succeeding them: the young businessman who shuns publicity and knows 
computers as well as compasses. 
</P>
<P>
"Twenty years ago, a shipowner was treated like a god," said <PERSON>Diamantis 
Diamantides</PERSON>, who controls 25 ships. "Now he's a simple person." 
</P>
<P>
The Greek shipping tradition is thousands of years old, a product of the 
country's entrepreneurial talent and its kinship with the sea, which is within 
50 miles of almost any part of <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The legend of the Greek tycoon began earlier this century with the "sea 
wolves," sea captains who acquired fleets. It reached its personification in 
<LOCATION>Niarchos</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Onassis</PERSON>, volatile, dynamic magnates with business savvy and a 
gambler's touch, whose lives and loves were chronicled on the front pages of 
the world press. 
</P>
<P>
Many of the newer managers have maintained their predecessors' passion for the 
sea and their strong preference for family-run firms. But they are increasingly 
making longer-term investments, imposing modern business practices and buying 
newer, high-tech ships. 
</P>
<P>
"We're tending toward structured companies in corporate form as opposed to 
personality-driven, Onassis-type companies," said <PERSON>Emmanuel A. Vordonis</PERSON>, 
director of <ORGANIZATION>Thenamaris Ships Management Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Until recently, Greeks owned the world's largest merchant fleet. The Japanese 
are now No. 1, but <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> is close behind, with 82 million tons of 
cargo-carrying capacity, according to the authoritative shipping magazine 
Naftiliaki. 
</P>
<P>
Some of the change of style in owning Greek ships is due to the crisis that hit 
the industry from <DATE>1975 to 1987</DATE>, stemming from overbuilding of ships and 
competitive freight-rate cutting at a time of stagnating world trade. This 
bustling port near <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION> is still haunted by memories of proud shipowners 
losing their vessels to creditors. 
</P>
<P>
Diamantides, 42, who began buying ships in <DATE>1975</DATE> after working in shipping 
offices, says old-time magnates could get bank loans on the strength of their 
names. 
</P>
<P>
"Now you have to convince them with your figures," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Business practices also have changed with the infusion of a different kind of 
shipowner -- either entrepreneurs from industry or construction attracted by a 
potential fortune, or the children of traditional shipowners, who have received 
advanced degrees in business or engineering at British or American 
universities. 
</P>
<P>
"The new generation of managers has a different investment approach," said 
<PERSON>Dimitri Krondiras</PERSON>, the local director of <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION>, the major lender for Greek 
ship purchases. "This new generation perceives that investment in shipping is 
high-risk." 
</P>
<P>
Because of that gamble, some shipowners have diversified into oil, banking or 
hotel chains. Others are trying to cater more to the changing market, 
purchasing newer, more customized ships. 
</P>
<P>
A few shipowners are even beginning to raise money by opening their companies 
to outside investment and floating shares on the stock market -- previously "a 
kind of heresy in Greek ship owning," says <PERSON>George Anastassopoulos</PERSON>, the former 
head of the <ORGANIZATION>Transport Commission</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>European Parliament</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
One example of the new Greek tycoon is <PERSON>Thanasis Martinos</PERSON>, whose family founded 
Thenamaris. Hailed as the "Mozart of shipping" for his precociousness, <ORGANIZATION>Martinos</ORGANIZATION> 
entered the business as a teen-ager when his mother and her brothers -- a 
shipping lawyer and a sea captain -- bought their first ship. 
</P>
<P>
Martinos worked with the firm while studying economics in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. Now 40, he 
and his two brothers head Thenamaris, which runs 55 ships itself and manages 
about 20 for other people. 
</P>
<P>
Vordonis, the director of the firm, says the older generation "had the risk 
approach, the hard-work approach, the entrepreneurial approach to bringing 
resources together that were difficult to bring together." 
</P>
<P>
Now, he says, shipowners rely on high-speed information relayed by computers, 
tight cost control and a team approach. 
</P>
<P>
Where old-style magnates used to make most decisions, sometimes screaming down 
cowering subordinates, the modern entrepreneurs are trying to attract and rely 
on technical experts to keep up with a fast-moving, efficient, more high-tech 
field. 
</P>
<P>
"In order to achieve, you need technology, modern management techniques," 
<PERSON>Vordonis</PERSON> says. "You go into how to manage people." 
</P>
<P>
A glance at the Thenamaris offices illustrates the change. Unlike the 
traditional rough-and-tumble offices tucked along the <LOCATION>Piraeus</LOCATION> waterfront, 
Thenamaris is a gleaming, glass-and-concrete ring in a lush coastal suburb. 
Sunlight pours into an airy core; water trickles through leafy plants in a 
central atrium. 
</P>
<P>
"We have round tables, where everyone feels equal. We tried to make it as 
friendly as possible," <PERSON>Vordonis</PERSON> says. "In addition to achieving efficiency, you 
must have people working in a high tone." 
</P>
<P>
In addition to keeping a lower profile at the office, the new tycoons avoid 
publicity in their private lives. Gone are the days when <PERSON>Niarchos</PERSON> and <PERSON>Onassis</PERSON> 
competed in the public eye, building ever-bigger yachts and purchasing islands 
they turned into paradises with imported trees and exotic birds. 
</P>
<P>
Onassis dominated gossip columns through his affair with opera singer <PERSON>Maria 
Callas</PERSON> and later his marriage to <PERSON>Jacqueline Kennedy</PERSON>, while <PERSON>Niarchos</PERSON> married, 
among others, <ORGANIZATION>Charlotte Ford</ORGANIZATION>, daughter of auto maker <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Today's shipowners keep elegant villas with swimming pools in <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>' northern 
suburbs and vacation getaways on the Greek islands, as well as homes in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION> or <ORGANIZATION>Monte Carlo</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But they are content to stay out of the spotlight. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Greek shipowner Aristotle Onassis and opera singer Maria Callas, above, 
leave Monte Carlo opera in 1960.; Photo, Below, Greek millionaire Stavros 
Niarchos with actress Olivia de Haviland in Corfu in 1955. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900108-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-08-90 1626EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-APN--NewTycoons Adv21   01-08 1120</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--New Tycoons, Adv 21,1151</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv21</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Jan. 21</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 3 b&amp;w
photos.)</NOTE>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The legend of the Greek shipping tycoons began
earlier this century with the ``sea wolves,'' sea captains who
acquired vast fleets, dynamic magnates with business savvy and a
gambler's touch. Their lives and loves were chronicled on the front
pages of the world press. Now a new breed is at the helm,
introducing modern business practices, and much of the adventure
has been lost.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>By MARY BETH SHERIDAN</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PIRAEUS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The legend of the Greek shipping tycoons began
earlier this century with the ``sea wolves,'' sea captains who
acquired vast fleets, dynamic magnates with business savvy and a
gambler's touch. Their lives and loves were chronicled on the front
pages of the world press. Now a new breed is at the helm,
introducing modern business practices, and much of the adventure
has been lost.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-2161</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CIRBKAGSFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920918
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  18 SEP 92 / Arts: Kings - Theatre
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW ST GEORGE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
There has been mileage in Homer since 600BC when the 'Sons of Homer' formed
a guild for public readings of The Iliad and <ORGANIZATION>The Odyssey</ORGANIZATION>.
<PERSON>Alan Howard</PERSON> and <PERSON>Christopher Logue</PERSON> are continuing the tradition with Kings at
the <ORGANIZATION>Cottesloe Theatre</ORGANIZATION>, a reading from <PERSON>Logue</PERSON>'s <DATE>1991</DATE> version of the first two
books of The Iliad.
This two-man, 90-minute performance shows how compelling epic can be when
well presented.
Aristotle was right to think that it should be read and not acted. <PERSON>Logue</PERSON>'s
Kings follows his epic companion piece, War Music (<DATE>1981</DATE>), which comprised a
version of books 16-19 of The Iliad.
His story keeps close to Homer, recounts the growing dissent among the
Greeks, their reaction to the imperiousness of <LOCATION>Agamemnon</LOCATION>, the sulking of
Achilles at the loss of his captured woman, <PERSON>Briseis</PERSON>, and the fatal prayer he
offers to his mother Thetis, to make the Greeks suffer.
Homeric style combines seriousness and accessibility: armies are compared to
forest fires, or flies around a milk pail.
Logue has caught the scope and pitch of Homeric epic by using translations
from <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> (1611) to <PERSON>Rieu</PERSON> (<DATE>1950</DATE>) and evolving a supple, muscular verse.
He has also preserved the wit in <LOCATION>Homer</LOCATION>. Besides the whining, jibing
Thersites, there is a malicious <ORGANIZATION>Athena</ORGANIZATION> ('We have arranged another death for
Agamemnon') and a skyful of ludic gods: 'How can a mortal make a god smile?
Tell him his plans.'
The Homeric lyricism has also been kept: retained: 'The dawn stepped
barefooted from her lover's bed and shared her beauty with the clouds.'
<PERSON>Logue</PERSON> has wisely kept his own speaking contributions relatively slight. The
evening is carried by <PERSON>Howard</PERSON>.
From the opening lines, 'Think of the <LOCATION>East Aegean</LOCATION> sea by night ..', <PERSON>Howard</PERSON>
is magnificent, delivering the speeches of Greeks and Gods seamlessly
intercut with passages of narration.
He crouches for the opening on a tall stool, fists clenched, conjuring
figures from the Greek camp out of the sea mist.
The famous speech from Odysseus, persuading the Greeks not to follow
Thersites home, is stunning.
Thersites has raised the cry of 'Home' like sudden gusts darkening a lake;
Odysseus calms the soldiers and beats him with a cane before handing the
situation back to <LOCATION>Agamemnon</LOCATION>.
Howard makes it come alive, and for a moment, you are standing on the shores
of history by the wine-dark sea.
Cottesloe Theatre (071 928 2033) until 19 <DATE>September</DATE>, and <DATE>27-29 October</DATE>.
<PERSON>Christopher Logue</PERSON>'s Kings is published by <PERSON>Faber</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06251089 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06251089 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  GREECE; ISLAND; UTILITY; SERVICE; BEGIN  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Electricity has finally arrived at the mythical birthplace of the god of
light.;   Officials on Friday turned on the power to this island in the Aegean
Sea, where Greek mythology says the god Apollo was born.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  APOLLO'S ISLAND GETS ELECTRICITY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The electricity, brought by underwater cable from the nearby island of
Mykonos, was turned on at a ceremony attended by Deputy Premier <PERSON>Tzannis
Tzannetakis</PERSON> and other officials, the <ORGANIZATION>Athens News Agency</ORGANIZATION> reported.;   The
two-square-mile island is the smallest island in the Cycladic chain. Thousands
of tourists visit the ancient sanctuary of Apollo, but the island is inhabited
only by a handful of museum guards and the staff of a small hostel for
archaeologists.;   It was once the political and religious center of the
Aegean, with a large population and with thousands of pilgrims visiting the
oracle of Apollo.;   Apollo was one of the 12 Olympian gods of the ancient
Greeks. Their chief god was Zeus and mythology holds that the gods lived on
<ORGANIZATION>Mount Olympus</ORGANIZATION> in central <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Delos, Greece  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910907  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  14A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  166  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, September 7, 1991
00251089,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06272014 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06272014 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mercury News File Photograph; NEW MOON -- Two images taken by
the satellite Voyager in 1989 show Proteus, the largest of six Neptunian moons
discovered during a satellite photo mission. The planet has eight known moons.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPACE; RESEARCH; NAME  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Six moons of Neptune discovered by the Voyager 2 spacecraft in 1989 have been
named after water nymphs and the children and lovers of the mythological Greek
sea god Poseidon, an astronomy organization said Friday.;   A recently
discovered moon of Saturn was named Pan after the flute-playing Greek god of
fields and shepherds who was half man and half goat, the group said.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ASTRONOMERS HAND OUT NAMES TO MOONS ORBITING 2
PLANETS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The planet <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is named for the Roman god of the sea, known to the
ancient Greeks as Poseidon.;   Announcement by telegram; The six Neptunian
moons discovered by Voyager 2 were named <ORGANIZATION>Naiad</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Galatea</LOCATION>, both water nymphs;
Thalassa and <PERSON>Larissa</PERSON>, both lovers of <LOCATION>Poseidon</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Proteus</ORGANIZATION>, one of the god's sons;
and <LOCATION>Despina</LOCATION>, a daughter.;   The names were revealed this week in a telegram
issued by the <ORGANIZATION>International Astronomical Union</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Central Bureau for
Astronomical Telegrams</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, reporting agency for astronomy
discoveries.;   The <ORGANIZATION>IAU</ORGANIZATION>'s executive committee voted to approve the names when
it met <DATE>Aug. 2</DATE> in <LOCATION>Buenos Aires</LOCATION>, said astronomer <PERSON>Brian Marsden</PERSON>, the bureau's
director.;   Hidden in <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s rings; <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s newest moon, which the group
named Pan, was discovered hidden among the planet's rings by <PERSON>Mark Showalter</PERSON>, a
scientist at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ames Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Mountain View.</LOCATION>;   <PERSON>Showalter</PERSON> found
the 12-mile-wide moon <DATE>July 2, 1990</DATE>, when he was analyzing pictures of <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>
taken by Voyagers 1 and 2 when the twin spacecraft explored the planet in <DATE>1980</DATE>
and <DATE>1981.</DATE>;   Voyagers 1 and 2, laden with TV cameras and instruments, were
launched from <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE>. They visited <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>. Voyager 2
explored Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE> and <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> in <DATE>1989.</DATE>;   The two spacecraft discovered
at least 23 moons during their <MONEY>$865 million mission.</MONEY>;   <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> now has eight
known moons. Two were discovered from Earth-based telescopes. One, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>,
named for a son of <LOCATION>Poseidon</LOCATION>, is <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s largest satellite, measuring 1,680
miles wide, and was discovered in <DATE>1846</DATE>. The other, <LOCATION>Nereid</LOCATION>, is 210 miles wide
and was discovered in <DATE>1949</DATE>. Naiad, the smallest of the newly discovered moons,
is 35 miles wide.;   <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> now has 18 known moons, 11 of which were
discovered by telescopes on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Los Angeles  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910928  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  391  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, September 28, 1991
00272014,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-7714</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CEPANACVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920516
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 MAY 92 / Hannibal-style habits / Consider the evidence of human
sacrifice
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By GERALD CADOGAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
IS HUMAN sacrifice a nasty habit or is it deeply rooted in tradition? The
truth is: a bit of both, and archaeology keeps finding new and startling
evidence of the practice where we least expect it. Recently I saw the latest
find, among the foundations of a new hotel at Amathus, near <LOCATION>Limassol</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>. The Phoenicians of <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> probably introduced the practice: they
had a long history of human sacrifice, and were a power in <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>. But other
stories come to mind, from <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, from <PERSON>Abraham</PERSON> and <PERSON>Isaac</PERSON>, and that of the
<PERSON>Lindow Man</PERSON>, a well-manicured, upper-class 25-year old who was hit on the
head, garroted and had his throat cut before he was placed in a marsh in
<LOCATION>Cheshire</LOCATION> as an offering to the Celtic water god. The custom of offering
young humans to a god as gifts is old and universal, but not frequent. It
was best to give one's own child, preferably a first-born male; if he was
not available, a daughter would do, or prisoners of war. In Greek stories
the habit is not common. It was seen as something reprehensible that created
blood pollution, but at times could not be avoided. The tragedians made good
use of it. When the gods deny the Greeks a fair wind to sail to <ORGANIZATION>Troy</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Agamemnon</LOCATION>, their leader, has to sacrifice his daughter Iphigeneia. His wife
<LOCATION>Clytemnestra</LOCATION> is furious and has 10 years at home during the siege of Troy in
which to nurture her bitterness. When Agamemnon comes home she hurls snide
fury at him, encourages him into a hot bath and stabs him. The next step is
for their son Orestes to kill his mother, for which he is condemned to
wander in exile, until he reaches the <LOCATION>Crimea</LOCATION> where he is reunited with his
sister Iphigeneia, and the pollution ends.
It is difficult to find examples of human sacrifice from the 5th century BC
when the tragedians were writing about it. But 800 to 1,000 years earlier,
in the Bronze Age, it was certainly happening. Children were buried under
thresholds, presumably as an offering of first fruits for the prosperity of
house and home. At <LOCATION>Knossos</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Crete</LOCATION> childrens' bones were found a few years
ago with butchery cuts as on animal bones. They are probably the left-overs
of cannibalism, perhaps a ritual to avert a disaster.
The leading sacrificers of the ancient world were the Phoenicians, who
traded throughout the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> and founded colonies in <LOCATION>Sicily</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sardinia</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION>. At their settlement at <LOCATION>Carthage</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Tunisia</LOCATION> - <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>'s great
enemy - you can see the place of sacrifice, called a tophet, by the harbour.
Here thousands of vases were found, all of the same type, containing burnt
childrens' bones and animal or bird bones. Stones mark the sacrifices.
The victims were placed in the hands of a bronze statue, wrote <PERSON>Diodorus
Siculus</PERSON>, and then dropped into the flames. Relations were forbidden to weep,
perhaps because tears diminished the sacrifice or perhaps rather that they
were inappropriate when it led to a desirable end: the children's
deification. The young blood rejuvenated the god and bound him to the person
who had offered it.
But in 310 BC, after Agathocles of <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION> defeated them, the Carthaginians
thought they had offended the gods by replacing nobles' children as victims
with children of low birth. When to make amends they decided to offer 200 of
the best, so many noble parents volunteered their young that they had 300 to
choose from. They also sacrificed prisoners of war, 3,000 of them after they
captured Himera in <LOCATION>Sicily</LOCATION> in 409, and continued these gruesome habits for
centuries, until the Romans defeated them and stopped the bloody business.
The newly-discovered tophet in <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> is on the Phoenicians' route to their
western settlements. Now cleared by archaeologists, it looked like a disused
rabbit warren when I saw it last month. Like <LOCATION>Carthage</LOCATION>, it is by the sea. A
slope runs up from the beach and vanishes beneath the concrete of what will
soon be bedrooms in the Four Seasons Hotel. Five hundred pots were found, as
at other tophets all of the same shape. Originally there would have been
many more.
Children, animals and birds burnt in tophets give poignancy to the story of
Abraham and <PERSON>Isaac</PERSON>.
When they reach the high place on the mountain, <PERSON>Isaac</PERSON>, carrying the wood for
his own pyre, asks: 'Where is the lamb for a burnt offering?'. And at the
last moment when <PERSON>Abraham</PERSON> has the knife in his hand, God stops him. He may
substitute a ram, a male sheep, caught in a nearby thicket.
The tale leads straight to the theology of the sacrifice of Jesus, God's
only son and also the lamb of God.
If you have booked into the hotel at Amathus and have a room on the beach,
sweet dreams, and sleep well.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page IX
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900906-0128
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900906-0128.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf:
   Singing the Rage of Achilles
   ----
   By Donald Lyons
</HL>
<DATE>
09/06/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   "Never forget -- we all sailed here with God," says a
Greek leader trying to pep up the spirits of the huge armada
beached at Asian Troy for 10 years to repossess Helen. He's
right: Troy is doomed.
   Homer's "Iliad" (c. 700 B.C.) tells of a few decisive but
not final incidents in this 10th year. As the epic opens with
its rousing invocation: "Rage-Goddess, sing the rage of
Peleus's son Achilles," the fierce ace of the Greek army is
leaving the fighting to sulk in his tent. It is Achilles's
tantrum that forms the epic's heart. When he returns, it is
to avenge the death of his friend, Patroclus, killed by
Hector, the noblest of the Trojans. Achilles's rampage
embroils in blood the very elements and highest gods, only to
subside in two astonishingly courteous ceremonies:
</LP>
<TEXT>
   We read how a civil and amused Achilles presides over
Greek funeral athletics in <LOCATION>Patroclus</LOCATION>'s honor. We read with
even more amazement of the meeting between Achilles and
<PERSON>Priam</PERSON>, the father of the murdered <PERSON>Hector</PERSON>, who begs him to
return his son's corpse: "I have endured what no one on earth
has ever done before  -- /I put to my lips the hands of the
man who killed my son." Gently, Achilles consents. He knows
that it is his turn to die next.
   It is the cruelest and the tenderest, the least humane and
the most profound of war stories. "War and Peace" alone has
the scope of the "Iliad," along with its frightening
altitude, as if told from a sheer height above a humanity
that is viewed, to use <ORGANIZATION>Eliot</ORGANIZATION>'s words, as "some infinitely
gentle/infinitely suffering thing."
   <PERSON>Robert Fagles</PERSON>, chairman of comparative literature at
<LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION> and distinguished translator of Aeschylus and
Sophocles, now has a go at this greatest of Greek poems
(introduction and notes by <PERSON>Bernard Knox</PERSON>, Viking, 683 pages,
<MONEY>$35</MONEY>). How does he do? Very well indeed. I noted with surprise
that <PERSON>Richmond Lattimore</PERSON>'s "Iliad," the first good modern
Englishing, appeared as long ago as <DATE>1951</DATE>. Lattimore stressed
the Greek's alienness and hieratic, formulaic stiffness as he
marched with unsmiling literalness and monotony in a
loose-fitting, six-beat, dactylic armor. Lattimore wrote: "I
put my lips to the hands of the man who has killed my
children." Notice how <PERSON>Mr. Fagles</PERSON>'s words, which are in fact
closer to the Greek, have the rhythm of English verse.
   Between <PERSON>Lattimore</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Fagles</PERSON> came <PERSON>Robert Fitzgerald</PERSON>,
who crucially returned to a five-beat, iambic meter, the
natural and native English beat. <PERSON>Mr. Fagles</PERSON> keeps the basic
five-beat iambic line but lets in air and space by often
expanding to six beats (like Alexander Pope before him) and
contracting to three. His verse units breathe and the
reader's eye is not confronted with 700 pages of lock-step
line-lengths.
   His happiest idiom is hard contemporary American: ". . .
look out/a heavy wave of ruin's about to break your neck."
"But night came in too soon. That's what saved them." "You've
only plunged him deeper in his pride." "My comrade's death
has cut me to the quick." "The gods are hard to handle --
/when they come blazing forth in their true power." ". . .
the wild mountain hawk, the quickest thing on wings."
   A lot of the "Iliad" is speech-war conferences, frontline
challenges and ripostes -- <PERSON>Mr. Fagles</PERSON>'s purified
colloquialism is ideal here. And he does bloody action
clearly: ". . . ramming the spearhead square between his
teeth so hard/he hooked him by that spearhead over the
chariot-rail/hoisted, dragged the Trojan out as an angler
perched/on a jutting rock ledge drags some fish from the
sea."
   He offers simplicity ("the funeral fires sank low, the
flames died down"). He offers pathos ("the boy goes up to his
father's old companions,/tugging at one man's cloak,
another's tunic,/and some will pity him, true,/and one will
give him a little cup to drink,/enough to wet his lips, not
quench his thirst"). And provides simile's energy ("She
{<ORGANIZATION>Athena</ORGANIZATION>} put fresh strength in his back, <DATE>spring</DATE> in his
knees/and filled his heart with the horsefly's raw
daring-/brush it away from a man's flesh and back it
comes,/biting, attacking, crazed for sweet human blood").
   Compare <PERSON>Mr. Lattimore</PERSON>'s unmusical "haul off the body and
give it to the dogs of Troy" with <PERSON>Mr. Fagles</PERSON>'s "drag the
trunk away to glut the dogs of Troy." The dance of ds, rs, ts
and gs in the latter shows a poet at work, and at work in a
specifically English-language tradition.
   We can hear <PERSON>Milton</PERSON> in <PERSON>Mr. Fagles</PERSON>'s "our great work lies
all before us, still to do," <PERSON>Keats</PERSON> in his "all your deathless
ease," Whitman in his "You are goddesses, you are there, you
know all things," and Shakespeare everywhere. And we also can
hear Ali in the words of the boxer Epeus, "I am the
greatest]" That's as accurate as and livelier than <PERSON>Mr.
Lattimore</PERSON>'s "I claim I am the champion" or <PERSON>Mr. Fitzgerald</PERSON>'s
"I'm best, I don't mind saying" -- neither of which sounds
like anything a boxer might conceivably utter.
   Pope remains the greatest translator (for one thing, he
can handle the divine comedy in Homer better than anyone
today), but <PERSON>Mr. Fagles</PERSON> can claim to be the 20th-century
champion.
   Hint to first-time readers: Read the "spine" books of the
narrative (1, 9, 16, 18, 22, 24) first; get an overall feel
for the big things; then go back and plunge in with a relaxed
sense of who are the stars and who the extras; play at being
a god.
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Lyons</PERSON> writes for Film Comment and the New Criterion.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ901227-0090
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
901227-0090.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS --
   Troy Today: The Ruins Are Real, the Horse Isn't
   ----
   By Jim Ottaway Jr.
</HL>
<DATE>
12/27/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A10
</SO>
<LP>
   One hundred years after the death of Heinrich Schliemann,
another German archaeologist is leading an international team
of 50 archaeologists, scientists and historians in a new
campaign to answer the fascinating questions raised by
Schliemann at Troy. He became famous as the man who
discovered and excavated the Homeric cities of Troy and
Mycenae between 1870 and his death in December 1890, and
became the father of Aegean prehistoric archaeology.
   In this anniversary year, Prof. Manfred Korfmann of
Tubingen University in West Germany, who is 48 years old, as
was Schliemann when he started digging at Troy in 1870, has a
Turkish permit to excavate the many levels of habitation at
Troy that span nine major periods carbon-dated back to about
3000 B.C. This fabled fortress lies six hours southwest of
Istanbul by bus or car at the southern entrance to the
Dardanelles on the Aegean coast of northwest Turkey.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Under <PERSON>Mr. Korfmann</PERSON>'s direction, German and Turkish
archaeologists are concentrating on Bronze Age remains of the
walled citadel of Troy from about 3000 B.C. to <DATE>1000</DATE> B.C.
(Troy I through VII). A team of American archaeologists led
by <PERSON>Stella Miller-Collett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Brian Rose</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Cincinnati</ORGANIZATION> are digging outside the walls for remains of
classical and Hellenistic Greek reoccupation of <LOCATION>Ilion</LOCATION> from
about 700 B.C. to 85 B.C. (Troy VIII), and Roman imperial
rebuilding of <LOCATION>Ilion</LOCATION> from 85 B.C. to 500 A.D. (Troy IX). There
are also British, Austrian, Mexican and Danish scientists and
scholars working at Troy.
   In addition to the traditional archaeologists and ancient
historians, there are geologists and chemists core-drilling
in the plains and bays below Troy to map the ancient contours
of the coastline; there are geologists and physicists with
magnetometers mapping the streets and walls of the
unexcavated city outside the citadel of Troy; and there are
scientists using thermoluminescence to analyze the dates and
the chemical content of clay pottery, and the nature of food
or wine or oils stored in that pottery.
   There are paleozoologists studying bones found at Troy,
man and mammal; physical anthropologists studying human
skeletons; numismatists looking at coins; epigraphers
studying inscriptions; architectural historians drawing maps
of ancient buildings and streets; and computer experts trying
to organize all this new information in a computerized data
bank.
   I visited Troy just before the <DATE>third year</DATE> of current
excavations got under way in <DATE>June</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr. Korfmann</PERSON>, who got
hooked on archaeology during a postgraduate motorcycle tour
of the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION>, enthusiastically explained some of the
old controversies he and his colleagues hope to find
archaeological evidence for or against.
   1. Is Homer's eighth century B.C. epic poem about a
10-year war between Mycenaean Greeks and Trojans a
magnificent myth, or is it based on historical events of the
Bronze Age 13th century <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>? There is considerable
archaeological evidence for Mycenaean Greek activities and
some settlements on the Aegean coast of <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION> in the 15th to
13th centuries <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>, but no proof that the Trojan War of the
Iliad took place or ended with the destruction of Troy. The
exact date is even more elusive.
   2. Is Homer a historical person? Did he create the 24
books of the Iliad and the Odyssey himself, or collect and
recite stories told by traveling poets for 500 years before?
Ancient Greeks and Romans believed in the essential historic
truth of Homer's story of the Greek siege and destruction of
Troy in the <LOCATION>Iliad</LOCATION>; and the founding of <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Aeneas</PERSON>, one of
the few surviving nobles of Troy, as told by <PERSON>Virgil</PERSON> in the
<LOCATION>Aeneid</LOCATION>. These stories were part of a classical education in
antiquity. In <DATE>fifth century</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>B.C. Greece</ORGANIZATION> and later in
antiquity, Homer was believed to be a blind Ionian poet,
perhaps from <LOCATION>Smyrna</LOCATION> or the Island of Chios, who composed the
story of the Iliad in about 730 B.C. and the Odyssey later,
around 700 B.C. Today, he is considered part of an oral
tradition of many poets reciting from memory the first great
epic of Western literature.
   3. Is the high mound of Hissarlik on the fertile plains
south of the modern Turkish town of Canakkale the site of the
"horserich," "windy" Troy described by Homer? Most scholars
think it must be Troy because it fits Homer's description
well and has so many stratified levels of habitation and
pottery. In antiquity Troy must have been 66 feet high from
bedrock -- "steepwalled" to be sure. This <DATE>summer</DATE>, the
German-Turkish team excavated two palatial buildings of Troy
II -- about <DATE>2500</DATE> B.C. -- built of two-foot-long mud bricks
and large square wooden beams. Atop the citadel of <ORGANIZATION>Troy</ORGANIZATION>, they
suggest this was an important power center more than 1,000
years before the Mycenaeans came from <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>.
   4. Where did the fabled 1,030 ships of the Greek fleet led
by Agamemnon of <LOCATION>Mycenae</LOCATION> land when they began the siege of
Troy, if they did what Homer tells us in the <LOCATION>Iliad</LOCATION>? <PERSON>Mr.
Korfmann</PERSON>'s excavations from <DATE>1982</DATE> to <DATE>1987</DATE> around <LOCATION>Besik Bay</LOCATION> on
the Aegean coast southwest of Troy have convinced many
scholars that the Greek fleet would have drawn up its ships
on the flat, sandy beaches of what was in the <DATE>13th century</DATE>
B.C. a much deeper bay, closer to the fortress of Troy, about
3.4 miles away. The previous assumption was that the Greek
fleet of the Iliad landed at the mouth of the <LOCATION>Skamander River</LOCATION>
directly north of Troy, inside the southeast entrance to the
Dardanelles in what was a bay with a river <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr.
Korfmann</PERSON> argues persuasively that the strong five-knot
southward current of Black Sea water funneling through the
mouth of the Dardanelles near Troy, and the steady northwest
winds averaging 10 miles an hour down the straits of the
Dardanelles, would have made it very difficult for Mycenaean
Greek ships to sail up into the Dardanelles to the mouth of
the Skamander. They were fitted only with oars and sails and
had no deep keels needed to sail against the wind.
   5. How extensive were the streets, houses, shops and
temples of the <LOCATION>Lower City</LOCATION> outside the walls of Troy in the
<DATE>13th century B.C.</DATE>, at the time of the Trojan War (the
so-called late Troy VI and VII)? How large was the new city
of <LOCATION>Ilion</LOCATION>, built and inhabited from the 12th to eighth
centuries <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>, through the Dark Ages to the Archaic Period
around 700 B.C. (Troy VIII)? And how much more prosperous did
<LOCATION>Ilion</LOCATION> become as a trading center and sacred site under the
patronage of Romans from 85 B.C. to 500 A.D. (Troy IX)?
   American classical archaeologists led by <PERSON>Ms.
Miller-Collett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Rose</PERSON> are exploring the fields south of
the citadel of Troy with magnetometric sounding and mapping,
and digging test trenches that are revealing a larger
settlement in later Greek and Roman times than was previously
suspected. This is breaking new ground, raising new questions
and hopes for answers to some of the riddles of Troy. This
<DATE>summer</DATE>, <PERSON>Ms. Miller-Collett</PERSON> cleared a sanctuary in the <LOCATION>Lower
City</LOCATION> with altars showing more religious activity and
continuous habitation from <DATE>1000</DATE> B.C. to the birth of Christ
than was previously imagined. <PERSON>Mr. Rose</PERSON> uncovered part of a
large Roman villa or glass factory of the <DATE>fourth century</DATE> A.D.
with painted walls, colored marble floors and a small marble
head of the god of health, Asclepius.
   Beyond the digging and publishing of their discoveries in
a new journal, <PERSON>Studia Troica</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Troy Commission</ORGANIZATION> of scholars
is making this celebrated site safe from tourist destruction
but also making it accessible to the 300,000 annual visitors.
New walking paths have been built through the site, and a
tourist information center with wall posters explaining the
history of Troy was opened to the public this <DATE>summer</DATE>.
Information signs throughout the site explain what you are
looking at each step of your way around the acropolis of
Troy. The biggest surprise for a first-time visitor to <ORGANIZATION>Troy</ORGANIZATION>
is a huge 60-foot-high dark wooden "Trojan Horse" at the
entrance, so big you can climb a ladder into the horse's
belly and imagine that you are Odysseus or one of his chosen
band waiting for the doomed defenders of Troy to drag your
horse into the citadel, where the Trojans were celebrating
false victory.
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Ottaway</PERSON> is a trustee of the <ORGANIZATION>American School of
Classical Studies</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION> and a senior vice president of
<ORGANIZATION>Dow Jones &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910305-0125
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910305-0125.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   The Gallery: An Intimate Look at Ancient Greece
   ----
   By Pamela Macleod Daigle
</HL>
<DATE>
03/05/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A14
</SO>
<LP>
   New Paltz, N.Y. -- They are the denizens of ancient Greece
in the years following the death of Alexander the Great:
elegantly draped and coiffed women, a staid young soldier in
short tunic and thick-rimmed hat, a pair of young women
playing a jacks-like game of "knucklebones," two cherubic
boys gleefully staging a cockfight, a sagging old nurse
cradling her infant charge, a dancing dwarf.
   Meet these people -- or rather miniature clay depictions
of them -- in an exquisite exhibition mounted by the College
Art Gallery at the State University of New York campus here.
It's up until March 15, and then at Harvard's Arthur M.
Sackler Museum from May 26 through July 28.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The 52 works in this small but ambitious show, titled "The
Coroplast's Art: Greek Terracottas of the Hellenistic World,"
show ancient <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> in a more intimate light than those
familiar monumental sculptures of Zeus and Aphrodite in
marble. The terracottas give us a glimpse of the life of the
common people -- their clothing, religious beliefs,
amusements, and even the diseases they fell prey to.
   During the Hellenistic period (323 B.C. to 31 B.C.), Greek
civilization dominated the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> basin north and
south. Trade boomed, as did royal and private patronage of
the arts. But the vastness of <ORGANIZATION>Alexander</ORGANIZATION>'s empire, and then
its collapse after his death, "fostered a feeling of
smallness and inconsequence for individuals," curator <PERSON>Jaimee
P. Uhlenbrock</PERSON> writes in the introduction to the show's
catalog.
   Sculptors responded, she explains, by emphasizing everyday
human experiences and emotions, "in contrast to the
extraordinary behavior of gods and heroes." The resulting
figurines, from a few inches to a couple of feet in height,
became extremely popular. They were offered to the deities at
temples and in home sanctuaries and were placed in graves to
scare away evil spirits, pay tribute to a particular god or
maybe just to keep the deceased company on his or her trip
into the afterlife. They also may have been used for purely
decorative purposes in the home, says <PERSON>Ms. Uhlenbrock</PERSON>, an
associate professor of classical art and archaeology here.
She organized the show in honor of the <DATE>90th birthday</DATE> of
<PERSON>Dorothy Burr Thompson</PERSON>, who pioneered the study of these
sculptures.
   The figurines were mass-produced by artists called
coroplasts, who were influenced by the talented bronze and
silver craftsmen and potters they worked alongside. To make a
figurine, the coroplast pressed moist clay into a pair of
molds, one for the front of the figurine, one for the back.
He used as many as 14 accessory molds depending on the
complexity of the statue. After the various pieces were
assembled, the statue was fired in a kiln, coated with gypsum
and painted.
   Variations in texture and clay color (cream to peach to
grayish brown) help pinpoint where the figurines were made.
The show focuses on six centers: <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>, Tanagra and <LOCATION>Corinth</LOCATION>
on the Greek mainland; <LOCATION>Myrina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Smyrna</LOCATION> on the <ORGANIZATION>coast of Asia
Minor</ORGANIZATION> (now <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>); and Taras in southern <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.
   The most well-known figurines are those in the Tanagra
style (which actually originated in <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>), heavily draped
women in serene standing or seated positions. Some can be
identified as women of means by their "melon" hairdo, a
series of twists or braids brought into a large bun at the
back of the head.
   Also typical of the Greek mainland are "personality
figures" -- dwarfs, aged nurses and contemplative old men.
Theatrical motifs were common as well: One statue of a boy
carrying a mask probably is a participant in a dramatic
festival in honor of the god Dionysus. Though the mask is
broken off at the bottom, we can still see that one eyebrow
is raised, the other relaxed. <PERSON>Ms. Uhlenbrock</PERSON> points out that
this was a common stage convention: The actor evinced a
particular mood by turning the appropriate side of the mask
toward the audience.
   Another delightful theatrical figurine from this region
shows an actor wearing the mask of a courtesan, so identified
by its flamelike "lampadion" (little torch) hairstyle. The
mouth of the mask is open and the tongue sticks out, possibly
indicating that this was a speaking part. A similar miniature
mask comes from <LOCATION>Myrina</LOCATION>, across the <ORGANIZATION>Aegean Sea</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> Minor.
It was probably sold at souvenir stalls near the theater; a
large loop at the top would allow it to be worn as a pendant.
   In the figurines from <LOCATION>Asia Minor</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ms. Uhlenbrock</PERSON> sees "a
culmination of fantasy and sensuality." Witness a beautiful
flying <ORGANIZATION>Nike</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>Myrina</LOCATION>, circa 180 <LOCATION>B.C</LOCATION>. This winged goddess
of victory wears a transparent, high-belted gown, her right
breast and left leg exposed. She is attributed to ananonymous
crafts man known as the coroplast of the victories, and was
meant to be suspended from the ceiling. "Notice the delicacy
of the work," says <PERSON>Ms. Thompson</PERSON>. "The Greeks had a wonderful
sense of restraint. They didn't overdo. Every little detail
was thoughtfully and delicately worked out."
   Not only did the coroplasts of <LOCATION>Myrina</LOCATION> give us
less-inhibited depictions of the female body, their
counterparts in nearby <LOCATION>Smyrna</LOCATION> began to sculpt -- often with
amazing clinical accuracy -- images of the physically
deformed. Some scholars hypothesize such people may have
journeyed to a medical college at <LOCATION>Smyrna</LOCATION> for treatment, where
the coroplasts could have seen them in the streets begging or
performing. <PERSON>Ms. Uhlenbrock</PERSON>'s favorite work falls in this cate
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861222-0144 </DOCNO>
<HL> If He Existed at All,
Nicholas of Myra
Was the First Santa
---
He Is Also the Patron Saint
Of Thieves and Lawyers;
The St. Nick Symposiums
---
By Philip Revzin
<DD> 12/22/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> DEMRE, Turkey  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The closest thing there is to a spiritual heir of <ORGANIZATION>St. Nicholas</ORGANIZATION> has no reindeer, no elves, doesn't live at the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION>, doesn't climb down chimneys bearing gifts on <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION> and doesn't say ho! ho! ho! 

   "Fine, fine, fine," says <PERSON>His Excellency Chrysostomos</PERSON>, the Metropolitan of the <ORGANIZATION>Holy See of Myra</ORGANIZATION>, when introduced to visitors outside the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Claus Church</ORGANIZATION> here. 
The bishop normally lives in <LOCATION>Istanbul</LOCATION>, which he would rather call <LOCATION>Constantinople</LOCATION>, where he helps run the <ORGANIZATION>Greek Orthodox Church</ORGANIZATION>. 
He has <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION>'s girth, but his red and gold vestment has no fur trim, and he doesn't wear a hat. 
With his neatly trimmed white goatee, he looks more like Col. <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> than <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION>. 

   The bishop sweeps up the steps behind the makeshift altar table to a stone pedestal in the nave of the church, which except for this special occasion is now just a museum. 
A six-member Greek chorus chants. 
With a golden staff in his left hand, he conducts a two-hour liturgical service. 

   "You could say I am the apostolic successor to <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON>," says the bishop of <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>, as he changes back into his black three-piece suit. 
"All of the <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> stories, well, they all start from here." 

   But for the twists of history, <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> might well speak Turkish, ride a camel, dress for the warm winter sun, bear gifts of oranges and tomatoes, and do his thing on <DATE>Dec. 5</DATE>, instead of <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION>. 

   According to the story, <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> was a genuine historical figure -- the first bishop of Myra -- born in the now-vanished town of <LOCATION>Patara</LOCATION>. 
The remains of <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>, a well-preserved amphitheater, are about 60 miles west of <LOCATION>Antalya</LOCATION> on the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> coast of <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>. 
As the story goes, <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> was known far and wide for his piety and charity, and because <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> was a thriving port town, he was considered the protector of sailors. 

   Turkish scholars say he was killed around A.D. 245, and after his martyrdom, on <DATE>Dec. 6</DATE>, tales of his good deeds lived on. 
Miracles were attributed to his intercession, and he was eventually sainted. 
Greek scholars say that he lived still later; indeed, they say he attended the first <ORGANIZATION>Ecumenical Council</ORGANIZATION> in 325, where his advice on organizing the church was warmly received. 

   In any event, his fame was so great that when the Italian branch of the Catholic church in the <DATE>11th century</DATE> began a drive to bring the remains of the most famous saints back to <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, thieves stole most of <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON>'s bones from the church tomb here and took them to <ORGANIZATION>Bari</ORGANIZATION>, a town on the <LOCATION>Adriatic Sea</LOCATION> in southern <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>. 
The bones have lain there since <DATE>1087</DATE>. 
From <ORGANIZATION>Bari</ORGANIZATION>, the cult of the patron saint of sailors spread north to other port towns. 

   When it got far enough north, <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> was abbreviated to <LOCATION>Claus</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>St. Nick</ORGANIZATION> became <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION>. 
All the stuff about reindeer, elves and the toyshop at the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION> was embroidered to fit local conditions and the exigencies of commerce. 
Santa Claus also came to be known as Father Christmas and, in <LOCATION>Moslem Turkey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Noel Baba</LOCATION>. 

   The gift-giving stories are strongest in Protestant countries, where saints aren't venerated. 
In <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> comes by boat from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Dec. 5</DATE>, in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> by sleigh out of the snowy woods on <DATE>Dec. 24</DATE>. 
Northern European Catholics began giving gifts on Christmas Day to show thanks to God, church scholars say, but the tradition has been swamped by that of <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> within the past few generations. 
Many Orthodox Greeks still exchange gifts on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>, the feast day of <LOCATION>St. Basil</LOCATION>; in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, gifts are given on Epiphany, <DATE>Jan. 6</DATE>, by the Three Wise Men. 

   The roots of the down-the-chimney story, popular in <LOCATION>northern Europe</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, may lie in one of the many tales told of the original <ORGANIZATION>St. Nicholas of Myra</ORGANIZATION>: 

   One day three maidens of <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> went to the bishop, saying that unless they could find dowries enabling them to marry, they would be sold into prostitution. 
The bishop, who came from a wealthy family, raised the money, and in the middle of the night threw a sack of gold through the open window of each one's house, to be found the next morning, thus saving the girls. 

   (This, incidentally, is said to be why the pawnbroker's symbol is three gold balls. 
St. <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> is not just the protector of sailors; he is also the patron of moneylenders, the patron of miners, the erstwhile patron saint of <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>, and the patron of thieves and lawyers.) 

   One thing that is known for sure is that virtually nothing is known for sure about the original <ORGANIZATION>Nicholas of Myra</ORGANIZATION>. 
There are no documents in which any such bishop is named and no records of the first <ORGANIZATION>Ecumenical Council</ORGANIZATION>. 
"He may or may not have existed," says <PERSON>Angela C. Hero</PERSON>, a professor of Byzantine history at <ORGANIZATION>Queens College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
Some scholars say that there definitely was a <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> who was a bishop of a town (not Myra) in <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION> but that he was never sainted. 

   This dearth of proof has led to any number of religious and historical spats. 
Many have been aired at the annual St. <PERSON>Nicholas Symposiums</PERSON> organized here for the past four years by the <ORGANIZATION>Greek Orthodox Church</ORGANIZATION>. 
The basic question: Was he or wasn't he? 

   "I'm absolutely certain that there was a bishop of <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> named <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> who was renowned for his charity," says <PERSON>Ernst Suttner</PERSON>, a professor of theology at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Vienna</ORGANIZATION>. 
"I can show you no proof, but for a cult and legend to have gone so deep into the world's consciousness, there must have been something at the start. 
From nothing, you get nothing." 

   Turkish scholars say that there was something here even before <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Enis Erdem Ece of Akdeniz University</ORGANIZATION> says the <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> legends grew from the myth of Apollo, who was also said to have been born in <LOCATION>Patara</LOCATION> and who was the protector of youth. 
Others say <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> was the Christian successor to <LOCATION>Poseidon</LOCATION>, god of the sea. 

   This is not pleasing to the Christians. 
"Nonsense," Prof. <PERSON>Suttner</PERSON> calls it. 
"You don't need old gods to explain <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON>. 
Myra is on the sea, so he became associated with the sea." 

   <PERSON>Fahri Isik</PERSON>, a professor of archaeology at <ORGANIZATION>Erzurum Ataturk University</ORGANIZATION>, offers different proof. 
He says there had to have been a famous personality named <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> before the <DATE>fifth century</DATE> "because, all of a sudden, people started naming their children <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON>." 
The Western names <PERSON>Nichols</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nicholson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Colson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> all derive from <PERSON>Nicholas of Myra</PERSON>, the professor adds. 

   Whatever the truth, today's tourist-conscious Turks have carefully preserved the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Claus Church</ORGANIZATION> here, and recently they erected in the gardens a statue of a hirsute, Western-style Santa (with a fur-trimmed suit and a sack over his shoulder) surrounded by children. 
The <PERSON>Noel Baba</PERSON> tea garden across the street caters to tourists all year long. 
The annual symposium this year attracted more than 200 people. 

   This year the Turks even granted the Greeks a major concession by allowing the religious Mass in the museum, the first time a <ORGANIZATION>Greek Orthodox Mass</ORGANIZATION> has been celebrated here since the <DATE>1922</DATE> "exchange of populations" between <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>. 

   To the townspeople of nearby <LOCATION>Demre</LOCATION>, most of whom grow oranges, lemons or tomatoes, the veneration shown by these pilgrims is inexplicable. 
Only a few locals stare at the bearded clergymen and the busloads of tourists. 
Rifle-toting soldiers stand in the surrounding orange groves, protecting the visitors. 
In the middle of the service, the call to prayer from the mosque next door threatens to drown out the Greek chants. 

   To Bishop <PERSON>Chrysostomos</PERSON>, the heir of <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON>, the melange of cultures and commerce is all to the good. 
"The message of Nicholas -- charity and love -- is universal," he tells the congregation. 
"<PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON> now belongs to the world." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062589-0049 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 74411 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 25, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Book Review; Page 7; Book Review Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1230 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
A GUIDE TO THE CLASSICS; 
</P>
<P>
THE OXFORD COMPANION TO CLASSICAL LITERATURE SECOND EDITION EDITED BY M.C. 
HOWATSON (OXFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS: $39.95; 605 PP., CHRONOLOGICAL TABLE, MAPS; 
0-19-866121-5) 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Nicholas Goodhue, Goodhue is the author of several publications in the field 
of classical archeology. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A revised edition of Sir <PERSON>Paul Harvey</PERSON>'s "Oxford Companion to Classical 
Literature," originally published in <DATE>1937</DATE>, has long been overdue. The task of 
revision has been admirably carried out by <PERSON>Margaret Howatson</PERSON> in this second 
edition. The object aimed at is unchanged: to provide "a handbook of 
information for readers of the literatures of <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, and of modern 
works which (touch) upon the classical world" (<ORGANIZATION>Howatson</ORGANIZATION>'s preface). But to 
attain this object in <DATE>1989</DATE> requires taking account not only of the many new 
discoveries and reappraisals that have been made in the <DATE>last half-century</DATE> but 
also of the fact that the reader of today cannot be presumed to have the 
background of knowledge of the classical world that could be taken for granted 
in the reader of <DATE>1937</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Accordingly, in her revision of <LOCATION>Harvey</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Howatson</PERSON> not only has incorporated the 
archeological and other findings that have furthered and in some cases 
substantially altered our understanding of certain aspects of classical 
civilization, but also has added new articles and expanded others so as to make 
the book suitable "for any reader who is curious to find out about the 
classical world." All Greek and Latin quotations, which the reader of <DATE>1937</DATE> was 
expected to be able to read unassisted, are now accompanied by English 
translations. 
</P>
<P>
Like all the <ORGANIZATION>Oxford</ORGANIZATION> "Companions," this one is in dictionary format, consisting 
of alphabetically arranged articles of widely varying length and generality, 
some of them dealing with particular names and terms in a few lines, others 
taking up several pages to treat broad subjects such as philosophy, religion, 
and education. Each of the classical authors is the subject of an article under 
the name of that author that provides a general account of the author's works 
and his or her place in the literary and historical scene; important individual 
works are summarized and discussed in separate entries under the title of the 
work. Literary forms are covered under such headwords as epic, tragedy, comedy, 
historiography, oratory, and lyric poetry. The reader curious to know why the 
term classical often means "ancient Greek and Roman" (as in the title of this 
book) will find an explanation under "classic (classics, classical)." There are 
major articles on <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, subdivided into sections on topography, 
history, administration, and economy. Sculpture, architecture, and painting are 
discussed under those words as well as in many related articles on particular 
artists, monuments, and genres (extensive cross-referencing helps the reader to 
find all that is relevant to the subject of interest). 
</P>
<P>
New articles added by <PERSON>Howatson</PERSON> include "astronomy," "Christianity in the Roman 
world," "gods" (dealing with the canonical 12 gods of the Greek pantheon), 
"homosexuality," "polis" (in which the meaning of <ORGANIZATION>Aristotle</ORGANIZATION>'s statement that 
"man is a political animal" is explained), "postal service," and numerous 
others. Other articles have been substantially enlarged. The entries that 
summarize individual books, poems, and plays are still <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON>'s (in the main), 
but in general very little has been left unchanged. 
</P>
<P>
The new "Companion" seems thoroughly up to date. Full account is taken of the 
decipherment in <DATE>1952</DATE> of the script known as Linear B and of the implications of 
that decipherment for our knowledge of early Greek civilization: Not only is 
there a new article "Linear A and B," but references to the decipherment have 
been added elsewhere as appropriate (in the articles on <LOCATION>Crete</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, and 
<LOCATION>Mycenae</LOCATION>, among others). The "Riace Bronzes," two bronze statues recovered from 
the sea off <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> in <DATE>1972</DATE>, are mentioned in "sculpture." The discovery of the 
tomb of <LOCATION>Philip of Macedon</LOCATION> at <LOCATION>Vergina</LOCATION> is discussed. Note is taken of the fact 
that <PERSON>Aeschylus</PERSON>' "The Suppliants," previously believed to be his earliest extant 
play, has been found to be of later date; the increasingly prevalent view that 
the "Prometheus Bound" is not by <ORGANIZATION>Aeschylus</ORGANIZATION> is referred to as well. A new entry 
is devoted to Menander's comedy "Dyscolus," which was found on papyri published 
in <DATE>1959</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
It is appropriate that a handbook to classical literature intended for the 
general reader should pay particular attention to matters that may be the 
subject of popular misconception. For example, the image of the priestess of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Delphic Oracle</ORGANIZATION> as delivering her prophecies while seated over a chasm from 
which "mephitic vapors" arose has a long history, but <PERSON>Howatson</PERSON> rightly notes 
that there is no good archeological or literary evidence for either the chasm 
or the vapors. She could have added that the notion that the <ORGANIZATION>Oracle</ORGANIZATION>'s responses 
typically were equivocal or ambiguous (an idea so firmly rooted that among the 
senses of the English words Delphic and oracular listed in any dictionary one 
is likely to find something like obscure, ambiguous, enigmatic) is likewise not 
true of any of the Delphic pronouncements regarded as definitely authentic. 
Correcting <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON>, she explains that <ORGANIZATION>Pandora</ORGANIZATION>'s Box was actually a large jar 
(pithos) and became a box only in later accounts through confusion with another 
story (<ORGANIZATION>Cupid</ORGANIZATION> and Psyche). As with <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON>, she makes it express that Cleopatra 
was Greek by descent, not "Oriental" or "African." 
</P>
<P>
One common misconception not adequately dealt with by <PERSON>Howatson</PERSON> concerns the god 
Apollo: She has retained unchanged <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON>'s statement that <PERSON>Apollo</PERSON> was "the god 
of light, sometimes identified with the sun," but it has long been established 
that <PERSON>Apollo</PERSON> was not originally a light-god or a sun-god and that his 
identification with the sun was confined to the speculations of learned 
philosophers until the Hellenistic period at the earliest (<PERSON>Joseph Fontenrose</PERSON> 
has shown that not even in the words of <LOCATION>Ovid</LOCATION> and other Latin poets of his time 
is Apollo identified with the sun, as commonly supposed). Under "<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, 
Judgment of," <PERSON>Howatson</PERSON> retains <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON>'s view that the Judgment is not mentioned 
by Homer, but this view is based on the assumption that lines 25-30 of book 24 
of the Iliad are not genuine, an assumption not now generally shared (I owe 
this observation to Prof. <PERSON>Steven Lattimore</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>). 
</P>
<P>
The preface states that "some guidance is given in the headwords to their 
pronunciation in English," but the marking of vowel lengths is sporadic and 
sometimes erroneous (even allowing for differences between British and American 
usage). Those especially interested in the English pronunciation of classical 
names will find <PERSON>Catherine Avery</PERSON>'s "New Century Classical Handbook" more useful 
for that purpose (out of print, but available in libraries). 
</P>
<P>
It should be remarked that <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON>'s frequent citations of "interesting points 
of connexion between the classics and medieval and modern English literature" 
(<ORGANIZATION>Harvey</ORGANIZATION>'s preface) have in this edition been substantially truncated or dropped 
altogether, evidently because of the need to make room for new material and 
presumably reflecting a judgment that today's reader is less likely than 
<PERSON>Harvey</PERSON>'s was to be interested in references to classical allusions in <LOCATION>Milton</LOCATION>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>, or Spenser. 
</P>
<P>
At the end of the volume is a chronological table setting forth historical and 
literary events in parallel columns, and a set of maps of the classical world. 
This excellent new edition of an old standby can be highly recommended to 
anyone interested in classical civilization and its legacy. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Philip of Macedon, a miniature head from the tomb at Vergina, whose 
discovery is one of the additions to the new "Oxford Companion to Classical 
Literature." 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Book Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-1966</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DLPC5ACWFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931216
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 DEC 93 / Technology: Troubled oil on Europe's waters - Greek worries
over tanker building controls
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KERIN HOPE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>'s shipowners have already had to accept tough new safety regulations
for tankers as the price of keeping access to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> oil transport market.
They are now worried that the UK or even the <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION> may adopt
equally stringent measures to prevent disastrous oil spills.
Greek owners control <MONEY>15 per cent</MONEY> of the world's oil tanker tonnage,
including a high proportion of very large and ultra large crude carriers
(VLCCs and ULCCs). The international tanker fleet amounts to fewer than
3,000 vessels, but its advancing age alarms environmental groups.
Sixty per cent of tankers are more than 15 years old, while most of the
VLCCs and <ORGANIZATION>ULCCS</ORGANIZATION> operated by Greek concerns were built in the mid-1970s.
The Greeks raise technical objections to the US Oil Pollution Act (OPA) of
<DATE>1990</DATE>, the law that could become a model for European legislators. Under its
provisions, all ships sailing in <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> waters and built after <DATE>1990</DATE> must have
double hulls, and shipowners face unlimited liability for accidents
involving gross negligence.
<PERSON>John Lyras</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Granicos Shipping</ORGANIZATION> says: 'We have to live with the double hull
requirement. But the evidence is that it is of limited use in improving
safety, and it's costly.'
The <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> law resulted from the Exxon Valdez accident in <DATE>1989</DATE> which poured more
than 25m gallons of oil into Alaskan coastal waters. Many Greek owners
believe another disaster on the scale of the Braer wreck off <LOCATION>Shetland</LOCATION> or the
grounding of the <ORGANIZATION>Aegean Sea</ORGANIZATION>, a Greek-owned supertanker, off a Spanish port -
both earlier this year - would mean the introduction of the double hull
requirement in European waters.
The <ORGANIZATION>Union of Greek Shipowners</ORGANIZATION> argues that double hulls, with a cushion of
air between the inner and outer steel plating, can reduce oil leakages only
if a collision or grounding occurs at low speeds.
If two ships collide at normal cruising speed, the cargo tanks are likely to
be ruptured and the tanker is more likely to sink. Also, an explosion is
more likely aboard a double-hulled ship in an accident, as the gap is filled
with oxygen which reacts with vapour from escaping oil.
'The fact that the Aegean Sea had a double bottom made things worse. When
the ship grounded, oil got into the space in between and triggered an
explosion. Damage to the ship was more extensive and more oil was spilled
than if it had a single hull,' says <PERSON>George Banos</PERSON> of Moundreas Shipbrokers.
Fitting a double hull adds at least <MONEY>15 per cent</MONEY> to the Dollars 120m (Pounds
80m) cost of building a supertanker, and cuts its carrying capacity by about
20 per cent.
Several large Greek oil carriers, among them the <PERSON>Onassis</PERSON>, <PERSON>Niarchos</PERSON> and
Livanos groups, have invested in double-hulled vessels. However, with the
shipping industry still in recession, there is little incentive for smaller
owners to switch.
The compromise solution advocated by the <ORGANIZATION>International Maritime Organisation</ORGANIZATION>
calls for tankers built after <DATE>1994</DATE> to have double bottoms and a series of
ballast tanks along the length of the cargo deck. But this would not
necessarily cut the risk of explosion as a fully-laden tanker would have air
in the ballast tanks.
As 80 per cent of tanker accidents are caused by human error, there is some
weight in the Greek owners' claims that higher standards of training for
both tanker crews and port officials would be as effective as shipbuilding
regulations.
Also, technologically advanced navigation assistance in congested
international waters could reduce the possibility for collisions and
groundings. 'What is needed is a shore-based electronic system, similar to
an air-traffic control system, that takes account of the limited ability of
a ship to manoeuvre in difficult weather,' <PERSON>Lyras</PERSON> says.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GRZ  Greece, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3713 Truck and Bus Bodies.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    TECH  Safety &amp; Standards.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 16
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-10122</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CEBAEACSFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920502
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 MAY 92 / Echoes of Achilles haunt this ancient mystery: Kerin Hope
investigates the evidence for a murder most foul
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KERIN HOPE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
AN ANCIENT whodunnit has a special fascination, particularly when the gentle
scraping of an archaeologist's trowel unexpectedly reveals the murder
victim.
<PERSON>Nikos Stampolidis</PERSON> has been excavating an early Greek cemetery at <LOCATION>Eleutherna</LOCATION>,
in the western foothills of <LOCATION>Mount Ida</LOCATION> on the island of <LOCATION>Crete</LOCATION>: 'a site full
of surprises,' as he puts it. Not the least of these is a striking
connection between his grisly find and a famous burial ceremony conducted
outside Troy, the ancient city described in <LOCATION>Homer</LOCATION>'s Iliad.
The city of <LOCATION>Eleutherna</LOCATION>, built in a splendid defensive position on a long
narrow hill cut off by a ravine on each side, flourished from the <DATE>11th
century</DATE> BC until the Romans conquered <LOCATION>Crete</LOCATION>.
In the <DATE>1920s</DATE> British archaeologists found several striking pieces of
sculpture of the archaic period. When the <ORGANIZATION>University of Crete</ORGANIZATION> resumed
excavations there in the mid-1980s, Doctor Stampolidis decided to dig on the
steep western slope.
He unearthed more statue fragments - some built into terracing for the olive
groves which now cover the hill - suggesting that <PERSON>Eleutherna</PERSON> was an
important centre of early Greek art. The leg of a finely carved 'kouros,' a
nude figure of a young man, dates from the 6th century BC. It is made of
local limestone, and would have stood almost six feet high.
Four small, delicately worked ivory heads of figurines, perhaps gods or
heroes, date from a century earlier. These were found in one of a
bewildering array of burials in the cemetery, which was used by generations
of city-dwellers from the 10th to the 6th century BC.
Children were often buried in pithoi: Ali Baba-style jars used for storing
oil or honey. Many adults ware cremated on funeral pyres built of neatly
stacked logs of pine or cypress. <PERSON>Nikos Stampolidis</PERSON> says: 'They wore their
best clothes and their jewellery; they were surrounded by offerings and
household goods. Afterwards the bones were collected and cleaned, then
preserved in a covered jar.'
Last <DATE>summer</DATE>, while cleaning the remains of one pyre, the excavators revealed
part of another, more extravagant cremation: 'a rich, important man, judging
from the bones of goats and cattle and and a pair of ox horns that were
found - all slaughtered for the burial.'
From one side of the pyre came a surprising find: a curving line of human
vertebrae. Beside it lay a whetstone, a perfume bottle and the neck of a
broken water jar. The leg bones were burned, and the skull was missing.
'Instead we found a double-edged iron knife, broken. It would have been
about 12 inches long.' Studies of the bones by <PERSON>Tina McGeorge</PERSON>, a British
expert, showed that the headless man was about 40 years old and powerfully
built. His spine was forced into an unnatural curve - apparently because his
arms were tightly bound behind his back, perhaps with a piece of wood thrust
in between, to pull back his head. His throat had been cut. 'The man was
killed in a kneeling position, and fell on to his right side. I think his
head was probably tossed on to the centre of the pyre.'
Was it an expiatory sacrifice, an execution, or a ritual revenge killing?
Stampolidis thinks the victim may have been a prisoner of war, executed at
the funeral of the man he killed. From the style of the perfume bottle, the
execution can be dated to about 725-700 BC.
This was the period, some five centuries after the probable date of the
Trojan war, when Homer's epic poems were written down. The execution remains
discovered on <LOCATION>Crete</LOCATION> vividly recall the scene in the <LOCATION>Iliad</LOCATION> where Achilles,
the Greek hero, buries his friend Patroclus on a huge funeral pyre, after
slitting the throats of 'twelve noble sons of great-hearted Trojans' in
revenge for his death.
The ritual of execution in early <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> was elaborate. A virgin brought
water in a jar to dampen the whetstone; the knife used to decapitate the
victim had to be broken and immediately discarded. If Patroclus' burial is
anything to go by, <PERSON>Nikos Stampolidis</PERSON> may find more human victims this <DATE>summer</DATE>
when he uncovers the rest of the pyre.
'Perhaps we shouldn't be so surprised to discover that some of Homer's
descriptions of the Trojan war were really drawn from contemporary Greek
life.'
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page VIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891106-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-06-89 2357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Israel-Cosmetics     11-06 0778</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-Cosmetics,0803</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ancient Perfumes, Cosmetics on Display</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NICOLAS B. TATRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The most dangerous women in the ancient world
spent a fortune on perfume, and the vanity of at least one Biblical
king can be measured by the size of his bathtub.
   The lavishness of the ancients' royal boudoir and bath will be
on display starting <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE> in an <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> Museum exhibition of a
1,000-piece collection of toiletries from ancient <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>.
   Blown-glass eyeliner kits, jewel-studded makeup palettes,
polished bronze mirrors, gold hairpins, faience cosmetic boxes.
   Among the collection is an ivory cosmetic spoon that once held
the eyeshadow of Queen Jezebel, the <DATE>9th century</DATE> B.C. ruler who gave
makeup a bad name. There is also the only surviving juglet of
balsam, the favorite scent of the Egyptian queen, <LOCATION>Cleopatra</LOCATION>.
   ``Cosmetics in antiquity appealed at first to both men and
women. Over the centuries, cosmetics became more used by women,''
said <PERSON>Michal Dayagi-Mendes</PERSON>, curator of Biblical archaeology and
organizer of the exhibit.
   She said cosmetics were used as a means to color the faces of
gods to make them appear less cold and remote. Soon, priestly
attendants adopted the colorings and ultimately so did ordinary
people.
   In the hot, dry climate of the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION>, cosmetics also
served a medicinal purpose.
   ``Wearing makeup repelled the little flies that caused
inflamation of the eyes. Also, eyeshadow took the place of
sunglasses, reducing the glare,'' she said.
   Like their modern counterparts, ancients squandered vast sums on
pampering themselves, indulging in cosmetic fads that sometimes
were silly and harmful.
   Ancient Egyptians used a reddish ochre makeup over the entire
face. Romans lightened their faces with a powder made from
crocodile excrement. Greek women used a finely ground lead to turn
their faces white and spent hours in the sun to bleach their hair.
   ``The Greeks were aware that the lead caused great damage, but
beauty was above everything else,'' Dayagi-Mendes said.
   Roman women went to great extremes to braid and curl their hair
and many wore wigs.
   But the greasy look was in, mainly because oil was used to
combat lice. The pests and more than 80 lice eggs were found, for
example, on a 2,000-year-old wooden comb recovered recently from
the <LOCATION>Qumran</LOCATION> caves near the Dead Sea.
   Nero's wife, <LOCATION>Pompaea</LOCATION>, was especially extravagant.
   ``Every day she took a bath in asses' milk. When she was finally
banished from <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, she was allowed to take 50 asses with her just
to make sure she could have her daily milk bath,'' said
Dayagi-Mendes.
   Her bath did not survive, but that of Herod the Great was
retrieved a few years ago from his ruined <PERSON>Kypros</PERSON> winter palace near
<LOCATION>Jericho</LOCATION>. The 1{-ton, six-foot-long alabaster bathtub is a monument
to the grandiose style of one of the ancient world's great builders
and architect of the <ORGANIZATION>Second Jewish Temple</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The man obviously had good taste and enjoyed all the
luxuries,'' she said, pointing to the regal tray where oils and
lotions once rested on the side of the tub.
   The costliest luxury in the ancient world, however, was perfume,
and ancient Israelites made the most famous variety, balsam, from a
now-extinct tree that once grew on the edges of the <LOCATION>Dead Sea</LOCATION>.
   To please Cleopatra, the Roman general <PERSON>Anthony</PERSON> acquired a whole
orchard of the precious balsam trees near <LOCATION>Jericho</LOCATION> so she would
always have a supply of her favorite fragrance, which cost twice as
much as silver.
   Calling it ``serpent's poison,'' sages of the Jewish Talmud
recount that the daughters of <LOCATION>Jerusalem</LOCATION> put balsam in their shoes
and, on seeing attractive young men, clicked their heels to release
the fragrance as a lure.
   Today, the only surviving balsam is a 1{-ounce flask covered in
palm matting that has lost all its allure. Only a musty, oily scent
remains in the padded box where it is kept.
   ``It must have been sweet, heavy and oily. It was their taste,
but you can't say more,'' said Dayagi-Mendes.
   To give museum goers a whiff of the past, Dayagi-Mendes has
enlisted the help of experts in <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> to recreate a
fragrance similar to the ones in Biblical times.
   ``I used all the plants mentioned in the <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION> in connection
with perfumes and scented ointments,'' she said, adding that
ingredients included cinnamon, myrrh and frankincense.
   The result is Avishag, a perfume named after a consort of King
<PERSON>David</PERSON>. A two-ounce bottle is being marketed at the exhibition for
<MONEY>$50</MONEY>.
   ``We thought it would be intriguing to smell something of
antiquity, and this way you can take something home to remember
besides a brochure,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910725-0104
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910725-0104.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf:
   Virgil in Prose and Fine Fettle
   ----
   By Donald Lyons
</HL>
<DATE>
07/25/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A6
</SO>
<LP>
   Talk about New World Order. In 27 B.C., Augustus, having
defeated Antony and Cleopatra and pacified much of the known
world, was busily consolidating the new Roman emperorship.
   This new Rome needed an arts policy to match its grand
self-image. Augustus, therefore, set up a virtual Imperial
Endowment for the Arts under the suave Etruscan magnate
Maecenas. It was Maecenas' luck to hire some of history's
greatest poets -- Virgil and Horace -- as enthusiastic
propagandists for the First Citizen. Virgil had already
celebrated Augustus as a restorer of peace and fertility to
the Italian countryside in "The Georgics." Now he had to
write the epic of Rome. "Epic" meant, since the Romans were
earnest followers of the Greeks, a long saga with gods and
battles. Just like Homer. He wrote "The Aeneid," a wonderful
new translation of which is recently out (Penguin Classics,
288 pages $6.95).
</LP>
<TEXT>
   This new <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> needed an arts policy to match its grand
self-image. Augustus, therefore, set up a virtual Imperial
Endowment for the Arts under the suave Etruscan magnate
Maecenas. It was <ORGANIZATION>Maecenas</ORGANIZATION>' luck to hire some of history's
greatest poets as enthusiastic propagandists for the <ORGANIZATION>First
Citizen</ORGANIZATION> -- <PERSON>Virgil</PERSON> and <PERSON>Horace</PERSON>. Virgil had already celebrated
<PERSON>Augustus</PERSON> as a restorer of peace and fertility to the Italian
countryside in "The Georgics." Now he had to write the epic
of <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>. "Epic" meant, since the Romans were earnest
followers of the Greeks, a long saga with gods and battles.
Just like Homer. He wrote "The Aeneid," a wonderful new
translation of which is recently out (<ORGANIZATION>Penguin Classics</ORGANIZATION>,
<MONEY>$5.95</MONEY>).
   Substantially complete, save for a few loose ends left
behind at <LOCATION>Virgil</LOCATION>'s death in 19 <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>, "The Aeneid" is the
story of the Trojan Prince Aeneas escaping the Greek sack of
his town and bringing a Trojan remnant to <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> as the
nucleus of the future <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>. This was a new job for an epic --
to tell a high-minded national foundation myth in archaic
drag. Homer's heroes had not been concerned with any sweep of
imperial history: Odysseus, for example, had enough problems
getting back to his small island of <LOCATION>Ithaca</LOCATION>.
   But what turns out to give electricity and life and anger
and tension to "The Aeneid" is not dull, worthy <PERSON>Aeneas</PERSON>'
imperial crusade, but the victims he crushes under those
implacably rolling chariot wheels. In the poem's second half,
<PERSON>Aeneas</PERSON> embroils sundry unoffending indigenous Italians in a
messy war to make room for him and his band. But it is in the
poem's first half that he accomplishes his most notorious
mischief -- the destruction of Dido.
   Driven from her homeland in <LOCATION>Phoenicia</LOCATION> by a cruel
brother-in-law, the adventurous and creative Dido had led an
elite of her people to the barren North African shore and was
in the process of founding the bustling utopian city of
<LOCATION>Carthage</LOCATION> when, deflected by <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> (<PERSON>Aeneas</PERSON>' mother), she
rescued the shipwrecked Trojans and fell in love with their
chieftain.
   Soon she was forgetting about the blueprints for the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate House</ORGANIZATION> and concentrating on reading entrails instead:
"But priests, as we know, are ignorant. What use are prayers
and shrines to a passionate woman? The flame was eating the
soft marrow of her bones, and the wound lived under her
breast. Dido was on fire with love and wandered all over the
city in her misery and madness like a wounded deer . . ."
This romantic internalizing is a new note in <LOCATION>Latin</LOCATION> epic;
<PERSON>Virgil</PERSON> had been impressed by such Greek heroines of erotic
tragedy as <LOCATION>Medea</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Phaedra</LOCATION>.
   Dido's reward for preferring private passion to public
glory was to see her lover sail away. But not before she gave
him a piece of her mind: "Look for your kingdom over the
waves . . . I shall follow you not in the flesh but in the
black fires of death . . . You will receive the punishment
you deserve and the news of it will reach me deep among the
dead." The mood music swells for the queen's last evening:
"It was night and weary living things were peacefully taking
their rest upon the earth . . . But not Dido . . . Her eyes
and mind would not accept the night."
   The queen rejects any notion of accompanying Aeneas and
regrets not having dealt differently with him at the start
("Could I not have taken him and torn him limb from limb and
scattered the pieces in the sea? . . . or served {<PERSON>Aeneas</PERSON>'
little son's} flesh at his father's table?") She decides on
suicide, leaving vengeance to some future Carthaginian (that
is, to <LOCATION>Hannibal</LOCATION>). The queen falls on her sword, and "All
warmth went out of Dido's body and her life passed into the
winds."
   <PERSON>David West</PERSON>'s new prose translation proves two things about
"The Aeneid." The first we knew: It is the victims' poem.
They -- the Italians and young Trojans like Nisus and
Euryalus, and above all Dido -- steal the story from the
rigid Roman robots backed by head god <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. Flesh beats
marble. Secondly, and surprisingly, prose can work superbly
to capture the sad, conflicted music of Virgil. Not
rollicking, whale-of-a-story prose, but sweet prose, clear
and clean and dancing like a mountain stream, as here.
   To gauge the nature and extent of <PERSON>Mr. West</PERSON>'s triumph,
compare his version of Dido and the entrails with the <DATE>1956</DATE>
Penguin prose of Jackson Knight: "But how pitifully weak is
the prescience of seers] There lay no help for her
infatuation in temples or in prayers." Compare it, too, with
the rapturously received <DATE>1983</DATE> verse translation of <PERSON>Robert
Fitzgerald</PERSON>: "Alas, what darkened minds have soothsayers]/
What good are shrines and vows to maddened lovers?" And here
is <PERSON>Mr. Fitzgerald</PERSON>'s version of Dido haranguing Aeneas: "You
will pay for this,/Unconscionable] I shall hear] The news
will reach me/Even among the lowest of the dead." And here is
<ORGANIZATION>Fitzgerald</ORGANIZATION> on Dido dead: "Her body's warmth fell into
dissolution,/And out into the winds her life withdrew."
   Prescience? Infatuation? Soothsayers? Unconscionable?
Dissolution? Dry polysyllables settle on those translations
like chalk dust. It's language like theirs that has kept
potential readers from "the classics." Preferring simplicity
to archaic locutions, <PERSON>Mr. West</PERSON> remains closer to the Latin
sense and quietly achieves many an iambic beat more naturally
than <PERSON>Mr. Fitzgerald</PERSON>. He opens the window and the winds bring
life into <PERSON>Virgil</PERSON>'s body.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881124-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-24-88 0104EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Onassis-Tragedy     11-24 0920</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Onassis-Tragedy,0953</SECOND>
<HEAD>Money Could Not Help Rootless Childhood, Family Tragedy</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Thursday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KERIN HOPE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Money never made up for <PERSON>Christina Onassis</PERSON>'
rootless childhood or the loss of the father she idolized. It could
not ease the pain after three members of her family died within two
years, or save any of her four marriages.
   ``The sudden death of <PERSON>Christina Onassis</PERSON> closes a circle that has
all the makings of a Greek tragedy,'' the daily newspaper
<PERSON>Eleftherotypia</PERSON> said in an obituary. It spoke of the ``tragic fate''
of the <PERSON>Onassis</PERSON> family, which it described as ``a dynasty of death.''
   <PERSON>Christina</PERSON> was 37 when she died on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> during a visit to
friends in <LOCATION>Buenos Aires</LOCATION>. Friends and relatives said she was happy.
Newspapers suggested she had a romantic interest in the brother of
her hostess.
   An autopsy report gave the cause of death as acute pulmonary
edema, accumulation of fluid in the lungs. Family members discounted
the possibility of suicide.
   ``A happy person could never commit suicide and <PERSON>Christina</PERSON> was
content and very happy,'' said <PERSON>Mary Onassis</PERSON>, an aunt. ``<PERSON>Christina</PERSON>
was in the best part of her life.''
   <PERSON>Mario Falak</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Alvear Palace Hotel</ORGANIZATION> in <PERSON>Buenos
Aires</PERSON>, said: ``She reserved a suite through <DATE>Dec. 4</DATE>. She had so much
baggage our employees had to make two trips to the airport.''
   <PERSON>Ioannis Georgakis</PERSON>, vice-president of the <ORGANIZATION>Alexander Onassis Public
Benefit</ORGANIZATION> foundation, dismissed suicide reports that arose when
medicine bottles were found on <LOCATION>Christina</LOCATION>'s bedside table.
   ``She had no health problems and it just seems her heart was too
tired to overcome the attack,'' he said.
   Greek newspapers quoted friends as saying the bottles probably
contained diet pills. Christina experienced wild swings in weight
throughout her life, often caused by alternating crash diets and
food binges.
   She was born <DATE>Dec. 11, 1950</DATE>, in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> and spent her
childhood shuttling from there to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Monaco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>.
   The three members of her immediate family died in only two years.
Christina's brother <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON> was killed in a plane crash in <DATE>January
1973</DATE>, her mother <ORGANIZATION>Athena</ORGANIZATION> died of a heart attack in <DATE>October 1974</DATE> and
her father Aristotle died of bronchial pneumonia in <DATE>March 1975</DATE>.
   ``She could never escape the consequences of a rootless
upbringing,'' according to a ``<PERSON>Aristotle Onassis</PERSON>,'' a <DATE>1977</DATE> biography
of the Greek tycoon. ``Never an eager student, she learned dancing
under <PERSON>Margot Fonteyn</PERSON> and was educated at a series of expensive
finishing schools. ... She emerged a good linguist but with no sense
of place.''
   Its authors, five investigative reporters on the staff of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> Times, described <PERSON>Christina</PERSON>'s relationship with her father as
``complex and self-contradictory.''
   Onassis women ``had to be satisfactory vehicles for
self-promotion and adoring females; and they had to simultaneously
accept his engulfing protectiveness and withstand his massive ego,''
the biographers wrote.
   <PERSON>Christina</PERSON> was 25 when her father died, and the event had an
enormous emotional impact. News reports said she spent the last two
weeks by his bedside and had to be sedated for more than two days
after his death.
   The biographers quote her as remarking that she found
relationships with men difficult ``because, how can I fall in love
when I have a father like mine?''
   Her love life was as turbulent as her father's.
   She married <PERSON>Joseph Bolker</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> real estate broker, in
<DATE>1971</DATE> and they were divorced nine months later. The second marriage,
to Greek shipping heir <PERSON>Alexandros Andreadis</PERSON>, lasted only until <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   Husband number three, Soviet shipping executive <PERSON>Sergei Kauzov</PERSON>,
came on the scene in <DATE>1978</DATE> and departed <DATE>two years later</DATE>.
   Last was <PERSON>Theirry Roussel</PERSON>, a French pharmaceutical heir, in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
Divorce proceedings followed eight months later. They have a
daughter, <ORGANIZATION>Athena</ORGANIZATION>, now 3.
   Aristotle Onassis married <PERSON>Athena Livanos</PERSON>, daughter of a wealthy
Greek shipowner, in <DATE>1946</DATE> and she bore him two children, <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON> in
<DATE>1948</DATE> and <LOCATION>Christina</LOCATION>.
   They separated in <DATE>1960</DATE> after his highly publicized affair with
opera star <PERSON>Maria Callas</PERSON>.
   He married <PERSON>Jacqueline Bouvier Kennedy</PERSON> in <DATE>1968</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Athena</ORGANIZATION> later
became the wife of his business rival, shipowner <PERSON>Stavros Niarchos</PERSON>,
who was married to <ORGANIZATION>Athena</ORGANIZATION>'s sister, <LOCATION>Eugenia</LOCATION>, until her death in <DATE>1970</DATE>.
   Reports at the time indicated <PERSON>Christina</PERSON> and her father's new wife
did not get along, and the relationship worsened after <PERSON>Aristotle
Onassis</PERSON> died.
   In <DATE>April 1975</DATE>, <PERSON>Christina</PERSON> ordered the personal belongings of
<PERSON>Jacqueline Onassis</PERSON> removed from <LOCATION>Skorpios</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Ionian Sea</LOCATION> island the
family had owned since <DATE>1963</DATE>.
   ``The hate that developed between <PERSON>Christina</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jackie Onassis</PERSON>
determined her future,'' the newspaper <ORGANIZATION>Eleftherotypia</ORGANIZATION> said in its
obituary.
   Christina plunged into her father's business.
   ``For two years she sat behind a desk learning every phase'' of
it, <PERSON>Apostolos Zambelas</PERSON>, an aide, said in a <DATE>1983</DATE> interview.
   He said her business training had begun soon after <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON> was
killed.
   ``Alexander was being groomed as the natural heir, something
<PERSON>Christina</PERSON> sort of resented,'' <PERSON>Zambelas</PERSON> said. ``Eventually she got
more than she bargained for.''
   Her brother's death was a turning point in <LOCATION>Christina</LOCATION>'s life.
   Eleftherotypia said in its obituary: ``They shared the same
distress over <PERSON>Jackie</PERSON> _ the widow, as she called her _ who
monopolized their father's attention.''
   Ta <ORGANIZATION>Nea</ORGANIZATION>, another <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION> paper, said: ``Alexander's death left her
inconsolable. It was the moment she understood that her apathy was
over and that she would have to run the fortune.''
   <PERSON>Georgakis</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Onassis Foundation</ORGANIZATION> executive, said a board of
trustess will manage the fortune until <ORGANIZATION>Athena</ORGANIZATION> becomes of age.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880618-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-18-88 0918EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Turkey-Ozal 3rdLd-Writethru   06-18 0664</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Turkey-Ozal, 3rd Ld - Writethru,a0454,0684</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Gunman Fires At Ozal During Convention; Premier Slightly Wounded</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with seven grafs to UPDATE Ozal's injury, raise
casualty count, add detail on gunmen, other details; picks up 5th
pvs: Ozal took...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ANKARA, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gunman shot and slightly wounded Premier
<PERSON>Turgut Ozal</PERSON> in the right hand as the leader addressed delegates at
his party's convention. At least 20 others were injured.
   The gunman was hit in the arm by return fire from <PERSON>Ozal</PERSON>'s
bodyguards and then arrested. Ankara Gov. <PERSON>Saffet Arikan Beduk</PERSON> said
16 other people were wounded by gunfire and four were trampled in
the panic after the attack.
   Ozal's doctor, <PERSON>Cengiz Aslan</PERSON>, told reporters a bullet entered
through <PERSON>Ozal</PERSON>'s right thumb and exited from the palm. The wound
required three stitches and the premier was in good condition, he
said.
   State television showed a picture of the gunmen at a hospital
and asked anyone who knew him to come forward and identify him to
police.
   The wounded include Labor Minister <PERSON>Imren Aykut</PERSON>, who suffered
scratches on her face, and one <ORGANIZATION>Motherland Party</ORGANIZATION> member of
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Beduk</PERSON> said. Two of the wounded required surgery but
were in satisfactory condition, he said.
   It was not immediately clear if the gunfire that hit some of the
wounded came from police or the gunman.
   A police official at the scene, who requested anonymity, said
the first bullet fired by the gunman hit the microphone in front of
<PERSON>Ozal</PERSON> and the second one hit his right thumb.
   Ozal took cover immediately behind the lectern when he heard the
shots, <ORGANIZATION>Anatolia</ORGANIZATION> said. Delegates and others inside the <PERSON>Ataturk</PERSON>
convention hall also took cover, it said.
   ``I saw the gunman take careful aim at the premier and fire at
him twice,'' <PERSON>Eyup Asik</PERSON>, a deputy chairman of the party, told the
agency.
   Interior Minister <PERSON>Mustafa Kalemli</PERSON> said the captured gunman gave
two different names to police and was insisting he acted alone. He
said the gunman first said his name was <PERSON>Hayati Ipek</PERSON>, then changed
this to <PERSON>Kartal</PERSON>, which means eagle in Turkish.
   Despite his injury, <PERSON>Ozal</PERSON> returned to the floor to continue his
speech.
   ``No one can take away the life given by God except God
himself,'' <PERSON>Ozal</PERSON> said.
   The delegates gave him a long standing ovation after this
statement.
   The injured were taken to a nearby hospital, but their
identities were not released.
   Later today, the delegates were expected to re-elect <PERSON>Ozal</PERSON> as
party chairman. There were no other candidates running against him.
   Ozal returned <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> from a historic three-day vist to
<LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, the first Turkish premier to visit its traditionally
hostile neighbor in 36 years.
   No solutions to major disputes between <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION> emerged
from his talks with Greek Premier <PERSON>Andreas Papandreou</PERSON>, but both
leaders said they wanted to continue their dialogue.
   The longtime enemies have clashed over several issues, including
the Aegean Sea and the island of <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>.
   Cyprus has been divided into separate Greek Cypriot and Turkish
Cypriot sectors since <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION> invaded in <DATE>1974</DATE> after an
Athens-inspired coup aimed at uniting the island with <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>March 1987</DATE>, <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION> came to the brink of war over
oil-drilling rights in the Aegean seabed.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, a court sentenced a Greek chemist to four months in
jail for throwing a tomato at <ORGANIZATION>Ozal</ORGANIZATION>'s car on the last day of his
visit to <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>. The chemist said he was angry about <PERSON>Ozal</PERSON>'s visit.
   In today's speech to the delegates, <PERSON>Ozal</PERSON> emphasized the
