<DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871109-0146 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf:
Three Sachems: Clay, Webster, Calhoun
---
By David Shribman</HL>
<DD> 11/09/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   Three decades ago, <PERSON>John Kennedy</PERSON>, obsessed with greatness in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> but unwilling to achieve it himself, headed a committee to select which senators to honor with portraits in the ornate Senate Reception Room. 
Scholars and commentators were consulted and the verdict was fairly predictable. 
The top three finishers were <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON>, <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON> and <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON>. 

   Clay, <PERSON>Webster</PERSON> and <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON> -- their names flow off the tongue in a group. 

   The leading political figures of the "second generation" of American leaders, they were, as <ORGANIZATION>University of Virginia</ORGANIZATION> historian <PERSON>Merrill Peterson</PERSON> puts it, "part of the furniture of American memory." 

   "The Great Triumvirate" (<ORGANIZATION>Oxford</ORGANIZATION>, 576 pages, <MONEY>$27.95</MONEY>) is an unusual alchemy -- one part history, one part biography -- by a leading American historian who argues that these three men -- one from the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>, one from the South, one from the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> -- were the match of the founding generation of Americans: "When the last of this 'second race of giants' passed away in <DATE>1852</DATE>, nothing was left to challenge the sway of the Lilliputians," he writes. 
"The republic lost its glory -- the regalia of great statesmen." 

   <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON>, the man <PERSON>John Quincy Adams</PERSON> called "a republican of the first fire," elevated the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> to new importance. 
He fashioned his own ideology, an "American System" that consisted of policies to encourage national economic development, chiefly protective tariffs and a series of internal improvements that now would be known as public-works projects. 
And though he thought slavery would wither away -- he later advocated repatriating slaves back to <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> as colonists -- he became known for his ability to sculpt compromise after compromise on the slavery question. 
Clay, according to <PERSON>Mr. Peterson</PERSON>, had a "genius for accommodation, sensitivity to opposing political forces and ingenuity in adapting old policies to new conditions." 

   Webster is known in history much the same way he was known as a young <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> lawyer with a gift for oratory -- the "guardian of the Constitution." 
<PERSON>Mr. Peterson</PERSON> credits him with pioneering the "theory of the Constitution as the fundamental law of one people, rather than a compact of sovereign states." 

   And <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON>. 
First pressed by the early Nullifiers, then their champion, he embraced this tool of expedience to assure his base in <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>, to protect his region from the threat of high tariffs and to muffle the drumbeats of Abolition. 
"It took possession of him, transfixed his political vision, and justified all his actions," says <PERSON>Mr. Peterson</PERSON>. 

   He once viewed slavery as scaffolding for the South, support that would be removed "when the building is finished." 
Later he came to call it "a great good." 
He was, moreover, a proponent of small government in the <LOCATION>Jefferson</LOCATION> model, aiming for nothing less, as he put it, "than to turn back the <ORGANIZATION>Government</ORGANIZATION> to where it commences operations in <DATE>1789</DATE>." 
<PERSON>Mr. Peterson</PERSON> sees <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>'s power resting "not on charisma or organization but on a political ideology that postulated unity in the state and eventually in the section as the only means of securing slavery and the South from an encroaching northern majority." 

   The three united in <DATE>1832</DATE> to oppose <PERSON>Andrew Jackson</PERSON> but, <PERSON>Mr. Peterson</PERSON> points out, spent most of their public lives dancing a political version of the country reel, changing partners and calculating their every move with an eye on what the others would do. 
Webster first opposed Clay on tariff protection, then switched sides and found himself opposing <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>. 
<PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>, as vice president under <PERSON>John Quincy Adams</PERSON>, stacked the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Foreign Relations Committee</ORGANIZATION> against <ORGANIZATION>Secretary of State Clay</ORGANIZATION>. 
And although Clay and <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>, the two leading Whigs, united in opposing an independent <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> scheme proffered by the <PERSON>Van Buren</PERSON> administration, they fought so much they paved the way for <PERSON>William Henry Harrison</PERSON> to snatch the presidency in <DATE>1840</DATE>. 

   Each had great achievements. 
From his position in the border state of <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, Clay formed two great compromises. 
Although he never shed the charges of "bargain and corruption" growing out of his maneuvers that left <PERSON>John Quincy Adams</PERSON> as president in <DATE>1824</DATE>, he was an active and successful secretary of state. 
Webster is now regarded as among the greatest secretaries of state in history, having prevented war with the British and helped fix the nation's northern border. 
And <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON> today is regarded as one of the few original thinkers of the era that followed the Founding Fathers'. 

   Despite the triumvirs' documented greatness, <PERSON>Mr. Peterson</PERSON> offers harsh assessments of their legacies. 
The Civil War that followed their deaths would have offered Clay "grim proofs of the limits of compromise." 
It would have demonstrated to <PERSON>Webster</PERSON> "the fragility of law and constitutions before moral and social forces he never truly understood." 
And it offered an "awful judgment" on <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>. 
His face ended up on the currency and postage stamps not of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, but of the Confederacy. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Shribman</PERSON> is a reporter in the Journal's <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> bureau. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880614-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-14-88 0140EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CapitolAdvertising Bjt   06-14 0678</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Capitol Advertising, Bjt,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON WIRE: Is Capitol Salesmanship `What This Country
Needs?'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans wanting to sell anything from
biscuits and cigars to plumbing and whiskey often have tried to
cloak their wares in the presumed respectability of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and
its most illustrious members.
   <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON>, for example.
   Webster, perhaps the most famous senator and orator of the
mid-19th century, had his face and his name used to promote cigars,
flour, and a concoction known as <ORGANIZATION>Dr. J.C. Ayres Cherry Pectoral</ORGANIZATION>,
promoted as a cure for coughs, colds, bronchitis, croup, whooping
cough and other ailments.
   According to a new three-case exhibit recently installed in a
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> corridor, the claim that <PERSON>Webster</PERSON> endorsed <PERSON>Dr. Ayres</PERSON>' elixer
may have been somewhat exaggerated.
   Promoters of the product claimed that <PERSON>Webster</PERSON> praised it in <DATE>1853</DATE>.
   The famed statesman died in <DATE>1852</DATE>.
   The exhibit, organized by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate Commission</ORGANIZATION> on Art and
Antiquities, includes a shiny metal spatula from <DATE>1910</DATE> which
demonstrates that even 58 years after <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>'s death his name
still had commercial appeal.
   Webster's features are engraved on the widest spot of the
antique pancake turner, which is also emblazoned with the words:
``<PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON> Flour, Better Than the Best'' and ``One Good Turn
Deserves Another.''
   <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>'s face was also used on the flour bag with the words:
``<PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON> Flour Bakes Everything Better.''
   In an age when a cigar brought to mind a politician, <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>
also was used to promote a brand of cigars.
   Their name?
   ``Websters,'' of course.
   The names and faces of <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>'s contemporaries, Sens. <PERSON>John C.
Calhoun</PERSON> of <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> also were used
to peddle cigars.
   And for years, Old Crow whiskey identified itself as, ``The
Whiskey That <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON> Took to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.''
   ``From the earliest days of advertising, senators have been
known to endorse commercial products,'' notes a news release issued
by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> commission.
   From the beginning of the advertising age in the mid-19th
century, ``our country's enterprises have understood the power of
national legislative symbols to influence the American consumer,''
the commission said.
   The display has a title _ ``What This Country Needs'' _ taken
from the <DATE>1917</DATE> declaration of Vice President <PERSON>Thomas Marshall</PERSON> that
``What this country needs is a good five cent cigar.''
   Although <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> did not recommend any particular brand of
nickel cigar, the exhibit makes clear that he would not have been
breaking new ground had he done so.
   A much later advertisement for Lucky Strike cigarettes reads:
``<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Sen. <PERSON>Gerald P. Nye</PERSON> Says: `I enjoy the comfort a light smoke
gives my throat.''
   The familiar image of the Capitol dome has been used, according
to the exhibit, to symbolize ``purity, wholesomeness,
respectability and success, innovation and leadership, prosperity
and celebration.''
   In one <DATE>1890</DATE>'s advertisement, the Capitol looms in the background
as two bearded senators are served Schlitz beer at a table
surrounded by ferns.
   ``The Capitol at <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> is painted with oxide of zinc,''
proclaims another advertisement, implying that American homeowners
would do well to use that ingredient on their own domicile.
   On display are advertisements for breakfast cereals, stationery,
soft drinks, biscuits, tires, soap, cameras, and plumbing, all
using the Capitol theme.
   One proclaims that the <LOCATION>Durham</LOCATION> Plumbing System has been installed
in ``the greatest building on this continent _ the Capitol at
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.''
   In another, fashionably dressed men, presumably senators, are
shown striding up the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s marble steps.
   All of this has caused an occasional raised eyebrows, and the
Arts and <ORGANIZATION>Antiquities Commission</ORGANIZATION> notes that the use of the Capitol
in commercial advertising never has been sanctioned by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   But neither has the practice been banned.
   In <DATE>1956</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION> reported out a bill
banning the use of ``pictures of the Capitol or other public
buildings in ... advertising when it would be reasonably calculated
to convey the false impression that the company has some connection
with, or was insured by, the <ORGANIZATION>United States Government</ORGANIZATION>.''
   The measure passed the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> failed to act on it.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890406-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-06-89 2136EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SenateBicentennial     04-06 0651</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Senate Bicentennial,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senate Celebrates Its First Two Centuries</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, told it ``is a guardian of
tradition without becoming a barrier to change,'' celebrated its
first two centuries of history on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, recalling its faltering
beginnings and noting its many milestones.
   <DATE>April 6, 1789</DATE>, was the date that the first <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, meeting in
<LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, finally reached a quorum _ and thus was able to
start conducting business _ after a frustrating month of failing to
do so.
   ``History oozes from these walls,'' said <PERSON>Sen. John Glenn</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Ohio</LOCATION>, as the day of commemoration began in the Old Senate Chamber
in the Capitol with the issuing of a postage stamp displaying the
gilt shield and eagle still suspended over the presiding officer's
chair.
   The eagle and shield were there during speeches on the old
chamber's floor which served the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> from <DATE>1810</DATE> to <DATE>1859</DATE>, and can
be seen in <DATE>19th century</DATE> prints involving three famous senators of
the era: <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>
and <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON> of <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>.
   Those three senators and the roles they played in the period
before the Civil War were invoked repeatedly as past and former
senators hailed the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> as an institution.
   <PERSON>Howard H. Baker Jr.</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, a former <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Republican
leader, said the sense of history in the old <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> hall, and in
the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s present chamber first occupied in <DATE>1859</DATE>, is so strong
that at times one can truly ``smell the marble.''
   Nearly 20 former senators _ including <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> and former
Democratic leader <PERSON>Mike Mansfield</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> _ joined senators in
the current 101st <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for the ceremonies. Members of the <ORGANIZATION>House
of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> celebrated the quorum bicentennial session of
that body on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Former <PERSON>Sen. Thomas F. Eagleton</PERSON>, a Democrat from <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, said
that the legacy of the early <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> is the art of the American
political compromise.
   ``Today compromise is woven into constitutional fabric of the
nation,'' <PERSON>Eagleton</PERSON> said.
   Although many senators past and present have regarded compromise
as morally wrong, <PERSON>Eagleton</PERSON> said it is politically essential.
   ``Compromise, in my judgment, is getting a bad rap,'' <PERSON>Eagleton</PERSON>
said. ``Without it we screech to a halt, paralyzed by
intransigence.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> session began at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME>, the hour of the first
session two centuries ago.
   With the conclusion of the ceremony's first half in the old
chamber, senators formed a procession to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s present
meeting place down the hall.
   Senior senators from the states answered the roll call,
beginning with <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, which became the first state in <DATE>1787</DATE>, and
continuing to <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, which in <DATE>1959</DATE> became the 50th to join the
union.
   When <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>'s name was called, Republican <PERSON>Strom Thurmond</PERSON>
gave this response: ``<LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> was not the first state to be
admitted, but it was the first to secede'' in <DATE>1860</DATE>. After the Civil
War, <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> returned to the union in <DATE>1868</DATE>.
   Sen. <PERSON>Ted Stevens</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Alaska</LOCATION>, noted <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON>'s description
of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> as a stage, and recalled some of the drama the
present chamber has witnessed, including the one-vote defeat of the
attempt to oust President <PERSON>Andrew Johnson</PERSON> during Reconstruction
after the Civil War, and the rejection of President <PERSON>Woodrow
Wilson</PERSON>'s effort to bring the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> into the <ORGANIZATION>League of
Nations</ORGANIZATION> after World War I.
the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> has undergone many changes over the years, it remains a
place where the rights of the minority are protected and speech can
remain virtually unlimited.
   ``It is a guardian of tradition without becoming a barrier to
change,'' he said.
   Senators moved in and out of the ceremonies to spirited <PERSON>John
Philip Sousa</PERSON> marches played by the <ORGANIZATION>Marine Corps</ORGANIZATION> band.
   A tourist asked a doorman: ``Does a band play every day the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> meets?''
   ``No,'' the doorman replied. ``Only once every 200 years.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870818-0148 </DOCNO>
<HL> Letters to the Editor:
Assessing Early American Tariffs</HL>
<DD> 08/18/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   It was amusing to read <PERSON>James Bovard</PERSON>'s "American History: Pass a Tariff, Start a War" (editorial page, <DATE>July 20</DATE>) in defense of free trade, because the truth about American history is that for the greater part of it, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> was a strongly protectionist nation. 
From <DATE>1789</DATE> until the end of World War II, our country rose to become the greatest economic power on earth behind high tariff walls. 
The Japanese and <LOCATION>Koreans</LOCATION> seem to have learned more from American history than we have. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Bovard</PERSON> cites anachronisms such as <PERSON>John Taylor</PERSON> and nonentities such as <PERSON>Frank H. Hurd</PERSON>. 
But those of us who believe a little trade regulation might be a very good thing indeed can take comfort in such historical allies as <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON>, <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON> and <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON> before he became the sectional spokesman for the free-trading but slave-holding plantation owners of the south. 


   Barry Gewen
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Bovard</PERSON> makes the bold claim that "Few people realize that restrictive trade policies were a major cause of the American Revolution." 
He cites <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s prohibiting Americans from "erecting any mill for rolling or slitting iron." 

   Americans during that time did not seem disturbed by this prohibition. 
<PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> wrote that, "<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> has all along consented, still consent and ever will consent, that Parliament . . . should regulate the trade of the dominions." 
And the <ORGANIZATION>First Continental Congress</ORGANIZATION>, in a resolution, declared that "we cheerfully consent to the operation of such Acts of the British Parliament, as are bona fide restrained to the regulation of our external commerce, for the purpose of securing the commercial advantages of the whole empire to the mother country, and the commercial benefits of its respective members." 

   Pre-Revolutionary Americans perhaps can be excused for thinking that trade restrictions benefit the nation. 
After all, <PERSON>Adam Smith</PERSON>'s "Wealth of Nations" had not yet been published. 
Modern Americans cannot likewise be excused. 

   Prof. <ORGANIZATION>William Irvine
   Wright State University
   Dayton</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881208-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-08-88 1727EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Marshals'Bicentennial     12-08 0758</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Marshals' Bicentennial,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawmen Celebrate 200 Years In Action</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER DIXON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From the days President <PERSON>George Washington</PERSON>
dispatched the first <LOCATION>United States Marshals</LOCATION> to quell the <ORGANIZATION>Whiskey
Rebellion</ORGANIZATION>, the storied lawmen have been part of the country's most
colorful and most violent episodes.
   They did the hanging for famous ``Hanging Judge'' <PERSON>Isaac Parker</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Fort Smith</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, after rounding up bank and train robbers hiding in
the brush of Indian Territory, smashed whiskey stills during
Prohibition and protected slaves freed after the Civil War.
   The nation's oldest law enforcement organization, the Marshals
began their bicentennial celebration <DATE>Thursday</DATE> with the opening of an
exhibit at the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> followed by a black-tie dinner at a
nearby hotel.
   Organized by the <ORGANIZATION>Marshals Service</ORGANIZATION> with the help of the
<ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Insitution</ORGANIZATION>, the exhibit displays artifacts from
massacres and shootouts that have earned the men their place in the
lore of the <LOCATION>Wild West</LOCATION> and their immortalization by movie legends
<PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON> and <PERSON>Henry Fonda</PERSON>.
   ``As the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> expanded across the continent, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Marshals and their deputies established the federal goverment's
authority over areas that had known little order and no goverment.
Most of them were rough, uncouth men,'' according to an excerpt of
the Marshals' official history by <PERSON>Frederick S. Calhoun</PERSON>.
   The brothers of Deputy <PERSON>Frank Dalton</PERSON>, one of many men killed in
Indian Territory, were also deputies before they turned to robbing
banks.
   ``They were the federal goverment at the local level,'' <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>
said. ``There was no infrastructure of a bureaucracy, so when the
citizens got mad they took it out on the federal marshals.''
   As a result, as many as 100 marshals and their deputies died in
Indian Territory between <DATE>1872</DATE> and <DATE>1896</DATE>, their deadliest era, <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>
said.
   ``With the exception of Indian Territory, the far most dangerous
time to be a marshal was in the South after the Civil War,'' <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>
said. ``If the <PERSON>Ku Klux Klan</PERSON> didn't get you, the moonshiners did.''
   At least 400 and as many as 700 marshals have died in the line of
duty, more than any other law enforcement agency. But the exact
number isn't known because of difficulties in determining whether
members of posses had actually been deputized before their deaths,
said <ORGANIZATION>Marshals Service</ORGANIZATION> director <ORGANIZATION>Stanley Morris</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``At almost every point in history when the federal government
was involved in a significant event, there were marshals
participating,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Marshals Service</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Stephen Boyle</PERSON>.
   A marshal who fired the gun that sent settlers scrambling for a
homestead in the <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> land run of <DATE>1889</DATE> at <LOCATION>Guthrie</LOCATION>; marshals
guarded the first black student at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Mississippi-Oxford</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>; and marshals ringed the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>
during the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> war protests of the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   They arrested gangster <PERSON>Al Capone</PERSON> twice and took the census until
<DATE>1880</DATE>.
   As evidence of those events, the Marshals' exhibit contains the
arrest warrant for Geronimo, an <DATE>1870</DATE> <PERSON>Ku Klux Klan</PERSON> robe and hood from
a recruit in the Klan's birthpace of <LOCATION>Pulaski</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, a <DATE>1790</DATE> whiskey
still from the Whiskey Rebellion era, and one of the two machine
guns from the <ORGANIZATION>St. Valentine</ORGANIZATION>'s Day massacre in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> _ the
bloodiest of Prohibition.
   The exhibit, which will tour a dozen cities over the next 2{
years, also includes a <PERSON>Jesse James</PERSON> vest and sidearm, and original
drawings by <PERSON>Wyatt Earp</PERSON> of four gunfights, including one at the OK
Corral involving the legendary wild West marshal.
   Appointed by the president, the 94 district <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> marshals are a
part of the executive branch, created by the first <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in the
Judiciary Act of <DATE>1789</DATE> _ the same law that established the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme
Court</ORGANIZATION> and the federal judicial system.
   The marshals of the <DATE>1980s</DATE> provide security in federal court and
protect <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> justices when they travel beyond <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
They operate the witness protection program that gives new
identities to those whose lives are jeopardized by testifying for
the government, and track down federal fugitives.
   They also take custody of those accused of federal crimes and
transport federal prisoners, running the government's only scheduled
airline service with two <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 727s and smaller aircraft out of
their <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> hub, <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said.
   They are responsible for property seized in the war on drugs and
other federal crimes and have managed horse ranches, restaurants,
condominums, a golf course and a greenhouse.
   With just 3,000 employees, the service is smaller than the <ORGANIZATION>New
York City Police Department</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said, yet its ranks are
stationed in every <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> judicial district from <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Virgin
Islands</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900111-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-90 1506EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-HomelessAid-List     01-11 0356</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Homeless Aid-List,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Homeless Aid Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the 126 counties dropped and 28
counties added this year by the <MONEY>$124.9 million</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Emergency Food and
Shelter National Board Program</ORGANIZATION>.
   Funding for counties and grant sizes are reconsidered each year
based on a formula that considers local poverty, unemployment and
the size of the overall labor force. The program was designed ``to
supplement and extend'' efforts on behalf of the homeless, and the
government does not guarantee funding to individual counties beyond
one year.
   DROPPED:
   <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Anchorage Borough
   Arkansas</LOCATION> _ <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Saline
   Colorado</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Montezuma
   Idaho _ Bannock</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bonner</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Nez Perce
   Illinois</LOCATION> _ <PERSON>Boone</PERSON>, <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edgar</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Fayette</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iroquois</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Knox</PERSON>,
<PERSON>McDonough</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ogle</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Tazewell</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Wayne</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>White</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Whiteside
   Indiana</LOCATION> _ Fayette, <ORGANIZATION>Grant</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Knox</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lawrence</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Miami
   Iowa</LOCATION> _ Blackhawk, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Wapello
   Kansas _ Crawford
   Kentucky _ Boyle</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Grayson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Greenup</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kenton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Letcher</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Lincoln</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montgomery
   Louisiana</LOCATION> _ <PERSON>Madison Parish</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Plaquemines Parish</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Union Parish
   Maine</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Cumberland
   Michigan</LOCATION> _ <PERSON>Barry</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Houghton</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Marquette</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mason</PERSON>, <PERSON>Monroe
   Minnesota _ Becker</PERSON>, <PERSON>Beltrami</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Carlton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Clay
   Mississippi</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Yazoo
   Missouri</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Washington
   Nebraska</LOCATION> _ Scotts Bluff
   <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Cibola</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Miguel
   North Carolina</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Beaufort</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Duplin</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Franklin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gaston</PERSON>, <PERSON>Haywood</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, Person, <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Stokes
   Ohio _ Adams</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Columbiana</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Coshocton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Defiance</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fayette</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fulton</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Gallia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hardin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Henry</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hocking</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Jefferson</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Marion</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Pike</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Putnam</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Washington
   Oklahoma</LOCATION> _ Lincoln, <LOCATION>Tulsa
   Oregon</LOCATION> _ Clatsop
   <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Cambria</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jefferson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Luzerne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tioga</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Westmoreland
   South Carolina</LOCATION> _ Cherokee, <LOCATION>Chesterfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Clarendon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colleton</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Dillon
   Tennessee _ Carroll</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dyer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Henry</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Jefferson</LOCATION>, <PERSON>McNairy</PERSON>, <PERSON>Marion</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Rhea
   Texas _ Bee</PERSON>, <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Fannin</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hale</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Midland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Palo Pinto</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Polk</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Walker</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Wood
   Virginia</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Halifax
   Washington</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Mason
   West Virginia</LOCATION> _ Lincoln, <LOCATION>Preston</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Upshur
   Wisconsin _ Brown</PERSON>, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Racine</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Rock</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Trempealeau
   Wyoming</LOCATION> _ Natrona
   
   ADDED:
   <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> _ Autauga, <PERSON>Butler</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Chambers</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Monroe
   California _ Del Norte
   Florida _ Okeechobee
   Georgia _ Barrow</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Paulding</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Polk
   Illinois</LOCATION> _ Aurora-Dupage-Kane
   <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> _ <ORGANIZATION>Scott
   Minnesota _ St. Cloud City-Benton Sherburn
   Mississippi</ORGANIZATION> _ <LOCATION>Grenada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neshoba</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Prentiss</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Wayne
   Missouri</PERSON> _ Dunklin
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Greene</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Orleans
   North Carolina</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Scotland
   South Dakota</LOCATION> _ <ORGANIZATION>Brown
   Tennessee _ Tipton
   Texas _ Morris
   Vermont _ Washington
   Virginia _ Henry</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Pulaski</LOCATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890329-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-29-89 0115EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SpeechFodder Bjt   03-29 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Speech Fodder, Bjt,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Politicians Get 520 Pages of Speech Fodder in New Book of Quotes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Politicians stumped for memorable quotations
to enliven their speeches need look no further than ``Respectfully
Quoted,'' a newly published book from the Library of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> that
is crammed with 2,100 oratorical gems from the past.
   The book might give some comfort to <PERSON>Sen. Joseph Biden</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Del.</LOCATION>,
whose <DATE>1988</DATE> presidential hopes were torpedoed partly by a
controversy over cribbed comments.
   If <PERSON>Biden</PERSON> recalls a famous line from President <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>'s
inaugural address in <DATE>1961</DATE>, he might be intrigued that Lebanese
writer <PERSON>Kahlil Gibran</PERSON> asked much earlier, ``Are you a politician
asking what your country can do for you, or a zealous one asking
what you can do for your country?''
   The book, a three-year project by <PERSON>Suzy Platt</PERSON> of the library's
congressional reference division, is a compilation of quotations
which members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> or their staffs over the past 75 years
have asked the library to verify for their exact wording and
origins.
   For the hapless politician scrambling to extricate himself from
trouble, there's this reputed quote from former Republican
presidential candidate <PERSON>George Romney</PERSON>: ``I didn't say that I didn't
say it. I said that I didn't say that I said it. I want to make
that very clear.''
   It was <PERSON>Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON> who cast this verbal harpoon at
President <PERSON>John Tyler</PERSON>: ``He has been called a mediocre man, but this
is unwarranted flattery. He was a politician of monumental
littleness.''
   Exasperation prompted former Rep. <PERSON>George E. Danielson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Calif.</LOCATION>,
to declare that trying to get answers from Attorney General <PERSON>John N.
Mitchell</PERSON> during <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> hearings on the Watergate scandal in <DATE>1974</DATE> was
``like trying to nail a drop of water to the wall.''
   ``These quotations come from the real world of cut-and-thrust
politics,'' says <PERSON>Charles A. Goodrum</PERSON>, former assistant director of
the library's <ORGANIZATION>Congressional Research Service</ORGANIZATION>, which compiled the
520-page dictionary of political quotes. ``They show the
combination of spirit and humor that represents American political
activity at its best.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Platt</PERSON> amassed verified quotations which researchers began
recording on 3-by-5 cards nearly 50 years ago to avoid
time-consuming duplication of efforts. The <ORGANIZATION>CRS</ORGANIZATION> handles more than
1,500 requests for information from <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> every day.
   The researchers discovered that some widely used quotes, now
part of American folklore, are impossible to trace to the person
who first uttered them. Other quotes have been mistakenly
attributed to a few legendary orators, such as <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>.
   It has never been verified, they say, that Lincoln _ or <PERSON>P.T.
Barnum</PERSON> _ observed that ``you may fool all the people some of the
time; you can even fool some of the people all the time, but you
can't fool all of the people all the time.''
   Who said, ``Winning isn't everything, it's the only thing?'' The
library says it wasn't the late <PERSON>Vince Lombardi</PERSON> but <ORGANIZATION>Red Sanders</ORGANIZATION>,
football coach at <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt University</ORGANIZATION>.
   Goodrum said <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> no longer produces thundering, long-winded
orators of the likes of <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON>, <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON> or <PERSON>John C.
Calhoun</PERSON>, and that television's insatiable hunger for 20-second
``sound bites'' is largely to blame.
   ``Today's politicians probably aren't as quotable as the
old-time orators who spoke in the measured cadences of the Bible
and Shakespeare,'' he said. ``Even though their quotes don't stand
up so they can be chiseled on marble as clearly, their speeches
reflect some very incisive thinking about the major issues of our
time.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061090-0213 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 231872 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 10, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 10; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1086 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AMERICA'S HEROES: MARBLE AND BRONZE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES HILLINGER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Each year, 1.5 million visitors view the bronze and marble statues that stand 
throughout the Capitol waiting to be recognized. 
</P>
<P>
Some are well-known. Many are not. 
</P>
<P>
Since <DATE>1864</DATE>, each state has been entitled to donate statues of two of its most 
distinguished deceased citizens for permanent exhibit in the <LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Once a state legislature decides who is to be honored, a statue is created and 
accepted by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for a place in the <ORGANIZATION>National Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION> -- <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s 
hall of fame. 
</P>
<P>
"People are always anxious to see the statues from their state. But often 
they're surprised and disappointed because they have no idea who (the people) 
depicted in the statues are," said <PERSON>Barbara Wolanin</PERSON>, 46, curator of <ORGANIZATION>Statuary 
Hall</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>1978</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s statues, both dedicated on <DATE>March 1, 1930</DATE>, are of a minister and a 
priest. It is the only state with two statues of clergy. 
</P>
<P>
Most visitors recognize Father <PERSON>Junipero Serra</PERSON>, the Franciscan priest who 
established nine <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> missions before he died in <DATE>1784</DATE>. Father <PERSON>Serra</PERSON>'s 
bronze likeness holds a little mission in his left hand, and in the right, a 
cross, held high above his head. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Thomas Starr King</PERSON> is not so familiar. "What did he do?" Californians typically 
ask when they see the statue. 
</P>
<P>
King, a Unitarian minister, came to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in <DATE>1860</DATE> from <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> to serve as 
pastor of the <ORGANIZATION>First Unitarian Church of San Francisco</ORGANIZATION>. It was during the Civil 
War and many Californians favored the Confederacy. Of the more than 100 
newspapers in the state, only 24 supported <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"King traveled throughout <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> championing the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> cause. He is 
remembered as the man whose matchless oratory kept <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in the union," 
curator <PERSON>Wolanin</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
King lived in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> only four years before dying at age 40 in <DATE>1864</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Of the 95 statues from 50 states, 14 are of religious leaders, including Father 
<PERSON>Damien</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>), who devoted his life to lepers on <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>; Father <ORGANIZATION>Kino</ORGANIZATION> 
(<LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>), a Jesuit missionary, and <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>), the <ORGANIZATION>Mormon Church</ORGANIZATION> 
leader. 
</P>
<P>
Five states -- <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> -- have 
contributed only one statue each. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>May 2</DATE>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> became the latest state to present its second statue, a 7-foot-7 
bronze likeness of lanky <PERSON>Philo T. Farnsworth</PERSON> (1906-1971), known as the "Father 
of Television." The statue shows <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> holding one of his first 
cathode-ray tubes. He transmitted his first electronic TV picture in <DATE>1927</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Students at <ORGANIZATION>Ridgecrest Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Butler</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, under the guidance of 
Principal <PERSON>Bruce Barnson</PERSON>, led the effort to put the <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> statue in the 
<LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In a statewide poll conducted by students, residents favored <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> over 20 
other Utahans, including <PERSON>Eliza Snow</PERSON>, a poet and wife of <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young; Mormon 
Church</ORGANIZATION> leader <PERSON>Ezra Taft Benson</PERSON>; hotelier <PERSON>J. Willard Marriott</PERSON>, and heavyweight 
boxing champion <PERSON>Jack Dempsey</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Among those present for <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Norman Bangerter</PERSON>'s unveiling of the statue 
was the inventor's 81-year-old widow, <PERSON>Elma</PERSON> (Pem) <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Three statues are of Presidents: <PERSON>George Washington</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Andrew Jackson</PERSON> 
(<LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>James A. Garfield</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>). Four are of vice presidents, 36 of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
senators, 23 of <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> members, 30 of governors and 32 of military heroes. (Some 
held more than one of these titles.) Six statues honor women: <PERSON>Dr. Florence 
Sabin</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>), author of the "Sabin Health Laws" that modernized <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>'s 
public health system; <PERSON>Frances Willard</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>), founder of the Women's <ORGANIZATION>Christian 
Temperance Union</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Marie Sanford</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>), educator and champion of women's 
rights; <PERSON>Jeannette Rankin</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>), the nation's first congresswoman; Mother 
<PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>), a Catholic nun who contributed to the fields of health care, 
education and social work, and <PERSON>Esther Hobart Morris</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>), the first woman to 
hold judicial office in the nation. 
</P>
<P>
six physicians. A king is here -- Kamehameha (<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>), and a famed cowboy 
artist -- <PERSON>Charley Russell</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>). Oklahoma honors two American Indians: 
Sequoya, inventor of the Cherokee alphabet, and <PERSON>Will Rogers</PERSON>, humorist, 
newspaper columnist and movie star. 
</P>
<P>
In keeping with <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON>' famous advice to "Always keep an eye on <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to see 
what they're up to," his statue is the only one facing the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> chamber. 
</P>
<P>
The feet of many of the statues gleam from constant rubbing, "for good luck," 
by visitors. Will <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> has the shiniest feet of all. 
</P>
<P>
There are statues of the president and vice president of the <LOCATION>Confederacy</LOCATION>, 
<PERSON>Jefferson Davis</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton Stephens</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>), respectively, as 
well as of "Father of Refrigeration" <PERSON>John Gorrie</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>), and steamboat inventor 
<PERSON>Robert Fulton</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>). 
</P>
<P>
America's best-known historic figures are here as well: Henry Clay (<LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Huey 
Long</PERSON> (<LOCATION>La.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>William Jennings Bryan</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON> (<LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Robert E. Lee</PERSON> 
(<LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Samuel Adams</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Roger Williams</PERSON> (<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON> (<LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>), <LOCATION>Sam 
Houston</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Stephen Austin</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>), and <PERSON>Ethan Allen</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>). 
</P>
<P>
Some of the lesser known include <PERSON>Jabez Curry</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Uriah Rose</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Edmund 
K. Smith</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>George Shoup</PERSON> (Ida.), <PERSON>Samuel Kirkwood</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>), <PERSON>George Glick</PERSON> 
(<LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Zachariah Chandler</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Zebulon Vance</PERSON> (<LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>Jason Lee</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>). 
Most visitors to <PERSON>Statuary Hall</PERSON> have no idea who they were, the curator said. 
</P>
<P>
"Other people pass away who are much more famous than many in Statuary Hall, 
but the states are stuck with those selected at an earlier time," longtime 
Capitol guide <PERSON>Madeline Allen</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Statuary Hall is in a part of the Capitol completed in <DATE>1807</DATE>, a domed 
semicircular room with sandstone walls and breccia marble columns, a room that 
housed the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> until <DATE>1857</DATE>, when the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> moved to its 
present, larger chamber. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed a bill in <DATE>1864</DATE> to create the <ORGANIZATION>National Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION> to house 
two marble or bronze statues from each state "of deceased persons illustrious 
for their historic renown or for distinguished civic or military services." 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1870</DATE>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> contributed the first statue, Revolutionary War hero 
<PERSON>Nathaniel Greene</PERSON>. By the <DATE>turn of the century</DATE>, 23 were on exhibit. 
</P>
<P>
By <DATE>1933</DATE>, there were 65 statues crowded into <PERSON>Statuary Hall</PERSON>, and it became clear 
that the floor would not support any more. 
</P>
<P>
It was then decided to keep most of the collection in the hall and place the 
others in prominent sites throughout the <LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Although the statues no longer stand in the same room, this gathering of heroes 
-- famous or not -- continues to be called <ORGANIZATION>National Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Visitors pass statue of John Peter Gabriel Muhlenberg, above, a 
Revolutionary War hero, in the National Statuary Hall. The statue of humorist 
and movie star Will Rogers, left, faces the House of Representatives. ; Photo, 
COLOR, States have been donating up to two statues of their most distinguished 
citizens, from George Washington to Sequoya to Zebulon Vance, to the Capitol's 
National Statuary Hall since 1870. California's statues of Thomas Starr King, 
above, and Father Junipero Serra were dedicated in 1930. CHARLES HILLINGER / 
Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Series 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
STATUES; MUSEUMS -- WASHINGTON DC; NATIONAL STATUARY HALL 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890908-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-08-89 1408EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LastResort Bjt   09-08 0718</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Last Resort, Bjt,0738</SECOND>
<HEAD>Historic Spa Foundering in Red Ink</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PG2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEDFORD SPRINGS, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For nearly two centuries, society's
highest and mightiest flocked to this <LOCATION>Allegheny Mountain</LOCATION> resort to
sip the natural mineral water and soak up elegance at one of
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s oldest spas.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>Bedford Springs Hotel</ORGANIZATION> is foundering these days as its
owners struggle to repay debts and avoid the auction block.
   ``We have the ability to revive something historic and to spur
the economy, and that should sound like government funding would be
available to do that,'' said <PERSON>Hobert Hobbs</PERSON>, 50, vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Sky
Group International Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which owns the hotel.
   Unless an investor comes to the rescue, the resort will be
auctioned off <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE>, nine days before <MONEY>$4.8 million</MONEY> is due the
bank. The money is what was spent from a <MONEY>$7.5 million</MONEY> loan made in
<DATE>1987</DATE> for renovations that weren't completed because of a dispute
between owners that ended up in bankruptcy court.
   Local folks fear that a new owner will raze the 185-year-old
hotel or modernize it to the point that all ambience is lost.
   Merchants in neighboring <LOCATION>Bedford</LOCATION>, a town of about 4,000 people
brimming with antique and art shops, say business already is off <PERCENT>20
percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> as a result of the hotel turmoil. Tourism
accounts for about a third of the area's income, according to <PERSON>Joe
Lurie</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Bedford County Office of Economic
Development</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It's like losing a big industry,'' he said.
   A few years ago, nearly 200 people worked at <ORGANIZATION>Bedford Springs
Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, a stately stretch of three- and four-story buildings on 2,300
acres in south-central <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>. They tended an 18-hole golf
course, tennis courts, a stocked lake, and hiking and riding trails
during the May-through-October season.
   Forty-seven employees are left. All but 66 of the hotel's 244
rooms are closed to guests, who dine at the golf clubhouse because
the main kitchen is shut down.
   Eight guest rooms were occupied on a recent weeknight, leaving
doorman <PERSON>Joe Koontz</PERSON> with little to do except read.
   ``They (guests) ask me what's going to happen next. Well I don't
know what's going to happen next,'' said <PERSON>Koontz</PERSON>, 61.
   <ORGANIZATION>Bedford Springs Hotel</ORGANIZATION>'s troubles, in part, reflect those of the
entire industry, according to industry observers.
   ``The hotel industry is in deep trouble all around the country,
big time. There are <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> more rooms than demand in the whole
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. It's an overbuilt industry,'' said <PERSON>Phil Goodman</PERSON>,
president of <ORGANIZATION>Western Media Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a marketing company in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Edward Watkins</PERSON>, editor of Lodging Hospitality, a monthly trade
magazine, estimates about 50 of the nation's 45,000 hotels and
motels are ``old-line resorts,'' which offer traditional types of
recreation in a spread-out, rural setting with a meal plan. Only a
dozen or so are 100 years old or more.
   ``The traditional guest they served is getting old and dying
off,'' he said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Bedford Springs Hotel</ORGANIZATION> was opened in <DATE>1804</DATE> by a doctor drawn by
the area's magnesia springs and their reputed curative powers. The
springs had been used for centuries before by Indians.
   The spa quickly attracted the notables of the times: <PERSON>Mrs. John
Quincy Adams</PERSON> and her daughters, <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON>, and statesmen <PERSON>Henry
Clay</PERSON>, <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON> and <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON>.
   President <PERSON>James Polk</PERSON> visited in <DATE>1848</DATE> followed by five other
presidents, including <PERSON>James Buchanan</PERSON>, who used the spa as a <DATE>summer</DATE>
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>. Candidate <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> stayed overnight in <DATE>1974</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> met at the resort to decide a case in
<DATE>1855</DATE>, the only time it ever met outside its chambers. And it was
there in <DATE>1858</DATE> that <PERSON>Buchanan</PERSON> received the first Trans-Atlantic cable,
a message from <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s Queen Victoria.
   During World War II, the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> established a radio training school
at the resort. The hotel also housed Japanese diplomats.
   <LOCATION>Bedford Springs</LOCATION> is being considered, along with <ORGANIZATION>State College</ORGANIZATION>, as
a possible <DATE>summer</DATE> home for the <ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hobbs and community leaders hope the orchestra's interest will
prompt the bank to grant a delay on payment of the loan.
   ``We're still confident something good is going to happen,''
<PERSON>Hobbs</PERSON> said. ``Was it <PERSON>Yogi Berra</PERSON> who said, `It ain't over til it's
over?' Well it ain't over til it's over.'''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900524-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-24-90 1557EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Wiltse     05-24 0188</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Wiltse,0195</SECOND>
<HEAD>Charles Wiltse, Historian of 19th Century Americans, Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HANOVER, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Charles Wiltse</PERSON>, a historian who was
considered a leading biographical expert on <DATE>19th century America</DATE>,
has died at the age of 83.
   <PERSON>Wiltse</PERSON> died <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Clinic</ORGANIZATION> after
suffering a heart attack, said <PERSON>John Wilson</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Rand-Wilson Funeral
Home</ORGANIZATION>.
   Wiltse edited the papers of <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON>, the prominent
congressman and secretary of state, in a 16-volume work completed
last year. He also was an expert on one of <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>'s
contemporaries, statesman and Vice President <PERSON>John Calhoun</PERSON>. In the
<DATE>1940s</DATE> he prepared a three-volume set on <ORGANIZATION>Calhoun</ORGANIZATION>'s papers.
   He was the author of ``The Jeffersonian Tradition in American
Democracy'' and ``The New Nation 1800-1845,'' as well as many
articles on the history of the period.
   He was a professor of history at <ORGANIZATION>Dartmouth College</ORGANIZATION> from <DATE>1966</DATE> to
<DATE>1972</DATE>, before retiring from teaching.
   <PERSON>Wiltse</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, and was a <DATE>1929</DATE> graduate of
<ORGANIZATION>West Virginia University</ORGANIZATION>. He earned a Ph.D. at <ORGANIZATION>Cornell University</ORGANIZATION>
in <DATE>1932</DATE>.
   He is survived by a sister, <PERSON>Clara Wiltse</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Muncie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind</LOCATION>. His
wife died in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920213-0086
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920213-0086.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf:
   The Trouble With Veeps
   ----
   By David Brock
</HL>
<DATE>
02/13/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A17
</SO>
<LP>
   Though presidential-primary results have yet to register,
it's a sure bet that politicians are already scheming and
cajoling behind the scenes in the hopes of landing the No. 2
spot on the 1992 ticket -- the Republican one, too. This
alone shows how far the much-maligned vice presidency has
come since Daniel Webster, in spurning the Whig nomination in
1848, explained: "I do not propose to be buried until I am
dead."
   Following John C. Calhoun, who was elected the seventh
vice president in 1825, no vice president was nominated to a
second term by a party convention until James S. Sherman, in
1912. As syndicated columnist Jules Witcover puts it in
"Crapshoot: Rolling the Dice on the Vice Presidency" (Crown,
450 pages, $25), through most of our history, the office was
a "certifiable dead end."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Judging by the dreadful bill of particulars <PERSON>Mr. Witcover</PERSON>
has assembled, this was a good thing. The overwhelming
majority of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> veeps have been dim, crooked, lowly and
loutish. Jefferson's vice president, <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON>, was indicted
for murder and tried for treason. Both of <PERSON>Ulysses S. Grant</PERSON>'s
running mates, <PERSON>Schuyler Colfax</PERSON> and <PERSON>Henry Wilson</PERSON>, were
implicated in the Credit Mobilier scandal. <PERSON>Calvin Coolidge</PERSON>
was counting on his veep, <PERSON>Charles Dawes</PERSON>, to break a tie in a
crucial <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> vote -- but <PERSON>Dawes</PERSON> slept through it.
   <PERSON>Herbert Hoover</PERSON>'s No. 2, <PERSON>Charles Curtis</PERSON>, was nicknamed
"Egg" for his wheeling and dealing for the poultry industry.
Under <PERSON>Franklin Roosevelt</PERSON>, the pro-Soviet <PERSON>Henry Wallace</PERSON> liked
to denounce American businessmen as "midget Hitlers." In a
delicious bit of foreshadowing, the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> once said
of <PERSON>Woodrow Wilson</PERSON>'s vice president, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Thomas
Marshall</PERSON>, "If <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> cannot raise men of presidential
caliber, she should at least try to train them to keep
silence when they have not the mental equipment to fit them
for an understanding of what is required."
   But dating from the tenure of <PERSON>Harry Truman</PERSON>, a scorned vice
president who turned out to be a heroic Cold War leader, the
vice presidency itself has been no joke (the current occupant
notwithstanding). Five of the past nine presidents had first
served as vice presidents, and in six of the past seven
national elections both nominees had first been presidential
understudies. Three -- <PERSON>Truman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lyndon Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gerald Ford</PERSON>
-- rose to the top spot following presidential death or
disgrace.
   The enhanced chance of today's vice president becoming
tomorrow's president has <PERSON>Mr. Witcover</PERSON> worried. He sees danger
in the slipshod selection process and the indifference of the
electorate.
   The fact is that advances in medicine and security make
the odds of a president dying or being killed in office
slimmer today than in <DATE>1850</DATE>. As for the vice presidency's
giving candidates a leg up in the race for the presidency,
this is due to television exposure and the ability to raise
money. In other words, it is due to politics; <PERSON>Mr. Witcover</PERSON>
writes as though vice presidents ascend through black magic.
   Still, it is deplorable that presidential candidates
continue to select running mates with little regard for their
worthiness as successors: <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON>, for instance,
tapped <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> because he wanted <PERSON>Mike Mansfield</PERSON> to be <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
majority leader rather than the treacherous LBJ. <PERSON>Richard
Nixon</PERSON> chose candidates who wouldn't outshine him, <PERSON>Spiro Agnew</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Mr. Ford</PERSON>. <PERSON>George McGovern</PERSON>, turned down by his first two
choices and unable to reach the third on the telephone,
picked the eventually discredited <PERSON>Sen. Thomas Eagleton</PERSON> on a
lark, thus ensuring that background checks would be part of
all future selections.
   <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> was no different from the pack in his choice
of <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>. But <PERSON>Mr. Witcover</PERSON>'s partisanship keeps him from
recognizing this, as he insists against his own evidence that
<PERSON>Mr. Quayle</PERSON> is uniquely unfit for higher office. He gives us
surely the most exhaustive list of <PERSON>Mr. Quayle</PERSON>'s gaffes in
print, but his portrait of the man is cursory and flat, and
he has almost nothing to say about <PERSON>Mr. Quayle</PERSON>'s substantive
record in the vice presidency, which is more impressive than
most of his predecessors'. (Even the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Post has
recognized this, leaving <PERSON>Mr. Witcover</PERSON> trailing behind the
Beltway's sluggish conventional wisdom.)
   One does not have to be a fan of <PERSON>Mr. Quayle</PERSON>'s to see that
<PERSON>Mr. Witcover</PERSON>'s huffing and puffing comes down to this: "What
if <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>, feeling his oats and prodded by his right-wing
constituency, brought in more doctrinaire conservatives to
restore the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> Revolution they feel was abandoned by
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>?" Personally, I think it would be pretty wonderful.
   The author is angry that the voters didn't punish <PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON>
for his choice. But for better or worse, vice presidents have
hardly ever made a difference one way or the other on
Election Day. To remedy this, <PERSON>Mr. Witcover</PERSON> wants to rob
voters of their right not to care. A new president would
submit his or her vice presidential nominee to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for
confirmation after the election, thereby eliminating
"blatantly political considerations" now impinging on the
choice. The idea that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> could make a decision free of
partisan politics, much less of character assassination, is
one that could only be held by a liberal <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
columnist.
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Brock</PERSON>, a journalist in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, is writing a
book on <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and foreign policy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890626-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-26-89 0127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SenateSilhouettes     06-26 0641</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Senate Silhouettes,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON TODAY: Senators of the Past Cut a Fine Figure</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At 400 pounds, <PERSON>Sen. Dixon Hall Lewis</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>
was the weightiest person ever to serve in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON>, a Democrat who served first in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, then in the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, was so heavy he had difficulty finding a carriage driver
willing to take the risk of hauling all those pounds.
   Once, wrote <PERSON>Isaac Bassett</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s assistant doorkeeper for
much of the <DATE>19th century</DATE>, <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> ``got into a hack and went right
through the bottom, onto the ground _ and if the horses had not been
very tame he would have been killed.''
   <PERSON>Sen. Lewis</PERSON> _ and the extreme rotundity of his profile _ is
presiding this <DATE>summer</DATE> over the marble-clad rotunda of the <ORGANIZATION>Russell
Senate Office Building</ORGANIZATION>, looming from a balcony in the form of a
giant, shadow-casting silhouette.
   <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> and the silhouettes of six of his senatorial colleagues of
his era form the somewhat whimsical background of an exhibit
illustrating the triumph and travail experienced by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> in
its first 100 years, 1789-1889.
   Born in <DATE>1802</DATE>, <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> served in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> for 15 years. He was
appointed to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1844</DATE>, dying <DATE>four years later</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Bassett</PERSON>, who made good use of his powers of observation during
his 60 years of service to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, noted that <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> rarely rose
from his specially constructed and commodious chair to address the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   Bassett wrote that <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> told him the reason ``was that he was so
big and fat that I would have to fan him, and it would not look very
dignified in such a body as the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.''
   But if <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> was an infrequent speaker, he did listen intently to
the major addresses of others.
   On <DATE>Jan. 26, 1830</DATE>, he walked across the Capitol and joined the
throng crowding into the chamber of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, determined to hear
<PERSON>Sen. Daniel Webster</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> defend the federal union.
   The ``enormous'' congressman was given a seat in the tiny lobby
behind the presiding officer's chair where he became wedged in by
other spectators.
   Because he was separated from the chamber by a painted glass
screen, he could hear <PERSON>Webster</PERSON> but could not see him.
   Describing the scene, <PERSON>Bassett</PERSON> said the frustrated congressman
``deliberately pulled out his knife and removed the obstructing
paint on the glass.''
   But the operation ``caused quite a noise,'' <PERSON>Bassett</PERSON> said.
``Everybody was looking to see where that scratching came from.''
   Finally, <PERSON>Bassett</PERSON> said, <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> cleared an area ``as large as a
man's hand,'' obtaining a ``good view'' of the famous <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>.
   The senatorial silhouettes, originally made on paper during the
<DATE>1840s</DATE> and <DATE>1850s</DATE> and now reproduced larger than life, bring together
an unuusal cast of characters.
   Joining <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> in larger-than-life profile is, for example, <PERSON>Sen.
John Randolph</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, a thin, stick-like figure described as
``one of the most brilliant, deranged and pathetic men ever to serve
in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.''
   <PERSON>Randolph</PERSON> was known to stride into the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> followed by a pack
of hunting hounds while flicking a riding crop and drinking a cup of
beer.
   Abusive in speech, he once provoked a duel with <PERSON>Sen. Henry Clay</PERSON>
from which both men emerged unscathed.
   Randolph lived to be 99, dying in <DATE>1833</DATE> just days before his 100th
birthday.
   Also on the railing above the rotunda floor is a far less
colorful lawmaker, <PERSON>Sen. Felix Grundy</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, who was described
by doorkeeper <PERSON>Bassett</PERSON> as a consummate insider and master of
parliamentary tactics.
   Near <LOCATION>Grundy</LOCATION> is <PERSON>Sen. John Forsyth</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> who cut a more
visible public swath with blistering oratory and cutting wit.
   Informed that President <PERSON>Andrew Jackson</PERSON>'s opponents were forming
the new Whig party, <PERSON>Forsyth</PERSON> remarked:
   ``It is a glorious name, and I have no doubt they will disgrace
it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880920-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-20-88 0253EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SenatorialHaircuts     09-20 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Senatorial Haircuts,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON TODAY: Senate Barbers Shaved Senators _ and Taxpayers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A shave and a haircut used to cost nothing, if
you were a <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> senator and were shaved and trimmed in the
<LOCATION>United States Senate</LOCATION> barber shop.
   And when one reform-minded senator tried to eliminate free
senatorial shaving and hair cutting 37 years ago, his
shaved-for-free colleagues rebelled.
   The senator was the late <PERSON>Paul Douglas</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, and his
experience was recalled in a recent <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> speech by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
Republican leader <PERSON>Bob Dole</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>.
   Douglas had gone to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> barber shop for a haircut.
   ``After the barber had done his work,'' said <PERSON>Dole</PERSON>, ``<PERSON>Douglas</PERSON>
began to think that his income was ample enough to pay for his own
haircut _ which then cost a dollar and a quarter _ and not charge
it to the taxpayer.''
   So <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON> introduced an amendment to the annual legislative
appropriations act to cut off funds for the barber shop unless it
began charging senators for its services.
   The counterattack was not long coming.
   At a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> hearing, <PERSON>Sen. Carl Hayden</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> complimented
<PERSON>Douglas</PERSON> on his haircut, then recalled that the haircut issue was
one that flared from time to time.
   <PERSON>Hayden</PERSON> said that when he first came to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> he became
disturbed at newspaper articles complaining about free senatorial
haircuts and discussed the matter with <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> veteran <PERSON>William Borah</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>.
   ``Senator <PERSON>Borah</PERSON> said, `You tell that reporter to go to the
devil. I want the same service that was received here by <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON>
and <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON>.'''
   Dole picked up the story, saying, ``After a good laugh, the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> shouted down Senator <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON>' amendment, and the free
haircut survived.''
   But only for the monent.
   ``I want to assure taxpayers that today senators pay their own
way when they have their hair cut, as Senator <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON> tried and
failed to accomplish 37 years ago,'' <PERSON>Dole</PERSON> said.
   While they pay more than a dollar and a quarter, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
barbering charges may be a bit gentler than those of most
commercial barbershops.
   The current charge for a haircut in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> barbershop is
<MONEY>$4.50</MONEY>.
   More elaborate cuts are <MONEY>$6.50</MONEY>. Hair styling costs <MONEY>$9.00</MONEY>.
   A shave costs <MONEY>$4.00</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   A shave and a haircut used to cost nothing, if
you were a <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> senator and were shaved and trimmed in the
<LOCATION>United States Senate</LOCATION> barber shop.
   And when one reform-minded senator tried to eliminate free
senatorial shaving and hair cutting 37 years ago, his
shaved-for-free colleagues rebelled.
   The senator was the late <PERSON>Paul Douglas</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, and his
experience was recalled in a recent <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> speech by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
Republican leader <PERSON>Bob Dole</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>.
   Douglas had gone to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> barber shop for a haircut.
   ``After the barber had done his work,'' said <PERSON>Dole</PERSON>, ``<PERSON>Douglas</PERSON>
began to think that his income was ample enough to pay for his own
haircut _ which then cost a dollar and a quarter _ and not charge
it to the taxpayer.''
   So <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON> introduced an amendment to the annual legislative
appropriations act to cut off funds for the barber shop unless it
began charging senators for its services.
   The counterattack was not long coming.
   At a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> hearing, <PERSON>Sen. Carl Hayden</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> complimented
<PERSON>Douglas</PERSON> on his haircut, then recalled that the haircut issue was
one that flared from time to time.
   <PERSON>Hayden</PERSON> said that when he first came to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> he became
disturbed at newspaper articles complaining about free senatorial
haircuts and discussed the matter with <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> veteran <PERSON>William Borah</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>.
   ``Senator <PERSON>Borah</PERSON> said, `You tell that reporter to go to the
devil. I want the same service that was received here by <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON>
and <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON>.'''
   Dole picked up the story, saying, ``After a good laugh, the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> shouted down Senator <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON>' amendment, and the free
haircut survived.''
   But only for the monent.
   ``I want to assure taxpayers that today senators pay their own
way when they have their hair cut, as Senator <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON> tried and
failed to accomplish 37 years ago,'' <PERSON>Dole</PERSON> said.
   While they pay more than a dollar and a quarter, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
barbering charges may be a bit gentler than those of most
commercial barbershops.
   The current charge for a haircut in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> barbershop is
<MONEY>$4.50</MONEY>.
   More elaborate cuts are <MONEY>$6.50</MONEY>. Hair styling costs <MONEY>$9.00</MONEY>.
   A shave costs <MONEY>$4.00</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911029-0073
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911029-0073.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Board of Contributors:
   A Bad Idea, Whose Time Has Come
   ----
   By Arthur Schlesinger Jr.
</HL>
<DATE>
10/29/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A22
</SO>
<IN>
LAW AND LEGAL AFFAIRS (LAW)
</IN>
<NS>
LAW &amp; LEGAL ISSUES AND LEGISLATION (LAW)
MANAGEMENT ISSUES (MNT)
POLITICS (PLT)
</NS>
<GV>
CONGRESS (CNG)
EXECUTIVE (EXE)
SUPREME COURT (SUP)
</GV>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Those last hearings before the confirmation of Justice
Thomas were a sordid spectacle. It may not be entirely
Pollyannaish, however, to note certain useful byproducts. The
nation's consciousness on the subject of sexual harassment
was significantly raised; about time, too. Moreover, the
television audience saw a succession of competent, posed,
well-spoken black witnesses who disagreed among themselves;
this should undermine the David Duke impression that black
leaders all dress up in African costumes and spout a racial
party line while the rank and file mug people in the streets.
   That about exhausts the good news. The hearings provoked
widespread titillation and disgust. Our national
self-righteousness demands a scapegoat, anyone but ourselves,
and is finding it in Congress. The Thomas confirmation
hearings come as a culmination of a series of scandals on the
Hill -- overdrafts at the House bank, unpaid bills at the
House restaurant, free massages in the House gym, fixed
parking tickets, junkets abroad, wine, women and song --
practices in which the rest of the population of course never
indulges. According to the New York Times/CBS News Poll, a
sizable number of Americans now see their national
legislators as generally pampered, arrogant and crooked.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Most of the practices under criticism are indeed
objectionable; and it is quite reasonable to hold members of
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to higher standards than we hold investment bankers,
stock manipulators, savings and loan operators and other
emblems of the private sector. Certainly the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Judiciary
Committee</ORGANIZATION> did not distinguish itself in the Thomas hearings.
   Yet it is a little hard, it seems to me, to place all the
blame for the mess on the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. Surely a considerable share
must go to the man who presented the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> with such a
dubious nomination. The <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> today is the most
undistinguished in my lifetime. In the past, presidents have
sought out people of national experience and distinction for
elevation to the court -- cabinet members, senators,
governors, eminent jurists, leaders of the bar, great legal
scholars. Even the reactionary justices who tried to kill the
<LOCATION>New Deal</LOCATION> half a century ago included men of intellectual
force like <PERSON>George Sutherland</PERSON>, <PERSON>Willis Vandevanter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Owen
Roberts</PERSON>. Today dimness seems almost a prerequisite for
appointment.
   <PERSON>Clarence Thomas</PERSON> is the third mediocrity in a row. It was a
cynical choice. The president called him "the best man for
the job on the merits" and denied that his race was a
consideration. But had <PERSON>Clarence Thomas</PERSON> been a white man with
the same qualifications, it is not very likely that he would
have been appointed. The opponent of affirmative action
ironically became the beneficiary of affirmative action.
   All presidents naturally enough appoint justices who they
believe will give their own views of public policy a
sympathetic hearing. But responsible presidents also have
some regard for the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> as an institution. When
their own predilections command a safe majority, they
sometimes take care to preserve the court's appearance of
impartiality by providing for other viewpoints. A rigidly
ideological and partisan <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> loses credibility and
falls into discredit. That is what happened to the "nine old
men" in the <DATE>1930s</DATE>. Balance is a reasonable consideration in
making appointments for life to the highest court in the
land.
   Thus <PERSON>Herbert Hoover</PERSON>, even if with reluctance, appointed
the great liberal justice <PERSON>Benjamin Cardozo</PERSON>. <PERSON>Franklin
Roosevelt</PERSON> made <PERSON>Calvin Coolidge</PERSON>'s attorney general his chief
justice. <PERSON>Harry Truman</PERSON> appointed <PERSON>Harold Burton</PERSON>, a Republican.
<PERSON>Dwight Eisenhower</PERSON> appointed <PERSON>William Brennan</PERSON>, a Democrat. But
<PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON> is not a lawyer and does not perhaps fully
appreciate the role of the court. One fears that he regards
judicial appointments as a convenient way of getting the hard
right off his back and thereby gaining a free hand on matters
that really interest him, like foreign policy. Had he
nominated someone like <PERSON>John Harlan</PERSON> or <PERSON>Lewis Powell</PERSON> or his
good friend <PERSON>Potter Stewart</PERSON>, none of this mess would have
happened.
   In the meantime, everyone is mad at <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>; and the
remedy of choice these days is term limitation. A number of
states have already adopted term limitation for their own
legislatures. Some states seek to impose limitations on their
representatives in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> as well -- a proposal of highly
dubious constitutionality, even given the present court.
According to the Gallup Poll, <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of American voters wish to
limit congressional terms.
   The argument is that limitation to a maximum 12 years of
service in either house would end the seniority system, shift
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> from constituent service to policy-making,
revitalize party competition, ensure a constant influx of new
legislators with new ideas and force legislators to pay
attention to the national interest rather than to their own
re-election.
   Well, perhaps. But the most certain result would be to
tilt the balance of the constitutional system even more in
favor of the executive. It is hard to imagine a greater boon
for the Imperial Presidency than to purge <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> of
experienced legislators who are specialists in issues, who
know the workings of government and who remember where bodies
are buried. What president would not prefer a revolving-door
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> filled with amateurs learning the ropes from scratch
and condemned to vanish when they have gained the experience
to be effective? Alas, it is not true, as <PERSON>William Jennings
Bryan</PERSON> is supposed to have said, that any man with sufficient
goodness of heart can write a currency bill.
   The Founding Fathers considered and rejected proposals of
term limitation. They were right to do so. It would have made
quite a difference to American history if such limitations
had ended after 12 years the careers of such illustrious
legislators as <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON>, <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON>, <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Thomas Hart Benton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Charles Sumner</PERSON>, <PERSON>James G. Blaine</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Henry
Cabot Lodge</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Robert M. LaFollette</PERSON>, <PERSON>George W. Norris</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sam
Rayburn</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robert P. Wagner</PERSON>, <PERSON>William E. Borah</PERSON>, <PERSON>Arthur
Vandenberg</PERSON>, <PERSON>George Aiken</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robert A. Taft</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jacob Javits</PERSON> and so
many others.
   Term limitations would bounce from our present <ORGANIZATION>Congress
Tom Foley</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Lee Hamilton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sam Nunn</PERSON>, <PERSON>Daniel Patrick Moynihan</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Richard Lugar</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON>, <PERSON>Stephen Solarz</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bill Green</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Charles Rangel</PERSON>, <PERSON>Tom Downey</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bob Michel</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dick Gephardt</PERSON>, <PERSON>Les
Aspin</PERSON> and other skilled legislators. Their replacement by
fresh-faced and untutored novices would unquestionably
increase presidential power, but would it really improve the
performance of the American government?
   One hears that the automatic return of incumbents is a
horrid new phenomenon. But recall the election of <DATE>1790</DATE>, where
38 out of 41 incumbent congressmen were reelected; or <DATE>1792</DATE>,
when all 45 incumbents were re-elected; or <DATE>1866</DATE>, when <PERCENT>85%</PERCENT> of
the incumbents seeking re-election made it; or <DATE>1934</DATE>, when 388
members ran and 325 were re-elected.
   Throughout American history, according to the
authoritative study by <PERSON>David Huckabee</PERSON>, the proportion of
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> incumbents running for re-election who were returned to
office has dropped below <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> only seven times and has
exceeded <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> most of the time. As <PERSON>Mr. Huckabee</PERSON> concludes,
"Incumbents who have sought reelection apparently have always
been relatively successful." As for the alleged tyranny of
incumbency today, hardly half of today's senators were
senators 10 years ago, and less than half the members of the
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> were members 10 years ago.
   When you think about it, the whole idea of term
limitations is profoundly anti-democratic. It assumes that
the quest for reelection corrupts legislators and that they
will better serve the national interest when they ignore the
wishes of their constituents. It assumes that the less
accountable a member of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is to popular desires and
needs, the better legislator he will be. It assumes, in
short, that the democratic process itself is the enemy of the
public interest.
   Surely a democracy requires a legislature that listens to
the people, not a legislature that couldn't care less about
the people. The desire to be re-elected, as <PERSON>Alexander
Hamilton</PERSON> wrote in the 72nd Federalist, gives the elected
official "the inclination and the resolution to act his part
well" and gives the voters opportunity to assess his
performance. When they approve his conduct, they can
"continue him in his office, in order to prolong the utility
of his talents and virtues, and to secure to the government
the advantage of permanency in a wise system of
administration." Term limitation, <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> said, "would be a
diminution of the inducements to good behavior." It would
increase "the temptation to sordid view, to peculation, and,
in some instances, to usurpation."
   If democratic government is about anything, it is about
the unfettered right of the voters to choose those who govern
them. Term limitation, by assuming that voters are too dumb
to choose wisely, is an insult to the people. Term
limitation, by weakening the power of the legislative branch
to counterbalance the executive branch, would be an injury to
the republic. And term limitation distracts attention from
the search for answers to the very grave substantive problems
that afflict and enfeeble the nation.
   ---
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881208-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-08-88 0320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Marshals'Bicentennial Bjt   12-08 0783</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Marshals' Bicentennial, Bjt,770</SECOND>
<HEAD>Legendary Lawmen Celebrate 200 Years in Action</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER DIXON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> marshals live in legend as the
men who tamed the Wild West, but their 200-year career is
intertwined with more of the country's history than just bringing
bandits to justice.
   The country's oldest law enforcement organization looks back at
its storied history today as it begins a bicentennial celebration
with the opening of an exhibit at the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> and a black-tie
gala at a nearby hotel.
   ``At almost every point in history when the federal government
was involved in a significant event, there were marshals
participating,'' says <PERSON>Stephen Boyle</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Marshals Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   A marshal fired the gun that sent settlers scrambling for a
homestead in the <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> land run of <DATE>1889</DATE>; marshals guarded the
desegregation battles of the <DATE>1960s</DATE>; they ringed the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> during
the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> war protests of the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   They smashed whiskey stills during Prohibition and arrested
gangster <PERSON>Al Capone</PERSON> twice; took the census until <DATE>1880</DATE>; captured
fugitive slaves before the Civil War and protected freed slaves
during Reconstruction; and did the hanging for ``Hanging Judge''
<PERSON>Isaac Parker</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Fort Smith</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, when <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> was still Indian
Territory and bank and train robbers hid in the brush.
   ``This is our heritage, the preservation of history,'' said <PERSON>Clint
Peoples</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Waco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Peoples is the executive marshal for the
bicentennial, and served as a marshal for 15 years in <LOCATION>North Texas</LOCATION>
and as chief of the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Rangers</ORGANIZATION>.
   Sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>United States Marshals Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, a non-profit
fund-raising organization, the special guest at tonight's event will
be <PERSON>James Arness</PERSON>, who played Marshal <PERSON>Matt Dillon</PERSON> on television's
``Gunsmoke'' for 20 years. One of those being honored is Deputy
Marshal <PERSON>Rey F. Cestero</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Savannah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, for his assistance in
apprehending two murder and abduction suspects in <DATE>August</DATE>.
   Included in the exhibit, organized with the help of the
<ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian</ORGANIZATION> Institution, are the arrest warrant for Geronimo, an
<DATE>1870</DATE> <PERSON>Ku Klux Klan</PERSON> robe from the Klan's birthplace of <LOCATION>Pulaski</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>,
a <DATE>1790</DATE> still from the Whiskey Rebellion era, and one of the two
machine guns from the <ORGANIZATION>St. Valentine</ORGANIZATION>'s Day massacre in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> _ the
bloodiest of Prohibition.
   The exhibit, which will tour a dozen cities over the next 2{
years, also includes a <PERSON>Jesse James</PERSON> vest and sidearm, and original
drawings by the legendary <PERSON>Wyatt Earp</PERSON> of four gunfights including one
at the <ORGANIZATION>OK Corral</ORGANIZATION>.
   During their first 100 years, marshals ``were the federal
government at the local level,'' says marshals historian <PERSON>Frederick
S. Calhoun</PERSON>. ``There was no infrastructure of a bureaucracy, so when
the citizens got mad, they took it out on the federal marshals.''
   Partly as a result, at least 400 and as many as 700 people in the
<ORGANIZATION>Marshals Service</ORGANIZATION> died in the line of duty, more casualties than in
any other law enforcement agency, officials say. The reason they
lack specific numbers is that officials are unsure whether all those
who died had been deputized or were simply parts of posses and that
``makes it very fuzzy,'' said <PERSON>Stanley Morris</PERSON>, director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Marshals Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   Appointed by the president, the 94 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> marshals are a part of
the executive branch, created by the first <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in the Judiciary
Act of <DATE>1789</DATE> _ the same law that established the federal judicial
system.
   The marshals of the <DATE>1980s</DATE> provide security in federal courts, and
protect <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> justices when they travel beyond <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
They track down federal fugitives and operate the witness protection
program that gives new identities to those whose lives are
jeopardized by testifying for the government.
   They also are responsible for property seized in the war on drugs
and other federal offenses, and currently have three-quarters of a
<MONEY>billion dollars</MONEY> in their inventory, <PERSON>Boyle</PERSON> said. Marshals have
managed horse ranches, restaurants, condominiums, a golf course and
a greenhouse taken in such raids.
   With just the 94 marshals, aided by some 2,000 deputies and about
1,000 support staff, the service is smaller than the <ORGANIZATION>New York City
Police Department</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said, yet its ranks are spread across
every <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> judicial district from <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>, who has a doctorate in history from the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Chicago</ORGANIZATION>, says the deadliest era in the service's history was before
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> statehood, when about 100 marshals died in Indian territory
between <DATE>1872</DATE> and <DATE>1896</DATE>.
   ``With the exception of Indian Territory, the far most dangerous
time to be a marshal was in the South after the Civil War,'' <PERSON>Calhoun</PERSON>
said. ``If the <PERSON>Ku Klux Klan</PERSON> didn't get you, the moonshiners did.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881011-0085 </DOCNO>
<HL> The First 'Heartbeat Away' Succession </HL>
<AUTHOR> Barry Sparks </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   Whether <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> or <PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> becomes vice president, the precise duties of the position they are seeking will be, as always, unclear. 
But the job does carry with it a sobering potential responsibility: to succeed the president in case of death, resignation or impeachment. 

   This fact has given vital significance to the public scrutiny of Messrs. 
<PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> and to their debate last week. 
But for the first 50 years of our nation's history, the position of vice president held no such importance: According to the way many political leaders of those years read the Constitution, there was no clear line of succession. 
No president had died in office, so the issue never had come up. 

   However, when the ninth president, <PERSON>William Henry Harrison</PERSON>, died a month after taking office in <DATE>1841</DATE>, there arose around his vice president, <PERSON>John Tyler</PERSON>, one of the fiercest political controversies in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history. 
There was, of course, no precedent for whether the vice president should be accorded the full power of the president or be regarded simply as acting chief executive. 
And the Constitution's language contributed to the problem, stating that "in case of the removal of the President from office or his death, resignation or inability to discharge the powers and duties of said office, the same shall devolve on the vice-president." 

   Did "the same" mean the office or the duties? 
Tyler said it meant the office, but his interpretation was not accepted by all Whig or Democratic leaders, newspaper editors or even his own inherited cabinet. 
Many maintained that the Founding Fathers did not intend the office to devolve on the vice president, just the duties. 

   Despite the doubts, <PERSON>Tyler</PERSON> acted decisively. 
<PERSON>Harrison</PERSON> died at <TIME>12:30 a.m.</TIME> on <DATE>Sunday, April 4</DATE>. 
Tyler, who had returned to his home in <LOCATION>Williamsburg</LOCATION> following the inauguration, rode 53 hours on horseback after receiving the news of <PERSON>Harrison</PERSON>'s death. 
He reached <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> around <TIME>5 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday, April 6</DATE>, convinced that he was the actual president, not an ad interim administrator. 
He felt the oath that he had taken as vice president was sufficient to assume the office of president, but in order to forestall any problems, he took a second oath. 
He was sworn into office by <PERSON>William Cranch</PERSON>, chief judge of the circuit court of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> Chief Justice <PERSON>Roger Taney</PERSON> was nearby in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, but refused to administer the oath because he hadn't been officially requested to do so. 

   As a vice presidential candidate on the Whig ticket, <PERSON>Tyler</PERSON> had done little campaigning, and he was not perceived as an important leader by politicians or the public. 
In fact, in the famous <DATE>1840</DATE> campaign slogan -- "Tippecanoe and Tyler Too" -- his name came as a sort of afterthought. 
As vice president, he had been expected to have little responsibility. 

   Now that he claimed the presidency, he met strong resistance, especially from former President <PERSON>John Quincy Adams</PERSON>, who insisted that <PERSON>Tyler</PERSON> was merely an "acting president." 
Adams felt <PERSON>Tyler</PERSON>'s ascent to the presidency was "in direct violation both of grammar and context of the Constitution." 

   Certainly the Whigs were stunned by the turn of events. 
In Tyler, they found themselves with a party leader who subscribed to few, if any, of their policies. 
Tyler had been a Democrat and was still a Democrat at heart who supported states' rights and opposed a national bank, in direct contrast to the beliefs of <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON>, the most powerful Whig. 

   Tyler held firm and won the day, although nearly six weeks after taking office his official status was still being questioned by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. 
On <DATE>May 31</DATE>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>John McKeon</PERSON> rose in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> to inquire if Tyler was indeed officially the "president." 

   Not surprisingly, <PERSON>Tyler</PERSON>'s nearly four-year term as president was a stormy one. 
He was constantly at odds with the Whigs, who controlled both houses. 
They were especially angered by his repeated vetoes of the national bank and high-tariff bills. 
Eventually, the Whigs disowned and denounced him, leading <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON> to call him the "president without a party." 

   Dissatisfaction with <PERSON>Tyler</PERSON> eventually led to impeachment proceedings against him, the first president to be so dubiously honored. 
The impeachment resolution, however, was defeated, 127-83, in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Despite all his problems, <PERSON>Tyler</PERSON> decided to run for re-election in <DATE>1844</DATE> as a Democrat. 
He was nominated at a <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> convention, but was persuaded to withdraw from the campaign <DATE>several months later</DATE>. 
This move was thought to have helped elect Democrat "dark horse" <PERSON>James Polk</PERSON> while defeating <PERSON>Tyler</PERSON>'s nemesis <PERSON>Henry Clay</PERSON>. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Sparks</PERSON> is a writer in <LOCATION>York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900208-0230 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-08-90 1311EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APArts:Lincoln Adv11-1stLd-Writethru-2Takes   02-08
1231</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-AP Arts: Lincoln, Adv 11-1st Ld-Writethru-2 Takes,b0526,1255</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv11</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Feb. 11, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Library of America Honors 16th President</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS 12th graf, In an open ... voters' time., to make it
Sangamon sted Sangamo; SUBs 14th graf, In his ... Sangamon River.,
to clarify family's moves; CORRECTS 17th graf, Elected to . ..
fellow Whig., to make it Mexican War sted Mexico; CORRECTS 37th
graf (18th graf of 1st add), On April ... following morning., to
make it Ford's sted Ford and Tyrannis sted Tyranus.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY303 of Feb. 6</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ``Every man is said to have his peculiar ambition. Whether it be
true or not, I can say for one that I have no other so great as
that of being truly esteemed of my fellow man, by rendering myself
worthy of their esteem.'' _ <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By HILLEL ITALIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Every man is said to have his peculiar ambition. Whether it be
true or not, I can say for one that I have no other so great as
that of being truly esteemed of my fellow man, by rendering myself
worthy of their esteem.'' _ <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910301-0120
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910301-0120.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   The Nays Didn't Have It
</HL>
<DATE>
03/01/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A8
</SO>
<CO>
   MDEST
</CO>
<GV>
CONGRESS (CNG)
</GV>
<LP>
   The following is a list of the representatives and
senators who voted against authorizing the use of force
against Iraq on Jan. 11. A related editorial appears nearby
(see: "Opportunity for Democrats" -- WSJ March 1, 1991).
                                                                                                       

</LP>
<TEXT>
   Senate
                                                                                                       
