<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880405-0202 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-05-88 1901EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LobsterRescue 1stLd-Writethru a0719 04-05 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lobster Rescue, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0719,0561</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lobsters Return To Sea After Roundabout Journey</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf ``Neuts grabbed'' and 14th graf ``Shirley,
whose'' to CORRECT by removing female pronouns for Shirley, a male
lobster.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AD2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY HARKAVY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE ELIZABETH, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With the flick of a tail and the
wave of a claw, two huge lobsters were freed <DATE>Monday</DATE> in the <LOCATION>Atlantic
Ocean</LOCATION>, safe from seafood lovers after a roundabout landlubbers tour
of the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``<PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>,'' a 25-pound male lobster, and ``Bob,'' his 19}-pound
companion, went down into the sea off foggy <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> Head Light.
   They had apparently already been hearing the call of the wild
and snacked on seafood in the tank where they were being kept
before their release.
   ``They were real frisky,'' Marine Patrol Officer <PERSON>Donald K.
Lockhart Jr.</PERSON> said. ``They put a quahog (a large clam) in there and
the big one just snapped it up like it was butter. They left a crab
in there overnight and it was gone <TIME>this morning</TIME>.''
   The two behemoths almost became a very expensive Easter dinner
in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> before an unlikely combination of animal rights
activists, seafood dealers and state officials came to the rescue.
   A 30-minute boat ride from <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> marked a storybook ending to
the rescue mission.
   <PERSON>Dana Neuts</PERSON>, retail manager of Harbor Fish Market in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>,
and <PERSON>Kevin Hill</PERSON>, owner of <ORGANIZATION>Main Line Seafood Co.</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>
suburb of <LOCATION>Ardmore</LOCATION>, had the honor of putting the monster crustaceans
into the water.
   Neuts grabbed <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>'s baseball mitt-sized claws and Hill took
the tail, and the two gently lowered the lobster over the side of
the 35-foot <ORGANIZATION>Maine Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION> boat. Bob went into the same
protected cove moments later.
   The two men who make their living from selling seafood agreed it
seemed strange to be returning it to the sea, but in the case of
<PERSON>Shirley</PERSON> and Bob they had no complaints.
   ``It feels great. It really does,'' <PERSON>Neuts</PERSON> said. ``I like the
idea of the whole thing.''
   ``These are well-traveled lobsters,'' <PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said. With his wife,
<PERSON>Vickie</PERSON>, he accompanied the two lobsters on their flight <DATE>Monday</DATE> from
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>.
   ``We shouldn't be catching lobsters this size. <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> is the only
state that's doing anything to protect them, and that's why we're
here,'' <PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said.
   <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> law protects lobsters with body shells longer than five
inches, covering crustaceans heavier than 4 to 5 pounds. It is the
only state with a legal limit on the maximum size of lobsters.
   Shirley, whose age has been estimated at 40 to 125 years old,
and the smaller companion were rescued from a <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> man who
wanted to serve them for Easter dinner.
   Col. <PERSON>Robert Fogg</PERSON>, chief of the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION> of the
state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Marine Resources</ORGANIZATION>, said the lobsters had
apparently gotten snagged in the nets of a dragger and were landed
in <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>.
   The lobsters had been trucked from <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, to Hill's
store, where retired carpenter Art <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> bought them for <MONEY>$287</MONEY>.
   After animal rights activists took up the lobsters' cause, Hill
persuaded <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> to take 45 pounds of smaller lobsters instead.
Pity <ORGANIZATION>Not Cruelty Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, an animal rights group, arranged to turn the
creatures loose and assumed the <MONEY>$40</MONEY> flight cost.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880405-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-05-88 1113EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-LobsterRescue 1stLd-Writethru a0448 04-05 0658</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lobster Rescue, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0448,0674</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lobsters Return to Sea After Roundabout Journey</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Rewrites throughout to UPDATE with lobsters returned to the
ocean, edit to conform.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Precede PORTLAND, Maine</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY HARKAVY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE ELIZABETH, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``<PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>,'' a 25-pound male
lobster with claws as big as baseball mitts, returned to the ocean
today, saved from a dinner plate by animal rights activists, a
seafood vendor and state officials.
   Lifting the giant crustacean by its claws and tail, seafood
dealers from <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> gently swung him over the
side of a <ORGANIZATION>Maine Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION> boat into 22-feet-deep water near
fog-shrouded <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> Head Light in this <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> suburb.
   Bob, a companion lobster weighing in at 19} pounds, was dropped
into the water moments later.
   <PERSON>Dana Neuts</PERSON>, retail manager of Harbor Fish Market in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>,
said he wasn't used to the idea of returning potential seafood to
the sea, but in the case of <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON> and Bob he had no complaints.
   ``It feels great. It really does,'' <PERSON>Neuts</PERSON> said. ``I like the
idea of the whole thing.''
   ``These are well-traveled lobsters,'' said <PERSON>Kevin Hill</PERSON>, the
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> seafood vendor who accompanied <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON> and Bob on
their flight to <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>. ``We shouldn't be catching
lobsters this size. <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> is the only state that's doing anything
to protect them, and that's why we're here.''
   The two lobsters spent the night in a 12-by-4-foot tank in
Neuts' market along the <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> waterfront before being placed
aboard the 35-foot boat for the half-hour ride through choppy seas
to a protected cove off <LOCATION>Cape Elizabeth</LOCATION>.
   Shirley, whose age has been estimated at 40 to 125 years old,
and her smaller companion were rescued from a <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> man who
wanted to serve them for Easter dinner.
   ``This is symbolic of what we're trying to do and what citizens
are trying to do for a natural, sustainable resource,'' said Col.
<PERSON>Robert Fogg</PERSON>, chief of the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION> of the state
<ORGANIZATION>Department of Marine Resources</ORGANIZATION>. ``By protecting these large
lobsters, there's more of a chance of them reproducing'' and
perpetuating the industry.
   ``It shows there's a lot of concern about our natural resources
out there,'' <PERSON>Fogg</PERSON> added.
   <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> law protects lobsters with body shells longer than five
inches, covering crustaceans heavier than 4 to 5 pounds.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION> said the two lobsters appeared to be in
``excellent'' shape after their flight and enjoyed a seafood dinner
in their tank at the <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> fish market.
   ``They were real frisky,'' said Officer <PERSON>Donald K. Lockhart Jr.</PERSON>
``They put a quahog in there and the big one just snapped it up
like it was butter. They left a crab in there overnight and it was
gone <TIME>this morning</TIME>.''
   The lobsters had been trucked from <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, to
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, where they were sold to a customer for <MONEY>$287</MONEY>.
   Animal rights activists took up the lobsters' cause when they
heard that Art <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>, a retired carpenter, planned to use them for
a feast.
   Hill, owner of <ORGANIZATION>Hill's Main Line Seafood Co.</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>
suburb of <LOCATION>Ardmore</LOCATION>, persuaded <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> to take 45 pounds of smaller
lobsters instead.
   Hill put the lobsters in a window tank for the rest of their
visit to <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>'s Main Line, acknowledging that saving
lobsters from dinner was something new for him.
   ``It's been very good for business,'' he said. Thousands of
people dropped by for a look at <LOCATION>Shirley</LOCATION>. ``If they don't buy now,
at least they know where we are,'' said Hill.
   Pity <ORGANIZATION>Not Cruelty Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a small animal rights group, made
arrangements with <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> officials to turn the creatures loose and
assumed the <MONEY>$40</MONEY> flight cost.
   It may seem a lot of trouble for a couple of lobsters, but group
vice president <ORGANIZATION>Gloria Felscher-Cohen</ORGANIZATION> makes no apologies.
   ``Why not?'' she asked. ``These two lobsters have survived
hazards, particularly <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>, over 100 years. Why should she need
to succumb to the cruelest predator of all, man?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880402-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-02-88 1313EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LobsterRescue     04-02 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lobster Rescue,0565</SECOND>
<HEAD>Massive Lobster Gets Reprieve From Easter Dinner</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAN GEHORSAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 25-pound lobster that nearly became
somebody's Easter dinner has been rescued and will be jetting to
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> to live out its old age beneath the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   Publicity forced a seafood company owner, a seafood lover, an
animal-rights group and the <ORGANIZATION>Maine Department of Marine Resources</ORGANIZATION>
into an unlikely alliance to save the creature, which was estimated
to be between 40 and 125 years old.
   Also saved from the pot was a 19}-pound companion.
   ``This was something that strikes you in your moral craw,'' said
<PERSON>Gloria Felscher-Cohen</PERSON>, vice president of the rights group, <ORGANIZATION>Pity Not
Cruelty Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Here is a very old lobster and it just seemed disgusting that
it should end its life to the cruelest predator _ man _ in a pot of
boiling water.''
   The 25-pounder, equipped with claws the size of baseball mitts,
arrived from <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 25</DATE> after an order got mixed up at
<ORGANIZATION>Hill's Main Line Seafood Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ardmore</LOCATION>.
   When owner <PERSON>Kevin Hill</PERSON> recovered from his astonishment, he and
his staff dubbed her <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>. Then he sold her and the other hefty
crustacean to a regular customer, a retired carpenter from
<LOCATION>Haverford</LOCATION>, for <MONEY>$287</MONEY>.
   But before <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON> was out the door, The <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> Inquirer
ran a story about her, and <PERSON>Hill</PERSON>'s phone began ringing with calls
from lobster advocates, including <PERSON>Ms. Felscher-Cohen</PERSON>.
   She told him it would be a ``lovely gesture'' during the
Passover and Easter holidays to celebrate themes of freedom and
resurrection by buying back the lobsters.
   She even offered to top the carpenter's price.
   After several calls like that, Hill was convinced. When the
carpenter came to pick up the second lobster, Hill offered him <MONEY>$387</MONEY>
for both.
   ``His first feeling was `What do you mean they're going to take
the lobsters?''' Hill said.
   ``I said, `Look, there's too many people (calling). Let's free
the things.''
   The customer, <PERSON>Robert Miller</PERSON>, agreed to exchange the large
lobsters for 45 pounds of smaller ones, rather than for money.
   ``I think it's ridiculous,'' <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said. ``What's the
difference between a one-pound lobster and a 25-pound lobster?''
   Pity Not Cruelty, meanwhile, had already made arrangements with
the state of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> to turn the creatures loose. The group assumed
the flight costs.
   Crated and covered with seaweed, the lobsters are due to fly to
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> for a few hours of observation.
   ``If they are healthy, we will liberate them the <DATE>next day</DATE>,''
said Lt. <PERSON>Joseph Fessenden</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Maine Bureau of Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION>.
   They should be freed off the shore of <LOCATION>Cape Elizabeth</LOCATION>, by the
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> Head Light, he said.
   In <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, he added, it would be illegal to catch <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>,
because she is much longer than the five-inch maximum (measured
from the rear of the eye socket to the end of the body shell)
allowed by the <ORGANIZATION>Maine Department of Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION>. The older
lobsters are protected, he said, because they have more offspring.
   His department will probably investigate <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>'s origins, he
said.
   The state helped save a 23{-pound Alaskan lobster from gourmands
<DATE>last November</DATE>, he said.
   That lobster ``was very lively,'' he said. ``I'm pretty
optimistic that these will fare as well.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06262207 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06262207 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  FOOD  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  CONSIDER the lobsters in the tank next time you're at the supermarket. Amid
rising bubbles they crawl, their claws clamped tight by thick rubber bands.;  
Always there, fun to look at. But these crustaceans are not for amusement like
fish in an aquarium. They are yours for steaming, cracking and eating -- the
ultimate shellfish.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Food  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  IT'S THE BARGAIN SEASON TO LET LIVE LOBSTERS CRAWL
INTO YOUR KITCHEN  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Seafood; See also related article on page 4D of this section.; Dotty Griffith
is food editor of the Dallas Morning News.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     How long since you splurged on lobster at home? Have you ever?;   If the
answer is a long time or never, perhaps it was the cost or the logistics that
dissuaded you. But now is the time, because lobster season is in full swing.
Prices are as good as they're going to get. (This week, at selected <ORGANIZATION>Safeway</ORGANIZATION>
stores, live <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> lobsters are selling for <MONEY>$4.98</MONEY> a pound.);   One-pound
lobsters, called chickens, are considered prime for individual servings of
whole lobster. Also desirable are 1 1/4-pounders, called quarters.;   And
following are Lobster Logistics: how to cook, crack and eat a lobster.;   To
cook lobster at home, try steaming instead of boiling. Maine lobster fishermen
prefer steaming because they say boiling can toughen the lobster and make the
meat soggy.;   Be prepared for an intense eating experience. In lobster
houses, bibs are standard equipment. Have lots of napkins on hand and be
prepared to eat with your fingers.;   How to steam a lobster;   Bring about an
inch of salted water to a boil in a pot large enough to hold lobsters. Place
lobsters (1 per serving) in pot, head first, and cover with lid. When water
returns to boil, add corn, allowing two ears for each serving. Steam lobsters
for 15 minutes, or until shells turn bright red and antennae pull out easily.
The corn should be done by then also. Serve with lots of melted butter.;   How
to eat lobsters;   First, twist off the large claws. Crack each claw with a
nutcracker, pliers, knife, hammer or rock. Separate the tail from the body by
arching the back until it cracks. Break off the tail flippers.;   Next, insert
a fork and push the tail meat out in one piece. Remove and discard the black
vein that runs the entire length of the tail.;   Then, unhinge the back shell
from the body. The green part in the body cavity is the "tomalley," which many
people consider the most delicious part of the lobster (it's the lobster's
liver -- some say it's not a good idea to eat more than one of these in a
day). The coral-colored roe is also edible.;   Finally, open the body by
cracking it apart sideways. Lobster meat lies in the four pockets (or joints)
where the small walking legs are attached. The small walking legs also contain
excellent meat that can be removed by sucking.;   <LOCATION>Trivia</LOCATION>;   From <PERSON>Ken Barnes</PERSON>,
captain of the schooner <PERSON>Stephen Taber</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Rockland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, who presides over a
weekly lobster roast for windjammer guests:;   "Lobsters' claws are bound with
rubber bands to keep them from hurting each other, not consumers. Because
lobsters are cannibalistic, their claws must be clamped shut to prevent them
from damaging each other during shipping.;   "The long narrow claw or 'thumb'
portion of each claw makes a perfect pick for getting to the meat in the body
and small walking legs of the lobster.";   From <PERSON>Peggy Dupont</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts
Lobstermen</LOCATION>'s Association:;   "Treat lobsters humanely by putting them in a
'trance' before they go into the pot. Rub on the underside of the tail for 30
to 40 seconds. When the lobster goes limp, quickly plunge it into the boiling
water head first. Add lobsters one at a time after water returns to boil."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DOTTY GRIFFITH, Universal Press Syndicate; Dotty Griffith column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910918  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  619  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, September 18, 1991
00262207,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880404-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-04-88 2001EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LobsterRescue 1stLd-Writethru a0602 04-04 0547</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lobster Rescue, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0602,0557</SECOND>
<HEAD>Big Old Lobsters Headed Back To Sea _ Hopefully</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with lobsters arriving in Maine, quotes,
details. New byline.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Precede PHILADELPHIA</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVA PARZIALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 25-pound lobster with claws the size of
baseball mitts that was saved from becoming an Easter dinner
arrived in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> on the final leg of a roundabout journey
back to the sea.
   Maine marine officials gently placed ``<PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>,'' a male
estimated at 40 to 125 years, and a 19}-pound companion lobster
into a 600-gallon tub of icy saltwater after their flight from
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>. Freed from their ice-packed travel boxes, the
lobsters immediately began moving their giant claws around.
   ``Very good, he's moving around already. That's a good sign,''
Col. <PERSON>Robert Fogg</PERSON>, chief of the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>Maine
Department of Marine Resources</ORGANIZATION>, said of <LOCATION>Shirley</LOCATION>. ``A real weak
lobster would be very lifeless.
   ``They're excellent. I'm pleased with the way they've shown up.''
   Marine officials planned to return the crustacean behemoths to
the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> early <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> off <LOCATION>Cape Elizabeth</LOCATION> if they remained
healthly overnight.
   ``This is symbolic of what we're trying to do and what citizens
are trying to do for a natural, sustainable resource,'' <PERSON>Fogg</PERSON> said.
``By protecting these large lobsters, there's more of a chance of
them reproducing'' and perpetuating the industry.
   <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> law protects lobsters with body shells longer than five
inches, covering lobsters larger than 4 to 5 pounds.
   If the lobsters' health deteriorated during the night and they
could not be saved, Lt. <PERSON>Joseph Fessenden</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Maine Bureau of
Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION> said the largest would be turned over to the <ORGANIZATION>Maine
State Museum</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``They're looking for a lobster to stuff,'' he said.
   Shirley and the companion lobster had been trucked to
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and sold for <MONEY>$287</MONEY>. After
crustacean rights advocates took up the cause, <PERSON>Kevin Hill</PERSON>, owner of
<ORGANIZATION>Hill's Main Line Seafood Co.</ORGANIZATION> in the suburb of <LOCATION>Ardmore</LOCATION>, persuaded
the buyer to take 45 pounds of smaller lobsters instead.
   Hill put the lobsters in a window tank for the rest of their
visit to <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>'s Main Line. He acknowledged that saving
lobsters from dinner palates was something new for him, ``which is
all right.''
   He also said that the lobsters had been good business, as
thousands of peole dropped by for a look at <LOCATION>Shirley</LOCATION>.
   ``It's been very good for business. If they don't buy now, at
least they know where we are,'' said Hill, who planned to travel to
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> to be on hand for the lobsters' release into the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   Hill delayed packing the lobsters for their trip until the last
possible minute. ``Believe it or not, I'm still getting people
coming by the window to look at 'em,'' he said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Pity <ORGANIZATION>Not Cruelty Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a small animal rights group, made
arrangements with <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> officials to turn the creatures loose and
assumed the <MONEY>$40</MONEY> flight cost.
   If it seems to be a lot of fuss over a couple of lobsters, group
vice president <ORGANIZATION>Gloria Felscher-Cohen</ORGANIZATION> makes no apologies.
   ``Why not? These two lobsters have survived hazards,
particularly <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>, over 100 years,'' she said. ``Why should she
need to succumb to the cruelest predator of all, man?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890324-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-24-89 0627EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     03-24 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>On The Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OMAHA, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A lobster who escaped the jaws of death when a
woman couldn't bring herself to eat him has found a home at the
<ORGANIZATION>Henry Doorly Zoo</ORGANIZATION>.
   The 24-pound crustacean called <PERSON>Clyde</PERSON> was the prize in a <DATE>January</DATE>
supermarket promotion, but the contest winner decided against making
a meal out of him and the <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> zoo took him temporarily.
   A Clyde the Lobster Zoo Fund helped raise some <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> money to
keep the lobster in <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>. At one point a man dressed as a lobster
stood on a downtown street corner and asked for donations, and a
radio station held a 28-hour fund-raising broadcast.
   Clyde was unveiled in his 240-gallon, <MONEY>$6,300</MONEY> saltwater tank
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The zoo opens its <DATE>1989</DATE> season today.
   ``Everything appears to be fine,'' aquarium supervisor <PERSON>Kathy
Vires</PERSON> said. ``He eats, he's active, he keeps his tail tucked. Those
are all signs of a healthy lobster.''
   Zoo employees sometimes find him standing on his tail with his
claws open and extending above the top of his tank, she said.
   Zoo Director <PERSON>Lee Simmons</PERSON> said the zoo would like to establish a
larger cold-water exhibit. But for now, <PERSON>Clyde</PERSON> is the only cold-water
creature on display.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A lobster who escaped the jaws of death when a
woman couldn't bring herself to eat him has found a home at the
<ORGANIZATION>Henry Doorly Zoo</ORGANIZATION>.
   The 24-pound crustacean called <PERSON>Clyde</PERSON> was the prize in a <DATE>January</DATE>
supermarket promotion, but the contest winner decided against making
a meal out of him and the <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> zoo took him temporarily.
   A Clyde the Lobster Zoo Fund helped raise some <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> money to
keep the lobster in <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>. At one point a man dressed as a lobster
stood on a downtown street corner and asked for donations, and a
radio station held a 28-hour fund-raising broadcast.
   Clyde was unveiled in his 240-gallon, <MONEY>$6,300</MONEY> saltwater tank
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The zoo opens its <DATE>1989</DATE> season today.
   ``Everything appears to be fine,'' aquarium supervisor <PERSON>Kathy
Vires</PERSON> said. ``He eats, he's active, he keeps his tail tucked. Those
are all signs of a healthy lobster.''
   Zoo employees sometimes find him standing on his tail with his
claws open and extending above the top of his tank, she said.
   Zoo Director <PERSON>Lee Simmons</PERSON> said the zoo would like to establish a
larger cold-water exhibit. But for now, <PERSON>Clyde</PERSON> is the only cold-water
creature on display.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881209-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-09-88 1415EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-LiberatedLobsters     12-09 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberated Lobsters,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Animal Rights Group Flies Restaurant Lobsters to New Home in Maine</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA M. HAMM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Animal rights activists on <DATE>Friday</DATE> spent <MONEY>$240</MONEY> to
buy seven live lobsters from a suburban <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> restaurant and fly
them to a new home off the coast of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>.
   Cam <ORGANIZATION>McQueen of People</ORGANIZATION> for the <ORGANIZATION>Ethical Treatment of Animals</ORGANIZATION> picked
up the lobsters from the <ORGANIZATION>House of Chinese Gourmet</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Rockville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>,
about <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME>, took them to <LOCATION>Washington National Airport</LOCATION> and boarded
a flight to <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, a PETA official said.
   Members of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> then were expected to escort her
and the lobsters to a boat station to release the creatures into
their new ocean home, <ORGANIZATION>PETA</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Victoria Thomas</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>House of Chinese Gourmet</ORGANIZATION> is popular among local vegetarians
who were offended when owner <PERSON>Jack Sun</PERSON> introduced the lobster tank
about a month ago, <PERSON>Ms. Thomas</PERSON> said.
   ``All of the sudden they put up a 125-gallon tank with live
lobsters, and there was a big outcry,'' she said. ``All their
vegetarian clientele got very upset.''
   Sun agreed to get rid of the lobster tank, <PERSON>Ms. Thomas</PERSON> said,
provided the animal activists bought the lobsters and arranged for
their freedom. The total cost of the lobster rescue was <MONEY>$240</MONEY> _ <MONEY>$40</MONEY>
for the lobsters and <MONEY>$200</MONEY> for the flight. The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> donated
its services.
   <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> is noted for its prime lobster growing areas.
   ``The water is cooler, and lobsters prefer that,'' <PERSON>Ms. Thomas</PERSON>
said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Thomas</PERSON> said there were no plans to free lobsters waiting to
be entrees in other restaurant tanks in the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> metropolitan
area.
   ``We particularly targeted that restaurant because we knew they
had a big vegetarian clientele,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-17306</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJIA1AEQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941008
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 OCT 94 / Food and Drink: First, catch your (Maine) lobster . . . -
Eating out / Nicholas Woodsworth's worthwhile struggle with steaming
crustaceans
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NICHOLAS WOODSWORTH
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Lobsters, I decided sitting back one evening and surveying my shell-strewn,
butter-spattered table at the <ORGANIZATION>Dolphin Marina Restaurant</ORGANIZATION>, are hard work.
I should have guessed as much when they began handing out foul-weather gear.
Disposable plastic bibs are de rigueur for lobster-eaters in even the more
sophisticated seafood establishments in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> - in some places motherly
waitresses will tie them on for you.
Then came the specialised equipment - the pincers for cracking claws, the
long skewers for probing recessed corners, the bowls for rinsing. It was all
new to me. I felt like a trainee dentist.
And what about the vast expertise required? How much experience, how many
botched jobs does it take before the seasoned lobsterer can artfully
dismember this complex little crustacean? I watched one man at the table
beside me deftly remove the meat from his lobster's tail with one clean
pull. There was hardly a drop of juice splattered on his bib. My own chest
looked like a <PERSON>Jackson Pollock</PERSON> painting. You could have made Thermidor with
what lay in my lap.
And is it, in the end, worth it? After the first bite I could only say yes,
it most certainly is. But lobsters, sadly, do not come cheap. Here, on the
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> coast, home of what are said to be the best cold-water lobsters in the
world, the pound-and-a-half beast I had just consumed cost Dollars 20. Try
eating the same creature in some up-scale restaurant in a western European
capital, though, and you might have to pay for it by instalments. All in
all, I decided, the lobster-lover's lot is a hard one.
'Just about as tough eating a lobster as it is catching one,' I remarked to
the young waitress who, as I mopped melted butter from my eyebrows, had
begun cleaning up the battlefield in front of me. It was only the happy
prattle that comes after a good dinner, of course, but she seemed to take it
literally.
She looked at me, looked out the window at a wind-whipped sea and boats
tossing at their moorings, then back at me again.
'Get real, will ya?' she said.
I decided, the very next day, to get real. My waitress had been right - much
as I liked lobster, I hadn't the faintest idea of how easy or difficult it
was to catch one. All I knew was that they were lured into large crate-like
traps. But no one visiting <LOCATION>Casco Bay</LOCATION>, east of <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, could avoid knowing
that; most people here make their living from lobstering and traps sit in
every backyard and on every wharf in sight. It should not be too difficult,
I thought, to get as close to a snapping live lobster as a steaming red one.
On <PERSON>Cook</PERSON>'s wharf, 20 minutes drive from the Dolphin Restaurant on <PERSON>Orr</PERSON>'s
<LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>, I came across hundreds of lobsters scuttling about the bottom of a
large holding tank. More importantly, I came across <PERSON>Ernest Hillman</PERSON>, the man
who caught them, and the <PERSON>Franny Ellen</PERSON>, the 36-ft lobster-boat he caught them
from.
<PERSON>Hillman</PERSON> was refuelling at the wharf's diesel pumps before heading out to
pull up 400 traps he had laid in 80 separate strings two days before. I
explained my interest in lobsters - not the ones already swimming in butter
but those still crawling about on the bottom of <ORGANIZATION>Harpswell Sound</ORGANIZATION>, the broad
<LOCATION>Casco Bay</LOCATION> channel that stretched away in front of us. Could I come along, I
asked? Why not, replied <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON>, he had something to tell me.
We shoved off with <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON> at the wheel and his two deckhands, <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Chris</PERSON>, sorting out cases of baitfish in the stern. A purpose-built
lobster-boat, the <ORGANIZATION>Franny Ellen</ORGANIZATION> carries a large tank of pump-circulated
sea-water and a platform for traps on her aft deck; there is not much
working space left over.
'Better ride with me in the wheel-house', <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON> warned as we headed into
the sound. 'Once the ropes start paying out it gets kind of hairy back there
 -you get your foot caught in a coil of rope and all of a sudden you'll find
yourself being dragged 80ft down on a string of traps. We lose one or two
men that way every year.' I rode, very happily, in the wheelhouse.
For a layman like me it was a perfect day; the wind of the previous evening
had dropped and we cruised out into a sunny, calm, scintillatingly clear
autumn morning. In this weather the thousands of coloured lobster buoys that
cluttered the sound - each one marking the beginning or end of a string of
traps - stood out brightly against the deep blue water.
For a lobsterman like <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON>, though, the day was less than perfect. It was
full moon, he explained, a phase that created huge tides rising and falling
more than 15 feet in <LOCATION>Casco Bay</LOCATION>. With strong currents like that running, he
said, lobsters tend not to wander round in search of food but to stay put in
holes and depressions on the floor.
We came to a floating buoy marking one of <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON>'s strings. His buoys are
black and orange, the other 30 or so lobstermen he fishes <LOCATION>Harpswell</LOCATION> Sound
with having their own colour combinations. Nonetheless, with some 12,000
traps out in the sound, locating one's own dispersed strings in this
multi-coloured maze - and not tangling them up with a neighbour's  -
requires a prodigious memory and skill.
The first string, as <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON> predicted, was disappointing. Winding the rope
attached to his bouy around a hydraulic winch, he began hauling in his
string of five traps. Each held three or four antenna-weaving,
tail-flapping, greeny-brown camouflaged lobsters; all but one, however, had
to be thrown back.
'Too small', <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON> explained, measuring each carefully with a brass
lobster gauge. Take anything measuring less than 3 1/4 in from eye to end of
body carapace and you loose your licence for three years. Take a female with
eggs and you are in real trouble. For every 100 lobsters I catch I keep only
about 20.'
As <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON> hauled traps, <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> rebaited them, sewing in two or three bait-fish
carefully trussed in nylon mesh. While the quaint lobster pots of the past -
knotted cord mounted on light frames of steamed wood - have long been
replaced by metal traps, the principle remains the same: lured by a
decomposing fish, the victim makes his way through a progressively smaller
aperture until, once inside, he cannot find his way out.
I began to understand <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON>'s warning after <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> had all five rebaited
traps lined up on the <ORGANIZATION>Franny Ellen</ORGANIZATION>'s stern. As he threw the first one
overboard <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON> hit the gas and 600 feet of rope and 75lb traps began
paying out at high speed. When you have to haul anything up to 750 traps a
day you do not waste time.
As he worked, <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON> talked. He is the quintessential Yankee Down-easter -
tough, resilient, enterprising and hard-working. He grew up on <LOCATION>Casco Bay</LOCATION> and
began lobster-fishing when he was 12 years old. In the <DATE>1970s</DATE> a hurricane
sank his boat and he had to fight hard to get back into what is an expensive
business - a lobster-boat these days costs upward of Dollars 60,000, a
single trap Dollars 75. But <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON> loves boats and fishing; they are only
thing he knows.
He surprised me, then, by asking if I wouldn't like to become the owner of
the <ORGANIZATION>Franny Ellen</ORGANIZATION> and all the gear that goes with her. I would not even have
to buy her. All I would have to do was win her.
Why? I asked. Six months ago, it turned out, a pile of lobster traps fell on
<PERSON>Hillman</PERSON>, damaging his spine and injuring an arm. He is fast reaching the end
of his trap-hauling days. When he put the <PERSON>Franny Ellen</PERSON> up for sale he
received a number of offers from young fishermen, deckhands wanting to start
up on their own. But lobster-fishing is a risky business: while some
skippers are in the six-figure income bracket, many more go bankrupt. None
of <PERSON>Hillman</PERSON>'s prospective buyers could come up with the bank loans they
needed.
Hillman's solution? He has set up an essay competition. If he can attract
2,000 contestants each paying an entrance fee of Dollars 50, he says, he can
recoup the value of his business. He walks away with the entry money, and
the writer of the best essay, to be independently judged, walks away with
his boat, 750 traps and 14 miles of rope. The essay topic? Fishing, of
course - 250 words of finely-honed prose on <PERSON>Ernest Hillman</PERSON>'s favourite
subject.
The morning wore on and slowly the tank on the <ORGANIZATION>Franny Ellen</ORGANIZATION>'s deck filled
with lobsters. In the end it turned out to be not too bad a catch: at <ORGANIZATION>Cook</ORGANIZATION>'s
wharf we off-loaded about 300 of the little brutes, each with their claws
carefully strapped tight with a pair of bright yellow elastic bands.
Later, flying home, I day-dreamed about those lobsters. I had no difficulty
imagining them flying off, like me, to distant destinations. In my mind's
eye I could see them roaming about restaurant display tanks in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,
diving into boiling vats of water in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, swimming through Newburg sauce on
dinner plates in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. And, if I closed my eyes and thought very hard
indeed, I could see them in a trap on the deck of my very own lobster boat
in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>.
Readers interested in <PERSON>Ernest Hillman</PERSON>'s essay contest may contact him on tel:
(207) 833 6010 or fax (207) 833 5956. Deadline for essay entries must be
postmarked on or before <DATE>October 15</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P5812 Eating Places.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Services &amp; Services use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880809-0115 </DOCNO>
<HL> The Lobster Clause Stirs Lots of Debate Over a Steamy Topic --- U.S. Lobstermen Seek a Ban On Imports of 'Immature' Crustaceans From Canada </HL>
<AUTHOR> Monica Langley (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> CANDA </CO>
<IN> MON </IN>
<G> CNG EXE </G>
<TEXT>
   Some Canadians and <LOCATION>New Englanders</LOCATION> are getting pretty steamed these days -- about lobsters. 

   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> recently hammered out a new pact designed to promote freer trade between the countries. 
Now, as the proposed agreement awaits approval from <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, a dispute has erupted over little lobsters. 
To be precise, Canadian lobsters measuring less than 3 7/32 inches from their eyes to the ends of their body shells, not including claws or tails. 

   "This isn't a joke," insists <PERSON>Sen. George Mitchell</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, who is leading the fight against the foreign crustaceans. 
Says <PERSON>Edward Blackmore</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Maine Lobstermen's Association</ORGANIZATION>: "I'm sure a lot of people out there equate lobsters with a luxury kind of thing, and can't get too worked up" over the topic. 

   But <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> lobstermen can. 
They are seeking a ban on importing the little lobsters. 
Conservation laws prohibit American lobstermen from harvesting lobsters of less than a certain length in order to allow the crustaceans to mature and reproduce. 
Canadian laws are more lenient, allowing fishermen to catch smaller lobsters, some of which they export to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
In fact, Canadians have captured half of the <MONEY>$731 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> lobster market. 

   American lobstermen are boiling mad. 
The Canadians are undermining conservation efforts and depleting the lobster population, the lobstermen say. 
Besides, they argue, if left alone, many of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s little lobsters would migrate south and grow up to be an ideal catch for any New Englander. 

   Nonsense, say the Canadians. 
An embassy official says the American lobstermen's efforts are "totally inappropriate" to the spirit of the free-trade agreement. 
The <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration also has cut the lobstermen adrift, saying the group's motivation in seeking the ban is protectionism. 
The agreement -- minus the lobster clause -- is likely to pass the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> today. 
But the lobstermen say they'll press on. 

   (The lobstermen also are seeking to bar imports of "berried," or pregnant, lobsters, or "scrubbed" lobsters that show evidence of eggs having been removed.) 

   Administration trade officials have tried several maneuvers to derail the lobstermen. 
First, they questioned whether lobsters migrate. 
The <LOCATION>New Englanders</LOCATION> fought back with studies that suggest they do. 
Then a trade official suggested the ultimate insult: Canadian lobsters mature and become sexually active at smaller sizes than lobsters that live in the warmer waters off <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>. 

   Trade officials also tried to butter up <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> interests by including in the trade pact a provision that would benefit potato farmers. 
To that, <PERSON>Sen. Mitchell</PERSON> retorts: "What's a potato without a lobster?" 

   American lobstermen are putting their faith in politics. 
They have high hopes for help from Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>, who they think is sympathetic to their cause. 
<PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON> recently assured the lobstermen that, if elected president, he'll still permit them to trap in the waters off his compound in <LOCATION>Kennebunkport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, despite possible <ORGANIZATION>Secret Service</ORGANIZATION> objections. 
"<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> understands," says <PERSON>Robert Brown</PERSON>, the president of <ORGANIZATION>Lusty Lobster</ORGANIZATION>, a lobster-supply business in <LOCATION>South Portland</LOCATION>. 

   In fact, the lobstermen figure they can't lose in this <DATE>fall</DATE>'s election. 
"Gov. 
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> knows a lot of lobsters are caught in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Mr. Brown</PERSON> says. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890201-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-01-89 0221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     02-01 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0562</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALTON, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was a good year for the company that
makes paper for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> currency, and that means more folding money for
its workers.
   <ORGANIZATION>Crane &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> it would contribute a record
<MONEY>$4.5 million</MONEY> to a profit-sharing plan for 1,100 employees at three
plants in western <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>. The payments amount to between <PERCENT>16
percent</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the annual salaries of workers, who make
<MONEY>$6</MONEY> to <MONEY>$12</MONEY> an hour, officials said.
   Last year, the company distributed <MONEY>$3.2 million</MONEY> to employees.
   Company officials declined to reveal how much of their total
sales of <MONEY>$119.8 million</MONEY> involved paper used in currency, and aside
from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, they would not identify the countries that
use their paper.
   Sales were up for all products made by <PERSON>Crane</PERSON>, such as stationery
and specialty papers for drafting, said personnel director <PERSON>James D.
Manning</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Manning</PERSON> did say <PERSON>Crane</PERSON> won a new three-year contract to produce
paper for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> bills in early <DATE>1988</DATE>. The company first began making
the paper for this country's legal tender in <DATE>1879</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was a good year for the company that
makes paper for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> currency, and that means more folding money for
its workers.
   <ORGANIZATION>Crane &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> it would contribute a record
<MONEY>$4.5 million</MONEY> to a profit-sharing plan for 1,100 employees at three
plants in western <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>. The payments amount to between <PERCENT>16
percent</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the annual salaries of workers, who make
<MONEY>$6</MONEY> to <MONEY>$12</MONEY> an hour, officials said.
   Last year, the company distributed <MONEY>$3.2 million</MONEY> to employees.
   Company officials declined to reveal how much of their total
sales of <MONEY>$119.8 million</MONEY> involved paper used in currency, and aside
from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, they would not identify the countries that
use their paper.
   Sales were up for all products made by <PERSON>Crane</PERSON>, such as stationery
and specialty papers for drafting, said personnel director <PERSON>James D.
Manning</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Manning</PERSON> did say <PERSON>Crane</PERSON> won a new three-year contract to produce
paper for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> bills in early <DATE>1988</DATE>. The company first began making
the paper for this country's legal tender in <DATE>1879</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>OMAHA, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was a good year for the company that
makes paper for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> currency, and that means more folding money for
its workers.
   <ORGANIZATION>Crane &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> it would contribute a record
<MONEY>$4.5 million</MONEY> to a profit-sharing plan for 1,100 employees at three
plants in western <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>. The payments amount to between <PERCENT>16
percent</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the annual salaries of workers, who make
<MONEY>$6</MONEY> to <MONEY>$12</MONEY> an hour, officials said.
   Last year, the company distributed <MONEY>$3.2 million</MONEY> to employees.
   Company officials declined to reveal how much of their total
sales of <MONEY>$119.8 million</MONEY> involved paper used in currency, and aside
from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, they would not identify the countries that
use their paper.
   Sales were up for all products made by <PERSON>Crane</PERSON>, such as stationery
and specialty papers for drafting, said personnel director <PERSON>James D.
Manning</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Manning</PERSON> did say <PERSON>Crane</PERSON> won a new three-year contract to produce
paper for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> bills in early <DATE>1988</DATE>. The company first began making
the paper for this country's legal tender in <DATE>1879</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900422-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-22-90 1616EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     04-22 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0533</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They came from all over to try the <ORGANIZATION>Scream
Machine</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Z Force</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Cyclone</ORGANIZATION>. The Mind <PERSON>Bender</PERSON> got
a pass, because as roller coasters go, it's no big thing.
   The Cyclone was getting most of the attention from about 450
members of the American Coaster Enthusiasts at their annual outing.
   ``Wood is a living, organic thing. Here, standing in the middle
of this one, it's like being in the heart of a great beast,'' said
<PERSON>Randy Geisler</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>St. Paul</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, president of the 3,500-member
organization.
   The enthusiasts were out in the fog <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> testing the
Cyclone, a new-style, old-fashioned wooden roller coaster at Six
Flags Over <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>.
   ``It's absolutely dynamite,'' said <PERSON>David Schini</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>,
who with his wife, <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>, had ``driven 11 hours to ride this
thing.''
   ``This one, it takes all the old-fashioned thrills and adds the
modern technology,'' <PERSON>Schini</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Cyclone</ORGANIZATION> combines the speed of a big, wooden roller
coaster with the twisting, banked turns of a steel coaster.
   ``To me, one of the most important things is the visual effect
of it _ white scaffolding, deep dips. The coaster will lift you off
your seat _ coaster riders call it `air time,''' said <PERSON>Glenn Allen</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Ocala</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   The 1 minute, 48 second, ride reaches a top speed of 50 mph.
   ``It's one of the great things about wooden roller coasters.
About all the members like the wooden roller coasters better,''
<PERSON>Allen</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>EDMOND, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They came from all over to try the <ORGANIZATION>Scream
Machine</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Z Force</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Cyclone</ORGANIZATION>. The Mind <PERSON>Bender</PERSON> got
a pass, because as roller coasters go, it's no big thing.
   The Cyclone was getting most of the attention from about 450
members of the American Coaster Enthusiasts at their annual outing.
   ``Wood is a living, organic thing. Here, standing in the middle
of this one, it's like being in the heart of a great beast,'' said
<PERSON>Randy Geisler</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>St. Paul</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, president of the 3,500-member
organization.
   The enthusiasts were out in the fog <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> testing the
Cyclone, a new-style, old-fashioned wooden roller coaster at Six
Flags Over <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>.
   ``It's absolutely dynamite,'' said <PERSON>David Schini</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>,
who with his wife, <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>, had ``driven 11 hours to ride this
thing.''
   ``This one, it takes all the old-fashioned thrills and adds the
modern technology,'' <PERSON>Schini</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Cyclone</ORGANIZATION> combines the speed of a big, wooden roller
coaster with the twisting, banked turns of a steel coaster.
   ``To me, one of the most important things is the visual effect
of it _ white scaffolding, deep dips. The coaster will lift you off
your seat _ coaster riders call it `air time,''' said <PERSON>Glenn Allen</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Ocala</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   The 1 minute, 48 second, ride reaches a top speed of 50 mph.
   ``It's one of the great things about wooden roller coasters.
About all the members like the wooden roller coasters better,''
<PERSON>Allen</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890717-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-17-89 0156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-LobsterResearch Bjt   07-17 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lobster Research, Bjt,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Biologists Hope to Unravel Mysteries of Lobster Supply</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA EMERY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maine lobstermen are laying three times as
much bait and scientists have even tried raising lobster larvae in
test tanks, but the harvest of the tasty crustaceans hasn't
increased in 20 years.
   Marine biologists from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maine</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Bigelow
Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>West Boothbay</LOCATION> are conducting a 10-day research cruise
next month, and hope their detailed probe of breeding grounds will
help explain the inability of lobstermen to increase the annual
catch.
   The lobstermen, some of whom have volunteered to assist
biologists as they map the ocean floor, are hoping the investigation
will lead to bigger catches.
   Lobster production is vital to <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>'s economy, not least because
of its contribution to tourism.
   ``We want to make sure that resource is around a thousand years
from now. It's so much a part of our income, our history and our
art, it's just incredibly important to us,'' said <PERSON>Dave Dow</PERSON>, director
of the <ORGANIZATION>Lobster Institute</ORGANIZATION>, a trade organization affiliated with the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Maine</ORGANIZATION>.
   The harvest of the ``bugs,'' as they are affectionately called by
lobstermen, has remained at about <MONEY>21 million pounds</MONEY> per year during
the past two decades, despite legal, scientific, and practical
measures to increase it.
   Biologists at the <ORGANIZATION>Cutler Marine Hatchery</ORGANIZATION> have coaxed thousands of
lobster eggs to grow at a quickened rate in warm-water tanks and
then stocked coastal waters with the immature larvae.
   State legislators have gradually increased the minimum size
limit, hoping more females would mature and reproduce.
   And lobstermen have worked harder; they haul about triple the
number of traps they put out 20 years ago. But the lobsters have
refused to take the extra bait, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Lobster Institute</ORGANIZATION>.
   In next month's cruise, five scientists aboard the research
vessel Argo <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> will survey four major lobstering sites in the
<LOCATION>Gulf of Maine</LOCATION>.
   They will use sonar to determine the sea bottom's
characteristics; search for and count larval lobsters; scuba dive to
survey lobster densities, shelter sizes and abundance of predators;
and sample ocean bottom sediment for invertebrates.
   The investigation could affect where lobstermen set their traps,
as well as plans to stock coastal waters, said <PERSON>Dave Cousins</PERSON>, a
lobsterman from <LOCATION>South Thomaston</LOCATION>, 75 miles northeast of <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>.
   University of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> marine biologist <PERSON>Robert Steneck</PERSON>, one of the
project leaders, has sought for eight years to explain the static
harvest.
   ``His theory operates on the premise that something in nature
limits our productivity out there,'' Dow said.
   The limiting factor could be the amount of suitable habitat the
lobsters can live in, the amount of food available for the
creatures, or the ecological balance of lobsters and their
predators, <ORGANIZATION>Dow</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The lobsters go through three planktonic, or swimming stages,
before they are ready to settle on the sea bottom, and the suitable
bottom habitat is distributed in patches along the shoreline.
   ``If Mother Nature, because of the way she works the tides and
currents, doesn't allow delivery to the appropriate habitats, that's
going to be important for the overall production,'' Dow said.
   The public's appetite for lobster is matched by the appetites of
various marine creatures, he said.
   ``There's a million lobster-seeking missiles waiting for those
little fellows to hit the bottom ... these little fellows are
subject to thousands of attacks a day.''
   Large codfish have been found to contain up to a dozen lobsters
when they are cut open, <ORGANIZATION>Dow</ORGANIZATION> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032990-0190 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 196732 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 29, 1990, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
654 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ORANGE COUNTY FOCUS: COUNTYWIDE; 
</P>
<P>
MARINE LIFE SERVED UP IN ROAD SHOW 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEN HALL) 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The arthropod, of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> spiny variety, was surrounded. 
</P>
<P>
Antennae waving, his layered tail twitching, the arthropod, more commonly known 
as a lobster, was eyeball to eyeball with about 10 second- and third-graders in 
<PERSON>Kendall Clark</PERSON>'s class at <ORGANIZATION>Andrew Jackson Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>. 
Everyone wanted to touch, but <PERSON>Carolyn Cosgrove-Wake</PERSON> warned them to be gentle. 
</P>
<P>
"Try not to touch his eyeball," Cosgrove-Wake said. "Would you want anybody 
touching your eyeball?" 
</P>
<P>
She pointed to the lobster's antennae. 
</P>
<P>
"They give him information," she said. "And his eyes, they look like a bug's 
because he is related to a bug." 
</P>
<P>
Cosgrove-Wake, a marine biologist, is the driver and lecturer of the <ORGANIZATION>Orange 
County Marine Institute</ORGANIZATION>'s traveling road show, Ocean in Motion. Out of a 
strategically loaded, new blue van, Cosgrove-Wake travels to schools all over 
the county offering a hands-on experience with live marine life. Joining the 
lobster on the traveling team is an octopus, a jar full of mussels, a sea star, 
oysters, clams and a sea urchin, among other creatures. The live lobster rides 
in a temperature controlled fiberglass aquarium custom made for the van by 
<ORGANIZATION>Cosgrove-Wake</ORGANIZATION>'s husband, <PERSON>John Wake</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The van also carries an assortment of shells, sand dollars, coral and other 
skeletal forms of marine life. The children listen for the sounds of the ocean 
and try to match the shells with a chart that identifies them. 
</P>
<P>
"We try to expose the children to a broader spectrum of their environment," 
Cosgrove-Wake said. "There's a living ocean out there they need to be aware of. 
We also try to instill a sense of conservation and preservation of the ocean." 
</P>
<P>
The alert, twitching <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> spiny lobster always wins lots of attention, 
Cosgrove-Wake said. The students learn that he doesn't have claws like his 
cousin from <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, the family member sometimes offered in upscale restaurants; 
that his tail can propel him backwards to escape dangers; that like his other 
cousins, the bugs, he's a scavenger on the ocean floor, and that because his 
flaps on his tail don't overlap, he is a he and not a she. 
</P>
<P>
Real live creatures such as the lobster can spark a fascination that may 
overcome what is, for many children, a dreaded word -- science. 
</P>
<P>
"I always tell the children right away, 'This is science,' " Cosgrove-Wake 
said. "I'm trying to bring science back into the classroom. I tell them that we 
have to understand science and that it is our real world. If I can influence 
just one child that if we don't protect our environment we'll lose everything 
that we have, (the class) is successful." 
</P>
<P>
For some in <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s class at <LOCATION>Jackson School</LOCATION>, this was their first experience 
with sea creatures. 
</P>
<P>
"Some of these kids have never been to the beach," said <PERSON>Gloria Roelen</PERSON>, 
principal of the 1,197-student school. The student enrollment is about <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> 
Latino, <PERCENT>17%</PERCENT> Asian, and the remainder a mixture of ethnicities. 
</P>
<P>
"Some of their parents might work <DATE>Saturdays</DATE> and <DATE>Sundays</DATE>, possibly they don't 
have transportation or they might not feel comfortable venturing out," <PERSON>Roelen</PERSON> 
said. "Many of the parents don't speak English." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s class, made up of a combination second- and third-graders, is called 
"immersion English," in which the students are learning the English language as 
well as the customs of what, in many cases, is their new country. Part of that 
process is hands-on experiences such as the lessons taught by <ORGANIZATION>Ocean in Motion</ORGANIZATION>, 
<PERSON>Roelen</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"The most important thing -- look at them -- is that they're learning and 
having fun doing it," <PERSON>Roelen</PERSON> said. "They're involved in the learning process 
and it's not someone dictating to them." 
</P>
<P>
Cosgrove-Wake travels from campus to campus, giving lectures at assemblies, 
talking to high school, junior high and grade school students. Wherever she 
goes, her family of creatures, especially the lobster, draws a crowd. 
</P>
<P>
"Sometimes I feel like the Pied Piper," she said. LEN HALL) 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Carolyn Cosgrove-Wake shows students live lobster, part of Orange County 
Marine Institute traveling sea life show. ; Photo, Mariam Cantoran's face 
reflects wonder as she hears the roar of the sea from a shell during show at 
Andrew Jackson Elementary School, Santa Ana. KARI RENE HALL / Los Angeles 
Times; Photo, FOCUS: Andrew Jackson Elementary School students in Santa Ana got 
a close look at sea shells -- part of Orange County Marine Institute's 
traveling show. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MARINE LIFE; ORANGE COUNTY MARINE INSTITUTE; ORANGE COUNTY -- EDUCATION; ORANGE 
COUNTY -- SCHOOLS; MARINE BIOLOGY; STUDENTS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870220-0074 </DOCNO>
<HL> Personally, We Would Like to See
How Marine Worms Would Look
---
By Kim Clark
<DD> 02/20/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> AUGUSTA, Maine  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When it comes to license plates, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> has always kept a fairly low profile. 
No dramatics like <ORGANIZATION>New Hampshire</ORGANIZATION> ("Live Free or Die"); no wishful thinking like <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> ("The Garden State"). 
Just a simple black and white plate with the words "<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>" and "Vacationland." 

   Last year, however, the state enacted a law that -- beginning <DATE>July 1</DATE> -- will force drivers to trade in the simple for the sublime: a new license plate in blue and white trim that features a bright red lobster. 

   And now, some normally reserved Mainers -- including lots of school children -- are boiling. 

   It seems that quite a few residents are having second thoughts about riding around with a lobster on their tail. 
"I am receiving letters from people all over the state," says Rep. <PERSON>Mary McBride</PERSON>, who is sponsoring a bill to give drivers a choice of license plates. 
"I didn't realize this was going to be such an emotional issue." 

   The children, however, are angry for the opposite reason: It was their idea to put lobsters on licenses in the first place. 
What began as a civics project in <DATE>1983</DATE> in a fourth-grade class in <LOCATION>Kennebunk</LOCATION> ended up as a statewide campaign to add a little flavor to <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>'s auto tags. 
With children crowding their chamber, legislators approved the change by a vote of 156-5. 

   Revising the law now would be a blow to the students, says <PERSON>Peter Towne</PERSON>, the teacher who started the whole thing. 
"The governor came down and signed the bill, and all the kids said, 'Boy, this is going to be on Dad's plate,'" he says. 
"The kids are a little upset." 

   Not surprisingly, the children are getting moral support from the state's lobstermen, who oppose any plans to give drivers a choice of plates, says <PERSON>Edward A. Blackmore</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Maine Lobstermen's Association</ORGANIZATION>. 
"If you don't like it, don't look at it," he says. 

   Those on the other side of the fence include animal-rights activists and vegetarians -- who note that lobsters are red only after they've been cooked -- and residents who would like to see license plates with a pine tree, a lighthouse, a potato, or even marine worms (a big industry in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>). 
Anything but a lobster. 

   <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> housewife <PERSON>Gayle Drummond</PERSON>, for example, says she is outraged by the legislature's capitulation to the students. 

   "You want to cheer kids on so they grow and learn," she says. 
"But this is like a cheap souvenir of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> . . . . 
It's more like <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION> than <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890222-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-22-89 1723EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Brites     02-22 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0417</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TACOMA, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A live <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> lobster bought for a
<ORGANIZATION>Valentine</ORGANIZATION>'s Day dinner got a reprieve from a boiling pot when a wife
told her husband she preferred the sea crustacean as a pet instead
of as a main course.
   <PERSON>Suzanne Brown</PERSON> had planned to serve the lobster to her husband,
<PERSON>Dave</PERSON>, to crown a romantic, home-cooked dinner.
   She presented her husband with the <MONEY>$14</MONEY> catch wrapped in
newspaper, a valentine attached. But when it came time to drop it in
the boiling water, <PERSON>Suzanne</PERSON> proved to be softer skinned than her
hard-shelled prey.
   ``I kinda fell in love with a lobster,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Brown</PERSON>. ``I
decided I wanted to keep him for a pet.''
   The 1\-pound lobster, dubbed Oscar, stayed alive in the <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>'s
refrigerator in a damp towel while <PERSON>Suzanne</PERSON> called around for help in
setting up a lobster tank.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Aquarium</ORGANIZATION> couldn't help her, nor could the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Washington</ORGANIZATION>. She finally went back to seafood market, where she
learned that the smallest commercial tanks go for <MONEY>$1,200</MONEY>.
   So <PERSON>Gary Gerontis</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Johnny</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Seaford</LOCATION> took the lobster back and
promised to fly it back to <LOCATION>Gloucester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, so that the wholesaler
can throw it back into the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   ``He could live another 50 years, or he could get caught next
week,'' said <PERSON>Harold Frisk</PERSON>, sales manager for the wholesaler,
<ORGANIZATION>International Lobster</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A live <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> lobster bought for a
<ORGANIZATION>Valentine</ORGANIZATION>'s Day dinner got a reprieve from a boiling pot when a wife
told her husband she preferred the sea crustacean as a pet instead
of as a main course.
   <PERSON>Suzanne Brown</PERSON> had planned to serve the lobster to her husband,
<PERSON>Dave</PERSON>, to crown a romantic, home-cooked dinner.
   She presented her husband with the <MONEY>$14</MONEY> catch wrapped in
newspaper, a valentine attached. But when it came time to drop it in
the boiling water, <PERSON>Suzanne</PERSON> proved to be softer skinned than her
hard-shelled prey.
   ``I kinda fell in love with a lobster,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Brown</PERSON>. ``I
decided I wanted to keep him for a pet.''
   The 1\-pound lobster, dubbed Oscar, stayed alive in the <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>'s
refrigerator in a damp towel while <PERSON>Suzanne</PERSON> called around for help in
setting up a lobster tank.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Aquarium</ORGANIZATION> couldn't help her, nor could the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Washington</ORGANIZATION>. She finally went back to seafood market, where she
learned that the smallest commercial tanks go for <MONEY>$1,200</MONEY>.
   So <PERSON>Gary Gerontis</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Johnny</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Seaford</LOCATION> took the lobster back and
promised to fly it back to <LOCATION>Gloucester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, so that the wholesaler
can throw it back into the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   ``He could live another 50 years, or he could get caught next
week,'' said <PERSON>Harold Frisk</PERSON>, sales manager for the wholesaler,
<ORGANIZATION>International Lobster</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901106-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-06-90 0823EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lite-MonsterLobster     11-06 0178</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lite-Monster Lobster,0200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Monster Lobster Headed for Platters</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mimi, the 17{-pound lobster described as the
<PERSON>Elizabeth Taylor</PERSON> of crustaceans, died of natural causes days after
being shipped to her new home - at a restaurant. She was 20 to 100
years old, officials said.
   Mimi, captured last week off the <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> coast and flown to
<LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, died <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in the tank at <ORGANIZATION>Carl's Chop House</ORGANIZATION>, which paid
<MONEY>$320</MONEY> for the huge lobster.
   ``She had quit moving. I picked her up. She still didn't move,''
said <PERSON>Barry Hornecker</PERSON>, executive chef at <ORGANIZATION>Carl's</ORGANIZATION>.
   So he chilled and poached <PERSON>Mimi</PERSON> and began making plans for a
feast.
   ``Mimi was like <PERSON>Elizabeth Taylor</PERSON>. ... She was always
beautiful,'' said <PERSON>Jim Richards</PERSON>, owner of the <ORGANIZATION>Long Wharf Lobster
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which flew the lobster to <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>.
   Although <PERSON>Mimi</PERSON> was a lot bigger than the 1{-pound average
lobster, she wasn't the biggest. Earlier this year, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s Sea
World adopted a 19-pound lobster, whose age was estimated at 100
years, from a grocery store in <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>.
   The largest known lobster lives in a museum in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. It weighs
58 pounds and is estimated to be 300 years old.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901129-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-29-90 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--BlueLobsters Adv03   11-29 0640</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Blue Lobsters, Adv03,0829</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv03</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Monday, Dec. 3, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Scientist Raises Blue Lobsters in Study of Hatcheries'
Effectiveness</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM C. HIDLAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WALPOLE, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Every year, a few lobstermen find a freak
when they haul in their traps - a lobster with a shell as blue as
the <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> sky.
   And they'll often call <PERSON>Sam Chapman</PERSON>, the godfather of blue
lobsters in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. He has about 400, ranging in hue from powder
blue to electric cobalt blue to ``a blue so dark it's almost
black.''
   Most lobsters plucked from the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>'s icy waters are a
mottled mixture of green, red and brown. They turn bright red when
they're cooked.
   Blue lobsters are genetic mutations in which the crustacean's
blue gene is dominant. About one in every 3 million or 4 million
lobsters caught along the <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> coast is blue, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said.
   ``Lobsters have genes for the production of red, yellow and
blue,'' said <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>, an aquaculture specialist at the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Maine</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Darling Marine Center</ORGANIZATION>. ``If the gene for red and the
gene for yellow aren't functioning, you get a blue lobster.''
   The disorder also produces lobsters with yellow shells, red
shells and even yellow with black spots, known as calico lobsters.
   Chapman has been raising blue lobsters since <DATE>1982</DATE> in a study to
determine if <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>'s fishing grounds can be restocked with lobsters
raised in hatcheries.
   Hatcheries have operated in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> off and on for decades. But
<PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said no one has ever proved that restocking coastal waters
increases the number of lobsters in the ocean.
   Part of the problem is that hatchery-raised lobsters are
released when they're the size of a thumbnail and hard to tag for
later identification.
   So with the blue lobster, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said, ``what you have is
essentially a colored tag.''
   ``You can do all of the plot sampling and research that you
want, but the proof of the pudding in this whole program is how
many blue lobsters show up in traps'' over the next five years, he
said.
   It took from <DATE>1982</DATE> - when he collected <PERSON>Amanda</PERSON> and <PERSON>Vinnie</PERSON>, the
first two blues he bred - until the <DATE>summer of 1988</DATE> to raise enough
blue lobsters to get started.
   In <DATE>June</DATE> and <DATE>July 1988</DATE>, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> and another <ORGANIZATION>University of Maine</ORGANIZATION>
researcher released 5,600 blue lobsters off <LOCATION>Boothbay Harbor</LOCATION>. In
<DATE>1989</DATE>, they sampled the area and found two blues. But sampling this
past <DATE>summer</DATE> turned up none.
   Chapman released 1,100 blue lobsters in <LOCATION>Pemaquid Harbor</LOCATION> this
past <DATE>summer</DATE> and 1,500 in <LOCATION>Cutler Harbor</LOCATION>.
   He thinks the latest restocking will be easier to monitor
because Pemaquid and <PERSON>Cutler</PERSON> are sheltered harbors. ``My feeling is
somewhere between three and four years after you let them go,
they'll start showing up in traps,'' <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said.
   He also has kept about 375 blue lobsters for behavior testing.
They're living in rows of cages in his laboratory, each 2 years
old, 3 to 4 inches long and bright blue.
   In addition, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> has older, larger blues that have been
donated over the years by lobstermen. He fetched two for a
photographer - a 1&rsqb; pounder that is 8 years old and a 2{ pounder
that is about 10 years old.
   ``An obvious question is do blue lobsters survive at the same
rate as regular lobsters do? What we need to know is do they behave
the same when they're introduced to the ocean bottom.'' he said.
   To answer those questions, he has begun studies to see how blue
lobsters behave when introduced to different environments with and
without the presence of predators.
   <PERSON>David Dow</PERSON>, a former lobsterman and executive director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Maine Lobster Institute</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maine</ORGANIZATION>, thinks
<PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s work could be important for the future of the industry.
   ``We don't know how long our production is going to last,'' he
said. ``Ten years down the road, we might not have as large a
supply. Or 10 years down the road, if we do our homework and expand
our markets, we might want to increase our supply.''
   <PERSON>Anthony D'Agostino</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Montauk Marine Science
Institute</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s project seemed
``worthwhile.''
   ``I just wonder if he has enough funding to do it properly,''
said <PERSON>D'Agostino</PERSON>, who has been studying lobsters since <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   Chapman's funding is slight - he started with <MONEY>$7,000</MONEY> from the
<ORGANIZATION>Lobster Advisory Council</ORGANIZATION> and keeps going with a yearly stipend of
about <MONEY>$600</MONEY> from the <ORGANIZATION>Maine Lobstermen's Association</ORGANIZATION>.
   For all <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s work, however, he can't answer the key
question on every lobster-lover's mind - do blues taste the same?
   ``Everyone asks that question,'' <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said. ``The problem is
we've never had enough to be able to eat any. So I don't know. I've
never eaten a blue lobster.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Mpnday Dec. 3</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Every year, a few lobstermen find a freak
when they haul in their traps - a lobster with a shell as blue as
the <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> sky.
   And they'll often call <PERSON>Sam Chapman</PERSON>, the godfather of blue
lobsters in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. He has about 400, ranging in hue from powder
blue to electric cobalt blue to ``a blue so dark it's almost
black.''
   Most lobsters plucked from the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>'s icy waters are a
mottled mixture of green, red and brown. They turn bright red when
they're cooked.
   Blue lobsters are genetic mutations in which the crustacean's
blue gene is dominant. About one in every 3 million or 4 million
lobsters caught along the <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> coast is blue, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said.
   ``Lobsters have genes for the production of red, yellow and
blue,'' said <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>, an aquaculture specialist at the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Maine</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Darling Marine Center</ORGANIZATION>. ``If the gene for red and the
gene for yellow aren't functioning, you get a blue lobster.''
   The disorder also produces lobsters with yellow shells, red
shells and even yellow with black spots, known as calico lobsters.
   Chapman has been raising blue lobsters since <DATE>1982</DATE> in a study to
determine if <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>'s fishing grounds can be restocked with lobsters
raised in hatcheries.
   Hatcheries have operated in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> off and on for decades. But
<PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said no one has ever proved that restocking coastal waters
increases the number of lobsters in the ocean.
   Part of the problem is that hatchery-raised lobsters are
released when they're the size of a thumbnail and hard to tag for
later identification.
   So with the blue lobster, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said, ``what you have is
essentially a colored tag.''
   ``You can do all of the plot sampling and research that you
want, but the proof of the pudding in this whole program is how
many blue lobsters show up in traps'' over the next five years, he
said.
   It took from <DATE>1982</DATE> - when he collected <PERSON>Amanda</PERSON> and <PERSON>Vinnie</PERSON>, the
first two blues he bred - until the <DATE>summer of 1988</DATE> to raise enough
blue lobsters to get started.
   In <DATE>June</DATE> and <DATE>July 1988</DATE>, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> and another <ORGANIZATION>University of Maine</ORGANIZATION>
researcher released 5,600 blue lobsters off <LOCATION>Boothbay Harbor</LOCATION>. In
<DATE>1989</DATE>, they sampled the area and found two blues. But sampling this
past <DATE>summer</DATE> turned up none.
   Chapman released 1,100 blue lobsters in <LOCATION>Pemaquid Harbor</LOCATION> this
past <DATE>summer</DATE> and 1,500 in <LOCATION>Cutler Harbor</LOCATION>.
   He thinks the latest restocking will be easier to monitor
because Pemaquid and <PERSON>Cutler</PERSON> are sheltered harbors. ``My feeling is
somewhere between three and four years after you let them go,
they'll start showing up in traps,'' <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said.
   He also has kept about 375 blue lobsters for behavior testing.
They're living in rows of cages in his laboratory, each 2 years
old, 3 to 4 inches long and bright blue.
   In addition, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> has older, larger blues that have been
donated over the years by lobstermen. He fetched two for a
photographer - a 1&rsqb; pounder that is 8 years old and a 2{ pounder
that is about 10 years old.
   ``An obvious question is do blue lobsters survive at the same
rate as regular lobsters do? What we need to know is do they behave
the same when they're introduced to the ocean bottom.'' he said.
   To answer those questions, he has begun studies to see how blue
lobsters behave when introduced to different environments with and
without the presence of predators.
   <PERSON>David Dow</PERSON>, a former lobsterman and executive director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Maine Lobster Institute</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maine</ORGANIZATION>, thinks
<PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s work could be important for the future of the industry.
   ``We don't know how long our production is going to last,'' he
said. ``Ten years down the road, we might not have as large a
supply. Or 10 years down the road, if we do our homework and expand
our markets, we might want to increase our supply.''
   <PERSON>Anthony D'Agostino</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Montauk Marine Science
Institute</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s project seemed
``worthwhile.''
   ``I just wonder if he has enough funding to do it properly,''
said <PERSON>D'Agostino</PERSON>, who has been studying lobsters since <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   Chapman's funding is slight - he started with <MONEY>$7,000</MONEY> from the
<ORGANIZATION>Lobster Advisory Council</ORGANIZATION> and keeps going with a yearly stipend of
about <MONEY>$600</MONEY> from the <ORGANIZATION>Maine Lobstermen's Association</ORGANIZATION>.
   For all <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s work, however, he can't answer the key
question on every lobster-lover's mind - do blues taste the same?
   ``Everyone asks that question,'' <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said. ``The problem is
we've never had enough to be able to eat any. So I don't know. I've
never eaten a blue lobster.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880831-0122 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf: Don't Poach Their Shellfish -- Or Else </HL>
<AUTHOR> John R. Alden </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   When it's sitting on a plate, all red and steaming, who thinks about anything besides cracking it open and sousing its meat in melted butter? 
But after the debris has been cleared away you may begin to wonder. 
How did that ungainly, overarmed lobster get from the bottom of the sea to the pot in the kitchen? 
Who caught it, who bought it, and how is the handsome sum you paid for dinner being divided? 

   "The Lobster Gangs of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>," by <PERSON>James M. Acheson</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>University Press of New England</ORGANIZATION>, 181 pages, <MONEY>$20</MONEY> cloth, <MONEY>$9.95</MONEY> paper) answers these and a host of other questions about the livelihood of lobstering. 

   The American lobster is found from <LOCATION>Newfoundland</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION>, but the heart of its territory lies in the <LOCATION>Gulf of Maine</LOCATION>. 
These waters are full of the fish, mollusks and small crustaceans that lobsters like to eat. 
A rocky bottom and extensive kelp beds provide plenty of shelter. 
Finally, the mean annual temperature in the <LOCATION>Gulf of Maine</LOCATION> is about 50 degrees -- not great for swimming, but perfect for lobsters. 

   Lobsters are caught in traps or "pots," wooden or metal mesh boxes three to four feet long, two feet wide, and about 16 inches high. 
The traps are baited with herring or fish heads (which smell good to a lobster) and are attached, usually in pairs, to a brightly painted styrofoam buoy by a long nylon rope. 

   A typical lobster boat is about 35 feet long, with a high bow and a low, square stern. 
Routines vary, but usually two men fish together, hauling about 500 traps in a two- or three-day cycle. 
The men hook a buoy, haul the pots with a hydraulic winch, empty and rebait their traps, and drop them back onto the ocean floor. 
Captured lobsters are measured and checked for eggs (egg-bearing females cannot be taken); legal lobsters are pegged or banded to immobilize their claws and tossed into a holding tank. 
At the end of the day the catch is crated, weighed and sold to a cooperative or dealer for whatever price is posted. 

   Although this book tells a lot about lobsters and lobstering, it is primarily about the men who fish for them. (Women hold <PERCENT>9%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>'s 9,000 lobster licenses, but only a few are among the state's 2,200 fulltime fishers.) 
Like ranchers and farmers, each lobsterman is an independent operator, owning his boat and gear and working on his own schedule. 
But he is also, this book emphasizes, part of a larger group -- a harbor gang. 
As is fitting for an anthropological study, these groups are the focus of <PERSON>Mr. Acheson</PERSON>'s attention. 

   Harbor gangs are not formal organizations. 
Lobstermen pay no dues, have no membership cards, and never hold annual meetings. 
Still, the groups are real. 
The men in a gang see each other almost every day. 
They share information, comradeship, problems and skills. 
More significantly, the harbor gangs restrict entry into the group and they "claim and defend fishing areas." 
They are, in short, territorial. 

   In many ways, harbor gangs reflect the structure of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>'s coastal communities. 
In these towns you are either an outsider (tourist, summer person or newcomer) or a local. 
The distinction is sharp and clearly understood, and winning admission to the community is difficult for anyone "from away." 

   Joining a harbor gang is similarly difficult. 
Like the members of a community, the members of a harbor gang know each other by sight and reputation, share a set of values, and view outsiders with distrust. 
And while there is a clear hierarchy within gangs, distinguishing the most successful fishermen, or "highliners," from the "moderates" and "dubs," every member of a gang has the right to fish in the group's territory. 

   These territories are more than unofficial -- they are illegal. 
No one owns the ocean floor, and the state says a license to fish is exactly that. 
Nevertheless, every fisherman knows that if he sets his pots outside of certain limits his buoys will get cut. 
At <MONEY>$40</MONEY> a trap, insisting on your right to fish for a <MONEY>$4</MONEY> lobster in someone else's backyard becomes unprofitable quickly. 

   Why do lobstermen, who generally obey the other laws regulating their business, continue to preempt territories? 
The answer is clear: Only so many lobsters mature every year, and more people fishing means a smaller share for each. 
<PERSON>Mr. Acheson</PERSON>'s data support this argument. 
Around islands, where territories are more strongly defended and entry into a harbor gang is more difficult, fishermen catch more lobsters per trap. 
Territorial rights, it seems, "help to conserve resources, promote economic efficiency, and result in higher incomes." 

   "The Lobster Gangs of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>" is wonderfully entertaining, and the information it contained agreed with everything I have learned during a decade of summers on the <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> coast. 
But like any reviewer, I wanted to check. 
So I showed the book to a local fisherman. 
"Ayuh," he confirmed. 
"That's pretty much the way it is." 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Alden</PERSON>, an anthropologist, writes from <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, in sight of several hundred lobster buoys. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA120990-0077 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 319681 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 9, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 39; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
735 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
A TRUE-BLUE TEST FOR LOBSTER EATERS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By WILLIAM C. HIDLAY, ASSOCIATED PRESS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WALPOLE, Me. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Every year, a few lobstermen find a freak when they haul in their traps -- a 
lobster with a shell as blue as the <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> sky. 
</P>
<P>
And they'll often call <PERSON>Sam Chapman</PERSON>, the godfather of blue lobsters in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. He 
has about 400, ranging in hue from powder blue to electric cobalt blue to "a 
blue so dark it's almost black." 
</P>
<P>
Most lobsters plucked from the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>'s icy waters are a mottled mixture of 
green, red and brown. They turn bright red when they're cooked. 
</P>
<P>
Blue lobsters are genetic mutations in which the crustacean's blue gene is 
dominant. About one in every 3 million or 4 million lobsters caught along the 
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> coast is blue, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"Lobsters have genes for the production of red, yellow and blue," said <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>, 
an aquaculture specialist at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maine</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Darling Marine Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
"If the gene for red and the gene for yellow aren't functioning, you get a blue 
lobster." 
</P>
<P>
The disorder also produces lobsters with yellow shells, red shells and even 
yellow with black spots, known as calico lobsters. 
</P>
<P>
Chapman has been raising blue lobsters since <DATE>1982</DATE> in a study to determine if 
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>'s fishing grounds can be restocked with lobsters raised in hatcheries. 
</P>
<P>
Hatcheries have operated in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> off and on for decades. But <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said no 
one has ever proved that restocking coastal waters increases the number of 
lobsters in the ocean. 
</P>
<P>
Part of the problem is that hatchery-raised lobsters are released when they are 
the size of a thumbnail and hard to tag for later identification. 
</P>
<P>
So with the blue lobster, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said, "what you have is essentially a colored 
tag." 
</P>
<P>
"You can do all of the plot sampling and research that you want, but the proof 
of the pudding in this whole program is how many blue lobsters show up in 
traps" over the next five years, he said. 
</P>
<P>
It took from <DATE>1982</DATE> -- when he collected <PERSON>Amanda</PERSON> and <PERSON>Vinnie</PERSON>, the first two blues 
he bred -- until the <DATE>summer of 1988</DATE> to raise enough blue lobsters to get 
started. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>June</DATE> and <DATE>July 1988</DATE>, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> and another <ORGANIZATION>University of Maine</ORGANIZATION> researcher 
released 5,600 blue lobsters off <LOCATION>Boothbay Harbor</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1989</DATE>, they sampled the 
area and found two blues. But sampling this past <DATE>summer</DATE> turned up none. 
</P>
<P>
Chapman released 1,100 blue lobsters in <LOCATION>Pemaquid Harbor</LOCATION> this past <DATE>summer</DATE> and 
1,500 in <LOCATION>Cutler Harbor</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
He thinks the latest restocking will be easier to monitor because Pemaquid and 
<PERSON>Cutler</PERSON> are sheltered harbors. "My feeling is somewhere between three and four 
years after you let them go, they'll start showing up in traps," <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
He also has kept about 375 blue lobsters for behavior testing. They are living 
in rows of cages in his laboratory, each 2 years old, 3 to 4 inches long and 
bright blue. 
</P>
<P>
In addition, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> has older, larger blues that have been donated over the 
years by lobstermen. He fetched two for a photographer -- a 1 3/8 pounder that 
is 8 years old and a 2 1/2 pounder that is about 10 years old. 
</P>
<P>
"An obvious question is do blue lobsters survive at the same rate as regular 
lobsters do? What we need to know is, do they behave the same when they're 
introduced to the ocean bottom?" he said. 
</P>
<P>
To answer those questions, he has begun studies to see how blue lobsters behave 
when introduced to different environments with and without the presence of 
predators. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>David Dow</PERSON>, a former lobsterman and executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Maine Lobster 
Institute</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maine</ORGANIZATION>, thinks <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s work could be important 
for the future of the industry. 
</P>
<P>
"We don't know how long our production is going to last," he said. "Ten years 
down the road, we might not have as large a supply. Or 10 years down the road, 
if we do our homework and expand our markets, we might want to increase our 
supply." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Anthony D'Agostino</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Montauk Marine Science Institute</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Long 
Island</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s project seemed "worthwhile." 
</P>
<P>
"I just wonder if he has enough funding to do it properly," said <PERSON>D'Agostino</PERSON>, 
who has been studying lobsters since <DATE>1975</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Chapman's funding is slight -- he started with <MONEY>$7,000</MONEY> from the <ORGANIZATION>Lobster Advisory 
Council</ORGANIZATION> and has kept going with a yearly stipend of about <MONEY>$600</MONEY> from the <LOCATION>Maine 
Lobstermen</LOCATION>'s Assn. 
</P>
<P>
For all <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s work, however, he can't answer the key question on every 
lobster-lover's mind -- do blues taste the same? 
</P>
<P>
"Everyone asks that question," <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said. "The problem is we've never had 
enough to be able to eat any. So I don't know. I've never eaten a blue 
lobster." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Sam Chapman shows off some blue lobsters in Walpole, Me. Chapman, an 
aquaculture specialist at the University of Maine, raises the blue lobsters in 
a study to determine whether Maine's fishing grounds can be restocked with 
lobsters that were raised in hatcheries. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891207-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-07-89 1542EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-07 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0505</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PEORIA, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Tom Stanesa</PERSON> is as comfortable flying
cross-country as most people are driving to work. He should be;
he's racked up more than 1 million miles in the air on business
trips for <ORGANIZATION>Caterpillar Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Flying planes was all I ever wanted to do,'' he said.
   He started out to be a pilot, but an accident during <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> flight
training affected his vision. So he's flown as a passenger, and
logged every run.
   About a year after he joined Peoria-based <ORGANIZATION>Caterpillar</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1967</DATE>,
<PERSON>Stanesa</PERSON> took a 140-mile business flight to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> and jotted the
mileage and a few flight details in a notebook.
   Two decades later, <ORGANIZATION>Stanesa</ORGANIZATION>'s weathered notebook is crammed with
37 single-spaced pages of notes documenting 1,403 flights for the
world's biggest maker of earth-moving equipment.
   His total so far is 1,008,752 miles.
   ``I know there are others in the million-mile category'' at the
company, said <ORGANIZATION>Caterpillar</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Mark Polzin</PERSON>. ``But <PERSON>Tom</PERSON>'s
probably the only one who can prove it.''
   His work has taken him to 26 countries on 42 different types of
airplanes. He has traveled on 29 domestic airlines and 30 foreign
carriers, and made 62 <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> crossings.
   Bad weather and risky landings have not soured Stanesa on
flying, but he does have a complaint.
   ``It's not very fun to fly anymore,'' he said. ``There's so much
lost luggage and incredible damage being done to luggage. And the
airports are extremely overcrowded.''
   No, <ORGANIZATION>Stanesa</ORGANIZATION> hasn't taken gotten any free flights _ <ORGANIZATION>Caterpillar</ORGANIZATION>
collects his frequent flier bonuses.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>FREEPORT, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Tom Stanesa</PERSON> is as comfortable flying
cross-country as most people are driving to work. He should be;
he's racked up more than 1 million miles in the air on business
trips for <ORGANIZATION>Caterpillar Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Flying planes was all I ever wanted to do,'' he said.
   He started out to be a pilot, but an accident during <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> flight
training affected his vision. So he's flown as a passenger, and
logged every run.
   About a year after he joined Peoria-based <ORGANIZATION>Caterpillar</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1967</DATE>,
<PERSON>Stanesa</PERSON> took a 140-mile business flight to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> and jotted the
mileage and a few flight details in a notebook.
   Two decades later, <ORGANIZATION>Stanesa</ORGANIZATION>'s weathered notebook is crammed with
37 single-spaced pages of notes documenting 1,403 flights for the
world's biggest maker of earth-moving equipment.
   His total so far is 1,008,752 miles.
   ``I know there are others in the million-mile category'' at the
company, said <ORGANIZATION>Caterpillar</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Mark Polzin</PERSON>. ``But <PERSON>Tom</PERSON>'s
probably the only one who can prove it.''
   His work has taken him to 26 countries on 42 different types of
airplanes. He has traveled on 29 domestic airlines and 30 foreign
carriers, and made 62 <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> crossings.
   Bad weather and risky landings have not soured Stanesa on
flying, but he does have a complaint.
   ``It's not very fun to fly anymore,'' he said. ``There's so much
lost luggage and incredible damage being done to luggage. And the
airports are extremely overcrowded.''
   No, <ORGANIZATION>Stanesa</ORGANIZATION> hasn't taken gotten any free flights _ <ORGANIZATION>Caterpillar</ORGANIZATION>
collects his frequent flier bonuses.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901107-0336 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-07-90 1919EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-LobsterDispute     11-07 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lobster Dispute,0541</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canadian Cabinet Rejects Proposed Settlement of Lobster Dispute</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM C. HIDLAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A Canadian board on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> rejected a proposal to settle a
free trade dispute between lobstermen in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   Canadian fishermen are allowed to keep and sell smaller lobsters
than their <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> counterparts. Representatives of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and
Canadian lobster industries recently had proposed increasing the
minimum size of lobsters taken along <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Atlantic Coast</LOCATION> to the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> level of 3\ inches.
   The proposal also called for creating a joint U.S.-Canadian
committee to discuss lobster management issues and for both
countries to work together to promote and market lobsters.
   But on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, Canadian Trade Minister <PERSON>John Crosbie</PERSON> announced
in <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> that the country's federal cabinet had rejected the
proposed settlement.
   <PERSON>John Kearney</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Maritime Fishermen's Union</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Yarmouth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nova Scotia</LOCATION>, hailed the decision.
   ``We have no biological reason in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> for increasing our
minimum size,'' he said. ``We have a whole range of management and
regulatory measures ... that are non-existent in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.''
   But lobster industry officials from <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> predicted a worsening
of relations between the two countries because of the decision.
   ``For them to pull out of it means there's going to be more
bickering and fighting among all the various factions of the
industry,'' said <PERSON>William Anderson</PERSON>, a lobsterman from <LOCATION>Lubec</LOCATION> and
chairman of the state's <ORGANIZATION>Lobster Advisory Council</ORGANIZATION>.
   To <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> fishermen, the dispute over size is much more than
academic because they compete against Canadian lobstermen who sell
the majority of their catch in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
