<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891110-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-10-89 1823EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-UnknownSoldier 2ndLd-Writethru a0651 11-10 0693</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Unknown Soldier, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0651,0711</SECOND>
<HEAD>Diary Solves Mystery of Unknown Soldier 45 Years After Death</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 7th graf pvs, `Lloyd Wibben ...' to CORRECT village west
sted east of Paris, mileage to 250 sted 300. Picks up 8th pvs, `They found
...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For 45 years, the fate of <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> Sgt. <PERSON>Lloyd
Willard Wibben</PERSON> was a mystery to both his family and the residents
of Treguier, a coastal village in northwestern <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   The family knew <ORGANIZATION>Wibben</ORGANIZATION> had died somewhere in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> during World
War II.
   The villagers knew an American soldier fell while liberating
their town, but they never knew his name.
   A historian's persistence finally led to the name, jotted in the
yellowed pages of a diary kept by the commander of <ORGANIZATION>Wibben</ORGANIZATION>'s
regiment.
   This week, <PERSON>Mervin Wibben</PERSON> of <LOCATION>St. Charles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, arrived in
Treguier, population 3,400, at the invitation of city elders to
join them in honoring his older brother.
   On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Armistice Day</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Wibben</ORGANIZATION> will lay a wreath
at a new monument the villagers are dedicating to the man who was
once their unknown soldier.
   <PERSON>Lloyd Wibben</PERSON> was 24 years old on <DATE>Aug. 14, 1944</DATE>, when his 15th
<ORGANIZATION>Cavalry Reconnaissance Squadron</ORGANIZATION> advanced just to the edge of
Treguier, a village 250 miles west of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   They found the road blocked by debris, so <ORGANIZATION>Wibben</ORGANIZATION> and other
soldiers left their vehicles to clear the road. Wibben was killed
in a barrage of German fire.
   The villagers placed a simple granite marker where he died,
dedicated ``to the unknown American soldier who died during the
Liberation 14 <DATE>August 1944</DATE>.'' He was buried in Plot K, Row 7, at the
American military cemetery at <LOCATION>St. James</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Normandy</LOCATION>, along with
about 4,400 other <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> soldiers who died in the fighting.
   The Americans took the village and eventually stopped the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>'
counterattack on Avranches.
   ``All we really knew was that that we got telegram from the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>
that <PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON> was killed in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,'' <ORGANIZATION>Wibben</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by
telephone from Treguier.
   ``We didn't know too much more of it until Treguier contacted us
to help in this ceremony,'' he said. ``He really is some kind of
hero to the people here.''
   The people of Treguier did not know the soldier's name until
local historian <PERSON>Yvon Herve</PERSON> launched a research project about two
years ago.
   His search eventually led him to retired Col. <PERSON>Robert Dwan</PERSON>, who
commanded the <ORGANIZATION>15th Cavalry Regiment</ORGANIZATION> and kept a diary listing all
the men under his command who had died.
   Dwan showed Herve the entry for <DATE>Aug. 14, 1944</DATE>, and further
investigation confirmed that <ORGANIZATION>Wibben</ORGANIZATION> was <ORGANIZATION>Treguier</ORGANIZATION>'s unknown soldier.
   ``Very few people in the war kept a diary like that,'' said
<PERSON>Mervin Wibben</PERSON>, a semi-retired meat processor who served with the
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>. ``Most of them just wanted to forget
about everything.''
   Herve considered the puzzle fully solved in <DATE>mid-September</DATE>, and
Treguier officials started planning a ceremony to place a bronze
plaque with <ORGANIZATION>Wibben</ORGANIZATION>'s name over the old granite marker.
   ``Because we have learned his identity, we wanted to invite his
brother,'' said <PERSON>Herve</PERSON>. ``For us, this ceremony is a symbol of our
freedom.''
   <PERSON>Mervin Wibben</PERSON> and his wife, <PERSON>Jan</PERSON>, flew to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> courtesy of <ORGANIZATION>Air
France</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> before traveling on to Treguier. They visited
<ORGANIZATION>Wibben</ORGANIZATION>'s grave and will tour the area around the World War II
battlefields before leaving for home <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   ``It really broke me up bad when <PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON> died,'' <PERSON>Mervin Wibben</PERSON>
said. ``He was five years older than me, but we were really close.
He left me his car when he volunteered for the service.''
   The family, natives of <LOCATION>Yankton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>, included seven brothers
and four sisters. Mervin is the first to visit Lloyd's grave.
   ``When they called, it brought back a lot of memories _ and a
few tears,'' he said. ``Lloyd was a prince. He wanted to go fight
for his country. He loved horses so much he signed up for the
cavalry ... but when he got to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> it was all mechanized.''
   <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s ceremony comes nine days before <PERSON>Lloyd Wibben</PERSON> would
have celebrated his 70th birthday.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890225-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-25-89 0918EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Britain-Hirohito 1stLd-Writethru a0486 02-25 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Britain-Hirohito, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0486,0573</SECOND>
<HEAD>Philip Honors War Dead in Simple Ceremony</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 5 grafs to UPDATE with Queen Elizabeth asking veteran
to end hunger strike over Philip's visit. Pickup 5th graf pvs, ``To many...''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MONIKA JAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>YOKOHAMA, Japan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince <PERSON>Philip</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, who has been
criticized at home for attending <PERSON>Emperor Hirohito</PERSON>'s funeral, today
honored British soldiers who died in World War II by laying wreaths
at a cemetery.
   Accompanied by Foreign Secretary <PERSON>Geoffrey Howe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Philip</PERSON> honored
the 1,738 British, Australian and other war dead buried at the
<ORGANIZATION>Yokohama Commonwealth War Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> a day after attending the
elaborate funeral of Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>.
   In drizzling rain, the two British representatives laid wreaths
at a crucifix in the center of the rolling cemetery grounds and
later spoke with members of the local British community.
   In <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> today, <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON> appealed to a World War II
veteran to end his hunger strike protest over <LOCATION>Prince Philip</LOCATION>'s
attendance at the funeral. There was no immediate reaction to the
latest appeal from <PERSON>Andrew Burgess</PERSON>, 70, who has been eating nothing
and drinking only black tea for the last nine days.
   Philip's attendance at <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s funeral has been criticized by
British war veterans and lawmakers who considered the late monarch a
war criminal and who saw no reason to honor a man they blamed for
the deaths of thousands of their comrades. The royal family was
criticized for sending the husband of Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, and the
decision was debated in editorial columns.
   ``To many millions outside <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> will be remembered
less for the dignified last years of his reign than for its first
phase, when aggressive war was waged in his name and barbarous
atrocities were committed,'' The Times of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> wrote in a <DATE>January</DATE>
editorial after <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s death. ``To those people, the emperor's
passing will bring back painful memories.''
   Fighting under <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s name, Japanese forces killed 27,000
British soldiers and another 20,000 Dutch.
   Many survivors also held <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> accountable for atrocities
committed against 127,000 Dutch people interned during the war.
   ``We are accustomed to hear such kind of criticism,'' said
<PERSON>Seizaburo Sato</PERSON>, a professor of political science at <ORGANIZATION>Tokyo
University</ORGANIZATION>. ``<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> made a mistake.''
   ``But didn't (the) British or Dutch do really bad things to
Asians they colonized, for example, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>? If they
think about what they have done for a much longer period of time
than <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> did, I think they should be more modest,'' he said in an
interview.
   Most historians maintain that the late emperor was merely a
glorified figurehead of his generals with little, if any, political
power. Hirohito died on <DATE>Jan. 7</DATE> at age 87, never having made clear
his role in the war.
   The cemetery is on the site of a playground that was opened by
<PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> himself more than 65 years ago when he was crown prince.
   Nestled in the hills of Hodogaya in <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION>, south of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, the
cemetery also holds the remains of soldiers from <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New
Zealand</LOCATION> and other Commonwealth nations, and the ashes of an
undetermined number of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> soldiers.
   Many died while being held as prisoners of war in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> or aboard
POW ships on the way to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in <DATE>1942</DATE> following the surrender of
<LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>. ``He loved his life but gave it in freeing the Japanese
people,'' read one epitaph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890720-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-07-20-89 2100EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-War     07-20 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-War,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dispute Over Captured Germans Who Helped Soviets In War</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRENCE PETTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An emotional dispute has broken out in <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION> over whether imprisoned German soldiers who spread
propaganda for their Soviet captors during World War II were
traitors or heroes.
   ``Many people consider these people traitors. But that's not the
case. They were opponents of the (Nazi) regime,'' said <PERSON>Peter
Steinbach</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Steinbach</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Passau University</ORGANIZATION> historian, arranged an exhibit
called ``Resistance to National Socialism'' that has generated
controversy.
   The failed <DATE>July 20, 1944</DATE> attempt by German generals to kill
<PERSON>Hitler</PERSON> is included in the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> exhibit, as are the wartime calls
for anti-Nazi actions by a group of university students known as
the <ORGANIZATION>White Rose</ORGANIZATION>.
   In both cases, those brave enough to oppose Hitler were tortured
and executed.
   But along with documents and photographs showing such widely
recognized attempts to disrupt the Third <PERSON>Reich</PERSON> is a controversial
display about thousands of captured German soldiers in Soviet
prisons who opposed the Third <PERSON>Reich</PERSON> and wanted the war to end.
   Some members of the <ORGANIZATION>National Committee</ORGANIZATION> for a Free <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> did
propaganda work for the Soviets during the war, using loudspeakers
at the front to urge German soldiers to quit fighting.
   That part of the exhibit has angered Germans who do not believe
the soldiers deserve the same place of honor as people like <PERSON>Claus
von Stauffenberg</PERSON>, who was executed for planting the <DATE>1944</DATE> bomb meant
to kill Hitler.
   <PERSON>Hartmut von Hoesslin</PERSON>, brother of another German officer involved
in the <DATE>1944</DATE> plot, Maj. <PERSON>Roland von Hoesslin</PERSON>, was at the exhibit's
opening on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Hartmut von Hoesslin</PERSON> said the display on imprisoned German
soldiers ``insulted all resistance-fighters.''
   A protest letter presented by <PERSON>Hartmut von Hoesslin</PERSON> to the
exhibit's organizers said propaganda by the imprisoned soldiers
amounted to ``psychoterror'' against fellow German troops.
   But <PERSON>Steinbach</PERSON> said members of the <ORGANIZATION>National Committee</ORGANIZATION> for a Free
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> deserve a place in the exhibit and argued they saw
themselves not as opportunists who wanted to placate Soviet
captors, but as authentic opponents of Hitler's rule.
   ``They felt they were representatives of the Allied cause to
stop the war,'' <PERSON>Steinbach</PERSON> said.
   The dispute has its roots in a long-standing German dilemma:
what kind of honor to bestow on German soldiers who died during the
war, and whether those who deserted are also deserving of praise.
   German peace activists have been behind numerous moves to erect
monuments to World War II deserters, often angering people who feel
it is an affront to those who died fighting.
   There is heated controversy in <LOCATION>Bockhorn</LOCATION>, where citizens are
embroiled in discussion over the community's memorial to soldiers
who fell during both world wars.
   An open letter from peace activists questioned whether every
fallen soldier deserves to be treated like a hero.
   The letter said, ``They (the fallen soldiers) had participated
in one of the greatest crimes of modern times,'' meaning the
tragedies and terror begun by <LOCATION>Nazi Germany</LOCATION> when it started World
War II.
   <PERSON>Kark Friedrich Schinkel</PERSON>, an officer in the West German navy,
said in the respected newspaper Die Zeit that such disputes
underscore the difficulties some Germans still have in coming to
terms with their homeland's Nazi past.
   He said such controversies ``raise the question, 50 years after
the German invasion of <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, whether the concept of individual
heroism can be applied against the backdrop of mass murder.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900527-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-27-90 1248EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-MedalofHonor     05-27 0729</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Medal of Honor,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Medals of Honor Considered for Black Heroes of World Wars</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIM I. MILLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two years and another administration ago, the
<ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> promised to study the records of black soldiers to
determine why none of them received the Medal of Honor for valor
during World Wars I and II.
   Since then, <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> was elected president and the two
congressmen who were bird-dogging the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> on the subject are
gone: Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Texas</LOCATION>, died in a plane crash and <PERSON>Joseph
DioGuardi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-N.Y.</LOCATION>, was defeated for re-election.
   But the probe has not been scuttled, a <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said
last week.
   Neither has it been finished.
   ``The study is still going on and the reason it's taking so long
is most of these black soldiers were with French units,'' Maj. <PERSON>Doug
Hart</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> spokesman, said in an interview.
   The French records of one World War I unit became available only
in <DATE>February</DATE>, <PERSON>Hart</PERSON> said. Military researchers are also looking at
World War II records of three black <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> seamen who received the
<ORGANIZATION>Distinguished Service Cross</ORGANIZATION>, he said.
   <PERSON>Hart</PERSON> said the investigations will probably be completed later
this <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   That pleases <PERSON>Leroy Ramsey</PERSON>, an <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, historian who six
years ago began a lonely quest to correct what he feels is a great
injustice.
   ``I'm kind of perturbed that it's taken so long but I am pleased
that the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> agreed to give it a full review,'' <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> said in
an interview last week.
   A black World War II veteran himself, <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> was stunned to
discover while researching a book that not one of the 1.5 million
black Americans who served in the world wars received the nation's
highest military decoration for bravery.
   Blacks were excluded from <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> combat units in both world wars.
But more than a few were cited for bravery, <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> learned upon
examining the records of servicemen awarded the <ORGANIZATION>Distinguished
Service Cross</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>French Croix de Guerre</ORGANIZATION>.
   Ramsey then read the nation's more than 1,200 Medal of Honor
citations and concluded that at least one black World War I soldier
and one black World War II seaman had records strong enough to
warrant the highest honor.
   ``I didn't want this to be token because these guys were
black,'' <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> stressed.
   The two he selected were <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> Sgt. <PERSON>Henry Johnson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Seaman Dorrie Miller</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Waco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Both are dead.
   By <DATE>1987</DATE>, <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> had succeeded in interesting <PERSON>DioGuardi</PERSON> and
<LOCATION>Leland</LOCATION> in his cause. The two sponsored legislation to award
posthumous Medals of Honor to <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> but the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>
opposed the bill because it singled out two individuals.
   In <DATE>October 1988</DATE>, then Defense-Secretary <PERSON>Frank Carlucci</PERSON> announced
the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> would review the records of black World War I heroes and
said he would ask the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> about the feasibility of doing the same
with blacks in World War II.
   <PERSON>Hart</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> is now looking at the records of <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>
and all the men in his unit. <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>'s record also is under review,
along with those of Seamen <PERSON>William Cook Pinckney</PERSON> and <PERSON>Leonard Roy
Harmon</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hart</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, who fought with the French army in World War I, killed
four German soldiers, rescued a wounded comrade and captured a
stockpile of weapons, all despite severe wounds. He was awarded the
<ORGANIZATION>Croix de Guerre</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s highest military honor, but was never
cited by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. He died in <DATE>1930</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> was a mess steward on the <LOCATION>USS West Virginia</LOCATION> when it was
attacked at <LOCATION>Pearl Harbor</LOCATION>. While the battleship was being shelled,
he helped moved its wounded captain from the ship's bridge, then
returned to man a machine gun. Miller received a <ORGANIZATION>Distinguished
Service Cross</ORGANIZATION> and a warship was named for him in <DATE>1971</DATE>. He was
killed in a torpedo attack in <DATE>1943</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Harmon</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, was a mess attendant aboard the USS <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION> during a battle with the Japanese near the <LOCATION>Solomon
Islands</LOCATION> in <DATE>1942</DATE>. He deliberately exposed himself to hostile gunfire
in order to protect a wounded shipmate and was killed, according to
his citation.
   Pinckney, of <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>, was a cook on the <ORGANIZATION>USS Enterprise</ORGANIZATION> in
a battle with the Japanese near the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Islands</LOCATION> in <DATE>1942</DATE>.
During heavy bombing, <PERSON>Pinckney</PERSON> carried a comrade to safety before
pushing his way out of a burning compartment.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06267006 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06267006 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; WAR; MEMORIAL; HISPANIC; VETERAN; CEREMONY; SACRAMENTO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Samuel Ortega's voice filled with emotion as he shared his vision of a
California memorial to honor Hispanic veterans.;   "The bottom line is, we
want recognition," said Ortega, who is spearheading a $1 million fund-raising
effort to expand a small memorial for Hispanics on the west side of the
California Capitol.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HISPANIC VETS IN CALIFORNIA WORK TO GET WAR
MEMORIAL  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "We don't see anyone else doing it for us, so we've got to do it for
soldiers of Hispanic descent served their country with distinction, <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON>
said.;   "We are being slighted," he said. "Our contributions are viewed as
insignificant, and that is not true.";   During World War II and <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, for
example, 18 Hispanics were awarded the Medal of Honor, he said. Of the 5,033
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> soldiers killed or missing in action in the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War, 836 were
of Hispanic descent.;   The memorial, which is targeted to be unveiled on
<ORGANIZATION>Cinco de Mayo</ORGANIZATION> (May 5) <DATE>1993</DATE>, is planned as an extension of the <LOCATION>El Soldado</LOCATION>
monument, which was dedicated in <DATE>1951</DATE> by a local group, the Mexican-American
War Mothers, to honor World War II Hispanic veterans in <LOCATION>Northern California.</LOCATION>; 
 That memorial originally was dedicated at the Mexican Cultural Center at
Sixth and W streets. When the center was sold, the memorial was relocated in
<DATE>1975</DATE> next to the Capitol.;   The new memorial would recognize those who
served, were killed or were missing in action during World War II, <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. There would be a special pedestal honoring the Medal of Honor
winners.;   It also would include an artistic mural depicting the military
history of Hispanics.;   <PERSON>Manuel C. Perez</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> resident who was a <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>
seaman in the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION> during World War II, said he is touched by the
memorial effort.;   "This gives credit to those who served, and especially
those who died," <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> said. "We've been in this state, this country, a long
time, but we've never been given any credit.";   <PERSON>Perez</PERSON>, 70, said his mother,
<PERSON>Antima Perez</PERSON>, was among the women who worked hard to get the first monument
erected. "My younger brother, <LOCATION>Abelardo</LOCATION>, died over there in <DATE>October 1944</DATE>," he
said.;   "I have two sons who served in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> during <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. This must be
remembered.";   At least 40 cities throughout the state with significant
Hispanic populations, including <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Stockton</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>,
will be called on to help raise funds.;   "We have the population, the
economic base and the organizations to pull this off," <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON> said.;   IF
YOU'RE INTERESTED; Fund-raising posters depicting the new monument may be
obtained for <MONEY>$10</MONEY> from the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Mexican-American Veterans Memorial, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION>
Box 188944, <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> 95818.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  McClatchy News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Sacramento  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910923  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  447  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, September 23, 1991
00267006,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890613-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-89 0002EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Germany-SovietPOWs     06-13 0310</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Germany-Soviet POWs,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Release Names of Missing German Soldiers In Humanitarian
Gesture</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Germany-Gorbachev, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a gesture of reconciliation more
than four decades after the end of World War II, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>
has released the names of 1,500 German soldiers who died in its
prisoner-of-war camps.
   The list was presented to the German Red Cross to coincide with
the arrival <DATE>Monday</DATE> of Soviet President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>.
   It was the first time the Soviets had provided a list of German
soldiers still unaccounted for after the war, West German officials
said.
   Thousands of German soldiers died in Soviet prisoner-of-war camps
and many prisoners were not released until the early <DATE>1950s</DATE>.
   German Red Cross officials applauded the Soviet action, saying it
was a ``moving gesture of reconciliation and an important first step
in clarifying the fate of these missing men.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> and another West German group, the Federation for
the Preservation of German War Graves, said they hoped to be able to
inform relatives of the soldiers on the list soon.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> said it hoped that additional lists of missing
soldiers would follow.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION> has also agreed allow greater access to several
cemeteries in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> where German soldiers are buried.
   German Red Cross President <PERSON>Botho Prinz</PERSON> zu Sayn-Wittgenstein
called the Soviet gesture a ``breakthrough in the humantarian
relations'' between the two nations.
   The bitter legacy of World War II and the Nazi attack on the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> has clouded West German-Soviet relations for decades.
   According to official estimates, more than 20 million Soviets
were killed in the war and Nazi armies destroyed vast areas of the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   Soviet prisoners of war were subjected to brutal treatment by the
Nazis and thousands died in forced labor and concentration camps
until the German defeat in <DATE>1945</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062990-0002 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 240212 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 29, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 6; Column 6; Editorial Writers Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
248 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LOCAL WATCH; 
</P>
<P>
VETERANS AT WAR 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It's sad: Once soldiers side by side. Now veterans waring among themselves. 
</P>
<P>
Who should be listed on a proposed <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> monument to American soldiers of 
Japanese ancestry? The question threatens a community project designed to honor 
those who served in three segregated World War II units. 
</P>
<P>
One group wants the privately funded monument in <LOCATION>Little Tokyo</LOCATION> to list the names 
of all 12,000 members -- living and dead -- of the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s all-Japanese-American 
100th Battalion and 442nd <ORGANIZATION>Infantry Regimental Combat Team</ORGANIZATION>, which served in 
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Military Intelligence Service</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>. An opposing group 
wants to honor only the 700 killed during World War II, but to include the 
names of 325 Japanese-Americans who died during the Spanish-American War, World 
War I and the Korean and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> conflicts. 
</P>
<P>
The debate is muddling the intent of the monument: To make a special 
acknowledgement of the blood, sweat and tears of those Japanese-American 
soldiers who fought hard to prove their loyalty to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> so their 
families, unjustly interned in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> concentration camps during the war, would 
be more readily accepted by other Americans. 
</P>
<P>
They were tested as few others were. They deserve an enduring testimonial -- 
one designed with the names of all the Japanese-Americans who served in World 
War II as the centerpiece of the monument. The design also could incorporate 
secondarily the names of others who died in combat. 
</P>
<P>
They don't deserve to be fought over like this. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Editorial 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900212-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-12-90 0238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FuneralLament     02-12 0630</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Funeral Lament,0649</SECOND>
<HEAD>Doing More With Less Means Cuts for Vets' Funeral</HEAD>
<NOTE>eds: Phillip Morris, 7th graf, is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE LOCKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST SPRINGFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   World War II veteran and <ORGANIZATION>Purple
Heart</ORGANIZATION> winner <PERSON>Anthony Beggetta</PERSON> died expecting to be buried with
military pomp.
   But when his family tried to arrange the color guard, rifle
salute and bugle-blown ``Taps,'' they discovered a change in policy
at <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>'s main army base because of budget constraints.
   ``My father didn't talk too much about it, but he said he wanted
a military funeral,'' said <PERSON>Beggetta</PERSON>'s daughter, <PERSON>Jeanne Udas</PERSON>. ``It's
just something we knew all our lives that he wanted.''
   Beggetta, who was 75 when he died <DATE>Jan. 19</DATE>, got his military
sendoff when officials at the local <ORGANIZATION>Veterans of Foreign Wars Post</ORGANIZATION>
sent a color guard.
   But although the family appreciated the efforts, the funeral
``wasn't of course as impressive as what my father expected or
wanted,'' <PERSON>Udas</PERSON> said.
   The problem, military officials say, is that the veteran
population from World War II is aging at a time when the military
is under pressure to trim spending.
   ``There's no intent to slight veterans. That's not the point.
When there's less money, we have to find ways to cut,'' said
<PERSON>Phillip Morris</PERSON>, spokesman for <LOCATION>Fort Devens</LOCATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Ayers</ORGANIZATION>.
   Army policy is to provide funeral details for soldiers who die
on active duty and Medal of Honor winners, said <PERSON>Shari Lawrence</PERSON>,
spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Personnel Command</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va</LOCATION>. Any
veteran is entitled to the presence of a service representative of
equal rank, who usually presents the family with a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> flag, she
said.
   Beyond that, policy is up to individual commanders and <PERSON>Lawrence</PERSON>
said there was no centralized information on how funerals are
handled. Still, she said she was not aware of problems nationally.
   <LOCATION>Fort Devens</LOCATION> sends out funeral details for 20-year retirees and
former prisoners of war, <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said. In the <ORGANIZATION>Begetta</ORGANIZATION>'s case, a
sergeant was sent to present the flag to the family.
   Previously, the base had responded to most requests within 300
miles with 15-man details, including pallbearers, a bugle player
and a rifle group. In <DATE>1988</DATE>, 3,345 soldiers were assigned to details
at 229 funerals. Smaller groups, using 768 soldiers were sent to 96
funerals, he said.
   ``We were sending them all over the six-state <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> area,
lots of them. It was a drain,'' he said.
   During the <DATE>first six months of 1989</DATE>, 118 full details and 77
smaller contingents went out. After the policy change, the number
dwindled to only 26 full funerals and 18 smaller details.
   How the base came to be in the position of sending out so many
details is difficult to tell, <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said.
   ``I think it just kind of progressed and progressed and finally
got to the point where we were just doing all those funerals,'' he
said.
   <PERSON>Bill Smith</PERSON>, director of public affairs for the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>,
headquarters of the <ORGANIZATION>VFW</ORGANIZATION>, said the problem could be that the World
War II veterans are growing older, with an average age of 67.
   He said he understands that some families would prefer the
attention of a military base.
   ``We are a substitute,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said he does not know how much the base is saving through
cutting the funeral details because it involves too many variables.
At one point, <LOCATION>Fort Devens</LOCATION> was on a list of bases under
consideration for closure, but it has since acquired the
<ORGANIZATION>Information System Command</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I think it's pretty obvious that we were expending lots of
troop labor to support veterans funerals all over <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>,''
<PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said. ``It was one of many things that we've cut back. The
times are getting leaner and we have to do more with less.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1442EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--UnknownSoldier     12-02 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Unknown Soldier,0195</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Return Remains of Unknown Italian Soldier</HEAD>
<DATELINE>REDIPUGLIA, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The remains of an Italian Unknown
Soldier who died in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> during World War II were
formally given to Italian authorities at a military cemetery on
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The remains symbolized the 90,000 Italians who died on the
Russian front while fighting with the German army against the
Soviets.
   The arrival of the urn at the military cemetery at Redipuglia in
northern <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> marked the beginning of a program in which Italian
remains from World War II are to be exhumed in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and
sent home.
   An accord on the program is to be signed in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   A Soviet military delegation and Italian President <PERSON>Francesco
Cossiga</PERSON> attended <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s ceremony.
   ``The return of the Unknown Soldier is a sign of the times,''
said <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION> Minister <PERSON>Virginio Rognoni</PERSON> at the ceremony in front of
a military shrine.
   ``With the disintegration of the walls that divided peoples,
with freedom and dialogue returning to many parts of the world
through perestroika, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>USSR</ORGANIZATION> feel like neighbors.''
   About 40,000 people attended the ceremony.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890225-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-25-89 1434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-WarMemories     02-25 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-War Memories,0505</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prince Philip Honors War Dead in Simple Ceremony</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MONIKA JAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>YOKOHAMA, Japan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Prince <PERSON>Philip</PERSON> laid a wreath at a
war cemetery <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in a move to honor memories and appease
veterans angered that he paid last respects to <PERSON>Emperor Hirohito</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s World War II leader.
   Philip, accompanied by Foreign Secretary <PERSON>Geoffrey Howe</PERSON>, honored
the 1,738 British, Australian and other war dead buried at the
<ORGANIZATION>Yokohama Commonwealth War Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> a day after attending <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s
elaborate funeral.
   In light rain, the two British representatives laid wreaths at
the center of the rolling cemetery grounds and later spoke with
members of the local British community.
   British war veterans and lawmakers decried the attendance of
Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>'s husband at the funeral of the late monarch,
whom they denounced as a war criminal.
   In <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Queen Elizabeth II</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> appealed to one World
War II veteran to end his hunger strike, which was begun in protest
of <LOCATION>Philip</LOCATION>'s attendance.
   There was no immediate reaction to the latest appeal from
70-year-old <PERSON>Andrew Burgess</PERSON>, who has been eating nothing and drinking
only black tea for the last nine days.
   Fighting under <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s name, Japanese forces killed about
27,000 British soldiers and 20,000 Dutch troops. Many survivors also
held <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> accountable for atrocities committed against 127,000
Dutch people interned during the war.
   ``We are accustomed to hearing such kinds of criticism,'' said
<PERSON>Seizaburo Sato</PERSON>, a professor of political science at <ORGANIZATION>Tokyo
University</ORGANIZATION>. ``<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> made a mistake.''
   ``But didn't (the) British or Dutch do really bad things to
Asians they colonized, for example, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>? If they
think about what they have done for a much longer period of time
than <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> did, I think they should be more modest.''
   Most historians maintain that the late emperor was merely a
glorified figurehead with little political power. Hirohito died on
<DATE>Jan. 7</DATE> at age 87, never having made clear his role in the war.
   The cemetery is on the site of a playground that <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> opened
more than 65 years ago when he was crown prince.
   Nestled in the hills of <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION>, south of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, the cemetery
also holds the remains of soldiers from <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>
and other Commonwealth nations, and the ashes of an undetermined
number of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> soldiers. Many died while being held as prisoners of
war or aboard <ORGANIZATION>POW</ORGANIZATION> ships on the way to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in <DATE>1942</DATE> following the
surrender of <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>.
   At least one British war veteran attending the wreath-laying
ceremony thought <PERSON>Philip</PERSON>'s visit to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> was justified. The quick
trip to <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION> was largely seen as an attempt to appease anger
over his attendance at the funeral.
   ``People are entitled to their own opinions,'' said <PERSON>Edward Ward</PERSON>,
77, who said he had served in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s intelligence corps and has
lived in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> for about 10 years.
   ``But human rights would be in a sad state if people held grudges
forever more.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891215-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-15-89 1531EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Rubitsky-Medal 2ndLd-Writethru a0657-a0490 12-15 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Rubitsky-Medal, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0657-a0490,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Denies Medal of Honor to World War II Veteran</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Combines pvs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> board has refused to grant the Medal
of Honor to a World War II veteran who colleagues claimed was
passed over for decoration because he was Jewish, an <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> official,
Lt. Col. <PERSON>Terry Adkins</PERSON>, said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   <PERSON>David S. Rubitsky</PERSON>, then an <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> sergeant, had been recommended
for the medal by company and battalion commanders. They cited a
battle in the jungles of <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION> in which he was said to have
killed more than 500 Japanese soldiers.
   <PERSON>Adkins</PERSON> said an ``exhaustive'' two-year investigation into
<PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>'s claims showed the battle ``did not occur as alleged.''
   As for the claim that <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> was denied the medal because of
anti-Semitism, he said, ``I could not find any basis of fact in
this.''
   Rubitsky, who lives in <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, was notified <DATE>Thursday</DATE> night of
the decision and the army presented its findings to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> today,
<PERSON>Adkins</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s decision was first reported today by <ORGANIZATION>The New York
Times</ORGANIZATION>.
   Board officials said the lack of official records, the death of
witnesses and the failing memories of those who survived the
campaign thwarted their review.
   But the toughest obstacle was the implausibility that one
soldier _ armed with a machine gun, automatic rifle and a carbine _
could inflict such damage singlehandedly.
   They said <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> would have needed large amounts of ammunition
and would have been able to fire only one weapon while the Japanese
returned his fire, forcing him to keep his head down and shoot
without taking aim.
   Board officials said it was most likely <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> fought well and
had inflicted heavy casualties.
   The story of <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>'s heroics had been largely forgotten until
<DATE>1986</DATE>, when during a reunion of the 128th Regiment he fought in, it
was learned he had never been recommended for the <ORGANIZATION>Medal of Honor</ORGANIZATION>.
After the war, <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> traveled the world as a merchant marine for
more than 30 years.
   <PERSON>J.M. Stehling</PERSON>, his company commander, said in a recently
notarized statement: ``I personally inspected the battle scene and
there were more than 500 Japanese killed or wounded by the actions
of Sgt. <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>. His actions were heroic, and he should receive
the Medal of Honor.''
   In another statement, <PERSON>Herbert A. Smith</PERSON>, a retired major general
who was <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>'s battalion commander, said he passed <PERSON>Stehling</PERSON>'s
recommendation to Col. <PERSON>John H. Mott</PERSON>, chief of staff of the <ORGANIZATION>32nd
Division</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Col. <PERSON>Mott</PERSON>'s answer was, `You mean a Jew for the Congressional
Medal of Honor?''' said <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, who died three months ago.
   <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said <PERSON>Mott</PERSON>, who also is dead, ``just laughed and walked
away.''
   The board also looked at a handwritten notation on a yellowing
photograph that had been removed from the body of a Japanese
officer 47 years ago. He said he would commit suicide to atone for
having sent into battle ``600 fine Japanese soldiers (who) died
because of a solitary American soldier.''
   Secret Service experts in counterfeiting told <PERSON>Sen. Herbert H.
Kohl</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>, that the ink and paper of the photograph that
recently came to light were consistent with materials used in <DATE>1942</DATE>.
They concluded there was no reason to believe the photo was
``anything other than genuine.''
   Kohl's office had interceded on behalf of <LOCATION>Rubitsky</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>
resident.
   Of 295 Medals of Honor awarded in World War II, none went to
black soldiers. Only two went to Jews, according to the Jewish War
Veterans of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010889-0033 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 2644 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 8, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 6; Page 4; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1119 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ANDERSONVILLE, GA., MUSEUM HONORS THE NATION'S POWS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES HILLINGER, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ANDERSONVILLE, Ga. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
I am dying, comrades dying 
</P>
<P>
Far away from friends and home 
</P>
<P>
In this rebel den I'm lying 
</P>
<P>
suffering, staring, all alone 
</P>
<P>
 -- From poem written by an unknown Andersonville prisoner 
</P>
<P>
All that is left of the infamous Confederate prison in this small, central 
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> town are graves. In the 3-foot-deep trenches are the remains of 12,912 
Union soldiers and sailors, buried side by side, shoulder to shoulder. 
</P>
<P>
Usable clothing was removed to be worn by surviving prisoners or guards. Then 
dirt was shoveled on top of their partially clad or naked bodies. 
</P>
<P>
For the living, <ORGANIZATION>Andersonville</ORGANIZATION> was a place of horror. Prisoners lived in 
squalor, their excrement everywhere. Many went insane. Many killed fellow 
prisoners for a few morsels of food. Still others committed suicide, died from 
scurvy, gangrene, dysentery and other diseases caused by poor sanitation, 
malnutrition, contaminated water, overcrowding, exposure to the elements. 
</P>
<P>
Largest of the Confederate military prisons, Andersonville existed for 14 
months -- from <DATE>February, 1864</DATE>, to the end of the war in <DATE>May, 1865</DATE>. More than 
45,000 Union troops were held here. 
</P>
<P>
All prison buildings were torn down after the Civil War. The grounds are now 
occupied by the <ORGANIZATION>Andersonville National Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>National Historic Site</ORGANIZATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>National Prisoner of War Museum</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Only POW Museum 
</P>
<P>
Since <DATE>November, 1987</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Park Service</ORGANIZATION>, in cooperation with the 
<ORGANIZATION>American Ex-Prisoners of War</ORGANIZATION>, has operated the <ORGANIZATION>National Prisoner of War Museum</ORGANIZATION>, 
the only one of its kind in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It is appropriate that here at <LOCATION>Andersonville</LOCATION>, where so much suffering occurred 
to <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> prisoners, we honor and commemorate the sacrifices of all American 
POWs throughout history," said <PERSON>Helen Smith</PERSON>, 62, historian since <DATE>1972</DATE> of the 
30,000-member American Ex-Prisoners of War. 
</P>
<P>
She is the wife of <PERSON>Allen Smith</PERSON>, 66, a retired <LOCATION>Diana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, millwright and World 
War II <ORGANIZATION>Army Air Corps</ORGANIZATION> sergeant who was captured in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and held 
prisoner by the Japanese for 42 months. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Helen Smith</PERSON> worked with <PERSON>John Tucker</PERSON>, 40, superintendent of the <ORGANIZATION>Andersonville 
National Historic Site</ORGANIZATION>, to establish the <ORGANIZATION>POW</ORGANIZATION> museum, housed temporarily in a 
62-year-old storage building on the cemetery grounds. Early this year, the 
organization will launch a <MONEY>$2.5-million</MONEY> fund drive to help finance construction 
of a larger permanent POW museum in <LOCATION>Andersonville</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Letters and Diaries 
</P>
<P>
The temporary museum is filled with memorabilia from POWs of World Wars I and 
II, <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. "We have space in the present museum to display only 
about <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of our archival resources," <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said. "The museum's purpose is to 
tell the <ORGANIZATION>POW</ORGANIZATION> story to the American people through interpretive exhibits." 
</P>
<P>
On display are letters from POWs, prison camp diaries and artwork, exhibits 
explaining psychological warfare, photographs of emaciated POWs upon their 
release from the camps and maps showing their locations. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
WWII Prison Camps 
</P>
<P>
Another exhibit describes the 666 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> prison camps that housed 400,000 
Germans, 50,000 Italians and 5,000 Japanese during World War II. 
</P>
<P>
POWs from throughout the nation come to <LOCATION>Andersonville</LOCATION> to meet with museum 
visitors and explain their lives as prisoners of war. Often they are 
accompanied by their wives, who detail their own nightmares -- not knowing 
whether their husbands were dead or alive, sometimes for months or years. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
New Jersey Monument 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>William J. Thompson</PERSON>'s haunting sculpture of a crippled POW leaning on a crutch 
stands in front of hundreds of marble headstones marking the burial place of 
Andersonville prisoners. Presented by <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> in <DATE>1976</DATE>, the statue honors all 
American prisoners involved in all of the nation's wars, and carries the words 
of Zechariah: "Turn you to the stronghold, ye prisoners of hope." 
</P>
<P>
New Jersey erected a monument here in <DATE>1899</DATE> in memory of its residents who died 
in the Confederate camp. 
</P>
<P>
The graves were cared for then by the <ORGANIZATION>Grand Army</ORGANIZATION> of the Republic's Woman's 
<ORGANIZATION>Relief Corps</ORGANIZATION> auxiliary. From <DATE>1910</DATE> to <DATE>1970</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>GAR</ORGANIZATION> served as caretaker of the 
graves. Since then the <ORGANIZATION>National Park Service</ORGANIZATION> has had the responsibility. 
</P>
<P>
At the turn of the century, 20 states whose soldiers died here erected 
monuments in their honor. The monument for <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> is particularly poignant, a 
weeping woman with the inscription: "<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> honors the turf that wraps their 
clay. Death before dishonor." The names of all Iowans buried here are on the 
monument. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Kept Records of Dead 
</P>
<P>
At war's end <PERSON>Clara Barton</PERSON>, founder of the <ORGANIZATION>American Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>, came here with a 
detachment of laborers and soldiers, and former prisoner <PERSON>Dorence Atwater</PERSON> to 
properly identify all the graves. 
</P>
<P>
While a prisoner, it was Atwater's duty to keep records of the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> dead. When 
a man died, a wooden stake bearing a number was hammered into the ground over 
his remains. Atwater kept the list of names corresponding to the numbers. 
</P>
<P>
Later, he and <PERSON>Barton</PERSON> directed the placement of wooden markers bearing the names 
and state of each of the dead. In the <DATE>1870s</DATE> and <DATE>1880s</DATE> marble headstones 
replaced the wooden ones. Barton also directed the successful campaign to 
convert the <LOCATION>Andersonville Prison</LOCATION> graveyard to a <ORGANIZATION>National Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Perched atop the marble headstone of <PERSON>Lewis S. Tuttle</PERSON>, a young soldier from 
Saco, <LOCATION>Me.</LOCATION>, is a marble carving of a dove. No one knows how it got there, when 
or why. It's the only headstone different from all the others. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Only Person Charged 
</P>
<P>
Capt. <PERSON>Henry Wirz</PERSON>, the commandant of <ORGANIZATION>Andersonville Prison</ORGANIZATION>, was the only Civil 
War veteran charged with war crimes, was found guilty and then hanged on <DATE>Nov</DATE>. 
10, <DATE>1865</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Charged with "conspiring to impair and injure the health and destroy the lives 
of federal prisoners in violation of the laws of war," <PERSON>Wirz</PERSON> was described as a 
monster and a fiend by <ORGANIZATION>Northerners</ORGANIZATION>. Southerners claimed he was a scapegoat, a 
good soldier, a hero and martyr. 
</P>
<P>
The Daughters of the Confederacy erected a large monument to <PERSON>Wirz</PERSON> on 
Andersonville's main street "to rescue his name from the stigma attached to it 
by embittered prejudice." 
</P>
<P>
Wirz's daughter and granddaughter unveiled the monument on <DATE>Nov. 10, 1909</DATE>, the 
44th anniversary of his hanging. An annual memorial service is conducted there. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Honored Posthumously 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1981</DATE> Wirz was posthumously awarded the <ORGANIZATION>Confederate Medal of Honor</ORGANIZATION> at a 
convention of the <ORGANIZATION>Sons of Confederate Veterans</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>. Wirz Street in 
<LOCATION>Andersonville</LOCATION> is named in his honor. 
</P>
<P>
"Feelings continue to run deep to this day about Capt. <PERSON>Wirz</PERSON>, about 
Andersonville Prison, about the Civil War," said Mayor <PERSON>Lewis F. Easterlin</PERSON>, 79, 
grandson of <PERSON>William Easterlin</PERSON>, a Confederate drummer boy at <ORGANIZATION>Andersonville 
Prison</ORGANIZATION>. "It's good to research history and research it right, good to remember 
history and remember it right." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mayor Lewis Easterlin and the Wirz monument. ; Photo, Monument at the 
Confederate prison cemetery. CHARLES HILLINGER / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Series; Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ANDERSONVILLE NATIONAL HISTORIC SITE; NATIONAL PRISONER OF WAR MUSEUM; CIVIL 
WAR; GEORGIA -- LANDMARKS; PRISONERS OF WAR; MEMORIALS; MUSEUMS; PRISONS -- 
GEORGIA; CEMETERIES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900402-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-02-90 2326EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--MilitaryCemetery Adv15-2Takes   04-02 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Military Cemetery, Adv 15-2 Takes,0666</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv15</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, April 15</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 2 b&amp;w
photos.)</NOTE>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The tombstones tell the story, a litany of all
of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s wars and the men who fought in them. It's not so large
as <ORGANIZATION>Arlington National Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>, but the small burial ground at the
<ORGANIZATION>West Point Military Academy</ORGANIZATION> is unmatched in its historical scope.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By MIKE HENDRICKS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST POINT, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The tombstones tell the story, a litany of all
of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s wars and the men who fought in them. It's not so large
as <ORGANIZATION>Arlington National Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>, but the small burial ground at the
<ORGANIZATION>West Point Military Academy</ORGANIZATION> is unmatched in its historical scope.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890530-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-30-89 0039EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-MemorialDay-Capital     05-30 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Memorial Day-Capital,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Americans Go to Capital to Honor War Dead</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX6</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> laid a wreath at the
Tomb of the Unknowns, two Soviet veterans paid their respects at
the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> memorial and thousands of people flocked to the capital
to honor <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s war dead.
   Almost perfect weather with clear blue skies, temperatures in
the 80s and a gentle breeze served as backdrop to the 120th
Memorial Day services at <LOCATION>Arlington National Cemetery</LOCATION>, where 200,000
veterans are buried _ each tombstone marked by an American flag for
the holiday.
   On a smaller scale, eight wreaths at the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> memorial
honored the women who died in that conflict.
   In brief, somber ceremonies at the Tomb of the Unknowns, <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>
placed the wreath of flowers before the four graves _ each
representing unidentified casualties from World War I, World War
II, the Korean War and the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   The observance began with a 19-gun artillery salute. A drummer
from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army Band</ORGANIZATION> sounded four muffled ruffles, followed by a
bugler blowing taps and then 30 seconds of silence.
   Addressing more than 5,000 people, many in shorts and T-shirts,
<PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> called the war dead ``our nation's true heroes, the solid
pillars upon which our freedom rests.''
   The national cemetery is the resting place for ``Americans for
whom the words duty, honor and country are not just a phrase. They
were a way of life,'' said <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>, whose military record became the
subject of controversy last year because he had avoided serving in
the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War by joining the <ORGANIZATION>Indiana National Guard</ORGANIZATION> in the late
<DATE>1960s</DATE>.
   Across the <LOCATION>Potomac River</LOCATION> in the shadows of the <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln Memorial</ORGANIZATION>,
several thousand <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans mingled and talked about
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s most recent war. Some have made the trip to the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
Veterans Memorial each Memorial Day since the monument, a
chevron-shaped wall with the names of 58,156 war dead and missing
in action etched in its black granite, was dedicated in <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   The monument, which has become the most popular in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
attracts more than 3.6 million visitors a year, according to the
<ORGANIZATION>National Park Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   This Memorial Day, the ceremony was aimed at honoring the women
who died in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. Eight wreaths were placed at locations where
the names of eight women, casualties of the war, are etched into
the wall.
   Veterans who were influential in getting the monument built,
reminded the audience that most <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans returned from the
war zone to a country that was at best indifferent and at times
hostile.
   ``Our nation can never again abandon our soldiers,'' declared
<PERSON>Ronald Gibbs</PERSON>, a member of the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> Veterans Memorial Fund board
of directors. ``If we must send our youth off to battle, let's
stand by them to the end with moral conviction and support.''
   Among the thousands of visitors to the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> Veterans Memorial
on <DATE>Monday</DATE> were a Soviet general who fought in World War II and a
veteran of the Soviet fighting in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>.
   Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Vladamir Orlov</PERSON>, chief of a World War II veterans group
in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Mikhail Vishnyakov</PERSON>, a veteran of the
fighting in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, marveled at the impact of the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
memorial.
   The two even traced some of the names, according to <PERSON>John
Wheeler</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veteran who helped arrange the visit.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s military struggle in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, from which
the country was forced to withdraw after years of fighting, has
been compared to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military involvement in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> provided supplies and weapons to the <LOCATION>North
Vietnamese</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Viet Cong</ORGANIZATION> during the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880530-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-30-88 1216EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-MedalofHonor     05-30 0883</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Medal of Honor,880</SECOND>
<HEAD>Historian Seeking Medal of Honor for Two Black War Heroes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIM I. MILLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Not one Medal of Honor went to any of the 1.5
million blacks who fought in World Wars I and II, a fact historian
<PERSON>Leroy Ramsey</PERSON> wants to change.
   <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> has found the records of two black servicemen he says
deserve the medal: Sgt. <PERSON>Henry Johnson</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Seaman
Dorrie Miller</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Waco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Johnson served in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> during
World War I; <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> was in the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> in the Second World War. Both
have since died.
   It was an accident that <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON>, also of <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, discovered no
blacks had won the nation's highest military honor for bravery
during the world wars, although blacks have won the medal for
heroic deeds in other wars. It was also a discovery born of anger.
   ``In <DATE>1984</DATE>, I was watching television when they celebrated the
40th anniversary of D-Day in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>,'' he said in a telephone
interview last week. ``The president was over there, and the whole
week was as white as a Ku Klux Klan rally.''
   A black World War II veteran himself, <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> got angry that his
experience of the war was not recognized, but turned that emotion
into a useful pursuit.
   ``I decided to do a book on the black American in World War II,
and when I got into my research I began to realize that no black
had received the Medal of Honor in either World War I or World War
II,'' said <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON>, a former associate history professor at <ORGANIZATION>Hofstra
University</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>. ``So I put the book on the back burner
and took off on an effort to see if I could get that righted.''
   Ramsey looked at the records of black servicemen who had won
other high military honors, including the <ORGANIZATION>Distinguished Service
Cross</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>French Croix de Guerre</ORGANIZATION>. He looked into the history of
the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s Medal of Honor, established by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1861</DATE>, and the
<ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s, established in <DATE>1862</DATE>. And, he said, he read the more than
1,200 citations of the Medal of Honor since its inception, ``to
make sure I was on solid ground.''
   ``I didn't want this to be token because these guys were
black,'' he said. ``I didn't want any compromising of principle on
the Medal of Honor.''
   Ramsey discovered that <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, who fought with the French army,
killed four German soldiers, rescued a wounded comrade and captured
a stockpile of weapons all despite severe combat wounds. For his
actions, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> earned the <ORGANIZATION>Croix de Guerre</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s highest
military honor. He died in <DATE>1930</DATE>.
   Miller served at <LOCATION>Pearl Harbor</LOCATION> aboard the USS <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> said. When the Japanese attacked, <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>, a mess steward,
helped move his mortally wounded captain from the ship's bridge,
then returned to man a machine gun, according to <ORGANIZATION>Ramsey</ORGANIZATION>'s research.
   Afterward, the secretary of the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> awarded <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> a letter of
commendation, but Adm. <PERSON>Chester Nimitz</PERSON>, commander in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>,
upgraded that to the <ORGANIZATION>Navy Cross</ORGANIZATION>, the second-highest award, <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON>
said. <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> was killed in <DATE>1943</DATE> in a torpedo attack.
   Ramsey built up his case, but for two years, he couldn't get any
public official to listen. He sent copies of a 21-page letter to
every member of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> congressional delegations,
but ``<PERCENT>102 percent</PERCENT> of those people ignored the hell out of me.''
   ``It would have been easier for me to get a Boy Scout merit
badge for a communist,'' he said.
   Finally, he received a letter of support from Rep. <PERSON>Mario Biaggi</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>, but <PERSON>Biaggi</PERSON> became embroiled in criminal trials in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
and <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON>'s cause languished until <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON>
decided it had merit.
   ``<PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON> wrote me a very long letter and he took the time to
personally write each member of the congressional delegation in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and ask them to help me,'' <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> said.
   ``Then, as if a voice from the dark, <PERSON>Joe DioGuardi</PERSON> came through.
And the effort never stopped.''
   Last <DATE>October</DATE>, <PERSON>DioGuardi</PERSON>, a Republican congressman from
<LOCATION>Westchester County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Texas</LOCATION>,
cosponsored bills to waive the statute of limitations for the Medal
of Honor so both men can be considered for the award.
   In the cases of <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> and <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, both the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> have
opposed the bills, which are now before the <ORGANIZATION>House Armed Services
Committee</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>DioGuardi</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> did not specify why, according to <PERSON>DioGuardi</PERSON>, but the
<ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> laid out several reasons in a letter to Rep. <PERSON>Les Aspin</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Wisc.</LOCATION>, who is chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Services Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Delbert L. Spurlock</PERSON>, assistant secretary of the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> for
manpower and reserve affairs, wrote that while others, including
members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, had written to the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> requesting special
consideration for <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, ``At this late date, it would be
inappropriate to single out former <PERSON>Sergeant Johnson</PERSON> for award of
the Medal of Honor and to provide preferential treatment to him
over the thousands of other black soldiers who served so bravely in
combat.''
   Spurlock also said that <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>'s records were destroyed in a
fire in <DATE>1973</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Personnel Records Center</ORGANIZATION>,
although <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> said he obtained certified copies from archives in
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> state.
   <PERSON>DioGuardi</PERSON> said he would not give up the fight.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880626-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-26-88 2252EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-AfghanMonument     06-26 0376</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Afghan Monument,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Stone Laid for Monument to Soldiers Killed in Afghanistan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first stone was laid <DATE>Sunday</DATE> for a monument in
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> to the more than 13,000 Soviet soldiers who have been killed
fighting in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the official <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> news agency said.
   The monument, which includes an eternal flame to the dead, will
be built in <LOCATION>Friendship Park</LOCATION>, a popular spot in the Soviet capital's
northwest near the <LOCATION>Moscow River</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said.
   It said veterans of the Afghan war sang songs at a ceremony for
the laying of the cornerstone <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, a day celebrated here as
``Soviet Youth Day.''
   The creation of the memorial was a sign that the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>
may be increasingly coming to grips with the costs of the war it
did not win.
   During much of the 8{-year Soviet involvement in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>,
the state-run media and officials made scant mention of Soviet
soldiers who had been killed. Many of the war dead were buried with
no hint on their tombstones of where or why they had died.
   The Soviets have been more frank about the casualties under
<PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>'s policy of ``glasnost,'' or openess.
   The government disclosed on <DATE>May 25</DATE> that 13,310 Soviet troops had
been killed and 35,478 wounded since the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> intervened in
<LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> in <DATE>December 1979</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION> began withdrawing its
troops on <DATE>May 15</DATE> under a U.N.-brokered agreement concluded the
previous month.
   Tass said the war monument will be erected to ``Soviet soldiers
who died while fulfilling their internationalist duty in
<LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>.'' According to official Soviet thinking, the <ORGANIZATION>Red Army</ORGANIZATION>
did not intervene in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, but came to the aid of a Marxist
government beleaguered by a nationwide insurgency.
   Tass said that for <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s ceremony, a lamp was lit at the Tomb
of the Unknown Soldier near the <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION> that honors World War II
dead, and brought to the spot in <LOCATION>Friendship Park</LOCATION> where the
cornerstone was laid.
   The lamp will be kept by the state-sanctioned <ORGANIZATION>Soviet Peace
Committee</ORGANIZATION> until the monument is completed, <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Members of the <ORGANIZATION>Peace Committee</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> city organization
of the military reserve collected donations for the monument and
for the construction of a rehabilitation hospital for soldiers
wounded in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881006-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-06-88 1542EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-MedalofHonor     10-06 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Medal of Honor,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army To Study Whether Blacks Unjustly Denied Medals in WWI</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIM I. MILLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> has agreed to review the records of
black World War I heroes following an acknowledgement by <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION>
Secretary <PERSON>Frank Carlucci</PERSON> that racial discrimination ``could well
have extended to individual decisions leading to the awarding of
medals,'' a lawmaker said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Rep. <PERSON>Joseph DioGuardi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-N.Y.</LOCATION>, made the disclosure in releasing
letters from <PERSON>Carlucci</PERSON> and another <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> official.
   DioGuardi and Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Texas</LOCATION>, have been seeking
posthumous Medals of Honor for two black servicemen: <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> Sgt.
<PERSON>Henry Johnson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, who served during World War I; and
<PERSON>Navy Seaman Dorrie Miller</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Waco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, who died in World War II.
   The congressmen introduced legislation last <DATE>October</DATE> that would
have waived the five-year statute of limitations governing the
awarding of Medals of Honor, opening the way for consideration of
the <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> and <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> cases. But because of <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> objections,
the bills stalled in the <ORGANIZATION>House Armed Services Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   DioGuardi and <LOCATION>Leland</LOCATION>, along with 102 colleagues, wrote to
<PERSON>Carlucci</PERSON> in <DATE>June</DATE>, and the letter released <DATE>Thursday</DATE> was the
secretary's reply.
   ``It is clear that unjust discrimination existed during World
Wars I and II that could well have extended to individual decisions
leading to the awarding of medals in recognition of heroic
actions,'' <PERSON>Carlucci</PERSON> wrote.
   ``As you know, while there were a number of instances where
black World War I and World War II service members were recognized
by individual awards for heroism, none was awarded the Medal of
Honor.''
   Some 1.5 million blacks served in the world wars.
   <PERSON>Carlucci</PERSON> emphasized that the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> ``does not
support a symbolic award'' of the Medal of Honor, the nation's
highest military honor. He also reiterated the department's
objections to bills singling out <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> ``when many
other individuals might have been equally deserving.''
   ``Nevertheless, I am willing as a result of your expressed
concern to conduct further research to examine the conditions
existing in the past concerning award of decorations and medals and
the extent to which racial discrimination might have been part of
those conditions,'' the secretary wrote.
   DioGuardi also released a letter from <ORGANIZATION>Assistant Defense</ORGANIZATION>
Secretary <PERSON>Grant S. Green Jr.</PERSON>, who said the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> will review the war
records of blacks who served in World War I and received French
military honors or the <ORGANIZATION>Distinguished Service Cross</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s
second-highest honor.
   ``Research will be difficult because of the passage of time and
the destruction of so many records in the fire at the <ORGANIZATION>National
Personnel Records Center</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1973</DATE>,'' Green wrote.
   He estimated that the review, which has already begun, would
take ``in excess of six months.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> research will cover servicemen from the all-black 92nd
and 93rd Divisions during World War I and will attempt ``to
ascertain why Sgt. <PERSON>Henry Johnson</PERSON>, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>93rd Division</ORGANIZATION>,
was not recognized by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> for his actions in combat and
for wounds received in action,'' Green wrote.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> will also try to identify any black World War I
soldiers who were recommended for the Medal of Honor but were
disapproved or received lesser awards, he said.
   In a handwritten footnote, <ORGANIZATION>Green</ORGANIZATION> said he has asked the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> ``to
report back to us on the magnitude of doing something similar for
WWII.''
   Blacks were denied naval combat duty during World War I, making
such research unnecessary, <PERSON>DioGuardi</PERSON> said. But he said he is trying
to get the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> to do similar research into black soldiers who
served in World War II.
   <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, who served in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, was on sentry duty <TIME>one night</TIME> when
he killed four German soldiers, rescued a wounded comrade and
captured a stockpile of weapons, despite being severely wounded
himself. He received the <ORGANIZATION>Croix de Guerre</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s highest military
honor.
   <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> was serving as a mess steward aboard the USS <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>
when the ship was attacked at <LOCATION>Pearl Harbor</LOCATION>. After the captain was
mortally wounded, <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> dragged him off deck. Miller then manned a
machine gun and shot down two enemy aircraft.
   He was awarded the <ORGANIZATION>Navy Cross</ORGANIZATION>, the service's second highest
honor, and was killed when his ship was torpedoed in <DATE>1943</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880530-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-30-88 0318EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-MemorialDayRdp Bjt   05-30 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Memorial Day Rdp, Bjt,0695</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nation Remembers Its Dead; Revelers Head For Beaches</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhotos</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LARRY RYCKMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The mournful sound of buglers playing taps and the cadence of
marchers in Memorial Day parades helped Americans remember those
who died fighting for their country, while beaches and parks were
packed with holiday revelers.
   A sea of fluttering American flags marked the 72,000 graves at
<ORGANIZATION>Willamette National Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore</LOCATION>. Officials planned
ceremonies of remembrance today at <ORGANIZATION>Arlington National Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and at the <LOCATION>Vietnam Memorial</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Gettysburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, Gen. <PERSON>William Westmoreland</PERSON>, commander of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
troops in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> during the war, planned to speak after a parade
honoring soldiers who died in the Civil War battle 125 years ago
this <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   In <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>, a brass band today planned to wend its way
through a pioneer cemetery to salute a <DATE>19th century</DATE> madam called
``the hooker with a heart of gold.''
   And on <LOCATION>Attu Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, Americans and Japanese erected a
monument that was to be dedicated to the thousands of soldiers from
both sides of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> who died there _ the site of the only
World War II battle fought on North American soil.
   A snowstorm in the <LOCATION>Southwest</LOCATION> stranded some campers in <ORGANIZATION>Cedar
Breaks National Monument</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> and whipped up waves that sank an
unoccupied 60-foot houseboat on <PERSON>Lake Powell</PERSON>, authorities said.
   Temperatures in the 80s lured hundreds of thousands of
sunbathers to beaches from <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>.
   ``It's like the people are saying, `Welcome to <DATE>summer</DATE>,''' said
police Sgt. <PERSON>William Selig</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Rockport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION> ``It's like this until
the cold weather comes. In a few months we'll be looking forward to
fall.''
   In <LOCATION>Ocean City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, a swimmer drowned in the ocean 90 minutes
before lifeguards went on duty <DATE>Saturday</DATE> for the first time in the
season, police said.
   An estimated 100,000 people headed to <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> beaches on
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> to enjoy sun and sand on the opening weekend of the <DATE>summer</DATE>
beach season.
   Lifeguards were on duty for the first time this year at the
city's <LOCATION>Jones Beach State Park</LOCATION>, but there wasn't much for them to do
because of the cold water.
   ``Most people are just sunbathing,'' said <PERSON>Joseph Lescinski</PERSON>, park
superintendent.
   About 10,000 people, mostly bikers, ended their two-day <ORGANIZATION>American
Motorcycle Jamboree</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Cobleskill</LOCATION>, 30 miles west of
<LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   ``I didn't see a single wheelie,'' Mayor <PERSON>Nicholas Iorio</PERSON> said.
   The pace was quicker in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, where an estimated 350,000 to
450,000 people watched <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s 72nd running of the <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>
500. About 100 people were arrested in prerace revelry, and one man
died after falling out of a pickup truck, police said.
   <PERSON>Rick Mears</PERSON>, 36, overcame an early one-lap deficit to win the
race for the third time in his career.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Prospect Hill Preservation Brass Band</ORGANIZATION> planned its
eighth-annual Memorial Day tribute to <PERSON>Anna Wilson</PERSON>, who ran <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>'s
highest-priced house of ill repute for 30 years before donating it
to the city as a hospital shortly before her death in <DATE>1911</DATE>.
   In <LOCATION>Menands</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, a veterans group took time out from the
<DATE>weekend</DATE> sun and fun to honor President <PERSON>Chester A. Arthur</PERSON>, who is
buried in the <ORGANIZATION>Albany Rural Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Nobody else had opted in an official capacity to do anything
for this former president,'' said <PERSON>Martin O'Connell</PERSON>, organizer of
the memorial service for the nation's 21st president, who served
from 1881-1885. ``I think it's shameful that the federal government
should ignore the grave of a former commander-in-chief on Memorial
Day weekend.''
   In <LOCATION>Hackensack</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, submarine veterans <DATE>Sunday</DATE> held their 15th
annual ceremony in memory of the 52 submarines lost in World War II
and peace time.
   A wreath was tossed into <LOCATION>Boston Harbor</LOCATION> from the 190-year-old USS
Constitution, the nation's oldest commissioned warship.
   And about 1,200 Boy Scouts, <PERSON>Girl Scouts</PERSON>, <PERSON>Brownies</PERSON> and Cub Scouts
placed flags on all 78,200 graves at <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles National Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``You can see all those who fought, but it's sad because they
all died,'' said 9-year-old <PERSON>Andrew Marek</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891109-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-89 0322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MedalFight Bjt   11-09 0679</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Medal Fight, Bjt,0698</SECOND>
<HEAD>WWII G.I. Who Killed 500 Enemy Soldiers Awaits Medal</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MI1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JULIE AICHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Jewish soldier who says he saved his
battalion by singlehandedly shooting to death more than 500
Japanese soldiers may soon receive the Medal of Honor he believes
was denied because of his religion.
   Marshaling the support of a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator, an authenticated
photograph taken from the body of a Japanese soldier, and
affidavits from two former commanders, <PERSON>David S. Rubitsky</PERSON> thinks he
has enough evidence to win official recognition 47 years after the
deed.
   Rubitsky, 72, believes he was nominated for a Medal of Honor
during World War II but denied the award because of the actions of
an anti-Semitic commander. He has vowed to keep fighting for the
award.
   ``If I give up, I'm beaten and I'm a fighter,'' <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> said in
an interview last year. ``If I lose, the Jewish people lose and
then I'm going to let them down.''
   According to <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>'s story, the heroic deed took place <DATE>Dec.
1-2, 1942</DATE>, in a <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION> swamp known as ``The Triangle,'' during
an attack by Japanese troops on <ORGANIZATION>Rubitsky's 128th Infantry</ORGANIZATION> unit.
   The former communications sergeant jumped into a machine gun
fortification after it was abandoned by other soldiers and fired
nearly 3,500 rounds of ammunition on the Japanese during 21 hours.
   Officials investigating <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>'s complaint said a photograph
discovered this <DATE>spring</DATE> has brought strong credence to his claim.
   Rubitsky came across the photograph in <DATE>March</DATE> while visiting an
<ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> companion in <LOCATION>Mesa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>. The photograph, reportedly taken from
the pocket of dead Japanese soldier, shows a group picture of a
Japanese military unit.
   A handwritten message in Japanese on the back said the picture's
bearer had decided to commit suicide after he and other officers
sent men into a battle in which ``600 fine Japanese soldiers died
because of a solitary American soldier.''
   <PERSON>Sen. Herbert Kohl</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>, began working on <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>'s behalf in
<DATE>January</DATE> and had the photograph examined this <DATE>spring</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Secret Service</ORGANIZATION> confirmed the photo was printed on paper from
<DATE>1942</DATE> and the writing was from ink produced in <DATE>1942</DATE>. The note on the
back was interpreted by the <ORGANIZATION>Library of Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Based on my review of the evidence, as well as the contacts my
office has had with <PERSON>Mr. Rubitsky</PERSON>, I have concluded that he earned
the Medal of Honor,'' <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> said.
   Maj. <PERSON>Joe Padilla</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Army Awards Branch</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>,
said a review of <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>'s case began in <DATE>January 1988</DATE> and a
decision should be issued by the end of the year.
   Under Title 10 of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Code, all recommendations for a medal
from World War II had to have been submitted by <DATE>May 1951</DATE>. Thus
investigators must determine whether a recommendation was made for
<PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>, and if so whether anti-Semitism played on role in the
denial of the award, <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said.
   He said the investigation into the medal ``must prove
incontestable evidence. This is very difficult to do, after nearly
half a century.''
   Rubitsky has declined interviews recently, saying he wants to
wait for the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s decision.
   But in an editorial he wrote for the <LOCATION>Milwaukee Sentinel</LOCATION> <DATE>last
year</DATE>, he said he was told in <DATE>1986</DATE> that his former commanding
officers had nominated him for a medal.<PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> said he then began
investigating why he hadn't received it.
   <PERSON>Joseph Stehling</PERSON>, a retired brigadier general who lives in <ORGANIZATION>Beaver
Dam</ORGANIZATION>, signed an affidavit outlining <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON>'s actions and
confirming he nominated <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> for the honor. Retired Gen.
<PERSON>Herbert Smith</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>September</DATE>, signed a similar affidavit.
   Another affidavit signed by a military messenger said Col. <PERSON>John
Mott</PERSON>, now dead, had denied <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> his medal because <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> was
Jewish.
   In the <DATE>1988</DATE> interview, <PERSON>Rubitsky</PERSON> said he had received numerous
anti-Semitic phone calls and threats after deciding to fight for
the medal.
   ``It's not really the medal,'' he said. ``It is the
anti-Semitism that existed then and still exists now. I want people
to know there is still discrimination.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880423-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-23-88 1333EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-AfghanLegacy 1stLd-Writethru   04-23 1048</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Afghan Legacy, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0532,1075</SECOND>
<HEAD>Afghan Wounds Are Deep in War Soviets Didn't Win</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 3rd graf, `The human...' to CORRECT spelling of
Chizhukovskoye. Pick up 4th pvs, `The troops...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOS7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MINSK, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The white marble headstone on <PERSON>Vladimir
Mikhalev</PERSON>'s grave is a reminder in this bastion of World War II
valor that he died in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, but there is no monument to
those who fought the war the Soviets didn't win.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s 115,000 troops are to begin the long-awaited
march home this <DATE>spring</DATE>. And the nation must deal with the problem
of how to remember those who served and those who died in
<LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>.
   The human losses suffered since Soviet soldiers entered
<LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> in <DATE>December 1979</DATE> and the emotional wounds were
unmentionable topics in <DATE>1981</DATE>, when <PERSON>Mikhalev</PERSON>, 23, was buried in
Chizhukovskoye cemetery among the heroes of World War II.
   The troops were sent in to defeat a revolt by anti-communists
and leave behind an Afghan army capable of standing on its own.
Neither goal was fulfilled, war weariness has set in and Soviets
are now anxious for withdrawal.
   The Afghan war has left many returning soldiers deeply disturbed
by their tour of duty in that Asian land. Drug addiction, a
predilection for violence, apathy, disease, crippling wounds and
broken marriages also are byproducts of the Afghan war.
   Significantly, the veterans are called ``the Afghans'' by many
Soviets _ a clear sign, say many returning soldiers, that they are
branded as outcasts.
   In few other cities is the contrast between the social status of
Afghan veterans and those who struggled against the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION> more
apparent than in <LOCATION>Minsk</LOCATION>, a ``Hero City'' virtually destroyed in
World War II and rebuilt as a monument to Soviet suffering and
perseverance.
   Every major intersection and park has a war memorial or statue
depicting a local hero. Here and in other cities, veterans of what
is known as the Great Patriotic War proudly wear their medals and
campaign ribbons.
   But not a single memorial has been erected in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>
to the soldiers killed in the 8-year-old Soviet military
intervention in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>.
   The sole reminders are the stern young faces and bronze busts of
young men staring from graveyards around the country. Few
tombstones say the youths were killed in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, but all who
pass by know the meaning of the inscription ``he died while
fulfilling his internationalist duty.''
   At Chizhukovskoye cemetery, the plaque on <ORGANIZATION>Vladislav Ivanovsky</ORGANIZATION>'s
headstone is engraved with rare directness: ``Perished in
<LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>.''
   An estimated 10,000 Soviets died in the war that was
unmentionable until Soviet leader <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>'s drive for
``glasnost,'' or openness, made it acceptable conversation.
   The casualty estimates by Western sources pale in comparison
with the 20 million Soviets killed during World War II. But grief
is no easier for survivors of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> victims, and veterans
from both conflicts acknowledge the problem goes deeper than
numbers.
   ``It's been 40 years since World War II,'' <PERSON>Sergei Kuznetsov</PERSON> told
an American reporter at a recent meeting of Afghan vets in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
``We are sometimes an uncomfortable reminder to those accustomed to
peace.''
   Soviets cling to the euphemisms used to label their activity in
<LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, denying it was a war, contending they never sought
victory, and always lowering their voices when the subject comes up.
   ``It cannot be said that we went there to win. We went there to
help,'' explained <PERSON>Alexander Maslov</PERSON>, a metal worker in <LOCATION>Minsk</LOCATION> who
alongside his twin brother <PERSON>Mikhail</PERSON> served two years in <LOCATION>Kabul</LOCATION>. ``The
leadership of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> asked us to help.''
   A tone of defensiveness permeates his discussion of the war.
``There is no reason to consider this a mistake,'' the 24-year-old
veteran said, referring to the <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION>'s decision to send in
troops. ``If it were necessary, we would do it again.''
   The Maslov twins contend <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> veterans receive priority
for housing and jobs. Yet each lives with his wife and child in a
single room of a city dormitory.
   State-run media have come a long way in the past few years in
acknowledging that Soviet soldiers were involved in combat and that
there was resistance at home, from fearful mothers of draft-age
boys to advisers at the top levels of power.
   The Soviets' experience in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> is similar to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
soldiers' service in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. But the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War was brought home
to Americans daily through media coverage that focused as much on
individual suffering as on the political issues involved.
   In contrast, Soviet media have carefully sanitized reports to
cast the conflict as a ``situation around <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>'' brought
about by imperialist interference.
   Spurred on by glasnost, about 2,000 Afghanistan veterans groups
have sprung up around the country to talk to school children about
their service, to help widows and mothers, and to talk over
experiences they say outsiders don't understand.
   In <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sergei Kuznetsov</PERSON>'s group, which gathers on occasional
<DATE>Saturdays</DATE>, has found a medium in song for issues most of the men
find difficult to openly discuss.
   The mournful ballads about buddies killed in battle and the
frustration of fighting a distant and little understood war have
been collected and issued by the <ORGANIZATION>Young Guard</ORGANIZATION> recording company.
   One song reflects veterans' disillusionment, and a glimmer of
the belief that Soviet involvement in a foreign civil war was
pointless. In part, it says:
   ``They fight for the prophet <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON>,
   ``While we defend only our Soviet truck.''
   ``The Return,'' a short documentary making its way into Soviet
theaters, for the first time shows wounded soldiers and blown up
tanks, and talks with troubled veterans and a bereaved mother.
   ``I'm a terrible enemy of this war,'' says a tearful <PERSON>Klavdia
Ilyin</PERSON>, with a picture of her fallen son on a shelf in the
background. ``I don't see why our children are there.''
   Newspapers have announced fund-raising campaigns to erect
monuments to the ``soldier-internationalists,'' and articles in the
national dailies have decried the second-class treatment of Afghan
veterans by those who don't want to be reminded of the war.
   ``Most people think our boys have been down there planting
flowers and building roads,'' observed one World War II veteran in
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>. ``How can they earn the respect they deserve when so few
know what they have done?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881025-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-25-88 1513EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Kohl     10-25 0818</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Kohl,0843</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Says `Hard' Talks with Gorbachev, Clash on Berlin
Reunification</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   West German Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he
and President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON> failed to agree on whether to
reunify <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, but signed accords to help the sick Soviet food
industry and put a West German in space.
   The chancellor earlier highlighted his concern for human rights
by meeting with <PERSON>Andrei D. Sakharov</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION> laureate
at the West German ambassador's residence.
   Kohl, speaking to reporters before a second round of talks with
<PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>, took a philosophical view to the dispute over <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> that
surfaced in banquet speeches the night before.
   ``The last word of history is neither spoken by me or by <PERSON>Mr.
Gorbachev</PERSON>,'' <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> said.
   In a dinner speech, <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> had said of the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> dispute:
   ``The attempts to upset what has been created in the (postwar)
process or push through unrealistic policies is an unpredictable and
even dangerous business.''
   He appeared to be referring to <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON>'s proposal for a change in
the status of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> and closer relations between <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> member <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION> and Moscow-aligned <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>.
   Since the end of World War II, <LOCATION>West Berlin</LOCATION> has been under the
control of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, the victorious
allies. The city has been divided since <DATE>1961</DATE> by a wall that
symbolizes the East-West hostility of the Cold War. Kohl said in a
radio interview in <DATE>January</DATE> ``there can be no real improvement in
relations between <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> if <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> is not included.''
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> told reporters he was not surprised by
<PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>'s remarks on <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>.
   ``The world can't be changed in a couple of hours,'' he said,
adding that he was optimistic agreement eventually could be reached.
   Kohl said <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s talks had been ``often and in part hard.''
   The two met again <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, but a <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> news agency dispatch on the
session did not say whether they discussed the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> dispute.
   Tass said aides signed agreements, including one on the peaceful
uses of outer space. It said the pact provides for the possibility
that a West German would fly aboard the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s orbiting
space station, <LOCATION>Mir</LOCATION>. West German officials said the pact also could
have German astronauts join Soviets in traveling to Mars in <DATE>1994</DATE>.
   West Germans have traveled to space in <DATE>1983</DATE> and <DATE>1985</DATE> aboard the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space shuttle.
   During recent visits by Austrian and Italian leaders, the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION> invited citizens of those countries to fly aboard the Mir
observe the launch of a French-Soviet space crew to the station.
   Another agreement signed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> calls for West German companies
to help modernize about 200 Soviet food and consumer goods
factories, <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> reported. The <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION>, faced with growing
complaints, has placed priority on eliminating food and consumer
goods shortages.
   Kohl met earlier <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> with Soviet Premier <PERSON>Nikolai I. Ryzhkov</PERSON>
to discuss economic cooperation, which includes a <MONEY>$1.6 billion</MONEY>
German credit to the <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION> to finance exports in food, leather,
textile and clothing.
   Sakharov, the founding father of the <DATE>1970s</DATE> Soviet dissident
movement told Kohl there still are political prisoners in the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION> and they must be released and rehabilitated, according to
German spokesman <PERSON>Friedhelm Ost</PERSON>.
   Sakharov was banished to the closed city of Gorky in <DATE>1980</DATE> for
criticizing the <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION>'s military push into <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>
allowed him to return to <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> in <DATE>December 1986</DATE>.
   Kohl, who arrived in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> on a four-day visit <DATE>Monday</DATE>, paid
homage <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to Soviet and German victims of World War II. In
freezing weather and under an gray sky, <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> laid a wreath at the
Soviet Tomb of the Unknown Soldier beside the <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION> wall. The
ceremony, a protocol must for foreign dignitaries visiting <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>,
takes on a special poignancy when performed by a German.
   ``The distinguished guest honored by a minute of silence the
memory of millions of Soviet people who died in the Great Patriotic
