<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891011-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-11-89 1450EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Hispanics 1stLd-Writethru a0572 10-11 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hispanics, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0572,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hispanic Population Tops 20 Million</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 2nd graf to CORRECT Del Pinal's title. For Release 6:30
p.m. EDT.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There are more than 20 million people of
Hispanic origin in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, a nine-year increase of 5{
million, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``This is our first estimate of over 20 million,'' said <PERSON>Jorge
Del Pinal</PERSON>, chief of the Ethnic and <ORGANIZATION>Hispanic Statistics Branch</ORGANIZATION> at
the bureau. ``It's up from about 14.5 million in <DATE>1980</DATE>.''
   Hispanics constitute <PERCENT>8.2 percent</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population and are
the fastest growing large population group. The bureau said
immigration was a major factor in the increase, accounting for
about half of the growth.
   About two-thirds of the Hispanics in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> live in
just three states. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> leads with <PERCENT>34 percent</PERCENT>, followed by
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>21 percent</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's Hispanics, and there are
significant populations in <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New
Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, the bureau reported.
   Estimates are not prepared for every state because ``Hispanics
are not well spread out throughout the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,'' <ORGANIZATION>Del Pinal</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   The Census report estimated the total Hispanic population of the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> at 20,076,000 as of <DATE>March</DATE>, up from 19,431,000 a year
earlier.
   The largest segment is Mexicans at 12,567,000, followed by
people of Central and South American origin, 2,545,000, <LOCATION>Puerto
Ricans</LOCATION>, 2,328,000, and Cubans, 1,068,000. The balance were of
Spanish or other Hispanic origin.
   Mexicans were mostly concentrated in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, the
report said. Cubans are mostly in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, while <LOCATION>Puerto Ricans</LOCATION> tend
to live in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, and Central and South Americans are largely in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   While Mexicans were the largest group they are not the fastest
growing, the report said.
   Comparing the estimates for <DATE>1982</DATE> and <DATE>1989</DATE>, the bureau said
<ORGANIZATION>Central</ORGANIZATION> and South Americans had increased by <PERCENT>67 percent</PERCENT>. The
``other Hispanic'' category rose <PERCENT>31 percent</PERCENT>, followed by Mexicans,
up <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>Puerto Ricans</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT> and Cubans, <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891012-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-12-89 0134EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-HispanicPopulation     10-12 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hispanic Population,410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hispanic Population Tops 20 Million</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has more than 20 million
Hispanic residents, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports, meaning only five
other countries have larger Latin American populations.
   ``This is our first estimate of over 20 million,'' <PERSON>Jorge Del
Pinal</PERSON>, chief of the Ethnic and <ORGANIZATION>Hispanic Statistics Branch</ORGANIZATION> at the
bureau, said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. ``It's up from about 14.5 million in <DATE>1980</DATE>.''
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has the largest Latin American population at more than
147 million people.
   The only other countries in this hemisphere with more Hispanics
than the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> are: <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> with 86.7 million; <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>,
31.9 million; <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, 31.2 million and <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>, 21.4 million.
   The new Census analysis showed that as of last <DATE>March</DATE> Hispanics
constituted <PERCENT>8.2 percent</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population and are the fastest
growing large population group.
   The bureau said immigration accounted for about half the growth.
   About two-thirds of the Hispanics in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> live in
just three states. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> leads with <PERCENT>34 percent</PERCENT>, followed by
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>21 percent</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's Hispanics, and there are
significant populations in <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New
Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, the bureau reported.
   Estimates are not prepared for every state because ``Hispanics
are not well spread out throughout the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,'' <ORGANIZATION>Del Pinal</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   The Census report estimated the total Hispanic population of the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> at 20,076,000 as of <DATE>March</DATE>, up from 19,431,000 a year
earlier.
   The largest segment is Mexicans at 12,567,000, followed by
people of Central and South American origin, 2,545,000, <LOCATION>Puerto
Ricans</LOCATION>, 2,328,000, and Cubans, 1,068,000. The balance were of
Spanish or other Hispanic origin.
   Mexicans were mostly concentrated in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, the
report said. Cubans are mostly in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, while <LOCATION>Puerto Ricans</LOCATION> tend
to live in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, and Central and South Americans are largely in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   While Mexicans were the largest group they are not the fastest
growing, the report said.
   Comparing the estimates for <DATE>1982</DATE> and <DATE>1989</DATE>, the bureau said
<ORGANIZATION>Central</ORGANIZATION> and South Americans had increased by <PERCENT>67 percent</PERCENT>. The
``other Hispanic'' category rose <PERCENT>31 percent</PERCENT>, followed by Mexicans,
up <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>Puerto Ricans</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT> and Cubans, <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50701 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat004_c_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-004 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<F P=101> Chiapas Crisis </F>
<H3> <TI>   Army Recovers Regions Taken by Zapatist Rebels </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0501151094 Mexico City NOTIMEX in Spanish 1132 GMT 5 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0501151094 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City NOTIMEX </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpt] <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, 5 Jan (NOTIMEX) -- 
The authorities announced that the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Army</ORGANIZATION> has been able to 
recover several townships taken over last <DATE>Saturday</DATE> by an armed 
group in the southeastern <LOCATION>State of Chiapas</LOCATION>, although there are 
still some regions that are considered "unsafe." 
  Official Spokesman <PERSON>Eloy Cantu</PERSON> stated <TIME>last night</TIME> that the 
government had virtually recovered control of <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de 
las Casas, <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Las Margaritas</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Altamirano</PERSON>, population 
centers occupied by the so-called <ORGANIZATION>Zapatist National Liberation 
Army</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>]. 
  Nevertheless, in reporting on the events that took place in 
<LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>, the aforementioned <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Government</ORGANIZATION> spokesman 
explained that "there are still specific areas where conditions 
of insecurity still persist." "Institutional life and normalcy 
are painstakingly being recovered, in other words, with each 
passing moment civilian authority is being reinstated," <PERSON>Cantu</PERSON> 
stated. 
  Dozens of bodies with evidence of bullet wounds where laying 
along <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>'s streets after the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> was able establish 
control of the last population center taken by the armed group. 
The rebel groups decided to withdraw to the mountain region 
located in the north-central part of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>. 
  In <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, located 800 kms south east of <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>, 
Zapatista members attempted to hold on to the last population 
center it originally took. After taking over the first four 
communities, the up until now unknown <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> began to appear in 
other communities such as <LOCATION>Abasolo</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chanal del Carmen</PERSON>, and 
<ORGANIZATION>Oxchuc</ORGANIZATION>. During the last few hours the rebel group also withdrew 
from <LOCATION>Oxchuc</LOCATION>. [Passages omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50966 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat007_c_94016" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-007 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<F P=101> Chiapas Crisis </F>
<H3> <TI>   Poverty in Chiapas Seen as Major Source of Strife </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA1001201794 Mexico City Canal 13 Television Azteca Network 
in Spanish 1300 GMT 10 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1001201794 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City Canal 13 Television Azteca Network 
in Spanish 1300 GMT 10 Jan 94 </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105>Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Juan Manuel Pereyra</PERSON> and <PERSON>Marisa Lopez</PERSON> from the </F>
"Good Morning From <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>" newscast] 
  [Excerpts] [<LOCATION>Pereyra</LOCATION>] <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s 32 departments register 
different poverty levels. Experts feel that poverty is 
ancestral since its origins date back 500 years. <ORGANIZATION>Oaxaca State</ORGANIZATION> 
has a poverty level of <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> and is the poorest state in 
the country. <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>, with a poverty level of <PERCENT>0.1 percent</PERCENT>, 
is the least impoverished. <ORGANIZATION>Chiapas State</ORGANIZATION>'s 111 municipalities 
are poor. It is the second most impoverished state in the 
country. The poverty there, as anywhere else, generates 
ignorance. There is poverty, not misery, in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>. Poverty 
and the ignorance of those suffering from its consequences have 
become a breeding ground for professional terrorists who have 
pit the people of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> -- luckily a minority of them -- 
against their institutions. Rural areas have the highest poverty 
levels in this state. Monoculture is the chief occupation of 
the people here. [passage omitted] It is in these areas where 
the level of production and service infrastructure is very low. 
About <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> residents live in rural areas. 
Moreover, <PERCENT>99 percent</PERCENT> of the state's 16,400 towns are rural. 
Poverty in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> has many indicators. For instance, <PERCENT>60 
percent</PERCENT> of the economically active population earns minimum 
wages. Indians make up one-fifth of the population. Also, <PERCENT>19 
percent</PERCENT> of the people have no income. The illiteracy rate is <PERCENT>30 
percent</PERCENT>. There are no roads. [passage omitted] 
  [<PERSON>Lopez</PERSON>] <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> has a population of approximately 3.6 
million. The current strife zone is located in six of its 111 
municipalities. Four of these municipalities have a population 
of a little more than 360,000 persons, or <PERCENT>11.8 percent</PERCENT> of the 
population. The majority of the people in <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San 
Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, <LOCATION>Las Margaritas</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Comitan</LOCATION> de 
<PERSON>Dominguez</PERSON>, the site of <DATE>last week</DATE>'s clashes, work the land. That 
is where one cause of the conflict lies. With almost 
nonexistent land reform following the victory of the revolution 
and inadequate land distribution during the <PERSON>Cardenas</PERSON> eras, 
pressure on the land has displaced a large number of people, 
mostly Indians. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101289-0113 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 119493 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 12, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
595 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
STATE'S LATINO POPULATION IS UP 2 MILLION, U.S. ESTIMATES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ROBERT J. VICKERS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s Latino population, which represents one-third of the Latinos 
nationally, has increased by nearly 2 million since <DATE>1980</DATE>, according to a <ORGANIZATION>Census 
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimate released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The bureau said that the nation's total Latino population has grown by <PERCENT>39%</PERCENT> 
since <DATE>1980</DATE>, rising to a record 20.1 million. Latinos now make up <PERCENT>8.2%</PERCENT> of the 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population and have a population growth rate that is five times that of 
non-Latinos, the bureau said. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Carmen Denavas</PERSON> said that half of the 6.7 million 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> residents of Latino origin are immigrants. Immigration accounted for 
about <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of the national increase in the Latino population. 
</P>
<P>
"This is our first estimate of over 20 million," said bureau spokesman <ORGANIZATION>Jorge 
Del Pinal</ORGANIZATION>. "It's up from about 14.5 million in <DATE>1980</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
The figures in the report are estimates and include illegal immigrants. There 
are no precise figures for the numbers of illegal immigrants in the state or 
the country, and estimates of the number vary widely. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> retains its rank as the state with by far the largest Latino 
population, followed by <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which is home to <PERCENT>21%</PERCENT> of the nation's Latinos. 
Next are <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT>. The report also identified 
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> as having significant 
Latino populations. 
</P>
<P>
Estimates are not prepared for every state because "Hispanics are not well 
spread out throughout the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>," <ORGANIZATION>Del Pinal</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, Mayor <PERSON>Tom Bradley</PERSON> joined with Latino leaders and 
celebrities to kick off a city campaign designed to encourage Latino youths to 
stand and be counted in the <DATE>1990</DATE> census. 
</P>
<P>
"Tell your friends, tell your family that Hispanics must be counted to earn 
political power," came a message shouted not from the mouth of a politician, 
but by Latin American rock star <PERSON>Jose Luis Rodriguez</PERSON>, who attended the event at 
<ORGANIZATION>Roosevelt High School</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
And, based on the high-pitched screams of approval from hundreds of teen-agers, 
the words were well received. 
</P>
<P>
The city of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, bolstered with <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> in funding, has joined forces 
with a host of community and civic groups to find ways to reach traditionally 
undercounted groups, including Latinos, the homeless and those who live in 
overcrowded apartments. 
</P>
<P>
Officials said they have targeted high school-age Latino youths because the 
students can pass along census information to their parents and push them to 
fill out forms for the <DATE>April 1</DATE> head count. 
</P>
<P>
As part of the campaign, schools in areas with large immigrant populations will 
be sent census lessons for classroom instruction throughout the campaign, which 
lasts until <DATE>April 1</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The official <DATE>1980</DATE> count missed as many as <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Latinos, according to 
federal officials. 
</P>
<P>
The Census Bureau report said that the largest segment of the Latino population 
is of Mexican descent, about 12.6 million. Residents of Central and South 
American origin total 2.5 million, while those of Puerto Rican descent total 
2.3 million and those of Cuban descent account for 1.1 million. The remainder 
are of Spanish or other Latino origin. 
</P>
<P>
While people of Mexican descent are the largest Latino group in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>, they are not the fastest-growing segment, the report said. 
</P>
<P>
Comparing estimates from <DATE>1982</DATE> and <DATE>1989</DATE>, the bureau said that the number of 
Central and South Americans had increased by <PERCENT>67%</PERCENT>. The "other Hispanic" category 
rose <PERCENT>31%</PERCENT>, followed by Mexicans, up <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>Puerto Ricans</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>14%</PERCENT>, and Cubans, <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT>. 
</P>
<P>
Times staff writer <PERSON>Stephanie Chavez</PERSON> contributed to this story from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Students cheer as Tom Bradley, Fernando Valenzuela and singer Jose Luis 
Rodriguez, below, kick off census campaign. JOSE GALVEZ / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Poll or Survey 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CALIFORNIA -- POPULATION; HISPANICS -- CALIFORNIA; ILLEGAL ALIENS -- 
CALIFORNIA; CALIFORNIA -- IMMIGRATION; CENSUS; STATISTICS; HISPANICS -- LOS 
ANGELES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101289-0182 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 119664 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 12, 1989, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
682 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
STATE'S LATINO POPULATION IS UP 2 MILLION, U.S. ESTIMATES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ROBERT J. VICKERS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s Latino population, which represents one-third of the Latinos 
nationally, has increased by nearly 2 million since <DATE>1980</DATE>, according to a <ORGANIZATION>Census 
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimate released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The bureau said that the nation's total Latino population has grown by <PERCENT>39%</PERCENT> 
since <DATE>1980</DATE>, rising to a record 20.1 million. Latinos now make up <PERCENT>8.2%</PERCENT> of the 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population and have a population growth rate that is five times that of 
non-Latinos, the bureau said. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Carmen Denavas</PERSON> said that half of the 6.7 million 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> residents of Latino origin are immigrants. Immigration accounted for 
about <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of the national increase in the Latino population. 
</P>
<P>
"This is our first estimate of over 20 million," said bureau spokesman <ORGANIZATION>Jorge 
Del Pinal</ORGANIZATION>. "It's up from about 14.5 million in <DATE>1980</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
While the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimate did not include specific Orange County 
figures, the <ORGANIZATION>National Planning Data Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a Los Angeles-based research firm, 
has estimated that the local Latino population has increased by <PERCENT>53%</PERCENT> since <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
Orange County Latinos totaled 286,339 or about <PERCENT>14.8%</PERCENT> of the population in <DATE>1980</DATE> 
compared to an estimated 440,117 -- about <PERCENT>19.2%</PERCENT> -- in <DATE>1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Latinos account for <PERCENT>22.8%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>North County</LOCATION> residents, while they represent only 
<PERCENT>8.7%</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>South County</LOCATION> population. 
</P>
<P>
The figures in the report are estimates and include illegal immigrants. There 
are no precise figures for the numbers of illegal immigrants in the state or 
the country, and estimates of the number vary widely. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> retains its rank as the state with by far the largest Latino 
population, followed by <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which is home to <PERCENT>21%</PERCENT> of the nation's Latinos. 
Next are <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT>. The report also identified 
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> as having significant 
Latino populations. 
</P>
<P>
Estimates are not prepared for every state because "Hispanics are not well 
spread out throughout the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>," <ORGANIZATION>Del Pinal</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, Mayor <PERSON>Tom Bradley</PERSON> joined with Latino leaders and 
celebrities to kick off a city campaign designed to encourage Latino youths to 
stand and be counted in the <DATE>1990</DATE> Census. 
</P>
<P>
"Tell your friends, tell your family that Hispanics must be counted to earn 
political power," came a message shouted not from the mouth of a politician, 
but by Latin American rock star <PERSON>Jose Luis Rodriguez</PERSON>, who attended the event at 
<ORGANIZATION>Roosevelt High School</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
And, based on the high-pitched screams of approval from hundreds of teen-agers, 
the words were well received. 
</P>
<P>
The city of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, bolstered with <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> in funding, has joined forces 
with a host of community and civic groups to find ways to reach traditionally 
under-counted groups, including Latinos, the homeless and those who live in 
overcrowded apartments. 
</P>
<P>
Officials said they have targeted high school-age Latino youths because the 
students can pass along census information to their parents and push them to 
fill out forms for the <DATE>April 1</DATE> head count. 
</P>
<P>
As part of the campaign, schools in areas with large immigrant populations will 
be sent census lessons for classroom instruction throughout the campaign, which 
lasts until <DATE>April 1</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The official <DATE>1980</DATE> count missed as many as <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Latinos, according to 
federal officials. 
</P>
<P>
The Census Bureau report said that the largest segment of the Latino population 
is of Mexican descent, about 12.6 million. Residents of Central and South 
American origin total 2.5 million, while those of Puerto Rican descent total 
2.3 million and those of Cuban descent account for 1.1 million. The remainder 
are of Spanish or other Latino origin. 
</P>
<P>
While people of Mexican descent are the largest Latino group in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>, they are not the fastest-growing segment, the report said. 
</P>
<P>
Comparing estimates from <DATE>1982</DATE> and <DATE>1989</DATE>, the bureau said that the number of 
Central and South Americans had increased by <PERCENT>67%</PERCENT>. The "other Hispanic" category 
rose <PERCENT>31%</PERCENT>, followed by Mexicans, up <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>Puerto Ricans</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>14%</PERCENT>, and Cubans, <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT>. 
</P>
<P>
Times staff writers <PERSON>Carla Rivera</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stephanie Chavez</PERSON> contributed to this story 
from <LOCATION>Costa Mesa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Students cheer as Tom Bradley, Fernando Valenzuela and singer Jose Luis 
Rodriguez, below, kick off census campaign. JOSE GALVEZ / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Full Run; Poll or Survey 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CALIFORNIA -- POPULATION; HISPANICS -- CALIFORNIA; ILLEGAL ALIENS -- 
CALIFORNIA; CALIFORNIA -- IMMIGRATION; CENSUS; STATISTICS; HISPANICS -- LOS 
ANGELES; HISPANICS -- ORANGE COUNTY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50708 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat004_c_94013" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-004 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<F P=101> Chiapas Crisis </F>
<H3> <TI>   Armed Forces Resume Bombing of EZLN Positions </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0501192694 Madrid EFE in Spanish 1834 GMT 5 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0501192694 </F>
<F P=104>  Madrid EFE </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, 5 Jan (EFE) -- 
The Mexican Armed Forces on 5 <DATE>January</DATE> resumed bombing enemy 
positions in the mountainous zone of <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, 
<ORGANIZATION>Chiapas State</ORGANIZATION>, civilian sources told <ORGANIZATION>EFE</ORGANIZATION>. 
  At least three helicopters and two planes are participating 
in the bombings that began in early this morning in a zone 
located approximately 4 kms south of <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas 
and where there are 13 Indian towns with a population of 5,000. 
The main towns under attack, where clashes have been held with 
scattered guerrillas of the <ORGANIZATION>Zapatista National Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> 
(<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>), are: Corralito, <LOCATION>San Isidro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>El Ocotal</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Corazon de Maria</ORGANIZATION>, 
<LOCATION>San Antonio Los Banos</LOCATION>, and Pinavetal. 
  The residents of <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas have said the 
situation has become "alarming" because the bombings started 
behind the mountain ranges and are now continuing on the 
outskirts of the city, although sources said that at first 
glance one cannot detect the presence of guerrillas. The 
sources could not say how many soldiers are involved in the 
operation but noted there are 10,000 soldiers just in the 
state's capital, <PERSON>Tuxtla Gutierrez</PERSON>, in addition to other 
contingents in <LOCATION>Altamirano</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Las Margaritas</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, where 
the fighting continues. 
  Official reports indicate the bombings and clashes have 
ceased, although there is the possibility that the authorities 
have refused to give information on the new attacks to keep it 
from leaking to other rebel groups and warning them. 
  This past <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> alone, approximately 5,000 soldiers, 27 
tanks, two amphibious vehicles, 18 all-terrain vehicles, two 
fuel trucks, a repair unit, and 10 troop transport trucks 
arrived in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas. Unofficial sources 
indicated that the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> had possibly uncovered several rebel 
headquarters located in the <LOCATION>Lacandona</LOCATION> jungle and those were the 
objectives being bombed at the moment. According to experts, 
the force deployed to <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> is greater than any used by 
neighboring Central American countries against a particular 
guerrilla force. This force has become a genuine military 
offensive. 
  Unofficially it is being said that, despite the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> having 
regained near total control of the municipalities of <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, 
the Zapatists continue to harass nearby communities. Ocosingo 
as well as the communities of Altamirano, <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION>, and La 
Margaritas have not yet returned to their daily work or school 
activities, neither has potable water, electricity, or gas been 
reestablished. 
  On the other hand, several warnings have appeared written in 
red on the walls of buildings in the municipality of <LOCATION>Tapachula</LOCATION>, 
located 12 kms from the Guatemalan border, indicating: "We are 
already here, we will continue our struggle," and describe the 
population as cowards. 
  In the meantime, rumors still persist in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> 
related to the alleged capture of "Commander <PERSON>Marco</PERSON>," leader of 
the armed uprising that broke out this past <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. The 
prosecutor general of the republic has scheduled a news 
conference in the next few hours to provide details on the 
numerous rumors circulating on the situation. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-52017 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat019_c_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-019 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<H3> <TI>   CNDH Reports on Chiapas Situation </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA2701164094 Mexico City Canal 13 Television Azteca Network 
in Spanish 1300 GMT 26 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA2701164094 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City Canal 13 Television Azteca Network 
in Spanish 1300 GMT 26 Jan 94 </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105>Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Samuel Prieto Rodriguez</PERSON> in <LOCATION>San Cristobal de Las </F>
Casas</LOCATION> from the "Good Morning From <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>" newscast] 
  [Text] The <ORGANIZATION>National Human Rights Committee</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>CNDH</ORGANIZATION>] issued 
from <LOCATION>San Cristobal de Las Casas</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Chiapas State</ORGANIZATION>, a report on its 
work in <LOCATION>Los Altos de Chiapas</LOCATION>. 
  According to the report, there has been an individualized 
follow-up investigation of the legal situation of 131 persons 
reportedly arrested, including three minors. Of those persons, 
60 have formal arrest warrants against them, and 58, including 
one minor, are free. 
  It is also known that 18 persons who are Guatemalan, 
Salvadoran, and Honduran nationals are at the disposal of the 
immigration authorities in <LOCATION>Tapachulas</LOCATION> for violating the General 
Population Law [<ORGANIZATION>Ley General de Poblacion</ORGANIZATION>]. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>CNDH</ORGANIZATION> reports that out of 400 missing person reports, 278 
people have been located. 
  Regarding the criticisms from nongovernmental organizations 
-- particularly from <LOCATION>Amnesty International</LOCATION> -- the <ORGANIZATION>CNDH</ORGANIZATION> said it 
believes the time will come for them to settle those 
differences. For the time being, the <ORGANIZATION>CNDH</ORGANIZATION> said, it is focusing 
all its attention on complaints and its work in support of the 
civilian population. 
  On another topic, <PERSON>Samuel Ruiz</PERSON>, bishop of <LOCATION>San Cristobal de 
Las 
Casas</LOCATION>, said all the Mexican people, regardless of their 
religious preferences, must get involved in the search for a 
profound solution to the problems brought up during the conflict. 
  <PERSON>Ignacio Diaz De Leon</PERSON>, executive secretary of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Inter-Religious Council</ORGANIZATION> meeting in <LOCATION>San Cristobal de Las Casas</LOCATION>, 
said the role of the <ORGANIZATION>Council</ORGANIZATION> is to raise society's consciousness 
regarding the dignity of the indigenous groups. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50467 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat001_c_94007" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-001 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<H3> <TI>   Rebels Oppose NAFTA </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0201171194 Paris AFP in Spanish 1555 GMT 2 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0201171194 </F>
<F P=104>  Paris AFP </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, 2 Jan (AFP) -- 
Members of the <ORGANIZATION>Zapata National Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>) remain in 
the towns of <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, and they apparently also remain in the 
towns of <LOCATION>Altamirano</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chanal</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Las Margaritas</LOCATION>, after suddenly 
leaving <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, it was reported on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> by 
media sources. 
  The guerrilla members, it was confirmed by TIEMPO newspaper 
in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION>, burned the municipal palace in <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION> <TIME>early 
this morning</TIME> and continued to hold their positions in the town 
as of <DATE>0730</DATE> (1330 GMT). 
  The <ORGANIZATION>San Cristobal Municipal Police</ORGANIZATION> said the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> members 
left 
the city, the second most important one in the Mexican state of 
<LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>, and painted graffiti on the wall to announce they were 
en route to the town of <ORGANIZATION>Rancho Nuevo</ORGANIZATION>. A local journalist, 
however, noted that the announcement was actually "black humor," 
because the 31st Military Zone is located in <LOCATION>Rancho Nuevo</LOCATION> and 
the guerrilla members "will not walk into the wolf's lair." 
  The <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> members' graffiti indicated they will continue 
along 
their way "to <PERSON>Tuxtla Gutierrez</PERSON> (capital of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>) and there 
will be no rest." Other graffiti read: "We do not want <ORGANIZATION>NAFTA</ORGANIZATION>. 
We want freedom and a legitimate government." 
  The authorities have yet to issue a report on the situation 
which prevails in <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Las Margaritas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chanal</PERSON>, and 
<PERSON>Altamirano</PERSON>, or to indicate if troops are pursuing the guerrilla 
forces which left <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> and whose whereabouts are 
unknown. 
  According to different reports, the toll of the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>'s 
arrival is six dead -- three in <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION> and three in <LOCATION>Las 
Margaritas</LOCATION>. 
  <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>, on the Guatemalan border, is located 700 km south 
of 
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>, and it is one of the most backward and poorest 
states in the country and has a predominantly Indian population. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06182061 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06182061 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  US; HISPANIC; MINORITY; LIFESTYLE; IMMIGRATION; UNUSUAL; MEXICO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Professor David Hayes-Bautista, a third-generation Mexican-American who sends
his daughter to Mexico for tennis lessons, is part of an immigrant wave that
he says is unlike any other in American history.;    Because of the
geographical closeness of the country of his ancestors and because of modern
communications and transportation, he and other Mexican-Americans are
maintaining ties with their ancestral culture to a degree generally not
possible for other immigrant groups.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  U.S. HISPANICS LIVING IN TWO WORLDS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The connections are vivid in interviews with Mexican immigrants in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>, and form a unifying theme in a three-year study of Hispanic cultural
attitudes by <PERSON>Hayes-Bautista</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Chicano Studies Research Center</ORGANIZATION> at
separate those of Mexican descent from other Hispanic people, <PERSON>Hayes-Bautista</PERSON>
said he believed that many of the findings about cultural ties could be
generalized to include descendants of <LOCATION>Puerto Ricans</LOCATION>, Cubans or other Hispanic
nationalities who predominate in other areas of the country.;    He said
attitudes expressed by more than 1,000 participants in his study about
language, culture and self-identification led him to the conclusion that
Hispanic people are evolving into a bilingual, dual culture.;    "We could
come back in 100 years and the Latinos will not have assimilated in the
classic sense," <PERSON>Hayes-Bautista</PERSON> said. "I'm pretty sure they will still have a
sense of being Latinos.";    The nation's Hispanic minority grew by about 2.5
million people over the past decade, to about 22.4 million, or <PERCENT>8.9 percent</PERCENT> of
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population in <DATE>1990</DATE>, the census found.;    In <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, about 7.7
Mexican-Americans make up <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the Hispanic population in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
as against <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>65 percent</PERCENT> of the Hispanic population nationwide,
<PERSON>Hayes-Bautista</PERSON> said.;    If Mexican-Americans have stronger cultural ties to
their ancestral country than many other immigrant groups have had over the
years, one explanation is the history of seasonal or temporary migration from
Mexico.;    Jobs in the north are one part of the national dream in a country
that shares 2,000 miles of border with the <LOCATION>United States.</LOCATION>;    In
<PERSON>Hayes-Bautista</PERSON>'s study, many respondents said Hispanic history should be
taught in schools and that children should maintain their families' Hispanic
culture.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Los Angeles  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910630  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  20A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  385  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday June 30, 1991
00182061,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50713 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat004_c_94018" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-004 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<F P=101> Chiapas Crisis </F>
<H3> <TI>   Spokesman, Human Rights Ombudsman Discuss Events </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0601034394 Mexico City Radio ACIR Network in Spanish 0124 
GMT 6 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA0601034394 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City Radio ACIR Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Juan Carlos Santoyo</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] We arrived in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, <ORGANIZATION>Chiapas 
State</ORGANIZATION>, after a long journey, as has been the case in the past 
days. We learned that <PERSON>Eloy Cantu Segovia</PERSON>, the federal 
government's official spokesman in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, 
will give a news conference. He told us, as we reported to our 
listeners moments ago, that <PERSON>Jorge Madrazo Cuellar</PERSON>, president of 
the <ORGANIZATION>National Human Rights Commission</ORGANIZATION>, would visit <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION>. 
We will give details of <PERSON>Madrazo</PERSON>'s news conference later. 
  He reported that there were clashes overnight, that clashes 
continued at about 0400, especially in the mountain areas near 
<LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas. It was also reported that the 
rebels managed to corner a squad that was attacking these law 
violators, but the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Army</ORGANIZATION> rescued them. 
  Cantu admitted that there are still areas where uncertainty 
prevails. The rebels continue to operate out of and to hide in 
National Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>] are hiding in houses there and 
holding its occupants hostage to protect their own lives. 
  He said that the bodies of 20 <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> members were found in 
<LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>. According to the observations and estimates we made 
on 4 <DATE>January</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> sustained more than 30 dead here. Cantu 
added that the rebels have sustained 61 dead so far. This is 
the figure registered by the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Army</ORGANIZATION>, which managed to 
arrest 34 subversives. 
  As for <PERSON>Jorge Madrazo Cuellar</PERSON>'s visit here, <PERSON>Cantu</PERSON> said that 
the priority is to ensure a respect for human rights and the 
civilian population. He added that greater guarantees will be 
granted to reporters to allow us to perform our work. Cantu 
also reported that in a few hours there will be shipments of 
food, potable water, and food to the residents of <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, 
which will mark its fifth day under siege, so to speak, or amid 
clashes. 
  Cantu profoundly regretted the incidents involving our 
fellow 
reporters who were sent here. He added that each incident will 
be investigated. We will now hear <PERSON>Jorge Madrazo Cuellar</PERSON>, 
president of the <ORGANIZATION>National Human Rights Commission</ORGANIZATION>, during his 
news conference. 
  <PERSON>Madrazo</PERSON> said that he came with other officials of this 
commission to register complaints and reports on human rights 
violations during the clashes. Madrazo reaffirmed that each of 
these reports will be investigated, because human rights are 
respected and guaranteed in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. He added the following: 
  [Begin Madrazo recording, in progress] ...in <LOCATION>Tuxtla 
Gutierrez</LOCATION>. We initially responded to a request to help in 
evacuating tourists from the conflict area [words indistinct] I 
am accompanied in this work brigade by the first general 
inspector, the third general inspector, experts on criminology 
and forensic medicine, and personnel who are involved in 
investigations and communications. 
  At this juncture of the conflict the <ORGANIZATION>National Human Rights 
Commission</ORGANIZATION>'s work will focus on offering support to civilians 
who have nothing to do with the armed confrontation. The 
commission will also register all existing evidence on alleged 
human rights violations. The investigation and the report on 
conclusions will take place within the terms established by the 
Constitution and the Basic Law of the <ORGANIZATION>National Human Rights 
Commission</ORGANIZATION>. [end recording] 
  These were the highlights of developments that occurred on 5 
<DATE>June</DATE> in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, <ORGANIZATION>Chiapas State</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910612-0013
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910612-0013.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   U.S. Population Grew Less White in '80s
   As Hispanics, Asians Boosted Presence
   ----
   By Timothy Noah
</HL>
<DATE>
06/12/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A6
</SO>
<GV>
COMMERCE DEPARTMENT (COM)
</GV>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
GEORGIA (GA)
ILLINOIS (IL)
MINNESOTA (MN)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEVADA (NV)
NEW YORK (NY)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
WISCONSIN (WI)
</RE>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- The overall U.S. population became
significantly less white and Anglo-Saxon during the 1980s,
largely because of growth in the number of Hispanics and
Asians living in this country, according to the 1990 census.
   The proportion of U.S. residents identifying themselves as
white declined to 80.3% in 1990 from 83.1% in 1980. At the
same time, the proportion of Hispanics increased to 9% in
1990 from 6.4% in 1980. Roughly half of those who identified
themselves as Hispanic, the most rapidly growing minority
group, also identified themselves as white. Asians and
Pacific Islanders grew to 2.9% of the population from 1.5% 10
years ago.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In addition, blacks became a slightly larger segment of
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population, increasing to <PERCENT>12.1%</PERCENT> in <DATE>1990</DATE> from <PERCENT>11.7%</PERCENT>
in <DATE>1980</DATE>, and Native Americans grew to <PERCENT>0.8%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>0.6%</PERCENT>.
Although still an overwhelming majority in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, whites
have shrunk as a proportion of the population from <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> in
<DATE>1960</DATE>.
   Among Hispanics, the largest group remains people of
Mexican origin, followed by Puerto Ricans and Cubans. But the
census numbers suggest that a sizable migration of Central
and South Americans is under way. Between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1990</DATE>, the
number of people identifying themselves as "other Hispanic,"
a group largely from <ORGANIZATION>Central</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, increased by
two-thirds. They now represent <PERCENT>2%</PERCENT> of the population.
   People of Chinese descent remain the largest element in
the growing <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population of Asians and <LOCATION>Pacific Islanders</LOCATION>,
followed by those of Philippine and Japanese origins. In
addition, the census found significant growth among certain
groups from <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> -- especially the Hmong, who are from
mountainous regions of <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>, and people from <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sri Lanka</LOCATION>. Emigres from <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> and the
Asian subcontinent have been arriving in significant numbers,
but they don't yet represent a large portion of the overall
population.
   Minority groups remain unevenly distributed around the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, with Asians and Hispanics concentrated in the West,
blacks and Cuban-Americans concentrated in the South, and
Puerto Ricans concentrated in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION>. More recent
arrivals, however, appear to be dispersed less predictably.
According to <PERSON>Jesus Garcia</PERSON>, a census statistician, growth in
the "other Hispanic" category was evenly divided among the
<ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION>, the South and the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>, though it was slower in
the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>.
   In addition, people of Mexican, Cuban or Puerto Rican
origin are more widely dispersed than in the past. The number
of people of <LOCATION>Puerto Rican</LOCATION> origin living in <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, for example, more than doubled in the <DATE>last decade</DATE>.
   "When a group gets larger, it simply cannot concentrate
the way it used to," said <PERSON>Marty Riche</PERSON>, director of policy
studies for the nonprofit <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION>.
   Among Asians, those of Hmong descent were most numerous in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, while those of Pakistani
descent were found principally in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891012-0135 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891012 </DD>
<AN> 891012-0135. </AN>
<HL> Hispanics' Growth in U.S.
@  Outpaces That of Others </HL>
<DD> 10/12/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<GV> FEDERAL GOVERNMENT (FDL) </GV>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The number of Hispanics in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> grew in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> more than five times as fast as the rest of the population, the government reported. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said that the nation's Hispanic population numbered 20.1 million as of <DATE>March 1989</DATE>, <PERCENT>38.9%</PERCENT> greater than in <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
The rest of the population grew <PERCENT>7.5%</PERCENT> in the same years. 

   The bulk of the Hispanics in the U.S.-about six in every 10 -- are of Mexican origin. 
About one in 10 is from <LOCATION>Puerto Rican</LOCATION> roots. 
Nearly all the rest come from other Central or South American countries, although the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> also counts as Hispanics persons from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and those who describe themselves as Spanish or Latino. 

   Two-thirds of this country's Hispanics live in three states, the bureau added. 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>34%</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>21%</PERCENT>, most of them Mexican. 
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>, most of them <LOCATION>Puerto Rican</LOCATION>. 

   Hispanics now account for about <PERCENT>8.2%</PERCENT> of the 243.7 million people living in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32338 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat025_c_94009" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-025 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<H3> <TI>   EZLN Asks Nongovernment Organizations For `Peace Cordon' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0602154594 Mexico City NOTIMEX in Spanish 0618 GMT 6 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0602154594 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City NOTIMEX </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>San Cristobal de Las Casas</LOCATION>, 5 Feb (NOTIMEX) -- The 
<ORGANIZATION>Zapatist National Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>) has asked Mexican 
nongovernmental organizations to create a "peace cordon 
[cinturon de paz] to avoid pressure, intimidation, or even 
attacks" by the parties involved in conflict. 
  In a communique dated 1 <DATE>February</DATE> and released in this 
southeastern Mexican city on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> [5 <DATE>February</DATE>], it was noted 
that the request was made in view of the imminent start of peace 
talks between Peace and Reconciliation Commissioner <PERSON>Manuel 
Camacho Solis</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>. The fact that the dialogue could be 
held within a conflict zone would entail risks of provocation 
that could obstruct or bog down the dialogue. 
  "With the goal of reducing undesirable tensions to a minimum 
between the parties involved, a security or peace cordon should 
be formed around the dialogue site to avoid pressure, 
intimidation, or even attacks by one of the parties involved in 
the conflict against the other." 
  Meanwhile, Peace Commissioner <PERSON>Manuel Camacho Solis</PERSON> said here 
today that the direct talks with the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> "will be held very 
soon," and he added that "everything is set and there are no 
problems in holding the meeting." 
  After meeting with <PERSON>Samuel Ruiz</PERSON>, bishop of <LOCATION>San Cristobal de 
Las Casas</LOCATION> -- the link between the armed group and the 
commissioner -- <PERSON>Camacho</PERSON> said "we will come out ahead" in efforts 
to find a peaceful solution in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>. Buffer zones were 
created to hold the meetings in the area of <LOCATION>Los Altos de Chiapas</LOCATION> 
at the request of <PERSON>Camacho Solis</PERSON>. This request was accepted by 
the armed group on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The towns of <LOCATION>San Miguel</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Guadalupe Tepeyac</LOCATION>, in north central and southeastern <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>, 
respectively, were proposed as the two areas that will remain 
free of any armed presence and where the <ORGANIZATION>International Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> 
would provide assistance to the civilian population. 
  <PERSON>Camacho Solis</PERSON> explained this idea is intended "to create 
areas of detente" to support the population that has been 
adversely affected by the conflict. The armed group added that 
it would withdraw its men from <LOCATION>San Miguel</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Guadalupe Tepeyac</LOCATION> 
when the <ORGANIZATION>International Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> installs its camps to provide 
the humanitarian aid. 
  On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>International Red Cross Committee</ORGANIZATION> announced 
it would restore medical services in certain areas of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> 
and would organize a program to supervise the health centers run 
by Mexican personnel. According to the plan, the <ORGANIZATION>International 
Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> will only provide humanitarian aid to the civilian 
population and medical treatment to all, including the 
transportation of patients to hospitals in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> or anywhere 
else in the country as required. 
  Another action that contributed to the progress of the peace 
process was the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>'s sending of a communique to Bishop Ruiz. 
In the communique, the rebels announced they would "shortly" 
release former <ORGANIZATION>Chiapas State</ORGANIZATION> Governor <PERSON>Absalon Castellanos 
Dominguez</PERSON>, who was kidnapped on 2 <DATE>January</DATE>. 
  In another communique addressed to the <ORGANIZATION>Executive 
Coordinating 
Commission of the State Council</ORGANIZATION> of Indian and <ORGANIZATION>Peasant 
Organizations</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> said those Zapatists who "had verbally 
assaulted local residents who did not support our struggle have 
been reprimanded." This communique added: "Neither physical nor 
verbal threats to force anyone to join our struggle will be 
tolerated from our troops and supporters. Our war laws are very 
clear in this regard, and we have already taken action to 
correct the damage done and to prevent the problem from 
recurring." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50779 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat005_c_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-005 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<F P=101> Chiapas Crisis </F>
<H3> <TI>   EZLN Seizes Tenejapa, Fighting in Other Towns </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0701011394 Madrid EFE in Spanish 2250 GMT 6 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0701011394 </F>
<F P=104>  Madrid EFE </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpt] <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>, 6 Jan (EFE) -- The <ORGANIZATION>Zapatista 
National Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>) today seized Tenejapa, 
approximately 40 km from the city of <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas. 
Meanwhile, fighting continues in the nearby towns of <LOCATION>El 
Corralito</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Isidro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>El Ocotal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> de las Bajos, 
<ORGANIZATION>Corazon de Maria</ORGANIZATION>, and <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>. 
  Early <TIME>this morning</TIME>, the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> bombed towns near <LOCATION>San 
Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, forcing many people who live in the 
mountains to flee to the archeological area of <LOCATION>Palenque</LOCATION> or take 
refuge in the city. 
  The rebels today sent a letter to <PERSON>Rigoberta Menchu</PERSON>, winner 
of 
the <DATE>1992</DATE> Nobel Peace Prize, warning her that the Mexican 
Government might accuse the Guatemalan refugees living in 
southeastern <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> of being members of the rebel groups. The 
rebels indicated in the document that the government accepted 
the refugees 10 years ago "to give the world an image of 
humanitarianism and political opening." 
  Nevertheless, they added, that image "is not carried over in 
its relations with our own poor and exploited people, who suffer 
the same policies of genocide and ostracism that are practiced 
against Indian peoples in several Latin American nations." 
  From the beginning of the conflict, <PERSON>Menchu</PERSON> expressed her 
concern about the possible repression of the rebels and the 
conflict's repercussions on the Indian and popular organizations 
of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>. She was especially concerned that the return of the 
Guatemalan refugees, which was scheduled to begin now, might be 
hindered. 
  In this regard, the rebels indicated in the letter that "no 
one knows better than us about their poverty and their desire 
for a decent life, which is denied in their own country, and we 
will not be the ones to prevent or use force against our 
brothers' return to their places of origin." 
  Meanwhile, the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Army</ORGANIZATION> today increased its military 
movement in the mountainous areas of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> and is preparing 
for new clashes with the rebels, who refuse to lay down their 
weapons and are recruiting more peasants to their ranks. 
  The conflict zone has been under siege by thousands of 
soldiers who are guarding all roads, with dozens of tanks, 
helicopters, and airplanes that are overflying the area to 
prevent a new offensive by rebel forces. 
  So far, the armed conflict in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> has left, according to 
military figures, 96 dead. Unofficially, the number of deaths 
is estimated at 250, including soldiers, rebels, and civilians, 
and the number of wounded is estimated at 1,000. 
  With the intensification of the military offensive, hundreds 
of Indians and peasants are becoming the victim of thefts, and 
many have abandoned their homes and are fleeing to nearby towns 
in search of refuge. The <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> has expressed 
its concern over the human rights violations that have been 
committed in the strife-torn area and has urged the government 
not to put down the violence with more violence. 
  <PERSON>Jorge Madrazo</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>National Human Rights 
Commission</ORGANIZATION>, traveled to <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> to investigate charges about 
violations of the civilian population's constitutional rights, 
as well as excesses and arbitrary actions by the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> in its 
attempts to capture the rebels. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32071 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat022_c_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-022 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  2 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<H3> <TI>   Peace Commissioner Camacho Announces New `Buffer Zones' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0102230094 Paris AFP in Spanish 2147 GMT 1 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0102230094 </F>
<F P=104>  Paris AFP </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>San Cristobal de Las Casas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, 1 Feb (AFP) -- 
Peace Commissioner <PERSON>Manuel Camacho</PERSON> announced in this city on 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the creation of two "buffer zones" on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in the 
towns of <LOCATION>San Miguel</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Guadalupe Tepeyac</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Chiapas State</ORGANIZATION> to 
"create detente areas" following the armed conflict. 
  Camacho read a communique to the media which stated that 
free 
access will be allowed to two "buffer zones" in <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Las 
Margaritas</LOCATION> "as long as weapons are not carried." 
  <LOCATION>San Miguel</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Guadalupe Tepeyac</ORGANIZATION> are villages located far 
from <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> and to which the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> has never had access 
during the conflict because of local guerrilla resistance. 
  Camacho also said that armed members of the <ORGANIZATION>Zapatist 
National 
Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>), which began a military uprising in 
southern <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> on 1 <DATE>January</DATE>, should not be present in the area, 
either. 
  Camacho, who announced a series of actions in support of the 
"life and dignity" of the people in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>, did not talk about 
the possibility of a dialogue with the rebels, which remains at 
a standstill. 
  The communique read by <PERSON>Camacho</PERSON> and addressed to the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN 
General Command</ORGANIZATION> said "these will be the first two buffer zones" 
to be established in the state, and he added that "the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican 
Army</ORGANIZATION> from its positions will offer facilities for the movement 
of residents, supplies, and medicines to each one of these 
villages." 
  "The Mexican <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> has already left all areas where it had a 
presence in <LOCATION>Chiapas State</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Camacho</PERSON> in his message to the 
guerrillas. 
  He said that "traffic will be allowed through the access 
routes" to the buffer zone towns "as long as no weapons are 
carried." He added that the perimeters proposed for these 
places "must be respected." 
  "In these areas there must be no armed presence of the 
<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>," 
stated the commissioner, and added that the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> 
will provide in both towns "humanitarian health services and 
will assist with supplies." 
  Camacho added that "everyone will receive health care," but 
"only the civilian population" will receive supplies. 
  <PERSON>Camacho</PERSON> said the services provided at the two places will 
consist of health brigades to fight malaria and cholera, to 
provide universal vaccinations and first aid, and to support the 
transportation of patients to hospitals in <LOCATION>Chiapas State</LOCATION> or in 
other places in the country in the cases that may so require. 
  Regarding the supplies, the commissioner announced that 
warehouse and distribution centers for supplying the civilian 
population will be "gradually" installed and that humanitarian 
organizations may support the effort in coordination with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>. He added that the effort "will have full public and 
private support." 
  "With these actions, we all support the life and dignity of 
individuals over all forceful actions and military presence," 
the commissioner stressed. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50878 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat006_c_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-006 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  10 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<F P=101> Chiapas Crisis </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Initiates Operation To Aid Civilians </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0701173194 Madrid EFE in Spanish 1600 GMT 7 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0701173194 </F>
<F P=104>  Madrid EFE </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <PERSON>Tuxtla Gutierrez</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>), 7 Jan (EFE) -- The 
Mexican Government has undertaken an operation to help the 
civilian population in <LOCATION>Chiapas State</LOCATION>, victims of the armed 
conflict between the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> and rebel groups since 1 <DATE>January</DATE>. 
  With the intensification of clashes between the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican 
Armed 
Forces</ORGANIZATION> and the rebel <ORGANIZATION>Zapatist National Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>) 
near dozens of civilian towns, thousands of residents are 
without basic services and have fled their homes to save their 
lives. Almost 1,000 peasants and Indians have been caught in 
the middle of the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> bombardment of the mountainous <LOCATION>San 
Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas area and in the midst of crossfires that 
have destroyed homes and crops. 
  In response to complaints by civilians, the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Army</ORGANIZATION> has 
reiterated that its forces have not attacked civilian towns and 
pledged not to do so. 
  The government, church, and civilian organizations are 
setting up shelters for the Indians and peasants who have fled 
their homes because of the bombings. Thus far two shelters have 
been established in towns far from <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas 
and near neighboring <LOCATION>Tabasco State</LOCATION>, where civilians seeking help 
will be temporarily housed and their safety against rebel 
attacks guaranteed. It is expected that between today and 
tomorrow another two shelters will be opened. Additionally, 
corn, beans, rice, sugar, oil, powdered milk, and soup 
concentrate are being distributed among the most severely 
affected civilians. State-owned <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> expects to 
send approximately 20 tons of supplies to the area between <DATE>today</DATE> 
and tomorrow. 
  Hundreds of <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> members have focused on occupying small 
towns in southern <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> to threaten the authorities and 
proclaim fragile victories over the soldiers; in the process, 
they have cut off sewage services and the supply of gas, power, 
and potable water. Dozens of tanker trucks have been sent from 
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> with 50,000 liters of potable water to prevent the 
spread of gastrointestinal diseases among the civilian 
population. As a result of the shortage of domestic gas, the 
operation of a mobile plant has been authorized in the war zone 
to normalize the supply of fuel and to avoid further problems 
for the civilian population. 
  Meanwhile, the <ORGANIZATION>Institute of Social Security and Services for 
Government Workers</ORGANIZATION> (ISSSTE) has sent ambulances, several tons of 
surgical equipment, analgesics, antidiarrhetics, plasma 
expanders, and first aid material. It is expected that the 
ISSSTE and other medical institutions will continue to send 
medicine, vaccines against typhoid fever and tetanus, oral 
serum, antibiotics, and other first aid material. 
  Meanwhile, the <ORGANIZATION>National Defense Secretariat</ORGANIZATION> (SDN) reiterated 
today in a press communique that the Armed Forces have not 
staged any attacks whatsoever on civilian targets. "The <ORGANIZATION>SDN</ORGANIZATION> has 
paid special attention to the protection of the civilian 
population and respect for human rights during the course of the 
operations under way in the area," the communique asserts. The 
communique also states that during combat on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> one 
soldier was killed and eight were seriously wounded. The <ORGANIZATION>SDN</ORGANIZATION> 
has officially announced that almost 100 people have been killed 
in the clashes, including soldiers, rebels and civilians, but 
<ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> reports indicate that the bodies of at least 190 
rebels have been picked up from the streets. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32073 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat022_c_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-022 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  2 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<H3> <TI>   Camacho Acknowledges EZLN Communique </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0202034694 Mexico City NOTIMEX in Spanish 0258 GMT 2 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0202034694 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City NOTIMEX </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpts] <LOCATION>San Cristobal de Las Casas</LOCATION>, 1 Feb (NOTIMEX) -- 
<PERSON>Manuel Camacho Solis</PERSON>, commissioner for peace in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>, today 
described as "an important step" toward peace a recent 
communique issued by the armed group [<ORGANIZATION>Zapatist National 
Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>] operating in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> 
communique states that a direct dialogue is "imminent." 
  The message is "an important step toward meeting and 
advancing the process for peace and reconciliation in <LOCATION>Chiapas 
State</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Camacho Solis</PERSON> said in a communique released to the media 
in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION>, 1,200 km southeast of <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. [passage 
omitted] 
  <PERSON>Camacho Solis</PERSON>, in his second communique issued on 1 
<DATE>February</DATE>, 
termed as an additional advancement the fact that the group is 
willing to broaden media coverage of the possible direct 
dialogue. 
  The armed group also agreed today to <PERSON>Camacho Solis</PERSON>' proposal 
for national and foreign journalists to cover the eventual 
negotiations, but the group excluded the private Mexican 
television networks <ORGANIZATION>Televisa</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Television Azteca</ORGANIZATION>. 
  <PERSON>Camacho Solis</PERSON> responded: "My stance is not to exclude anyone 
and to make accreditation and access to the talks subject only 
to the appropriate security measures." 
  The commissioner deemed "appropriate the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>'s suggestion 
for the registration of the media and the procedures for 
coverage to be carried out through the group's mediator, <PERSON>Bishop 
Samuel Ruiz Garcia</PERSON>." 
  <PERSON>Camacho Solis</PERSON>, in his first communique today read this 
morning in <LOCATION>San Cristobal de Las Casas</LOCATION>, proposed to the armed 
group the creation of two "buffer zones" without an armed 
presence to ease the situation and help the civilian population. 
  <PERSON>Camacho Solis</PERSON> also announced that the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Army</ORGANIZATION> has 
withdrawn from the towns in the conflict area. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50466 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat001_c_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-001 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<H3> <TI>   Radio Reports Situation </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0201170094 Mexico City Radio ACIR Network in Spanish 1512 
GMT 2 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA0201170094 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City Radio ACIR Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The most important event featured today in <LOCATION>Mexico 
City</LOCATION>'s newspapers is the following: An armed group, mostly 
Indians, the self-styled <ORGANIZATION>Zapata National Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>] 
-- linked with the Procup [<ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Workers Clandestine 
People's Union Party</ORGANIZATION>] and the <ORGANIZATION>Poor People's Party</ORGANIZATION>, according to 
state officials -- violently seized on the morning of 1 <DATE>January</DATE> 
the municipal offices in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, 
<PERSON>Altamirano</PERSON>, <PERSON>Chanal</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Las Margaritas</LOCATION>, with a toll of at least 
11 dead and dozens of injured -- three in clashes sustained with 
public forces -- according to unofficial sources. 
  According reports from state officials, the Indians -- 
according to witnesses, there were about 2,200 of them -- were 
armed with AR-15 rifles, .22 caliber rifles, and shotguns, and 
they simultaneously stormed the five municipalities. Given the 
situation, the government secretariat warned it cannot justify 
the fact that fair social demands, for which there exists a 
willingness to provide a solution, be used as a pretext to 
violate legal order. 
  A <ORGANIZATION>Government Ministry</ORGANIZATION> communique said the government is 
urging these groups to act wisely, recant, and establish 
negotiations within a legal framework. Meanwhile, state 
officials called these actions a violent provocation. They also 
ordered public security forces to dissuade the armed groups, 
making it possible to seek a solution to their demands, which 
have yet to be stated, through dialogue and legal means. 
  Given the situation, the bishops of <ORGANIZATION>Chiapas State</ORGANIZATION> issued an 
appeal to the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> forces to accept the bishops' mediation in an 
effort to restore harmony and social tranquility in the 
municipalities involved in the conflict. Furthermore, it is 
appropriate to mention that contacts are being maintained 
between federal government officials and state officials in an 
effort to quickly resolve the situation. 
  The declaration of war issued by the <ORGANIZATION>Sandinist National 
Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION>, excuse me, the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>, to the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Federal 
Army</ORGANIZATION> asks the nation's legislative and judicial branches to 
strive to restore the nation's legality and stability. The <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> 
is asking international organizations and the <ORGANIZATION>International Red 
Cross</ORGANIZATION> to supervise and regulate the clashes that its forces are 
waging to protect the civilian population. 
  The declaration of war rejects any links to drug 
traffickers, 
narcoguerrillas, or any other groups when referring to the 
struggle waged by the <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>, which has ordered its military 
forces to advance toward the country's capital, defeat the 
<ORGANIZATION>Mexican Federal Army</ORGANIZATION>, and allow the liberated people to 
democratically elect their own administrative authorities. 
  This is, in short, what is currently taking place in five 
municipalities in <LOCATION>Chiapas State</LOCATION> -- <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, 
<LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Altamirano</PERSON>, <PERSON>Chanal</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Las Margaritas</LOCATION> -- where the 
self- proclaimed <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> violently seized the municipal offices and 
where there is a toll of 11 dead and dozens wounded. 
  A report issued early this morning by <ORGANIZATION>NOTIMEX</ORGANIZATION> reports that, 
after stating the need to contribute their efforts to prevent a 
possible confrontation involving the people of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>, the 
bishops of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> agreed to take part as mediators to restore 
harmony and peace in the municipalities involved in the conflict. 
  A communique issued by the diocese of <PERSON>Tuxtla Gutierrez</PERSON> and 
<LOCATION>Tapachula</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Chiapas State</ORGANIZATION>, stated that, in an effort to create 
conditions that will allow a fruitful dialogue, we issue an 
appeal to the so-called <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION>, urging it to accept four points. 
The bishops request an end to violence, respect for people's 
lives, the release of kidnapped people, and they urge them to 
put down their weapons, respect the law and human rights, and to 
take part in a dialogue to resolve social problems. 
  The bishops' document mentions that, in the event that their 
proposal is accepted, within the next 48 hours the bishops 
promise to ask the government to establish an office to handle 
social problems in the region. The bishops said they have been 
trying to contact the bishop of <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, 
<PERSON>Samuel Ruiz Garcia</PERSON>, since <TIME>early this morning</TIME>. Their efforts 
have failed so far, but they add they can count on the 
solidarity of this diocese's pastor. 
  The bishops of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> note that their agreement to serve as 
mediators was prompted by requests they received from different 
social groups in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> to search for a solution to the 
problems that have arisen in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas, 
<LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Las Margaritas</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Altamirano</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900305-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-05-90 1554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s w BC-APN--HispanicsinAmerica Adv18-1stAdd   03-05 0785</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Hispanics in America, Adv 18-1st Add,0807</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv18</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, March 18</NOTE>
<HEAD>WASHN: industry experts.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   As far as Hispanics are concerned, ``the word minority is
becoming extinct in some parts of the country, although that may
not have hit the policy types yet,'' says <PERSON>Elvira Valenzuela Crocker</PERSON>
of the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican-American National Women's Organization</ORGANIZATION>.
   About two-thirds of the Hispanics in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> live in
just three states. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> leads with <PERCENT>34 percent</PERCENT>, followed by
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>21 percent</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's Hispanics, and there are
significant populations in <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New
Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports.
   Latinos are younger, on average, than the rest of the
population. In <DATE>1980</DATE> their median age was 23, compared to 30 for
Americans in general.
   That means more are in the childbearing years and they are
producing a higher growth rate than the rest of the nation. In
<DATE>1988</DATE>, Hispanics averaged 94 births per 1,000 women ages 18 to 44,
compared to 67 per 1,000 for the rest of the country.
   That also means more young Latin Americans are in the nation's
schools, raising the issue of bilingual education in many cities.
   That as-yet-unresolved debate centers on whether it is better to
teach children in their own language while they learn English, or
to immerse them only in English as a means of improving their
skills in that language while they are learning other subjects as
well.
   Only about <PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT> of Hispanics age 25 and over have
completed high school, compared to nearly <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of
non-Hispanics.
   <PERSON>Cary Davis</PERSON>, a researcher at the private <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference
Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, views the growing Hispanic population as a source of needed
labor in the coming years.
   ``When the baby boom starts to retire in 20 to 30 years, who
will provide the work force? It will be an increasingly minority
and Hispanic society,'' <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> says.
   ``The labor force is going to be very different in the next
couple of decades, with a need for improved literacy and employment
training to educate the work force,'' adds <PERSON>Navarrete</PERSON>. ``We see this
as a challenge for the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, but also a very positve
thing.''
   ``We have to think through what kind of investment to make in a
group with lower levels of educational attainment, that doesn't
have a tradition of education,'' <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> says.
   And <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> cautions non-Hispanics against being ``overly
pessimistic'' about these changes.
   ``They will not be all newly arrived immigrants, there is an
assimilation process going on,'' he says.
   ``Hispanics will soon become the majority of entry-level workers
in some metropolitan areas,'' reported the <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> in a <DATE>1988</DATE> analysis of the Hispanic population.
   However, limited educations and language skills have held down
incomes, with per-capita income in <DATE>1988</DATE> averaging <MONEY>$7,956</MONEY> for
Hispanics, compared to <MONEY>$8,271</MONEY> for blacks and <MONEY>$13,896</MONEY> for whites.
   While many Hispanics are not citizens, the Constitution
specifies that the census count all residents of the country, not
just <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> citizens. Thus, when census figures are used for
political reapportionment and distribution of federal and state
funds, areas with more people _ Hispanic and otherwise _ will be
the gainers.
   Their presence will mean added clout for areas where they live
following the <DATE>1990</DATE> census.
   Between <DATE>1974</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE> the number of Hispanic elected officials
in the country grew from 1,500 to 3,300, including 10 members of
the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>William O'Hare</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION> has speculated
that minorities, including Hispanics, could gain six to 10 more
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats after the <DATE>1990</DATE> census.
   While Hispanics are not as likely to register as other
Americans, that gap has been narrowed by registration drives in
recent years.
   And when they do register they are as likely to vote as anyone
else.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE>, officials estimate, <PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT> of voting-age Hispanics
were registered, compared to <PERCENT>54 percent</PERCENT> of blacks and <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of
whites.
   The census report estimated the total Hispanic population of the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> at 20,076,000 as of <DATE>March 1989</DATE>, up from 19,431,000 a
year earlier.
   The largest segment is Mexicans at 12,567,000, followed by
people of Central and South American origin, 2,545,000; <LOCATION>Puerto
Ricans</LOCATION>, 2,328,000; and Cubans, 1,068,000. The balance were of
Spanish or other Hispanic origin.
   In addition to the challenges they pose, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> points out that
the growing <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Hispanic community can form an important resource
in international business relationships in coming years.
   ``The notion of a smaller world tells us that as we look to
international trade we have a community of representatives who can
work in Central and <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> and help establish linkages to
those countries,'' he says.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880907-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-07-88 0120EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Hispanics     09-07 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hispanics,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Number of Hispanics Up By One-Third This Decade</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The number of Hispanics has grown by more than
one-third since <DATE>1980</DATE> and now represents <PERCENT>8.1 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's
population, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> says.
   In a report issued <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the bureau also said the rate of
Hispanic growth is nearly five times that for the rest of the
population, and more than half of all Hispanics in this country
live in just two states: <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   The bureau estimated there were 19.4 million Americans of
Hispanic background as of last <DATE>March</DATE>. That is <PERCENT>34 percent</PERCENT> more than
the 14.5 million people who listed themselves as Hispanics in the
<DATE>1980</DATE> census.
   The nation's non-Hispanic population increased by about <PERCENT>7
percent</PERCENT> in the same period.
   About half the Hispanic increase was a result of immigration and
half resulted from birth rates exceeding death rates.
   While people of Spanish ancestry made up a growing share of the
nation's residents, they are extremely concentrated geographically,
the bureau found. About one-third, <PERCENT>33.9 percent</PERCENT>, live in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, and <PERCENT>21.3 percent</PERCENT> live in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, meaning those two
states account for well over half of all Hispanics in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.
   The study did not estimate the Hispanic population of every
state, but it said that nearly <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> live in just nine states.
   Those are <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, 6.6 million; <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 4.1 million; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,
2.1 million; <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, 1.5 million; <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, 801,000; <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>,
648,000; <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, 646,000; <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, 543,000, and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>,
368,000.
   Other findings of the report include:
   _The unemployment rate among Hispanics was <PERCENT>8.5 percent</PERCENT>, compared
with <PERCENT>5.8 percent</PERCENT> for non-Hispanics.
   _People of Mexican heritage were the largest Hispanic group at
12.1 million. They were followed by Puerto Ricans living on the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mainland, 2.5 million; Central and South Americans, 2.2
million; and Cubans, 1 million.
   _The proportion of Hispanic families anchored by a married
couple was <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT>, down from <PERCENT>74 percent</PERCENT> when it was last
measured in <DATE>1982</DATE>. At the same time, the share of families headed by
a woman with no spouse present increased from <PERCENT>26 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT>.
   _More than half (<PERCENT>51 percent</PERCENT>) of Hispanics have completed high
school, and <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> have completed four years of college. That
still trails non-Hispanics, of whom <PERCENT>78 percent</PERCENT> are high school
graduates and <PERCENT>21 percent</PERCENT> have finished college.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50462 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat001_c_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-001 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<H3> <TI>   Further on Rebel Group </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0101200694 Paris AFP in Spanish 1908 GMT 1 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0101200694 </F>
<F P=104>  Paris AFP </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>, 1 Jan (AFP) -- According to several 
sources, a group of Indians rose up in arms today and seized by 
force the mayor's office in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las Casas in the 
southern state of <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION>. 
  In a communique, the rebels announced the creation of a 
guerrilla group called the <ORGANIZATION>Zapata National Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> 
communique calls on <ORGANIZATION>EZLN</ORGANIZATION> forces "to advance toward the capital 
of the country, defeat the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Federal Army</ORGANIZATION>, protect the 
civilian population during this liberating advance, and allow 
the liberated people to elect their own administrative 
authorities in a free and democratic manner." 
  Eyewitness <PERSON>Ernesto Riedwyl</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>AFP</ORGANIZATION> that in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de 
las Casas some 200-300 people took over the municipal palace. 
According to <LOCATION>Riedwyl</LOCATION>, these people are now engaged in 
destroying and looting the building. Riedwyl said: "They are 
all wearing uniforms with green trousers, brown shirts, and red 
hats and scarfs. They are also carrying weapons of various 
calibers, and they have modern radio communications equipment." 
  He added, "Most of them are Indians, but there are also some 
white people with light-colored eyes." 
  According to this witness, the rebellion began at <DATE>0230</DATE> (0830 
GMT) when the rebels took over the <ORGANIZATION>Justice Palace</ORGANIZATION>, which they 
burned. Later, they took over the <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las <ORGANIZATION>Casas 
Mayor's Office</ORGANIZATION>. According to <ORGANIZATION>Radio Red</ORGANIZATION>, the rebels are also 
causing "disturbances" in other areas of <ORGANIZATION>Chiapas State</ORGANIZATION>, which 
borders <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>. 
  According to reporters, security forces in <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> have 
tried 
to persuade the rebels to resolve their problems through legal 
means, but this report has not been officially confirmed. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890914-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-14-89 0423EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-HispanicElderly     09-14 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hispanic Elderly,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Commission Says Older Hispanics Suffer More, Get Less Help</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NANCY BENAC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Elderly Hispanics suffer more financial
hardships and serious health problems than older Americans in
general but are less likely to benefit from Social Security and
private pensions, a private study shows.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Commission on Elderly People Living Alone</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> its
study of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s 1 million older Hispanics shows they ``generally
are not sharing in the economic prosperity enjoyed by other elderly
Americans.''
   The commission, established in <DATE>1985</DATE> by the Commonwealth Fund
philanthropic foundation, said the problems confronting Hispanics in
later years ``reflect cumulative deficits throughout life.''
   For example, it said, <PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT> of elderly Hispanics received an
eighth-grade education or less and <PERCENT>39 percent</PERCENT> speak only Spanish.
   ``These handicaps have consigned many elderly Hispanics
throughout their lifetimes to jobs that offered low pay and no
pension or health insurance benefits,'' the commission said.
``Despite having worked for most of their lives, many Hispanics find
themselves in old age without the means to maintain their
independence.''
   Higher levels of education and English fluency may help younger
Hispanics get better jobs and retirement benefits, but school-age
Hispanics have high dropout rates and ``many may already be on their
way to lives of low-paying jobs and poverty,'' the report said.
   Advocates for the elderly were to discuss the federal
commission's report at a hearing today of the <ORGANIZATION>House Select Committee
on Aging</ORGANIZATION>.
   The study, based on a national survey of 2,299 older Hispanics,
found <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT> of elderly Hispanics live below the federal poverty
line, compared with <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of all elderly Americans. Fifty-four
percent of older Hispanics report poor or fair health, compared with
<PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> of all elderly.
   Forty-eight percent of Hispanic elders are very satisfied with
their lives, compared with <PERCENT>64 percent</PERCENT> of all elderly, the survey
found.
   Hispanics currently make up <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> elderly
population, but are the fastest-growing segment of the senior
population. Their ranks are expected to quadruple to 4 million by
the <DATE>year 2020</DATE>, when they will make up <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT> of the elderly
population, the commission said.
   It attributed lower percentages of Social Security and private
pension beneficiaries among today's elderly Hispanics to the
immigration of some later in life and to their work in service,
unskilled and farm jobs with few benefits.
   Seventy-seven percent of elderly Hispanics receive Social
Security, compared with <PERCENT>92 percent</PERCENT> of all elderly; <PERCENT>19 percent</PERCENT> of
older Hispanics receive a pension, compared with <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> of all
elderly, the survey found.
   Because of their lower incomes, <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of poor elderly
Hispanics receive benefits under <ORGANIZATION>Supplemental Security Income</ORGANIZATION>, a
government program providing minimum income to poor people who are
elderly, blind or disabled. Sixty-seven percent of poor older
Hispanics are eligible for the benefits, but many don't know they
qualify, the report said.
   Although the report found poverty and health problems throughout
the elderly Hispanic population, there were differences among
different ethnic categories.
   For example, because elderly Mexican-Americans were the most
likely to have been born in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and work there longer,
<PERCENT>85 percent</PERCENT> received Social Security benefits. But <PERCENT>74 percent</PERCENT> of
Puerto Ricans living in the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <PERCENT>66 percent</PERCENT>
of Cuban-Americans receive the benefits.
   Cuban-Americans were the best educated and had the lowest poverty
rate _ <PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> _ compared with <PERCENT>42 percent</PERCENT> for <LOCATION>Puerto Ricans</LOCATION> and
<PERCENT>43 percent</PERCENT> for Mexican-Americans.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50479 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat001_c_94019" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-001 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<H3> <TI>   Security Heightened in Mexico City </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0301140694 Mexico City Radio ACIR Network in Spanish 1300 
GMT 3 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA0301140694 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City Radio ACIR Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "Panorama Newscast"] </F>
  [Excerpts] The civilian population in <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> de las 
Casas, <LOCATION>Ocosingo</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Abasolo</PERSON>, <PERSON>Chanal del Carmen</PERSON>, and <ORGANIZATION>Las Margaritas</ORGANIZATION> 
face an uncertain situation, fearing new surprise attacks by the 
so-called <ORGANIZATION>Zapata National Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION>, which has declared a 
war on the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Army</ORGANIZATION>. 
  There are scenes of destruction and death today. Members of 
the armed group are warning they will not remain entrenched. 
They intend to advance to the central part of the state and the 
country to demand the formation of what they call a free and 
democratic government. 
  The most recent offensive launched by the armed group 
resulted in the kidnapping of former <LOCATION>Chiapas</LOCATION> Governor General 
<PERSON>Absalon Castellanos</PERSON>. Approximately 40 heavily armed men arrived 
at his ranch in Margaritas municipality. There is still no clue 
as to the whereabouts of <PERSON>Absalon Castellanos</PERSON>. 
  Today, the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Army</ORGANIZATION> controls the city of <LOCATION>San Cristobal</LOCATION> 
de 
las Casas, which was suddenly abandoned by the rebels who tried 
to storm the 31st Military Zone's general headquarters. 
However, the action was successfully repelled by the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican 
Army</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Clashes between the two sides in two days have left 57 dead. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> has decided not to go into areas of conflict 
given the lack of security for its humanitarian work. This 
follows attacks on two <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> ambulances in <LOCATION>San Cristobal de 
las Casas</LOCATION>, where a rescue team member was killed. The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> 
is warning it lacks medicine and the necessary material to 
handle the emergency. [passage omitted] 
  The Judicial Police and the <ORGANIZATION>General Secretariat of 
Protection 
and Highways</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> have launched a special security 
operation which includes heightened security at government 
facilities, media installations, and embassies. This is being 
done as a precautionary measure to prevent any surprise takeover. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-11059 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat052_c_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-052 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> MEXICO </F>
<H3> <TI>   Chiapas Groups Agree To Press for Reform </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA1503211594 Mexico City Radio Acir Network in Spanish 0000 
GMT 15 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1503211594 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City Radio Acir Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 
