<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890227-0267 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-27-89 0211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Gardening:Ladybugs     02-27 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Gardening: Ladybugs,0653</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Gardening: Ladybugs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EARL ARONSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Who says the only good bug is a dead bug? One of the best bugs to
have in your garden is the ladybug. Each day, it feeds on many
``bad'' insects, such as aphids, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> potato beetles, grape
rootworms, alfalfa weevils, plus others. This helps keep things in
natural balance.
   The black-spotted red ladybird, better known as ladybug, is a
voracious, predatory beetle described as one the most beneficial on
earth.
   Millions of them have been released on croplands, their hearty
appetites helping to reduce aphid populations _ with biological pest
control.
   <ORGANIZATION>Cornell University</ORGANIZATION> scientists note the advantages of biological
controls: There is no environmental damage; the pests do not develop
resistance to their predators as they do to chemicals, and a small
initial investment results in a safe, permanent control method.
   In <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, some years ago, park officials released
300,000 ladybugs to fight plant pests. Gardeners in <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>, scattered more than 2.5 mlllion ladybugs to protect plants. In
<LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Perkins</PERSON> invited thousands of ladybugs to
an aphid feast in their rose test garden.
   National Geographic magazine has reported 4,300 known species of
ladybugs, or which <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> has 370. Remember tne children's
chant: ``Ladybug, ladybug, fly away home, your house is on fire,
your children will burn.'' This was a plea by English farmers
concerned for the safety of ladybugs during the annual burning of
hop fields.
   Given a chance, an adult egg-laying ladybug may consume up to 200
aphids a day. One larva may eat between 200 and 300 during its
development.
   National Geographic noted that ladybugs were put to work by man
in the late 1800s when a species, Rodolia cardinalis, was imported
into <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to combat the cottony cushion scale
insect, saving the citrus industry in <DATE>two years</DATE> at a cost of only
<MONEY>$1,500</MONEY>.
   Ladybugs are sold by the pint, quart and gallon; a half-pint
means about 4,000 ladybugs.
   A major concern is in getting the tiny migratory insects not to
fly away home. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> studies indicate that <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> wing off
after release. Since they don't fly at night, a late afternoon or
early evening release will encourage at least an overnight stay.
   The beetles are very mobile. When there only a few aphids around,
a <ORGANIZATION>Cornell</ORGANIZATION> researcher reported, they migrate, searching for other
areas of food, scouting apple crops, oats, winter wheat, sugar beets
and beans. The researchers imported the predacious European
seven-spotted lady beetle to help protect potato and alfalfa fields.
   There is no correlation between the number of spots and the
beetle's age. The number of spots on a beetle's back is
characteristic of its species, not its age.
   Ladybugs are but one example of millions of harmless insects,
<ORGANIZATION>Cornell</ORGANIZATION> noted. In fact, fewer than <PERCENT>2 percent</PERCENT> of all insects are
pests and those are ``often controlled by natural enemies.'' The
researchers recommend that gardeners and homeowners be certain that
insects are actually doing damage before they take action.
   Insects belong in a garden. They are natural and often harmless,
if not beneficial. Spray only if you detect damage. Beneficial
insects such as ladybugs ot all kinds and green lacewings should be
protected, entomologists say. By learning to identify their eggs and
larvae, we may save time, money, energy and the environment.
   Many ladybugs have been released in recent years to devour aphids
feeding on upstate <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> alfalfa, peaches and potatoes.
   If you see an unattractive, dark insect with orange, blue and
black patches and a deeply segmented body covered with spines, don't
squash it. It may be an immatore lady beetle, hungry and looking for
a meal.
   One catalog (<ORGANIZATION>Burpee</ORGANIZATION>) offers a half-pint for <MONEY>$9.95</MONEY>, a quart for
<MONEY>$17.95</MONEY>, recommending they be released in small batches.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100189-0036 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 114543 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 1, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 1; Column 2; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1812 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BUG BUSINESS; 
</P>
<P>
DEMAND FOR COMMERCIALLY PRODUCED INSECT PREDATORS HAS NEVER BEEN HIGHER AS 
FARMERS SEEK ALTERNATIVES TO PESTICIDES. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARIA L. La GANGA, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The tools are simple; the task is anything but. 
</P>
<P>
Entomologist <PERSON>Don Norlund</PERSON> is holed up in a bug-filled <LOCATION>Weslaco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, laboratory, 
armed with nothing but cardboard grids and swaths of filmy organza cloth, 
trying mightily to drag the insect industry into the <DATE>20th Century</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"Right now, the industry is not using neat technology to produce beneficial 
insects," said <PERSON>Norlund</PERSON>, a research entomologist for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of 
Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>. "It is not automated to any extent whatsoever. It's a lot of 
manual labor." 
</P>
<P>
Thanks to aldicarb, a pesticide that contaminated watermelons in <DATE>1985</DATE>, and 
alar, a chemical growth regulator that frightened consumers in <DATE>1989</DATE>, an 
increasing number of farmers are searching for non-chemical methods of pest 
control, and breeders of beneficial bugs throughout <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> are having a 
field day. 
</P>
<P>
Demand is outstripping supply for the first time in the industry's short life. 
And nowhere is the bug boom more evident than in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, which has a corner 
on the creepy-crawly market. 
</P>
<P>
But it's no simple task to breed beneficial bugs -- like green lacewings -- 
that eat bad bugs -- such as aphids. The process is low tech and labor 
intensive. There are no quality-control standards. Only one in three 
insectaries actually rears the bugs that it sells. 
</P>
<P>
And while interest in so-called biological control -- pesticide-free methods of 
growing crops -- is at an all-time high, some say the infant insect industry is 
not up to the challenge. 
</P>
<P>
"Mass rearing methods have to be developed and maintained and quality control 
programs must be worked up," said <PERSON>Marjorie Hoy</PERSON>, professor of entomology at the 
itself . . . or people will go back to chemicals. We don't want this to 
happen." 
</P>
<P>
Enter <PERSON>Don Norlund</PERSON>, the bug world's <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION> wanna-be. For the past year, 
<ORGANIZATION>Norlund</ORGANIZATION> has been trying to find a way to mass produce green lacewings, a 
predatory insect that will attack nearly any soft-bodied bug that crosses its 
path. 
</P>
<P>
His project is the nation's first large-scale attempt to automate the bug 
business, to "gear the system up to a commercial level," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Right now, feeding the bugs is extremely inefficient. Because they are 
cannibalistic, they must be kept apart in half-inch square compartments in 
small cardboard grids, he said. The grid has no top or bottom, but is covered 
with strips of organza, a thin, stiff fabric commonly used for women's hats and 
bridal gowns. 
</P>
<P>
To feed the lacewings, strips of flannel are soaked in synthetic liquid food 
and laid underneath the grid, and the bugs suck the liquid out through the 
organza. The problem is that up to <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of the food stays in the flannel and is 
wasted. So Norlund and his research group are trying to create a diet for the 
lacewings that resembles insect eggs -- prepackaged, intact, cost-effective and 
efficient. 
</P>
<P>
Harvesting lacewing eggs for sale is also a problem. The bugs secrete a 
substance that forms tiny "stalks" on which they lay their eggs, presumably to 
keep them off the ground and away from ants, which will eat the pale green 
ovals. 
</P>
<P>
"We are trying to design a cage that . . . would allow you to mechanically 
harvest the eggs off their little stalks," he said. "Right now, it's being done 
by hand. We brush the eggs with a little piece of wadded nylon cloth. It breaks 
the stalks of lots of them, but it also squashes lots. We're looking at ways of 
creating a hot wire to burn the stalk below the eggs and suck the eggs up with 
a vacuum cleaner." 
</P>
<P>
When you figure that it takes up to 20,000 lacewings per acre per season to 
bring aphids, whiteflies, scale and mealybugs under control, you can see why 
technology is so important to the insect industry. 
</P>
<P>
Without it, bug watchers say, insectaries will never be able to supply the 
number of insects necessary to make biological control a viable alternative to 
chemical pesticides. 
</P>
<P>
Rincon-Vitova <ORGANIZATION>Insectaries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION> is cooperating with Norlund in 
his attempt to automate the industry. Arguably the oldest, largest and most 
established insectary in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, Rincon-Vitova is also the most 
efficient producer of the dozen species of insects that it rears and sells. 
</P>
<P>
"These guys are some of the best producers of beneficial insects in the 
country," <PERSON>Norlund</PERSON> said, "but it's still not the type of technology that you 
need to produce the numbers of beneficials that it will require to replace a 
significant amount of insecticide." 
</P>
<P>
Still, it's enough to give Rincon-Vitova customers in all 50 states and six 
foreign countries and to generate more than <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> in sales for the company 
annually -- a good chunk of a market that's estimated at <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> worldwide. 
That figure would be larger, but for the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, where 
biological control is a government, rather than a private enterprise. 
</P>
<P>
suppliers of beneficial organisms in 19 states and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> is atop 
the insect heap, with 29 of those enterprises. <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> is next with five. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> is a pretty progressive state," said <PERSON>Jake Blehm</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rincon-Vitova</PERSON>'s 
vice president for marketing and communications. "There isn't a farmer here who 
doesn't know what biological control is. But there are a lot of places in the 
country where they don't have an inkling, the middle-aged farmers who started 
during the chemical era when pesticides were wonder drugs." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Bug Shortages 
</P>
<P>
Still, in the past several years, grocery shoppers have clamored for 
pesticide-free produce like never before, and many farmers have responded by 
kicking their chemical habits and buying beneficial bugs from insectaries such 
as Rincon-Vitova. 
</P>
<P>
"Last year, we had a predatory mite shortage because of demand from strawberry 
growers," <PERSON>Blehm</PERSON> said. "We've also had lacewing shortages. We had to quit taking 
orders in <DATE>June</DATE>, <DATE>July</DATE> and late <DATE>May</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
A lack of ladybugs has also been a problem since <DATE>1987</DATE>, <PERSON>Blehm</PERSON> said, but only in 
part because of consumer demand. Ladybugs -- the aphid-eating Hippodamia 
convergens -- do not reproduce well enough on a synthetic diet to make them 
economical to rear. 
</P>
<P>
So suppliers depend on roving bands of bug-pickers who trek through the High 
Sierra in search of the orange-and-black insects. Hippodamia convergens 
hibernate through the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> winters in inches-thick beds at the base of 
pine trees, hidden beneath layers of dead leaves and pine needles. Harvesters 
scoop them up and sell them to suppliers such as Rincon-Vitova and <ORGANIZATION>Fountain</ORGANIZATION>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>Sierra Bug Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which is based in Rough and Ready, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Ladybugs are getting so scarce, you can't get enough to keep people happy," 
said <PERSON>H. H. Fountain</PERSON>, the company's owner. "From <DATE>1974</DATE> to <DATE>1977</DATE>, we sold three to 
four times as many bugs as we do now. There were a lot more bugs to be had to 
begin with." 
</P>
<P>
Forest fires, logging and urban encroachment are the major culprits in the 
ladybug shortage, <ORGANIZATION>Fountain</ORGANIZATION> said. "Loggers tear the beds up completely to where 
the bugs won't come back," he mourned. "Forest fires will burn them out." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Research Needed 
</P>
<P>
And then there's research support -- or the lack thereof. An estimated <MONEY>$450 
million</MONEY> in mostly private funding is spent each year on research and 
development for chemical pesticides, according to <PERSON>Kenneth Cook</PERSON>, director of a 
Washington-based environmental research group called the <ORGANIZATION>Center for Research 
Economics</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In contrast, he said, the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> spends only about <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> each year on 
biological control research. Concern is so great that a recent <ORGANIZATION>National Academy 
of Sciences</ORGANIZATION> study called for an additional <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> annually to be spent on 
research into alternative methods of agriculture. 
</P>
<P>
"Biological control has been seriously neglected," <PERSON>Cook</PERSON> said. "The <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> 
is an optimistic number. The potential has not nearly been exploited. When you 
one of the great health risks, it's really ludicrous that we're spending as 
little as we are on biological control." 
</P>
<P>
Hoy of <ORGANIZATION>UC Berkeley</ORGANIZATION> has spent years breeding an improved strain of predatory 
mites -- beneficial bugs that clear fields of pest mites. While she has shared 
the better bugs with commercial insectaries, she said there is far too little 
of that give and take. As a result, <PERSON>Hoy</PERSON> said, it's tough to get new bugs from 
the lab to the marketplace. 
</P>
<P>
"First of all, you have to convince someone that it's going to work and that 
it's worth their while to learn how to use it and mass rear and sell it," she 
said. "The transfer of information from researcher to consumer is really 
difficult." 
</P>
<P>
Adding such problems as the ladybug shortage and the dearth of research support 
to the sheer drudgery of insect rearing, makes it easy to see why there aren't 
more producing insectaries. For not only must insect breeders rear beneficial 
insects, they often must rear the pests, too, to give the beneficials something 
to eat. 
</P>
<P>
"It's surprising," <PERSON>Blehm</PERSON> said. "Probably <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> of the time, effort, labor and 
resources goes to rearing host insects. We could get rid of <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> of our space if 
we didn't have to do that." 
</P>
<P>
It's not unlike feeding humans, he said, whereby it takes expanses such as 
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> to sustain an island such as <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. Rincon-Vitova sells 
fly parasites, so it has to breed common houseflies. The company sells 
lacewings, so it has to breed a moth called sitotroga, too. 
</P>
<P>
"If we had a reliable source for insects," <PERSON>Blehm</PERSON> said, "we'd get out of 
production and go entirely into retail and consulting. That's the neat part of 
the business. The growing part is the drudgery. But at this point in time, we 
haven't found anyone as reliable as we are." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
1 THE LADYBUG 
</P>
<P>
Also called ladybird, it was introduced in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in the late 19th Century 
to help save the fruit crop from a scale infestation. Since <DATE>1987</DATE>, the bugs have 
been growing scarce as habitats and breeding grounds disappear. 
</P>
<P>
2 DIET 
</P>
<P>
Feeds chiefly on aphids 
</P>
<P>
and scale insects. Does not 
</P>
<P>
reproduce well on a synthetic diet. 
</P>
<P>
3 THE FAMILY 
</P>
<P>
A small round beetle, usually bright red or yellow with black, red, white or 
yellow spots. Belongs to the order Coleoptera and make up the family 
Coccinellidae. There are about 150 species. 
</P>
<P>
4 LIFE CYCLE 
</P>
<P>
Ladybugs hibernate through the winter by crawling under pine needles and 
leaves. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
CRYPTOLAEMUS 
</P>
<P>
Known as the "Mealybug Destroyer." An Australian import and member of the 
ladybug family, adults are black with orange head and tail. 
</P>
<P>
PREDATORY MITES 
</P>
<P>
Beneficial varieties feed on pest mites, consuming between 5 and 20 mites -- or 
their eggs -- a day. Adults are orange with a pear-shaped body. 
</P>
<P>
GREEN LACEWING 
</P>
<P>
A voracious predator that feeds on virtually any soft-bodied insect. Adults are 
a delicate green and about three-quarters of an inch long. 
</P>
<P>
Source: <ORGANIZATION>Rincon-Vitova Insectaries Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Jake Blehm, vice president at Rincon-Vitova, with trays in which host 
moths are raised. LARRY BESSEL / Los Angeles Times; Drawing, THE LADYBUG; 
Drawing, CRYTOLAEMUS; Drawing, PREDATORY MITES; Drawing, GREEN LACEWING 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
INSECTS; PEST CONTROL; PESTICIDES; ANIMAL BREEDING; ANIMAL CONTROL; RINCON 
VITOVA INSECTARIES INC; TECHNOLOGY; PRODUCT DEVELOPMENT 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900419-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-19-90 1757EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-PestDistress Bjt   04-19 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pest Distress, Bjt,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>Medfly War Killing Beneficial Bugs, Gardeners Battling to Save
Blossoms</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Bartje in 19th graf cq</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ladybugs, honey bees and crickets are
dropping like flies in Medfly-infested regions of <LOCATION>Southern
California</LOCATION> soaked in pesticide, leaving gardeners to battle aphids
thriving with their natural enemies gone.
   ``It's gross. It's sickening,'' said <LOCATION>San Gabriel Valley</LOCATION>
homeowner <PERSON>Peggy Watson</PERSON>, whose orange trees are covered with aphids.
   Frustrated gardeners are making a bee line for pesticide shelves
at nurseries and garden centers, where there has been a run on <MONEY>$4</MONEY>
tubes containing 1,000 ladybugs.
   ``We have people calling us up asking to reserve ladybugs,''
said <PERSON>Henrick Mar</PERSON>, manager of the <ORGANIZATION>San Gabriel Nursery</ORGANIZATION>.
   Pesticides sprayed by helicopters were intended to rid the
region of the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> fruit fly.
   The Medfly, thought to enter the country in illegally imported
fruit, threatens part of the state's <MONEY>$16 billion</MONEY> a year farm
economy because it feeds on and lays eggs in more than 200
varieties of cash crops.
   Gov. <PERSON>George Deukmejian</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> there was no alternative to
spraying. He said it would continue despite vocal protests and
attempts by municipalities to stop what they view as a potential
health menace.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> is pursuing what is a
time-tested method of eradicating the Medfly,'' <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON> told
reporters. ``We cannot give up on this. We have to eradicate it.''
   <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON> said if eradication efforts fail there will be higher
food prices, quarantines on <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> fruit by foreign
governments, loss of jobs and even placement of maggot-infested
fruit on supermarket shelves.
   The blossom-devouring aphid has flourished because the pesticide
malathion has killed off its predators _ ladybugs, lacewings and
tiny wasps. They have been all but eliminated within the nearly 400
square miles of quarantine and spray zones.
   Wild honeybees, which pollinate fruit trees, also have fallen
victim to malathion spraying. ``It's as if they drop dead in
mid-flight,'' said <PERSON>Watson</PERSON>.
   Medfly spraying also has robbed <DATE>spring</DATE> of one of its traditional
sounds: the chirping of crickets.
   Aphids, leaf-scales and whiteflies survive the sprayings because
they live close to petals or beneath leaves, shielding them from
the pesticide droplets.
   ``Malathion spraying causes an imbalance,'' said <PERSON>Lester Ehler</PERSON>,
seven or eight sprays over an urban area is enough to kill off
beneficial insects.
   The aphid, enjoying a backyard garden feast without reprisal,
leaves disfigured rosebuds, wilted orchids and mold-coated leaves.
   ``There are aphids on my violets, aphids covering my herbs. It's
horrifying,'' said <PERSON>Marty Asolas</PERSON>, 42, of <LOCATION>Bellflower</LOCATION>. ``I have just
decided not to plant anything else because I can't bear to see my
flowers attacked.''
   The aphid infestation was expected by state officials.
   ``We knew this was going to happen. But it is infinitely
preferable to what the Medfly can do to the state,'' said <PERSON>Robert
Dowell</PERSON>, senior economic entomologist for the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Food and Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>.
   Aphids have become a hot topic among members of the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Rose
Society</ORGANIZATION>, said the organization's president <PERSON>Bartje Miller</PERSON>. But
members also blame prime aphid breeding weather _ a dry winter
followed by warm <DATE>spring</DATE> showers.
   ``It's a whole combination of factors. I think <ORGANIZATION>Mother Nature</ORGANIZATION> is
just throwing us a curve,'' said <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>, who is also chairwoman of
<LOCATION>Wrigley Gardens</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>.
   The aphids are ``the worse I've seen in the eight years I've
been here,'' said <PERSON>Clair G. Martin III</PERSON>, curator of roses at the
Marino</LOCATION>.
   It could take up to a year or longer after malathion spraying
ends for gardens to become home again to beneficial insects. ``We
don't know what the long term effects are on plant life,'' <PERSON>Ehler</PERSON>
said.
   Entomologists advise gardeners to control aphids and other pests
by hand-washing leaves with soap and water. Using more pesticide
will only prolong the time it takes beneficial bugs to return and
could burn leaves.
   Malathion spraying in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> began in force last
<DATE>summer</DATE> and was recently ordered over a wide area of <LOCATION>Riverside
County</LOCATION> that includes a commercial citrus grove.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890827-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-27-89 1527EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BugEatBug     08-27 0471</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bug Eat Bug,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bugs That Bug Other Bugs Big Biz For California Company</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VENTURA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's a bug-eat-bug world for <PERSON>Jack Blehm</PERSON>
and son.
   Jack and <PERSON>Jake Blehm</PERSON> breed good insects to eat bad insects at
<PERSON>Rincon Vitova</PERSON>, one of a group of 15 ``insectaria'' nationwide. Every
day, <PERSON>Rincon</PERSON> produces more than 80 million voracious critters from
ladybugs to wasps.
   Business at <ORGANIZATION>Rincon Vitova</ORGANIZATION> has tripled in the past five years as
farmers concerned about the effects of pesticides are turning to
natural alternatives.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE> alone, the Blehms say, they supplied <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY>
worth of natural predators to customers across three continents.
   The 15 insectaria have sales totaling <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> annually, the
Blehms estimate.
   Most insects are sold to cotton and vegetable growers, plus back
yard farmers.
   Some colleges and universities are adding classes on integrated
pest management _ ways of holding down troublesome pests while
minimizing the use of pesticides. The <ORGANIZATION>Association of Applied Insect
Ecologists</ORGANIZATION>, a trade group, is producing a video that shows farmers
how to work with beneficial insects.
   ``This is the future,'' added <PERSON>Ken Hagen</PERSON>, a professor of
great need. The farmers are desperate.''
   State agriculture officials estimate less than <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Golden State</ORGANIZATION>'s growers use the method. Controlling pests with
beneficial insects takes longer. And because pesticides kill good
bugs along with bad, farmers are forced to stop chemical spraying
while waiting for the good bugs to do their duty.
   ``The hardest thing for the farmer is to have enough faith,''
<PERSON>Jake Blehm</PERSON> said. ``He's not used to seeing pests in the field; he's
used to a quick knockdown.
   ``With this method, you have to watch for several weeks before
you see a difference. And at the beginning, all the farmer sees is
that his crop is contaminated with bugs.''
   Rincon Vitova sells 15 species including beetles, mites and
parasitic wasps that help control flies around chickens and cattle.
   <PERSON>Jack Blehm</PERSON>, a licensed pest control adviser, provided the
business and production expertise. His partner, <PERSON>E.J. Dietrick</PERSON>, an
entomologist formerly with the biological control division at <ORGANIZATION>UC
Riverside</ORGANIZATION>, provided the field know-how.
   The company employs about 40 workers during peak season from
<DATE>April</DATE> to <DATE>September</DATE>. The insects are grown in a series of former ship
cargo containers.
   Rincon Vitova even sells bugs to movie makers. Last <DATE>summer</DATE>, a
studio filming a horror movie placed a request for four gallons of
maggots. ``We shipped them <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION> to their location site in
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Jake Blehm</PERSON> said.
   More than 600 species of beneficial insects have been introduced
into American agriculture in the past 100 years to curb pest
populations, according to the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, which
must approve the insects for use before insectaria start breeding
and releasing them.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091089-0033 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 105321 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 10, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 3; Column 2; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
551 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IT'S A BUG-EAT-BUG WORLD; 
</P>
<P>
FIRMS SUPPLY FARMERS WITH 'GOOD' INSECTS TO CHEW UP THE 'BAD' ONES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
VENTURA, Calif. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
For <PERSON>Jack Blehm</PERSON> and son, it's a bug-eat-bug world. 
</P>
<P>
Jack and <PERSON>Jake Blehm</PERSON> breed good insects to eat bad insects at <PERSON>Rincon Vitova</PERSON>, one 
of a group of 15 insect firms nationwide. Every day, <PERSON>Rincon</PERSON> produces more than 
80 million voracious critters from ladybugs to wasps. 
</P>
<P>
Farmers concerned about effects of pesticides are turning to organic 
alternatives, and business at <PERSON>Rincon Vitova</PERSON> has tripled in the last five years. 
In <DATE>1988</DATE> alone, the <PERSON>Blehms</PERSON> said, they supplied <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> worth of bugs 
to customers on three continents. 
</P>
<P>
The close-knit group of insect firms have sales that total <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> 
annually, the Blehms estimated. 
</P>
<P>
Most insects are sold to cotton and vegetable growers, as well as to back-yard 
farmers who want to avoid pesticides. 
</P>
<P>
The low-tech bio-pest control is the latest rage in pest eradication. It was 
first used by the Chinese thousands of years ago and was in vogue in the late 
19th Century. 
</P>
<P>
And the idea is catching on again. Some campuses are adding classes on 
integrated pest management. The <ORGANIZATION>Assn. of Applied Insect Ecologists</ORGANIZATION>, a trade 
group, is producing a video that shows farmers how to work with beneficial 
insects. The state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> approves of the low-tech method. 
</P>
<P>
"This is the future," added <PERSON>Ken Hagen</PERSON>, a professor of entomology at <ORGANIZATION>UC 
Berkeley</ORGANIZATION>. "There is a great need. The farmers are desperate." 
</P>
<P>
State agriculture officials estimate that less than <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s growers 
use the method. Controlling pests this way takes longer, and because pesticides 
kill good bugs along with bad, farmers are forced to stop chemical spraying 
while waiting for the good bugs to do their job. 
</P>
<P>
"The hardest thing for the farmer is to have enough faith," <PERSON>Jake Blehm</PERSON> said. 
"He's not used to seeing pests in the field; he's used to a quick knockdown. 
</P>
<P>
"With this method, you have to watch for several weeks before you see a 
difference. And at the beginning, all the farmer sees is that his crop is 
contaminated with bugs." 
</P>
<P>
Rincon Vitova began in <DATE>1948</DATE> and today sells 15 species, including beetles, 
mites and parasitic wasps that help control flies at chicken and livestock 
ranches. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jack Blehm</PERSON>, a licensed pest-control adviser, provided the business and 
production expertise. His partner, <PERSON>E. J. Dietrick</PERSON>, an entomologist formerly 
with the biological control division at <ORGANIZATION>UC Riverside</ORGANIZATION>, provided the field 
know-how. 
</P>
<P>
They took their name from <LOCATION>Rincon Beach</LOCATION>, where they first set up shop, and 
Vitova Insectaries, a Riverside-based firm they bought in <DATE>1972</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Business has grown steadily for <PERSON>Rincon Vitova</PERSON>, which today sells about <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> of 
its bug crop to universities and the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The firm employs about 40 workers during the peak season, from <DATE>April</DATE> to 
<DATE>September</DATE>, and houses its offices in cottages along railroad tracks. The bugs 
hang out in a series of former ship-cargo containers. 
</P>
<P>
Rincon Vitova even sells bugs to movie makers. Last <DATE>summer</DATE>, a studio filming a 
horror movie placed a request for four gallons of maggots. "We shipped them 
<ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION> to their location site in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Jake Blehm</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
More than 600 species of beneficial insects have been introduced into American 
agriculture in the <DATE>last century</DATE> to curb pest populations, according to the 
<ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION>, which must approve the insects for use before the firms breed them. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881017-0243 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-17-88 1211EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--BugWars Adv20   10-17 1004</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Bug Wars, Adv 20,1032</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv20</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Thursday, Oct. 20, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Biological Pest Controls, A Natural Solution</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ODell, no apostrophe, is cq.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KAREN SCHWARTZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOUTH KINGSTOWN, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Mexican mite is being tested
against the <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> potato beetle that also devastates tomatoes
and eggplants. A Chinese wasp may stop a butterfly that eats
broccoli, cabbage and <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> sprouts.
   Humans increasingly have allies in the enemy camp in the war on
insects.
   Biological controls like these and others using insects against
problem plants have been used commercially for more than 100 years,
racking up hundreds of successes. In the <DATE>last 10 years</DATE>, though,
interest has grown.
   Last year, for example, the federal government spent more than
<MONEY>$85 million</MONEY> on nearly 800 biological control projects, four times
the number in existence a decade ago, said <PERSON>Jim Cate</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We are now just getting back into an era where entomologists
are realizing you can't solve the problem with pesticides alone,'
said <PERSON>Robert Metcalf</PERSON>, who has worked more than 50 years on pest
controls. ``For a long time there were advocates of the sole use of
each one. Now I think you'll find almost everybody agrees you need
a little of each.''
   ``There are many different crop pests that have been serious and
are not serious because they have been able to find biological
controls,'' said <PERSON>Patrick Logan</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Rhode Island</ORGANIZATION>
entomologist working on potato beetles.
   The mites, Chrysomelobia lapidomerae Eickwort, live on adult
beetles and suck fluid from them. Up to 2,000 can infest each
beetle. They can shorten the beetles' lifespans up to <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT>,
reducing the number of eggs laid, and they hinder the beetles'
flying ability, reducing migration, <LOCATION>Logan</LOCATION> said.
   University of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> researchers are studying a \-inch
wasp from <LOCATION>northwest China</LOCATION> named Apanteles rubecula, which inserts
its tiny needle into a cabbage butterfly larva and lays eggs. The
wasp larvae eat the pest.
   The wasps have flourished in a patch of collard greens in
<LOCATION>Deerfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, and have attacked an estimated <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the
butterfly larvae in the field, said entomologist <PERSON>Roy Van Dreische</PERSON>.
The needles are too small to hurt humans.
   Most insects became pests after their natural environments were
upset, letting them run rampant. Others were accidentally imported
on vegetables and plants to areas where they had no natural
predators.
   Biological controls seek to restore nature's balance.
   ``It's a totally natural way to regulate (pest) populations,''
doesn't pollute, it doesn't cost anything if it works, it's
self-regulating and self-correcting.''
   Still, biological controls aren't always sucessful, and can be
virtually ineffective as with the gypsy moth.
   The gypsy moth escaped from a <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> researcher in <DATE>1882</DATE>
as he was trying to cross it with a silkworm to make stronger silk.
It feeds on oak trees and occassionally neighborhood rose gardens,
but isn't a problem in its native <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> where more than 100
insects prey upon it, <PERSON>Metcalf</PERSON> said.
   In this country, it ``can make a forest look like winter in
<DATE>June</DATE>,'' sad <PERSON>Tom ODell</PERSON>, a research entomologist at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Forest
Research Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Hamden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn</LOCATION>. This year the moth ravaged areas
of <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   From <DATE>1905</DATE> to <DATE>1911</DATE>, researchers brought 2 million species of the
moth's natural enemies from <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, said
<LOCATION>Logan</LOCATION>. But the effort failed because, ``in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> there are a large
number of natural enemies, each of which controls a small number''
of the moths. Of the 127 species introduced against the moth, only
eight have survived in this country, said ODell.
   ``It's not like some of the other pests where we've been able to
to find a single natural enemy that regulates it,'' <PERSON>Logan</PERSON> said.
   One of 225 successful uses of biological controls was against
the <ORGANIZATION>Cottony Cushiony Scale</ORGANIZATION>, which almost wiped out the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
citrus industry after it was inadvertently brought to the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1880s</DATE>, said <PERSON>Cate</PERSON>, who is also a researcher at <ORGANIZATION>Texas A
&amp; M University</ORGANIZATION>.
   An <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> entomologist brought the <LOCATION>Vendalia</LOCATION>
beetle, a type of ladybug and a natural enemy of the scale, from
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Metcalf</PERSON>. That worked until after World War II, when
DDT killed off the beetle.
   In fact, many pests became a problem when pesticides killed
their natural enemies, <LOCATION>Logan</LOCATION> said. But pesticides can also be
ineffective because the harmful insects develop a tolerance to the
chemicals, and development can't keep up.
   ``It costs <MONEY>several million dollars</MONEY> to formulate a new material _
to develop it, test it. It's very slow, very expensive,'' he said.
   The introduction of biological controls also is slow. Despite
the growth in the number of projects over the past decade, the
level of federal funding has stayed relatively stable when adjusted
for inflation, <PERSON>Cates</PERSON> said.
   Also, scientists face delays while they work to show the
government that their controls are harmless to all but the pest.
   The Mexican mite, being tested at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Rhode
Island</ORGANIZATION>, was quarantined for six months before scientists could
prove it was a species known in this country. Then the government
required tests to show it would not harm beneficial insects like
ladybugs or honeybees.
   It took seven years from the time the mite was found until it
was approved.
   Reassuringly, ``There just haven't been any notable examples of
anything going wrong with this process,'' said <PERSON>Metcalf</PERSON>.
   Biological controls also may be victims of their own success.
When they work ``people forget they had a problem,'' said Cate.
``You solve the pest problem and you walk away from it.''
   Companies that invest huge sums in research, ``want a return on
their investment,'' said <LOCATION>Logan</LOCATION>. ``Nobody is going to make any money
off importing exotic insects,'' <PERSON>Cate</PERSON> said.
   As a result, smaller, isolated pests, like the potato beetle,
are often overlooked by the large chemical companies.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Oct. 20</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA071990-0145 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 249471 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 19, 1990, Thursday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Ventura County Life; Part J; Page 18; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
767 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
EARTHWATCH; 
</P>
<P>
GOOD BUGS; 
</P>
<P>
A SPRINKLING OF LADYBUGS AND MANTISES CAN KEEP THE REALLY NASTY INSECTS AWAY 
FROM YOUR COOKOUTS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVID LUSTIG 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Wander into your back yard during the <DATE>summer</DATE> months and you can almost hear the 
jubilation. 
</P>
<P>
"Barbecue!" roar the ants. "Fruits and vegetables!' add the aphids and white 
ash flies. "People!" say the mosquitoes and wasps, invariably followed by the 
not-so-happy retort from your family, "Let's go inside." 
</P>
<P>
Yesterday, the solution was simple: Purchase every type of bug death on the 
market, don the gas mask and attack, spraying everything that moves back there. 
And, oh yes, "Dear, I've just sprayed, so keep the kids away until about 
<DATE>December</DATE>, OK?" 
</P>
<P>
No, it's not OK. Summer is a great time for family get-togethers, and there are 
safe, non-destructo ways to keep bugs at arms length without having to take out 
the radiation detector every time your family enters the back-yard nuclear hot 
zone. 
</P>
<P>
"There are many natural things you can use to get rid of the unwanted bugs," 
says <PERSON>Lucy Burkard</PERSON>, the manager of <ORGANIZATION>Green Meadow Nursery</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> and a 
fourth-generation greens person. "There are even a few things the kids can 
watch and learn about nature." 
</P>
<P>
Tops on her list? Ladybugs and praying mantises. 
</P>
<P>
Available in many nurseries, especially in early <DATE>spring</DATE> and early <DATE>summer</DATE> (it 
gets too hot to ship them past early <DATE>summer</DATE>, although <ORGANIZATION>Burkard</ORGANIZATION> says they can be 
special-ordered during other months), bugs like this are considered "beneficial 
insects," and attack other bugs. Sort of a good bug with the white hat and bad 
bug with the black hat analogy. 
</P>
<P>
Burkard recommends releasing ladybugs ln the <TIME>evening</TIME>, after watering, "because 
they don't fly at night and will look for prey in the immediate area." OK, but 
even at about <MONEY>five dollars</MONEY> for several hundred ladybugs, what's to stop them 
from leaving my yard for others in the neighborhood? "As long as you have 
enough bad bugs in the area," she says, "the ladybugs will be content to stay 
where they are." 
</P>
<P>
As will the praying mantises. 
</P>
<P>
They usually come two egg cases to a container (again, for about five dollars). 
Within a few days you'll have about 400 babies breaking out and looking for 
food. 
</P>
<P>
"What's fun is to put a thread through the egg case and hang it from a nearby 
tree in the infested area," <PERSON>Burkard</PERSON> says. "Then the kids can come out every day 
and watch the eggs until they hatch.' 
</P>
<P>
OK, sounds great, but what do I do with a back yard full of praying mantises 
and ladybugs (which the mantises won't eat, by the way)? Nothing. When the bad 
bugs are gone, the beneficial bugs will move elsewhere. 
</P>
<P>
Another product <PERSON>Burkard</PERSON> recommends is Safer Soap, manufactured by <ORGANIZATION>Safer Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 
(189 <LOCATION>Wells Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Newton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION> 02159. 617/964-2990). 
</P>
<P>
According to <ORGANIZATION>Mark Dockser of Safer</ORGANIZATION>, the company markets more than 50 products 
refined to have a maximum effect on bad bugs while not harming the beneficial 
ones such as honey bees and ladybugs. 
</P>
<P>
The various soaps, he says, are different from their petrochemical counterparts 
in that they are considerably less toxic and break down into harmless 
substances in about 48 hours, which means no potential to contaminate ground 
water. 
</P>
<P>
And the products are selective in the insects they kill. For example, some 
soaps go after moths, algae and weeds, yet leave delicate plants such as 
African violets undisturbed. 
</P>
<P>
There are, however, certain ground rules. 
</P>
<P>
"You have to hit the bug to make the product work," <PERSON>Dockser</PERSON> says, "but if you 
spray both sides of the leaves you have a good chance of nailing everything 
that's around." Unless the infestation is heavy, he says the average back yard 
can go up to two weeks between sprays. 
</P>
<P>
"And," <PERSON>Burkard</PERSON> adds, "some studies indicate that some Safer soaps have affected 
the white ash fly larvae." 
</P>
<P>
Get rid of the white ash fly? Those pesky little things that look like 
thousands of pieces of large dandruff falling from the sky? The answer, she 
says, is yes. 
</P>
<P>
Burkard says the soap (there also are other brands but she says Safer is the 
biggest) comes in ready-to-use packages or in concentrated form to be diluted 
with a hose sprayer. One package should easily do a couple hundred square feet 
of shrubs with no problem and you should start noticing a difference in a 
couple of days. 
</P>
<P>
One caveat, however. Wear protective clothing, perhaps even consider a face 
mask. Nothing in the soap would harm you, but why ingest anything into your 
body you don't have to? 
</P>
<P>
* IN <LOCATION>VENTURA</LOCATION> COUNTY: Ladybugs and praying mantises are available at most large 
nurseries. Safer Soap can be purchased at most lawn and garden centers, 
nurseries and home shopping centers such as the Home Depot and Builder's 
Emporium. 
</P>
<P>
 Regular <ORGANIZATION>Earthwatch</ORGANIZATION> columnist <PERSON>Richard Kahlenberg</PERSON> is on vacation. 
</P><P></P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Drawing, DAN HUBIG / For The Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890831-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-31-89 1218EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Briefs Adv04   08-31 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Briefs, Adv 04,0630</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv04</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Sept. 4, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Georgia State Psychologist Finds People Eat More in a Crowd</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A roomful of diners is probably a roomful of
people eating more than they would if they were alone, according to
research indicating that people on diets might do well to decline
invitations to eat out.
   ``Eating in a social setting increases the duration of the meal.
You're eating at the same speed but you're eating longer,'' said
<PERSON>John de Castro</PERSON>, who reported on his work in <DATE>August</DATE>'s <ORGANIZATION>American
Journal of Clinical Nutrition</ORGANIZATION>.
   De <PERSON>Castro</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Georgia State University</ORGANIZATION> psychologist, hired 63
adults in the <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> area to keep seven-day diaries of their how
much they ate, what they ate, where they ate it and how they felt
physically.
   People tend to eat <PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT> more food when eating with others
than when eating alone, and the bigger the group the bigger the
individual's appetite. In addition, the food eaten in social
settings was often higher in fat and that eaten when alone was more
healthful, he said.
   Contrary to de <PERSON>Castro</PERSON>'s expectations, he did not find many
instances of people stuffing themselves out of the watchful gaze of
others. ``I had expected to see people become closet eaters. That
wasn't the case,'' he said.
   The three-year study of nutritional habits is continuing at
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia State</ORGANIZATION>, with more people to be hired to keep diaries. De
<PERSON>Castro</PERSON> said the research could eventually yield a complete picture
of what factors contribute to overeating.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Bugs That Bug Other Bugs Big Biz For California Company</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VENTURA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A roomful of diners is probably a roomful of
people eating more than they would if they were alone, according to
research indicating that people on diets might do well to decline
invitations to eat out.
   ``Eating in a social setting increases the duration of the meal.
You're eating at the same speed but you're eating longer,'' said
<PERSON>John de Castro</PERSON>, who reported on his work in <DATE>August</DATE>'s <ORGANIZATION>American
Journal of Clinical Nutrition</ORGANIZATION>.
   De <PERSON>Castro</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Georgia State University</ORGANIZATION> psychologist, hired 63
adults in the <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> area to keep seven-day diaries of their how
much they ate, what they ate, where they ate it and how they felt
physically.
   People tend to eat <PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT> more food when eating with others
than when eating alone, and the bigger the group the bigger the
individual's appetite. In addition, the food eaten in social
settings was often higher in fat and that eaten when alone was more
healthful, he said.
   Contrary to de <PERSON>Castro</PERSON>'s expectations, he did not find many
instances of people stuffing themselves out of the watchful gaze of
others. ``I had expected to see people become closet eaters. That
wasn't the case,'' he said.
   The three-year study of nutritional habits is continuing at
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia State</ORGANIZATION>, with more people to be hired to keep diaries. De
<PERSON>Castro</PERSON> said the research could eventually yield a complete picture
of what factors contribute to overeating.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sept. 4</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06165019 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06165019 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  INSECT; POISON  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  WHEN you visit your doctor, you often take along a specimen in a small jar
that you pass along to the nurse as rapidly as possible.;    The past few
weeks people have been bringing me small jars with specimens. There are two
differences. I don't have a nurse (not a bad idea, though) and most of the
specimens that come to my office are alive and running around the jar;    One
such specimen that arrived this week was one of the more unusual found in the
area. Picture a praying mantis' body with a giraffe's neck and head. The fact
that it slightly resembles a mantis is fortunate because it saves it from
being blasted with pesticides by people who shoot first and ask questions
later.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Garden  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHAT'S THIS WITH A PRAYING MANTIS' BODY AND
A GIRAFFE'S NECK AND HEAD?
BEFORE YOU SPRAY, FIND OUT IF IT'S REALLY
A PEST  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Troubleshooting
Dan Pratt is a certified nurseryman in Sacramento.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The person who brought in this specimen was asking questions first, and the
answer is that it is a very beneficial insect called a snakefly.;    They are
found over much of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> coast, hiding under loose bark on trees or in
litter at the base of a tree.;    The reason for hanging around trees? Both
adult and larvae stages of snakeflies are predators of wood-boring insects
that attack trees.;    Since we have been having a serious problem with borers
attacking so many of our tree varieties, I hope we will see a lot more
snakeflies in the near future.;    There are several other beneficial insects
you should watch for on trees and plants right now. Let's start with the
leatherwing beetles. As the name indicates, the wings are the color of
leather, very old leather. The rest of the body and the head can range from
light orange to almost red. Size varies from a third to half an inch depending
on how well you feed them.;    What do you feed a leatherwing beetle? Aphids,
aphids and more aphids. On cherry, plum and apple trees, where there has been
the all-time greatest crop of aphids. After a visit from the leatherwings
there are just piles of white aphid bones.;    Most people would quickly
recognize the distinct red and black colors of the adult ladybug. It is one of
the most familiar insects, even to those who are not gardeners. There are also
ladybugs that are plain red (no spots) or navy gray and just as effective in
controlling pests.;    Even more effective pest control is performed by the
larval stage of any of the ladybugs. The soft body is shaped like a tiny
alligator, is dull gray-black in color and is covered with short spines and
yellow or orange spots in the middle of the back. Unfortunately, at least a
dozen times a week, I have people bringing in ladybug larvae in those little
bottles, wanting to know what to spray to get rid of these "pests" they think
are attacking their plants.;    The most important part of logical pest
control is knowing what you need to control. When you find an insect that you
don't recognize, put it in one of those little bottles and bring it to the
nursery or to a <ORGANIZATION>University of California Cooperative Extension</ORGANIZATION> office for
positive identification. If it's a bad guy, we will tell you how to control
it. If it's a good guy, we will tell you how to encourage it. If enough of you
bring in specimens, I just may need to get a nurse.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DAN PRATT, Special to the Mercury News  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910613  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  572  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday June 13, 1991
00165019,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA063090-0143 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 247811 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 30, 1990, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Home Design; Part N; Page 1; Column 3 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1358 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GARDENING; 
</P>
<P>
PEST CONTROL WITHOUT PESTICIDES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JULIE BAWDEN DAVIS, Julie Bawden Davis is a regular contributor to Home 
Design. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Sharon Whatley</PERSON> likes to know what her family is eating. 
</P>
<P>
And it's not always easy to find out. 
</P>
<P>
"There is no way to tell what is sprayed on vegetables and fruit before they 
get to the supermarket, and I wanted to have control over that," said the 
<LOCATION>Tustin</LOCATION> resident. 
</P>
<P>
She started a garden in her back yard six years ago to ensure that her family 
ate only naturally grown, chemical-free produce. 
</P>
<P>
Then the bugs invaded her pure environment. 
</P>
<P>
"When I began to get garden pests and went to the nursery for advice, they 
suggested I use harsh chemical methods, which defeated the whole purpose of 
having a garden," she said. 
</P>
<P>
Whatley began searching for alternatives to chemical pest control. She 
conducted research on her own and then hooked up with the <ORGANIZATION>Orange County Organic 
Gardening Club</ORGANIZATION>. She now controls pests organically. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Orange County Organic Gardening Club</ORGANIZATION> offers members and guests educational 
programs, speakers and demonstrations. The group meets every second <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> of 
the month at <ORGANIZATION>Mercury Federal Savings</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tustin</LOCATION>. Seventy families are members of 
the 25-year-old club. 
</P>
<P>
Club members say you can trash the chemicals and start fresh. By using 
alternative pest-control methods, back-yard gardeners avoid the harmful effects 
of chemicals in the soil and on the produce. 
</P>
<P>
"Your first line of defense against pests is to have healthy plants," said <PERSON>Bud 
Anderson</PERSON>, vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>Organic Gardening Club</ORGANIZATION>. "When plants become 
stressed because of lack of water or nutrition or start aging, pests will 
attack them." 
</P>
<P>
Insects are attracted to yellow -- the color of sickly plants. "Yellow means 
food to them," said <PERSON>Sharron Clark</PERSON>, a professor of biology at <ORGANIZATION>Golden West 
College</ORGANIZATION> who will teach a class on alternative methods of garden maintenance 
this <DATE>fall</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Problems can be prevented by selecting strong, healthy green plants. After 
planting, be sure to keep the area free of debris and remove any yellowing 
leaves or ailing plants. 
</P>
<P>
Another important element to consider during plant selection is disease 
resistance. You can prevent infestations by choosing plants that can ward off 
certain devastating diseases. 
</P>
<P>
When selecting tomato plants, for instance, look for the VFN label, which 
indicates that the plant is resistant to three main types of deadly soil-borne 
diseases. Seed packages also indicate that plants are resistant. 
</P>
<P>
Pests thrive, too, on young, tender plants. Start seeds in containers and 
transplant them when they're the size of plants found in the nursery. 
</P>
<P>
"To protect transplants, put a newspaper collar around the stems," said <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>. 
"This will keep cutworms and other pests away. As the plants grow, the 
newspaper will disintegrate." 
</P>
<P>
Once pesky insects are spotted, there are several organic chemical control 
methods that can be used. Insecticidal soaps are a popular, safe way to 
suffocate aphids, white flies and mealybugs, while not harming friendly 
predators such as lacewings, ladybugs and praying mantises. These soap 
solutions can be made at home or purchased. 
</P>
<P>
To mix your own, put a few drops of dish detergent into water and spray it on 
your plants. If you want a stronger solution, mix fresh onion juice, garlic and 
hot pepper into the soapy water. After some experimentation, every gardener 
comes up with his or her own favorite mixture. 
</P>
<P>
Effective, readily biodegradable insecticidal soaps -- like Safer -- can be 
found in most gardening centers. These are designed to kill aphids, mealybugs, 
whiteflies, mites, tent caterpillars, thrips and other destructive pests. Spray 
in the early morning or late afternoon to avoid leaf burn. 
</P>
<P>
Another chemical that acts as a stomach poison for beetles, thrips, weevils and 
borers is Rotenone, which is an extract from the roots of tropical legumes. It 
is usually found in a combination spray with Pyrethrum. This comes from the 
flower heads of the <ORGANIZATION>Pyrethrum Chrysanthemum</ORGANIZATION>, a form of the daisy found in 
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. Pyrethrum kills leaf hoppers, thrips, whiteflies and aphids. 
</P>
<P>
When using organic chemical sprays, keep in mind that their effects don't last 
long, which is why they don't become part of your food. If pests persist, 
sprays must be reapplied. 
</P>
<P>
Another form of controlling pests is through biological means. "So that we are 
not overrun by any one species in nature, organisms feed on one another," said 
<PERSON>Clark</PERSON>. "You can use such biological controls in your own garden." 
</P>
<P>
A good cure for soil-borne pests such as pill bugs, sow bugs, snails and slugs 
is <LOCATION>Diatamascious Earth</LOCATION>. "This is made up of the shells of a small sea creature 
which is mined from the ocean floor," said <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON>. "When it is mixed into the 
soil, the pests eat them and the sharp edges tear up their insides." 
</P>
<P>
Another control is the bacteria <LOCATION>Bacillus Thuringiensis</LOCATION>, which can kill all 
kinds of caterpillars, fly larvae and worms. "When you see holes in leaves and 
vegetables such as tomatoes and actual caterpillars and worms on your plants, 
spray them with this solution and the pests will soon die from eating the 
leaves and ingesting the bacteria, which poisons their guts," said <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>. This 
product is sold under the brand names Attack and Dipel and is readily 
available. 
</P>
<P>
You can also control pests by introducing certain "good" insects into your 
garden, such as ladybugs, praying mantises, lacewings, spiders and wasps. Many 
of these can be bought at the nursery and set free in your garden. 
</P>
<P>
Barrier methods are also effective in controlling some pests. Whatley has found 
that a shallow pan or dish filled with stale beer and soap stops snails as they 
attempt to climb into her garden. Salt also harms the troublemakers. Stop 
snails by putting salt on cardboard strips and placing them around the 
outskirts of your garden. Avoid getting salt into the soil. 
</P>
<P>
Netting is another effective barrier method for plants such as broccoli and 
cauliflower. This prevents the white cabbage butterfly and other similar 
insects from laying eggs on the plants. 
</P>
<P>
Certain companion plants deter pests. 
</P>
<P>
"Because of their pungent odor, marigolds ward off many pests," said <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON>, 
who has them planted throughout his garden. Nasturtiums are attractive flowers 
that repel aphids and squash bugs. Plant them near cabbage, lettuce, squash and 
radishes. Some herbs are also useful. 
</P>
<P>
"We enjoy the odor and taste of sweet basil, but tomato and cabbage worms don't 
like it," said <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON>. Mint, too, deters many pests that affect cabbage and 
tomatoes. 
</P>
<P>
Don't bunch similar crops in the same area. "Nature doesn't have all of the 
same tree in one spot or a meadow filled with pure grass," said <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>. "When we 
plant all one crop in one area, we upset the balance of nature, and this 
encourages pests, because each type tends to feed on similar crops. 
</P>
<P>
"For instance, if you have rows of lettuce, the insects who feed on that will 
move readily from plant to plant and destroy your crop. However, if you 
interplant dissimilar crops between rows and within rows, when an insect is 
feeding on lettuce and then moves over to radishes, it is likely to find this 
vegetable distasteful." 
</P>
<P>
Many organic gardeners use truly simple solutions: water and picking bugs off 
leaves. Aphids can often be killed with a strong jet of water, while many 
caterpillars, worms and snails can be picked from plants. To catch sow bugs and 
pill bugs, place a piece of wood in the garden and they will crawl under it. 
"Don't kill the blue sow bugs, though," said <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>. "They have a disease that 
will kill the other ones." 
</P>
<P>
Of course, no garden is going to be completely free of pests. "You're not 
insect-proof, you're insect- and pest-deterrent," explained <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON>. "You must 
remember that all of the 'pests' are there for a reason -- they actually have a 
place in the earth's continuum. We don't want to destroy everything, which is 
why alternative methods work so well. They create a natural balance in your 
garden." 
</P>
<P>
Since she started using alternative methods, <PERSON>Whatley</PERSON>'s pest problems have 
decreased. "Five years ago, when I used toxic chemical controls, I constantly 
battled pests," she said. "Today I don't have very many problems. My garden is 
really healthy, and I'm able to eat produce that is chemical-free." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Sharon Whatley grows chemical-free produce for her family in 
their back yard. ; Photo, Sharon Whatley sprays her romaine lettuce with a 
mixture of garlic, onion and water that deters bugs. ALEXANDER GALLARDO / Los 
Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PEST CONTROL; INSECTS; GARDENING; GARDENS; PESTICIDES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910829-0097
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910829-0097.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Enterprise:
   Bio-Control Sector Learns Lessons on Client Education
   ---
   Growers of Pest-Fighting Insects Are
   Bugged by Confusion on Many Fronts
   ----
   By Mark Robichaux
</HL>
<DATE>
08/29/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B2
</SO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
</MS>
<IN>
CHEMICALS, PLASTICS (CHM)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
ENVIRONMENT (ENV)
</IN>
<NS>
COMMODITIES MARKET (CMD)
ENVIRONMENTAL NEWS (ENV)
</NS>
<GV>
AGRICULTURE DEPARTMENT (AGD)
</GV>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
FLORIDA (FL)
NORTH CAROLINA (NC)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Jake Blehm's biggest business problem isn't selling his
product -- it's explaining to baffled customers what exactly
it is they've just bought.
   Mr. Blehm, owner of Buena Bio Systems Inc. in Santa Paula,
Calif., recently mailed nearly 500,000 trichograma wasps to a
client to fight moth larvae, which attack tomatoes and corn.
The wasps, mailed in the form of larvae inside moth eggs,
emerge two or three days later. Buena Bio Systems glues these
grainy eggs to small sheets of heavy paper.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   When the shipment arrived, the bewildered customer called
<PERSON>Mr. Blehm</PERSON>. "He said, `Hey, where are the wasps you were
supposed to send me. All I got are three sheets of
sandpaper,'" says <PERSON>Mr. Blehm</PERSON>. "I told him to find the
instructions and pull out a magnifying glass. He wrote us a
letter later apologizing."
   <PERSON>Mr. Blehm</PERSON>'s farm produces beneficial insects that devour
crop-destroying bugs. These tiny beasts of prey -- ranging
from ladybugs to praying mantises -- are gaining favor with
farmers as an alternative to costly and environmentally
hazardous pesticides. A smaller sect of farmers raise bugs
that eat weeds.
   Though fledgling, the beneficial-insect industry is
growing fast. It is a small slice of the biological-control
world, but it has grown from nothing five years ago to about
60 firms with combined sales of close to <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> today.
In that time, <PERSON>Mr. Blehm</PERSON> and others in the field have
discovered what people in other businesses have long known:
New products confuse people.
   These entrepreneurs are learning that any company
introducing a product -- be it a six-legged arthropod or a
laptop computer that transmits data over radio waves -- has
to educate the public on what the product is and how it
works.
   Customers aren't the only ones having trouble figuring out
the firms. Some states have lumped beneficial-insect
companies -- which sell only bugs -- into the same regulatory
category as pesticide dealers.
   Another problem: Some state agencies don't distinguish
between beneficial insects that these firms sell, and
micro-organisms and pathogens, which require <ORGANIZATION>Environmental
Protection Agency</ORGANIZATION> registration. Led in part by the newly
formed <ORGANIZATION>Association of Natural Bio-control Producers</ORGANIZATION>, firms
are rushing to develop model regulations.
   "All we want," says <PERSON>Synthia Penn</PERSON>, president of the group
and her company, <ORGANIZATION>Beneficial Insectary</ORGANIZATION>, "are regulations that
are appropriate to our industry -- specifically, naturally
occurring arthropods. We pose no threat to the public or to
the environment."
   The firms are scrambling to ease the new-product
confusion. They are trying to establish guidelines to assure
the accuracy of advertising claims and to set uniform
standards for raising, shipping and releasing the insects.
   "Biological control has been sort of a novelty in many
areas, but now people are beginning to take it seriously, and
the credibility is being scrutinized," says <PERSON>Glenn Scriven</PERSON>,
owner of <ORGANIZATION>Biotactics Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a company based in <LOCATION>Grand Terrace</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, that deals mainly in predatory mites.
   Adds <PERSON>Marjorie Hoy</PERSON>, an entomology professor at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, "If the industry is
going to grow, it must develop standards and educate
consumers."
   For all its new-product problems, biological control isn't
brand new. In the <DATE>1880s</DATE>, for example, a parasite and a small
lady beetle were imported from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to attack the
cottony cushion scale, an insect that was devastating
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s citrus industry.
   But practitioners are now much more sophisticated. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
scientists import weedeating and bug-eating insects from
around the world to test. Beneficial insects that aren't
collected in the field are raised in roughly a dozen <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
insectaries -- large, environmentally controlled buildings,
similar to greenhouses, lined with racks and trays filled
with insects.
   Some bugs take longer -- sometimes years longer -- than
quick-acting herbicides or pesticides to get results. Some
species are self-perpetuating, and thus are ultimately much
cheaper than chemicals, advocates say. Still others are
native and must be reapplied seasonally.
   <PERSON>Hunter Nadler</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> raisin farmer who runs an
80-acre vineyard, buys roughly <MONEY>$6,000</MONEY> of predatory mites,
trichogramma wasps, green lacewings, beetles and ladybird
beetles a year. "It's a lot safer than chemicals, and in some
fields, we've seen increases in production," says a satisfied
<PERSON>Mr. Nadler</PERSON>.
   But not all customers come away as satisfied as <PERSON>Mr.
Nadler</PERSON>. New-product confusion helps some unscrupulous firms
make bogus claims about their insects. Others withhold
information to make a sale -- neglecting to point out, for
example, that parasitic insects attack their pesthosts only
in particular life-cycle phases, such as the egg or larval
stage.
   "People will call a company and say I've got a caterpillar
problem on my lettuce, and some companies ship them insects
no matter what stage the host is in," says <PERSON>Diane Belvanis</PERSON>, a
research entomologist and former employee at a biological
control firm.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Association of Natural Biocontrol Producers</ORGANIZATION> discussed
model industry regulations in a meeting this month with state
officials of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, which has been seeking to revamp its
pesticide rules. States such as <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>
also are reviewing ways to regulate the cottage industry.
Meanwhile, a federal effort to coordinate biological control
efforts is under way in the <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION>'s newly
formed <ORGANIZATION>National Biological Control Institute</ORGANIZATION>.
   But even as insect companies struggle with the big issues,
they have to grapple with more minute matters. <PERSON>Reed Finfrock</PERSON>,
owner of <ORGANIZATION>Sespe Creek Insectary</ORGANIZATION>, a three-year-old firm in
<LOCATION>Fillmore</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, frets over the difficulties of counting the
minuscule creatures he sells. "How," he asks, "do you get
everyone to agree on how to measure 10,000 bugs?"
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890725-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-25-89 1921EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite     07-25 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cuomo Makes Ladybug State Insect</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BELLAFIORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ladybug, ladybug, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is your home.
   Your fame is ensured, the job has been done.
   Gov'nor <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON> says you're his bug _ you alone.
   Ladybug, ladybug, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is your home.
   
   Good Gov'nor <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON> has ruled on a bill.
   It makes you state insect, oh what a thrill!
   The bluebird, the beaver, the rose and the trout,
   They've all gone 'ere you for <ORGANIZATION>New Yorkers</ORGANIZATION> to tout.
   
   Ladybug, ladybug, good company you suit
   With apples for muffins and as fruit to boot.
   Garnet as gem, sugar maples as trees
   And fossil Eurypterus, a scorpion of seas.
   
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is your land, where milk is the choice
   Empire for beetles, even you have a voice.
   You've earned your new title, your honorable nom;
   Excelsior! little ladybug, good rest in your home.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Ladybug, ladybug, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is your home.
   Your fame is ensured, the job has been done.
   Gov'nor <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON> says you're his bug _ you alone.
   Ladybug, ladybug, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is your home.
   
   Good Gov'nor <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON> has ruled on a bill.
   It makes you state insect, oh what a thrill!
   The bluebird, the beaver, the rose and the trout,
   They've all gone 'ere you for <ORGANIZATION>New Yorkers</ORGANIZATION> to tout.
   
   Ladybug, ladybug, good company you suit
   With apples for muffins and as fruit to boot.
   Garnet as gem, sugar maples as trees
   And fossil Eurypterus, a scorpion of seas.
   
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is your land, where milk is the choice
   Empire for beetles, even you have a voice.
   You've earned your new title, your honorable nom;
   Excelsior! little ladybug, good rest in your home.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060990-0142 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 231751 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 9, 1990, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Orange County Life; Part N; Page 5; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
554 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GARDENERS: DON'T GIVE BUGS A BREAK 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KENNETH R. BAZINET, Kenneth R. Bazinet writes for United Press 
International. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It took weeks to till all the soil and clear the dead leaves and other debris 
from the patch of land that -- with any luck -- will deliver tasty vegetables 
or a picturesque flower show. 
</P>
<P>
But don't get lazy now. There are a few unwelcome visitors in the garden that 
have to be taken care of. 
</P>
<P>
That green thing hanging off the tomato plant is not a leaf. And those brown, 
squishy things look like they're building a patio under the lettuce. Those 
pesky garden pests that were not there when the planting began are ruining all 
your work. 
</P>
<P>
"The pests just make your plants and ornamentals a mess," says <PERSON>Micheal D. 
Smith</PERSON>, managing editor of the gardening division of <ORGANIZATION>Ortho Books</ORGANIZATION>. "But there are 
ways to counter them." 
</P>
<P>
Thousands of insect and insect-family pests invade gardens at various times 
each year. Most of the tiny terrors arrive by their sensory perception -- they 
tell plants by color, texture and fragrance -- then decide if the particular 
vegetation is something they want in their diet. 
</P>
<P>
A few pests, such as the gypsy moth and various mites, reach a garden by 
accident, perhaps hitching a ride under a car or truck or on a pant leg from 
someone's favorite overalls. 
</P>
<P>
Once in the garden, the pests can maul plants in a variety of ways -- some 
munch away at stems, leafs and petals, others dig around plants, and some even 
suck and sponge away nutrients needed to keep the vegetation healthy. 
</P>
<P>
Different insects, whether they invaded your garden intentionally or by 
accident, require different strategies to get rid of them, depending on the way 
they feed. 
</P>
<P>
Predators are friendly insects that devour the garden-gorging pests. The 
beneficial insects, like the praying mantis, snail-eating ground beetle and 
ladybug larvae, can be imported into the garden, where they police the area for 
the leaf- and flower-munching pests. 
</P>
<P>
Smith warns, however, that if chemicals are going to be used in a garden in 
addition to the predators, extra care should be taken in reading and 
understanding the potency of the pesticides. 
</P>
<P>
"Of course, understanding the chemical pesticides is important no matter what, 
but in particular, you don't want to kill off the pests' natural predators," he 
says. "You have to take care in understanding chemical pesticides." 
</P>
<P>
Other ways to combat pests include using sticky traps that catch pests as they 
make their way into the garden or up a fruit tree. 
</P>
<P>
Another alternative is building barriers to keep crawling bugs out, but this is 
a time-consuming project that can involve digging trenches or wrapping aluminum 
stripping around the border of the garden. 
</P>
<P>
There has also been research into creating pathogenic diseases that fight off 
and eliminate pests while not harming people, pets or wildlife. The disease 
germs can be introduced into the garden in ways similar to spreading chemical 
pesticides. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> says the best way to combat a specific pest is to first identify the 
insect by appearance -- "a photo will do" -- then research what the particular 
pest is known to eat. "From there, you can learn the best way to get rid of the 
pests," he says. 
</P>
<P>
But bear in mind that winning a battle against a pest doesn't necessarily mean 
that the war is over. 
</P>
<P>
"Pests return," <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> says. "You have to make sure the plants are healthy. You 
don't want leaves with holes in them or browning." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PEST CONTROL; INFESTATIONS; INSECTS; GARDENS; GARDENING 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042290-0030 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 207702 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 22, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Opinion; Part M; Page 6; Column 1; Editorial Writers Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
426 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE SPRING OF OUR DISCONTENT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The scene is increasingly common in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>. Flowers stand not full 
and robust but drooped over and shriveled. The roses for display on the dining 
table are so distorted from their natural shape that they look more like 
doilies for the place settings. Outside dead bees line the patio; crickets 
aren't chirping. If it is not quite a silent spring around here right now, it 
is certainly a disquieted one. 
</P>
<P>
The problem now is aphids, those parasitic insects that huddle together on new 
shoots, buds and leaves. They are invading local gardens in distressingly high 
numbers. The natural predators that usually keep aphids under control -- 
ladybugs, lacewings and tiny wasps -- have been destroyed in some 400 square 
miles of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>. So have wild honeybees, which pollinate fruit 
trees. All this, plus the lack of chirping crickets, have been attributed to 
aerial malathion spraying that has descended upon many local areas during the 
last nine months. 
</P>
<P>
The state has sprayed the pesticide in a campaign to rid the region of the 
crop-destroying Mediterranean fruit fly. That pest continues to pop up in 
unexpected places, giving farmers fits, local residents sleepless nights and 
state officials heartburn. But one of the certain unfortunate side effects of 
malathion spraying is that it is extraordinarily efficient in eliminating some 
"good" bugs. 
</P>
<P>
Without them, the natural controls crucial to a linked ecosystem begin to break 
down. And so, we are all robbed of one of the great joys of <DATE>spring</DATE> -- a lovely 
and healthy garden. The negative effects were expected, say entomologists, and 
the bad news in the back yard is nothing compared to the damage the Medfly 
could cause to the food supply. 
</P>
<P>
Maybe. We can only hope that <PERSON>Rachel Carson</PERSON>'s words from <DATE>1962</DATE> don't return to 
ring in our ears: "It is ironic to think that man might determine his own 
future by something so seemingly trivial as the choice of an insect spray. 
</P>
<P>
"All this has been risked -- for what? Future historians may well be amazed by 
our distorted sense of proportion. How could intelligent beings seek to control 
a few unwanted species by a method that contaminated the entire environment and 
brought the threat of disease and death even to their own kind? Yet this is 
precisely what we have done. All this is not to say there is no insect problem 
and no need of control. I am saying, rather, that control must be geared to 
realities, not to mythical situations, and that the methods employed must be 
such that they do not destroy us along with the insects." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Editorial 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06130155 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06130155 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  GARDEN; LIFESTYLE; RELATION; ENVIRONMENT; CONSERVATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  LIVING in harmony with nature seems to be developing as the dominant theme of
gardening. The disposable era has made a 180-degree turn. The signs are
everywhere.;    Nurseries advertise beneficial insects for sale. Praying
mantis or ladybugs retail at $4.99 a container (about 1,500 baby ladybugs or
800 baby praying mantis). Some nurseries also pay for the return of empty
plastic plant containers, offering five cents for the one-gallon size to 50
cents for the 15-gallon.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Garden  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MORE GARDENERS WORK IN HARMONY WITH NATURE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Trends  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Xeriscaping, the use of such plant material, has become a buzzword in areas
facing water shortages or rationing.;    The latest national magazine of the
<ORGANIZATION>Perennial Plant Association</ORGANIZATION>, a trade group, features an article by
horticulturist <PERSON>Luren Springer</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, who says:;    "The key to growing
perennials successfully is to choose plants that will thrive in the climate
where they are planted. Native plants are making inroads into our perennial
palette. Many of these tolerate heat, humidity, drought and even hail with the
greatest of ease.;    "It's time hybridizers and plants people devoted more
time to selecting and developing better strains of these, instead of the
newest almost-white daylily, variegated hosta or huge bearded iris.";    <ORGANIZATION>Toro
Manufacturing Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> has been promoting a "Don't Bag It, Compost
It" program. The company says <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the solid waste generated in this
country comes from grass clippings and tree leaves and claims compost from a
typical yard can provide up to <MONEY>$100</MONEY> of free humus, fertilizers and soil
conditioners a year.;    Toro, of course, like many other manufacturers, sells
lawn mowers and other equipment designed for such recycling.;    But it wasn't
too many years ago that talk of composting brought guffaws from many college
horticulture instructors. One of my years-ago professors at <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State
University</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Vic Miller</PERSON>, was among the dissenters, saying, "If we would keep
these materials on our own property, we probably would cut our landfill needs
in half.";    <ORGANIZATION>National</ORGANIZATION> companies catering to gardeners also have been taking
pains to tell how they are working to preserve the environment. For example,
<ORGANIZATION>Smith &amp; Hawken of Mill Valley</ORGANIZATION>, which has offered first-rate equipment for
years, includes this opening declaration in its new catalog: "We plant two
trees for every one we use; we use recycled paper in our offices and our
catalogs, and we sell only ecological beneficial garden products.";    It used
to be fashionable to spray insecticides on a definite schedule. (It's <DATE>May</DATE>, so
spray for mealybugs, aphids and spider mites.) One of my outdated books,
printed in <DATE>1939</DATE>, even recommends spraying pesticides to kill lacewings. Now
pesticide labels often recommend spraying only when pests are noticed and urge
protection of beneficials.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JAMES E. WALTERS, Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910509  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  446  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday May 9, 1991
00130155,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042190-0126 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 207731 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 21, 1990, Saturday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
241 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VENTURA COUNTY NEWS ROUNDUP: FILLMORE; 
</P>
<P>
INSECTARY'S BUGS TARGET CITRUS PESTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JANET BERGAMO 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The 9,000 acres of orange trees surrounding <ORGANIZATION>Fillmore</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Piru</ORGANIZATION> are swarming with 
insects -- and that's good news to <PERSON>Monte Carpenter</PERSON>, manager of the Fillmore 
Insectary. Servicing the pest-control needs of the 350-member <ORGANIZATION>Fillmore Citrus 
Protective District</ORGANIZATION>, the insectary has raised and released 20 species of 
beneficial insects since <DATE>1926</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
During the past 20 years, <PERSON>Carpenter</PERSON> said, less than <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> of the district's total 
acreage has required insecticidal spray. Consequently, some beneficial insects, 
such as ladybugs and green lacewings, have stable and abundant populations. The 
insectary no longer raises them for release in local groves. 
</P>
<P>
"The cooperation of area growers is what makes it work," <PERSON>Carpenter</PERSON> said. Only 
one or two smaller orchards do not belong to the district, which means that one 
farmer's beneficial insects are not endangered by the management of his 
neighbor's grove. 
</P>
<P>
"Any time you spray for injurious insects, you kill the beneficials as well," 
<PERSON>Carpenter</PERSON> said. Orchards such as those in the <LOCATION>San Joaquin Valley</LOCATION> "are on a 
pesticide treadmill," he added. 
</P>
<P>
With five full-time workers supplemented by two part-time staff members, the 
insectary raises two insect predators that feed on red and black scale, the 
most prolific citrus pests. About 180 million beneficial insects are released 
annually in member orchards. Spraying is reserved for the rare, heavy 
infestation that defies biological control. JANET <LOCATION>BERGAMO</LOCATION> 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Manager Monte Carpenter examines banana squash used to raise insects at 
the Fillmore Citrus Protective District. DEBRA MYRENT / For The Times; Photo, 
Beneficial insects that control citrus pests are vacuumed into a tube. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920221-0150
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920221-0150.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Growing Appetite
   For Attack Insects
   Spawns an Industry
   ---
   Greenhouse Gardeners Spur
   Sales of Natural Enemies
   For the War on Parasites
   ----
   By Bob Hagerty
</HL>
<DATE>
02/21/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<MS>
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
BIOTECHNOLOGY (BTC)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
MEDICAL &amp; BIOTECHNOLOGY, GENETIC RESEARCH, PROSTHETICS (MTC)
</IN>
<NS>
COMMODITIES MARKET (CMD)
</NS>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
NETHERLANDS (NL)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   In the antenna-to-antenna combat of the insect world, the
predatory anthocorid wields terrifying powers.
   Just ask Bunting Biological Control Ltd. of Great
Horkesley, England. The company is breeding millions of the
three-millimeter Rambos. It aims to sell them this spring or
summer to greenhouse-vegetable growers in need of troops to
deploy against the dreaded Western flower thrip, an avid
muncher of peppers and cucumbers.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Bunting's brochure describes how the anthocorids operate:
"Both the adults and the nymphs feed by inserting their
proboscis-like mouthparts into the prey and sucking out the
body juices." Not just one or two helpings, either: Bunting
promises that its bugs will drain as many as 15 thrips a day.
The predators also snack on aphids and spider mites. If
nothing else is around, they devour one another.
   But it's a bug-eat-bug business, and greenhouse farmers
can't be too fastidious about the thuggish habits of some of
their allies, known in the trade as "natural enemies" or
"beneficial insects."
   For a few dozen mite-size European and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> companies,
finding and breeding these natural enemies is becoming a
fast-growing business.
   Although greenhouse farmers began dabbling with natural
enemies in the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, such pest control remained little more
than a curiosity for decades. After World War II, new
chemical pesticides proved so devastating that few farmers
bothered with any other weaponry. Then, in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and
<DATE>1970s</DATE>, some farmers began to doubt that it was healthy for
people who work in glasshouses to spray lots of chemicals
around.
   One of the doubters was Jan <PERSON>Pieter Koppert</PERSON>, a Dutch
greenhouse grower whose respiratory problems prompted him to
experiment with natural enemies for his own use in the late
<DATE>1960s</DATE>. Soon he was selling killer insects to his neighbors.
Now <ORGANIZATION>Koppert B.V.</ORGANIZATION>, owned and managed by the late <PERSON>Mr. Koppert</PERSON>'s
sons, exports brandname bugs as far afield as <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. In the past five years, the company's annual
sales have more than tripled to around <MONEY>30 million guilders</MONEY>
(<MONEY>$16.6 million</MONEY>). That, says export manager Cor-Jan van der
Elzen, makes <PERSON>Koppert</PERSON> "the main leader in the world" of
natural enemies. (The company also supplies bumble bees for
pollination work-along with bee food called BeeHappy.)
   Koppert and rival companies -- such as <LOCATION>Bunting</LOCATION> and Chr.
<PERSON>Hansen</PERSON>'s Bio Systems AS of <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> -- remain bullish on bugs.
Tough environmental rules in many countries are pressuring
farmers to use fewer chemical pesticides and making those
pesticides more expensive to develop. At the same time, some
consumers are clamoring for unsprayed fruit and vegetables.
   So far, most people aren't willing to pay the premium for
unsprayed produce. But <PERSON>Joop van Lenteren</PERSON>, an expert on
natural enemies at the <ORGANIZATION>Agricultural University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wageningen</LOCATION>,
the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, thinks the trend is toward fussier
consumers. "In <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>," he says, "they're even more keen on
clean food than we are here."
   To satisfy that demand, bug breeders scour the wilderness
for new predators and parasites. The trick is to track down
the most efficient killers. Frogs, for instance, may eat lots
of insects, but they can't be relied upon to go after any
particular pest. Certain types of mites, on the other hand,
zero right in on thrip larvae.
   So <PERSON>Koppert</PERSON> breeds mites and packs them into plastic
bottles marked Thripex. It advises cucumber growers to
sprinkle the mites over their plants like salt.
   Among other hired guns on the market are aphid midges,
lacewings, ladybird beetles, mealybug destroyers, gypsy moths
and onion maggots. The predatory snail (Rumina decollata)
stands ready to pounce on garden snails.
   Since no one can patent a snail or an insect, competition
can be fierce; new suppliers keep crawling out of the
woodwork. Two years ago, Biolab of <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> opened a
state-of-the-art bug plant near <LOCATION>Cesena</LOCATION>, partly financed by
government funds. Koppert is so wary of rivals that it
refuses to let visitors tour its labs or breeding plant. <PERSON>Mr.
van Lenteren</PERSON> says Russian scientists plied him with vodka,
unsuccessfully, to learn bug-production secrets.
   Even a few giant companies are getting involved. <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>BASF AG</ORGANIZATION>, for example, sells capsules full of ichneumon flies
to combat the infamous corn borer. <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Chemical
Industries PLC</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> doesn't sell insects but offers
chemical pesticides designed for use alongside them.
   Rather than breeding bugs, big chemical and drug companies
generally are more interested in developing bacteria, fungi
and viruses to serve as "biopesticides." County <ORGANIZATION>Natwest
WoodMac</ORGANIZATION>, a British stockbroker, estimates that the world
market for biopesticides -- most of them based on a bacterium
called Bt, or Bacillus thuringiensis -- totals <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY> a
year, or <PERCENT>0.5%</PERCENT> of the global market for agrochemicals. Natural
enemies constitute an even smaller business.
   Even <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON>, one of the world's leading
advocates of natural enemies and other types of biological
pest control, doesn't think they can render chemicals
obsolete.
   For now, natural enemies are unleashed mainly in
greenhouses. Outdoors, a bigger variety of pests and
unpredictable weather make it hard for warrior bugs to
perform reliably; most farmers stick to chemical weapons for
their field crops. Still, natural enemies are sometimes used
outdoors for strawberries, apples, cotton and corn.
   <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> thinks more outdoor applications are
possible. He preaches using natural enemies along with
chemical pesticides in a way that minimizes the need for the
latter.
   Toward that end, he and his colleagues in <LOCATION>Wageningen</LOCATION> are
using government grants to study bug warfare.
   Remember <PERSON>Pavlov</PERSON>'s dog? Meet van <ORGANIZATION>Lenteren</ORGANIZATION>'s insect. When a
young woman wore a potent perfume in the lab one day, <PERSON>Mr. van
Lenteren</PERSON>'s students were seized with an inspiration: Why not
teach parasitic wasps to respond to an artificial odor, such
as perfume? The students wafted various perfumes over the
wasps as they laid their eggs. Later the wasps associated
certain scents with egg-laying.
   "Now we know we can train them to many things -- to
shapes, to colors," marvels <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON>. Why bother?
Because, he says, insect breeders will be able to sell bugs
trained to search out a particular enemy more effectively.
<PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> says he's in negotiations to license the
technology to several companies.
   The professor also is teaming up with botanists to try to
make life easier for natural enemies. A case in point is
Encarsia formosa, a parasitic wasp used to counter the white
fly. "Encarsia formosa," <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> admits, "is a
rather stupid animal in several respects." Peering through
their microscopes, entomologists noted that the wasp kept
stumbling into the minute hairs on cucumber leaves as it
looked for white-fly larvae. "It's like a drunken man on a
sidewalk with many lamp posts," <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> explains.
   The obvious solution was to seek out a strain of cucumbers
with hairless leaves. But researchers found that Encarsia
formosa, when set loose on a hairless leaf, zipped around so
fast it was liable to pass over a juicy larva without even
noticing. Somehow, the wayward wasp had to be slowed down.
The answer: promote a type of cucumber with <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> less leaf
hair.
   With such discoveries, <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> says, "we are
scoring in international journals."
   Suppliers boast about their lab feats, too. One of the hot
areas of research revolves around uses for nematodes.
   Bunting already is promoting its Nemasys brand of
nematodes as a scourge for sciarid flies and vine weevils.
Stored in a special gel, the nematodes come in convenient
packages of 50 million. <PERSON>James Finch</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Bunting</ORGANIZATION>'s marketing
manager, concedes it's difficult for customers to be sure of
the count in each pack. "They have to trust us," he says.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051890-0035 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 220534 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 18, 1990, Friday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 6 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
769 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
APHIDS INFLICTING HUGE LOSSES ON ORGANIC FARMS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PSYCHE PASCUAL, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Organic farmers in <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION> stand to lose <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in crops 
this year because of the worst outbreak of aphids in a decade. 
</P>
<P>
Growers, who blame the outbreak on drought conditions, say that crops most 
endangered by the insect are organically grown lettuce, broccoli, cabbage and 
celery. 
</P>
<P>
"In the mountains, all the vegetation is dry up there, so they come after our 
crop in stronger numbers," said organic farmer <PERSON>Dean Walsh</PERSON>. "This is the worst 
year we've had in 10 years." 
</P>
<P>
Up and down the central coast, organic farmers are trying to exterminate armies 
of the tiny, winged insects. They say they are severely hampered, however, 
because -- unlike other farmers -- they do not use pesticides. 
</P>
<P>
"We've had an aphid problem like we've never seen in our lives," said <PERSON>Mary Ann 
Sprinkle</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for the <LOCATION>Carpinteria</LOCATION> chapter of <ORGANIZATION>California Certified 
Organic Farmers</ORGANIZATION>. "Aphids are on things I've never seen them on before." 
</P>
<P>
There is only a small contingent of organic farmers in <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION>. Fourteen 
farmers till 1,200 acres, producing between <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> and <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY> of 
vegetables and fruit, growers estimate. 
</P>
<P>
Without organic solutions to the aphid outbreak, "you're looking at a 
multimillion-dollar loss for the county," said <PERSON>Bob Scowcroft</PERSON>, executive 
director of the <ORGANIZATION>California Certified Organic Farmers</ORGANIZATION>, which represents 630 
growers. 
</P>
<P>
While other farmers can spray chemicals to rid their produce of the pest, 
organic farmers say they are almost powerless to prevent the damage aphids can 
wreak. They are turning to nontoxic methods to kill the irksome insects: soapy 
water, and other bugs. 
</P>
<P>
Organic farmers have been spraying their fields with soapy water by hand to 
wash aphids off their crops. They also have introduced ladybugs and lacewings, 
which feed on aphids, into their fields to reduce the aphid population. 
</P>
<P>
Walsh runs the largest organic farm in <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION>, a 540-acre ranch in 
<LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION>, and a 280-acre farm near <LOCATION>Lompoc</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Santa Barbara County</LOCATION>. His farm 
ships about 1 million cartons of organic vegetables to domestic markets each 
year. 
</P>
<P>
The green bugs suck vegetables dry, ruining produce that is ready for market. 
Even vegetables believed to be clean of bugs have made their way to supermarket 
stands, only to be found sprinkled with aphids. 
</P>
<P>
About <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> of <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON>'s green vegetables were lost to hungry aphids last 
month when 15 acres were infested, he said. Harvested crops had to be dumped 
after supermarkets discovered the insect and rejected the produce. 
</P>
<P>
While organic farmers blame lack of rain for the aphid outbreak, county 
agriculture officials refrain from attributing the outbreak only to the 
drought. They say the bugs are returning as part of a seasonal reproductive 
cycle, but admit the population is unusually large this year. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Phil Phillips</PERSON>, a pest management specialist with the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> 
farm adviser's office in <LOCATION>Ventura</LOCATION>, said lack of rain has broken down the 
resistance of crops to predatory insects such as aphids. Moreover, plant 
