<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880927-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-27-88 1551EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-BRF--Ferraro-Debate     09-27 0163</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Ferraro-Debate,160</SECOND>
<HEAD>Geraldine Ferraro Says She Taught George Bush To Debate</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> says both Democrat <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> and Republican
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> did well in <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s debate, but <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s success
came ``probably because I taught him how to do it.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>, who debated <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> during the <DATE>1984</DATE> campaign, also
said her unsuccessful campaign would continue to be significant
until a woman is elected to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I have a place in history,'' she said <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> before a
speech at <ORGANIZATION>Emory University</ORGANIZATION>. ``And I'll have that place in history
until a woman runs and wins. Then I'll fade into the woodwork.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>, a former <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> congresswoman, was the running
mate chosen by Democratic presidential nominee <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>,
making her the only woman ever nominated for president or vice
president by a major political party.
   The <DATE>1984</DATE> Democratic ticket suffered one of the worst defeats
ever in a presidential race.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021090-0001 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 174151 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 10, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 35; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
86 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ANTONETTA FERRARO; MOTHER OF GERALDINE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Antonetta Ferraro</PERSON>, 84, mother of former vice presidential candidate <PERSON>Geraldine 
Ferraro</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I always said I had two role models in life," said <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, the 
one was <PERSON>Antonetta Ferraro</PERSON>. She worked all her life. She worked in sweatshops 
when they were really sweatshops. She learned a trade at 13 that put me through 
law school." <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>'s father died in <DATE>1943</DATE>. In <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> on <DATE>Feb</DATE>. 
2 of emphysema and cancer. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Obituary 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880928-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-28-88 0542EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-PoliticalBriefs     09-28 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Political Briefs,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>VP Debate, Playoff Starting Times Adjusted to Avoid Conflict</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> starting times for the
vice-presidential debate and the major league baseball playoffs
have been juggled to avoid a conflict, officials involved said.
   The 90-minute debate between Democrat <PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> and
Republican <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> was moved from a <TIME>9 p.m. EDT</TIME> starting time to
<TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>, officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The start of the first game of the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> playoffs,
scheduled for the home of the <ORGANIZATION>East Division</ORGANIZATION> winner, was moved from
<TIME>8:28 p.m.</TIME> to <TIME>1:20 p.m.</TIME>, and the first pitch of game two in the
<ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> playoffs at <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> was pushed back from <TIME>3:07
p.m. to 10:08 p.m.</TIME>
   ABC will televise the baseball games. All the major networks
will televise the debate.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<HEAD>Geraldine Ferraro Says She Taught George Bush To Debate</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> starting times for the
vice-presidential debate and the major league baseball playoffs
have been juggled to avoid a conflict, officials involved said.
   The 90-minute debate between Democrat <PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> and
Republican <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> was moved from a <TIME>9 p.m. EDT</TIME> starting time to
<TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>, officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The start of the first game of the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> playoffs,
scheduled for the home of the <ORGANIZATION>East Division</ORGANIZATION> winner, was moved from
<TIME>8:28 p.m.</TIME> to <TIME>1:20 p.m.</TIME>, and the first pitch of game two in the
<ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> playoffs at <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> was pushed back from <TIME>3:07
p.m. to 10:08 p.m.</TIME>
   ABC will televise the baseball games. All the major networks
will televise the debate.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<HEAD>Heavy Metal Adds Heavy Cost To VP Debate</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OMAHA, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> starting times for the
vice-presidential debate and the major league baseball playoffs
have been juggled to avoid a conflict, officials involved said.
   The 90-minute debate between Democrat <PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> and
Republican <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> was moved from a <TIME>9 p.m. EDT</TIME> starting time to
<TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>, officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The start of the first game of the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> playoffs,
scheduled for the home of the <ORGANIZATION>East Division</ORGANIZATION> winner, was moved from
<TIME>8:28 p.m.</TIME> to <TIME>1:20 p.m.</TIME>, and the first pitch of game two in the
<ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> playoffs at <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> was pushed back from <TIME>3:07
p.m. to 10:08 p.m.</TIME>
   ABC will televise the baseball games. All the major networks
will televise the debate.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-02-04-90 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Ferraro'sMother     02-04 0210</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Ferraro's Mother,0217</SECOND>
<HEAD>Geraldine Ferraro's Mother Dies At 84</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Antonetta Ferraro</PERSON>, mother of former vice
   <PERSON>Mrs. Ferraro</PERSON> died <DATE>Friday</DATE> at her daughter's <ORGANIZATION>Forest Hills</ORGANIZATION> home of
emphysema and cancer.
   ``I always said I had two role models in life,'' <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>
told <ORGANIZATION>New York Newsday</ORGANIZATION>. ``One was <PERSON>Eleanor Roosevelt</PERSON> and one was
<PERSON>Antonetta Ferraro</PERSON>. She worked all her life. She worked in
sweatshops when they were really sweatshops. She learned a trade at
13 that put me through law school.''
   <PERSON>Mrs. Ferraro</PERSON>, whose husband, <PERSON>Dominick</PERSON>, died in <DATE>1943</DATE>, had left
the hospital two months ago to be with her daughter and her family.
   The family has set up the <PERSON>Antonetta Ferraro</PERSON> Scholarship Fund at
<ORGANIZATION>Marymount Manhattan College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>
graduated.
   ``It's a scholarship fund for girls who have been raised
(solely) by their mothers,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>, the Democrat nominee
for vice-president in <DATE>1984</DATE>. ``My mother felt she never had an
education, but I always told her she did pretty well by me.''
   In addition to her daughter, <PERSON>Mrs. Ferraro</PERSON> is survived by a son,
<PERSON>Carl</PERSON>, and six grandchildren.
   The funeral was set for <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in the <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> borough of
<LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06335052 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06335052 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: (Geraldine Ferraro)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  LETTER  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  As a woman and a journalist, I was offended by the Los Angeles Times story
"Ferraro in the running again," in the Nov. 20 Mercury News.;   Why did Josh
Getlin feel it pertinent to his story to include evidence of Ferraro's
appearance in his lead? Why do I need to know that her face is "more deeply
lined" or that her hair, once "frosted blond," has now "gone gray"?  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  The Letters Page  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GERALDINE FERRARO LOOKS QUALIFIED BY ANY MEASURE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Letters Page  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     This is classic evidence of the societal prejudice against older women, if
not women in general. Appearance over substance. Aging men are
"distinguished," while older women get "dumpy" or "matronly.";   Our
male-dominated society has it all figured out: Men always improve -- they get
wiser; women always decay, losing their appearances and thus their value.;  
<PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> deserves better, especially in light of the fact she fights these
stereotypes for a living and furthered the women's movement immeasurably when
she became the first woman vice presidential candidate in <DATE>1984.</DATE>;   Now she is
striving to wrest the power from the sexist legislators who apparently feel
comfortable allowing a lying, sexual vigilante to sit on the highest court in
America.;   Getlin should have recognized that <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>'s substance is all that
matters and besides, she still looks damn good to <LOCATION>me.</LOCATION>;   But then, if we use
his logic, maybe <PERSON>Getlin</PERSON> is just too adorable (i.e., lacks the gray matter) to
get the big picture.;   -- <PERSON>Brooke Shelby Biggs</PERSON>;   Executive Editor;   Spartan
Daily, SJSU; <PERSON>Josh Getlin</PERSON>'s characterization of <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> is another
example of media sexism.;   Why is it that a woman's appearance always
requires comment. I don't see journalists describing male political candidates
as having "blond hair gone gray" and having "more deeply lined" faces. I would
think that journalists today would have greater professionalism.;   --
<PERSON>Margaret Flores</PERSON>;   <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Josh Golin</PERSON> states that "On a hot <DATE>summer night
seven years ago</DATE>, <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> became the first woman in history to be nominated for
the vice presidency.";   That statement is not correct. Not only was <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>
not the first woman to run for the vice presidency, she wasn't even the third
or fourth. Many third parties have nominated women for vice president and
president. Nor was she the first woman to receive an electoral college vote.
That piece of history belongs to <ORGANIZATION>Tonia Nathan</ORGANIZATION>. She received an electoral
college vote in <DATE>1972</DATE>. She ran on the Libertarian Party ticket.;   If you're
interested in new ideas, such as running a woman for president or vice
president, you can be sure <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s third parties will be the first to try
it. Next year if you want to vote for a woman for the vice presidential spot,
one option will be <PERSON>Dr. Nancy Lord</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Libertarian Party</ORGANIZATION>'s nominee. I doubt
you'll have that option on the Demo-Republican ticket.;   -- <PERSON>Mark Hinkle</PERSON>;  
<LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911130  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  469  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, November 30, 1991
00335052,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06325155 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06325155 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mercury News File Photograph; A FIRST -- Geraldine Ferraro made
history in 1984 when presidential candidate Walter Mondale nominated her to be
vice president.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  POLITICS; WOMAN; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE FROSTED blond hair has gone to gray, her face is more deeply lined and
there's a subtle barrier, a distance, between Geraldine Ferraro and the
well-wishers who crowd around her these days.;   But when it comes to letting
the old boys have it, especially the Republicans who tormented Ferraro during
her 1984 run for the vice presidency, the homemaker from Queens who made
history is remarkably unchanged.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FERRARO IN THE RUNNING AGAIN  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "Lemme tell ya, there's a vicious rumor about me going around," she tells a
group of business and professional women on a blustery morning. "They say I
have my eyes on <PERSON>Sen. Al D'Amato</PERSON>'s seat.";   Pause.;   "I don't have my eyes on
his seat. It's his job that I want.";   The cheering crowd in a hotel banquet
room rises to its feet, and <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> is rolling once again. A hero and role
model to many women present, she's attempting a political comeback from the
ashes of her disastrous national campaign. And nobody is counting her out.;  
On a hot <DATE>summer night seven years ago</DATE>, <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> became the first woman in
history to be nominated for the vice presidency. Based largely on that
memorable event, she continues to enjoy a political celebrity few can match.
Although the <ORGANIZATION>New York Senate</ORGANIZATION> election is almost a year away, her battle to
unseat <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON>, a two-term <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> incumbent, is drawing enthusiastic crowds.;  
So far, however, <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> has been preaching to the choir. The people begging
for autographs these days don't seem too concerned about questions of ethical
impropriety that dogged her vice presidential campaign, even though they are
likely to be raised in <DATE>1992</DATE>. She has yet to face an ugly crowd -- the kind
that derided her support for abortion rights and insulted members of her
family.;   Those scars have not yet healed, and the <DATE>1991</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Ferraro</ORGANIZATION> is a warier
political creature. She is less trusting of the press this time around and can
be impatient with slow questioners at political events. Determined to protect
her privacy, she has nonetheless put herself under the microscope again.;   
AT SOME point, <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> agrees, she will have to face the past: old questions
about her husband's real estate deals, whispered allegations of his mob ties,
her son's conviction for attempted sale of cocaine and charges that she
mishandled her finances as a three-term congresswoman. But for now, there is
no mistaking the excitement and feeling of rebirth surrounding her senatorial
race, especially when she speaks to women's groups.;   "I was thinking about
the unemployment bill that President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> vetoed (this <DATE>summer</DATE>)," <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> told
the <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION> crowd. "And then I realized, he probably thinks that if <PERSON>Clarence
Thomas</PERSON> can get a job, anybody can get a job.";   The audience applauds,
cheering her digs at the all-white, all-male <ORGANIZATION>Senate Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION> that
debated <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>' nomination for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>. But the biggest
applause comes for a line she uses in every speech.;   "Women in this country
have a feeling they've been had," she said. "And I'll be damned if I'm going
to let the '90s go down as the decade in which the Soviets won their rights
and American women lost theirs.";   "You have to understand, this woman
changed my life," said <PERSON>Virginia Hundt</PERSON>, a businesswoman who is running for a
local office next year and who has been waiting 30 minutes to have her picture
taken with Ferraro.;   "She showed women that they could make a difference on
the national political level, and she's a tremendous inspiration to us all."; 
 Others are more skeptical. Across the room, <PERSON>Mary Carswell</PERSON>, a deputy airport
manager, agrees that <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> is a historic figure and not just another
political big shot. Still, <PERSON>Carswell</PERSON> wonders why the candidate would again put
herself through the torture of public examination: "I wouldn't change places
with her for the world. Who needs the punishment? Why do it again?";   Indeed,
some critics dismiss <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>'s campaign as an exercise in nostalgia,
predicting that she cannot win a hotly contested Democratic primary next year
against three other candidates. The formidable field includes <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
Attorney General <PERSON>Robert Abrams</PERSON>, <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> Comptroller <PERSON>Elizabeth Holzman</PERSON>
and Rep. <PERSON>Robert Mrazek</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>;   But a recent <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo News</ORGANIZATION> poll had good news
for <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>. Taken after the <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> hearings, it showed her leading Abrams <PERCENT>40
percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>38 percent</PERCENT>, with <PERSON>Holzman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mrazek</PERSON> far behind.;    YET EVEN if she
wins the primary, critics say, <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> could make mincemeat of her. They
believe <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>, weighted by her own baggage, is the only Democratic candidate
who could not credibly attack D'Amato for political corruption.;   The senator
has been stung by charges of malfeasance over the allocation of federal
housing funds in his district and is plummeting in the polls. Although he was
exonerated by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> ethics committee, <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> is believed vulnerable in
<DATE>1992</DATE>, especially to a squeaky-clean candidate.;   "The point is, <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>'s
vulnerable too," said a veteran Republican campaign consultant who asked not
to be identified. "Voters will remember her problems, and if they don't
remember, they'll certainly be reminded.";   If she is bothered by the
conventional wisdom, however, <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> doesn't show it. Do the fellas want to
play rough? She'll play rough.;   "I won't let anyone get away with attacking
me," she said, settling in for a long drive from <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION> to her next
political event, in <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> "If somebody hits me, my response (in a TV
spot) will be in the can. I don't run away from a fight. I'm a fighter."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JOSH GETLIN, Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Syracuse, N.Y.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911120  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  942  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, November 20, 1991
00325155,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06088089 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06088089 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; US; PRESIDENT; CANDIDATE; FUTURE; CONGRESS; ELECTION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Geraldine Ferraro, the unsuccessful 1984 Democratic vice presidential
candidate, will seek the U.S. Senate seat held by Republican Alfonse D'Amato,
her daughter said Wednesday.;    "She's planning on running," said Donna
Zaccaro, a political aide to her mother.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DAUGHTER SAYS FERRARO WILL RUN FOR U.S. SENATE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     State Democratic Chairman <PERSON>John Marino</PERSON> said <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> told him <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of
her plan.;    <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> is the only woman ever to run on a major party's
national ticket. The losing slate was led by former Vice President <PERSON>Walter
Mondale.</PERSON>;    <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> said <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> wouldn't make a formal announcement for the
Democratic nomination until later this year.;    <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> said he was confident
he would win a third six-year <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> term in the <DATE>1992</DATE> election.;    <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> is
under investigation on allegations that relatives, friends and major campaign
contributors received special treatment in seeking federal development
grants.;    <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> is expected to face a tough fight for the Democratic
nomination. State Attorney General <PERSON>Robert Abrams</PERSON> already has announced he will
run, and Rep. <PERSON>Robert Mrazek</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION> also has expressed an interest.;   
Other potential Democratic candidates include <PERSON>Elizabeth Holtzman</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION> comptroller who lost a three-way race to <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> in <DATE>1980</DATE>; and <PERSON>Mark Green</PERSON>,
the <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> consumer affairs commissioner who lost to <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> in <DATE>1986</DATE>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Albany, N.Y.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910328  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  203  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday March 28, 1991
00088089,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880212-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-12-88 2007EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Women-Constitution     02-12 0628</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Women-Constitution,0645</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ferraro Says Women's Equality Depends On More Female Officeholders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, whose vice presidential
nomination marked a peak for the women's equality movement, said
<DATE>Friday</DATE> that women must translate their increasing power at the
ballot box to campaigns for elective office.
   ``If you don't run, you can't win,'' <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> said. ``And
just as important, every time a woman runs, women win.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> addressed some 1,500 women attending a symposium on
women and the Constitution convened by former first ladies <PERSON>Rosalynn
Carter</PERSON> and Lady Bird <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>.
   She said there are more female officeholders than ever, but the
numbers are not representative of the population.
   ``Women are, by any measure, grossly underrepresented in
elective office,'' <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> said. ``I would say shockingly
underrepresented; however, nobody is shocked. That's simply how it
is.''
   Coretta <PERSON>Scott King</PERSON>, wife of slain civil rights leader <PERSON>Martin
Luther King Jr.</PERSON>, echoed <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> in urging women, particularly
black women, to seek office.
   ``We have a strength and tenacity and a gift for nurturing and
compassion which has been finely honed and tempered in our struggle
to raise families in a sexist society,'' <PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON> said on the
closing day of the two-day symposium.
   ``Let me put it this way _ if the women of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> don't lead
the struggle against poverty, racism and militarism, then we must
ask, who will?'' she said.
   According to the <ORGANIZATION>National Women's Political Caucus</ORGANIZATION>, in <DATE>1987</DATE>
women held <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT> of the higher statewide elective offices in
the country. At the same time, there are only 23 women serving in
the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> _ and only one black woman _ two female governors and two
women in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>, a former congresswoman from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, said many of
those officeholders are not yet in positions of national power or
leadership, which she said would likely delay nomination of a woman
as a presidential candidate.
   However, more women will become interested in politics and the
numbers elected will increase, she said. <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> said her <DATE>1984</DATE>
campaign with Democratic presidential nominee <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>
inspired thousands of women to write her and describe how the
candidacy inspired them to go to law school, medical school, or run
for office.
   ``Every time a woman runs for any elective office, it's like
throwing a stone in a lake,'' she said. ``The ripple effect is felt
far beyond the immediate point of impact.''
   <PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON> compared the challenge facing women in the workplace
and in politics to that faced by blacks during the civil rights
struggle led by her late husband. She said women can learn much
from the tactics used by blacks to gain rights.
   ``The movement showed millions of Americans that you can, indeed
you must, defy authority when that authority is in the wrong,''
<PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON> said.
   Women have become a distinct and powerful voting group in recent
years, <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> said, pointing to the <DATE>1986</DATE> mid-term elections
that brought a Democratic majority to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. She said nine
Democrats won by getting less than <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the male vote, and
more than <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the female vote.
   ``Women voted more strongly Democratic, and on key issues like
peace, disarmament, social welfare and the environment, differently
from men,'' she said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> said that after she was nominated for vice president
the thousands of joyfully weeping women she saw told her that
equality, and a female president, are coming.
   ``She will have shown that she possesses the rare combination of
qualities the American people look for in a president, and then it
will be time. And tears will be cried like you wouldn't believe,''
she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900322-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-22-90 2157EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Women     03-22 0361</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Women,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Says He's an Expert on Running Against Women; Ferraro
Disagrees</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIM I. MILLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that he's an
expert when it comes to running a political campaign against women,
but at least one female politician took exception to the contention.
   ``I don't know how he'd call himself an expert,'' former Rep.
<PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> said from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. ``Only in politics does one
little meeting an expert make.''
   <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> was <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>'s vice presidential running mate in
the <DATE>1984</DATE> race against incumbent President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and Vice President
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s comments at a news conference were prompted by a question
about the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> gubernatorial race that may pit Democrat <PERSON>Ann
Richards</PERSON> against <ORGANIZATION>Republican Clayton Williams</ORGANIZATION>.
   Williams has said he would feel less comfortable running against
<PERSON>Richards</PERSON> than Attorney General <PERSON>Jim Mattox</PERSON>. Richards, the state
treasurer, and <PERSON>Mattox</PERSON> will battle for the Democratic nomination in
an <DATE>April 10</DATE> run-off election.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said he had some opinions about running against women,
calling himself ``an expert in the field'' because of his contest
against <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>.
   But <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> said <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s memory of the race is flawed, and that
the only time they went head-to-head was in one televised debate.
   ``We did not run against each other. It was <PERSON>Fritz Mondale</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> who were running against each other,'' <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> said.
``If we were both running against each other, if we were both at
the top of the ticket, then I think his comment about being an
expert would be valid.''
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was asked if he had any advice for <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I have none at all, but I know exactly what he means and I
refuse to elaborate on it,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said.
   Ferraro, meanwhile, said <PERSON>Richards</PERSON> didn't need any advice from
her.
   ``Ann has run against men before. I'm sure she's not
uncomfortable with it,'' <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> said, suggesting <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>' problem
may be a common male ailment.
   ``The only way I can see it, being uncomfortable, is when you
lose to a man it's humiliating enough,'' she said. ``But if you're
a macho guy and you lose to a woman, it has to be devastating.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881003-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-03-88 0900EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ZaccaroMugging     10-03 0109</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Zaccaro Mugging,0111</SECOND>
<HEAD>Geraldine Ferraro's Mother-in-Law Mugged</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 80-year-old mother-in-law of former vice
snatched her purse and pushed her to the ground, police said.
   Rose <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> was treated for a cut lip and a bruised cheek and
forehead after the attack, which occurred <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> near her
home in <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>. She was released from <ORGANIZATION>St. John's Hospital</ORGANIZATION> after
X-rays showed no broken bones.
   Police said <PERSON>Mrs. Zaccaro</PERSON>'s assailant snuck up from behind as she
was walking. Detectives reported no suspects in the attack.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Zaccaro</PERSON> is the mother of <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>'s husband, <PERSON>John
Zaccaro</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881002-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-02-88 1123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-RunningMates Bjt   10-02 0770</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Running Mates, Bjt,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Experts Say Top of Ticket, Not Running Mates, Sways Voters' Choice</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrats who hope <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> will
help the ticket win his home state of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and perhaps the
presidential election could do well to regard the fate of <PERSON>Henry
Gassaway Davis</PERSON>.
   In case anyone doesn't remember, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> was Democrat <PERSON>Alton B.
Parker</PERSON>'s running mate when <PERSON>Parker</PERSON> ran for president against
<ORGANIZATION>Republican Teddy Roosevelt</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1904</DATE>.
   The voters chose between <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Parker</PERSON>, and their choice
was Roosevelt by a 3-2 margin.
   Experts concede that the vice presidential debate in <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> between <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> and Republican <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> may
make a difference, but they say the voters' final decision will
come down to a choice between the top of the tickets, Democrat
<PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> and Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>.
   ``Unless <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> is absolutely destroyed in the debate with
<PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>, I don't think it will hurt <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>,'' said <PERSON>Leo Ribuffo</PERSON>, a
specialist in political history at <ORGANIZATION>George Washington University</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   ``People will be looking for <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> to blow it,'' said <PERSON>Samuel H.
California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. ``If he can get through the debate in a
competent fashion where he looks unexceptional, it will be a real
success for him.''
   <PERSON>Eddie Mahe Jr.</PERSON>, a Republican political consultant, said, ``I
think it is reasonable to suggest that <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> would have won
<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Quayle</ORGANIZATION>'s home state) without <PERSON>Mr. Quayle</PERSON>, and with <PERSON>Mr.
Bentsen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mike Dukakis</PERSON> is still not going to carry <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. So you
wash that out.''
   ``I think the odds are that <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> will have little or no effect
on the ultimate choice,'' said <PERSON>Thomas Mann</PERSON>, program director for
   <PERSON>Elspeth Rostow</PERSON>, a political scholar at the <ORGANIZATION>Lyndon B. Johnson
School of Public Affairs</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>, said
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s choice of <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> ``doesn't seem to have too much effect on
the voters, at least so far.''
   ``I don't think, if indeed <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was disposed to choose <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> to
appeal to women, that so far it has had that effect,'' <PERSON>Ms. Rostow</PERSON>
said.
   ``I think the conventional wisdom that the selection of a
running mate is rarely decisive one way or another is absolutely
true,'' said <PERSON>Ribuffo</PERSON>.
   A survey conducted this year by the <ORGANIZATION>Hearst Corp.</ORGANIZATION> supports this
view.
   Eighteen percent of the 1,001 voters surveyed said they had
changed their minds about a presidential candidate at one time or
another because of their opinion of his running mate. Of those, <PERCENT>70
percent</PERCENT> said they voted against that ticket.
   Political experts agree that if a running mate has any effect,
he is more likely to hurt than help.
   Examples cited include President <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s selection of <PERSON>Sen. Robert
Dole</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, who was criticized for his slashing debating style
in <DATE>1976</DATE>, and <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>'s choice of <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, who
suffered from examination of her family's finances in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   ``Clearly in my opinion <PERSON>Bob Dole</PERSON> in <DATE>1976</DATE> in that debate (with
<PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>'s running mate) cost <PERSON>Jerry Ford</PERSON> votes,'' <PERSON>Mahe</PERSON>
said. ``Clearly in <DATE>1984</DATE> in my opinion, <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> cost
<PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON> votes probably.''
   In <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>'s unsuccessful campaign of <DATE>1960</DATE>, some thought
that Republican vice presidential candidate <ORGANIZATION>Henry Cabot Lodge</ORGANIZATION> hurt
the ticket's chances by pledging that <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> would appoint a black
to the Cabinet _ a statement <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> disavowed.
criticized for taking naps and not campaigning hard enough. ``Some
have thought that if he had used his prestige from the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> more
effectively, <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> might have edged out <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Ms. Rostow</PERSON> said.
   There are exceptions to the rule that running mates don't help
much, the experts said.
   While there is disagreement over whether Lodge hurt <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> in
<DATE>1960</DATE>, almost everybody agrees that <PERSON>Lyndon B. Johnson</PERSON> helped Kennedy
by enabling him to carry <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   ``I don't think <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> would have won without <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>,''
<PERSON>Ribuffo</PERSON> said.
   Also, <PERSON>Ribuffo</PERSON> said, <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON> may have helped <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> win election
in <DATE>1976</DATE> by imparting legitimacy to the former <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> governor in
the eyes of skeptical liberals.
   Then there was the running mate that Republicans chose in <DATE>1900</DATE>
to help the colorless <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON> win a second term against
the dynamic Democrat, <PERSON>William Jennings Bryan</PERSON>. The ticket of
<ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> became known as ``the kangaroo ticket
because it had a kick in the tail,'' <PERSON>Ms. Rostow</PERSON> said.
   There haven't been many tickets in any other year, including
<DATE>1988</DATE>, with that much of a kick in the tail, the experts agree.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881114-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-14-88 1538EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Reagan-Schoolchildren     11-14 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan-Schoolchildren,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan on Woman President: `I Welcome It.'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MERRILL HARTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
inevitably will have a woman president, and ``I welcome it.''
   But during a question-and-answer session with a group of school
children in the <ORGANIZATION>State Dining Room of the White House</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> also
said he thought a woman would likely get to the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> only by
serving first as vice president.
   Asked whether there would ever be a woman chief executive, he
replied, ``I don't know. Believe, I'm certainly not against it. ...''
   ``As a matter of fact, the statesman in the world that I have
met, that I respect the most, is the prime minister of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON>, and she's done a remarkable job for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>,''
the president said.
   Reagan will play host to <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> for an official visit and
state dinner at the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> later this week. The British prime
minister has been his closest friend and ally in the <ORGANIZATION>Western
Alliance</ORGANIZATION> during his nearly eight years in office.
   As for a women president, <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> said the idea would take ``a
little getting used to on the part of some people. But I think it's
inevitable that in this country there will be a woman president
because they've come up in so many different fields.''
   He added: ``It's just my feeling that probably, rather than one
of them just entering the fray to run for president to begin with,
that maybe it would probably start with one of them, as we did in
the election in <DATE>1984</DATE>, ... running for vice president. She didn't
make it, but that might be the start of it, and I welcome it.''
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> was referring to then-Rep. <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>, who
had the second spot on the Democratic ticket headed by then-Vice
President <PERSON>Walter F. Mondale</PERSON>.
   Reagan swept to a 49-state landslide over the ticket, with the
Mondale-Ferraro team carrying only <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>'s home state of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>
and the <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION>.
   Reagan's appearance before students from five Washington-area
junior and senior high schools was the first of four such talks the
president plans to give before leaving office on <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>.
   Before taking questions from the pupils, <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> told his audience
that he would look to young people to carry forth the message of the
American revolution to the rest of the world. But as the world goes
through rapid technological and social change, he said, ``the
permanent truths which give meaning to our lives don't change.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880406-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-06-88 1201EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ZaccaroTrial 2ndLd-Writethru a0586 04-06 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Zaccaro Trial, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0586,0600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Potential Juror: Media Picked On Geraldine Ferraro and Her Family</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 12 grafs to UPDATE with jury selection continuing
today, picking up 9th graf pvs, `Zaccaro, then ....'
^By DANICA KIRKA</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RUTLAND, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A potential juror in the cocaine trial of
<PERSON>John Zaccaro Jr.</PERSON> said she thought the press picked on his family
during the <DATE>1984</DATE> vice presidential candidacy of his mother,
<PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>.
   The woman was one of 15 candidates selected after painstaking
questioning of 25 people during jury selection, which resumed <TIME>this
morning</TIME> for a third day.
   Opening arguments were expected later today or <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Twelve
jurors and two alternates are needed for the trial.
   <ORGANIZATION>Addison County State</ORGANIZATION>'s Attorney <PERSON>John Quinn</PERSON> said the selection of
a jury was slowed by the publicity given the case and the fact
<PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> is so well-known.
   ``Selecting a jury is probably the most important part of the
case,'' he said. <PERSON>Quinn</PERSON> said if even one juror bore a grudge, it
could influence the jury's verdict.
   Most of those questioned said they had read newspaper accounts
of the case since <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON>, 24, was charged in <DATE>1986</DATE> with selling
one-quarter gram of cocaine to an undercover police agent.
   One potential juror said <DATE>today</DATE> that he would discount anything
he read in the newspapers though because of a basic distrust of the
press. ``They have a tendency to present people as guilty just
because they have been charged,'' said <PERSON>Donald Cioffi</PERSON>.
   Only one person has been dismissed for acknowleging that the
prominence of <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON>'s mother could affect his view of the case.
   Jury pool member <PERSON>Joanne Cillo</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that she felt that
press treatment of <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> during the <DATE>1984</DATE> campaign carried over to
<PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON>.
   ``I can't say I don't feel the press picked on these people,''
<PERSON>Cillo</PERSON> said when asked if she was pleased with how <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> has been
treated.
   She said her views would not interfere with her judgment if she
is chosen to hear the case. ``The press is not trying this case,''
she said. ``The issue is, did this gentleman sell drugs?''
   ``I don't believe it's up to me to make restitution for what the
press may or may not have done,'' she added.
   <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON>, then a senior at <ORGANIZATION>Middlebury College</ORGANIZATION>, pleaded innocent
to the charge. He has been accompanied to court each day by his
mother and father, <PERSON>John Zaccaro Sr</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>, a lawyer, sat behind her son and his lawyers, taking
notes intently, but stopping when <PERSON>Cillo</PERSON> spoke about her family. At
that point she rested her head in her hand and looked down.
   She later declined to comment on the case, telling one reporter,
``It's nothing against you personally. We're just not answering
anything for anybody.''
   The start of <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s trial came two years after her son was
arrested outside the <LOCATION>Middlebury</LOCATION> restaurant where he worked.
   Six reporters were allowed to watch the questioning, which was
briefly interrupted <DATE>Monday</DATE> when <PERSON>Judge Francis McCaffrey</PERSON> imposed and
then lifted a gag order on reporters covering jury selection.
   Defense lawyers sought the gag order for fear too many reporters
could intimidate potential jurors. But <PERSON>McCaffrey</PERSON> lifted it
following a challenge from reporters and an agreement to limit
their number in the courtroom.
   The case has wound its way slowly through the courts. Zaccaro's
attorneys challenged several aspects of the case and claimed
unsuccessfully that <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> was singled out for prosecution because
of his mother.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Vermont Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> refused to dismiss the case.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900111-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-90 0247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Ferraro-Senate     01-11 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ferraro-Senate,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ferraro Considering Political Comeback</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIM I. MILLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, the first woman to win a
slot on a major party's presidential ticket, says she's considering
a political comeback.
   <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>, <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>'s running mate on the <DATE>1984</DATE> Democratic
ticket, is weighing a challenge to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Republican <PERSON>Sen. Alfonse
D'Amato</PERSON>.
   The former three-term congresswoman says she isn't worried that
a political campaign would resurrect hurtful stories about her or
her family.
   ``I don't think there's very much that the people of this state
or this nation don't know about me or about my family,'' <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>
said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in a telephone interview from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> was hounded by questions about her family's finances
during the <DATE>1984</DATE> campaign. She later complained that her political
fame hurt her family and led to harsher court treatment of her
husband and son.
   Her husband, <PERSON>John Zaccaro</PERSON>, pleaded guilty in <DATE>1985</DATE> to a
misdemeanor charge in a real estate deal. Her son, <PERSON>John Zaccaro
Jr.</PERSON>, later was convicted of selling a quarter-gram of cocaine while
at <ORGANIZATION>Middlebury College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>.
   ``I would love to back in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, I would love to be part of
the decision-making process with reference to what's going on in
this country,'' said <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>, 54, who lives in the <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>
borough of <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>.
   A race against Rep. <PERSON>Thomas Manton</PERSON>, who holds <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>'s former
seat, is out of the question, she said.
   ``I endorsed him and he is a Democrat who represents my district
very, very well.''
   D'Amato's second term ends in <DATE>1992</DATE>. Recent polls show his
popularity is slipping, primarily because of reports that he used
his influence to steer money from the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Housing and
Urban Development</ORGANIZATION> to friends nd political supporters.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> ethics committee has hired an outside counsel to
decide whether it should launch a full-scale investigation of
D'Amato.
   Ferraro flirted with the idea of taking on D'Amato in <DATE>1986</DATE>, but
pulled back, citing personal reasons.
   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> said she ruled out that <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> race because
she feared the power of Attorney General <PERSON>Edwin Meese III</PERSON>. The
<ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> was investigating complaints that she had failed
to fully disclose her husband's finances while she was in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``That investigation continued well past the campaign, nursed by
people within the <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION>, and I found out later that <PERSON>Ed
Meese</PERSON> had personal interest in it and was tying it to my political
decisions,'' she said.
   ``I did not doubt for one minute that he would use it
politically against me.''
   The 22-month investigation ended with the department deciding
there was no basis for a criminal or civil action.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880621-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-21-88 2021EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-NOW-Jackson     06-21 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NOW-Jackson,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>NOW to Call for Jackson or `Non-White' Woman as Democratic No. 2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DARREN DOPP</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUFFALO, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Organization for Women</ORGANIZATION> plans
to urge likely Democratic nominee <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> to select rival
<PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> or a ``non-white'' woman as his running mate, the
group's president said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Molly Yard</PERSON> said it would take the selection of <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, who is
very sensitive to women's issues, or ``a woman from <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s
constituency'' to smooth relations between the women's movement and
the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The whole stance of the party since <DATE>1984</DATE> has been to blame us
for the defeat of <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>,'' she said.
   NOW, the nation's largest women's rights organization, has been
a major influence in Democratic politics and was a factor in the
selection of <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> as <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>'s running mate in
the <DATE>1984</DATE> presidential race. The ticket later was defeated by the
largest margin in the history of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> presidential races.
   <PERSON>Ms. Yard</PERSON> said the group plans to introduce a resolution calling
on <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> to heed their advice on the vice presidential choice.
The NOW president did not provide a date for the resolution, but
the group is holding its national conference in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> this week.
   Dukakis is currently considering potential running mates.
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, runner-up to the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> governor in the delegate
race, has said he has earned the right to be offered the No. 2
spot, but <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> has not made any commitment.
   Yard also charged that Democratic leaders have tried to keep NOW
out of the <DATE>1988</DATE> election.
   ``They say they don't want the party captive to special
interests,'' she said. ``I don't know how they can call the
nation's largest group of voters a special interest.''
   There are 10 million more women registered to vote than men, she
said.
   The NOW president also said the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> could lose the
women's vote and the <DATE>1988</DATE> presidential election if it doesn't pay
more attention to women's issues.
   Yard warned that millions of women would vote Republican if the
<ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> is perceived as caring more than the Democrats about women.
   ``Even though their platform is a disaster, they'll get votes
because they're seriously considering a woman as a vice
presidential candidate,'' <PERSON>Yard</PERSON> said of the Republicans.
   ``Everything depends on who you showcase at the convention,''
she said.
   <PERSON>Elizabeth Dole</PERSON>, the former transportation secretary, is
considered a candidate for the No. 2 spot on the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> ticket that
will be headed by all-but-certain nominee <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>.
   Selection of <PERSON>Mrs. Dole</PERSON> as a running mate could hand <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> the
presidency, <PERSON>Yard</PERSON> said. <PERSON>Mrs. Dole</PERSON> is the wife of <PERSON>Kansas Sen. Bob
Dole</PERSON> who battled <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> unsuccessfully for the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> presidential
nomination.
   NOW calculates that <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>'s apparent early lead over <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
could disappear if he loses a significant portion of the women's
vote. National polls indicate <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is running significantly behind
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> among women while running about even among men.
   ``It's not the time for the Democrats to send signals that they
will in any way deny the importance of women's issues,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880712-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-12-88 1209EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p PM-Ferraro-Women 1stLd-Writethru a0505 07-12 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ferraro-Women, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0505,450</SECOND>
<NOTE>EDs: New in first 5 grafs with Ferraro reax to Bentsen. Edits for
transition and picks up 6th graf pvs bgng: `Had I ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, who four years ago became
the first woman on a major party's national ticket, said <DATE>today</DATE> she
was ``delighted'' with <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>' plans to name <PERSON>Texas Sen.
Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> as his Democratic running mate.
   She said that had there been enough women in political office to
provide <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> with a good choice for a female running mate she
would have been disappointed at his choice of a man.
   ``But because we don't have a woman in that spot, I am not
(disappointed),'' she said in a telephone interview from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>, part of the losing Democratic ticket with <PERSON>Walter
Mondale</PERSON> in <DATE>1984</DATE>, said <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> ``has been fine on issues that I and
many women care about and in addition to that he's going to be a
very strong help to the ticket, rounding it out beautifully so that
with a Democrat in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> it's going to make a difference
for the women in this country.''
   ``I'm delighted. I think it's an indication that Governor
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> intends to run a strong national campaign. I think he's
going to go down <LOCATION>South</LOCATION> and seriously battle the Republicans for
those votes that should be ours based upon the conditions facing
this country,'' she said.
   Earlier, <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Today</DATE> that there were not enough
women in positions from which national offices are traditionally
chosen _ the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and statehouses _ to provide
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> with a good choice. She said no women currently in elected
office meet <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' need of a candidate strong on foreign policy
experience who will also give him geographic balance.
   She said <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> ``does not have those credentials that,
politically, <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> needs in his vice president.''
   ``Had I not been a woman _ and I'm the first one to say it _ I
probably would not have been chosen,'' she told the newspaper. ``In
<DATE>1984</DATE> ... it was time to remove this final barrier from women's
achieving political power.''
   She said her candidacy in <DATE>1984</DATE> and <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s campaigns are
expanding participation in the political process.
   ``Between <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s campaign this year and <DATE>1984</DATE>, we as a nation
said, `Enough already, we're going to let everybody have a chance
to participate.' That's a big thing nobody can take away,'' she
said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>, 52, said she also has no bitterness over a national
profile that brought harsh scrutiny of her family and criminal
investigations of her husband. Her son was convicted of a drug
charge this year.
   ``<DATE>1984</DATE> was an incredible opportunity for me. That doesn't lead
one to be bitter. I genuinely feel my husband and son were singled
out. That doesn't make us bitter,'' she said. ``I'm not going to
let that happen to me.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900604-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-04-90 2055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-CuomoNominated     06-04 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cuomo Nominated,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>New York Democrats Nominate Cuomo for Third Term</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARC HUMBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON> was nominated <DATE>Monday</DATE> to run
for a third term, but some at the state Democratic convention
wondered if he'd serve out the term if re-elected or take a run at
the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   With the convention band breaking into ``I Love <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,'' the
57-year-old governor was nominated by acclamation.
   Cuomo, considered a potential <DATE>1992</DATE> Democratic presidential
candidate was scheduled to address the delegates <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Last week, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Republicans chose <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> economist and
businessman <PERSON>Pierre Rinfret</PERSON>, a political unknown, to challenge <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON>.
   Making appearances at the convention were <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>David
Dinkins</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sen. Daniel Patrick Moynihan</PERSON> and former vice presidential
candidate <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, who spoke out for abortion rights.
   The former <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION> congresswoman who ran on the <DATE>1984</DATE> Democratic
presidential ticket with <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON> is considering a <DATE>1992</DATE> run
for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> seat currently held by Republican <PERSON>Alfonse
D'Amato</PERSON>.
   Another speaker was actor <PERSON>Christopher Reeve</PERSON>, who pressed for
greater efforts to clean up the environment.
   Most speakers stressed the party's goal of claiming majority
control of the Republican-dominated state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   Delegates nominated Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Stan Lundine</PERSON> to run again with
<PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON>. If re-elected, it would be <PERSON>Lundine</PERSON>'s second term as
lieutenant governor.
   The governor, refusing to rule out a possible bid for the
presidency in <DATE>1992</DATE>, announced his re-election plans <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. He
considered a presidential campaign in <DATE>1988</DATE>, but ultimately bowed out.
   <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> said Democrats nationwide favor <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON>.
   ``They believe that he can be the person who can carry the
Democrats to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1992</DATE>,'' she said of party followers
she's met across the country.
 
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900822-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-22-90 1348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Zaccaro     08-22 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Zaccaro,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>Geraldine Ferraro's Son Seeks Remainder of Probation Dismissed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RUTLAND, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>John Zaccaro Jr.</PERSON> has been a model
probationer and should be released early from probation on a
cocaine-selling conviction, his lawyer argued today.
was convicted two years ago of selling one-quarter gram of cocaine
for <MONEY>$25</MONEY> to an undercover officer while a student at <ORGANIZATION>Middlebury
College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   Zaccaro's attorney, <PERSON>Charles Tetzlaff</PERSON> argued that <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> should
be released from probation early because he is beginning his first
semester as a law student at <ORGANIZATION>Catholic University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, and would have to return monthly to <LOCATION>New York state</LOCATION>, which is
supervising his probation.
   The <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> won't accept any probation cases unless
there is less than a year in the term.
   <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> has been serving a sentence of one to five years on
probation. But <PERSON>Tetzlaff</PERSON> said that under <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> state regulations,
<PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> would be eligible for release from probation in <DATE>December</DATE>.
   Addison County States Attorney <PERSON>John Quinn</PERSON> argued that <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON>
should be supervised for at least another semester because he was
arrested while in a college atmosphere and now he is back in that
atmosphere.
   Vermont District <PERSON>Judge Francis McCaffery</PERSON> made no immediate
decision on the request to dismiss <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> from probation.
   <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> served three months of his sentence under house arrest
at a <LOCATION>Burlington</LOCATION> luxury apartment whose amenities were ridiculed by
some who argued the former congresswoman's son received special
treatment from the courts.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880616-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-06-16-88 0136EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-Dukakis-WomanVeep Bjt   06-16 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dukakis-Woman Veep, Bjt,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prospects Of Female Running Mate For Dukakis Appear Dim</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONALD M. ROTHBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> begins the process of
selecting a Democratic vice presidential nominee, the surest bet in
politics is that his choice will be a man.
   Not even the women who worked so hard four years ago to get
<PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> on the Democratic ticket expect <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> to follow
<PERSON>Walter F. Mondale</PERSON>'s history-making example.
   ``It certainly isn't the top-of-line discussion it was in
<DATE>1984</DATE>,'' said <PERSON>Joanne Howes</PERSON>, a political consultant and director of
the non-partisan <ORGANIZATION>Women's Vote Project</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Is that a priority in his campaign this year, or in the
party?'' said <PERSON>Irene Natividad</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>National Women's
Political Caucus</ORGANIZATION>. ``It doesn't seem like it.''
   So when <PERSON>Paul Brountas</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> lawyer who is heading the
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> search for a running mate came to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> to talk vice
presidential politics, the big names on his calling list were all
male, names like <PERSON>John Glenn</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sam Nunn</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON>.
   He did pay a call on <PERSON>Sen. Barbara Mikulski</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>. But now
in her second year as a senator, she is on no one's list of vice
presidential prospects.
   Missing from <PERSON>Brountas</PERSON>' list was Rep. <PERSON>Pat Schroeder</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>,
who came close to running for president and is the most credible
vice presidential prospect among Democratic women.
   Three women often are mentioned as potential running mates for
Dole</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sen. Nancy Kassebaum</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and former <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> Ambassador
<PERSON>Jeane Kirkpatrick</PERSON>. This is the party that turned its back on the
Equal Rights Amendment and demands that its national candidates
take strong stands against abortion.
   Analysts talk of a ``gender gap'' that favors Democrats, the
fact that a far higher percentage of women than men support
Democratic candidates.
   Yet, this election year, the likely women vice presidential
candidates are Republicans, not Democrats.
   ``I think the major reason is obvious,'' said <PERSON>Celinda Lake</PERSON>, a
senior associated with <ORGANIZATION>The Analysis Group</ORGANIZATION>, a Democratic polling
organization. ``There are lots of ways in which the Democrats are
turning away from the '84 experience.
   ``And one of the ways, which I think is incorrect, is they think
they would not benefit from nominating a woman as the vice
president.''
   The ``'84 experience,'' of course, was the fact the
<ORGANIZATION>Mondale-Ferraro</ORGANIZATION> ticket was beaten in 49 of 50 states as President
<PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> received an estimated <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT> of the women's vote.
   ``I also think,'' said <PERSON>Lake</PERSON> ``there is somewhat of a shortage of
women who are both ready and willing. ... Because the Democrats
have been out of office for eight years, we don't have the women in
the administrative pipeline.''
   That view was echoed by others, including <PERSON>Joanne Symons</PERSON>, a
political consultant who worked on Rep. <PERSON>Richard Gephardt</PERSON>'s
presidential campaign.
   ``There are not enough (Democratic) women in the pool,'' she
said, because a Republican president has been filling Cabinet
positions the <DATE>past seven and a half years</DATE>.
   Lake also cited an ambition factor.
   She listed Gov. <PERSON>Madeleine Kunin</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>, along with <PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Mikulski</PERSON> as Democratic women who have the stature to be vice
presidential candidates and said, ``I don't think they want it.
They want to be No. 1, not No. 2.''
   <PERSON>Howes</PERSON> said, ``The real goal is to be prepared in the <DATE>1990s</DATE> for a
woman to be ready to be president of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and to run
for president of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and to win.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-3092</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CIPCHAGMFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920915
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 SEP 92 / NY Senate race sets new standards in seediness
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALAN FRIEDMAN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
EVERYONE knows that <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> politics can be among the roughest and meanest
in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>. But even by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> standards the four-way <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Senate</ORGANIZATION>
primary race - culminating in today's vote - will go down as one of the most
vitriolic campaigns in many years.
The winner of this melee will challenge <PERSON>Mr Alfonse 'Al' D'Amato</PERSON>, a
right-wing politician from suburban <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>, who has thus far tramped
about the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> citing the fact that he has been rebuked rather than censured
by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> ethics committee as proof that he has been exonerated of past
influence-peddling charges.
<PERSON>Mr D'Amato</PERSON> is considered vulnerable this year, not least because of his
chequered record. But the Democrats have engaged in so much mud-slinging
that there is unlikely to be much high ground left to be gained by his
opponent.
Although her substantial early lead has nearly evaporated, the front-runner
among the Democrats is 56-year-old Ms <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, the former
congresswomen from the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION> who in the <DATE>1984</DATE> presidential election served
as <PERSON>Mr Walter Mondale</PERSON>'s controversial running mate.
Ms <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>'s troubles first began during the <DATE>1984</DATE> campaign when allegations
were made about the legality of her husband's business dealings. He pleaded
guilty to a misdemeanour after the campaign.
An unabashed supporter of capital punishment, <PERSON>Ms Ferraro</PERSON> styles herself as a
no-nonsense feminist with a working-class background.
It is the negative campaigning of her rivals that has raised the possibility
that she may not make it after all. Advertisments by rivals have accused <PERSON>Ms
Ferraro</PERSON>'s landlord husband of ties to the <LOCATION>Mafia</LOCATION> and have repeatedly alleged
he rented a house to a child pornographer.
Ms <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>'s keenest challenger, <ORGANIZATION>New York State</ORGANIZATION> attorney-general <PERSON>Mr Robert
Abrams</PERSON>, has not been hesitant to make use of the controversy. Neither has Ms
<PERSON>Elizabeth Holtzman</PERSON>, a former congresswomen and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s current
comptroller.
Oddly enough the only candidate who has not attacked <PERSON>Ms Ferraro</PERSON> over ethics
is the normally demagogic Rev <PERSON>Al Sharpton</PERSON>. He arrived at a televised debate
last week with a symbolic bucket of mud for his colleagues. The debate among
the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Democratic primary candidates became so heated that the moderator
kept intervening to say: 'Ladies, ladies, ladies, <PERSON>Ms Holtzman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ms Ferraro</PERSON>. .
.'
Issues have thus taken a back seat to insults, which means that even if Ms
<PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> does win today, she is unlikely to be the unblemished sort of
challenger who can make much of the various investigations of <PERSON>Mr D'Amato</PERSON>.
The seediness of this year's <ORGANIZATION>New York Senate</ORGANIZATION> race looks set to continue.
<PERSON>Jurek Martin</PERSON> adds from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>; Another race of interest concerns
Congressman <PERSON>Stephen Solarz</PERSON>, the Democratic foreign policy expert.
His old safe <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> seat in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> has been redrawn  -
with the purpose of promoting Hispanic representation in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> - and he
may be vulnerable to the challenge of Ms <PERSON>Elizabeth Colon</PERSON>, an advocate of
Puerto Rican interests.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 8
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890814-0180 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-14-89 1029EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv26   08-14 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv26,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Saturday, Aug. 26</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 26</DATE>, the <DATE>238th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 127
   Today's highlight in history:
   Twenty-five years ago, on <DATE>Aug. 26, 1964</DATE>, President <PERSON>Lyndon B.
Johnson</PERSON> was nominated for a term of office in his own right at the
appeared before the delegates to announce he had chosen as his
running-mate <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> Sen. <PERSON>Hubert H. Humphrey</PERSON>, who was also
nominated that night, by acclamation.
   On this date:
   In 55 <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>, Roman forces under <PERSON>Julius Caesar</PERSON> invaded <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1847</DATE>, <LOCATION>Liberia</LOCATION> was proclaimed an independent republic.
<LOCATION>Council Bluffs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1883</DATE>, the island volcano Krakatoa began erupting with
increasingly large explosions.
guaranteeing American women the right to vote, was declared in
effect.
   In <DATE>1933</DATE>, <PERSON>Helen Hull Jacobs</PERSON> captured the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Lawn Tennis
Association</ORGANIZATION> singles title when <ORGANIZATION>Helen Wills Moody</ORGANIZATION> defaulted in the
third set because of back and hip pain.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, the first televised major league baseball games were
shown on station W2XBS _ a double-header between the <ORGANIZATION>Cincinnati
Reds</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Brooklyn Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Ebbets Field</LOCATION>. (The Reds won the
first game, 5-2; the Dodgers won the second game, 6-1.)
   In <DATE>1957</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> announced it had successfully tested
an intercontinental ballistic missile.
   In <DATE>1961</DATE>, the official <ORGANIZATION>International Hockey Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> opened
in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1972</DATE>, the Summer Olympics opened in <LOCATION>Munich</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1974</DATE>, <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>, the first man to fly solo, non-stop
across the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, died at his home in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> at the age of 72.
   In <DATE>1978</DATE>, <PERSON>Cardinal Albino Luciani</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION> was elected the 264th
Pope of the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> following the death of <PERSON>Paul VI</PERSON>.
The new pontiff took the name Pope <PERSON>John Paul I.</PERSON>
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, Soviet President <PERSON>Yuri V. Andropov</PERSON> offered to
``liquidate'' his country's medium-range missiles as part of a
superpower agreement on arms reductions.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, West German Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> said his country
would destroy its 72 Pershing I-A rockets if <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>
were to scrap all their intermediate-range nuclear weapons.
   Ten years ago: An <ORGANIZATION>Aeroflot</ORGANIZATION> jetliner remained parked at <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kennedy International Airport</LOCATION> for a third day, with <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
officials continuing to demand an interview with Soviet ballerina
<PERSON>Lyudmila Vlasova</PERSON>, whose husband, <PERSON>Alexander Godunov</PERSON>, had defected.
   Five years ago: Democratic vice-presidential nominee <PERSON>Geraldine
Ferraro</PERSON> celebrated her 49th birthday by noting it was also the 64th
anniversary of women's suffrage and urging women voters to make her
the nation's first female vice president.
   One year ago: Republican <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> denounced Democrat <PERSON>Michael
Dukakis</PERSON>' criticism of <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration's drug policies as ``an
insult,'' one day after the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> governor had said <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
dealings with Panamanian Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Noriega</PERSON> were ``criminal.''
   Today's birthdays: Former Attorney General <PERSON>William French Smith</PERSON>
is 72. Washington Post executive editor <PERSON>Benjamin C. Bradlee</PERSON> is 68.
Author <PERSON>Ben J. Wattenberg</PERSON> is 56. Former Democratic vice-presidential
nominee <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> is 54. Singer <PERSON>Valerie Simpson</PERSON> is 41.
   Thought for today: ``Spiritually a woman is better off if she
cannot be taken for granted.'' _ <PERSON>Germaine Greer</PERSON>, Australian
feminist author (<DATE>1939</DATE>- ).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881115-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-15-88 0131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Reagan-WomanPresident     11-15 0273</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Reagan-Woman President,270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Says Woman President `Inevitable'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> told a group of schoolchildren
that he believes it's ``inevitable'' that a woman will one day be
president, most likely after first serving as vice president.
   The president's comments came during a question-and-answer
session with junior and senior high school students from four
Washington-area schools.
   ``As a matter of fact, the statesman in the world that I have
met, that I respect the most, is the prime minister of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON>, and she's done a remarkable job for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>,''
the president said.
   Reagan will play host to <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> for an official visit and
state dinner at the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> later this week. The British prime
minister has been his closest friend and ally in the <ORGANIZATION>Western
Alliance</ORGANIZATION> during his nearly eight years in office.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> said the idea of a woman president would take ``a little
getting used to on the part of some people. But I think it's
inevitable that in this country there will be a woman president
because they've come up in so many different fields.''
   He added: ``It's just my feeling that probably, rather than one
of them just entering the fray to run for president to begin with,
that maybe it would probably start with one of them, as we did in
the election in <DATE>1984</DATE>, ... running for vice president. She didn't
make it, but that might be the start of it, and I welcome it.''
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> was referring to then-Rep. <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>, who
had the second spot on the Democratic ticket headed by former Vice
President <PERSON>Walter F. Mondale</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880816-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-16-88 1403EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Zaccaro     08-16 0197</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zaccaro,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ferraro Won't Apologize For Son's Luxury Digs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former vice presidential candidate <PERSON>Geraldine
Ferraro</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> her son is not living a life of luxury _
despite his <MONEY>$1,500-a-month</MONEY> apartment _ while serving a four-month
sentence for cocaine possession.
   <PERSON>John Zaccaro</PERSON> is staying in a <LOCATION>Burlington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>, hotel-style
apartment, which has room service and cable TV, as part of a
``house arrest'' program, aimed at easing prison overcrowding.
   ``I go up for weekends and come home and I'm crazy,'' <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON>
said. ``It's better than being in jail, but ... he's by himself, he
does his own cooking.''
<DATE>1984</DATE>, denied reports that <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> has a servant.
   ``It's not true,'' she said. ``They give you clean linens once a
week and they vacuum.''
   ``We can't apologize for it _ we had to get him housing,''
<PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> told the <ORGANIZATION>New York Post</ORGANIZATION>. ``I won't apologize for it.''
   <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> was convicted in <DATE>April</DATE> of selling a quarter-gram of
cocaine to an undercover officer while a student at <ORGANIZATION>Middlebury
College</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>. He was sentenced to one to five years in prison,
with all but four months suspended.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880802-0105 </DOCNO>
<HL> Remembrances of Things Past: Never Say Unelectable </HL>
<AUTHOR> Vermont Royster </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<G> EXE </G>
<TEXT>
   As I wandered around the floor of the <DATE>1984</DATE> Democratic convention, the recurring question seemed to be whether a woman could ever be elected president, or even vice president, that office only a heart's beat from the presidency. 

   This year I was a stay-at-home, but judging from the TV coverage the question was whether a black could so aspire. 
Frequently, the question was put bluntly. 
Was the fact that the Rev. <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> is black what barred him as Gov. <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>'s running mate? 

   In neither case were the questions really answered. 
<PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> was nominated for vice president in <DATE>1984</DATE> but the ticket led by <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON> was defeated. 
<PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>'s presence on that ticket may have had something to do with it, not just because she was a woman but because of some cloudy matters surrounding her conduct as a congresswoman and her husband's legal problems. 
Besides, that year the Democrats were up against <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>, then at the height of his political popularity; any Democratic ticket would have lost. 

   As for <PERSON>Mr. Jackson</PERSON>, there were reasons other than race why he was passed over. 
For one, <PERSON>Mr. Dukakis</PERSON> needed a candidate from <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> -- no Democrat has won the presidency without the Lone Star State -- and <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bensten</PERSON> has once before defeated Vice President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and is a proven vote-getter in that state. 

   Moreover, as Mayor <PERSON>Andrew Young</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, himself a black, pointed out, <PERSON>Mr. Jackson</PERSON> for all his charisma has never held a public office or even run for one before. 
<PERSON>Mr. Young</PERSON> thought that a lacuna in the <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> record. 

   Anyway, the question of a future woman or black as a viable candidate for national office remains moot and will be debatable endlessly. 
For the moment, white males still hold their historical monopoly on both the presidency and vice presidency. 

   I have no crystal ball, but as a senior citizen -- a very senior citizen -- I have a long memory. 
And I remember when other political figures were supposedly unelectable to our highest offices for reasons unrelated to either their sex or their race. 

   From almost the founding of the Republic it was believed that no Roman Catholic could be elected in this basically Protestant country. 
That conventional wisdom seemed borne out by the defeat of <PERSON>Al Smith</PERSON>, the Democratic candidate in <DATE>1928</DATE>. 
Gov. <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> won only 87 electoral votes against <PERSON>Herbert Hoover</PERSON>, and his Catholicism certainly played a part in this. 
There was much dirty propaganda that if Gov. <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> were elected, the pope would sit at his right hand in the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION>. 

   But <PERSON>Al Smith</PERSON> was also defeated because he was a premature "wet," favoring the repeal of the Prohibition amendment, and mainly because his opponent was the highly respected <PERSON>Mr. Hoover</PERSON>. 
Because of the Depression that followed, many have forgotten that in <DATE>1928</DATE> <PERSON>Mr. Hoover</PERSON> was one of our most highly regarded public figures and had been so for 20 years, since his masterly handling of the world relief problem after World War I. 

   <DATE>Thirty years later</DATE>, <PERSON>John Kennedy</PERSON>, a devoted <PERSON>Roman Catholic</PERSON>, was elected president with a large share of the votes of the majority Protestants. 
So much for that "conventional wisdom." 

   For a hundred years after our Civil War there was another bit of conventional wisdom: that no Southerner could be elected president. 

   But then came <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>, a Southerner born and bred, who used the governorship of <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> as his springboard to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>. 
He didn't win by much, but he won with a lot of Yankee votes. 
Once more the conventional wisdom got its comeuppance. 

   So I shouldn't be surprised when the day comes that we have a woman or a black (or both) on a winning national ticket. 
Indeed, it may come in the time of many now living and will not seem any more of a "big deal" than having a Southerner or a Catholic in high office. 

   But when that day does come I don't think either will be in the mold of <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> or <PERSON>Mr. Jackson</PERSON>. 
We have long grown accustomed to senators and even governors who are women, and there are many blacks today not only in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> but as mayors of some of our biggest cities, including <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>. 

   These people haven't won their offices by being stridently "feminists" or narrowly black spokesmen. 
They won by exhibiting the same broad regard for their whole constituency as have successful white, male politicians and by a regard for the interests of a broad spectrum of voters. 
They have also learned, often the hard way, how to deal with the problems of government that confront every political leader. 
Neither <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> nor <PERSON>Mr. Jackson</PERSON> fit that mold. 

   <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> had an appealing personality but she floundered when discussing the issues, foreign and domestic, of her time. 
<PERSON>Mr. Jackson</PERSON> is, without doubt, charismatic in person and a stem-winding orator. 
But if that was all that was required we would have had <PERSON>William Jennings Bryan</PERSON> for president in <DATE>1896</DATE> or <DATE>1900</DATE>, when both times he raised the Democratic delegates to a high pitch of enthusiasm. 

   <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> did much the same at this year's convention with a moving sermon, just as he had often done on the campaign trail. 
But a sermon it was, long on idealism and short on ways and means to achieve any of his desires. 
You could applaud the rhetoric but not the political program because you couldn't find one. 

   The future presidential nominee of a woman or a black will seem little different from past or present ones except for their sex or the color of their skin. 
Like their white, male predecessors they will have a record in public service to be examined by the electorate. 
They will doubtless be middle-aged and, whatever their origins, they will share the manner and values of the middle class that embraces the great majority of our voters. 

   When such a candidate, female or black, will make it to the White House I have no idea. 
All I can say is that a remembrance of things past convinces me never to say never in American politics. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Royster</PERSON> is editor emeritus of the Journal. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870223-0020 </DOCNO>
<HL> U.S. Will Not Sue Ferraro,
Spouse on Disclosure Issue</HL>
<DD> 02/23/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS) </IN>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> said it dropped the idea of possible court action against former <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> or her husband, <PERSON>John Zaccaro</PERSON>, in connection with federal financial-disclosure statements. 


   Last <DATE>May</DATE>, department officials announced the close of a lengthy criminal investigation of the matter, which began in <DATE>summer 1984</DATE>, without prosecuting <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> or her spouse. 
But at the time, government attorneys held open the possibility of filing a civil suit over <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON>'s failure to disclose her husband's finances on annual federal financial reports while she served in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Over the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, a <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman said the decision came after government attorneys concluded that they didn't have sufficient evidence to show that the former Democratic lawmaker knowingly or willfully violated federal disclosure laws. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880213-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-13-88 1657EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Women-Constitution     02-13 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Women-Constitution,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Women Can Ensure Constitution's `Equality' At Ballot Box, Group
Told</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some 1,500 women who spent two days discussing
how they could secure the Constitution's ``blessings of liberty''
were urged to become more active in politics and to run for
elective office.
   It was no accident that the event was sandwiched between <DATE>last
week</DATE>'s <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> presidential caucuses and <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>
primary, said <PERSON>Linda Kurtz Hallenborg</PERSON>, a member of the symposium's
executive committee.
   ``This is a way to highlight the fact that we need to get more
women involved in politics,'' she said in an interview <DATE>Friday</DATE>. ``We
need to make it clear to the presidential candidates that we make
up <PERCENT>53 percent</PERCENT> of the electorate, and women's issues need to be
taken seriously.''
   Those attending the symposium included <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court
Justice Sandra Day O'Connor</ORGANIZATION>; <DATE>1984</DATE> vice presidential candidate
<PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>; <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON>, widow of slain civil rights
leader <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON>; syndicated newspaper columnist <PERSON>Erma
Bombeck</PERSON>; and former <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> congresswoman <PERSON>Bella Abzug</PERSON>.
   The two-day symposium on ``Women and the Constitution'' at the
<ORGANIZATION>Carter Presidential Center</ORGANIZATION> was convened by former first ladies
<PERSON>Rosalynn Carter</PERSON> and Lady Bird <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>.
   In speeches and seminars, women who attended the event that
ended <DATE>Friday</DATE> heard that political power could be their best hope to
achieve equality in other fields besides politics.
   They also heard that the Constitution, as originally drawn up
200 years ago, deserved criticism as unfair to women and minorities.
   ``Our criticism of the unamended Constitution is not intended to
be divisive,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON>. ``Some people apparently feel that
blacks and women should join in an uncritical celebration of a
document that protected the slave trade and denied women their
democratic rights.''
   Sixty-eight years after the ratification of the <DATE>19th</DATE> Amendment,
which guaranteed women the right to vote, women make up just <PERCENT>14
percent</PERCENT> of the higher statewide political officeholders around the
country, according to the <ORGANIZATION>National Women's Political Caucus</ORGANIZATION>.
   There are 23 women in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House</ORGANIZATION> and two in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. Two
women are governors of states.
   Both <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON> urged women to run for office and
continue working in other campaigns. <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> described a
``ripple effect'' that she discovered when her <DATE>1984</DATE> campaign
generated thousands of letters from women whom her candidacy had
inspired.
   ``It's the young woman writing after the election, `I've decided
to go to medical school because of you,''' <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> said. ``It's
the 7-year-old writing from her school in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, `Someday I'm
going to run for president.'
   ``If you don't run, you can't win.''
   While <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> spoke of a future in which women will share
equally in the political landscape, <PERSON>Ms. Hallenborg</PERSON> said the present
administration _ and a return to traditionalism by some women _ has
slowed down the women's movement.
   ``I think the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> presidency has been extremely detrimental
to the progress we have made,'' she said. ``Every president up to
<PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> made progress in bringing women into power.''
   The <DATE>1988</DATE> elections represent an opportunity for women to
reassert themselves at the ballot box, and the outcome could
determine whether eight years of Republican conservatism has
splintered the women's equality movement for good, <PERSON>Ms. Hallenborg</PERSON>
said.
   ``This is a clarion call that women need to rise up and be
counted in the political process,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880219-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-19-88 1235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     02-19 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0591</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EXETER, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scores of jostling and shouting
photographers besieged <PERSON>Princess Elena</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Exeter
University</ORGANIZATION>, where she is studying on a teaching fellowship.
   Students and staff watched with a mixture of amusement and alarm
<DATE>Friday</DATE> as photographers and TV crews closed in on the 24-year-old
daughter of King <PERSON>Juan Carlos</PERSON> and <PERSON>Queen Sophia</PERSON>.
   But the princess appeared unruffled and even shook hands with
some of the photographers who had converged on the campus in
southwestern <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Elena</PERSON>, a teacher and friend of Princess <PERSON>Diana</PERSON>, is on a six-month
teaching fellowship, working with children with special learning
needs.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>COLUMBUS, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scores of jostling and shouting
photographers besieged <PERSON>Princess Elena</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Exeter
University</ORGANIZATION>, where she is studying on a teaching fellowship.
   Students and staff watched with a mixture of amusement and alarm
<DATE>Friday</DATE> as photographers and TV crews closed in on the 24-year-old
daughter of King <PERSON>Juan Carlos</PERSON> and <PERSON>Queen Sophia</PERSON>.
   But the princess appeared unruffled and even shook hands with
some of the photographers who had converged on the campus in
southwestern <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Elena</PERSON>, a teacher and friend of Princess <PERSON>Diana</PERSON>, is on a six-month
teaching fellowship, working with children with special learning
needs.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>COLORADO SPRINGS, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scores of jostling and shouting
photographers besieged <PERSON>Princess Elena</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Exeter
University</ORGANIZATION>, where she is studying on a teaching fellowship.
   Students and staff watched with a mixture of amusement and alarm
<DATE>Friday</DATE> as photographers and TV crews closed in on the 24-year-old
daughter of King <PERSON>Juan Carlos</PERSON> and <PERSON>Queen Sophia</PERSON>.
   But the princess appeared unruffled and even shook hands with
some of the photographers who had converged on the campus in
southwestern <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Elena</PERSON>, a teacher and friend of Princess <PERSON>Diana</PERSON>, is on a six-month
teaching fellowship, working with children with special learning
needs.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scores of jostling and shouting
photographers besieged <PERSON>Princess Elena</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Exeter
University</ORGANIZATION>, where she is studying on a teaching fellowship.
   Students and staff watched with a mixture of amusement and alarm
<DATE>Friday</DATE> as photographers and TV crews closed in on the 24-year-old
daughter of King <PERSON>Juan Carlos</PERSON> and <PERSON>Queen Sophia</PERSON>.
   But the princess appeared unruffled and even shook hands with
some of the photographers who had converged on the campus in
southwestern <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Elena</PERSON>, a teacher and friend of Princess <PERSON>Diana</PERSON>, is on a six-month
teaching fellowship, working with children with special learning
needs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880616-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-16-88 1621EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Zaccaro Bjt   06-16 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zaccaro, Bjt,0656</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zaccaro Sentenced to Four Months for Cocaine Conviction</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos RUT2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANICA KIRKA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RUTLAND, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
candidate <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> was sentenced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to four months
in jail for selling <MONEY>$25</MONEY> worth of cocaine to an undercover police
officer.
   <PERSON>John Zaccaro Jr.</PERSON>, 24, also was ordered to pay a <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY> fine and
perform 300 hours of community service.
   ``We are obviously very disappointed by the harshness of the
sentence,'' <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> said, noting that other defendants in <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>
drug cases have received lighter penalties. She said the conviction
would be appealled.
   During his sentencing hearing, <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> told <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> District
<PERSON>Judge Francis McCaffrey</PERSON> in a shaky voice that he has sworn off
drugs.
   ``I'd like to make a personal pledge to you and my family that I
will never again be involved in drugs or any illegality,'' he said.
   Zaccaro's attorney, <PERSON>Charles Tetzlaff</PERSON>, asked <PERSON>McCaffrey</PERSON> to accept
a probation officer's recommendation of a suspended sentence,
probation and community service.
   But <PERSON>McCaffrey</PERSON> told <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON>, ``I can't in good conscience
sentence you without any time to serve.'' Zaccaro faced a maximum
of five years in prison and a <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> fine.
   <ORGANIZATION>Addison County State</ORGANIZATION>'s Attorney <PERSON>John Quinn</PERSON> said he was pleased
with the sentence. He denied treating the case differently.
   ``This was a case in which we caught someone red-handed, and I
mean red-handed,'' <PERSON>Quinn</PERSON> said. ``I felt that it was important for
the court to say it doesn't matter who you are. If you commit a
drug offense in the state of <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>, you'll be treated with great
severity.''
   McCaffrey suggested the jail time be served through the
<ORGANIZATION>Chittenden Community Correctional Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Burlington</LOCATION> so that
<PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> could participate in a special corrections program that
allows him to be kept under house arrest.
   <PERSON>Quinn</PERSON> said <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> would have to be accepted into the program.
   During the sentencing, <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> stood stoically beside his
father, <PERSON>John Zaccaro</PERSON>, and his mother, who was <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>'s
running mate on the Democratic ticket in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> was arrested in <DATE>February 1986</DATE> and convicted by a
<ORGANIZATION>District Court</ORGANIZATION> jury <DATE>last April</DATE>. He was arrested after selling
one-quarter gram of cocaine to undercover agent <PERSON>Laura Manning</PERSON> while
he was attending <ORGANIZATION>Middlebury College</ORGANIZATION>, about 30 miles north of
<LOCATION>Rutland</LOCATION>.
   Manning testified that she went to <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON>'s off-campus home,
where <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> produced a tray of cocaine packets from underneath
the living room sofa. <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON> was arrested that night outside the
restaurant where he worked.
   Tetzlaff argued that police used <PERSON>Manning</PERSON> as bait to snare him
during a college party weekend. The prosecution denied the charge.
   At the sentencing hearing, a tearful <PERSON>Ferraro</PERSON> had asked <PERSON>McCaffrey</PERSON>
not to treat her son differently than any other person convicted of
selling <MONEY>$25</MONEY> worth of cocaine. She also said <PERSON>Zaccaro</PERSON>'s arrest and
conviction have taken a heavy toll on her family and son.
   ``He doesn't go to church with us,'' she said. ``He doesn't want
to be seen with us. It's not because he's ashamed of us. It's
because he's ashamed of what he's done.''
