<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890522-0281 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-22-89 1344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-MisnamedCemetery Adv30   05-22 0920</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Misnamed Cemetery, Adv 30,0947</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tue AMs, May 30 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Expert Says Ancient Egyptian Burial Ground `Misunderstood, Misnamed'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VALLEY OF THE QUEENS, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This quiet, bone-dry ravine
of death, overshadowed since antiquity by the Valley of the Kings
just over the hills, slowly is shedding its mystery.
   And with the mystery, its name.
   Ancients called the valley Ta-Set Neferu, the <ORGANIZATION>Place of Beauty</ORGANIZATION>.
To the Arabs it was Gates of the Ladies. Egyptologists and
guidebooks perpetuate the homage to entombed royal women: the
Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>.
   ``It's wrong. This valley has been misunderstood and misnamed by
all Egyptologists,'' said <PERSON>Christian LeBlanc</PERSON>, field director for a
continuing 17-year French-Egyptian project to record and study its
history.
   ``We should be calling it the Valley of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Children</ORGANIZATION>. They
were here first, but the valley became tied only to the queens and
named by tradition rather than history.''
   Season after archaeological season, <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON>'s team has scoured
the sloping, dusty hillsides dotted with cave-like tombs to find
the origins of a sequence of burials that would last almost 2,000
years. Tombs were used repeatedly, as late as the Christian era
when pharaonic designs sometimes were plastered over and crosses
painted on.
   <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said the first burials were princes and princesses of
ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s 18th dynasty, a 243-year renaissance when, after a
period of decline, pharaohs and their kin once again lived and died
like kings.
   That dynasty ended in <DATE>1307</DATE> B.C., and Ramses I, founder of the
19th dynasty, changed tradition by burying his queen Sat-Re here.
   <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said it's unclear why he did or why the practice
continued. In addition to queens, royal children still were buried
here, and concubines who cared for them and pharaohs' mothers.
   Paintings in some of the tombs show <PERSON>Hathor</PERSON>, the goddess of women
and love, emerging from a grotto that dominates the valley. <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON>
said perhaps this indicates that religion brought the ancients
here, because <PERSON>Hathor</PERSON>'s realm also included the cemeteries on what
is called the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION> across the <ORGANIZATION>Nile</ORGANIZATION> from present-day <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION>.
   The 18th dynasty, when the graveyard for royal children began,
was a time when queens traditionally shared their pharaoh's tombs
in the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>. Many of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s greatest rulers
were buried there, along with the young pharoah Tutankhamun, whose
treasure-filled tomb was discovered by <PERSON>Howard Carter</PERSON> in <DATE>1922</DATE>.
   That discovery brought international fame to the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the
Kings</ORGANIZATION>. Hundreds of other royals and officials also were buried on
the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION>. But to the world, the glory of the pharaohs meant
the Valley of the Kings _ not the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>, the Valley
of the Monkeys or the Tombs of the <LOCATION>Nobles</LOCATION>.
   For tourist agencies, the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION> became an
afterthought, a place to fill a half-hour after an exhausting visit
to the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>.
   When the joint expedition began, 78 burial places had been found
in the limestone hillsides enclosing the valley. Today 98 are known.
   ``We couldn't understand the cemetery before, because we were
working tomb-by-tomb,'' <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said. ``Today, we've uncovered all
the major tombs and have returned the valley to the way it would
have looked when burials began.
   ``For the first time, we can write its history.''
   As <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> talked, he and <PERSON>Fathy Hassanein</PERSON>, director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization's National Documentation Center</ORGANIZATION>,
walked through scores of excavators digging toward the valley's
bedrock. The job at hand was almost done, another tomb uncovered
from rubble that has obscured the cemetery for most of its
existence.
   An aim of the project is to restore tombs in the valley so that
more can be opened to tourists. Fewer than six are now.
   The valley's most beautiful tomb, the fabulous burial chambers
of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses II</ORGANIZATION>'s powerful queen <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>, is among those so
deteriorated that they remain off-limits. More than half its
paintings of the elaborately dressed and coiffured queen have been
destroyed by natural forces.
   <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said one source for the valley's history has been
tidbits left by workers who built and decorated the tombs. For
generations they lived in a village inside the valley. Their
records, on papyrus, provided the team not only with answers but
with mysteries.
   Workers recorded the construction of tombs for Queen Isis
<LOCATION>Nefret</LOCATION>, one of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses II</ORGANIZATION>'s many wives, and a queen named
Duat-Iny-Pet.
   <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said they might have been same person, but ``where are
they?''
   He also is intrigued by a lack of burial objects or pieces of
the queens' mummies.
   ``This is strange,'' he said. ``Did those who came afterwards
destroy them?'' He added that it could mean another royal cache
exists, perhaps mummies of queens and children.
   Typical of the tales <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> has faced in rewriting a new
history for the valley is the story of a mummified fetus inside the
tomb of 9-year-old prince Amon-Hir-Khopshef, son of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses III</ORGANIZATION>.
   Local guides tell fascinated visitors that <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON>' queen became
so distraught over the death of their son that she miscarried and
the mummies of both Amon-Hir-Khopshef and the fetus were entombed.
   The story is nonsense, <PERSON>Leblanc</PERSON> said.
   Early this century, the Italian excavator <PERSON>Ernesto Schiaparelli</PERSON>
found the fetus in a rubbish pile outside the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>.
It was <PERSON>Schiaparelli</PERSON>, not ancient priests, who placed it inside the
prince's empty sarcophagus.
   Today, the mummified fetus is so popular a tourist attraction
that it has its own tiny case.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tue AMs, May 30</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061189-0088 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 68754 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 11, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 5; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
907 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ANCIENT EGYPTIAN BURIAL GROUND IS 'MISUNDERSTOOD AND MISNAMED' 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MIMI MANN, Associated Press Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
VALLEY OF THE QUEENS, Egypt 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
This quiet, bone-dry ravine of death, overshadowed since antiquity by the 
Valley of the Kings just over the hills, slowly is shedding its mystery. 
</P>
<P>
And with the mystery, its name. 
</P>
<P>
Ancients called the valley Ta-Set Neferu, the <ORGANIZATION>Place of Beauty</ORGANIZATION>. To the Arabs it 
was Gates of the Ladies. Egyptologists and guidebooks perpetuate the homage to 
entombed royal women: the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It's wrong. This valley has been misunderstood and misnamed by all 
Egyptologists," said <PERSON>Christian LeBlanc</PERSON>, field director for a continuing 17-year 
French-Egyptian project to record and study its history. 
</P>
<P>
"We should be calling it the Valley of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Children</ORGANIZATION>. They were here 
first, but the valley became tied only to the queens and named by tradition 
rather than history." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Hillsides Scoured 
</P>
<P>
Season</ORGANIZATION> after archeological season, <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON>'s team has scoured the sloping, 
dusty hillsides dotted with cave-like tombs to find the origins of a sequence 
of burials that would last almost 2,000 years. Tombs were used repeatedly, as 
late as the Christian era when Pharaonic designs sometimes were plastered over 
and crosses painted on. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said the first burials were princes and princesses of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>18th Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>, a 243-year renaissance when, after a period of decline, Pharaohs 
and their kin once again lived and died like kings. 
</P>
<P>
That dynasty ended in <DATE>1307</DATE> B.C., and Ramses I, founder of the <ORGANIZATION>19th Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>, 
changed tradition by burying his queen Sat-Re here. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said it is unclear why he did or why the practice continued. In 
addition to queens, royal children still were buried here, and concubines who 
cared for them and Pharaohs' mothers. 
</P>
<P>
Paintings in some of the tombs show <PERSON>Hathor</PERSON>, the goddess of women and love, 
emerging from a grotto that dominates the valley. <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said perhaps this 
indicates that religion brought the ancients here, because <PERSON>Hathor</PERSON>'s realm also 
included the cemeteries on what is called the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION> across the <ORGANIZATION>Nile</ORGANIZATION> from 
present-day <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Treasure-Filled Tombs 
</P>
<P>
The 18th Dynasty, when the graveyard for royal children began, was a time when 
queens traditionally shared their Pharaoh's tombs in the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>. 
Many of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s greatest rulers were buried there, along with the young 
<PERSON>Pharaoh Tutankhamun</PERSON>, whose treasure-filled tomb was discovered by <PERSON>Howard Carter</PERSON> 
in <DATE>1922</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
That discovery brought international fame to the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>. Hundreds 
of other royals and officials also were buried on the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION>. But to the 
world, the glory of the Pharaohs meant the Valley of the Kings -- not the 
Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>, the Valley of the Monkeys or the Tombs of the <LOCATION>Nobles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For tourist agencies, the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION> became an afterthought, a place 
to fill a half-hour after an exhausting visit to the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
When the joint expedition began, 78 burial places had been found in the 
limestone hillsides enclosing the valley. Today 98 are known. 
</P>
<P>
"We couldn't understand the cemetery before, because we were working 
tomb-by-tomb," <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said. "Today, we've uncovered all the major tombs and 
have returned the valley to the way it would have looked when burials began. 
</P>
<P>
"For the first time, we can write its history." 
</P>
<P>
As <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> talked, he and <PERSON>Fathy Hassanein</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities 
Organization's National Documentation Center</ORGANIZATION>, walked through scores of 
excavators digging toward the valley's bedrock. The job at hand was almost 
done, another tomb uncovered from rubble that has obscured the cemetery for 
most of its existence. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Restoration Work 
</P>
<P>
An aim of the project is to restore tombs in the valley so that more can be 
opened to tourists. Fewer than six are now. 
</P>
<P>
The valley's most beautiful tomb, the fabulous burial chambers of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses II</ORGANIZATION>'s 
powerful queen <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>, is among those so deteriorated that they remain 
off-limits. More than half its paintings of the elaborately dressed and 
coiffured queen have been destroyed by natural forces. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said one source for the valley's history has been tidbits left by 
workers who built and decorated the tombs. For generations they lived in a 
village inside the valley. Their records, on papyrus, provided the team not 
only with answers but with mysteries. 
</P>
<P>
Workers recorded the construction of tombs for Queen Isis <LOCATION>Nefret</LOCATION>, one of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses 
II</ORGANIZATION>'s many wives, and a queen named Duat-Iny-Pet. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said they might have been same person, but "where are they?" 
</P>
<P>
He also is intrigued by a lack of burial objects or pieces of the queens' 
mummies. 
</P>
<P>
"This is strange," he said. "Did those who came afterwards destroy them?" He 
added that it could mean another royal cache exists, perhaps mummies of queens 
and children. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Mummified Fetus 
</P>
<P>
Typical of the tales <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> has faced in rewriting a new history for the 
valley is the story of a mummified fetus inside the tomb of 9-year-old prince 
Amon-Hir-Khopshef, son of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses III</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Local guides tell fascinated visitors that <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON>' queen became so distraught 
over the death of their son that she miscarried and the mummies of both 
Amon-Hir-Khopshef and the fetus were entombed. 
</P>
<P>
The story is nonsense, <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Early this century, the Italian excavator <PERSON>Ernesto Schiaparelli</PERSON> found the fetus 
in a rubbish pile outside the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>. It was <PERSON>Schiaparelli</PERSON>, not 
ancient priests, who placed it inside the prince's empty sarcophagus. 
</P>
<P>
Today, the mummified fetus is so popular a tourist attraction that it has its 
own tiny case. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900917-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-17-90 1343EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i BC-APN--NewTombs Adv30   09-17 0884</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--New Tombs, Adv30,1110</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv30</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Sept. 30</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 2 b&amp;w
photos. ColorFoto subscribers get 2 35mm slides.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - It sounds like something <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> would do, build
replicas of the tombs of Egyptian pharaohs for the tourists to look
at. But the people responsible for preserving <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s antiquities
say they have little choice. The real tombs are deteriorating
rapidly in the crush of the tourist flow. To close them would mean
losing the tourist trade.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - It sounds like something <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> would do, build
replicas of the tombs of Egyptian pharaohs for the tourists to look
at. But the people responsible for preserving <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s antiquities
say they have little choice. The real tombs are deteriorating
rapidly in the crush of the tourist flow. To close them would mean
losing the tourist trade.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LUXOR, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - It sounds like something <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> would do, build
replicas of the tombs of Egyptian pharaohs for the tourists to look
at. But the people responsible for preserving <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s antiquities
say they have little choice. The real tombs are deteriorating
rapidly in the crush of the tourist flow. To close them would mean
losing the tourist trade.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - It sounds like something <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> would do, build
replicas of the tombs of Egyptian pharaohs for the tourists to look
at. But the people responsible for preserving <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s antiquities
say they have little choice. The real tombs are deteriorating
rapidly in the crush of the tourist flow. To close them would mean
losing the tourist trade.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890720-0211 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-20-89 0954EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-UnfoundTreasures Adv27   07-20 0983</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Unfound Treasures, Adv 27,1014</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thurs PMs July 27 or Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Much of Ancient Egyptian World Remains Undiscovered</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Treasures even greater than those in <LOCATION>King
Tut</LOCATION>'s tomb may still be lying under the desert sands of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.
   ``When I'm asked if there's another Tut's tomb out there, I
always answer at least one, maybe more,'' said <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, director
of the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids area outside <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> and the huge ancient
cemetery of <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION>, 11 miles to the south.
   ``My guess is we've found no more than <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of what's
buried. After all, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> is <PERCENT>97 percent</PERCENT> desert. ... We can't begin to
imagine what the sands have hidden.''
   The tomb of <ORGANIZATION>Pharaoh Tutankhamun _ King Tut</ORGANIZATION> _ was found almost
intact in <DATE>1922</DATE> by the British archaeologist <PERSON>Howard Carter</PERSON>.
   It took <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> 11 years more to document the hoard of gold,
semiprecious stones, furniture and knickknacks stuffed into the
makeshift tomb dug into the hills of southern <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s Valley of the
<LOCATION>Kings</LOCATION>.
   But <PERSON>Tutankhamun</PERSON> was a lesser king and the discovery of his tomb
left archaeologists to wonder what treasures might have accompanied
ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s great monarchs into the afterlife.
   Some intriguing trophies have eluded both early archaeologists
and their modern successors:
   _Mummies and relics of <LOCATION>Pharaoh Cheops</LOCATION>, whose pyramid on <LOCATION>Giza
Plateau</LOCATION> is among the world's best-known monuments.
   _The tomb of the architect Imhotep at <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION>, where more than
4,600 years ago he built for Pharaoh Zozer a step pyramid, an
architectural feat that quickly evolved into the true pyramid.
Generations of later Egyptians worshipped Imhotep as a god.
   _At least seven tombs of royalty and officials from the <LOCATION>New
Kingdom</LOCATION>, the era of Tutankhamun and the <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON> line.
   _The tomb of Alexander the Great, the young Macedonian conqueror
who died at the age of 33 in 323 <ORGANIZATION>B.C. Records</ORGANIZATION> say he wanted to be
buried in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Siwa Oasis</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>, but finally was encased in
a gold coffin in <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> city he founded.
   _The 50,000-man army of Persian conqueror Cambyses, which
vanished in a sandstorm in 525 B.C. while en route to <LOCATION>Siwa</LOCATION> to punish
the powerful priests of the temple of the <ORGANIZATION>Siwan Oracle</ORGANIZATION>.
   Egyptian officials realize the historical value that any of those
finds would entail. But the mammoth job of preserving what is said
already to be the world's greatest national storehouse of
antiquities has halted treasure hunts.
   ``I'm trying to keep what's standing, standing,'' said <PERSON>Sayed
Tawfik</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION>. ``What
I'd like to do is to keep what's buried, buried until we can deal
with it. It's usually safer for the pieces not to be exposed to
modern pollutants.''
   As <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s population rapidly expands, however, roadways, gas
lines and housing projects unearth a vast ancient legacy just
beneath the ground. Often, excavations are rescue missions.
   Archaeological work in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> generally is restricted to the
cooler winter months, and last season's work was filled with
surprises. Giza director <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said the results give a glimpse of
what lies ahead when archaeologists begin anew in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   In <DATE>January</DATE> five magnificent statues that rival the loveliest
artwork the ancient Egyptians produced were unearthed in a pit
beneath the tourist-trampled courtyard of <ORGANIZATION>Luxor Temple</ORGANIZATION>. Seventeen
more statues, many broken, later were discovered in the cache.
   In <DATE>March</DATE> a mummy of a young woman, her <PERSON>Mona Lisa</PERSON> smile frozen in
a gypsum mask, was found on <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> Plateau a few feet from a roadway
through the pyramids.
   Other discoveries ranged from gold to fortresses, some found on
sites once impenetrable except by camel or donkey, now accessible by
paved roads.
   One area to be surveyed in the fall is <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>'s East
Cemetery, a Pharaonic burial ground for royalty and officials beside
<LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> pyramid.
   ``I'm sure we're going to find an intact burial of a prince or
official, because the area never has been excavated properly,''
<PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   ``In <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION>, where we know Imhotep is buried, you don't even
need to have shovels and picks to find tombs. You can just use your
hands, dig in the sand. They're there.''
   Modern man owes rich finds to the ingenuity of ancient priests,
who reburied important pieces to ensure survival during politically
troubled times, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said. These caches, which may explain the
<ORGANIZATION>Luxor Temple</ORGANIZATION> statues, give clues to what may still be hidden.
   He believes the pyramids area contains at least one major cache
from the reign of Old Kingdom Pharaoh <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>, whose relics include
the world's largest pyramid, a full-sized boat and an ivory statue
so small it can be held between two fingers.
   ``I think out there is <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' mummy, maybe statues, maybe
personal items,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   ``Four priests were in charge of their safety, but in the next
dynasty (after <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>) his memory soured. There was a revolt. His
monuments were damaged, perhaps because he made himself a god.''
   Hawass believes that like the <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION> find the <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> discovery
will be accidental.
   ``We have magnificent statues of his successors (and) delicate
funerary items of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' mother, ... so we know such things did
exist,'' he said.
   ``One day you'll be digging a power line, or cleaning, and there
they'll be.''
   Hawass thinks chance also may locate the long-sought tomb of
Alexander the Great in <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION>.
   ``We have early descriptions of his tomb, but <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION> has gone
through many changes,'' he said.
   ``We're not going to find the tomb, if it even still exists, by
going after it. We'll find it by accident, when somebody's digging a
foundation for a house or installing sewer lines.''
   Hawass insists that people who think incredible discoveries
remain to be found aren't dealing in fantasy.
   ``We've got too much evidence,'' he said: ``Kings without tombs,
places we know existed but never were found.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Thurs PMs July 27</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901123-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-23-90 1315EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i BC-Tut'sTombReborn Adv02   11-23 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Tut's Tomb Reborn, Adv02,0847</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv02</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday Dec 2 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Artisans Reprise Great Moment, Re-creating Tut's Tomb</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Artisans are re-creating one of the great
moments of archaeology on an island south of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Nov. 26, 1922</DATE>, English archaeologist <PERSON>Howard Carter</PERSON> opened the
tomb of the boy <ORGANIZATION>Pharaoh Tutankhamun</ORGANIZATION> and found a glittering world of
delicate statues, inlaid chests, feather-light fans and decorated
coffins of solid gold.
   The riches he discovered amazed the world.
   Now, 68 years after <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> peered into the small tomb in
southern <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, the artisans are fashioning Tut's netherworld once
again, working from photographs and other records. The replicas of
Tut's treasures are to be entombed as the archaeologist saw them.
   Twenty-two artists, sculptors, engineers and university students
are rekindling craftsmanship unseen since the days of the Pharaohs.
   They are halfway through their assignment: to duplicate his
four-chambered tomb and 1,000 of the 1,703 Tut objects in the
Egyptian Museum, as they were left by priests 3,313 years ago and
the robbers who came later.
   Ever-watchful jackals, goddesses in sleek gowns, open-mouthed
lions and even the boy Pharaoh himself, out for a walk in thonged
sandals, cram the bustling workshop on <ORGANIZATION>Jacob</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>.
   A year from now, every day on Jacob's Island will be <DATE>Nov. 26,
1922</DATE>.
   Until then, people wanting to marvel at <ORGANIZATION>King Tut</ORGANIZATION>'s storied world
must travel to the two places they have visited for decades: the
treasure hoard in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>'s Egyptian Museum and his tomb, with the
mummy, 450 miles to the south, in the Valley of the <LOCATION>Kings</LOCATION>.
   ``It's the wonder that we must produce in our tomb - the shock,
which you don't feel when you see the objects away from the tomb,''
said <PERSON>Mahmoud Mabrouk</PERSON>, a sculptor and art professor who directs the
Jacob's Island project.
   ``We work as a team, just as the ancients did,'' he said.
   Novices think Tut's treasures were all of solid gold. There was
plenty of that, but there also were objects of wood, silver and
other metals, alabaster, ivory, leopard skins, leather, pottery and
gemstones.
   Decisions on whether to replicate individual items, big or
small, were based on whether they were important to history or to
art knowledge.
   The project is costing 1 million Egyptian pounds (almost
<MONEY>$360,000</MONEY>) and is the brainchild of former diplomat <PERSON>Hassan Ragab</PERSON>, an
entrepreneur who revived <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s extinct papyrus industry.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE> he opened his Pharaonic Village on <PERSON>Jacob</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>, where
tourists come to view life from the days of <PERSON>King Tut</PERSON>, but without
the boy Pharaoh himself.
   ``<PERSON>Dr. Ragab</PERSON> asked me to create a full-scale tomb with exact
copies of objects so that tourists would feel the wonder as <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>
felt it,'' <PERSON>Mabrouk</PERSON> said. ``The tomb was no problem, but nobody knew
how to make the objects. Everybody I talked with told me to refuse
the offer.''
   Mabrouk, who advises an international committee working to save
the Sphinx, said he accepted the challenge for two reasons.
   ``First, I wanted to enter the mind of the ancient artist,'' he
said. ``What kind of people were these, to create things so
beautiful, but things that would never be seen by the living?
   ``Today, we artists have exhibitions and everybody congratulates
us. Not these artists. Their creations were locked up with Tut.''
   The second reason harks back to <ORGANIZATION>Mabrouk</ORGANIZATION>'s childhood.
   ``I was 12 when my brother and I saw the Tut collection in the
museum,'' he said. ``We were so happy, but we were sad. The objects
were beautiful, but nobody knew anything about them.''
   ``I want Egyptian youth to look back on their history with a
sense of pride, a sense of identity. It's an Arab problem that
Egyptians turn their backs on anything about the Pharaohs.''
   Mabrouk said he is astounded by the quality of Tut relics. ``We
had to start with the simplest items,'' he said. ``Once we mastered
the techniques, we could tackle the most difficult.''
   Reproduction has been made more difficult because objects in the
museum must be examined from behind glass and many Tut objects are
locked in storerooms. Books contain conflicting information, and
<PERSON>Mabrouk</PERSON> said many of <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>'s notes are inaccurate.
   Even lowly artifacts proved tricky. A simple pair of sandals
took three months to reproduce.
   Many of the 50 alabaster items from the tomb were lovingly
worked with exquisite designs. Alabaster posed one of the toughest
challenges.
   ``We spent six months working in alabaster factories outside the
Valley of the <LOCATION>Kings</LOCATION>, just to see how to use the stone,'' <PERSON>Mabrouk</PERSON>
said. ``We finally made three simple vases, but even that took a
month.''
   Still to come are <ORGANIZATION>Tutankhamun</ORGANIZATION>'s gold death mask and the
elaborately inlaid gold sarcophagus.
   ``Sometimes you just have to compromise,'' <PERSON>Mabrouk</PERSON> said. ``We'll
use gold-plated copper instead of gold, but the effect will be the
same.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday Dec 2</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Artisans are re-creating one of the great
moments of archaeology on an island south of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Nov. 26, 1922</DATE>, English archaeologist <PERSON>Howard Carter</PERSON> opened the
tomb of the boy <ORGANIZATION>Pharaoh Tutankhamun</ORGANIZATION> and found a glittering world of
delicate statues, inlaid chests, feather-light fans and decorated
coffins of solid gold.
   The riches he discovered amazed the world.
   Now, 68 years after <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> peered into the small tomb in
southern <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, the artisans are fashioning Tut's netherworld once
again, working from photographs and other records. The replicas of
Tut's treasures are to be entombed as the archaeologist saw them.
   Twenty-two artists, sculptors, engineers and university students
are rekindling craftsmanship unseen since the days of the Pharaohs.
   They are halfway through their assignment: to duplicate his
four-chambered tomb and 1,000 of the 1,703 Tut objects in the
Egyptian Museum, as they were left by priests 3,313 years ago and
the robbers who came later.
   Ever-watchful jackals, goddesses in sleek gowns, open-mouthed
lions and even the boy Pharaoh himself, out for a walk in thonged
sandals, cram the bustling workshop on <ORGANIZATION>Jacob</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>.
   A year from now, every day on Jacob's Island will be <DATE>Nov. 26,
1922</DATE>.
   Until then, people wanting to marvel at <ORGANIZATION>King Tut</ORGANIZATION>'s storied world
must travel to the two places they have visited for decades: the
treasure hoard in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>'s Egyptian Museum and his tomb, with the
mummy, 450 miles to the south, in the Valley of the <LOCATION>Kings</LOCATION>.
   ``It's the wonder that we must produce in our tomb - the shock,
which you don't feel when you see the objects away from the tomb,''
said <PERSON>Mahmoud Mabrouk</PERSON>, a sculptor and art professor who directs the
Jacob's Island project.
   ``We work as a team, just as the ancients did,'' he said.
   Novices think Tut's treasures were all of solid gold. There was
plenty of that, but there also were objects of wood, silver and
other metals, alabaster, ivory, leopard skins, leather, pottery and
gemstones.
   Decisions on whether to replicate individual items, big or
small, were based on whether they were important to history or to
art knowledge.
   The project is costing 1 million Egyptian pounds (almost
<MONEY>$360,000</MONEY>) and is the brainchild of former diplomat <PERSON>Hassan Ragab</PERSON>, an
entrepreneur who revived <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s extinct papyrus industry.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE> he opened his Pharaonic Village on <PERSON>Jacob</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>, where
tourists come to view life from the days of <PERSON>King Tut</PERSON>, but without
the boy Pharaoh himself.
   ``<PERSON>Dr. Ragab</PERSON> asked me to create a full-scale tomb with exact
copies of objects so that tourists would feel the wonder as <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>
felt it,'' <PERSON>Mabrouk</PERSON> said. ``The tomb was no problem, but nobody knew
how to make the objects. Everybody I talked with told me to refuse
the offer.''
   Mabrouk, who advises an international committee working to save
the Sphinx, said he accepted the challenge for two reasons.
   ``First, I wanted to enter the mind of the ancient artist,'' he
said. ``What kind of people were these, to create things so
beautiful, but things that would never be seen by the living?
   ``Today, we artists have exhibitions and everybody congratulates
us. Not these artists. Their creations were locked up with Tut.''
   The second reason harks back to <ORGANIZATION>Mabrouk</ORGANIZATION>'s childhood.
   ``I was 12 when my brother and I saw the Tut collection in the
museum,'' he said. ``We were so happy, but we were sad. The objects
were beautiful, but nobody knew anything about them.''
   ``I want Egyptian youth to look back on their history with a
sense of pride, a sense of identity. It's an Arab problem that
Egyptians turn their backs on anything about the Pharaohs.''
   Mabrouk said he is astounded by the quality of Tut relics. ``We
had to start with the simplest items,'' he said. ``Once we mastered
the techniques, we could tackle the most difficult.''
   Reproduction has been made more difficult because objects in the
museum must be examined from behind glass and many Tut objects are
locked in storerooms. Books contain conflicting information, and
<PERSON>Mabrouk</PERSON> said many of <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>'s notes are inaccurate.
   Even lowly artifacts proved tricky. A simple pair of sandals
took three months to reproduce.
   Many of the 50 alabaster items from the tomb were lovingly
worked with exquisite designs. Alabaster posed one of the toughest
challenges.
   ``We spent six months working in alabaster factories outside the
Valley of the <LOCATION>Kings</LOCATION>, just to see how to use the stone,'' <PERSON>Mabrouk</PERSON>
said. ``We finally made three simple vases, but even that took a
month.''
   Still to come are <ORGANIZATION>Tutankhamun</ORGANIZATION>'s gold death mask and the
elaborately inlaid gold sarcophagus.
   ``Sometimes you just have to compromise,'' <PERSON>Mabrouk</PERSON> said. ``We'll
use gold-plated copper instead of gold, but the effect will be the
same.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122389-0038 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 152561 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 23, 1989, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 20; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
329 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CAPISTRANO VALLEY GETS HEALTHY IN VICTORY OVER CORONA DEL MAR 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BARBIE LUDOVISE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MISSION VIEJO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Corona del <ORGANIZATION>Mar High School</ORGANIZATION>'s basketball team displayed an impressive amount of 
tenacity <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in its nonleague game against <LOCATION>Capistrano Valley</LOCATION>, the 
county's second-ranked team. 
</P>
<P>
Was it good enough for an upset? Not quite. Not with <ORGANIZATION>Capistrano Valley</ORGANIZATION> forward 
<PERSON>Scott McCorkle</PERSON> back in the lineup after missing one game because of the flu. 
</P>
<P>
McCorkle scored a game-high 38 points -- including 16 in the first half -- to 
lead <LOCATION>Capistrano Valley</LOCATION> to a 66-53 victory at <ORGANIZATION>Saddleback College</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For <ORGANIZATION>Capistrano Valley</ORGANIZATION> (8-2), the victory should help to boost the team's 
confidence for its next venture: the <ORGANIZATION>King Cotton</ORGANIZATION> tournament, one of the most 
prestigious in the nation, <DATE>Dec. 26-30</DATE> at <LOCATION>Pine Bluff</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Especially uplifting for the <ORGANIZATION>Cougars</ORGANIZATION> was the play of <ORGANIZATION>McCorkle</ORGANIZATION>, a 6-foot-5, 
210-pound senior forward headed for <ORGANIZATION>Syracuse</ORGANIZATION> next year. <PERSON>McCorkle</PERSON> did not play 
in <LOCATION>Capistrano Valley</LOCATION>'s 82-59 loss to <LOCATION>Edison</LOCATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. But against <ORGANIZATION>Corona 
del Mar</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>McCorkle</PERSON> was tough to stop, especially in the <DATE>first quarter</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Corona del Mar (4-5) struggled early, forcing shots and making mental mistakes 
as <LOCATION>Capistrano Valley</LOCATION> took a 10-3 lead. After a timeout, <ORGANIZATION>Corona del Mar</ORGANIZATION> upped 
its man-to-man defensive pressure, and slowly chipped away at <ORGANIZATION>Capistrano 
Valley</ORGANIZATION>'s lead. 
</P>
<P>
After trailing 31-24 at halftime, <ORGANIZATION>Corona del Mar</ORGANIZATION> held <LOCATION>Capistrano Valley</LOCATION> 
scoreless for the first four minutes of the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>, as it went on an 8-0 
run to take a 32-31 advantage. The score was tied at the start of the <DATE>fourth 
quarter</DATE>, 39-39. 
</P>
<P>
That would be as close as Corona del Mar would get. As the <ORGANIZATION>Sea Kings</ORGANIZATION>' game fell 
apart -- thanks, in part, to a pressing <ORGANIZATION>Capistrano Valley defense</ORGANIZATION> -- <ORGANIZATION>Capistrano 
Valley</ORGANIZATION> went on an 11-2 run, thanks to a three-pointer and a layup off a steal 
by <PERSON>Chris Kostoff</PERSON> and six points, four on free throws, by <ORGANIZATION>McCorkle</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Kostoff, who scored 40 points <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, was held to 11 points, nine in 
the fourth period. <PERSON>Warren Johnson</PERSON> had 24 points to lead the <ORGANIZATION>Sea Kings</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Doug 
Hesse</PERSON> added 16. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Airborne -- Scott McCorkle of Capistrano Valley shoots over Doug Hesse 
of Corona del Mar in Cougars' 66-53 victory. ; Photo, Mark Flint of Corona del 
Mar High School tries to elude Tom Airey of Capistrano Valley Friday night. LEO 
JARZOMB / For The Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA120990-0146 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 319852 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 9, 1990, Sunday, South Bay Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 12; Column 5 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
338 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TEMECULA VALLEY CLIPS PALOS VERDES; 
</P>
<P>
FOOTBALL: SEA KINGS STOPPED IN CIF SOUTHERN SECTION DIVISION VIII CHAMPIONSHIP 
GAME, 29-7 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVID RAATZ, SPECIAL TO THE TIMES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Ronnie Long had three touchdown runs and intercepted three passes as <ORGANIZATION>Temecula 
Valley High</ORGANIZATION> claimed its first CIF championship <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> with a 29-7 
victory over visiting <PERSON>Palos Verdes</PERSON> in the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Section Division VIII</ORGANIZATION> title 
game. 
</P>
<P>
The loss marked the last football game for <PERSON>Palos Verdes</PERSON>, which is closing next 
year. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Temecula Valley</LOCATION> (11-3) took the lead for good at 10-7 on Long's two-yard run 
with 4:25 left in the first half. Long led the Bears with 83 yards in 16 
carries. 
</P>
<P>
After <PERSON>Mike Lassig</PERSON>'s fumble recovery near midfield, <LOCATION>Temecula Valley</LOCATION> took a 16-7 
lead on <PERSON>David Gonzalez</PERSON>' 26-yard pass to <PERSON>Greg Campbell</PERSON> with 46 seconds remaining 
in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Palos Verdes (8-6), which had a four-game winning streak snapped, took its only 
lead at 7-3 as running back <PERSON>George Felactu</PERSON> scored from a yard out, culminating 
the first drive of the <DATE>second quarter</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Sea King quarterback <PERSON>Tim King</PERSON> dropped back to pass only six times in the <DATE>first 
half</DATE>, but was guilty of three turnovers. King threw two first-half 
interceptions and was hit in the pocket before losing the ball to <PERSON>Lassig</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
On the game's opening series, the Bears drove to the Palos Verdes 29-yard line 
before missing a field goal. Then, on the first drive for <PERSON>Palos Verdes</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Sea 
Kings</ORGANIZATION> gained 41 yards in four carries before <PERSON>King</PERSON> was intercepted by Long. 
</P>
<P>
That turnover helped produce the game's first score on the ensuing drive, a 
36-yard field goal by <LOCATION>Temecula Valley</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>James McKee</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Long closed the scoring with two short touchdown runs in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Felactu paced <PERSON>Palos Verdes</PERSON>' attack with 65 yards in 12 carries. 
</P>
<P>
Gonzalez picked apart the <PERSON>Palos Verdes</PERSON> defense with short passes in the first 
half, completing 11 of 14 attempts for 101 yards and no interceptions. 
</P>
<P>
For the game, <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> completed 17 of 24 passes for 201 yards. 
</P>
<P>
Gonzalez' favorite receiver was <PERSON>Campbell</PERSON>, who had 10 catches for 84 yards. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Sea Kings</ORGANIZATION> committed six turnovers; the Bears had only one. 
</P>
<P>
A 70-yard punt by <PERSON>John Miller</PERSON> was one of <PERSON>Palos Verdes</PERSON>' highlights. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880412-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-12-88 1244EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EgyptianBracelet     04-12 0650</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Egyptian Bracelet,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fragment of Gold Bracelet Linked to Ramses' Favorite Wife</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Workmen cleaning the dusty tomb of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses
II</ORGANIZATION>'s beautiful <PERSON>Queen Nefertari</PERSON> found a fragment of beaten gold
jewelry that grave robbers and tourists apparently overlooked for
3,250 years.
   Resins clinging to the etched fragment indicate it may have been
attached originally to her missing mummy, Egyptian and American
officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in announcing the find.
   If the fragment is determined to have belonged to the queen, it
would be rare indeed. The only other surviving legacy of <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>
is the lid of her sarcophagus, on exhibit at the <ORGANIZATION>Turin Egyptian
Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.
   Egyptian Culture Minister <PERSON>Farouk Hosni</PERSON> called the jewelry, which
is 1{ inches long and an inch wide, ``a significant discovery _
only the second object ever found that probably belonged to
<PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>.''
   The piece resembles segments of armlets or bracelets surviving
from <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON>' <LOCATION>New Kingdom</LOCATION> era, with golden pieces linked by chains
and beads and decorated with flowers.
   The fragile gold sheet was in an anteroom behind the queen's
burial chamber, found during a project to stop the decay of
<PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>'s tomb in southern <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>.
Sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Getty
Conservation Institute of Marina del Rey</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, the project began
18 months ago and is expected to last another 3{ years.
   With its splendid vividly colored wall paintings, <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>'s is
the greatest among 80 tombs in shallow valleys called ``the place
of beauty.'' Royal wives and children were buried there in rock-cut
tombs opposite the ancient capital <LOCATION>Thebes</LOCATION>, now called <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION>, 450
miles south of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Luis Monreal</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Getty Institute</ORGANIZATION>'s director, said nobody
believed anything of significance had escaped the attention of
grave robbers or the thousands of tourists and conservators who
visited the tomb since its discovery in <DATE>1904</DATE>.
   Workmen inching across the floor of the tomb's final chamber,
clearing away the centuries of dust by hand, found the fragment on
<DATE>Feb. 8</DATE>, <PERSON>Monreal</PERSON> said.
   It lay ``covered by dust, then by broken bits of wall paintings
which in themselves were covered by layers of dust,'' he said.
   ``Another real bonus that we hadn't expected is that we
recovered pieces of a complete segment (of wall painting), which
will cover some 10 square feet when we reattach it to the rear
wall,'' he said.
   Although proof hasn't been found that the fragment was
<PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>'s, there are indications, including its hieroglyphic
inscriptions, <PERSON>Monreal</PERSON> said.
   Los Angeles-based British Egyptologist <PERSON>Helen Strudwick</PERSON>, who
studied the piece for <ORGANIZATION>Getty</ORGANIZATION>, found significance in the ritual
inscription ``true of voice,'' a phrase ancient Egyptians normally
used after the name of the person who died.
   She noted that the phrase had a feminine ending. That, plus the
fragment's discovery inside <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>'s tomb, ``highly suggests''
that it was from the queen's burial paraphernalia, perhaps even
torn from her mummified body.
   ``The piece does not rank with the Tutankhamun treasure in
esthetic terms, but it still has historical and sentimental value
because the powerful <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON> simply vanished,'' <PERSON>Monreal</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>, the beautiful and bold wife of warrior-hero <PERSON>Ramses
II</PERSON>, is thought to have died about age 45 about 3,250 years ago. Her
tomb paintings and inscriptions depict her as a woman of great
charm and exquisite taste, adorned with magnificent jewelry and
wearing fashionable gowns.
   Ramses' favorite of 13 wives, <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON> accompanied her husband
in battle and helped negotiate the world's first peace treaty,
<PERSON>Ramses</PERSON>' agreement with the troublesome <ORGANIZATION>Hittites of Asia Minor</ORGANIZATION>. In
her famous temple at <PERSON>Abu Simbel</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON> is pictured begging
<PERSON>Ramses</PERSON> to be gentle with his captives.
   ``<PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON> was the world's first first lady,'' <PERSON>Monreal</PERSON> said.
``She was last seen accompanying her husband to consecrate the two
temples at <LOCATION>Abu Simbel</LOCATION> in <DATE>1255</DATE> B.C. Then we know nothing of her.
Maybe this piece will tell us about her death.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06055149 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06055149 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COLLEGE; BASKETBALL; CHAMPIONSHIP  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  De Anza and West Valley rolled to easy victories in the first round of the
men's community college state basketball tournament Saturday night, De Anza
beating visiting Napa 118-69 and host West Valley routing Gavilan 98-74.;   
Kurt Siwek had 21 of his 31 points in the first half for De Anza (25-6), which
won its 18th in a row. De Anza's next game will be Wednesday against Kings
River at De Anza. Kings River beat Sierra 76-73 in overtime Saturday.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DE ANZA, WEST VALLEY ADVANCE IN TOURNEY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Napa finished 13-17.;    <PERSON>Tomas Thompson</PERSON> scored 33 points and <PERSON>Dave Smith</PERSON> 20
to lead <LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION> (25-5) past <PERSON>Gavilan</PERSON> (15-15). <LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>'s next game will
be against the winner of <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s Lassen-American River game.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Staff Report  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910224  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  122  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday February 24, 1991
00055149,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881124-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-24-88 2358EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Tut'sTomb     11-24 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tut's Tomb,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tut's Real Curse: Bacteria Eating Wall Paintings In Famous Tomb</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VALLEY OF THE KINGS, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rapidly multiplying bacteria
are eating away vivid pictures from the walls of <ORGANIZATION>King Tut</ORGANIZATION>'s tomb,
one of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s most-visited tourist sites.
   Specialists have begun applying an antidote they hope can arrest
the bacteria, but antiquities officials say the original color never
can be restored to the small, pox-like black specks and blotches
marring the walls.
   ``The situation inside the tomb is extremely serious,'' said
Mutaw'ie Balboush, the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION>'s director
for upper <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>. ``Damage is appearing almost everywhere you look
among the figures.''
   At the start of the winter tourist season in early <DATE>November</DATE>,
officials were so worried they considered closing the tomb to let
conservators work unhindered.
   After the antidote was developed last week, however, work to save
the paintings was scheduled before and after tourist hours.
   Tutankhamun, a young pharaoh who died in <DATE>1323</DATE> B.C., was buried in
a makeshift tomb stuffed with riches in the barren Valley of the
Kings _ the southern wasteland where royalty and nobility were
buried for 500 years.
   During tourist season, his single-chambered tomb draws more than
2,500 visitors a day.
   Its wall paintings, some with colors as bright as the day they
were painted, depict noblemen and officials transporting Tut's mummy
to the tomb. They include a unique scene of the ``Opening of the
Mouth'' rite in which the dead king is given eternal life.
   ``We can't simply remove the infection, because the bacteria have
become part of the paint itself,'' said restoration director <PERSON>Shawky
Nakhla</PERSON>. ``We have to put the bacteria in a situation that won't
endanger the tomb itself.
   ``In the past the bacteria were dormant, but something has
triggered them to life. When we looked at them in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, they were
so active they were duplicating every day.''
   They found four kinds of bacteria and actinomycetes _ an
intermediate step between bacteria and fungi that in humans cause
abscesses under the skin.
   <PERSON>Omar Arini</PERSON>, science officer at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, said
bacteria have been present in Egyptian tombs since they were sealed
thousands of years ago.
   ``If something changes the environment inside a tomb, such as a
rise in humidity, then bacteria can come to life,'' <PERSON>Arini</PERSON> said.
   ``When this happens, the situation is extremely dangerous not
only for the tomb but for others in the vicinity. The bacteria can
spread.''
   <PERSON>Nakhla</PERSON> said bacteria in Tut's tomb could have been activated by
high humidity, difficult to control with so many visitors. And the
number of tourists is expected to increase dramatically during peak
season over the next two months.
   Though smaller and with lesser-quality paintings than some of the
62 nearby tombs, <PERSON>Tut</PERSON>'s burial place mesmerizes visitors.
   It owes part of its allure to the myth of a curse visited on
anybody who violates it. It gained prominence in the <DATE>1920s</DATE> and
<DATE>1930s</DATE>, after a number of people from the expedition team that found
the tomb in <DATE>1922</DATE> died unusual deaths.
   Egyptologists scoff at the idea. Grave robbers violated the tomb
at least twice in antiquity and <PERSON>Egyptologist Howard Carter</PERSON>, the
expedition leader, died naturally in <DATE>1939</DATE> at age 66.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870805-0140 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
Emperors Among Orchards
---
By Gail King</HL>
<DD> 08/05/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> Beijing  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stonecutters squat in the field alongside the outer wall of the Jing Ling tomb, chipping away at large granite blocks. 
Watched over by a marble Chinese lion, they work with hammer and chisel, echoing the work of the 15th- and 16th-century stonecutters who worked on these magnificently crafted <ORGANIZATION>Ming Tombs</ORGANIZATION>. 
As the 30 or so men strike their blocks, the melody they make rings in harmony with the guide's rendition of his spiel: <PERSON>Chang Ling</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Ming</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Ding Ling</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Ming</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Jing Ling</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ming</LOCATION>. 

   A cock crows in the distance, a workman with a shovel over his shoulder ambles by, and it is easy to believe that times have not changed much since the days of the <ORGANIZATION>Ming Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The Ming emperors ruled a prosperous and fairly peaceful <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> from <DATE>1368</DATE> to <DATE>1644</DATE>. 
When the third emperor moved the capital from <LOCATION>Nanking</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> he set about finding a proper and peaceful royal burial place, near enough to the capital for fitting ceremonial respect to be paid, but remote enough to discourage curious visitors. 
Geomancers finally chose this forested, mountain-protected valley, about 30 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>. 

   Thirteen of the 16 Ming emperors lie here in elaborate tombs, each approached through a series of stylized, symbolic gates, screens and buildings. 
These structures are in various states of repair. 
It appears that the stonecutters are working to renovate <PERSON>Jing Ling</PERSON>, but that is not the case. 
The men are actually shaping stones to be used as the guardrails for a "flyover" (overpass) on the new superhighway being built nearby. 

   Ten thousand visitors a day come to look at the tombs. 
They drive through the Sacred Way, lined with mammoth stone animals and Chinese entrepreneurs hawking orange soda pop, T-shirts, cloisonne bracelets and fur hats. 
Past the Sacred Way, individual roads lead to the tombs. 

   <PERSON>Chang Ling</PERSON>, the oldest and largest of the tombs, has been meticulously renovated, but not excavated. 
All the tombs are easy to spot. 
The double-roofed stele pavilions immediately in front of each grave tumulus were built to command the valley, and their red roofs still dominate the scene. 
It is the names that confuse Westerners. 
The Ming emperors had a personal name and a reign name. 
Each tomb has a separate name, as does the temple within. 
Add to this the change in Chinese-to-English Romanization (Peking to <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, Ching-ling to <PERSON>Jing Ling</PERSON>) and it's easy to see why the tombs are referred to by number, chronologically. 
Tomb One (<ORGANIZATION>Chang Ling</ORGANIZATION>) holds the third Ming emperor, but the first to be buried in the valley. 

   The 10th tomb, <PERSON>Ding Ling</PERSON>, has been excavated and is open to the public. 
After climbing three flights of stairs, visitors can see the magnificent blue-and-white porcelain jars in which oil was set aflame as the tomb was closed (to create an oxygen-free vacuum) and the massive four-ton marble tomb doors that sealed from the inside. 

   Tomb Three, <PERSON>Jing Ling</PERSON>, where the stonecutters work, has not been excavated nor has its exterior been as meticulously restored as that of the first tomb. 
It was built by the fifth Ming emperor, who ruled 1425-35. 
Since most tourists go to the first or 10th tomb, a visit here can be a serene glimpse into Ming history and architecture. 
Once inside the outer walls it is easy to appreciate the peace that the emperors sought. 

   Inside the first courtyard, a triple set of steps leads up to what was once a sacrificial hall. 
The hall is gone, and the expanse of open ground where it was gives a feeling of spaciousness. 
A steep ramp leads up to the stele pavilion, forcing visitors to stoop as they approach the grave site. 

   The pavilion dominates <PERSON>Jing Ling</PERSON> and holds the grave stele, the emperor's flattering "tombstone." 
A hidden passageway connects this building with the actual grave site. 
The emperor does not lie alone in <LOCATION>Jing Ling</LOCATION>. 
His empress is buried with him, as are 10 concubines. 

   When the tomb is eventually opened it is apt to contain a trove of blue-and-white porcelain like the jars in Ding Ling that inspire feverish whispers among tourists. 
It was during the fifth emperor's reign that this famous porcelain was perfected. 

   Except for developments in porcelain and a penchant for amassing collections (including one of Korean virgins), the fifth emperor made few ripples in history. 
One incident, however, does stand out. 
When the guardian families of Jing Ling village, whose job it was to protect the tomb, cut some trees that the emperor thought important to the beauty and serenity of the site, he had the villagers executed. 

   He might not take kindly to the stonecutters, whose steady chipping helps to build a highway to bring the curious more easily to his tomb site. 
And he would certainly be appalled at the sight of the helicopter poised in a small clearing between the peach and apple orchards that ring Jing Ling. 
It waits to take customers on a noisy flying tour of the <ORGANIZATION>Ming Tombs</ORGANIZATION>. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Ms. King</PERSON>, a free-lance writer based in the <LOCATION>Ohio Valley</LOCATION>, recently visited <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011290-0110 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 161082 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 12, 1990, Friday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 6; Column 5 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
412 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SERVICES, DANCING, SINGING AMONG EVENTS HONORING MARTIN LUTHER KING DAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ELLEN YAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Korean dancers, a choir of singers from seven churches and a student drill team 
will highlight <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Day</ORGANIZATION> events in the <LOCATION>San Fernando Valley</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The dancers and choir will appear during services <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> titled "His 
Dream Is Our Dream," sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Valley Interfaith Council</ORGANIZATION>, a coalition of 
about 200 churches. 
</P>
<P>
The service will start with a procession of about 40 elected officials and 
clergy from various religious faiths. Rabbi <PERSON>Aaron Weis</PERSON>, who walked with King in 
<LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, will be among the speakers. 
</P>
<P>
"What we're trying to do is get a Hispanic, <LOCATION>Jewish</LOCATION>, Korean, Protestant 
representation out here . . . to demonstrate that it's not just a holiday for 
blacks," said <PERSON>Barry Smedberg</PERSON>, executive director of the interfaith council. The 
services will begin at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>St. Catherine of Siena Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>, 
18115 <ORGANIZATION>Sherman Way</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Reseda</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Also <DATE>Monday</DATE>, a drill team, choirs and dancers from at least 10 area schools 
will perform during a five-hour tribute beginning at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> in the <ORGANIZATION>Pacoima 
Community Center</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Glen Oaks</LOCATION> and Van Nuys boulevards. Essays and art with the 
theme "His Dream Is Our Dream" will be shown at the <ORGANIZATION>Youth Culture Center</ORGANIZATION>, next 
door. 
</P>
<P>
"When I watch the young people perform, it's like a class," said <PERSON>Arthur 
Broadous</PERSON>, youth center director, who has seen the King tribute at least seven 
years. "A lot of kids never sat in the back of the bus, knew what it was like 
not to be able to eat in a restaurant." 
</P>
<P>
Also <DATE>Monday</DATE>, a student discussion of the "unfinished business" in <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s legacy 
will end three hours of programming on the activist aired on KLCS-TV, Channel 
58, the educational station of the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Unified School District</ORGANIZATION>. The 
programs begin at 10 a.m. 
</P>
<P>
In events today <ORGANIZATION>Harding Street School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sylmar</LOCATION> will hold its 21st annual 
commemoration of King, featuring a six-foot mural of the activist and 150 
students singing his favorite hymns. 
</P>
<P>
"The music is fantastic," said <PERSON>Susan Alves</PERSON>, a teacher and co-director of the 
program. "We had a dress rehearsal and two teachers were crying. . . ." 
Programs begin at <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> and <TIME>1:15 p.m</TIME>. The school is at 13060 Harding St. 
</P>
<P>
Other events today include reenactments of <PERSON>Rosa Parks</PERSON>' bus trip in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, 
where she refused to give up her seat to a white man in <DATE>1955</DATE>, triggering civil 
rights demonstrations. Re-enactments will be performed at <TIME>10:30 a.m.</TIME> and <TIME>1:30 
p.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Fenton Avenue School</ORGANIZATION>, 11828 Gain St. in <LOCATION>Lake View Terrace</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
All events are free and open to the public. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06063202 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06063202 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COLLEGE; BASKETBALL; PLAYOFF; GAME; RESULT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The season ended for the West Valley College men's basketball team Saturday
night with a 63-60 loss to Kings River in Saratoga in the third round of the
Northern California junior college playoffs.;    Kings River (26-9) advances
to the state tournament.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WEST VALLEY OUSTED IN J.C. PLAYOFFS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     West Valley (26-6) was led by sophomore guard <PERSON>Dave Smith</PERSON> and sophomore
forwards <PERSON>Tomas Thompson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ted Bull</PERSON>, each of whom scored 15 points.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Staff Report  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910303  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  68  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday March 3, 1991
00063202,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880830-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-88 0337EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AncientTomb     08-30 0514</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ancient Tomb,0529</SECOND>
<HEAD>4,000-Year-Old Funeral Boat Gently Moved into Elaborate Museum
Tomb Scene</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL A. DRISCOLL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly 4,000 years after it was built, the
funeral boat of one of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s most powerful pharaohs takes another
journey this week.
   The delicate, 32-foot long, wooden craft was gently lifted off
the floor of the <ORGANIZATION>Field Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> and
rotated 180 degrees. Expert riggers who performed the tricky
maneuver kept their hands off, fearing sweat or body oils would
harm the ancient wood.
   Today, the boat used in the funeral of King Sen-wosret III in
about <DATE>1850</DATE> B.C. will be moved inch by inch a few yards to its new
setting in the museum _ a <MONEY>$2.2 million</MONEY> permanent exhibit.
   When the exhibit opens in <DATE>November</DATE>, it will allow visitors to
walk through the eerie world of tombs, mummies, shrines to cat
goddesses and other treasures from ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>. The museum said
the exhibit would give visitors the only opportunity outside <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>
to enter and explore a life-size tomb complex.
   King Sen-wosret's boat _ a graceful, crescent-shaped canoe-like
craft _ is but one of more than a thousand artifacts and treasures
from the museum's collection used to recreate the burial scenes.
   Visitors enter the tomb chambers of the 5th Dynasty pharaoh,
<PERSON>King Unis</PERSON>, dating to <DATE>2400</DATE> B.C. and excavated from <LOCATION>Saqqara</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>,
in <DATE>1908</DATE>.
   Beneath a false door, a 35-foot burial shaft takes visitors into
the dark and eerie burial chamber. The sarcophagus is empty. When
it was excavated, the pharaoh's mummy was gone, stolen by robbers
or destroyed by time.
   Leaving the burial chamber, the visitor passes through a roughly
hewn tomb robbers' tunnel and into another scene depicting a
variety of Egyptian burial rites.
   ``This could well be the most fascinating part of the exhibit,''
said its developer, <PERSON>Janet Kamien</PERSON>. ``It gives them (visitors) a
chance to explore the age-old mysteries of mummies and life after
death.''
   Next month, the museum staff will move 23 mummies into the
exhibit, along with the accouterments their souls were to take with
them to the afterworld.
   Sen-wosret's boat will be displayed nearby.
   No one actually knows if the boat was used to transport the
king's body across the <LOCATION>Nile River</LOCATION> to the burial site, said <PERSON>Frank
Yurco</PERSON>, a scholar on ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Oriental Institute</ORGANIZATION> and a
consultant on the museum project.
   The boat was one of six found at the burial compound in 1893-94
by <PERSON>Jacques DeMorgan</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Welsh Egyptologist</ORGANIZATION>. Two badly deteriorated
ones were left at the site.
   Two of the four DeMorgan saved are at the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Museum</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>.
   Sen-wosret is remembered for military campaigns that extended
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s boundary into the Nubian region of <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Sudan</LOCATION>,
as well as securing control of the <LOCATION>Nile River</LOCATION> to the south, he said.
   He also centralized the Egyptian government, setting the pattern
for several hundred years.
   Sen-wosret is believed to have died when he was about 50, said
Yurco.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA070490-0020 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 242541 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 4, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
San Gabriel Valley; Part E; Page 3B; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
295 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BOOK TAKES STEP BACK INTO THE REGION'S PAST; 
</P>
<P>
THE SAN GABRIEL VALLEY: CHRONICLES OF AN ABUNDANT LAND, BY WILLIAM F. KING. 
WINDSOR PUBLICATIONS INC.. $27.95, 152 PAGES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BEN SULLIVAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> and the Spanish government established La Mision 
del <ORGANIZATION>Santo Arcangel San Gabriel de Los Temblores</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1769</DATE>, the surrounding land 
was marked chiefly by broad grass plains and clusters of oak and alder trees. 
</P>
<P>
Today, the area known as the <LOCATION>San Gabriel Valley</LOCATION> is better identified as home to 
nine freeways, more than two dozen cities and communities and close to 2 
million residents. 
</P>
<P>
That transition from virgin land to major metropolis is the subject of 
historian <PERSON>William F. King</PERSON>'s "The <LOCATION>San Gabriel Valley</LOCATION>: Chronicles of an Abundant 
Land." 
</P>
<P>
Commissioned by the <ORGANIZATION>Alhambra Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, the book looks at the area's 
history and its impact on the rest of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For example, as one of the state's most fertile regions, the valley was an 
original site of what was to become <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s booming citrus industry, King 
writes. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1940</DATE>, the state's first freeway was built in the <LOCATION>San Gabriel Valley</LOCATION>. The 
</P>
<P>
Today, <PERSON>King</PERSON> said, the <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> and the region's 
aerospace industry continue to affect the rest of the state, country and world. 
</P>
<P>
A native of <LOCATION>Glendora</LOCATION> and history professor at <ORGANIZATION>Mt. San Antonio College</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>King</PERSON> 
said much of the material for the book came from the college courses he 
teaches. 
</P>
<P>
"Chronicles of an Abundant Land" is one of a series of community and regional 
histories produced by <ORGANIZATION>Windsor Publications</ORGANIZATION>. Others in the series include the 
<LOCATION>San Fernando Valley</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>St. Paul</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minn</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
According to <LOCATION>Windsor</LOCATION> editor <PERSON>Jeffrey Reeves</PERSON>, the books chronicle histories of 
areas that might otherwise go unrecorded. "They tell a story that doesn't 
normally get told." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Elias J. Baldwin, second from right, bought part of the Santa Anita 
Anita Race Track and Arcadia now stand. ; Photo, Crowds gathered for 1954 
opening of San Bernardino Freeway. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Book Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06238221 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06238221 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COLLEGE; FOOTBALL; GAME; DATE; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  GOLDEN GATE CONFERENCE; Chabot  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  JUNIOR COLLEGE FOOTBALL SCHEDULES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Merced</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- Sequoias, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> --
<LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- (*)SJCC, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- at (*)<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>CCSF</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>Diablo Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Laney</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> --
(*)<LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- Sierra, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- at
<LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> -- <ORGANIZATION>Butte</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>CCSF</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Chabot</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Diablo Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 1</DATE> --
at (*)<LOCATION>Laney</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>West
Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> -- at (*)SJCC, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Diablo Valley</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 13</DATE> -- at
<LOCATION>Santa Rosa</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> -- <LOCATION>American
River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- at (*)SJCC, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- at (*)<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Chabot</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> --
at (*)<LOCATION>CCSF</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>Laney</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Laney</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> at <LOCATION>Shasta</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 20</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Sierra College</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> at <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 11</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> -- at
(*)<LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 25</DATE> -- (*)SJCC, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 1</DATE> -- (*)<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>Chabot</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Diablo Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>CCSF</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; CC <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Gavilan</LOCATION>, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Santa Rosa</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> -- <ORGANIZATION>Shasta</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> --
(*)<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- at (*)SJCC, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Chabot</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Nov. 1</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Diablo Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov.
16</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Laney</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE>
-- at <LOCATION>De Anza</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- Cabrillo, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> -- at <ORGANIZATION>Contra
Costa</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 11</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>Laney</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- (*)CCSF, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> --
(*)<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Chabot</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>Diablo
Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>San Jose City College</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> --
at <LOCATION>Los Medanos</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Sequoias</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- at
(*)<LOCATION>Chabot</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>Diablo Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 25</DATE> -- at
(*)<LOCATION>Laney</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>,
<TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- (*)CCSF, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> -- (*)<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>;
<DATE>Sept. 13</DATE> -- Foothill, <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>De Anza</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 4</DATE> --
<LOCATION>American River</LOCATION>, <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>Diablo Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> --
(*)<LOCATION>Laney</LOCATION>, <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 1</DATE> -- (*)CCSF, <TIME>2
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE> -- (*)<LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- at (*)<LOCATION>Delta</LOCATION> <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> --
at (*)<LOCATION>Chabot</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;   (*) -- GGC opponent.; COAST CONFERENCE; NORTH
DIVISION; De Anza; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- <LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- <LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>1
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Hancock</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Monterey</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>
-- <LOCATION>Porterville</LOCATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Hartnell</LOCATION>, <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 25</DATE> -- at 
<LOCATION>Foothill</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Los Medanos</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Kings River</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Foothill</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 13</DATE> -- At <LOCATION>West Valley</LOCATION>, <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Sept. 20</DATE> -- Butte, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> -- <ORGANIZATION>UC Davis JV</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 4</DATE> --
Cabrillo, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- At <LOCATION>Gavilan</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- At <PERSON>Hancock</PERSON>, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 25</DATE> --  De Anza, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> -- At  <LOCATION>Kings River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE>
--  <LOCATION>Los Medanos</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Kings River</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> --
<LOCATION>Monterey</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Siskiyous</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Sequoias</LOCATION>, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> -- <PERSON>Hancock</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Cabrillo</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> --
<LOCATION>Porterville</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Los Medanos</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> --  Foothill, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>De Anza</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Los
Medanos</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Marin</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Yuba</LOCATION>,, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>sept. 28</DATE> --
SJCC, <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> -- <PERSON>Hartnell</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Monterey</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct.
19</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Gavilan</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Kings
River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>De Anza</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Foothill</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- At Butte, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> --
At (*)<LOCATION>Porterville</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> -- <PERSON>Gavilan</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- At <LOCATION>Hartnell</LOCATION>,
<TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- At Cabrillo, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Los Medanos</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> -- At  <LOCATION>De Anza</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Kings River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE> -- At 
Foothill, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; SOUTH DIVISION; <LOCATION>Cabrillo</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Yuba</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE>
-- at <LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 4</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Foothill</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Kings
River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Hancock</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Porterville</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Monterey</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- at 
<LOCATION>Gavilan</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> --  <PERSON>Hartnell</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Gavilan</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- CCSF, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 20</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>American River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- Foothill, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Los Medanos</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- at 
<LOCATION>Porterville</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Monterey</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Hartnell</LOCATION>, <TIME>7:30
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> --  Cabrillo, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Hancock</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Allan
Hancock</PERSON>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> -- De Anza, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct.
5</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Kings River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- Foothill, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- 
Cabrillo, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Hartnell</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Porterville</LOCATION>, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Monterey</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> --  <PERSON>Gavilan</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Hartnell</LOCATION>;
<DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- <LOCATION>American River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Merced</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE>
-- at <LOCATION>Los Medanos</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- De Anza,
<TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Monterey</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> --  <PERSON>Hancock</PERSON>, <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> --  <PERSON>Gavilan</PERSON>, <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Porterville</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> --
at  <LOCATION>Cabrillo</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Monterey Peninsula</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> -- At <LOCATION>Kings River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- Mendocino, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> -- At <LOCATION>Marin</LOCATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> -- De
Anza, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- At <LOCATION>Los Medanos</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> --  <PERSON>Hartnell</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> -- At  <LOCATION>Gavilan</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> --  Cabrillo, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> -- 
<PERSON>Hancock</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> -- At  <LOCATION>Porterville</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Porterville</LOCATION>; <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> --
<PERSON>Victor Valley</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Chaffey</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>De Anza</LOCATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> -- at <LOCATION>Kings River</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Oct.
26</DATE> --  <PERSON>Gavilan</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Cabrillo</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE> -- at  <LOCATION>Hancock</LOCATION>,
<TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> --  <PERSON>Hartnell</PERSON>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE> --  <LOCATION>Monterey</LOCATION>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;     --
Division opponent.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910825  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  13D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,206  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, August 25, 1991
00238221,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011589-0156 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 5834 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 15, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 5; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
309 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MARTIN LUTHER KING DAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<DATE>Monday</DATE> marks the celebration of <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Day</ORGANIZATION>. The 60th anniversary of 
his birth is today. 
</P>
<P>
Closed: All government offices, courts, banks, schools, libraries and post 
offices. 
</P>
<P>
Open: Stock and commodity exchanges and most businesses. <ORGANIZATION>RTD</ORGANIZATION> buses will follow 
daily schedules. 
</P>
<P>
Among the celebrations on <DATE>Monday</DATE> are: 
</P>
<P>
* The <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Memorial Golf Tournament</ORGANIZATION> to benefit the <ORGANIZATION>Southern 
Christian Leadership Conference</ORGANIZATION> begins at <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> Rio <ORGANIZATION>Hondo Golf Course</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Downey</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* Volunteers will go door to door asking for donations for the third annual 
King Day drive for food and clothing for the homeless. Volunteers will gather 
at <TIME>10:30 a.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Holman Methodist Church</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>3320</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>W. Adams Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Bethel Lutheran 
Church</ORGANIZATION>, 700 E. 70th St., <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, and the Church in <LOCATION>Ocean Park</LOCATION>, 235 Hill 
<ORGANIZATION>St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* The fourth annual Kingdom Day Parade begins at <TIME>11 a.m</TIME>. The route travels east 
along <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Boulevard, beginning at <ORGANIZATION>Crenshaw Boulevard</ORGANIZATION> and 
ending at <ORGANIZATION>Exposition Park</ORGANIZATION> with a <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> rally. 
</P>
<P>
* Anti-apartheid student march and rally. It starts at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> at the site of 
the former <ORGANIZATION>South African Consulate</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>9107</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Wilshire Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>, and ends at 
consulate's current site, 510 <ORGANIZATION>N. La Cienega Blvd</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* Mayor <PERSON>Tom Bradley</PERSON> will address an ecumenical tribute at noon. Greater 
<ORGANIZATION>Cornerstone Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>5946</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>S. Figueroa St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* Student organizations of the <ORGANIZATION>Claremont Colleges</ORGANIZATION> will sponsor a commemorative 
ceremony at noon in the <ORGANIZATION>McKenna Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> on the <ORGANIZATION>Claremont McKenna College</ORGANIZATION> 
campus in <LOCATION>Claremont</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* The <ORGANIZATION>New CalArts Twentieth Century Players</ORGANIZATION> will perform two original pieces at 
a musical tribute to King at 12:10 p.m. <ORGANIZATION>Transamerica Center Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1149</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>S. 
Hill St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* The <ORGANIZATION>San Fernando Valley Interfaith Commemoration of King</ORGANIZATION>'s birthday begins at 
<TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> Valley <PERSON>Beth Shalom Temple</PERSON>, 15739 <LOCATION>Ventura Blvd.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Encino</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900913-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-13-90 1349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Moses-Egypt Bjt   09-13 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Moses-Egypt, Bjt,0694</SECOND>
<HEAD>Author Claims Moses was Egyptian Pharaoh</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Author uses spelling Akhenaten, but Ikhnaton conforms to
style.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GRAHAM HEATHCOTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The author of a new book claims the Jewish prophet
<PERSON>Moses</PERSON> was known to ancient Egyptians as <ORGANIZATION>Ikhnaton</ORGANIZATION>, the ruler and
religious reformer.
   ``I am convinced that I have identified <PERSON>Moses</PERSON> as <ORGANIZATION>Ikhnaton</ORGANIZATION>, the
prophet, poet and king in the <DATE>14th century B.C.</DATE>, who shut the
temples of the ancient gods, sent the priests home and declared
there was only one god,'' said <PERSON>Ahmed Osman</PERSON>.
   His book, ``Moses: Pharaoh of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>,'' was published in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Grafton Books</ORGANIZATION>. The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> rights are under negotiation.
   Osman's first book in <DATE>1987</DATE>, ``Stranger in the Valley of Kings,''
theorized that the mummy of a royal official named <PERSON>Yuya was Joseph</PERSON>,
the biblical figure with the coat of many colors who led the tribe
of <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> into <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.
   Osman, 55, an Egyptian who has pursued research in Egyptology
and the <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> for 25 years, is regarded by academics as a
controversial but respected outsider.
   Younes Ahmed el-Batrik, cultural counselor at the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian
Embassy</ORGANIZATION>, held a reception <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> to launch Osman's book.
``It's a very interesting subject and a very controversial book and
I will be interested to hear what the experts say about it,'' he
said.
   In identifying <PERSON>Moses</PERSON> with <ORGANIZATION>Ikhnaton</ORGANIZATION>, Osman builds on <PERSON>Sigmund
Freud</PERSON>'s last book, ``Moses and Monotheism,'' in which the father of
psychoanalysis commented on the similarity of the teachings of the
two ancients.
   Sydney Leperer, a senior history lecturer at <ORGANIZATION>Jews' College</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, said of Osman's Ikhnaton-Moses theory:
``There is a faint possibility that it is true, although I have my
doubts.''
   <PERSON>Naim Dangoor</PERSON>, editor of The Scribe, a journal on Babylonian
Jewry, said he had read and reviewed both of Osman's books. Osman
``knows a great deal about the period,'' and his theories ``invite
further investigation,'' <PERSON>Dangoor</PERSON> said.
   Osman said in an interview that scholars had always had
difficulty establishing links between any of the important figures
in the Old Testament and Egyptian history.
   ``I believe that <PERSON>Moses</PERSON> had an Israelite mother and an Egyptian
father,'' he said.
   ``He was the son of <ORGANIZATION>Pharaoh Amenhotep III</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Queen Tiye</PERSON>,
daughter of <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> the Patriarch. Tiye's first son had mysteriously
disappeared so when <PERSON>Moses</PERSON> was born, Tiye sent him by water for
safekeeping to her Israelite relatives. I think that was the origin
of the story that <PERSON>Moses</PERSON> was found in the bulrushes on the Nile.''
   After 17 years as pharaoh, <ORGANIZATION>Ikhnaton</ORGANIZATION> was deposed and succeeded by
the boy prince, <LOCATION>Tutankhamen</LOCATION>.
   ``I believe Ikhnaton survived and went into exile in <LOCATION>Sinai</LOCATION> with
a few followers,'' <PERSON>Osman</PERSON> said. ``When the oppressor Pharaoh
Horemheb died, <PERSON>Ikhnaton</PERSON> saw his chance to regain his throne as
there was no heir. He challenged <ORGANIZATION>Horemheb</ORGANIZATION>'s general, <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON>, for
the throne but <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON> attacked him and forced him to flee. The
flight was the Exodus, in <DATE>1333</DATE> B.C.''
   ``Ikhnaton and his followers attempted to enter Canaan, the
Promised Land, but were slaughtered by <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON>' successor, <PERSON>Seti</PERSON> I.
This fight is recorded in the <ORGANIZATION>Temple</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Karnak</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION>,'' the
author said.
   Jewish narratives are silent on any blood connection between
<PERSON>Moses</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> because of memories of the oppression, <PERSON>Osman</PERSON>
believes. ``However, the Talmud (the Jewish law) indicates that
<PERSON>Moses</PERSON> became a king and was forced to abdicate,'' he added.
   <PERSON>Eric Uphill</PERSON>, an Egyptologist at <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>University College</ORGANIZATION>,
said he helped and supported <PERSON>Osman</PERSON>'s research because he regarded
Osman as a serious student with extensive knowledge.
   Osman's manuscript was based on the right sources for Egyptian
history, <PERSON>Uphill</PERSON> said, but he would not comment on the conclusions
without further study.
   ``The problem with <PERSON>Moses</PERSON> is that the historical truth about him
is very unclear and lends itself to many theories, some of them
haywire,'' <PERSON>Leperer</PERSON> said.
   Dangoor said <PERSON>Moses</PERSON>' death is a mystery that is not resolved in
the Exodus accounts. ``Osman's explanation that he was killed by
Seti I is very plausible,'' <PERSON>Dangoor</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072990-0161 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 254201 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 29, 1990, Sunday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 18; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
683 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CONEJO VALLEY MADE IT TOUGH BUT OFTEN FOUND A WAY TO WIN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JEFF RILEY, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>Conejo Valley</LOCATION> established a reputation for playing exciting baseball this year, 
but it wasn't always in a positive manner. 
</P>
<P>
In fact, <ORGANIZATION>Conejo Valley</ORGANIZATION>'s young team had a tendency to be downright sporadic, as 
it was <DATE>Saturday</DATE> during a 10-9 win over District 16 rival <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> in the third 
round of the <ORGANIZATION>American Legion 6th Area</ORGANIZATION> playoffs. 
</P>
<P>
A gallon of bleach could not have cleaned <LOCATION>Conejo Valley</LOCATION>'s mess, but Coach <PERSON>Craig 
Sturges</PERSON> was still beaming over the opportunity to play at <ORGANIZATION>Jackie Robinson 
Stadium</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"We do some strange things out there, but you gotta love it," <PERSON>Sturges</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sturges</PERSON>' heart has been in his mouth lately. His team avoided a disaster by 
inches when <PERSON>Jim Chergey</PERSON>'s diving catch ended a nerve-wracking ninth. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Conejo Valley</LOCATION> took a 10-4 lead into the inning, but <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> (21-5), the 
District 16 champion, scored five runs -- four unearned -- courtesy of three 
<LOCATION>Conejo Valley</LOCATION> errors. 
</P>
<P>
"You probably saw more of that than I did, because I had my hands covering my 
eyes most of the time," <PERSON>Sturges</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
It was not the first time <LOCATION>Conejo Valley</LOCATION> fans had seen such unspectacular play. 
Last <DATE>spring</DATE>, all but one of <LOCATION>Conejo Valley</LOCATION>'s players attended Thousand Oaks 
High. The Lancers led the <ORGANIZATION>Marmonte League</ORGANIZATION> in errors last season, still, the 
team developed a knack for come-from-behind wins. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Garth Marcus</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Lancers</ORGANIZATION>' assistant coach, was at <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s game sporting a 
familiar grin. "TO baseball, baby," he said. <LOCATION>Conejo Valley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>a.k.a. Thousand 
Oaks</LOCATION>, had lost three of four games to <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> during the regular season. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Conejo Valley</LOCATION> continued to employ its cardiac style in the playoffs. It came 
from behind to beat <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>, 9-8, in 10 innings <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, and its shaky 
defense allowed <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> to crawl back into <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s contest. The magic 
ended a few hours later, however, when <LOCATION>Woodland Hills West</LOCATION> eliminated <LOCATION>Conejo 
Valley</LOCATION>, 13-8. 
</P>
<P>
"We emphasize a loose approach, but I think we played it a little too loose," 
<PERSON>Sturges</PERSON> said with a smile. 
</P>
<P>
Camarillo's <PERSON>Chris Borchard</PERSON>, who had led off the ninth inning <DATE>Saturday</DATE> with a 
walk and reached third on <PERSON>Jon McMullen</PERSON>'s single, scored after an error on <PERSON>Mike 
Mitchell</PERSON>'s grounder. <PERSON>Mike Muncy</PERSON>'s bloop single drove in two more runs and cut 
the deficit to 10-7. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Conejo Valley</LOCATION> pitcher <PERSON>Bryan Corey</PERSON>, who had relieved <PERSON>Nick Brown</PERSON>, dropped a pop 
fly that would have ended the game. Then <PERSON>Kasha Clemons</PERSON> -- who had hit his 11th 
home run in the sixth -- stepped into the batter's box representing the tying 
run. 
</P>
<P>
"I told (<ORGANIZATION>Conejo Valley</ORGANIZATION> third baseman) <PERSON>Billy Hall</PERSON> that if <PERSON>Kasha</PERSON> hits a three-run 
dinger, we'll have to run over and revive <PERSON>Sturges</PERSON>," <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Gary Wagner</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Clemons</PERSON> didn't homer but still gave <PERSON>Sturges</PERSON> palpitations with a long fly ball 
