<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-6696</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EE2AAADQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940528
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  28 MAY 94 / Scrabble takeover bid on the board
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, the biggest US toy and games group, yesterday made a surprise move
to become the world's undisputed Scrabble champion. It launched a Pounds
46.9m unsolicited bid for <ORGANIZATION>JW Spear</ORGANIZATION>, the British company which owns rights to
the board game outside <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
Scrabble, which ranks alongside Monopoly as a board game known throughout
the world, is produced in more than 20 languages and accounts for about 30
per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s Pounds 38.7m turnover. This year the company is planning
to introduce versions in Turkish and Hungarian.
Hasbro had sales of Dollars 2.7bn (Pounds 1.8bn) in <DATE>1993</DATE>. It has owned
Scrabble in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, where the game was invented more than 50
years ago, since <DATE>1989</DATE>.
It has been the UK company's biggest shareholder outside the Spear family
interests for the past four years, with 26.7 per cent. The trustees of some
Spear family trusts have given undertakings to accept the <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> bid in
respect of a further 24.9 per cent. The undertakings become irrevocable next
<DATE>Friday</DATE> if a higher offer is not received.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> is offering 900p a share, a premium of more than 21 per cent to the
last reported dealing price of 740p on <DATE>May 12</DATE>.
The Spear board will meet this morning to consider the bid. The company,
which in <DATE>March</DATE> raised its final dividend by 36 per cent on the back of a <MONEY>22
per cent</MONEY> rise in profits to Pounds 4.51m, is expected to find the offer
inadequate.
<PERSON>Mr Francis Spear</PERSON>, chairman, would make no comment <TIME>last night</TIME>, although he
dismissed any idea of a family row. <PERSON>Mr Paul Lipscomb</PERSON>, finance director, said
the bid had come like a bolt from the blue.
Spear's other products include Atmosfear, a board game linked to a video,
and more traditional pastimes such as Snakes and Ladders.
<PERSON>Mr Alan Hassenfeld</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, said the acquisition would be 'a
logical extension of <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s strategy to develop and expand its core
operations around the world'.
The origins of <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> lie in the <DATE>1930s</DATE> when it was developed as a
crossword game by <PERSON>Alfred Butts</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> architect whose practice was in
trouble after the Wall Street crash.
It was launched as <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1949</DATE> after almost two decades of rejection by
leading games players as too highbrow. The game took off in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> after
the chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Macy</ORGANIZATION>'s department store in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> became hooked and placed
a large order.
<PERSON>Mr Butts</PERSON>, a poor speller, earned only a <MONEY>5 cent</MONEY> royalty on each set.
Nevertheless, at the peak sales levels in the late <DATE>1950s</DATE> and <DATE>1960s</DATE>, he was
getting about Dollars 50,000 a year.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Hasbro Inc.
    JW Spear and Sons.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 26
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-6484</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EE3BUADLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940530
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 MAY 94 / UK Company News: JW Spear board split over Pounds 47m bid
from Hasbro
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW BOLGER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The board of <ORGANIZATION>JW Spear</ORGANIZATION>, which owns the rights to the board game Scrabble
outside <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, has been split by the unsolicited offer for the UK
company made by <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, the biggest US toys and games group.
At a board meeting on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, all but one of the Spear directors rejected
the Pounds 46.9m cash offer, which was launched late on <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
The exception was <PERSON>Mr Francis Spear</PERSON>, the group's chairman, who said he
thought the terms - worth 900p per share - were fair and reasonable.
In its offer, <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> said it intended to encourage <PERSON>Mr Spear</PERSON> to continue to
manage <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Enfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, manufacturing plant.
The rest of the Spear board, and the company's financial adviser, <LOCATION>Barings</LOCATION>,
said <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s offer was totally inadequate. The board instructed <LOCATION>Barings</LOCATION> to
solicit higher offers.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> is in a strong position, since it already owns a 26.7 per cent stake
in <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION> and has received undertakings to accept its offer from some Spear
family trusts which control a further 24.9 per cent.
The undertakings become irrevocable on <DATE>Friday</DATE> if a higher offer has not
received.
Barings is approaching other international toy companies which might be
interested in Spear, but the tight timetable makes it doubtful that another
buyer would have time to intervene. It seems most likely that the rest of
the board will try to obtain a higher offer from <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, in exchange for
their recommendation.
Spear is also probably of the greatest value to <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, which since <DATE>1989</DATE> has
owned Scrabble in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, where the game was invented.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> said the acquisition would be a logical extension of its strategy to
develop and expand core operations around the world.
It also seems unlikely that Spear could see off <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> by just selling the
Scrabble business to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> group.
Scrabble accounts for 40 per cent of the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> group's sales and one source
said 'the rest of the games portfolio hangs on the back of it.'
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s offer of 900p a share is a premium of more than 21 per cent to the
last reported dealing price of 740p on <DATE>May 12</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>JW Spear and Sons.
    Hasbro Inc.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
    USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
    P3942 Dolls and Stuffed Toys.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 16
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-5454</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFEASAB5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940604
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 JUN 94 / UK Company News: Mattel bids Pounds 52m for Spear - The
scrap over Scrabble gathers pace
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID WIGHTON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The battle between <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s two leading toy makers moved to the Scrabble
board yesterday after <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> trumped <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s bid for <ORGANIZATION>JW Spear</ORGANIZATION>, the word
game's UK maker.
In the corporate finance equivalent of getting all seven letters out on a
triple word score, <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s advisers solicited a Pounds 52m bid from <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>
which was launched just five minutes before <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s deadline.
The offer of Pounds 10 a share beats the 900p bid from <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> and was
immediately welcomed by <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s board. However, Action Man maker <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>,
which has the rights to Scrabble in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, is widely expected to
return with a higher offer.
'There must be a pretty good chance,' admitted a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> team.
The scrap over <LOCATION>Scrabble</LOCATION> continues a rivalry which spilled over into the law
courts 18 months ago when <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> claimed <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s Sindy doll looked too
similar to its own <ORGANIZATION>Barbie</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> dropped its lawsuit after <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> agreed to
give Sindy a facelift.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, which has held a 26.7 per cent stake in Spear since <DATE>1990</DATE>, launched
its bid after it received undertakings to accept the offer from <PERSON>Spear</PERSON> family
trusts which control a further 24.9 per cent. The undertakings were to
become irrevocable if a higher offer was not received by <TIME>midnight</TIME> on
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The trusts have little option but to accept the highest bid.
The original bid split <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s boardroom with <PERSON>Mr Francis Spear</PERSON>, chairman,
saying it was 'fair and reasonable' and the other directors dismissing it as
'totally inadequate'.
Although welcoming the new offer <PERSON>Mr Spear</PERSON> has yet to join the other
directors in advising shareholders that the <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> offer 'represents a
better prospect for the future development of the business of Spear'.
<PERSON>Mr Spear</PERSON> is close to the <PERSON>Hassenfeld</PERSON> family which founded <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> but the rest
of the management are understood to be worried that Spear would disappear
within <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s international games business.
In contrast, <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION> would be the first sizeable move into board games for
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, which has previously expressed interest in the area. This made it a
natural target for <ORGANIZATION>Barings</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s advisers, when searching for a rival
bidder. <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> finally responded at 5pm and <PERSON>Robert Fleming</PERSON>, its swiftly
appointed merchant bank, launched the bid six hours later.
The last recorded trade in Spear shares was at 740p on <DATE>May 12</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>'s
offer represents 18.4 times <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s earnings last year.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Mattel Inc.
    Hasbro Inc.
    JW Spear and Sons.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3942 Dolls and Stuffed Toys.
    P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 8
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-5899</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-ELAD8AEMFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941201
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 DEC 94 / Waddington passes Monopoly to Hasbro and collects Pounds 50m
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BLACKWELL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Hasbro yesterday bought <PERSON>Waddington</PERSON>'s games division for Pounds 50m in cash,
giving the biggest US toy and games group a monopoly on Monopoly, the
world's best-selling board game.
Mention Monopoly in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, and people immediately think of <PERSON>Waddington</PERSON>. But
the archetypal game of capitalists, once banned in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> as
ideologically unsound, was invented in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1930s</DATE>.
Waddington has always been a printing company, diversifying into games in
the <DATE>1920s</DATE> by printing playing cards. The grandfather of <PERSON>Mr Victor Watson</PERSON>,
who retired as chairman <DATE>last year</DATE>, obtained the Monopoly licence for the
<ORGANIZATION>British Empire</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1935</DATE>. The licence was granted by <ORGANIZATION>Parker Brothers</ORGANIZATION> of the
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, now part of the <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> empire. Hasbro itself had a licence to market
<ORGANIZATION>Cluedo</ORGANIZATION>, owned by <PERSON>Waddington</PERSON>, outside the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Michael Buckley</PERSON>, chief executive of <LOCATION>Waddington</LOCATION>, said that the sale of the
games division was viewed with some regret, but it was matched by pleasure
at how the group could use the cash. 'The games division is a super company,
but we did not think we could make it any bigger or better.'
The deal will leave <PERSON>Waddington</PERSON> cash positive to the tune of Pounds 13m. It
plans to invest further in both the printing and packaging divisions.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> was pipped to the post this <DATE>summer</DATE> in a battle for Scrabble with
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, its main rival in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> market. <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> paid Pounds 62m for JW
Spear, the UK company with the rights to Scrabble outside <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, which owns the <ORGANIZATION>North American Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> rights, said it felt the
winning price for Spear, at about 21 times earnings, was too high. However,
it is paying about 21 times earnings for the <ORGANIZATION>Waddington</ORGANIZATION> division, which made
operating profits of Pounds 3.5m on sales of Pounds 25.9m in the year to
<DATE>April</DATE>, because of the quality of the portfolio.
<PERSON>Mr Brian Ellis</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro UK</ORGANIZATION>, said the <PERSON>Waddington</PERSON> catalogue had 850 items,
only about 60 of which were games. Monopoly, which sold 300,000 sets in the
UK <DATE>last year</DATE>, represented only 15 per cent of the turnover.
'It is much more of a general toy company than a games company,' he said,
citing in particular the Get Set craft products, which are expecting 35 per
cent growth this year.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Hasbro Inc.
    John Waddington.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
    USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9651 Regulation of Miscellaneous Commercial Sectors.
    P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
    P2759 Commercial Printing, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    COMP  Disposals.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 25
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060189-0067 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 64373 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 1, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Glendale; Part 9; Page 1; Column 2 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
638 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
EXCHANGING VOWELS; 
</P>
<P>
SCRABBLE FANS FIND GAME A MARRIAGE OF CHALLENGE, DISCIPLINE, MENTAL STIMULATION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LISA TURNER, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Under rows of harsh fluorescent lights, they sit at folding tables, hunched 
over boards covered with small, square tiles. 
</P>
<P>
The room is silent as 10 pairs of players sweat it out in a battle of wits, 
probing their minds for obscure words and letter combinations. 
</P>
<P>
They're playing Scrabble, but this is not exactly the game that many people 
remember playing with their grandmothers over pound cake and iced tea on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> 
afternoons. 
</P>
<P>
These are hard-core Scrabble players, many of whom also play chess, who enjoy 
the game for its challenge, discipline and mental stimulation. 
</P>
<P>
And they take their games seriously, memorizing hundreds of obscure words and 
mastering strategies and lingo. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Eagle Rock Scrabble Club</ORGANIZATION> was started in <DATE>July</DATE> by <PERSON>George Heussenstamm</PERSON>, a 
classical composer who teaches music composition and theory at <LOCATION>Cal State Los 
Angeles</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Cal State Northridge</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
300 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Clubs 
</P>
<P>
The club, one of more than 300 in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, meets from 7 to <TIME>10 p.m.</TIME> 
the second and <DATE>fourth Wednesday</DATE> of the month in the <ORGANIZATION>Yosemite Senior Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Members pay <MONEY>$1</MONEY> for admission, which covers <ORGANIZATION>Heussenstamm</ORGANIZATION>'s mailings and the 
cookies and coffee provided at the meetings. 
</P>
<P>
When Heussenstamm, a veteran Scrabble aficionado, started the club, there were 
only a handful of players. 
</P>
<P>
Now the group averages 17, and he expects it to grow, following a national 
trend of increasing interest in the game, he said. 
</P>
<P>
"It's something of an obsession," <PERSON>Heussenstamm</PERSON> said. "It's the kind of thing 
that once you start, it's hard to stop." 
</P>
<P>
The club is an eclectic mix of people. At one table, a thin, dark man is 
listening through earphones to a portable tape player, moving his head slightly 
as his eyes flicker back and forth across his tiles. 
</P>
<P>
His opponent is an unemployed <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veteran who is also an avid chess player. 
</P>
<P>
At another table, a 22-year-old physics major from <ORGANIZATION>Occidental College</ORGANIZATION> is 
battling a heavyset woman who is an administrator with the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> school 
district. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Highly Organized 
</P>
<P>
Scrabble clubs are highly organized and strictly follow a set of <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> rules 
promulgated by <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble Crossword Game Players Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a national organization. 
</P>
<P>
Games are timed using chess clocks, and each player is allowed three minutes 
per move. And the players are serious about their games and strategies. 
</P>
<P>
Like chess, <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> entails strategic planning. 
</P>
<P>
Players learn rack management, a method of keeping a balance of vowels and 
consonants. Good players also have to know when to pass their turn, and how to 
work toward bingos -- a move in which all seven letters are used in one turn. 
But the most important strategy is building vocabulary. 
</P>
<P>
True Scrabble aficionados fervently study their <ORGANIZATION>Official Scrabble Players 
Dictionary</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
They pore over lists of words, memorizing thousands of two- and three-letter 
words and their possible prefixes and suffixes to help them in their 
strategies. 
</P>
<P>
Some of the word lists are so obscure that they almost look like random pages 
from a beginning Latin handbook. 
</P>
<P>
Scrabble players learn such oddities as "os," meaning orifice; "ta," an 
expression of gratitude, and "ho," an exclamation of surprise. 
</P>
<P>
"The key is in knowing your words," <PERSON>Heussenstamm</PERSON> said. "You have to build a big 
vocabulary if you want to be good at this game. It involves more than just 
slapping letters on a board." 
</P>
<P>
Someone bellows "challenge" from the far corner of the room, and <PERSON>Heussenstamm</PERSON> 
scurries away to settle the dispute. 
</P>
<P>
Heussenstamm started the club in <ORGANIZATION>Eagle Rock</ORGANIZATION> because he wanted to be able to 
play in a group close to his La Crescenta home. 
</P>
<P>
But as director, he has duties to fulfill. 
</P>
<P>
If an even number of players show up, Heussenstamm doesn't play, and he must 
act as referee in the case of disputed words. 
</P>
<P>
"It's been somewhat sacrificial for me," <PERSON>Heussenstamm</PERSON> said. "I don't get to 
play much any more." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, The Eagle Rock Scrabble Club was started by George Heussenstamm, who 
says it's "something of an obsession." Games are timed, and strategy is serious 
business. ; Photo, After a losing game, Gwen Bishop of Eagle Rock reviews 
opponent's words. TORU KAWANA / Los Angeles Times; Photo, ; Photo, 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122990-0088 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 328774 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 29, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 13; Column 5; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
282 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COMPUTAINMENT: DELUXE SCRABBLE SCORES WITH NONTRADITIONALISTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JEANE deCOSTER and DAVID CROOK, SPECIAL TO THE TIMES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Virgin Mastertronics</PERSON>' "The Deluxe Computer Edition of Scrabble" trades away 
much of the familiar appeal of the classic board game for some intriguing bells 
and whistles. Serious players looking to exercise their skills and stretch 
their vocabularies probably will embrace the new features. 
</P>
<P>
But traditionalists will long for the competition, surprise and camaraderie 
possible only between human players. 
</P>
<P>
In its most basic form, this computer version of Scrabble -- actually a totally 
redesigned update of an earlier electronic version of the game -- closely 
resembles the actual board game. After fellow players -- human or computer -- 
and difficultly levels are chosen, random letters are assigned to each player. 
</P>
<P>
Words are formed and placed on the board in the same way you would with actual 
tiles. A very welcome calculating feature keeps track of the point values for 
all levels of scoring. 
</P>
<P>
Unfortunately, however, the computer version doesn't do a very good job of 
hiding tiles. Whether playing the computer or another human, it is all but 
impossible not to know what your opponent has in his/her/its rack. Using the 
hide feature doesn't help much either. 
</P>
<P>
We also found a lot to be desired with the huge (2.5 megabytes) dictionary 
program that comes with the game: golfer and offer for two. The game makers 
promised the entire "Official Scrabble Player's Dictionary," but our trusty 
<DATE>1979</DATE> paperback edition turned out to be a bit more complete than the <DATE>1990</DATE> 
electronic one. 
</P>
<P>
"Deluxe Computer Scrabble" has enough pluses to make it as a good solitaire 
game, but it is definitely not a substitute for an evening with the original 
board game and a couple of good friends. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, DELUXE SCRABBLE Rating: *** IBM &amp; compatibles, Tandy 1000; 640K. 
List: $59.95 Computer games are rated on a five-star system, from one star for 
poor to five for excellent. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-15399</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EGJAPACHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940709
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  09 JUL 94 / UK Company News: Hasbro raises offer for JW Spear by Pounds
2 a share
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BLACKWELL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, the largest US toy and games group, yesterday raised its bid for <ORGANIZATION>JW
Spear</ORGANIZATION>, the UK company which owns the rights to the Scrabble board game
outside <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>US</ORGANIZATION> group, which already owns the North American rights for Scrabble as
well as 26.7 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>, increased its offer to Pounds 11 a share,
valuing Spear at Pounds 57.3m. It is also offering a loan note alternative.
The new terms are 100p above an offer from <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, the rival US toy company,
and 200p ahead of its original offer, made at the end of <DATE>May</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mr Norman Walker</PERSON>, a director of <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro UK</ORGANIZATION>, said the increased offer
represented 'significant enhanced value for shareholders' and reflected
<ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s past performance and future prospects.
<PERSON>Mr Paul Lipscombe</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s finance director, said the board would meet next
week 'to consider all aspects of the situation'. The latest offer closes on
<DATE>August 5</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, whose offer closes on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, said it had noted the new
bid and was considering its options.
Hasbro received no acceptances for its original offer, which was launched
after trustees of some Spear family trusts had given undertakings to sell
their 24.9 per cent stake unless a higher offer was received in three
working days.
The Spear board sought a white knight and found <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, which launched its
bid at five minutes to <TIME>midnight</TIME> on the <DATE>last day</DATE>.
Hasbro went to the <ORGANIZATION>High Court</ORGANIZATION>, claiming that <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>'s late offer had not
been properly announced; but the judge released the trustees from any
obligation to sell their shares to <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>.
The Spear board, which was not recommending either offer, has since allowed
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> to take a more detailed look at the company and its forecasts.
The trustees have given no further undertakings to <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>. Hasbro argues
that its offer gives the trusts and families that own a large part of Spear
an opportunity to escape from the limited liquidity of the shares.
The last recorded trade in Spear shares was at 740p on <DATE>May 12</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s
latest offer represents 20 times Spear's earnings last year.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Hasbro Inc.
    JW Spear and Sons.
    Hasbro UK.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-2069</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFUD5AE1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940621
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  21 JUN 94 / UK Company News: Hasbro may raise its 900p a share offer for
JW Spear
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BLACKWELL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, the biggest US toy and games group, yesterday did not rule out
raising its bid in the battle for JW Spear, the British company which owns
the rights to the Scrabble board game outside <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
So far <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, which owns Scrabble in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, has received no
acceptances for its 900p a share bid, launched at the end of <DATE>last month</DATE>.
Yesterday it extended its offer, which values Spear at Pounds 46.9m, to <DATE>July
11</DATE>.
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, the rival US toy group which made a last minute bid for <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>,
yesterday posted its offer document to Spear shareholders, offering Pounds
10 a share in cash or loan notes.
<PERSON>Mr Nigel Hutton</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro UK</ORGANIZATION> said the group was still considering all its
options, and would be looking at both the Spear defence document and the
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> offer document closely.
The Spear defence document is expected later this week. The board is not
expected to find either offer fair and reasonable, although the higher
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> bid will be preferred.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, which already owns more than 26 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>, launched its bid
after trustees of some Spear family trusts had given undertakings to sell a
further 24.9 per cent unless a higher offer was received in three working
days.
The <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> bid was launched at five minutes to <TIME>midnight</TIME> on the <DATE>last day</DATE>.
Last week a <ORGANIZATION>High Court</ORGANIZATION> judge released the trustees from any obligation to
sell their shares to <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, who had claimed that <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>'s late offer had
not been properly announced.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Hasbro Inc.
    Mattel Inc.
    JW Spear and Sons.
    Hasbro UK.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
    USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3942 Dolls and Stuffed Toys.
    P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06262267 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06262267 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; EDUCATION; GAME  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE FIRST World Scrabble Championship will be next week in London, with
competitors from 20 countries vying for the $10,000 first prize. It should be
fun to hear or read the news reports about this championship because they are
certain to feature the most obscure, obsolete, and lengthy words played during
the final game.;   Most Scrabble players realize, however, that it is not the
very long words, but the very short words instead that are the keys to victory
in this game. There are 86 two-letter words, for example, that are considered
acceptable for Scrabble play, but many (such as "jo," "li," and "od") are just
as obscure as their sesquipedalian counterparts. (Let's see, that's 1 for the
"s," 2, 3, plus 10 for the "q," plus 1, plus 1, and 3 for the "p" . . . )  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  East Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TAKE THE SCARE OUT OF SCRABBLE FOR CHILDREN  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Education; Family Learning Also ran in EX1/3, EX4/4 WL4; Dr. William F.
Russell's books for parents and children include "Classics to Read Aloud to
Your Children" and "Classic Myths to Read  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     So, if this most-popular word game (<PERCENT>27 percent</PERCENT> of American homes have at
least one Scrabble set) hinges on words that aren't a common part of any
adult's speaking or writing vocabulary, can it possibly be a good teaching or
learning tool for parents to use with their children?;   THE answer is yes,
but not if it is played the way it is in championships or in most competitions
among adults. The game of Scrabble was designed to put a premium on knowledge
and skill during the course of play. There is a measure of luck involved (as
in the drawing of letters, for example), but <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> is a very scary game to
those who feel less than confident in their own vocabulary or spelling
ability.;   And so when children, even teen-age children, are asked to join a
<ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> game with their parents, they are intimidated by the likelihood that
their comparative ignorance of words and spellings will be exposed during the
play, and they will not only lose, but be embarrassed at the same time.;   One
way to include people of varying abilities in a single game of <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> is to
give all players a pencil and note pad, so that they can write down various
words and letter combinations before having to display their selection on the
board. This levels the playing field somewhat by reducing the advantage of
those who can "see" various words in their mind without having to write them
out.;   You can also make a dictionary available for players to use during the
game -- not just for challenges. This practice not only encourages and builds
dictionary skills, but it also helps the entire family become more familiar
with the "family dictionary." (This is yet another reason not to select a
bigger-than-a-breadbox version for your home.);   A THIRD technique for
encouraging "family Scrabble" is to play in teams rather than as individuals.
The weakest and strongest players can be paired as a team (on opposite sides
of the table), and their scores combined. In this way, children can
concentrate on contributing some points, even just a few, at each turn, rather
than being solely responsible for their total score at the end of the game.;  
All three techniques can, of course, be employed at the same time, and other
adaptations are possible as well.;   There are many language benefits that can
come from playing Scrabble, including a knowledge of letter frequencies,
common word endings, and letter combinations. But there are even more benefits
that can come from "family Scrabble," if we will just tune ourselves to our
children's abilities and fears, and adapt this game, like all family games, in
ways that will make everyone eager to participate.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  William Russel column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910918  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  629  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, September 18, 1991
00262267,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-4308</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-ECKD9AFJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940311
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 MAR 94 / UK Company News: JW Spear jumps to Pounds 4.51m
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BLACKWELL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
JW <ORGANIZATION>Spear &amp; Sons</ORGANIZATION>, maker of Scrabble and other indoor games, is proposing to
lift its full-year dividend by 36 per cent on the back of a substantial
increase in profits for <DATE>1993</DATE>.
The pre-tax figure rose by 22 per cent from Pounds 3.71m to Pounds 4.51m.
Earnings per share increased from 47.3p to 56.55p.
The recommended final dividend of 16p (11.5p) lifts the total pay-out for
the year from 14p to 19p.
Turnover increased by nearly Pounds 6m to Pounds 38.7m. The figure contains
Pounds 4.49m from acquisitions, including a contribution from the games
division of Murfett Regency (<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>) acquired last <DATE>May</DATE> for Pounds 1.8m
cash. The purchase brought with it the rights to <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
Scrabble is made in more than 20 languages and accounts for about 30 per
cent of turnover. This year sees the introduction of versions in Turkish and
Hungarian.
<PERSON>Mr Michael Bucher</PERSON>, managing director, said <DATE>1993</DATE> marked the sixth successive
year of increases in turnover and profits 'in spite of generally poor market
conditions for traditional games in comparison with video and computer
games.'
The company has fought back with the introduction of board games linked to
video cassettes and compact discs. Overall, it has introduced 121 new and
revised items this year.
Last year reduced UK sales were offset by strong growth in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and the
addition of the Benelux countries and the Australian markets.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>JW Spear and Sons.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>FIN  Annual report.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 25
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-14857</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EGMDEAGSFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940712
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  12 JUL 94 / Mattel lifts bid to win battle for JW Spear
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BLACKWELL and RICHARD TOMKINS
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> yesterday snatched victory from rival US toy group <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> in the
battle for JW Spear, the British company which owns the rights to the
Scrabble board game outside <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, the maker of Barbie dolls, raised its offer for shares in Spear from
Pounds 10 to Pounds 11.50, valuing the company at Pounds 62m. Last <DATE>Friday</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> increased its offer from Pounds 9 to Pounds 11.
Spear's directors and family trustees have irrevocably pledged 2,695,000
shares, or 51.2 per cent of the company, to <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>. Last night, <PERSON>Mr Francis
Spear</PERSON>, chairman said: 'We at <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION> are happy with the revised offer. We
believe it reflects a fair and reasonable value for the company.'
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> entered the battle for Spear as a white knight after <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> launched
a surprise bid in late <DATE>May</DATE>. It wanted a more secure foothold in the market
for board games.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> already owns the North American rights for <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION>, as well as a
26.7 per cent stake in Spear. The company said <TIME>last night</TIME> that it was
considering its position and would be making a statement today. However, it
said it considered Pounds 11 a 'a very full offer'. It appears likely that
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> will now sell its stake.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s original offer was made after it received undertakings from the
trustees of some <PERSON>Spear</PERSON> family trusts to sell their 24.9 per cent stake
unless a higher offer was received within three working days.
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> launched its counter attack at five minutes to <TIME>midnight</TIME> on the <DATE>last
day</DATE>. Hasbro went to the <ORGANIZATION>High Court</ORGANIZATION>, claiming <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>'s offer had not been
properly announced. But the judge released the trustees from any obligation
to sell their shares.
The Spear board, which was split by the original offer, was not recommending
either bidder. Hasbro raised the stakes <DATE>last Friday</DATE> after Spear allowed it
to take a closer look at the company and its forecasts.
The last recorded trade in Spear shares was at 740p on <DATE>May 12</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>'s
offer represents an exit multiple of 21.1 times the company's earnings last
year.
<PERSON>Richard Tomkins</PERSON> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> adds: <PERSON>Mr John Amerman</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> chairman and chief
executive, said he was 'delighted' at the victory. 'This is an excellent
outcome not only for the shareholders but also for <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s employees and
customers,' he said.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Mattel Inc.
    JW Spear and Sons.
    Hasbro Inc.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3942 Dolls and Stuffed Toys.
    P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06191210 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06191210 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  WOMAN; GAME; PROFESSIONAL; DEATH; OBITUARY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Ethel Cannon Sherard, affectionately known as "the Scrabble lady" and author
of a popular word book for players of the board game, has died. She was 95.;  
 Ms. Sherard died June 30 at Huntington Memorial Hospital, her daughter,
Gwendolyn Sherard-Bishop, said Monday.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ETHEL SHERARD, 95, 'THE SCRABBLE LADY'  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Obituaries  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     A longtime Scrabble expert, she continued to play in regional tournaments
despite failing health, and won a tourney in <LOCATION>Riverside</LOCATION> four years ago.;    At
age 84, <PERSON>Ms. Sherard</PERSON> published The Double List Word Book, a reference work of
100,000 words for use by <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> and crossword puzzle fans. The book lists
words by size and common first and last letters.;    "The book might seem like
a lot of work to some people, but it didn't seem like work to me," <PERSON>Ms. Sherard</PERSON>
said earlier this year. "I've always liked word games and taking big words and
finding small words in them.";    <PERSON>Ms. Sherard</PERSON> started playing Scrabble in the
<DATE>1930s</DATE>, when it was known as Criss-Cross. The title changed to <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1948</DATE>. The game's premise is to form interlocking words in crossword fashion
across a 225-square grid and score points.;    "She bought it for us as a
Christmas gift one year and the family began playing it," her daughter said.
"We started buying all kinds of dictionaries so we could have more words.
Everything went from there.";    <PERSON>Ms. Sherard</PERSON> frequently served as a word judge
at national Scrabble tournaments. She celebrated her 95th birthday in <DATE>January</DATE>
playing in a Scrabble contest at <LOCATION>Pasadena City College.</LOCATION>;    Born in <LOCATION>La Grange</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1896</DATE>, <PERSON>Ms. Sherard</PERSON> graduated from <LOCATION>Atlanta University</LOCATION>. She operated a
grocery store in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and worked as a clerk with the federal government.;  
 She later moved to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and was a resident of the <ORGANIZATION>Eagle Rock</ORGANIZATION> area of
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> when she died. Her husband, <PERSON>Benjamin Sherard</PERSON>, died five years
ago.;    In addition to daughter, <PERSON>Gwendolyn</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ms. Sherard</PERSON> is
survived by a son, <PERSON>Edgar Sherard</PERSON>, of <PERSON>Gary</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>; eight grandchildren; and 13
great-grandchildren.;    Funeral services were scheduled today at <ORGANIZATION>Cedar Park
Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Pasadena  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910709  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  345  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday July 9, 1991
00191210,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-4275</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFJCMAD1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940610
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 JUN 94 / UK Company News: Judge to rule over Scrabble squabble
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BLACKWELL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
A High Court judge will next <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> be asked to decide on the squabble over
<LOCATION>Scrabble</LOCATION>, the board game which is the main target for two US toy groups
battling for control of <ORGANIZATION>JW Spear</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, the biggest US toy company and maker of Action Man, is proceeding
against trustees controlling 24.9 per cent of the family-run group. It will
argue that the trustees are still bound by agreements to sell the stake, in
spite of an eleventh hour bid by <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> rival.
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, maker of Barbie dolls, yesterday noted news of the court case 'with
regret.' The group said its offer of Pounds 10 a share - Pounds 1 above the
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> offer - was made at <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s invitation.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, which launched its Pounds 46.9m unsolicited bid on <DATE>May 27</DATE>, has been
the biggest shareholder outside the Spear family for the past four years,
with 26.7 per cent. The trustees had given irrevocable undertakings to
accept unless a better offer was made within three business days.
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>'s offer, valuing Spear at Pounds 52m, was made at just five minutes
to <TIME>midnight</TIME> on the final day.
The announcement was lodged with the <ORGANIZATION>Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, while the <ORGANIZATION>Takeover
Panel</ORGANIZATION> and both sets of advisers were informed of the offer.
Hasbro claims that this was not a public announcement, and so the
undertakings remain valid.
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> has been advised that the announcement of its bid was 'sufficient to
release the trustees from their undertakings to <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>.' It understood that
the trustees had received identical advice.
If <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> wins on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, it will be able to declare its offer
unconditional. If it loses it could, under the terms of its original bid,
increase its offer.
The Spear board - apart from <PERSON>Mr Francis Spear</PERSON>, chairman - yesterday
reiterated its description of the <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> offer as 'wholly inadequate.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>JW Spear and Sons.
    Hasbro Inc.
    Mattel Inc.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3942 Dolls and Stuffed Toys.
    P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-4970</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFHA0AD9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940607
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  07 JUN 94 / UK Company News: Hasbro turns up the heat in scrabble for
Spear
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PEGGY HOLLINGER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Hasbro yesterday turned up the heat in its battle for control of <ORGANIZATION>JW Spear</ORGANIZATION>,
the games group, with a veiled threat of legal action against trustees
controlling 24.9 per cent of the family-run group.
The US toy maker said the trustees were still bound by agreements to sell
the stake, in spite of an eleventh hour bid by <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, the rival toys group.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> launched its Pounds 9 a share bid for <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>, maker of the word game
<ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION>, 10 days ago, valuing the group at Pounds 47m. The trustees had
agreed to sell their shares to <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, as long as Spear did not publicly
announce an alternative, higher bid in three working days.
On the <DATE>last day</DATE>, at just five minutes to <TIME>midnight</TIME>, <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> jumped in with a
Pounds 10 a share offer valuing Spear at Pounds 52m. The announcement was
lodged with the <ORGANIZATION>Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, while the <ORGANIZATION>Takeover Panel</ORGANIZATION> and both sets of
advisers were informed of the offer.
Hasbro now claims this was not a public announcement and so the undertakings
are valid. 'All the steps were taken of getting ready to make a public
announcement, but no public announcement was ever made,' said <PERSON>Mr Francis
Jackson</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>J Henry Schroder Wagg</ORGANIZATION>, its advisers and merchant bank.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> said it was considering its options regarding legal action if the
trustees did not adhere to the undertakings. No response had yet been
received from the trustees.
Spear rejected <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s claim and said it had received professional advice
that the <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> offer had been validly announced. The board, with the
exception of <PERSON>Mr Francis Spear</PERSON>, the chairman, was recommending <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>'s
offer. <PERSON>Mr Spear</PERSON> originally backed <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>'s offer, but has been silent since
the <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> bid.
The regulatory authorities appear to be divided on the issue raised by
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>. Under <ORGANIZATION>Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> guidelines, a public announcement is made by
notifying the <ORGANIZATION>Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> and at least two national newspapers and two
news wires.
However, <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s advisers, the merchant bank <PERSON>Barings</PERSON>, are understood to have
consulted the <ORGANIZATION>Takeover Panel</ORGANIZATION> on their interpretation of a public
announcement. While the <ORGANIZATION>Panel</ORGANIZATION> would not comment on the contract signed by
the trustees, it is believed to have defined a public announcement as
notification to itself, the <ORGANIZATION>Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, the company, <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> and both
sets of advisers.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Hasbro Inc.
    JW Spear and Sons.
    Mattell Inc.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
    USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-11226</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DEECIAEVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930505
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  05 MAY 93 / UK Company News: JW Spear makes Australian buy
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
JW Spear, which makes Scrabble and other games, is acquiring the games
division of Murfett Regency (<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>) for ADollars 1.38m (Pounds 620,000)
cash on completion.
Included in the deal are the total rights to <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, which
consolidates <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s ownership of the rights to <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION> throughout the
world outside <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
Sales of the Australian business were ADollars 5.78m for the year to <DATE>June 30
1992</DATE>; it is currently operating at about break-even.
The new company will trade as <ORGANIZATION>JW Spear &amp; Sons</ORGANIZATION> from <DATE>July 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>JW Spear and Sons.
    Murfett Regency (Australia).
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
    AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
    COMP  Disposals.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-3322</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFODGAD6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940615
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 JUN 94 / Battle for Scrabble maker reopened
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN MASON, Law Courts Correspondent
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The battle for control of <ORGANIZATION>JW Spear</ORGANIZATION>, the maker of the '<ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION>' board game,
was thrown open again yesterday when a High Court judge released the
company's trustees from any obligation to sell their shares to <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, the
US toy group.
The judge ruled that <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, a rival US toy company, had acted properly in
announcing an improved offer five minutes before the deadline for the
operation of a clause allowing the trustees to be released from an
irrevocable undertaking to sell a controlling interest to <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>.
The court's decision now leaves the Spear trustees - who own 24.9 per cent
of the company - free to accept the <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> bid or any higher one.
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> was <TIME>last night</TIME> considering its options: to mount an appeal against
the ruling, out-bid <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, or walk away. The company is certain to reach
its decision before <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, after which an undertaking given yesterday by
the trustees not to sell their shares to anyone else will expire.
The dispute arose after the Spear trustees gave irrevocable undertakings on
<DATE>May 27</DATE> to accept a Pounds 46.9m bid from <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> which, with 26.7 per cent,
has been the largest shareholder outside the <PERSON>Spear</PERSON> family for the past four
years. However, <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> responded with a Pounds 52m bid. This was announced
at five minutes to <TIME>midnight</TIME> on <DATE>June 2</DATE>, the final day when the escape clause
applied to allow the trustees to accept higher bids.
The legal action centred on whether <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> had fulfilled its obligations to
make a public announcement of its offer. <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> had informed the <ORGANIZATION>Stock
Exchange</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Takeover Panel</ORGANIZATION> in the minutes leading up to the final
deadline, but not the national press.
Lawyers for <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> argued that the offer should also have been announced to
at least two national newspapers and two UK wire services.
Giving judgment, <PERSON>Mr Justice Chadwick</PERSON> said that when the escape clause was
agreed between <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> and the trustees, it was likely that their intention
was to guarantee the commitment of third-party bidders rather than informing
the investing public.
Spear, its trustees and <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> welcomed yesterday's outcome.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>JW Spear and Sons.
    Mattel Inc.
    Hasbro Inc.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9211 Courts.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 23
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910927-0035
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910927-0035.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   My Brother the Scrabble Whiz
   ----
   By Paul B. Carroll
</HL>
<DATE>
09/25/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A8
</SO>
<LP>
   The first-ever World Scrabble Championship begins tomorrow
in London, and leading the U.S. delegation will be a
35-year-old who won a tense victory at the biggest U.S.
tournament in Cincinnati last month. He happens to be my
older brother, Charles.
   Chuck has come a long way. He had seemed normal as a
toddler -- at least to our parents -- but our father got an
inkling of what was in store when he asked five-year-old
Chuck how he did on a test. Laconic even then, Chuck replied:
"Let's see. Four columns. Sixteen rows. Sixty-four questions.
Missed one. Got 63 out of 64 right." By first grade, he was
helping our babysitter with her algebra. By third grade, he
was doing our father's budgets for his part of Westinghouse's
public-relations operation.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In high school outside <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> and in college at
<LOCATION>Carnegie Mellon</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> earned full credentials as a math nerd
and computer weenie, but the game of bridge had become his
passion. He, a partner and two innocent bystanders once drove
two hours to a dog track, and the two partners discussed a
single bridge hand the entire trip. After betting for four
hours, <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> and his partner resumed in mid-sentence and
discussed the same hand the whole way back. Chuck became a
Life Master, bridge's highest rank, at age 20 and finished
second in a national event. Then, in his mid-20s, he became
bored and dropped the game cold.
   Rubik's Cube fascinated him briefly. During a lull as he
and I toured <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> some 10 years ago, I noticed he was
scribbling strings of numbers and letters on a scrap of
paper. I finally figured out that he was trying to
mathematically work through the cube's permutations.
   Chuck soon moved on to gambling, quitting his job as a
computer programmer to move to <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> for four months. He
made money counting cards at blackjack and lightening the
wallets of the drunk tourists at the poker table. But he lost
much of the money by experimenting with systems for betting
on sports.
   The interest in gambling ended abruptly, too, and <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON>,
by now a manager for a computer company in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, took
up Scrabble. His assault on the game began with some
simple-enough pointers: 1) Learn the 86 two-letter words
because they let you connect to existing words; 2) Pay more
attention to what's on the board than what tiles are in your
rack; 3) Worry about what tiles you're stuck with after you
play a word. But most of his approach falls into the
don't-try-this-at-home-kids-because-this-is-for-
professionals-realm.
   Among other things, he has used a computer to generate
lists of words that include seven of the letters he is most
likely to find on his rack, plus one more letter. Chuck
drills himself on those words to keep them fresh in his mind.
He plays Scrabble six hours or so a week and studies for more
than an hour a day. The image that endures of him is of the
dutiful father strolling around his living room carrying a
screaming infant in a Snugli and studying his flashcards. At
his first nationals, in <DATE>1988</DATE>, <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> finished 16th. "Lucky,"
he said. The next year, he slipped to 19th. "Unlucky," he
explained. Last year, in his third try, he finished eighth
and had clearly become a force in the game. When a friend of
our father's went to a tournament and asked a player to point
him toward <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON>, he got the sort of stunned silence he would
have expected if he had wandered into a <LOCATION>Little Italy</LOCATION> social
club and asked to see <PERSON>John Gotti</PERSON>.
   This <DATE>August</DATE>, against the toughest field assembled in
years, <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> was on a roll. Although the tournament didn't
carry the imprimatur of <PERSON>Milton Bradley</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION>'s owner, it
did include all the big names, such as <PERSON>Robert Felt</PERSON>, the
reigning official champ because he won the <DATE>1990</DATE> national
tournament.
   In one game, <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON>'s first three plays were "bronzier,"
"oracular" and "notturni," giving him three 50-point bonuses
for playing all seven letters in his rack. The score at that
point was 215 to 26. In another game, <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON>'s opponent got
50-point bonuses -- known as "bingos" -- on his first two
turns but found himself trailing Chuck by 190 points. Chuck
had scored a career-high 212 points on one word, "landform,"
which hit two triple-word scores. Other games produced the
words "zoeae," "codeia," "tirrivee," "duvetyn," "beigy" and
"qaids" (the latter, which according to the <ORGANIZATION>Official Scrabble
Player</ORGANIZATION>'s Dictionary means "Far Eastern rulers," turns out to
be one of the most common plays in high-level Scrabble).
   Nobody much watched the tournament, with its 160
contestants huddled over their boards for 20 hours over 4 1/2
days in the ballroom of a <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> hotel. "Too boring,"
<PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> said. But there was plenty of tension going into the
final day's play, as <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON>'s 18-6 record tied him with three
others for first. He was ahead on the tiebreaker, the spread
between the points he had scored and the total his opponents
had scored, but he also was worried. He had to start off
against <PERSON>Peter Morris</PERSON>, a former champion who <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> describes
as "the smartest person who plays Scrabble."
   Chuck played "yclepe," which was a "phony," or fake word,
that looked like two Old English words. But <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> is a
graduate student specializing in Victorian literature and
caught it right away. Chuck lost big after <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> challenged.
When <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> and <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> both won their next games, they were
pitted against each other in the final game. Chuck not only
had to win, he had to win by 143 points to have the better
spread. "A hundred-to-one shot," <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> said.
   But <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> got both blanks in the final game and played
four bingos, including "klavern," a <PERSON>Ku Klux Klan</PERSON> cell. Things
got tight when <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> drew the "q" right at the end with
nowhere to play it, especially because <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> describes <PERSON>Morris</PERSON>
as "the best end-game player in the history of the world."
Still, <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> won by 152 points.
   Chuck collected his check for <MONEY>$3,900</MONEY> and celebrated by
taking the bus to <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>. He used the time to study
words. It's a good thing, since players at the world
championship will be able to use words from all official
English-language Scrabble dictionaries, so <PERSON>Chuck</PERSON> had 20,000
words to learn by this week.
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Carroll</PERSON> covers the computer industry for the Journal
in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   910925-0103
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-15919</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DDHB2ADNFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930408
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 APR 93 / Observer: Obiter dicta
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
How many bona fide two-letter words are there in English? Anyone knowing the
answer off pat will probably be an addict of Scrabble (in which short words
can be decisive in end-play) and so have cause to lament the death of the
game's <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> inventor Alfred Butts.
As old as the century and an architect by training, he devised the
word-based board game in the <DATE>1930s</DATE> only to have it turned down by
manufacturers in the field. It was not until the early <DATE>1950s</DATE> that the <ORGANIZATION>Macy</ORGANIZATION>'s
retail chain began selling Scrabble, paving the way for an estimated total
sale in various languages which still seems low at 100m. He said he earned
only a few cents on each.
As for the two-letter words, according to <ORGANIZATION>Chambers English Dictionary</ORGANIZATION>, the
number is 106. The three-letter variety are far more plentiful, with 1,087.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-14622</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EGMDEAEUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940713
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 JUL 94 / (CORRECTED) UK Company News: Hasbro gives up on Spear
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID WIGHTON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Correction (published 14th <DATE>July 1994</DATE>) appended to this article.
Hasbro yesterday threw in its hand in the battle for JW Spear, the maker of
<ORGANIZATION>Scrabble</ORGANIZATION>, and said it would accept the Pounds 11.50 a share bid from US toy
rival <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>.
It described the Pounds 62m offer as 'very generous and above a level which
we could justify in business terms'.
The decision ends a fierce scrap over <LOCATION>Spear</LOCATION>, which started when <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>
launched a 900p a share bid for the company at the end of <DATE>May</DATE>. It had held a
26.7 per cent stake since <DATE>1990</DATE> and had received undertakings from the
trustees of some <PERSON>Spear</PERSON> family trusts to sell their 24.9 per cent stake
unless a higher offer was received within three working days.
After a frantic search for a white knight, <ORGANIZATION>Hambro</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s merchant bank,
persuaded <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> to launch a rival bid at Pounds 10 a share five minutes
before the deadline. Hasbro came back with an Pounds 11 a share offer last
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, which was topped by <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
<PERSON>Mr Norman Walker</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro International</ORGANIZATION>, said: 'Our offer at
Pounds 11 per share was a very full one which we are not prepared to
increase. We are very pleased at the outcome for all shareholders and will
of course realise a substantial gain on our own investment which we made in
<DATE>1990</DATE>.' Hasbro bought its original stake at under Pounds 3 a share.
The outcome leaves the rights to Scrabble divided between <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>,
which are fierce rivals in the doll market. <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, maker of <LOCATION>Sindy</LOCATION>, retains
the rights to Scrabble in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, leaving <ORGANIZATION>Barbie</ORGANIZATION>'s creator, <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>,
with the rest of the world.
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>'s victory is particularly sweet for <PERSON>Robert Fleming</PERSON>, the merchant
bank. It was appointed by <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> just six hours before the initial offer had
to be launched and completed the task with a few minutes to spare.
CORRECTION
JW Spear's merchant bank, which handled its successful sale to <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>,
was <PERSON>Barings</PERSON> not Hambros as stated yesterday.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Hasbro UK.
    JW Spear and Sons.
    Mattel.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
    USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 26
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06010224 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06010224 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  LIFESTYLE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE first time I placed a personal ad in a magazine, they said: "Just be
honest. Describe yourself, your likes and dislikes, and the type of woman
you're interested in meeting -- at least at 75 cents per word.";    Then they
handed me a slip of paper and a No. 2 pencil, and I wrote: "Short,
unattractive man with thick glasses seeks stunning yet insecure woman to cook,
take over my car payments and engage in occasional desultory sex. I like to
drink rum out of a jelly glass and play Scrabble; that's about it."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GETTING PERSONAL CAN BE A VERY HARD THING
TO DO  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cowherd is a columnist for the Baltimore Evening Sun.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The whole thing came to -- let's see -- 40 words. Cost me 30 bucks. Then I
went home and waited for the responses to roll in. Nothing. Zero. It was
unbelievable.;    Every day I'd stand out by the mailbox waiting for a
postcard from some hot-looking babe who wanted a shot at an advanced Scrabble
player. And every day Ted, my postman, would walk by and shake his head and
sing out: "Nothing for you today, Occupant!";    Finally, after a month or so
of no responses, I threw my hands in the air and shouted: "That's it! I'm
quitting the dating scene! I don't know what these women want anymore!";    A
buddy of mine, <PERSON>Neil</PERSON>, happened to be over the day I went ballistic. He asked to
see my personal ad and studied it for several minutes.;    "You gotta punch it
up a little bit," he said finally. "There must be something you like to do
besides play Scrabble.";    Not really, I said. For a while there, I was
hooked on Sorry. And before that I'd play a lot of Hungry, <ORGANIZATION>Hungry Hippo</ORGANIZATION>, which
is a game my 4-year-old niece turned me onto where you try to capture marbles
in a plastic cup shaped like a hippopotamus.;    But lately, I said, it's been
mostly Scrabble. Not to brag or anything, but I should point out . . .;   
"Listen," <PERSON>Neil</PERSON> said, "lose that Scrabble stuff. Put something in the ad like:
'Has won over 25 bowling trophies.' They'll be beating down the doors to go
out with you.";    <PERSON>Neil</PERSON> knows women, you've got to give him that. But I needed
a second opinion, which is the reason I showed the ad to <PERSON>Sarah Jean</PERSON> down at
the Laundromat.;    <PERSON>Sarah Jean</PERSON> was pretty busy making change; all 24 washers
and dryers were humming and she was cranking the quarters off the changer on
her belt so fast you could barely see her fingers.;    But finally she stopped
saying, "How much you need, Sugar?" and took a minute to look at my ad.;   
From the expression on her face, she didn't like what she was seeing -- unless
it was the No. 9 dryer knocking with those tennis shoes that was bothering
her.;    "Part of the problem," she said between drags on a Salem, "is your
opening sentence, especially that 'short, unattractive man with thick glasses'
business. A lot of women don't go for that type of guy.";    Man, I could have
kicked myself. She was right, of course. The more I thought about it, you
don't see too many <PERSON>Meg Ryan</PERSON> types with ugly, stumpy guys with Coke-bottle
glasses -- Scrabble background or no Scrabble background.;    Why I didn't
think of that in the first place is beyond me. Just stupid, I guess. Yeah,
that's it. Maybe the ad should have read: "Short, stupid, unattractive man
with thick glasses seeks . . .";    "Another thing," said <PERSON>Sarah Jean</PERSON>, "you
can't just say you're looking for someone to cook and pay for your car and
have sex with. That's going to turn women off. It's too -- honest.";    Well.
This was a fine how-do-you-do. Here the folks at the magazine were saying: "Be
truthful." But <PERSON>Sarah Jean</PERSON> was saying: "Sugar, to play this game, you gotta lie
like a rug.";    Anyway, once the morning rush was over, <PERSON>Sarah Jean</PERSON> and I sat
down and wrote out a new personal ad on the back of an empty box of Tide.;   
Actually, she dictated and I wrote with a big red Magic Marker that <PERSON>Earl</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Sarah Jean</PERSON>'s boss, uses to make up "This Dryer Out of Order" signs.;    "Tall,
rugged-looking Harvard grad seeks attractive, non-argumentative, financially
well-off woman for quiet candlelight dinners (your place), help with
philanthropic causes, erotic adventure (though on a limited basis.) Must have
sense of humor. Proficiency at spelling and board games preferred.";    I
don't know -- it doesn't really sound like my kind of personal. Plus I had to
pony up another 30 bucks to get it into the magazine.;    <PERSON>Sarah Jean</PERSON>, she can
get a little wordy.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Kevin Cowherd column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910110  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  787  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, January 10, 1991
00010224,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061689-0130 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 71062 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 16, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 2; Column 4; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
509 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
$85-MILLION DEAL; 
</P>
<P>
COLECO OKS HASBRO BUYOUT OFFER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HARTFORD, Conn. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Coleco Industries</ORGANIZATION> agreed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to be bought by <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro Inc.</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$85 million</MONEY>, 
marking the likely end of the company that made the hottest-selling toy in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
history, the Cabbage Patch Kids doll. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, the largest American toy maker, will receive all of <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION>'s product 
line, which includes Scrabble and Parcheesi board games, as part of the 
all-cash deal, <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Morton Handel</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The deal still must be approved by <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Bankruptcy Court</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, where 
<ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION>, swamped with <MONEY>$540.3 million</MONEY> in debt, sought protection from creditors a 
year ago. A hearing on the sale is expected next week or in early <DATE>July</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Handel</ORGANIZATION> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> is to receive warrants to purchase 1 million shares of <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> stock as 
part of the deal. <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Pawtucket</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, will get inventory, 
equipment to make products and some accounts receivable. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Appalachian Artworks Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, creator of Cabbage Patch Kids, and <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> directors 
also must approve the deal, which must be completed by <DATE>July 17</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
If the deal is approved, most of <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION>'s 250 employees are expected to be laid 
off, although some may be hired by <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Handel</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> has about 75 salaried workers in <LOCATION>Avon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, 75 in <LOCATION>Mayfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and 
a total of about 100 assembly-line workers at both locations. 
</P>
<P>
"Coleco always stood for innovation and the ability to take risks," said <PERSON>Paul 
Valentine</PERSON>, a toy analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Standard &amp; Poors</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. "The industry 
is poorer because of their demise." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Good, Stable Games' 
</P>
<P>
Russian immigrant <PERSON>Maurice Greenberg</PERSON> founded the <ORGANIZATION>Connecticut Leather Co.</ORGANIZATION> in 
<DATE>1932</DATE>. The firm company expanded its leather and shoe products line to toys in 
<DATE>1954</DATE> and its name was changed to <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1961</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Analysts said <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> ran into trouble after the phenomenal success of the 
Cabbage Patch doll, which became the best-selling toy of all time with more 
than <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> in sales in <DATE>1985</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>David Leibowitz</PERSON>, senior vice president of <ORGANIZATION>American Securities Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said 
<ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> borrowed money to expand after the success of the Cabbage Patch dolls. 
</P>
<P>
But when Cabbage Patch Kids sales tumbled and new products, including <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> 
home computer and toys based on the Rambo movies, did not sell, <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> couldn't 
pay off the new debts, he said. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, which makes GI <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mr. Potato Head</PERSON>, My Little Pony and <ORGANIZATION>Transformers</ORGANIZATION>, 
had sales of <MONEY>$1.34 billion</MONEY> last year, up from <MONEY>$104.3 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1980</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> in 
the <DATE>last decade</DATE> has bought big-name companies, including <ORGANIZATION>Milton Bradley Co.</ORGANIZATION>, 
and introduced a steady stream of new products. 
</P>
<P>
Hasbro Executive Vice President <PERSON>Barry Alperin</PERSON> said of the <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> deal: "It 
means the acquisition of good, stable game products, like Scrabble, Parcheesi 
and Aggravation . . . and it's a good chance to add to our toy division." 
</P>
<P>
After the transaction, <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> will have as much as <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY> in cash, <MONEY>$85 
million</MONEY> from <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> and about <MONEY>$65 million</MONEY> it had in banks in mid-March, <PERSON>Handel</PERSON> 
said. The cash will be used to pay off the company's debts, he said. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> also said it would retain some real estate assets, which will be 
converted to cash. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Cabbage Patch Kids, the dolls that put Coleco Industries on the map, are 
headed for a new owner. Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ACQUISITIONS; COLECO INDUSTRIES INC; HASBRO INC; TOYS; DOLLS; GAMES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-6806</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CHYAUAD2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920821
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  21 AUG 92 / UK Company News: Reduced deficit at JW Spear
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
JW Spear, the Enfield-based toys and games manufacturer, reported sharply
reduced losses in its seasonally unfavourable first half.
Losses before tax were Pounds 315,000 for the six months to <DATE>June 30</DATE>, down
from Pounds 638,000 at the same stage of <DATE>1991</DATE>. The group, famed for its
Scrabble game, achieved profits of Pounds 2.53m pre-tax in the full <DATE>1991</DATE>
year.
The outcome reflected lower interest payable of Pounds 5,000 (Pounds
125,000). Turnover was marginally lower at Pounds 8.28m as <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> proved a
'lacklustre' market following the impact of video games, said <PERSON>Mr Francis
Spear</PERSON>, chairman.
Losses per share were cut to 5.78p (8.19p) and the interim dividend goes up
to 2.5p (2p).
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890615-0291 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-15-89 1933EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Coleco-Hasbro     06-15 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Coleco-Hasbro,0594</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coleco To Be Sold To Hasbro for $85 Million</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Coleco Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> agreed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to
be bought by <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro Inc.</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$85 million</MONEY>, marking the likely end of
the company that made the hottest-selling toy in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history, the
Cabbage Patch Kids doll.
   <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, the largest American toymaker, will receive all of
<ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION>'s product line, which includes Scrabble and Parcheesi board
games, as part of the all-cash deal, <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Morton Handel</PERSON>
said.
   The deal still must be approved by <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Bankruptcy Court</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, where <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION>, swamped with <MONEY>$540.3 million</MONEY> in debt, sought
protection from creditors a year ago. A hearing on the sale is
expected next week or in early <DATE>July</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Handel</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Avon-based <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> is to receive warrants to purchase 1 million
shares of <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> stock as part of the deal. <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, based in
<LOCATION>Pawtucket</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, will get inventory, equipment to make products and
some accounts receivable.
   <ORGANIZATION>Appalachian Artworks Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, creator of Cabbage Patch Kids, and
<ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> directors also must approve the deal, which must be completed
by <DATE>July 17</DATE>.
   If the deal is approved, most of <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION>'s 250 employees are
expected to be laid off, although some may be hired by <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Handel</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> has about 75 salaried workers in <LOCATION>Avon</LOCATION>, 75 in <LOCATION>Mayfield</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and a total of about 100 assembly line workers at both
locations.
   ``Coleco always stood for innovation and the ability to take
risks,'' said <PERSON>Paul Valentine</PERSON>, a toy analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Standard &amp; Poors
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. ``The industry is poorer because of their
demise.''
   Russian immigrant <PERSON>Maurice Greenberg</PERSON> founded the <ORGANIZATION>Connecticut
Leather Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1932</DATE>. The company expanded its leather and shoe
products line to toys in <DATE>1954</DATE> and its name was changed to <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1961</DATE>.
   Analysts said <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> ran into trouble after the phenomenal
success of the Cabbage Patch doll, which became the best-selling toy
of all-time with more than <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> in sales in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   <PERSON>David Leibowitz</PERSON>, senior vice president of <ORGANIZATION>American Securities
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> borrowed money to expand after the Cabbage Patch
success.
   But when Cabbage Patch Kids sales tumbled and new products,
including <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> home computer and toys based on the Rambo movies,
did not sell, <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> couldn't pay off the new debts, he said.
   ``They managed their company for a sales revival that never
came,'' <PERSON>Valentine</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, which makes GI <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mr. Potato Head</PERSON>, My Little Pony and
<ORGANIZATION>Transformers</ORGANIZATION>, had sales of <MONEY>$1.34 billion</MONEY> last year, up from just
<MONEY>$104.3 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1980</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>last decade</DATE> has bought
big-name companies including <ORGANIZATION>Milton Bradley Co.</ORGANIZATION> and introduced a
steady stream of new products.
   Hasbro Executive Vice President <PERSON>Barry Alperin</PERSON> said of the <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION>
deal: ``It means the acquisition of good, stable game products, like
Scrabble, Parcheesi and Aggravation ... and it's a good chance to
add to our toy division.''
   After the transaction, <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> will have as much as <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY>
in cash, <MONEY>$85 million</MONEY> from <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> and about <MONEY>$65 million</MONEY> it had in
banks in mid-March, <PERSON>Handel</PERSON> said. The cash will be used to pay off
the company's debts, he said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION> also said it would retain some real estate assets, which
will be converted to cash.
   The companies also agreed that <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION> will participate in <ORGANIZATION>Coleco</ORGANIZATION>
business operations up to the close of the transaction as part of a
management consulting agreement.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-5005</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFHA0ADAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940607
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  07 JUN 94 / Observer: Scrabbling in Toytown
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Who will finally bag J W Spear, the UK owner of Scrabble? Will it be mighty
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, manufacturer of <ORGANIZATION>Barbie</ORGANIZATION>, aged 35? Or will <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, handler of <LOCATION>Sindy</LOCATION>,
33, finally win through? Hasbro was first, valuing Spear at almost Pounds
47m, but <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> squeezed in <DATE>last Friday</DATE>, valuing it at Pounds 52m.
Observer understands the matter has already passed into the hands of two top
executives, charged with thrashing out a compromise. Here's an excerpt of a
crucial weekend phone call.
S: Whaddya mean by this, tryin' to upstage ma show? Old man Spear has
already said he's happy with us.
B: Off your high horse, gal. All's fair in love, war and business. The other
Scrabble guys go for me.
S: Cheapskate] Flashing your legs ain't gonna make no difference.
B: At least I got legs worth flashing - punters paid more than Dollars 1bn
for me last year. And I got 55 per cent of the fashion doll market. You only
got 32 per cent, honey.
S: You ain't got a decent pedigree, sweetie pie. Ah'm British, through and
through.
B: British? Don't crease me up. You ain't been British since <DATE>1986</DATE>.
S: I jest know that Spear likes my looks better than yours.
B: Butt out, kiddo - your looks were a damn sight better before you got a
nose job in <DATE>'92</DATE>.
S: That was only 'cos you bitched so loudly that I was better-looking than
you.
B: Lighten up, loser. You ain't gotta hope in hell.
S: (Sounds of sniffles).
Click.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>JW Spear and Sons.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-5414</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFEASADBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940604
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 JUN 94 / Markets: Barbie and Sindy v Ken and Eddie - London
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By RODERICK ORAM
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
As double acts go, Barbie and <PERSON>Sindy</PERSON> may be less edifying than <PERSON>Ken and Eddie</PERSON>,
but more electrifying to investors. A rally of the dolls is underway with
their respective parents, <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Hasbro</ORGANIZATION>, battling each other for control
of <ORGANIZATION>JW Spear &amp; Sons</ORGANIZATION>, the British toy maker. Spear's stock is already up 58
per cent from its <DATE>January</DATE> low to 750p with every last Scrabble tile still to
fight for.
But is the stock market's uplift this week - achieved without assistance
from Chancellor <PERSON>Kenneth Clarke</PERSON> or Governor <PERSON>Eddy George</PERSON> - anything more than
a cosmetic correction?
After the dreadful drubbing stocks and bonds suffered the previous week, the
tide turned on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in the futures markets. The cash markets too saw
some genuine buyers attracted by near 9 per cent long gilt yields and 4 per
cent dividend yields.
The upturn proved fragile yesterday. No sooner did the latest US payroll
figures hit screens at lunchtime, than stocks and bonds headed south again.
Only when US bonds rebounded on some comforting words from the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
did UK markets recover their poise. The <ORGANIZATION>FT-SE</ORGANIZATION> 100 index finished with a 31.4
point gain on the week at 2,997.8.
Few investors doubt there is genuine value in equities and gilts at these
levels but none are in a hurry to buy. 'We feel slightly spoiled for
choice,' says <PERSON>David Manning</PERSON>, director of UK equities at <ORGANIZATION>Legal &amp; General</ORGANIZATION>, a
large institutional investor. But there is no need to rush to invest in
either market. 'They will still be here in two or three months' time at the
same sort of levels.'
One factor holding him back is the high yield on index linked gilts. Not
only is the 4 per cent return virtually the same as the stock market's
average dividend yield but it is also risk-free.
As the first of the accompanying charts show, the index linked yield is high
by historic standards apart from the period 1990-92 when it was boosted by
sterling's membership of the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION>. It is hard to envisage yields rising much
further. But even if the bond market fails to rally and achieves only
stability, equities could still gradually recover.
'If indexed linked yields do stabilise and one looks out through <DATE>1994</DATE> and
<DATE>1995</DATE> one can see an equity yield premium re-emerging fairly rapidly,' say
strategists at <ORGANIZATION>SG Warburg Securities</ORGANIZATION>, thanks to rapid dividend growth.
As the second chart shows, the dividend yield has rarely been so close to
the index linked gilt yield apart from the run up to the <DATE>1987</DATE> crash. At
current levels, equities are expensive but will become more attractive as
dividends grow and the yield ratio rises.
Such a modest stock market improvement later this year, led by expanding
earnings and dividends, seems much more likely than one led by a bond market
rally and falling interest rates. Even though a long gilt yield of around <MONEY>9
per cent</MONEY> is discounting more inflation than most people expect, there are
too many economic uncertainties at home and abroad for investors to chase
bond prices higher.
A parallel can be drawn with the market in mid-1985, says <PERSON>Vivian Bazalgette</PERSON>,
managing director of <ORGANIZATION>Gartmore Pension Fund Managers</ORGANIZATION>. 'This is a mid-cycle
reaction when the market is switching from being interest rate to earnings
driven. We see scope for the market to rise to its former peak or even a
little higher by the end of the year.' <ORGANIZATION>Gartmore</ORGANIZATION> has remained slightly
overweight in UK equities throughout the market's 15 per cent correction
from its <DATE>February</DATE> peak.
Most other UK institutional investors are also well represented in domestic
equities so they may not be a source of particularly heavy buying when the
market begins to recover. However, there are stocks to cherry pick. Legal
and <ORGANIZATION>General</ORGANIZATION>, for example, likes those big international stocks in the
Footsie which offer above average dividend yield and exposure to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
economy.
No companies reporting this week fit the profile although <ORGANIZATION>Siebe</ORGANIZATION> fails only
on the dividend count. The controls maker reported a 20 per cent rise in
pre-tax profits for the year to Pounds 217.2m and an 11.6 per cent increase
in full-year dividend to 11p for a gross yield of 2.4 per cent. Its
underlying profit margins held up through the recession and it is now
enjoying some growth in demand in the <LOCATION>Americas</LOCATION> and elsewhere.
The most pleasant results surprise came from Boots. Reporting pre-tax
profits for the year up 19 per cent to Pounds 484.4m and the dividend up 12
per cent to 15p, it shook off some of the investor doubts which have dogged
it for the past 18 months. It has yet to work out what to do with its
struggling drugs business or to show it can make money in the do-it-yourself
sector, but there is no doubting the strength of its core retailing
business.
In contrast, elsewhere in the retail sector, <ORGANIZATION>Kingfisher</ORGANIZATION> delivered a rather
downbeat annual general meeting statement. First quarter sales volume was
lower than a year earlier and its 'every day low-pricing' policy is still
not paying off convincingly. Its shares lost more ground and are now down 33
per cent from their high for the year of 778p.
<ORGANIZATION>Granada Group</ORGANIZATION> offered the most sparkling performance of the week. Its
interim pre-tax profits were up 51 per cent to Pounds 103m and its dividend
up 10 per cent at 3.33p. Acquisitions in catering and textile rental were
big contributors while LWT, the television franchise, chipped in only
one-month so far.
Although <ORGANIZATION>Granada</ORGANIZATION>'s results attest in part to the profitable audience for
glamorous game shows, <ORGANIZATION>Barbie</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Sindy</PERSON> are fighting on a higher intellectual
plane. Not for them the fripperies of outfits, accessories and hairstyle
they normally crave. This time they are each after <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>'s Scrabble
franchise. Sadly, there would be little contest if they challenged <PERSON>Ken</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Eddie</PERSON> to a game.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6231 Security and Commodity Exchanges.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    MKTS  Market data.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page II
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890731-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-31-89 0454EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     07-31 0468</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0486</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY9</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fourteen-year-old <PERSON>Adam Logan</PERSON> says he doesn't
remember when he first learned to play Scrabble or how he got so
good at it.
   ``I just know that it's fun,'' he said during a break after
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s first game of the <DATE>1989</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>National Scrabble Championship</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Logan</LOCATION>, a high school student from <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION>, is the youngest of the
151 expert players competing in a five-day tournament for the
<MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> top prize. Another 72 recreation-level players also are
competing at the <ORGANIZATION>New York Penta</ORGANIZATION> hotel in midtown <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>.
   The competitors are from 30 states and eight other countries.
   The <DATE>1987</DATE> champion, <PERSON>Rita Norr</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, is the only woman
to win the 7-year-old tournament.
   ``Some people feel that the women don't have the killer
instinct,'' she said. ``I'm not sure that that's really it. Men
maybe have the freedom to concentrate more on the game.''
   Norr, a freelance mathematics textbook writer with a computer
science background, said the game is more than knowledge of words.
   ``It's very mathematical,'' she said. ``A lot of it's even
spatial relationships and decisions about when to challenge, when
not to challenge, when to close the board, when to open it,
constantly keeping track of where you are in the game and how many
tiles are left.''
   But <PERSON>Loera Thompson</PERSON>, a 75-year-old <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> native, doesn't
take it so seriously.
   ``I don't care that much about it,'' she said _ as long as she
isn't outpointed. ``I like to win, of course.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fourteen-year-old <PERSON>Adam Logan</PERSON> says he doesn't
remember when he first learned to play Scrabble or how he got so
good at it.
   ``I just know that it's fun,'' he said during a break after
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s first game of the <DATE>1989</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>National Scrabble Championship</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Logan</LOCATION>, a high school student from <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION>, is the youngest of the
151 expert players competing in a five-day tournament for the
<MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> top prize. Another 72 recreation-level players also are
competing at the <ORGANIZATION>New York Penta</ORGANIZATION> hotel in midtown <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>.
   The competitors are from 30 states and eight other countries.
   The <DATE>1987</DATE> champion, <PERSON>Rita Norr</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, is the only woman
to win the 7-year-old tournament.
   ``Some people feel that the women don't have the killer
instinct,'' she said. ``I'm not sure that that's really it. Men
maybe have the freedom to concentrate more on the game.''
   Norr, a freelance mathematics textbook writer with a computer
science background, said the game is more than knowledge of words.
   ``It's very mathematical,'' she said. ``A lot of it's even
spatial relationships and decisions about when to challenge, when
not to challenge, when to close the board, when to open it,
constantly keeping track of where you are in the game and how many
tiles are left.''
   But <PERSON>Loera Thompson</PERSON>, a 75-year-old <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> native, doesn't
take it so seriously.
   ``I don't care that much about it,'' she said _ as long as she
isn't outpointed. ``I like to win, of course.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-6472</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CKTBNAGWFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921120
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 NOV 92 / Survey of Home Entertainment (6): Monopoly is still leading
the field - Non-Electronic Games
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CHRISTOPHER PRICE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
PURVEYORS of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s board games must have blanched at the news of fights
breaking out among several thousand youngsters locked out of a computer
games exhibition in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <DATE>earlier this month</DATE>.
It is not the sort of thing that happens in the staid world of
non-electronic games, where Monopoly (circa <DATE>1930</DATE>) remains the number one
seller, followed by old rivals Cluedo (circa <DATE>1950</DATE>), Scrabble and the newer
Trivial Pursuit.
'The traditional board games offer a good value way of bridging the
generation gap and in which all the family can participate,' says <PERSON>Mr Alan
Thompson</PERSON>, managing director of <ORGANIZATION>Waddington Games</ORGANIZATION>, makers of Monopoly.
'Computer games are usually designed for single players.'
However, the new wave of electronic entertainment has dented the growth in
board game sales, although they have held up well in the face of the
recession.
Last year, board game sales grew to Pounds 127m from Pounds 114m in <DATE>1988</DATE>,
with Monopoly selling 300,000 units - and <ORGANIZATION>Junior Monopoly</ORGANIZATION> an additional
200,000.
New growth areas are generally limited to one-off blockbusters such as
Trivial Pursuit, or adaptations from television game shows. Hence healthy
sales are expected this <DATE>Christmas</DATE> for the likes of 'Big Break', 'Give us a
Clue' and 'TV Addicts'. Toy executives maintain close contacts with
television companies, producing a two-way stream of games linked to TV and
vice versa.
Meanwhile, <PERSON>Subbuteo</PERSON>, the table football game, has seen a seven-fold increase
in sales in the past six years, mirroring renewed interest in the domestic
game. There has also been a flood of games on the 'Dungeons and <ORGANIZATION>Dragons</ORGANIZATION>'
theme.
However, a stroll down the aisle of any large toy store reveals hundreds of
board games lacking either the pull of television support or the staying
power of the established giants. One cannot help but fear a short shelf life
for the likes of '<ORGANIZATION>Mall Madness</ORGANIZATION>' and 'Beware the Bog]'.
The cost of introducing new games is high, with its success dependent on
good distribution. Periphery players also struggle because with two-thirds
of sales made in the Christmas period, large amounts of stock have to be
held throughout the year. 'I think the industry will become centred around
fewer players,' says <PERSON>Mr Thompson</PERSON>. Experienced toy industry watchers predict
a New Year fall-out for some of the smaller manufacturers.
One of the few new companies to make in-roads into the UK market is the
Japanese group <PERSON>Tomy</PERSON>, which in the past 10 years has seen its sales grow from
zero to Pounds 60m.
With no traditional board game as a backbone, <PERSON>Tomy</PERSON> has concentrated on
developing activity games with an emphasis on skill and dexterity. 'There's
nothing more boring than a flat piece of cardboard,' says <PERSON>Mr Peter Brown</PERSON>,
managing director of <ORGANIZATION>Tomy UK</ORGANIZATION>. 'People, and especially children, want
something extra to do while they're playing.'
But despite <PERSON>Tomy</PERSON>'s efforts to widen the market, the search for the lucrative
'new Monopoly' continues to exercise not only some of the great minds of the
toy world, but also the British public.
<PERSON>Mr Brown</PERSON> says he receives up to a dozen suggestions a week from the public
for new board games. At Waddingtons the number of suggestions regularly runs
to a hundred. In the meantime, Monopoly looks likely to live up to its title
and maintain its dominant position.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page II
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880119-0052 </DOCNO>
<HL> Coleco Sued in Canada Over Marketing Pact </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> CLO </CO>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
