<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890804-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-04-89 0742EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Census-Metros     08-04 1004</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census-Metros,0691</SECOND>
<HEAD>Half of All Americans Live in 37 Metro Areas</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: also on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two centuries after the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was
founded as a largely agricultural nation, nearly nine-tenths of the
population growth is occurring in metropolitan areas, the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports.
   Almost half of all Americans reside in just 37 major urban
areas, the bureau said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a new analysis of the patterns
of growth. And the metropolitan share of the population is growing
faster than that in rural areas.
   The ``rural renaissance'' reported in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> when small towns
and rural areas were growing seems to have ended, with increases in
cities and suburbs now well in the lead.
   The census study found that about <PERCENT>86 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's
population growth since <DATE>1980</DATE> has occurred in the 282 officially
designated metropolitan areas across the country. That pattern
represents a return to the metropolitan area dominance that has
been common since the era of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Depression</ORGANIZATION>, the bureau
reported.
   The analysis of <DATE>1987</DATE> figures found that nearly half of all
Americans, <PERCENT>48.9 percent</PERCENT>, reside in the 37 metro areas with
populations of a million or more.
   Led by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, these metro areas had 119
million residents in <DATE>1987</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> leads the way as the only state entirely included
within metropolitan areas, the bureau noted. The northern portion
of the state is included in the greater <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> metro area while
the southern portion is part of the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> region.
   Seven other states have more than <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of their
populations in metropolitan areas _ <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Idaho is the least metropolitan state with only about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>
of its residents in urban areas, the report added.
   Reflecting the nation's overall population trend, metropolitan
area growth has tended to flow to the South and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in recent
years, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> observed in its study of growth patterns
between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The population loss experienced in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> during the
<DATE>1970s</DATE> has halted in this decade, the agency found, while the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> has continued to have net losses in recent years.
   ``A slowdown in population growth has taken place since <DATE>1980</DATE> in
much of the interior of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, especially in
nonmetropolitan areas,'' noted the report prepared by <PERSON>Donald E.
Starsinic</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard L. Forstall</PERSON>.
   During this decade the nonmetropolitan population declined in 10
contiguous states _ <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
bureau pointed out.
   The nation's metro areas with 1 million or more residents, as of
<DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>, were <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 18.0 million; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, 13.5
million; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, 8.1 million; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, 5.9 million;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, 5.9 million; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, 4.6 million; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, 4.1
million; <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, 3.7 million;
   Also <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, 2.9
million; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, 2.7 million; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, 2.6 million; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>,
2.4 million; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
<LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
   And <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, 1.9 million; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, 1.9
million; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, 1.8 million; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, 1.7 million; <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>,
1.5 million; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, 1.5 million; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 1.4 million;
<LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
   Plus <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>,
1.1 million and Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION>, 1.1 million.
   Here is a state-by-state rundown of the percentage of the
population living in metropolitan areas as of <DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Two centuries after the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was
founded as a largely agricultural nation, nearly nine-tenths of the
population growth is occurring in metropolitan areas, the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports.
   Almost half of all Americans reside in just 37 major urban
areas, the bureau said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a new analysis of the patterns
of growth. And the metropolitan share of the population is growing
faster than that in rural areas.
   The ``rural renaissance'' reported in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> when small towns
and rural areas were growing seems to have ended, with increases in
cities and suburbs now well in the lead.
   The census study found that about <PERCENT>86 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's
population growth since <DATE>1980</DATE> has occurred in the 282 officially
designated metropolitan areas across the country. That pattern
represents a return to the metropolitan area dominance that has
been common since the era of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Depression</ORGANIZATION>, the bureau
reported.
   The analysis of <DATE>1987</DATE> figures found that nearly half of all
Americans, <PERCENT>48.9 percent</PERCENT>, reside in the 37 metro areas with
populations of a million or more.
   Led by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, these metro areas had 119
million residents in <DATE>1987</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> leads the way as the only state entirely included
within metropolitan areas, the bureau noted. The northern portion
of the state is included in the greater <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> metro area while
the southern portion is part of the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> region.
   Seven other states have more than <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of their
populations in metropolitan areas _ <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Idaho is the least metropolitan state with only about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>
of its residents in urban areas, the report added.
   Reflecting the nation's overall population trend, metropolitan
area growth has tended to flow to the South and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in recent
years, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> observed in its study of growth patterns
between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The population loss experienced in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> during the
<DATE>1970s</DATE> has halted in this decade, the agency found, while the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> has continued to have net losses in recent years.
   ``A slowdown in population growth has taken place since <DATE>1980</DATE> in
much of the interior of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, especially in
nonmetropolitan areas,'' noted the report prepared by <PERSON>Donald E.
Starsinic</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard L. Forstall</PERSON>.
   During this decade the nonmetropolitan population declined in 10
contiguous states _ <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
bureau pointed out.
   The nation's metro areas with 1 million or more residents, as of
<DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>, were <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 18.0 million; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, 13.5
million; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, 8.1 million; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, 5.9 million;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, 5.9 million; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, 4.6 million; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, 4.1
million; <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, 3.7 million;
   Also <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, 2.9
million; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, 2.7 million; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, 2.6 million; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>,
2.4 million; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
<LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
   And <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, 1.9 million; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, 1.9
million; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, 1.8 million; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, 1.7 million; <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>,
1.5 million; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, 1.5 million; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 1.4 million;
<LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
   Plus <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>,
1.1 million and Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION>, 1.1 million.
   Here is a state-by-state rundown of the percentage of the
population living in metropolitan areas as of <DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890329-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-29-89 1433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Census-Adjustment     03-29 0792</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census-Adjustment,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Projects Little Change from Census Adjustments</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A new study concludes that skewing the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s national headcount, as has been proposed in various forms
by lawmakers and special interest groups, would make little
difference in the allocation of <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats.
   Population shifts since <DATE>1980</DATE> are expected to result in the shift
of 18 or more seats, various experts agree.
   But even combining the various suggested adjustments would shift
a maximum of just four additional seats among <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, population analyst <PERSON>William P.
O'Hare</PERSON> reports.
   ``It appears that none of the adjustments to Census figures that
are being urged upon the bureau are likely to make a big difference
in the overall apportionment of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>,'' O'Hare reported in the
latest issue of ``Population Today,'' the newsletter of the private
<ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION>.
   The census, taken every 10 years, is required by the
Constitution to redistribute the 435 <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats, keeping them
relatively even in population. Because the number of <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> members
is limited, whenever a state gains a seat, another state must lose
one.
   Last year the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Department</ORGANIZATION>, which oversees the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, decreed that the <DATE>1990</DATE> results would not be adjusted.
Various interest groups, however, continue to push the idea.
Several lawsuits and congressional bills have been filed seeking to
force changes.
   The main dispute over adjusting the count centers on either
increasing the totals to add minorities presumed to have been
missed or reducing the total to subtract illegal aliens or people
who are ``imputed.''
   Imputed people are those counted despite the fact that Census
officials do not actually contact them. For example, when neighbors
say someone lives at a house even though the census taker
repeatedly cannot locate those people, that person is counted.
   The suit contending minorities are undercounted was filed in
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Dade County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>; the <ORGANIZATION>NAACP</ORGANIZATION> and groups representing Hispanics and
the nation's mayors.
   A separate suit, seeking to remove the effect of illegal aliens,
was filed in <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>Immigration
Reform Law Institute</ORGANIZATION> on behalf of 42 members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and the Federation for <ORGANIZATION>American
Immigration Reform</ORGANIZATION>.
   An analysis of the <DATE>1980</DATE> census concluded that more than <PERCENT>5
percent</PERCENT> of blacks and Hispanics were missed, considerably more than
the number of whites who were said to have been uncounted. Thus,
interest groups have urged increasing the minority count in each
state by a predetermined percentage.
   Such a move would be expected to benefit states with large
minority populations, but <LOCATION>O'Hare</LOCATION>'s calculations said that would not
be the case.
   ``Interestingly,'' concluded <LOCATION>O'Hare</LOCATION>, ``minority undercount
adjustment, the modification of the census figures which has
received the most attention, would not result in the movement of
any seats between states.''
   On the other hand, he calculated that eliminating illegal aliens
from the count would result in the transfer of one <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seat from
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>.
   ``This is not surprising when you realize that the <DATE>1980</DATE> census
figures for <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> included an estimated 1 million illegal
aliens,'' O'Hare commented. Taking them out of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
population would cost that state a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seat; <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> would
be next in line for that seat.
   Some states are more difficult to count and thus have more
imputed people than others, <LOCATION>O'Hare</LOCATION> found. He estimated that
subtracting imputed people from the count would cost <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> a
seat. Once again, the gainer would be <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>.
   O'Hare also calculated the results of various combinations of
these adjustments:
   _Adding in allegedly uncounted minorities and subtracting
estimated illegal aliens would move one seat from <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>.
   _Adding in minorities and subtracting the imputed people would
transfer seats from <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   _Subtracting both illegal aliens and imputed people would move
one <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seat from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>.
   _Making all three adjustments would move one seat from
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>.
   The various changes calculated by O'Hare would be in addition to
reallocartions of <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats caused by discernable shifts in
population since <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   While the exact shifts won't be known until after the census,
the <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION> and the private <ORGANIZATION>Election Data
Service</ORGANIZATION> have projected changes based on recent <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>
population estimates.
   Both groups anticipate the shift of 18 seats from northern
states to the South and West, mirroring the flow of population.
   Gainers are expected to be: <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, 5; <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 4; <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, 3;
<LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, 2; <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, 2; <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, 1 and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, 1.
   Expected to lose seats are: <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 3; <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, 3;
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, 2; <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, 2; <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, 2; <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, 1; <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, 1;
<LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, 1; <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, 1; <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, 1, and <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, 1.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890509-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-09-89 1934EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CensusSuit     05-09 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census Suit,0501</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Dismisses Suit On Aliens In Census</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER MATTIACE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge has dismissed a lawsuit by 42
congressmen and three states seeking to block the counting of
illegal aliens in the <DATE>1990</DATE> census, in part because they could not
prove they will lose seats in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> by reapportionment.
   The plaintiffs said they feared states with more illegal aliens
would get a disproportionate number of <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats and electoral
votes, thus diminishing the political power of states with fewer
illegal aliens.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> argued it is constitutionally obligated to
count everyone, including illegal aliens, for congressional
apportionment and has done so since the first census in <DATE>1790</DATE>. House
seats are redistributed every 10 years to reflect population
changes.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge William L. Standish</PERSON> said, in a ruling filed
late <DATE>Monday</DATE>, that the plaintiffs cannot show they would be hurt by
the <DATE>1990</DATE> census because ``they are unable to establish how many
illegal aliens will be present ..., in which states these illegal
aliens will reside, or to what extent the illegal population will
come forward to be counted.''
   The lawsuit was filed last year by the congressmen, led by
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Republican <PERSON>Tom Ridge</PERSON>, and the states of <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>.
   Ridge said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that <PERSON>Standish</PERSON> dismissed the lawsuit ``on
technical, legal grounds and not on the merits of the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s plans.''
   Ridge, recently named vice chairman of a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee that
oversees the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, said he may appeal <PERSON>Standish</PERSON>'s decision
and will introduce legislation in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to change the method of
the <DATE>1990</DATE> count.
   Standish's opinion noted that the congressmen's demographer
offered estimates that up to 5.6 million illegal aliens will be
counted in <DATE>1990</DATE>. The demographer predicted a gain of up to four
congressional seats for <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and one seat for <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and the
possible loss of one seat each for <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>.
   The judge noted another congressional analyst had predicted
gains for <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> at the
expense of <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>.
   But, the judge said, ``Based on the evidence offered, it is
sheer speculation as to the identities of the states that will be
affected by the inclusion of illegal aliens.''
   Standish also said the state governments of <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> cannot show they would be damaged by ``reduced power or
prestige'' with the loss of congressional representation. He said
only the residents of the states might suffer and they did not file
the lawsuit.
   Standish noted that the non-profit <ORGANIZATION>Federation of American
Immigration Reform</ORGANIZATION>, a co-plaintiff in the lawsuit, filed a similar
legal action in <DATE>1980</DATE> that was dismissed by a three-judge federal
panel in the <LOCATION>District of Columbia</LOCATION>.
   Ridge was joined by 19 colleagues from <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, and others
from <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900829-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-90 2120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Census-States 1stLd-Writethru a0659 08-29 0689</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census-States, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0659,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Population Gains to Give Sunbelt States More Seats in Congress</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts new 6th graf with 1980 population</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The flow of Americans to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> has pushed
the <ORGANIZATION>Golden State</ORGANIZATION> far ahead of all rivals in population and will
census figures indicate.
   Preliminary <DATE>1990</DATE> population figures show <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> picking up
seven <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats, followed by <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> with four, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> three and a
handful of other warm-weather states with one each.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> hung on to its No. 2 ranking in population behind
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in the new figures _ with <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> closing fast
in third and fourth places _ but will lose three seats in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
because its population rose only slightly in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   Four Northern industrial states _ <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> _ lost population during the decade and will have two
fewer seats each.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated a national count of just under 246
million, including 29.3 million in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, 17.6 million in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, 16.8 million in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and 12.8 million in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. Wyoming
was last, at just under 450,000, passed by <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, which had the
smallest population in <DATE>1980</DATE> but grew to almost 546,000 in <DATE>1990</DATE>.
   The total population count in <DATE>1980</DATE> was 226,545,805.
   House seats are redistributed among the states after each
Census. Because the number is limited to 435 seats, when a growing
state gains a seat some other state must lose one.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s slight population gain was quickly disputed by state
officials, who had predicted repeatedly that the state would be
undercounted.
   ``I don't believe it,'' Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON> said in <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>. ``Do
you really, honestly believe that everybody who should be counted
has been counted? The answer is of course not. My mother had
trouble; she didn't want to answer.''
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>David N. Dinkins</PERSON> called the city's estimated
slight decline ``unadulterated nonsense'' and promised to pinpoint
where he said the government had made errors.
   Overall 19 <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats will change states according to the
figures, which could change significantly before the final report
is issued <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>.
   The widely noted movement of Americans to the Sun Belt was
documented anew in the Census Bureau figures. Besides <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, states gaining a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seat each were <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Besides the two-seat losers _ <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> _ there will be one less seat each for <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION>.
   Overall, the preliminary Census figures show the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
with a population of 245,837,683 residents. That's somewhat below
the 250 million that the bureau had estimated earlier this year.
   However, 4 million or more may be added as the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>
conducts follow up counts and completes tabulations before the
final reports are made public. If those are added in only a few
states, some of the seats allocated in the preliminary tally could
shift again.
   For example, a study by the private firm <ORGANIZATION>Election Data Services</ORGANIZATION>
showed <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> neck and neck for the last seat
allocated. <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> got the seat, but a shift of 3,000 people
could shift it to <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Kimball Brace</PERSON>, head of EDS, stressed that the figures are
subject to change.
   In addition to changes made after local officials assess the
preliminary figures, there is a chance that the final report could
be adjusted next <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   The bureau has been criticized for undercounting minorities in
the past and is conducting a post-census check on its count this
time. If officials determine that some group has been missed a
decision could be made to statistically adjust the final numbers.
   That ruling will be made by the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>mid-July 1991</DATE>.
   The national total was completed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with the reports for
the final four states _ <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>.
   Census officials emphasize that the figures are provided to
allow local governments to question the results in the event people
were missed or overcounted.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900830-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-90 0218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Census Bjt   08-30 0665</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census, Bjt,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Democrats Mobilizing to Protest Preliminary Census Figures</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Census-States List and PM-Census-House List</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONALD M. ROTHBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrats are mobilizing local officials to
protest preliminary census figures and pressure the government to
take another look at the count for the nation's cities and rural
areas.
   ``I don't believe it,'' <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
when the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated that his state's population grew
by fewer than 70,000 during the past decade.
   ``Way out of line,'' <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Maynard Jackson</PERSON> said of the
estimate for his city.
   An analysis done for Democratic state legislators said the
preliminary figures for rural areas, particularly in the <LOCATION>South</LOCATION>,
were consistently below the population estimates issued by the
<ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>February</DATE>.
   With the release of numbers for <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> completed its estimate of the
population for all 50 states.
   Overall, the preliminary census figures show the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
with a population of 245,837,683. Ten years ago, the census set the
nation's population at 226,545,805.
   To no one's surprise, the numbers showed Americans continued to
move <LOCATION>South and West</LOCATION> during the past 10 years.
   Nineteen <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House</ORGANIZATION> seats will follow that population shift to
the Sun Belt.
   That trend was good news for Republicans, who consider the Sun
Belt the area of their strongest growth. But a similar trend in the
<DATE>1980</DATE> Census, when 17 <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats shifted South and West, failed to
yield expected <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> gains because most of the state legislators who
drew the new district lines were Democrats.
   The big winner when the shift takes place in time for the <DATE>1992</DATE>
election will be <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, which is expected to gain seven new
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats for a total of 52. With a population expected to push
close to 30 million, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> would have 21 more <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats than
the second-largest state, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Based on the preliminary population figures, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> would gain
four <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> three. Picking up one each would be
<LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> would lose three <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats and <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> two each. Losing one seat each would be <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>.
   Officials who think the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> missed a lot of people in
their areas have 15 working days to submit information to support
claims they were undercounted.
   Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> called the estimate that his
city lost 40,000 people ``unadulterated nonsense'' and pledged to
``comb through the bureau's data to locate those areas where the
count is too low, identifying housing units the bureau overlooked
and buildings it missed entirely.''
   ``Do you really honestly believe everybody who should be counted
was counted?'' Cuomo asked. Answering his own question, the
governor said, ``Of course not. My mother had trouble. She didn't
want to answer.''
   Rep. <PERSON>Vic Fazio</PERSON> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House Democratic</ORGANIZATION>
group monitoring reapportionment, urged local officials to
challenge the preliminary figures.
   ``Now is not the time to be ringing partisan alarm bells,'' said
<PERSON>Fazio</PERSON>. ``But when a Republican administration is on a track leading
us to a less than fair and accurate census count, Democrats must
challenge at every opportunity available.''
   <PERSON>Kimball Brace</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Election Data Services</ORGANIZATION>, a consulting
firm that analyzes census data for Democratic state legislators,
told a news conference that the figures were subject to
considerable adjustment before the government comes out with final
numbers on <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>. Even then, the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Department</ORGANIZATION> will have
until <DATE>July 15, 1991</DATE>, to determine whether to adjust for an
undercount.
   Brace said he understood the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> has found up to 4
million additional people but has not yet included them in the
state figures. He said no estimate was available on where those
people are distributed among the states.
   Brace cited <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION> as states where
figures for rural areas were well below earlier estimates.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880330-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-30-88 1245EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CensusAdjustment     03-30 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census Adjustment,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Adjusting the Census: Little Difference</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If the two sides trying to force changes in
the <DATE>1990</DATE> census both get their way, the results would nearly
balance one another, a population expert said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> is under pressure to exclude illegal aliens
from its national head count. Traditionally, it counts everyone
living in the country.
   Groups which have filed suit to ignore the aliens contend large
concentrations of them could result in in some states gaining seats
in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> at the expense of other states.
   Meanwhile, other groups want the final census totals to be
increased to account for people who may be overlooked in the census
_ most often blacks and Hispanics living in urban areas.
   At stake are the 435 seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, which are distributed
among the states on the basis of population.
   ``If both sides get their way, the only change would be a
flip-flop of one seat from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>William
O'Hare</PERSON>, director of policy studies for the independent <ORGANIZATION>Population
Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION>.
   O'Hare told a breakfast briefing for <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>
members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> that he estimates their region will lose 14
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats following the <DATE>1990</DATE> census. That would continue a trend
evident over the last several decades, he noted.
   Using estimates of the number of illegal aliens and undercounted
minorities, he said that deleting the one group and adding in the
other would make little difference in the long run.
   The only change, he said, would be that <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> would gain
five new seats instead of six, while <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> would add two rather
than just one.
   ``That's easy to understand, since there are so many
undocumented aliens in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,'' he commented.
   O'Hare's study of potential changes in <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats _ based on
<DATE>1990</DATE> projections with no adjustments _ calls for <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to be
the big gainer, adding six <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats, followed by <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> with a
gain of four and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> adding three.
   Expected to pick up one seat each are <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>.
   On the other hand <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> would lose three seats. States losing
two apiece would be <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>.
Expected to lose one house seat are <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890908-0224 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-08-89 0903EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-MetroAreas 1stLd-Writethru f0030 09-08 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Metro Areas, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0030,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>Metro Population Growth Still Strong</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS word to `top' sted `two' in 2nd graf</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The fast-growing <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> metropolitan area
jumped two spots to surpass both <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports.
   New population estimates for the nation's metropolitan areas show
few changes among the top 25 urban areas, with <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> still firmly
in first place, followed by <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   The biggest move among the 25 largest communities was by <LOCATION>San
Diego</LOCATION>, which rose from 19th in <DATE>1987</DATE> to 17th last year. It added
84,100 people, climbing to 2,370,400 metro-area residents.
   That pushed the <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> city past <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> was listed with 2,342,500 residents, up 31,900
from the year before, and <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> declined 7,900, to 2,284,100.
   Not far down the list, fast-growing <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> pushed past the
burgeoning Tampa-St. Petersburg region.
   Phoenix added 51,500 residents over the year to climb to
2,029,500 and rise one spot to the nation's 20th largest metro area.
Tampa-St. Petersburg dropped to 21st, despite a gain of 38,000
people for a <DATE>1988</DATE> total of 1,995,100.
   While revised <DATE>1987</DATE> figures contained in the new report indicate
that <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> actually moved ahead of Tampa-St. Petersburg in that
year, the <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> metropolitan area had been listed as the larger of
the two on the basis of preliminary <DATE>1987</DATE> estimates.
   The <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>, metro area edged up
one spot to 24th, passing Milwaukee-Racine, which fell to 25th.
   The calculations are for metropolitan areas, which are officially
regional designations are used for federal statistical purposes.
Generally they consist of central cities of at least 50,000 people
and the surrounding regions that are economically interrelated.
   Here is a rundown on the nation's 25 most populous metropolitan
areas, their estimated populations as of <DATE>1988</DATE>, and the change from
the year before.
18,120,200, up 41,000.
   2. Los Angeles-Anaheim-Riverside, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, 13,769,700, up 311,700.
   3. Chicago-Gary-Lake County, Ill.-Ind.-<LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION>, 8,180,900, up 34,300.
   4. <LOCATION>San Francisco-Oakland-San Jose</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, 6,041,800, up 93,700.
   5. Philadelphia-Wilmington-Trenton, Pa.-N.J.-Del.-<LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, 5,963,300,
up 52,500.
   6. Detroit-Ann Arbor, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, 4,620,200, down 6,500.
   7. Boston-Lawrence-Salem, Mass.-N.H., 4,109,900, up 18,400.
   8. <LOCATION>Dallas-Fort Worth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 3,766,100, up 33,700.
   9. <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, D.C.-Md.-<LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, 3,734,200, up 80,100.
   10. Houston-Galveston-Brazoria, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 3,641,500, up 19,700.
   11. <LOCATION>Miami-Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, 3,000,500, up 50,400.
   12. Cleveland-Akron-Lorain, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, 2,769,000, down 6,900.
   13. <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, 2,736,600, up 80,400.
   14. <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, Mo.-Ill., 2,466,700, up 11,300.
   15. <LOCATION>Seattle-Tacoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, 2,420,800, up 69,400.
   16. Minneapolis-St. Paul, Minn.-Wis., 2,387,500, up 52,700.
   17. <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, 2,370,400, up 84,100.
   18. <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, 2,342,500, up 31,900.
   19. Pittsburgh-Beaver Valley, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, 2,284,100, down 7,900.
   20. <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, 2,029,500, up 51,500.
   21. Tampa-St. Petersburg-Clearwater, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, 1,995,100, up 38,000.
   22. Denver-Boulder, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>, 1,858,000, up 1,700.
   23. Cincinnati-Hamilton, Ohio-Ky.-<LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>, 1,728,500, up 8,700.
   24. <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, Mo.-Kan., 1,575,400, up 24,500.
   25. Milwaukee-Racine, <LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION>, 1,571,700, up 14,200.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880401-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-88 0255EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-HouseSeats     04-01 0270</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-House Seats,260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Population Estimates Would Move House Seats</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Population Outlook</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With political strength following population,
new <DATE>1990</DATE> Census projections give <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> a
rosy outlook.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> would jump to 50 members of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, a gain of
five, according to an analysis by the <ORGANIZATION>Library of Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>David C. Huckabee</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Library's Congressional Research
Service</ORGANIZATION> recalculated the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> distribution based on the new <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> projections of populations in <DATE>1990</DATE>. The estimates were
released <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Huckabee cautioned, however, that his calculation is based on
estimates, and a very small change in population can shift a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
seat from one state to another.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, for example, a difference of fewer than 300 people gave
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> rather than <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> an additional <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seat, he said.
   With <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats limited to 435, every gain by one state means a
loss for another.
   In addition to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Huckabee</PERSON> calculated that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> would
gain four new seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> would gain three.
   Adding two seats would be <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, while <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> would each pick up one.
   On the other hand, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> would each drop
three seats, he calculated. Losing two apiece would be <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>. Expected to lose one would be <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>.
   Huckabee's figures differ slightly from those of <LOCATION>William O'Hare</LOCATION>
at the private <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, who used a different
set of <DATE>1990</DATE> estimates.
   <ORGANIZATION>Election Data Services</ORGANIZATION>, a private consulting firm, also issued
somewhat different reapportionment estimates earlier this year,
based on <DATE>1987</DATE> Census estimates.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901227-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-27-90 0036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CensusCount Bjt   12-27 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census Count, Bjt,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Census Shows 249.6 Million Americans; Sun Belt Still a Gainer</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM BOVEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation grew to 249.6 million people in the
<DATE>1980s</DATE> as more Americans left the industrial and agricultural
heartlands for the South and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s first ``final'' figures from the <DATE>1990</DATE>
census, released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, showed the pull of the Sun Belt
remained strong, despite efforts by the industrial North to promote
growth and the collapse during the <DATE>1980s</DATE> of the oil and savings and
loan industries - two mainstays of the Southern and Western states.
   The census figures are used to adjust the number of
representatives each state sends to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> so that political
clout is in line with population. The figures also determine the
division of federal money among states and localities.
   The numbers could change next <DATE>summer</DATE> when the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce
Department</ORGANIZATION> decides whether to adjust the count. Some states and
cities are likely to challenge the tallies, whichever way the
adjustment decision goes.
   More than 6,000 local governments challenged the accuracy of a
preliminary count based mainly on the <DATE>April 1</DATE> census taken by mail.
The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> responded with a series of recounts and an ad
campaign urging people who thought they had been missed to come
forward.
   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> criticized the count released
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, saying it underestimated the city's population and as a
result will cost the city <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in federal funds each
year.
   ``Since at least <DATE>1940</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Department</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> have systematically under counted Americans of color and
Americans who live in cities,'' <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said at a <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> news
conference.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s final national population total was nearly 4
million people more than the preliminary number it released earlier
this year.
   Five states, all in the South or West, grew by more than a
fourth in the decade: <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, up <PERCENT>50.7 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>37.4
percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>35.3 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>33.4 percent</PERCENT>; and
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>26.1 percent</PERCENT>.
   The six states having growth of less than <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> included
some industrial powerhouses: <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, up <PERCENT>0.4 percent</PERCENT>;
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>0.5 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>0.7 percent</PERCENT>; and <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>0.8
percent</PERCENT>. Grain-growing <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> grew by a bare <PERCENT>0.9 percent</PERCENT>.
<LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, hard hit by the collapse in oil prices in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>,
grew <PERCENT>0.8 percent</PERCENT>.
   Five states lost population. The biggest percentage loser was
<LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, whose population dropped by <PERCENT>7.6 percent</PERCENT> to
1,801,625. Other states losing population were <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>4.3
percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>2.9 percent</PERCENT>; and <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>1.7
percent</PERCENT>. The <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> also lost population, <PERCENT>4.5
percent</PERCENT>.
   America's population grew at a slower pace in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> than in
decades past: <PERCENT>10.2 percent</PERCENT>, compared with <PERCENT>11.4 percent</PERCENT> in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>
and <PERCENT>13.4 percent</PERCENT> in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>.
   This year's population count, 249,632,692, for the first time
included some Americans living abroad. The <DATE>1980</DATE> population figure,
226,504,825, counted only people living within the nation's
borders.
   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s release was only the first burst of what will be a
barrage of census numbers detailing not only the number of people
but their ages, races, housing situations, incomes and a wealth of
other data.
   The last figures in the <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY> census won't be released
until <DATE>1993</DATE>.
   All regions had more people in <DATE>1990</DATE> compared with 10 years
earlier. The <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> regions had the
sharpest growth, and the <ORGANIZATION>East North Central</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>West North Central</LOCATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>East South Central</ORGANIZATION> regions had the slowest.
   The Pacific states were the fastest growing region, <PERCENT>23.4
percent</PERCENT>, followed by the Mountain states, <PERCENT>20.6 percent</PERCENT>, and the
<LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> states, <PERCENT>18.8 percent</PERCENT>. In the <DATE>1970s</DATE> those regions had
each showed double-digit growth.
   By contrast, the <ORGANIZATION>East North Central</ORGANIZATION> states grew a bare <PERCENT>1.1
percent</PERCENT>; the <LOCATION>West North Central</LOCATION> states, <PERCENT>3.1 percent</PERCENT>; and the <LOCATION>East
South Central</LOCATION> states, <PERCENT>3.9 percent</PERCENT>. Those numbers represented a
falloff from each region's growth in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   Other facts from the census release:
   -<LOCATION>Besides California</LOCATION>, states gaining representatives will be
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, four; <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, three; and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, one seat each.
   -States losing representatives will be <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, three;
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, two each; and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, one each.
   -The <DATE>1990</DATE> census counted 922,819 members of the armed forces,
civilian employees of the federal government and their dependents
living abroad. Other Americans living overseas weren't counted.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ901227-0001
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
901227-0001.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Census Bureau Adds 3.8 Million to Count
   But Critics Say Millions Remain Missing
   ----
   By David Wessel
</HL>
<DATE>
12/27/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A3
</SO>
<GV>
COMMERCE DEPARTMENT (COM)
CONGRESS (CNG)
</GV>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- The Census Bureau added 3.8 million more
people to its 1990 headcount, but critics continue to
complain that the bureau is missing millions more.
   The bureau said yesterday that its almost-final tally from
the 1990 census is 249,632,692 people, 10.2% more than the
1980 census found.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The addition of 3.8 million people to the preliminary
total released this <DATE>summer</DATE> reflects 2.9 million residents the
bureau missed the first time as well as the anticipated
922,819 military and other federal employees and dependents
overseas.
   Under the Constitution, the new headcount will result in a
shift of 19 seats in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> is the big winner, adding seven seats to give
it 52 representatives, or nearly <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> of all the seats in the
435-member <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is the big loser. It will lose
three seats and end up with 31 seats after the <DATE>1992</DATE> election.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> tally includes military and other federal workers
and dependents living overseas. The <DATE>1980</DATE> tally didn't.
Excluding those people, the resident population of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
grew by <PERCENT>9.8%</PERCENT> during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>Barbara
Bryant</PERSON> said.
   The bureau may yet make additional adjustments to the
tally. Under terms of an out-of-court settlement of a lawsuit
brought by <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> and others who argued that the
census disproportionately misses minorities, the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce
Department</ORGANIZATION> must decide by <DATE>July 15</DATE> whether to adjust the
tallies statistically to compensate for the undercount.
Commerce Undersecretary <PERSON>Michael Darby</PERSON> yesterday called the
<DATE>1990</DATE> census "full, fair and efficient."
   But congressional skepticism persists. "It's not a
question of whether we have counted everyone. The census
never does," said Rep. <PERSON>Thomas Sawyer</PERSON> (D., <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>), chairman of
the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> census subcommittee. "The question is how close
they've come to the truth."
   <ORGANIZATION>New York State Attorney</ORGANIZATION> General <PERSON>Robert Abrams</PERSON>, among those
suing the bureau, was quick to complain that the <DATE>1990</DATE> census
still undercounted his state. "When large segments of our
residents are left out of the political process, democracy is
devalued for all of us," he said.
   Additions to the preliminary tally reflect, among other
things, recanvassing of a substantial number of housing units
by census enumerators. With aid from state and local
governments, the bureau also identified about 125,000 housing
units it had missed. It also turned up an extra 400,000
people from parole records, <PERSON>Mrs. Bryant</PERSON> said recently.
   <PERSON>Mr. Darby</PERSON> noted that the new tally is "surprisingly close"
to earlier projections that the census would find a
population of 250 million. But Rep. <PERSON>Sawyer</PERSON> noted that the
249.6 million total is still substantially shy of the
bureau's recent projections, based on demographic data, of
253.4 million.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> census confirms trends identified in earlier
reports, such as the rapid growth of the western states. "The
West is the big population gainer," <PERSON>Mrs. Bryant</PERSON> said. In the
past decade, the population of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> has grown by <PERCENT>22%</PERCENT>,
while the South grew by <PERCENT>13.5%</PERCENT>, the Northeast by <PERCENT>3.4%</PERCENT>, and the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> by <PERCENT>1.3%</PERCENT>.
   The reassignment of seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> reflects these
trends, with the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and Sunbelt states gaining at the
expense of the big industrial states of the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>. In addition to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, states adding seats
include <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, which gains four seats; <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which gains
three seats; and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, which each gain one seat.
   Besides <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, states losing seats include <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, which each lose two seats;
and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, which each lose one
seat.
   None of these shifts comes as a surprise, however. Earlier
bureau reports on the <DATE>1990</DATE> count pointed to all of them.
   The figures may provide new ammunition for the <ORGANIZATION>District of
Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s perennially unsuccessful campaign for statehood.
Although the census found that the district lost population
during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, it still is larger than either <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. Yet the district hasn't any seats in the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, and its one representative in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> can't vote.
   The bureau also noted yesterday that four states lost
population in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. They are <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>.
   ---
                       Population Power
                                                                                                       

   State-by-state tally of population and seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House
of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> based on <DATE>1990</DATE> census
                                                                                                       

                               <DATE>1990</DATE>        TOTAL    CHANGE
                            POPULATION     HOUSE     FROM
                          (In millions)    SEATS    PRESENT
                                                                                                       

   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>                 29.84         52          7
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>                   18.04         31         -3
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>                      17.06         30          3

   <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>               11.92         21         -2
   Illinois                   11.47         20         -2
   <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>                       10.89         19         -2
   <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>                    9.33         16         -2
   <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>                  7.75         13         -1
   <ORGANIZATION>N. Carolina</ORGANIZATION>                 6.66         12         -1
   <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>                     6.51         11         -1
   <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>                    6.22         11          1
   <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>               6.03         10         -1
   <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>                     5.56         10       None
   <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>                    5.14          9       None
   <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>                   4.91          9       None
   <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>                  4.89          9          1
   Tennessee                   4.90          9       None
   <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>                    4.80          8       None
   <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>                   4.39          8       None
   <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>                   4.24          7         -1
   <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>                     4.06          7       None
   Kentucky                    3.70          6         -1
   <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>                     3.68          6          1
   <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>              3.51          6       None
   <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>                    3.31          6       None
   Connecticut                 3.30          6       None
   Oklahoma                    3.16          6       None
   <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>                      2.85          5       None
   <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>                        2.79          5         -1
   <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>                 2.59          5       None
   Kansas                      2.49          4         -1
   Arkansas                    2.36          4       None
   <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>               1.80          3         -1
   <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>                        1.73          3       None
   <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>                    1.58          3       None
   <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>                  1.52          3       None
   <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>                       1.23          2       None
   <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>                      1.21          2       None
   <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>                      1.12          2       None
   New Hampshire               1.11          2       None
   <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>                       1.01          2       None
   <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>                1.01          2       None
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>                     0.80          1         -1
   <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>                0.70          1       None
   Delaware                    0.67          1       None
   <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>                0.64          1       None
   <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>                     0.56          1       None
   <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>                      0.55          1       None
   Wyoming                     0.46          1       None
   Dist. of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>           0.61         --         --
   TOTAL                     249.6         435
                                                                                                       

   Source: <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Census Bureau
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Census-States     12-29 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census-States,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Census Figures Could Affect Reapportionment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Census Bureau figures released today indicate
that seven states are likely to gain seats in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION> in reapportionment, while as many as a dozen states
will lose at least one seat, forecasters say.
   The next reapportionment will be based on the final <DATE>1990</DATE> Census
figures, which will be collected in the 10-year census next year.
The state population figures released <DATE>today</DATE> go up to mid-1989 and
represent one last checkpoint before the final, official count.
   The non-profit <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said that if the
trends in this latest report hold true through the final <DATE>1990</DATE>
figures, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> will gain seven seats, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> each
will gain three, and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>
will gain one apiece.
   At the same time, 11 states are likely to lose one or more
seats, the <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said. It said <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> will
lose three seats, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> each
will lose two, and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> each will lose one.
   Comparable predictions by <ORGANIZATION>Election Data Services Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a
Washington-based political consulting firm, differed little. The
firm, however, added <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> to the list of losers, dropping one
congressional seat, and predicted that <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> will gain four
seats, rather than three.
   However, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> figures on which the predictions are
based do not include members of the military and their dependents
living overseas. They will be counted in the <DATE>1990</DATE> reapportionment,
the government recently announced, and that change could mean the
difference in whether some states gain or lose a seat.
   The Census figures show that the populations of five states grew
at rates faster than <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> <DATE>from 1985</DATE> to mid-1989.
   The state that experienced the largest percentage increase in
population between <DATE>1985</DATE> and mid-1989, <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, grew by <PERCENT>18 percent</PERCENT>.
Second was <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>, followed by <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New
Hampshire</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   At the same time, seven states lost population, the bureau said:
<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1801EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Census-States     12-28 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census-States,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>For release 12:01 a.m. EST Friday; time set by sources</HEAD>
<HEAD>New Census Figures Could Affect Reapportionment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The populations of five states grew at rates
faster than <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> in the <DATE>last half of the 1980s</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a report that is causing revised estimates
for congressional reapportionment.
   The Census figures on state population, issued for release
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, showed Nevadawith the biggest population gain at <PERCENT>18 percent</PERCENT>
<DATE>from 1985</DATE> to the middle of <DATE>1989</DATE>. Arizona had the second highest
growth rate, at <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>, followed by <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>
at <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   Seven states lost population during the same period, the bureau
said: <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>.
   The population figures are closely watched at the end of each
decade because they determine how many seats in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION> each state will have. The next reapportionment will
be based on the final <DATE>1990</DATE> Census figures, which will be collected
in the 10-year census next year.
   The report issued <DATE>Thursday</DATE> represents one last checkpoint before
that final, official count, and two forecasting groups on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
issued revised reapportionment predictions based on the trends.
   While the two reports varied on some specifics, they agreed on
the overall trend: states in the Sunbelt will generally pick up
seats lost by states in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>.
   The non-profit <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said that if the
trends in <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s report hold true through the final <DATE>1990</DATE>
figures, 11 states are likely to lose one or more seats in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
while seven will gain.
   It said <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> will lose three seats, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> two, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>
two, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> two, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> two, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> one, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> one,
<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> one, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> one, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> one and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> one.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> will gain seven
seats, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> will gain three, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> three, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> one, <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION> one, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> one and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> one.
   The comparable prediction by <ORGANIZATION>Election Data Services Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a
Washington-based political consulting firm, differed only for a few
states. It said <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> is likely to pick up four seats, rather
than three, and it added <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> to the list of those losing
seats, dropping one.
   There is still a wild card in the deck which cannot, at this
point, be predicted with certainty. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> figures on
which the projections are based do not include members of the
military and their dependents living overseas.
   The government recently announced that they will be counted in
the <DATE>1990</DATE> reapportionment. This change could tip the balance in some
states that now appear close to winning or losing a seat.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06024339 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06024339 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  US; POPULATION; SURVEY; RESULT; CITY; STATISTIC; CONTROVERSY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Final population figures for some areas released by the Census Bureau on
Wednesday prompted renewed charges by officials in several cities that the
1990 census had missed thousands of their residents.;    "It's a serious,
serious undercount," said Susan Weed, Chicago's assistant commissioner for
planning.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BIG CITIES CRITICIZE FINAL CENSUS DATA AS
SERIOUSLY SHORT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Associated Press contributed to this report.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reported <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s population at 2.78 million, more than
140,000 short of the figure the city submitted last fall in an official
challenge. While the final figure represented a gain of about 58,000 over
preliminary numbers released in late <DATE>summer</DATE>, <PERSON>Weed</PERSON> said the city was not
satisfied with the final count, which could mean a loss of millions of federal
dollars.;    <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> defends data;  <PERSON>Barbara Everitt Bryant</PERSON>, director of
the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, has defended the quality of the <DATE>1990</DATE> census, saying the
<ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> figures have in most cases proven to be more accurate than those
from the cities.;    <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s population figures -- for counties, towns and
cities in 18 states and the <LOCATION>District of Columbia</LOCATION> -- are part of the continuing
release of data from the <DATE>1990</DATE> census, which was conducted last <DATE>spring</DATE>. Figures
for the remaining states are scheduled to be released <DATE>today</DATE> and Friday.;   
Figures were released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>District
of Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia.</LOCATION>;    Flak from big cities;  While
thousands of local jurisdictions had challenged the preliminary findings, it
was the big cities that were most critical of the <DATE>1990</DATE> census. Even before the
census was conducted, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> and other communities filed a
suit to force the federal government to compensate for residents missed in the
head count by using a statistical formula to arrive at new population
figures.;    As a result of that suit, the government agreed to consider such
an adjustment, and a decision will be announced by <DATE>July 15.</DATE>;    In the
meantime, complaints from cities grew even louder <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, when officials
saw that their population counts fell short of the figures they believe are
more accurate.;    <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>'s complaint;  "It's embarrassing for the government
to put forward this as a final piece of work," said <PERSON>Allan Stern</PERSON>, a city
official in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> responsible for the census.;    While city officials
believe <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>'s population is more than 600,000, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> published
a final count of 574,283, a gain of 20,571 over the preliminary number.;   
The statistics hold special significance in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, which lost a
congressional seat in the <DATE>1990</DATE> reapportionment based on its population.;   
"We're losing a seat by 12,000 human beings," <PERSON>Stern</PERSON> said. "They're off by more
than twice that in this city alone.";    <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> sued;  In <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, where city
officials filed a separate lawsuit in <DATE>December</DATE> challenging the census numbers,
the city's final figure prompted similar dismay.;    The Census Bureau's
figure for <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> was 394,017, a gain of 9,864 over the preliminary number.; 
  "The feeling is those figures are wrong," said <PERSON>Lyn May</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for
Mayor <PERSON>Maynard Jackson</PERSON>. She said the city would pursue its lawsuit.;    The
city believes its population is 437,000. "We stand by those numbers," <DATE>May</DATE>
said.;    This is the first time the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> has released detailed
population figures for the whole nation this early in the census reporting
process. Normally, population counts for localities are released one state at
a time over a period of many months.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Washington Post  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910124  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  565  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday January 24, 1991
00024339,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900222-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-22-90 2014EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Reapportionment     02-22 0393</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reapportionment,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reapportionment Changes, A Bit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The political outlook may have improved a bit
for the North in new Census population estimates.
   The South and West will wrest away some seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION> after the <DATE>1990</DATE> national head count _ but maybe not
as many as had originally been thought.
   The Constitution requires seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> to be redistributed
among states after each census.
   The private <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION> analyzed a complex
series of new Census estimates on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, and predicted that 14
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats will move from the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> to the South
and West after the census.
   Earlier analyses by the same group had indicated as many as 18
seats would move.
   The Census estimates include four sets of possible state
populations for <DATE>1990</DATE>, each differing slightly depending on the
amount of interstate movement by people.
   One set included no movement, and was discounted by the private
analysis group.
   But while reapportionment calculations based on the other three
varied slightly, the overall shift in seats was consistent.
   The big winner will be <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, gaining six seats based on
the new figures. The previous calculations had called for
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to gain five seats.
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> will gain three seats each, the new estimates
indicate. Earlier calculations had shown <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> adding four seats
and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> three.
   <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, which had previously been expected to gain
two seats apiece, are now expected to add one, the new study said.
   <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> also will gain one, as had been expected. <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION> would add one seat under two of the estimates, but would
remain unchanged under the third.
   On the losing side, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is still expected to lose three
seats. <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, which had been expected to drop three, now
appears likely to lose just two. <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> will
drop two each, the same as previously expected.
   Also unchanged are losses of one seat each by <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, which had been expected to lose a seat, would not do
so under the new figures. And <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> would lose a seat under two
estimates but not under the third.
   Following the <DATE>1990</DATE> census, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> will present the
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> with the final state population figures and the new
reapportionment numbers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901226-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-26-90 2324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-CensusCount 3rdLd-Writethru a0629 12-26 0785</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census Count, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0629,860</SECOND>
<BYLINE>249.6 Million People Counted in 1990 Census</BYLINE>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to CORRECT California increase from 26.3 percent
to 26.1 percent; SUBS grafs 13-15 bgng: ``The sharpest,'' to
CORRECT Arizona from 36 percent to 35.3 percent; South Atlantic
from 18.4 percent to 18.8 percent and ``West South Central'' to
``East South Central''</NOTE>
<HEAD>With BC-Census Count-States</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM BOVEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population stood at 249,632,692 as of
the <DATE>1990</DATE> census, the government said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in a numerical
portrait of a nation growing far more rapidly in the Sun Belt than
in the industrial north and agricultural heartland.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, the nation's largest state, added more than 6
million people in the decade, a <PERCENT>26.1 percent</PERCENT> increase to 29,839,250
people.
   Wyoming remained the smallest state, with 455,975 people, down
<PERCENT>2.9 percent</PERCENT> from <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> was the biggest population gainer in percentage terms,
and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> each grew by more than one-third as
millions of Americans flocked to the sunshine.
   <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> was the largest loser in percentage terms.
   In all, the population increased by <PERCENT>10.2 percent</PERCENT> from the
226,504,825 people counted in the <DATE>1980</DATE> census, below the <PERCENT>11.4
percent</PERCENT> population growth recorded from <DATE>1970 to 1980</DATE>, and the <PERCENT>13.4
percent</PERCENT> rate from <DATE>1960</DATE> to <DATE>1970</DATE>.
   The information was contained in the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s first
release of ``final figures'' - really tentative final figures -
from the <DATE>1990</DATE> count. The information will be used for everything
from readjusting the size of each state's congressional delegation
to parcelling out federal aid.
   In political terms, the population shifts will give <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
seven new <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats, and add lawmakers to seven other states.
Thirteen states will lose representation.
   Because of the importance of the population estimates, some
states and cities are likely to challenge the tallies, and a final
count isn't expected until next <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   The cost of the <DATE>1990</DATE> census, from planning begun in <DATE>1984</DATE> to a
final release of data in <DATE>1993</DATE>, is estimated at <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY> by the
bureau.
   Still locked in <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> computers - to be doled out over
the next several years - is a wealth of information about age,
race, living conditions and other details of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> near the turn
of the century.
   Besides <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, four other states lost population. The biggest
percentage loser was <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, whose population dropped by <PERCENT>7.6
percent</PERCENT> to 1,801,625. Other states losing population were <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
down <PERCENT>4.3 percent</PERCENT>, and and <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>1.7 percent</PERCENT>. The
<ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> also lost population, <PERCENT>4.5 percent</PERCENT>.
   The sharpest gainer in percentage terms was <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>. That state's
population grew by <PERCENT>50.7 percent</PERCENT> to 1,206,152. Besides <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
other states with gains of more than <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> were <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, up
<PERCENT>33.4 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, up <PERCENT>35.3 percent</PERCENT>; and <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, up <PERCENT>37.4
percent</PERCENT>.
   The Pacific states were the fastest growing region, <PERCENT>23.4
percent</PERCENT>, followed by the Mountain states, <PERCENT>20.6 percent</PERCENT>, and the
<LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> states, <PERCENT>18.8 percent</PERCENT>. By contrast, the <ORGANIZATION>East North
Central</ORGANIZATION> states grew a bare <PERCENT>1.1 percent</PERCENT>, and the <LOCATION>West North Central</LOCATION>
states, <PERCENT>3.1 percent</PERCENT>.
   Some regions went against the broader trend. <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>, which
had a boom in high-tech industry during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, grew by <PERCENT>7.2
percent</PERCENT>. The East South Central states grew only <PERCENT>3.9 percent</PERCENT>.
   Because of the high financial and political stakes, the census
numbers and the way they were obtained are certain to draw
continued sharp scrutiny.
   More than 6,000 local governments challenged the accuracy of a
preliminary count based mainly on the <DATE>April 1</DATE> census taken by mail.
The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> responded with a series of recounts and an ad
campaign urging people who thought they had been missed to come
forward.
   The final national population total was nearly 4 million people
more than the preliminary number released by the bureau earlier
this year.
   <ORGANIZATION>Commerce</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Robert Mosbacher</PERSON> has until <DATE>July 1991</DATE>, to
decide whether to adjust the census numbers to account for a
statistically determined undercount of minorities. An adjustment
would increase political representation of areas with a high
percentage of minorities, and lower that of other areas.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> will gain seven seats, giving it 52 in the 435-member
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> will gain four; <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, three; and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, one seat each.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> will lose three seats; <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, two seats each; and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>,
one seat each.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> census for the first time counted some Americans living
abroad. The total included 922,819 members of the armed forces,
civilian employees of the federal government and their dependents.
   The comparable numbers from 10 years earlier counted only people
living within the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The Census Bureau on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> released two sets of <DATE>1980</DATE>
numbers. The 226,504,825 figure used by the bureau for comparison
with the <DATE>1990</DATE> national total was released in <DATE>December 1980</DATE> but was
later adjusted slightly to get rid of minor problems. The adjusted
figure was 226,545,805.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> population count was nearly 64 times the 3,929,214
counted in <DATE>1790</DATE>, the first census in the nation's history. By <DATE>1900</DATE>,
the population had reached 76,212,168.
   In <DATE>1950</DATE>, the first census after World War II, the population was
151,325,798.
   In <DATE>January</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> will begin sending information on
small areas, in some cases the size of a city block, to state
legislatures so they can begin drawing new congressional and
legislative boundaries.
   That process will be completed by <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
   The bureau will put off releasing detailed demographic data
until after the decision on adjusting the figures.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901227-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-27-90 0223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Census-Politics 2ndLd-Writethru a0426 12-27 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census-Politics, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0426,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Potent California: More House Members Than 21 states Combined</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 4th graf, ``The news xxx to CORRECT last time
presidential candidate won White House without carrying California</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the politics of the future, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> will
exercise more clout than any smoke-filled room of politicians ever
did.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> emerges from the <DATE>1990</DATE> census as a political behemoth,
with 52 <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats, a population bigger than <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s and <PERCENT>20
percent</PERCENT> of the electoral votes needed to be elected president.
   Add together the congressional representation of 21 states and
they still will total fewer than the delegation from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
which swells by seven in <DATE>1992</DATE>, the result of a <PERCENT>26 percent</PERCENT> surge in
population in the <DATE>last 10 years</DATE>.
   The news is nothing but promising for Republicans. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
except for <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> in <DATE>1976</DATE>, no one has won the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
while losing <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> since <DATE>1912</DATE>, when Democrat <PERSON>Woodrow Wilson</PERSON>
lost the state but defeated <PERSON>Bull Mooser Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON> and
Republican <PERSON>William Howard Taft</PERSON> anyway.
   Republicans can find more cheer in most of the other shifts in
political power ordered up by the population figures released by
the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The industrial <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> will lose standing in
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and the electoral college. The West, the South and the Sun
Belt, increasingly Republican, gain.
   ``The political consequences advantage the Republicans,'' summed
up <PERSON>Stephen Hess</PERSON>, political analyst at the <ORGANIZATION>Brookings Institution</ORGANIZATION>, a
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> research organization.
   The census sets the stage, as well, for brutal redistricting
battles from coast to coast, promising to generate nasty
colleague-versus-colleague races in some of the 13 states where the
number of <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats must shrink.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> will suffer the biggest loss, three seats, and on the
streets of <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>, that could come down to a brawl between two
Democratic incumbents, Reps. <PERSON>Charles Schumer</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stephen Solarz</PERSON>.
They may have to compete for a single seat.
   It is no coincidence, <PERSON>Hess</PERSON> observed, that <PERSON>Schumer</PERSON> and <PERSON>Solarz</PERSON>
have built up campaign warchests in the million-dollar range, each
anticipating a costly battle - or perhaps a race elsewhere, maybe
taking on Republican <PERSON>Alfonse M. D'Amato</PERSON> for his <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> seat.
   Four states lose two <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> members - <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, going to 20;
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, to 16; <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, to 19; and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, to 21.
   Eight states will lose one each - <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, down to five; <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, to
four; <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, to six; <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, to seven; <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, to 10;
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, to one; <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, to 13; and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, to three.
   Among the gainers are <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, up four to 23, and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> up three
to 30. And one additional seat in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> will go to five states
- <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, going to six; <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, to 11; <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, to 12;
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, to 11; and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, to nine.
   But it is <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> where the gains are most dramatic. In
<DATE>January 1993</DATE>, that state will have more representatives than 21
other states combined - <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New
Hampshire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   All states except the six which now have only one representative
- <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>
- will have to redraw congressional boundaries. The purpose is to
give each representative 572,466 constituents, or as close to that
figure as possible.
   The cry of gerrymandering - rigging election lines to favor one
party - is sure to be heard. In <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, the election of
Republican <PERSON>Pete Wilson</PERSON> as governor will serve as a check if the
Democratic legislature tries to squeeze out Republicans, already
outnumbered 27-18.
   Elsewhere, black leaders in <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> have served notice that
they want the new lines drawn to create districts where blacks have
substantial majorities and a chance to elect a member of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We will oppose any friend or fight any foe to ensure that
there is a black congressional district in <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> in <DATE>1991</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Jack
Gravely</PERSON>, president of that state's <ORGANIZATION>NAACP</ORGANIZATION>, announced last fall.
   <PERSON>Curtis Gans</PERSON>, director of the non-partisan <ORGANIZATION>Committee</ORGANIZATION> for the
Study of the <ORGANIZATION>American Electorate</ORGANIZATION>, disputed what he said was the
widespread view of the census figures as a ``windfall for the
Republicans.''
   Most states that picked up new seats did so because of growing
Hispanic populations, <PERSON>Gans</PERSON> said, and he predicted that Hispanics
will become increasingly loyal Democrats.
   ``Hispanics of the class that is expanding the population in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> tend to vote 2-1
Democratic,'' he said. ``Eventually that's going to tell - probably
within the next decade.''
   Only in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, where Cuban-Americans favor conservative
candidates, can the Republicans anticipate long-term gains, he
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880127-0086 </DOCNO>
<HL> REGIONS </HL>
<AUTHOR> Eugene Carlson </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> ENV MON BNK </IN>
<G> CNG </G>
<TEXT>
      Americans on the Move
   Are on the Rebound
   EVERY few years, Americans stuff their worldly goods into cardboard boxes and change homes. 
From the end of World War II until the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, annually about <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population changed residences. 

   During the <DATE>1970s</DATE> and early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, however, the "geographic mobility rate" drifted as low as <PERCENT>16%</PERCENT>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> says. 
Bureau demographers believe that rising housing costs, especially high interest rates, made lots of people postpone moves, the bulk of which are local and tend to be more discretionary than long-distance ones. 

   Newly released figures show American mobility snapping back to more traditional levels, with <PERCENT>20.2%</PERCENT> of the population moving in <DATE>1985</DATE>, compared with <PERCENT>17.3%</PERCENT> a year earlier. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, which has been charting household moves since <DATE>1948</DATE>, finds the year-to-year increase of three percentage points "unprecedented," says <PERSON>Larry Long</PERSON>, of the bureau's <ORGANIZATION>Center for Demographic Studies</ORGANIZATION>. 
The mobility rise followed a sharp drop in mortgage rates from unusually high levels. 
<PERSON>Mr. Long</PERSON> speculates that many potential movers were simply waiting for housing to become more affordable. 

   Long-distance moves in <DATE>1984-85</DATE> marked the first time in several decades that the South didn't score a big population gain. 
Some 1.3 million people moved into Southern states, but nearly as many, 1.2 million, moved out, most to the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. 
Census demographers say they aren't sure whether this shift in <LOCATION>Southern</LOCATION> net migration is a one-year statistical aberration or the start of a significant trend. 

   Shift to the Sun
   Belt For Congressional Seats
   POLITICIANS are starting to speculate how the population drift toward the Sun Belt during the <DATE>1980s</DATE> will alter the balance of power in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. 
If state population trends continue as they have so far this decade, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> would gain six seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1990s</DATE>. 
Two other Sun Belt states with prospective big gains in <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats are <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, with four, and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, with three. 
<LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> each would add one seat. 
