<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900101-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-01-90 1023EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ManateeDeaths     01-01 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Manatee Deaths,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>1989 A Record Year For Manatee Deaths</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A record number of manatees, 160,
died in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> waters in <DATE>1989</DATE>, and state biologists fear recent
cold weather will kill more of the lumbering marine mammals.
   ``We're quite worried about the increasing number of deaths,''
said <PERSON>Bruce Ackerman</PERSON>, a researcher with the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Natural
Resources</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>St. Petersburg</LOCATION>.
   Biologists estimate at least 1,200 manatees, an endangered
species, live in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. The population had been estimated at as
many as 10,000 a few decades ago.
   In <DATE>1989</DATE>, 51 manatees died after hitting boats or barges, and
five were killed by other human-caused problems, such as
entanglement in fishing nets, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE>, 133 manatees were found dead in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. Boats killed
43 manatees, then a record.
   Environmentalists and government biologists cite these
statistics when they promote boating speed limits and increased
protection of manatee habitat, issues state lawmakers could debate
this <DATE>spring</DATE>.
   Manatees frequent rivers, estuaries, canals and protected
coastal areas that also are magnets for the state's more than
710,000 registered motor boats.
   The average adult manatee is about 10 feet long and weighs 1,000
pounds, though some weigh three times that much. Gray and
slow-moving, they can be difficult for speedy boaters to spot, said
<PERSON>Lori Price</PERSON>, captive marine mammal specialist for the <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I think very few of them (boaters) actually maliciously intend
to run down a manatee,'' she said. ``They're very difficult to
see.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890616-0187 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-16-89 1344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--ManateeBlues Adv26-1stLd-Writethru b0912 06-16
0615</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Manatee Blues, Adv 26 - 1st Ld-Writethru, b0912,0629</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, June 26, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Outlook For Sea Cows Bleak As Boat Traffic Increases</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf to CORRECT spelling of Marjory sted Marjery</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SANDRA WALEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A groggy volunteer crew of five gathered early New
Year's Day and raced to where a 500-pound sea cow had been found
with deep gashes from a boat propeller in its grayish-brown,
leathery back.
   But the West Indian manatee wasn't injured in the congested
Intracoastal Waterway, it was the <LOCATION>Everglades</LOCATION>. ``It shows you they
aren't safe anywhere,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Gregory Bossart</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Miami Seaquarium</LOCATION>
veterinarian and pathologist.
   Besides the unmistakable prop marks, the manatee had three
fractured ribs and a punctured lung. The injuries caused a bubble to
form inside the animal, leaving it floating helplessly.
   The manatee _ dubbed <ORGANIZATION>Marjory</ORGANIZATION> after <PERSON>Marjory Stoneman Douglas</PERSON>, a
protector of the Everglads _ has been recovering at the <LOCATION>Seaquarium</LOCATION>,
one of two marine parks _the other is Sea World in <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION> _ in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> that are authorized to rescue the protected animal.
   An estimated 1,200 of the prehistoric-looking creatures live in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, based on aerial surveys. The docile, plant-eating
creatures, weighing more than 3,000 pounds and ranging from eight to
14 feet long, are found from northern <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> to as far north
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>.
   They face a growing threat from <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s development boom.
   A total of 133 manatee deaths were reported last year, including
a record 43 from being hit by boats; there were 39 boat-related
deaths in <DATE>1987</DATE>. The 45 deaths so far this year exceeds the <DATE>1987</DATE>
period. Through <DATE>March</DATE>, 15 deaths have been blamed on boats, and 23
carcasses were recovered last month alone.
   ``Our guess is that the numbers increased through the <DATE>'60s</DATE> and
<DATE>'70s</DATE> as there was more protection, but in the '80s they've held
about steady,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Bruce Ackerman</PERSON>, a state marine mammal
researcher. ``If that's the case, the fact that deaths are
increasing is of considerable concern.''
   Even if boat-related deaths were reduced, the manatee faces other
obstacles such as a low reproductive rate and diminishing habitat,
officials say.
   ``We're not that optimistic. ... Their ability to recover from
any kind of problem is limited, even if everything was perfect,''
<PERSON>Ackerman</PERSON> said.
   The rehabilitation of injured manatees is a painstaking process
that takes months. There is also the question of what awaits them
and babies born in captivity once they are returned to the wild.
   ``There's no problem with breeding in the wild. The problem we
have is habitat destruction,'' said <PERSON>J.P. Garner</PERSON>, assistant manager
of <LOCATION>Homosassa Springs Park</LOCATION>, where nine manatees are kept.
   Manatees rely on seagrass beds for food and have begun to
congregate around the warm-water discharges of power plants, where
boat traffic is often heavy.
   <PERSON>Patrick Rose</PERSON>, a marine mammal coordinator for the state
<ORGANIZATION>Department of Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION>, said <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> is focusing efforts on
tying manatee protection to county growth management plans. In
addition, there has been an extensive campaign to increase public
awareness about the creatures' plight.
   Singer-songwriter Jimmy Buffet gave a big boost to the manatee
cause eight years ago when he became chairman of the ``Save the
<ORGANIZATION>Manatee Club</ORGANIZATION>,'' which now boasts an international membership of
about 22,000.
   ``They have absolutely no ability to be aggressive,'' said Rose.
``People identify with them as the ultimate victim.''
   More than five months after being picked up, <ORGANIZATION>Marjory</ORGANIZATION> remains in
guarded but stable condition in a <LOCATION>Seaquarium</LOCATION> tank, <PERSON>Bossart</PERSON> said.
``She's feeling a lot better and is able to dive better.''
   Unlike many others of the gentle mammals, she still has a
fighting chance.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for June 26</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900514-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-14-90 0502EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Outdoors:Manatee     05-14 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Outdoors: Manatee,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>BC-SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Outdoors: Manatee</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BILL SCHULZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> ended as a disaster for the West Indian
manatee.
   A record 174 of the huge, endangered mammals were found dead in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>, primarily because they were struck by
boats and barges in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> waters, according to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and
<ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>'s regional office in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>.
   So far, <DATE>1990</DATE> is even worse for the sea cows.
   A record 74 manatee deaths were reported in <DATE>January</DATE> alone, most
of that due to the ``Christmas freeze'' that sent temperatures
plunging in <LOCATION>north Florida</LOCATION>.
   The service has been studying manatee deaths since <DATE>1974</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>FWS</ORGANIZATION> said there were 510 deaths in those 15 years for which a
cause could be found. Of that number, 418 were attributed to the
animals being struck by boats or barges. Seventy-eight died when
they were crushed or drowned in floodgates of locks in canals and
50 were killed by humans. Some were shot, others caught in fishing
nets or lines.
   The population was estimated at 1,000 animals in <DATE>1980</DATE>, and
aerial surveys of warm-water refuges in <DATE>December</DATE> found 1,200
individuals.
   The manatee has been around for 60 million years, evolving from
four-footed animals about the time the dinosaurs were on their last
legs.
   Because of the deaths in <DATE>1989</DATE>, the state of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> proposed
stringent new measures to help protect them.
   The measures include establishment of manatee protection plans
in those <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> counties that had the highest rates of
boat-manatee collisions last year. They also call for creation of
new manatee protection zones, where boats may travel only at
reduced speeds to help prevent collisions, and controlling
expansion of new boating facilities in areas inhabited by manatees.
   The state also is planning stepped up enforcement of all laws to
protect the species.
   The big, slow moving animals simply can't get out of the way of
fast boats. The animals, which can reach a length in excess of 10
feet and a weight of more than 1,000 pounds, lounge in rivers and
canals feeding on plants.
   Although they do move out into salt water, they spend most of
their lives in fresh water.
   They winter in warm water areas, such as springs, and have found
new habitat in the warm-water discharges of power plants as far
north as south <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Crystal River National Wildlife Refuge</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Coast</ORGANIZATION>
was established as a haven for manatees. <ORGANIZATION>Merritt Island National
Wildlife Refuge</ORGANIZATION> on the <LOCATION>Atlantic Coast</LOCATION> also has areas closed for
manatee protection.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890814-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-14-89 0620EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BoatingDeaths     08-14 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boating Deaths,0695</SECOND>
<HEAD>Battle Lines Drawn in Florida Over Proposed Speed, Boating Rules</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boating in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> has never been more
popular _ or more deadly _ as boats race at speeds up to 100 mph in
crowded waterways, threatening other boaters and wildlife like the
manatee.
   Now the state that has led the nation in recreational boating
deaths for the past two years is trying to establish a boating
speed limit, require more education and charge higher license fees
to bring the boating explosion under control.
   There are some 700,000 boat owners in the state _ seven times
the number of registered boaters in <DATE>1961</DATE>. And that figure is
expected to double in the next 10 years, according to <ORGANIZATION>Florida
Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION> estimates. Many boaters strongly oppose any new
regulations.
   The boating fatality rate in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> is 2{ times the national
average, with the number of deaths soaring from 40 in <DATE>1986</DATE> to 102
in <DATE>1987</DATE> and 105 last year.
   The recent outcry for greater regulation was sparked by a
Memorial Day weekend collision along the Intercoastal Waterway in
<LOCATION>Pinellas County</LOCATION> that killed four teen-agers.
   Dr. <PERSON>William LaTorre</PERSON>, 48, was arrested <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and charged with
four counts of manslaughter by culpable negligence after his sleek
35-foot boat collided with a 17-foot boat carrying five teen-agers
on the state's west coast near <LOCATION>St. Petersburg</LOCATION>.
   This week, the heads of state agencies will hold public hearings
in <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION> on a proposal by the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION> to
set a statewide speed limit of 30 mph, and 20 mph in 12 counties
heavily populated by manatees. The proposed speed limits are
scheduled to be voted on at a <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE> Cabinet meeting.
   ``I think there's not a lot of sentiment right now for a
statewide (speed) zone,'' said <PERSON>Sally Munroe</PERSON>, an aide to Gov. <PERSON>Bob
Martinez</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Marjorie Lamphear</PERSON>, education director of Save the <ORGANIZATION>Manatee Club</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Maitland</LOCATION>, says the lower speed limits proposed for the 12
counties could help the manatee _ a large sea mammal also known as
sea cows.
   ``Manatees do recognize danger and try to get out of the way,''
she said. ``But between a speeding boat and a slow manatee, the
combination is not in favor of the manatee.''
   Between <DATE>January</DATE> and <DATE>July</DATE>, 103 manatees have been found dead,
with 37 deaths attributed to vessels, according the natural
resources department. During the same period last year, 29 of 93
manatee deaths were blamed on boaters. An estimated 1,200 of the
docile, plant-eating creatures, weighing more than 3,000 pounds and
ranging from eight to 14 feet long, live in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
   ``We could lose 150 this year,'' <PERSON>Ms. Lamphear</PERSON> said. ``We need to
take drastic measures.''
   Next month, the natural resources department will ask the
governor and his Cabinet for mandatory education for boaters and
higher license fees to help pay for better enforcement of boating
laws, according to a draft report released last week by the agency.
   Some view the proposed regulations as an unnecessary intrusion.
   Last <DATE>spring</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Legislature</ORGANIZATION> rejected a boating safety bill that
included a statewide speed limit.
   ``Why the heck should the government be sticking its nose in
something that should be individually involved?'' asked state Rep.
<PERSON>Jim King</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Jim Robinson</PERSON>, state executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Marine Industries
Association</ORGANIZATION>, doubts a 30 mph speed limit will lower the number of
deaths.
   Speed isn't the prime factor behind boating deaths, he
contended. They also were caused by lack of life jackets,
overloaded craft, carelessness and bad weather conditions, he said.
   Robinson called the proposed regulations an imposition on the
public, and warned, ``You better believe there's going to be a
battle.''
   But Col. <PERSON>Don Ellingsen</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Florida Marine Patrol</ORGANIZATION>,
said the regulations are needed because of the increasing
congestion on <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> waterways and the increase in speed.
   ``We don't believe that 30 mph will affect the vast majority of
boat owners,'' he said. ``We are trying to slow down the floating
rockets that go 80 to 100 mph.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901228-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-28-90 0551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BRF--ManateeDeaths     12-28 0164</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Manatee Deaths,0177</SECOND>
<HEAD>Record Manatee Deaths for 1990</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MELBOURNE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A record 201 manatees died in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>
waters this year, authorities said.
   At least 46 of the endangered sea cows were found dead in the
weeks following a three-day freeze <DATE>last Christmas</DATE>, and boat
collisions killed at least 46 more, said <PERSON>Bruce Ackerman</PERSON>, a marine
mammal researcher with the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION>.
   A variety of factors contributed to the other deaths.
   Last year, 166 manatees were killed, up from 133 in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   State officials estimate there are 1,200 to 1,500 West Indian
manatees in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, down from an estimated 10,000 several decades
ago.
   The manatee has been around for 60 million years, evolving from
four-footed creatures about the time the dinosaurs were on their
last legs. The big, slow sea cows loll in warm, shallow areas in
oceans, rivers and canals to feed on underwater grass. They can be
longer than 10 feet and weigh more than 1,000 pounds and are unable
to avoid fast boats.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891025-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-25-89 2048EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Manatee-Campaign     10-25 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Manatee-Campaign,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Miss Her Now or Miss Her Forever'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists, marine enforcement and
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> businesses are pulling together to save the manatee from
boaters in a campaign keyed to the mammal's endangered status:
``Miss her now or miss her forever.''
   ``I think the slogan has really got a message,'' <PERSON>Vi Stewart</PERSON> of
the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION> marine research
laboratory said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. ``It's very significant, but you've got
to think about it. It doesn't jump out and grab you like `where's
the beef?'''
   Marine experts estimate there are probably 1,200 West Indian
manatees left in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, down from as many as an
estimated 10,000 a few decades ago. Almost all are in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s
coastal waters.
   So far this year through <DATE>September</DATE>, 125 have died in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, 41
after being struck by boats or barges. Last year 113 deaths were
recorded.
   Aiming to slow this record-setting pace, a multimedia
advertising blitz is planned for the time of year when the gentle
giant is most vulnerable to boaters.
   As the temperature drops and the water cools, the lumbering sea
cows move into warmer waters near springs or thermal discharges of
power plants, thus increasing the risk of contact with boaters.
   ``The next six months is the most critical time for the
manatee,'' said <PERSON>Ralph Campbell</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>HLA Advertising and
Public Relations of Tampa</ORGANIZATION>, which donated work on the campaign and
came up with the slogan.
   The state Cabinet is recommending posting speed limits for boats
and the licensing of operators in a two-fold effort to reduce
boat-related deaths and to protect manatees.
   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> has 711,000 registered boats. The state had 105
boating-related deaths last year.
   Gov. <PERSON>Bob Martinez</PERSON> and the Cabinet also voted <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to require
13 counties where the manatees are concentrated to decide within 60
days whether to immpose countywide speed limits or adopt more
specific plans.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900109-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-09-90 0432EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DeadManatees     01-09 0310</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dead Manatees,0322</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sea Creatures Dying in Record Numbers After Florida's Cold Snap</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIM S. MARTIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than half of an unprecedented number of dead
manatees found in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> waterways during the past nine days may
be victims of the Christmas cold snap, state officials said.
   The carcasses of 41 of the endangered marine mammals have been
discovered in the new year, the state's <ORGANIZATION>Department of Natural
Resources</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   There were only 15 manatees found dead last year in all of
<DATE>January</DATE>, said <PERSON>Dr. Bruce Ackerman</PERSON>, marine mammal researcher at the
department's <ORGANIZATION>Florida Research Institute</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It's the worst winter die-off we've had since we've been
counting,'' he said. ``They are literally coming in so fast we
can't keep our records up.''
   Ackerman's department has been documenting manatee deaths since
<DATE>1974</DATE>.
   Most of the carcasses have been found in the waters off <LOCATION>Brevard
County</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Violet Stewart</PERSON>, an institute spokeswoman, said 27 of the
gentle sea cows have been found there.
   ``It appears that the water over there got particularly cold,''
she said. ``We had some reports of water temperatures down into the
40s.''
   She said marine biologists estimate that 25 to 30 of the deaths
are cold-related, although precise causes will take time to
determine.
   ``They are finding that manatees died with this cold snap and
they sank,'' <PERSON>Ms. Stewart</PERSON> said. ``As they decay they rise to the
surface, so they are just now being recovered.''
   <PERSON>Ackerman</PERSON> said that since manatees are tropical, they have no
layer of blubber like seals and whales.
   ``They lose their ability to digest food and gradually become
more run-down,'' he said. ``When they get run-down, they lose the
ability to swim to a warmer place.''
   Last year, there were a record 165 manatee deaths. Biologists
estimate that <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> has only 1,200 of the endangered creatures
left.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-15527 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov045_r_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-045 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Situation in Credit System Reported </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  NC0503205094 Baku TURAN in English 1718 GMT 5 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC0503205094 </F>
<F P=104>  Baku TURAN </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION> (<DATE>March 5</DATE>) TURAN -- For <DATE>February 1</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION> 
of the republic registered 178 banks with 174 commercial and 4 
state ones. The number of functioning banks total 163. 
  From <DATE>January 1, 1993</DATE> til <DATE>February 1, 1994</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION> 
granted credits totalling <MONEY>100.207 billion manats</MONEY>. The <ORGANIZATION>Ministry 
of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> received <MONEY>13.8 billion manats</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>State Company</ORGANIZATION> 
"Azerineft" -- <MONEY>7 billion manat</MONEY>, "Azerittifag" -- <MONEY>2.9 billion 
manats</MONEY>, the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Trade</ORGANIZATION> -- 2.2 billion manats, State 
Company "Azerigas" -- 1.9 billion manats, State Company 
"Azerenerzhi" -- <MONEY>1.7 billion manats</MONEY>, the Ministry of grain crops 
-- <MONEY>0.6 billion manats</MONEY>. 
  The debts of state enterprises and organizations to each 
other to the state total <MONEY>89.302 billion manats</MONEY>. It is 51.977 
billion manats higher than was in <DATE>January 1994</DATE>. 
  Last month <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION> did not granted credits to those 
banks. It is expected to give those means to the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of 
Finance</ORGANIZATION> to overcome budget deficit. On <DATE>February 1</DATE> the credits, 
which <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION> granted to commercial banks, amounted to <MONEY>6.1 
billion manats</MONEY>. It is 8.7 billion manats less as compared with 
<DATE>January 1, 1994</DATE>. 
  The banks which were registered after <DATE>March 1, 1994</DATE> have to 
pay <MONEY>50 million manats</MONEY> (erlier 20 million manats) to a special 
fund. 
  The government did not pay the wages to the population 
amounting to <MONEY>13 billion manats</MONEY>. 
  <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION> promised to inform about the situation in 
credit system every month. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-54690 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov001_r_94011" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-001 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Manat Becomes Sole Currency as of 1 Jan </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  NC3112220493 Baku TURAN in English 1948 GMT 31 Dec 93 </F>
<F P=103> NC3112220493 </F>
<F P=104>  Baku TURAN </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION> (<DATE>December 31</DATE>) TURAN -- In line with the 
President <PERSON>Aliyev</PERSON>'s decree, since <DATE>January 1 1994</DATE> only 
<LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>'s national currency manat will have purchasing power 
of money on the territory of the country. 
  Ministries, concerns, unions and enterprises irrespective of 
form property are ordered to transfer all financial operation to 
manats. If the enterprises have roubles on their accounts, the 
Banks must exchange roubles in manats (correspondingly 1 manat 
amounts to 10 roubles). 
  Bank-notes with value 1, 3, 5, and 10 roubles issued in 
<DATE>1961</DATE>- 
<DATE>1992</DATE> can be exchanged in manats during <DATE>December 31</DATE> (1 manat 10 
roubles). 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-40683 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov118_r_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-118 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  18 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Presidential Decree Increases Welfare Benefits </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Presidential Decree Increases Welfare Benefits </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC1806194394 Yerevan SNARK in English 1646 GMT 18 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC1806194394 </F>
<F P=104>  Yerevan SNARK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "Business SNARK" file] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION> [Dateline as received]--<PERSON>Geydar Aliyev</PERSON>, 
President of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>, signed on <DATE>June 15</DATE> a Decree on 
"Strengthening the social protection of the population and 
stabilization of the financial situation in the economy". 
  According to this decree, the rate of the minimal wage is 
increased from <DATE>June 1</DATE> up to 2 thousand manats, pensions of those 
not working and scholarships -- 1.5 thousand manats. The rate 
of compensations for each child under 16 years from families 
with an income less than 4 thousand manats will be 750 manats. 
  The government is entrusted with suspending the building of 
objects on account of the budget funds, beside those to be 
finished this year, cancelling all its previous decisions on 
privileged crediting of state enterprises, passing to the system 
of money compensation to socially low-protected residents 
instead of the system of privileged taxation of physical and 
juridical persons. 
  Since <DATE>June 16</DATE> the price of petrol AI-92 has increased from 
17 
to 100 manats per liter, and the price on bread -- from 20 to 80 
manats. In <DATE>May</DATE> the minimal consumer's basket made up 30 
thousand manats and the average wage -- 8.3 thousand manats, the 
minimal wage -- 900 manats. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890816-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-16-89 2109EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BoatingRegulations     08-16 0354</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boating Regulations,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>Speed Limits Proposed To Curb Florida Boating Deaths</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By IKE FLORES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Florida leads the nation in boating deaths
and unless strict speed limits are set and enforced, the situation
will soon become unmanageable, state officials said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Department of Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION> officials opened three days of
public hearings on proposed new boating regulations with statistics
on <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s exploding population of boaters and the casualties they
cause among humans and the endangered manatee.
   Boaters killed 105 people in the state last year _ 2.5 times the
national average _ and set a record in known manatee deaths with 29.
That record has already been surpassed this year with 37 manatee
deaths.
   The state has about 1 million registered and non-registered boats
and 3.5 million to 4 million people operating them, he said.
   ``It's very congested out there now, and with 100 boats being
added to the state total every day, we will double the number in the
next 10 years,'' said <PERSON>Don Ellingson</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>DNR</ORGANIZATION>'s director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Division of Law Enforcement</ORGANIZATION>. ``Unless we find ways to deal with that
congestion, we're going to have problems.''
   A key issue is expected to be the state's proposal of a statewide
speed limit of 30 mph on navigational channels in inland waterways.
This would drop to 20 mph in 12 counties with large numbers of the
sea cows.
   Except for a hodge-podge of local go-slow ordinances, there are
no boating speed limits now.
   Local and county elected officials and regulatory agency staffers
from <LOCATION>Dade</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sarasota</LOCATION>, Brevard and Suwannee counties expresed support
for the proposed rules, with some reservations and suggestions for
fine-tuning.
   The 12 counties being considered for manatee-protecting speed
limits are Brevard, <LOCATION>Broward</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Citrus</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Collier</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Dade</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Duval</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Indian
River</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Lee</PERSON>, <PERSON>Martin</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Palm Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>St. Lucie</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Volusia</LOCATION>.
   Commissioner <PERSON>Charles Williams</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Suwannee County</LOCATION> said that while
there was support for the <ORGANIZATION>DNR</ORGANIZATION> proposals, he suggested a maximum
speed limit of 40 mph because of the importance of water skiing in
the state. Skiers say it is impossible to carry out their maneuvers
at 30 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011589-0122 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 5752 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 15, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 25; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
623 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ELEPHANT'S UNDERWATER COUSIN TO BE PROTECTED; 
</P>
<P>
IVORY COAST PLANS RESERVE FOR MANATEE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MICHAEL RODDY, Reuters 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Plans are under way to create the first reserve in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> for the manatee, the 
1-ton, 10-foot-long underwater cousin of the elephant. 
</P>
<P>
The manatees live in lagoons, rivers and coastal areas from <LOCATION>Senegal</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The reserve, on an inlet of the <LOCATION>Bandama River</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Abidjan</LOCATION>, could be 
established as soon as <DATE>March</DATE>, according to <ORGANIZATION>Gbande Die</ORGANIZATION>, director of the adjacent 
<ORGANIZATION>Azagny National Park</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"This will be the first protected zone for manatees in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>," Die said in an 
interview. 
</P>
<P>
No one knows precisely how many manatees, also known as sea cows, there are in 
<LOCATION>Abidjan</LOCATION>, whose oceanfront lagoons make ideal habitats, but officials say the 
population is dwindling and estimate their numbers in the hundreds rather than 
thousands. 
</P>
<P>
"When we ask the peasants, they tell us they used to see lots of manatees and 
now they don't," Die said. 
</P>
<P>
The reserve will allow scientists to study manatees, which are found in 
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>West Indies</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> basin and <LOCATION>West Africa</LOCATION>, and whose behavior 
is little known. 
</P>
<P>
The experts will also determine how best to protect the animals, which are 
hunted for their beef-like flesh. 
</P>
<P>
Manatees are mammals and had a common ancestor with the elephant 75 million 
years ago. They have been a protected species since this former French colony 
became independent in <DATE>1960</DATE>, but that has not stopped fishermen from poaching 
them. 
</P>
<P>
"It's hard to enforce because the law is just a piece of paper," Die said. "And 
it's not just manatees, it's virtually all wild animals in <LOCATION>Ivory Coast</LOCATION> that 
suffer." 
</P>
<P>
Much of the impetus for creating the reserve and protecting manatees arises 
from work here by <PERSON>James Powell</PERSON>, 34, an American naturalist from <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife 
Conservation International</ORGANIZATION>, an arm of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"We should be as concerned about the manatees as we are about the rhinoceros," 
<PERSON>Powell</PERSON> said recently. "Manatees are big, impressive and unique. There is 
nothing else like them." 
</P>
<P>
He said that manatees, whose night-time squeals are believed to have sparked 
mermaid myths and who are associated in <LOCATION>West Africa</LOCATION> with a spirit called "<PERSON>Mamie 
Wata</PERSON>," are timid and gentle. 
</P>
<P>
The West African manatee, which has a wide muzzle and a long, bulbous trunk 
with two side flippers, looks a bit like a toothless walrus or a sea lion. 
</P>
<P>
"They are extremely strong but they don't seem to have an aggressive bone in 
their bodies," said <PERSON>Powell</PERSON>, who has trapped 18 manatees to fit them with radio 
transmitters so he can track their movements. He was able to work with them 
without tranquilizing them. 
</P>
<P>
He said that visitors have flocked to see a baby manatee he raised in a pen 
near a popular beach resort, but the animal died several months ago. 
</P>
<P>
He doubted that the dark-gray manatees, which are almost impossible to see in 
the murky lagoons, could become a tourist attraction, as they have in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. 
But <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> thinks man and manatee could learn to live side by side. 
</P>
<P>
"They have an important role in the estuarine environment," he said. "They are 
the only large herbivores, so they eat off the unwanted vegetation." 
</P>
<P>
He also said that if hunting were regulated manatees could provide an important 
source of protein. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Powell</PERSON> and officials of <ORGANIZATION>Ivory Coast's Ministry of Water</ORGANIZATION> and Forests said the 
key to saving the manatee is learning more about them and educating fishermen 
about the perils of poaching. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kouadio Akoi</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>Education Ministry</ORGANIZATION> officer who works with <PERSON>Powell</PERSON>, said that it 
is hard to persuade people to give up a source of food but that it can be done. 
</P>
<P>
"The fishermen tell us, 'First you say don't kill the tortoise, then you say 
don't kill the manatee -- what are we going to eat?' "But the disappearance of 
an animal would be a loss to everybody. We have a heritage we have to leave to 
our children." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-46990 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpusr063___94050" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-USR-94-063 </AU>
JPRS 


</HEADER>

<ABS>  FBIS Report: Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   7 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> CAUCASUS </F>
<F P=101> AZERBAIJAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Grain Purchase Prices Increased </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Grain Purchase Prices Increased </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   944K1394A Baku BAKINSKIY RABOCHIY in Russian 7 Jun 94 p 1 </F>
<F P=103> 944K1394A </F>
<F P=104>  Baku BAKINSKIY RABOCHIY </F>
<F P=105>  Russian </F>


<TEXT>
CSO 

<FÊP=106> [Unattributed article: "The Peasants Will Be Satisfied. </F>
Grain Procurement Prices Raised"] 
  [Text] In order to increase the material incentive for 
producers to increase volumes of grain sales to the state and in 
order to save on the expenditure of hard currency funds on the 
acquisition of grain from abroad, and also taking into account 
the higher costs of material and technical resources and energy 
sources used on the farms, the growth of inflation, and the 
higher prices on the world market, the <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> Cabinet of 
Ministers considered it expedient to adopt the proposals of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>State Grain Products Company</ORGANIZATION>, and 
the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Economics</ORGANIZATION> to raise prices of grain from internal 
reserves. 
  As an AZERTADZH correspondent was told in the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of 
Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, the average selling price of one tonne of grain 
from the <DATE>1994</DATE> crop sold to the state is 50,000 manats, a 
sevenfold increase over last year's prices. Taking into account 
the fact that priority in raising procurement prices has been 
given to hard and strong strains of wheat, the following prices 
have been set: for one tonne of hard wheat meeting requirements 
of class I--65,000 manats, of class II--62,000 manats, and of 
class III--55,000 manats; for strong and soft strains, 
regardless of class--48,000-53,000 manats; for one tonne of 
barley--46,000 manats, of corn--50,000 manats, and of peas for 
human consumption--94,000 manats. 
  The ministry has prepared additional recommendations in 
order 
to increase the material incentive for machine operators and 
other workers to harvest the grain at optimal times and without 
losses. It is stipulated that each combine operator 
participating in the harvest may be issued as wages 50 manats 
and 10 kilograms of grain, and their assistants, 35 manats and 7 
kilograms of grain for each tonne harvested; truck drivers are 
to be issued, in addition to their wages, one kilogram of grain 
for each tonne that is transported. Additionally, combine 
operators are to be paid bonuses in the amount of 1,500-2,500 
manats, depending on the volume of grain reaped during the 
season. 
  <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> workers think that raising grain 
procurement prices will have a positive effect on strengthening 
the economies of the farms, will increase the material incentive 
for workers, and will make it possible to achieve an increase in 
the volumes of grain sold to the state. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-17961 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov062_r_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-062 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Local Currency Plight, Inflation Growth Viewed </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PM3003075594 Moscow ROSSIYSKAYA GAZETA in Russian 29 Mar 94 
First Edition p 6 </F>

<F P=103> PM3003075594 </F>
<F P=104>  Moscow ROSSIYSKAYA GAZETA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Russian </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by Arif Useynov: "Manats Float"] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION> -- The manat -- the national monetary unit of 
<LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> -- has had a difficult time. It is losing value not 
by the day but by the hour. To cover up this patent devaluation 
the <ORGANIZATION>National Bank of Azerbaijan</ORGANIZATION> periodically sets a new manat 
rate against the currencies of the former <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> republics. 
  The initial rate was confusing -- one manat to 10 Russian 
rubles [R]. Why not 20? Commercial bank specialists have 
reason to call a "ceiling" -- this arbitrarily established rate 
has not been borne out by any exchange trading. So what 
prompted the new rate of one to 14? 
  As a rule, attempts to discern the economic laws on which 
the 
exchange rate is based prove pointless. 
  On the currency black market -- the famous "Molokanka" (from 
the name of a pleasant little square in downtown <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>) -- people 
are trading at a rate of R1,000 to 275 manats, paying no 
attention to the bankers' sluggishness. The people on the 
square do not rule out the possibility that in a month or so a 
ruble could be worth the same as a manat. 
  Hyperinflation has long been part and parcel of the 
Azerbaijani economy, forcing the manat into the most improbable 
contortions. This was to be expected: Deformations in the 
economy seem to happen on their own, and the manat has been left 
to its own devices, as if orphaned. Despite the fact that state 
property has not been privatized and the mechanism of market 
relations has not been fully realized, the new manat has been 
allowed to float. No currency can function normally without a 
weight of goods to back it -- and home-produced goods at that. 
Having failed to make deliveries of output and goods outside 
the republic under the clearing system, enterprises have been 
deprived of reciprocal shipments worth <MONEY>6 billion manats</MONEY>. Half 
of last year's cotton and grape crops were not harvested. 
Meanwhile <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of foodstuffs are bought on the side for 
foreign currency -- weak petrodollars. And these are getting 
fewer and further between, since oil extraction in the republic 
has fallen by 800,000 tonnes. 
  There is no harm in admitting that home-grown businessmen 
are 
making a good living from the people's baleful position. The 
state owes <MONEY>22 billion manats</MONEY> in wages and pensions, while 
ministries, departments, enterprises, and commercial structures 
are keeping R27 billion that they owe to others in Russian bank 
accounts, earning fabulous rates of interest. 
  President <PERSON>Heydar Aliyev</PERSON> has demanded that the leaders of 
debtor organizations repatriate forthwith their exported capital 
or the products that have been bought with it. Meanwhile 
specialists believe that the hidden billions are unlikely to 
save the Azerbaijani economy. The following weighty argument is 
also quoted: Transactions with Russian banks are not effective 
[ne deystvuyut], and the <ORGANIZATION>Central Bank of Russia</ORGANIZATION> is hardly likely 
to agree to such operations, recalling <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>'s large debts. 
  Has not the time come to print larger-denomination manats? 
Those in circulation cannot keep up with galloping prices. The 
consignment of manats expected to arrive from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> will be 
enough to pay the wage and pension backlog. 
  And the manat continues to float. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-61470 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov088_r_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-088 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Country's Currency Suffers as Exchange Rate Soars </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Country's Currency Suffers as Exchange Rate Soars </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC0505123694 Baku AZERTAC in English 1721 GMT 4 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC0505123694 </F>
<F P=104>  Baku AZERTAC </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>, 4 May (AZERTAC)--<LOCATION>Manat</LOCATION>, Azeri national 
monetary unit seems to undergo the same fate as the Ukrainian 
Karbovanets. The manats exchange rate against the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar 
has gone down by 90 per cent and against the Russian ruble by 
2.5 times correspondingly. Thus, today one <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar costs 
<DATE>1000</DATE> manats and the Russian ruble 0.6 manats. The Azeri 
currency's rapid downfall provoked a feverish mood in the 
country. At <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>'s parallel market on Molokanka square, the 
exchange rate of the foreign currency is being updated up to 
three times a day. 
  However, official exchange rates have not been adapted yet. 
According to the information available, the Azeri national bank 
pays 182.5 manats per dollar and <MONEY>1 manat</MONEY> per 10 Russian rubles. 
That is why the center of currency transactions has moved from 
banking offices at the parallel market. According to 
specialists view, this is one more factor provoking the 
disastrous downfall of the local currency. 
  Azeri experts consider the principal reason of the present 
economic situation the absence of a flexible monetary policy in 
<LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>. Some experts explain this situation by the small 
amount of foreign currency that is being earned by <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> 
since the <ORGANIZATION>Republic</ORGANIZATION>'s industry has virtually stopped working. 
Moreover, the manat has not become an independent currency and 
its condition depends on fluctuation of rate of exchange of the 
Russian ruble as the national bank has not determined the manats 
real value so far. One of the local televisions observers has 
expressed a very original opinion concerning this situation. He 
explained it by the reason that governmental officers take their 
bribes in freely convertible currency only. However, he may 
guess all too near: <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION> newspapers give many examples of this 
kind. 
  Though predictions are dismal -- experts think that dollars 
rate will increase in about 40 per cent every month -- the 
<LOCATION>Republic</LOCATION> is trying to find the way out from this crisis. 
Abolition of the law of limitation on export of strategic goods 
will undoubtedly provide more constant flow of currency. The 
experts think that the situation might be improved by creation 
of currency exchange offices where monetary transactions will be 
done in accordance with the reasonable rates of currency. The 
experts also say that development of the local industry and 
creation of normal conditions for small enterprises will be more 
effective in this case. 
  However, present monetary and credit crisis resulted in 
retirement of administration of the national bank. Through the 
ever falling manats exchange rate more people live below the 
poverty line. Now 60 per cent of the republics population -- 
about 4 million people -- live in poverty. According to one of 
<LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>'s newspapers, each of the poor needs 12,600 manats monthly, 
if not to take inflation into consideration, in order to satisfy 
the minimum needs. This amount of money is 70 and 170 per cent 
as much as it was necessary in <DATE>March</DATE> and <DATE>January this year</DATE>. 
According to <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Labour and Social Security</ORGANIZATION>, one 
citizen needs 16 thousand manats for showing a sign of life, it 
is a so-called physiological minimum. 
  Meanwhile, a minimum salary of <MONEY>900 manats</MONEY> is enough to buy 
half a kilogram of meat. So an average citizen of the Republic 
has to display miracles of resourcefulness in order not to kick 
the bucket. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06279156 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06279156 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  Federal officials have ordered marine parks to keep captive manatees from
having sex so they won't have babies, baffling people trying to increase the
numbers of the endangered species.;   "Dumb," says Dr. Jesse White, a
Dunnellon veterinarian and manatee expert who pioneered captive-born manatee
programs.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FEDERAL RULES ON SEA COW SEX BAFFLE EXPERTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "We've been having births without necessarily planning them, and that's
been filling up facilities with animals that we're not sure what to do with,"
said <PERSON>Robert Turner</PERSON>, who coordinates manatee protection programs for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service.</ORGANIZATION>;   Until a captive-breeding plan is developed and
approved by his agency, the mammals should be separated by sex, <PERSON>Turner</PERSON> said
<DATE>Wednesday.</DATE>;   "If we're going to wait for bureaucrats to develop a plan, we'd
still be in the ice age," argued White, who has captive manatees at <ORGANIZATION>Homosassa
Springs State Wildlife Park</ORGANIZATION>. "If we act now, we still have time.";   Experts
say there are fewer than 2,000 of the docile sea cows left in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> today.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Homosassa Springs, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911005  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  12A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  161  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, October 5, 1991
00279156,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-68875 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpusr056___94057" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-USR-94-056 </AU>
JPRS 


</HEADER>

<ABS>  FBIS Report: Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   14 May 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> CAUCASUS </F>
<F P=101> AZERBAIJAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Draft State Budget Ready for Parliament </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Draft State Budget Ready for Parliament </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   944K1244B Baku ZERKALO in Russian 14 May 94 p 3 </F>
<F P=103> 944K1244B </F>
<F P=104>  Baku ZERKALO </F>
<F P=105>  Russian </F>


<TEXT>
CSO 

<FÊP=106> [Unattributed report: "Draft State Budget Sent to Parliament </F>
for Approval"] 
  [Text] According to the republic's deputy minister of 
finance, <PERSON>Fikret Yusifov</PERSON>, the income part of the budget assumes 
revenue of <MONEY>138.4746 billion manats</MONEY>, and the expense 
part--<MONEY>181.3717 billion manats</MONEY>. Thus, the budget will have a 
deficit of <MONEY>42.8971 billion manats</MONEY>. 
  F. Yusifov noted that such a large deficit is the result of 
a 
decline in the level of production, which has dropped 
several-fold as compared to <DATE>1992</DATE>. In order to cover the deficit, 
the following steps are being planned, in particular: 
implementation of the state privatization program, which will 
help to earn <MONEY>5 billion manats</MONEY>; changing prices for alcoholic 
beverages, which should bring 1.3 billion into the budget; 
raising prices for fuel and energy and bread; introducing 
value-added tax on imported goods, which will bring in 4.6 
billion over the remaining seven months; and so on. The deputy 
minister of finance also emphasized that raising the minimum 
wage from 900 to 2,000 manats is in the works, which will 
require additional budget expenditures. This difference is 
expected to be covered by raising retail prices on gasoline and 
the recently approved tax in the amount equal to two minimum 
wages on each square meter of space occupied by commercial trade 
and public catering entities. <PERSON>F. Yusifov</PERSON> said, however, that 
raising the minimum wage will only lead to another jump in 
market prices and in the final count an even greater decline in 
the population's living standard. As a KHABAR-SERVICE 
correspondent learned from competent sources in the republic 
government, three options for raising gasoline prices are now 
under consideration: 40, 50, and 60 manats per liter. Most 
likely the middle figure will be chosen, which will bring into 
the budget an additional <MONEY>25-30 billion manats</MONEY>, but still will 
not be enough to raise the minimum wage. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-61005 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov085_r_94007" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-085 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  2 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Ministry of Economy Modifies 1994 Prognosis </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Ministry of Economy Modifies 1994 Prognosis </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC0205183294 Baku TURAN in English 1734 GMT 2 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC0205183294 </F>
<F P=104>  Baku TURAN </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>, 2 <DATE>May</DATE> (TURAN)--<LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of 
Economy</ORGANIZATION> handed reviewed prognosis of socio-economic development 
for <DATE>1994</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Finance</ORGANIZATION>. 
  According to the <PERSON>Milli Majlis</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Finance</ORGANIZATION> has 
to 
take into account this prognosis when finishing off the work 
over the budget draft. 
  According to prognoses, in <DATE>1994</DATE> the inflation will total 600 
per cent. In the first variant of the prognoses this figure was 
240 per cent. 
  A representative of the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Finance</ORGANIZATION> told TURAN that 
their employees don't agree to the forecasted level of inflation 
since it does not correspond to real economical situation. Over 
the <DATE>first quarter of 1994</DATE> the inflation totalled 300 percent and 
the production reduced by 25 per cent. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Economy</ORGANIZATION> forecasted the volume of gross 
national product <MONEY>910 billion manats</MONEY> and national income <MONEY>677 
billion manats</MONEY>. In the first variant these figures were 313 and 
<MONEY>272 billion manats</MONEY>, relatively. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-18018 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov083_r_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-083 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Drop in Manat's ROE Prompts `Explosion of Prices' </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Drop in Manat's ROE Prompts `Explosion of Prices' </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PM2904125994 Moscow ROSSIYSKAYA GAZETA in Russian 29 Apr 94 
Single Edition p 3 </F>

<F P=103> PM2904125994 </F>
<F P=104>  Moscow ROSSIYSKAYA GAZETA </F>
<F P=105>  Russian </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Arif Useynov report: "<LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>: Panic on the Black </F>
Market"] 
  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION> -- It would appear that the situation that had 
been long predicted has become a reality: The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar has 
shot up to 1,000 manats on the black market. Thus the 
population is <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> poorer, since the day before the same 
dollar could be bought for 800 manats. The same has happened 
with the exchange rate of the Russian ruble -- on the black 
market it is expressed in terms of the dollar rate and has 
reached 1 manat to 2 rubles. The manat is clearly dropping away. 
  Correspondingly, prices of basic necessities also shot up, 
getting beyond the reach of the majority of the population. The 
opposition press believes that what is happening on the currency 
market is the consequence of serious economic upheavals. In 
particular, the opinion is being expressed that the financial 
magnates who manipulate black market transactions are ready to 
blow the situation in the republic apart from within. It is not 
yet clear according to what scenario events will develop. The 
population has been agitated by the explosion of prices on the 
market -- a minimum salary today will only buy 1.5 kg of beef. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06038113 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06038113 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  FLORIDA; WATER; ANIMAL; NUCLEAR; PLANT; ACCIDENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A 1,200-pound manatee was puttering around in a nuclear power plant cooling
pond, being fed 24 heads of lettuce a day, after being sucked in from the sea
through a huge pipe.;    The pipe at the St. Lucie plant was the same one a
scuba diver was dragged through in 1989. He escaped with minor injuries.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MANATEE GOES NUCLEAR
PULLED INTO PLANT VIA PIPE IN SEA  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The cooling pond is part of a system that cools the nuclear reactor through
intermediate piping loops, so the incidents didn't disrupt plant operations
and the pond water isn't radioactive.;    The manatee was in good condition
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> while utility employees tried to find a way to cage and move it.;   
"We think it's pretty unusual that this manatee did what it did," said <PERSON>Ray
Golden</PERSON>, spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Florida Power &amp; Light Co</ORGANIZATION>. He said employees have been
feeding the 9-foot sea mammal 24 heads of lettuce a day since it showed up in
the pond Friday.;    Sea World biologists plan to gradually introduce a cage
into the pond, and when the manatee gets used to it, trap it, possibly by
<DATE>Monday</DATE>. They will take the animal for a checkup and release it.;    The
1,500-foot pipeline is the only route into the pond. Three concrete slabs
arranged over the sea opening reduce the speed of the water flowing into the
intake, but two have large holes. The utility plans to begin replacing the
slabs next month at a cost of <MONEY>$22 million</MONEY>, Golden said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Hutchinson IsLand, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910207  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  242  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday February 7, 1991
00038113,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880907-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-07-88 1132EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-FloridaFlooding     09-07 0310</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Florida Flooding,0320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Floods on Gulf Coast Cause Evacuations of 1,000</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRADENTON, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Flooding caused by several days of heavy
rainfall led to the evacuation of about 1,000 people, closed
schools and forced police to patrol in garbage trucks today,
authorities said.
   About 1,000 people were evacuated from trailer parks and
low-lying areas in eastern <LOCATION>Manatee County</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Florida National
Guard</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The rainfall was the heaviest since Hurricane <PERSON>Elena</PERSON> in <DATE>1985</DATE>, but
no injuries were reported. One community reported 13 inches of
rainfall.
   <LOCATION>Manatee County</LOCATION> supervisors and the <LOCATION>Bradenton</LOCATION> city council met in
emergency session this morning to seek ways to combat flooding
along the <ORGANIZATION>Manatee and Little Manatee</ORGANIZATION> rivers.
   Police in <LOCATION>Palmetto</LOCATION>, across the <LOCATION>Manatee River</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Bradenton</LOCATION>,
were forced to abandon their patrol cars and travel in garbage
trucks.
   Manatee High in <LOCATION>Bradenton</LOCATION> and several other schools were
flooded, said county school Superintendent <PERSON>Gene Witt</PERSON>; the school
board called off classes across the county.
   ``The roads are heavily flooded and we're having sewage problems
with water backing up into the schools,'' he said. ``In the <DATE>last 25
years</DATE> I haven't seen anything of this magnitude.''
   Parts of <LOCATION>Manatee County</LOCATION>, just south of <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, have received up
to 10 inches of rain in the <DATE>last two days</DATE>, <PERSON>Witt</PERSON> said; four more
inches could <DATE>fall today</DATE>, forecasters predicted.
   Up the coast from <LOCATION>Bradenton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Yankeetown</LOCATION> reported 13 inches of
rain.
   ``All the rivers around here are over their banks,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Coast
Guard Petty</ORGANIZATION> Officer <PERSON>Eric Hermann</PERSON> in the <LOCATION>Yankeetown</LOCATION> station.
``There's a lot of street flooding and stuff.''
   In northern <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, officials in <LOCATION>Clay County</LOCATION> began to evacuate
families along swollen <ORGANIZATION>Black Creek</ORGANIZATION>, said Chief <PERSON>Pete Cummings</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Clay County Public Safety Department</ORGANIZATION>.
   Deputies went house-to-house in a boat just after daybreak
today, offering assistance to families and making sure they could
get out, said <PERSON>Cummings</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-15584 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov069_r_94013" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-069 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Budget Deficit Soares in 1993 </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Budget Deficit Soares in 1993 </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC0904202894 Baku TURAN in English 1628 GMT 9 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC0904202894 </F>
<F P=104>  Baku TURAN </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION> (<DATE>April 9</DATE>) TURAN -- It was announced yesterday 
in the <LOCATION>Milli Majlis</LOCATION> that in <DATE>1993</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION>'s budget deficit 
totalled <MONEY>25.1 billion manats</MONEY>, despite the fact that it was not 
supposed to reach <MONEY>11.7 billion manats</MONEY>. 
  Fikret Yusifov, <ORGANIZATION>Deputy Minister of Finance</ORGANIZATION>, stated that the 
reason for the high deficit is due to the negative development 
in the economy, the fall in productivity and heightened 
financial crisis. 
  The deputies from the <ORGANIZATION>PFA</ORGANIZATION> [People's Front of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>], 
the 
Musavat party and the <ORGANIZATION>National Independence Party</ORGANIZATION> urged that the 
government accelerate activities in order to curb the inflation 
and balance prices in the country with the low salaries. 
Discussions about the deficit are to continue next week. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-64104 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov103_r_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-103 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  26 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azebaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Parliament Passes Budget for 1994 </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Parliament Passes Budget for 1994 </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC2605190294 Baku AZERTAC in English 1704 GMT 26 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC2605190294 </F>
<F P=104>  Baku AZERTAC </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>, 26 <DATE>May</DATE> (AZERTAC)--Today, after a two-day 
debate, the parliament of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> passed the Republic budget 
for <DATE>1994</DATE> year with a deficit of 23.6 per cent. The MPs 
considered this level of deficit more acceptable than a deficit 
level of 31.2 per cent stipulated by the previous draft budget. 
  According to the passed budget, the Republic revenue will 
come to <MONEY>138.5 billion manats</MONEY> and expenditure--<MONEY>181.4 billion 
manats</MONEY> this year. The <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Finance</ORGANIZATION> proposes to cover a 
deficit of 43 billion manats by releasing domestic loan, 
increasing tax dues as well as by means of privatization, draft 
of which was approved by the president in <DATE>April</DATE>, however was not 
been passed by the parliament so far. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-41073 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov120_r_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-120 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Parliament Revises Privatization Program </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Parliament Revises Privatization Program </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC2106131794 Baku TURAN in English 0735 GMT 21 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC2106131794 </F>
<F P=104>  Baku TURAN </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 20</DATE> (TURAN) -- <PERSON>Gudrat Abdulsalimzade</PERSON>, head 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Committee for Property</ORGANIZATION> told at today's press-conference 
that the <ORGANIZATION>Committee</ORGANIZATION> submitted to the Milli Mejlis new draft of 
privatization program. 
  The new draft provides increase of privatisation share of 
each civilian of the republic to 120,000 manats. "It has been 
done in connection with the last overestimation of the 
privatised property", said <PERSON>Abdulsalimzade</PERSON>. 
  According to the program 8,768 enterprises and objects are 
scheduled to be privatized in <DATE>1994</DATE>. It makes <PERCENT>14.8 percent</PERCENT> of 
all enterprises and objects of the republic, covers <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT> of 
all funds and <PERCENT>3.1 percent</PERCENT> of all employees working in the state 
section. 
  Expenses for privatisations will total <MONEY>400 million manats</MONEY> in 
<DATE>1994</DATE>, said the Head of the <ORGANIZATION>Committee</ORGANIZATION>. According to him, "small" 
privatization, i.e. privatization of enterprises totalling no 
more than 200 people, is to complete in <DATE>1995</DATE>. Middle and part 
of large enterprises will be privatized during 1996-1998. 
  Answering journalists question concerning the delay in the 
adoption of the program, even after it was signed by President, 
<PERSON>Abdulsalimzade</PERSON> said that there are people in the highest 
legislative body and in the ministries and among the leaders of 
enterprises, opposing the privatization program. 
  The high rank employee of the <ORGANIZATION>Committee for Property</ORGANIZATION> told 
TURAN that there are two approaches to this problem in the 
highest circles. "The part of them want to organise wholesale 
of state property, the others are opposed [to] privatization at 
all, referring to the war. "Privatization will not take place 
until they come to common decision", said the employee. 
  Law for privatization was adopted in <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> on <DATE>January 
7, 
1993</DATE>. Up to today only 5,000 taximotors [taxicabs] are 
privatized in the country. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06249212 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06249212 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  A manatee was captured while taking a nap on the shore of a cooling pond at a
nuclear power plant.;   "I still can't believe it," said Florida Power &amp; Light
spokesman Ray Golden. "We knew we might never get another opportunity like
this, so we took it."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MANATEE FOUND IN N-PLANT POND  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The sea cow, nicknamed <PERSON>Pamela</PERSON>, was spotted <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. It apparently was
sucked from the ocean through one of three pipes that pulls water into the
pond at the <LOCATION>St. Lucie</LOCATION> plant on this barrier island.;   Utility company
officials moved quickly because another manatee, nicknamed <PERSON>Natalie</PERSON>, got stuck
in their pond last year after eluding several rescue attempts. It was freed
after two months.;   <LOCATION>Pamela</LOCATION>, a 7-foot manatee, was hoisted onto a stretcher
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and trucked to <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Lowry Park Zoo</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Hutchinson Island, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910905  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  128  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, September 5, 1991
00249212,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-38462 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov104_r_94010" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-104 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> CAUCASUS </F>
<F P=101> Azerbaijan </F>
<H3> <TI>   1994 State Budget Outlined </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    1994 State Budget Outlined </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC2905193194 Yerevan SNARK in English 0516 GMT 29 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC2905193194 </F>
<F P=104>  Yerevan SNARK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "Business SNARK file] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION> [dateline as received]-- The bill on <LOCATION>Azerbaijan 
Republic</LOCATION> state budget for <DATE>1994</DATE> has been approved by <ORGANIZATION>Milli Majlis</ORGANIZATION> 
on <DATE>May 26</DATE>. According to the document, the income part of budget 
is planned at a level of <MONEY>138 billion manats</MONEY>, while the 
expenditure will be at amount of <MONEY>181 billion manats</MONEY>. Thus the 
deficit will make nearly <MONEY>43 billion manats</MONEY>, which is <PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT> 
of GNP. The expected inflation level by the end of the year may 
reach <PERCENT>360 percent</PERCENT>. 
  The following allocations are planned in the budget: 
  <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT>--for economy purposes; 
  <PERCENT>5.38 percent</PERCENT>--for industrial engineering; 
  <PERCENT>1.2 percent</PERCENT>--for science; 
  <PERCENT>9.6 percent</PERCENT>--for control bodies; 
  <PERCENT>7.3 percent</PERCENT>--for servicing of international debts and 
credits; 
  <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>--for needs of power and law enforcement 
structures. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-17654 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov060_n_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-060 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  24 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Turkmenistan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Turkmenistan's Economic Plight Viewed </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PM2803112494 Moscow SELSKAYA ZHIZN in Russian 24 Mar 94 p 5 </F>
<F P=103> PM2803112494 </F>
<F P=104>  Moscow SELSKAYA ZHIZN </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Russian </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by correspondent <PERSON>Grigoriy Kolodin</PERSON>: "The Manat Has </F>
Prompted Respect for...the Ruble"] 
  [Text] <LOCATION>Turkmenia</LOCATION> -- It has been nearly five months since 
the introduction of the national currency in <LOCATION>Turkmenia</LOCATION> -- the 
manat. That is certainly long enough to consider the initial 
results of the circulation of the new money and what effect this 
unavoidable step has had on the country's economy. It was 
indeed unavoidable, although banknotes and coins manufactured 
beforehand in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, were ready and waiting, but the 
government thought that at that time <LOCATION>Turkmenia</LOCATION> was not yet fully 
prepared for the switch to its own currency. It was only when 
it became obvious that the Russian authorities were planning to 
force their <ORGANIZATION>CIS</ORGANIZATION> neighbors out of the ruble zone that <LOCATION>Turkmenia</LOCATION> 
accelerated the introduction of the manat. 
  <DATE>November</DATE> was a month of euphoria and...empty pocketbooks. 
The exchange of citizens' savings was carried out in such a way 
as to drastically reduce the money supply. However, even with a 
mere handful of coins in his pocket, a person felt quite 
solvent. For 5 kopeks (that is what people here habitually call 
the small change -- the tenge) you could buy the latest 
newspaper or eat a bread roll, and for 20 you could buy a loaf 
or stick of wheaten bread. With 2 chervonets, you could buy 10 
eggs, some green vegetables, and a couple of kilograms of 
apples. Potatoes cost 1 manat, and, just as in the good old 
days of stagnation, traders would stick cardboard price tickets 
into their piles of late melons, saying "1 melon -- 1 ruble." 
And although, after the first pay packets were issued in the 
new money, the Turkmens learned to count their small change in a 
new way, for an average wage of 400 manats you could not only 
feed yourself, but also buy, say, a pair of Italian shoes for 
110 manats or a washing machine for 120 manats. 
  Alas, <DATE>November</DATE> and <DATE>December</DATE>, when the family budget was 
"tight" but you could fill a bag with food products for a small 
sum, are remembered here today as months of plenty and days of 
bright hopes which, unfortunately, are not yet fated to become 
reality. In <LOCATION>Turkmenia</LOCATION> it is still not the custom to publish 
information on the inflation rate or to calculate the cost of 
the consumer basket, but every inhabitant of the Republic can 
see for himself every day how life is growing increasingly 
expensive. Meat prices in the bazaars have risen from 5 to <MONEY>50 
manats</MONEY> a kilogram, the cost of fruit and vegetables has also 
gone up, for the third month in succession the shelves of stores 
selling industrial products are practically empty, and in the 
few commercial stores the prices are certainly not suited to 
people who are living only on a wage. And without the 
continuing government subsidies on flour and bread for the 
population, so that bread still costs 20-30 tenge, without the 
free provision of electricity, natural gas, and water and the 
very low cost of housing, of sending children to preschool 
institutions, and of travel on public transport, things would be 
very tight indeed for the Turkmens. 
  It is certainly not the manat as such that is to blame for 
the fact that the Republic, which in all previous years had a 
deficit-free budget, is today spending more than it receives. 
The financial hole in the state's pocket was caused by the huge 
debts of the former brothers in the Union for natural gas 
supplied in the past year. It is no joking matter that 
<LOCATION>Turkmenia</LOCATION> is owed <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> by <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>, 
and the other <ORGANIZATION>CIS</ORGANIZATION> countries -- a shortfall of nearly 380 
"greenbacks" for every local inhabitant. The main debtors -- 
<LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> -- asked for their last year's debt of <MONEY>$700 
million</MONEY> and <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY> respectively to be classified as a 
<ORGANIZATION>Turkmen Government</ORGANIZATION> loan. Their wishes were accommodated, but 
the first two months of this year elapsed without either <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> 
or <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> keeping its promise -- to pay for gas every 10 days. 
It was necessary to resort to extreme measures and close the 
valves on the pipelines to <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION>. But apparently the 
Ukrainian authorities are today more worried about the purely 
internal political struggle and the disastrous decline of their 
own economy. 
  President <PERSON>Saparmurad Niyazov</PERSON> and his team are intensively 
seeking a way out of the crisis situation. Preparations have 
been stepped up for the implementation if the plan for a gas 
pipeline which will convey Turkmen natural fuel via <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. The possibility of pumping gas through 
<LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> is being examined. A major reform of 
the agrarian sector is under way: More than 50,000 hectares of 
formerly unused land has been handed over to private ownership. 
  But for the moment the manat remains a sideshoot of the 
dollar and the ruble. Its real rate is falling rapidly. Having 
ostensibly been set as equivalent to <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> and 500 Russian 
rubles in <DATE>November</DATE>, today it only runs to <MONEY>1 cent</MONEY> and 20 rubles. 
The lack of Russian currency in the banks has been a severe blow 
to state and business structures, which are <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> "tied" to 
<LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>. Contracts are being broken, former links are being 
lost, and business circles can be heard increasingly frequently 
dreaming: "If only we were back in the ruble area! We cannot 
survive without <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION> yet..." 
  As for survival, this is, of course, a slight exaggeration. 
But common sense and the example of Belorusia [<LOCATION>Belarus</LOCATION>] 
suggests that it is not a question of what picture there is on 
the banknotes, but of preventing them from degenerating into 
pretty colored candy wrappers. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-3135</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFPCDAATFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930616
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 JUN 93 / Azeris recall Brezhnev era leader
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By STEVE LEVINE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BAKU, AZERBAIJAN
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>AZERBAIJAN</LOCATION>'S <PERSON>Brezhnev</PERSON> era <ORGANIZATION>KGB</ORGANIZATION> and communist party chief, <PERSON>Mr Heidar Aliyev</PERSON>,
made a remarkable political comeback yesterday, winning election as chairman
of the former Soviet republic's parliament.
The election makes <PERSON>Mr Aliyev</PERSON>, 70, nominally the second most powerful leader
to <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> President <PERSON>Abulfaz Elchibey</PERSON>.
But diplomats and other foreign observers in <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>, the capital, believe that
the wily <PERSON>Mr Aliyev</PERSON> has carved himself out a significant chunk of <PERSON>Mr
Elchibey</PERSON>'s power and that new elections are likely. Given the present
despondent political mood, <PERSON>Mr Aliyev</PERSON> probably would be <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>'s
strongest presidential candidate.
The political and economic deterioration was demonstrated when <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>
newspapers yesterday announced that <PERSON>Mr Elchibey</PERSON> had postponed complete
introduction of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>'s new currency, the manat.
The government, which began circulating the manat on <DATE>June 2</DATE>, had announced
that the rouble would be invalidated on <DATE>June 15</DATE>, but the move now has been
delayed at least until <DATE>July 1</DATE>. 'We need to wait until the situation
stabilises. As soon as that happens, the reforms will take place,' said <PERSON>Mr
Elman Rustamov</PERSON>, deputy chairman of the ministry of foreign economic
activity.
On <DATE>Monday</DATE> the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> embassy recommended that American nationals leave the
country, and many foreign businessmen, including oil company employees, have
departed on flights to <LOCATION>Istanbul</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
It was not clear whether <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>'s political upheaval was over. <PERSON>Mr
Aliyev</PERSON>'s comeback was forewarned a week ago, when rebel troops seized
<LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION>'s second city, <LOCATION>Gyanja</LOCATION>, and demanded <PERSON>Mr Elchibey</PERSON>'s resignation.
Though the troops, led by a charismatic businessman, <PERSON>Mr Surat Huseynov</PERSON>, have
voiced their support for <PERSON>Mr Aliyev</PERSON>, they now have taken control of up to
half the Caspian Sea nation, and are within 70 miles of <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Elchibey</PERSON>, whose popularity has steadily waned since he came to power
about a year ago, has threatened to use force to defend his government. But
it is unclear how much loyalty he still enjoys in the military, or among the
Azeri population of 7m.
The key factor in <PERSON>Mr Elchibey</PERSON>'s loss of popularity have been the lack of
economic improvements and a string of military defeats in the war in the
enclave of <LOCATION>Nagorno-Karabakh</LOCATION>. On <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> ethnic Armenians from
<ORGANIZATION>Nagorno-Karabakh</ORGANIZATION> finally agreed to a brokered settlement. But at the same
time ethnic Armenian troops appeared to be encircling yet another important
city in the region, <LOCATION>Agdam</LOCATION>, which actually lies outside <LOCATION>Nagorno-Karabakh</LOCATION>.
The continued fighting was bound to put new pressure on <PERSON>Mr Elchibey</PERSON>, and
give <PERSON>Mr Aliyev</PERSON> a stronger hand ultimately to topple him.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AZZ  Azerbaijan, East Europe.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9111 Executive Offices.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 3
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06333158 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06333158 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  ONE of the most useful holiday gifts you can give a child is a book that
teaches appreciation of the Earth and the importance of taking care of it.
Until a few years ago, there were few good ones. But now environmentalism for
kids is a growing field, and there are a number of excellent books to choose
from.;   Here are four that you can probably find in a local store, with
quotes to give you an idea of the style and suitable age group. But be sure to
ask for recommendations at your local bookstore. There are new eco-books being
published all the time.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ECOLOGY BOOK A WORTHY GIFT FOR KIDS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  EarthWorks  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     (check)  "The Great Kapok Tree: A Tale of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> Rain Forest" by <PERSON>Lynne
Cherry</PERSON> (<PERSON>Harcourt Brace Jovanovich</PERSON>, <DATE>1990</DATE>; <MONEY>$14.95</MONEY>; color illustrations). One of
the nicest eco-story books for young children, beautifully illustrated.
Sample: "The tops of the trees in the rain forest are called the canopy. The
canopy is a sunny place that touches the sky. The animals that live there like
lots of light. Colorful parrots fly from tree to tree. Monkeys leap from
branch to branch. . . . In this steamy environment, the great Kapok tree
shoots up through the forest and emerges above the canopy. This is the story
of a community of animals that live in one such tree in the rain forest.";  
(check)  "How Nature Works: 100 Ways Parents and Kids Can Share the Secrets of
Nature" by <PERSON>David Burnie</PERSON> (Reader's Digest, <DATE>1991</DATE>; <MONEY>$24</MONEY>). Profusely illustrated
with color photos, experiments and diagrams. Not as simple or accessible as it
first appears, but still the best "Nature 101" book for older kids and adults
we've seen. Sample: "Over 260 million years ago, turtles and tortoises evolved
-- long before their larger relatives, the dinosaurs. The armor-plating of
these fascinating animals protects them against most predators when adults,
but they are vulnerable when young because they reproduce by laying eggs.
Particularly threatened are the sea-going turtles that lay their eggs at night
on sandy beaches. . . . Some species are now seriously endangered.";   (check)
 "Kid Heroes of the Environment: Simple Things Real Kids Are Doing to Save the
Earth" by the <ORGANIZATION>EarthWorks Group</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>EarthWorks Press</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1991</DATE>, <MONEY>$4.95</MONEY>; black and white
illustrations). Includes stories about kids all over the country, with
step-by-step instructions and resources. Sample: "When <PERSON>Lyle Solla-Yates</PERSON> was in
first grade, his favorite animals were manatees -- rare mammals also known as
"sea cows" that live off the coast of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. One day Lyle read a report in
the newspaper about a manatee that had been injured by a motor boat. It made
him angry. 'I really wanted to do something to help the manatees,' he says. So
in <DATE>1989</DATE>, he started a group called <ORGANIZATION>Pals of Wildlife</ORGANIZATION> to raise money to help
save them. His group raised <MONEY>hundreds of dollars</MONEY> and has donated the money to
various environmental organizations. Lyle says: 'We've gotten people to see
they can change things. And we learned that helping the environment can be
fun!' ";   (check)  "My First Green Book: A Life-Size Guide to Caring for Our
Environment" (Dorling-Kindersley, <DATE>1991</DATE>; <MONEY>$12</MONEY>). English book whose main
attraction is its attractive design and beautiful color photographs. Includes
projects and basic information. Sample: "One of the main sources of everyday
waste is packaging. Packaging can be useful. It protects goods and may provide
useful information about them. But many things come in layers and layers of
unnecessary paper, plastic and cardboard. Usually, the more expensive a
product is, the more layers of wasteful packaging it has. The best way to
reduce waste is to avoid buying anything that is over-packaged. Here you can
see the amount of packaging used for a takeout meal for one child."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  John Javna column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911128  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  11H  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  631  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, November 28, 1991
00333158,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47245 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpusr069___94060" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-USR-94-069 </AU>
JPRS 


</HEADER>

<ABS>  FBIS Report: Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   21 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> CAUCASUS </F>
<F P=101> AZERBAIJAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Edict on Welfare, Economic Stability </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Edict on Welfare, Economic Stability </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   944K1526A Baku BAKINSKIY RABOCHIY in Russian 21 Jun 94 pp 1-2 </F>
<F P=103> 944K1526A </F>
<F P=104>  Baku BAKINSKIY RABOCHIY </F>
<F P=105>  Russian </F>


<TEXT>
CSO 

<FÊP=106> [Republic of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> presidential edict: "Measures To </F>
Increase Social Protection of the Population and Financial 
Stabilization of the Economy"] 
  [Text] The increase in inflation and the decline in 
production have led in recent times to a lowering of the living 
standard of society and have exerted a negative influence on the 
financial state of the republic. This has been connected to a 
decisive extent with the inefficient use of the financial and 
credit resources of public enterprises and organizations, the 
unjustified increase in their crossover into nonstate 
structures, and the absence of precise mechanisms of the pursuit 
of a price policy and the regulation of wages and the currency 
market. All this is creating difficulties for the implementation 
of the program of market transformations and bringing about a 
growth of socioeconomic tension. 
  To increase social protection of the population and ensure 
financial stabilization of the economy I resolve: 
  1. To establish as of 1 <DATE>June 1994</DATE> minimum remuneration at 
<MONEY>2,000 manat</MONEY> a month. 
  2. To appoint as of 1 <DATE>June 1994</DATE> for social and nonworking 
retirees, students of day courses at higher educational 
institutions, and trainees of technical schools and 
vocational-technical schools monetary compensation amounting to 
1,500 manat, and for families with a per capita monthly income 
of less than the minimum wage times two, monetary compensation 
amounting to <MONEY>750 manat</MONEY> a month per child 16 years of age and 
under. These sums of compensation shall be paid from the 
resources of the republic budget. 
  To consider lapsed in this connection the Republic of 
<LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> presidential edict of 22 <DATE>November 1993</DATE> "Payment of 
Compensation to Nonworking Retirees" and clause two of Republic 
of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> presidential edict of 22 <DATE>November 1993</DATE> 
"Supplementary Measures in the Field of Regulation of the <ORGANIZATION>Price 
of Bread and Bakery Products</ORGANIZATION> and Increased Social Protection for 
the Needy Strata of the Populace." 
  3. That the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Cabinet of Ministers</ORGANIZATION> 
shall 
implement the following system of anti-inflation measures to 
ensure financial stabilization in the economy: 
  as of 16 <DATE>June 1994</DATE>, increase the prices of energy and bread 
and hence forward review them not less than quarterly with 
regard to the rate of inflation; 
  within three days' time, make the corresponding changes, 
based on coordinated proposals of the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Finance</ORGANIZATION> and 
the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Labor and Social Protection</ORGANIZATION> of the Populace, to 
the uniform wage scale for workers and employees to prevent the 
formation of an appreciable gap between the remuneration of 
employees of the low-income and high-income categories; 
  prior to the end of <DATE>1994</DATE>, suspend the construction of 
facilities financed from funds of the republic budget, except 
for projects of the current year that are close to completion, 
and adopt measures to ensure the safe preservation of these 
facilities; 
  reverse the decisions it adopted earlier on public 
enterprises being granted soft loans; 
  in interaction with the banks, adopt measures to ensure the 
public enterprises' repayment of credit within the established 
timeframe; 
  within two weeks' time, present proposals for the 
reorganization of the structure of the central organs of state 
administration in the direction of a reduction in their numbers 
and also a downsizing of staff and administrative-managerial 
costs, thanks to a reduction in the number of official motor 
vehicles included; 
  within 10 days' time, devise rules for the allocation of the 
resources of public enterprises and organizations on charitable 
purposes and introduce a precise mechanism of supervision to 
ensure that these resources be used as specifically intended; 
  within 10 days' time, confirm the maximum rate of use of the 
profits of public enterprises and organizations for wages; 
  in the necessary quantity to partially cover the budget 
deficit, provide for the manufacture and sale of government 
securities; 
  within a month's time, prepare and present proposals 
concerning a transition from the system of tax and nontax 
privileges for particular categories of individuals and legal 
entities to a system of monetary compensation for the socially 
unprotected strata of the populace; 
  ensure strict compliance with legislation on the 
registration 
and issue of a certificate to higher and secondary specialized 
educational institutions and adopt the necessary measures aimed 
at a reduction in the admittance of trainees to 
vocational-technical schools and of students to evening and 
correspondence departments of higher educational institutions 
funded from the state budget; 
  within a month's time, devise and present for consideration 
by the president of the Republic of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> a concept for 
transition to insurance medicine and also proposals pertaining 
to its legal support. 
  4. That the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Ministry of Economics</ORGANIZATION> and 
the <ORGANIZATION>State Committee for Antitrust Policy</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Support of 
Enterprise</ORGANIZATION> shall intensify supervision of the formation of 
prices at public enterprises that are monopolies and 
systematically present to the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Cabinet of 
Ministers</ORGANIZATION> information on enterprises permitting a deviation from 
the market prices of the products (services) they manufacture 
(provide). 
  That the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Cabinet of Ministers</ORGANIZATION> shall 
adopt stringent measures against enterprise executives 
permitting such a deviation. 
  5. That the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Ministry of Finance</ORGANIZATION> 
shall: 
  within a month's time conduct an audit of the resources of 
public enterprises and organizations diverted into founder's and 
other contributions to the nonstate sector of the economy. 
  That the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Cabinet of Ministers</ORGANIZATION> shall 
provide for the adoption of specific measures for the more 
efficient use of these resources; 
  provide for the precise delineation of the republic and 
local 
budgets, broadening the independence of the local budgets with 
regard to the fuller use of levers of their formation; 
  with regard to inflation review quarterly in conjunction 
with 
the <ORGANIZATION>Main State Tax Inspectorate</ORGANIZATION> of the Republic of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> 
the treasury tax receipt targets. 
  6. To propose that the <ORGANIZATION>National Bank of the Republic of 
Azerbaijan</ORGANIZATION>: 
  tighten the reserve requirements in respect to 
joint-stock-commercial and commercial banks and, with regard to 
the rate of growth of inflation, review quarterly the discount 
rate on centralized credit resources; 
  disallow the practice of the mutual off-setting of arrears 
between enterprises and organizations; 
  implement measures to terminate lending to enterprises and 
organizations with foreign currency assets; 
  adopt all measures to ensure the stabilization of the 
exchange rate of the manat and the regular operation of the <ORGANIZATION>Baku 
Interbank Currency Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. For this purpose authorize the 
<ORGANIZATION>National Bank of the Republic of Azerbaijan</ORGANIZATION>, following 
consultation with the president of the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan</ORGANIZATION>, 
to use resources of the Stabilization Fund for restrained 
intervention in the interbank currency market; 
  provide in conjunction with the joint-stock-commercial 
agro-industrial and industrial-investment banks for their 
transition as of 1 <DATE>July 1994</DATE> to a system of correspondent 
accounts to prevent the issue of credit not backed by resources; 
  adopt in conjunction with the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan 
Ministry 
of Economics</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Ministry of Finance</ORGANIZATION>, 
and the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Main State Tax Inspectorate</ORGANIZATION> 
measures to stabilize monetary circulation and reduce money 
issue by means of the establishment of a stimulatory deposit 
interest rate and regulation of the activity of the commercial 
sector in the sphere of monetary circulation. 
  7. For an increase in the efficiency of the use of public 
financial resources to propose that public enterprises and 
organizations switch to full credit-payment and cash service in 
joint-stock-commercial banks whose controlling block of shares 
is publicly owned. That the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Cabinet of 
Ministers</ORGANIZATION> shall implement urgent measures in this sphere. 
  8. To propose that the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan National 
Assembly</ORGANIZATION> speed up the confirmation of the guidelines of the 
credit policy of the Republic of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> for <DATE>1994</DATE> and the 
official program of privatization as an important means of 
economic and financial stabilization and the adoption of a law 
on property and other legislative instruments ensuring a legal 
basis for the transition to a market economy. 
  9. To commission the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan Cabinet of 
Ministers</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan National Bank</ORGANIZATION> with 
presenting the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Azerbaijan</ORGANIZATION> president with information 
monthly on execution of this edict. 
  [Signed] <PERSON>Geydar Aliyev</PERSON>, Republic of <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> president 
  <LOCATION>Baku</LOCATION>, 15 <DATE>June 1994</DATE> 

</TEXT>
