<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881228-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-88 1740EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush-Pintlala     12-28 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Pintlala,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>President-Elect To Fish For Bass Near Historic Rural Site</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KENDAL WEAVER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PINTLALA, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President-elect <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>'s bass-fishing
trip to a private lake <DATE>Thursday</DATE> will take him to a small, historic
community that once played host to another vice president, <PERSON>Aaron
Burr</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s itinerary calls for four hours of fishing with <PERSON>Ray Scott</PERSON>,
whose 55-acre lake is near the historic Pintlala site in rolling
terrain 15 miles south of <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION>.
   ``We just want to get in some fishing,'' said <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>, who became a
friend, political ally and infrequent fishing partner of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s in
<DATE>1978</DATE>. ``His fishing is so token, he doesn't have a chance to get at
it much.''
   Scott, who got a call from <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to arrange the outing, has
brought attention to a crossroads community that is little more than
a small elementary school, a library, a fire station and <PERSON>Mosley</PERSON>'s
store and service station.
   Reporters and photographers descended on <PERSON>Mosley</PERSON>'s in anticipation
of the visit. ``It's been a three-ring circus around here,'' said
<PERSON>Mary Meadows</PERSON> as she prepared hot dogs for the throng <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Secret Service</ORGANIZATION> agents checked out ``every squirrel
nest and deer stand'' on his property.
   Scott, who built the lake a couple of years ago and now has a
whitetail deer research program on his land, said the old Federal
Road that crossed through Pintlala _ a paved portion of which now
runs in front of <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>'s gate _ was the route taken by Gen. <PERSON>Andrew
Jackson</PERSON>, later the nation's seventh president, on his way to <LOCATION>New
Orleans</LOCATION> during the War of <DATE>1812</DATE>.
   Scott and historians also say <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>, the vice president who killed
<PERSON>Alexander Hamilton</PERSON> in a duel, paid an unplanned visit to Pintlala.
Burr was captured in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> in <DATE>1807</DATE> after being accused of treason
and was brought up the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Road</ORGANIZATION>. According to <LOCATION>Scott</LOCATION>, he spent
one night at <ORGANIZATION>Manac</ORGANIZATION>'s Tavern in the town.
   Burr was acquitted of treason but remained disgraced and retired
from politics.
   Scott, who founded the <ORGANIZATION>Bass Anglers Sportsman Society</ORGANIZATION> two decades
ago and sold the publishing enterprise for <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, is a
conservationist who predicted <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> will rival Teddy Roosevelt in
supporting <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s outdoors.
   ``He feels we've spent enough money on research ... and it's time
for action,'' <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> said. ``He'll be reasonable but firm'' in
protecting the environment.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881229-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-88 0132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Bush-Pintlala     12-29 0578</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush-Pintlala,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>President-Elect Drops Line Near Historic Rural Site</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KENDAL WEAVER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PINTLALA, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President-elect <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s bass fishing
excursion today takes him to a crossroads community that once played
host to another vice president _ <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s itinerary calls for about four hours of fishing with
prominent <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> sportsman <PERSON>Ray Scott</PERSON>, whose 55-acre private lake is
set in rolling countryside about 15 miles south of <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION>.
   ``We just want to get in some fishing,'' said <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>, who became a
friend, political ally and infrequent fishing partner of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> in
<DATE>1978</DATE>. ``His fishing is so token, he doesn't have a chance to get at
it much.''
   Scott, who founded the <ORGANIZATION>Bass Anglers Sportsman Society</ORGANIZATION> two decades
ago and sold the publishing enterprise for <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, is
an outspoken conservationist who predicts <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> will rival Teddy
Roosevelt in supporting <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s outdoors.
   ``He feels we've spent enough money on research ... and it's time
for action,'' said <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> in an interview. ``He'll be reasonable but
firm'' in protecting the environment.
   Scott, who got a Thanksgiving Day call from <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to arrange the
bass fishing outing, has brought attention to a farm community that
is composed mainly of a small elementary school, a library, a fire
station and <PERSON>Mosley</PERSON>'s store and service station at the junction of
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 31 and <ORGANIZATION>Federal Road</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>, who also has a whitetail deer research program on his
land, enjoys talking about the legends of Pintlala, including visits
made by <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> figures prior to <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>.
   He said the old Federal Road that crossed through Pintlala _ a
paved portion of which now runs in front of <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>'s gate _ was the
route taken by Gen. <PERSON>Andrew Jackson</PERSON> on his way to <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> for the
battle of <DATE>1812</DATE>. Scott and historians also say <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>, the vice
president who killed <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton</PERSON> in a duel, paid an unplanned
visit to Pintlala in <DATE>1807</DATE>.
   Burr was was captured in southwest <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> on treason charges in
<DATE>Februrary 1807</DATE> and was brought up the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Road</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> said <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>
spent one night at <ORGANIZATION>Manac</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Tavern</LOCATION>, which was located at a site about
a quarter-mile from <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>'s property at <LOCATION>Pintlala</LOCATION>.
   ``Pintlala is a Creek Indian word that means `fish swamp.' It
once was a heavy Creek settlement,'' said <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>. ``Manac's Tavern
was owned by <PERSON>Sam Manac</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Creek</ORGANIZATION> with large landholdings.... Manac's
son, <PERSON>David</PERSON>, was the first Indian ever to graduate from West Point.''
   The news media descended on <PERSON>Mosley</PERSON>'s store and service station in
anticipation of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s visit.
   ``It's been a three-ring circus around here,'' said <PERSON>Mary Meadows</PERSON>
as she prepared hot dogs for the lunch crowd <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> said
<ORGANIZATION>Secret Service</ORGANIZATION> agents had checked out ``every squirrel nest and deer
stand'' on his property.
   The only overt indication that the president-elect was on his way
was a sign outside the <ORGANIZATION>Pintlala Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION>. It read: ``Welcome
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>. Godspeed and Good Fishing.''
   <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>, who remains as a figurehead of the <LOCATION>B.A.S.S.</LOCATION> operation,
plays host at its fishing tournaments, some of which are carried on
cable television.
   <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> said he met <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION> about 10 years ago and was
asked to manage <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s <DATE>1980</DATE> campaign in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>. ``I'm not sure his
pickin' was too good, otherwise he wouldn't have picked me,'' said
<PERSON>Scott</PERSON>, recalling their loss to <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> in the state's primary.
   ``But I'm a good salesman. That's about all politics is anyway,''
he said. ``We just always clicked.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901119-0156 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-19-90 1846EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Lewis&amp;Clark     11-19 0516</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lewis &amp; Clark,0615</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newly Found Letters Offer Insight Into Early American Explorers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLEN G. BREED</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A long-hidden cache of personal letters
unveiled <DATE>Monday</DATE> should give historians new insight into one of the
leaders of the famed <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> expedition that explored the
<LOCATION>northern Plains</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Northwest</ORGANIZATION>.
   The 47 letters from Capt. <PERSON>William Clark</PERSON> - five of them written
during the 1803-1806 expedition into the newly acquired <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>
Territory - are a ``tremendous find,'' said <PERSON>James R. Bentley</PERSON>,
executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Filson Club</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> historical
repository that now owns the letters.
   Among the more important illuminations are <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s thoughts on
the mysterious death in <DATE>1809</DATE> of expedition commander <PERSON>Meriwether
Lewis</PERSON> and his opinion of the treacherous <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON>, vice president
under <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON>, whose <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>Louisiana Purchase</LOCATION>
doubled the nation's size.
   The letters, dated from <DATE>1792</DATE> to <DATE>1811</DATE>, are addressed to Gen.
<PERSON>Jonathan Clark</PERSON>, the explorer's older brother. Until two years ago
the letters were hidden away in the <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> attic of <ORGANIZATION>Clark</ORGANIZATION>'s
descendants.
   Some historians have argued that <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON>, then governor of the
territory he helped explore and map, was murdered on his way to
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, but <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s letters support the theory that his
friend killed himself.
   ``<PERSON>Clark</PERSON> clearly indicates in his letters that he believed <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON>
was in an unstable state of mind and was very capable of committing
suicide,'' said <PERSON>James J. Holmberg</PERSON>, curator of manuscripts for the
<ORGANIZATION>Filson Club</ORGANIZATION>.
   In one letter, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> calls <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> a ``poor fellow'' who was
``much distressed'' about how the public might perceive his
handling of financial matters in the territory.
   <PERSON>Holmberg</PERSON> said that in another letter <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> tells how <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> had
asked him and others to help sell his property and settle his debts
shortly before his death.
   References to <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>, perhaps best known for killing <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION>
Secretary <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton</PERSON> in a duel, turn up frequently in the
correspondence.
   The references focus on <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>'s alleged attempts to raise an army
and overthrow the government. In his letters, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> refers to <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>
as a ``second <PERSON>Napoleon</PERSON>,'' <PERSON>Holmberg</PERSON> said.
   ``He told President <PERSON>Jefferson</PERSON> that <PERSON>Burr</PERSON> was a real danger and
that something needs to be done about him,'' <PERSON>Holmberg</PERSON> said. ``And
something was. He was arrested.''
   The letters will force revision of several biographies, <PERSON>Holmberg</PERSON>
said, including that of <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s slave, <LOCATION>York</LOCATION>, who accompanied the
group on the excursion.
   <PERSON>Holmberg</PERSON> said a <DATE>1985</DATE> book about <LOCATION>York</LOCATION> - ``In Search of York,'' by
<PERSON>Robert Betts</PERSON> - was extremely thorough. But he said new information
in the letters explains some important events in <LOCATION>York</LOCATION>'s life, such
as how <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s refusal to reunite York with his slave wife caused
an irreparable rift between the two men.
   The <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> descendants just recently completed the legal process
of turning the documents over to the <ORGANIZATION>Filson Club</ORGANIZATION>, which now owns
six of the 12 existing letters <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> wrote during the expedition.
The six others are scattered in other collections. The <ORGANIZATION>Filson Club</ORGANIZATION>
would not disclose what it paid for the letters.
   <PERSON>Winifred George</PERSON> of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, incoming president of the
1,500-member, Montana-based <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Clark Trail Heritage
Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, said it was a ``wonderful'' find.
   ``It's been some years since something new has been
discovered,'' <PERSON>George</PERSON> said. ``We often forget how important that
expedition was to the entire westward development,'' she said.
   Bentley acknowledged that the documents won't exactly rewrite
the history books, but said they offer illuminating details.
   ``What struck me most was the insight on <PERSON>William Clark</PERSON> ... It
shows a side of him that would hard to find otherwise,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890703-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-03-89 1020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv11   07-03 0441</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv 11,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv11 ^For Release Tuesday, July 11</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>July 11</DATE>, the <DATE>192nd day of 1989</DATE>. There are 173
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>July 11</DATE>, the <DATE>192nd day of 1989</DATE>. There are 173
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for July 11</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06100026 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06100026 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3); PHOTO: Richard Nixon; PHOTO: Aaron Burr; PHOTO: Agnew  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; US; VICE-PRESIDENT; ARTS; GOVERNMENT; OFFICIAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  SET IN niches along the ornate hallways and vast chambers of the U.S. Senate
are white marble busts of the vice presidents -- from John Adams to Walter
Mondale.;    Everyone except Spiro Agnew.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WERE IT A ROGUE'S GALLERY, AGNEW MIGHT HAVE
MADE IT  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Agnew</PERSON>, who resigned in disgrace in <DATE>1973</DATE> after pleading no contest to tax
evasion, is the only former vice president missing from the gallery of carved
figures that represents the men who toiled a heartbeat away from being chief
executive. Even the bust of the most recent former vice president -- <PERSON>George
Bush</PERSON> -- waits in storage for its pedestal.;    Across from <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>'s bust is
the visage of his predecessor, <PERSON>Nelson Rockefeller</PERSON>, on a brown marble stand
next to the likeness of <ORGANIZATION>Gerald Ford</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Agnew</PERSON>'s successor. But on the other side
of the tiled hallway sits the bust of <PERSON>Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON>. And next to the
<PERSON>Mondale</PERSON> bust is an antique wooden clock.;    The likeness of the former
<LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> governor, the first vice president to resign under legal fire, is
nowhere to be found on two floors of statuary decorating the place where vice
presidents have served as presidents of the Senate.;    In "The Capitol," a
picture book published by the <ORGANIZATION>Government Printing Office</ORGANIZATION>, page after page
shows marble busts. For <PERSON>Agnew</PERSON>'s entry, there is a snapshot and the caption,
"pending.";    UNDER a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> resolution passed in <DATE>1898</DATE>, the architect of the
Capitol or the chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Rules Committee</ORGANIZATION> contacts the vice
president -- or his family -- after he leaves office for the commission of a
formal bust.;    "I don't know what the reason is. I guess we're waiting for
the family or the committee," said <PERSON>William F. Raines Jr.</PERSON>, a spokesman for the
architect of the Capitol, acknowledging that <PERSON>Agnew</PERSON> is the only one among the
43 former vice presidents whose bust has not been commissioned.;    "It's
generally handled by the architect's office," said <PERSON>Jim King</PERSON>, a spokesman for
the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Rules Committee.</ORGANIZATION>;    The subject of an <PERSON>Agnew</PERSON> bust comes up "from
time to time, when something might happen on that," <PERSON>Raines</PERSON> said. "We don't
have anything in the <PERSON>Agnew</PERSON> file." He added quickly, "We don't even have a file
on that.";    <PERSON>George M. White</PERSON>, architect of the Capitol since <DATE>1971</DATE>, said the
staff or family of the last several vice presidents called his office to start
the process.;    "It's probably as much my neglect as theirs," said <PERSON>White</PERSON>, who
blamed his lack of initiative on other <LOCATION>Capitol chores.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Agnew</PERSON>, a
businessman now living in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>, could not be reached for
comment, but Rep. <PERSON>Helen Delich Bentley</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Md.</LOCATION>, believes that the former vice
president has been snubbed.;    'H E hasn't been treated fairly," said
<PERSON>Bentley</PERSON>, a former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> maritime commissioner. "He did step down, true, and he
was under pressure. We need to look at the whole picture. Others who have been
in that position have been under fire.";    Not only under fire but fired
upon. The nation's third vice president, <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON>, was charged by <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for shooting <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton</PERSON> in a duel but was never brought
to trial. He also was tried on treason charges but was acquitted.;    <PERSON>Schuyler
Colfax</PERSON>, vice president from <DATE>1869</DATE> to <DATE>1873</DATE>, was deeply implicated in a bribery
scandal but remained in office after the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> declined to
start impeachment proceedings.;    Both men are memorialized by marble busts,
as is former Vice President <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>, whose bust was completed in <DATE>1965</DATE> --
long before <LOCATION>Watergate</LOCATION> -- and is prominently displayed outside a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> chamber
door.;    White denied that there was any deliberate effort to block the
commissioning of an <PERSON>Agnew</PERSON> bust. "Not on my part, and I'm the one who's
supposed to do it," he said.;    When White was asked whether he would contact
the former vice president about a bust, he said, "Now that you mention it, I
probably should."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  TOM BOWMAN, Baltimore Sun  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910409  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  644  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday April 9, 1991
00100026,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880705-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-05-88 0752EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv11   07-05 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv11,0441</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv11</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday, July 11</NOTE>
<HEAD>Retransmitting to fix header</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   Today is <DATE>Monday, July 11</DATE>, the <DATE>193rd day of 1988</DATE>. There are 173
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>July 11, 1804</DATE>, Vice President <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON> mortally wounded
former <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton</PERSON> in a pistol duel near
<LOCATION>Weehawken</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1533</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Pope Clement VII</ORGANIZATION> excommunicated <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>King Henry
VIII</ORGANIZATION>.
States</LOCATION>, was born in <LOCATION>Braintree</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1798</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Marine Corps</ORGANIZATION> was created by an act of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1864</DATE>, Confederate forces led by Gen. <PERSON>Jubal Early</PERSON> began their
invasion of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> D.C.
   In <DATE>1934</DATE>, President <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> became the first chief
executive to travel through the <LOCATION>Panama Canal</LOCATION>, aboard the cruiser
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1955</DATE>, the new <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force Academy</ORGANIZATION> was dedicated at <ORGANIZATION>Lowry
Air Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1974</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>House Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION> released volumes of
evidence it had gathered in its Watergate inquiry.
   In <DATE>1977</DATE>, the Medal of Freedom was awarded posthumously to the
Rev. <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> in a <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> ceremony.
   In <DATE>1979</DATE>, the abandoned <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space station Skylab made a
spectacular return to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, burning up in the atmosphere and
showering debris over the <LOCATION>Indian Ocean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, American hostage <PERSON>Richard I. Queen</PERSON>, freed by <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> after
eight months of captivity because of poor health, left <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> for
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <PERSON>Nolan Ryan</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Houston Astros</ORGANIZATION> became the first
pitcher in major league baseball to strike out 4,000 batters as he
fanned <PERSON>Danny Heep</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mets.
   Ten years ago: A tanker truck overfilled with propylene gas
exploded on a coastal highway south of <LOCATION>Tarragona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, setting
off a fireball that devastated a nearby campsite, killing 215
tourists as well as the driver. The <ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> downed the
<ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION>, 7-3, in baseball's 49th annual All-Star Game.
   Five years ago: The <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration filed its first school
desegregation suit, charging that <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>'s public colleges and
universities were practicing racial segregation.
   One year ago: Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON> won a third
consecutive term, becoming the first Labor Party leader in the
country's history to be elected to three straight terms in office.
   Today's Birthdays: Actor <PERSON>Tab Hunter</PERSON> is 57. Singer <PERSON>Bonnie Pointer</PERSON>
is 37. Boxer <PERSON>Leon Spinks</PERSON> is 35.
   Thought for Today: ``History is written by the winners.'' _ <PERSON>Alex
Haley</PERSON>, American author.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv July 11</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870227-0193 </DOCNO>
<HL> When President Is a Four-Letter Word
---
By Matthew Cossolotto</HL>
<DD> 02/27/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   Call it four-letter chic. 
All of a sudden the <DATE>1988</DATE> presidential field is swarming with possible contenders who have one thing in common -- four-letter last names. 

   This is an odd situation. 
We have had only three four-letter chief executives: <PERSON>James Polk</PERSON>, <PERSON>William Taft</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gerald Ford</PERSON> -- who was appointed, not elected, to both the vice presidency and presidency. 
Three out of 40 is not what you would call an overwhelming percentage. 
The odds may be stacked against the current crop of four-letter <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> aspirants. 

   Who are they? 
The Republicans boast at least four principal possibilities: Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>, Rep. <PERSON>Jack Kemp</PERSON>, former <ORGANIZATION>Secretary of State Alexander Haig</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Minority Leader <PERSON>Bob Dole</PERSON>. 
And <PERSON>Horace Busby</PERSON>, former aide to President <PERSON>Lyndon Johnson</PERSON>, includes <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Tom Kean</PERSON> on his so-called "twitch list" of potential candidates. 

   The Democrats have no shortage in this department, either. 
Until recently, there were three four-letter Democrats widely touted for the presidency: former <PERSON>Sen. Gary Hart</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Senate Armed Services Committee</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Sam Nunn</PERSON>, and former <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Chuck Robb</PERSON>. 
The list is growing. 
A recent <ORGANIZATION>Newsweek</ORGANIZATION> article says <PERSON>Tennessee Sen. Albert Gore</PERSON> is a potential candidate. 
And <PERSON>Mr. Busby</PERSON>'s "twitch list" includes a prominent Democratic spokesman on foreign policy, <PERSON>Sen. Chris Dodd</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>. 

   It was way back in <DATE>1845</DATE> that <PERSON>James Polk</PERSON>, the only Democrat with a four-letter name to occupy the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, became president. 
Messrs. 
<PERSON>Hart</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robb</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nunn</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gore</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dodd</PERSON> may want to take this into account as they consider their presidential prospects. 
<PERSON>Mr. Hart</PERSON>, in particular, may have some new grounds for debating the wisdom of his decision to shorten his last name from <LOCATION>Hartpence</LOCATION>. 

   Rare as four-letter presidents have been, four-lettered vice presidents have come almost as few and far between -- only four. 
One, <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON>, is infamous, having killed <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton</PERSON> in a duel. 
Another, <PERSON>William King</PERSON>, vice president in <DATE>1853</DATE> during the <PERSON>Pierce</PERSON> administration, died the same year he was inaugurated. 
The other two, <PERSON>Gerald Ford</PERSON> and <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>, happen to be among the three most recent Republican vice presidents, <PERSON>Nelson Rockefeller</PERSON> being the multisyllabic exception. 
This recent trend, if that is what it is, may give hope to Republican vice presidential aspirants with four-letter surnames. 

   (Just for the record, 21 presidents have had two-syllable last names, while 11 presidential names have contained three syllables. 
Three presidents have had one-syllable last names not of four letters, and just one president -- <PERSON>Dwight Eisenhower</PERSON> -- has had four syllables in his last name.) 

   What can account for such a dismal showing of individuals with four-letter names? 
My own theory posits that Americans, already measurably cynical about politicians, simply want to avoid associating their national leaders with four-letter words. 
Lest the four-letter candidates get too discouraged -- and the other candidates become carried away with their good fortune -- bear this in mind: The first real test of presidential timber in <DATE>1988</DATE> comes in <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, a four-letter state. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Cossolotto</PERSON>, an aide in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, has no current intentions of running for president or shortening his name. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA070190-0031 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 241143 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 1, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 6; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1129 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SOUTH CAROLINA'S OLD GEORGETOWN HARBORS SOME INTERESTING SECRETS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JAMES T. YENCKEL, WASHINGTON POST 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
GEORGETOWN, S.C. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As much as any town can today, the historic colonial port of <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION> has the 
look of the Old South, and like much of the South it is rife with ghosts. I 
think I may have a crush on one of them. That's really how I happened to find 
<LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION> in the first place. 
</P>
<P>
Scattered down the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION> are several charming old towns that thrived 
briefly as cosmopolitan centers, and then faded into the pages of history. 
</P>
<P>
I think of the shipping port of Salem in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, which eventually 
declined as <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> grew, and nearby <LOCATION>Annapolis</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> capital that slept 
while <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> prospered. 
</P>
<P>
By chance, I stumbled this <DATE>spring</DATE> across yet another one, <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Once reputedly the world's rice-exporting capital, it now is a quiet but 
appealing backwater that was long ago overshadowed by <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION> to the south. 
</P>
<P>
Like Salem and <LOCATION>Annapolis</LOCATION>, however, it has preserved many of the gorgeous old 
homes built by wealthy families in the town's heyday before the Civil War. 
</P>
<P>
Georgetown is about midway on the 100-mile drive down the <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> coast 
from <LOCATION>Myrtle Beach</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
I had never heard of the town before my <LOCATION>Carolina</LOCATION> trip this <DATE>spring</DATE>, and I 
remained unaware of its colonial significance until I got there. I might have 
hurried right through, except for <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON>'s daughter. 
</P>
<P>
I have read a couple of fairly recent biographies of <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>, the urbane but 
notorious <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> vice president who fatally wounded <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton</PERSON> in a 
famous duel. 
</P>
<P>
One of the saddest periods in <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>'s always-dramatic life was the tragic death 
of his intelligent and beautiful daughter <PERSON>Theodosia</PERSON>, wife of the governor of 
<LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Joseph Alston</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Planning to visit her father in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, Theodosia boarded a ship leaving 
<LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> on <DATE>Dec. 31, 1812</DATE>. The ship vanished without a trace, an unsolved 
mystery. Perhaps pirates attacked -- one of the legends surrounding <LOCATION>Theodosia</LOCATION> 
-- or it was sunk by a fierce gale known to have hit the coast. 
</P>
<P>
For some unexplainable reason, <PERSON>Theodosia</PERSON> and the story of her untimely death 
intrigued me. I am usually forgetful of names, but I retain hers. Can I have 
formed a romantic crush across the centuries? Perhaps. 
</P>
<P>
She was one of the most admired women of her day. So it was with astonishment 
and great delight that I read her name on a historical marker a few miles 
outside <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
I am a sucker for these roadside snippets from the past, and more often than 
not I'm rewarded with an interesting historic anecdote. 
</P>
<P>
The sign informed me that <PERSON>Theodosia</PERSON> and her husband had lived in the <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION> 
area. Their home site is now a part of <PERSON>Brookgreen Gardens</PERSON>, a large sculpture 
garden, just north of town, that's filled with an inviting mix of classically 
heroic and charmingly whimsical pieces. 
</P>
<P>
Indeed, <ORGANIZATION>Georgetown</ORGANIZATION> is the port from which <PERSON>Theodosia</PERSON> departed to meet her death. 
A huge 18th-Century mansion, the <ORGANIZATION>Man-Doyle House</ORGANIZATION>, still stands on Front Street, 
where she is said to have danced the night before the fatal trip. 
</P>
<P>
I decided I had to stop here for a while, drawn by my odd fascination with 
<LOCATION>Theodosia</LOCATION>. It is by such unexpected paths that travel discoveries are made. 
</P>
<P>
I gave myself an hour's time, but my visit stretched for another as 
<ORGANIZATION>Georgetown</ORGANIZATION>'s attractions revealed themselves. A weekend would have been more 
satisfying. 
</P>
<P>
Several bed and breakfast inns offer lodgings in or near the impressive 
<ORGANIZATION>Georgetown Historic District</ORGANIZATION>, which covers several blocks. 
</P>
<P>
Shaded by a canopy of moss-draped oaks, <PERSON>Georgetown</PERSON> sits at the confluence of 
four rivers forming <LOCATION>Winyah Bay</LOCATION>. It might have been <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s oldest European 
community, but the Spanish who settled in <DATE>1526</DATE> were quickly driven out by 
Indians and disease. The heritage, instead, is British, dating from <DATE>1729</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
More than 50 homes, buildings and sites from the <DATE>1700s</DATE> still remain in the 
historic district. Information about escorted or self-directed walking tours is 
available at the local chamber of commerce. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Harold Kaminski House</PERSON>, built about 1760, is a museum filled with antiques 
reflecting <ORGANIZATION>Georgetown</ORGANIZATION>'s link to the sea. 
</P>
<P>
Rice is no longer a commercial crop in <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>'s coastal low country, 
but <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION> today boasts a large and active shrimp-fishing fleet, which adds 
a definite bustle to its attractive waterfront setting. 
</P>
<P>
The town's colorful history is full of ghostly legends -- actually, <LOCATION>Georgetown 
County</LOCATION> enjoys some fame as the most haunted place in the South -- and the 
shrimping fleet has its own bag of superstitions. 
</P>
<P>
About 20 shrimp trawlers operate from the <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION> wharf, all of them 
sporting tall masts. The top of each mast, I noticed, is painted white. 
</P>
<P>
A curious coincidence? I wondered. Not a coincidence at all, but rather 
something of a safety feature, I was told by <PERSON>Bill Oberst</PERSON>, a young history buff 
in the <ORGANIZATION>Georgetown Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>. His family dates back to the town's 
colonial origins. 
</P>
<P>
The local lore maintains, according to <PERSON>Oberst</PERSON>, that if a shrimping vessel 
starts to sink, the white mast provides an appropriately clean spot "where the 
hand of God can grab hold and pull the boat back up to safety." 
</P>
<P>
This city's local legends are brought to life in an annual summer theater 
production called "Ghosts of the <ORGANIZATION>Coast</ORGANIZATION>." 
</P>
<P>
In my short stay, I strolled along Harbor Walk, a boardwalk that stretches for 
a couple of blocks along the waterfront, where you can dine pleasantly on fresh 
shrimp. 
</P>
<P>
And I stepped inside the small but very interesting Rice Museum on Front 
Street, which tells the story of <ORGANIZATION>Georgetown</ORGANIZATION>'s once-flourishing rice culture. 
</P>
<P>
Before the Civil War, the region supported more than 150 plantations, including 
one owned by <PERSON>Theodosia</PERSON> and her husband. But the end of slavery made cultivation 
impractical. 
</P>
<P>
Machines were developed that might have replaced slave labor, but they sank 
deep in the swampy soil of the low country. 
</P>
<P>
Just outside <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION>, a number of the old rice plantations have been 
restored as private homes. 
</P>
<P>
Although these fine old mansions are not open to the public, daily river boat 
tours sail past them on the same murky river ways that served the plantations 
as commercial highways two centuries ago. Watch for alligators on one narrow 
stretch of the route called "Alligator Alley." 
</P>
<P>
My two hours passed too quickly, as I sniffed the sea air and walked along 
elegant old streets exploring another chapter in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s rich history. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Oberst</PERSON> said he can stand under an old oak tree and feel things from the town's 
long past. I don't doubt him at all. 
</P>
<P>
Standing on Front Street before the <ORGANIZATION>Man-Doyle House</ORGANIZATION>, I easily imagined that I 
saw fair Theodosia in the second-floor ballroom enjoying a final dance before 
her fateful voyage. 
</P>
<P>
For more information on travel to <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION>, contact the <ORGANIZATION>Georgetown County 
Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 1776, <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 29442, (803) 546-8437. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, More than 350 pieces of statuary grace the Brookgreen Gardens. ; Photo, 
About 20 shrimp trawlers -- with their distinctive white-topped masts -- 
operate from Georgetown's wharf. ; Photo, A ghost named Alice is the lure of 
the Hermitage in Georgetown, S.C. ; Map, GEORGETOWN, VICTOR KOTOWITZ / Los 
Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870413-0050 </DOCNO>
<HL> Who's News:
Again, Burr and Lorenzo Part Company
As People's Founder Leaves Texas Air
---
By Paulette Thomas
<DD> 04/13/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> WNEWS TEX
AIRLINES (AIR) </IN>
<DATELINE> HOUSTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The last time <PERSON>Donald C. Burr</PERSON> parted company with <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON>, he had big plans. 
He left in <DATE>1980</DATE> to build an innovative new airline from scratch: <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Now, only a few months after <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> acquired <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> will be leaving <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s employ again. 
<PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON>, 45 years old, resigned effective this week as executive vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>, a post he had held only two months. 
But this time, his plans after <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> are far less ambitious. 
"Right now is a good time to just look around," he says. 

   There has been speculation about <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON>'s departure ever since <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>'s acquisition of <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> reunited <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> with <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>, his former low-fare competitor. 
<PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> said that his dealings with the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> chairman and chief executive officer were cordial, but he declined to be specific about his reasons for leaving. 
"I know -- surprise, surprise," <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> said in an interview. 
"But this was a mutually agreed-upon deal. 
We'll have to let people speculate about why." 

   The ups and downs of their past association were more conspicuous. 
In the days when the pair worked closely at <ORGANIZATION>Texas International</ORGANIZATION>, the predecessor of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> was best man at <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s wedding. 
After <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> left to start up <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> with another <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> International alumnus, <PERSON>Gerald Gitner</PERSON>, the two airlines competed in several markets, and both made a run at <ORGANIZATION>Frontier Airlines</ORGANIZATION> last year. 
<PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> won that round, but only to see his faltering empire bought at a cut-rate price by <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>, several months later. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON>'s new role at <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> was never outwardly apparent. 
He was named executive vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>February</DATE>, and a board member of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>. 
But his name was notably absent from a list of top management in company stock prospectuses last month. 
Even stranger was the sale of stock of <ORGANIZATION>Jet Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> -- which many took as a clue that he was among the tight circle of executives who run <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>. 
Jet Capital, a financial holding company controlled by <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>, holds a class of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> stock that controls appointments to three-quarters of the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> board. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> claims there were never plans for him at <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> in the long term. 
He said the Jet Capital stock sale was part of his "incentive package" negotiated last fall. 
He received no severance package, and even laughed at the idea. 
"No golden parachute," he said. 
<PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> said he has paid about <MONEY>$125,000</MONEY>, a one-quarter down payment on the Jet Capital stock, and isn't certain whether he will keep the stock. 

   Now that the operations of <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> have been merged into those of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, he said it was the proper time to leave. 
The poor service in the initial combined operations lived up to <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION>'s old nickname: "People Distress." 
The combined People and <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> operations resembled People's final days -- mountains of lost bags and dozens of canceled flights, but <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> says they have improved greatly since. 

   "I don't feel like we did as good as we could have, but it could have been a . . . lot worse," <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> said. 
He said he is satisfied because no <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> employees lost jobs in the merger, though many incurred financial losses after borrowing from <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> to buy <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> stock. 

   He won't discuss his plans, beyond writing a book about his experiences at <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION>, the cult-like company in which all employees were "managers," and to whom <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> would often give inspirational speeches via video screens. 
"There was some powerful learning in those strong early years," he said, "and I learned from the mistakes in the later years." 

   He hinted that perhaps that experience won't be for naught. 
"Some people are saying there's only going to be six major airlines," he said. 
"I certainly don't think it's going to be the case. 
We'll have to wait and see." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890104-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-04-89 0232EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-North-Privilege     01-04 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-North-Privilege,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>North Tactic Revives Old Debate: Can A President Be Forced To Testify?</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Iran-Contra Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The effort by <PERSON>Oliver North</PERSON> to compel President
<PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and President-elect <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to testify at his Iran-Contra trial
has renewed a debate, almost as old as the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION>, over ``executive
privilege.''
   Can a president, or a former one, be forced to testify in a legal
case? Courts have provided little guidance, but constitutional
experts said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION>'s legal tactic may succeed.
   No sitting president ever has testified in court in a criminal
trial, but several have provided testimony or what might be
considered the equivalent.
   The personal stakes are high for North. The former <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
aide is charged with theft, conspiracy to defraud the government and
several other felonies in the case involving the support of
Nicaraguan rebels with money from the sale of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> weapons to <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>.
   His trial is scheduled to begin <DATE>Jan. 31</DATE> _ just 11 days after <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
is to succeed <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>. Besides <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, subpoenas also have
been issued for other key figures in the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration,
including Secretary of State <PERSON>George P. Shultz</PERSON> and four other <ORGANIZATION>State
Department</ORGANIZATION> officials.
   The man who first tried to force a president to testify was <PERSON>Aaron
Burr</PERSON>, a former vice president who stood trial in <DATE>1807</DATE> on charges of
treason.
   Burr sought to force <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON>, the president under whom
he had served, to testify at the trial.
   Jefferson resisted. But Chief Justice <PERSON>John Marshall</PERSON>, presiding
over the trial, ruled against <PERSON>Jefferson</PERSON>. The president eventually
avoided having to appear by releasing some information <PERSON>Burr</PERSON> had
sought.
   The closest the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> has come to ruling on the issue
presented by <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION>'s subpoena came in the <LOCATION>Watergate</LOCATION> tapes decision
of <DATE>1974</DATE>, in a case called <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> vs. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
   The court then ruled, 8-0, that President <PERSON>Richard M. Nixon</PERSON> had to
comply with a special prosecutor's subpoena seeking the surrender of
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> tape recordings.
   ``The general assertion of privilege must yield to the
demonstrated, specific need for evidence in a pending criminal
trial,'' the high court ruled 15 years ago.
here, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the <DATE>1974</DATE> decision is a strong precedent for North.
   ``Whether <PERSON>Mr. Reagan</PERSON> or <PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON> can be subpoenaed was resolved
in <LOCATION>Nixon vs. U.S.</LOCATION>, and the answer is yes,'' <PERSON>Barron</PERSON> said.
   ``If the evidence (sought by North) is material, I think <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> can be required to appear,'' <PERSON>Barron</PERSON> said.
   On the other hand, unnamed <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> sources were quoted
by <ORGANIZATION>The Washington Post</ORGANIZATION> as saying that <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> vs. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> offers support
for fighting subpoenas of <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>. They said the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme
Court</ORGANIZATION> emphasized that its Watergate-tapes decision did not deal with
a claim of privilege based on national security grounds.
   <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department and White House</ORGANIZATION> officials have said they will
try to have the subpoenas thrown out.
   <ORGANIZATION>Stanley Brand</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lawyer who once served as general
counsel to the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION> may succeed.
   ``My sense is North has a good claim. The president was involved
in the process, and one of <LOCATION>North</LOCATION>'s defenses is that he was serving
the president by following orders,'' Brand said.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, then-President <PERSON>Gerald R. Ford</PERSON> gave a videotaped
deposition in the trial of <PERSON>Lynette</PERSON> ``Squeaky'' <PERSON>Fromme</PERSON>, who was
convicted of trying to assassinate <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>. The videotape was played
for jurors at <ORGANIZATION>Fromme</ORGANIZATION>'s trial.
   While in office, President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> provided videotaped
testimony in two criminal prosecutions.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870122-0057 </DOCNO>
<HL> Burr Comes Full Circle
With Post at Texas Air</HL>
<DD> 01/22/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> TEX WNEWS CAI </IN>
<DATELINE> HOUSTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Donald C. Burr</PERSON>, founder and former chairman of <ORGANIZATION>People Express Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, was named executive vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, effective <DATE>Feb. 1</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON>, 45, was president of <ORGANIZATION>Texas International Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, the forerunner of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>, before he left to start <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> has acquired <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> and will fold its operations into those of its <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> unit. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> left <ORGANIZATION>Texas International</ORGANIZATION> after feuds with <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON>, then-chairman and chief executive officer of the carrier, and currently chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>. 
As head of <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> continued to battle <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> as a competitor. 
After the takeover of <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> last month, it was been unclear what <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> would do. 

<ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> said that <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON>, among other duties, will be involved in personnel management and development at <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891208-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-08-89 2146EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MultipleShootings 1stLd-Writethru a0728 12-08 0672</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Multiple Shootings, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0728,0687</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Dead in Murder-Suicide; Seven Die in Other States</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 2-3, to CORRECT ages of gunman, slain woman, husband,
and family names of slain children; picks up 4th graf: `It was ...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HAL SPENCER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SPANAWAY, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gunman described in a pyschological
examination as unlikely to harm his ex-wife burst into her house
early <DATE>Friday</DATE> and killed her, their two daughters and her new
husband before killing himself.
   Neighbors identified the man, who left a note telling his
parents he was ``sorry for what he had to do,'' as <PERSON>Ronald Richard
Burris</PERSON>, 46.
   The others, all shot to death, included his ex-wife, <PERSON>Shirley Mae
Woody</PERSON>, 41, the couple's daughters, <PERSON>Vicki Marie Burris</PERSON>, 14, and <PERSON>Anne
Marie Burris</PERSON>, 6, and <PERSON>Shirley Woody</PERSON>'s husband, <PERSON>Robert James Woody</PERSON>,
31.
   It was one of three murder-suicides reported around the nation
on <DATE>Friday</DATE> in which 12 people died.
   In <LOCATION>Belleville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, a man identified as 48-year-old <PERSON>Kurt
Steibel</PERSON> shot and killed his wife, daughter and 1-year-old grandson,
then shot at firefighters before committing suicide by re-entering
his burning home, authorities said.
   After firefighters recovered <PERSON>Steibel</PERSON>'s body, they found the
bodies of his wife, <PERSON>Carolyn</PERSON>, and his daughter <PERSON>Cindy Townley</PERSON>, whose
ages were unavailable, and his grandson, <PERSON>Eric Townley</PERSON>. X-rays
showed that they had been shot to death. Police said they hadn't
determined a motive.
   In <LOCATION>Buxton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.D.</LOCATION>, authorities said farmer <PERSON>Wayne Nygaard</PERSON>, 42,
apparently shot his wife, <PERSON>Carol</PERSON>, 40, and their 11-year-old
daughter, <PERSON>Kate</PERSON>, before turning the gun on himself. The bodies were
found by the couple's 17-year-old son; authorities did not cite a
motive.
   In the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state case, authorities said <PERSON>Burris</PERSON> was armed
with a handgun and a shotgun.
   ``We have seasoned firefighters who were disturbed at what they
found,'' Fire District Capt. <PERSON>Bruce Carpenter</PERSON> said of the scene.
   ``We don't know for sure why he did it, except here you have an
ex-husband and a divorce that wasn't the nicest in the world,''
<PERSON>Curt Benson</PERSON>, spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Pierce County Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION>,
said as he stood on the rainswept, tree-lined street outside the
home.
   Divorce and child custody and support records, along with a <DATE>1988</DATE>
court order barring <PERSON>Burris</PERSON> from contact with his ex-family, show a
19-year marriage that broke up in <DATE>1987</DATE> after <PERSON>Shirley Burris</PERSON> accused
her husband of sexually molesting their daughters.
   The accusation, investigated by state child protective workers,
did not result in criminal charges against <PERSON>Burris</PERSON>, according to
records on file at the <ORGANIZATION>Peirce County Clerk</ORGANIZATION>'s office in nearby
<LOCATION>Tacoma</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Burris</PERSON>, who was a civilian logistics supply official at nearby
<ORGANIZATION>McChord Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>, denied the allegations in the divorce and
custody papers, calling them ``a wilfull and malevolent'' charge.
   His ex-wife later called him ``so anti-mother that the girls
resent it.'' That comment was made in a sworn statement used to
uphold a <DATE>February 1988</DATE> restraining order barring <PERSON>Burris</PERSON> from
contact with his daughters and living within two miles of his
ex-wife's home.
   A psychological examination in <DATE>September 1988</DATE> found that if
<PERSON>Burris</PERSON> was ``seriously inclined to do her harm, he would already
have done so,'' according to custody dispute records. Burris
submitted to the exam as a condition for getting the restraint
order lifted.
   <PERSON>Benson</PERSON> said <PERSON>Burris</PERSON> awoke his victims when he smashed through a
sliding glass door at the rear of the house and shot <PERSON>Woody</PERSON> in the
couple's bedroom as he called sheriff's deputies to report the
break-in.
   When deputies arrived minutes later, at about <TIME>5:12 a.m. PST</TIME>,
they found <PERSON>Burris</PERSON>' body in the living room where he had committed
suicide, <PERSON>Benson</PERSON> said.
   ``We then went into the master bedroom. We found a husband and
wife on the floor. Both died of apparent gunshot wounds.''
   Anne, 6, was found dead in her bedroom, and a 14-year-old <PERSON>Vicki</PERSON>
was shot in the doorway to her room, he said.
   Principals at the schools the girls attended said they had told
their pupils of the deaths and brought in psychologists to counsel
the children.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890103-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-03-89 1406EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--TridentBase Adv15   01-03 1162</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Trident Base, Adv 15,1205</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv15</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 15</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 3 b&amp;w photos.
ColorFoto subscribers get 3 35mm slides.)</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ In a small coastal town in rural southeast
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, you used to get the impression that anything destined to
happen there happened long ago. That was before the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> started
building a <MONEY>$1.7 billion</MONEY> base for 10 Trident submarines, which begin
arriving this month with their nuclear arsenals. <ORGANIZATION>St. Marys</ORGANIZATION> is
unlikely ever to be the same again.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ In a small coastal town in rural southeast
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, you used to get the impression that anything destined to
happen there happened long ago. That was before the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> started
building a <MONEY>$1.7 billion</MONEY> base for 10 Trident submarines, which begin
arriving this month with their nuclear arsenals. <ORGANIZATION>St. Marys</ORGANIZATION> is
unlikely ever to be the same again.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</NOTE>
<NOTE>Associated Press Writer</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ST. MARYS, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ In a small coastal town in rural southeast
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, you used to get the impression that anything destined to
happen there happened long ago. That was before the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> started
building a <MONEY>$1.7 billion</MONEY> base for 10 Trident submarines, which begin
arriving this month with their nuclear arsenals. <ORGANIZATION>St. Marys</ORGANIZATION> is
unlikely ever to be the same again.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Jan. 15</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890206-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-06-89 1127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv17   02-06 0362</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv 17,0376</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv17</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday, Feb. 17</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 17</DATE>, the <DATE>48th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 317
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Feb. 17, 1964</DATE>, 25 years ago, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> issued its
``one man, one vote'' decision, ruling that congressional districts
within each state must be roughly equal in population.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1801</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> broke an electoral tie
between <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON>, electing <PERSON>Jefferson</PERSON>
president. Burr became vice president.
   In <DATE>1817</DATE>, a street in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> became the first to be lighted
with gas from <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first gas company.
   In <DATE>1865</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, burned as the Confederates moved out and
<ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> forces began moving in. It's never been determined which side
set the blaze.
   In <DATE>1897</DATE>, the forerunner of the <ORGANIZATION>National PTA</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>National
Congress of Mothers</ORGANIZATION>, was founded in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1904</DATE>, <PERSON>Giacomo Puccini</PERSON>'s opera ``Madama Butterfly'' received a
poor reception at its premiere at <ORGANIZATION>La Scala</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1947</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Voice of America</ORGANIZATION> began broadcasting to the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1981</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> arrived in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> for the second visit
to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> by a pope.
   In <DATE>1986</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Johnson &amp; Johnson</ORGANIZATION>, maker of the painkiller Tylenol,
announced it would no longer sell over-the-counter medications in
capsule form, following a case of tampering that resulted in the
cyanide-poisoning death of a <LOCATION>Peekskill</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, woman.
   Ten years ago: Chinese troops struck against <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> along much
of their 480-mile border.
   Five years ago: President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> sent legislation to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
calling for quadrupling military aid for <ORGANIZATION>El Salvador</ORGANIZATION> to nearly <MONEY>$244
million</MONEY>.
   One year ago: Lt. Col. <PERSON>William Higgins</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officer serving
with a <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> monitoring group, was kidnapped in southern
<LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
   Today's birthdays: Singer <PERSON>Marian Anderson</PERSON> is 87. <ORGANIZATION>Sportscaster Red
Barber</ORGANIZATION> is 81. <PERSON>Margaret Truman Daniel</PERSON> is 65. Actor <PERSON>Hal Holbrook</PERSON> is
64. Actor <PERSON>Alan Bates</PERSON> is 55. Former football star <PERSON>Jim Brown</PERSON> is 53.
Actress <PERSON>Mary Ann Mobley</PERSON> is 50.
   Thought for today: ``Injustice anywhere is a threat to justice
everywhere.'' _ The <ORGANIZATION>Rev. Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890326-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-26-89 1337EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Reagan'sSubpoena     03-26 0910</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan's Subpoena,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Last President Subpoenaed Less Than 15 Years Ago</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   History is repeating itself rather quickly in
the demand by <PERSON>Oliver North</PERSON> that former President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> come from
his home in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to testify for North at his criminal trial.
   There was a gap of 167 years between the time <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON>
was subpoenaed and the <DATE>1974</DATE> summons to <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>, by then an
ex-president. Less than 15 years passed before the subpoena for
<PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>.
   During the <DATE>1974</DATE> Watergate cover-up trial, former aide <PERSON>John D.
Ehrlichman</PERSON> almost succeeded in his request for <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON>'s appearance.
It would have happened, too, had the former president not fallen
critically ill following surgery.
   ``I would have loved to have <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> in court, I had a few
questions I wanted to ask him myself,'' <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge John J.
Sirica</PERSON> wrote in his memoirs.
   But at the time, a team of court-appointed doctors determined
that <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> would be in no condition to travel for some time, which
would have delayed the trial. ``I ruled reluctantly,'' <PERSON>Sirica</PERSON>
remembered of his decision that the former president would not have
to appear. ``I did feel that no matter how anxious many of us were
to see <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> face the lawyers and testify under oath, having him in
court was not really critical to <PERSON>Ehrlichman</PERSON>'s defense.''
   Had he gone on the witness stand, <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> would have been the
first ex-president to do so under subpoena. That dubious
distinction will fall to <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> if <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Gerhard
Gesell</PERSON> accedes to <LOCATION>North</LOCATION>'s request.
   The debate whether a president must obey subpoenas and other
court orders dates to the beginning of the republic, and it is just
as volatile today as it was then.
   President <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON> received a subpoena in <DATE>1807</DATE> demanding
that he turn over a letter sought by defense lawyers in the treason
case against <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jefferson</PERSON>'s first vice president.
   Burr wanted <PERSON>Jefferson</PERSON> to appear in court and testify about the
letter written to the president by one of <ORGANIZATION>Burr</ORGANIZATION>'s alleged
co-conspirators. Chief Justice <PERSON>John Marshall</PERSON>, presiding over the
trial, declared that the president unlike a king was subject to law.
   Jefferson cited the independence of the executive branch of
government from the judicial branch and refused, at first, to
release the letter. Eventually, he turned it over but made clear
that his decision was voluntary and not in response to the subpoena.
   From then until Watergate, the concept of executive privilege
was never tested. No sitting president ever has testified in court
in a criminal trial, although several have provided testimony or
what might be considered an equivalent.
   It is not difficult to see why North's lawyers want <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> to
testify. Defense attorney <PERSON>Brendan Sullivan</PERSON> has attempted to show,
in his cross examination of prosecution witnesses, that <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> was
much more involved in the secret aid to the Contra rebels than was
known publicly before.
   The jury heard that <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> personally approved an
NSC-recommended deal in <DATE>1985</DATE> to give Honduras <MONEY>$110 million</MONEY> in
covert economic and military aid as an inducement to support the
Contras.
   The jury also heard that <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> apparently approved a plan from
North and others in the government to airdrop intelligence data and
recoilless rifles to the Contras for the purpose of destroying
ships carrying arms to the Nicaraguan government.
   Those actions all were at a time when <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> had banned <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
military aid to the Contras.
   The closest the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> has come to ruling on so-called
executive privilege was in the <LOCATION>Watergate</LOCATION> tapes case of <DATE>1974</DATE>. The
special prosecutor had subpoenaed the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> for tapes of 64
conversation and <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> didn't want to give them up.
   In the case called <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> v. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> the court ruled unanimously
that <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> had to comply with the subpoena. The specific need for
evidence in a criminal case, the court said, outweighed the
president's rights in the matter.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, President <PERSON>Gerald Ford</PERSON> gave a videotaped deposition as a
defense witness in the trial of <PERSON>Lynette</PERSON> (Squeaky) <PERSON>Fromme</PERSON> who was
convicted of attempting to assassinate <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>. Lawyers for the
administration tried unsuccessfully to have the court accept a
written statement by the president. The videotape was played in
court.
   <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>, too, as president, gave videotaped testimony _
twice. Once was as a government witness in the perjury and gambling
trial of a <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> state senator. The second time he taped
testimony for a federal grand jury that was investigating
allegations that fugitive financier <PERSON>Robert Vesco</PERSON> sought to bribe
members of the <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> administration.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> was served with the subpoena while he was still
president, along with then-Vice President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>. Both men sought to
quash the subpoenas.
   Attorney General <PERSON>Dick Thornburgh</PERSON> argued in a <DATE>Jan. 13</DATE> court
filing that the summonses ``raise profound constitutional concerns
... regarding the authority of the courts to compel appearances by
a former or sitting president.''
   He added that ``The spectacle of a former or sitting president
being subjected to peremptory judicial process may chill foreign
governments in the way they deal with the president now and in the
future.''
   On the day before the North trial started, <PERSON>Gesell</PERSON> ruled the
defendant had not shown that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> had ``relevant and material''
testimony to give and squashed the subpoena against the new
president.
   But <PERSON>Gesell</PERSON> left the decision on <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> open. He'll probably make
it this week when the defense starts presentation of its case.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880906-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-06-88 0710EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv14   09-06 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv14,0568</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv14</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Wednesday, Sept. 14.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE>, the 258th day of <DATE>1988</DATE>. There are
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Sept. 14, 1814</DATE>, <PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> wrote his famous poem ``The
Star-Spangled Banner'' after witnessing the British bombardment of
<ORGANIZATION>Fort McHenry</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1807</DATE>, former Vice President <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON> was acquitted of a
misdemeanor charge two weeks after he was found innocent of treason.
   In <DATE>1812</DATE>, the Russians set fire to <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> after an invasion by
<PERSON>Napoleon Bonaparte</PERSON>'s troops.
   In <DATE>1847</DATE>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces under Gen. <PERSON>Winfield Scott</PERSON> took control of
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1901</DATE>, President <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON> died in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, of
gunshot wounds inflicted by an assassin. Vice President <PERSON>Theodore
Roosevelt</PERSON> became president.
   In <DATE>1927</DATE>, modern dance pioneer <PERSON>Isadora Duncan</PERSON> died in Nice,
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, when her scarf became entangled in a wheel of her sports
car.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed the Selective Service Act, providing
for the first peacetime draft in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, a groundbreaking ceremony took place in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> at the
site of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>' world headquarters.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, <PERSON>Gerald R. Ford Jr.</PERSON> upset Congressman <PERSON>Bartel</PERSON> J.
``Barney'' Jonkman in <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s 5th District Republican primary.
   In <DATE>1957</DATE>, President <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> met in <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>,
with <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Orval Faubus</PERSON>, who pledged to uphold
court-ordered school integration, but also pleaded for patience.
   In <DATE>1963</DATE>, <PERSON>Mary Ann Fischer</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Aberdeen</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>, gave birth to
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first surviving quintuplets, four girls and a boy.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>Paul VI</PERSON> declared Mother <PERSON>Elizabeth Ann Bayley Seton</PERSON>
the first U.S.-born saint in an outdoor ceremony at the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Princess Grace</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Monaco</LOCATION>, who had gained fame as
American movie star <PERSON>Grace Kelly</PERSON>, died at age 52 of injuries she
suffered in a car crash the day before.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>'s president-elect, <PERSON>Bashir Gemayel</PERSON>, was killed
by a bomb that shattered the headquarters of his Lebanese Christian
Phalangist Party in east <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, Shiite Moslem extremists in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> released the Rev.
<PERSON>Benjamin Weir</PERSON>, an American missionary, after holding him captive
for 16 months.
   Ten years ago: At Camp <PERSON>David</PERSON>, President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> held
meetings with Egyptian President <PERSON>Anwar Sadat</PERSON> and Israeli Foreign
Minister <PERSON>Moshe Dayan</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION> Minister <PERSON>Ezer Weizman</PERSON> amid great
secrecy. Dayan also conferred with <PERSON>Sadat</PERSON>.
   Five years ago: The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> voted, 416 to
0, in favor of a resolution condemning the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> for
shooting down a Korean jetliner that had entered Soviet airspace on
<DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>, calling it a ``cold-blooded barbarous attack.''
   One year ago: President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Transportation Secretary</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Elizabeth Dole</PERSON>, submitted her resignation to devote herself to the
presidential campaign of her husband, <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Minority Leader <PERSON>Bob
Dole</PERSON>, R-Kan.
   Today's Birthdays: ``Lone Ranger'' <PERSON>Clayton Moore</PERSON> is 74. TV
newscaster <PERSON>Hughes Rudd</PERSON> is 67. Actress <PERSON>Zoe Caldwell</PERSON> is 55. Feminist
author <PERSON>Kate Millett</PERSON> is 54. Actor <PERSON>Nicol Williamson</PERSON> is 50.
Singer-actress <PERSON>Joey Heatherton</PERSON> is 44. Actress <PERSON>Mary Crosby</PERSON> is 29.
   Thought for Today: ``You're not supposed to be so blind with
patriotism that you can't face reality. Wrong is wrong no matter
who does it or says it.'' _ <PERSON>Malcolm X</PERSON>, American political activist
(1925-1965).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Wed Sept. 14</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890904-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-04-89 0859EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv14   09-04 0634</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv14,0659</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv14</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thursday, Sept. 14</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE>, the <DATE>257th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 108
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Sept. 14, 1814</DATE>, <PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> wrote his famous poem ``The
Star-Spangled Banner'' after witnessing the British bombardment of
<ORGANIZATION>Fort McHenry</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> during the War of <DATE>1812</DATE>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1807</DATE>, former Vice President <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON> was acquitted of a
misdemeanor charge two weeks after he was found innocent of treason.
   In <DATE>1812</DATE>, the Russians set fire to <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> after an invasion by
<PERSON>Napoleon Bonaparte</PERSON>'s troops.
   In <DATE>1847</DATE>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces under Gen. <PERSON>Winfield Scott</PERSON> took control of
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1901</DATE>, President <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON> died in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, of
gunshot wounds inflicted by an assassin. Vice President <PERSON>Theodore
Roosevelt</PERSON> became president.
   In <DATE>1927</DATE>, modern dance pioneer <PERSON>Isadora Duncan</PERSON> died in Nice,
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, when her scarf became entangled in the wheel of her sports
car.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed the Selective Service Act, providing for
the first peacetime draft in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, a groundbreaking ceremony took place in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> at the
site of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>' world headquarters.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, <PERSON>Gerald R. Ford Jr.</PERSON> upset Rep. <PERSON>Bartel J. Jonkman</PERSON> in
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s Fifth District Republican primary.
   In <DATE>1957</DATE>, President <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> met in <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>,
with <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Orval Faubus</PERSON>, who pledged to uphold court-ordered
school integration, but also pleaded for patience.
   In <DATE>1959</DATE>, the Soviet space probe Luna II became the first manmade
object to reach the moon as it crashed onto the lunar surface.
   In <DATE>1963</DATE>, <PERSON>Mary Ann Fischer</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Aberdeen</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>, gave birth to
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first surviving quintuplets, four girls and a boy.
   In <DATE>1964</DATE>, the third session of the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>21st
Ecumenical Council</ORGANIZATION> _ also known as <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> II _ convened in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>Paul VI</PERSON> declared Mother <PERSON>Elizabeth Ann Bayley Seton</PERSON>
the first U.S.-born saint.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Princess Grace</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Monaco</LOCATION>, who had gained fame as
American movie star <PERSON>Grace Kelly</PERSON>, died at age 52 of injuries she
suffered in a car crash the day before.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>'s president-elect, <PERSON>Bashir Gemayel</PERSON>, was killed by
a bomb that shattered the headquarters of his Lebanese Christian
Phalangist Party in east <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, Shiite Moslem extremists in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> released the Rev.
<PERSON>Benjamin Weir</PERSON>, an American missionary, after holding him captive for
16 months.
   Ten years ago: Actress <PERSON>Jean Seberg</PERSON>, who committed suicide, was
buried in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, the same day the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> admitted that in <DATE>1970</DATE>, it
spread rumors <PERSON>Seberg</PERSON> had become pregnant by a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Black
Panther Party</ORGANIZATION> in order to ``neutralize'' her support for black
militants.
   Five years ago: <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s new coalition government came into
being, with <PERSON>Shimon Peres</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION> as prime minister and
<PERSON>Yitzhak Shamir</PERSON> of the Likud bloc as foreign minister promising to
exchange roles for the second half of their terms.
   One year ago: Hurricane Gilbert, one of the strongest storms on
thousands of residents to flee. Bad weather forced Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON>
to make an unscheduled stop in <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION> during a tour of
southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.
   Today's birthdays: ``Lone Ranger'' <PERSON>Clayton Moore</PERSON> is 75.
Television newscaster <PERSON>Hughes Rudd</PERSON> is 68. Actress <PERSON>Zoe Caldwell</PERSON> is 56.
Feminist author <PERSON>Kate Millett</PERSON> is 55. Actor <PERSON>Nicol Williamson</PERSON> is 51.
Singer-actress <PERSON>Joey Heatherton</PERSON> is 45. Actress <PERSON>Mary Crosby</PERSON> is 30.
   Thought for today: ``My country right or wrong, is a thing no
patriot would think of saying except in a desperate case. It is like
saying, `My mother, drunk or sober!''' _ <ORGANIZATION>G.K. Chesterton</ORGANIZATION>, English
poet and essayist (1874-1936), commenting on a sentiment originally
expressed by <PERSON>Stephen Decatur</PERSON>, American naval officer (1779-1820).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Thursday, Sept. 14</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890213-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-13-89 0733EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv19   02-13 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv19,0422</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Feb. 19</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 19</DATE>, the <DATE>50th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 315
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Feb. 19, 1803</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> voted to accept <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>'s borders and
constitution. However, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> did not get around to formally
ratifying <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> statehood until <DATE>1953</DATE>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1473</DATE>, the astronomer <PERSON>Copernicus</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>Torun</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1807</DATE>, former Vice President <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON> was arrested in
<LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>. He was subsequently tried for treason and acquitted.
   In <DATE>1846</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> state government was formally installed in
<LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1878</DATE>, <PERSON>Thomas Edison</PERSON> received a patent for his phonograph.
   In <DATE>1881</DATE>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> became the first state to prohibit all alcoholic
beverages.
order making possible the wartime internment of Japanese-Americans.
   In <DATE>1945</DATE>, during World War II, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Marines landed on the
Japanese-held island of <LOCATION>Iwo Jima</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Western Pacific</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1963</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> informed President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> that
it would withdraw ``several thousand'' of an estimated 17,000 Soviet
troops in <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, 13 people were found shot to death at a gambling club in
<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Chinatown</LOCATION> district in what became known as the ``Wah Mee
Massacre.'' Two Chinese immigrants were later convicted of the
killings.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, about 150 people were killed when a Spanish jetliner
crashed into a mountain while approaching the airport at <LOCATION>Bilbao</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
   On this date:
   <DATE>Ten years ago</DATE>: <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> millionaire industrialist <PERSON>H. Ross Perot</PERSON>
announced at a <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> news conference that he had financed an
American-led commando squad that rescued two of his employees from
an Iranian prison on <DATE>Feb. 11</DATE>.
   Five years ago: the Winter Olympics officially ended in <LOCATION>Sarajevo</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>, hours after twin brothers <PERSON>Phil</PERSON> and <PERSON>Steve Mahre</PERSON> placed
first and second in the men's slalom event.
   One year ago: A group calling itself the Organization of the
Marine Lt. Col. <PERSON>William R. Higgins</PERSON>, who was in charge of a <ORGANIZATION>United
Nations</ORGANIZATION> truce observer group in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
   Today's birthdays: Former jockey <PERSON>Eddie Arcaro</PERSON> is 73. Singer
<PERSON>Smokey Robinson</PERSON> is 49. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Prince <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON> is 29. Actress
<PERSON>Justine Bateman</PERSON> is 23.
   Thought for today: ``Love is the child of freedom, never that of
domination.'' _ <PERSON>Erich Fromm</PERSON>, German-American psychoanalyst
(1900-1980).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Sunday, Feb. 19</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880822-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-22-88 0718EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv01   08-22 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv01,0524</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv01</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thursday, Sept. 1</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>, the 245th day of <DATE>1988</DATE>. There are 121
   Today's highlight in history:
   Five years ago, on <DATE>Sept. 1, 1983</DATE>, 269 people were killed when a
<ORGANIZATION>Korean Air Lines Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 747 was shot down by a Soviet jet fighter
after the airliner entered Soviet airspace.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1807</DATE>, former Vice President <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON> was found innocent of
treason.
   In <DATE>1878</DATE>, <PERSON>Emma M. Nutt</PERSON> became the first woman telephone operator
in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, for the <ORGANIZATION>Telephone Despatch Company of Boston</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1905</DATE>, <LOCATION>Alberta</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Saskatchewan</LOCATION> entered Confederation as the
eighth and ninth provinces of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1923</DATE>, the Japanese cities of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION> were
devastated by an earthquake that claimed some 150,000 lives.
   In <DATE>1932</DATE>, <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>James J.</PERSON> ``Gentleman Jimmy'' <PERSON>Walker</PERSON>
resigned following charges of graft and corruption in his
administration.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, World War II began as <LOCATION>Nazi Germany</LOCATION> invaded <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>.
Great <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> declared war against <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> two days
later.
   In <DATE>1945</DATE>, Americans received word of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s formal surrender,
ending World War II. (Because of the time difference, it was <DATE>Sept.
2</DATE> in <LOCATION>Tokyo Bay</LOCATION>, where the surrender took place.)
   In <DATE>1951</DATE>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> signed a
mutual defense pact that came to be known as the ANZUS treaty.
   In <DATE>1961</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> ended a moratorium on atomic testing
with an above-ground nuclear explosion in central <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1969</DATE>, a coup in <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> brought <PERSON>Moammar Gadhafi</PERSON> to power.
   In <DATE>1972</DATE>, American <PERSON>Bobby Fischer</PERSON> won the international chess
crown in <LOCATION>Reykjavik</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>, by defeating Soviet player <PERSON>Boris
Spassky</PERSON> in their final match.
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Wayne L. Hays</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ohio</LOCATION>, resigned in the wake
of a scandal in which he admitted having an affair with secretary
<PERSON>Elizabeth Ray</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, in a broadcast speech, called for a
``fresh start'' in the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> peace process, and endorsed
``full autonomy'' for Palestinians living in the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Gaza
Strip</ORGANIZATION>.
   Ten years ago: <ORGANIZATION>The Labor Department</ORGANIZATION> reported the nation's
unemployment rate declined in <DATE>August 1978</DATE> to <PERCENT>5.9 percent</PERCENT>, but
analysts said the overall job picture was little changed.
   Five years ago: <PERSON>Henry</PERSON> ``Scoop'' <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, a 30-year <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
veteran known for his liberal views on social issues and a hawkish
stand on national defense, died in <LOCATION>Everett</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, after suffering
a massive heart attack at age 71.
   One year ago: Peace demonstrator <PERSON>S. Brian Willson</PERSON> lost his legs
when he was hit by a train at the <ORGANIZATION>Concord Naval Weapons Station</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> while protesting weapons shipments to <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>.
   Today's birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>Former Defense</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Melvin Laird</PERSON> is 66.
Actress <PERSON>Yvonne De Carlo</PERSON> is 64. Country singer <ORGANIZATION>Conway Twitty</ORGANIZATION> is 55.
Conductor <PERSON>Seiji Ozawa</PERSON> is 53. Comedian-actress <PERSON>Lily Tomlin</PERSON> is 49.
Singer <PERSON>Barry Gibb</PERSON> is 42.
   Thought for today: ``History is the autobiography of a madman.''
_ <PERSON>Alexander Herzen</PERSON>, Russian author (1812-1870).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06277095 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06277095 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Huey Newton; ... Cops' longtime nemesis  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; BLACK; LEADER; MURDER; TRIAL; CLOSING; ANALYSIS  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Police and prosecutors' "dream" would have been to see longtime Black Panther
nemesis Huey Newton stoop so low as to be killed while trying to rip off a
crack cocaine dealer, but that's not the way it happened, the man prosecuting
Newton's alleged murderer told jurors Tuesday.;   In a fiery second day of
closing arguments in the trial of Tyrone Robinson, Alameda County Deputy
District Attorney Ken Burr lashed out at insinuations by Robinson's attorney
that police were engaged in a "great, big conspiracy" to frame Robinson for
murder.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  'CONSPIRACY' ASSAILED AT NEWTON TRIAL
FIERY ARGUMENTS ARE PRESENTED AT ROBINSON TRIAL  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "It's ironic because 20 years ago, that's the defense <PERSON>Huey P. Newton</PERSON> used"
when he beat charges that he murdered <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> police officer <PERSON>John Frey</PERSON>, <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>
said.;   <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION> attorney <PERSON>Alfons Wagner</PERSON> accused <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> police and prosecutors
of "fast and loose playing with witnesses" who escaped criminal charges
themselves while giving investigators statements that <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> murdered <PERSON>Newton</PERSON>
on a <LOCATION>West Oakland</LOCATION> street to gain status in the Black Guerrilla Family prison
gang.;   <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, 27, an admitted crack dealer who has spent most of his
adult life behind bars, contends he shot <ORGANIZATION>Newton</ORGANIZATION> three times after <PERSON>Newton</PERSON> fired
at him first.;   <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON> said authorities are seeking a murder conviction
rather than believing <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s self defense claim because they don't want
the public to think they are being lenient toward the man responsible for
their nemesis' death.;   In this case, authorities "kiss off anything (pending
against witnesses) because the prosecution was going to look good in the
prosecution of the guy who killed <PERSON>Huey Newton</PERSON> in this town of <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON>
told the jury.;   But prosecutor <PERSON>Burr</PERSON> responded that the conspiracy theory was
fanciful and he told the jury he personally resented it.;   "It implies I am
doing something improper, and illegal, and immoral," <PERSON>Burr</PERSON> said.;   <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON>
contends that the prosecution's key witness, <PERSON>Brian Keith Walton</PERSON>, lied in
stating he saw <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> shoot <PERSON>Newton</PERSON> first while <PERSON>Newton</PERSON>'s hands were in the
air and then twice more through the head as he lay on the ground. <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>, a
friend of <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s who died last year in an apparently unrelated drug-house
shooting, was facing an auto theft charge at the time he gave his taped
statement to investigators.;   During the trial, <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON> also presented a
string of witnesses to talk about violent incidents in <LOCATION>Newton</LOCATION>'s past,
including the killing of <ORGANIZATION>Frey</ORGANIZATION> -- in which a manslaughter conviction against
<ORGANIZATION>Newton</ORGANIZATION> was overturned -- and two other killings in which <ORGANIZATION>Newton</ORGANIZATION> was
implicated. The evidence was shown to demonstrate a lifelong propensity for
violence in support of <ORGANIZATION>Robinson</ORGANIZATION>'s contention that <PERSON>Newton</PERSON> was armed, even
though police found no gun near <LOCATION>Newton</LOCATION>'s body.;   <PERSON>Burr</PERSON> acknowledged that
<PERSON>Newton</PERSON> was a thorn in the side of local law enforcement for more than two
decades, a radical leader who "had a way of pulling law enforcement's chain, a
way of kind of rubbing law enforcement's noses in it." Most importantly, he
got away with <PERSON>Frey</PERSON>'s murder, in the eyes of <ORGANIZATION>Frey</ORGANIZATION>'s fellow <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> police
officers.;   "What better epitaph could the <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Police Department</ORGANIZATION> write
than that . . . he's fallen so low he was killed trying to rip off a crack
dealer," <PERSON>Burr</PERSON> said. "That sings.";   But in defending the investigation, <PERSON>Burr</PERSON>
said, the evidence showed <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> executed a defenseless <PERSON>Newton</PERSON> in the
"stupid" belief he'd "become somebody on the mean streets of <LOCATION>West Oakland</LOCATION>.";  
<PERSON>Burr</PERSON> is expected to complete his statements to the jury today.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  BARRY WITT, Mercury News Oakland Bureau  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Oakland  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Alameda County/Am  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911003  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  572  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, October 3, 1991
00277095,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890802-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-02-89 0157EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SovereigntyCommission 1stLd-Writethru a0414 08-02 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sovereignty Commission, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0414,0598</SECOND>
<HEAD>Records: Businessman Led FBI To Bodies In 1964</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: DELETES extraneous 10th graf, `Warren said...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JACKSON, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> businessman was the paid
informant who in <DATE>1964</DATE> led the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> to the graves of three slain
civil rights workers, according to records of a defunct
segregationist state agency.
   <PERSON>Olen Burrage</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>, received <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> from the
<ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> for this information,'' records from the <ORGANIZATION>Sovereignty Commission</ORGANIZATION>
show. The records quote their own informant.
   Burrage, however, denied that he had anything to do with the
killings.
   A federal judge last week ordered the records of the commission,
which tried to thwart civil rights groups in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and <DATE>1960s</DATE>,
be opened to the public. The judge later stayed his ruling pending
an appeal.
   Portions of the records are included in the personal papers of
former Gov. <PERSON>Paul B. Johnson Jr</PERSON>. The complete records are in the
archives of the <ORGANIZATION>McCain Graduate Library</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Southern Mississippi</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Hattiesburg</LOCATION>. Portions were made available
to The Clarion-Ledger in an agreement with the attorney general.
   Burrage told the newspaper <DATE>Monday</DATE> that he had nothing to do with
the killings of <PERSON>James Chaney</PERSON>, <PERSON>Andrew Goodman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael Schwerner</PERSON>.
He also denied that the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> paid him for information.
   Burrage's attorney, <PERSON>Robert Thomas</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, said his
client was tried on federal charges of conspiracy to violate the
civil rights of the three men in <DATE>1967</DATE> and acquitted.
   ``Hey, look, you can write whatever you want to,'' <PERSON>Burrage</PERSON> said
in a telephone interview with the <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> Clarion-Ledger. ``I
didn't have nothing to do with it. I'm not going to have anything
to do with it now.
   ``I've been harassed for years and years on this mess. I don't
even want to talk to you about it,'' he said.
   Commission investigator <PERSON>A.L. Hopkins</PERSON>' search for the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION>
informant is contained in the commission's records. Hopkins is dead.
   <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> wrote a report on his investigation <DATE>Aug. 6, 1964</DATE>, two
days after the three bodies were found in a grave at the base of a
pond dam under construction on <PERSON>Burrage</PERSON>'s land southwest of
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>.
   ``I have information from a confidential source ... that <PERSON>Mr.
Olen Burrage</PERSON>, a white male who owns the property where the bodies
were found, and who operates a truck line out of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, is the informant who directed the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> to the spot,''
<PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> said in the report.
   <PERSON>Joe Sullivan</PERSON>, who was the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> agent in charge of the <LOCATION>Neshoba
County</LOCATION> investigation, said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that <PERSON>Burrage</PERSON> never received money
for information.
   ``I didn't pay any money to anybody,'' <PERSON>Sullivan</PERSON> said in an
interview from his <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> home. ``I certainly don't know
anything about it.''
   <PERSON>Sullivan</PERSON> said a freelance writer working on the case during the
44 days federal and state officials looked for the three had
   ``That was the genesis of all the talk up there,'' <PERSON>Sullivan</PERSON>
said. ``I think he was affluent enough he could have paid the
reward.
   The <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> file shows an informant led agents to the dam, but
<PERSON>Sullivan</PERSON> refused to identify the individual. ``I have never named
anybody, and I don't want to.''
   The commission was created by the <LOCATION>Mississippi Legislature</LOCATION> on
<DATE>March 22, 1956</DATE>, to preserve segregation in the state. The
commission became inactive in <DATE>1973</DATE> when then-Gov. Bill <PERSON>Waller</PERSON>
vetoed its funding. The Legislature abolished the commission and
ordered its files sealed for 50 years in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06065081 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06065081 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Charles; Burr  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  OBITUARY; GARDEN; WRITING; PROFESSIONAL; NEWSPAPER; SAN-JOSE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Charles J. Burr, Mercury News garden writer for 17 years, died Saturday of
congestive heart failure at his home at The Sequoias in Portola Valley. He was
85.;    Mr. Burr was a garden writer for 52 years. His final Mailbag column
appeared Dec. 28, 1989, in the Mercury News.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CHARLES BURR, GARDEN WRITER  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and attended public schools there. He
received a horticulture degree in <DATE>1927</DATE> from the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Davis</PERSON>, where during the <DATE>1920s</DATE> he reported on sports for the university
newspaper.;    <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> worked for a nursery in <LOCATION>Niles</LOCATION> until <DATE>1936</DATE>, when he
moved to <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. He moved to <LOCATION>Portola Valley</LOCATION> 15 years ago.;    After
inheriting the roof garden nursery at the Emporium store in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, he
was approached by an editor for the then <ORGANIZATION>San Francisco News</ORGANIZATION>, which was located
in the same block. The editor's offer was that <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> write a weekly garden
column in exchange for a byline containing the name of his business.;    After
<PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> submitted about 80 garden articles, the News merged with the <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION> Call Bulletin, owned by <PERSON>William Randolph Hearst</PERSON>, and the garden
column continued, even after <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> closed his nursery.;    After he
submitted his 287th article, the <ORGANIZATION>San Francisco Examiner</ORGANIZATION> became an afternoon
newspaper and absorbed the News-Call Bulletin. <PERSON>Mr. Burr</PERSON> was not part of the
