<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-34334 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes025_s_94012" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-025 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Iran </F>
<H3> <TI>   Sultan of Brunei Concludes Visit, Departs </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  LD0602124094 Tehran IRNA in English 1107 GMT 6 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> LD0602124094 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran IRNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>, Feb 6, IRNA -- <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Sultan Muda Hassanal 
Bolkiah</PERSON> wrapped up his four-day visit to <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> [6 
<DATE>February</DATE>] morning and was officially seen off at <LOCATION>Mehrabad 
International Airport</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s President <PERSON>Akbar 
Hashemi-Ranfsanjani</PERSON>. 
  <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s minister of finance and a number of top-ranking 
officials were also accomanying the sultan in his visit. 
  Before his departure <PERSON>Sultan Bolkiah</PERSON> attended a press 
conference in which President <PERSON>Rafsanjani</PERSON> was also present. 
Sultan <PERSON>Bolkiah</PERSON> termed as "successful" his visit to <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and 
expressed happiness over having the chance to meet with the 
leader of Islamic revolution, <PERSON>Ayatollah 'Ali Khamene'i</PERSON>. He 
remarked that the issues discussed during his talks in <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> 
could be followed up later. He extended an invitation to 
President <PERSON>Hashemi-Rafsanjani</PERSON> to pay an official visit to <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. 
  The <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s sultan pointed to the present crises in the 
Islamic world and underlined the need for the settlement of the 
problems through joint measures at international forums and in 
(OIC). 
  President <PERSON>Hashemi-Ranfsanjani</PERSON> said that in the talks with 
the 
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s delegation, the two countries explored avenues for 
future cooperation and praised sultan <PERSON>Bolkiah</PERSON> for his stands on 
Islamic and international issues which he said were very close 
the sultan's visit to <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and accepted his invitation to pay a 
visit to <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-15263</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJFCBAA3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921006
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  06 OCT 92 / Sultan marks 25 years of wonderful wealth
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KIERAN COOKE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BANDAR SERI BAGAWAN, BRUNEI
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> does not like being called the world's richest
individual. But with a fortune estimated at Dollars 37bn (Pounds 20.7bn), it
is hard to deny being among the wonderfully wealthy.
His <PERSON>Majesty Paduka Seri Baginda Sultan Haji Hassanal Bolkiah Mu'izzaddin
Waddaulah</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sultan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Yang Di-Pertuan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Brunei Darussalam</LOCATION>, is celebrating
25 years as absolute monarch of this small but financially well endowed
state on the west coast of the island of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>.
Yesterday was the main event to mark the anniversary of the sultan's
'ascension' to the throne. The sultan also serves as prime minister and
defence minister. Government is very much a family affair. One brother is
minister of foreign affairs, another is finance minister.
Lavish is one word to describe the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s palace. Large is
another. A banqueting hall where 6,000 sat down to an anniversary meal
yesterday. A palace with 257 lavatories and a total of nearly 1,800 rooms.
Several sultans, princes and princesses, Asian heads of state and other
dignitaries watched the sultan ascend his throne. Tiaras were de rigueur.
Diamonds dazzled.
There have been no elections in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> for more than 30 years. A state of
emergency has been in force ever since British troops were brought in to put
down an uprising in <DATE>1962</DATE>. <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> only became fully independent in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
The sultan, still only in his mid-40s, made a royal anniversary statement.
The present system of monarchical government had served <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> well. There
would be no change. That means no elections and no political parties. Islam
would continue to be emphasised. The sultan would donate Dollars 1m of his
own money to help the Moslems in <LOCATION>Bosnia</LOCATION>.
One of the sultan's many Rolls Royces purred outside. The monarch was taken
a short distance and then off-loaded onto the royal chariot, a rather
unwieldly vehicle the length of a cricket pitch pulled and pushed by a small
army of courtiers.
The sultan is an ex-Sandhurst man. The guards slow-stepped in perfect
formation. The band played Malay music. It played '<ORGANIZATION>Colonel Bogey</ORGANIZATION>'.
Cash from oil and gas has transformed <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. With a population of only
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-34193 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes024_s_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Iran </F>
<H3> <TI>   Rafsanjani, Brunei Sultan To Discuss Islamic Topics </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  LD0302202894 Tehran IRIB Television First Program Network in 
Persian 1530 GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD0302202894 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran IRIB Television First Program Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Persian </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpts] Sir <PERSON>Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>, sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei 
Darussalam</LOCATION>, and his delegation arrived in <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> <TIME>this evening</TIME>. 
Our correspondent reports: [passage omitted] 
  Upon his arrival to <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Bolkiah</PERSON> said that the 
expansion of relations in all fields was the most important aim 
of his visit to our country. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Hashemi-Rafsanjani</PERSON> spoke on the visit of the sultan of 
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, saying: 
  [Begin <PERSON>Rafsanjani</PERSON> recording] <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> is an Islamic country, 
its people are committed Muslims, and its government and people 
are all Muslims and our brothers. 
  In our foreign policy we give priority to Islamic countries. 
I had asked the esteemed sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> to visit <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> to 
discuss common religious issues and the current situation in the 
world of Islam, which necessitates cooperation among Islamic 
countries. Also his excellency can become more familiar with 
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and we can get to know <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> better. We can also assess 
any kind of cooperation which may exist between us and <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. 
In any case, we believe that further cooperation among Islamic 
countries is in the interests of Muslims and their countries. 
We hope to pave the way for further cooperation and become 
closer to each other. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-10851</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKCDEAFNFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931103
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 NOV 93 / International Company News: Sultan adds New York hotel to
his collection
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KIERAN COOKE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KUALA LUMPUR
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
SULTAN <PERSON>Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> collects luxury hotels like the rest of us
collect postage stamps.
But when you have a personal fortune of Dollars 37bn you can afford to be a
bit choosy about where you put your head down for the night.
The Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> (left) this week agreed to pay Dollars 202m for the
luxurious <ORGANIZATION>New York Palace Hotel</ORGANIZATION> on Madison Avenue. The <PERSON>Sultan</PERSON> and his family
also own the top of the range <ORGANIZATION>Beverly Hills Hotel</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>Dorchester</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
Closer to home, the Sultan controls two Hyatt hotels in <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>. When the
<PERSON>Sultan</PERSON> held a sit-down dinner party last year at his palace in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> for
nearly 6,000 people as part of celebrations of his 25 years on the throne,
Hyatt chefs and waiters were flown in from <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>.
If the Sultan tires of hotel living on his frequent trips abroad there are
alternatives available. The Sultan's family are believed to have at least
two houses in <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION>.
There are various houses and flats dotted round <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. Then there is the
main British residence - a country house conveniently situated close to
<LOCATION>Heathrow</LOCATION> airport. The <PERSON>Sultan</PERSON> also has a mansion in central <LOCATION>Kuala Lumpur</LOCATION>.
The Sultan's latest acquisition has an interesting history. The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
Palace Hotel was once called the <ORGANIZATION>Helmsley Palace</ORGANIZATION>, after <PERSON>Mrs Leona Helmsley</PERSON>,
once the most famous hotelier in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and a leading <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> socialite.
But the <PERSON>Helmsley</PERSON> hotel empire came crashing down in <DATE>1989</DATE> when <PERSON>Mrs Helmsley</PERSON>,
known as the 'Queen of Mean' for her treatment of hotel employees, was
sentenced to imprisonment for tax evasion and mail fraud.
As the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s investment advisers were putting the final touches
to documents buying the old <ORGANIZATION>Helmsley Palace</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mrs Helmsley</PERSON> herself was moving
into less salubrious hotel accommodation - a halfway-house low-cost hotel
just down the road from her old stamping ground.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    MYZ  Malaysia, Asia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7011 Hotels and Motels.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Facilities.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-12983</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJRAMAD5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921017
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  17 OCT 92 / Despatches: Dinner for 5,750 please, James - Brunei / Kieran
Cooke sups with a sultan but finds the six-hour wait tedious
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KIERAN COOKE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
WHEN THE richest man in the world issues a dinner invitation, it is best to
be punctual. The sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, estimated to be worth a cool Dollars 37bn
(Pounds 20.7bn) at the last count, was throwing a little anniversary bash
marking his 25 years on the throne.
Dinner was at 7.30. At 5.30, a few select members of the international media
arrived at the palace gates. The sultan is known to be a bit of a stickler
when it comes to dress. Slept-in suits were brushed down. Scuffed shoes were
given a quick wipe. Stained ties were adjusted. The man from Russian TV
looked in need of a snort of vodka.
It was going to be a cosy affair. Just us, the sultan, a sprinkling of Malay
royalty, a layer of heads of state, a few prime ministers added as garnish.
Plus a few thousand other dignitaries, even a few ordinary people. A mere
5,750 altogether, all seated in the same room.
You either hide your wealth or flaunt it. Sultan <PERSON>Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>, 29th
sultan and absolute ruler of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, is not afraid of spending a bob or two.
His palace is described as the biggest in the world. There are nearly 2,000
rooms. There is a throne room that can seat 2,000. Marble covers more than
12 acres of wall. Carpets as lush as newly-fallen snow. Chandeliers that
weigh a ton apiece. Gold that hurts the eyes. Nearly 300 lavatories.
The meal was running late. No one can raise a fork until the sultan gives
the word. We waited. The dining room was a cross between <LOCATION>Versailles</LOCATION> and high
season at Butlins.
'G'day,' said an Australian waiter, one of more than 700 catering staff
flown in for the occasion. 'Not a bad little party, eh?'
In the kitchens, chefs sweltered and tempers frayed. Plates of prawns
collided with sides of mutton. The meat for the meal was flown in from
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> where the sultan's ranch is twice the size of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> itself.
More waiting. A few of the down top table guests sloped in. Prince <PERSON>Edward</PERSON> -
representing his mother, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON> - sat in the corner by
the royal serving hatch. A Thai prince smiled serenely at the ceiling. A
Malay princess adjusted a troublesome tiara.
The sultan, still only in his mid-40s, has two wives and 10 children. And a
great deal else besides. Two palaces in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> plus a hotel in <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION> and
another which he bought, then sold, to the <ORGANIZATION>Brunei Investment Agency</ORGANIZATION> (BIA), a
secretive organisation that handles an estimated Dollars 35bn of the
country's international investments.
The sultan has a mansion in <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>. He owns the <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> hotel in the
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, plus another couple of houses in <LOCATION>Tinseltown</LOCATION>.
His father was something of an anglophile who even had a special <ORGANIZATION>Winston
Churchill</ORGANIZATION> museum built in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. That has been closed but the present
sultan - who spent time at <LOCATION>Sandhurst</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s military college for
officers - still maintains strong British links.
He bought the <LOCATION>Dorchester</LOCATION> hotel in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> but sold it recently to the <ORGANIZATION>BIA</ORGANIZATION>.
There are various flats and houses dotted round the British capital. The
sultan's main residence is a country house situated on the flight path to
<LOCATION>Heathrow</LOCATION> airport.
The sultan is partial to planes. He bought his own 747 recently and has a
couple of other jets in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. Then there are the automobiles: estimates of
the number of his Rolls-Royces vary between 135 and 157. Plus a whole
starting grid of sports cars.
Dinner was getting very late. There were ugly mutterings from the
international press. No alcohol allowed in this increasingly Islamic state.
Diplomats, dressed in their full regalia, perspired quietly; their wives
glowed.
The sultan loves polo. He flies in whole teams to play special tournaments.
His horses are said to have air-conditioned stables.
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> has a battalion of Gurkhas stationed in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. The sultan has his
own Gurkha battalion, made up of retired soldiers who now form the palace
guard. Any mutinous sounds from the waiting diners and the kukris might be
out.
Army chaps were the only ones to maintain stiff upper lips throughout the
long wait. They would not even taste a tumbler of water until the sultan -
always referred-to among expatriates as 'HRH' - had first lifted a glass.
It was 9.45 pm when the sultan finally arrived. The whole family was in
attendance. The sultan doubles up as prime minister and minister of defence.
A brother is foreign minister, another is minister of finance.
Sultan, princes, princesses and prime ministers sat down, stock still. Not a
word was spoken. Just the sound of a thousand camera shutters clicking.
The press were ordered back to table. The sultan had given the word. Food
was fallen on. The Russian fantasised about the cold of a <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> winter.
'And then you drink - like that,' he said, knocking back a pineapple juice.
We rose. 'Tut, tut,' said the army. Dammit all, everyone has to wait till
<ORGANIZATION>HRH</ORGANIZATION> has finished. We escaped through the kitchens.
'You people have no bloody decorum,' said the Australian waiter, smiling. We
agreed. Six hours of dinner was enough, even if it was with the richest man
in the world.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
Weekend Page 18
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-34194 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes024_s_94009" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Iran </F>
<H3> <TI>   Further Cooperation Welcomed </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  LD0302234094 Tehran Voice of the Islamic Republic of Iran 
First Program Network in Persian 2030 GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD0302234094 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran Voice of the Islamic Republic of Iran 
First Program Network </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Persian </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] During their talks <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> [3 <DATE>February</DATE>], the 
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> discussed and exchanged views on the latest world 
developments, regional issues, and bilateral cooperation between 
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. 
  During the talks, <PERSON>Hashemi-Rafsanjani</PERSON> thanked <PERSON>Hassanal 
Bolkiah</PERSON> 
for visiting <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and expressed the hope that mutual cooperation 
would further deepen in all cultural, political, economic and 
technical fields. 
  The president added: Our foreign policy gives a particular 
priority to cooperation with Islamic countries -- your country 
is one of them -- and that is a very good factor for the further 
expansion of cooperation between us. Hashemi-Rafsanjani added: 
We are aware of your satisfactory stances vis-a-vis the problem 
of <LOCATION>Bosnia-Herzegovina</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Islamic Conference Organization</ORGANIZATION> 
[ICO]. We hope to be able to increase the <ORGANIZATION>ICO</ORGANIZATION> activities. 
  Our country's president pointed out the existence of the 
Cooperation Organization</ORGANIZATION> in the two mainly Muslim regions, and 
described cooperation between <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> as an effective 
factor that can contribute toward further cooperation between 
the two regions. 
  Hashemi-Rafsanjani also stressed the need for the two 
countries' cooperation in the oil and gas industries and 
announced <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s readiness to help <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> with its technical and 
scientific needs in those industries. The president also 
welcomed the two countries' cooperation in cultural and artistic 
fields. 
  Then the Sultan of <PERSON>Brunei Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>, thanked our 
country's president for his kind remarks and praised the certain 
and valuable status of the Islamic Republic of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> at global 
levels and said: <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> has always supported <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s principled 
and progressive stance in international circles and believes 
itself in such stances. 
  He added: We cooperate very well within the <ORGANIZATION>ICO</ORGANIZATION> and the 
Non-Aligned Movement. We have always condemned the aggression 
against the Bosnian Muslims and are ready to help them. We are 
ready to cooperate in the oil and gas industries and hope to be 
able to witness the expansion of relations between the two 
countries in all fields, particularly cultural fields. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871001-0110 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sultan of Brunei to Pay $200 Million
For Beverly Hills Hotel, Sources Say
---
By Kathleen A. Hughes
<DD> 10/01/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL) </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, one of the world's wealthiest men, has agreed to buy the legendary <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> Hotel from oil tycoon <PERSON>Marvin Davis</PERSON> for more than <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY>, hotel sources said. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON> purchased the <ORGANIZATION>Beverly Hills Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, also known as the <ORGANIZATION>Pink Palace</ORGANIZATION> for its distinctive coloring and its star-studded clientele, from the family of <PERSON>Ivan F. Boesky</PERSON> and others for about <MONEY>$135 million</MONEY> last <DATE>December</DATE>. 
The sale followed <PERSON>Mr. Boesky</PERSON>'s <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> settlement of insider-trading charges brought by the <ORGANIZATION>Securities and Exchange Commission</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The hotel sources said <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON> and the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> have agreed on a price, and the transaction is expected to close sometime next week. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON> couldn't be reached, and spokesmen for him declined to comment. 

   The purchase of the posh hotel was the jewel in <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON>'s growing block of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> real estate and restored some of the glamour the investor gave up by selling <ORGANIZATION>Twentieth Century Fox Film Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch</ORGANIZATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON> also said, after he bought the hotel, that the purchase had personal meaning, because he spent his honeymoon in the hotel and once lived in one of its bungalows. 

   Since the purchase of the hotel, <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON> has frequently presided over breakfasts in the hotel's <ORGANIZATION>Polo Lounge</ORGANIZATION>, a popular breakfast locale for the entertainment industry. 

   Hotel sources also said they understood the sultan was reportedly a losing bidder in the <DATE>December</DATE> sale of the hotel but persisted in trying to buy the hotel from <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON>. 
"The guy finally came back with a price that was so far and away unbelievable that (<PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON>) just had to say OK," said one hotel source, adding, "<PERSON>Marvin</PERSON> has a deep personal attachment to the place." 

   Another factor in <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON>'s decision to sell the 75-year-old hotel was his discovery that renovation costs would be higher than originally estimated, according to the source. 
<PERSON>Michael Ullman</PERSON>, the hotel's general manager, has said the hotel was planning "substantial renovations" and even the addition of a nightclub. 
Many of the hotel's competitors, including the <LOCATION>Beverly Wilshire Hotel</LOCATION>, are being renovated. 

   A price-tag for the hotel of more than <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY> wouldn't make a very big dent in the net worth of the sultan. 
In its current issue, Fortune magazine pronounced him the world's richest man, estimating his personal net worth at <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY> or more. 
The sultan, who rules <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, a tiny country on the oil-rich island of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>, lives in a 1,788-room palace and owns more than 200 polo ponies, according to the story. 

   The sultan couldn't be reached for comment. 

   The hotel wouldn't be the sultan's first. 
He snapped up <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s elegant <LOCATION>Dorchester</LOCATION> Hotel 2 1/2 years ago for a price that wasn't disclosed from <ORGANIZATION>Regent International Hotels</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 
A hotel spokeswoman at the time said the price paid was "certainly in excess" of the <MONEY>$52 million</MONEY> that <ORGANIZATION>Regent</ORGANIZATION> had paid for the <LOCATION>Hyde Park</LOCATION> property less than a year earlier. 

   The sultan entered the national spotlight earlier this year when the congressional investigation into the Iran-Contra affair revealed that he had contributed <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> to the Contra rebels at the request of the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration. 
That contribution was eventually returned to the Sultan after it was deposited in the wrong Swiss bank account. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-48741 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas019_h_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-019 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brunei, Malaysia &amp; Singapore </F>
<F P=101> Brunei </F>
<H3> <TI>   Sultan, Albania's Berisha Meet, View Relations </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU2701164494 Tirana Radio Tirana Network in Albanian 1430 
GMT 27 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> AU2701164494 </F>
<F P=104>  Tirana Radio Tirana Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Albanian </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] [Announcer] President of the Republic <PERSON>Sali Berisha</PERSON> 
and the delegation accompanying him started a visit in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> 
today. Let us listen to a telephone report by Aida Shehu: 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Shehu</ORGANIZATION>] <TIME>This morning</TIME>, before his departure from <LOCATION>Langkawi</LOCATION> 
island, President <PERSON>Berisha</PERSON> held another meeting with press 
representatives, who wanted to know about <LOCATION>Albania</LOCATION>, its political 
and economic situation, his personal impressions about this free 
area, and so on. After the meeting, President <PERSON>Berisha</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs. 
Berisha</PERSON>, and the delegation accompanying him visited the 
Makamasuri museum, escorted by country authorities. There, 
<PERSON>Berisha</PERSON> attended the natives' ritual and honored the tomb of 
Princess Masuri. 
  After this visit, the president left <LOCATION>Langkawi</LOCATION> and started 
for 
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> on an official visit. As soon as he arrived, <PERSON>Berisha</PERSON> was 
received by the sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, His Majesty Sir <PERSON>Hassanal 
Bolkiah</PERSON> at an audience at the <ORGANIZATION>King's Palace</ORGANIZATION>. After a short 
meeting with the delegation members, President <PERSON>Berisha</PERSON> and his 
majesty held close talks for 30 minutes. The meeting discussed 
the relations between both countries, their expansion, the 
support that <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> may give to <LOCATION>Albania</LOCATION> to set up the 
infrastructure, and projects aimed at this goal. His majesty, 
the sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> assessed <LOCATION>Albania</LOCATION>'s achievements highly, 
assessed its stabilizing role and its realistic contribution to 
the situation in the region, and guaranteed the president his 
support. 
  This evening, the <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> foreign minister will host a dinner 
to honor President <PERSON>Berisha</PERSON>, to which he has invited the highest 
personalities of the political life in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> as well 
representatives of the diplomatic corps accredited here. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900309-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-09-90 1336EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Harrods     03-09 0273</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Harrods,0284</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sultan Of Brunei Denies Role in House of Fraser Bid</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> denied any role in
the <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> takeover of <ORGANIZATION>Harrods</ORGANIZATION> owner <ORGANIZATION>House of Fraser PLC</ORGANIZATION> by the
Al-Fayed brothers in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   The sultan said in a statement that he had no part in the
takeover, nor did he provide funds to <LOCATION>Mohamed</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Salah</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ali
Al-Fayed</PERSON> to help them buy it.
   The ruler of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> acknowledged that a power of attorney
privilege was granted to <PERSON>Mohamed Al-Fayed</PERSON> to buy the <LOCATION>Dorchester</LOCATION>
Hotel for the sultan.
   If this privilege was used for something else, it was done so
totally without the sultan's authority or knowledge, the statement
said.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the government released a report by <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Trade and Industry</ORGANIZATION> inspectors saying the Al-Fayeds lied about their
wealth and background to succeed with the bid and that it was
likely they used their association with the sultan to enable them
to obtain funds toward the takeover.
   They said they believed the Al-Fayeds did not have enough money
of their own to buy the retailing group.
   ``The evidence pointing to <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> is very strong indeed,'' the
report said, ``and we have conveyed our findings to the sultan. Our
views stand.''
   The Al-Fayeds deny they misled anyone and maintain that they
paid for <ORGANIZATION>House of Fraser</ORGANIZATION> with their own cash.
   Trade Secretary <PERSON>Nicholas Ridley</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he would not seek
disqualification of any of the company's directors.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Serious Fraud Office</ORGANIZATION> and the Director of the <ORGANIZATION>Public
Prosecutions</ORGANIZATION> announced last week they would not pursue a criminal
prosecution in connection with the takeover.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890707-0180 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-07-89 2239EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Sultan 1stLd-Writethru a0578 07-07 0815</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sultan, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0578,0839</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sultan's Birthday Overshadows International Conference</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERT 2 grafs after 14th graf, `More than...' ADDING marital
status, children. Picks up 15th graf, `The royal...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KENNETH L. WHITING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BANDAR SERI BEGAWAN, Brunei (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Association of Southeast
Asian Nations</ORGANIZATION> is in town for it 22nd meeting and the streets are
bedecked with bunting, so why do the decorations feature the number
43 instead of 22?
   Because the bunting isn't for the delegates; it's for the sultan,
who turns 43 on <DATE>July 15</DATE>.
   The sultan, who has 37 words in his name and title, is worth <MONEY>$30
billion</MONEY> and takes very good care of the 241,000 people over whom he
has absolute sway.
   He is <PERSON>Duli Yang Maha Mulia Paduka Seri Baginda Sultan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Yang
Di-Pertuan Negeri Brunei Awang Muda Hassanal Bolkiah Mu'issaddin
Waddaulah Ibni Duli Yang Teramat Mulia Paduka Seri Begawan Sultan
Awang Muda Omar Ali Aifuddin Saifuddin Sa'adul Khairi Waddin</PERSON>.
   Most people just call him Sir <PERSON>Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>.
   His sultanate, 2,226 square miles on the north coast of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>,
sits on a huge pool of oil and natural gas.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION> says Sir Hassanal is the
world's richest individual becauwe oil income and foreign currency
reserves totaling almost <MONEY>$30 billion</MONEY> are ``effectively at his
disposal.''
   Fortune magazine confirmed his enormous wealth and said <PERSON>King Fahd</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION> was second with <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>.
   Secular, religious and military power rest with the sultan, a
hereditary ruler who is head of state, prime minister, defense
minister and commander of the armed forces.
   One of his brothers is in charge of foreign affairs and another
heads the <ORGANIZATION>Finance Ministry</ORGANIZATION> of this former British protectorate,
which became fully independent five years ago.
   As well as being the richest person in the world, Sir Hassanal
lives with his relatives in the world's biggest palace _ a complex
of buildings built with 38 types of marble on a 300-acre hill near
the <LOCATION>Brunei River</LOCATION>.
   In case friends decide to stay over, it has 1,778 rooms and 257
toilets. There are 564 chandeliers, 18 elevators, 44 staircases and
a banquet hall that seats 4,000.
   His majesty's polo ponies have air-conditioned quarters.
   More than 2,000 workers completed the Istana (palace) <PERSON>Nurul Imam</PERSON>
for independence in <DATE>1984</DATE> and the sultan never said how much it cost.
Guesses at the time started at <MONEY>$250 million</MONEY>, but suppliers who know
what went into it _ including 22-carat gold tiles on interior arches
_ say at least <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY>.
   The sultan has two wives. He was married first to Her Majesty the
<PERSON>Raja Isteri Pengiran Anak Saleha</PERSON> and then to Her Royal Highness
Pengiran Isteri Hajjah Mariam. He has three sons and six daughters.
Saleha, the sultan's first cousin, resides in the <LOCATION>Nurul Imam</LOCATION>.
   Mariam (born <ORGANIZATION>Mariam Bell</ORGANIZATION>) keeps house in a smaller and newer
palace, <LOCATION>Nurulizza</LOCATION>, 14 miles from the capital. Their marriage caused
a rift between the sultan and his father, <PERSON>Sir Omar</PERSON>, because she was
a commoner and part Japanese. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> occupied <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> during World War
II. The sultan met <PERSON>Mariam</PERSON> when she was a hostess on the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Brunei
Airlines</ORGANIZATION>.
   The royal family, in power for 29 generations, ensures continued
support for autocracy by providing subsidized food, fuel, housing
and free education and medical care. There is no personal income tax.
   Shortly after independence, <LOCATION>Sir Hassanal</LOCATION> was quoted as saying his
subjects enjoyed ``a good life. Why should they want more?''
   Bruneians seem content. The happiest probably are the civil
servants, who make up <PERCENT>46 percent</PERCENT> of the work force of 85,000. Along
with standard benefits, they get free pensions and interest-free
loans to buy cars and houses.
   Traffic jams are common in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, which has one car for every
2.3 people.
   Prince <PERSON>Mohamed Bolkiah</PERSON>, the foreign minister, told reporters
covering the conference: ``The people seem to be very happy with the
way we are running things. The people accept it.''
   They certainly are spared worries that trouble the foreigners
here assembled. There is no national debt, no trade deficit, no
balance of payments problem and the budget always shows a surplus.
Oil and natural gas account for <PERCENT>99 percent</PERCENT> of exports.
   Sir <PERSON>Hassanal</PERSON> was attending <ORGANIZATION>Sandhurst Military College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>
when his father abdicated in <DATE>1967</DATE> and he was summoned home at age 21
to take the throne.
   Sultan Omar continued to run things from behind the scenes for
another 15 years, however, and the polo-playing young potentate took
the opportunity to build an international reputation as a playboy.
   <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s last flirtation with an elected parliament was in <DATE>1962</DATE>,
when it was still a British protectorate.
   The Parti Rakyat <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, since outlawed, won all 16 seats on the
<ORGANIZATION>Legislative Council</ORGANIZATION>. Sultan Omar refused to convene the council and
an uprising ensued.
   Britain crushed the rebellion and a state of emergency declared
at the time remains in force.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890710-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-89 1813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SultanBurglarized     07-10 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sultan Burglarized,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burglars Loot London Home of Sultan's Brother</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Burglars stole <MONEY>$6.5 million</MONEY> worth of jewelry and
cash from the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> home of Prince <PERSON>Jefri Bolkiah</PERSON>, whose brother is
a sultan considered to be the world's richest man, police said
<DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The intruders entered through a first-floor window of the red
brick house in the north <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> district of <ORGANIZATION>East Finchley</ORGANIZATION> late in
the afternoon <DATE>Thursday</DATE> or in the <TIME>evening</TIME>, said Detective
Superintendent <PERSON>David Staff</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> Yard.
   Police said details were being kept confidential at the sultan's
request.
   Prince <PERSON>Jefri</PERSON> is the youngest brother of the 42-year-old sultan of
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, who has 37 words in his name and title but is generally
called Sir <PERSON>Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>. The sultan is worth an estimated <MONEY>$30
world's richest man.
   Staff, the detective superintendent, said the prince's wife,
<PERSON>Princess Norhayti</PERSON>, was not at home when the robbery occurred.
   ``No physical violence'' was involved, he said, and the thieves
had ``no contact'' with any of the household staff or security
guards. He would not elaborate. He also would not say whether the
house had been ransacked or if selected items were taken.
   <PERSON>Fred McColl</PERSON>, the family's lawyer, said additional security
measures had been taken but he would not give details. Asked whether
former employees were being questioned, he replied: ``We are
questioning a number of people.''
   Newspaper reports said the gang must have had intimate knowledge
of the complex security systems and alarms in the house.
   <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, on the northwest coast of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>, is rich in oil and
natural gas and the revenues go to the sultan, who also is prime
minister and defense minister. It is a former British protectorate
and became fully independent on <DATE>Dec. 31, 1983</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s record robbery was of an estimated <MONEY>$48 million</MONEY> from a
safe deposit center in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Knightsbridge</LOCATION> district in <DATE>1987</DATE>. The
center's owner, <PERSON>Parvez Latiff</PERSON>, and three other men were convicted of
the crime last <DATE>January</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910923-0148
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910923-0148.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Letters to the Editor:
   Here's a Rich One
</HL>
<DATE>
09/23/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A15
</SO>
<RE>
BRUNEI (BX)
FAR EAST (FE)
</RE>
<LP>
   In regard to your Aug. 22 article calling the sultan of
Brunei the world's richest man: Here is a story that was told
to me by his relative, the sultan of Johor:
   Some months ago, the sultan of Brunei visited Barney's,
and selected a few suits and shirts. When he tried to pay
with his American Express traveler's checks, the cashier
requested a driver's license and two other forms of ID.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   When the sultan told her that he didn't have a driver's
license, she said, "Sorry, it's against store policy for me
to accept your check."
   At that moment, one of the sultan's quick-thinking
bodyguards presented the cashier with a <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> dollar (Guess
whose portrait is on the money?) and inquired, "Will you
accept this as a photo ID?"
   <LOCATION>Keith Green
   New York</LOCATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910822-0080
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910822-0080.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Sultan of Brunei Is Richest
   In the World, Says Fortune
</HL>
<DATE>
08/22/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B2
</SO>
<CO>
   TWX
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Brunei's Sultan, Haji Hassanal Bolkiah
Mu'Izzaddin Waddaulah, is still the world's richest man --
and considerably richer than he was last year, says Fortune
magazine.
   The sultan, whose wealth is mainly in oil and gas reserves
and real estate, now has $31 billion, up from $25 billion in
1990, according to Fortune's annual survey of billionaires.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   This year, there are 202 billionaires on Fortune's list,
up from 182 in <DATE>1990</DATE>, with 41 new billionaires added and 26
delisted. Average net worth is <MONEY>$2.7 billion</MONEY>, up <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>
form <DATE>1990</DATE>'s average.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> has 60 billionaires, the most of any country,
including the second-biggest billionaire, <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, who is
worth, along with his family, <MONEY>$21.1 billion</MONEY>. <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has 23
billionaires, including <PERSON>Prince Albert</PERSON> von Thurn und Taxis; at
eight years old, he is the youngest billionaire on Fortune's
list. <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> have 23, 14 and 12,
respectively.
   Newcomers to the list are <PERSON>Donald</PERSON> and <PERSON>Doris Fisher</PERSON>, <MONEY>$1.9
billion</MONEY>, who founded the <ORGANIZATION>GAP Inc.</ORGANIZATION> clothing chain; and <PERSON>Samuel
Heyman</PERSON>, <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY>, who owns most of chemical maker <ORGANIZATION>GAF</ORGANIZATION>.
Among the fallen are <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Harold Simmons</PERSON>, both
victims of wilting stocks.
   The magazine also profiled 13 billionairesses. Leading the
pack was Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, whose net worth was reported at
<MONEY>$10.7 billion</MONEY>. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> cosmetics queen <PERSON>Estee Lauder</PERSON> and
family are second, with <MONEY>$5.2 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890710-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-89 1554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-SultanBurglarized 2ndLd-Writethru a0549 07-10 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sultan Burglarized, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0549,0394</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burglars Loot London Home of Brother of World's Richest Man</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 6 grafs to CORRECT that home owned by sultan's brother,
not sultan; picks up 4th graf, ``No physical...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Burglars broke into the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> home of the brother
of the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> and stole <MONEY>$6.5 million</MONEY> worth of jewelry and
cash, police said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   Thieves broke in through a first floor window of the house in the
north <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> district of <LOCATION>East Finchley</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in the late
afternoon or evening, said Detective Superintendent <PERSON>David Staff</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> Yard.
   Details of the robbery had been kept secret at the sultan's
request, police said.
   The red-brick house is owned by the sultan's youngest brother,
<PERSON>Prince Jefri</PERSON>, a spokesman for the sultan said, and not by the sultan
himself as <ORGANIZATION>The Daily Express</ORGANIZATION>, The Daily Telegraph and the domestic
news agency <ORGANIZATION>Press Association</ORGANIZATION> had earlier reported.
   The sultan is the richest man in the world.
   Staff said the prince's wife, <PERSON>Princess Norhayti</PERSON>, was not home at
the time of the robbery.
   ``No physical violence'' was involved, the officer said, and the
thieves had ``no contact'' with any of the household staff or
security guards. He would not elaborate. Nor would he say whether
the house had been ransacked or if selected items were taken.
   Family lawyer <PERSON>Fred McColl</PERSON> said additional security measures have
been installed, but he would not give details. Asked whether former
employees are being questioned, he replied, ``We are questioning a
number of people.''
   Newspaper reports today said the gang must have had intimate
knowledge of the complex security systems and alarms in the house.
   <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, on the northwest coast of the island of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>, is rich
in oil and natural gas and the revenues go to the sultan, Sir <PERSON>Muda
Hassanal Bolkiah Mu'izuddin Waddaulah</PERSON>, 42, who is also prime
minister and defense minister.
   The sultan's country of less than 250,000 people is a member of
the 48-nation <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth of Britain</ORGANIZATION> and its former colonies. His
personal fortune is estimated at more than <MONEY>$23 billion</MONEY>.
   The British robbery record is an estimated <MONEY>$48 million</MONEY> from a
safe deposit center in <DATE>1987</DATE> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Knightsbridge</LOCATION> district. The
center's owner, <PERSON>Parvez Latiff</PERSON>, and three other men were convicted of
the crime in <DATE>January</DATE> and jailed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-27403 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi036_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-036 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  23 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Southeast Asia &amp; Pacific </F>
<H3> <TI>   Jiang Zemin Greets Sultan Bolkiah on Brunei National Day </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK2202140794 Beijing China Radio International in Malay 1230 
GMT 22 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK2202140794 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing China Radio International </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Malay </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Message from President <PERSON>Jiang Zemin</PERSON> to <PERSON>Sultan Haji Hassanal </F>
Bolkiah</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>State of Brunei Darussalam</ORGANIZATION> on the <DATE>10th 
anniversary of the National Day</DATE> of the <ORGANIZATION>State of Brunei 
Darussalam</ORGANIZATION> dated 22 <DATE>February</DATE>] 
  [Text] <PERSON>Bandar Seri Begawan</PERSON>, 
  <PERSON>Your Majesty Sultan Haji Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>, 
  On the occasion of the <DATE>10th anniversary of the National Day</DATE> 
of the <ORGANIZATION>State of Brunei Darussalam</ORGANIZATION>, I on behalf of the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese 
Government</ORGANIZATION> and people and on my own behalf would like to extend 
warm congratulations and wishes to you and to the government and 
people of the <ORGANIZATION>State of Brunei Darussalam</ORGANIZATION>. 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Brunei Darussalam</LOCATION>, friendly relations and cooperation 
between the two nations have developed smoothly. In particular, 
your successful state visit to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> last year elevated 
relations between the two nations to a new stage. 
  I am confident that friendly relations and cooperation 
between the two nations, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brunei Darussalam</LOCATION>, which were 
coexistence, will be further developed. 
  May the <ORGANIZATION>State of Brunei Darussalam</ORGANIZATION> prosper and its people be 
happy. 
  [Signed] <PERSON>Jiang Zemin</PERSON>, president of the People's Republic of 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 
  [Dated] 22 <DATE>February 1994</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871007-0036 </DOCNO>
<HL> Beverly Hills Hotel Is Sold
By Davis to Sajahtera Inc.</HL>
<DD> 10/07/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL) </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Oil man <PERSON>Marvin Davis</PERSON> said he sold the <ORGANIZATION>Beverly Hills Hotel to Sajahtera Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 
The price wasn't disclosed. 

   Spokesmen for <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON> declined to provide any details about Sajahtera or to elaborate on a short press release. 
However, as previously reported, hotel sources have indicated the hotel was sold to the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> for more than <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON> purchased the hotel from the family of <PERSON>Ivan F. Boesky</PERSON> and others for about <MONEY>$135 million</MONEY> in <DATE>December</DATE>. 
The sale followed <PERSON>Mr. Boesky</PERSON>'s <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> settlement of insider-trading charges brought by the <ORGANIZATION>Securities and Exchange Commission</ORGANIZATION>. 

   In its current issue, Fortune magazine pronounced the sultan the world's richest man, estimating his net worth at <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>. 
The sultan, who rules <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, a tiny country on the oil-rich island of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>, lives in a 1,788-room palace and owns more than 200 polo ponies, according to the story. 

   The release said the new owners intend to pursue existing plans for "major improvements" to the posh pink hotel, which has 260 rooms and cottages. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890213-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-13-89 1328EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Asia'sLastRoyals Adv19   02-13 1209</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Asia's Last Royals, Adv 19,1236</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Feb. 19, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Asia's Few Remaining Monarchs Changing with the Times</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>BY DENIS D. GRAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On a continent where kings were once
revered as gods, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>'s half-dozen surviving monarchies include a
diverse clutch of modernizing kings and a sultan who wields absolute
power.
   King <PERSON>Bhumibol Adulyadej</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>, the world's longest reigning
monarch following the death <DATE>Jan. 7</DATE> of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Emperor Hirohito</PERSON>, has
initiated several thousand rural projects and spends much of each
year in the countryside personally helping peasants to design
irrigation canals, improve crops and combat disease.
   Aside from <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, monarchs also reign in <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Bhutan</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Himalayias</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>.
   Unlike his remote predecessors in <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION>, Harvard-educated <PERSON>King
Birendra</PERSON> criss-crosses his mountainous nation and has set a goal of
fulfilling the basic needs of an impoverished populace by the year
<DATE>2000</DATE>.
   In the kingdom of <LOCATION>Bhutan</LOCATION>, <PERSON>King Jigme Singye Wangchuk</PERSON> pores over
economic development plans and almost daily deals with petitions
submitted by subjects.
   Hirohito, whose funeral will be held <DATE>Feb. 24</DATE>, is widely credited
with having helped <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s postwar economic miracle by preserving
national unity and traditional virtues through his symbolic role.
But the late emperor, who renounced his divinity after <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s
defeat in World War II, spent most of his 62 years on the
Chrysanthemum Throne behind the walls of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Palace</ORGANIZATION>.
   His son and successor, Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>, 55, broke with tradition
by marrying a commoner and has travelled with his family by train,
thrown out the first ball at baseball games and mixed with his
fellow Japanese at numerous public functions.
   Though he is expected to breach some of the barriers between
emperor and subjects, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> is unlikely to interact as intimately
with his subjects and their daily problems as do the other Asian
royals _ nor wield anywhere near as much tangible power.
   The most powerful and richest of the continent's five remaining
hereditary monarchs is <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s Sultan <PERSON>Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>, an absolute
ruler who resides in a 1,788-room palace and keeps some of his 200
horses in air-conditioned stables. Fortune magazine in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> named him the world's richest man, with assets
estimated at <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>.
   Besides being head of state, he is also prime minister and
defense minister and has included two of his brothers in the Cabinet
to help rule over the oil-rich nation about the size of <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> on
the north coast of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION> island.
   <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s sultan harkens back to days when the pomp, pageantry and
proclamations of hundreds of bluebloods _ kings, princes, sultans,
maharajahs, newabs and nizams _ were as vital a part of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> as its
rice fields.
   But by mid-century, royal ranks had been thinned by communist
revolutions, independence struggles and the spread of Western
democracy. Other crowns have toppled in more recent times.
   The last emperor of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> abdicated in <DATE>1912</DATE>. Communists ended
imperial rule in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> at the end of World War II. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
independence from <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE> sounded the knell for
myriads of royals. <LOCATION>Cambodia</LOCATION>'s kingdom ended amidst war and chaos in
<DATE>1970</DATE>, though Prince <PERSON>Norodom Sihanouk</PERSON>, formerly the king, is still
active as an exiled guerrilla faction leader. The last king of
<LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mohammad Zaher Shah</PERSON>, was toppled in <DATE>1973</DATE> and is exiled
in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> but recently offered to help in a transitional government
in his country.
   Today, there remain but five Asian hereditary kingdoms and
<LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>, where every five years one of the country's sultans is
elected a constitutional monarch.
   Nine of <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>'s 13 states have sultans who are constitutional
heads of the state governments. They have no political power. Every
five years these sultans meet to elect by secret ballot one of
themselves to be the national king. By tacit agreement each state
gets a turn at having its sultan king sooner or later. At the
national level the king is the constitutional head of state but
political power rests with prime minister.
   The present king of <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> is Sultan <PERSON>Mahmood Iskandar</PERSON> from
Jahore state. His term expires this year.
   Today's Asian monarchies have deep roots and their forseeable
futures appear secure.
   Akihito is 125th in a line of emperors said to stretch back 2,600
years in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. Though historians regard the first 14 emperors as
figures of myth, the Japanese imperial line is still the world's
oldest hereditary monarchy, and current public opinion polls favor
its continuation.
   Bhumibol, probably the most respected man in <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>, is heir to
750 years of monarchy.
   Bolkiah is <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s 29th ruler while <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bhutan</LOCATION> both have
centuries-old royal traditions.
   Although a constitutional monarch, the 61-year-old Thai king is
regarded as semi-divine by some and widely viewed as having held the
country together in wake of the coups and abortive power grabs that
have marked recent decades. He openly intervened to stop a serious
student-led uprising in <DATE>1973</DATE> and has in other moments of national
crisis played a decisive behind-the-scenes role.
   Named king in <DATE>1946</DATE> and crowned <DATE>four years later</DATE>, when he was a
jazz-loving teen-ager, <PERSON>Bhumibol</PERSON> was initially viewed as someone to
be used by military strongmen. Instead, he gradually reversed the
decline in prestige of the throne, largely by by-passing the elite
to work for the mass of have-nots in the countryside.
   <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Birendra</LOCATION>, 43, likewise has sought links with the rural
poor, making frequent trips to remote areas to hand out relief
supplies and sound out the problems of villagers. But knowledgable
sources in <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION> and neighboring <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> say much of the effort is
negated by corruption within the royal family and its retainers _ an
open secret in <LOCATION>Katmandu</LOCATION>, the capital.
   Birendra has initiated some political reforms during his 16-year
rule but there are quiet critics of both the monarchy and limited
democratic rights. The king himself, seen as a reincarnation of the
Hindu god Vishnu, by law cannot be criticized.
   In <LOCATION>Bhutan</LOCATION>, the publicity-shy, 33-year-old <PERSON>King Jigme Singye
Wangchuk</PERSON> has continued his father's attempts at political evolution
and improvement in the lives of his 1.4 million, largely illiterate
people.
   ``Development is important but preserving our culture and our
values is equally important,'' <PERSON>Jigme Singye</PERSON> has said.
   <LOCATION>Bhutan</LOCATION> was only opened up from its medieval seclusion by his
reform-minded father.
   International aid agencies have been welcomed to <LOCATION>Bhutan</LOCATION> but mass
tourism has not. Tourism is seen as a destroyer of the old ways
upheld by the king, who always wears the traditional, robe-like
``kho'' _ even while playing basketball _ and is married to four
sisters of noble line, another time-honored custom.
   <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s politics are said to be among the most sterile in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>
but the tiny state's 227,000 people have yet to show significant
signs of discontent. Under the 42-year-old sultan, the country
continues to prosper from its oil and natural gas reserves. Medical
care and education are free and the per capita annual income of
<MONEY>$21,000</MONEY> is among the highest in the world.
   The sultan, who has snapped up hotels, companies and other
investments around the world, moves freely among his subjects and is
credited with a number of civic improvements.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Feb. 19</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880816-0016 </DOCNO>
<HL> Trump Sniffs at Plaza Bid, Leaving a Sultan Sulking </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> FREST </CO>
<IN> REL </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON> bought the Plaza Hotel for roughly <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> this year, the judgment of many real estate observers was that he paid too much. 

   Industry sources, however, say <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON> already has received -- and rejected -- an offer for the Plaza that would have net him a <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> profit. 

   The sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, reputedly the world's richest person, recently offered to buy it for a little more than <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY>. 
When <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON> declined, the sultan upped his bid to roughly <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY>, the sources say. 
But <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON> said no deal. 

   The sultan apparently didn't get wind that the Plaza had been on the market before <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON>, who bought it from the <PERSON>Robert M. Bass Group</PERSON>, had more or less locked it up. 
"It was the one hotel he wanted to own more than any in the world," a source said of the sultan. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON> declined to sell because he likes owning the famed, landmark hotel and wants to make good on his vow to make it the world's best, sources say. 
<PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON> declined to comment. 

   The ruler of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, a tiny Asian nation on the oil-rich island of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>, has a fortune estimated at <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>, and lives in a 1,788-room palace. 

   Last year, the sultan bought the <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> Hotel from oil and entertainment tycoon <PERSON>Marvin Davis</PERSON>, reportedly for more than <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY> -- just months after <PERSON>Mr. Davis</PERSON> purchased it from one-time stock speculator <PERSON>Ivan Boesky</PERSON> for roughly <MONEY>$135 million</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-48845 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr103_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-103 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  26 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Cote d'Ivoire </F>
<H3> <TI>   Diplomatic Relations Established With Brunei </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Diplomatic Relations Established With Brunei </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AB2705145594 Abidjan Radio Cote d'Ivoire Chaine 
Nationale-Une Network in French 1900 GMT 26 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB2705145594 </F>
<F P=104>  Abidjan Radio Cote d'Ivoire Chaine 
Nationale-Une Network </F>

<F P=105>  French </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Joint communique issued by <LOCATION>Brunei Darussalam</LOCATION> and the </F>
Republic of Cote d'Ivoire; place and date not given] 
  [Text] The government of His Majesty the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei 
Darussalam</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sultan Bolkiah Hassanal</PERSON>, and the Government of the 
Republic of Cote d'Ivoire have decided to establish diplomatic 
relations at ambassadorial level effective 25 <DATE>May</DATE>. The decision 
is in line with the two countries' desire to strengthen 
friendship between their peoples and to foster cooperative 
relations between their countries on the basis of the principles 
enshrined in the <ORGANIZATION>UN Charter</ORGANIZATION>, notably the principles of equality, 
mutual respect, national sovereignty, and noninterference in the 
domestic affairs of states. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-52759 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes005_s_94015" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-005 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Iran </F>
<H3> <TI>   Brunei's Envoy, Velayati Meet; Sultan to Visit </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  LD0601140294 Tehran Voice of the Islamic Republic of Iran in 
English 1130 GMT 6 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD0601140294 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran Voice of the Islamic Republic of Iran </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpt] Following the opening of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s embassy in 
<LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>, (Haj Suhini Bin Haj Muhammad Hassan), that country's 
first charge d'affaires in the <LOCATION>Islamic Republic of Iran</LOCATION>, 
yesterday met with the Iranian foreign minister, <PERSON>Mr. Velayati</PERSON> 
and presented his credentials. 
  In the meeting, the two officials discussed the expansion 
and 
the strengthening of the two countries' relations, and the 
coming visit of the sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Haj Hassan Bolkiah</PERSON>, to 
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>. 
  The Bruneian charge d'affaires considered the Islamic 
Republic of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> as a second home, and stressed the willingness 
of his country's officials in strengthening relations with the 
Islamic Republic of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>. 
  Pointing to the results of their previous meetings and 
discussions of the two countries' officials, and the positive 
steps which have been taken in line with the two countries' 
ties, <PERSON>Mr. Velayati</PERSON> considered the Bruneian ruler's coming visit 
to <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> as a significant step for expansion of relations. 
[passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880912-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-12-88 0455EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-WealthyBrunei     09-12 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wealthy Brunei,0623</SECOND>
<HEAD>Few Problems In Oil-Rich Nation Ruled By World's Wealthiest Man</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARI S. MANIAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BANDAR SERI BEGAWAN, Brunei (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man ranked the wealthiest
in the world runs this tiny oil-rich Moslem kingdom, and diplomats
report little dissent from people unencumbered by income taxes,
medical payments or tuition fees.
   King <PERSON>Sultan Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON> rules the enclave on the
northeastern tip of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION> from his 1,788-room palace. Earlier this
month, Fortune magazine called him the richest man in the world,
worth <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>.
   Citizens of this southeast Asian nation do not appear to object
to the king's rule because he spreads some of the money around.
   ``They (the people) are well looked after, with free education,
medical treatment, cheap housing, good pensions and any one doing
well in his studies can easily get a university education abroad at
the government's expense,'' said one diplomat, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   He said there are no beggars, and about half the workforce is
employed by the government. The per capita income is estimated at
about <MONEY>$18,000</MONEY>, one of the highest in the world, according to
bankers and diplomats.
   All the money comes from oil and gas, which <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> exports
mainly to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   A <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> government official said recently that <DATE>1986</DATE> exports
amounted to <MONEY>$2.03 billion</MONEY> _ <PERCENT>99 percent</PERCENT> of it oil and gas. Imports
for the same year totaled <MONEY>$785 million</MONEY> in cars, foodstuffs and
other goods.
   The nation, about the size of <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, covers just 2,226 square
miles, much of which is not suitable for cultivation, an
agricultural officer said.
   Without daily newspapers, the nation's 227,000 people get their
news mainly through state-run radio, <LOCATION>Television Brunei</LOCATION> and some
government publications.
   An official in the <ORGANIZATION>Planning Unit</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Malays</PERSON> form the majority
of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s population, but there are also about 60,000 Chinese and
other non-Malays.
   About 87,000 people are employed and of these 28,000 are foreign
workers, including foreign maids, doctors, lawyers, engineers,
accountants and others.
   <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> has no elected <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Sultan Bolkiah</PERSON> rules the
nation with the help of a Cabinet comprising two of his brothers
and about seven other people.
   The 41-year-old monarch, who studied in neighboring <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>
before a stint at the <ORGANIZATION>British Military Academy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sandhurst</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1966</DATE>, was crowned the 29th King of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> in <DATE>1967</DATE> by
his father Sir <PERSON>Omar Ali Saifuddin</PERSON>, who abdicated in favor of his
son.
   The king loves polo and has about 200 Argentine polo ponies,
some of which are kept in air-conditioned stables. He has two wives
and six children.
   In the 14th and <DATE>15th century</DATE>, <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> was a large empire
stretching from the northern <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> to most parts of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>,
but when the colonialists came <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> shrank. <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> became a
British protectorate in <DATE>1906</DATE> and won its independence on <DATE>Dec. 31,
1983</DATE>.
   The country has no income tax, gasoline is cheap and there are
no major taxes on cars, which are imported from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and
elsewhere. Diplomats estimate foreign reserves at <MONEY>$20 billion</MONEY>.
   The King has powers to detain and hold without trial anyone
deemed to be a threat to the security of the nation. On <DATE>July 14</DATE>,
the government released 34 such detainees, leaving just six still
in custody.
   Diplomats say there appears to be no long-term threat to
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s economy as the 120,000 barrels of oil being pumped daily
is expected to last ``well into the next century''.
   <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> is officially known as <LOCATION>Brunei Darusalam</LOCATION>.
   Darusalam means abode of peace ``and there is indeed peace
here'' said a diplomat, who added ``they could have added
prosperity to it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890710-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-89 0044EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Baker-Reporter'sNotebook     07-10 0527</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Baker-Reporter's Notebook,0541</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker, a Critic of Authoritarian Rulers, Rubs Elbows With Them on
Tour</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA_ ^Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MUSCAT, Oman (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration has welcomed the
global trend away from authoritarian rule, but at least two stops on
Secretary of State <PERSON>James A. Baker III</PERSON>'s swing through <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> seem immune to such democratic changes.
   <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> has spent much of the past four days in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION>,
both sultanates that are virtually devoid of the democratic
trappings normally advocated by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In this <LOCATION>Arabian Peninsula</LOCATION> nation, there are no political parties,
no legislature and no elections. All power rests with <PERSON>Sultan Qaboos</PERSON>,
the latest in a line of monarchs who have ruled this Kansas-sized
land since the <DATE>1740s</DATE>.
   Baker decided to stop off in <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION> mainly to rest before joining
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, the first stop on a four-nation European
tour.
   Oman was chosen in part because few Arab nations, if any, are
friendlier to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. Oman was one of the first Arab
nations that endorsed the <DATE>1978</DATE> Camp <PERSON>David</PERSON> peace agreement between
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>.
   As authoritarian rulers go, <PERSON>Qaboos</PERSON> appears to be more benign than
most. When he deposed his father in <DATE>1970</DATE>, <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION> was a land plagued by
poverty, disease and illiteracy.
   In <DATE>19 years</DATE>, <PERSON>Qaboos</PERSON> has been able to forge what is for the most
part a modern, prosperous nation, overcoming such obstacles as a
forbidding climate that often sends temperatures above 130 degrees.
   According to <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> figures, there were only three
schools in <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION> in <DATE>1970</DATE>. In <DATE>1986</DATE>, there were 697. The number of
hospital beds rose from 12 to 2,800 in the same time period.
   Oil helped finance the boom, much as it did in <PERSON>Baker</PERSON>'s previous
stop, <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>.
   Unlike <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> has a constitution, but it provides <PERSON>Sultan
Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON> with supreme executive authority.
   The occasion for <PERSON>Baker</PERSON>'s visit to <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> was the annual meeting
of the six-member <ORGANIZATION>Association of Southeast Asian Nations</ORGANIZATION>.
   Like <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> has a system with a social conscience,
providing subsidized food, fuel, housing, free education and medical
care.
   <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s 250,000 citizens enjoy an unusually high standard of
living, which permits them to over look the opulent lifestyle of
their ruler and his two wives.
   The main attraction in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, about the size of <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, is the
sultan's palace, a 1,788-room extravaganza with a dining room
capable of accommodating 6,000 for a sit-down meal. Need a bathroom?
The palace has more than 200.
   Amid such abundance, the sultan is somewhat wary about
inquisitive reporters. Before the start of the <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> conference,
reporters were told to write about the conference, not about <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>.
   Still, the sultan has been unable to conceal his role as perhaps
the world's richest man, with an estimated wealth of <MONEY>$28 billion</MONEY>,
almost four times the gross national product of <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION>.
   He is one of a handful of men who has claim to a fortune that
dwarfs the estimated <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> to <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> of <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION>'s autocratic
president, <PERSON>Mobutu Sese Seko</PERSON>, the last foreign leader whom <PERSON>Baker</PERSON>
entertained before departing on his tour.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-34335 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes025_s_94013" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-025 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Iran </F>
<H3> <TI>   Communique Issued on Visit </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  LD0602124794 Tehran IRNA in English 1155 GMT 6 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> LD0602124794 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran IRNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>, Feb 6, IRNA -- <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> here <DATE>Sunday</DATE> 
[6 <DATE>February</DATE>] issued a joint communique at the end of the 4-day 
visit to <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> of the <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s sultan <PERSON>Muda Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>. 
  The communique was signed by the ambassador of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> here 
<PERSON>Haji Subaini</PERSON> ben <PERSON>Haji Mohammad Hassan</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s accredited 
ambassador to <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> Ahmad Adjalluian [names as received]. 
  It condemned human rights violation and continuation of 
aggression in <LOCATION>Bosnia-Herzegovnia</LOCATION>, ethnic cleansing in 
particular, and expressed concern over prolongation of the 
seizure and bombardment of <LOCATION>Sarajevo</LOCATION>. 
  The two sides also reiterated their support for firm 
(OIC) in calling for an end to the arms embargo on Bosnian 
Muslims. 
  The Islamic Republic and <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> share common views on 
different international issues, specially those related to 
Muslims, added the communique. The two countries underlined 
the need for closer cooperation for the establishment of 
international peace and stability as well as respect for the 
principled regulations asserted in the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations Charter</ORGANIZATION>. 
  <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> called as effective establishment of 
cooperation and relations between the <ORGANIZATION>Economic Cooperation 
Organization</ORGANIZATION> (ECO) and <ORGANIZATION>Associatiion of South East Asian Nations</ORGANIZATION> 
(ASEAN). 
  The communique also called for further bilateral cooperation 
in <ORGANIZATION>OIC</ORGANIZATION> and for joint measures to employ the organization's 
resources for boosting cooperation among other <ORGANIZATION>OIC</ORGANIZATION> member states. 
  Among other issues, the communique underlined the need for 
the encouragement of bilateral trade relations, joint ventures 
and cultural, educational and academic cooperation. 
  Expressing satisfaction over promotion of cordial relations 
between the two countries, <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> hoped that the visit 
would pave the way for further expansion of ties and mutual 
cooperation. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-978</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-ELVDSAFMFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941222
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 DEC 94 / International Company News: 'No intention' to sell Plaza
stake, Trump says
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Mr Donald Trump</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> property developer, said yesterday he had no
intention of selling his 51 per cent stake in the landmark Plaza Hotel in
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, but said his company had been approached by people interested in
acquiring a stake in the <LOCATION>Plaza</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Reuter</ORGANIZATION> reports from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Trump</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>CNBC</ORGANIZATION> cable television that his company had had contacts with
the representative of the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, who is considered one of the
world's richest people.
'The Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, his people have spoken to us, various other people
have spoken to us and we may do some kind of partnership or something,' <PERSON>Mr
Trump</PERSON> said.
The <ORGANIZATION>New York Post</ORGANIZATION> had earlier reported that the sultan and his partners had
bid more than Dollars 300m for the Fifth Avenue hotel.
However, <ORGANIZATION>Trump Organisation</ORGANIZATION> chief executive <PERSON>Mr Nicholas Ribis</PERSON> said there had
been no substantive discussions.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Trump Organisation Inc.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7011 Hotels and Motels.
    P6552 Subdividers and Developers, Ex Cemeteries.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Shareholding.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-9616</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CBKBQADOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920211
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 FEB 92 / Sultan Of Brunei may buy 10 percent of PAL
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MANILA
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> is negotiating to buy 10 per cent of the equity of
<ORGANIZATION>Philippine Airlines</ORGANIZATION> (PAL), Reuter reports from <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>. The Philippine
government said the Sultan had reached agreement with the committee on
privatisation last week. A 67 per cent stake in <ORGANIZATION>PAL</ORGANIZATION> was awarded to a
consortium led by <ORGANIZATION>AB Capital and Investment Corporation</ORGANIZATION> at a <DATE>January 30</DATE>
auction.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 3
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BigSpender     10-28 0181</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Big Spender,0192</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sultan of Brunei Spends $950,000 on Birthday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, one of the world's richest
men, reportedly spent at least <MONEY>$950,000</MONEY> on his nephew's ninth
birthday party.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Sunday Express</ORGANIZATION> said the sultan converted a ballroom at
<ORGANIZATION>Claridge</ORGANIZATION>'s in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> into a replica of <ORGANIZATION>Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles</ORGANIZATION>
headquarters.
   An army of workers turned the ballroom into a giant <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION> sewer for the party for young <PERSON>Prince Bahar</PERSON>, the paper said.
Four men dressed as the superheros, <ORGANIZATION>Donatello</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Leonardo</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Michelangeo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Raphael</PERSON>, mingled with the young guests.
   A group of luxurious anterooms were transformed into a network
of gurglig drains, the paper said. Music was provided by the pop
duo Partners in <LOCATION>Kryme</LOCATION>, who were flown to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> to perform their
hit ``Turtle Power,'' the newspaper said.
   Claridge's banqueting staff served pizza in a neon-lit pizza
parlor, <ORGANIZATION>The Sunday Express</ORGANIZATION> said. It did not say what day the party
took place.
   ``It was an incredible sight,'' said one member of <PERSON>Claridge</PERSON>'s
staff, who spoke to the newspaper on condition of anonymity.
   The report could not be independently confirmed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870605-0086 </DOCNO>
<HL> REVIEW &amp; OUTLOOK (Editorial):
Pick Your Side</HL>
<DD> 06/05/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MDEST LATAM
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
AEROSPACE (ARO)
EXECUTIVE (EXE)
CONGRESS (CNG) </IN>
<TEXT>
   Congressmen interrogating <PERSON>Elliott Abrams</PERSON> have been criticizing evasions. 
It's time to ask them for a straight answer of their own. 
As <PERSON>Pete Seeger</PERSON> would put it: Which side are you on, boy? 
The Sandinistas or the anti-communists? 

   <PERSON>Mr. Abrams</PERSON> represents the success of the <ORGANIZATION>Contra</ORGANIZATION> policy, having helped keep the anti-communist cause alive while <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> was trying to kill it without taking responsibility for the results of doing so. 
As Secretary <PERSON>Shultz</PERSON> said in a statement <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Abrams</PERSON> has done a "sensational" job. 
That is precisely why congressmen are calling for his resignation, and they ought to say so. 

   The congressmen of course claim they are upset because he lied to them, but in 10 hours of questioning they failed to make that case. 
So they resorted to pure badgering. 
<PERSON>Sen. Howell Heflin</PERSON> (D., <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>) asked him if the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> had a school to teach evasive answers. 
Rep. <PERSON>Lee Hamilton</PERSON> (D., <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>) said, "We cannot advance <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> interests if public officials who testify before the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> resort to legalisms, word games, claim ignorance about things they either knew about or should know about and, at critical points, tell the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> things that are not true." 
And from Rep. <PERSON>Jack Brooks</PERSON> (D., <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>), "I can only conclude after this that you're either extremely incompetent or that you are still, as I say, deceiving us with semantics." 

   A bunch of politicians complaining about legalisms and semantics? 
Come on, congressmen. 
In those immortal words, where's the beef? 

   The case that <PERSON>Mr. Abrams</PERSON> misled <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> now rests on one incident, the soliciting of the sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. 
What happened was this: On <DATE>Nov. 25, 1986</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Abrams</PERSON> testified before the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Intelligence Committee</ORGANIZATION>, answering questions from <PERSON>Sen. Bill Bradley</PERSON> (D., <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>) about funding for the Contras from abroad. 
His answers were literally correct, but he did not volunteer his solicitation of <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> from the sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, which was obviously relevant to the senator's concerns. 

   Now, the solicitation was perfectly legal. 
Indeed, the <DATE>1986</DATE> Intelligence Authorization explicitly authorized the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> to solicit third countries for humanitarian aid. 
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> refused to fund the Contras and instead wanted the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> to go, tin cup in hand, to solicit money for them from third countries. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Abrams</PERSON> had a dilemma; as he testified this week, he'd given the sultan's government a "flat, absolute promise of confidentiality." 
Unhappy with his answers to the committee, <PERSON>Mr. Abrams</PERSON> asked <PERSON>Mr. Shultz</PERSON> if he could call the leadership of the intelligence committee and tell them about <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. 
The secretary told him to break the confidentiality with the sultan if he thought he should. 
So he went back to the committee to voluntarily tell them about <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> and apologize for having misled them. 

   A man who does this, the congressmen profess to believe, can't be trusted. 
Certainly he can't associate with the boy scouts who inhabit Capitol Hill hearing rooms. 
Off with his head. 

   What is the bottom line here, anyway? 
Demands that <PERSON>Mr. Abrams</PERSON> resign are best understood as subterfuge for some members' longstanding opposition to the Contras. 
Crocodile tears were shed when <PERSON>Mr. Abrams</PERSON> was told no more aid to Contras unless he resigned. 
So the congressmen, the same ones who ask for straight answers, are going to make <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> foreign policy out of pique with individual <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> figures? 

   The issue is not <PERSON>Mr. Abrams</PERSON>, but the communists in <LOCATION>Managua</LOCATION>. 
What does the <ORGANIZATION>United States Congress</ORGANIZATION> propose to do about them? 
Does <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> stand with <PERSON>Elliott Abrams</PERSON> or with <PERSON>Dear Comandante Danny Ortega</PERSON>? 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA071089-0100 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 80804 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 10, 1989, Monday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 2; Column 6; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
45 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SULTAN'S KIN LOSES $6 MILLION TO BURGLARS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Reuters 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
LONDON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Burglars stole jewelry and cash worth an estimated <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY> from the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> 
home of the brother of the world's richest man, the <PERSON>Sultan Muda Hassanal 
Bolkiah</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The house belongs to <PERSON>Prince Jefri</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s finance minister, and his wife 
Princess Norhayti. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-9909</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CKCCTAFKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921103
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 NOV 92 / Commodities and Agriculture: Brunei still sits cosily in its
Shell - A longstanding relationship that suits both parties
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KIERAN COOKE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
EARLY THIS century two intrepid British geologists were cycling along a path
near the coast in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, on the west of the island of <LOCATION>Borneo</LOCATION>. They paused
for a rest. Then one uttered the magic words: 'I smell oil'.
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> has never looked back. The economy of the tiny sultanate is a
relatively simple affair. At present it produces 182,000 barrels of oil a
day. Exports of crude in <DATE>1990</DATE>, the last year for which official figures are
available, were worth <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> Dollars 2.02bn (Dollars 1.27bn). Liquefied
natural gas exports were worth a similar amount.
Vast savings have accumulated over the years. The secretive <ORGANIZATION>Brunei
Investment Agency</ORGANIZATION> is believed to control a Dollars 35bn portfolio of
international investments, the income from which is now estimated to
contribute more to the government's coffers than revenues from oil and gas
combined.
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s 270,000 people have one of the highest per capita incomes in the
world. Sultan <PERSON>Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>, now celebrating 25 years of absolute rule,
is generally regarded as the world's richest individual, with a personal
fortune estimated at Dollars 37bn.
The Sultan and the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dutch/Shell</ORGANIZATION> group, in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> since <DATE>early this
century</DATE>, are the two main focuses of attention in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>. Shell has a
monopoly on <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s oil and gas exports. There is very little other
industry in the country. The <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> group is by far the country's biggest
employer - apart from the government, which employs about 50 per cent of the
labour force.
Shell is reluctant to discuss amounts of revenue from its local operations.
But Singapore-based oil industry analysts estimate that <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> contributes
about 10 per cent of the <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> group's overall world-wide profits.
The company now has seven offshore oil fields in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> and two onshore. It
 -and <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> - have been fortunate that oil discoveries have tended to
coincide with the oil price rise shocks of the <DATE>last 20 years</DATE>.
Oil analysts say that exploration technology now being used in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> is
among the most advanced in the world: using three dimensional seismic
exploration techniques finds have been made under existing oil fields. In
recent years the <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> government has been stressing the need to conserve
resources.
'This year <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> has successfully pressed the <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> government for an
increase in oil production so as to recoup the recent investments it has
made in high technology exploration,' says an industry analyst. 'Next year
production will probably fall back to 150,000-160,000 b/d and at that rate
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> has about 25 years' reserves of oil and about 40 years' reserves of
gas.'
Gas has been <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s big success story. Twenty years ago, <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> built in
<LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> what was then the world's biggest LNG processing plant. Gas is piped
from fields more than 30 km (18 miles) offshore and cooled at the plant
until it liquefies. It is then loaded on to <ORGANIZATION>LNG</ORGANIZATION> carriers and transported to
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
The <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> plant has produced more than 90m tonnes of LNG over the past 20
years. Apart from domestic consumption, all LNG is purchased by three
Japanese companies: <ORGANIZATION>Tokyo Electric</ORGANIZATION> (the world's biggest private electricity
utility), <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> Gas and <LOCATION>Osaka</LOCATION> Gas.
LNG exports to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> have been made under a 20-year contract that runs out
at the end of <DATE>March next year</DATE>. Another 20-year contract is being negotiated,
but there have been considerable problems. The seven LNG ships that
transport the gas to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> are owned jointly by <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>
government. At one stage the Japanese wanted a whole fleet of new tankers -
no small request with each ship costing around Dollars 300m.
The prices of <ORGANIZATION>LNG</ORGANIZATION> exports to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> are determined by a complex formula based
on average prices of Japanese imported crude and referred to in the trade as
'The <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> Crude Cocktail'.
There continues to be arguments over price. Shell says talks are at a
crucial stage with no clear sign of when agreement can be reached. Industry
analysts say <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> has the upper hand: the country has established itself
as a reliable, long-term supplier and about 14 per cent of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s total LNG
imports come from the sultanate. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> wants to import more - if the
Japanese do not buy then <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> is a ready market.
All <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION>'s operations in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> have a 50 per cent government shareholding.
<ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi</ORGANIZATION>, the Japanese conglomerate, has 25 per cent stakes in <ORGANIZATION>LNG</ORGANIZATION>
processing and transport operations.
Most industry analysts see the Brunei/Shell relationship continuing. But
others are eager to enter. <LOCATION>Elf Aquitaine</LOCATION> has formed a partnership with a
local company believed to be controlled by <PERSON>Prince Jufri</PERSON>, the Sultan's
younger brother and minister of finance. Elf has found oil but it is
believed to be in fields that either stretch into Malaysian waters or into
adjacent Shell areas.
The present sultan and his advisers have pressed for a greater share of
profits from the <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> operations. Analysts feel the government has been
clever in its handling of the oil giant: it has not threatened to
nationalise but by taking a 50 per cent stake in all operations, it has been
able to exert a large degree of control.
For its part <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> is very careful to obey various government edicts.
Official requirements on employing large numbers of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> Malay people
rather than Chinese or others have led to serious staff shortage
difficulties. For all its economic clout, <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> makes sure it is not seen to
be interfering in any of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s internal affairs.
'No one outside really knows the exact terms of the contract between <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION>,' says an industry analyst. 'But one thing is certain - it's very
good for <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> and good for <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> as well.'
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 30
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-13820</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJTC2ACPFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931020
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 OCT 93 / Brunei default on debts alleged
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PHILIP STEPHENS, Political Editor
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
A <ORGANIZATION>GROUP of Labour</ORGANIZATION> MPs <TIME>last night</TIME> accused the <ORGANIZATION>High Commission of Brunei</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> of failing to honour debts incurred by sponsored students from the
<LOCATION>Sultanate</LOCATION>.
In a motion tabled under parliamentary privilege, the MPs called on the
Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> to 'meet the debts owed by his <ORGANIZATION>High Commission</ORGANIZATION> to landlords
and other debts in the <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION>'.
The MPs, led by <PERSON>Mr Nigel Griffiths</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Edinburgh South</ORGANIZATION>), said the commission
had failed to honour payments owed to the landlords of properties rented by
their students.
They added that promissory notes issued by the High Commissioner in the name
of the Sultan were 'worthless'. The <ORGANIZATION>High Commission</ORGANIZATION> failed to honour the
securities it had given to creditors.
The motion said that the High Commissioner had failed to answer
correspondance from solicitors and MPs and warned all universities of the
'financial unreliability' of the <ORGANIZATION>High Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
    BNZ  Brunei, Asia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
    P8221 Colleges and Universities.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 14
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870204-0163 </DOCNO>
<HL> 

---
Scandal in Southeast Asia
Threatens Financier's Empire
---
By Raphael Pura
<DD> 02/04/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> FREST
BANKS, THRIFT INSTITUTIONS (BNK) </IN>
<DATELINE> BANDAR SERI BEGAWAN, Brunei  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
    Six months ago, <ORGANIZATION>Finance
Ministry</ORGANIZATION> officials of this oil-rich sultanate entered the
headquarters of <ORGANIZATION>National Bank of Brunei</ORGANIZATION> to seize all
documents related to the privately held bank's <MONEY>$687 million</MONEY>
loan portfolio.
   It didn't take long. 
The chief of the raiding party soon left with two dozen thin files tucked under one arm. 

   "There would be a signature card and nothing else," says a <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> source familiar with the episode. 
"It was amazing: Here you had <MONEY>hundreds of millions of dollars</MONEY> in loans with no documentation whatsoever, no record of security, nothing." 

   What the officials did discover, however, was that about <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of the loans outstanding -- <MONEY>$621 million</MONEY> -- went to companies linked to or relatives of the wealthy Malaysian financier and hotelier Tan Sri Khoo <ORGANIZATION>Teck Puat</ORGANIZATION>, whose family owned more than <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION> affair has developed into one of the biggest financial scandals in <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> in recent years and threatens to embroil the Khoo family and the government of the tiny former British protectorate in protracted legal battles. 
Already, it has tarnished Tan Sri Khoo's name in financial circles, forcing him to resign from the board of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Standard Chartered PLC</ORGANIZATION> and to sell the bulk of his <PERCENT>29%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Exco International PLC</ORGANIZATION>, also of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. 

   Many bankers believe it also will force him to dismantle his vast business empire -- consisting of investments in hotels, property and financial services in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> -- to pay off more than <MONEY>$470 million</MONEY> owed by Khoo-related companies at the end of <DATE>1986</DATE>. 

   Neither <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> officials nor spokesmen for Tan Sri Khoo will discuss details of the affair publicly. 
But an account of what happened can be pieced together from interviews with those familiar with the case and from an examination of documents obtained in <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> sources close to the investigation of the bank, which the government seized and shut down on <DATE>Nov. 20</DATE>, say audits show that it functioned essentially as a powerful money machine for the 70-year-old financier and his family. 

   The inquiry's findings, corroborated in part by associates of the Khoo family, indicate that the big acquisitions that earned <PERSON>Tan Sri Khoo</PERSON> a reputation as a financial wizard with bottomless pockets were financed partly by what amounted to interest-free loans from <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION>. 
The acquisitions included stakes in both <ORGANIZATION>Exco</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Standard Chartered</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Among the <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> government's other discoveries: 

   --<ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION> pumped an ever-rising tide of funds into Khoo-family companies, with such loans jumping to <MONEY>$622 million</MONEY> by mid-1986 from <MONEY>$93 million</MONEY> at the end of <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
Almost all the loans were overdrafts, with no fixed schedule of repayment. 
Most went to shell companies that had minimal capitalization and pledged no security for the loans. 
Although the bank accrued interest on the loans and recorded it as profit, in many cases the Khoo companies failed to pay any interest for years at a time or paid only sporadically. 

   --The bank listed as active credits loans on which it hadn't received payments of interest or principal for years. 
In some cases, the borrowing concerns were defunct. 

   --The bank financed almost all of its Khoo-related lending with short-term, interbank borrowings from more than 30 non-Brunei banks, mainly in <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>. 
It also used the borrowings to meet operating expenses, pay dividends and repay interest and principal on earlier borrowings. 
As the financial obligations of the Khoo family and <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION> grew, such borrowing escalated sharply, rising to <MONEY>$228 million</MONEY> at the end of <DATE>last October</DATE> from <MONEY>$129 million</MONEY> at the end of <DATE>1985</DATE> and just <MONEY>$32 million</MONEY> at the end of <DATE>1983</DATE>. 

   Documents obtained in the <ORGANIZATION>National Bank</ORGANIZATION> investigation also shed new light on one of the central mysteries of the affair: the close but enigmatic relationship between the Khoo family and <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s ruling royal family, headed by 40-year-old <PERSON>Sultan Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>, who has served as both monarch and prime minister since <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>'s independence in <DATE>1984</DATE>. 

   The documents indicate that the Khoo family made several offers in <DATE>1985</DATE> and <DATE>1986</DATE> to sell its entire interest in the bank to the sultan and to manage the bank on his behalf. 
