<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880829-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-88 0631EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ElephantDeath     08-29 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Elephant Death,0489</SECOND>
<HEAD>San Diego Zoo Mourns Loss of Oldest Elephant</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHARON L. JONES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Zookeepers and elephants are mourning the death
of the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo's oldest and most popular elephant, a
10,000-pound matriarch that led the herd for 47 years and
entertained millions of tourists.
   The 51-year-old Asian elephant, named <PERSON>Lucki</PERSON>, was put to sleep
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> because her health had deteriorated to where she could no
longer stand, even with the help of a forklift, said spokesman <PERSON>Jeff
Jouett</PERSON>.
   ``She was one of most popular and best-loved animals at the
zoo,'' said <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON>, who estimated that 102 million tourists had
seen her over the years.
   <PERSON>Lucki</PERSON>, who came to <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> in <DATE>1941</DATE> from a zoo in <LOCATION>Calcutta</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, was the zoo's biggest and most dominant elephant. She stood
9 feet at the shoulder.
   ``It's a major passage in the zoo elephant herd when the
matriarch dies,'' <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. ``The current elephant keepers love
her dearly and are stunned by her loss. ... It's a subdued day at
the zoo.''
   About 10 years ago, <PERSON>Lucki</PERSON> started suffering from chronic tooth
and foot ailments, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said.
   In <DATE>1981</DATE>, <PERSON>Lucki</PERSON> became the first captive elephant to have a tooth
pulled. Keepers regularly trimmed her foot pads to lessen her
problems, which were caused by lack of exercise.
   But during the past week, her condition worsened because of an
infection in her front feet. <DATE>Sunday</DATE> morning <PERSON>Lucki</PERSON> was unable to
stand.
   ``The veterinarian believes she reputured the muscles in (her)
back legs while trying to push herself up,'' <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. ``They
tried coaxing her up. They brought in a forklift with a crane
attached. There was no way she could move.''
   After consulting with elephant keepers and curator of mammals
<PERSON>Rick Barongi</PERSON>, veterinarian <PERSON>Don Janssen</PERSON> injected the fatal shot of a
drug, the spokesman said.
   Among the witnesses were the zoo's director, <PERSON>Doug Myers</PERSON>, who
came in on his day off, and eight former or present elephant
keepers. The zoo's five other elephants were brought in later.
   ``Elephants are very intelligent and they can understand why one
of their own is no longer with them,'' <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. ``They do a
very similar thing in the wild, so Maya and other elephants got an
hour to pay last respects.''
   Maya is a 49-year-old Asian elephant that came from <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> with
<PERSON>Lucki</PERSON> and was her best friend, he said.
   As matriarch, <PERSON>Lucki</PERSON> was always the first in the herd to eat and
enter the yard from the barn, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. She also was responsible
for disciplining members of the herd, as well as defending it from
intruders.
   Asian elephants have lived to nearly age 70 in captivity, but
are believed to have shorter life spans in the wild, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said.
<PERSON>Lucki</PERSON>'s body was transported to the zoo's hospital for a necropsy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ElephantEuthanized     12-24 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Elephant Euthanized,0398</SECOND>
<HEAD>Matriarch of San Diego Zoo Elephant Herd Euthanized After Accident</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 51-year-old elephant at the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> had
to be killed because of injuries she suffered after falling
headfirst into a concrete moat, officials said.
   Maya, an Asian elephant who was the oldest mammal at the zoo,
apparently suffered torn ligaments in her legs <DATE>Sunday</DATE> as she tried
to climb out of the moat surrounding her enclosure, said zoo
spokesman <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON>.
   Veterinarians resorted to a fatal dose of sedative when Maya was
unable to stand on her own following a treatment of fluids,
painkillers and steroids.
   ``I counted 27 people there trying to help,'' <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said.
``When she would try to rock and stand up, there was a lot of
calling and urging to her.''
   Elephants cannot convalesce while sitting or lying down because
their weight exerts life-threatening pressure on their lungs,
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said 51 is fairly elderly for an elephant, but they have
been known to live into their 60s in captivity.
   Maya, who was captured in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and brought to the zoo <DATE>Nov. 8,
1941</DATE>, was bumped into the moat by another elephant. Two nearby
keepers didn't see the <DATE>fall</DATE> but heard the commotion.
   The 7,100-pound elephant was walking without difficulty in the
moat, but she apparently crippled herself while trying to climb out
on bales of hay that zookeepers set up like steps, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said.
   Maya then was fitted with a harness and lifted by crane into a
sitting position. But it was evident when workers tried to get her
to stand that her legs wouldn't support her, and she was then put
to death.
   Elephants have been knocked into the moat before without
suffering serious injury, but <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said <PERSON>Maya</PERSON>'s age may have made
her accident worse. Tests after her death showed she suffered from
degenerative arthritis in her legs.
   He described her as a generally calm, easygoing creature, but
one who often would assert herself to show she still led the herd.
   ``There's some concern over how the remaining four elephants
will react,'' <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. ``They'll notice she's gone and I'm sure
it will be upsetting to them.''
   After the accident, the zoo's <LOCATION>Elephant Mesa</LOCATION> was closed to the
public for the rest of the day.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06075142 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06075142 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-DIEGO; ANIMAL; PARK; PROFESSIONAL; DEATH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A 27-year-old elephant keeper was killed Thursday when she tried to break up a
fight between two of the Asian elephants she cared for at the San Diego Wild
Animal Park, officials said.;    It was the first animal-caused death of a
keeper at the 19-year-old park, which is an affiliate of the San Diego Zoo,
according to zoo spokesman Jeff Jouett.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  KEEPER KILLED WHILE TRYING TO BREAK UP ELEPHANT
FIGHT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  California News.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The dead trainer was identified as <PERSON>Pamela C. Orsi</PERSON>. She suffered head
injuries.;    "We don't know exactly how that happened, whether it was a
trunk, foot or leg from the elephant that caused the injuries," <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said.
He added, "Right now, we're just stunned. It's a sad, sad day.";    The <LOCATION>San
Diego County</LOCATION> Medical Examiner's Office was called to investigate the death.;  
 <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said another keeper at the park's elephant yard, Dusty Janeke, heard
the commotion of the two elephants fighting, went to investigate and found
<PERSON>Orsi</PERSON> on the ground.;    "She apparently stepped in to break up a fight,"
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. "Fights are a fairly frequent part of elephant life. They fight
to establish position in the pecking order of the herd.;    "When the fighting
gets particularly violent, the keeper's job is to intervene to keep the
elephants from injuring each other, and it's highly likely she was trying to
protect one of the elephants from being injured by the other.";    The two
elephants involved, females named <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> and Cha-Cha, were herded into the
elephant barn for the night.;    <PERSON>Orsi</PERSON> had been a zoo keeper for six years,
including four years' experience with elephants, three of those at the <LOCATION>Bronx
Zoo</LOCATION>. She had been at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> park for the past year.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Diego  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910315  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  282  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday March 15, 1991
00075142,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06063181 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06063181 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  ANIMAL; PARK; MOVE; DELAY; SACRAMENTO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Her trunk is ready, but Winky has no place to go.;    The Sacramento Zoo's
only elephant had been scheduled to move to the San Diego Wild Animal Park.
But park officials now say they can't take the 38-year-old Winky because their
own elephants aren't getting along well.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ZOO IN ELEPHANTINE SOCIAL FIX  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "Things just weren't clicking the way they wanted them to," said <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>
Zoo spokeswoman <PERSON>Liz Brenner</PERSON>, "so they said they're no longer in a position to
receive Winky.";    The zoo has been trying to find a new home for Winky
because she's alone since the zoo's other elephant died and because her
enclosure, her residence for 35 years, fails to measure up to modern
standards.;    Elephants are social animals and zoo officials had hoped <ORGANIZATION>Winky</ORGANIZATION>
could assimilate into the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>'s herd of eight female
Asian elephants. But herds are tightly knit groups with strict pecking orders
and it can takes weeks or months before they will accept a newcomer.;    The
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> herd still hasn't accepted Omar, a male elephant born there eight
months ago. Park officials said <PERSON>Omar</PERSON>'s mother and the rest of the herd had
never seen a baby elephant, and rejected it.;    "It's taking a lot longer
than we imagined to get Omar accepted," park spokesman <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON> said.
"Trying to add the baby is going to cause some shifting and rumbling in the
herd.;    "To try to add an adult at the same time could really upset the
order of things and be dangerous for the baby, <ORGANIZATION>Winky</ORGANIZATION> and the keepers involved."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Sacramento  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final Street  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910303  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  259  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday March 3, 1991
00063181,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061490-0044 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 233261 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 14, 1990, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
460 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BABY ELEPHANT OFF TO SHAKY START; 
</P>
<P>
SURVIVAL: WILD ANIMAL PARK OFFICIALS WORRY ABOUT SURVIVAL OF NEWBORN ASIAN 
ELEPHANT AFTER HIS MOTHER REJECTS HIM. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAN PARKS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A newborn Asian elephant at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> had to be separated 
from his mother shortly after birth <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, leading keepers to worry whether 
the valuable young pachyderm will survive. 
</P>
<P>
"The calf bellowed and scared the mom, and so Mom began to kick, stomp and try 
to kill the baby," said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, a spokesman for the park. "At that point, 
the keepers physically placed themselves between Mom and the baby." 
</P>
<P>
Hanscom, who witnessed the event, said it was "miraculous" that no one was 
injured. 
</P>
<P>
"For a while it was all a jumble of keepers and elephants, and she did strike 
out and hit the keepers," he said. 
</P>
<P>
The attack occurred shortly after veterinarians cleared Omar the calf's lungs 
of fluid and reunited the elephants, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The park has tried since <DATE>1984</DATE> to establish an Asian elephant breeding program, 
but has been unsuccessful. Three fetuses have been stillborn at the park in 
recent years, so officials are willing to take extraordinary measures to save 
Omar, the first to make it out of the womb alive. 
</P>
<P>
The park now has eight Asian elephants, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
A healthy male Asian elephant is worth <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY>, said <PERSON>Mike Keele</PERSON>, 
assistant curator at the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Park Zoo in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Twenty-four Asian elephants have been born in the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> zoo since <DATE>1962</DATE>, 
making it the most successful such program in the country, <PERSON>Keele</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Raising elephants is difficult "primarily because of the bull elephant's 
enormous size and power," he said. "There are not that many facilities in the 
country that can house a bull. . . . They are capable of tearing down a 
building." 
</P>
<P>
It is also difficult to get them to breed because they need a free-roaming, 
"herd feeling," <PERSON>Keele</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
More emphasis has been placed on raising Asian elephants than African elephants 
because Asians are fewer, but both are in danger of extinction, he said. A team 
of at least five keepers and veterinarians are monitoring the infant and 
17-year-old mother, <ORGANIZATION>Connie</ORGANIZATION>, around the clock "until the situation changes 
drastically," <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
It is unsafe for the 265-pound calf to suckle from his mother, and zoo 
officials cannot milk enough from Connie themselves to ensure his survival, 
<PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Getting milk to the calf is crucial because it contains ingredients that 
develop the youngster's immune system, but park officials are taking it slowly. 
The pair are being reunited every four hours for short periods to try to get 
Connie to accept her son. 
</P>
<P>
"We are still concerned that she might repeat this aggression," <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
During the get-acquainted sessions, <ORGANIZATION>Connie</ORGANIZATION> is bound with leg chains and <ORGANIZATION>Omar</ORGANIZATION> is 
on a leash. The restraints are necessary for the safety of the elephants and 
park officials, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Elephant keeper Ed Marquez offers bottle to the newborn calf. ; Photo, 
BABY ELEPHANT: A baby elephant has been born at Wild Animal Park and park 
officials are worried about its survival. The mother rejected the offspring, 
and keepers are trying to get her to nurse him. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122790-0186 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 328002 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 27, 1990, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 7; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
687 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ZOO ELEPHANT'S DEATH STIRS FUROR; 
</P>
<P>
ANIMALS: HUMANE SOCIETY CRITICIZES SAN DIEGO ZOO OVER ITS 'EXTREMELY DANGEROUS' 
PACHYDERM EXHIBIT. BUT OFFICIALS SCOFF AT HIS STATEMENTS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY WALLACE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Investigators at the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> sent a letter 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo charging that its elephant exhibit is inadequate 
and "extremely dangerous" for both the huge mammals and their keepers. 
</P>
<P>
The letter to <PERSON>Doug Meyers</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION>, was 
prompted by the death <DATE>Sunday</DATE> of <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>, a 51-year-old Asian elephant that was put 
to death after she fell into a moat and crippled herself. 
</P>
<P>
"We do not question the care Maya received after her tragic fall into the moat, 
nor the fact that euthanasia was the humane decision to make on her behalf," 
wrote <PERSON>David K. Wills</PERSON>, a vice president in the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society's Department of 
Investigations</ORGANIZATION>. "However, we are concerned as to what steps zoo officials are 
going to take to improve conditions for the surviving elephants." 
</P>
<P>
Wills criticized the exhibit for its uninsulated floors and its lack of heat 
inside the barn, its limited outdoor shelter and its daily reliance upon chains 
to restrain the elephants. In addition, he charged that a catwalk that connects 
two areas of the elephant yard is precariously narrow, and he called for it to 
be widened. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON>, a spokesman for the zoo, acknowledged that the nearly 30-year-old 
elephant yard is "not perfect," but he said the zoo is in the midst of making 
improvements. So far, they have planted shade trees, he said, and replaced 
decaying floor boards with cement. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said the zoo also plans to widen the catwalk. But he rejected Wills' 
claim that "if the catwalk were widened, <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION> might still be alive today," 
saying that while no one witnessed her fall, her placement in the moat 
indicated she did not fall off the walkway. Jouett also dismissed Wills' 
assertion that the exhibit, which now houses one African and three Asian 
elephants, is "grossly inadequate." 
</P>
<P>
"It has passed <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> inspections, and we'll welcome the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> to come look at it 
again," <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said, noting that <ORGANIZATION>Wills</ORGANIZATION> has asked the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of 
Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> to investigate the exhibit. He called most of Wills' allegations 
"just exaggerations to catch the public's attention. It makes nice quotes but 
it's just not true." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Dr. Homer Malaby</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> animal care specialist in <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, said he will 
visit the zoo next week to investigate the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION>'s allegations. Of 
particular interest, he said, was their charge that the animals have no way to 
escape the rain during the day because they are locked out of their barn. 
</P>
<P>
"If the only shelter the animals have from inclement weather is their indoor 
housing facility, and if they're put out every morning and not allowed back in, 
no matter what the weather, then yes, that would be a violation of the Animal 
Welfare Act," <PERSON>Malaby</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said that the barn door is always opened when it rains. 
</P>
<P>
"They only need walk into the barn," he said, characterizing Wills' letter as 
an attempt to drum up negative publicity. "It's the animal ambulance chaser 
syndrome -- take a tragedy and use it to get your name in the paper." 
</P>
<P>
Wills' letter asserts that nearly half of the zoos approved by the <ORGANIZATION>American 
Assn. of Zoological Parks</ORGANIZATION> and Aquariums have abandoned the practice of chaining 
elephants at night. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said he was "sure" that was an overstatement -- he has only heard of 
a handful of zoos that don't use chains. In the winter months, he said, the <LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION> Zoo chains its elephants for 16 hours a day, while the rest of the year 
the animals are chained for about 12 hours a day. 
</P>
<P>
"They're chained for the protection of the elephants and the people to make 
sure they don't steal each others' food and to maintain the safety of the 
keepers," <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Jouett called Wills' contention that the elephant barn should be heated 
"intentional misrepresentation." 
</P>
<P>
"The temperature in the elephant barn is not cold," he said. Even during the 
recent frigid weather, he said, when the barn is closed at night "a person 
could walk in there and break a sweat. We have four huge animals that are like 
furnaces -- four huge masses of body heat. Elephants have a problem staying 
cool, not staying warm. It's not a concern." 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ELEPHANTS; ANIMAL DEATHS; SAN DIEGO ZOO; INVESTIGATIONS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122790-0085 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 327751 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 27, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 21; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
361 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ZOO'S CARE OF ELEPHANTS CRITICIZED; 
</P>
<P>
ANIMALS: HUMANE SOCIETY LETTER IS PROMPTED BY DEATH OF AN ANIMAL THAT FELL INTO 
MOAT. A SPOKESMAN DENIES CONDITIONS ARE 'GROSSLY INADEQUATE.' 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY WALLACE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In a letter to the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, investigators at the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> of the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> contended <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that the zoo's elephant exhibit is inadequate 
and "extremely dangerous" for both the huge mammals and their keepers. 
</P>
<P>
The open letter to <PERSON>Doug Meyers</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION>, 
was prompted by the death <DATE>Sunday</DATE> of <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>, a 51-year-old Asian elephant. Zoo 
officials ordered that Maya be killed after being crippled by a fall into an 
elephant yard moat. 
</P>
<P>
"We do not question the care Maya received after her tragic fall, nor the fact 
that euthanasia was the humane decision to make on her behalf," wrote <PERSON>David K. 
Wills</PERSON>, a vice president in the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society's Department of Investigations</ORGANIZATION>. 
"However, we are concerned as to what steps zoo officials are going to take to 
improve conditions for the surviving elephants." 
</P>
<P>
Wills contended that there are uninsulated floors and insufficient heat inside 
the barn-like structure and that the exhibit provides limited outdoor shelter. 
He also questioned the daily reliance on chains to restrain the elephants and 
called for widening of the catwalk connecting two parts of the elephant yard. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON>, a spokesman for the zoo, acknowledged that the nearly 30-year-old 
elephant yard is "not perfect," but he said the zoo is improving it. Shade 
trees have been planted and decaying floorboards replaced, he said. The zoo 
also plans to widen the catwalk. 
</P>
<P>
Jouett rejected Wills' charge that Maya might be alive if the catwalk were 
wider, saying no one witnessed her fall or her position on the walkway. He also 
denied that the exhibit, which houses one African and three Asian elephants, is 
"grossly inadequate." 
</P>
<P>
"It has passed <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> inspections and we'll welcome the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> to come look at it 
again," <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said, noting that <ORGANIZATION>Wills</ORGANIZATION> has asked the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of 
Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> to investigate the exhibit. He called most of Wills' allegations 
"exaggerations to catch the public's attention. It makes nice quotes but it's 
just not true." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Dr. Homer Malaby</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> animal-care specialist in <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, said he will 
visit the zoo next week to investigate the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION>'s allegations. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Workers try to help Maya, an injured elephant officials ordered killed. 
San Diego Zoo 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SAN DIEGO ZOO; ANIMALS; ANIMAL DEATHS; HUMANE SOCIETY OF THE UNITED STATES; 
SAFETY; ELEPHANTS; INVESTIGATIONS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA041189-0041 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 42521 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 11, 1989, Tuesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 1; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
767 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
USDA CALLS DUNDA DISCIPLINE EXCESSIVE IN LETTER OF WARNING 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVID SMOLLAR, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The discipline applied by <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal Park keepers to Dunda the 
elephant in <DATE>February, 1988</DATE>, exceeded acceptable measures under federal 
regulations concerning the handling of animals, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of 
Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> concludes in a letter of warning to the <ORGANIZATION>Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <DATE>April 6</DATE> letter said that results of an investigation by the department's 
measures" on <DATE>Feb. 17 and 18, 1988</DATE>, to the 18-year-old female African elephant 
"did cause bruising and damage to the skin on the elephant's head and signs of 
behavioral stress." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>James W. Glosser</PERSON>, the administrator of <ORGANIZATION>APHIS</ORGANIZATION>, reminded the <ORGANIZATION>Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> 
of federal law regarding animal treatment. "Handling of animals shall be done 
as expeditiously and carefully in a way so as not to cause unnecessary 
discomfort, behavioral stress, or physical harm to the animal," <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> wrote. 
"Care should be exercised also to avoid harm to the handler." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said that while zoos obviously require animal control and discipline to 
assure both the safety of animals and the public, "We must warn you that any 
further documented use of such excessive disciplinary measures (as occurred 
with Dunda) may result in legal action to secure compliance" with federal laws. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that its officials 
disagree with the letter's conclusion. 
</P>
<P>
"We stand by our own investigation and the investigations by the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego 
Humane Society</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> city attorney, and the <ORGANIZATION>American Assn. of 
Zoological Parks</ORGANIZATION> and Aquariums, which found that <ORGANIZATION>Dunda</ORGANIZATION>'s short disciplinary 
training sessions were not excessive and did not cause unnecessary discomfort," 
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said that <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> inspectors lack expertise in handling exotic, or zoo 
animals, because their usual experience has been in dealing with domesticated 
animals. 
</P>
<P>
"We are willing to work closely with the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> to develop elephant-training 
guidelines that are beneficial for elephants, and to allow their keepers to 
work safely," <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Sessions Criticized as Brutal 
</P>
<P>
Zoo officials maintain that the discipline, which included chaining <ORGANIZATION>Dunda</ORGANIZATION>'s 
legs, pulling her to the ground, and beating her on the head with ax handles 
for short periods, was necessary to train Dunda not to lash out and try to 
injure her keepers. The incident occurred shortly after <PERSON>Dunda</PERSON> was transferred 
to the Wild Animal Park from the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, where she had spent most of her 
life. 
</P>
<P>
Several of <ORGANIZATION>Dunda</ORGANIZATION>'s former keepers at the zoo criticized the sessions as 
unnecessary and brutal, but the numerous subsequent investigations produced 
conflicting conclusions. While the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> and city attorney's 
office concluded that there was insufficient evidence to prosecute anyone on 
animal cruelty charges, the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> called the 
incident a clear case of abuse. 
</P>
<P>
The incident raised questions of how elephant discipline is handled at zoos 
around the world and whether changes need to be considered. 
</P>
<P>
Sen. <PERSON>Dan McCorquodale</PERSON> (D-San Jose), who took an active interest in the case and 
has introduced legislation to ban zoo elephant rides and limit types of 
discipline, said <DATE>Monday</DATE> he was pleased at the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> letter. 
</P>
<P>
"The people who are on the outside and unrelated to the city and zoo have said 
there was excessive force used, and those that have close ties (to the zoo) 
have tried to smooth the issue over, so I'm satisfied with what the (<ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION>) did 
and it did give a good strong warning and said clearly it will be watching 
things in the future," <PERSON>McCorquodale</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Prohibitions Under Legislation 
</P>
<P>
His legislation, on which a public hearing will be held in the state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> 
later this month, would prohibit elephant discipline that involved use of 
electricity, deprivation of food, water or rest, or any action that results in 
damages, scars or breaks in the skin. It would also prohibit insertion of any 
instrument into an animal's bodily orifices. 
</P>
<P>
"Hopefully, the zoo will look back on this in hindsight and say that what was 
done was not a good thing and go on and try to rebuild its image as it existed 
in the past," <PERSON>McCorquodale</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said that the zoo, while it disagrees with the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> and will so respond, 
"is onto other things" as well. 
</P>
<P>
"There are two elephants now pregnant, three others are suspected of being 
pregnant, and we expect an elephant birth in <DATE>August</DATE>," <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. Dunda is not 
yet ready for a mate, however, because she needs more time to be fully accepted 
into the Wild Animal Park herd, he said. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891202-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-02-89 0540EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SickElephant     12-02 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sick Elephant,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Asian Elephant Dies During Surgery After Caesarean Section</HEAD>
<NOTE>By DAVID SEDENO</NOTE>
<NOTE>Associated Press Writer</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Asian elephant who earlier underwent an
unprecedented Caesarean section died during emergency surgery at
the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>.
   A team of veterinarians worked on Jean, the 19-year-old,
7,000-pound elephant, for about three hours <DATE>Friday</DATE> in hopes of
alleviating complications caused by the death of the fetus in her
womb. But in the end there was nothing they could do to save her,
park spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   The elephant was destroyed with a fatal dose of anesthetic while
still unconscious for the surgery, he said.
   Jean had been fighting a severe abdominal infection caused by
the dead 300-pound fetus, which was removed <DATE>Nov. 20</DATE> during the
first Caesarean section known to have been performed on an elephant.
   After the infection started, veterinarians fed Jean
intravenously and gave her antibiotics and pain killers, but her
condition did not improve and veterinarians operated again <DATE>Friday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME> in a last-ditch attempt to save the pachyderm's life.
   ``Veterinarians attempted to repair the uterus. They were unable
to do so. They also attempted to do a hysterectomy but were unable
to do that because of its size and inaccessibility,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   Jean had made the record books after being pregnant for more
than 730 days, surpassing the pregnancy of an Asian elephant that
gave birth at a zoo in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> after 720 days. The normal gestation
period for the Asian elephant is between 618 and 648 days.
   ``If there is any positive sign to the ordeal, in our attempt to
save her life we have gained a tremendous amount of knowledge that
we can hopefully apply to the care of other elephants,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON>
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030289-0003 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 25063 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 2, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 1; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
564 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BILL WOULD BAN ZOO ELEPHANT RIDES, LIMIT DISCIPLINE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JANE FRITSCH, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Legislation that would ban elephant rides at zoos, circuses and carnivals is 
being prepared at the request of <PERSON>Sen. Dan McCorquodale</PERSON> (D-San Jose), chairman 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Natural Resources Committee</ORGANIZATION>, as part of a comprehensive bill 
dealing with the handling of captive elephants. 
</P>
<P>
The ban, believed to be the first in the country, will be considered <DATE>March 9</DATE> at 
a meeting of a task force formed by <ORGANIZATION>McCorquodale</ORGANIZATION> after an elephant-beating 
incident at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>McCorquodale</PERSON> also has asked the legislative counsel to draft language that 
would make it illegal to discipline an elephant by using electricity, depriving 
it of food, water or rest, or in any way that damages, scars or breaks its 
skin. The bill also would make it a violation of the Penal Code to discipline 
an elephant by inserting any instrument into any bodily orifice, according to a 
letter <PERSON>McCorquodale</PERSON> sent to <ORGANIZATION>Legislative Counsel Bion Gregory</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
McCorquodale plans to introduce the legislation some time this year, but it is 
unclear whether the final version will include the ban on rides, according to 
an aide to <PERSON>McCorquodale</PERSON> who asked not to be named. The aide called the proposed 
ban "very preliminary." The task force, an advisory group that includes zoo 
officials and animal rights activists, will be asked for comment on the bill at 
the meeting in <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> next week. 
</P>
<P>
Strong opposition from zoos throughout the state is expected. 
</P>
<P>
"I can't think of any other spot in the world where it's against the law to 
ride elephants," said <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> of 
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. "Elephant rides are one of the most popular 
attractions. They're a rare opportunity for people to come into contact and 
appreciate the animals in a very special way. Rides are a part of elephant 
history and something that has happened for thousands of years." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> zoos may coordinate a protest of the proposed ban for presentation 
at the task force meeting, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Big Money Maker 
</P>
<P>
Last year, 156,912 elephant rides were given at the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> by a private 
contractor, netting the zoo <MONEY>$80,020</MONEY>, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. The Wild Animal Park, which 
uses its own elephants, gave 60,571 elephant rides in <DATE>1988</DATE>, bringing in 
<MONEY>$106,000</MONEY>, he said. The <ORGANIZATION>Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> operates both the park and the zoo. 
</P>
<P>
Elephant rides also are "extremely popular" at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, according 
to <PERSON>Ed Alonso</PERSON>, animal collection curator there. The rides "give another 
dimension to the public understanding of elephants," <PERSON>Alonso</PERSON> said. "They've been 
domesticated for a number of years." 
</P>
<P>
The push for the ban on elephant rides comes from animal rights advocates on 
the task force who allege that excessive discipline is required to make 
elephants docile enough to safely carry children. 
</P>
<P>
"The thing I have against (rides) is they're the first step toward making 
elephants circus animals in the zoo," said <PERSON>Cleveland Amory</PERSON>, head of the New 
York-based Fund for Animals and a member of <ORGANIZATION>McCorquodale</ORGANIZATION>'s task force. "We have 
to stop all these stupid tricks and standing on drums." 
</P>
<P>
Elephants are so "brow-beaten" in the process of training for rides, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> 
said, "that, by the time it's over, they're not elephants any more, they're 
large zombies." 
</P>
<P>
"They say they have to beat them to protect the keepers, well they have to beat 
them all the harder to protect the public," <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ElephantDies     05-13 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Elephant Dies,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zoo Experts Believe Kidney Failure Caused Elephant's Death</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SYRACUSE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kidney failure was suspected in the death
of an elephant whose calf was stillborn in a Caesarian section last
month, zookeepers said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Babe, a 36-year-old Asian elephant, died <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at Burnet Park
Zoo. The 7,700-pound elephant was taken to <ORGANIZATION>Cornell University</ORGANIZATION>'s
veterinary school, where an autopsy continued <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, said <PERSON>Don
Moore</PERSON>, the zoo's curator of mammals.
   Final autopsy results won't be available for a week to 10 days,
though veterinarians may have preliminary lab results by <DATE>Monday</DATE>,
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> said.
   Babe's death has prompted criticism from animal rights activists
angry over the zoo's breeding program. Burnet Park is small by zoo
standards but has an ambitious breeding program.
   ``May God grant her the peace that man never did,'' said <PERSON>Joyce
Goike</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Central New York Humane Association</ORGANIZATION>. On
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> she asked the zoo to put Babe to sleep rather than
prolong the elephant's suffering.
   Babe's 22-month pregnancy drew worldwide attention from
zookeepers trying to breed endangered Asian elephants in captivity.
   Had the pregnancy been successful, Babe would have been the
oldest elephant to become a first-time mother in a North American
zoo. But after a stalled labor, Babe underwent a Caesarian section
<DATE>April 23</DATE>. Her 266-pound bull calf died in the womb when it could
not position itself properly for birth.
   No elephant has ever recovered after a Caesarian section,
zookeepers said.
   Right up to the time of Babe's death, zookeepers were hopeful
she would recover. A day earlier, Babe had been taken off the
critical list and upgraded to stable condition.
   <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, who helped on the autopsy, said Babe's ``kidneys didn't
look too good'' and that kidney failure probably caused her death.
   <PERSON>Gary MacLachlan</PERSON>, who heads the <LOCATION>Onondaga County</LOCATION> parks agency that
runs the zoo, said Babe's death will raise questions about the
zoo's decision to breed her. ``This may add fuel to any skepticism
people have had,'' he said.
   Animal rights activists complain about the mortality rate of
newborns at the zoo. Of about 300 mammals born there last year, 59
died.
   The zoo's breeding program will continue despite Babe's death,
said County Executive <PERSON>Nicholas Pirro</PERSON>. A second Asian elephant at
the zoo is expected to give birth in <DATE>July 1991</DATE>.
   ``Nothing that has happened will stop us from what the zoo
people believe, and I agree, is the best we can do to preserve this
species,'' <PERSON>Pirro</PERSON> said.
   An Asian elephant expert agreed that Burnet Park should continue
its breeding program.
   ``They're certainly not guilty of anything except incredibly bad
luck,'' said <PERSON>Roger Henneous</PERSON>, senior elephant keeper at the
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Park Zoo in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore</LOCATION>. The <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Park Zoo, the
nation's premier Asian elephant breeder, has had 24 births in the
past 28 years.
   Only 62 Asian elephants have been born in captivity. The species
numbers fewer than 45,000 in the wild.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06076080 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06076080 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; SHE WAS THEIR FRIEND -- A months-old photo
shows trainer Pamela C. Orsi with one of her pachyderm charges.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-DIEGO; ANIMAL; PARK; ACCIDENT; DEATH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  State and federal agencies began their investigation Friday into the death of
an elephant keeper who was trampled during a fight between two elephants at
the San Diego Wild Animal Park.;    Park officials are conducting their own
inquiry, along with the independent investigations opened by the California
Division of Occupational Safety and Health and the U.S. Department of
Agriculture.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  U.S., STATE PROBE ZOO TRAGEDY
TRAINER CAUGHT IN THE MIDDLE AS ELEPHANTS
FOUGHT  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Pamela C. Orsi</PERSON>, 27, was killed <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. She suffered extensive head
injuries after being knocked to the ground during the fight between Asian
elephants named <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> and Cha-Cha.;    Park spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON> said the
accident was witnessed by four park visitors who said one elephant charged the
other and that <PERSON>Orsi</PERSON> was caught in the middle.;    Initially, it was thought
she may have tried to intervene to break up the fight between the elephants.
But <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said that, based on the witness accounts, it appeared she did not
have a chance to react and literally was caught between the two battling
elephants.;    <ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> cautioned it was too early to say exactly what
happened. He said the park has indefinitely suspended its elephant shows and
public feedings of the animals. He added that park officials were reviewing
policies and procedures regarding the handling of elephants.;    No
disciplinary or isolation measures are planned against the animals involved.
Hanscom said it is common for elephants to physically challenge each other to
establish a social order within the herd.;    There are nine Asian elephants
at the park.;    The death of <PERSON>Orsi</PERSON> was the first animal-caused fatality at the
19-year-old park, which is affiliated with the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Orsi</PERSON> was
recalled <DATE>Friday</DATE> as an animal lover and a warm, outgoing person.;    "She was a
perfect child," her father, <PERSON>Ronald Orsi</PERSON>, said from his home in <LOCATION>Manhasset</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Orsi</PERSON> said his daughter had moved to <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> just about a year ago
after working at the <LOCATION>Bronx Zoo</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for five years.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Diego  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910316  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  345  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday March 16, 1991
00076080,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA041189-0023 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 42423 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 11, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 3; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
357 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WILD ANIMAL PARK DRAWS WARNING ON INCIDENT INVOLVING ELEPHANT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVID SMOLLAR, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Discipline exceeding acceptable levels was applied by <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal 
Park keepers to Dunda the elephant in <DATE>February, 1988</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of 
Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> has concluded in a letter of warning to the <ORGANIZATION>Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> of 
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <DATE>April 6</DATE> letter said that results of an investigation by the department's 
measures" on <DATE>Feb. 17 and 18, 1988</DATE>, to the 18-year-old female African elephant 
"did cause bruising and damage to the skin on the elephant's head and signs of 
behavioral stress." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>James W. Glosser</PERSON>, inspection service administrator, said that while zoos have 
to employ discipline to assure both the safety of animals and the public, "we 
must warn you that any further documented use of such excessive disciplinary 
measures (as occurred with Dunda) may result in legal action to secure 
compliance" with federal laws. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that its officials 
disagree with the letter's conclusion. 
</P>
<P>
"We stand by our own investigation and the investigations by the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego 
Humane Society</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> city attorney and the <ORGANIZATION>American Assn. of 
Zoological Parks</ORGANIZATION> and Aquariums, which found that <ORGANIZATION>Dunda</ORGANIZATION>'s short disciplinary 
training sessions were not excessive and did not cause unnecessary discomfort," 
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Zoo officials maintain that the discipline, which included chaining <ORGANIZATION>Dunda</ORGANIZATION>'s 
legs, pulling her to the ground and beating her on the head with ax handles for 
short periods, was necessary to train Dunda not to lash out and try to injure 
her keepers. The incident occurred shortly after <PERSON>Dunda</PERSON> was transferred to the 
Wild Animal Park from the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, where she had spent most of her life. 
</P>
<P>
Several of <ORGANIZATION>Dunda</ORGANIZATION>'s former keepers at the zoo criticized the sessions as 
unnecessary and brutal, but the numerous subsequent investigations produced 
conflicting conclusions. While the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> and city attorney's 
office concluded that there was insufficient evidence to prosecute anyone on 
animal cruelty charges, the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> called the 
incident a clear case of abuse. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SAN DIEGO WILD ANIMAL PARK; CRUELTY TO ANIMALS; INVESTIGATIONS; ANIMAL RIGHTS; 
ELEPHANTS; DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (U.S.); ZOOLOGICAL SOCIETY OF SAN DIEGO; 
ANIMAL TRAINING 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880412-0118 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf: Pachyderm Portraits </HL>
<AUTHOR> Raymond Sokolov </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Cynthia Moss</PERSON> left <ORGANIZATION>Newsweek</ORGANIZATION> in the late <DATE>1960s</DATE> for a vacation in the game parks of <LOCATION>East Africa</LOCATION>. 
She was hooked for life and settled over there permanently in <DATE>1968</DATE>, eventually embarking on a 14-year study of the free-ranging elephants in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Amboseli Park</LOCATION>. 
For much of that time she lived in a tent with a view of <ORGANIZATION>Mt. Kilimanjaro</ORGANIZATION>. 
Although she was not a biologist when she arrived, she was a quick study and has published many articles in professional journals about every aspect of elephant life and death, based on a unique backlog of experience in the field. 

   In "Elephant Memories: Thirteen Years in the Life of an Elephant Family" (<ORGANIZATION>Morrow</ORGANIZATION>, 336 pages, <MONEY>$22.95</MONEY>), <PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON> speaks to the general reader, with charm as well as scientific authority. 
In the end, her elegantly written and ingeniously structured account makes a powerful argument for the preservation of elephants from poachers who supply ivory to Japanese carvers and from legal marksmen hired to "cull" park herds and thereby save trees from being devoured. 

   She was helped along by the African Wildlife Fund, the <ORGANIZATION>New York Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> and various individuals. 
Her main tool of research was an aged Land Rover that took her safely among the big beasts. 
For all the years she went out day after day looking for elephants, her most basic and valuable activity was the one she began on the first day. 
It amounted to taking attendance. 
Having given every one of several hundred elephants an individual name and memorized their appearances from observation and from studying photographs systematically shot for identification purposes, she was then in a position to "know" a large wild population. 
And by the time you get even a short way into <PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON>'s book, so will you. 

   Drawing on hundreds and hundreds of days of meticulous observation, <PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON> introduces her discussions of one subject or another with true stories built on real experience. 
Sometimes the narrative is clearly straight firsthand reportage. 
Other times it is a composite rendering or an imaginative reconstruction. 

   It is hard to see how any fair-minded person could object to these graceful vignettes. 
People with a strong aversion to anthropomorphic writing about animals will, however, find some passages to object to here. 
<PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON> is not shy about claiming to know what is in the minds of elephants at various times. 
On the other hand, many of her inferences do seem reasonable. 
For example, she concludes that an orphaned elephant calf is mourning his mother when he strokes her dismembered jaw, having come upon it in <PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON>'s camp where she was studying it several weeks after the death. 

   Some of these anthropomorphic passages serve mainly to show something quite interesting about the mentality of a sensitive animal researcher. 
When she describes the death of the matriarch <PERSON>Teresia</PERSON>, from infected Maasai spear wounds, <PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON> imagines what the semiconscious elephant is thinking: "She had reached a state of feeling little and she mostly dreamed, perhaps of vast swards of sweet new grass and clear, cool hill streams. 
Or the taste and feel of the sweet juices that squirted out when she crunched down on her favorite wild fruit. 
Or most likely the smell and touch and sounds of her family -- those who were still alive and others who were long gone, her grandmother, mother, sisters and brothers, sons and daughters." 

   That's not merely an affecting passage, one which brings a sad tale of killing to an end, it is a window into the mind of <PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON> and it shows the sort of imaginative sympathy that drove her forward for 14 years and helped her define and solve formal problems of elephant behavior. 
By thinking herself as best she could into the processes of elephant "thought," using what she knew scientifically and intuitively about the animal she knew best -- herself -- she was able to position herself fruitfully in the park and to hypothesize effectively. 
If she had not been interested, as a woman, in motherhood and female sexuality, would <PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON> have been such a successful documenter of the patterns of movement and sociability that can be lumped together as an objective proof that elephant families are a functioning, self-conscious matriarchy? 
If she had not been struck, as a woman, by the grotesque exudations streaming from the temporal glands and four-foot, S-shaped penises of certain adult male elephants, would she have been led to identify this "disease" as musth, the sexual frenzy of male estrus never before documented in African elephants? 
The whole wild mess of musth never did appeal to her. 
"Personally," she writes, "I cannot imagine why Tia wanted to mate with Bad Bull, but then she may have seen something in him that I did not." 

   This is a passionate book written for the most part with scientific restraint. 
<PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON> cares deeply about educating the rest of us, but she also wants to communicate the orderly excitement of field research and of entering into elephant life. 
By drawing us in, she hopes to recruit all of us to her cause, which is the elephant's. 
In a brief call to arms at the end of this splendid addition to the literature of natural history, <PERSON>Ms. Moss</PERSON> permits herself a plea from the heart: "In the <DATE>last two years</DATE> I have realized that more than anything else, more than scientific discoveries or acceptance, what I care about and what I will fight for is the conservation, for as long as possible, not of just a certain number of elephants, but of the whole way of life of elephants." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122990-0058 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 328702 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 29, 1990, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1226 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BATTLE INTENSIFIES OVER ZOO'S ELEPHANT EXHIBIT; 
</P>
<P>
ANIMAL CARE: HUMANE SOCIETY ATTACKS CREDIBILITY OF PARK'S SPOKESMAN, WHO DENIES 
ENCLOSURE IS INADEQUATE FOLLOWING THE DEATH OF A 51-YEAR-OLD MAMMAL. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY WALLACE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In the latest tit-for-tat exchange with the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, investigators at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> attacked the credibility of the 
zoo's spokesman and restated their belief that the elephant exhibit is badly in 
need of repairs. 
</P>
<P>
"There is no nice way to put this," <PERSON>David K. Wills</PERSON>, a vice president in the 
<ORGANIZATION>Humane Society's Department of Investigations</ORGANIZATION>, said in a press release 
rebutting several published statements made by <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON>, the zoo's 
spokesman. "He's just not telling the truth." 
</P>
<P>
To support that claim, Wills provided documents that appear to show that top 
zoo officials sought in <DATE>1984</DATE> to widen a narrow cat walk and in <DATE>1985</DATE> assessed 
how much it would cost to install heaters in the elephant barn. As yet, neither 
improvement has been made, and <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> has said that heaters are unnecessary 
because the elephants' body heat is furnace-like. 
</P>
<P>
Wills and <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> have been trading charges in the press since <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, when 
The Times reported that the Humane Society was seeking an investigation of the 
exhibit after the death of <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>, a 51-year-old Asian elephant that was 
euthanized after she fell into a moat and injured herself. Wills charged that 
<ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>'s death proved that the elephant enclosure is "grossly inadequate." 
</P>
<P>
But, on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Wills</ORGANIZATION>' allegations stemmed solely from "a 
disgruntled employee who now makes a profession out of zoo-bashing" -- a 
reference to <PERSON>Lisa Landres</PERSON>, a former elephant keeper at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo who is 
now a <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> investigator based in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. Landres resigned in <DATE>1989</DATE> 
because, she said, the zoo was punishing her for being outspoken about the 
beating of the elephant Dunda. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON>, who has acknowledged that the elephant exhibit is "not perfect," said 
that, by necessity, repairs at the 100-acre zoo must be done in order of 
priority. Although the zoo plans to widen the cat walk eventually, he said, it 
is not an urgent need. 
</P>
<P>
"If there's an immediate concern for animal health or safety or human health or 
safety, then it rises to the top of the priority list," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Wills, meanwhile, provided a copy of an internal zoo memo, dated <DATE>Aug. 9, 1984</DATE>, 
in which zoo officials listed, in order of priority, what they called 
"modifications requirements" in the elephant mesa. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Alan Roocroft</PERSON>, the elephant supervisor for the zoo and Wild Animal Park, said 
the first priority was improved access for heavy-duty vehicles -- an 
improvement that <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said has since been completed. The second priority, in 
a list of six, suggested replacing a large pool with a smaller one in order to 
accommodate wider walkways. 
</P>
<P>
"Currently it is not possible for more than one animal to safely negotiate its 
way around the pool," <PERSON>Roocroft</PERSON>'s memo said. "In addition, the space is so 
narrow that the possibility always exists that an animal might lose its footing 
and tumble into the moat." 
</P>
<P>
Another memo a month later estimated that it would cost <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> to make those 
changes to the pool and cat walk. 
</P>
<P>
When asked whether <PERSON>Roocroft</PERSON>'s safety concerns would classify the 
walkway-widening project as urgent, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said no. He said that, although no 
one witnessed <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>'s fall on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, he believes she did not fall off the cat 
walk. 
</P>
<P>
"An elephant can be bumped into the moat from any point in the exhibit, whether 
on the cat walk or not," he said. In response to the memo, he said: "It doesn't 
say the elephants were at risk if they were walking in single file. It doesn't 
say that one animal is in danger. Yesterday I saw two elephants there -- they 
walked the whole length and lived to tell about it." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Steve Friedlund</PERSON>, an elephant keeper who was the first to rush to <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>'s aid 
after she fell, said that it is "almost an absolute sure bet" that <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION> fell 
from the cat walk. When Friedlund found the elephant, her back legs were in the 
moat and her front elbows were resting on the cat walk, indicating that she had 
fallen head-first from the walk and was trying to right herself. 
</P>
<P>
"The walkway is a death trap," said <PERSON>Friedlund</PERSON>, who estimated the cat walk is 2 
1/2 feet wide. "The zoo has known the problem for a long time. They're 
defending their Disneyland image that everything is safe and sound here. It's 
time to get on with the business of solving the problem." 
</P>
<P>
Another inter-office memo provided by <ORGANIZATION>Wills</ORGANIZATION> estimates the cost of installing 
elephant barn floor heating. In the <DATE>September, 1985</DATE> memo, <PERSON>Hella Winter</PERSON>, a 
project coordinator in the zoo's architecture and design department, estimated 
that it would cost <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY> to install a 12-foot-wide heated strip in the 
concrete floor that would run the full length of the barn. 
</P>
<P>
The memo was addressed to Friedlund, <PERSON>Carmi G. Penny</PERSON>, the zoo's curator of 
mammals, and another animal care specialist who has since left the zoo. At the 
bottom, <DATE>Winter</DATE> has written: "Please call us &amp; let's decide ASAP what to 
do!" 
</P>
<P>
According to <LOCATION>Wills</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Winter</ORGANIZATION>'s memo came in response to keeper documentation of 
frigid temperatures -- 40 degrees and lower -- in the elephant barn at night. 
</P>
<P>
"Without heating in the floor, the concrete draws the body heat away from the 
elephants when they lie down," Wills' press release asserts, adding that the 
keepers recorded the cold temperatures when there were seven elephants in the 
barn. "With only four left, <PERSON>Mr. Jouett</PERSON>'s idea that they are 'furnaces' loses 
even more credibility." 
</P>
<P>
Jouett responded that he had heard that <PERSON>Landres</PERSON> and Friedlund measured the 
temperatures in a zoo office, not in the barn, "in an attempt to prove their 
point." 
</P>
<P>
Friedlund countered that in fact, <PERSON>Curby Simerson</PERSON>, the zoo's assistant animal 
care manager, was the person who held the thermometer in the barn. It read 34 
degrees, he said. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said that was impossible. 
</P>
<P>
"It's not 40 degrees in the barn with the elephants," he said. "Consider the 
source. . . . Two years gone and 3,000 miles away, <PERSON>Lisa</PERSON> (<PERSON>Landres</PERSON>) is still 
trying to push through her pet projects, and she's using (The Times) to do 
that." 
</P>
<P>
Reached in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <PERSON>Landres</PERSON> said, "That's just a lie. You wouldn't 
believe how cold it is in there. Whether I worked there or not, why don't they 
focus their energy on making the place better?" 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sally Mackler</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for the animal rights group <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Animal 
Advocates, echoed those sentiments. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a poor excuse and an easy out to blame a 'disgruntled employee,' " 
<PERSON>Mackler</PERSON> said in a statement. "We should take a closer look at why <PERSON>Lisa Landres</PERSON> 
was dissatisfied with zoo policies and methods regarding the elephants' care." 
</P>
<P>
Wills also contested <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON>'s claim that the elephants may take shelter in 
their barn during inclement daytime weather. 
</P>
<P>
"The elephant barn has not been made available to the elephants as a shelter 
from the rain, except in rare, isolated instances when past keeper staff let 
the elephants indoors due to extreme cold or wind," Wills wrote. "With this 
documentation in hand, you may join with us in realizing that it's difficult to 
know what to believe when the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo responds to criticism." 
</P>
<P>
Jouett responded: "In a hard, cold rain, the doors are opened. If it's a warm 
day or a light shower, and they're showing no ill effects, the doors probably 
won't be open. For an elephant, that's not inclement weather." 
</P>
<P>
He added, "What happens if it rains in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>? Do the elephants run in 
the barn then? The elephants like the rain." 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890301-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-01-89 0927EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ElephantTrouble     03-01 0264</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Elephant Trouble,0272</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tacoma Zoo Needs More Room for Elephants</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TACOMA, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The elephants of Point Defiance Zoo are
getting bigger homes at a <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> cost, improvements
necessitated largely by a profoundly problematic pachyderm named
<PERSON>Cindy</PERSON>, the zoo director says.
   Cindy, a 24-year-old from <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, is returning after six years on
loan to the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. In fact, the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> zoo
is pleading with <LOCATION>Tacoma</LOCATION> officials to hasten <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON>'s return, said zoo
director <PERSON>Tom Otten</PERSON>.
   It isn't so much that the four-ton <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> wouldn't mate with any
of the bull elephants in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, but three weeks ago she broke a
handler's collarbone with a slap of her trunk.
   ``From time to time, <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> has made aggressive motions toward
keepers she doesn't like, and that's most of our keepers,'' said
<PERSON>Joel Edelstein</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> zoo. ``We wouldn't fight the
decision to let her go.''
   The return has added urgency to the need to build bigger elephant
barns, using money from a prior bond issue.
   Otherwise, <PERSON>Otten</PERSON> said, ``We'll have to go out of the elephant
business.''
   <PERSON>Moyo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Thandi</PERSON>, the zoo's 8-year-old female African elephants,
also could use larger quarters, <PERSON>Otten</PERSON> said.
   Part of the plan is for construction this <DATE>summer</DATE> of a special
yard for <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> with an elephant ``crush,'' a hydraulic steel device
to contain the animal while trainers trim toenails and tusks,
administer medication and take blood and fluid samples.
   The <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> zoo does not have such a device, so trainers must
rely on each other to keep elephants still.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA020189-0013 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 12541 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 1, 1989, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 2; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1132 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PROBLEM ELEPHANT BREAKS COLLARBONE OF KEEPER AT ANIMAL PARK 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TOM GORMAN, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A rambunctious female Asian elephant with a history of outbursts attacked an 
animal keeper without provocation <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>, 
sending him to the hospital with a broken collarbone. 
</P>
<P>
The elephant, a 26-year-old named <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON>, shoved the keeper with her trunk and 
head. The trainer ended up at the bottom of an 8-foot-deep concrete moat before 
other keepers came to his rescue. 
</P>
<P>
The keeper was identified as 21-year-old <PERSON>David SaoMarcos</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, who had 
worked at the park for a year and was assigned to the Asian and African 
elephant yards. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Similar Attack 3 Years Ago 
</P>
<P>
SaoMarcos was taken by <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> paramedics to <ORGANIZATION>Palomar Medical Center</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>, where he was listed in fair condition with a fractured clavicle, 
bruises, cuts and scrapes. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s incident was the second in which the 8,000-pound <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> caused injury 
to a Wild Animal Park employee, park spokeswoman <PERSON>Martha Baker</PERSON> said. Three years 
ago, <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> lashed out at another keeper with her trunk, knocking him to the 
ground and also breaking his collarbone. Cindy has also tussled with other 
keepers at the park during her six years there, but without serious injuries, 
<PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said. SaoMarcos, who does not work directly with <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON>, was cleaning the 
Asian elephant yard <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> and was pushing a wheelbarrow of manure 
when <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> "rapidly approached him from across the yard and struck him with her 
trunk and head," <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"SaoMarcos tried to get away by going through a gate, but <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> followed and 
continued to hit and kick him" with her front feet, <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"Then, the details get sketchy. SaoMarcos ended up at the bottom of the moat. 
He's not sure if he slipped, jumped or she pushed him," <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said. "Within two 
minutes, other keepers came to his aid. He was climbing out of the moat, but 
was in great pain." 
</P>
<P>
The elephant was not disciplined after <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s incident, <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said, because 
about two minutes had passed between the attack and the time other keepers 
arrived, "and she wouldn't have associated any punishment with what she did." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Reluctant to Compare 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said she was reluctant to compare <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> to Dunda, an 18-year-old African 
elephant at the park that became the focus of investigations into the handling 
and discipline of elephants at the facility, renowned for its success in 
breeding endangered species. 
</P>
<P>
Dunda was chained by all four legs, pulled to the ground and beaten on the 
forehead with ax handles and the wooden end of elephant hooks over two days 
last year as discipline for striking out at keepers, park officials said. <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> 
said <PERSON>Dunda</PERSON> was disciplined immediately after she lashed out at trainers. The 
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> city attorney's office declined to prosecute trainers for the 
incident, which generated intense debate about proper discipline of the 
animals. 
</P>
<P>
Cindy is on a breeding loan to the Wild Animal Park from <ORGANIZATION>Point Defiance Zoo</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Tacoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, where she was known as a rogue, having injured trainers there -- 
one so badly that he too had to be hospitalized. 
</P>
<P>
Cindy was a 2-year-old refugee from a traveling zoo and was the only elephant 
at the <ORGANIZATION>Point Defiance Zoo</ORGANIZATION> during her 18 years there, said <PERSON>Lily Moore</PERSON>, the zoo's 
assistant director. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> said <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> was maladjusted because of her years in isolation from other 
elephants, and said keepers hoped she would not only breed but experience the 
normal hierarchal nature of elephants at the Wild Animal Park. 
</P>
<P>
But the park's elephant keepers said <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> never acclimated to her new 
surroundings and failed to socialize with the other animals. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Bull Doesn't Like Her 
</P>
<P>
The park's breeding bull "does not like her," <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said. Even before <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s 
attack, the park was planning to transfer her to yet another zoo, thereby 
freeing her stall for a more willing breeding partner. 
</P>
<P>
Cindy's unruly behavior was well known among the trainers and keepers who work 
with the park's elephants, <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said. "The keepers are very wary around her 
and take extra precautions. Only two keepers will work closely with her. The 
other keepers stay away." 
</P>
<P>
Cindy is not used for rides at the park, nor does she have a role in the park's 
elephant shows, although her trainers have had some success in teaching her to 
lie down and to raise her right foot in a sort of salute. 
</P>
<P>
Baker described <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON>'s behavior <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as "totally unexplainable, 
unpredictable and out of the blue." The elephant was not removed from the herd 
of eight other Asian cows and the single bull Asian elephant. 
</P>
<P>
"There was no point in isolating her," <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said. "She received nothing for 
her activity because, unless you catch them in the act, they can't associate 
that (punishment) with that misbehavior." 
</P>
<P>
In contrast, <PERSON>Dunda</PERSON> has not misbehaved since she was disciplined, <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Not Sure What to Do 
</P>
<P>
Point Defiance Zoo officials, meanwhile, are not sure what to do with <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"We are looking at a number of facilities as possible relocations for her," 
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> said, "including bringing her back to <ORGANIZATION>Point Defiance</ORGANIZATION>. We haven't decided 
what's best for <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON>, and that's our bottom line: what's best for her 
long-term care." 
</P>
<P>
Asian elephants live into their 60s, and are in their prime breeding years 
between 25 and 40, meaning that <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> is potentially important for the 
endangered species, <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Cindy's problem is a result of her upbringing as an only elephant, keepers 
said. 
</P>
<P>
"She grew up alone, which isn't a good idea because she's a herd species and 
needed to be subjected to normal hierarchical kinds of things that elephants 
establish in a herd," <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> said. "But <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> didn't have that, and that was 
part of her behavioral maladjustment. 
</P>
<P>
"A parallel would be for a person to be raised to adulthood and never being 
taught manners, and expecting her to be able to behave by the rules. It's 
certainly not <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON>'s fault she's got behavioral problems, and it's not the 
fault of the person who raised her here." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Hard to Find a Good Home 
</P>
<P>
Officials hoped she would do better at the <ORGANIZATION>Wild Animal Park</ORGANIZATION>, with its herd of 
Asian elephants and more room to roam. 
</P>
<P>
"But the disappointment for them is that she's still a difficult animal, and 
will be, wherever she is," <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> said. "Since she is our animal, we'd like to 
bring her home or find a suitable home for her, but finding a suitable home is 
more than just name-that-zoo." 
</P>
<P>
Among the zoos negotiating for <PERSON>Cindy</PERSON> is the one in <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, which has a 
proven breeding bull. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Don Moore</PERSON>, curator of mammals at the <ORGANIZATION>Syracuse Zoo</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that he is 
still interested in <LOCATION>Cindy</LOCATION> despite her attack on the keeper. 
</P>
<P>
"These animals aren't like dogs," he said. "They're bigger than Volkswagens. We 
know their danger potential. They are individuals, but they are handleable. In 
<PERSON>Cindy</PERSON>'s case, we're prepared for a certain amount of hands-off management." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Cindy, shown in a 1983 photo at the Wild Animal Park, was transferred 
from Tacoma, Wash., but has not adjusted well. DAVE GATLEY / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901208-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-08-90 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ElephantMan Bjt   12-08 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Elephant Man, Bjt,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arkansas Man Opens Elephant Farm</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JULIE STEWART</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LITTLE ROCK, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Scott Riddle</PERSON> is making a home where the
elephants roam, where he and the pachyderms can play. Three of
them, weighing at least 4,000 pounds each, lumber around his farm
where cows once grazed.
   Riddle has trained elephants for 26 years for circuses, movies
and advertising. Now the veteran of the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo and other
zoos is establishing a breeding farm and sanctuary for elephants on
his 330-acre spread in <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>.
   ``He's an unusual man,'' said <PERSON>Tony Valenzuela</PERSON>, curator of
mammals at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo and a member of the board of
<ORGANIZATION>Riddle</ORGANIZATION>'s organization.
   Last fall, <PERSON>Riddle</PERSON> left his home in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, for <LOCATION>Quitman</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ark</LOCATION>. He and his wife, <PERSON>Heidi</PERSON>, packed up their two children in the
family motor home, and <PERSON>Mary</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Mugsy</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Solomon</PERSON> climbed into their
custom-built trailer.
   Mary, a 16-year-old Asian elephant, has been with <PERSON>Riddle</PERSON> for
half of her life. She was deemed untrainable when he found her, but
now children climb aboard her for rides at the Little Rock Zoo.
   His other two elephants are from <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, where they had faced
death in a culling, or herd-thinning, operation. Riddle, who
disagrees with culling, said baby elephants that can be sold are
spared.
   That's how Solomon and Mugsy ended up in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. Riddle said
they had been bought by a wealthy man ``who wanted a bunch of
elephants.'' When the novelty wore thin for the prior owner, Riddle
acquired them about five years ago.
   Besides beginning a breeding program, Riddle plans to take in
other orphan elephants. ``We will open the door to any elephant
that needs a home,'' he said. ``And I think that people will call
us.''
   But it's costly to run an elephant farm. Riddle estimated the
weekly cost of keeping one elephant runs about <MONEY>$100</MONEY>. He established
a non-profit corporation last <DATE>summer</DATE> to seek donations,
sponsorships and memberships.
   ``We're the only non-profit corporation dedicated solely to
elephants, I believe, in the world. ... The animal business is
getting very hard because of the position in the world of the
animals, especially elephants, getting extinct,'' he said.
   Poaching, culling and loss of habitat are the greatest threats
to the elephant's survival, said <PERSON>Riddle</PERSON>, who calls for a lifting of
limits on importation of elephants to this country.
   At his farm, Riddle plans to offer instruction on basic handling
of elephants. ``You'd be surprised how many people in the public
want to do it,'' he said.
   ``I'm not a bleeding heart but I think if we can save one
elephant, we can accomplish something. If we save one person from
being hurt, we've accomplished something, because elephants can be
dangerous,'' he said.
   Riddle ranks elephants alongside dolphins and the great apes in
intelligence.
   ``I've been around elephants long enough to know that they are
very, very intelligent,'' he said. ``They have a very intricate
social structure, they discipline their young.
   ``They think, they reason, they plan.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900416-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-16-90 0016EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PregnantPachyderms     04-16 0755</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pregnant Pachyderms,0776</SECOND>
<HEAD>Asian Elephant Birth Important Event For Zoo, Species Survival</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM KATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYRACUSE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The amorous escapades of a 10,000-pound
Asian elephant named Indy have captured the attention of the zoo
world.
   The 18-year-old pachyderm has impregnated two females at the
Burnet Park Zoo. Babe is expected to deliver her baby around the
<DATE>last week of April</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Romani</ORGANIZATION> is due in <DATE>July 1991</DATE>.
   That's earth-shaking news for the continent's zoos, where just
62 calves have ever been born in captivity. It's also a sign of
promise for the 35,000 to 45,000 Asian elephants that remain in the
wild as an endangered species.
   ``North American zoos are getting serious about reproducing
elephants. The two pregnancies at <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION> is evidence we are
making progress,'' said <PERSON>Tom Foose</PERSON>, conservation director for the
<ORGANIZATION>American Association of Zoological Parks</ORGANIZATION> and Aquariums.
   To highlight the importance of the twin pregnancies,
<LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> Zoological Park Director <PERSON>Dale Tuttle</PERSON> said there are
only six other zoos with pregnant Asian elephants. An elephant's
pregnancy lasts 22 months.
   Only 14 of the AAZPA's approximately 150-member zoos have the
facilities to breed Asian elephants, said <PERSON>Tuttle</PERSON>, coordinator of
the AAZPA's Species Survival Plan for Asian elephants.
   ``There are only 11 proven male breeders in captivity and just
12 females that have reproduced,'' said <PERSON>Foose</PERSON>. ``What's going on in
<LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION> is very impressive _ and very significant.''
   ``The survival of the species is dependent, in part, upon the
establishment and maintenance of viable breeding of captive
populations in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>. And that's where we come in,'' said
Burnet Park Zoo Director <PERSON>Dave Raboy</PERSON>.
   Like the decision to have a child, starting an elephant family
is not a commitment entered into lightly.
   The zoo decided in <DATE>1979</DATE> that it wanted to breed elephants, said
curator <PERSON>Don Moore</PERSON>. It began by transforming the 350-square-foot
indoor pen that housed its one elephant, <PERSON>Siri</PERSON>, into a spacious
3,200-square-foot indoor-outdoor living area with a breeding barn.
   Romani was purchased in <DATE>1984</DATE> from a circus, which bought her
from an elephant orphanage in <LOCATION>Sri Lanka</LOCATION>. Indy, also an ex-circus
performer from <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Babe</ORGANIZATION>, a one-time gift to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
ambassador to <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, came to <LOCATION>Burnet Park</LOCATION> in <DATE>June 1985</DATE>.
   With dual pregnancies and a virile male to make it worthwhile,
<LOCATION>Burnet Park</LOCATION> this year is spending <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> to thrust itself fully
into elephant breeding. The money will be used to further enlarge
and modify the zoo's elephant habitat.
   A single elephant can cost more than <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> and a suitable
habitat, hundreds of thousands more.
   ``There's no secret,'' said <PERSON>Roger Henneous</PERSON>, the senior elephant
keeper at the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Park Zoo in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, the nation's
premier Asian elephant breeder. ``In order to have babies you have
to accommodate adult males. You're talking a tremendous financial,
physical commitment to accommodate a mature male. Most places can't
or won't. It's that simple.''
   <LOCATION>Washington Park Zoo</LOCATION>, which has had 24 births in the <DATE>past 28
years</DATE>, has accommodations for three males among its 12-animal herd.
   <PERSON>Chuck Doyle</PERSON>, the senior elephant handler at <LOCATION>Burnet Park</LOCATION>, says
there are other important factors in elephant breeding, one of
which is luck.
   ``Copulation is a learned behavior among elephants. A female has
to see another couple mating, otherwise she won't allow the male to
breed her,'' said <PERSON>Doyle</PERSON>, who broke some ribs in attempts to get
Babe matched up with a mate. ``For three years, we watched Indy
push the females around without success. Finally, he pushed Babe
the right way. Romani needed less time because she witnessed Indy
and Babe.''
   Babe's calf, which will likely weigh about 200 pounds, will be
the first one born at <LOCATION>Burnet Park</LOCATION>. So it's understandable the zoo _
like a first-time parent _ has been excited about the pregnancy.
   ``I feel like I felt having our first child,'' said <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>.
   It's also a first for Babe, who at 36 may be the oldest
first-time Asian elephant mother in captivity. Trainers worry she
may not know what to do when she delivers.
   Babe has gained more than 1,150 pounds since she became pregnant
in <DATE>June 1988</DATE>. She tipped 7,450 when she was weighed by state police
on a truck scale <DATE>Jan. 24</DATE>.
   ``She's a very, very nervous animal, and she's not real thrilled
about people,'' <PERSON>Doyle</PERSON> said at one point, although he said she has
become more sociable during her pregnancy.
   Romani and <PERSON>Siri</PERSON>, who has resisted Indy's advances, will be
allowed to watch the birth, zoo officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102189-0083 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 123723 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 21, 1989, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1059 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
2 ELEPHANTS AT ZOO KEPT CHAINED IN CRAMPED BARNS; 
</P>
<P>
ABUSE: CRITICISM BY THE PRIVATE KEEPER OF THE ANIMALS, WHICH FOR SIX YEARS GAVE 
RIDES AT THE ZOO, ADDS FUEL TO A CONTROVERSIAL SUBJECT. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY WALLACE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Two elephants, which have worked at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo giving rides for six 
years, have spent more than 18 hours a day chained in cramped camel barns since 
the zoo <DATE>last week</DATE> severed a contract with the company that owns them. 
</P>
<P>
Since <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>, when the zoo abruptly fired <ORGANIZATION>Trunk &amp; Hump</ORGANIZATION>, the elephant and 
camel ride company, it has not allowed the elephants, <PERSON>Katie</PERSON> and Gypsy, to play 
in its recreation areas, according to their keeper, <PERSON>Steve Whitebread</PERSON>. When 
Whitebread let them exercise in the smaller ride area, he said, zoo officials 
told him to stop because they were ruining the foliage. Whitebread disobeyed. 
</P>
<P>
"I just decided there's no way we'd leave them chained up all day," he said. 
"The zoo cut us off. Their attitude is, 'Just keep (the elephants) quiet, don't 
let anybody see them, and get them out of here as soon as possible.' " 
</P>
<P>
The zoo's eagerness to hide the elephants was evident <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, when 
employees put up four 8-foot wooden barriers to hide <PERSON>Katie</PERSON> and Gypsy from 
public view. <PERSON>Georgeanne Irvine</PERSON>, a zoo spokeswoman, said the blinds were erected 
after a keeper saw a family climb the low fence and begin petting the animals. 
"It was a potential safety hazard," she said. 
</P>
<P>
Irvine acknowledged that the elephants have not used zoo recreation areas all 
week, but attributed that to a series of misunderstandings. Whoever told 
Whitebread that the areas were off-limits was mistaken, she said. 
</P>
<P>
"We realize they need to exercise," she said. 
</P>
<P>
Whitebread's criticism comes at a time when the zoo is particularly sensitive 
about its treatment of elephants because of news stories last year about Dunda, 
an elephant that was beaten by its keepers after being moved from the zoo to 
the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Whitebread said zoo officials have told him that, because they expect national 
news attention to focus on the Soviet arts festival, which kicks off <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, 
they want the <ORGANIZATION>Trunk &amp; Hump</ORGANIZATION> animals out by <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Whitebread said that is impossible. His 
</P>
<P>
employer, <ORGANIZATION>Trunk &amp; Hump</ORGANIZATION> owner <PERSON>Marty Dinnes</PERSON>, has a ranch in <LOCATION>Saugus</LOCATION>, north of 
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, where he can put the two camels, <PERSON>Doc and Walter</PERSON>, still living at 
the zoo. But the elephants will be harder to house. 
</P>
<P>
"They didn't give him any notice, so he's not sure what to do with them," 
<PERSON>Whitebread</PERSON> said. Dinnes was in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> and could not be reached. 
</P>
<P>
Last week, zoo officials said they had canceled the contract with Dinnes 
because of space constraints. <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON>, a zoo spokesman, said animals from 
the zoo's Chit Chat Show will be moved into the area until a <MONEY>$5.5-million</MONEY> 
renovation of their home, <LOCATION>Wegeforth Bowl</LOCATION>, is complete. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> said the zoo's contract with Dinnes specifies that each party would give 
30 days' notice before canceling the rides, but she said that last week both 
had agreed to end the rides immediately and that the zoo would pay Dinnes for 
30 more days, about <MONEY>$14,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
From <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> until <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the two Asian elephants had spent most of their time 
in the camel barns, with chains around one front and one hind leg. Because of 
the configuration of the open-air barns, the animals cannot be together. 
Because of poor drainage, they often stand for hours in their own urine. 
Whitebread, who feeds the elephants and cleans their cages twice a day, said 
they have sorely missed what used to be a thrice-weekly ritual: their visits to 
the zoo's elephant recreation area. 
</P>
<P>
"They hate being chained," said <PERSON>Whitebread</PERSON>, a part-time <ORGANIZATION>San Diego State 
University</ORGANIZATION> student who has worked with <PERSON>Katie</PERSON> and Gypsy since they arrived at 
the zoo six years ago. "They used to love playing and swimming in that yard." 
</P>
<P>
As Whitebread spoke with a reporter and photographer <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <PERSON>Tom Hall</PERSON>, the 
zoo's operations manager, appeared. "Have you heard?" he asked Whitebread. "You 
can use our recreation area any time you want." 
</P>
<P>
Whitebread thanked him, but later said: "Of course I hadn't heard. He hadn't 
told me. They've never let us use the yard any time we want. Never." 
</P>
<P>
Whitebread says that for years he has asked the zoo to make changes in the 
camel barns that would improve the elephants' living conditions. He asked for 
the wall between the two barns to be torn down so the elephants could huddle 
together. He asked for grooves to be cut into the concrete floors of the barns 
to provide drainage. In the <DATE>winter</DATE>, when the open-air barns left the animals 
exposed to the cold, he asked for some kind of wind barrier. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Marty Dinnes</PERSON> said he'd pay for half of anything they did, that he wanted the 
best, but they wouldn't do it," <PERSON>Whitebread</PERSON> said, turning to look at the 
barriers the zoo had installed <DATE>Friday</DATE>. "When I asked, they couldn't do it. But 
when they want it done, it happens overnight." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> said: "We've made some improvements, but there haven't been a lot. 
Sometimes things move slowly around here." She said recent estimates showed 
that it would cost <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> to provide the improvements Whitebread 
requested. 
</P>
<P>
Whitebread said he is worried about what will happen to the elephants once they 
leave the zoo. Katie, a 23-year-old, rambunctious animal who stands nearly 10 
feet tall, will fare best, he said. During her time at the zoo, she has 
occasionally traveled to other locations to work on movies or magazine photo 
assignments, he said. "She can adjust to anything." 
</P>
<P>
But Gypsy is older and more set in her ways. Records put her age at 38 years, 
but elephant keepers believe that the wrinkled, 8-foot-tall animal may be as 
old as 60. "It's hard to say, because every time an elephant is sold, they 
knock a few years off to get a better price," <PERSON>Whitebread</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"Every time <PERSON>Katie</PERSON> went away, Gypsy would just cower without her," said <PERSON>Steve 
Friedlund</PERSON>, a keeper who works with the zoo's elephants. "She's just a 
frightened old lady elephant. She's worn out." 
</P>
<P>
Friedlund said he believes Whitebread has done a good job with the elephants, 
given the limited resources available to him. "But wherever <PERSON>Marty Dinnes</PERSON> takes 
these elephants next and whatever yahoo help he hires -- who knows what these 
elephants will suffer." 
</P>
<P>
A spokesman for the Humane Society of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Larry Boersma</PERSON>, said it has 
been two weeks since the society received any complaints about Gypsy and <PERSON>Katie</PERSON>. 
The society investigated those complaints, which alleged that the animals were 
not being well cared for, but found no basis for intervention, he said. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Katie, left, and Gypsy in their enclosures. Gypsy, the elder elephant, 
holds her leg up to keep it out of dung. ; Photo, Gypsy can be seen behind 
barrier that zoo erected to hide her and her partner from public view. BRUCE K. 
HUFF / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110690-0005 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 303531 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 6, 1990, Tuesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
471 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
POOL IS NOW OPEN; TRUNKS REQUIRED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JONATHAN GAW, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Connie was the first to test the waters, delicately dipping the tip of her 
trunk into the murky water, much as a person might wet a toe to check the 
temperature. 
</P>
<P>
She trumpeted loudly. Then, finally, <ORGANIZATION>Connie</ORGANIZATION> took the plunge. 
</P>
<P>
She was the bravest of the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal Park's seven female Asian 
elephants, which edged up cautiously to their plush new pool shortly after 
being released into the compound <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The pool is designed to provide a more 
aesthetic and natural environment, as well as to get the pachyderms exercising 
more. 
</P>
<P>
"Nita we would have expected to go in right away because she's the dominant 
elephant, and she's usually the one who goes trying something out before others 
will," said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, spokesman for the park. 
</P>
<P>
Eventually, <PERSON>Nita</PERSON> and the others took turns getting wet, only to fling dirt on 
themselves with their trunks once they got out. 
</P>
<P>
"Elephants, when they get wet, they get itchy," elephant program manager <PERSON>Alan 
Roocroft</PERSON> explained. 
</P>
<P>
A boulder placed in a clearing in the compound is at a height just right for 
them to scratch their undersides after a swim, he said. 
</P>
<P>
The <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> Asian elephant pool, which opens to the public today, has been 
five months in the making and is the first step toward bringing patrons within 
arm's length of the floppy-eared beasts at the park near <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
It replaces an older, smaller pool and is similar in size to one built for the 
African elephants in a neighboring compound. 
</P>
<P>
The park hopes to eventually build a deck reaching to the edge of the wading 
pool and to plant grass in parts of the compound, which now is mostly dirt. 
</P>
<P>
The pool and the compound, which includes boulders and ficus and bamboo trees, 
was designed for the convenience and health of the elephants, park employees 
said. 
</P>
<P>
A collage of boulders, some of them weighing 6 tons, were placed in a pattern 
that makes it impossible for them to be dislodged. 
</P>
<P>
"It's kind of like a jigsaw puzzle," <PERSON>Roocroft</PERSON> said. "We want them to be able to 
get to them and use them as scratching posts, but obviously we don't want them 
to be moving them. Given the right terrain, though, they could move those rocks 
quite easily." 
</P>
<P>
The elephants did succeed in rocking one of the boulders forward, but could not 
pull it out. 
</P>
<P>
The pool gives the elephants a chance to swim, something they couldn't do in 
their old pool. 
</P>
<P>
"Elephants don't move normally in captivity, and you've got to find ways to get 
them to exercise," <PERSON>Roocroft</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The pool, which is 9 feet deep and has two entrances, is deep enough to put the 
8-foot-tall elephants through a healthy workout and is designed to accommodate 
their social structure. 
</P>
<P>
"If we were to build a pool with just one entrance, you may have a dominant 
animal at the entrance keeping a sub-dominant one in or out of the pool," 
<PERSON>Roocroft</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, A pair of Asian elephants keep their trunks safely above water in their 
new pool at the San Diego Wild Animal Park. ; Photo, Three Asian elephants 
think things over carefully before making the plunge into pool, which they were 
introduced to Monday. ; Photo, (A2) Testing the Waters: The San Diego Wild 
Animal Park unveils its latest addition today, a 9-foot-deep swimming pool for 
its Asian elephants that is designed to more closely simulate the animals' 
environment and to give them some needed exercise. Above, a pachyderm takes the 
plunge in the new pool, which was five months in the making. VINCE COMPAGNONE / 
Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900423-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-23-90 1250EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-PregnantElephant 2ndLd-Writethru a0540 04-23 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pregnant Elephant, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0540,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>Elephant Undergoing C-Section After Drug Fails To Trigger Labor</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with preparations for surgery under way
after labor-inducing drug fails.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SYRACUSE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A veterinary surgical team began a risky
Caesarean section operation today to help Babe, a 36-year-old Asian
elephant, deliver a calf after her labor stopped five days ago.
   The seven-member team led by <PERSON>Dr. Michael Schmit</PERSON>, a veterinarian
from the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Park Zoo in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, began preparations
for the surgery at about <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> after drugs administered to the
7,700-pound elephant failed to induce labor.
   ``Everybody's kind of nervous. We've got several hours worth of
surgery ahead,'' said <PERSON>Yvonne Pelletreau</PERSON>, a spokeswoman at the
<ORGANIZATION>Burnet Park Zoo</ORGANIZATION>.
   It will be the third time the veterinary team has attempted a
C-section on an Asian elephant, she said. Only one of the
operations was successful, she said.
   Babe would become the oldest first-time elephant mother to give
birth in a North American zoo.
   Babe began labor <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, but stopped it early <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
Female elephants have the ability to stop their labor when they are
feeling pain and it is not unusual for elephants to take up to five
days to deliver a calf. But zoo officials became concerned about
both mother and infant as the delay continued.
   On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, a group of four veterinarians from <ORGANIZATION>Cornell
University</ORGANIZATION> checked Babe and found that her cervix was probably too
small for her calf to pass through. They injected her with
Estrabiol to start her cervix dilating, said <PERSON>Pelletreau</PERSON>.
   The drug had some effect, but not enough, so on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> the
veterinarians gave Babe a second injection, she said.
   That second injection caused the elephant's cervix to widen
enough for a calf to pass. Early today, the veterinarians gave Babe
ocytocin, a labor-inducing drug, but it didn't work, she said.
   Babe is one of eight Asian elephants currently pregnant in North
American zoos. A second Burnet Park elephant, <PERSON>Romani</PERSON>, is expected
to give birth in <DATE>July 1991</DATE>.
   Asian elephants are an endangered species that number fewer than
45,000 in the wild.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030289-0007 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 25073 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 2, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
384 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TACOMA TO TAKE BACK CINDY, AN ALBATROSS OF AN ELEPHANT FOR PARK 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ANDREW LePAGE, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
