<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911004-0152
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911004-0152.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   On Sports: Basketball at 100
   ----
   By Frederick C. Klein
</HL>
<DATE>
10/04/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   If James Naismith had a better sense of history, he would
have invented basketball a few weeks after he did, sometime
in late December of 1891. That would have given his sport's
centennial a Columbian parallel, and also would have made it
coincide with an Olympiad in which basketball is expected to
be a, and maybe the, featured attraction, thanks to the
recently named "dream team" of U.S. professional stars.
   Naismith, however, fashioned the game in response to a
more immediate imperative. In his 1941 book, "Basketball: Its
Origin and Development," he recounts how, as a new,
30-year-old gym instructor at the YMCA International Training
School in Springfield, Mass., now Springfield College, he was
put in charge of a class of administrators-in-training that
was bored to the point of mutiny with its daily winter
regimen of calisthenics. He'd badgered superiors with his
belief that if exercise could be made to seem like play
instead of work, the most re-calcitrant pupils would
participate willingly. One responded by giving him the
troublesome class, saying, in effect, "Put up or shut up."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "I went to work with this class," <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> wrote. "I tried
{having the men play} soccer and we smashed all the windows.
I tried lacrosse and smashed most of the fellows' arms. Rugby
football finished the students up, until they were ready to
quit on recreative games."
   He went on: "In a day or two I would have to report to the
faculty the success or failure of my attempts. So far they
had been all failures. How I hated the thought of admitting
that, after all my theories, I, too, had failed to hold the
interest of the class."
   So he repaired to his office to meditate on the sort of
game that might be played indoors and be challenging but not
rough. It must, of course, involve a ball -- didn't they all?
-- and be easy to learn. But what of the fun element?
   The most interesting game at that time was American rugby
(football), he mused, but it was inappropriate for indoors
because it involved tackling. Why? Because players were
allowed to run with the ball and it was necessary to stop
them. But . . . if they couldn't run with the ball, tackling
could be eliminated]
   "I can still recall how I snapped my fingers and shouted,
`I've got it]'" he wrote.
   The rest -- the elevated, horizontal goal and general
rules -- fell into place, and within days <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION>'s Y
charges were happily playing the game that would be the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>'s most important gift to sports. Baseball may be our
poets' choice, and football may be No. 1 on the domestic
tube, but basketball, with its free-flowing form and abundant
opportunities for individual virtuosity, is the American game
the world has chosen. <ORGANIZATION>FIBA</ORGANIZATION>, the Olympic regulator of the
sport, recognizes national governing bodies in 176 countries,
10 more than belong to the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>. Surveys I've seen
identify basketball as the world's foremost spectator sport.
   It is, furthermore, the game that is most purely "ours,"
baseball and football having direct British antecedents. My
encyclopedia mentions a 16th-century Aztec game called
"ollamalitzli," in which players tried to throw a ball
through an elevated stone ring. But it notes that any player
who succeeded was entitled to the clothes of all the
spectators, so it couldn't have been very high scoring.
   Several things about basketball's beginnings seem worth
mentioning in this centennial year. One is the biography of
<ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION>. This was a man of parts. Born and raised in the
northern <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION> hamlet of <PERSON>Bennie</PERSON>'s Corners, he was orphaned
at eight and at times had to drop out of public school to
support himself as a logger or farmhand. Nonetheless, he
would receive a degree in theology from <ORGANIZATION>McGill University</ORGANIZATION> and
an M.D. from <ORGANIZATION>Gross Medical School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>.
   He never held a pastorate, though, nor did he practice
medicine. He wrote that his aim in life was to "do good," and
he concluded that encouraging wholesome leisure pursuits
among the young would accomplish this best. A naturalized
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> citizen, he spent most of his working life at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Kansas</ORGANIZATION>, where he became chairman of the
physical education department. He died in <DATE>1939</DATE> at age 78.
   Secondly, we are reminded of the role of chance in
invention; many of basketball's most salient features just
kind of happened. For instance, <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> wanted boxes to
serve as goals, but the janitor he asked had only peach
baskets handy. They were placed 10 feet off the ground
because that was where the balcony of the <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION> gym, on
which they were nailed, began. And backboards were
introduced, in <DATE>1893</DATE>, to keep spectators from helping their
favorite teams by swatting away opponents' shots.
   Lastly, once basketball's foundations were laid, it was
remarkable how quickly it approached its present form. Free
throws after fouls were introduced in <DATE>1894</DATE>, the point system
of two points for field goals and one for free throws came in
<DATE>1896</DATE>, five-player teams were accepted in <DATE>1897</DATE> and the dribble
-- the most important change in <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION>'s original plan --
was made legal in <DATE>1898</DATE>. In later life, he liked to remark
that the biggest difference between the game he devised and
the one that evolved was in the skill of the players.
   Over the next few months, the centennial will be marked in
a number of ways. The <ORGANIZATION>YMCA</ORGANIZATION>, which also spread the game
abroad, has various celebrations planned, and the game's <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>
of Fame in <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION> will host a series of events
culminating in a black-tie gala on <DATE>Dec. 21</DATE>. That's the day
set as the game's birthday, although nobody knows for sure.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Basketball Association</ORGANIZATION>, whose teams begin
practice this week, says its players will wear centennial
patches on their warmup suits in the coming season, and other
commemorations will be staged. But it's questionable how
<ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> would regard the league. He wrote that basketball
would be basketball as long as four things didn't change: The
large, light ball; the elevated, horizontal goal; and no
personal contact or running with the ball. Seems that NBAball
qualifies on only two of those counts.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06357101 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06357101 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COLLEGE; BASKETBALL; GAME; RESULT; SAN-JOSE; STATE; SANTA-CLARA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  SATURDAY was the 100th anniversary of basketball's creation. On the afternoon
of Dec. 21, 1891, a physical education professor in Massachusetts named James
Naismith nailed a peach basket to a wall and bounced a soccer ball onto the
floor.;   And on the afternoon of Dec. 21, 1991, at Toso Pavilion, the
basketball teams of San Jose State and Santa Clara commemorated the event by
nailing each other with elbows -- and bouncing their torsos off the floor, the
basket supports, the bleachers and anything else that was handy.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  STILL A PEACH OF A GAME  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     And <ORGANIZATION>San Jose State</ORGANIZATION> came from behind to score a ragged and rugged 61-60
victory.;   "The game is 100 years old today?" asked Spartans Coach <PERSON>Stan
Morrison</PERSON> afterward. "Well, we set it back 50 years.";   Not entirely true.
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s game hardly was an outright dog. The drama was thick. <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>San Jose State</LOCATION> were two struggling teams, trying to find their stride
early in the season. The Broncos are still searching. At the final buzzer,
<LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> forward <PERSON>Rhea Taylor</PERSON> was lying flat on his back in agony, pounding
his fists on the hardwood after he missed the final shot. Meanwhile, <ORGANIZATION>San Jose
State</ORGANIZATION>'s players hugged and yelped at center court.;   In short, it was like
the finish of thousands -- millions? -- of basketball games played over the
<DATE>last century</DATE>. It was why the game has lasted so long and become so much a part
of our sports landscape. <DATE>Saturday</DATE> was an occasion to toast all of that,
although <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> was not in the mood. The Broncos, with all five starters
back from last season, are 2-6.;   "The 100th anniversary, huh?" said <PERSON>Carroll
Williams</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>'s head coach, then added in sarcastic frustration: "It's
a great game, isn't it? A great game.";   The sport's centennial has not drawn
the attention here that it has in other places, because the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> is
nowhere close to being a hoops hotbed, the Warriors' current exalted state
aside. Of the 25 largest college basketball arenas, none is located in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. And only 1,425 spectators showed up for <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s game.;   But
that doesn't mean <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s historical moment should pass without mention.
Today, worldwide, basketball is more omnipresent than ever. And the recent
success of the women's teams at <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> indicates the sport
may be entering a whole new level of popularity.;   Yet it gives one pause.
What if <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> hadn't been able to find a peach basket that fateful day in
<DATE>1891</DATE>? Or what if he'd slipped on the ice, broken his hip, and had never made
it to the gym? Would we now be spending the winter watching <ORGANIZATION>ESPN</ORGANIZATION> telecasts of
<LOCATION>Big East</LOCATION> croquet? Or curling?;    "I CAN'T imagine what the world would be
like without basketball," <PERSON>Morrison</PERSON> said. "In my view, it's right up there with
the invention of the wheel. Without basketball, I don't know what I would be
doing right now. I would probably be a teacher, I guess. Or an architect.";  
At least one of <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s players was pondering the same thoughts. As he
packed his duffel bag after the game, the Spartans' <PERSON>Terry Cannon</PERSON> proudly
pulled out a certificate that the <ORGANIZATION>American Basketball Congress</ORGANIZATION> has sent to
every college player this year, commemorating their appearance in the
centennial.;   "Basketball isn't just a sport for some people, it's a
lifestyle, a livelihood," said <ORGANIZATION>Cannon</ORGANIZATION>. "It's allowed me to receive an
education and allowed others to earn a living by teaching it.";   A major
cultural force, in other words. From small-town driveways, to big-city
playgrounds, to <LOCATION>Toso Pavilion</LOCATION> on a <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. Happy birthday, hoops.
You've earned the right to party.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mark Purdy; Sports Editor column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911222  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  607  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, December 22, 1991
00357101,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870512-0082 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
On Sports: 'All-Short' Basketball
---
By Frederick C. Klein</HL>
<DD> 05/12/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Basketball Association</ORGANIZATION> playoffs are in full swing, a fact that delights some but produces ennui in others. 
The yawners say it's a waste to tune in an <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> game until the last two minutes, or that even tuning in before <DATE>June</DATE> is a waste. 

   Still others believe that it isn't just the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>'s brand of hoops that's lacking, but modern basketball in general. 
Members of this faction hold that the players have outgrown the facilities and turned <PERSON>Dr. Naismith</PERSON>'s noble invention into a track meet for giraffes. 
They would like to raise the baskets, enlarge the court and trim the number of contestants to four from five. 

   I must say that I do not count myself among basketball's critics. 
Knocking the players for being too tall, too swift and too agile reminds me of the character in the movie "Amadeus" who faulted a Mozart tune for having too many notes. 
Nevertheless, I feel obliged to pass along the news that a new professional basketball league is being planned that will answer at least one of the malcontents' beefs. 
No player loftier than 6-foot-4-inches tall will be allowed to perform. 

   The league has been dubbed the <ORGANIZATION>International Basketball Association</ORGANIZATION>. 
At the moment, it is mainly a gleam in the eyes of a handful of individuals who have yet to purchase a basketball. 
The backgrounds of some of them, however, indicate that they may own several one day soon. 

   The league's chairman is <PERSON>Ben Hatskin</PERSON>, a resident of <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Manitoba</LOCATION>, who owned the <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> Jets in the old <ORGANIZATION>World Hockey Association</ORGANIZATION>. 
His signing of <PERSON>Bobby Hull</PERSON> away from the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Blackhawks</ORGANIZATION> gave that loop the shot it needed to rival and, later, merge into the <ORGANIZATION>National Hockey League</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The guy who'll run the league is <PERSON>Dennis Murphy</PERSON>, who helped start the <ORGANIZATION>WHA</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>American Basketball Association</ORGANIZATION> and Team Tennis. 
In charge of basketball operations when there are some, and public relations in the meantime, is <PERSON>Bob Cousy</PERSON>, the old <ORGANIZATION>Boston Celtics</ORGANIZATION>' flash. 
Some say basketball hasn't been the same since the 6-foot-1-inch <ORGANIZATION>Cooz</ORGANIZATION> hung it up back in <DATE>'63</DATE>. 

   Cousy now broadcasts Celtics games, and says he has no enmity for the established circuit. 
"Basketball's a great sport and the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>'s a great league," says he. 
"We see ourselves existing alongside the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>, not competing with it. 
Kind of like a little brother, if you know what I mean." 

   The IBA's founders say that the size of the players won't be the only novelty of their enterprise. 
They are aiming for a summer schedule of 50 to 60 games beginning in <DATE>1988</DATE>, there will be a salary cap of <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> on each team's roster of 10 or 11 players, and the "International" in their name will be no mere curtsy to our immediate neighbor to the north. 

   According to <PERSON>Murphy</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>IBA</ORGANIZATION> plans to promote international competition on two fronts. 
He says the league will petition the <ORGANIZATION>International Olympic Committee</ORGANIZATION> to begin staging competitions in a 6-foot-4-and-under division in addition to the open-to-all one it now maintains. 
He points out, with justice, that boxing and wrestling are conducted by weight class. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>IBA</ORGANIZATION> has moved on its own to internationalize the sport by agreeing to meet a team from the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> in a series in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> next <DATE>September</DATE>. 
It will hold tryout camps in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> this <DATE>summer</DATE> to pick a 10-man All-Short team to make that trip. 
Murphy hopes this will be the first of a broader series of contests matching teams from various countries in what eventually would become a sort of World Cup of Short Basketball, in which his league would represent the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   "Basketball is the No. 2 sport in popularity -- behind soccer -- in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, and the game in those places is quickly reaching <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> standards," he says. 
"If you equalize for height, you'd have good competition right off the bat." 

   The nearer-term prospects for the <ORGANIZATION>IBA</ORGANIZATION> will depend on getting a domestic league off the ground (but not too far), and <PERSON>Murphy</PERSON> says that strides have been made in that direction. 
He says that groups from seven localities -- <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> -- have ponied up <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> each for the right to form IBA teams. 
The plan is to sell five more franchises at <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> each for an inaugural-season circuit of 12 squads. 
By contrast, the 23-team NBA just peddled four new franchises for <MONEY>$32.5 million</MONEY> apiece. 

   Getting players will be no problem, the league's founders believe. 
They point out that our nation's colleges excel in producing highly qualified basketballers, many in the 6-4-or-under class, and that the existing domestic professional loops -- the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> and minor-league <ORGANIZATION>Continental Basketball Association</ORGANIZATION> -- employ just a fraction of the available talent. 

   "The best of the shorter players, like {6-foot-2-inch} <PERSON>Steve Alford</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, will still sign with the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>, but that'll leave plenty for us," says <PERSON>Cousy</PERSON>. 
"Guys like {5-foot-11-inch} <PERSON>Billy Donovan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION> or {5-foot-3-inch} <ORGANIZATION>Muggsy Bogues of Wake Forest</ORGANIZATION> would be perfect for our league, and we'd showcase them best because they wouldn't be playing against giants." 

   The IBA would further distinguish itself from the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> by using a 30-second shot clock to the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>'s 24 seconds, allowing five timeouts a game to the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>'s nine (hurrah!) and letting players whip the ball into play themselves after back-court violations instead of waiting for a referee to bless the sphere (double hurrah!). 

   Mostly, though, the IBA is banking on the box-office appeal of normal-size players. 
"Who does the average-sized person identify with? 
Another average-sized person, of course," avers founder <PERSON>Murphy</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060590-0073 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 229141 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 5, 1990, Tuesday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 6; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
964 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COMMENTARY; 
</P>
<P>
MIKAN WAS THE GIANT OF HIS DAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By STEVE JACOBSON, NEWSDAY 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>George Mikan</PERSON> likes to tell about being the good-natured giant of his day, of 
the time he made the mistake of bringing an offensive rebound low enough for 
<ORGANIZATION>Red Holzman</ORGANIZATION> to tie him up. So they had a jump ball at <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON>'s free-throw line 
-- little Red against big <PERSON>George</PERSON>. "The referee tossed the ball up and I tipped 
it into the basket; two points," <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> said. Ha, ha. Holzman called him a big 
(unprintable). Ha, ha again. In the enormous boom of basketball, the game never 
has properly honored its roots. At the recent "Night of 100 Stars," <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> was 
introduced, limped across the stage and waved to a crowd of mostly unknowing 
stares. 
</P>
<P>
"Who's he?" 
</P>
<P>
He's the Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> of basketball, that's all. Except that they didn't move the 
fences back and make them tall for Ruth the way they did for <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON>. He changed 
the course of basketball as a player. He wore No. 99. It was only 35 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>National Basketball Association</ORGANIZATION> was called the <ORGANIZATION>Basketball Association of 
America</ORGANIZATION> for two years before the merger. Mikan played in the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Basketball League</ORGANIZATION>, which was poo-pooed because it had teams in <LOCATION>Sheboygan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION>, 
and <LOCATION>Anderson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
It had <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON>, who invented the big man. He was 6-foot-10 and as broad at a time 
when hardly anybody else was. "He could move down the court," <PERSON>Bob Cousy</PERSON> 
recalls. "He'd get down and wipe you out at his end." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mikan</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Minneapolis Lakers</LOCATION> won the <ORGANIZATION>NBL</ORGANIZATION> championship and then earned five titles 
in their first six seasons in the merged <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>. It was like the <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION> 
joining the haughty <ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION> and doing the same thing they did 
to the <ORGANIZATION>All-America Conference</ORGANIZATION>. The one year the Lakers lost, in <DATE>1951</DATE>, was when 
<PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> had a broken leg and <LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION> with <PERSON>Holzman</PERSON> beat them. "The doctors taped 
a plate on it for the playoffs," <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> said. "I played all right, scored in the 
20s. I couldn't run, sort of hopped down the court." 
</P>
<P>
He says if you watch the old black-and-white films you'll see that the game 
hasn't changed all that much -- except they used the two-hand set shot and the 
jump shot was still being invented and all the black players were still with 
the <ORGANIZATION>Harlem Globetrotters</ORGANIZATION>. That's all. 
</P>
<P>
And you won't see a dunk. It was illegal because of him, he says. In college, 
at <ORGANIZATION>DePaul</ORGANIZATION>, he would bat the ball out of the basket, so they instituted rules 
against goaltending, and included offensive goaltending. "We used to dunk in 
pregame practice, not in the game," <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> said. "If they didn't get rid of that 
rule, there'd be no <PERSON>Michael Jordan</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
Because of <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> the three-second lane was widened from 6 feet to 12 feet, and 
to the present 16 feet. And the shot clock was created. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1950</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>Fort Wayne Pistons</ORGANIZATION> held the ball against the <LOCATION>Lakers</LOCATION>, beating them 
<DATE>19-18</DATE> in the lowest-scoring game in <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> history. "They wouldn't play," <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> 
said. The 24-second rule came in three seasons later. "That game was the 
biggest cause," he said. 
</P>
<P>
He also was the first commissioner of the red-white-and-blue <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION>. The 
three-colored ball came and went with his league, but the three-point shot 
stayed. Mikan might have changed the history of the game again if he'd been 
more effective. Uniondale might have been the capital of the game. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kareem Abdul-Jabbar</PERSON> was graduating from <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> as <PERSON>Lew Alcindor</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON>'s owners 
got together to draft <PERSON>Alcindor</PERSON> and share the cost for the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> franchise, 
which was the Nets en route from <LOCATION>Commack</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>Nassau Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>. "We felt if we 
could get accepted in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, we'd be accepted anywhere," <PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> said. "The 
secondary plan was to have each team sign one top player from the other league. 
They wouldn't follow my direction." 
</P>
<P>
They did steal <PERSON>Rick Barry</PERSON> and prepared a check for <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> for <PERSON>Alcindor</PERSON>, who 
said he wanted to play in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. He said that he'd take just 
one offer from each league. "One million was beyond anybody's imagination," 
<PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> said. "It was a shock when he turned us down and went to <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>. We 
thought a million was a pretty good deal in <DATE>1968</DATE>." We can only guess what would 
have evolved if Abdul-Jabbar had played his 19 seasons with the Nets. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> left his mark as a player. "We were playing <LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION> and when I got a 
defensive rebound, <PERSON>Les Harrison</PERSON> wanted <PERSON>Holzman</PERSON> to stand right in front of me so 
I couldn't get upcourt. The first time, I knocked Red 15 feet. He yelled to 
<PERSON>Harrison</PERSON>, 'If you want it done, do it yourself."' 
</P>
<P>
I'd take my chances with this team against anybody: <PERSON>Jerry West</PERSON>, <PERSON>Oscar Robertson</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Bob Cousy</PERSON> at guard; <ORGANIZATION>Elgin Baylor</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Bob Pettit</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bill Russell</PERSON> at forward 
and <PERSON>Wilt Chamberlain</PERSON> at center. 
</P>
<P>
Today <PERSON>Cousy</PERSON> would be <PERSON>John Stockton</PERSON>. An assist was an assist then; none of these 
assists for passing out for a three-point shot. 
</P>
<P>
"No question they'd do fine," Knicks assistant <PERSON>Paul Silas</PERSON> said. "Those guys 
were a lot more fundamentally sound than players of today. Today there's a lot 
of flash. These guys throw passes behind their backs; what a pass is supposed 
to do is get the ball from one point to the other. The two-hand chest pass is 
still the best pass." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mikan</PERSON> said that he loves the present game; he buys the excesses as so much show 
business. <PERSON>Silas</PERSON> and <PERSON>Cousy</PERSON> are not quite so permissive. 
</P>
<P>
"The game hasn't changed, the athlete has changed," <PERSON>Cousy</PERSON> said not too long 
ago, citing the 6-7, 280-pound football player who runs 40 yards in four 
seconds. "In basketball you see 7-foot guys doing things of a 6-footer. We shot 
<PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT>; that wouldn't get you by in Division III." 
</P>
<P>
Cousy popularized the flash that consumes so much of today's game, except that 
he used the flash when the orthodox wouldn't do. He dribbled behind his back 
the first time in a game because he was being overplayed. "Today every 
12-year-old in the schoolyard is doing it, probably better," he said. "But they 
do it bringing it upcourt to no advantage." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06083038 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06083038 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  WATER; CONSERVATION; SCIENCE; SHOW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  There simply are not enough superlatives to describe the wonderful, fantastic,
incredibly awesome basketball launcher invented by 9-year-old Taylor Holmes.; 
  With 10 springs and a little thread, Taylor turned an ordinary pair of
gloves into a launcher extraordinaire. The third-grader swears he gets an
extra six inches or a foot on every throw.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  INVENTIVE KIDS SHOW OFF GADGETS TO LAUNCH
BALLS, CONSERVE WATER  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "I have a friend who was kind of getting mad at himself because he couldn't
get the ball to go through the hoop with a regular basketball, so I thought
maybe the gloves would help," said Taylor.;    "And it works.";    <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>, a
student at <ORGANIZATION>Camino Pablo Elementary School</ORGANIZATION>, unveiled his top-secret invention
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> during his class's annual Invention Convention.;    For the third
consecutive year, students in <PERSON>Marlene Thier</PERSON>'s class have come up with a
dazzling array of new devices.;    There's the automatic pet scratcher, the
automatic room picker-upper, the automatic trash taker-outer and the PetAway
security system that comes complete with motion sensors and timers that
trigger sprinklers to soak trespassing pets.;    <ORGANIZATION>Thier</ORGANIZATION>'s 25 students are part
of a group of 10,000 students nationwide competing in the Invent America
Program sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Patent Model Foundation</ORGANIZATION>. After a team of
<ORGANIZATION>Lawrence Hall of Science</ORGANIZATION> judges selects the best of the lot, <PERSON>Thier</PERSON> hopes her
winning student will get to compete with national winners in <LOCATION>Washington.</LOCATION>;   
There were also many water-saving devices in this fifth year of drought. The
Shower Timer measures water as it's used to let a bather know when 20 gallons
have gone down the drain. The Rain Keeper is a giant plastic canopy that
catches rain water. Wash and Flush sends drain water from the sink into the
toilet, where it's used for flushing.;    But pets were a strong theme.;   
<PERSON>Amanda Malmquist</PERSON> created the pet scratcher, mounting a pasta fork on a box
over a little battery-run motor. The flick of a switch starts the motor
whirring and the fork moving back and forth.;    "My grandma has a dog, and my
hand gets so tired scratching its back," said <PERSON>Amanda</PERSON> as she demonstrated her
device on a stuffed rabbit.;    <PERSON>Jason Chiu</PERSON> had a mission when he set out to
create PetAway: no more strays wandering through the yard.;    His elaborate
security device uses motion sensors and timers that trigger sprinklers. Best
of all, wayward dogs set off a taped recording of a roaring lion.;    There's
only one hitch.;    The device can't tell the difference between a letter
carrier and a poodle.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Moraga  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910323  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  416  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday March 23, 1991
00083038,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880307-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-88 1542EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     03-07 0518</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0536</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FREDERICK, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   No order is too tall for <ORGANIZATION>Richlee Shoes</ORGANIZATION>,
which specializes in elevator shoes.
   It even sells elevator bedroom slippers.
   ``If you're going to be taller at the office and the company
picnic, why wouldn't you want to be taller at home? Won't the
neighbors notice if you run out to get the paper that you're
shorter?'' said <PERSON>Bob Martin</PERSON>, who operates the company with his
sister and three brothers.
   Ninety styles, priced <MONEY>$40</MONEY> to <MONEY>$120</MONEY>, are displayed in 100,000
square feet of warehouse space just south of <PERSON>Frederick</PERSON>. It sells
direct and through mail order.
   ``We don't feel we've even scratched the surface'' of the number
of men who want to appear taller, said <PERSON>Martin</PERSON>. ``Depending on the
style, our shoes can make a man two inches taller. I've had people
call me up ... they say `the difference in my height has made a
difference in my social life.'''
   Elevator shoes have come a long way from the days when the
company's celebrity spokesman, <PERSON>Mickey Rooney</PERSON>, sported oxfords with
chunky heels that didn't hide their purpose. Today's elevator shoes
look like normal shoes but have a built-up insole.
   <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said he even has one regular customer who stands 6-foot-5.
   ``I asked him why,'' he said. ``He said he was a basketball
player in college and all his friends were 6-feet-7 or 8.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MAITLAND, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   No order is too tall for <ORGANIZATION>Richlee Shoes</ORGANIZATION>,
which specializes in elevator shoes.
   It even sells elevator bedroom slippers.
   ``If you're going to be taller at the office and the company
picnic, why wouldn't you want to be taller at home? Won't the
neighbors notice if you run out to get the paper that you're
shorter?'' said <PERSON>Bob Martin</PERSON>, who operates the company with his
sister and three brothers.
   Ninety styles, priced <MONEY>$40</MONEY> to <MONEY>$120</MONEY>, are displayed in 100,000
square feet of warehouse space just south of <PERSON>Frederick</PERSON>. It sells
direct and through mail order.
   ``We don't feel we've even scratched the surface'' of the number
of men who want to appear taller, said <PERSON>Martin</PERSON>. ``Depending on the
style, our shoes can make a man two inches taller. I've had people
call me up ... they say `the difference in my height has made a
difference in my social life.'''
   Elevator shoes have come a long way from the days when the
company's celebrity spokesman, <PERSON>Mickey Rooney</PERSON>, sported oxfords with
chunky heels that didn't hide their purpose. Today's elevator shoes
look like normal shoes but have a built-up insole.
   <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said he even has one regular customer who stands 6-foot-5.
   ``I asked him why,'' he said. ``He said he was a basketball
player in college and all his friends were 6-feet-7 or 8.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06356080 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06356080 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  BASKETBALL; HISTORY; CHANGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  MEMORIES of the founders of our games are mostly lost in history. Nobody
living today knew Abner Doubleday, if indeed he nurtured baseball's roots.;  
Football evolved from rugby and soccer. Hockey was first played by forgotten
Canadian soldiers. Scottish shepherds topped the early golf balls. French
clerics plopped the first tennis ball into a net.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NAISMITH MAY HAVE CRIED FOUL OVER TODAY'S SALARIES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Dave Anderson is a columnist for the New York Times.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     But as basketball awaits this <DATE>weekend</DATE>'s celebration in <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>,
of its 100th birthday, its creator, <PERSON>Dr. James Naismith</PERSON>, is still alive in the
mind of one of his grandsons.;   "I remember Papa Jimmy taking me to the old
<ORGANIZATION>Madison Square Garden</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1936</DATE> on his way to <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> for the Olympics," <PERSON>Jim
Naismith</PERSON>, 68, said the other day. "I think we were in the Garden for the
Olympic Trials and after he tossed up the first ball, I sat with him in the
press row. But that day he was angry about something.";   Now stocky and
white-haired, the grandson was 12 then, and his grandfather was 74. For the
first time, the Olympics would include basketball.;   But the man who in <DATE>1891</DATE>
had peach baskets hung in the <ORGANIZATION>Young Men's Christian Association Training
School</ORGANIZATION> gym in <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION> was annoyed at the selection process of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
team.;   "He was happy basketball was going to be played in the Olympics that
<DATE>August</DATE>," his grandson recalled, "but he was disappointed that it wasn't
serving the purpose it was meant to: a game you played for sportsmanship and
to use the winter months.";   In that case, what would <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> think of
today's basketball with its multimillion-dollar pros about to soar into midair
in the Olympics next <DATE>summer</DATE>, its multimillion-dollar college tournament, its
multimillion-dollar television contracts, its multimillion-dollar sneaker
contracts for coaches?;   "I think he would consider the game itself to be a
natural evolution," his grandson said, "but the salaries might bother him. He
never thought of making money out of basketball. . . . He wasn't interested in
money. He turned down a considerable amount of money to endorse cigarettes."; 
 <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> was a doctor of medicine and a doctor of divinity who also held a
master's degree in physical education.;   "He was a very firm Presbyterian
minister," his grandson remembered. "To him, it was important for the
spiritual, mental and physical aspects of life to work in harmony. But he was
a very kind, genial man. When he was at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Kansas</ORGANIZATION>, he would
drive out in his Model T <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> to visit us in <LOCATION>Fort Collins</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo</LOCATION>. I would go
fishing and camping with this man I liked very much.";   He remembered
basketball's founder as a stocky 5-foot-8, with sturdy forearms from growing
up as a Canadian lumberjack.;   "He had a cauliflower ear, and he always had
that mustache you see in all those younger pictures of him wearing a suit and
a starched collar," he said with a smile. "That mustache was a prickly one. I
know that from all the times he kissed me.";   As it turned out, their day at
the <DATE>1936</DATE> Olympic Trials was the last time <PERSON>Jim Naismith</PERSON> would see his
grandfather, who died in 1939.;   "I follow the <LOCATION>Knicks</LOCATION>; I'm glad when they
win," said this now-retired chairman of the performing arts program at
<ORGANIZATION>Rockland County Community College</ORGANIZATION>. "But as a youngster, I was a terrible
basketball player. I couldn't dribble, I couldn't pass and I certainly
couldn't hit the basket. Not that my grandfather would have cared. To him,
other things in life were always more important."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Dave Anderson column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  West Nyack, N.Y.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911221  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1G  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  599  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, December 21, 1991
00356080,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051489-0115 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 56873 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 14, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 4; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1778 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THERE'S EVEN ROOM FOR ROMAR IN THE BASKETBALL HALL OF FAME 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KEVIN HUNT, Hartford Courant 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SPRINGFIELD, Mass. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Part of the world's most extensive Romar collection hangs in a back room at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Basketball Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION>, away from public view. 
</P>
<P>
The legend of <PERSON>Lorenzo Romar</PERSON>, a 6-foot-1 guard, began when he averaged 9.3 
points as a University of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> senior. Or was it when the <ORGANIZATION>Golden State 
Warriors</ORGANIZATION> selected him in the seventh round of the <DATE>1980</DATE> draft, or when he 
averaged 7.6 points in his best <ORGANIZATION>National Basketball Assn.</ORGANIZATION> season, was waived 
three times in little more than a year, played for the <ORGANIZATION>Continental Basketball 
Assn.</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Evansville Thunder</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tampa Bay Thrillers</LOCATION> in <DATE>1984-85</DATE>, or . . . 
</P>
<P>
Before the 24-second clock runs out, let's toss this one up: What in the name 
of <ORGANIZATION>Topsy Del Gobbo</ORGANIZATION> is a <PERSON>Lorenzo Romar</PERSON> uniform doing here anyway? 
</P>
<P>
It's time <PERSON>Romar</PERSON> thanked the <LOCATION>Detroit Pistons</LOCATION> for waiving him <DATE>Nov. 8, 1984</DATE>. He 
went to <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>, a free agent. His <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> uniform went to the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame, 
a goodwill contribution. 
</P>
<P>
Sometimes basketball fame is nothing more than convenience. The Pistons didn't 
need <PERSON>Lorenzo Romar</PERSON>, or his uniform. The <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame needed a Piston uniform 
for an exhibit of representative <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> uniforms. The rest, as they say at 1150 
<LOCATION>West Columbus Ave.</LOCATION>, is basketball history. 
</P>
<P>
"Me? In the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame?" said <PERSON>Romar</PERSON>, 30, who became a Christian six years ago 
and joined Athletes in Action in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. "I wasn't even aware of it. It's a 
complete shock. And I'm not sure it makes a lot of sense." 
</P>
<P>
Well, history at the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> can mean many things. It can mean <PERSON>George 
Mikan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bob Pettit</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bill Russell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bob Cousy</PERSON>, <PERSON>Wilt Chamberlain</PERSON>, <PERSON>Pete Maravich</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Julius Erving</PERSON>. And it can mean <PERSON>Lorenzo Romar</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Paxson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mark McNamara</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Clemon Johnson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s All-American Redheads, the <ORGANIZATION>South Philadelphia Hebrew 
Assn.</ORGANIZATION> and the menu from <PERSON>Larry Bird</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> Connection restaurant in French 
Lick, <LOCATION>Ind</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Maybe," <PERSON>Romar</PERSON> said, "they're trying to draw some sort of contrast." 
</P>
<P>
Much of the contrast -- and a surprising number of genuine basketball artifacts 
-- is tucked away beyond the "Spalding Shoot Out," past the <PERSON>Bob Coyne</PERSON> cartoons, 
the Sports Illustrated covers and the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> locker-stall exhibit. 
</P>
<P>
In an isolated storage area not much bigger than the <ORGANIZATION>Boston Celtics</ORGANIZATION>' locker 
room, a Romar uniform shares rack space with those of <PERSON>Earl Jones</PERSON> of Springarn 
High School in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Neal Walk</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> (the difference between 
him and <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Lew Alcindor</PERSON> was a coin flip in the <DATE>1969</DATE> draft), <PERSON>LaRue Martin</PERSON> of 
<LOCATION>Loyola</LOCATION>, <PERSON>John Paxson</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>San Antonio Spurs</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Clemon Johnson</PERSON> of the 
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 76ers. 
</P>
<P>
From the sublime to the generic: jerseys from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Connecticut</ORGANIZATION> 
(women's), <ORGANIZATION>Slippery Rock College</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Punxsatawney High School</ORGANIZATION>. Detroit Piston 
fans should note that the latter was acquired for a Groundhog Day display, not 
for a tribute to Coach <PERSON>Chuck Daly</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Here one can find trophies, stained green by time, saluting national industrial 
league champions from 30 years past, <ORGANIZATION>Civilian Conservation Corps</ORGANIZATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Caterpillar</ORGANIZATION> (as in tractor) AAU jerseys, a watch by <ORGANIZATION>Elgin</ORGANIZATION> commemorating the 
<DATE>1944</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>NBL</ORGANIZATION> champion <PERSON>Zollner Pistons</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
And, oh, those basketballs. A red, white and blue <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION> edition ("<PERSON>Dave 
DeBusschere</PERSON>, Commissioner") signed by <PERSON>Julius Erving</PERSON> or immortalizing a 92-foot 
field goal by the <ORGANIZATION>Pacers</ORGANIZATION>' <PERSON>Jerry Harkness</PERSON> that beat the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Chaparrals <DATE>Nov</DATE>. 
19, <DATE>1967</DATE>. Even a ball from the <DATE>1924</DATE> National Interscholastic championship game 
-- <LOCATION>Windsor</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>) 25, <LOCATION>Yankton</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>) 6. 
</P>
<P>
Follow the bouncing balls and you'll find one dribbled 451.8 miles from 
<PERSON>Hodgdon</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 14-21</DATE>, <DATE>1984</DATE> for the opening of the new Hall. Do not, under 
any circumstances, overlook the nonstop dribbling record of 347.2 miles at 
<ORGANIZATION>Covenant Children's Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Decatur</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, <DATE>Aug. 8-11, 1981</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Authenticity? Be serious. There's more tread left on <PERSON>Kareem Abdul-Jabbar</PERSON>'s 
head. 
</P>
<P>
Could those be <PERSON>Bob Lanier</PERSON>'s size-22 sneakers? And, there, below a tabletop with 
<PERSON>Michael Jordan</PERSON>'s NBA All-Star jersey and <ORGANIZATION>Elgin Baylor</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Seattle University</ORGANIZATION> 
jersey, <ORGANIZATION>Spud Webb</ORGANIZATION>'s garment bag. Hold on . . . sorry, it's another <PERSON>Lanier</PERSON> 
colossus, a white canvas <ORGANIZATION>Converse</ORGANIZATION>, in a king-size sneaker bag. The other 
sneaker was part of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> exhibit at last <DATE>summer</DATE>'s World Expo in <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. The <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>'s prized <PERSON>Lanier</PERSON> pieces are a bronzed pair on display. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Spike Lee</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael Jordan</PERSON> weren't even Air-born when <PERSON>Lanier</PERSON> first laced up 
what may be the most famous artifacts in basketball history. 
</P>
<P>
"You're talking industrial-strength odor-eaters," says <PERSON>Michael Brooslin</PERSON>, the 
<PERSON>Hall</PERSON>'s curator. 
</P>
<P>
Behind the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>'s storage walls are 150-200 basketballs, 300 uniforms, a table 
of trophies, trinkets and watches, six shelves of sneakers, pennants, plaques, 
cartoons and life-size cutouts of Parade All-Americans. Boxes are stacked on 
top of boxes. And still more boxes: The <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>'s inventory grows by 300-400 items 
yearly. Only a small percentage makes it to the big show, the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> 
floor. 
</P>
<P>
Some trophies are broken. You'll have to excuse the shooter's shattered left 
leg on the <DATE>1980</DATE> Pepsi-Cola NBA Old-Timers game trophy. But the gold touchtone 
phone presented to <PERSON>Ed Gottlieb</PERSON> at the <DATE>1969</DATE> NBA All-Star game probably could get 
through to the <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> Heat hotline. 
</P>
<P>
Some, like the <DATE>1986</DATE> Hall of Fame game trophy, are unwanted. 
</P>
<P>
"I think it was supposed to be given to the Celtics," <PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> said. "They 
never took it." 
</P>
<P>
Politics (President <PERSON>Calvin Coolidge</PERSON>), royalty (<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s Prince Felipe de 
Borbon), Hollywood (<PERSON>Cary Grant</PERSON>), fantasy (Linus, <ORGANIZATION>Snoopy</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Charlie Brown</PERSON>), <PERSON>Lana 
Turner</PERSON> and <PERSON>Andre Turner</PERSON> converge here as unlikely memories of a game invented 
in <DATE>1891</DATE> by <PERSON>Dr. James Naismith</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Springfield College</ORGANIZATION> professor. 
</P>
<P>
How to organize such a mess? <PERSON>Andy Warhol</PERSON>'s estate recruited <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Hall 
of Fame</ORGANIZATION> has only Brooslin to sort, document and organize an intriguing 
collection from the <DATE>1890s</DATE> to the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. Brooslin, 33, became the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>'s first 
curator almost two years ago. 
</P>
<P>
"Virtually everything was in boxes before I came here," <PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> said. "Now we 
pretty much know what we have. But it's a five-year type of deal. It looks like 
we'll go to a computer next year. That will help.' 
</P>
<P>
Until then, <PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> sits before stacks of index cards, tagging and 
cataloguing. Although <PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> admits to visiting the old <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame at 
<ORGANIZATION>Springfield College</ORGANIZATION> only once while a student at nearby <ORGANIZATION>American International</ORGANIZATION>, 
he says he's having the time of his life. Beats his last job by a longshot -- 
curator of the <ORGANIZATION>National Rollerskating Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Lincoln</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neb</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Some items <PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> will never ID, such as the faded orange tanktops with 
stenciled numbers, no player or team names. The tag reads, "Orange tank, 
unidentified." 
</P>
<P>
"It looks like, 'Why the heck do I even have these?' " he says. 
</P>
<P>
On a recent afternoon <PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> returned from the basketball shelves, his eyes 
as big as the <PERSON>Walter Brown</PERSON> Trophy. 
</P>
<P>
"We've never had a complete inventory," he says. "I didn't even know I had this 
Hollywood stars basketball until two days ago." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Cary Grant</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jimmy Stewart</PERSON>, <PERSON>Tony Curtis</PERSON>. <PERSON>Lana Turner</PERSON>, <PERSON>Barbara Stanwyck</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hayley 
Mills</PERSON>. Gene <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>, <PERSON>Doris Day</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gina Lollabrigida</PERSON>. <PERSON>Tony Randall</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sandra Dee</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Rock 
Hudson</ORGANIZATION>. It's a bouncing Hollywood autograph book, auctioned by <PERSON>Dorothy Lamour</PERSON> 
to raise funds for the <DATE>1968</DATE> Olympic team. The <ORGANIZATION>Beta Shoe Company</ORGANIZATION> bought it for 
<MONEY>$285</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
If only the names were so clear on the lace-up ball signed by <PERSON>Calvin Coolidge</PERSON>. 
His signature and the year, <DATE>1924</DATE>, are clearly visible. So is <PERSON>John C. Jeets</PERSON>, 
tournament director. That's about it. 
</P>
<P>
"I've gone through it and through it," <PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> said. "I can't even figure out 
what tournament it is." 
</P>
<P>
A classic ball -- so, it looks like a football exposed to a mutant air pump -- 
with a president's signature doesn't make the cut. It sits next to a ball 
dribbled 185 miles by <ORGANIZATION>Boxboro High School</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Dec. 23, 1973</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"We like to use it not so much for the signature," <PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> said, "but it's one 
of the better lace-up balls we have. 
</P>
<P>
Collectors pay up to <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> for a uniform. The <PERSON>Coolidge</PERSON> ball? 
</P>
<P>
"For that particular basketball," says <PERSON>Carol Sherman</PERSON> of Profiles in History, an 
autograph broker in <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, "we'd probably price it at 
<MONEY>$500</MONEY>-<MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>. If we knew who else signed it, it might be worth much more." 
</P>
<P>
Profiles prices the "Hollywood" ball at <MONEY>$750</MONEY>-<MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>. Of course, once in the 
<PERSON>Hall</PERSON>, always in the Hall. 
</P>
<P>
"Collectors," <PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> said, his faced curled in a sour look. "I don't even 
want to talk about it. With old stuff, it can be difficult for us. But anything 
new, you know who's going to get it." 
</P>
<P>
Remember the <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> peacock, brought to you in living color? Presenting <ORGANIZATION>Ira 
Harge</ORGANIZATION>'s contribution to basketball history, a 1971-72 ABA <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> Floridians 
uniform: black, orange with a magenta stripe and stirrups. Let's be kind and 
say the design lies somewhere between <PERSON>Bo Ellis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Alexander Julian</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
And no <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION> collection is complete without a <PERSON>Marvin Barnes</PERSON> (never inducted, 
never indicted) original, "Spirits of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>" printed in orange over the 
<LOCATION>Lindbergh</LOCATION> plane with "Marvin" on the back. 
</P>
<P>
For pure, glow-in-the-dark slickness, we suggest a red satin jacket with an 
Indian emblem worn by <PERSON>Clarence</PERSON> (Bevo) <PERSON>Francis</PERSON>. An appropriately flashy outfit 
for someone who scored 113 points for <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande College</ORGANIZATION> against <ORGANIZATION>Hillsdale Feb</ORGANIZATION>. 
2, <DATE>1954</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Francis</PERSON>' jacket was displayed in the old <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>, more a shrine for <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> 
basketball. Now the uniforms of <PERSON>Walter Luckett</PERSON> (Kolbe-Bridgeport), <PERSON>Tom Roy</PERSON> 
(<LOCATION>South Windsor</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>Ron Perry</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Catholic Memorial</ORGANIZATION>) and a ball commemorating 
<PERSON>Danny Moore</PERSON>'s <TIME>71-point night</TIME> for South Catholic <DATE>Feb. 13, 1970</DATE> are here, in the 
Hall of Fame but not quite. 
</P>
<P>
Well, take heart. Fillipe de <PERSON>Borbon</PERSON>'s Celtic jersey, a replica of that given 
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s prince at the <ORGANIZATION>McDonald's Open</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>, didn't make it. Even though, 
<PERSON>Brooslin</PERSON> says, "It's our first piece of royalty." 
</P>
<P>
You'll also find <PERSON>Rick Barry</PERSON>'s No. 24 (<ORGANIZATION>Golden State Warriors</ORGANIZATION>), <PERSON>Oscar Robertson</PERSON>'s 
No. 4 from the <LOCATION>Cincinnati Royals</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Earl Monroe</PERSON>'s No. 10 from <LOCATION>Winston-Salem</LOCATION>, 
ceramic ashtrays made by <PERSON>Maurice Stokes</PERSON>, the uniform top of <PERSON>Dick Van Arsdale</PERSON> 
(<ORGANIZATION>Phoenix Suns</ORGANIZATION>) and the shorts of twin brother <PERSON>Tom</PERSON>, a crumbling banner from the 
<DATE>1904</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Universal Expo</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
And <PERSON>Lorenzo Romar</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I'd love to give some reasons why I'm there," <PERSON>Romar</PERSON> said, "but I can't think 
of any statistic that would qualify me for the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION>. I had a career 
high of 22 points, twice. I had eight steals once. I had 14 assists a couple of 
times -- guys are almost averaging that now." 
</P>
<P>
But he was waived at the right time. Twice. Don't bother looking for <ORGANIZATION>Romar</ORGANIZATION>'s 
Warrior uniform. You'll never see it. The other half of the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>'s Romar 
collection is open year-round to the public, part of the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> uniform exhibit. 
</P>
<P>
It's true. <PERSON>Lorenzo Romar</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Detroit Pistons</LOCATION>, has made it to the floor of the <ORGANIZATION>Hall 
of Fame</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Don't give up hope, <PERSON>Mike Smrek</PERSON>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA013089-0093 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 12051 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 30, 1989, Monday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 23; Column 4; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
595 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SEPARATING THE FACTS FROM OPINIONS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN EISENBERG, Baltimore Sun 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Fact: Until the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers' Super Bowl victory, never before had teams 
from one state simultaneously held the pro football, baseball and basketball 
championships. (You can look it up.) 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: Had cornerback <PERSON>Lewis Billups</PERSON> not dropped an easy interception in the 
end zone in the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> Bengals would have won the Super 
Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: Eight of the top 12 scorers in <DATE>this week</DATE>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Basketball Assn</ORGANIZATION>. 
rankings left college before their senior years. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: I'm so happy <PERSON>George Steinbrenner</PERSON> was pardoned. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: <PERSON>Larry Brown</PERSON> already is quietly complaining that he is miserable coaching 
the <LOCATION>San Antonio Spurs</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: Pistons and Lakers in the finals. Pistons in six. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: About <PERCENT>79%</PERCENT> of the Proposition 48 cases are eligible. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: You can have my seat to Leonard-Hearns. A couple of has-beens. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: One year ago, college basketball's ultimate national champions were in 
the middle of a four-game losing streak, their record dropping to 12-8. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: <PERSON>Charles Oakley</PERSON> for <PERSON>Bill Cartwright</PERSON> is the most lopsided trade of the 
year in sports. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: <PERSON>Carl Yastrzemski</PERSON>'s father, <PERSON>Carl Sr.</PERSON>, still works a daily shift at the 
port in <LOCATION>Boston Harbor</LOCATION>. He is 72 and works inside maintenance. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: Making <PERSON>Dave Schmidt</PERSON> a permanent starter is a good move. The Orioles 
should have done it 2 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: There was a standing ovation the other night at <ORGANIZATION>Halsey Field House</ORGANIZATION> when 
poor <PERSON>Derric Turner</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> basketball player who is 6 for 44 shooting free 
throws this season, made one against UNC <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: With freshman Alonzo Mourning and sophomores <PERSON>Dikembe Motumbo</PERSON> and <PERSON>John 
Turner</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Georgetown</ORGANIZATION> has truly frightening potential. I can see the Hoyas winning 
2 national championships in the next 4 years. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: Seventeen of pro basketball's 25 head coaches are in their first or 
second seasons with their current teams. (On the other hand, head coaches in 
the <LOCATION>Big East</LOCATION>, Big Ten and <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Coast Conference</ORGANIZATION> have been in their current 
positions an average of 9 years.) 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: It says much about the state of American soccer when, in the year the 
national team finally should qualify for the World Cup, the coach of the team, 
<PERSON>Luthar Osiander</PERSON>, quits because he would rather be a maitre d' at a restaurant 
in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: <ORGANIZATION>Oregon State</ORGANIZATION> basketball Coach <PERSON>Ralph Miller</PERSON>, retiring this year after 38 
years in the business, knew <PERSON>James Naismith</PERSON>, who invented the game. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: It's popular to say <PERSON>Mario Lemieux</PERSON> is hockey's best player now because 
he is far ahead of <PERSON>Wayne Gretzky</PERSON> in the scoring race. Before this becomes law, 
however, it might be nice for <PERSON>Lemieux</PERSON> to lead a team to the playoffs once. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: The <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> basketball team has not won a game this year. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: Back from the Supe in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, I must admit I like stone crabs more than 
<LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> crabs. (Nah, did I say that?) 
</P>
<P>
Fact: <PERSON>Reggie Lewis</PERSON> is averaging 19 points as <PERSON>Larry Bird</PERSON>'s replacement. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: I bet <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> has a lot to say about Proposal 42. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: The Blast of the <ORGANIZATION>Major Indoor Soccer League</ORGANIZATION> had 10 days off, then played 
back-to-back games this week. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: <PERSON>Pete Rozelle</PERSON>, the old pitchman, is losing his public relations touch. 
Before the Super Bowl, he said the <LOCATION>Overtown</LOCATION> riots had "ruined part of his 
week," and that the leftovers from his mega-party would be given to the 
homeless. Such compassion. 
</P>
<P>
Fact: After only 4 months at No. 2, <PERSON>Ivan Lendl</PERSON> again is the world's No. 1 
tennis player after winning the Australian Open. 
</P>
<P>
Opinion: There is no better show in college basketball this year than <LOCATION>Louisiana 
State</LOCATION> freshman <PERSON>Chris Jackson</PERSON>. Yow. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06136198 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06136198 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; BASKETBALL; PROFESSIONAL; AWARD; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IN THE official NBA Register, in the section titled "All-Time Greats," on
Pages 292 and 293, compressed into 67 lines of type is the basketball career
of one Nathaniel Archibald, more familiarly known as Nate or Tiny, a
cherubic-faced child of the Bronx who fought his way out and, much more
significantly, fought his way back in.;    Monday night, in Springfield,
Mass., Tiny Archibald was one of seven men enshrined in the Basketball Hall of
Fame.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  'TINY' ARCHIBALD: A BIG MAN JOINS HALL OF
FAME  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Bill Lyon is a columnist for the Philadelphia Inquirer.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     His likeness, cast in bronze, will appear in the building named for <PERSON>James
Naismith</PERSON>, who invented the game that Tiny Archibald elevated to another level.
You like to think that <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> would have a special fondness for <PERSON>Archibald</PERSON>,
who was a comparative runt at 6-foot-1, 160 pounds, but who befuddled the
bigger people with his fearless, slashing sorties down the lane and his
clever, creative passing. Left-handed, he would nail the pull-up jumper or
ride on invisible currents of air to the hoop, a sprite whose eyes shone with
excitement and the simple joy of playing. Peter Pan in sneaks.;    <LOCATION>Tiny
Archibald</LOCATION> is in the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame on extravagant statistical merit, having
amassed more than 16,000 points, more than 6,400 assists, more than 2,000
rebounds in 13 professional seasons. That is a most impressive career
triple-double.;    But there is another, rarer, more admirable triple that
Tiny Archibald is soon to complete. It is an educational triple. He has
acquired his bachelor's degree and his master's, and now he is closing in on
his doctorate, in education. Tiny, the Ph.D. Dr. Archibald. It has a certain
ring.;    Now 42, he resides in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>, father of five. He has, indeed,
gone home again. But more, he is one of the special ones who make a
difference. In the mornings, he serves as a recreation director for homeless
men, talking to them, not down to them: "I grew up with a lot of these guys;
they know I'm just trying to help them realize they can make it, too.";    In
the afternoons, he makes the rounds of elementary and junior high schools,
counseling, encouraging, just as he remembers being inspired when he was
younger: "Just trying to pass it on.";    In the evenings, he attends classes
at <ORGANIZATION>Fordham University</ORGANIZATION>, closing in on that educational triple. It is an object
lesson in persistence and perseverance.;    Tiny Archibald learned the city
game on the asphalt proving grounds of the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>, went to <LOCATION>Arizona Western</LOCATION>,
then to <ORGANIZATION>Texas-El Paso</ORGANIZATION>, then to the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>. In the <DATE>1970</DATE> draft, he was taken in the
second round by <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>. He would be traded three times, waived once,
signed as a free agent once. He would be on the roster of five different teams
between <DATE>1970</DATE> and <DATE>1984</DATE>. He would miss one entire season with a torn Achilles'
tendon. He would be an all-NBA first-teamer three times, second team twice. He
would be an All-Star Game MVP. He would be a member of a championship team.;  
 In short, there was nothing in the mad, nomadic, intoxicating, chaotic,
potentially destructive life of a professional athlete that Tiny Archibald
would miss, from the champagne-spray giddiness of the championship ring to the
bleak despair of the surgeon's scalpel.;    If the sport ever gets around to
compiling an official register that lists what a man did with his life after
he stopped bouncing the ball, then top billing belongs to <PERSON>Tiny Archibald</PERSON>, who
scours the shelters and the schools, nurtures the abandoned and the confused,
a <ORGANIZATION>Pied Piper</ORGANIZATION> of the sidewalks, the steam vents and the playgrounds.;    The
only thing about him that doesn't fit is his nickname. In all that truly
matters, Tiny is a giant.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Bill Lyon column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Philadelphia  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final Street  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910515  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  632  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday May 15, 1991
00136198,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900314-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-14-90 0042EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Baseball-Media Bjt   03-14 0836</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Baseball-Media, Bjt,0864</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baseball Lockout Forces Media Companies to Make Alternate Plans</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If the baseball lockout never ends, what will
the sports media write and talk about this <DATE>summer</DATE>?
   Some media companies already are juggling their plans even as
they hope they will never have to answer that question.
   The lockout has blocked the opening of <DATE>spring</DATE> training camps for
nearly a month, and it already has cost the ESPN cable network five
of the 10 <DATE>spring</DATE> training games it planned to televise this year.
   Potential problems loom for <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>, which is to begin broadcasting
baseball in <DATE>April</DATE>; The National, the new daily sports newspaper,
and The Sporting News, the sports weekly.
   ``It hasn't affected us yet, but baseball is the only game in
town in the summertime,'' said <PERSON>Tom Osenton</PERSON>, president and chief
executive of <ORGANIZATION>The Sporting News Publishing Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. ``If
you take the game away, you have nothing to write about.''
   ESPN is in the first season of its <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> contract to
carry up to 175 games in each of the next four years.
   ``Getting that contract was such an exciting moment for us,''
said <PERSON>Mike Soltys</PERSON>, manager of programming information for <ORGANIZATION>ESPN</ORGANIZATION>. ``To
start out in this manner is certainly discouraging.''
   The network filled the gaps created by the lost games with live
tennis, auto racing and other programming it had originally planned
to tape for later replay, he said.
   Plans are to substitute a college basketball playoff game, a
college baseball game and college wrestling, among other events if
the remaining <DATE>spring</DATE> training games are canceled, <PERSON>Soltys</PERSON> said.
   He said the network is sticking with its plans to run a baseball
show, <ORGANIZATION>Baseball Tonight</ORGANIZATION>, seven nights a week starting as scheduled
next <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   If the lockout continues, the show will deal with developments
in negotiations between the players and owners and may feature
coverage of minor league baseball, he said.
   But <ORGANIZATION>ESPN</ORGANIZATION> faces a more serious problem in <DATE>April</DATE>, when it planned
to begin carrying six games a week. The network has hired 19
commentators to handle the nightly baseball show and the games,
<PERSON>Soltys</PERSON> said, and has sold more than <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of its season's
advertising inventory in the games.
   <PERSON>Soltys</PERSON> said the advertisers are being given the options of
appearing on the replacement programs, holding off until the games
start or getting refunds.
   But he said the lockout has hurt the climate for selling
advertising. ``There is no way of knowing where we would be without
this,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Soltys</PERSON> said ``there are provisions for lost games'' under the
network contract with baseball, but he refused to describe them. A
source familiar with the contract said <ORGANIZATION>ESPN</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> will be given
additional games in the next three years for games lost this year.
   The lockout has posed a less serious problem so far for <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>,
which agreed to pay <MONEY>$1.06 billion</MONEY> for the right to broadcast 16
regular season games, the All-Star game, the playoffs and World
Series every year for four years.
   CBS' first baseball broadcasts are scheduled for <DATE>April 14</DATE> and
<DATE>April 21</DATE>, but its third broadcast is not scheduled until <DATE>June 16</DATE>.
   CBS Sports spokesman <PERSON>Tony Fox</PERSON> said the network has not decided
what sports programs will replace the <DATE>April</DATE> game broadcasts.
   Fox said more than half of <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>' advertising inventory for
baseball had been sold, but he declined to discuss what plans were
being made for advertisers if games are canceled.
   The network plans to run its baseball season preview show on
<DATE>March 31</DATE> as scheduled no matter what happens with the lockout, <ORGANIZATION>Fox</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   As at <ORGANIZATION>The Sporting News</ORGANIZATION>, the lockout has had little impact so
far on The National, according to editor-in-chief <PERSON>Frank Deford</PERSON>. The
newspaper debuted <DATE>Jan. 31</DATE> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Deford</PERSON> said readers of <ORGANIZATION>The National</ORGANIZATION> usually are interested in
several sports, and there has been plenty of activity recently in
college and professional basketball, boxing and hockey to interest
them.
   But if the baseball lockout continues into mid-summer, ``that
would be a real blow to us, there is no question.''
   At <ORGANIZATION>The Sporting News</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Osenton</PERSON> said plans are being made to beef
up basketball and hockey coverage over the next few weeks and said
if the lockout persists, the tabloid may increase coverage of minor
league baseball.
   <PERSON>Deford</PERSON> said it was unlikely The National would start covering
minor league or Japanese baseball because he doen't think readers
want it. ``You can't give people something they don't want,'' he
said.
   He said if the lockout continued into <DATE>June</DATE>, there probably would
be more coverage of major tennis, soccer, golf and swimming events.
He said the paper also could be trimmed to 32 pages from the 40-48
pages it has been running.
   Deford professes to be unconcerned and has made no contingency
plans. ``My best judgment is I cannot conceive of a situation where
they will not be back by <DATE>June</DATE>,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA020790-0085 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 172841 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 7, 1990, Wednesday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 11; Column 4; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1409 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
POINT GUARDS: VIPS OF BASKETBALL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By RON KROICHICK, MCCLATCHY NEWS SERVICE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Rewind the basketball VCR, back to a time when a kid named <PERSON>Earvin</PERSON> -- not yet 
Magic -- wore out the sidewalks of <LOCATION>Lansing</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, with his incessant 
dribbling. 
</P>
<P>
The game revolved around centers. Wilt posted up, <PERSON>Wilt</PERSON> got the ball, Wilt 
dunked. Russell swatted away shot after shot. "Sky hook" entered the 
vernacular. 
</P>
<P>
Now fast-forward to <DATE>1990</DATE>. Earvin has long since become Magic, joined by friends 
known as <LOCATION>Isiah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>K.J.</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Stockton</PERSON>. They do not play center, but now the game 
revolves around them. 
</P>
<P>
With all necessary apologies to <PERSON>Patrick Ewing</PERSON>, <PERSON>Akeem Olajuwon</PERSON> and <PERSON>David 
Robinson</PERSON>, centers just aren't enough anymore. Basketball has grown, stretched, 
quickened. Point guards are hip. 
</P>
<P>
Got a great point guard? You're in the hunt. Got an ordinary one? Forget it. 
Just ask Akeem. 
</P>
<P>
"It's harder to find a great point guard than a player at any other position," 
<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> Jazz president <PERSON>Frank Layden</PERSON> says. "It requires more skills, and the 
biggest is to be a decision-maker." 
</P>
<P>
The importance of great point men intensifies the search. The Jazz dipped into 
<LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1984</DATE>, plucking unheralded <PERSON>John Stockton</PERSON> from unheralded 
<ORGANIZATION>Gonzaga University</ORGANIZATION>. Projected as <ORGANIZATION>Rickey Green</ORGANIZATION>'s backup, <PERSON>Stockton</PERSON> instead became 
a star. 
</P>
<P>
As <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> knows, that does not automatically mean a championship ring; it's 
simply a key piece to the puzzle. Each of the last two NBA Finals have matched 
Magic <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Isiah Thomas</PERSON>, good buddies and top-flight point guards. <PERSON>Glen 
Rice</PERSON> may have scored bushels of points, but <PERSON>Rumeal Robinson</PERSON> was equally 
important to <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> title team last <DATE>spring</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Pete Newell</PERSON>, who coached <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> to the national championship in <DATE>1959</DATE> and now 
scouts for the <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Cavaliers</ORGANIZATION>, sees this as no coincidence. "You'll have a 
hard time winning a championship without a great point guard," <PERSON>Newell</PERSON> says. 
</P>
<P>
And today, "great point guard" has wider meaning than in the past. Point guards 
once did not worry about scoring. Dribble, organize, pass. Keep teammates 
happy. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Maurice Cheeks</PERSON>, now with <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, epitomizes that kind of point guard. As 
he climbed the basketball ladder, his job description seemed clear. Be a 
playmaker. 
</P>
<P>
"That's it," Cheeks says. "Just pass. Nothing else. It was never in my makeup 
to score <DATE>20-25</DATE> points a game. 
</P>
<P>
"Now these guys are more able to score. It's a time for younger guys who can 
score and penetrate. They're more versatile." 
</P>
<P>
They score, they penetrate, they pass, they lead. Stockton and <PERSON>Kevin Johnson</PERSON>, 
widely considered the leading point guards for the '90s, have firmly put an end 
to the old style. 
</P>
<P>
Johnson last season became only the fifth player in <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> history to average at 
least 20 points and 10 assists (joining <ORGANIZATION>Magic</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nate Archibald</PERSON> and <PERSON>Oscar 
Robertson</PERSON>). Stockton averaged 17.1 points and a league-high 13.6 assists. 
</P>
<P>
They are the wave of the future for several reasons. As defenses expand -- more 
double-teaming, more traps and thinly veiled zones -- coaches want swift point 
guards who can rush the ball upcourt, create fast breaks or at least start the 
offense quickly. 
</P>
<P>
And since the point guard most often has the ball, he must be a threat to shoot 
the jump shot or drive to the basket. Forget about poor-shooting, 
10-points-per-game stuff. 
</P>
<P>
"That's out," Magic says, grimacing and shaking his head. "All these guys can 
score. You've got to be a 17-12 man, or 17-11. That (10 points) just doesn't 
get it. The defense will let you have the shot." 
</P>
<P>
Since this is a story about point guards, we'll let <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> have the first 
shot. He has earned it. 
</P>
<P>
THE MAGIC MAN 
</P>
<P>
Most conventional concepts of the point guard took a beating in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE>. 
A tall guy with a wide smile emerged from <ORGANIZATION>Everett High School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Lansing</LOCATION>, then 
moved on to nearby <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION>. They called him <ORGANIZATION>Magic</ORGANIZATION>. They said he played 
the point. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jerry Reynolds</PERSON>, the <PERSON>Kings</PERSON>' director of player personnel, remembers his 
reaction. 
</P>
<P>
"When I first heard about him in college as a 6-9 point guard, I said, 'Oh, 
<LOCATION>B.S.</LOCATION> You're saying he's a point guard, but he really isn't,' " <PERSON>Reynolds</PERSON> 
recalls. "Then I saw him, and he really was a point guard. 
</P>
<P>
"It was like seeing the pyramids for the first time." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Earvin Johnson</PERSON> handled the basketball as if he were 5-foot-9. He loved to push 
the ball upcourt, where he could creatively pass off to teammates. He had a 
funky, ugly set shot -- which he made just <PERCENT>46 percent</PERCENT> of the time in college -- 
but then, point guards did not need a great shot. 
</P>
<P>
Neither did most 6-9 players. Johnson just never fit the traditional role of a 
big man, comfortable only within an arm's reach of the basket. 
</P>
<P>
"I was tall, but I could always dribble," he says. "Everywhere I went as a kid 
-- to the store, wherever -- I dribbled. I became a point guard because I 
dribbled so much. 
</P>
<P>
"And passing always gave me just as much satisfaction (as shooting). To make a 
good pass was like a rush, a high, and it still is." 
</P>
<P>
Johnson grew up admiring <PERSON>Nate Archibald</PERSON>, taking ideas for passes from <PERSON>Kevin 
Porter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Pete Maravich</PERSON>. Porter played for <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>'s home state <LOCATION>Detroit 
Pistons</LOCATION>, and he still holds the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> single-game record of 29 assists. 
</P>
<P>
That mark -- and not much else -- has eluded <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>. His magical act, which 
took <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> to the '79 NCAA title, became an instant <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> hit. In 
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>'s very first season, 1979-80, he and skyhook inventor <PERSON>Kareem 
Abdul-Jabbar</PERSON> led the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Lakers</LOCATION> to the league championship. 
</P>
<P>
In <PERSON>Kareem</PERSON>'s first four seasons in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, the Lakers never won a title. 
When a great point guard arrived, they immediately did. 
</P>
<P>
Johnson has since added four more rings to his collection. In becoming the 
player most synonymous with winning since <PERSON>Bill Russell</PERSON>, he sparked a 
fashionable trend in high schools and on playgrounds across <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Suddenly, tall kids wanted to handle the ball. Their coaches may not have 
trashed the idea as quickly as they once did -- "Well, if Magic can do it ..." 
-- but no replica showed up in the <DATE>'80s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"We get carried away with Magics," says <PERSON>Lee Rose</PERSON>, formerly a successful college 
coach and now the <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION> Bucks' director of player personnel. "We think 
everybody's going to be a Magic. Hell, there's only one <ORGANIZATION>Magic</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"His ability to find those open men isn't necessarily because he's 6-9. A lot 
of people that height cannot do what he does." 
</P>
<P>
If anything, point guards have shrunk since <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>'s entrance. His chief 
rivals in the league today -- <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Stockton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kevin Johnson</PERSON> -- all must 
stretch to exceed six feet. 
</P>
<P>
Many respected basketball people hesitate to drop <ORGANIZATION>Magic Johnson</ORGANIZATION> into this 
group. <PERSON>Jerry West</PERSON>, a decent player in his day, harkens back to earlier times 
when speaking of <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> -- when guards were guards. 
</P>
<P>
"Magic's a guard, because he can do everything," says West, now the <ORGANIZATION>Lakers</ORGANIZATION>' 
general manager. "If you watch him, <ORGANIZATION>Magic</ORGANIZATION> is a pretty simple player. He just 
has charisma. 
</P>
<P>
"When Magic was born, they sprinkled a little extra gold dust on him." 
</P>
<P>
So how exactly do we measure <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>'s impact on the position? He clearly 
brought focus and attention to point men. He helped accelerate the game into 
the open court, where guards have more impact than centers. 
</P>
<P>
And passing became a bit more chic. 
</P>
<P>
"I'd say I've made people aware of being a passer," Magic says. "Players now 
are conscious of doing that. Since that's happened, I feel good about it." 
</P>
<P>
THE EVOLUTION 
</P>
<P>
For all his wondrous achievements, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> did not hang around the peach basket 
with <PERSON>James Naismith</PERSON>. It only seems as if Magic were there, offering suggestions 
about how to position players in this new game. 
</P>
<P>
Actually, the key moments in the evolution of the point guard are easily 
distinguishable. The first sign of life occurred when big men stopped jumping 
so often. 
</P>
<P>
"Before the war, guards were great big plodding guys, because there was a 
center-jump after every basket," <PERSON>Newell</PERSON> says. "The fast break started back 
then, with the elimination of the center jump." 
</P>
<P>
Then in <DATE>1954</DATE>, a major rule change forever changed the role of point guards. 
Dismayed by slowdown strategy and low-scoring games, <ORGANIZATION>Syracuse Nationals</ORGANIZATION> owner 
<PERSON>Danny Biasone</PERSON> introduced the 24-second clock. 
</P>
<P>
Suddenly, point guards such as <PERSON>Bob Cousy</PERSON>, <PERSON>Slater Martin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dick McGuire</PERSON> spent 
less time dribbling around, protecting leads and shooting free throws. The 
clock made teams PLAY and made point guards do more than handle the ball. 
</P>
<P>
Twenty-five years later, another new rule completed the shape of today's game. 
When the league adopted the three-point shot in <DATE>1979</DATE>, defenses had even more to 
worry about. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA123090-0158 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 329293 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 30, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 3; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
831 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MIKE DOWNEY: A BASKETBALL HISTORIAN MAKES USC HISTORY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MIKE DOWNEY 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Harold Miner</PERSON> watches the little guy in the black-and-white movie, weaving in 
and out, in and out, dribbling and driving, dribbling and driving. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Bob Cousy</PERSON> always kept his teammates happy. That was his specialty. And he was 
never satisfied. Cousy always tried to elevate his game to another level. I try 
to incorporate that into my own style of play." 
</P>
<P>
And now Miner watches a taller guy in another old movie, working over a 
defender, making his move, making his shot, making his man look bad. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Oscar Robertson</PERSON>, now he was a consummate basketball player. Watch him back the 
guy guarding him toward the basket, use his body and his strength to his 
complete advantage. I'm built more like Oscar. I'd like to be more like him." 
</P>
<P>
Miner pops still another cassette into his VCR. He watches poetry in motion. He 
watches an artist at work. He watches <PERSON>Julius Erving</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"Now with Doctor J, it was more like ballet. It was grace and style. He turned 
basketball into an art form. Everything <PERSON>Julius Erving</PERSON> did on that court was a 
thing of beauty." 
</P>
<P>
And finally the films are in living color and current and hi-fi'd and <ORGANIZATION>Dolby'd</ORGANIZATION>. 
And the star of the show is a guy from <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, a guy with his tongue hanging 
out, a guy who makes other guys' jaws drop. And this guy looks amazingly like 
<PERSON>Harold Miner</PERSON>, only older. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Michael Jordan</PERSON>? Well, the only word that I can think of to describe <PERSON>Michael</PERSON> is 
greatness. You know, people try to compare me to <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>, and I just laugh and 
laugh at that. I'm no <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>, no way, no how. God, well, He doesn't make too 
many <PERSON>Michaels</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Harold Miner</PERSON>, 19, already has become something of a basketball historian. He is 
a student of the game, this <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> sophomore who has developed into one of the 
nation's top scorers. He raids the video stores and book shops, checking out 
every videotape or volume that has anything to do with basketball, past or 
present, from <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Dean Smith</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
In this respect, <ORGANIZATION>Miner</ORGANIZATION> is much like <PERSON>Mike Tyson</PERSON>, who even in his teens had 
committed to memory details and facts from the fights of <PERSON>Jack Dempsey</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gene 
Tunney</PERSON>, <PERSON>Joe Louis</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rocky Marciano</PERSON>, <PERSON>Muhammad Ali</PERSON> and others before and after. 
Miner studies basketball players like homework, oldies and newies. He's 
different from other guys his age who wouldn't know <PERSON>Bob Cousy</PERSON> from <PERSON>Bing Crosby</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Has it paid off? Well, it hasn't hurt. Miner almost certainly will break <PERSON>John 
Block</PERSON>'s quarter-century old <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> record for points in a season. Already this 
season, the 6-foot-5 guard has lit up <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION> for 35 points and nine 
rebounds, made <PERSON>Digger Phelps</PERSON> regret not landing him as a recruit and moved <PERSON>Dick 
Vitale</PERSON> to refer to Miner as "the best thing to happen to <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> since football." 
</P>
<P>
He keeps playing the way he's playing, some day they'll make movies about him. 
</P>
<P>
With <PERSON>George Raveling</PERSON>'s Trojans only now venturing into the taller weeds of 
their schedule, beginning <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Miner</ORGANIZATION> has become the 
Pac-10's player to watch, the conference's leading returning scorer from last 
season. He is building a Miner cult following. A fan club. Harold examiners? 
</P>
<P>
His nickname is Baby <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>. Like <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>, he shaves his head, rubs his fingers 
together like a dice shooter, floats to the hoop with his tongue in a droop. He 
says he sometimes has dreams at night in which he leaps for a dunk from the 
free-throw line and jams the ball through the basket backward. 
</P>
<P>
Miner is so infatuated with <PERSON>Michael</PERSON> that he thought about enrolling at <LOCATION>North 
Carolina</LOCATION>, just for a shared experience. Even his number is 23. Harold 
identifies with him so, he probably pours Diet <ORGANIZATION>Coke</ORGANIZATION> over his Wheaties. 
</P>
<P>
Also like <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, however, <PERSON>Miner</PERSON> would sacrifice some of his personal success 
if only <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> could establish itself as more of a force in college basketball, 
after having losing records over five consecutive seasons. The Trojans were 
49-95 during that span. 
</P>
<P>
He could lead them out of the hoop wilderness. 
</P>
<P>
"I think Miner is one of the best players in the country," <PERSON>Phelps</PERSON> said after 
<ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION>'s 105-95 loss to <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>South Bend</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION> "We really wanted him here, 
and you can see why. He's going to be one of the greatest scorers the game has 
seen." 
</P>
<P>
Funny thing about Miner picking USC: One of the main reasons he did so was to 
play closer to his family in <LOCATION>Inglewood</LOCATION>. Then his father, <PERSON>Melvin Miner</PERSON>, a 
computer programmer for <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>, was transferred to <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>. So, when <PERSON>Harold</PERSON> 
scored 24 points in <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>'s 74-67 victory on <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> at <LOCATION>Colorado State</LOCATION>, it was the 
first chance his father had to see him play in a collegiate game. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, attendance is growing at <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> home games, as both <PERSON>Miner</PERSON> and the team 
get better and better. 
</P>
<P>
No matter who is out there watching him, <ORGANIZATION>Miner</ORGANIZATION> is a performer suitable for 
children or adults. He is a sensation with the critics, even if he is not yet 
big box office, and we definitely give him thumbs up. 
</P>
<P>
"Hey, it doesn't matter if it's a hundred people," <PERSON>Miner</PERSON> said. "When Doctor J 
was playing at <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, he was always playing in front of empty crowds." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Harold Miner 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MINER, HAROLD; BASKETBALL PLAYERS; COLLEGE ATHLETICS; UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN 
CALIFORNIA 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062589-0178 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 74732 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 25, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 9; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1477 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HOOSIER HALL OF FAME; 
</P>
<P>
NEW CASTLE, IND., WILL BE HOME OF $2.5-MILLION PREP BASKETBALL SHRINE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES HILLINGER, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW CASTLE, Ind. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Ron Newlin</PERSON> stood on a rise in this rolling hill country, 35 miles east of 
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, gazing in wonder at the nearly completed building, then shot a 
roll of film, getting progress photos of the construction project. 
</P>
<P>
"It should be finished (soon)," he said. "It will take seven or eight months 
after that to set all the exhibits in place. We hope to be open in time for the 
state tournament next <DATE>March</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Newlin</PERSON>, 30, is executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Indiana Basketball Hall</ORGANIZATION> of Fame, soon 
to be located here in <LOCATION>New Castle</LOCATION> in its first permanent home, a <MONEY>$2.5-million</MONEY> 
shrine to the favorite game of <ORGANIZATION>Hoosiers</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"There's the <PERSON>Basketball Hall</PERSON> of Fame in <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, dedicated to the 
game played all over the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, but no other state has anything like 
this," he said. 
</P>
<P>
"The <ORGANIZATION>Indiana Basketball Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> represents the spirit, the values, the 
tradition of being a Hoosier. This museum will salute the schools, the players, 
the coaches, the communities that have made <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> the nation's basketball 
leader." 
</P>
<P>
Basketball was invented by <PERSON>James Naismith</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1891</DATE> and 
was first played in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> in <DATE>1894</DATE> at the <LOCATION>Crawfordsville YMCA</LOCATION>. Since then, 
more than 250,000 Hoosiers, boys and girls, have played the game on the high 
school varsity level and worn the colors of 1,200 different schools. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> has been absolutely nuts about basketball since the first state 
championship tournament in <DATE>1911</DATE>," <PERSON>Newlin</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"It is by far the most important sport in the state, outdistancing football and 
baseball in popularity. Hoosier hysteria over basketball is part of our 
culture, part of what <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> is all about. On a per-capita basis, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> has 
produced more professional basketball players than any other state." 
</P>
<P>
He rattled off the names of such Hoosier hoop luminaries as <PERSON>John Wooden</PERSON>, <PERSON>Oscar 
Robertson</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Larry Bird</ORGANIZATION>. He told how the state tournament each year draws more 
than a million fans. He mentioned that <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> has eight high school basketball 
gyms that seat more than 7,000 spectators. 
</P>
<P>
"No other state can say that," he boasted. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> crowns a hill next to <ORGANIZATION>New Castle</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler High School</ORGANIZATION>, which 
has the biggest prep basketball gym in the world, seating 9,350. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Indiana Basketball Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> has captured the imagination and pride of 
people all over the state, from <LOCATION>Aberdeen</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Zipp</PERSON> and Zulu, in <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Evansville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Terre Haute</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Lafayette</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Gary</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Elkhart</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Bend</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON>, 
<LOCATION>Muncie</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Marion</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Bloomington</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Young America</LOCATION>, Windfall, <LOCATION>Wawpecong</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mongo</PERSON> 
and Old Tip Town. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Henry County</LOCATION>, in which <ORGANIZATION>New Castle</ORGANIZATION> is located, passed a <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> restaurant and 
beverage tax to raise <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> toward the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION>'s cost, and <DATE>last 
month</DATE>, donations from individuals and groups had exceeded <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>. Marsh, an 
<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> supermarket chain, gave <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY>. Two well-heeled <ORGANIZATION>Hoosiers</ORGANIZATION> each kicked 
in <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY>. There are <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame committees in every one of the state's 92 
counties. 
</P>
<P>
A <MONEY>half-million dollars</MONEY> has been raised in the "sale" of bricks -- 2,500 that 
went for <MONEY>$100</MONEY> each and 500 more that sold for <MONEY>$500</MONEY> each. In the center of the 
<PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame's courtyard, a 70 x 36-foot map of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> will be made up of the 
<MONEY>$100</MONEY> bricks, containing donors' names, and the <MONEY>$500</MONEY> bricks will be inscribed 
with names of teams and coaches. 
</P>
<P>
Botany Prof. <PERSON>Robert Hoshaw</PERSON>, 67, teaching at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Arizona</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION> 
for the <DATE>last 39 years</DATE>, is typical of how many former <ORGANIZATION>Hoosiers</ORGANIZATION> have reacted to 
the hall.He said that he and the five other surviving members of the <DATE>1939</DATE> 
seven-man <ORGANIZATION>Monticello High School</ORGANIZATION> basketball team each purchased a <MONEY>$100</MONEY> brick. 
</P>
<P>
"Our school had less than 200 students," he said. "We had a great team 50 years 
ago. We wound up in the regional final, one of the top 32 schools in the state. 
Four of us went into teaching, one into insurance, one became a judge in the 
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> area, and one of the fellows died. 
</P>
<P>
"As part of Hoosier Hysteria, we figured it was only right we do our part in 
contributing to the <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Basketball Hall of Fame. Twenty of us from 
<LOCATION>Monticello</LOCATION> High each also chipped in <MONEY>$25</MONEY> to buy a brick in memory of our 
outstanding basketball coach, the late <PERSON>Alva Staggs</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sam Alford</PERSON>, 46, basketball coach at <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> High the <DATE>last 14 years</DATE>, is the 
father of <PERSON>Steve Alford</PERSON>, 24, former All-American at <ORGANIZATION>Indiana University</ORGANIZATION>, now with 
the <ORGANIZATION>Golden State Warriors</ORGANIZATION>. The <PERSON>Alford</PERSON> family bought a brick, since five Alfords 
played basketball in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> -- <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>'s father, <PERSON>Sam</PERSON> and his brother, and <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>'s 
two sons. 
</P>
<P>
"The five of us scored 8,000 points playing basketball in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> in high 
school and college," <PERSON>Alford</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Megaphones, trophies, uniforms, letter jackets, game balls, cheerleader 
sweaters, yearbooks, scrapbooks, class rings, mascots and other basketball 
memorabilia is pouring into the hall's temporary office in what was an old 
school building in downtown <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, at 520 <LOCATION>Virginia Ave.</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
"Team nicknames are something else," <PERSON>Newlin</PERSON> said, laughing. "Epson Salts for 
<ORGANIZATION>Epson High School</ORGANIZATION>. I thought the <ORGANIZATION>Monroe City Blue Jeans</ORGANIZATION> came by their name 
because there was a denim factory in town. I was wrong. It came from an 
early-day governor, who lived in <LOCATION>Monroe City</LOCATION>, <PERSON>James</PERSON> (Blue Jeans) <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
Over the years, there have been 1,200 high schools in the state that put 
basketball teams on the floor. Today, because of consolidations, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> has 
400 high school teams. 
</P>
<P>
"We will have something from every high school that ever had a team," <PERSON>Newlin</PERSON> 
said. "Alumni are tickled pink to have a chance to do something for the old 
alma mater." 
</P>
<P>
Every day's mail brings something new. <PERSON>James Griffin</PERSON> sent in scores he compiled 
of every state tournament played in the <DATE>last 78 years</DATE> from the sectional level 
through the state final. 
</P>
<P>
The letter jacket of <PERSON>Larry Hobson</PERSON>, holder of a single-season scoring record at 
<LOCATION>Pekin High</LOCATION>, where he averaged 30.2 points a game in <DATE>1963</DATE>, is in the stack of 
memorabilia. So are one <DATE>1904</DATE> player's heavy-duty pants, used to play on an 
outdoor cinder parking lot at Freelandville High. 
</P>
<P>
The hall will chronicle and preserve the heritage of the game as played by the 
thousands of teams in the Hoosier state, and will depict through exhibits, film 
footage and video what basketball means to the state's culture, history and 
personality. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Tom Carnegie</PERSON>, long-time track announcer for the <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 500-mile race, and 
businessman <PERSON>Ray Johnson</PERSON>, both members of the <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> downtown <ORGANIZATION>Lions Club</ORGANIZATION>, 
came up with the idea of a shrine dedicated to <ORGANIZATION>Hoosier Hysteria</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1962</DATE>, the first five of the 250 members of the <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Basketball Hall of 
Fame were selected: 
</P>
<P>
 -- Wooden, who was on the <DATE>1927</DATE> Martinsville state championship team. He went 
on to become an All-American at <LOCATION>Purdue</LOCATION> and coached at <ORGANIZATION>South Bend Central High</ORGANIZATION> 
