<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50414 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu020_d_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-020 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  31 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SLOVAKIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Hungary Offered Increase in Danube Water </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU2701201794 Bratislava NARODNA OBRODA in Slovak 25 Jan 94 p 
2 </F>

<F P=103> AU2701201794 </F>
<F P=104>  Bratislava NARODNA OBRODA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Slovak </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [TA SR report: "No Retreat From Positions"] </F>
  [Excerpts] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>--"By 2 <DATE>May 1994</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak 
Government</ORGANIZATION> will submit to the <ORGANIZATION>International Court of Justice</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION> the `Memorandum of the Slovak Republic on the 
<ORGANIZATION>Gabcikovo-Nagymaros Hydroelectric Power Project</ORGANIZATION>.' We expect the 
document to consist of 2,000-2,500 pages," <PERSON>Jan Lisuch</PERSON>, state 
secretary at the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, told yesterday's 
meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>National Council</ORGANIZATION> of the Slovak Republic [NRSR] 
Commission for Issues of the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Hydroelectric Projects</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The state secretary also briefed the <ORGANIZATION>NRSR</ORGANIZATION> commission on 
findings acquired thus far about the impact of the Gabcikovo 
hydroelectric project on the level of underground water in Zitny 
Ostrov [<LOCATION>Rye Island</LOCATION>, area along the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> in southern <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>], 
on water supply in the system of Danube branches, and on 
improving navigation on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>. [passage omitted] 
  At their meeting yesterday, members of the <ORGANIZATION>NRSR</ORGANIZATION> commission 
also discussed a reply to a letter from <PERSON>Andras Pap</PERSON>, chairman of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Parliament</ORGANIZATION>'s committee dealing with the 
hydroelectric project. The reply states that the solution to 
the problem of a sufficient amount of water in the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> 
branches [on Hungarian territory] lies in the "mutually agreed 
construction of a dam at Dunakiliti. This would make it 
possible to supply the network of branches in the <LOCATION>Szigetkoz</LOCATION> area 
with up to 140 cubic meters of water per second." Academician 
<PERSON>Juraj Hrasko</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>NRSR</ORGANIZATION> commission, stressed that the 
flow in the old river bed [of the Danube] could be increased 
after the completion of an automatic water diversion system at a 
newly built small hydroelectric power plant [at Dunakiliti]. 
This pledge [to increase flow in the old riverbed] would mean a 
reduction in the production of electricity in Gabcikovo by about 
28 million kilowatt-hours annually, which would extend the 
period necessary for the investment costs to be recouped. "On no 
account will the Slovak side consider this temporary solution to 
be a retreat from positions during the discussion of the 
Slovak-Hungarian dispute before the <ORGANIZATION>International Court of 
Justice</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION>. The failure to implement solutions, the 
blueprints of which are ready and agreement on which had already 
been reached, runs counter to our common interest in the 
creation of optimal conditions for the ecological system of 
Danube wetland forests," the reply from the <ORGANIZATION>NRSR</ORGANIZATION> commission to 
<ORGANIZATION>Andras Pap</ORGANIZATION>'s letter states. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-55381 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu093__a94026" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-093-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Ministry Proposes Danube Talks </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Ministry Proposes Danube Talks </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1105191794 Prague CTK in English 1827 GMT 11 May 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1105191794 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

today, the ministry told <ORGANIZATION>CTK</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The Ministry proposed that talks take place on <DATE>May 18-19</DATE> in 
<LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>. "It is already the second date proposed by the 
ministry for talks on the temporary water regime on the river 
and it would therefore welcome it if the Hungarian side said it 
was ready for such talks," the note says. It says that such 
talks should help achieve goals proposed by the <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> 
(<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>) experts. "It is necessary, however, to take into account 
the possibilities of technical realization and economic impact 
of individual solutions," the note says. 
  Beside the dispute over the Gabcikovo hydroelectric project 
itself which was taken to the <ORGANIZATION>International Court of Justice</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION> <DATE>last July</DATE>, <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> are also in 
disagreement over the temporary water regime on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> to 
function until a verdict is passed in <LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION>. 
  Hungary demands that <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> let more water to flow into 
the 
<LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>'s old course even at the cost of restricting electricity 
production at <LOCATION>Gabcikovo</LOCATION>, while Slovak experts say that the 
improvement of the state of the <ORGANIZATION>Danube</ORGANIZATION>'s tributaries on the 
Hungarian side which are drying up does not so much depend on 
the flow of water but rather on the construction of the system 
of weirs which would raise the water level to such an extent as 
it flows also into the tributaries. However, the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian 
Parliament</ORGANIZATION> rejected the construction of the weirs and decided to 
supply the tributaries with water with the help of pumps. An 
attempt to reach a compromise undertaken by <ORGANIZATION>EU Commission</ORGANIZATION> 
experts has so far failed. 
  Nevertheless, <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> made it clear it is willing to be 
accommodating when during a meeting of the two countries' 
environment ministers in mid-April in <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> <PERSON>Juraj Hrasko</PERSON> 
promised to his Hungarian counterpart to double the amount of 
water flowing through Mosoni-Duna tributary on Hungarian 
territory as of <DATE>May 15</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-67521 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpten013___94045" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEN-94-013 </AU>
JPRS 
Environmental Issues 

<DATE1>  9 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST EUROPE </F>
<F P=101> AUSTRIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   WWF Warns Against Water Pollution by Slovak Danube Dam </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    WWF Warns Against Water Pollution by Slovak Danube Dam </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU0905175494 Prague CTK in English 1537 GMT 9 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0905175494 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9</DATE> (CTK) -- Representatives of the 
Austrian section of the World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF) warned 
today of the pollution of the Danube flood plain forests by the 
Slovak Gabcikovo water project. 
  The area, which is located on a large gravel subsoil, is the 
second biggest European source of drinking water. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>WWF</ORGANIZATION>, which is now launching a campaign to establish a 
national park in the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> flood plain forests between <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION> 
and Slovak border, demonstrated the adverse effects of the 
regulated water flow on nature to journalists from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, and the <LOCATION>Czech Republic</LOCATION> during a several-day educational 
excursion. 
  The self-purification of the flood plain forests as well as 
the heterogeneity of its fauna and flora depend on the changing 
level of the river. Regular floods in this unique landscape are 
a precondition of its existence, <PERSON>Alexander Zinke</PERSON> from the <ORGANIZATION>WWF</ORGANIZATION> 
said. 
  By diverting <PERCENT>80-90 percent</PERCENT> of the Danube water into an 
insulated channel, the old riverbed receives only a minimum 
amount of water, which will soon entirely change the natural 
character of the landscape. 
  The Austrian environmentalists have proposed a ``tender 
variant'' which entails letting <PERCENT>65-75 percent</PERCENT> of the Danube 
waters flow in the old riverbed. 
  At least three years will elapse before the Hungarian-Slovak 
dispute at the <ORGANIZATION>International Court of Justice</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>The Hague</ORGANIZATION> is 
settled. In the meantime, many species will be exterminated, 
the <ORGANIZATION>WWF</ORGANIZATION> stressed. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-31456 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu111__a94025" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-111-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Rejects EU Danube Recommendation </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Government Rejects EU Danube Recommendation </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU0706140094 Prague CTK in English 1218 GMT 7 Jun 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0706140094 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> <DATE>June 7</DATE> (CTK) -- Slovak Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Eduard Kukan</PERSON> today confirmed <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>'s rejection of the 
recommendation by a <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> expert commission that more 
water be diverted into the old course of the <LOCATION>River Danube</LOCATION> and 
less into the canal that serves the hydroelectric power project 
at Gabcikovo-Nagymaros. 
  The recommendation was intended as a compromise in the 
Slovak-Hungarian dispute over what water regime should be 
adopted until the <ORGANIZATION>International Court</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>The Hague</ORGANIZATION> delivers its 
judgement about the disputed hydroelectric project. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Parliament</ORGANIZATION> agreed with the experts' 
recommendations, but decided to supply the branches of the river 
which are drying up by means of pumps rather than by building 
weirs. 
  Kukan said in a radio interview that the commission's 
recommendation to increase the flow in the old Danube course by 
800 cubic metres a second "is not acceptable to the Slovak 
Government". He said there were other technical measures which 
might permit a different compromise solution with <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> wanted to discuss them. 
  "We have certain positive signs that the Hungarian position 
might be changing, but I would be realistic and wait and see 
what actually happens," <PERSON>Kukan</PERSON> said. He said he assumed talks 
would continue after the new Hungarian Government was formed. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-30874 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu027__a94035" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-027-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Moravcik Discusses `Partnership,' Gabcikovo </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU0802182694 Prague CTK in English 1703 GMT 8 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0802182694 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>, Feb 8 (CTK) -- Slovak Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Vladimir Meciar</PERSON> will sign a general document on <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>Partnership for Peace</ORGANIZATION> plan in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [9 
<DATE>February</DATE>], Foreign Minister <PERSON>Jozef Moravcik</PERSON> confirmed today. 
  Moravcik also reported that the government approved a bill 
on 
the principles of the provisional water management regime at the 
Danube hydroelectric power station at Gabcikovo-Nagymaros, on 
the Slovak- Hungarian border. The bill is based on reports 
compiled by an expert group from the <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>) 
commission and the two states involved in construction, <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>. He said the government favors the provisional 
water management regime, as the Slovak section of the commission 
recommended. 
  <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> proposes that, at the beginning of the vegetation 
phase, the Danube branch be flooded while the current flow in 
the old riverbed is preserved, he said. 
  <PERSON>Moravcik</PERSON> stressed <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> fully respected Hungarian fears 
that too little water would be left in the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> on Hungarian 
territory and would implement concrete measures to prevent this 
from happening. He added that in approving the bill the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak 
Government</ORGANIZATION> was making no comment on the original <DATE>1977</DATE> agreement 
on the construction of the dam and that any agreement on the 
water management regime would be valid only until the 
<ORGANIZATION>International Court of Justice</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION>, which is to settle 
the dispute between <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, delivers its judgment. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-9551 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu058__a94025" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-058-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   No Evidence of Sabotage Found </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU2403123394 Prague CTK in English 2007 GMT 22 Mar 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2403123394 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 22</DATE> (CTK) -- The investigation 
underway into the shipping accidents that have blocked two locks 
at the Gabcikovo-Nagymaros hydroelectric power project on the 
<LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> has so far not revealed any evidence of external 
interference, according to a <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Government</ORGANIZATION> statement which 
<ORGANIZATION>CTK</ORGANIZATION> has obtained. 
  "Only the findings of the government commission working at 
the Gabcikovo water project will be authoritative," the 
government statement reads. 
  Economics Minister <PERSON>Peter Magvasi</PERSON> refused to speculate about 
the possibility that the accidents were caused by sabotage, 
saying the commission had to continue and complete their 
investigation. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Government</ORGANIZATION> expressed regret today at its session 
that international passage on the Danube remained impossible 
because the right-hand lock at Gabcikovo was still blocked by 
the Ukrainian tugboat Zernograd which sank on <DATE>February 11</DATE>. The 
government announced it hoped river traffic could be resumed 
within a few days. 
  A section of the bottom gate of the left lock was damaged -- 
it is not known how -- on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> [20 <DATE>March</DATE>] <TIME>night</TIME> and the 
resultant wave under the dam damaged mechanisms on the bottom 
gate of the right lock. Subsequently international ship 
transport along this section of the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> has been interrupted. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> earlier issued a statement 
asserting that the Slovak Government bore full responsibility 
for the blockage and asked countries supporting free passage on 
the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> to call on <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> to re-open the river. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-8457 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu072__a94029" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-072-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Minister Hrasko Discusses Meeting on Gabcikovo </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Minister Hrasko Discusses Meeting on Gabcikovo </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1404092794 Prague CTK in English 1932 GMT 13 Apr 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1404092794 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 13</DATE> (CTK) -- A meeting between the 
Slovak and Hungarian environment ministers which included 
discussion of the Gabcikovo hydroelectric project ended without 
concrete results today. 
  On the controversial subject of the division of the Danube 
waters, Slovak Environment Minister <PERSON>Juraj Hrasko</PERSON> said he and his 
Hungarian counterpart <PERSON>Janos Gyurko</PERSON> had agreed to recommend that 
their governments prepare themselves to discuss the approval of 
a political decision. 
  "We did not bind ourselves to any conclusions. However, we 
both said the tone of the meeting was much friendlier than in 
the past," <PERSON>Hrasko</PERSON> said, adding that he was ready to continue 
negotiations with the aim of improving the state of the drying 
out branches of the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>. 
  Hrasko confirmed that in the dispute over the dividing of 
the 
<LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> waters between the old river course and the Gabcikovo 
canal he had proposed negotiations without the participation of 
experts from the <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>), but declined to give 
further details. 
  Gyurko, however, rejected the offer of bilateral 
negotiations, thus sticking to <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s demand that talks take 
place with the participation of <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> experts. However, he 
appreciated the change for the better in the atmosphere of the 
negotiations. If the Slovaks were to send more water into the 
old course than before -- and this would mean a fall in the 
output of electricity from Gabcikovo -- the Hungarians would 
support any request made of <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> by a third party for 
compensation for these losses. 
  "We were assured that no standpoint from the Hungarian 
Parliament or Government had to be definitive in the search for 
an agreement," said <PERSON>Hrasko</PERSON>, who used to be chairman of the 
parliamentary committee for Gabcikovo. 
  "A mare is never sold at a market for the asking price, but 
nor is the first offer paid," he added. 
  The compromise proposal by Western experts on the division 
of 
the Danube waters was approved conditionally by <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, but 
<LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> rejected it. However, the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Parliament</ORGANIZATION> then 
went against the recommendations of both the experts and its own 
government, and decided that the drying out branch of the Danube 
would be supplied with water by pumps, not by the building of a 
dam. 
  Nonetheless, <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> recently invited <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> to resume 
talks forthwith, to which <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> replied that it was still 
prepared to negotiate. 
  Hrasko said <DATE>today</DATE>'s talks also concerned broader issues of 
cooperation in environmental protection and improving the 
quality of contacts between the two countries. Concretely, they 
discussed the creation of a joint national park on the border 
area and an agreement on a common approach to the pollution of 
waters. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-8393 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu046__a94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-046-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Hungary </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Accuses Slovakia of Diverting Danube </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU0803171294 Budapest MTI in English 1527 GMT 8 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0803171294 </F>
<F P=104>  Budapest MTI </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION>, 8 <DATE>March</DATE> (MTI) -- The Hungarian 
representative in the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION> recently forwarded a 
letter to representatives of the other member states, Hungarian 
Foreign Affairs Spokesman <PERSON>Janos Herman</PERSON> announced on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> [8 
<DATE>March</DATE>]. 
  In the letter, the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Government</ORGANIZATION>, citing the <DATE>February</DATE> 
tragedy of the Ukrainian tugboat, reminded the member states of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION> that the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Government</ORGANIZATION>, in serious 
violation of its international contractual obligations, 
rechanneled the Danube river flow in a 40-kilometer section from 
the river's natural bed, previously used for international 
shipping, and has thus prevented navigation on this section. 
  In order to fully enforce the safety and freedom of Danube 
shipping, the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Government</ORGANIZATION> considers it necessary for 
the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION> to call on the <ORGANIZATION>Government</ORGANIZATION> of the Slovak 
Republic to continuously provide the necessary water amount in 
the natural bed of the Danube in order to restore the original 
conditions of navigation, as was previously demanded by the 
Hungarian side. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Government</ORGANIZATION> also deems it necessary for the 
<ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION> to call on <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> to restore the official 
announcement system which has not been in force since the 
Gabcikovo facility was unilaterally placed into operation. 
Under the terms of the system, the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION>, and 
through it the governments of the countries concerned, must 
immediately be informed of all circumstantial events -- for 
instance, the serious accident in <DATE>February</DATE>. 
  However, the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION> has still not received any 
such notification concerning the Ukrainian boat accident. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Government</ORGANIZATION> has requested that the <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> 
place these issues on the discussion agenda for the session next 
month. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-9224 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu055__a94019" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-055-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  18 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Denounces Hungary's `Propaganda' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU2103090194 Prague CTK in English 2137 GMT 18 Mar 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2103090194 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 18</DATE> (CTK) -- The Slovak Government 
today said it regretted <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s abuse of the accident of the 
Ukrainian tugboat Zernograd at Gabcikovo earlier this year for 
"dubious propaganda" against the Gabcikovo-Nagymaros 
hydroproject on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>. 
  A statement by the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> addressed to the 
members of the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION>, received by <ORGANIZATION>CTK</ORGANIZATION> today, said 
that <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s representative to the <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> had accused 
<LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> of failure to honor the official system of announcing 
emergency occurrences on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>. 
  According to preliminary information by Slovak authorities, 
the accident in the lock at <LOCATION>Gabcikovo</LOCATION> was due to man's failure 
as the captain grossly violated regulations guiding passage 
through the lock. 
  "The unequivocal conclusions stated by <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> are evidently 
aimed at discrediting the reliability of the Gabcikovo 
hydroproject and its positive contribution to international 
navigation and to its safety," the statement says. 
  It points out without specification that <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s 
"unilateral" moves, that are at variance with its international 
commitments, raise serious obstacles to international navigation. 
  The statement also points out <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s effort "to get the 
<ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION> entangled in the dispute between <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> [over Gabcikovo] even though both parties have agreed to 
settle the dispute before the <ORGANIZATION>International Court of Justice</ORGANIZATION> in 
The Hague." 
  The statement also protests against the effort to include 
Gabcikovo in the agenda of the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION>'s 
deliberations. It stresses that at the next session of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION>'s relevant body, <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> will raise the question of 
"seeking solution to the unfavorable navigation conditions 
caused by the moves taken by <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>." 
  Under agreement reached by Slovak and Ukrainian bodies the 
Zernograd will be removed from the lock on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> [19 <DATE>March</DATE>]. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-54588 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu085__a94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-085-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Inter-European Affairs </F>
<H3> <TI>   Slovakia, Hungary Seek Ruling on Gabcikovo </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Slovakia, Hungary Seek Ruling on Gabcikovo </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU0205153694 Prague CTK in English 1443 GMT 2 May 94--FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0205153694 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] The Hague, <DATE>May 2</DATE> (CTK) -- <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> today 
officially submitted their dispute over the Gabcikovo-Nagymaros 
hydroelectric works to the <ORGANIZATION>International Court of Justice</ORGANIZATION>. 
  <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> accuses <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> of not honoring the commitments it 
took on in the Czechoslovak-Hungarian agreement concluded in 
<DATE>September 1977</DATE>. <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> blames <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> for undertaking 
unilateral steps, causing damage through restricting the flow in 
the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>'s original bed and negatively affecting the 
environment, The court is also to evaluate whether or not the 
<DATE>1977</DATE> agreement is valid. 
  <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> decided to turn to the international 
court in <DATE>April 1993</DATE>, after their talks on the issue were 
stalemated. A commission of experts from the <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> 
(<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>) worked out an objective analysis of the issue. 
  Documents containing the two sides' arguments were brought 
to 
the court in two fully-packed vans. 
  The agreement to present the dispute to the <ORGANIZATION>International 
Court of Justice</ORGANIZATION> was reached by the two countries quite 
smoothly. Today's behavior of both Hungarian and Slovak 
representatives indicated that the former tension between 
<LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> has dwindled for the time being. The 
two countries also express their willingness to respect the 
court's decision. 
  However, the dispute is expected to drag on for long due to 
the controversial issue itself and the rightfulness of most 
arguments. The <ORGANIZATION>International Court</ORGANIZATION> will not decide on the 
problem before <DATE>1997</DATE>, as first it has to solve another six big 
disputes. 
  The idea of damming the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> in its Slovak-Hungarian 
border 
section first appeared in <DATE>1910</DATE>. It was reappeared in <DATE>1950</DATE>, but 
the agreement on the construction of a giant project was signed 
between Czechoslovak and Hungarian communist regimes only on 
<DATE>September 15, 1977</DATE>. In <DATE>1989</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and 
government began to distance themselves from the project and 
later decided to halt the construction of its Hungarian part in 
<LOCATION>Nagymaros</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> completed the hydroelectric waterworks in 
Gabcikovo in late <DATE>1992</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-32733 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu125__a94053" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-125-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  10 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Accident at Gabcikovo Exacerbates Controversy </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Accident at Gabcikovo Exacerbates Controversy </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   94CH0293A Prague PRAGUE POST in English 10 May 94 p 7--FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> 94CH0293A </F>
<F P=104>  Prague PRAGUE POST </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
CSO 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>Ann Marsh</PERSON>: "Slovak Dam Project Remains a Source </F>
of International Tension"] 
  [Text] Water traffic along the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> river, blocked for 
more than a month because of a malfunction at <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>'s 
Gabcikovo dam, lurched back into motion <DATE>April 27</DATE>, clearing the 
way for hundreds of irate ship owners to complete their 
deliveries. 
  Caused by a mixture of bad luck, bad blood and bad planning, 
the breakdown of the dam's lock system has featured the 
suspected murder of a ship captain, insinuations of espionage 
and <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in damages claimed by shipping companies. 
  It also has fulfilled some of the worst predictions about 
the 
communist-era dam and hydroelectric project, which began 
operating in <DATE>1992</DATE>. 
  "The impact is tremendous," said <PERSON>Karl Brewi</PERSON>, general 
director 
of the Vienna-based <ORGANIZATION>Austrian Danube Shipping Company</ORGANIZATION> (DDSG), 
which had 30 vessels delayed. Although Slovak dam officials say 
80 vessels were stuck in queues--51 upstream and 29 
downstream--shipping companies put the number in the hundreds as 
crews waited in Hungarian or Austrian ports for the go-ahead. 
  The most recent trouble at the controversial Gabcikovo 
hydroelectric plant--which has been the focus of a 
Hungarian-Slovak transborder dispute for years--began <DATE>Feb. 11</DATE> 
when a Ukrainian tugboat capsized in the dam's right lock. The 
captain was found hanged inside the half-submerged vessel. 
  Slovak police are suspicious of the apparent suicide. 
  "A ship has an accident and the captain thinks he must hang 
himself in the next couple of minutes?" said <PERSON>Miroslav Liska</PERSON>, 
spokesman for the Bratislava-based <ORGANIZATION>Water Development Authority</ORGANIZATION> 
(<ORGANIZATION>Vodohospodarska</ORGANIZATION> vystavba), which operates the dam. The captain, 
<PERSON>Liska</PERSON> pointed out, was nearing retirement and had just bought a 
car that he was bringing home to <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION>. 
  "A Ukrainian who just bought a car would not hang himself," 
he said. "It shows that maybe he did not hang himself, but was 
hanged." 
  Slovak police may never learn the full story, because the 
Ukrainian crew left the scene shortly after the accident, when 
<LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> insisted on removing the crippled vessel without Slovak 
participation. This operation took close to a month, while 
Ukrainian ships arrived and then removed the tug. "We wanted to 
remove it immediately," <PERSON>Liska</PERSON> said, "but we were too benevolent." 
  During this time, Gabcikovo's left lock slowly ferried the 
dam's regular 20 to 30 ships a day back and forth, although it 
had been scheduled to shut down <DATE>Feb. 12</DATE> for a routine 
inspection, <PERSON>Liska</PERSON> said. On <DATE>March 20</DATE>, just over a month after the 
first accident, the left lock broke down, bringing all traffic 
to a halt. 
  Shipping companies were outraged to learn that Gabcikovo has 
no emergency gate--a standard feature of any lock system. Aside 
from criticism about the dam's effect on local farmland and 
water tables, this omission supported long-standing claims that 
the dam was poorly constructed. 
  Under the terms of the original Slovak-Hungarian agreement 
for constructing the cross-border waterworks, signed in <DATE>1979</DATE>, 
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> was to build an emergency gate on its side. After 
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> unilaterally backed out of the agreement in <DATE>1992</DATE>, a move 
Slovaks continue to call illegal, no emergency gate was built. 
One is under construction now on the Slovak side and should be 
completed by late <DATE>1995</DATE>, according to <PERSON>Liska</PERSON>. 
  Though Slovak dam officials have no explanation for the 
breakdown of the left lock, diving teams claim to have found a 
cable that may have interfered with the lock's seal. Espionage 
is suspected. The final word is pending, however, while the left 
lock is fully drained and an investigation is completed. 
  River traffic started moving again <DATE>April 27</DATE> after the right 
lock went back into operation and a Romanian ship passed through 
a test run at <TIME>11 a.m</TIME>. The last of the ships stuck in the 
month-long queue was expected to pass through by the next day. 
  With delayed deliveries of steel, iron ore, agricultural 
products and liquid fuel, DDSG puts its damages at more than <MONEY>$3 
million</MONEY>. 
  "It is not correct to operate a lock system like Gabcikovo 
without these doors," DDSG's <PERSON>Brewi</PERSON> said. Brewi plans to seek 
damages from <LOCATION>Gabcikovo</LOCATION> and expects his Hungarian and Ukrainian 
counterparts to do the same. "They have suffered even higher 
losses than we have," he said. 
  One possibility may be to appeal through the technical 
section of the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Commission</ORGANIZATION>, which oversees operation along 
the river but has little authority to extract fines. Another 
possibility is taking the matter to the <ORGANIZATION>International Court of 
Justice</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION>. 
  In either case, the shipping companies are ready for a 
fight. 
  Gabcikovo has already rejected a <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY> claim from 
Ukrainian shipping companies, <PERSON>Liska</PERSON> said. "I don't think anyone 
can claim damages [from road authorities] when a big crash 
happens on the highway and the traffic is delayed." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-32732 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu125__a94052" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-125-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  27 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Kovac Views Possible Reconciliation With Hungary </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Kovac Views Possible Reconciliation With Hungary </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU2706155094 Prague CTK in English 1432 GMT 27 Jun 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2706155094 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> <DATE>June 27</DATE> (CTK) -- Slovak President <PERSON>Michal 
Kovac</PERSON> said it may be possible to withdraw the disputed case of 
the Gabcikovo hydroelectric power project on the Danube from the 
  If indeed a historical reconciliation has come about between 
<LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, consideration could also then be given to 
whether it would be "more advantageous" and "wiser" to withdraw 
the case and resolve it together, <PERSON>Kovac</PERSON> told journalists in 
<LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> today. 
  <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> accuses <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> of violating its commitments in an 
international agreement concerning the project in <DATE>1977</DATE>. <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> 
accuses <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> of unilaterally deciding to divert the <LOCATION>River 
Danube</LOCATION> from its old course and of thereby causing great 
environmental damage. The case was taken to The Hague in <DATE>May</DATE>. 
  <PERSON>Kovac</PERSON> said he would test the possibility of a historical 
reconciliation on his visit to <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> this <DATE>autumn</DATE>, on which he 
has been invited by Hungarian President <PERSON>Arpad Goncz</PERSON>. The two 
heads of state returned today from a visit to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> 
during which they held talks with President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> and 
received an award from the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for East-West Studies</ORGANIZATION> 
(IEWS) for their efforts in seeking a settlement between 
<LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>. 
  On his visit to <PERSON>Hungary Kovac</PERSON> hopes to hold talks not only 
with <PERSON>Goncz</PERSON> but also with members of the new Hungarian 
Government, he said. Maybe then questions like the 
Gabcikovo-Nagymaros dam could be de-politicised and settled more 
easily, he said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-11298</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJ0BMAA8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921027
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 OCT 92 / Hungary backed by Germany over dam
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NICHOLAS DENTON and ARIANE GENILLARD
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BUDAPEST, PRAGUE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
GERMANY weighed in yesterday behind <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s increasingly frantic efforts
to stop <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> from damming and diverting the river Danube to feed the
controversial Gabcikovo hydroelectric barrage.
<PERSON>Mr Klaus Kinkel</PERSON>, the German foreign minister, issued a veiled warning of the
economic price of 'rash decisions' in the dam dispute after <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> began
at the <DATE>weekend</DATE> to block the Danube with quarry rock and concrete blocks.
<PERSON>Mr Kinkel</PERSON> said, without explicitly singling out <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>, that the <ORGANIZATION>European
Community</ORGANIZATION>'s 'goodwill' in providing economic support was in danger. 'The row
has sparked a new, utterly unnecessary crisis in <LOCATION>eastern Europe</LOCATION>,' he said,
repeating calls for a negotiated settlement. The strong German intervention
drags the dam dispute squarely on to the European stage before tomorrow's
summit meeting between the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> and leaders of the central European countries.
<LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>, despite pressure for a temporary halt, yesterday took construction
beyond the point of no return, diverting much of the river's flow into its
own territory.
The Hungarian government reacted yesterday with talk of reprisals. <PERSON>Mr Janos
Martonyi</PERSON>, state secretary at the Hungarian foreign ministry, ruled out
military action but pointedly kept all other options open and cast doubt on
the future of regional co-operation embodied in the <LOCATION>Visegrad</LOCATION> group of
central European countries.
<PERSON>Mr Martonyi</PERSON> re-emphasised <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s position that the diversion of the main
flow of the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>, the international border, represented a territorial
violation as well as an environmental catastrophe in the making. Hungary
says that the dam will lower the water table, dry up marshes around the
Danube and damage the water supply.
The <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> government argues that the Gabcikovo barrage complex is
essential to the energy security and economic well-being of <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>, which
is to become independent from the new year.
The Czech and Slovak regional governments yesterday ratified a customs union
agreement between the two republics, writes Ariane Genillard in <LOCATION>Prague</LOCATION>. The
agreement was negotiated by by <PERSON>Mr Vaclav Klaus</PERSON>, the Czech prime minister,
and <PERSON>Mr Vladimir Meciar</PERSON>, his Slovak counterpart.
It allows for the free flow of goods between the republics after they become
independent on <DATE>January 1</DATE> and should facilitate a renegotiation of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>'s
<LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION> association agreement. EC officials are tomorrow to meet in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> the <LOCATION>Czech</LOCATION>, Slovak, Hungarian and Polish prime ministers to discuss
extension of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> trade agreements.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 3
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50058 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu015_d_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-015 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SLOVAKIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Fails To Meet Deadline on Dam </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU2101214194 Bratislava PRAVDA in Slovak 19 Jan 94 pp 1, 8 </F>
<F P=103> AU2101214194 </F>
<F P=104>  Bratislava PRAVDA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Slovak </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by Jan Skoda: "Waiting Not for Water but for the </F>
Government"] 
  [Excerpts] On <DATE>Monday</DATE> [17 <DATE>January</DATE>], <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> presented to 
the <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>] headquarters in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> its official 
response to the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> experts' recommendation concerning the 
division of Danube water at Gabcikovo. This was announced by 
<PERSON>Gyorgy Tatar</PERSON>, Hungarian ministerial commissioner [title as 
published] for the Gabcikovo-Nagymaros hydroelectric power 
project. Tatar stated in the Hungarian daily NEPSZABADSAG that, 
while <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> submitted its response by the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>'s deadline, the 
same allegedly cannot be said of <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>. 
  We have, therefore, contacted the Slovak mission at the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> 
headquarters in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>. They confirmed to us that, in a letter at the 
beginning of the year, <LOCATION>Jan Lisuch</LOCATION>, state secretary at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, asked <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> mediator <PERSON>Pablo Benavidez</PERSON> 
to extend the original 15 <DATE>January</DATE> deadline, set for the 
Hungarian and Slovak sides to submit their responses, until the 
end of the month. He explained this request by the fact that 
the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Government</ORGANIZATION> has been unable to discuss its standpoint 
so far. The standpoint had been prepared several times, but it 
was necessary to incorporate into it comments from individual 
government departments, which has delayed the whole process. 
According to <PERSON>Vladimir Cemez</PERSON>, PhD, from the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Foreign 
Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, the response was to be on the agenda of yesterday's 
meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Government</ORGANIZATION>. According to our information, 
however, this did not happen. [passage omitted] 
  <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> is now accusing us that a month and a half was not 
enough for us to assume a position on the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>'s recommendation 
concerning the temporary division of Danube waters. Gyorgy 
Tatar claims, moreover, that the Slovak attitude actually 
confirms our negative stand on the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> recommendation, which, 
according to Hungarian newspapers, proposes that <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of 
the Danube water remain in the river's original bed and that 
<LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> build two small dams on its territory. 
  In this affair, which may seem immaterial, we are, thus, 
once 
again in the position of the "evil" side that does not honor its 
commitments. Without trying to act as a judge, let us only 
observe that, this time, this is absolutely unnecessary. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-8309 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu070__a94077" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-070-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Readiness To Negotiate Danube Division Reported </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Readiness To Negotiate Danube Division Reported </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU0804200694 Prague CTK in English 1638 GMT 8 Apr 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0804200694 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 8</DATE> (CTK) -- A note sent today by 
the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> expresses <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>'s readiness to resume as early as 
possible the talks on the establishment of a temporary water 
regime on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Ministry</ORGANIZATION> thus responded to a note from the 
<ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> of <DATE>March 28</DATE>, in which <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> urged 
the Slovak government to resume the negotiations immediately. 
The Hungarian note reacted to <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>'s rejection of a 
compromise proposal by <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> experts for the method of 
division of the <ORGANIZATION>Danube</ORGANIZATION>'s water between the original bed of the 
border river and a derivation canal built by <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> on 
Slovak territory. Budapest itself accepted the compromise 
proposal, though with reservations. 
  In opposition to this, the Slovak note recalls that the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> 
experts had also recommended to build weirs in the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>'s 
original bed to prevent drying up of some river's branches, but 
the Hungarian parliament recently rejected the weirs' 
construction. Nevertheless, in its document <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> says it 
favors further search for a rational and effective solution to 
the problem. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-10876</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJ2B8AAOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921029
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  29 OCT 92 / Danube dam threatens to open floodgates of hostility: An
explosive project
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NICHOLAS DENTON and ANTHONY ROBINSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
SINCE <DATE>last weekend</DATE> wave after wave of Slovak trucks have been lining up on
barges strung out across the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> river near the village of Cunovo, a few
hundred metres from the border with <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>. Round the clock they have been
tipping rock and concrete blocks into the swirling waters.
Less deadly than the exchange of tank and artillery fire in <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>, the
frenzied activity along this Slovak section of the Danube populated mainly
by ethnic Hungarians is nevertheless one of the most serious flashpoints in
the short history of post-communist <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> accuses the Slovak dammers of violating its sovereignty and has
invoked the emergency procedures of the <ORGANIZATION>Conference on Security</ORGANIZATION> and
Co-operation in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Acutely aware of the hot breath of reawakened
nationalist passions at home, it has also threatened reprisals against
<LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> if the damming is not stopped. Only military action has been ruled
out.
<LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> is outraged because the international frontier runs down the middle
of the old course of the river and the Cunovo dam stops the river just short
of the Hungarian frontier. It diverts the main flow into an artificial
channel entirely within Slovak territory, leaving only a relative trickle in
the old channel.
<LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> has responded to Hungarian protests about territorial violation by
accusing Hungarian nationalists of wanting to stop the dam in order to
damage the Slovak economy and exacerbate tensions between Slovaks and the
republic's 500,000-strong ethnic Hungarian minority.
The Hungarian aim, they add, is to create instability 'to better pursue the
policy of autonomy for Hungarian minorities and later restoration of the
Hungarian empire,' according to <PERSON>Mr Julius Binder</PERSON>, head of Hydrostav, the
Czechoslovak state company building the barrage.
Western politicians appear only now to have woken up to the escalating
dispute just 70km downstream from <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>. 'The row has sparked a new,
utterly unnecessary crisis in <LOCATION>eastern Europe</LOCATION>,' said <PERSON>Mr Klaus Kinkel</PERSON>, German
foreign minister, earlier this week while supporting <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>.
Yesterday, in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, attempts to settle the crisis with <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> mediation
continued against the background of the broader talks between central
European leaders and the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> represented by <PERSON>Mr John Major</PERSON>,
current head of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> presidency, and <PERSON>Mr Jacques Delors</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>European
Commission</ORGANIZATION> president.
The dam is a time-bomb left by the former Communist regimes who operated
under the rules of 'proletarian internationalism' which turned state borders
into little more than administrative boundaries and historical relics.
The project goes back to <DATE>1977</DATE>, when the two governments signed an agreement
on a complex of dams along the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> designed as a monument to socialist
engineering and fraternal co-operation.
But when <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s democratic movement emerged in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, it coalesced
around opposition to the dam on environmental grounds. Ecologists argued
that the dam and hydroelectric project at Gabcikovo would destroy the last
remaining inland delta along the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> and pollute drinking water supplies.
The fear was, and remains, that carcinogenic sediment will build up in the
reservoir and pollute the falling water table.
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s last reformist Communist government pulled out of the
hydroelectric project under popular pressure and the conservative coalition
government headed by <PERSON>Mr Jozsef Antall</PERSON> then unilaterally abrograted the <DATE>1977</DATE>
treaty last year. But <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>, anxious to phase out polluting coal-fired
power plants and Soviet-designed nuclear power stations, argues that it
cannot afford to lose electricity from <LOCATION>Gabcikovo</LOCATION> nor waste the huge
investment already made in construction.
The economic case has become more pressing as <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> approaches
independence, increasingly concerned about energy security and about its
economic future without Czech subsidies.
<PERSON>Mr Zdenko Pirek</PERSON>, the deputy foreign minister heading the Czechoslovak
negotiating team, says they have gone out of their way to take Hungarian
sensibilities into account. The Czechoslovak side is not diverting the
waters at this time to start generating electricity from Gabcikovo but to
prevent early flooding sweeping away existing construction work, they say.
There the two sides stand today, each marshalling its own legal and
environmental arguments in a campaign for international support, and
moderates on both sides privately hoping that the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> will help them find an
internationally binding face-saving formula.
See <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> survey
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-9474 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu080__a94043" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-080-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Moravcik Denies Conditioning Meeting With Boross </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Moravcik Denies Conditioning Meeting With Boross </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU2204174094 Prague CTK in English 1057 GMT 22 Apr 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2204174094 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 22</DATE> (CTK) -- Slovak Premier <PERSON>Jozef 
Moravcik</PERSON> remains ready for a meeting with Hungarian Premier 
<PERSON>Peter Boross</PERSON> if the meeting contributes in some way to solving 
mutual problems, <PERSON>Moravcik</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>CTK</ORGANIZATION> today. 
  On <DATE>Thursday</DATE> [21 <DATE>April</DATE>] the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> 
expressed regret that <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> appeared to have no interest in a 
working meeting of the two premiers. Ministry Spokesman <PERSON>Janos 
Herman</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> had set unacceptable conditions for such 
a meeting. 
  "We specified no conditions for the meeting with Premier 
<PERSON>Boross</PERSON>," <PERSON>Moravcik</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE>. "We were interested in a 
communique being issued. It would be enough for us if the 
Hungarian side expressed the political will to accept our 
request: To explicitly confirm the pledge to guarantee present 
borders," the Slovak Premier emphasized. 
  The form of the expression was open, and <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> was keen 
to 
accept even the loosest formulation, he said. He said he felt 
the guaranteeing of borders was self-evident and could not cause 
anybody a problem. 
  He rejected the claim that <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> had decided to wait 
until 
the <DATE>September</DATE> elections were over before contemplating a meeting. 
  "From the point of view of solving our problems we do not 
regard parliamentary elections as an obstacle. We don't attach 
special significance to them. Whatever happens in the elections 
in <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> or here, the governments on either side still have to 
resolve existing problems, which are of vital importance to both 
sides," <PERSON>Moravcik</PERSON> said. 
  "Both countries want integration in the <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION>. But 
no international community is going to gladly grant membership 
to states between which some open questions exist," because 
those imported problems might stir trouble within the 
association, he said. Slovak-Hungarian talks were in the 
objective interests of both sides and would also develop 
bilateral trade, he said. 
  <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> have not signed a treaty guaranteeing 
the inviolability of present state borders and the status and 
rights of the Hungarian minority. Another difficulty is the 
opening of new border crossings, which <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> thus far has 
made conditional upon the signing of a readmission treaty 
returning illegal migrants. 
  Furthermore the states have taken their quarrel over the 
Gabcikovo-Nagymaros hydroelectric project on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> to the 
<ORGANIZATION>International Court of Justice</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION>, and the two 
countries have still not reached agreement on the division of 
the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> waters between the old river course and the Gabcikovo 
canal. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-9550 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu058__a94024" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-058-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  23 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Ministry Protests Hungarian Pressure Over Dam </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU2303174394 Prague CTK in English 1523 GMT 23 Mar 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2303174394 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 23</DATE> (CTK) -- The Slovak Foreign 
Ministry strongly protests against Hungarian pressure on the 
international public designed to discredit the contribution of 
the Gabcikovo dam to traffic on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>, a ministry's 
statement published today says. 
  The statement responds to <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s [22 <DATE>March</DATE>] statement by 
the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Government</ORGANIZATION>, saying the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Government</ORGANIZATION> bears 
responsibility for the blockage of the Danube at the 
Gabcikovo-Nagymaros hydro-electric power station for 
unilaterally redirecting part of the Danube along a derivation 
canal on Slovak territory in <DATE>November 1992</DATE>. 
  The Hungarian Government called upon countries supporting 
free passage on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> to urge <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> to "stop its illegal 
activities and revive without delay the conditions for traffic." 
  Ship transport was interrupted due to accidents at the 
Gabcikovo dam in southern <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 21</DATE>. 
  The Slovak statement says there are no international 
dimensions of the danger to the power station. By contrast, the 
one-year operation of at Gabcikovo confirmed that conditions for 
accelerated ship transport along a 42-kilometers route had 
improved. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> says that Slovak authorities would take 
all necessary steps in order to revive international traffic. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-7566 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu063__a94016" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-063-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  30 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Hungary </F>
<H3> <TI>   Ministry Calls For Danube Talks With Slovakia </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Ministry Calls For Danube Talks With Slovakia </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU3003195894 Budapest MTI in English 1808 GMT 30 Mar 94 -- 
FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU3003195894 </F>
<F P=104>  Budapest MTI </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION>, 29 <DATE>March</DATE> (MTI) -- On <DATE>March 29</DATE>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> passed a verbal request to the Slovak 
embassy in <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION>. 
  The Hungarian Government -- in accord with <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION> 
recommendations for water division, which were rejected by 
<LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> -- calls upon the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Government</ORGANIZATION> to open bilateral 
talks on a temporary water management regime immediately, the 
ministry's press department informed MTI on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [30 <DATE>March</DATE>]. 
  The Slovak side unilaterally diverted the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> in <DATE>1992</DATE>, to 
operate the Gabcikovo power station. Since then, the main 
riverbed has been supplied with much less water than before, 
endangering the ecological balance of the Szigetkoz region. 
  The negotiations are urgent because the vegetation growth 
period has already begun. The talks are also justified by 
obligations which the two sides assumed in a Separate Treaty 
concluded in connection with The Hague trial. 
  <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s government stressed in the communique that it is 
indispensable to guarantee a considerable increase in the water 
discharge to the main riverbed. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-9403 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu080_d_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-080 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  19 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SLOVAKIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Water Discharged Into Danube To Double in May </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Water Discharged Into Danube To Double in May </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU2504133194 Bratislava HOSPODARSKE NOVINY in Slovak 19 Apr 
94 p 2 </F>

<F P=103> AU2504133194 </F>
<F P=104>  Bratislava HOSPODARSKE NOVINY </F>
<F P=105>  Slovak </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [TA SR report: "More Water as of May"] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>--Barring any unforeseen circumstances, 
the small hydro-electric plant on the Moson branch of the <ORGANIZATION>Danube</ORGANIZATION> 
will be completed in the <DATE>first half of May</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Vodohospodarska</ORGANIZATION> 
vystavba <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> state enterprise will, as of 15 <DATE>May</DATE>, double 
the volume of water discharged from 20 cubic meters per second 
to 40 cubic meters per second and will contribute significantly 
to supplying the Danube branches and the Danube wetlands in 
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, said Environment Minister <PERSON>J. Hrasko</PERSON>. Environment 
Ministers <PERSON>J. Gyurko</PERSON> and <PERSON>J. Hrasko</PERSON> last week recommended that 
their governments adopt a political decision that would bring 
them closer together. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880527-0230 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-27-88 2112EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Danube-Ecologists     05-27 0326</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Danube-Ecologists,0339</SECOND>
<HEAD>2,000 Protest Danube Power Project</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 2,000 Hungarian environmentalists
marched to the <ORGANIZATION>Austrian Embassy</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> to protest a <LOCATION>Danube River</LOCATION>
power project near <LOCATION>Nagymaros</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, which is being financed by
<LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, a participant said.
   The man said police refrained from interfering and even cleared
the way for marchers through car-congested streets from downtown
<LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> to the embassy in the foreign diplomats' central district.
   The marcher, who spoke on condition of anonymity, called it an
unusual sign of police cooperation with the young members of the
unofficial <ORGANIZATION>Danube Circle</ORGANIZATION> ecological group.
   In another departure, state-run television ran, without comment,
a one-minute film segment on its main evening newscast showing
protesters arriving at the embassy. Among them was biologist <PERSON>Janos
Varga</PERSON>, a leader of the ecologists.
   The marchers carried placards and banners demanding a halt to
the project, a joint venture involving hydropower installations on
the Danube at Gabcikovo in <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION> and at <LOCATION>Nagymaros</LOCATION>.
   Banners read ``We Want Clear Water,'' ``No Dams'' and ``We Want
Our Danube.''
   Hungarian and Austrian ecologists have said that damming up the
Danube water and slowing its flow will threaten drinking water
reserves of millions of Hungarians and destroy large areas of
riverside forestland in both <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Czechsolovakia</LOCATION>.
   The protester said demonstrators were met with applause and
cheers from passers-by on the march to the embassy.
   Under an Austrian-Hungarian contract signed on <DATE>May 29, 1986</DATE>, <PERCENT>70
percent</PERCENT> of the construction work <MONEY>$483 million</MONEY> will be carried out
by Austrian companies.
   A delegation of four was allowed to enter the embassy to hand
over a resolution protesting <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>'s financial participation,
<ORGANIZATION>Austria Press Agency</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   It said the Austrian ambassador was not there but promised the
protesters by telephone a written reply to their plea.
   The first turbine of the Nagymaros station is to go into
operation in <DATE>1990</DATE>.
   Hungary will repay construction costs by supplying <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION> with
electricity for 20 years, starting in <DATE>1996</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-55266 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu092_d_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-092 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SLOVAKIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Meeting To Solve Danube Dispute Proposed </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Meeting To Solve Danube Dispute Proposed </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   LD1105172194 Bratislava Rozhlasova Stanica Slovensko Network 
in Slovak 1630 GMT 11 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD1105172194 </F>
<F P=104>  Bratislava Rozhlasova Stanica Slovensko Network 
in Slovak 1630 GMT 11 May 94 </F>

<F P=105> Slovak </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <PERSON>Ivo Hlavacek</PERSON>, the director of the section for 
international law and consular affairs of the <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Foreign 
Affairs Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, has handed a note to the <ORGANIZATION>Embassy</ORGANIZATION> of the 
Republic of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>. The note is a reaffirmation 
of <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>'s readiness to continue in talks on the temporary 
water economy regime on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> in connection with the 
Gabcikovo hydroelectric project. The note reasserts that the 
Slovak side regards such talks as desirable and already proposes 
the second date this year for holding a meeting that should take 
place in <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> between 18 and <DATE>19 May</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880528-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-28-88 0450EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Hungary-Protest     05-28 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hungary-Protest,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Help 2,000 Protest Danube Power Project</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police stood by peacefully as about
2,000 people protested a <LOCATION>Danube River</LOCATION> power project, a sign of
Communist authorities' increasing tolerance of dissent that does
not challenge them directly.
   A participant in <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s demonstration said police refrained
from interfering and even cleared the way for marchers as they
wound their way through downtown <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>Austrian Embassy</ORGANIZATION>.
   The project in <LOCATION>Nagymaros</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, is being financed largely by
<LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>.
   The marcher, who spoke on condition of anonymity, called it an
unusual sign of police cooperation with the young members of the
unofficial <ORGANIZATION>Danube Circle</ORGANIZATION> ecological group.
   State-run television also took the unusual step of running,
without comment, a one-minute film segment on its main evening
newscast showing protesters arriving at the embassy.
   Among them was biologist <PERSON>Janos Varga</PERSON>, a leader of the ecologists.
   The marchers carried placards and banners demanding a halt to
the project, a joint venture involving hydropower installations on
the Danube at Gabcikovo in <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION> and at <LOCATION>Nagymaros</LOCATION>.
   Banners read ``We Want Clear Water,'' ``No Dams'' and ``We Want
Our Danube.''
   Hungarian and Austrian ecologists have said that damming the
<LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> and slowing its flow will threaten drinking water reserves
of millions of Hungarians and destroy large areas of riverside
forestland in both <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Czechsolovakia</LOCATION>.
   Under an Austrian-Hungarian contract signed on <DATE>May 29, 1986</DATE>,
Austrian companies will carry out <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of the <MONEY>$483 million</MONEY>
worth of construction work.
   A delegation of four was allowed to enter the embassy to hand
over a resolution protesting <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>'s financial participation,
<ORGANIZATION>Austria Press Agency</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   It said the Austrian ambassador was not there but promised the
protesters by telephone a written reply to their plea.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-41617 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov123_e_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-123 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  24 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> UKRAINE </F>
<F P=101> International Affairs </F>
<H3> <TI>   Ukraine Joins Danube Commonwealth </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Ukraine Joins Danube Commonwealth </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   LD2406214594 Kiev UT-1 Television Network in Ukrainian 1800 
GMT 24 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD2406214594 </F>
<F P=104>  Kiev UT-1 Television Network </F>
<F P=105>  Ukrainian </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Summary] <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> became a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth of 
Danube Lands</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>Spivdruzhnist Dunayskykh Zemel</ORGANIZATION>] on 23 <DATE>June</DATE>. A 
session of the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION> took place near <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> on 23 <DATE>June</DATE>, 
where <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> was represented by <LOCATION>Odessa Oblast</LOCATION>. The issues of 
losses caused by <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> sanctions against former <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>, the 
economy, the environment, and joint action by Danube lands in 
the areas of sport and tourism were examined at the session. 
Delegations from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, the Czech and <ORGANIZATION>Slovak 
Republics</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Bulgaria</LOCATION> took part. 
  <PERSON>Ruslan Bodelan</PERSON>, people's deputy of <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> and chairman of 
<ORGANIZATION>Odessa Oblast Council</ORGANIZATION>, who headed the Ukrainian delegation, said 
at <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> airport: "This is another step toward our state's 
claim to the possibility of resolving issues jointly with our 
counterparts, with other countries. This especially concerns 
use of the Danube artery as a river, along which cargoes can and 
should be transported with the help of our <ORGANIZATION>Danube Shipping 
Company</ORGANIZATION>. It is about resolving problems of the ecological state 
of the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>, preserving our reservations and national parks, 
and developing national culture and national traditions." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-67361 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpten011___94023" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEN-94-011 </AU>
JPRS 
Environmental Issues 

<DATE1>  15 April 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> EAST EUROPE </F>
<F P=101> HUNGARY </F>
<H3> <TI>   Environmental Minister Views Bos Debacle </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Environmental Minister Views Bos Debacle </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1804120394 Budapest MAGYAR HIRLAP in Hungarian 15 Apr 94 p 
3 </F>

<F P=103> AU1804120394 </F>
<F P=104>  Budapest MAGYAR HIRLAP </F>
<F P=105>  Hungarian </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Interview with Environmental Protection Minister <PERSON>Janos </F>
Gyurko</PERSON> by <PERSON>Janos A. Szilagyi</PERSON>; place and date not given: "No 
Breakthrough on the Bos Issue"] 
  [Excerpts] [passage omitted] 
  <PERSON>Szilagyi</PERSON>: After the fall of the 
Meciar-government, which represented a rigid position also 
regarding the Bos river barrage issue, many people hoped for an 
improvement in relations and progress in settling the Bos issue. 
Did the meeting in <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION> justify these positive 
expectations? 
  Gyurko: Regarding the inter-ministerial 
cooperation, the Slovak side showed a constructive attitude. 
They showed a positive approach toward solving the common 
environmental and nature protection problems, and gave up the 
planned construction of the dangerous waste incinerator plant in 
<LOCATION>Parkany</LOCATION>, which would strongly pollute the air in the 
Dorog-Esztergom area. We decided to create a joint cooperation 
committee within 30 days to tackle concrete issues, a committee 
led by the two public administration state secretaries. I 
cannot report, though, on serious progress in the Bos issue. 
However, it is a promising development that these talks were 
held in a better atmosphere than previous talks. 
  Szilagyi: Did the two positions get closer to each 
other? 
  Gyurko: Very few concrete things were said, 
because the presentation of each side's position took up most of 
the time. At first, the Slovaks opposed the idea of maintaining 
the mediatory role of the <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION>; instead, they 
suggested bilateral talks. Later, however, they gave up this 
idea. I made it clear that, at the talks on the distribution of 
water, we seek a temporary solution valid until the decision of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Hague International Court</ORGANIZATION>, and not a final solution. I also 
made it absolutely clear that <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> continues to expect a 
solution to the problem from <LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION>. I presented the latest 
decision of the Hungarian Parliament on the supply of water to 
the Szigetkoz area. In connection with this, I asked them to 
take concrete measures to protect the Hungarian natural 
environment and let more water in the main <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> and into the 
Mosoni-Danube branch. <PERSON>Mr. Hrasko</PERSON> promised to support the flow 
of some 20 cubic meters of water per second into the <PERSON>Mosoni 
Danube</PERSON>. This would signify definite progress in saving the 
Szigetkoz area, because we could redirect this surplus water in 
the various side branches of the Szigetkoz area and, thus, the 
costs of pumping would drop. [passage omitted] 
  <PERSON>Szilagyi</PERSON>: Did you also talk about the serious 
technical fault involving the sluice chambers at Bos and the 
subsequent halt in the navigation of the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>? 
  Gyurko: The Slovak delegation said that the 
sluice chambers problem was an unpleasant development that came 
at the wrong time. It seems that the reports on the upcoming 
opening of navigation on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> are unfounded and it is 
possible that the repair works will last for another month. The 
task of the Danube committee may be to settle the issue and 
discuss the possible compensation demands. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-11520</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJZBOAAJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921026
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 OCT 92 / Hungarians furious over damming
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NICHOLAS DENTON
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BUDAPEST
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>SLOVAKIA</LOCATION> began damming the river Danube at the <DATE>weekend</DATE> to divert the river
into the controversial Gabcikovo hydroelectric barrage. The move prompted
furious diplomatic protests from neighbouring <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> which is resisting the
project.
Slovak trucks began dumping rocks into the river after negotiations with
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE> under <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> auspices broke down
in acrimony.
<LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> reacted immediately by saying it was turning to the Conference on
Security and Co-operation in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> (CSCE) and invoking the international
crisis procedures previously applied to the former <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>.
Hungary also fired off an appeal to the <ORGANIZATION>International Court of Justice</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION> even though <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION> has refused its jurisdiction.
Slovak and Hungarian negotiators will meet again next week as part of the
<LOCATION>Visegrad</LOCATION> central European group's talks with the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>, which are expected to
be overshadowed by the dam dispute.
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> is understood to be exerting strong pressure on the Czechoslovak
government to exercise its authority over <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> while the country remains
united and to freeze construction work until there is a negotiated
settlement.
But <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>'s decision to move ahead with the final stage of construction,
which will result in the diversion of the main flow of the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> in the
next few days, makes agreement all but impossible.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-45684 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpten006__l94011" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEN-94-006-L </AU>
JPRS 
Environmental Issues 

<DATE1>  24 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> EAST EUROPE </F>
<F P=101> HUNGARY </F>
<H3> <TI>   International Agreement Needed to Secure Water Supply </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    International Agreement Needed to Secure Water Supply </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU2405105994 Budapest MTI in English 0653 GMT 24 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU2405105994 </F>
<F P=104>  Budapest MTI </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION>, 24 <DATE>May</DATE> (MTI) -- A sophisticated 
environment-protection programme for the Danube region has been 
initiated recently by the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Ministry of Environment and 
Regional Policy</ORGANIZATION>. Hungary also claims that an international 
project should be approved in order to provide for all drainage 
areas of the river. <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> is the only European country 
threatened by critial conditions in water supply around the year 
<DATE>2000</DATE>. 
(FAO) registers <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> among the first 30 (mainly desert) 
states whose drinking water supply is not secured for the 
future. Ninety-five percent of the surface waterways of the 
country originate abroad, which causes purity and quantity 
problems. In <DATE>1992</DATE> Hungary initiated an environment-protection 
programme for the <LOCATION>Danube Basin</LOCATION>. In order to solve present 
problems, which foreshadow further ones in the future, water 
management should be regulated under an agreement, with strong 
commitment by all concerned to carry through their respective 
obligations, Hungarian authorities say. Hungarian specialists 
say that although the country's water reserves are expected to 
decline in the following years, they will probably still meet 
all demand after the turn of the century. 
  Waiting to see the issue of surface waterways settled, 
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> is striving to preserve its underground water reserves. 
There is no agreement with <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, or <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> that 
would oblige these countries to inform <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> on water 
pollution occurring in their own territories. <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION>, for 
example, takes out such a large amount of water from the river 
Sajo each <DATE>summer</DATE> that the <PERSON>Sajo</PERSON> enters <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> no longer as a 
river but rather as a small stream. Besides, <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> operates 
two barrage irrigation systems on the river Ipoly. Another major 
problem is the decline in water reserves near the Gabcikovo 
barrage system. 
  Water filtered through gravel beds is excellent for 
consumption. Wells operating on this principle supply the 
population of the <ORGANIZATION>Danube Bend</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> through a pipe water 
system and might serve as the drinking water source of around 4 
million people in the future. (The population of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> is 10.3 
million.) Nitrate pollutants have to be filtered in these wells 
too, although 15 years ago this was not necessary. (Most of the 
pollution is due to the lack of sewage networks in nearby 
settlements.) The river Tisza in the eastern part of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, 
which springs from <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> and has been known for its clean 
water over the past 25 years, has recently become polluted at 
places. The river <PERSON>Koros</PERSON>, originating in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, has also 
declined in quality. 
  "Karst" and artesian waters are the real preserves of 
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>. According to recent figures, their quantity exceeds the 
consumption of the public, industry, and agriculture. Though 
mining has caused long-lasting and difficult-to-remedy changes, 
experts expect earlier, better conditions to return within a 
decade's time. 
  The Danube-Tisza region in eastern <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> has been 
seriously 
endangered by the lack of irrigation water. In the past 15-20 
years, successive droughts have reduced the ground water 
surface. Traditional plants being unable to absorb water from 
3-6 metres down, new species had to be introduced. However, 
declines in the region's agricultural production have been 
considerable. 
  Ninety-eight per cent of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s population drinks piped 
water. Per capita water consumption has fallen to 150 litres per 
day from 250 litres in earlier years. Experts say that drinking 
water should be separated from water used for other purposes 
(washing, watering, etc.) with an extra pipe system added, as it 
has been already in some western European countries. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881003-0198 </DOCNO>
<HL> Europe: Danube Dams Threaten Hungarian Reforms </HL>
<AUTHOR> Peter Keresztes </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP </CO>
<IN> ENV </IN>
<TEXT>
   Now that <PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON> has seized the full reins of power in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> he'll presumably press on with making the Soviet economy more like that of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>. 
So it would be timely to take a look at the furor going on behind the <LOCATION>Iron Curtain</LOCATION> over the Czechoslovak-Hungarian hydroelectric project being built on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> -- which has entangled <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION> in an embarrassing mess. 

   The great Danube dams have emerged as a white elephant, characteristic of Stalinist central planning -- monstrously expensive, of dubious utility, ruinous to the environment and contrary to popular will. 
Yet the Hungarian government of <PERSON>Karoly Grosz</PERSON> is having difficulty making the adjustment that a rational, market-oriented approach would require. 
The authorities in <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> are denying that the system is a waste, as an energy shortage is possible in the <DATE>1990s</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Grosz</PERSON> is complaining bitterly that the regime's opponents are blowing the project into "a political issue." 
The dams on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>, in any event, have become one of the issues splitting the Hungarian party and endangering the <PERSON>Grosz</PERSON> regime. 

   Widespread opposition in <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> began to mount as details of the plans -- launched secretively 17 years ago -- dribbled into public view and as site-preparation began last fall on <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s dam at <LOCATION>Nagymaros</LOCATION>. 
The Czechoslovak work on its Gabcikovo portion, glasnost watchers will note, raised no strenuous opposition and is nearing completion. 
In <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION>, though, mass demonstrations, biting articles in the state-monitored press, selectively aired opposition in the <ORGANIZATION>Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION>, and criticism from political figures are pressuring the <PERSON>Grosz</PERSON> regime to reconsider the project. 

   The dam controversy spilled over into <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, where the Greens forced the abandonment in <DATE>1985</DATE> of a nearly complete dam at <LOCATION>Hainburg</LOCATION>, near the Hungarian and Czechoslovak border. 
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION> then struck a deal to buy electricity from the Hungarian part of the project, which the Austrians' participation made possible. 
<LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>'s critics accuse it of exploiting the nondemocratic conditions in <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> and to export there its environmental problems and construction overcapacity. 
Financing has been guaranteed by the Austrian government on a contract to deliver to <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION> over 20 years most of the Hungarian share of the project's electricity output, augmented by power from other sources such as <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s Paks nuclear plant, which is enlarged. 

   The Austrian opponents, including some "green" conservatives in the People's Party, have questioned in Parliament the morality of <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>'s participation. 
Some support canceling the credit guarantees. 
The Austrian chancellor, <PERSON>Franz Vranitzky</PERSON>, has stated that Nagymaros was "purely a Hungarian decision" and that Austrian construction companies involved are bound by their contractual obligations. 

   The project is in a flat region engineers agree is ill-suited for hydroelectric power. 
The system requires altering 120 miles of the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>, damming it for a drop of 70 feet at Gabcikovo and 27 feet at Nagymaros and rerouting <PERCENT>97.5%</PERCENT> of the water flow over 20 miles. 
The system is said to be a serious threat to, among other things, the drinking water for three million people, farmlands and forests. 

   Benefits meanwhile will be negligible. 
The plants would, beginning in the year <DATE>2015</DATE> when deliveries to <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION> end, supply only <PERCENT>2%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s power requirements. 
Equivalent investment in modernizing the country's antiquated energy-guzzling industry, critics point out, would not only save at least as much power but would enhance productivity. 
Associated benefits -- navigation, flood control, a linkup to an international power grid and the use of the Nagymaros dam as a highway bridge -- are either marginal or could have been achieved by other means much more cheaply and effectively. 

   The project's actual costs, let alone huge associated expenses for things like environmental-protection, and waste and water treatment, have not been disclosed, though <PERSON>Mr. Grosz</PERSON> has conceded that "now, we would not launch the project because the money is needed in other areas." 
Indeed, resources are being diverted to the barrage. 
Badly needed sewerage and water treatment facilities in two major cities, <LOCATION>Miskolc</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Debrecen</LOCATION>, for example, have been postponed. 

   The government is claiming that the restoration and contract-penalty costs of abandoning Nagymaros would exceed the expense of completion. 
Abandonment would cost <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> in hard currency, argue the rulers of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, which already owes <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY> to non-socialist lenders. 
The government says the construction will cost the equivalent of <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>. 
Austrian financing for a third of the originally estimated construction costs obligates <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> to pay principal and interest with 11 billion Austrian schillings worth of electricity beginning in <DATE>1996</DATE>. (At current exchange rates, that's worth <MONEY>$830 million</MONEY>.) 

   The construction cost projection was made four years ago and assumed a <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>6%</PERCENT> annual inflation rate. 
This year prices in <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> are climbing by more than <PERCENT>17%</PERCENT> and, according to <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>'s most authoritative economic weekly, HVG, will likely remain in the double-digit range for the next two years. 
Recent unofficial figures in <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> newspapers put the cost of the construction alone at <MONEY>$1.25 billion</MONEY>, while estimates from the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> go much higher. 

   Government promises to protect the environment are no easier to accept than its cost estimate. 
It agreed years ago to go along with scientists' recommendation to install a system to monitor water quality. 
To establish monitoring constants, scientists say, the devices should be in place five years before the system starts up. 
Completion is less than three years away, yet there is still no monitoring system. 

   <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> is pushing ahead with work toward making the project irreversible -- the lining of the riverbed with concrete -- while attempting to seem reasonable and democratic by having ordered up expert opinions on the costs and legal implications of abandonment and by preparing to justify its decision before Parliament at the fall session, starting <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 

   To appease public opinion <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> has begun to lobby with <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION>, the worst industrial polluter in the upper <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>, to complete treatment facilities before the start-up. 
<LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> may even agree to a ban on a peak-shedding operation, though <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION>, which gets half of the power from the complex, may not without big penalties. 
Peak-shedding would involve stopping the river flow for lengthy periods -- which is said to have the most detrimental of all the project's environmental effects -- to fill the upriver Gabcikovo reservoir and then release large amounts of water when electricity demand peaks. 

   Thus it seems that it's where rhetoric collides with costly projects involving bricks and mud that perestroika and glasnost meet their toughest test. 
<PERSON>Mr. Grosz</PERSON> has called completion of the project a question of "prestige." 
But the credibility of would-be economic reformists depends in large part on eliminating white elephants of the sort conceived by the Stalinists. 
A market system would already have written off the Danube dams. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Keresztes</PERSON> is deputy editorial page editor of The Wall Street Journal/Europe. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-9353 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu056__a94037" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-056-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Slovakia </F>
<H3> <TI>   `Sabotage' Alleged in Gabcikovo Accidents </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU2203141494 Prague CTK in English 1055 GMT 22 Mar 94 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2203141494 </F>
<F P=104>  Prague CTK </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bratislava</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 22</DATE> (CTK) -- <PERSON>Julius Binder</PERSON>, 
director of the construction company which built the 
controversial Gabcikovo dam on the <LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION>, told <ORGANIZATION>Slovak Radio</ORGANIZATION> 
today he did not rule out that the accidents at the gates of 
Gabcikovo's two locks were the result of sabotage. 
  A part of the left lock's bottom gate was torn on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> [20 
<DATE>March</DATE>] <TIME>night</TIME> due to a so far unknown reason. The resultant wave 
under the dam damaged mechanisms on the bottom gate of the right 
lock, which has been blocked by the wrecked Ukrainian boat 
Zernograd. International ship transport in this section of the 
<LOCATION>Danube</LOCATION> has been interrupted. It is expected to be resumed by 
the end of the week. 
  "The commission in charge of finding the cause of the damage 
has not yet disclosed its conclusions. Accident is 
inconceivable, and intentional damage cannot be ruled out," 
<PERSON>Binder</PERSON> said. "Everyday efforts to block the success of the dam 
are evident," he added. 
  He pointed out that the locks' gates have been operating for 
a year, and before the wreckage of Zernograd on <DATE>February 11</DATE> they 
were to undergo modification to eliminate problems. Binder 
stressed that any defect in the gates was unlikely. 
  Binder said that neither the accidents nor the <DATE>spring</DATE> thaw 
posed a threat to the residents of the surrounding area. There 
is a reserve to divert surplus water, he explained. 
  "It is strange that since the beginning the left lock and 
the 
Gabcikovo dam as a whole have been accompanied by many hazards," 
<PERSON>Binder</PERSON> said. He referred to the theft of electronic regulating 
devices at the left lock, the tearing off of control cameras by 
a lorry, irresponsibility of the crew of Zernograd and the slow 
pace of its removal, and the unnatural substances found in wells 
destined for the examination of underground water. "Enemies of 
the dam exist here and are working intensively," Binder 
emphasizes. 
  He said that the repair of the locks will not cost much, 
only 
millions, not tens of millions of crowns. "However, the problem 
lies in the moral damage, in negativistic tendencies which will 
emerge throughout the world," he pointed out. 

</TEXT>
