<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890707-0246 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-07-89 2231EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-World'sRichest     07-07 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World's Richest,0605</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tsutsumi Tops Forbes Billionaires List Third Straight Year</HEAD>
<HEAD>Embargoed By Source For Release After 6:30 p.m. EDT Sunday, July
9</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six of the 10 richest people in the world are
Japanese but the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> still leads the world in the total
number of billionaires, according to estimates compiled by Forbes
magazine.
   For the third year running, <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON> led <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>' list of
private billionaires even though his wealth wasn't quite as much as
it had been 12 months earlier.
   Tsutsumi, head of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Seibu Railway Group</ORGANIZATION>, has a personal net
worth of at least <MONEY>$15 billion</MONEY>, over <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> less than estimated
last <DATE>summer</DATE> due mainly to a rise in the dollar against other major
currencies, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The estimate was far greater than that made by Fortune magazine
in its <DATE>September 1988</DATE> ranking of those it considered the world's
richest people _ which valued <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON>'s holdings at a mere <MONEY>$2.8
billion</MONEY>.
   In last year's list, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> estimated <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON>'s net worth was
<MONEY>$18.9 billion</MONEY>.
   The magazine reports in its <DATE>July 24</DATE> issue that <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON> edged out
second-ranked Taikichiro Mori by less than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   Mori, a former economics professor who owns 72 office buildings
in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, has an estimated net worth of <MONEY>$14.2 billion</MONEY>. In last
year's survey, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> placed Mori's worth at about <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>.
   The third-richest on the list was American <PERSON>Sam Moore Walton</PERSON>,
founder of the third largest retailer in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart
Stores Inc</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> and his family are worth an estimated <MONEY>$8.7
billion</MONEY>, up from <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' <DATE>1988</DATE> estimate of <MONEY>$6.5 billion</MONEY>.
   After the Waltons came <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers, owners of the
<ORGANIZATION>Olympia &amp; York</ORGANIZATION> real estate empire, with a combined net worth of
about <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>.
   The rest of the 10 richest people in the world, their country and
industries, according to <LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION>, were: <PERSON>Shin Kyuk-ho</PERSON>, <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>,
candy, real estate; <PERSON>Hirotomo Takei</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, publishing,
real estate; <PERSON>Kitaro Watanabe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, hotels; <PERSON>Haruhiko
Yoshimoto</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate; <PERSON>Hans</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gad Rausing</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, liquids packaging; and <PERSON>Eitaro Itoyama</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, land.
   Forbes said it identified 226 individuals or families around the
world with personal assets worth over <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was the country with the most billionaires,
with 55 individuals qualifying for that title. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> ranked second,
with 41, and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> was third with 20.
   American also accounted for the most billionaires in the <DATE>1988</DATE>
survey, with 47 individuals, followed by <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s 32 and <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION>'s 16.
   Among the richest of the world's rich were people who didn't
necessarily come by their money in an honest way.
   <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s cocaine barons, for instance, are still putting away
piles of money from selling the illegal drug even though profit
margins in the cocaine trade have been shrinking during recent years.
   Three of them made Forbes ``World Billionaires'' list including
<PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON>, leader of the notorious <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cocaine
cartel, with an estimated personal net worth of <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>. The
other cocaine kingpins on the list were the <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON> family, worth more
than <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>, and <PERSON>Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha</PERSON>, with more than <MONEY>$1
billion</MONEY>.
   In compiling its list, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> does not consider royal families
and heads of state in compiling its list of wealthy people and
individuals ``because their wealth derives more from political
heritage than from economic effort _ theirs are feudal fortunes, not
capitalistic ones.''
   The magazine also excludes dictators, such as <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Fidel Castro</PERSON>
or <LOCATION>North Korea</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Kim Il Sung</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890709-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-09-89 1411EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-World'sRichest Bjt   07-09 0584</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World's Richest, Bjt,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japanese Businessman Tops Forbes Billionaires List Third Straight
Year</HEAD>
<HEAD>Embargoed Until 6:30 p.m. EDT; Time set by source.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-World's Richest-List</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six of the 10 richest people in the world are
Japanese but the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> still leads the world in the total
number of billionaires, according to estimates compiled by Forbes
magazine.
   For the third straight year, <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON> led <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' list
of private billionaires even though his wealth wasn't quite as much
as it had been 12 months earlier.
   Tsutsumi, head of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Seibu Railway Group</ORGANIZATION>, has a personal net
worth of at least <MONEY>$15 billion</MONEY> _ nearly <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY> less than
estimated last <DATE>summer</DATE> due mainly to a rise in the value of the
dollar against other major currencies, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The estimate was far greater than the <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> that Fortune
magazine placed as <ORGANIZATION>Tsutsumi</ORGANIZATION>'s worth in its <DATE>September 1988</DATE> ranking of
those it considered the world's richest people.
   In last year's list, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> estimated <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON>'s net worth as
<MONEY>$18.9 billion</MONEY>.
   The magazine reports in its <DATE>July 24</DATE> issue that <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON> edged out
second-ranked Taikichiro Mori by less than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   Mori, a former economics professor who owns 72 office buildings
in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, has an estimated net worth of <MONEY>$14.2 billion</MONEY>. In last
year's survey, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> placed Mori's worth at about <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>.
   The third-richest on the list was American <PERSON>Sam Moore Walton</PERSON>,
founder of the third-largest retailer in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart
Stores Inc</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> and his family are worth an estimated <MONEY>$8.7
billion</MONEY>, up from <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' <DATE>1988</DATE> estimate of <MONEY>$6.5 billion</MONEY>.
   After the Waltons came <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers, owners of the
<ORGANIZATION>Olympia &amp; York</ORGANIZATION> real estate empire, with a combined net worth of
about <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>.
   The rest of the 10 richest people in the world, their country and
industries, according to <LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION>, were: <PERSON>Shin Kyuk-ho</PERSON>, <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>,
candy, real estate, <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Hirotomo Takei</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>,
publishing, real estate, <MONEY>$7.8 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Kitaro Watanabe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real
estate, hotels, <MONEY>$7 billion-plus</MONEY>; <PERSON>Haruhiko Yoshimoto</PERSON> and family,
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Hans</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gad Rausing</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>,
liquids packaging, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>; and <PERSON>Eitaro Itoyama</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, land, <MONEY>$6.6
billion</MONEY>.
   Forbes said it identified 226 individuals or families around the
world with personal assets worth more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was the country with the most billionaires,
with 55 individuals qualifying for that title. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> ranked second,
with 41, and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> was third with 20.
   American also accounted for the most billionaires in the <DATE>1988</DATE>
survey, 47, followed by <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s 32 and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s 16.
   Among the richest of the world's rich are people who didn't
necessarily come by their money in an honest way.
   <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s cocaine barons, for instance, are still putting away
piles of money from selling the illegal drug even though profit
margins in the cocaine trade have been shrinking during recent years.
   Three of them made Forbes ``World Billionaires'' list, including
<PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON>, leader of the notorious <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cocaine
cartel, with an estimated personal net worth of <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>. The
other cocaine kingpins on the list were the <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON> family, worth more
than <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>, and <PERSON>Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha</PERSON>, with more than <MONEY>$1
billion</MONEY>.
   In compiling its list, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> does not consider royal families
and heads of state ``because their wealth derives more from
political heritage than from economic effort _ theirs are feudal
fortunes, not capitalistic ones.''
   The magazine also excludes dictators, such as <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Fidel Castro</PERSON>
or <LOCATION>North Korea</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Kim Il Sung</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA071089-0048 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 80404 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 10, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 2; Column 3; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
538 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JAPAN'S TSUTSUMI STILL TOPS FORBES' RICHEST LIST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Six of the 10 richest people in the world are Japanese but the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> 
still leads the world in the total number of billionaires, according to 
estimates compiled by Forbes magazine. 
</P>
<P>
For the third straight year, <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON> led <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' list of private 
billionaires even though his wealth wasn't reported to be quite as great as had 
been estimated 12 months ago. 
</P>
<P>
Tsutsumi, head of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Seibu Railway Group</ORGANIZATION>, has a personal net worth of at 
least <MONEY>$15 billion</MONEY> -- nearly <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY> less than estimated last <DATE>summer</DATE> due 
mainly to a rise in the value of the dollar against other major currencies, 
<ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The estimate was far greater than the <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> that Fortune magazine had 
reported as <ORGANIZATION>Tsutsumi</ORGANIZATION>'s worth in its <DATE>September, 1988</DATE>, ranking of those whom it 
considered to be the world's richest people. 
</P>
<P>
In last year's list, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> estimated <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON>'s net worth at <MONEY>$18.9 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The magazine reports in its <DATE>July 24</DATE> issue that <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON> edged out second-ranked 
Taikichiro Mori by less than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Mori, a former economics professor who owns 72 office buildings in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, has 
an estimated net worth of <MONEY>$14.2 billion</MONEY>. In last year's survey, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> placed 
Mori's worth at about <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Walton No. 3 
</P>
<P>
The third-richest on the list was American <PERSON>Sam Moore Walton</PERSON>, founder of the 
third-largest retail operation in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart Stores Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 
<PERSON>Walton</PERSON> and his family are worth an estimated <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY>, up from <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' <DATE>1988</DATE> 
estimate of <MONEY>$6.5 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
After the Waltons came <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers, owners of the <ORGANIZATION>Olympia &amp; 
York</ORGANIZATION> real estate empire, with a combined net worth of about <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The remainder of the 10 richest people in the world, their country and 
industries, according to <LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION>, were: <PERSON>Shin Kyuk-ho</PERSON>, <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>, candy, real 
estate, <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Hirotomo Takei</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, publishing, real estate, 
<MONEY>$7.8 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Kitaro Watanabe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, hotels, <MONEY>$7 billion-plus</MONEY>; 
<PERSON>Haruhiko Yoshimoto</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Hans</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gad 
Rausing</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, liquids packaging, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>; and <PERSON>Eitaro Itoyama</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, 
land, <MONEY>$6.6 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Forbes said it identified 226 individuals or families around the world with 
personal assets worth in excess of <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was the country with the most billionaires, with 55 
individuals qualifying for that title. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> ranked second with 41, and <LOCATION>West 
Germany</LOCATION> was third with 20. 
</P>
<P>
America also accounted for the most billionaires in the <DATE>1988</DATE> survey, 47, 
followed by <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s 32 and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s 16. 
</P>
<P>
Among the richest of the world's rich are people who didn't necessarily come by 
their money in an honest way. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Not All Legitimate 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s cocaine barons, for instance, are still putting away piles of money 
from selling the illegal drug even though profit margins in the cocaine trade 
have been shrinking in recent years. 
</P>
<P>
Three of them made Forbes "World Billionaires" list, including <PERSON>Pablo Escobar 
Gaviria</PERSON>, leader of the notorious <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cocaine cartel, with an estimated 
personal net worth of <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
In compiling its list, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> does not consider royal families and heads of 
state "because their wealth derives more from political heritage than from 
economic effort." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
List; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
WEALTHY PEOPLE; FORBES MAGAZINE; EXECUTIVES; JAPANESE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880708-0259 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-88 0128EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-World'sRichest     07-08 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-World's Richest,0466</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tsutsumi Heads Forbes List of Billionaires for Second Year</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON> is a bit poorer than he was
last year _ make that less wealthy _ but the Japanese railroad
magnate still ranks as the world's richest person, according to
Forbes magazine.
   Tsutsumi, head of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Seibu Railway Group</ORGANIZATION>, has a personal
net worth of at least <MONEY>$18.9 billion</MONEY>, making him the world's richest
person for the second straight year, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The magazine, in a report on the richest people outside the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, estimated <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON>'s fortune at approximately <MONEY>$20
billion</MONEY> last fall in its first survey of the world's richest people.
   The story appears in the magazine's <DATE>July 25</DATE> issue.
   The designation for <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON> again puts Forbes at odds with
Fortune magazine. In its compilation of the world's billionaires
last <DATE>October</DATE>, Fortune estimated <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON>'s holdings in railroads,
hotels and golf clubs were worth a far smaller _ but still
substantial _ <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   The second richest person on <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>' list is also Japanese.
<PERSON>Taikichiro Mori</PERSON>, a former economics professor who owns 68 office
buildings in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, is worth <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>, the magazine estimated.
In the previous survey, <PERSON>Mori</PERSON>'s fortune was put at <MONEY>$15 billion</MONEY>.
   Following the two Japanese are the <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>,
who have built a <MONEY>$9 billion</MONEY> fortune in real estate, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Shin Kyuk-ho</PERSON>, a South Korean with interests in candy making,
hotels and real estate, is ranked No. 4 (<MONEY>$8 billion-plus</MONEY>), and
<PERSON>Kenneth Cole Irving</PERSON>, a Canadian with interests in oil distribution,
paper and land, is No. 5 (<MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>).
   The survey identifies 119 non-American individuals or families
around the world whose personal net assets are worth more than <MONEY>$1
billion</MONEY>, up from 90 in the previous list.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> still accounts for more billionaires than any
other country, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> noted. The magazine said at least 47 American
individuals and 20 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> families are worth more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>,
compared with 32 individuals and families in second-place <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and
16 in third-ranked <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>.
   The leading American billionaire is <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, the head of
major retailer <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart Stores</ORGANIZATION>, who ranks seventh worldwide with a
net worth of <MONEY>$6.5 billion</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> estimates.
   Not all the fortunes listed in <LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION>' list were amassed in a
respectable way.
   Three of them belong to people the magazine identified as
Colombian drug dealers, two individuals and one family, who are all
part of the notorious <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cocaine cartel.
   Two of the Colombian cocaine fortunes, those of <PERSON>Pablo Escobar
Gaviria</PERSON> and the <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON> family, are each more than <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>
said. It estimated the third, amassed by <PERSON>Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha</PERSON>,
at between <MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY> and <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900709-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-09-90 1548EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-World'sRichest 2ndLd-Writethru f0154 07-09 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World's Richest, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0154,0722</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japanese Developer Again Tops Billionaires List, But Trump Missing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf pvs to CORRECT day of week. Also moving on
general news wires.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With BC-World's Richest-List</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY13, Graphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BART ZIEGLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Japanese developer again topped a list of the
world's richest people, but the annual tally has one conspicuous
deletion this year: <PERSON>Donald J. Trump</PERSON>.
   Despite the financial troubles of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> developer, the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> continues to contain the world's largest number of
billionaires _ 62 _ according to estimates by Forbes magazine. In
addition, there are 37 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> families with fortunes over <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>,
<ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> says in its <DATE>July 23</DATE> issue.
   Forbes, in estimates released <DATE>Monday</DATE>, says the world's
wealthiest person for the fourth straight year was <PERSON>Yoshiaki
Tsutsumi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, whose railroad and real estate empire includes
golf courses, ski resorts and hotels. Forbes estimated his net
worth at <MONEY>$16 billion</MONEY>, up about <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> from last year.
   That estimate was far greater than that of rival business
magazine Fortune, which put Tsutsumi's net worth at <MONEY>$3.1 billion</MONEY>
last <DATE>September</DATE>.
   Fortune said the world's richest person is the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>,
at <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>. Forbes excludes heads of state from consideration.
   Following the 56-year-old <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON> on the Forbes list was
Japanese developer <PERSON>Taikichiro Mori</PERSON>, a former economics professor
who now owns 78 office buildings. Forbes put Mori's net worth at
<MONEY>$14.6 billion</MONEY>.
   Ranked third was the family of <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, founder of <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION>,
the third-largest <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>retail chain. Forbes estimates that the
Waltons, who also were third-ranked last year, are worth <MONEY>$13.3
billion</MONEY>, up from <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1989</DATE>.
   America's du <PERSON>Pont</PERSON> family was fourth, with a net worth estimated
at <MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY>. They were followed by <PERSON>Hans</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gad Rausing</PERSON>, two
Swedish brothers who control a packaging empire worth <MONEY>$9.6 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Kitaro Watanabe</PERSON>, a Japanese real estate owner, was sixth at <MONEY>$9.2
billion</MONEY>. He was followed by <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers, owners of
the <ORGANIZATION>Olympia &amp; York</ORGANIZATION> real estate company, at <MONEY>$9 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Kenkichi Nakajima</PERSON> and his family, founder of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s largest
maker of pachinko machines, a gambling game similar to pinball,
were eighth at <MONEY>$8.4 billion</MONEY>.
   <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Shin Kyuk-ho</PERSON>, who owns a candy and real estate
empire, was ninth at <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY> to <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>; and <PERSON>Forrest E. Mars</PERSON>
and family of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, of Mars candy fame, were 10th at
an estimated <MONEY>$6 billion</MONEY>.
   Other American families with net worth exceeding <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>
included the <ORGANIZATION>Newhouse</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Hearst</ORGANIZATION> and Cox families, which derive their
fortunes from publishing and broadcasting; the Bass family of
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>; the <PERSON>Mellon</PERSON> family of banking fame; the <PERSON>Dorrance</PERSON> family,
whose wealth comes from <ORGANIZATION>Campbell Soup Co.</ORGANIZATION>; and <PERSON>Bill Gates</PERSON>, founder
of the computer software company <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON> remained the richest American individual,
according to <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Kluge</PERSON>, founder of the media company
<ORGANIZATION>Metromedia</ORGANIZATION>, has an estimated net worth of <MONEY>$5.2 billion</MONEY>, placing him
in a tie for 12th place on the worldwide list with the Newhouses.
   As for <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> put his net worth last year at <MONEY>$1.7
billion</MONEY>, but it dropped sharply this year as the value of his real
estate and airline empire plummeted. In <DATE>April</DATE>, the magazine said he
was worth about a half <MONEY>a billion dollars</MONEY>. Some sources peg it even
lower.
   Forbes says one trend it noticed in compiling this year's list
was the number of wealthy Germans. The magazine identified 38 West
German billionaire families _ far more per capita than in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> or
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The list includes 40 Japanese and 99 American individuals or
families with a net worth over <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   Forbes says it identified 271 billionaire individuals or
families worldwide, up from 226 last year. The compilation is based
on recent stock valuations, comparable real estate valuations and
currency exchange rates, among other factors.
   The magazine says it excludes from consideration royal families
and heads of state because their wealth ``derives more from
political heritage than from economic effort.''
   But it doesn't exclude drug dealers. Among the billionaires it
lists are <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON>, the head of the
<LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cocaine cartel, at about <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>, and <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON>
family, at about <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06190037 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06190037 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  WORLD; WEALTH; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  An 87-year-old Japanese real estate tycoon, worth an estimated $15 billion, is
the world's richest person, Forbes magazine says.;    Taikichiro Mori moved
past Yoshiaki Tsutsumi, who made his money in railroads and golf courses, to
lead the magazine's annual list of billionaires.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  $15 BILLION MAKES WORLD'S RICHEST MAN
MAGAZINE SAYS U.S. HAS MOST BILLIONAIRES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related story on this page.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Tsutsumi, 57, with an estimated worth of more than <MONEY>$14 billion</MONEY>, had topped
the list for four years.;    <PERSON>Sam Moore Walton</PERSON>, founder of the <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart Stores</ORGANIZATION>
discount chain, would be the world's richest individual, but he has split his
money among five family members. The Waltons' <MONEY>$18.5 billion</MONEY> is nearly <MONEY>$9
billion</MONEY> more than the next family fortune, the du Ponts', <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said.;   
<PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON>, founder of <ORGANIZATION>Metromedia</ORGANIZATION>, an entertainment and communications
conglomerate, remained the richest American, the magazine said. He was
estimated to have a net worth of <MONEY>$5.6 billion.</MONEY>;    Despite Mori, the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> led the list of billionaires, with 64 individuals and 32 families
estimated to have a net worth of more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> was second, with
41 billionaires; <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> was third with 40.;    The American billionaires are
worth a total of <MONEY>$207 billion</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said, and the Japanese are worth more
than <MONEY>$126 billion.</MONEY>;    Two of the billionaire fortunes identified belong to
Colombian cocaine smugglers. <PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON> recently turned himself in
and the <LOCATION>Ochoa</LOCATION> brothers are already in prison. Both of their fortunes are
estimated to exceed <MONEY>$2.5 billion.</MONEY>;    The list appears in the magazine's <DATE>July
22</DATE> issue.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910708  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  248  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday July 8, 1991
00190037,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA070990-0111 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 245311 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 9, 1990, Monday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part P; Page 3; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
324 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
P.M. BRIEFING; 
</P>
<P>
JAPANESE DEVELOPER WORLD'S RICHEST MAN, TRUMP OFF THE LIST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A Japanese railway and real estate developer has earned the ranking of the 
world's richest businessman for the fourth straight year, according to <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' 
annual list of the world's billionaires released today. 
</P>
<P>
And American real estate tycoon <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>, who suffered huge financial 
setbacks during the year, was dropped from the list. 
</P>
<P>
With an estimated net worth of <MONEY>$16 billion</MONEY>, <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON> ranked first 
among 271 individuals and families worldwide whose personal net assets are 
worth more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said in its <DATE>July 23</DATE> issue. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> led the list with 62 individual billionaires and 37 
billionaire families, for a total of 99, the magazine said. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> followed with 
40 billionaire fortunes, and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> ranked a close third with 38, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Ranking second after <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON> was another Japanese businessman, <PERSON>Taikichiro 
Mori</PERSON>, a former economics professor turned real estate developer, the magazine 
reported. 
</P>
<P>
The highest-ranking American on the list was <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart Stores</ORGANIZATION> founder <PERSON>Sam Moore 
Walton</PERSON> and his family who, with a combined net worth of <MONEY>$13.3 billion</MONEY>, placed 
third. Coming in fourth was the <PERSON>Du Pont</PERSON> family, with a combined net worth of 
<MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Ranking fifth were two Swedish brothers, <PERSON>Hans</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gad Rausing</PERSON>, who control a 
packaging empire worth <MONEY>$9.6 billion</MONEY>, the magazine said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON>, founder of <ORGANIZATION>Metromedia</ORGANIZATION>, continues to be the richest 
individual American billionaire, with an estimated net worth of <MONEY>$5.2 billion</MONEY>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
Other Americans earning a spot on the list were financier <PERSON>Warren Edward 
Buffett</PERSON>, publishers S. I. and <PERSON>Donald Newhouse</PERSON> and <PERSON>H. Ross Perot</PERSON>, founder of 
<ORGANIZATION>Electronic Data Systems</ORGANIZATION>. Other Americans on the list included real estate mogul 
<PERSON>Harry Helmsley</PERSON>, cable television maverick <PERSON>Ted Turner</PERSON>, <PERSON>Laurence</PERSON> and <PERSON>Preston 
Tisch</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Loews Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, takeover artist and head of <ORGANIZATION>Pan American World Airways</ORGANIZATION> 
<PERSON>Carl Icahn</PERSON>, publisher <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>David Rockefeller</PERSON>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; List; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881011-0232 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-11-88 0014EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-RichestRich Bjt   10-11 0653</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Richest Rich, Bjt,0669</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Crash Hurt, But They're Still Really Rich</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARIANN CAPRINO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The legion of American billionaires has
broadened to include 51 people, despite the <DATE>1987</DATE> stock market crash
that realigned the fortunes of many of the nation's wealthiest.
   Forbes magazine says its annual survey shows the net worth of
the ultra-affluent totaled <MONEY>$84.8 billion</MONEY> _ nearly <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> more
than the combined wealth of <DATE>last year</DATE>'s 49 billionaires.
   The other 349 people who constitute <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>' list of the 400
richest Americans were worth about <MONEY>$135.2 billion</MONEY>.The average
fortune is <MONEY>$551 million</MONEY>, up <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> from last year.
   Topping the list released <DATE>Monday</DATE> is 70-year-old <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, who
held the No. 1 spot for the fourth straight year even though his
net worth shrank by <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> following the crash.
   <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>, head of the Arkansas-based <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> discount store
empire, scoffs at his <MONEY>$6.7 billion</MONEY> fortune. He calls it ``just
paper _ all I own is a pickup truck and a little <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> stock.''
   <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> is the world's fifth-richest person after
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON>, worth <MONEY>$18.9 billion</MONEY>; <ORGANIZATION>Taikichiro Mori</ORGANIZATION>,
<MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>; and <PERSON>Haruhiko Yoshimoto</PERSON>, <MONEY>$7.8 billion</MONEY>; and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s
<PERSON>Kenneth Cole Irving</PERSON>, <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>.
   But last year's <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> financial market crash slashed fortunes
and caused 22 former members to be dropped from the list because
their fortunes slipped below <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>' <MONEY>$225 million</MONEY> cutoff.
   The list appears in the <DATE>Oct. 24</DATE> edition of <LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION> and is based
on holdings as of <DATE>Aug. 30</DATE>.
   Runner-up to <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> on the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> billionaire list is <PERSON>John Werner
Kluge</PERSON>, the German-born head of <ORGANIZATION>Metromedia Co.</ORGANIZATION>, with a net worth of
<MONEY>$3.2 billion</MONEY>. Kluge was followed by <PERSON>H. Ross Perot</PERSON>, founder of
<ORGANIZATION>Electronic Data Systems</ORGANIZATION>, with <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>; publishers <PERSON>Samuel I.
Newhouse Jr.</PERSON> and <PERSON>Donald Newhouse</PERSON>, <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY> each; and <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>
industrialist <PERSON>Henry Lea Hillman</PERSON>, <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   Underscoring the adage that the more you have, the more you can
lose, billionaires were among those hit hard by the crash.Among the
big losers were <PERSON>David Packard</PERSON>, founder of <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>, media
magnate <PERSON>Keith Rupert Murdoch</PERSON> and retailer <PERSON>Leslie Wexner</PERSON>, each of
whom lost up to <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of their fortunes.
   Among those new to the billionaire club are flamboyant <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
real estate developer <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>, who claims a net worth of <MONEY>$3.47
billion</MONEY>, though <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>' estimate is in the <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> range.
   Joining Trump as list rookies are: <PERSON>Sumner Murray Redstone</PERSON>, who
boosted his balance sheet with the takeover of <ORGANIZATION>Viacom</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$1.4
billion</MONEY>; press-shy <PERSON>Charles Feeney</PERSON>, who runs Duty-Free Shoppers at
airports, <MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Charles Sammons</PERSON>, head of the privately held
<ORGANIZATION>Sammons Enterprises</ORGANIZATION>, the nation's 15th largest cable TV operator,
<MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Charles de Ganahl Koch</PERSON> and <PERSON>David Hamilton Koch</PERSON>,
brothers involved in oil services, <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY> each, and <PERSON>Ronald O.
Perelman</PERSON>, takeover strategist and head of <ORGANIZATION>Revlon</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   Four businessmen returned to the ranks of multimillionaire when
their fortunes sank below <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>: <PERSON>Laurence</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Tisch</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Loews Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, each estimated at <MONEY>$850 million</MONEY>; <PERSON>Milton Petrie</PERSON>, the
philanthropist and head of <ORGANIZATION>Petrie Stores</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$750 million</MONEY>; and
financier <PERSON>Carl Lindner II</PERSON>, <MONEY>$950 million</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>William Henry Gates III</PERSON>, who dropped out of <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> and founded
the <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> software company, remained the youngest self-made
billionaire at age 32. His net worth is estimated at <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY>.
   The oldest person new to the list is <PERSON>Mansfield Freeman</PERSON>, who
holds a stake in <ORGANIZATION>American International Group</ORGANIZATION>. With a fortune of
<MONEY>$240 million</MONEY>, he made the list for the first time at age 93.
   Among the 52 who disappeared from the list, 22 vanished because
of Black Monday-associated losses, 26 were surpassed by greater
fortunes and four died. Other Forbes standbys include: real estate
tycoon <PERSON>Harry Helmsley</PERSON>, <MONEY>$1.7 billion</MONEY>; takeover strategist <PERSON>Carl
Icahn</PERSON>, <MONEY>$940 million</MONEY>; brewer <PERSON>August Busch Jr.</PERSON>, <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY>;
designer <PERSON>Ralph Lauren</PERSON>, <MONEY>$450 million</MONEY>; cosmetics queen <PERSON>Estee Lauder</PERSON>,
<MONEY>$450 million</MONEY>; and vintners <PERSON>Ernest</PERSON> and <PERSON>Julio Gallo</PERSON>, <MONEY>$350 million</MONEY>
each.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891010-0213 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-10-89 0012EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-ForbesRichest Bjt   10-10 0832</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Forbes Richest, Bjt,0855</SECOND>
<HEAD>At $5.2 Billion, Metromedia's John Kluge Tops Richest List</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY23 of Oct. 9, LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEFAN FATSIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Charity began at home for <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> stores
founder <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, who ended a four-year reign as Forbes
magazine's richest American by sharing his <MONEY>$9 billion</MONEY> fortune with
his four children.
   <ORGANIZATION>Metromedia Co</ORGANIZATION>. Chairman <PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON>, with an estimated net
worth of <MONEY>$5.2 billion</MONEY>, climbed into first place on <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>' annual
list of the nation's 400 wealthiest people.
   The prototypical member of <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' ultra-rich was a 63-year-old
male with 3.1 children working on his 1.4th marriage with a net
worth of <MONEY>$672 million</MONEY> last year, more than the gross national
product of <LOCATION>Lesotho</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said.
   The compilation contains 346 men and 54 women. Of those, 159
inherited their wealth. Eight states lack a resident on the list.
   Among alma mater represented, <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> educated 22 of the richest,
<ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> 17 and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION> 12; the 45 with
master's degrees in business had an average net worth of <MONEY>$895
million</MONEY>, while the 10 high-school dropouts had an average of <MONEY>$854
million</MONEY>.
   Overall, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>' richest are worth an estimated total of about
<MONEY>$269 billion</MONEY>, up nearly <MONEY>$50 billion</MONEY> from <DATE>last year</DATE>, a <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT>
increase that substantially outpaced last year's <PERCENT>4.4 percent</PERCENT>
inflation rate.
   That total wealth would come just short of bailing out te
nation's failed savings and loans over the <DATE>next 30 years</DATE>, the cost
of which was estimated by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> at <MONEY>$285 billion</MONEY>.
   The list, released <DATE>Monday</DATE>, appears in the <DATE>Oct. 23</DATE> issue of
<LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION> and is based on estimated holdings as of <DATE>Sept. 8</DATE>.
   At the pinnacle is <PERSON>Kluge</PERSON>, 75, of <LOCATION>Charlottesville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, whose
holdings rose an estimated <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> from the previous year thanks
to a tripling in the value of his investment in cellular
telephones, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said.
   Kluge moved up from the No. 2 spot. The magazine noted that
``klug'' in German means smart.
   <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>, 71, of <LOCATION>Bentonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, who milked cows during the
Depression to support his family, split his <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> and other
assets equally with his four children. While the family's total
holdings increased from <MONEY>$6.7 bilion</MONEY>, the individual family members
tied for 20th on the list, each at <MONEY>$1.8 billion</MONEY>.
   Moving up to second from 12th place is investor <PERSON>Warren Buffett</PERSON>,
59, of <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>, the head of <PERSON>Berkshire Hathaway</PERSON>, whose stock
market-based fortune nearly doubled, to <MONEY>$4.2 billion</MONEY>. Behind him is
<PERSON>Sumner M. Redstone</PERSON>, head of moviehouse operator <ORGANIZATION>National Amusements
Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and TV-cable giant <ORGANIZATION>Viacom</ORGANIZATION>, with <MONEY>$2.88 billion</MONEY>.
   The number of billionaires increased to 66 from 51. The minimum
net worth to make the list rose to <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$225 million</MONEY>.
   America has more billionaires than any other nation _ <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is
second with 41 _ but the richest of the world's rich are foreigners.
   Kluge's fortune makes him the ninth-wealthiest private
individual in the world, according to <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>. He is topped by six
Japanese, a South Korean and Canadian publisher <PERSON>Kenneth Roy
Thompson</PERSON>. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON>, who made his money in land,
railroads and resorts, is worth about <MONEY>$15 billion</MONEY>, making him the
richest, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said.
   Eighteen new billionaires joined the Forbes American list,
including <PERSON>Laurence</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Tisch</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Loews Corp.</ORGANIZATION> at <MONEY>$1.36 billion</MONEY>
apiece, entertainment mogul <PERSON>Kirk Kerkorian</PERSON> at <MONEY>$1.29 billion</MONEY>,
<ORGANIZATION>Trans World Airlines Inc.</ORGANIZATION> boss <PERSON>Carl Icahn</PERSON> at <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON> also is among the individual standouts, adding <MONEY>$700
million</MONEY> to his empire of hotels, casinos and an airline for a <MONEY>$1.7
billion</MONEY> total.
   For the second straight year, the youngest self-made billionaire
is 33-year-old <PERSON>William Gates</PERSON> III at <MONEY>$1.25 billion</MONEY>. Gates dropped
out of <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> to found <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, a computer software company, in
<DATE>1972</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> beer and baseball magnate <PERSON>August Anheuser Busch Jr.</PERSON>,
who died <DATE>Sept. 29</DATE> at age 90, is included on the list with <MONEY>$1.5
billion</MONEY>. Forbes said it compiled its profiles before he died.
   The youngest person on the list is <PERSON>Caroline Marie Getty</PERSON>, 32,
daughter of the late <PERSON>George Getty</PERSON>, with her <MONEY>$330 million</MONEY>
inheritance. The oldest remained 94-year-old <PERSON>Mansfield Freeman</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Greensboro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>, whose <MONEY>$360 million</MONEY> worth includes a stake in
insurer <ORGANIZATION>American International Group</ORGANIZATION>.
   Among the losers were real estate investor and builder <PERSON>Fred
Trammell Crow</PERSON>, whose net worth, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> estimated, sank to <MONEY>$300
million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$775 million</MONEY>, thanks to softness in commercial real
estate. Penthouse publisher <PERSON>Bob Guccione</PERSON> slipped into something
less comfortable and dropped off the list.
   About <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>, or 82, of those listed live in or near <LOCATION>New
York City</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> is second with 32 and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> third at
19. Twenty-one people on the list own at least one-third of a major
league sports franchise.
   Publisher <PERSON>Malcolm Forbes</PERSON> included his own biographical data and
outside reported estimates of his net worth but refused, as usual,
to divulge his wealth. Forbes' sketch was included in the under
<MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> category. ``I'm solvent,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101089-0057 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 118571 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 10, 1989, Tuesday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 1; Column 2; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
878 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FORBES RANKS KLUGE AS RICHEST AMERICAN; 
</P>
<P>
WALTON ENDS 4-YEAR REIGN BY DIVIDING FORTUNE AMONG CHILDREN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Metromedia Co</ORGANIZATION>. Chairman <PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON> is worth an estimated <MONEY>$5.2 billion</MONEY>, 
but he had to back into first place on Forbes magazine's annual list of the 400 
richest Americans. 
</P>
<P>
Kluge displaced <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> stores discount chain, who 
divvied his <MONEY>$9-billion</MONEY> fortune among himself and his four children and ended a 
four-year reign as <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' wealthiest person. 
</P>
<P>
Among other notables on the list, developer <PERSON>Donald J. Trump</PERSON> compounded his 
already considerable fortune and financiers <PERSON>Michael Milken</PERSON> and <PERSON>Carl C. Icahn</PERSON> 
joined the billionaires club. 
</P>
<P>
Overall, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>' richest are worth an estimated total of about <MONEY>$269 billion</MONEY>, up 
nearly <MONEY>$50 billion</MONEY> from the previous year, a <PERCENT>22%</PERCENT> increase that substantially 
outpaced last year's <PERCENT>4.4%</PERCENT> inflation rate. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Prototypical Member 
</P>
<P>
By comparison, the total wealth of the richest would come just short of bailing 
out the nation's failed savings and loans over the <DATE>next 30 years</DATE>, the cost of 
which was estimated by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> at <MONEY>$285 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The list, released <DATE>Monday</DATE>, appears in the <DATE>Oct. 23</DATE> edition of <LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION> and is 
based on estimated holdings as of <DATE>Sept. 8</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The prototypical member of <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' ultra-rich was a 63-year-old male with 3.1 
children who has been married 1.4 times and had a net worth of <MONEY>$672 million</MONEY> 
last year, more than the gross national product of <LOCATION>Lesotho</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> stated. 
</P>
<P>
For the richest, the last year has been a very good one. Many of the wealthy 
rebounded nicely from the <DATE>October, 1987</DATE>, stock market crash. 
</P>
<P>
The number of billionaires increased to 66 from 51. The minimum net worth to 
make the list rose to <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$225 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
At the pinnacle was <PERSON>Kluge</PERSON>, 75, of <LOCATION>Charlottesville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, whose holdings rose an 
estimated <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> from last year thanks to a tripling in the value of his 
holdings in cellular telephones, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Kluge moved up from the No. 2 spot. The magazine noted that "klug" in German 
means smart. 
</P>
<P>
For <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>, charity began at home. The 71-year-old from <LOCATION>Bentonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, who 
milked cows during the Depression to support his family, split his <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> and 
other assets equally with his four children. While the family's total holdings 
increased to <MONEY>$9 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$6.7 billion</MONEY>, the individual family members tied 
for 20th on the list. 
</P>
<P>
Moving up to second from 12th place was investor <PERSON>Warren Buffett</PERSON>, 59, of <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>, the head of Berkshire Hathaway whose stock market-based fortune nearly 
doubled to <MONEY>$4.2 billion</MONEY>. Behind him was <PERSON>Sumner Murray Redstone</PERSON>, head of 
<ORGANIZATION>National Amusements Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and entertainment giant <ORGANIZATION>Viacom</ORGANIZATION>, with <MONEY>$2.88 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
New Billionaires 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> has more billionaires than any other nation -- <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is second with 41 
-- but the richest of the rich live abroad. 
</P>
<P>
Kluge's fortune makes him the ninth-wealthiest private individual in the world, 
according to <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>. He is topped by six Japanese, a South Korean and Canadian 
publisher <PERSON>Kenneth Roy Thompson</PERSON>. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON>, who made his money 
in land, railroads and resorts, is worth about <MONEY>$15 billion</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
Eighteen new billionaires joined the Forbes American list, including <PERSON>Laurence</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Robert Tisch</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Loews Corp.</ORGANIZATION> at <MONEY>$1.36 billion</MONEY> apiece, entertainment mogul 
<PERSON>Kirk Kerkorian</PERSON> at <MONEY>$1.29 billion</MONEY>, indicted junk bond financier <PERSON>Milken</PERSON> at <MONEY>$1.27 
billion</MONEY> and <ORGANIZATION>TWA</ORGANIZATION> boss <PERSON>Icahn</PERSON> at <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Trump also was among the individual standouts, adding <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY> to his 
empire of hotels, casinos and an airline for a <MONEY>$1.7-billion</MONEY> total. 
</P>
<P>
For the second straight year, the youngest self-made billionaire was 
33-year-old <PERSON>William Henry Gates</PERSON> III at <MONEY>$1.25 billion</MONEY>. Gates dropped out of 
<ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION> to found <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1972</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> beer and baseball magnate <PERSON>August Anheuser Busch Jr.</PERSON>, who died on 
<DATE>Sept. 29</DATE> at age 90, was included on the list with <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY>. Forbes said it 
compiled its profiles before the death. 
</P>
<P>
The youngest on the list is 32-year-old <PERSON>Caroline Marie Getty</PERSON>, daughter of the 
late <PERSON>George Getty</PERSON>, with her <MONEY>$330-million</MONEY> inheritance. The oldest of the wealthy 
remained 94-year-old <PERSON>Mansfield Freeman</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Greensboro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>, who holds a stake in 
the insurer <ORGANIZATION>American International Group</ORGANIZATION>, with <MONEY>$360 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Among the losers were real estate investor and builder <PERSON>Fred Trammell Crow</PERSON>, 
whose net worth, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> estimated, sank to <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$775 million</MONEY>, 
thanks to softness in commercial real estate. Penthouse publisher <PERSON>Bob Guccione</PERSON> 
slipped into something less comfortable and dropped off the list. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
New York Address 
</P>
<P>
The list contains 346 men and 54 women; 159 inherited their wealth; no one from 
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> qualified; <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> had 22 of the richest, <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> 17 
and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION> 12; the 45 with master's degrees in business 
had an average net worth of <MONEY>$895 million</MONEY>, while the 10 high-school dropouts had 
an average of <MONEY>$854 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
About <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT>, or 82, of those listed live in or near <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, with <LOCATION>Los 
Angeles</LOCATION> second in plutocratic residences with 32 and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> third at 19. 
Twenty-one people on the list own at least one-third of a major league sports 
franchise. 
</P>
<P>
Publisher <PERSON>Malcolm Forbes</PERSON> included his own biographical data and reported 
estimates of his net worth but refused, as usual, to divulge his wealth. 
Forbes' sketch was included in the under-<MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> category. "I'm solvent," 
he said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Full Run; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900710-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-90 0116EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-World'sRichest-List 2Takes   07-10 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-World's Richest-List, 2 Takes,0550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ranking Foreign Billionaire Fortunes as compiled by Forbes
Magazine</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-World's Richest Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of the world's richest people with net worth of
more than <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>, as estimated in the <DATE>July 23</DATE> issue of Forbes
magazine.
   Forbes excludes royal families and heads of state on the ground
that their fortunes aren't based on economic prowess.
   Listed are the billionaires, their home nation, business and
estimated personal net worth.
   
   1. <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, land, railroads, resorts, <MONEY>$16
billion</MONEY>.
   2. Taikichiro Mori, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, property development, <MONEY>$14.6 billion</MONEY>.
   3. <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, retailing, <MONEY>$13.3
billion</MONEY>.
   4. du <PERSON>Pont</PERSON> family, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, inheritance (Du Pont), <MONEY>$10
billion</MONEY>.
   5. Hans and <PERSON>Gad Rausing</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, liquids packaging, <MONEY>$9.6 billion</MONEY>.
   6. <PERSON>Kitaro Watanabe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, <MONEY>$9.2 billion</MONEY>.
   7. Reichmann brothers, (<PERSON>Paul</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Albert</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ralph</PERSON>), <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, real
estate, investments, <MONEY>$9 billion</MONEY>.
   8. Kenkichi Nakajima, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, pachinko machines, <MONEY>$8.4 billion</MONEY>.
   9. Shin Kyuk-ho, <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, candy, real estate, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>-<MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY>.
   10. Forrest <PERSON>E. Mars</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, candy, <MONEY>$6 billion</MONEY>.
   11. <PERSON>Eitaro Itoyama</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, land, <MONEY>$5.8 billion</MONEY>.
   12. <PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, media, real estate, <MONEY>$5.2
billion</MONEY>.
   Samuel I. and <PERSON>Donald E. Newhouse</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, publishing,
<MONEY>$5.2 billion</MONEY>.
   14. <PERSON>Erivan Haub</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, supermarkets, <MONEY>$5 billion-plus</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Haruhiko Yoshimoto</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, <MONEY>$5
billion-plus</MONEY>.
   16. Bass family (<LOCATION>Robert</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Lee</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sid</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edward</PERSON>), <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, oil,
investments, <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   Brenninkmeyer family, <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION>, retailing, <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Barbara Cox Anthony</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Anne Cox Chambers</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,
inheritance, <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Kenneth Colin Irving</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, oil distribution,
paper, land, <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Yohachiro Iwasaki</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, logging, property, resorts, <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   Quandt family, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, autos, industry, <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Kenneth Roy Thomson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, publishing, retailing, <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   23. Cargill-MacMillan, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, grain, <MONEY>$4.8 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Kiyoshi Sagawa</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, delivery service, <MONEY>$4.8 billion</MONEY>.
   25. <PERSON>Giovanni Agnelli</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, autos, <MONEY>$4.7 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Jay Arthur</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Alan Pritzker</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, financier,
manufacturing, <MONEY>$4.7 billion</MONEY>.
   27. <PERSON>Junichi Murata</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, facsimile equipment, industrial
machinery, <MONEY>$4.6 billion</MONEY>.
   28. Hearst family, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, inheritance (media), <MONEY>$4.4
billion</MONEY>.
   29. Mellon family, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, inheritance, <MONEY>$4.2 billion</MONEY>.
   30. <PERSON>Hirotomo Takei</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, publishing, real estate, <MONEY>$4
billion-plus</MONEY>.
   31. Takenaka family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, construction, <MONEY>$3.9 billion</MONEY>.
   32. <PERSON>Warren Edward Buffett</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, stock market, <MONEY>$3.8
billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Dorrance</PERSON> family, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, food products, <MONEY>$3.8 billion</MONEY>.
   34. Seydoux-Schlumberger family, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, textiles, media, oil
services, <MONEY>$3.7 billion</MONEY>.
   35. <PERSON>Hattori</PERSON> family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, watches, <MONEY>$3.5 billion</MONEY>.
   36. <PERSON>Charles de G. Koch</PERSON> and <PERSON>David H. Koch</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,
inheritance (oil services), <MONEY>$3.4 billion</MONEY>.
   Yoneichi Otani, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, hotels, <MONEY>$3.4 billion</MONEY>.
   38. <PERSON>William Henry Gates III</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, computer software,
<MONEY>$3.2 billion</MONEY>.
   39. <PERSON>Friedrich Karl Flick</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, heavy industry, <MONEY>$3
billion-plus</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Gerald Cavendish Grosvenor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION>, real estate, <MONEY>$3 billion-plus</MONEY>.
   Haniel family, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, trading, retailing, <MONEY>$3 billion-plus</MONEY>.
   Henkel family, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, consumer products, <MONEY>$3 billion-plus</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Hisakichi Yamaguchi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, cans, <MONEY>$3 billion-plus</MONEY>.
   44. <PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, cocaine, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Keizo Saji</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, liquor, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Rinji Shino</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, leisure, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890711-0223 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-11-89 0217EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-World'sRichest-Walton Bjt   07-11 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-World's Richest-Walton, Bjt,0521</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wealthy Wal-Mart Founder Just Another Neighbor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER M. FULFORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LITTLE ROCK, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   He's ranked as the richest man in the
nation by a leading business magazine, but to folks in <LOCATION>Bentonville</LOCATION>,
a town of about 8,700 people, <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON> is just another neighbor.
   ``He's just a part of the community,'' said <PERSON>Curt Loyd</PERSON>, executive
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Bentonville Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>. ``He's a neat
person. He calls <LOCATION>Bentonville</LOCATION> home, and that is special to us.''
   <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>, who prefers bird-hunting, tennis and opening new <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION>
stores to trumpeting his personal financial holdings, is again
shunning publicity about his third consecutive ranking among the
world's top billionaires. According to Forbes magazine's <DATE>July 24</DATE>
edition, the <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> family's estimated worth is <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY>, up
from its <DATE>1988</DATE> estimate of <MONEY>$6.5 billion</MONEY>.
   ``He is unavailable,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Don Shinkle</PERSON> of the
silver-haired founder of the nation's third-largest retail chain,
based in <LOCATION>Bentonville</LOCATION>, about 150 miles northwest of Little Rock.
   <PERSON>Shinkle</PERSON> said he received about 10 calls from reporters <DATE>Monday</DATE>
<TIME>morning</TIME>, when the Forbes list appeared in newspapers. <PERSON>Shinkle</PERSON> said
news coverage about <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> ``usually sets off a press frenzy'' for
comments from him. But the 71-year-old businessman declined to
comment.
   ``He feels any attention to <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON> is to the individual and
he prefers attention to <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON> (the founder of) the company,''
<PERSON>Shinkle</PERSON> said.
   ``He very seldom schedules interviews about his feelings. It just
puts him in a position he doesn't want to be.''
   But <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> occasionally offers peeks that reveal personal
modesty. Just after the <DATE>1987</DATE> stock market crash, in which <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>'s
family-owned chunk of <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> stock lost millions in value, he
quipped in response to questions at a news conference on another
topic that it was only paper. Walton then changed the subject.
   Walton was first listed by <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> as the nation's richest man in
<DATE>October 1985</DATE>. Three years ago, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> also began listing the world's
wealthiest people. Walton made that listing as the richest American
every year since. This year he ranks third, behind two Japanese
businessmen.
   <PERSON>Shinkle</PERSON> said <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> stays busy visiting many of the more than
1,400 stores operated by the company he started as a single
five-and-dime at <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION> more than two decades ago. He is out of the
office up to four days a week, the spokesman said.
   ``He spends most of his time talking to associates and
customers,'' <PERSON>Shinkle</PERSON> said, ``and he always comes back with many
ideas from them.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> calls its sales help associates instead of employees.
   When <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> first made the Forbes list of richest Americans,
recalled Little Rock investment banker <PERSON>Warren Simpson</PERSON>, calls came in
from all over about the billionaire from the <LOCATION>Ozarks</LOCATION>.
   ``They wanted to know about the stock and the company,'' said
<PERSON>Simpson</PERSON>, who works for <ORGANIZATION>Stephens Inc.</ORGANIZATION> ``You'd think that he'd be
living in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> or LA, not <LOCATION>Bentonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>. But now people
just accept it.
   ``When it comes out now, it's just, `Yeah, he's still there,'''
<PERSON>Simpson</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890707-0244 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-07-89 2230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-World'sRichest-List     07-07 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World's Richest-List,0428</SECOND>
<HEAD>Embargoed by source for release 6:30 p.m. EDT Sunday, July 9</HEAD>
<HEAD>World's Richest People, According to Forbes Magazine</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-World's Richest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the world's richest people, as estimated
in the <DATE>July 24</DATE> issue of Forbes magazine:
   Forbes excludes royal families and heads of state on the ground
that their fortunes aren't based on economic prowess.
   Listed are the billionaires, their home nation, business and
estimated personal net worth.
   1. <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, land, railroads, resorts, <MONEY>$15
billion</MONEY>.
   2. Taikichiro Mori, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, property development, <MONEY>$14.2 billion</MONEY>.
   3. <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, retailing, <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY>.
   4. Reichman brothers (<PERSON>Paul</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Albert</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ralph</PERSON>), <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, real estate,
<MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>.
   Shin Kyuk-ho, <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, candy, real estate, <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>.
   6. <PERSON>Hirotomo Takei</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, publishing, real estate,
<MONEY>$7.8 billion</MONEY>.
   7. <PERSON>Kitaro Watanabe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, hotels, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY> plus.
   8. <PERSON>Haruhiko Yoshimoto</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>.
   Hans and <PERSON>Gad Rausing</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, liquids packaging, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>.
   10. <PERSON>Eitaro Itoyama</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, land, <MONEY>$6.6 billion</MONEY>.
   11. <PERSON>Kenneth Roy Thomson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, publishing, retailing, <MONEY>$6
billion</MONEY>.
   12. Kenkichi Nakajima, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, pachinko, <MONEY>$5.8 billion</MONEY>.
   13. Brenninkmeyer family, <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION>, retailing, <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   14. <PERSON>Kenneth Colin Irving</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, oil distribution, paper, land,
<MONEY>$4.5 billion</MONEY>.
   15. Takenaka family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, construction, <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY>-<MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   16. <PERSON>Giovanni Agnelli</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, autos, investments, <MONEY>$3.7
billion</MONEY>.
   17. <PERSON>Mohn</PERSON> family, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, publishing, <MONEY>$3.6 billion</MONEY>.
   18. <PERSON>Warren Edward Buffett</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, investments, <MONEY>$3.5
billion</MONEY>.
   19. <PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, media, real estate, <MONEY>$3.2
billion</MONEY>.
   20. <PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, cocaine, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> plus.
   <PERSON>Gerald Cavendish Grosvenor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, property, investment,
<MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> plus.
   22. Ramon Areces, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, retailing, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Friedrich Karl Flick</PERSON>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, industry, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Henry Ross Perot</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, industry, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Keizo Saji</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, liquor, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   Johannes von Thurn und Taxis, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, land, investments, <MONEY>$3
billion</MONEY>.
   27. <PERSON>Erivan Haub</PERSON>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, supermarkets, <MONEY>$2.9 billion</MONEY>.
   28. Quandt family, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, autos, industry, <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Hisashi Ishii</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, finance, <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Samuel Irving Newhouse</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, publishing, <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Donald Edward Newhouse</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, publishing, <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY>.
   32. <PERSON>Henry Lea Hillman</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, real estate, venture
capital, <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Sumner Murray Redstone</PERSON>, communications, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <MONEY>$2.5
billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Ted Arison</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, cruise lines, <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   Garry and <PERSON>Galen Weston</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, supermarkets, <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Hisakichi Yamaguchi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, cans, <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890710-0245 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-89 0658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-World'sRichest-List     07-10 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-World's Richest-List,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>World's Richest People, According to Forbes Magazine</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-World's Richest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of people with more than <MONEY>$2
billion</MONEY> in net worth, as estimated in the <DATE>July 24</DATE> issue of Forbes
magazine:
   Forbes excludes royal families and heads of state on the ground
that their fortunes aren't based on economic prowess.
   Listed are the billionaires, their home nation, business and
estimated personal net worth.
   1. <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, land, railroads, resorts, <MONEY>$15
billion</MONEY>.
   2. Taikichiro Mori, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, property development, <MONEY>$14.2 billion</MONEY>.
   3. <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, retailing, <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY>.
   4. Reichmann brothers (<PERSON>Paul</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Albert</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ralph</PERSON>), <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, real estate,
<MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>.
   Shin Kyuk-ho, <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, candy, real estate, <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>.
   6. <PERSON>Hirotomo Takei</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, publishing, real estate,
<MONEY>$7.8 billion</MONEY>.
   7. <PERSON>Kitaro Watanabe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, hotels, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY> plus.
   8. <PERSON>Haruhiko Yoshimoto</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>.
   Hans and <PERSON>Gad Rausing</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, liquids packaging, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>.
   10. <PERSON>Eitaro Itoyama</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, land, <MONEY>$6.6 billion</MONEY>.
   11. <PERSON>Kenneth Roy Thomson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, publishing, retailing, <MONEY>$6
billion</MONEY>.
   12. Kenkichi Nakajima, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, pachinko, <MONEY>$5.8 billion</MONEY>.
   13. Brenninkmeyer family, <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION>, retailing, <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   14. <PERSON>Kenneth Colin Irving</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, oil distribution, paper, land,
<MONEY>$4.5 billion</MONEY>.
   15. Takenaka family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, construction, <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY>-<MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   16. <PERSON>Giovanni Agnelli</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, autos, investments, <MONEY>$3.7
billion</MONEY>.
   17. <PERSON>Mohn</PERSON> family, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, publishing, <MONEY>$3.6 billion</MONEY>.
   18. <PERSON>Warren Edward Buffett</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, investments, <MONEY>$3.5
billion</MONEY>.
   19. <PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, media, real estate, <MONEY>$3.2
billion</MONEY>.
   20. <PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, cocaine, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> plus.
   <PERSON>Gerald Cavendish Grosvenor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, property, investment,
<MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> plus.
   22. Ramon Areces, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, retailing, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Friedrich Karl Flick</PERSON>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, industry, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Henry Ross Perot</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, industry, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Keizo Saji</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, liquor, <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   Johannes von Thurn und Taxis, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, land, investments, <MONEY>$3
billion</MONEY>.
   27. <PERSON>Erivan Haub</PERSON>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, supermarkets, <MONEY>$2.9 billion</MONEY>.
   28. Quandt family, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, autos, industry, <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Hisashi Ishii</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, finance, <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Samuel Irving Newhouse</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, publishing, <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Donald Edward Newhouse</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, publishing, <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY>.
   32. <PERSON>Henry Lea Hillman</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, real estate, venture
capital, <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Sumner Murray Redstone</PERSON>, communications, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <MONEY>$2.5
billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Ted Arison</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, cruise lines, <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   Garry and <PERSON>Galen Weston</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, supermarkets, <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Hisakichi Yamaguchi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, cans, <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890710-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-89 0056EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     07-10 0959</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0993</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Being a woman has not made it difficult to govern
some difficulties for her political opponents and Moslem
fundamentalists.
   ``I don't often think of myself as a woman prime minister,'' <PERSON>Ms.
Bhutto</PERSON> said in a televised interview <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with <PERSON>David Frost</PERSON>.
   ``I just think of myself as someone who's leading the government,
who's got a job to do, not an easy one, and who would like to have
the prayers of well-wishers everywhere in completing the task in
strengthening the rule of law and improving the quality of life for
the people of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON>, 35, is the first woman in modern times to lead a
Moslem country and is the world's youngest prime minister.
   ``I think it may be a little difficult for my opponents or the
fundamentalists to have a woman prime minister,'' she said.
   ``Of course, it's different being a woman. There's a greater
formality or distance which must be followed so I try to make the
best of it.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON> won power in <DATE>November</DATE> in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s first free
elections in more than a decade. She arrived in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
for a week's visit.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEWPORT BEACH, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Being a woman has not made it difficult to govern
some difficulties for her political opponents and Moslem
fundamentalists.
   ``I don't often think of myself as a woman prime minister,'' <PERSON>Ms.
Bhutto</PERSON> said in a televised interview <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with <PERSON>David Frost</PERSON>.
   ``I just think of myself as someone who's leading the government,
who's got a job to do, not an easy one, and who would like to have
the prayers of well-wishers everywhere in completing the task in
strengthening the rule of law and improving the quality of life for
the people of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON>, 35, is the first woman in modern times to lead a
Moslem country and is the world's youngest prime minister.
   ``I think it may be a little difficult for my opponents or the
fundamentalists to have a woman prime minister,'' she said.
   ``Of course, it's different being a woman. There's a greater
formality or distance which must be followed so I try to make the
best of it.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON> won power in <DATE>November</DATE> in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s first free
elections in more than a decade. She arrived in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
for a week's visit.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Being a woman has not made it difficult to govern
some difficulties for her political opponents and Moslem
fundamentalists.
   ``I don't often think of myself as a woman prime minister,'' <PERSON>Ms.
Bhutto</PERSON> said in a televised interview <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with <PERSON>David Frost</PERSON>.
   ``I just think of myself as someone who's leading the government,
who's got a job to do, not an easy one, and who would like to have
the prayers of well-wishers everywhere in completing the task in
strengthening the rule of law and improving the quality of life for
the people of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON>, 35, is the first woman in modern times to lead a
Moslem country and is the world's youngest prime minister.
   ``I think it may be a little difficult for my opponents or the
fundamentalists to have a woman prime minister,'' she said.
   ``Of course, it's different being a woman. There's a greater
formality or distance which must be followed so I try to make the
best of it.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON> won power in <DATE>November</DATE> in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s first free
elections in more than a decade. She arrived in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
for a week's visit.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Longer version moving on financial wire.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Being a woman has not made it difficult to govern
some difficulties for her political opponents and Moslem
fundamentalists.
   ``I don't often think of myself as a woman prime minister,'' <PERSON>Ms.
Bhutto</PERSON> said in a televised interview <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with <PERSON>David Frost</PERSON>.
   ``I just think of myself as someone who's leading the government,
who's got a job to do, not an easy one, and who would like to have
the prayers of well-wishers everywhere in completing the task in
strengthening the rule of law and improving the quality of life for
the people of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON>, 35, is the first woman in modern times to lead a
Moslem country and is the world's youngest prime minister.
   ``I think it may be a little difficult for my opponents or the
fundamentalists to have a woman prime minister,'' she said.
   ``Of course, it's different being a woman. There's a greater
formality or distance which must be followed so I try to make the
best of it.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON> won power in <DATE>November</DATE> in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s first free
elections in more than a decade. She arrived in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
for a week's visit.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Version moving on sports wire.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WIMBLEDON, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Being a woman has not made it difficult to govern
some difficulties for her political opponents and Moslem
fundamentalists.
   ``I don't often think of myself as a woman prime minister,'' <PERSON>Ms.
Bhutto</PERSON> said in a televised interview <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with <PERSON>David Frost</PERSON>.
   ``I just think of myself as someone who's leading the government,
who's got a job to do, not an easy one, and who would like to have
the prayers of well-wishers everywhere in completing the task in
strengthening the rule of law and improving the quality of life for
the people of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON>, 35, is the first woman in modern times to lead a
Moslem country and is the world's youngest prime minister.
   ``I think it may be a little difficult for my opponents or the
fundamentalists to have a woman prime minister,'' she said.
   ``Of course, it's different being a woman. There's a greater
formality or distance which must be followed so I try to make the
best of it.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Bhutto</PERSON> won power in <DATE>November</DATE> in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s first free
elections in more than a decade. She arrived in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
for a week's visit.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06281170 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06281170 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Walton  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; WEALTH; PERIODICAL; RANKING; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Sure the recession hurt some of America's wealthiest people. But most kept
getting richer.;   Entertainment mogul John Werner Kluge is worth more than
any other American for the third straight year. But computer whiz Bill Gates
is closing the gap, Forbes magazine said in its 10th annual ranking of the
richest.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  KLUGE TOPS LIST OF AMERICA'S RICHEST
MAGAZINE'S LIST INCLUDES RECORD 71 BILLIONAIRES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related article on page 8A of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The net worth of the 400 wealthiest Americans hit <MONEY>$288 billion</MONEY> -- the
highest ever recorded by <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>. The list appears in the magazine's <DATE>Oct. 21</DATE>
issue.;   The recession made ex-moguls of some, mostly in real estate, where
values have dropped and vacancies skyrocketed, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said in a report
released <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. A record 71 billionaires populate the list, up from 66 <DATE>last
year</DATE> and 13 in the magazine's first ranking in <DATE>1982.</DATE>;   Fifty-eight of the 400
are women. The list's average age is 64.;   Amid the recession, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>
undertook something of an apology for wealth in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. The magazine, which
describes itself as a "capitalist tool," said in an essay that the rich are
having a tough time, too.;   "Since <DATE>1989</DATE> the economy has slowed -- for blacks,
for whites, for rich, for poor," <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said. "The median net worth of the
Forbes 400 has stagnated since <DATE>1989</DATE>, not even keeping pace with inflation.";  
<ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> found that the fortune of <PERSON>Kluge</PERSON>, a 77-year-old German immigrant who
founded <ORGANIZATION>Metromedia Co.</ORGANIZATION>, keeps growing. At an estimated <MONEY>$5.9 billion</MONEY>, it's up
<MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> from last year.;   No. 2 is <PERSON>William Henry Gates III</PERSON>, 35, a
<ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> dropout who in <DATE>1975</DATE> formed <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, now the biggest computer
software maker. The bulk of his estimated worth of <MONEY>$4.8 billion</MONEY> comes from
company stock, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said. Last year, he ranked 16th with <MONEY>$2.5 billion.</MONEY>;  
Gates replaces <PERSON>Warren Buffett</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> investor tapped to clean up
scandal-tainted <ORGANIZATION>Salomon Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Buffett's estimated stock-market fortune grew to
<MONEY>$4.2 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$3.3 billion</MONEY>, but he slipped to eighth on the list.;   Ahead
of him are <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart Stores Inc.</ORGANIZATION> founder <PERSON>Sam Moore Walton</PERSON> and his family.
Walton divided his wealth equally among himself and his four children. Each is
estimated to be worth <MONEY>$4.4 billion.</MONEY>;   Next are industrialist <PERSON>Henry Lea
Hillman</PERSON>, <MONEY>$3.3 billion</MONEY>; <ORGANIZATION>Amway Corp.</ORGANIZATION> partners <PERSON>Richard Marvin DeVos</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jay Van
Andel</PERSON>, <MONEY>$2.9 billion</MONEY> each; and publishing brothers <PERSON>Samuel Newhouse Jr.</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Donald Newhouse</PERSON>, <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> apiece.;   The magazine said financier <PERSON>Michael
Milken</PERSON>'s criminal guilty plea didn't erase his junk-bond driven fortune. He's
"making about <MONEY>30 cents</MONEY> an hour at prison labor, to add to net worth estimated
over <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY>," <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said.;   <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said it bases the rankings on
inheritances, stock ownership and conservative estimates for private companies.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911007  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  449  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, October 7, 1991
00281170,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880708-0256 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-88 0558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BusinessHighlights 1stAdd   07-08 0540</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights, 1st Add,0571</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s latest nominee for a seat
on the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> has been accused of attempting to
dodge taxes in negotiating a <MONEY>$2.5-million</MONEY> ``golden parachute''
compensation agreement with the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> bank holding company he
heads.
   <PERSON>John P. LaWare</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Shawmut National Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> he was not sure a tax dodge was involved in the agreement,
which he said was offered to assure him his <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> annual income
until he reaches age 65. He turned 60 on <DATE>Feb. 20</DATE>.
   Despite concern expressed by <PERSON>Sen. William Proxmire</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>,
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Banking Committee</ORGANIZATION>, there was no indication
the issue would affect LaWare's nomination.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s latest nominee for a seat
on the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> has been accused of attempting to
dodge taxes in negotiating a <MONEY>$2.5-million</MONEY> ``golden parachute''
compensation agreement with the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> bank holding company he
heads.
   <PERSON>John P. LaWare</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Shawmut National Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> he was not sure a tax dodge was involved in the agreement,
which he said was offered to assure him his <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> annual income
until he reaches age 65. He turned 60 on <DATE>Feb. 20</DATE>.
   Despite concern expressed by <PERSON>Sen. William Proxmire</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>,
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Banking Committee</ORGANIZATION>, there was no indication
the issue would affect LaWare's nomination.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BLOOMINGTON, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s latest nominee for a seat
on the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> has been accused of attempting to
dodge taxes in negotiating a <MONEY>$2.5-million</MONEY> ``golden parachute''
compensation agreement with the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> bank holding company he
heads.
   <PERSON>John P. LaWare</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Shawmut National Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> he was not sure a tax dodge was involved in the agreement,
which he said was offered to assure him his <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> annual income
until he reaches age 65. He turned 60 on <DATE>Feb. 20</DATE>.
   Despite concern expressed by <PERSON>Sen. William Proxmire</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>,
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Banking Committee</ORGANIZATION>, there was no indication
the issue would affect LaWare's nomination.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s latest nominee for a seat
on the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> has been accused of attempting to
dodge taxes in negotiating a <MONEY>$2.5-million</MONEY> ``golden parachute''
compensation agreement with the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> bank holding company he
heads.
   <PERSON>John P. LaWare</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Shawmut National Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> he was not sure a tax dodge was involved in the agreement,
which he said was offered to assure him his <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> annual income
until he reaches age 65. He turned 60 on <DATE>Feb. 20</DATE>.
   Despite concern expressed by <PERSON>Sen. William Proxmire</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>,
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Banking Committee</ORGANIZATION>, there was no indication
the issue would affect LaWare's nomination.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s latest nominee for a seat
on the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> has been accused of attempting to
dodge taxes in negotiating a <MONEY>$2.5-million</MONEY> ``golden parachute''
compensation agreement with the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> bank holding company he
heads.
   <PERSON>John P. LaWare</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Shawmut National Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> he was not sure a tax dodge was involved in the agreement,
which he said was offered to assure him his <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> annual income
until he reaches age 65. He turned 60 on <DATE>Feb. 20</DATE>.
   Despite concern expressed by <PERSON>Sen. William Proxmire</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>,
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Banking Committee</ORGANIZATION>, there was no indication
the issue would affect LaWare's nomination.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s latest nominee for a seat
on the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> has been accused of attempting to
dodge taxes in negotiating a <MONEY>$2.5-million</MONEY> ``golden parachute''
compensation agreement with the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> bank holding company he
heads.
   <PERSON>John P. LaWare</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Shawmut National Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> he was not sure a tax dodge was involved in the agreement,
which he said was offered to assure him his <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> annual income
until he reaches age 65. He turned 60 on <DATE>Feb. 20</DATE>.
   Despite concern expressed by <PERSON>Sen. William Proxmire</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>,
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Banking Committee</ORGANIZATION>, there was no indication
the issue would affect LaWare's nomination.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881011-0106 </DOCNO>
<HL> Not All Rich Got Richer, Forbes' Annual List Says </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Last <DATE>October</DATE>'s stock-market crash took its toll on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> fortunes, according to Forbes magazine's annual ranking of the 400 richest Americans. 

   Although <PERSON>Sam M. Walton</PERSON>, founder of <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart Stores Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, remains the richest person in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, the crash lopped off <PERCENT>31%</PERCENT> of his fortune -- it fell to <MONEY>$5.9 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$8.5 billion</MONEY>. 
By <DATE>August</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Walton</PERSON>'s fortune was back up to <MONEY>$6.7 billion</MONEY>, more than double that of second-ranked <PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON>, principal owner of <ORGANIZATION>Metromedia Co</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Three others in the top 10 of last year's Forbes 400 watched their fortunes drop <PERCENT>32%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> in the week after the crash. 
<ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch</ORGANIZATION>, the media magnate, who saw a <PERCENT>48%</PERCENT> loss, to <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$2.1 billion</MONEY>, in the week after the crash, fell to 35th place from eighth with a net worth of <MONEY>$1.08 billion</MONEY>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co</ORGANIZATION>. Chairman <PERSON>David Packard</PERSON>, who had a <PERCENT>32%</PERCENT> drop, to <MONEY>$1.9 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$2.87 billion</MONEY> after the crash, fell nine spots in the ranking to 13th with a fortune of <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Limited Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Chairman <PERSON>Leslie Wexner</PERSON>, who saw a <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> drop to <MONEY>$1.05 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$2.1 billion</MONEY> after the crash, fell to 49th place from 10th with <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>. 

   Of the 52 who dropped off the "Forbes 400" list, 22 fell because their stocks declined. 

   Although tops in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Walton</PERSON> is the sixth-richest person in the world. 
Above him on the list are three Japanese, a Korean and a Canadian. 
