<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06285224 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06285224 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Tiny Tim and his ukulele will perform Saturday with Dr.
Demento's 20th Anniversary Celebration at the Warfield Theater in San
Francisco.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; CELEBRITY; MAN; QA; PROFILE; INTERVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AT FIRST, he was just Herbert Khaury from Queens, a middle-aged man with long
hair and a photographic memory for the styles of ancient crooners.;   But then
he became Tiny Tim, playing smoky Greenwich Village clubs and winning a campy
cult. And finally, in the late '60s, he became a star.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TINY TIM: STILL ON HIS TIPTOES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  SAY ANYTHING  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     He had a hit album, "God Bless Tiny Tim." He played <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> for a
reported <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> a week. He married <PERSON>Miss Vicki</PERSON> on the <PERSON>Johnny Carson</PERSON> show.;  
Those days are gone. But Tiny <PERSON>Tim</PERSON>, 61 -- or is it 68? The reference books
disagree -- still tours. He still plays the ukulele and does pitch-perfect
impressions of <PERSON>Bing Crosby</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rudy Vallee</PERSON>. He's been in a Diet <ORGANIZATION>Pepsi</ORGANIZATION>
commercial and played a killer clown in a barely seen horror movie called
"Blood Harvest." He's still in show business.;   In a way, <ORGANIZATION>Tiny Tim</ORGANIZATION> is show
business. And every interview is a performance.; Q: I know you're a very
formal person. Should I call you Tiny Tim? Mr. Tiny? <PERSON>Mr. Tim</PERSON>?;   A: Oh Tiny's
all right. Tim is all right. It's all OK.;   Q: Well, what sort of songs do
you do in concert these days, Tiny?;   A: What I've done for years. Little
tidbits like "Grand Old Flag," "I'm a Yankee Doodle Dandy," "He's Got the
Whole World in His Hands" -- songs everyone knows. And in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, if I
don't forget, (sings) "<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, open your golden gate, you'll find no
strangers there, beside your door.";   Q: And "Tiptoe Through the Tulips"?;  
A: Every show, every time.;   Q: What made that such a big hit for you?;   A:
Originality is the key to success in any business. And that song had an
original sound. It was good enough to make them wonder "What's that?";   Q: A
while ago you were also doing some country and western songs. Are you still
pursuing that?;   A: Oh, whatever's popular I pursue. That's a good memory,
<PERSON>Mr. Whitty</PERSON>. That was back in <DATE>'88</DATE>. Yes, as a matter of fact. I had an album
that was supposed to come out. But the guy's check bounced. But there was a
single from that album released called "Leave Me Satisfied." And people loved
it until they found out it was <ORGANIZATION>Tiny Tim</ORGANIZATION>. (Sings with a drawl) "Someone else is
on your mind, it's plain to see / And you believe you love him more than me."
People said "That can't be Tiny Tim!";   Q: Sort of a different sound for
you.;   A: You ain't kidding.;   Q: So you think the name scared country fans
off a bit?;   A: Yes. The strange name and the appearance. You know, I've lost
more women with the way I look than the way I sound! Nothing I can do about it
though. . . . Originality brings success but what can I tell you. My second
wife is leaving <LOCATION>me.</LOCATION>;   Q: Really?;   A: She's going to her lawyer.;   Q: When
you married your first wife it was one of the highest-rated TV programs ever.
Do you ever see Miss <PERSON>Vicki</PERSON>? Or your daughter, <ORGANIZATION>Tulip</ORGANIZATION>?;   A: Tulip I take care
of every month. She gets about <MONEY>$320</MONEY>. She's working for the <ORGANIZATION>Teamsters</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>. She has a daughter . . . Miss <PERSON>Vicki</PERSON> has married a third time. I
don't see her or talk to her. There's no reason to talk to the past. There's
an old song in the '20s by <PERSON>Johnny Marvin</PERSON>: "After I've called you sweetheart,
how can I call you friend?" The same way it'll be with this one if she leaves.
But from what I hear <PERSON>Miss Vicki</PERSON> is the manager of a luggage shop in <LOCATION>Cherry
Hill</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>;   Q: So it looks like you're going to be available again.;   A:
Well, I don't know to who! Although Miss Jan hasn't gotten her divorce yet. .
. . But what can I tell you. I'm in love with a woman who doesn't love me.
She's 24 years old, she's in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, but she's a perfect woman, at least in my
mind. I fantasize about her every day.;   Q: Let's go back to music. What do
you think of rap? Any interest in a Tiny Tim rap song?;   A: Sure. I tell you,
whatever's popular in music, whether it's <DATE>1991</DATE> or 1891 it's the trend of
youth. Youth always brings their own music . . . Back in <DATE>1927</DATE>, <DATE>1925</DATE> there was
a song (sings) "Collegiate, collegiate, yes we are collegiate" -- that was a
new trend. Led into the flapper-dapper era. And parents were saying, "What's
happened to our youth?" Youth always brings its own music. And today it's rap,
and heavy metal, which I love.;   Q: Any favorite heavy metal bands?;   A: I
love Guns N' Roses. I have one of their cassettes floating around. I just
bought <ORGANIZATION>Metallica</ORGANIZATION> last week. I really like what's happening today. I even have
a heavy metal record.;   Q: You mean you recorded a heavy metal record?;   A:
Oh yes, with <ORGANIZATION>His Majesty</ORGANIZATION>'s Orchestra, a heavy metal band in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. I
recorded it in <DATE>1983</DATE>. (Sings) "I'm on the highway to hell . . ." It's yet to be
released here. It sold 80 copies in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> a couple of years ago and then it
dropped to zero. But that was 80 copies more than I'd sold in the <DATE>last 10
years.</DATE>;   Q: Do you have a favorite singer?;   A: There were some who were
outstanding. Of course <PERSON>Rudy Vallee</PERSON>, who I thought was a great romantic singer.
My favorite singer of about <DATE>1900</DATE> was <PERSON>Byron G. Harlan</PERSON>, who in my opinion was
the first popular singer of the American phonograph . . . And just a snip of
how he sounded (sings and plays the ukulele), "School days, school days, dear
old Golden Rule days . . ." Just love that sound. And the early <PERSON>Bing Crosby</PERSON>,
from '28 just to <DATE>'35</DATE>. I don't think there ever was a greater popular singer
than the young <PERSON>Mr. Crosby</PERSON> . . . (sings and plays the ukulele) "Lend your
little ear to my plea, lend a little cheer to my plea . . ." I love that early
Bing sound. And <PERSON>Harry Richman</PERSON> . . . (sings, again) "Gee but it's great,
staying out late, walking my baby back ho-o-o-ome." He knocked them dead.;  
Q: <PERSON>Rudy Vallee</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bing Crosby</PERSON> were both performing into their 70s and beyond.
Can you see yourself still doing this then?;   A: If I'm alive and well and
able to get on stage. But I tell you, when I do my own shows -- all these
artists, <PERSON>Wayne Newton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Frank Sinatra</PERSON> who do hour shows -- I only like to do
about 20 minutes. In the old days of vaudeville, that's all they did.;   Q:
Always leave 'em wanting more?;   A: Oh yes. My theory is hit 'em with a
couple of great songs, make them remember you and leave while you're ahead.
Hit 'em with "Grand Old Flag" and go out with "Tiptoe Through the Tulips" and
they'll say, "Well -- he wasn't as bad as we thought."; Tiny <PERSON>Tim; Dr.
Demento</PERSON>'s 20th Anniversary Celebration, with <PERSON>Bobby</PERSON> "Boris" <PERSON>Pickett</PERSON>, <PERSON>Eddie</PERSON> "The
Old Philosopher" <PERSON>Lawrence</PERSON> and "Weird Al" <PERSON>Yankovic</PERSON>; When: <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> and
<TIME>11 p.m.</TIME>; Where: <ORGANIZATION>Warfield Theater</ORGANIZATION>, 982 Market St., <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; Tickets: <MONEY>$19</MONEY>
floor, <MONEY>$18</MONEY> balcony; (510) 762-BASS, (408) 998-BASS.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  STEPHEN WHITTY, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911011  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  20  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,258  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, October 11, 1991
00285224,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900312-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-12-90 2015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     03-12 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LANGLEY, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taking ukuleles to <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>
sounds about as misplaced as shipping coals to <ORGANIZATION>Newcastle</ORGANIZATION>.
   But that's what 25 Vancouver-area students, aged 9 to 19, are
doing this week.
   ``Even though the ukulele is the key instrument in their society
_ it's as Hawaiian as the grass skirt _ the school authorities over
there want to learn the Canadian teaching methods we use which are
so successful,'' said <PERSON>Peter Luongo</PERSON>, vice principal and music
specialist at <PERSON>Alice Brown</PERSON> elementary.
   The school has become so skilled at teaching the four-stringed,
guitarlike instrument that word has reached <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>.
   The ukulele, introduced from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> into the <LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION>
about <DATE>1879</DATE>, was first used in Canadian schools in the Maritime
provinces about 20 years ago to teach music, he said.
   ``It came to <LOCATION>Langley</LOCATION> about 15 years ago and we got some really
keen kids,'' he said. ``I picked up the program when I came here
and developed a senior honors group.''
   The students have played in concerts across <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and will pay
for most of the 10-day trip beginning <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``We will be given a lot of hospitality but we'll be going to
schools that are very meager compared to ours and I think our
students will learn a lot about the other side of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> _ it's not
all plush hotels,'' <PERSON>Luongo</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taking ukuleles to <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>
sounds about as misplaced as shipping coals to <ORGANIZATION>Newcastle</ORGANIZATION>.
   But that's what 25 Vancouver-area students, aged 9 to 19, are
doing this week.
   ``Even though the ukulele is the key instrument in their society
_ it's as Hawaiian as the grass skirt _ the school authorities over
there want to learn the Canadian teaching methods we use which are
so successful,'' said <PERSON>Peter Luongo</PERSON>, vice principal and music
specialist at <PERSON>Alice Brown</PERSON> elementary.
   The school has become so skilled at teaching the four-stringed,
guitarlike instrument that word has reached <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>.
   The ukulele, introduced from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> into the <LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION>
about <DATE>1879</DATE>, was first used in Canadian schools in the Maritime
provinces about 20 years ago to teach music, he said.
   ``It came to <LOCATION>Langley</LOCATION> about 15 years ago and we got some really
keen kids,'' he said. ``I picked up the program when I came here
and developed a senior honors group.''
   The students have played in concerts across <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and will pay
for most of the 10-day trip beginning <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``We will be given a lot of hospitality but we'll be going to
schools that are very meager compared to ours and I think our
students will learn a lot about the other side of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> _ it's not
all plush hotels,'' <PERSON>Luongo</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ARLINGTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taking ukuleles to <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>
sounds about as misplaced as shipping coals to <ORGANIZATION>Newcastle</ORGANIZATION>.
   But that's what 25 Vancouver-area students, aged 9 to 19, are
doing this week.
   ``Even though the ukulele is the key instrument in their society
_ it's as Hawaiian as the grass skirt _ the school authorities over
there want to learn the Canadian teaching methods we use which are
so successful,'' said <PERSON>Peter Luongo</PERSON>, vice principal and music
specialist at <PERSON>Alice Brown</PERSON> elementary.
   The school has become so skilled at teaching the four-stringed,
guitarlike instrument that word has reached <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>.
   The ukulele, introduced from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> into the <LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION>
about <DATE>1879</DATE>, was first used in Canadian schools in the Maritime
provinces about 20 years ago to teach music, he said.
   ``It came to <LOCATION>Langley</LOCATION> about 15 years ago and we got some really
keen kids,'' he said. ``I picked up the program when I came here
and developed a senior honors group.''
   The students have played in concerts across <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and will pay
for most of the 10-day trip beginning <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``We will be given a lot of hospitality but we'll be going to
schools that are very meager compared to ours and I think our
students will learn a lot about the other side of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> _ it's not
all plush hotels,'' <PERSON>Luongo</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072690-0095 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 252604 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 26, 1990, Thursday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Ventura County Life; Part J; Page 4; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
975 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MUSIC: THE FOLK SCENE; 
</P>
<P>
'HOOTS' LIVE ON; 
</P>
<P>
MUSICIANS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTY ARE PICKING AND STRUMMING TO KEEP A GRASS-ROOTS 
SOUND ALIVE. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMELIA CHAFFEE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Does much of today's rock 'n' roll make you reel? Do you find yourself tearing 
up when you hear a refrain of "Puff, the Magic Dragon?" Fear not, there is an 
antidote for what ails you. Folk music is alive in <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Although this grass-roots music enjoys a popular resurgence from time to time, 
it has always had a faithful following and folk musicians will keep on picking 
and strumming no matter what comes and goes on the hit charts. 
</P>
<P>
Folk music itself represents the creative expression of people worldwide. But 
what is typically thought of as American folk music comes from many ethnic 
influences including black gospel, Irish working and drinking songs and 
Appalachian love ballads. While the omnipresent guitar has become the symbol of 
folk music, the banjo, fiddle, mandolin, harp, autoharp and dulcimer are also 
used extensively. 
</P>
<P>
The Ventura folk scene offers plenty of opportunities for those who enjoy 
participating as well as those who don't. Hootenannies, or "Hoots" for short, 
are essentially sing-alongs and are held several times a week in the homes of 
various enthusiasts who call themselves the Songmakers. 
</P>
<P>
The group has been meeting continuously since it first got together in the '40s 
as a way for songwriters to share their material with their fellow composers. 
Their most famous member has been American folk singer <PERSON>Pete Seeger</PERSON>, member 
<PERSON>Jackie Smith</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The Songmakers, which boasts 300 paid members, has grown to include those who 
enjoy singing and playing as well as writing folk music. On any given evening, 
20 to 30 musicians gather to listen to one anothers original compositions or 
interpretations of more traditional melodies. All instruments and levels of 
ability are welcome, both professional and amateur, said <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, as the emphasis 
is on fun. 
</P>
<P>
The Ventura chapter meets in <LOCATION>Simi Valley</LOCATION> every <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> as well as the third 
<DATE>Friday</DATE> of each month. Call (805) 527-7340 for more information. There is no 
charge. 
</P>
<P>
Several cities in the county also offer <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> concerts for those who 
prefer to sit back rather than sing along. The oldest in the series is a 
"coffeehouse" in <LOCATION>Thousand Oaks</LOCATION>, which is held the first <DATE>Friday</DATE> of each month. 
Now in its 10th year, this event draws both local and out-of-the-area 
musicians. 
</P>
<P>
This month, <PERSON>Paul Sanchez</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Rabbit MacKay</ORGANIZATION>, two <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION> residents, 
performed a combination of folk, blues, country, rock and original music. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>, <PERSON>Mickey Bochard</PERSON>, a mother-and-daughter contemporary gospel duo are 
scheduled to perform. Call (805) 499-4355, the Arts Council of the <LOCATION>Conejo 
Valley</LOCATION>, for more information on the <DATE>August</DATE> concert. Admission is free. 
</P>
<P>
In response to the many musicians who wanted another showcase for their 
talents, <ORGANIZATION>Newbury Park</ORGANIZATION> started its own series of concerts called <ORGANIZATION>Fireside 
Offerings</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Dawn Kuznkowski</PERSON>, program organizer and musician. Now, <DATE>five 
years later</DATE>, 100 folk music lovers gather in a cozy nook of the <ORGANIZATION>Borchard 
Community Center</ORGANIZATION> on the second <DATE>Friday</DATE> of each month to hear anything from 
foot-stomping bluegrass fiddles to twanging Hawaiian ukuleles. 
</P>
<P>
The center attracts everything from semiprofessional performers to amateurs, 
with the only restriction being that all performers play acoustic instruments. 
</P>
<P>
This month's offerings included a balladeer from the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> area, <PERSON>Mark 
Levy</PERSON>, who performed original political satire/protest songs, followed by mother 
and daughter, <PERSON>Mary</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dana Crooks</PERSON>, who sang haunting Appalachian harmonies, 
and continuing with local musicians <PERSON>Jim St. Ours</PERSON>, <PERSON>Paul Sanchez</PERSON> and <PERSON>Glenn 
Scrivner</PERSON>, who played a variety of traditional ballads. They are also preparing 
to perform at the county fair later this <DATE>summer</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The next concert will be <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>. The performance, like all Fireside Offerings, 
is a surprise for the audience, said <PERSON>Kuznkowski</PERSON>, since the evening agenda isn't 
set until right before concert time. For more information, call (805) 498-3124 
or 495-5118. A <MONEY>$2</MONEY> donation is requested and refreshments are served. 
</P>
<P>
Camarillo is the latest community to catch the folk vision, and has been 
hosting a third-Friday-of-the-month "Camarillo Cafe" at the "O" Club at the 
<LOCATION>Camarillo Airport</LOCATION> for the past year. It goes from <TIME>8 p.m. to 12 a.m.</TIME>, event 
coordinator <PERSON>Jack Zigray</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The cafe has been around for nearly a year and offers an eclectic mix of 
acoustic music, from traditional folk and blues to classical and even some rock 
'n' roll (of course, without amplifiers). 
</P>
<P>
At the <DATE>July</DATE> show, <PERSON>Harvey Taylor</PERSON> played blues and ragtime acoustic guitar, 
<PERSON>Barbara Brussels</PERSON> sang show tunes, guitarist and singer <ORGANIZATION>Elyna Le Fevre</ORGANIZATION> performed 
traditional folk songs, followed by acoustic duo <PERSON>Jerry Faigin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Linda Marie</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
For information on the <DATE>August</DATE> show, call (805) 482-1996, 482-0978 or 482-0986. 
Concerts sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>Pleasant Valley Recreation</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Park District</ORGANIZATION> are free and 
refreshments are served. 
</P>
<P>
No attempt at covering folk music in the county would be complete without 
mentioning two popular groups who perform regularly. The Old <ORGANIZATION>Time Fiddlers 
Assn.</ORGANIZATION>, a group of 30 or more, get together on the second and <DATE>fourth Sundays</DATE> of 
each month at the <ORGANIZATION>Community Center</ORGANIZATION> in Oak View to play their old favorites. 
Families bring blankets and picnics. A snack bar is also available. The event 
is free. Call (805) 486-8744 or 646-1583 for details. 
</P>
<P>
Another group is the Acousticats. Until recently, they called themselves The 
<PERSON>Phil Salazar</PERSON> Band and played predominantly bluegrass. According to <PERSON>Kim Louks</PERSON>, 
wife of the band's leader, the five-member group has had a change of style. 
They now characterize their music as "new acoustic," which is "progressive with 
traditional folk and jazz influences." 
</P>
<P>
The Acousticats will play at <ORGANIZATION>Henson's Music Festival</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 11</DATE>. 
Call (805) 482-6115 for details. 
</P>
<P>
* ON THE COVER: <ORGANIZATION>Mark Levy of Boulder Creek</ORGANIZATION> performs at the <ORGANIZATION>Borchard Community 
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Newbury Park</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mary Crooks of Simi Valley delivers a soft melody at a gathering of folk 
singers at the Borchard Community Center in Newbury Park. GEORGE WOLF / For The 
Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880420-0257 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-20-88 0851EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-ReligionintheNews Adv22   04-20 0805</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Religion in the News, Adv 22,0829</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv22</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Fri PMs April 22, or thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Hawaiian Pastor Advocates Ukulele, A Formula And Aloha</HEAD>
<NOTE>With Laserphoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE W. CORNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Religion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Among the the flowers, palms and deep-blue
waters of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, a widely esteemed native minister, the Rev.
<PERSON>Abraham K. Akaka</PERSON>, bears a message of the ukulele _ for islanders
and the world.
   To the state's singularly mixed culture of races, traditions and
ancestry, he advises, ``Think of yourselves as strings on a
ukulele, each different from the other strings, each preserving its
own tone, yet all necessary to make that beautiful harmony.''
   The objective, he said in a telephone interview, is unity in
diversity, of maintaining valued differences to enrich the whole,
something <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> particularly manifests, and the world needs.
   ``The key to it is that all the strings, all the races, nations
and cultures of mankind need to be tuned to one tuner, God, whose
name is love,'' <PERSON>Akaka</PERSON> said. ``When they do that, they retain their
individuality, but in a way that accepts the other strings, in
unity and harmony.''
   Akaka, 71, pastor emeritus of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s oldest church, the
<ORGANIZATION>Kawaiahao Church</ORGANIZATION> in downtown <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>, and among few clergymen of
original Hawaiian descent, strums the ukulele himself.
   He also has a special formula for diversified mutuality.
   It's a gentle revision of <PERSON>Albert Einstein</PERSON>'s famous formula,
energy equals mass times the speed of light squared, by which the
first atomic chain reaction was achieved in <DATE>1942</DATE> while <PERSON>Akaka</PERSON> was in
seminary in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   For different purposes, he proposes his own formula: CM
(creative mutuality) squared equals P (prosperous peace).
   ``It holds great hope for the future of mankind,'' he said. ``If
foreign policies of all nations used the formula, if every family
used it, every corporation and government used it, it would change
the world.
   Akaka for 28 years led the 1,000-member <LOCATION>Kawaiahao</LOCATION> church, built
in the <DATE>1830s</DATE> of cream-colored coral from island reefs. It's
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s only church with royal pews _ for <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s one-time
monarchy. He retired in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   But he keeps busy _ speaking, leading weddings and funerals,
blessing new homes, stores and other buildings. Gifts for his
services go to a foundation for native Hawaiian scholarships and to
help the needy.
   ``You cannot retire from the Lord,'' he said.
   More than a third of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s million people are Christians,
Protestants and Roman Catholics, including most Caucasians and the
native minority, while nearly a third are Buddhist, the rest
Shintoists or other faiths.
   ``We do not have religious strife,'' <PERSON>Akaka</PERSON> said.
   A clergyman of the <ORGANIZATION>United Church of Christ</ORGANIZATION>, he said the
different religious groups have become ``more and more cooperative
in dealing with issues affecting the well-being of the people.''
   He called modern mass communications media ``an instrument of
God, binding people closer, life with life, nation with nation,
culture with culture, race with race, enabling them to learn about
each other and understand each other.''
   That multicultural quality characterizes <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, where <PERCENT>24.5
percent</PERCENT> of the population is Caucasian, <PERCENT>23 percent</PERCENT> is of Japanese
ancestry, <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> is Hawaiian and part-Hawaiian, <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT>
Filipino, and smaller numbers of Chinese, <LOCATION>Koreans</LOCATION>, Samoans and
blacks.
   Native Hawaiians such as <PERSON>Akaka</PERSON> are descended from Polynesians
who came in large canoes from legendary ``Hawaiki'' (believed to be
<LOCATION>Marquesas Island</LOCATION>) to the west as long as 2,000 years ago.
   A second wave came from <LOCATION>Tahiti</LOCATION> around <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> 1000. The Hawaiians
lived in isolation from the world until a British naval officer,
Capt. <PERSON>James Cook</PERSON>, came on the lovely isles in <DATE>1778</DATE>.
   The native religion was polytheistic, with idols to many gods
and goddesses. After the monarchy developed, <PERSON>Queen Kaahumanu</PERSON> in
<DATE>1819</DATE> abolished the native religion.
   The gap soon was filled by Protestant missionaries, first sent
in <DATE>1820</DATE> by Congregationalist antecedants of <ORGANIZATION>Akaka</ORGANIZATION>'s present
denomination.
   They set up schools and churches, learned the Hawaiian language,
putting it into writing for the first time, introduced democratic
principles. Roman Catholic missionaries came in <DATE>1827</DATE>. Natives
overwhelmingly became Christians.
   <PERSON>Akaka</PERSON> said that unlike cases in which invading Western
civiliation ``overturned and sometimes destroyed native cultures,
the Hawaiian people were pretty fortunate. Large credit is due to
work of the missionaries.''
   Much of ``our culture and history was preserved and
perpetuated,'' <PERSON>Akaka</PERSON> said. `We are Americans today. We love our
country, love the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>... But like any other people, we
love our roots.''
   Noting the names of the main old gods, ``Wakea'' and ``Papa,''
mean space and place _ ``arms that embrace all humanity,'' he added:
   ``That is the meaning of <LOCATION>Aloha</LOCATION>, the name that the people chose
for our state, the <ORGANIZATION>Aloha State</ORGANIZATION>. It emphasizes love for all people.
Aloha means we love you, care for you, welcome you. It expresses
that we are a family belonging to each other.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv22</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090389-0131 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 102863 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 3, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Page 53; Calendar Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
903 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GEORGE BENSON RETURNS TO HIS JAZZ ROOTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEONARD FEATHER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>George Benson</PERSON> is the <PERSON>Nat King Cole</PERSON> of the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. Like <PERSON>Cole</PERSON>, he earned fame as 
an instrumentalist before reaching world renown as a singer. 
</P>
<P>
Now, just as <PERSON>Cole</PERSON> did late in his career, he has made an album that reminds the 
public of his origins. "Tenderly" (<ORGANIZATION>Warner Bros.</ORGANIZATION> 25907), in which the eminent 
jazz pianist <PERSON>McCoy Tyner</PERSON> plays a major role, entered the jazz chart <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE> and 
has already leaped to the No. 1 spot. 
</P>
<P>
The guitarist, whose vocal personality made a fortune for him, plays on almost 
every track; three are strictly instrumental and the title cut is a guitar 
solo. 
</P>
<P>
"Even my pop fans like it," he said, just before leaving for a week in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>. 
"They like the ballady things. My wife fell in love with 'This Is All I Ask.' 
But what knocked me out was that my mother's favorite was 'I Could Write a 
Book,' which is strictly a jazz thing. And my stepfather, who taught me how to 
play ukulele and then guitar, starting when I was 9, now says that his faith in 
my playing is reaffirmed! He was always very helpful but sometimes very 
critical -- told me I was playing too fast and he couldn't follow me. But when 
he heard this album he said, 'Boy, that's what I call guitar playing!' " 
</P>
<P>
Benson, who will appear at the Wiltern Theatre <DATE>Sept. 22-25</DATE>, using his regular 
sidemen and an orchestra, recalls that his collaboration with <PERSON>Tyner</PERSON> came about 
by sheer chance. "Last year, on my way to the <ORGANIZATION>Blue Note Club</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, I was 
listening to a jazz program on the radio and they played a tune from an old 
<PERSON>Johnny Hartman</PERSON> album. When they said <PERSON>McCoy Tyner</PERSON> was the pianist on it, I said 
to myself, 'He must have been a baby back then!' But he was already musically 
mature." (The album was made in <DATE>1963</DATE> with <PERSON>John Coltrane</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tyner</PERSON>, then 24, 
accompanying <PERSON>Hartman</PERSON>.) 
</P>
<P>
An idea occurred to <PERSON>Benson</PERSON>. "I realized how well McCoy plays behind vocalists, 
and of course we're both instrumentalists. I decided to get in touch with him. 
Our sons are close friends -- they're both together now. The next day, <PERSON>McCoy</PERSON>'s 
son was over at my house and I said 'Get in touch with your pop and ask him if 
he'd like to make a record with me.' His father called back from <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and 
said he would." 
</P>
<P>
Aware that record companies, when confronted with noncommercial projects, react 
as if they have been asked to commit suicide, <PERSON>Benson</PERSON> went into a studio and 
produced the first five songs on his own. "The Japanese booked us as soon as 
word reached them that we were in the studio! Then <PERSON>George Wein</PERSON> got word of the 
record and set us up with a European tour." 
</P>
<P>
Having launched the idea, <PERSON>Benson</PERSON> got in touch his producer, <PERSON>Tommy Li Puma</PERSON>. 
"Tommy then contacted the record company and got them real excited. Even <PERSON>Mo 
Ostin</PERSON>, the chairman of the board at <ORGANIZATION>Warners</ORGANIZATION>, called and said, '<PERSON>George</PERSON>, this is 
a gutsy move, to do an album like that at this time in your career.' " 
</P>
<P>
The three-week European tour lived up to everyone's expectations. "We had a lot 
of fans who came because they'd heard my name, but many of them knew <PERSON>McCoy</PERSON>'s 
name and were curious to see what was going to happen." 
</P>
<P>
Coincidentally, <PERSON>Benson</PERSON> found himself involved in several other jazz 
partnerships. "I guest-starred with <ORGANIZATION>Dizzy Gillespie</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Boy, was he 
packing them in! I like working with the old-timers because that's really where 
I learned to play; in fact, when I was growing up, I always wanted to get into 
that bag. My first recorded attempts at that kind of music were for <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, 
which is why <PERSON>John Hammond</PERSON> liked me, I guess." (The late <PERSON>John Hammond</PERSON> recorded 
<PERSON>Benson</PERSON> in a series of strictly instrumental small group sessions in <DATE>1966-67</DATE>. 
"The <PERSON>George Benson</PERSON> Cookbook" is still available only in cassette form on 
CS9413.) 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, typically, offered <PERSON>Benson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tyner</PERSON> the most wide-ranging chances to 
stretch out. "Over there, we had additional help from <ORGANIZATION>Freddie Hubbard</ORGANIZATION> on 
trumpet and <PERSON>Joe Henderson</PERSON> on saxophone. That exciting horn sound gave us even 
more of a jazz flavor," <PERSON>Benson</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1966</DATE>, playing in the <LOCATION>Newport Jazz Festival</LOCATION>'s Guitar Workshop, <PERSON>Benson</PERSON> was 
hailed by Down Beat as "a young guitarist with roots in <PERSON>Charlie Christian</PERSON> and a 
wonderful beat." The reference to Christian, who revolutionized jazz guitar in 
his 1939-40 recordings with <PERSON>Benny Goodman</PERSON>, came to mind again last <DATE>June</DATE> when 
<PERSON>Benson</PERSON> was teamed with <PERSON>Lionel Hampton</PERSON> in a <ORGANIZATION>Carnegie Hall</ORGANIZATION> concert, "Hamp and 
<PERSON>George Salute Benny</PERSON>." "That was the greatest honor in the world," he says, 
"sitting in for <PERSON>Charlie Christian</PERSON> and bringing back the tunes he and <PERSON>Benny</PERSON> and 
Lionel played back then." (<PERSON>Benson</PERSON> played and recorded briefly with <PERSON>Goodman</PERSON> in 
the '70s.) 
</P>
<P>
Despite the wealth and worldwide acclaim his singing has brought him, <PERSON>Benson</PERSON> 
(and again the parallel with <PERSON>Nat King Cole</PERSON> is clear) still wants to retain the 
respect of the musicians and jazz fans who were his original admirers. "It's 
real nice," he says, "to do an album like this new one and have some jazz 
people say appreciate things about you." 
</P>
<P>
Benson's success seems to have mellowed him; part of the cause, or possibly the 
effect, may be his religious convictions. 
</P>
<P>
"I've been a dedicated <ORGANIZATION>Jehovah</ORGANIZATION>'s Witness for 10 years," he says, "and I studied 
the <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION> long before that. I think I've changed my ways a little from my wild 
young days. I'm very careful in what I do; I'm no saint, but I do try to keep 
away from anything that will bring reproach on me. Religion has helped me 
escape some pitfalls -- helped me, I like to think, become a better man." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, George Benson's "Tenderly" leaped to No. 1 on jazz chart. ART WILKINSON 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BENSON, GEORGE; MUSICIANS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031689-0030 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 31282 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 16, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 1; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
668 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JACK SMITH: IN HAWAII, HOW GREEN IS HIS VALLEY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Jack Smith 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> the lush <LOCATION>Nuuanu Valley</LOCATION> rises through a pass in the dark green 
mountains to a precipice called the pali. It is a place where people often stop 
and park their cars to peer from a viewpoint above the stupendous cliff out 
over the velvet green coastal plain below. 
</P>
<P>
Our friend <PERSON>Harry Albright</PERSON> drove us up through the valley through vegetation so 
green and thick it made us forget for a moment the concrete excrescence that 
<LOCATION>Waikiki</LOCATION> had become. From the pali we could see the rugged windward shore of the 
island, and the town of <LOCATION>Kaneohe</LOCATION>. It was still relatively small and low in 
profile. 
</P>
<P>
For nearly two years one of my jobs on the <TIME>night</TIME> desk of the Advertiser had 
been to call the local police departments in <LOCATION>Kaneohe</LOCATION> and other outposts on the 
island to ask if there was any news. The routine never varied: 
</P>
<P>
"This is the Advertiser. Any news tonight?" 
</P>
<P>
"No. No news tonight." 
</P>
<P>
The only time they ever had any news was on <DATE>Dec. 7, 1941</DATE>, and that night I 
never bothered to call. We had enough news. 
</P>
<P>
My wife remembered standing at the pali one day when the eminent pianist <PERSON>Artur 
Rubinstein</PERSON> walked up and stood beside her. He was playing that night in 
<LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> and she went to hear him. Culture is where you find it. 
</P>
<P>
The pali is famous in Hawaiian legend. King Kamehameha, who brought all the 
<LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION> under his crown, is said to have driven the locals to the pali 
and pushed them over, as commemorated in the popular song (as I remember it): 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>King Kamehameha</PERSON>, conqueror of the Islands, 
</P>
<P>
Became a famous hero one day. 
</P>
<P>
He conquered the native army, 
</P>
<P>
And pushed them over the pali 
</P>
<P>
And crowned himself 
</P>
<P>
the king of <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii Nei</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
We drove back down through <LOCATION>Waikiki</LOCATION> and around <ORGANIZATION>Diamond Head</ORGANIZATION> and up into its 
crater, a shallow bowl that has become a park. The old gun emplacements could 
still be seen around its crest. It was supposed to make Oahu impregnable, but 
on <DATE>Dec. 7</DATE> it was helpless against the attack by air. 
</P>
<P>
That evening we dined with three shipmates in the Orchids Room of the 
<LOCATION>Halekulani</LOCATION>, one of the three remaining hotels of the prewar era. It had been a 
charming retreat, a low central building surrounded by cottages. Now the 
cottages were gone, of course, replaced by concrete towers, but the hotel 
itself looked reminiscent of the original, though modernized. 
</P>
<P>
Before dining we had a drink on the terrace overlooking <LOCATION>Waikiki Beach</LOCATION>. Towering 
palm trees were lighted dramatically. A trio of Hawaiian musicians sang the old 
favorites, among them "Farewell My Tane." 
</P>
<P>
My chest tightened. I had learned that song as a scullion on the <ORGANIZATION>S.S. Monterey</ORGANIZATION>. 
At night after our watch the chief scullion, a pure Hawaiian, would get out his 
ukulele and sing Hawaiian songs. My favorite of all he sang was "Farewell My 
Tane." 
</P>
<P>
I used to lie on my bunk in the ship's glory hole (that part of the forecastle 
where the lower forms of marine life lived) and wonder if I would ever meet my 
Tane, and whether our relationship would be that poignant. 
</P>
<P>
 Farewell my <PERSON>Tane</PERSON>, child of a coral sea 
</P>
<P>
We dreamed of heaven, now you've forgotten me 
</P>
<P>
As it turned out, I never met my Tane. I married a haole girl, and we are still 
together. 
</P>
<P>
In the morning the hostess at our hotel's restaurant asked whether we wanted 
the American or the Japanese buffet. "What's in the Japanese?" I asked naively. 
"Rice, raw fish . . . ,"she began. "American," I interrupted. 
</P>
<P>
I know the war is over. I am even willing to concede that in some respects the 
Japanese won. But my acceptance of things Japanese does not extend to raw fish. 
</P>
<P>
We flew home in a plane so crowded that my wife and I, having changed from a 
later flight, couldn't sit together. Oh well, we had survived longer 
separations. 
</P>
<P>
I ordered white wine with lunch and the flight attendant brought me a small 
can. The weather was rough, and when I opened it, I discovered from the spots 
on my necktie and my pants, alas, that it was red. 
</P>
<P>
But who could complain? At least the door didn't blow out in flight. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890828-0223 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-28-89 2105EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--Bradley Adv08-10   08-28 0784</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Bradley, Adv 08-10,0806</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv08-10</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Sept 8-10 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Nashville Sound: Harold Bradley Played and Played and Played</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NS1 of Aug. 28.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOE EDWARDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress <PERSON>Sissy Spacek</PERSON>, after recording the
soundtrack to the <DATE>1980</DATE> movie ``Coal Miner's Daughter,'' handed
guitar player <PERSON>Harold Bradley</PERSON> a note.
   ``Pick them strings, guitar man. Loved working with you,'' it
said.
   Bradley did pick. And pick. And pick.
   In the city known worldwide for its guitar players, <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> has
been the most productive. <PERSON>Chet Atkins</PERSON> is more famous, and <PERSON>Roy Clark</PERSON>
helped popularize the term ``picker,'' but <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> has been more
prolific.
   In a career spanning 43 years, the 63-year-old <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> has played
in literally thousands of recording sessions. No one in <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>,
perhaps no one else anywhere, comes close to matching his output.
   ``My career sounds like a lie, but it's really happened,''
<PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> says calmly in a manner that belies the fervor with which he
plays.
   Twelve of the records on which he played with <ORGANIZATION>Elvis Presley</ORGANIZATION>
became million-sellers. Just a few of the other singers he's
accompanied include <PERSON>Willie Nelson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Marie Osmond</PERSON>, <PERSON>Roger Miller</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Loretta Lynn</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Davidson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Patsy Cline</PERSON>, <PERSON>Tom Jones</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Buddy Holly</ORGANIZATION>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Everly Brothers</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Hank Williams</PERSON>, <PERSON>Conway Twitty</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Charley Pride</LOCATION> and
<PERSON>Joan Baez</PERSON>.
   He's played on movie soundtracks such as ``Pink Cadillac'' and
``Smokey and the Bandit II'' in addition to ``Coal Miner's
Daughter.''
   A few of the songs on which he's played include ``Jingle Bell
Rock,'' ``Only the Lonely,'' ``Stand by Your Man,'' ``I'm Sorry,''
``King of the Road,'' ``It's Such a Pretty World Today'' and ``Make
the World Go Away.''
   For good measure, he played at the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1978</DATE>,
accompanying country music stars <PERSON>Tom T. Hall</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lynn</PERSON> and <PERSON>Twitty</PERSON> who
were invited by President <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> to provide some down-home
entertainment.
   This illustrious production came from a musician who taught
himself how to play at age 15 and still practices an average of a
couple hours a day. Even at age 45, he briefly took lessons in
classical music.
   ``I love it,'' he says as he approaches a half-century of
plucking the strings. ``I love to practice. You have to practice.
There is no end to being a good guitar player.
   ``It's like you've got this big jigsaw puzzle in front of you.
You put a few pieces in and you get an idea of the picture. Then you
realize there's more pieces on the outside so you keep trying to put
them in. And you realize you can never fill in the whole thing.''
   Bradley, who does not sing, has been enterprising as well as
busy. For sound effects, he once went to his car and got a pair of
tire chains, returned to the studio and dropped them to the floor
during the recording session for the song ``Chain Gang.''
   He has no preference among the various electric or acoustical
guitars, saying simply: ``I prefer what I'm playing at the time. I
like to play all of 'em.''
   An engaging man with volumes of scrapbooks and memorabilia about
his career, <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> believes versatility has been his helpmate as
much as ability.
   ``I don't know that I am good. But I can offer experience. I've
been very lucky to play a wide variety of music: country, big band,
rock 'n' roll, gospel.
   ``If I played one kind, I wouldn't have been around this long. If
I was a rock 'n' roll specialist, they would not have needed me on
other recordings that required different abilities.''
   He also plays other instruments, joking that ``I play two in
self-defense, the banjo and mandolin.''
   He says his biggest thrills are those indescribable moments when
musicians combine for special sounds in the studio.
   ``When something magic happens, you get a tremendous high. You
can't turn creativity off and on like water. I've enjoyed that
several times with several artists where it was such a marvelous
music experience that you felt something great happened.''
   Bradley feels that he is still getting better except for his rock
'n' roll playing.
   ``To do that, you have to go out and play it,'' he said. ``And I
play a certain style, rockabilly style, pretty good. But to go out
and play like <PERSON>Van Halen</PERSON> and those guys, no, I'll never do that. But
he'll never come here and play the guitar, the bass guitar, the
banjo, the mandolin, the ukulele. So it's kind of a tradeoff.
   ``What you're buying if you buy me is experience and intonation
and ability. But even that can't guarantee a hit record. The public
decides that.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Sept 8-10</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900907-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-07-90 1444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e AM-APArts:Geldof Adv11   09-07 0845</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AP Arts: Geldof, Adv11,0862</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv11</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Tuesday AMs, Sept. 11, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Sir Bob Picks Up His Guitar and Plays</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY McSHANE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Bob Geldof</PERSON>, musician, is back.
   Not <PERSON>St. Bob</PERSON>, the humanitarian of British tabloid headlines. Not
Sir <PERSON>Bob</PERSON>, knighted by <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth</PERSON> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, nominated for the
Nobel Peace Prize that same year. Not author <PERSON>Bob</PERSON>, who's already
written a best-selling autobiography, ``Is That It?'' And not
businessman <PERSON>Bob</PERSON>, who oversaw millions and <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in
contributions for the starving Third World.
   Geldof remains chairman of the board of trustees for Band Aid,
although he says the organization will cease to exist fairly soon.
But his main focus these days is ``The Vegetarians of Love,'' his
critically acclaimed second solo album.
   This is no Boomtown Rats rock 'n' roll extravaganza; <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> has
instead assembled a mostly acoustic band featuring accordion,
violins, flute, tin whistle, mandolin and ukulele.
   ``For me, I suppose, it's simply a reaction to stuff I hear on
the radio which I don't like _ basically, house music and New Kids
on the Block or <PERSON>Kylie Minogue</PERSON>,'' <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> said in a recent interview.
   For the new album, <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> enlisted an old friend _ ex-Rats
bassist <PERSON>Pete Briquette</PERSON> _ and four traditional musicians he'd never
met. They recorded 28 songs in five days; any song that didn't
click after three takes was thrown out. Geldof improvised many of
the lyrics on the spot.
   ``I came in on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, said hello to four guys I didn't
know ... I'd bash out a song and say, `Right! OK, let's go,' ''
<PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> recalled of the session.
   ``They'd say, `What do you want me to play?' I'd say, `Whatever
you want to play.' They'd say, `Where do you want me to play it?'
I'd say, `Wherever you feel its right.' And `When does the song
finish?' And I'd say, `When it stops, it's over.' ''
   The spontaneity shows. On ``A Gospel Song,'' <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> tells the
band ``middle eight coming up'' during an instrumental break.
Geldof asks at the start of another cut, ``Are we rolling?'' And at
the end of ``The Great Song of Indifference,'' the entire band is
heard laughing loudly.
   ``Indifference'' is already a Top 40 hit in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. ``The last
thing everybody expected was this Irish pub song. And it became a
big dance hit, you know? Thirteenth-century dance music,'' says
<PERSON>Geldof</PERSON>, laughing.
   After almost a decade as front man for the New Wave-era Boomtown
Rats, <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> became a household name in <DATE>1984</DATE> _ by organizing the
cream of British musicians to record ``Do They Know It's
Christmas?'' and raise money for African famine victims.
   That was followed by <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> for <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s ``We Are the World'' and
the internationally televised Live Aid benefit. For two years,
<PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> met with heads of state and political power brokers; the
scruffy Irishman was photographed with everyone from <ORGANIZATION>Nobelist
Mother Theresa</ORGANIZATION> to British Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON>.
   Geldof looks back on those days with pride tempered by the
realization there was only so much that could be done.
   ``I mean, I never said we were going to stop world poverty or
world hunger. I said it was a Band-Aid. `You don't put a Band-Aid
on a gaping wound,' if I remember, was the quote at the time,''
said <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON>.
   ``That wasn't the function, to stop world hunger. It was to
raise the issue to the top of the political agenda, and we did
that.''
   Geldof is still the nominal head of the organization: ``I'm the
chairman of the board of trustees, which requires me to go to a
meeting once every two months. In reality, the buck still stops
here.''
   But he says projects are winding down, and the end of Band Aid
could come in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   ``We have a million pounds left, which is contingency, which we
don't touch, in case there's an emergency or a shortfall on a
project,'' said <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON>. ``When all that's finished, about two
years, then we just close.''
   So <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> is back with his first love, music. He's not sure if
``Vegetarians'' will be his long-awaited commercial breakthrough,
and he's aware that there's no immediate market for his songs on
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> radio.
   ``So what if it doesn't fit? It's still music,'' says <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON>.
``For every 3 million people who love <LOCATION>Bon Jovi</LOCATION>, there's a quarter
of a million who can't stand it. I'm not at all bitter. I'm sort of
philosophical.''
   The philosopher looks much the same as he did at Live Aid,
except for the bit of gray in his unruly mop of hair. Geldof
considers the music scene today, and he sees many of the same
things flourishing which led to the punk scene.
   ``I feel a real sort of betrayal now when I listen to the radio.
I understand that this is now a giant, monolithic industry, and I
understand so many millions of people depend on their livelihoods
for it, and they play it safe,'' said <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tuesday AMs, Sept. 11</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030389-0050 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 25732 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 3, 1989, Friday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part 6; Page 28; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
667 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MUSIC A FAMILY AFFAIR FOR DAVID JACK; 
</P>
<P>
EVEN 4-YEAR-OLD SON HELPS CHILDREN'S RECORDING ARTIST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LYNNE HEFFLEY, Heffley is a Burbank free-lance writer. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Children's recording artist <PERSON>David Jack</PERSON> tries out new songs on a discriminating 
audience -- his 4-year-old son Benjamin. "If Benjamin likes it, it's a go," 
<PERSON>Jack</PERSON> says. 
</P>
<P>
So far, <PERSON>Benjamin</PERSON> is on a roll: His dad's "Don't Wake Up the Baby" and "Dance in 
Your Pants" audiotapes were hot enough to be picked up by national 
distributors; "Dance in Your Pants" won the <DATE>1988</DATE> "Parents Choice Award" for 
excellence. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jack</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> native, is <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>'s manager of music operations, working on 
in-house programming and license negotiations. In his free time, he performs 
his songs. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> at 2, children and parents can hear <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> in concert at <LOCATION>Kids 
Gym</LOCATION>, 12526 <ORGANIZATION>Riverside Drive</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Studio City</LOCATION>, (818) 343-7116. Tickets are <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> per 
child, <MONEY>$5</MONEY> per adult. 
</P>
<P>
For ages 1 and up ("a 9-year-old won't be bored," he says), it will be 40 
minutes of music and audience participation: singing, clapping and dancing. 
</P>
<P>
Referring to the Canadian children's singer superstar, <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> describes himself 
as "like Raffi, only hipper." (<ORGANIZATION>Raffi</ORGANIZATION> often sings familiar children's standards 
as well as folk and contemporary songs.) 
</P>
<P>
"I want to separate myself from the people who do the same 'Old <PERSON>MacDonald</PERSON>' 
stuff," he says. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jack</PERSON>, 29, dark-haired, wide-grinned and irrepressible, may or may not be hipper 
than <PERSON>Raffi</PERSON>, but his work has contagious appeal. "Dance in Your Pants" is a 
bouncy, professional mix of styles from jazz and gentle rock to Hawaiian 
ukulele. 
</P>
<P>
Lyrics, by older sister <PERSON>Susan Jack Cooper</PERSON>, a San Diego-based writer, are 
guaranteed children-pleasers: 
</P>
<P>
 "Suppose I said my tuna fish was calling on the phone? Or at my door was a 
dinosaur with a chocolate ice cream cone?" and "Are there 'tee-hees' in your 
T-shirt? Are there 'ha-ha's' in your hat? Do your shorts just hop and never 
stop? Well, what you gonna do about that?" 
</P>
<P>
The collaboration with <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON>, who "still calls me her kid brother," started 
when <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> graduated from <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> with a degree in music education. It became 
serious when <PERSON>Benjamin</PERSON> was born. 
</P>
<P>
"I was looking for some good children's music," <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> says, "and I found the 
same old rehashed stuff we grew up with. So we wrote our first song, 
"Sleepies." From there, we decided to do an album of lullabies that would give 
a child a sense of family. ("I like us, I like this family, I like this house I 
live in, I'm glad I'm me.") 
</P>
<P>
After that, writing a second album that "little kids could dance to" seemed a 
natural progression. Jack and <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON> are now working on a third, "Gotta Hop!" 
</P>
<P>
Since <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON> lives in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, it means working on the phone and through the 
mail, but <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> says he always looks forward to their face-to-face collaboration 
"because I know we're going to laugh." 
</P>
<P>
Jack's Ta-Dum Production company is definitely a family affair. Jack's father, 
a retired music teacher, plays oboe on the tapes, and brother <LOCATION>Louis</LOCATION> plays 
piccolo. Jack supplies drums and keyboard as well as vocals. 
</P>
<P>
His mother, also a music teacher, serves as marketing manager. She took "Don't 
Wake Up the Baby" "to nursery schools and small stores until it was eventually 
picked up by the <ORGANIZATION>Columbia House Record Club</ORGANIZATION>" and other national distributors. 
</P>
<P>
His wife, <PERSON>Vicky</PERSON>, a former nursery school teacher who is expecting their second 
child this <DATE>summer</DATE>, serves as educational consultant. Even Benjamin makes a 
vocal appearance on both cassettes. 
</P>
<P>
Jack says he writes his music not only for children, but for parents who "are 
looking for entertaining music that doesn't drive them crazy to hear over and 
over, music with a message in it somewhere that a child can extract without 
knowing it." 
</P>
<P>
But "first and foremost," he says, "our music says, 'Enjoy yourselves, be happy 
with yourselves and with the things that you can do.' " 
</P>
<P>
After the <ORGANIZATION>Studio City</ORGANIZATION> concert <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> will do two free concerts: one in 
<LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>March 11</DATE> at A Child's Fancy, 140 <ORGANIZATION>W. Colorado Blvd.</ORGANIZATION> (818) 
793-4085, and one in <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION> at noon <DATE>March 25</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Quinby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <DATE>1109</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Montana 
Ave.</ORGANIZATION> (213) 394-1141. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Children's musician David Jack and his toughest critic, 4-year-old son 
Benjamin. BRIAN GADBERRY 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880524-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-24-88 2000EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-FolkArtAwards     05-24 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Folk Art Awards,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>NEA Makes Grants for Preserving Traditional Arts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA M. HAMM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A dozen American folk artists, ranging from a
Czech-American egg painter to a Hawaiian cowboy singer and ukelele
player, have been awarded grants from the <ORGANIZATION>National Endowment</ORGANIZATION> of the
Arts for their efforts to preserve the artistic legacy of their
forebears.
   The 12 were selected from among 155 traditional artists
nominated by their peers to receive the <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>National Heritage
Fellowships</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>NEA</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Frank Hodsoll</PERSON> said in announcing the
grants <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``Among this nation's greatest treasures is our rich and varied
traditional heritage,'' <PERSON>Hodsoll</PERSON> said. ``Through these awards, we
seek to honor <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s great traditional artists _ those who
successfully preserve and pass on the artistic legacy of their
forebears and enrich our culture.''
   ``In a way, it's a celebration of ourselves in all of our
glorious diversity,'' said <PERSON>Dan Sheehy</PERSON>, assistant director of the
endowment's folk arts program, which initiated the awards in <DATE>1982</DATE>
to honor master practitioners of the traditional arts.
   The awards will be presented to the recipients formally at a
ceremony on <DATE>Sept. 29</DATE> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   The recipients included <PERSON>Amber Densmore</PERSON>, 87, of <LOCATION>Chelsea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>, who
has made countless quilts, bedspreads, lace doilies and hooked rugs
in her lifetime but has never sold a single piece of work.
   In a statement issued by <ORGANIZATION>NEA</ORGANIZATION>, she said, ``I've given it all
away. You'll just have to go and see my grandchildren.''
   Arthel ``Doc'' <PERSON>Watson</PERSON>, 65, an Appalachian guitar player and
singer from Deep Gap, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, recently announced his plans to retire
after 26 years on the road. <PERSON>Watson</PERSON>, who was blinded at age 2 and
first picked up a guitar at 12, has won four Grammy awards from the
   <PERSON>Yang Fang Nhu</PERSON>, who was born in a small Hmong mountain village in
northern <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> in <DATE>1912</DATE>, came to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> with her husband,
<PERSON>Yang Nouyi</PERSON>, in <DATE>1984</DATE>. She is a master weaver and embroiderer and is
passing on her skills to her daughter-in-law, with whom she and her
husband currently live in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>.
   The other award recipients were:
   <PERSON>Pedro Ayala</PERSON>, 77, a Mexican-American accordion player from <LOCATION>Donna</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Kepka <LOCATION>Belton</LOCATION>, 54, a Czech-American egg painter from <LOCATION>Ellsworth</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kan</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Michael Flatley</PERSON>, 30, an Irish-American stepdancer from <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   Sister <PERSON>Rosalia Haberl</PERSON>, 91, a German-American bobbin lacemaker
from <LOCATION>Hankinson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.D.</LOCATION>
   <PERSON>John Dee Holeman</PERSON>, 58, an Afro-American dancer, musician and
singer from <LOCATION>Durham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>
   <PERSON>Kenny Sidle</PERSON>, 57, an Anglo-American fiddler in the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>
tradition from <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Albert Luandrew</PERSON>, 81, also known as ``Sunnyland Slim,'' an
Afro-American blues pianist and singer from <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Willie Mae Ford Smith</PERSON>, 82, an Afro-American gospel singer from
<LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Clyde Sproat</PERSON>, 60, a Hawaiian cowboy singer and ukulele player
from <LOCATION>Kapaau</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06285253 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06285253 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: From left, Lois Weaver, Peggy Shaw, Precious Pearl and
Bette Bourne (in tub); PHOTO: Lois Weaver as Stella, top, and Peggy Shaw as
Stanley  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  THEATER; SHOW; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  'BELLE Reprieve" should have been a hoot. But it ain't.;   When two gay
theater troupes -- a London company called Bloolips and a New York lesbian
company called Split Britches -- set out to deconstruct "A Streetcar Named
Desire," they ought to have had only one problem: culling the material into a
manageable show.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  'BELLE' BENDS GENDERS WHILE DERAILING 'STREETCAR'  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  PERFORMANCE  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     They culled, all right, but eccentrically. Eight irrelevant songs -- nine
if you count the overture, a lesbian revision of "Someone to Watch Over Me" --
have been inserted, as well as a fairy with a ukulele, whom I don't recall
from "Streetcar" (but perhaps I've got one of those expurgated '50s
editions).;   In order to embarrass us with all these riches, the
actor-writers have unencumbered the play of plot, structure and through-line.;
  Lord knows there's enough to parody in <LOCATION>Tennessee Williams</LOCATION>, for the first
half of his life one of the most miserable homosexuals on record and for the
last half one of the drunkest.;   Literature critics have had a field day with
gender analyses of his work. The great roles he wrote for women -- Blanche in
"Streetcar" and <PERSON>Maggie</PERSON> the Cat -- are thinly disguised portraits of himself,
and the men in their lives are brutal, like <PERSON>Stanley Kowalski</PERSON>, or aloof and
enigmatic, like Brick in "Cat on a Hot Tin Roof," or charming heels, as both
also are.;   However, Split Britches and <PERSON>Bloolips</PERSON> explore this fertile ground
only in the last eight minutes of their play, prefacing the tragicomic
gender-bender confrontation of Blanche and <ORGANIZATION>Stanley</ORGANIZATION> with 112 other minutes of
nonsense.;   Some of it's funny; a lot is tasteless; some is just there. The
title, for instance, is a parody: The old plantation in "Streetcar" is <LOCATION>Belle
Reve</LOCATION>, pronounced reeve. Nothing much comes of it.;   But a few bits are right
on the mark, such as a bathtub dialogue between Blanche and <PERSON>Stella</PERSON> that
lampoons every crossed-purpose conversation <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION> ever wrote. And the
script is cleverly intercut with passages from "The Glass Menagerie,"
"Suddenly Last Summer" and (I think) a lot of the later,REVIEW; forgettable
plays; and -- of course -- <PERSON>Bette Davis</PERSON> movies. (This is, after all, gay
theater.);   But all of it could have been scrapped in favor of starting at
Point A and progressing, just for laughs, to Point B and so on. That shows you
how boring and Aristotelian I am.;   Blanche is played by "<PERSON>Bette Bourne</PERSON>," a
co-founder of Bloolips, who looks like <PERSON>Vivien Leigh</PERSON> in an advanced state of
decay. He whistles quite operatically. <PERSON>Mitch</PERSON>, played by one "Precious Pearl,"
acts grayly but plays the ukulele very well for a beginner.;   Stella and
<ORGANIZATION>Stanley</ORGANIZATION> are enacted by <PERSON>Lois Weaver</PERSON> and <PERSON>Peggy Shaw</PERSON>, co-founders of Split
Britches and longtime partners who are mostly interested in "getting those
colored lights going." Their acting is indescribable, though "lousy" gets us
about halfway there, until <PERSON>Weaver</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Marilyn Monroe</PERSON> parody, which leaves me
speechless.;   I am not given to comment on women's physical attributes, but
<ORGANIZATION>Shaw</ORGANIZATION> in the famous <PERSON>Stanley Kowalski</PERSON> singlet, sans bra, is not a sight for the
faint-hearted.;   The cast taps rather neatly, and its singing is bearable
when covered by the piano, whose ivories were tickled by one "Laka Daisical."
Pearl does a wonderful straight-faced recitation of "My Way," whose words are
three times as dumb when divorced from their monotonous melody. I liked the
two cream-pie jokes and the dancing votive candles.;   This thing, whose <LOCATION>West
Coast</LOCATION> premiere is being presented by Theater Rhino, won an Obie Award this
year -- and for "ensemble performance," no less, a quality that shows up only
in the tap-dance finale. There are several possible answers: The jury was
asleep, the other contenders were desperately bad, the jury was asleep . . . I
vote for the first and last.; Belle Reprieve; Bloolips/Split Britches;
Producer: Theater Rhino; Through: <DATE>Oct. 27</DATE>; Where: <PERSON>Victoria Theater</PERSON>, 2961 16th
St., <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; Tickets: <MONEY>$14</MONEY>-<MONEY>$25</MONEY>. (415) 861-5079; Parking: Street  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JUDITH GREEN, Mercury News Theater Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911011  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  25  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  685  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, October 11, 1991
00285253,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091190-0178 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 275081 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 11, 1990, Tuesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part P; Page 10; Column 3; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
464 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BOB GELDOF IS BACK UNDER ORIGINAL GUISE: MUSICIAN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LARRY McSHANE, ASSOCIATED PRESS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Bob Geldof</PERSON>, musician, is back. 
</P>
<P>
Not <PERSON>St. Bob</PERSON>, the humanitarian of British tabloid headlines. Not Sir <PERSON>Bob</PERSON>, 
knighted by <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth</PERSON> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, nominated for the Nobel Peace Prize that 
same year. Not author <PERSON>Bob</PERSON>, who's already written a best-selling autobiography, 
"Is That It?" And not businessman <PERSON>Bob</PERSON>, who oversaw millions and <MONEY>millions of 
dollars</MONEY> in contributions for the starving Third World. 
</P>
<P>
Geldof remains chairman of the board of trustees of Band Aid, although he says 
the organization will cease to exist fairly soon. But his main focus these days 
is "The Vegetarians of Love," his critically acclaimed second solo album. 
</P>
<P>
This is no Boomtown Rats rock 'n' roll extravaganza; <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> has instead 
assembled a mostly acoustic band featuring accordion, violins, flute, tin 
whistle, mandolin and ukulele. 
</P>
<P>
"For me, I suppose, it's simply a reaction to stuff I hear on the radio which I 
don't like -- basically, house music and New Kids on the Block or <PERSON>Kylie 
Minogue</PERSON>," <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> said in a recent interview. 
</P>
<P>
For the new album, <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> enlisted an old friend -- ex-Rats bassist <PERSON>Pete 
Briquette</PERSON> -- and four traditional musicians he had never met. They recorded 28 
songs in five days; any song that didn't click after three takes was thrown 
out. Geldof improvised many of the lyrics on the spot. 
</P>
<P>
The spontaneity shows. On "A Gospel Song," <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> tells the band "middle eight 
coming up" during an instrumental break. Geldof asks at the start of another 
cut, "Are we rolling?" And at the end of "The Great Song of Indifference," the 
entire band is heard laughing loudly. 
</P>
<P>
"Indifference" is already a Top 40 hit in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. "The last thing everybody 
expected was this Irish pub song. And it became a big dance hit, you know? 
Thirteenth-Century dance music," said <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON>, laughing. 
</P>
<P>
After almost a decade as front man for the New Wave-era Boomtown Rats, <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> 
became a household name in <DATE>1984</DATE> by organizing the cream of British musicians to 
record "Do They Know It's Christmas?" to raise money for African famine 
victims. 
</P>
<P>
That was followed by <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> for <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s "We Are the World" and the 
internationally televised Live Aid benefit. For two years, <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> met with 
heads of state and political power brokers; the scruffy Irishman was 
photographed with everyone from <ORGANIZATION>Nobelist Mother Teresa</ORGANIZATION> to British Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Geldof looks back on those days with pride tempered by the realization that 
there was only so much that could be done. 
</P>
<P>
"I mean, I never said we were going to stop world poverty or world hunger. I 
said it was a Band-Aid. 'You don't put a Band-Aid on a gaping wound,' if I 
remember, was the quote at the time," <PERSON>Geldof</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"That wasn't the function, to stop world hunger. It was to raise the issue to 
the top of the political agenda, and we did that." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Bob Geldof 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901102-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-02-90 0729EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:Young Adv15   11-02 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Young, Adv 15,0856</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv 15</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thurs PMs, Nov 15 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Veteran Musician Rocks Back in `Ragged Glory'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN HORN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Entertainment Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MALIBU, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Neil Young</PERSON> had just seen the movie
``Spinal Tap'' for the first time. And his life took on new
meaning.
   ``That's my life. My life is `Spinal Tap,''' said <PERSON>Young</PERSON>,
reaching for the morning's first cup of coffee.
   The <DATE>1984</DATE> mock documentary follows hapless rockers on tour, their
future imperiled by a rift with the band's co-founder. Young, who
turned 45 on <DATE>Nov. 12</DATE>, doesn't struggle like those low-rent
musicians. He was, though, estranged, saying a few years ago he
never would play again with longtime companions <ORGANIZATION>Crazy Horse</ORGANIZATION>.
   But now Young has recorded an album with the legendary bar band.
   Awestruck critics say ``Ragged Glory'' resurrects Young's
spontaneous, hard-driving rock 'n' roll. That freewheeling sound
was shelved at times in favor of <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s acoustic ballads and
country rock on solo albums and collaborations with <ORGANIZATION>Mynah Birds</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Buffalo Springfield</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Crosby</PERSON>, Stills and <PERSON>Nash</PERSON>.
   Young said the time was right to reunite with <ORGANIZATION>Crazy Horse</ORGANIZATION>. Any
bad blood between him and the band is forgotten.
   ``Crazy Horse is a band that I'm a part of,'' said <PERSON>Young</PERSON>,
wearing his standard uniform: jeans, T-shirt, tennis shoes, <PERSON>Ray
Bans</PERSON> and stubble. ``I lead the band, yeah. But I'm just a member.
It's like returning to your roots. It brings me back to where I
started.''
   Two of <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s most popular and acclaimed albums - <DATE>1975</DATE>'s
``Tonight's the Night'' and <DATE>1979</DATE>'s ``Rust Never Sleeps'' - were
recorded with <ORGANIZATION>Crazy Horse</ORGANIZATION>. Their first effort together was <DATE>1969</DATE>'s
``Everybody Knows This Is Nowhere.'' Their last was <DATE>1986</DATE>'s
``Life.''
   Crazy Horse's own new album is titled ``Left for Dead'' in part,
the band members say, because Young and others in the business
abandoned them. In ``Ragged Glory,'' Young is joined by <ORGANIZATION>Crazy
Horse</ORGANIZATION>'s guitarist <PERSON>Frank Sampedro</PERSON>, bassist <PERSON>Billy Talbot</PERSON> and drummer
<PERSON>Ralph Molina</PERSON>.
   ``It may be the best one I've ever done with them,'' <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said.
``It's even. And that's a little peculiar. There's not one song
that really stands out.''
   Last year, Young released what some considered the best album of
<DATE>1989</DATE> and perhaps of his career: ``Freedom.'' Young, who's hardly
given to flowery self-promotion, believes ``Ragged Glory'' is
superior.
   ``I was amazed at the success of `Freedom,' not because I didn't
think it was good, but I was surprised that its shortcomings were
not mentioned more often,'' <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said.
   And what were these shortcomings? ``Well, `Ragged Glory' has
what `Freedom' doesn't have,'' he said. ```Freedom' was OK to
listen to; it's got all the soft songs. But in this album, we'll
lose all the people who like the soft songs.''
   Indeed, only one track on ``Ragged Glory'' - ``Days That Used to
Be'' - could be considered contemplative both lyrically and
musically.
   Filled with longing reminiscences of the '60s - ``Psychedelic
music fills the air, Peace and love live there still'' - the
melancholy song says that personal dreams are threatened by
``possessions and concessions.''
   ``I usually shy away from this kind of song,'' <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said a few
days before setting off on another trip on his sailboat. ``I was in
the middle of the ocean on my boat, halfway between here and there,
and had been there for about 10 days. No airplanes. No other boats.
No noise. But I did see a couple of humpback whales. The song came
to me.''
   The album was recorded at <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s 2,000-acre ranch.
   The band doesn't rehearse, arranges on the spot and avoids
re-recording takes to cover glitches or raw edges. The album stands
like a piece of unfinished furniture.
   ``It doesn't matter how you get it as long as it sounds good in
the end,'' said bassist <PERSON>Talbot</PERSON>. ``People make music, not the
instruments. It's just us hanging out together.''
   On a whim, the band recorded the R&amp;B classic ``Farmer John'' for
the album, even though Young was the only one who knew how to play
it. That carefree approach carries over to <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s songwriting,
too.
   ``I don't sit down and say I'll play a G or something. It's
mindless. It's the other way around from what most people think. It
comes to you and you grab it and then find out what it is.''
   Young was born in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> and received a ukulele as a Christmas
gift at age 13. He joined the <PERSON>Squires</PERSON> in <DATE>1963</DATE>, and met <PERSON>Stephen
Stills</PERSON> soon thereafter; he teamed with Stills in <LOCATION>Buffalo
Springfield</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Crosby</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Stills Nash &amp; Young</ORGANIZATION>.
   Throughout his career, he has been irreverent. His <DATE>1988</DATE> song,
``This Note's for You,'' a critique of commercialism in the music
business, yielded a controversial and award-winning video.
   ``I'm the lost character in this place because I don't know
where I fit,'' <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said. ``The record company is building an
image, grooming you. I have no idea what that's all about. Where do
I fit with this?''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Neil Young</PERSON> had just seen the movie
``Spinal Tap'' for the first time. And his life took on new
meaning.
   ``That's my life. My life is `Spinal Tap,''' said <PERSON>Young</PERSON>,
reaching for the morning's first cup of coffee.
   The <DATE>1984</DATE> mock documentary follows hapless rockers on tour, their
future imperiled by a rift with the band's co-founder. Young, who
turned 45 on <DATE>Nov. 12</DATE>, doesn't struggle like those low-rent
musicians. He was, though, estranged, saying a few years ago he
never would play again with longtime companions <ORGANIZATION>Crazy Horse</ORGANIZATION>.
   But now Young has recorded an album with the legendary bar band.
   Awestruck critics say ``Ragged Glory'' resurrects Young's
spontaneous, hard-driving rock 'n' roll. That freewheeling sound
was shelved at times in favor of <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s acoustic ballads and
country rock on solo albums and collaborations with <ORGANIZATION>Mynah Birds</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Buffalo Springfield</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Crosby</PERSON>, Stills and <PERSON>Nash</PERSON>.
   Young said the time was right to reunite with <ORGANIZATION>Crazy Horse</ORGANIZATION>. Any
bad blood between him and the band is forgotten.
   ``Crazy Horse is a band that I'm a part of,'' said <PERSON>Young</PERSON>,
wearing his standard uniform: jeans, T-shirt, tennis shoes, <PERSON>Ray
Bans</PERSON> and stubble. ``I lead the band, yeah. But I'm just a member.
It's like returning to your roots. It brings me back to where I
started.''
   Two of <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s most popular and acclaimed albums - <DATE>1975</DATE>'s
``Tonight's the Night'' and <DATE>1979</DATE>'s ``Rust Never Sleeps'' - were
recorded with <ORGANIZATION>Crazy Horse</ORGANIZATION>. Their first effort together was <DATE>1969</DATE>'s
``Everybody Knows This Is Nowhere.'' Their last was <DATE>1986</DATE>'s
``Life.''
   Crazy Horse's own new album is titled ``Left for Dead'' in part,
the band members say, because Young and others in the business
abandoned them. In ``Ragged Glory,'' Young is joined by <ORGANIZATION>Crazy
Horse</ORGANIZATION>'s guitarist <PERSON>Frank Sampedro</PERSON>, bassist <PERSON>Billy Talbot</PERSON> and drummer
<PERSON>Ralph Molina</PERSON>.
   ``It may be the best one I've ever done with them,'' <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said.
``It's even. And that's a little peculiar. There's not one song
that really stands out.''
   Last year, Young released what some considered the best album of
<DATE>1989</DATE> and perhaps of his career: ``Freedom.'' Young, who's hardly
given to flowery self-promotion, believes ``Ragged Glory'' is
superior.
   ``I was amazed at the success of `Freedom,' not because I didn't
think it was good, but I was surprised that its shortcomings were
not mentioned more often,'' <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said.
   And what were these shortcomings? ``Well, `Ragged Glory' has
what `Freedom' doesn't have,'' he said. ```Freedom' was OK to
listen to; it's got all the soft songs. But in this album, we'll
lose all the people who like the soft songs.''
   Indeed, only one track on ``Ragged Glory'' - ``Days That Used to
Be'' - could be considered contemplative both lyrically and
musically.
   Filled with longing reminiscences of the '60s - ``Psychedelic
music fills the air, Peace and love live there still'' - the
melancholy song says that personal dreams are threatened by
``possessions and concessions.''
   ``I usually shy away from this kind of song,'' <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said a few
days before setting off on another trip on his sailboat. ``I was in
the middle of the ocean on my boat, halfway between here and there,
and had been there for about 10 days. No airplanes. No other boats.
No noise. But I did see a couple of humpback whales. The song came
to me.''
   The album was recorded at <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s 2,000-acre ranch.
   The band doesn't rehearse, arranges on the spot and avoids
re-recording takes to cover glitches or raw edges. The album stands
like a piece of unfinished furniture.
   ``It doesn't matter how you get it as long as it sounds good in
the end,'' said bassist <PERSON>Talbot</PERSON>. ``People make music, not the
instruments. It's just us hanging out together.''
   On a whim, the band recorded the R&amp;B classic ``Farmer John'' for
the album, even though Young was the only one who knew how to play
it. That carefree approach carries over to <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s songwriting,
too.
   ``I don't sit down and say I'll play a G or something. It's
mindless. It's the other way around from what most people think. It
comes to you and you grab it and then find out what it is.''
   Young was born in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> and received a ukulele as a Christmas
gift at age 13. He joined the <PERSON>Squires</PERSON> in <DATE>1963</DATE>, and met <PERSON>Stephen
Stills</PERSON> soon thereafter; he teamed with Stills in <LOCATION>Buffalo
Springfield</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Crosby</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Stills Nash &amp; Young</ORGANIZATION>.
   Throughout his career, he has been irreverent. His <DATE>1988</DATE> song,
``This Note's for You,'' a critique of commercialism in the music
business, yielded a controversial and award-winning video.
   ``I'm the lost character in this place because I don't know
where I fit,'' <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said. ``The record company is building an
image, grooming you. I have no idea what that's all about. Where do
I fit with this?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06229056 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06229056 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: The Jets leap into action in a number from 'West Side Story,'
which mixed classic discipline, Broadway dazzle  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  DANCE; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  NOBODY, but nobody, has done more for Broadway dance than Jerome Robbins.;   
He broke into show biz at a time when "musical theater" meant glorified revues
or plays-with-inserted-songs, and he changed all that. He invented theatrical
dance that established the mood, advanced the plot, described and shaped
character -- and was, still and foremost, fabulous dance. All the while, he
maintained a productive profile in classical ballet.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SHOWSTOPPERS
HIS DANCES STOPPED SHOWS. BUT 'JEROME ROBBINS'
BROADWAY' IS SIMPLY STOPPED STILL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  PERFORMANCE
REVIEW  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "<PERSON>Jerome Robbins</PERSON>' Broadway" was his slightly belated 70th birthday gift (it
opened in <DATE>1989</DATE>, when he was 71) to the street that saw his greatest successes,
including such landmark works as "West Side Story" (<DATE>1957</DATE>) and "Fiddler on the
Roof" (<DATE>1964</DATE>).;    I can't begrudge the national tour (which pulled into the
Golden Gate <DATE>Theater this week</DATE> for a limited engagement that ends <DATE>Sept. 8</DATE>) its
advance sales, because <PERSON>Robbins</PERSON>' work is so wonderful that seeing this much of
it under any circumstances is a must. But I think it could look better than it
does.;    It contains excerpts from nine shows, including major set-pieces
from "Billion-Dollar Baby" (<DATE>1945</DATE>), "High-Button Shoes" (<DATE>1947</DATE>) and "The King
and I" (<DATE>1951</DATE>), and a 40-minute chunk of "West Side Story" that includes all
the big dance numbers.;    But what's the connection, besides <PERSON>Robbins</PERSON>? The
libretto is bald and haphazard, and it gets no assist at all from <PERSON>Paul
Kreppel</PERSON>'s unengaging performance as the narrator (as well as Tevye in
"Fiddler" and Pseudolus in "A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum").
The approach is neither chronological nor thematic; if it's based on anything
at all, it's backstage traffic (How many dancers need to make a costume change
here? And how fast can they do it?) -- which is no way to plan a show of this
size and scope.;    The company is unmemorable, except for <PERSON>Leilani Jones</PERSON>, a
Hawaiian-born performer who croons the show's unknown song, the sinuous "<PERSON>Mr.
Monotony</PERSON>," in a tigress' purr. She's also the fiery Anita in "<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>" from
"West Side Story" (which is done in its stage version, as an all-female
number). Fortunately, her miscastings -- as the narrator for "The <ORGANIZATION>Small House</ORGANIZATION>
of Uncle Thomas" (the Siamese "Uncle Tom's Cabin" in "The King and I") and
<PERSON>Grandma Tzeitel</PERSON> in the dream sequence of "Fiddler" -- were disguised by her
costumes.;    A <LOCATION>New York City Ballet</LOCATION> dancer, <PERSON>Alexia Hess</PERSON>, is the putative
leaddancer, but her roles are limited to colorless non-dance parts: Maria in
the cha-cha from "West Side Story" and the shy girl, <PERSON>Louise</PERSON>, who isn't yet
grown into <PERSON>Gypsy Rose Lee</PERSON> when three strippers strut their stuff for her in
"You Gotta Have a Gimmick" from "Gypsy.";    But the choreography makes up for
all. Robbins is brilliant and versatile, and there's something of all his
gifts here. The beach-cabana sequence from "High-Button Shoes" is an
affectionate parody of all <PERSON>Mack Sennett</PERSON> production numbers, but it also zips
through the plot and perpetrators with clarity and economy, like one of those
portraits you used to be able to buy for a dime from a seaside sketcher. And
it's wonderfully funny.;    So is the <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION> from "Billion-Dollar Baby,"
which presents every cliche of the Prohibition era -- flappers, coppers,
gangsters, bootleggers and speakeasy sophisticates with raccoon coats, porkpie
hats and ukuleles -- in a wild chase and great dance number all in one.;   
"Uncle Thomas" brightly mixes Balinese dance and Chinese and Japanese
classical theatrics with a dash of humor and a dash of pathos, reconciling the
contradictions in <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> and Western storytelling even as it exploits them.
"Gimmick" is pure shtick, but what shtick! And its innocence somehow cancels
its hard-bitten subject matter (the exploitation of women's bodies).;    And
for pure dance-drama, what has ever topped "West Side Story"? The dangerous
beauty of its disaffected teen-agers, their exuberant claim on territory and
time, the moves that combine menace and vulnerability -- after all the years
and so many imitations, these still read as powerfully as when they first
appeared. (Incidentally, I just saw "West Side Story" and "The King and I" on
video, and <PERSON>Robbins</PERSON>' dances survive virtually intact in both, though in "West
Side Story" the brilliant camera-work -- directed by <PERSON>Robbins</PERSON> for the dance
sequences -- require you to be an active partner in making sense out of the
choreographic whole.);    It's too bad the show looks so scrappy -- not
disgraceful, but not quite polished. Robbins is supposed to be a fierce
perfectionist, but this production doesn't look as though a perfectionist got
anywhere near it. The dancers have a lot of energy and exuberance and nearly
every number is attractive, but the dazzle meridian remains stubbornly
uncrossed. And a few pieces -- e.g., "Comedy Tonight" from "Forum" -- are
positively unkempt.;    As if that weren't enough damning with faint praise,
the design is dullsville. The original designers -- <PERSON>Raoul Pene du Bois</PERSON>, <PERSON>Irene
Sharaff</PERSON>, <PERSON>Tony Walton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Patricia Zipprodt</PERSON>, <PERSON>Boris Aronson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jo Mielziner</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Oliver Smith</PERSON>, among others -- are credited in the program, but the costumes
look as though they came out of stock and the backdrops like charmless,
quickie cartoons. (Did the Sharks and Jets in the original production wear
matching letter jackets, as if they were neighborhood softball teams?) A
national touring show with this budget shouldn't look like this.;     <PERSON>Jerome
Robbins</PERSON>' Broadway; Through: <DATE>Sept. 8</DATE>; Where: Golden Gate Theater, 1 <ORGANIZATION>Taylor St.</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; Tickets: <MONEY>$22</MONEY>-<MONEY>$45</MONEY>. BASS; Parking: <MONEY>$6</MONEY> at adjacent garage and
nearby lots  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JUDITH GREEN, Mercury News Theater Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910816  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  47  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  927  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday August 16, 1991
00229056,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06208157 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06208157 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO:; Raymond Kane breezes in from the islands. (Color)  </CAPTION>
<LEADPARA>  What's that? You say your plans for a Hawaiian vacation died somewhere between
the mortgage payment and the car-insurance premium? You can stop crying into
that floral-print shirt and cheer up -- because two of the most-acclaimed
practitioners of real Hawaiian music are on their way to the Bay Area.;   
Raymond Kane, probably Hawaii's greatest living slack-key guitar player, spent
more than 60 years mastering the unwritten rules of the folk idiom. His
intricate guitar style -- with rhythm and lead played simultaneously -- and
his resonant, haunting vocals are one-of-a-kind. George Kuo is a master
ukulele player and, like Kane, an accomplished storyteller and folk-historian.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DON'T BE BLUE; HAWAII'S NEARBY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  EYE OPENERS  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Tonight <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> and Kuo have an 8:30 concert at Freight and Salvage, <DATE>1111</DATE>
<ORGANIZATION>Addison St</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$9</MONEY> advance, <MONEY>$10</MONEY> at the door. (415) 548-1761.
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, they'll be at the Kuumbwa Jazz Center, 320 Cedar St., <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>.
Tickets for the 7 and <TIME>9:30 p.m.</TIME> concerts are <MONEY>$10</MONEY> advance, <MONEY>$12</MONEY> at the door.
(408) 427-2227.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  -- David Plotnikoff  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910726  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  31  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  181  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday July 26, 1991
00208157,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-16913</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJDB4ACQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931004
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 OCT 93 / Arts: Experience the divine Bette Midler - New York
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KAREN FRICKER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
With the Broadway theatre season still a few weeks off, <PERSON>Bette Midler</PERSON> is
about the only show in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> these days. She is playing a six-week stint
at <ORGANIZATION>Radio City Music Hall</ORGANIZATION>, where her famously loyal following is paying up to
Dollars 100 per ticket to Experience the Divine, as the concert is called.
(Though the run, which ends <DATE>October 23</DATE>, is ostensibly sold out, there are
returns available at Radio City most evenings).
<PERSON>Midler</PERSON> has not appeared in a major concert for 10 years - she has been busy
becoming internationally famous - and there was much speculation about which
<PERSON>Bette</PERSON> we were going to see: the raunchy, raucous 'Divine Miss M', who got
her start singing in gay bathhouses in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, or the kinder, gentler
<DATE>1980s</DATE> <PERSON>Bette</PERSON>, she of Disney films (Down and Out in <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION>, Beaches)
and treacly top-10 pop songs (From a Distance, <ORGANIZATION>Wind Beneath my Wings</ORGANIZATION>).
Experience the Diviney mixture of both <PERSON>Bettes</PERSON>. Alternately brassy and coy,
loud and girlish, belting and crooning, <PERSON>Midler</PERSON> owns the stage; she is simply
one of the best live entertainers around (two of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s other great divas
 -<PERSON>Shirley MacLaine</PERSON> and <PERSON>Liza Minnelli</PERSON> - were in the audience, adding to the
starry frisson). Platinum blond and slender, <PERSON>Midler</PERSON> has never looked better,
and she knows it; one of her first songs is a playful rap called 'I Look
Good'. She is well into her forties, but her asides about 'being too old for
this' are clearly disingenuous; the show lasts three hours, and <PERSON>Midler</PERSON>'s
energy never flags.
Midler knows that her ballads are what the audience - mostly middle-aged
suburbanites - wants, and she works through them all, backed with
appropriate lushness by a seven-piece band. But the concert's divinest
moments are when she is in high-attitude mode; she hits her stride halfway
through the first set with her torchy old hit '<ORGANIZATION>Delta Dawn</ORGANIZATION>' ('This song's
from the 70s . . . as are most of you. Hell, so am I]')
The brassy spirit of <PERSON>Sophie Tucker</PERSON>, the legendary vaudeville performer and
<PERSON>Midler</PERSON>'s idol, hangs over the concert, and <PERSON>Midler</PERSON> conjures her directly in a
series of bawdy jokes she delivers as 'Soph'. <PERSON>Midler</PERSON>'s onstage identity,
like <PERSON>Tucker</PERSON>'s, has much to do with her Jewishness, and she gets a lot of
comic mileage out of the recent <ORGANIZATION>High Holy Days</ORGANIZATION> and out of current political
events ('Oy] This food] If Yassir Arafat knew what our food was like, this
treaty would be off in a second]'). She finishes off the first set with a
rousing 'Rose's Turn' from the classic <PERSON>Jule Styne</PERSON> musical Gypsy, a nifty
piece of advertising for a television version of the musical that she is
starring in this autumn.
The second set veers quickly into high camp, with a routine that <PERSON>Midler</PERSON>
aficionados found hilarious but which mystified me - the performer was in
the guise of <PERSON>Dolores Delago</PERSON>, a blue-tailed mermaid in a motorised wheelchair
who spouts self-help palaver.
While the band and backup singers (who <PERSON>Midler</PERSON> calls 'The Harlettes') make
their way through a ukulele number (a tribute, perhaps, to <PERSON>Midler</PERSON>'s roots;
she was born and raised in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Midler</PERSON> changes into a sophisticated
beige cocktail dress and then offers a particularly committed rendition of
the classic wailer, 'Stay With Me, <ORGANIZATION>Baby</ORGANIZATION>'.
An old-fashioned entertainer, <PERSON>Midler</PERSON> ends the concert with old-fashioned
good manners, coming out after the final encore to wish the audience
good-night and tell them they are fabulous. So is she.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ   United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7922 Theatrical Producers and Services.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06259043 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06259043 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Surfers competing in meets such as this one off Honolulu could
one day make it into the museum's Hall of Fame.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  CALIFORNIA; TRAVEL; HISTORY; MUSEUM; OCEAN; WATER; SPORT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  CATCH a wave that really cranks, one that is powerful and fast, and you're
shredding. Challenge one that breaks precariously close to shore, and it's
hairball. And fall in dramatic fashion, and you've had a flaming wipeout.;  
This is the vocabulary of surfers, who embrace the sea air, brave the chilly
waters and dive into their favorite activity along the Southern California
coast and other surfing spots across the globe.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  YOU'RE HISTORY, DUDE: MUSEUM HONORS SURFING GREATS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Discovering California; Additional information attached to the end of this
article.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     It's also the kind of talk that can be heard at the <ORGANIZATION>Huntington Beach
International Surfing Museum.</ORGANIZATION>;   At a time when surfing museums are becoming
more popular -- with museums in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mission Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ventura</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> -- the 2,200-square-foot facility stands apart. Opened in <DATE>July 1988</DATE>,
the museum is billed as the world's largest tribute to surfing. "It offers a
unique, international collection of surfboards and surfing-related artifacts,"
said <PERSON>Ann Beasley</PERSON>, the non-profit museum's executive officer.;   It also
provides an education in surfing, say museum visitors and professional
surfers.;    A little perspective; "I'm happy that young kids can go to a
place where they can take an interest in surfing and (find out) where it all
came from. It adds a little depth and perspective to the sport," said <PERSON>David
Nuuhiwa</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Oceanside</LOCATION>, a five-time national surfing champion during the late
<DATE>1960s</DATE> and early <DATE>1970s</DATE>. Now 42, <ORGANIZATION>Nuuhiwa</ORGANIZATION> surfs professionally on the masters
circuit.;   <PERSON>Tom Andrusky</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Huntington Beach</LOCATION>, a non-surfer visiting the museum
for the fourth time, said he was impressed with the presentation of surfing
history.;   "You can learn a lot in a very short time in a very small space,"
Andrusky said.;   For example, he discovered that Capt. <PERSON>James Cook</PERSON> of the
British navy first documented surfing in <DATE>1778</DATE>, after he witnessed natives
using large boards to slide along waves off the <LOCATION>Sandwich Islands</LOCATION>, later to be
called <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. The origins of surfing are unknown, however.;   Closer to home,
Hawaiian surfer <PERSON>George Freeth</PERSON> is credited with introducing the sport to
<LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> in <DATE>1907</DATE>, and the rest is gnarly history, dude.;   Surfing
has given a major boost to the economy of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>, said
<PERSON>Assemblyman Tom Mays</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Huntington Beach</LOCATION>, an avid surfer.;   "It's generated a
whole new business -- surfing-related sportswear companies," he said. "And
it's generated a lot of tourist dollars over the years.";   The museum
highlights surfing's contributions, <PERSON>Mays</PERSON> added. "It shows people in the area
how surfing has affected us," he said.;   As visitors walk into the museum,
they are greeted by volunteer docents. The first exhibit is the <ORGANIZATION>International
Surfing Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION>, which describes surfing legends and their contributions
