<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880304-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-88 0447EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Falklands     03-04 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Falklands,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>Britain Says Falklands Exercise Not Intended To Provoke Argentina</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL WEST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government says a weeklong military exercise
in the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> set to begin <DATE>Monday</DATE> is not intended to
provoke <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, noting that fewer than 1,000 troops are to take
part.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, which claims the islands it calls <LOCATION>Malvinas</LOCATION>, lost a
74-day war with <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> for their possession in <DATE>1982</DATE> and still has
not formally declared an end to hostilities in the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   A communique <DATE>Thursday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s Foreign Affairs and
<ORGANIZATION>Defense Ministries</ORGANIZATION> said <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> has adopted plans for ``vigilance
and defensive alert'' during the British exercise and, if
necessary, ``will execute corresponding defense plans.'' It did not
elaborate.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Minister of State</ORGANIZATION> for the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Ian Stewart</PERSON>,
told the <ORGANIZATION>House of Commons</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> that fewer than 1,000
troops and only a small number of aircraft would take part in the
exercise, code-named Fire Focus.
   <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> said the exercise involves an airlift and is part of a
defensive strategy to keep a minimum of troops in the islands about
400 miles east of the southern Argentine coast.
   The <ORGANIZATION>British Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> announced last <DATE>June</DATE> that it was
reducing the strength of its Falklands garrison, but refused to
disclose the size of the cut. Published reports at the time said
the move would cut the garrison then consisting of more than 2,500
troops by about 400.
   Britain completed an international airport at <LOCATION>Mount Pleasant</LOCATION>
near the Falklands capital of <ORGANIZATION>Stanley</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>June 1985</DATE>. The airport can
take wide-bodied military jets, enabling <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> to fly in
reinforcements at short notice if necessary.
   <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> said the development of contingency plans for a massive
airlift had enabled <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> to halve the size of the garrison.
   He gave no figures for the present strength of the costly
garrison but added: ``Such a substantial reduction of the military
presence ... serves to confirm that our purpose is entirely
defensive.''
   A <ORGANIZATION>Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman, who in accordance with British
practice declined to be named, said later: ``We are not intending
to increase the tension down there ... There is nothing significant
about the timing of it (the exercise). It is not meant in any way
to be provocative to <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>.''
   A <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Office</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> recently notified
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> through Swiss diplomatic channels that the exercise was
purely one of reinforcement.
   Diplomatic ties between <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, cut during the
<DATE>1982</DATE> war, remain severed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890905-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-05-89 1727EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Falklands     09-05 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Falklands,0335</SECOND>
<HEAD>Argentina Asks for Cut in Britain's Falkland Garrison</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> wants <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> to make major troop
reductions in the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> as part of an agreement to
normalize relations, <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Eduardo Menem</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>
said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Menem, brother of President <PERSON>Carlos Menem</PERSON>, also told a news
conference he believes negotiations in <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> next month will lead
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> to restore diplomatic relations.
   Diplomatic ties were severed during the <DATE>1982</DATE> Falkland Islands
war, when <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> drove Argentine invaders from the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION>
archipelago.
   ``Demilitarization means only one thing,'' <PERSON>Menem</PERSON> said. ``Of
course, it is a reduction of forces in the area. I think there is a
consensus for making the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> an area of peace.'
   Menem was in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> for a meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>Inter-Parliamentary
Union</ORGANIZATION>, a 108-nation conference of legislators. He shook hands and
chatted with <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> when she opened the
meeting.
   Since taking office <DATE>two months ago</DATE>, his brother has initiated
peace overtures toward <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, including ending an economic embargo
this week.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> maintains a military garrison in the islands, as well as
fighter aircraft and Rapier missiles, to guard the 1,600 British
inhabitants.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> refused <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to give the current strength
of the garrison. British newspapers say it is down to about 1,000
troops, about one-fourth the earlier size, because <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> is
confident <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> will not attack again.
   The <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> talks are expected to focus on fishing rights and
restoring air links between <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and the islands.
   Many observers believe <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> wants to patch up the
differences because <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> is a key member of the <ORGANIZATION>European Economic
Community</ORGANIZATION>. The 12-nation community is due to drop remaining trade
barriers and become a single market in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   Senator <PERSON>Menen</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> ``never put economic considerations
in the forefront in our consideration of this subject.'' He added,
``But if through this we manage to establish good commercial
relations, then be it welcome.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900529-0091
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900529-0091.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Argentina Revives $1.4 Billion Accord
   With IMF and Sets Talks With Banks
   ----
   By Peter Truell
</HL>
<DATE>
05/29/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A8
</SO>
<CO>
   LATAM
</CO>
<IN>
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
BANKS (BNK)
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC NEWS AND STATISTICS (IEN)
</IN>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- Argentina, striving to repair relations with
its foreign creditors, has revived a $1.4 billion loan
negotiations Thursday on resuming payments to its main
commercial bank creditors.
   Late Friday, the IMF's executive board cleared a $240
million loan to Argentina, after the board had approved
revised targets for an economic program originally agreed to
in November 1989. Argentina can draw the $240 million
immediately; it previously had drawn another $240 million of
the $1.4 billion credit. The IMF had held up further
disbursements until Argentina had set revised targets for
such important economic indicators as inflation and the size
of the government deficit.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The Latin American country has succeeded in reviving its
agreement with the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> after two months of much-improved
management under Economy Minister <PERSON>Erman Gonzalez</PERSON>. Inflation
has moderated, and the government even seems to be balancing
its budget.
   The renewed <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> agreement will, for the first time, allow
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> to set aside <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> of what remains of the <MONEY>$1.4
billion</MONEY> credit to allow it to pursue plans to reduce its bank
debt. Faced with a total of about <MONEY>$60 billion</MONEY> of foreign debt
-- with more than half of that owed to commercial banks,
Argentine officials are eager to try such strategies.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s leading commercial bank creditors struggled
hard -- but failed -- to ensure that the country made an
interest payment to them before it could restore its
relations with the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>. They also had hoped to extract an
interest payment from the Argentines as the price of resuming
talks on <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s approximately <MONEY>$30.5 billion</MONEY> of medium-
and long-term foreign bank debt. But that strategy also
didn't succeed.
   Nevertheless, the banks remain hopeful that they will
receive a payment around the time the talks start in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>. "I think that they'll make a payment when we start
talking," said a senior <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> banker. <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> is as much as
<MONEY>$6 billion</MONEY> in arrears on interest payments to banks, having
not paid interest to them for as much as two years. It is
struggling to restructure its economy, and is reluctant to
make payments to banks from its estimated <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> of
foreign-exchange reserves.
   In a statement released in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>William Rhodes</PERSON>, the
<ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> executive who heads the 13-bank committee that
negotiates with <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Javier Gonzalez Fraga</PERSON>, the
vice president of the Argentine central bank, said they had
agreed to resume negotiations. <PERSON>Mr. Rhodes</PERSON> said they will
discuss "the resumption of a regular flow of payments by
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> to commercial bank creditors" on the country's
medium-term and long-term public-sector debt.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s progress with its foreign creditors contrasts
with <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, which has yet to reach agreement with the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>
and reopen talks with foreign bank creditors. <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, which
now has interest payment arrears to its commercial banks that
amount to about <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>, seems to be preoccupied with
trying to improve the enactment of its economic plan.
   Its economy minister, <PERSON>Zelia Cardoso de Mello</PERSON>, visited
senior bankers in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> recently. They seemed
disappointed. "She's not doing much in the way of listening,"
said one. With reserves of as much as <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>, the bankers
reckon that <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> could start to clean up its payments
arrears before they become unmanageably large.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880307-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-88 2016EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Falklands     03-07 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Falklands,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Briton Begins Begins Military Maneuvers In Falklands</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> began a 25-day military exercise <DATE>Monday</DATE> to
test its ability to protect the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> from invasion, the
<ORGANIZATION>Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> reported. <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> said its forces would be on
``defensive alert.''
   ``At this stage, it's very much a paper exercise,'' a ministry
spokesman said. ``The exercise will start with intelligence reports
that an enemy is raising the threat level. They will play out a
scenario.''
   An infantry batallion of 600-1,000 soldiers based in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>
will fly to the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> archipelago <DATE>March 17-18</DATE>, the
spokesman said on condition of anonymity.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> claims the islands off its coast, which it calls the
<LOCATION>Malvinas</LOCATION>, and invaded them in <DATE>April 1982</DATE>. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> sent a naval task
force and won a 74-day war that killed 712 Argentines and 258
Britons.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> says the exercise, called Fire Focus, is purely
defensive. One of its functions will be to test a new <MONEY>$690 million</MONEY>
airport built since the war.
   <PERSON>Ian Stewart</PERSON>, the armed forces minister, said criticism of the
exercise from <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and other Latin American nations resulted
from misunderstanding of its size.
   ``I do not see how something which is purely a defensive
exercise can be seen as provocative,'' he said.
   ``We have to defend the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION>. We had a very unfortunate
experience six years ago. We not only have a right to have a
defensive garrison in the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION>, we have a responsibility to do
so.''
   The exercise, scheduled to end <DATE>March 31</DATE>, is the largest since
the war and the first with reinforcements flown from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
Military units could not be airlifted in <DATE>1982</DATE> because the airport
was inadequate, and the naval force took weeks to reach the islands.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> says the islands are part of its inheritance from
Spanish colonial rule and claims <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> stole them in <DATE>1833</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> has refused to discuss sovereignty, declaring that the
1,900 Falkland Islanders prefer to remain British, but <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON>
said: ``In other respects we would like to have more normal
relations with <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-13157</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CAWAWAA0FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920123
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  23 JAN 92 / Argentina tries to draw in ex-Soviet migrants
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN BARHAM
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BUENOS AIRES
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>ARGENTINA</LOCATION> wants to attract thousands of migrants from the former <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION> to populate the country's vast interior. Officials even hope that the
migrants will bring <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in investment capital with them.
'We are considering immigrants who would bring capital to dynamise the
economy. We are talking with the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> to provide credits for
potential migrants to settle and create companies in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>,' said <PERSON>Mr
Geraldo Molnes</PERSON>, the interior ministry's population secretary.
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> is the second Latin American country to offer to take such
migrants. <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> said at the <DATE>weekend</DATE> it was seeking some with scientific
and technical skills.
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> covers an area the size of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> but a third of the population is
in <LOCATION>Buenos Aires</LOCATION>, leaving most of <LOCATION>Patagonia</LOCATION> - the far south - sparsely
inhabited.
Populating <LOCATION>Patagonia</LOCATION> has obssessed Argentine officialdom since it took
control of the region early in <DATE>this century</DATE>, but the comforts of city life
in <LOCATION>Buenos Aires</LOCATION> have been generally preferred to the distant steppes. <PERSON>Mr
Molnes</PERSON> hopes any newcomers will go to <LOCATION>Patagonia</LOCATION> and to small cities in the
interior.
The government hopes immigrants will begin arriving at a rate of 20,000 a
year and quickly reach 100,000 a year. <PERSON>Mr Molnes</PERSON> denied that <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> was
discriminating against dark-skinned immigrants from nearby countries in
favour of Europeans.
An <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> diplomat, though, poured cold water on the notion: 'They have not made
a formal approach yet. In any case, some of us do not trust the Argentines,
who give the impression of just wanting the money. Others, especially the
Germans, say it amounts to trade in human lives. It could be done
tastefully, but I doubt anything will come of it.'
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-6424</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-ECBDOABUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940302
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 MAR 94 / Argentina wins loan of Dollars 509m
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By GEORGE GRAHAM
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> board yesterday approved a loan of Dollars 508.5m (Pounds
348.2m) for an innovative project to develop <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s capital markets.
The Washington-based development institution agreed to lend Dollars 500m for
a 'backstop' facility that will guarantee <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s commercial banks a
source of liquidity if interest rates rise in the future, and will thus
encourage them to lend money for longer periods to small and medium-sized
businesses.
The backstop fund will be owned by the Argentine government and managed by
an internationally recognised financial institution. It will undertake to
buy bonds from the commercial banks if interest rates rise beyond a fixed
level, to allow them to refinance loans made for periods longer than six
years.
The hope is that the facility will help strengthen the balance sheets of the
top 15 or 20 Argentine banks if interest rates turn upwards.
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> is one of the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>'s biggest borrowers, with loans totalling
Dollars 3.6bn since the current government took office in <DATE>1989</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>ARZ  Argentina, South America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
    P9611 Administration of General Economic Programs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 7
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901003-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-03-90 1202EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-IMF-Argentina     10-03 0144</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-IMF-Argentina,0136</SECOND>
<HEAD>Argentina Loan Reportedly Suspended</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION>
has suspended payment of a <MONEY>$245 million</MONEY> loan to <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> because
the government failed to achieve promised economic reforms during
the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>, according to a report published <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> did not accomplish adequate cuts in its inflation
rate, which was in double digits each month from Juyy to <DATE>September</DATE>,
and the government's fiscal surplus for the period turned out to be
lower than promised, according to a daily financial newspaper, <ORGANIZATION>El
Cronista Comercial</ORGANIZATION>.
   Citing sources in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, the newspaper reported that
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> can reclaim the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> standby loan if it cuts its
government deficit, its inflation rate and the size of the public
sector work force. That would require massive layoffs, the paper
reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06038008 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06038008 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  USSR; SPACE; VEHICLE; ARGENTINA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A 40-ton Soviet space station the size of a railroad car tumbled into the
Earth's atmosphere and burned up over Argentina before dawn today, but no
damage or injuries were immediately reported.;    Argentina's government news
agency Telam said pieces of Salyut 7 apparently fell somewhere in the Andes
Mountains, near the Chilean frontier, but no precise location was given.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SOVIET SPACE STATION FALLS, RAINS 'FIRE'
OVER ARGENTINA  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "Salyut 7 triggered a rain of fire when it entered the atmosphere, that
could be seen from several towns in the provinces of <LOCATION>Cordoba</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Mendoza</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Luis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neuquen</LOCATION> and Chubut," said Telam.;    The Argentine air
force said it had no information on where Salyut 7 may have fallen. There were
agency <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said Salyut 7 and an attached spacecraft re-entered the atmosphere
over a sparsely populated area of central <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> at <TIME>12:47 a.m. local time</TIME>
(<TIME>7:47 p.m. PST</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>).;    The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Space Command</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>, said the spacecraft was traveling about 17,000 mph at re-entry.;   
Salyut 7 was put into orbit in <DATE>April 1982</DATE>. Tass said it should have stayed in
orbit several more years but a sudden increase in solar activity in <DATE>1988</DATE>
caused it to descend sharply.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Buenos Aires, Argentina  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910207  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  206  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday February 7, 1991
00038008,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900216-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-16-90 1556EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-MeteoriteMan     02-16 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Meteorite Man,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Accused of Meteorite Theft Leaves Argentina</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM H. HEATH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> businessman charged
with trying to steal a 37-ton meteorite from a small Argentine town
left for home <DATE>Friday</DATE> after a judge ordered a 90-day postponement of
his trial.
   ``I've got my passport, and I'm out of here,'' <PERSON>Robert Haag</PERSON>, 33,
of <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, said in a telephone interview a few hours before
departure.
   ``I'm supposed to come back in 90 days,'' said <PERSON>Haag</PERSON>, also known
as the Meteorite Man. ``I'd like to come back and clear myself, but
I just don't know. Right now all I want to do is get back to my
business'' of selling meteorites.
   <PERSON>Haag</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION> photographer <PERSON>Jeffrey Smith</PERSON>, 31, and <PERSON>Miguel
Fernandez</PERSON>, an Argentine, were arrested <DATE>Jan. 21</DATE> when they were
stopped by police near the small town of <LOCATION>Gancedo</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Chaco
Province</LOCATION>, 620 miles northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Buenos Aires</ORGANIZATION>.
   The three defendants were charged in the neighboring town of
Charata with the theft of the meteorite, roughly the size of a
small automobile, that police said they found in the back of a
tractor-trailer the men were driving.
   The meteorite, found in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>, reputedly is one of the
world's four largest. Charges against <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> were dropped and he
returned to <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>.
   The area is rich in meteorites, and several years ago provincial
lawmakers made all meteorites provincial property and forbade their
unauthorized sale.
   Haag was released on <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> bond but was forbidden to leave
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>.
   Fernandez, unable to post <MONEY>$8,600</MONEY> bond, remains in custody in
<LOCATION>Charata</LOCATION>.
   Haag claimed he planned to purchase the meteorite in a deal
arranged by <PERSON>Fernandez</PERSON> with the owner of the land on which the
object had been found.
   But he expressed no regrets <DATE>Friday</DATE> over the outcome of the
expedition.
   ``This has been a super adventure,'' he said. ``I met a lot of
people in the <LOCATION>Chaco</LOCATION>, and at the end all kinds of them were trying
to sell me meteorites.''
   <PERSON>Haag</PERSON>'s case was being heard in Charata by <PERSON>Judge Juan Carlos
Clauter</PERSON>. The judge postponed the trial and returned <PERSON>Haag</PERSON>'s passport
on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> after <PERSON>Haag</PERSON> said he needed to return home to take care
of business.
   ``I'm losing at least <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> a day by being here,'' said <PERSON>Haag</PERSON>,
who claims to do ``half a <MONEY>million dollars</MONEY> of business a year''
selling meteorites to private collectors, schools and museums.
   <PERSON>Haag</PERSON>, known to mineral enthusiasts back home as the Meteorite
Man, said he planned to sell the meteorite he is accused of trying
to steal. ``I could have gotten a <MONEY>million dollars</MONEY> for it,'' he said.
   If convicted, <PERSON>Haag</PERSON> could be sentenced to from 30 days to two
years in jail. If he fails to return when his trial resumes <DATE>May 13</DATE>,
he would forfeit his bail.
   Meteorites are common in the <LOCATION>Chaco</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Haag</PERSON> said, ``because a long
time ago a giant asteroid broke into millions of pieces, showering
the area with fragments, some the size of marbles and basketballs,
others weighing a ton or more.''
   The value of meteorites ``depends on the kind of material they
contain,'' he said. ``Some are fragments of the moon, others are
the heads of comets.''
   ``But I'm through dealing with meteorites in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Haag</PERSON>
added. ``The last thing I want to do is to try to get anything out
of here.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910730-0102
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910730-0102.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   International:
   Argentina Receives
   Large IMF Credit
   To Boost Economy
   ----
   By Cristal Baron
</HL>
<DATE>
07/30/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<CO>
   TAXES
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
ALL BANKS, BANKING NEWS AND ISSUES (BNK)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC NEWS AND STATISTICS (IEN)
PETROLEUM (PET)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
INTERNATIONAL TRADE NEWS (TRD)
</IN>
<NS>
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC NEWS AND ANALYSIS (IEN)
TAXES, ISSUES, LEGISLATION, ASSISTANCE, EVASION (TAX)
ACQUISITIONS &amp; MERGERS, TAKEOVERS, BOARD BATTLES (TNM)
TRADE ISSUES (TRD)
</NS>
<GV>
INTERNATIONAL AGENCIES AND INSTITUTIONS (INT)
</GV>
<RE>
AFRICA (AF)
ARGENTINA (AG)
SOUTH AMERICA (SM)
TANZANIA (TZ)
</RE>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- The International Monetary Fund approved a
$1.04 billion standby credit to Argentina to support the
government's economic program through 1992.
   At the request of the Argentine government, 25% of the IMF
funding will be set aside for debt reduction, the IMF said in
a statement.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s economic program is aimed at fostering
economic growth, rapidly reducing inflation and maintaining
an adequate level of international reserves.
   In fighting the country's periodic bouts of inflation,
Argentine authorities have frozen public-sector tariffs,
salaries and pensions, which led to a sharp decline in
inflation and interest rates in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s economic program, supported by the standby
credit, also seeks to improve tax administration, reduce
staffing levels in the government, open up the economy to
international trade and further privatize public enterprises.
   The largest of these enterprises is the state oil company,
which is being trimmed in size for eventual privatization.
Price controls on petroleum products were eliminated in
<DATE>January</DATE> and parts of the company's operations have already
been sold.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> hopes to reschedule its official debt and to
normalize relations with commercial bank creditors, the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   Separately, the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> agreed to provide <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> with <MONEY>$242
million</MONEY> to support its economic program through <DATE>June 1994</DATE>.
The program is aimed at fostering an average annual growth
rate of at least <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT>, while further reducing inflation.
<LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> has been successful at working toward those goals
the past three years, the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> also is seeking to open up its financial-services
sector to private investors, both domestic and foreign, and
to revamp its public financial institutions, the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> money will be disbursed over three years, with
about <MONEY>$70.7 million</MONEY> available the first year in two
installments.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-4407</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CCJCSACNFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920310
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 MAR 92 / International Company News: Ford Canada in Argentina deal
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By BERNARD SIMON
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   TORONTO
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
FORD'S Canadian subsidiary is reportedly close to a deal to export as many
as 125,000 cars to <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> over the next two years from a plant in
<LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>.
The Canadian media reported yesterday that financing is still required for
the sale, which would be worth more than USDollars 1bn. A <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> spokesman
said that 'it's not quite a done deal from our end, but we are extremely
hopeful that the financing will soon be in place'.
The mid-sized <ORGANIZATION>Ford Tempos</ORGANIZATION> would be used as taxis in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>. Phoenix Plus,
a <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> company which is brokering the sale, would buy the cars from <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>
and sell them through an association of Argentine taxi owners to individual
operators.
<PERSON>Mr Howard Wolle</PERSON>, president of <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> Plus, said the company is close to
securing loan guarantees from the national bank of <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>.
If the deal goes through, 65,000 cars would be shipped this year, with the
possibility of another 60,000 in <DATE>1993</DATE>. The order represents about 25 per
cent of the capacity of the <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> plant in <LOCATION>Oakville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 30
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870925-0050 </DOCNO>
<HL> Argentina Continues Probe
Of Local Banks It Closed</HL>
<DD> 09/25/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> LATAM
BANKS, THRIFT INSTITUTIONS (BNK)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> BUENOS AIRES (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Argentine central bank said it will continue investigating the six banks it closed, in the largest action taken by the state banking authority since President <PERSON>Raul Alfonsin</PERSON> was elected in <DATE>1983</DATE>, and will attempt to have them acquired by other financial institutions. 

   The central bank said the six banks were closed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> because of "the serious deterioration of their solvency and liquidity" and "fraudulent administration." 
The closings were expected because the banks had been under investigations since as long ago as <DATE>December 1984</DATE>. 

   The biggest of the closed banks is <ORGANIZATION>Banco del Oeste</ORGANIZATION>, the 16th-largest institution in the country. 
The bank has 54 branch offices nationwide, and its deposits a year ago totaled <MONEY>$55 million</MONEY>. 
The other banks closed were <ORGANIZATION>Banco del Argense</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Banco de Credito Rural Argentino</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Banco del Iguazu</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Miguel Cooperativo Limitado</LOCATION> and Libertadores Cooperativo Limitado. 
They range in size from the 38th-largest to the 155th-largest in the country, though the size of their deposits wasn't immediately known. 

   Holders of accounts at the closed banks were told to go to the central bank to make claims for withdrawals, which are guaranteed by law. 

   Acquiring banks must try to assure the jobs of the closed banks' employees, the central bank said. 
But the uncertainty surrounding that situation caused the 2,400 employees affected by the closings to refuse to leave the banks yesterday. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0202 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Falklands 1stLd-Writethru a0805 12-22 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Falklands, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0805,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prime Minister Calls for Improved Relations with Argentina</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with consular ties restored Thursday,
quotes, details. No pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> called <DATE>Friday</DATE> for
improved commercial and diplomatic relations with <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, but
she also insisted <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> retain control of the disputed <LOCATION>Falkland
Islands</LOCATION>.
   In a Christmas address to the 1,800 islanders, <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON>
said <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, in recent talks with the new Argentine government,
had not wavered from its position that control of the <LOCATION>South
Atlantic</LOCATION> islands is not negotiable.
   Her message followed the restoration <DATE>Thursday</DATE> of consular ties
between <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, severed at the time of the <DATE>1982</DATE>
Falklands War.
   Consular flags were hoisted <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON>,
but full diplomatic links between the two countries remain severed.
   In the speech broadcast by the <ORGANIZATION>British Broadcasting Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mrs.
Thatcher</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> would uphold its commitments to residents of
the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION>.
   Argentine troops invaded the British colony off southern
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> in <DATE>1982</DATE>. Britain sent troops and drove out the invaders
in a 74-day war.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> has claimed sovereignty to the islands it calls the
<LOCATION>Malvinas</LOCATION> since <DATE>1832</DATE>.
   The prime minister commended the Falklands' growing prosperity
from its fishing industry and independence.
   ``You're deciding the kind of life you want for yourselves and
your children, and you're taking a greater share of responsibility
for your own affairs,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> said in the message,
broadcast on the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>World Service</ORGANIZATION> ``Calling the Falklands''
program.
   On <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> said: ``We want to improve ordinary
commercial and diplomatic relations because that is in the
interests of us all, including the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900103-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-03-90 2131EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Argentina-Britain 1stLd-Writethru a0682 01-03 0278</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-Britain, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0682,0286</SECOND>
<HEAD>Britain Eases Falklands Exclusion Zone</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with specifics. No pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Argentine merchant ships now may
sail near the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> for the first time since <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>
lost its <DATE>1982</DATE> battle with <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> for the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION>
archipelago, the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Britain modified the 150-mile ``protection zone'' it has
enforced since regaining the islands in a 74-day war.
   Argentine merchant ships may travel within the area from 150
miles out to 12 miles, the territorial limit enforced by <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
To sail into the 12-mile limit, British permission is needed.
   The vessels may not fish in the zone without permission.
   Argentine military ships must still request and receive British
permission before entering the zone.
   The new arrangement, which took effect <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>, was agreed to
last <DATE>October</DATE> at British-Argentine talks in <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION>.
   The two countries resumed consular relations last month for the
first time since <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> invaded the windswept territory it has
claimed since <DATE>1810</DATE> and which it calls the <LOCATION>Malvinas</LOCATION>. Talks are to
resume in <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> <DATE>Feb. 14-15</DATE> after which full diplomatic relations
may be restored.
   The issue of sovereignty has been set aside, but <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> has
refused to give up its claim to the territory.
   The Falklands are home to 1,800 islanders.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>United Kingdom</ORGANIZATION> lifted yesterday the restriction on the
navigation of Argentine merchant ships in the 150-mile military
zone,'' Foreign Minister <PERSON>Domingo Cavallo</PERSON> told reporters.
   ``<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> has the firm intention of recovering its sovereignty
through negotiation,'' a ministry communique stated <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the
157th anniversary of the ousting by British forces of an Argentine
garrison on the islands in <DATE>1833</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880317-0212 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-17-88 0052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Falklands     03-17 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Falklands,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Troops Take Off In Practice Airlift For Falklands</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRIZE NORTON, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of British troops took off
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> on an 8,000-mile practice airlift to reinforce the
remote <LOCATION>Falklands Islands</LOCATION> garrison in the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   The first of up to 10 transport planes carrying 900 troops
departed at about <TIME>10 p.m.</TIME> from <ORGANIZATION>Brize Norton Royal Air Force</ORGANIZATION> base,
60 miles northwest of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, said a <ORGANIZATION>Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman,
who was not identified in keeping with British custom.
   It was part of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s controversial Fire Focus military
exercise, which marks <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s first major drill in the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION>
since it won a <DATE>1982</DATE> war with <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> over the islands. The 25-day
exercise began <DATE>March 7</DATE>.
   Phantom fighter jets and other planes will fly in from other
British bases, <ORGANIZATION>Royal Air Force</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Michael Hill</PERSON> said.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, backed by other Latin American nations, has called
the <MONEY>$690 million</MONEY> troop movement ``aggravating.'' <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> insisted
it is defensive.
   In the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION>, Gen. <PERSON>Neil Carlier</PERSON> told reporters at <LOCATION>Mount
Pleasant</LOCATION> airport ``it is much cheaper to mount an exercise like
this than to hold a vast number of people down here at taxpayers'
expense which might also, perhaps, send out the wrong signals.''
   <PERSON>Carlier</PERSON> called the nature of the exercise misunderstood and said
the airlift was needed because ``we've just set up in a new base
and not yet had the opportunity to prove the system for having
reinforcements.''
   The 2,000 troops stationed on the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> archipelago
were placed in a state of high readiness to prepare for the arrival
of the reinforcements <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and <DATE>Friday</DATE>, he said.
   The reinforcements will include troops taking the role of the
enemy. Advance personnel, equipment and reporters arrived <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Britain built the airport after the <DATE>1982</DATE> war to accommodate
wide-bodied jets which could be used to rush troops there in the
event of a build-up of tension in the region.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, Argentine forces invaded the islands. Lack of a
suitable runway forced <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> to form a naval task force that took
weeks to reach the islands.
   Britain recaptured the colony after a 74-day conflict which
killed 712 Argentines, 255 Britons and three <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION>
civilians.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, 200 miles west of the islands, claims it inherited
the Falklands from Spanish colonial days and that they were stolen
by <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, which has ruled them as a colony since <DATE>1833</DATE>.
   The 1,900 islanders, most of British descent, say they prefer
British rule.
   This month, the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION> voted 25-0 to
urge <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> to reconsider the exercise. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>St.
Lucia</LOCATION>, a former British colony, abstained.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880308-0187 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-08-88 1617EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Falklands     03-08 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Falklands,0324</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thatcher Says Falklands Exercise `No One Else's Business'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s current military exercise to reinforce the <LOCATION>Falkland
Islands</LOCATION> against possible attack by <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> was ``no one else's
business.''
   Flatly rejecting protests by <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and other Latin American
countries, <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> told the <ORGANIZATION>House of Commons</ORGANIZATION> that <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> had
a right and also ``a duty to see that reinforcement proposals could
in fact be carried out.''
   ``It is no one else's business except the defense of people's
rights in the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON>.
   About 900 troops will travel 8,000 miles next week to the
<LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> from <PERSON>Brize Norton</PERSON> air base, north of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, as
part of the exercise, called Fire Focus.
   The exercise began this week with mythical ``intelligence
reports'' warning that <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> was preparing again to invade the
south <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> archipelago which it has long claimed. The 1,800
British-descended islanders fiercely reject Argentine rule.
   Fire Focus is the first major maneuver announced by <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>
since it recaptured the islands from invading Argentine troops in a
74-day war in <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> has said it gave notice last month to <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> of the
intended exercise and has since announced that Fire Focus will
involve fewer than 1,000 men.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> maintains a garrison, reportedly of about 2,000 men, on
the islands and says it must practice sending in reinforcements in
order to avoid keeping more troops there permanently.
   Briefing reporters at <PERSON>Brize Norton</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, Foreign Office
Assistant Under Secretary <PERSON>Robin Fearn</PERSON> said Fire Focus ``threatens
no one. It is entirely defensive.''
   ``Far from being a cause for concern, it is an integral part of
our policy of reducing tension,'' he added.
   He said the initial post-war garrison had been halved in recent
years after the completion of a new runway at the Falklands
capital, <LOCATION>Port Stanley</LOCATION>, which can take wide-bodied jets.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-6578</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DE0B8AG7FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930527
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 MAY 93 / Survey of Argentina (6): Uncertainty over pensions -
Financial market reform is one of the government's frustrations
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN BARHAM
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
FINANCIAL market reform must rank among the government's great frustrations.
Despite <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s dramatic economic recovery, officials complain that few
private banks have made sufficient progress in modernisation.
And to the government's undisguised concern, bankers have responded to
deregulation by financing a consumer boom. The equity market has failed to
recover from a speculative binge last year.
The principal uncertainty hanging over financial markets is the shape of the
future pension system, which the government hopes will become a cornerstone
of a modern capital market. But pension reform has run into heavy opposition
in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
Politicians have already rejected the plan of economy minister <PERSON>Domingo
Cavallo</PERSON> to force all employees to pay <MONEY>11 per cent</MONEY> of their income into
individual retirement savings accounts, which would be administered by fund
managers.
Instead, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> has made contribution to private pension schemes
voluntary. It has also ordered the government-owned <ORGANIZATION>Banco de la Nacion
Argentina</ORGANIZATION> (BNA) to provide contributors to its pension funds with a minimum
dollar-based guaranteed return.
<PERSON>Mr Cavallo</PERSON> maintains that these are only superficial changes, which do not
affect the heart of pension reform. He is confident that most people will
prefer private pension funds, which he believes will offer higher returns
and will be seen as less risky than the <ORGANIZATION>BNA</ORGANIZATION>'s government-guaranteed fund.
Bankers nevertheless worry that <ORGANIZATION>BNA</ORGANIZATION>'s guaranteed return could not only
hamper private sector competition but would also fail to lighten the burden
of the government's existing pension liabilities. They also wonder how the
government can guarantee millions of <ORGANIZATION>BNA</ORGANIZATION> clients guaranteed dollar incomes,
irrespective of the risk of a devaluation.
Question marks must also remain over the wider issue of how much and how
quickly the pension system can boost <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s savings rate and reduce its
reliance on imported capital. <PERSON>Mr Roque Fernandez</PERSON>, central bank president,
commented that pension funds 'will not bring a phenomenal change. I hope it
comes, but I think it will be gradual.'
Meanwhile, the equity market, which will one of the principal beneficiaries
of a reformed pension system, is in the doldrums. Share prices have been
unable to recover from a disastrous price slide that began last <DATE>June</DATE>. The
Merval market index now stands at less than half its <DATE>May 1992</DATE> high of 882.
The decline has continued this year, spurred by a huge overhang of
overpriced shares still held by investors. Share prices dipped sharply in
<DATE>April</DATE> and <DATE>May</DATE> in anticipation of <DATE>July</DATE>'s planned privatisation of <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s
largest company, the national oil corporation <ORGANIZATION>YPF</ORGANIZATION>. Uncertainty over
President <PERSON>Menem</PERSON>'s re-election bid has also dampened enthusiasm. However,
Argentine stocks are still not cheap, with price/earnings ratios averaging
about 18.
Market capitalisation of USDollars 18bn is equivalent to only 8 per cent of
GDP, a low ratio even by regional standards. Daily turnover rarely exceeds
Dollars 30m, and the market continues to be gripped by a strong speculative
mentality.
Investors are deterred by a narrow market in which liquidity is a problem in
all but a few actively traded stocks. Three companies - two privatised
telephone stocks and the <ORGANIZATION>Perez Companc</ORGANIZATION> holding company - account for half of
market capitalisation.
Instead of listing, companies are actually departing the market, with only
164 companies now quoted against 171 last year. Thirty years ago, the Buenos
Aires market had more than 600 quoted companies. The government's <ORGANIZATION>Comision
Nacional de Valores</ORGANIZATION> checked capital markets regulator has approved more than
30 companies to list, but only a few have come to the market.
Low international interest rates make bond issues more attractive for
companies. <ORGANIZATION>Salomon Brothers</ORGANIZATION> says that last year more than 20 Argentine
companies issued Dollars 1.97bn in bonds, notes and commercial paper.
Possibly the government's greatest frustration is its inability to force
banks to lower interest rates and improve terms for industrial borrowers,
particularly for smaller companies unable to approach the local and
international capital markets.
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s banking system has changed beyond recognition from the chaos and
speculative frenzy of the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. In <DATE>June 1989</DATE>, as hyperinflation raged,
central bank liquid reserves were a mere Dollars 112m. In <DATE>April</DATE>, the second
anniversary of <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s celebrated convertibility law, the central bank's
liquid reserves exceeded Dollars 10bn.
As a result of the confidence brought by convertibility, bank deposits have
risen dramatically and maturities have been stretched out. Last month,
deposits - less than half of them in dollars - stood at Dollars 29.3bn,
against <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 18bn a year earlier. As a result, lending rose to Dollars
41.38bn, against Dollars 24.4bn in <DATE>April 1992</DATE>.
Banks are immensely profitable. Spreads at about 2-3 percentage points
remain high - although they have fallen sharply - and private banks have cut
costs aggressively and boosted lending and fee-based income.
For instance, <PERSON>Banco Frances</PERSON>, a locally owned commercial bank and one of
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s top five banks, saw its net assets grow 137 per cent to Dollars
1.08bn last year, against Dollars 378m prior to currency convertibility. Net
income in the year to <DATE>June 1993</DATE> is forecast at Dollars 47.6m, 37 per cent
more than last year.
Banks are less interested in lending to companies, especially risky small
and medium-sized ones. Instead, most of the profit growth is coming from
lending to consumers.
<PERSON>Mr Nicholas Grose Hodge</PERSON>, chief manager of <ORGANIZATION>Lloyds Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, says
'This continues to be a pretty good year for banks, with one notable
exception - that bad debts and credit risk are getting much worse.' Under an
admittedly broad central bank definition, problem loans stand at 4 to <MONEY>6 per
cent</MONEY> of the private banking system's total loans.
The government is trying use the weight of <ORGANIZATION>BNA</ORGANIZATION>, which is also the country's
biggest financial institution, to drive interest rates down. Interest rates
vary from a real negative monthly rate of 0.5 per cent on blue chip
corporate loans to a stinging real 5 to <MONEY>6 per cent</MONEY> per month for riskier
borrowers.
It has announced that <ORGANIZATION>BNA</ORGANIZATION> will lend Dollars 4.5bn at below market interest
rates to small companies and farmers. But bankers say <ORGANIZATION>BNA</ORGANIZATION>'s efforts are
unlikely to have the desired effect, simply because they have little
intention of competing in the small company and farm lending sectors.
Neither are central bank capital adequacy regulations making much
difference. Central bank regulations require banks charging higher interest
rates to set aside more capital. The government believed this would force
banks to lower rates. But banks, whose gearing, at about 8 times capital, is
low by international standards, have been happy to use their capital as
profitably as possible.
Bankers say that the real culprits are inefficient regional banks, most of
them owned by provincial governments, which distort interest rates
throughout the system. Their funding costs are high, a reflection of the
poor quality of their portfolios. Their operating costs are also higher,
because few government-owned banks have cut costs sufficiently. The
government rejects these claims, stating that banks - private and government
banks alike - remain highly inefficient.
Living with stability is becoming increasingly difficult for smaller and
medium sized banks, a majority of which flourished in the bad old days of
heavy inflation and high interest rates. <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> still has more than 160
banks of varying shapes and sizes. Many will probably merge, seek out niches
in the investment bank market or simply close down.
Some foreign banks with small branch networks have already decided to wind
up retail operations. Chase <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> has sold its 15-branch network and its
credit card business.
<PERSON>Marcelo Podesta</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Chase</ORGANIZATION>'s Buenos Aires managing director, says: 'We did not
want to invest in systems to get up to the scale the (retail) market
required. It is not a priority investment for the bank.' Instead, Chase is
concentrating on sophisticated financial products and project finance for
large clients. The trouble is that with so many banks thinking the same way,
competition in the wholesale market is fierce.
Many retail and wholesale banks have taken an increasingly active role in
privatisations. Some, such as <ORGANIZATION>Banco Rio de la Plata</ORGANIZATION> - the country's biggest
bank - have taken direct stakes in privatised companies. Others have backed
investors in privatisations, underwritten privatisation share flotations, or
structured financing for privatised companies' investments.
<PERSON>Mr Fernandez</PERSON> wants banks to adopt greater securitisation of both their
assets and liabilities, which would reduce institutions' vulnerability to
mismatching or sudden shifts in market conditions. Foreign bankers also
expect the market to make increasing use of sophisticated derivative
products, such as bond- and equity-linked swaps and options.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>ARZ  Argentina, South America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6371 Pension, Health, and Welfare Funds.
    P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
    P6081 Foreign Banking and Branches and Agencies.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 37
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890825-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-25-89 1250EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Falklands Bjt   08-25 0631</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Falklands, Bjt,0653</SECOND>
<HEAD>Falkland Islanders Divided About British-Argentine Talks</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN LEONARD</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STANLEY, Falkland Islands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Falklanders have mixed feelings
about talks on restoring relations between <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>,
which made their rocky, windswept archipelago a battleground seven
years ago.
   Most residents see negotiations as inevitable, but many fear a
deal that could cost them their British status. The first round is
scheduled for <DATE>Oct. 17-18</DATE> in <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION>.
   About 1,800 people live on the bleak islands 300 miles east of
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s tip. The main occupations are fishing and grazing sheep
on the chill moorlands.
   ``I think it's a bit worrying, really,'' said <PERSON>Nancy Poole</PERSON>.``How
far will they go? If they carry on, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> will think <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> is
saying yes to a transfer of sovereignty eventually, I would think.''
   <PERSON>Mrs. Poole</PERSON> is secretary of Desire the Right, the only organized
political party. It hs taken no official position on the talks and
<PERSON>Mrs. Poole</PERSON> said her views were personal.
   <PERSON>Charles Keenleyside</PERSON>, an elected member of the islands' executive
and legislative councils, welcomeed the talks.
   He said a briefing by <PERSON>William Fullerton</PERSON>, the colonial governor,
convinced him ``we are not moving into a situation where items are
being discussed that are specifically against the wishes of the
Falkland Islanders.''
   Keenleyside added, however, that many people oppose any
resumption of links with <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and have deep suspicions about
the negotiations.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> invaded the British colony, which it calls the
<LOCATION>Malvinas</LOCATION>, in <DATE>April 1982</DATE> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> sent a naval force that expelled
the invaders in a 74-day war that cost nearly 1,000 lives. The
Argentines claim the islands under rights dating from Spanish
colonial days.
   Attempts to begin talks foundered on <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s refusal to
negotiate the sovereignty of the islands. They are beginning now
because <PERSON>Carlos Menem</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s new president, agreed to set the
sovereignty issue aside.
   Most islanders trust Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON>'s
determination not to negotiate the islands away, but some wonder
what will happen when she leaves office.
   Senior magistrate <PERSON>Rosie McIlroy</PERSON> is grateful for movement.
   ``I'm glad to see there are talks because it seems to me that the
stalemate that existed before could not benefit anyone,'' she said.
``I do think some form of link with <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> for the <LOCATION>Falkland
Islands</LOCATION> is necessary.''
   Issues at stake include shipping, air and communications links
with <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, all severed since the war.
   Many islanders want no connections at all. They remember the
decade before the war, when the Argentine air force operated the
first regular air service to the islands and its ticket office in
<LOCATION>Stanley</LOCATION> was an intelligence outpost.
   When their troops landed, Argentine commanders had detailed
military and civilian knowledge of the islands.
   ``<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, OK,'' shop owner <PERSON>Peter Short</PERSON> said about
the talks, then added: ``Falklands and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, no.''
   <PERSON>Brian Summers</PERSON>, commercial officer for Cable and Wireless, said of
Menem: ``This man is far too smart. He is going to say all the right
things to the right people.''
   By playing down the sovereignty issue, he suggested, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>
could gradually restore links of all kinds with the islands until
the transfer of sovereignty became inevitable.
   <PERSON>Joe Newell</PERSON>, a former farm manager, took the view that ``we're
going to have to deal with them sometime,'' and lawyer <PERSON>Kevin
Kilmartin</PERSON> said: ``It's quite obvious that <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>
should talk to each other.''
   <PERSON>Kilmartin</PERSON> said he hoped <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> would allow the Falklands
government to make policy in those areas of particular concern to
the islanders.
   Among the thorniest issues is protection of fish stocks in the
<LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION>, where Argentine and Falkland fishing zones abut.
   Islanders also want <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> to stop influencing other South
American nations to deny access to a Falklands passenger and cargo
ship, which now may operate only to <ORGANIZATION>Punta Arenas</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA050390-0241 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 213673 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 3, 1990, Thursday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 2; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
164 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NATION; 
</P>
<P>
D.C.-SIZED ICEBERG LOSING GIRTH 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The oldest known drifting iceberg, a structure once twice the size of the 
nation's capital, is breaking up in the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION>, officials said <DATE>today</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
First spotted by satellite in <DATE>January, 1978</DATE>, when it was about twice the size 
of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, the iceberg was measured in <DATE>1983</DATE> by a <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> 
icebreaker, which found that it still had one side exceeding 20 miles in 
length. 
</P>
<P>
"And that was only the tip of the iceberg," said <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Capt. <PERSON>Tom Callaham</PERSON>, 
"For four years it was grounded in more than 200 feet of water." 
</P>
<P>
The iceberg drifted free in <DATE>1982</DATE> and moved west around <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, driven by a 
current that circulated counterclockwise along the continent's coast, <PERSON>Callaham</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
After a 5,700-mile odyssey that took it almost entirely around the Antarctic 
continent, the iceberg was last sighted in early <DATE>February</DATE> southwest of the 
<LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION>, off the Argentine coast, he said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2032EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Argentina-Britain     12-21 0246</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-Britain,0254</SECOND>
<HEAD>Argentina, Britain Resume Consular Relations</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> resumed
consular ties on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> after a nearly eight-year gap that dated
back to the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> War.
   <PERSON>Alan Hunt</PERSON> presented his credentials to the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> and
was accepted as <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s consul. A similar ceremony took place in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Santos Goni</PERSON> was accredited as the Argentine consul.
   Since the <DATE>1982</DATE> war, which <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> launched to recover
territory in the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> it has claimed since the <DATE>last
century</DATE>, each country has maintained only an interest section in
the other: <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> at <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s embassy in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> at the
<ORGANIZATION>Swiss Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Buenos Aires</LOCATION>.
   Consular flags will be hoisted in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Buenos Aires</ORGANIZATION> on
<DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   The way was paved for a thaw in relations by the election of
<PERSON>Carlos Menem</PERSON> as <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s president last <DATE>May</DATE>. Menem dropped the
government's previous insistence that ownership of the Falklands be
an issue in any bilateral talks.
   The countries have agreed to resume air and maritime
communications and lift all remaining commercial and financial
restrictions and restrictive practices imposed since <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   They also agreed to an umbrella clause that protects their
respective claims to sovereignty over the islands, which are
inhabited by 1,800 people, mostly British descendants.
   A further meeting in <DATE>February</DATE> is expected to lead to resumption
of full diplomatic relations.
   Buenos Aires surrendered to a British task force on <DATE>June 14,
1982</DATE>, 74 days after invading the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> archipelago.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890214-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-14-89 2318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Argentina     02-14 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peronist Candidate Demands Argentine Sovereignty over Falklands</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICENTE L. PANETTA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Presidential candidate <PERSON>Carlos
Menem</PERSON> of the opposition <ORGANIZATION>Peronist Party</ORGANIZATION> was quoted on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as
saying the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> belong to <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and will be
recovered ``even if we must suffer the spilling of blood.''
   ``<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> will not give in,'' <PERSON>Menem</PERSON> said during a campaign
swing <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, according to <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s two independent news
agencies, <ORGANIZATION>Diarios y Noticias</ORGANIZATION> and Noticias Argentinas.
   The Malvinas _ <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s name for the territory off its south
coast that it has claimed since <DATE>1810</DATE> _ ``will return to form part of
the national territory even if we must suffer the spilling of
blood,'' he was quoted as saying.
   Menem was on a visit to <LOCATION>Ushuaia</LOCATION>, 2,045 miles south of the capital
city of <ORGANIZATION>Buenos Aires</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> went to war over the sparsely populated,
windswept and virtually treeless islands in <DATE>1982</DATE>. Argentine troops
invaded on <DATE>April 2</DATE>. A British expeditionary force recovered the
islands after a counterattack in which 712 Argentine and 255 British
soldiers died.
   The war lasted 74 days. <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> surrendered but refused to
formally declare an end to hostilities. Neither side resumed
diplomatic relations.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s claim dates to <DATE>1833</DATE>. It has since fortified the islands
and enforced a 200-mile zone of exclusion around them. <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> has
tried to isolate the islands commercially by prohibiting direct
flights or ships from the mainland.
   It has tried to apply international pressure to force <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> to
negotiate the islands' sovereignty. British Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret
Thatcher</PERSON> has refused.
   The two agencies also quoted Menem as saying: ``I don't know how
much time will pass or how much blood we will have to spill to see
that the <LOCATION>Malvinas</LOCATION> return to Argentine territory.''
   President <PERSON>Raul Alfonsin</PERSON> and Foreign Minister <PERSON>Dante Caputo</PERSON>, who
also is president of the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>, have said <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>
inherited the islands upon declaring independence from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, and
the government will try to recover them peacefully through
negotiation.
   Ownership is an article of faith here. Argentine maps identify
the islands as the <LOCATION>Malvinas</LOCATION>, and schoolchildren are taught they were
stolen by <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
   Recovering the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION> is a main foreign policy theme of
political groups from both left and right, along with the 4
million-member <ORGANIZATION>General Labor Confederation</ORGANIZATION> which backs <PERSON>Menem</PERSON>.
   Menem in the past said he would seek the islands' recovery by
diplomacy if he wins election on <DATE>May 14</DATE>. It was not known whether he
was speaking rhetorically in <LOCATION>Ushuaia</LOCATION>, or shifting and hardening his
position.
   A telephone call seeking comment from the British Interests
Section at the <ORGANIZATION>Swiss Embassy</ORGANIZATION> rang repeatedly but was not answered.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900216-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-16-90 0543EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Britain-Argentina 1stLd-Writethru   02-16 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Britain-Argentina, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0468,0594</SECOND>
<HEAD>Britain, Argentina Restore Ties Despite Falklands Dispute</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS graf after 5th pvs, `In Buenos...' to UPDATE with
Menem naming ambassador; picks up 6th pvs, `Menem, however...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL WEST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> renewed diplomatic ties
severed nearly eight years ago over the Falklands War, but
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> said it would keep pressing its claim over the islands.
   Foreign Secretary <PERSON>Douglas Hurd</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> praised the accord
reached <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> after two days of talks.
   ``It underlines the fact that we have no quarrel with <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>,
and this has been achieved without any sacrifice of sovereignty,''
he said on <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s private Sky Television.
   Foreign Minister <PERSON>Domingo Cavallo</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s
accord ``means passing from a state of war to a state of peace.''
   In <ORGANIZATION>Buenos Aires</ORGANIZATION>, President <PERSON>Carlos Menem</PERSON> said the accord opened
up trade possibilities for <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, a major meat exporter. It
followed the resumption <DATE>last month</DATE> of direct air service between
the two nations, who traditionally were heavy trading partners.
   Menem also named Deputy Foreign Minister <PERSON>Mario Campora</PERSON>, nephew
of former president <PERSON>Hector Campora</PERSON>, as the ambassador to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
   Menem, however, repeated <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s claim to sovereignty of the
<LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> islands 300 miles off his country's southeastern
coast. He said its claim was not diminished by restoring diplomatic
ties.
   The Falklands War broke out after Argentine forces invaded the
British-ruled islands on <DATE>April 2, 1982</DATE>. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> sent a military
task force that recaptured them after a 74-day war.
   The fighting claimed the lives of 712 Argentines, 255 Britons
and three islanders.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> began ruling the islands as a colony in <DATE>1833</DATE> after <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>
ceased to govern <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and abandoned the archipelago.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> claims it inherited the islands under the name <ORGANIZATION>Las
Malvinas</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and says <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> stole them.
   British Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> has refused to discuss
Falklands sovereignty with <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>. In turn, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> refused
until <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to declare the war officially over.
   U.N. Secretary-General <PERSON>Javier Perez de Cuellar</PERSON> applauded the
accord, saying it ``creates an atmosphere of confidence.''
   Talks between British and Argentine officials on resuming normal
relations began in <DATE>August</DATE> after <PERSON>Menem</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> would not use
them to raise its claim over the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION>.
   A key to the <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> agreement was <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s agreement to lift
its 150-mile military protection zone around the islands. British
submarines, ships and planes have patrolled the zone.
   The islands are guarded by about 2,000 British troops.
   The British Foreign office said the two nations had agreed to
inform each other about movements of their warships and military
aircraft in key areas of the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> and give notice of
large military exercises.
   Under the arrangement, Argentine warships wishing to come within
50 miles of the islands and Argentine warplanes wishing to come
within 70 miles must give 48 hours warning.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Office</ORGANIZATION> said ambassadors will be exchanged ``in due
course.''
   Hurd said: ``It is for the <ORGANIZATION>Falkland Islanders</ORGANIZATION> to decide on their
own contacts with the mainland (<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>).''
   Most of the 1,900 islanders are fiercely pro-British. Their
legislative council refused an invitation to join the <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> talks.
   <PERSON>William Fullerton</PERSON>, governor of the islands, told British
television's Channel 4 News from <ORGANIZATION>Stanley</ORGANIZATION>, the capital: ``They
accept that there should be good relations between <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>.''
   He added, `The thing they would be worried about is the
sovereignty issue, and all along that has been specifically
excluded from the talks.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021690-0066 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 177193 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 16, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 17; Column 3; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
204 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ARGENTINA, BRITAIN HEAL RIFT CAUSED BY FALKLANDS WAR 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MADRID 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>South Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The announcement capped two days of talks here between Argentine and British 
officials. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> agreed to lift by <DATE>March 31</DATE> a 150-mile military protection zone enforced 
around the islands since <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> invaded them in <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The pact calls for advance notice by each side of military exercises around the 
islands, which are home to about 1,900 people. 
</P>
<P>
In the war over the islands, called the Malvinas by <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, 712 Argentines, 
255 Britons and three islanders died. <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Buenos Aires</ORGANIZATION> broke diplomatic 
relations during the conflict. 
</P>
<P>
The agreement announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> stipulated that talks will continue between 
the two nations on fishing around the islands -- an important source of revenue 
-- and that the <ORGANIZATION>International Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> will work out visits by Argentines to 
war cemeteries in the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
By mutual consent, the latest talks did not touch on claims to sovereignty over 
the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION>, which <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> have disputed since <DATE>1833</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ARGENTINA -- FOREIGN RELATIONS -- ENGLAND; ARGENTINA -- DIPLOMATIC RECOGNITION 
-- ENGLAND; FALKLAND ISLANDS; FALKLAND ISLANDS WAR 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910130-0109
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910130-0109.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   International:
   Menem Cabinet
   Shuffled After
   Currency Dives
   ----
   By Thomas Kamm
</HL>
<DATE>
01/30/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A7
</SO>
<CO>
   LATAM
</CO>
<IN>
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC NEWS AND STATISTICS (IEN)
FOREIGN-EXCHANGE MARKETS (FRX)
BANKS (BNK)
</IN>
<LP>
   The two main watchdogs over Argentina's fragile economy
resigned after a massive run on the national currency.
   The resignations of Economics Minister Antonio Erman
Gonzalez and Central Bank Governor Javier Gonzalez Fraga
followed a 20% plunge in the value of the austral against the
U.S. dollar on Monday. The austral's plummeting fortunes --
it's down 40% so far this month -- is likely to translate
into a burst of inflation, undermining Argentina's shaky
economic recovery, economists say.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The resignation of <PERSON>Mr. Gonzalez</PERSON>, nicknamed "Superman" for
his initial success in cutting inflation, underlines the
continued instability of <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s politics and economy.
<PERSON>Mr. Gonzalez</PERSON>, an ally of President <PERSON>Carlos Menem</PERSON>, was viewed
abroad as a courageous minister. His resignation is a new
setback for <PERSON>Mr. Menem</PERSON> at a time when the president is trying
to contain damage caused by a short-lived military rebellion
last month, an unpopular amnesty granted to several of
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s former military rulers and accusations by the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ambassador of government corruption.
   A presidential spokesman said Foreign Minister <PERSON>Domingo
Cavallo</PERSON>, a Harvard-trained economist, will succeed <PERSON>Mr.
Gonzalez</PERSON>, becoming <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s fourth economics minister
since <PERSON>Mr. Menem</PERSON> took office 19 months ago. <PERSON>Mr. Gonzalez</PERSON> will
be the new defense minister.
   Argentine authorities closed banks and financial markets
yesterday, but said they would reopen today. Messrs. <PERSON>Cavallo</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> gave a joint news conference <TIME>last night</TIME> and <PERSON>Mr.
Cavallo</PERSON> pledged to pursue <PERSON>Mr. Menem</PERSON>'s unpopular free-market
policies, including privatization of state companies and
trade liberalization, while seeking to bring down the
overvalued austral in order to boost production and exports.
   While <PERSON>Mr. Menem</PERSON> spent most of the day in conferences with
<PERSON>Messrs. Gonzalez</PERSON>, <PERSON>Cavallo</PERSON> and other top officials, scenes of
confusion filled the country. Cash machines ran out of bills
as they were raided by Argentines caught off-guard by the
bank closure. The federation of small shopkeepers urged
members to stay closed during the bank holiday because of
price uncertainty. Other stores raised prices by as much as
<PERCENT>40%</PERCENT>. The price of meat at the Liniers cattle market, the
country's biggest, rose by <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> yesterday.
   Although the size and swiftness of the austral's nose dive
was a surprise, the market had been signaling its displeasure
with the artificially low exchange rate for some time. While
it succeeded in reducing inflation -- the consumer price
index has been below two digits for three months and fell to
<PERCENT>4.7%</PERCENT> in <DATE>December</DATE> -- the low rate created huge problems for
industrial exporters and farmers, who recently threatened to
stop paying taxes because of their declining revenue.
   President <PERSON>Menem</PERSON> reportedly asked conservative economist
<PERSON>Roberto Alemann</PERSON> to become <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s seventh central bank
president in 18 months. If <PERSON>Mr. Alemann</PERSON> accepts, a clash looms
with <PERSON>Mr. Cavallo</PERSON>. <PERSON>Mr. Alemann</PERSON>, who twice served as
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s economy minister, reportedly wants autonomy for
the <ORGANIZATION>Central Bank</ORGANIZATION>, which regulates interest rates, the money
supply and transfers to heavily indebted provincial banks.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900208-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-08-90 1224EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Falklands     02-08 0313</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Falklands,0323</SECOND>
<HEAD>British, Argentine Officials Open Talks on Falklands</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MADRID, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   British and Argentine officials opened two
days of talks <DATE>Thursday</DATE> on issues related to the disputed <LOCATION>Falkland
Islands</LOCATION>, a step toward restoring full diplomatic ties, embassy
spokesmen said.
   An <ORGANIZATION>Argentine Embassy</ORGANIZATION> official who spoke on condition of
anonymity said <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> would ask <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> to drop the 150-mile
military ``protection zone'' around the Falklands, which <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>
calls the <LOCATION>Malvinas Islands</LOCATION>.
   The zone has been enforced since <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> invaded the <LOCATION>South
Atlantic</LOCATION> islands in <DATE>1982</DATE>. The Argentine soldiers were driven off by
British troops after a 74-day war.
   Britain now requires Argentine military ships to request and
receive British permission before entering the zone.
   The talks <DATE>Thursday</DATE> were held at the Argentine ambassador's
residence in central <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION>. On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the talks will move across
the street to the <ORGANIZATION>British Embassy</ORGANIZATION>.
   A <ORGANIZATION>British Embassy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said details of the meetings were
not expected to be made public.
   The talks serve as a preliminary step to high-level meetings in
<LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> on <DATE>Feb. 14-15</DATE> that will be aimed at restoring full
diplomatic relations.
   <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> has claimed the islands since declaring independence
from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1816</DATE>. British claims to the islands are based on
   Relations between the two countries have improved considerably
since <DATE>October</DATE>, when two days of talks in <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> ended with the
restoration of consular relations and an agreement to move toward
normal diplomatic and economic relations.
   Since then, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> has allowed British vessels and planes to
operate freely in Argentine territory, and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> has lifted a
restriction on the navigation of Argentine merchant ships in the
150-mile military protection zone around the <LOCATION>Falklands</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s five-man delegation at this week's talks was led by
<PERSON>Adrian Beamish</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Office</ORGANIZATION>'s assistant undersecretary of
state for the <LOCATION>Americas</LOCATION>.
   The Argentine side was headed by <PERSON>Jose Maria Otegui</PERSON>,
director-general for the <LOCATION>Malvinas</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-5122</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFFAXABRFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930605
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  05 JUN 93 / Glory days gone for now: Edward Balls says England's
football decline mirrors its economy
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By EDWARD BALLS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Gutted', 'gob-smacked', 'sick as a parrot' - no footballing cliche can
adequately characterise the depth of national despair that engulfed <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>
after <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s World Cup defeat at the hands of <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> - where the game of football was invented - was beaten 2-0 in <LOCATION>Oslo</LOCATION>
and probably ejected from the <DATE>1994</DATE> World Cup final round, to be held in
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> next year.
And at the hands of <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>, too. <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>, more famous for its fish than its
football, with a population a 10th that of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s. A country that
worshipped English soccer (as <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> commentator <PERSON>John Motson</PERSON> reminded his
unfortunate audience) had trounced <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s national team.
But the defeat has been interpreted as more than just a freak - a single
poor performance by a disorganised team. Instead, it is seen as further
evidence that the decline of English football has become terminal. 'Fatal
flaws of woeful <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> exposed', thundered The Times; 'Norse manure', The
Sun added.
Yet was anyone really surprised? <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> still has a seat on the <ORGANIZATION>UN Security
Council</ORGANIZATION>; it has nuclear weapons; it even won the World Cup (at home) in
<DATE>1966</DATE>. But surely the decline of English football has gone hand in hand with
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s relative economic decline.
Starting with the 6-3 home defeat at the hands of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> in <DATE>1953</DATE>, the
first-ever defeat at <LOCATION>Wembley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s footballing star has been waning,
along with its economic clout. Since <DATE>1953</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>England</ORGANIZATION> has slipped from second to
fifth in the world in terms of output; it has fallen considerably further
down the league table of income per head. More populous nations, such as
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, have risen to prominence on the world footballing
stage.
The <ORGANIZATION>FT</ORGANIZATION>'s analysis of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s World Cup record since <DATE>1953</DATE> suggests that the
English soccer team has continued to do better than might be expected from
the country's size and economic power. The analysis awards points for
performance in the final rounds of the World Cup (failure to qualify scores
no points). It divides the 10 World Cup competitions from <DATE>1953</DATE> into two
groups, the split coming between the <DATE>1970</DATE> and <DATE>1974</DATE> contests. The year <DATE>1973</DATE>
was a watershed for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. In addition to the <ORGANIZATION>Opec</ORGANIZATION> oil shock and the
<PERSON>Barber</PERSON> boom, it saw the English soccer team draw 1-1 with <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Wembley</ORGANIZATION>
in <DATE>October</DATE>. The side was eliminated from the competition during the
qualifying stages (see charts).
From <DATE>1954</DATE> to <DATE>1970</DATE>, English soccer continued to fare comparatively well,
despite the country being overtaken in economic size by <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, and suffering the shock of sterling's <DATE>1967</DATE> devaluation. The English
team ranked third, well behind <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
From <DATE>1970</DATE> on, it was downhill all the way. Inflation soared during the
<DATE>1970s</DATE>, labour relations deteriorated, and the <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> team failed to qualify
for either World Cup tournament. Despite qualifying in <DATE>1982</DATE>, <DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1990</DATE>,
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> has been overtaken in the rankings by <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. Only <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s fortuitous <DATE>1990</DATE> victory over <LOCATION>Cameroon</LOCATION> prevented the
team from falling behind <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>.
The biggest shifts in relative soccer performance since <DATE>1970</DATE> have been the
slippage of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and the collapse of the communist teams - only <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> has
bucked the trend, coming from nowhere to sixth place in <DATE>1974-90</DATE>; the rise of
continental European football; and the enormous success of <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> since
the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
The economic background to these changes provides few clues as to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s
relative footballing decline. High and fluctuating inflation since <DATE>1973</DATE>
might have been a clue to the decline of both <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, though on
different scales, were it not for the rise of <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>. Nor does the
decline of Soviet-style collectivism help explain why British soccer has
withered alongside British socialism. If anything, the rise of Thatcherite
individualism is a better explanation for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s poor performance at team
games.
Despite the present gloom, it appears that <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s declining World Cup
performance has continued to outstrip its economic record. Over the period
1974-90, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> ranked seventh in the FT World Cup league table. But among
World Cup qualifying nations, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> now has only the 11th-biggest
population and the 14th-highest income per head. Defeat by <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION> is not so
surprising. Though smaller, it is now much richer than <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> - Dollars
6,000 a person a year richer in <DATE>1990</DATE>, according to the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>.
So why has England taken the defeat so badly? Part of the explanation is
economic. For a country grappling to get out of recession, and with a prime
minister ill at ease with himself, failure to qualify for the <DATE>1994</DATE> World Cup
final seems disastrous. The other reason is more simple: <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s
performance on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> was terrible. A shocked <PERSON>Mr Graham Taylor</PERSON>, the
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> manager, accused his players of giving up. 'It's a performance that
will make people back home very angry,' he said.
But <PERSON>Mr Taylor</PERSON> must take his share of the blame. It was his last-minute
tactical decisions which caused the players to appear like 'headless
chickens' on the pitch. Refusing to select <PERSON>Chris Waddle</PERSON>, and playing <PERSON>Gary
Pallister</PERSON> at left-back, made little sense.
Following <PERSON>Mr John Major</PERSON>'s example, he will have to consider a reshuffle. But
it may not be enough to produce a winning team.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7941 Sports Clubs, Managers, and Promoters.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-10571</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CG3AYAATFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920730
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 JUL 92 / Latin America Debt Crisis: Chronolgy of events - 1982-1985 /
Ten years ago next month the Latin American debt crisis broke - and threw
the world financial system into turmoil. On these pages writers who followed
the story for the Financial Times from the outset analyse how the crisis was
handled. And they pose the question: Is there life after debt?
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALEXANDER NICOLL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
1982
<LOCATION>MEXICO</LOCATION>, facing foreign borrowing requirement of more than Dollars 20bn
(Pounds 10.4bn) for the year, raises Dollars 5bn in <DATE>first quarter</DATE>, although
at higher interest rates than previously. Outflow of dollars prompts several
sharp devaluations of peso during year. Inflation accelerates rapidly and
oil revenues decline.
<DATE>April</DATE> - <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s invasion of <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> provokes conflict with
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and slows new lending to <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>. Mexico draws on swap line
with <ORGANIZATION>US Federal Reserve</ORGANIZATION> and meets difficulties in arranging loans from
banks.
<DATE>August</DATE> - <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> introduces exchange controls, seeks emergency finance from
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and international financial institutions. On <DATE>August 20</DATE> finance minister
meets creditor banks in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and announces three-month moratorium on
Dollars 10bn of debt principal repayments. Central banks agree Dollars
1.85bn emergency loan to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> 'to ensure continued smooth functioning of
the international financing system'. US provides Dollars 2bn credit. Mexico
to seek <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> and bank loans. Creditor banks form
advisory committee chaired by <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION>.
<DATE>September</DATE> - <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> nationalises banks and imposes total exchange control.
Central bank heads consider Latin American payment problems. One says: 'To
say that we are concerned could be an understatement.' International
Monetary Fund and <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> hold annual meetings in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> in atmosphere
of panic.
<DATE>October</DATE> - <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> arranges emergency short-term bank loan, sells gold.
<DATE>November</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> managing director <ORGANIZATION>Jacques de Larosiere</ORGANIZATION> tells bank chairmen he
expects them to make new Dollars 5bn loan to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and Dollars 1.5bn loan
to <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, to support economic policies under <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION>
programmes.
<DATE>December</DATE> - Banks commit to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> loan. <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> arranges Dollars 1.5bn in
emergency loans from <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and says it will seek new 'jumbo' bank loan. But, as
year ends, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> also halts repayment of debt principal.
<DATE>1983
January</DATE> - Pattern emerges for handling LDC debt problems. Key elements are:
IMF-agreed economic programme and <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> loan, rescheduling of some debt
principal repayments to banks and governments, and large new loans. This
involves close co-operation among debtors, international institutions and
creditors. Packages under way for <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION> and,
soon, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> contain all these elements. Bridging loans tide
borrowers over until the full agreements are signed.
<DATE>February</DATE> - <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> signs Dollars 4bn new bank loan and Dollars 4.8bn
rescheduling, but suffers severe difficulties in maintaining short-term
interbank lines of credit to foreign branches of its banks, a crucial
element of financing programme. It misses <DATE>first-quarter</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>International
Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> economic targets. Interest payment arrears build up to Dollars
2bn by <DATE>August</DATE>. Economic programme and rescue package have to be re-drawn.
March - <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s banks sign Dollars 5bn new loan (agreed in <DATE>1982</DATE>) and, in
<DATE>August</DATE>, agreements rescheduling Dollars 20bn of debt principal falling due
to banks in <DATE>1983</DATE> and <DATE>1984</DATE>.
<DATE>September</DATE> - At <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> annual meeting, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> agrees in
principle with creditors on Dollars 11bn rescue package involving Dollars
6.5bn new bank loan, rescheduling of debts falling due up to the end of
<DATE>1984</DATE>. Leading creditor banks and central bankers embark on successful
worldwide 'roadshow' to persuade other creditor banks to join the deal.
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> begins to reduce interest arrears.
1984
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> builds up interest arrears of Dollars 2.7bn by end-March. Impasse
in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>'s negotiations with <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> and banks means <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> banks must count
loans as 'non-performing' for first time in debt crisis.
<DATE>June</DATE> - Banks agree in principle to provide 'multi-year rescheduling
agreement' (Myra) for <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, lowering interest rates on rescheduled debt
and stretching out six years' maturities, totalling Dollars 48bn. <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>
signs Myra in <DATE>July</DATE>. In <DATE>September</DATE> Venezuela agrees in principle on <LOCATION>Dollars
21bn Myra</LOCATION>. In <DATE>December</DATE> Argentina agrees in principle on Dollars 14bn Myra
and agrees to cut interest arrears, and <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> endorses
economic programme.
<DATE>1985</DATE>
<ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> suspends loans to <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> as
economic targets missed. In negotiation of new targets, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> seeks greater
flexibility from <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> - but in <DATE>August</DATE> finance
minister and central bank governor resign in frustration over lack of
economic austerity policies, and government embarks on expansionist
approach. <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> announces unilateral limit on debt service payments: 10 per
cent of export receipts. <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> agrees new economic stabilisation package
with <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> as inflation reaces 1,000 per cent. In
<DATE>July</DATE>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> introduces new austerity package as oil revenues drop and
misses International Monetary Fund targets. In <DATE>September</DATE>, earthquakes
devastate <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> seeks <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> 'monitoring
of economy' rather than full agreement.
<DATE>September</DATE> - At <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> annual meeting in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
treasury secretary <PERSON>James Baker</PERSON> unveils new approach to debt, known as
<ORGANIZATION>Programme</ORGANIZATION> for Sustained Growth or Baker Plan. Key elements are:
Economic reform by debtor countries to promote growth and balance of
payments adjustment, and to reduce inflation.
Increased structural adjustment lending by multilateral development banks as
well as continued central role for <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>.
Increased lending by commercial banks: net new lending of Dollars 20bn over
next three years to heavily indebted middle-income countries.
Maintenance of case-by-case approach to debtors.
Larger debtors and creditors give qualified support to <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> Plan.
Chronology of events: <DATE>1986-1992
1986
June</DATE> - Mexican finance minister <PERSON>Jesus Silva Herzog</PERSON> resigns as oil revenues
drop and economy worsens. In <DATE>July</DATE> his successor <PERSON>Gustavo Petricioli</PERSON> agrees
growth-oriented economic programme with <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION>,
clearing the way for negotiations with banks.
At <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION> annual meeting, a year after <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> Plan
announced, banks and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> agree in principle on Dollars 7.7bn new loan and
Dollars 54bn loan rescheduling, first under the plan, with 20-year maturity
and <PERCENT>13/16 percentage point</PERCENT> interest margin - seen as too concessional by
some banks. By <DATE>December</DATE> banks' commitments to loan are sufficient to put the
<ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION>'s rescue package into effect.
<DATE>1987
February</DATE> - <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> halts interest payments on Dollars 68bn of debt to banks.
<DATE>April</DATE> - <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> agrees with banks in principle on <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> Plan deal for new
loan and Dollars 24bn rescheduling on terms similar to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s. Package
features first 'menu of options,' including chance for banks to convert
loans into 'exit' bonds.
May - <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION>, biggest lender to third world, adds Dollars 3bn to loan loss
reserves and says it will seek to 'liquefy' third world loan portfolio by
selling loans and using instruments such as debt/equity swaps. Its share
price rises. Other <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> banks follow with similar loss provisions.
