<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880318-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-18-88 2251EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BuffaloBill     03-18 0433</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Buffalo Bill,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Largest Buffalo Bill Collection Sold At Auction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY McGRATH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Museum curators, history buffs and urban
cowboys bought up the biggest collection of <PERSON>William F.</PERSON> ``Buffalo
Bill'' Cody memorabilia ever auctioned <DATE>Friday</DATE>, including a
silver-trimmed rifle that brought <MONEY>$22,500</MONEY>.
   The collection, sold at <ORGANIZATION>Butterfield &amp; Butterfield</ORGANIZATION>, consisted of
more than 300 items originally preserved by <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>'s sister, <PERSON>Julia
Cody Goodman</PERSON>.
   A pair of chaps worn by the <ORGANIZATION>Pony Express</ORGANIZATION> rider, Indian fighter,
buffalo hunter, <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> scout and showman sold for <MONEY>$1,400</MONEY>, and a rope
lariat went for <MONEY>$500</MONEY>.
   A silver-handled Plains rifle fetched <MONEY>$22,500</MONEY>. Other items
included <PERSON>Cody</PERSON>'s buffalo-hide coat and his silver-handled toothbrush.
   ``Who better symbolizes the American West than Buffalo Bill?''
asked <PERSON>R.L. Wilson</PERSON>, historical consultant to <ORGANIZATION>Colt Firearms Co.</ORGANIZATION> of
<LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn</LOCATION>. He came to bid on a single-action Colt revolver,
one of eight guns in the collection.
   The collection was sold by <PERSON>Greg Martin</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> gun
collector and history buff who bought the artifacts for <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY>
last year in <LOCATION>Billings</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mont</LOCATION>. He had wanted to buy only a shotgun
inscribed to <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>, but had to buy the whole lot to get the shotgun
from the elderly owner.
   Rival bidders eyeing each other across the auction floor
included curator <PERSON>Paul Fees</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cody</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Thomas B. Morrison</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill Ranch Historic
Park</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neb</LOCATION>.
   They vied for a collection of letters to <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>'s sister
discussing his marriage, the death of his son and other intimate
events.
   ``We are interested in the correspondence because it is so
revealing and personal,'' said Fees. ``We have a strong
biographical interest.''
   The collection was unique for its large number of personal
items, including a tomahawk from his friend D.F. ``White Beaver''
<PERSON>Powell</PERSON> and dozens of photographs, show bills and theater tickets
chronicling Cody's life as the roughrider who along with shooting
champion W. ``Doc'' <PERSON>Carver</PERSON> founded the first Wild West Show.
   <PERSON>Carl Otis</PERSON>, owner of Pawnee Bill's Wild West Exposition
Re-enacted, a <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> traveling show, dressed in white
Stetson hat and buckskin jacket for the occasion. He bid <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> on
a <ORGANIZATION>Smith &amp; Wesson</ORGANIZATION> ivory-handled revolver used in Cody's Wild West
Show but the gun went for <MONEY>$9,000</MONEY>.
   Private collector <PERSON>George Kramer</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> real estate
developer, hoped to buy Cody's silver riding bit for his
80-year-old father, who still rides. But he bid first on <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>'s
Winchester rifle, inscribed and hand-carved with buffalo.
   ``That's the one item I wanted most,'' said <PERSON>Kramer</PERSON>, who
successfully bid <MONEY>$11,000</MONEY> for it.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880319-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-19-88 0433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BuffaloBill     03-19 0393</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Buffalo Bill,0402</SECOND>
<HEAD>Buffalo Bill Collection Sold At Auction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY McGRATH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> developer and a Wild West show
owner are among the Western history buffs who bought up the largest
collection of ``Buffalo Bill'' Cody memorabilia ever auctioned _
with some pieces fetching more than twice their appraised value.
   ``Who better symbolizes the American West than <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill?''
said buyer <PERSON>R.L. Wilson</PERSON>, a historical consultant to the <ORGANIZATION>Colt
Firearms Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, who bid <DATE>Friday</DATE> on one of eight
guns in the collection.
   The prices paid ranged from <MONEY>$175</MONEY> for a telegram sent by the
legendary roughrider and showman to <MONEY>$22,500</MONEY> for a silver-handled
Plains rifle.
   In all, more than <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> was spent on the collection of over
300 items, which were perserved by <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>'s sister, <PERSON>Julia Cody
Goodman</PERSON>, auction officials said.
   The collection was sold by <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> gun collector <PERSON>Greg
Martin</PERSON>, who bought the artifacts for <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> last year, removing
them from storage in <LOCATION>Billings</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>, for the first time in 20
years.
   The collection was unique for its large number of personal
items, including Cody's buffalo-hide coat that sold for <MONEY>$18,000</MONEY> and
a letter that sold for <MONEY>$3,575</MONEY> in which <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION> discusses the death of
his son. The prices included a <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> fee for the auction
house, <ORGANIZATION>Butterfield &amp; Butterfield</ORGANIZATION>.
   Also up for auction were other letters to <PERSON>Cody</PERSON>'s sister
discussing his marriage and other intimate events.
   ``We are interested in the correspondence because it is so
revealing and personal,'' <PERSON>Paul Fees</PERSON>, curator of the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill
Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cody</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, said before the bidding began. ``We have a
strong biographical interest.''
   Other bidders for the letters included <PERSON>Thomas B. Morrison</PERSON>, of
the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill Ranch Historic Park</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neb</LOCATION>. Cody
descendant <PERSON>Walter Goodman</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Julia Cody</PERSON>'s grandson, was
expected to bid for the letters by phone, <PERSON>Fees</PERSON> said. The names of
the successful bidders were not known.
   A pair of chaps worn by <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION> sold for <MONEY>$1,400</MONEY> and a rope lariat
went for <MONEY>$500</MONEY>. Other items included <PERSON>Cody</PERSON>'s silver-handled
toothbrush, a family Bible and dozens of photographs, show bills
and theater tickets chronicling <PERSON>William F. Cody</PERSON>'s life as the
Indian fighter, buffalo hunter and scout who, along with shooting
champion W. ``Doc'' <PERSON>Carver</PERSON>, founded the first Wild West Show. Cody
died in <DATE>1917</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880318-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-18-88 0831EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BuffaloBill     03-18 0510</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Buffalo Bill,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>Buffalo Bill Collection Largest Ever To Go On Auction</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Auction set for 1 p.m.; tops uncertain.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARY McGRATH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Buffalo <PERSON>Bill</PERSON>'s buffalo-hide coat, eight
guns and a tomahawk go on the auction block today in the largest
sale yet of Wild West memorabilia collected by the legendary
<PERSON>William F. Cody</PERSON>.
   The 300 items offered for sale belong to <LOCATION>San</LOCATION> Franciscan <PERSON>Greg
Martin</PERSON>, who acquired the collection after he had been unable to buy
the single item he wanted.
   It was a double-barrel shotgun that brought <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> to a
warehouse in <LOCATION>Billings</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>, last year.
   ``I saw it up in storage ... and my pulse skipped a beat,'' said
<PERSON>Martin</PERSON>, who offered to buy the Westley-Richards English shotgun
inscribed to Cody.
   When the elderly owner refused to sell just one item, <PERSON>Martin</PERSON>
wrote a check for <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> for the entire collection and took it
out of storage for the first time in 20 years.
   ``He is the living symbol of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and one of the most famous
Americans who ever lived,'' said <PERSON>Martin</PERSON>, 49, a gun collector and
aficionado of American history. ``The way we look at the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> is
because of how <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill showed it to us.''
   The collection, to be auctioned by <ORGANIZATION>Butterfield &amp; Butterfield</ORGANIZATION>,
includes the buffalo-hide coat worn by <PERSON>Cody</PERSON> and the gun he carried
as a 14-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Pony Express</ORGANIZATION> rider. Cody's single-action Colt
revolver, the type he used as a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> scout, is one of eight
guns in the collection.
   Items such as a tomahawk from <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>'s friend D.F. ``White
Beaver'' <PERSON>Powell</PERSON>, along with dozens of photographs, show bills and
theater tickets chronicle <PERSON>Cody</PERSON>'s life as an Indian fighter, buffalo
hunter and scout who along with shooting champion W. ``Doc'' <PERSON>Carver</PERSON>
founded the first Wild West Show.
   For 11 years, after dime-novel writer <PERSON>Ned Buntline</PERSON> persuaded
Cody to appear in the first ``Scouts of the Prairie'' show, <PERSON>Cody</PERSON>
traveled between <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> theaters and the plains.
   The collection consists of items preserved by <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>'s adoring
sister, <PERSON>Julia Cody Goodman</PERSON>, and includes the <PERSON>Cody</PERSON> family Bible and
letters to <LOCATION>Julia</LOCATION> in which <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION> discussed a troubled marriage, the
death of his son and other intimate events.
   The engraved shotgun, the only item not up for auction, will
remain in <ORGANIZATION>Martin</ORGANIZATION>'s home, a three-story Victorian crammed with
Western artifacts including a likeness of Chief Sitting Bull and
the pearl-handled <ORGANIZATION>Smith &amp; Wesson</ORGANIZATION> revolvers owned by <PERSON>Annie Oakley</PERSON>.
   Martin, a former real estate broker, once paid <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> for
<ORGANIZATION>Bill Harrah's Pony Express Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Reno</ORGANIZATION>, and maintains his
collection with the help of his wife, <PERSON>Petra</PERSON>, a former federal judge
in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
   He flew to Billings in search of the collection when he learned
<PERSON>Julia Cody Goodman</PERSON>'s daughter, <PERSON>Josie</PERSON>, sold it for <MONEY>$1</MONEY> to a woman
named <PERSON>Stella Foote</PERSON> to keep it from going to the <ORGANIZATION>Cody Museum</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Cody</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said.
   The collection traveled the world under the sponsorship of the
<ORGANIZATION>Department of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> before it was placed in storage by <PERSON>Foote</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06074219 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06074219 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  TRAVEL; WYOMING; HISTORY; US; PARK; NEIGHBORHOOD  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THIS LITTLE town 52 miles from Yellowstone National Park pretty much lives on
the legend of William F. "Buffalo Bill" Cody.;    It should -- he founded the
town around the turn of the century.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Venture  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CODY IS A MUST FOR YOU BUFFALO BILL BUFFS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Venture -- Celebrating the Active Life
See also related story on P. 1G of this section  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     There's the <LOCATION>Buffalo Bill Village</LOCATION>, a re-created Western town with authentic
buildings.;    Outside town is the big <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill Reservoir. Then there is
the <ORGANIZATION>Bill Cody Ranch Resort</ORGANIZATION>, a hunting/fishing/riding lodge owned by <PERSON>Buffalo
Bill</PERSON>'s 78-year-old grandson, also named Bill Cody.;    A few miles up the
road, not far from the entrance to <ORGANIZATION>Yellowstone National Park</ORGANIZATION>, is the <ORGANIZATION>Pahaska
Tepee Resort</ORGANIZATION>, which was built by <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill.</ORGANIZATION>;    And of course there is the
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill Historical Center. A visit to this museum, whether you are a
Western buff or not, is worth the trip to Cody.;    The big, modern museum is
broken into four sections -- <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill memorabilia, Western art, Plains
Indians and firearms. The museum is closed for the winter, but the group I was
with was lucky enough to get a two-hour tour of all but the firearms
collection, which was being moved to a newly-built wing.;    It was not nearly
enough time. I could have spent a day in the art section alone. It features
<PERSON>Frederic Remington</PERSON> and <PERSON>Charles M. Russell</PERSON> but has a massive collection of
other Western art.;    Officially called the <ORGANIZATION>Whitney Gallery of Western Art</ORGANIZATION>,
it was created through a grant by <PERSON>Cornelius Vanderbilt Whitney</PERSON>. The gallery
was renovated and rededicated in <DATE>1987.</DATE>;    The Plains Indian Museum offers one
of the nation's finest collections of Indian artifacts, and the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill
Museum</ORGANIZATION> is made up of memorabilia from <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>'s career as a <ORGANIZATION>Pony Express</ORGANIZATION> rider,
frontiersman, scout, buffalo hunter and creator of the Wild West show the
toured the world.;    The <ORGANIZATION>Cody Firearms Museum</ORGANIZATION>, which will re-open this <DATE>summer</DATE>
in a new wing of the museum, displays the world's largest collection of
American-made guns.;    An interesting point made by our guide during the tour
of the Plains Indian section of the museum is that inside the museum are a
number of "medicine bundles," which are collections of items sacred to a
tribe.;    These bundles are kept in a special room with access denied to all
but specific Indians who, as representatives of their tribe, have a right to
see them. Even the curators of the museum cannot enter the room unless taken
in by a tribal representative.;    Another place worth visiting is the <LOCATION>Irma</LOCATION>, a
hotel Buffalo Bill built for his youngest daughter, <PERSON>Irma</PERSON>, in <DATE>1902</DATE>. Many of the
rooms in the hotel are being lovingly restored by the current owners.;    The
best rooms need to be booked well in advance, but an alternative is to dine in
the big room that used to be the hotel's bar room. The centerpiece is a bar
presented to Buffalo Bill by <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Queen Victoria</PERSON> in appreciation for a
command performance.;  IF YOU'RE INTERESTED; For more information on <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>, or
reservations at any of the area hotels or resorts, call the <ORGANIZATION>Cody Chamber of
Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, (307) 587-2297.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  BILL SUNDERLAND, Venture Editor  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Cody, Wyo.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910314  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7G  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  525  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday March 14, 1991
00074219,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890708-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-89 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BuffaloBill 1stLd-Writethru a0421 07-08 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Buffalo Bill, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0421,0515</SECOND>
<HEAD>Medal of Honor Restored to Buffalo Bill</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: REWRITES throughout to CORRECT name of medal to Medal of Honor,
sted Congressional Medal of Honor; Add that medals not restored for four
other scouts, as well as more than 900 others; other background. No pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CODY, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seventy-two years after <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> stripped
<PERSON>Buffalo Bill Cody</PERSON> of his Medal of Honor, the Indian scout's name has
been restored to the honor roll.
   ``He's entitled to the honor, he was given the honor and he
should have the honor,'' said <PERSON>Buffalo Bill</PERSON>'s grandson, 76-year-old
<PERSON>Bill G. Cody</PERSON>. ``We've always contended that once he was awarded the
medal, they shouldn't revoke it _ especially after he was dead.''
   <PERSON>William F. ``Buffalo Bill'' Cody</PERSON>, who became a famous western
showman after the Indian wars, received the medal in <DATE>1872</DATE> for his
gallantry as an <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> scout during the wars.
   But it was revoked, along with medals of 910 other recipients, in
<DATE>1917</DATE> after <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> retroactively tightened up the rules for the
honor. Among other changes, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> held that only enlisted men and
officers could receive the award. A scout was considered a civilian;
in all, five scouts lost medals in <DATE>1917</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Sens. <PERSON>Alan Simpson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Malcolm Wallop</PERSON>, who jointly announced
the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s decision <DATE>Friday</DATE>, said <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill deserved the honor.
   ``Today's action by the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> sets the record straight,'' <PERSON>Wallop</PERSON>
said. ``After extensive research and review of the facts, the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>
has decided that <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill clearly deserves our nation's highest
honor.''
   Buffalo Bill gained fame for his western show that toured the
country and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> glamorizing the western frontier with real
cowboys and Indians re-enacting battles.
   <PERSON>Paul Fees</PERSON>, senior curator of the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill Historical Center</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Cody</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION> _ a town named for <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill _ said the western
show may have cost <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill some credibility as a real hero.
   <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s action restores that credibility, said Fees.
   ``The fact that this medal was restored for cause, people can
believe that he was a true hero and earned his reputation rather
than had it invented for him through press agents,'' said Fees.
   Buffalo Bill, known by his contemporaries as a <ORGANIZATION>Pony Express</ORGANIZATION>
rider, Indian scout and buffalo hunter, received the honor for valor
after leading a cavalry charge against a raiding band of <ORGANIZATION>Sioux
Indians</ORGANIZATION>. He killed two, recovered several horses, and pursued the
retreating band.
   Although Buffalo <PERSON>Bill</PERSON>'s name was stricken from the Medal of Honor
roll in <DATE>February 1917</DATE>, one month after he died, the medal itself was
never recalled and remains in the historical center.
   Fees said only one of the other 910 persons to lose medals in the
<DATE>1917</DATE> purge of the rolls has since regained it, a woman <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> surgeon
during the Civil War whose medal was restored in <DATE>1978</DATE>.
   He said he hoped that the families of the other four scouts
affected by the 72-year-old ruling would take the same steps the
<PERSON>Cody</PERSON> family did to get their relatives' medals awarded again.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880918-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-18-88 1402EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Fires-TreeSpared     09-18 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fires-Tree Spared,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tree Inscribed By Buffalo Bill Spared As Forest Fire Surrounds It</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Fires Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CODY, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A forest fire that swept out of <ORGANIZATION>Yellowstone
National Park</ORGANIZATION> threatened a fir tree inscribed by western showman
<PERSON>Buffalo Bill Cody</PERSON>, and his grandson feared the worst for his
namesake's landmark.
   But it survived even though trees 6 feet away were burned.
   ``You talk about a miracle. I'll say it was,'' <PERSON>Bill Cody</PERSON> said.
   The fir tree's 4-foot-thick trunk was inscribed ``Camp Monaco
<DATE>1913</DATE>'' when <PERSON>Buffalo Bill</PERSON> was host to <ORGANIZATION>Prince Albert of Monaco</ORGANIZATION> on a
hunting trip in the <ORGANIZATION>Shoshone National Forest</ORGANIZATION>. Cody's famous Wild
West show was a hit in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
   ``It was about this time of year when <LOCATION>Granddad</LOCATION> took the prince
up there,'' <PERSON>Cody</PERSON> said.
   He had been worried about the tree ever since the Clover-Mist
fire surged into the North Fork drainage about two weeks ago, but a
helicopter flight over the area with <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> rangers
confirmed the tree was safe.
   Camp <ORGANIZATION>Monaco</ORGANIZATION> is a half day's horseback ride from <LOCATION>Pahaska Tepee</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Buffalo Bill</LOCATION>'s hunting lodge near <LOCATION>Yellowstone</LOCATION>'s east entrance.
   Cody said he had been considering attempting to salvage the
inscription if the tree burned, but he started to fear the worst
when he saw from the air how much damage the fire had caused.
   ``It was a disaster all the way up the <LOCATION>North Fork</LOCATION>. On both sides
of the river there was nothing but burn, burn, burn,'' he said.
   But when the helicopter approached a meadow near <LOCATION>Camp Monaco</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Cody</PERSON> spotted a clump of green amid hundred of acres of black.
   ``It looked just like a pinpoint in the middle of a pie,'' he
said.``When I saw the tree was saved I let out a yell. There were
burned trees within 6 feet of it, and a bottle lying about 6 feet
away was scorched.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA040889-0095 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 41413 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 8, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 16; Column 3; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
319 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GENE AUTRY MUSEUM SALUTES THE WOMEN OF THE WILD WEST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DICK RORABACK 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
With typical myopia borne of chauvinism, they talk about the Old West as the 
idyllic era when "Men Were Men." Starting this <DATE>weekend</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Gene Autry Western 
Heritage Museum</ORGANIZATION> will take a giant step toward correcting the impression, in a 
wide-open tribute to "Daring Women of the Wild West." 
</P>
<P>
The two-month salute will draw overdue attention to the role of women in 
<LOCATION>Western</LOCATION> rodeos and shows from the <DATE>1800s</DATE> to the present. Focus of the show will 
be an exhibit lent by the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill Cody Center of Cody</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>'s shows 
featured a variety of feisty and courageous female performers), an exhibit 
enhanced by <PERSON>Autry</PERSON>'s own collection of show material from the <DATE>1880s</DATE> through the 
"Golden Age of Rodeos" in the <DATE>1920s</DATE> up to the barrel racers and other distaff 
daredevils of today. 
</P>
<P>
Special entertainment and pertinent films will include a pair of one-man shows 
by actor <PERSON>Eric Sorg</PERSON>, next <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> through <DATE>April 16</DATE>. Matinee performances, titled 
"<PERSON>Annie Oakley</PERSON> and the Wild West," will trace "Li'l Missy's" career as seen 
through the eyes of <ORGANIZATION>Cody</ORGANIZATION>, her mentor. Evening shows are "Cody! An Evening With 
Buffalo Bill," not entirely pertinent to the theme but a fascinating attempt to 
separate the reality from the myth of Cody. 
</P>
<P>
A series of musical performances will kick off today at <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> with <PERSON>Patsy 
Montana</PERSON> -- first female Western singer to sell a million copies of her records 
-- and an all-women Western band playing twice each afternoon on <DATE>April 29</DATE> and 
<DATE>May 29</DATE>. Other entries in a rich and varied program will be cowgirl roping, 
Hollywood stuntwomen and films (<PERSON>Barbara Stanwyck</PERSON> 's "Annie Oakley" and <PERSON>Gail 
David</PERSON>'s TV series of the same name). 
</P>
<P>
General admission to the museum, at 4700 Zoo Drive in <LOCATION>Griffith Park</LOCATION> (adjacent 
to the zoo), is <MONEY>$4.75</MONEY>, students and seniors <MONEY>$3.50</MONEY>, children 2-12 years <MONEY>$2</MONEY>. 
Theater admission is <MONEY>$3</MONEY> for the general public and <MONEY>$1</MONEY> for museum members and 
paid visitors. Call (213) 667-2000. DICK <LOCATION>RORABACK</LOCATION> 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880311-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-11-88 0259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RemingtonExhibit Bjt   03-11 0669</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Remington Exhibit, Bjt,0684</SECOND>
<HEAD>Remington Artworks Are More Than A Wild West Show</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LORI DODGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Frederic Remington</PERSON>, the painter and sculptor
best known for his depiction of the Wild West, deserves recognition
as an American master, say the curators of a traveling exhibit of
his work that opens here today.
   ``Remington has been seen superficially,'' says <PERSON>Michael Edward
Shapiro</PERSON>, chief curator at the <ORGANIZATION>St. Louis Art Museum</ORGANIZATION>. ``He's been
stereotyped as a cowboy artist when he was a very sophisticated New
Yorker who drew from a lot of sources and created his own style,
which has astonishingly imprinted itself on the conscience of our
country.''
   <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON> and <PERSON>Peter H. Hassrick</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill
Historical Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cody</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, organized ``<PERSON>Frederic Remington</PERSON>:
The Masterworks,'' the first major traveling exhibit of <ORGANIZATION>Remington</ORGANIZATION>'s
work.
   The exhibition consists of 46 paintings and drawings and 20
bronze sculptures Remington created from <DATE>1889</DATE>, when he was 28,
until he died in <DATE>1909</DATE> at age 48 of complications from appendicitis.
   Among the works are ``A Dash for the Timber,'' an <DATE>1889</DATE> painting
acknowledged as <PERSON>Remington</PERSON>'s first masterpiece, and ``The <PERSON>Bronco
Buster</PERSON>,'' possibly the best-known American bronze sculpture of the
<DATE>19th century</DATE>.
   Remington began his art career as an illustrator, with his Wild
West scenes turning up in several popular magazines, including
<PERSON>Harper</PERSON>'s Weekly. His work illustrated what <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON> describes as the
forces of nature and man and the risk of death and danger in the
<LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in the action and energy of <LOCATION>Remington</LOCATION>'s horses and horsemen.
   He was especially successful at capturing the image of the horse
_ bucking, rearing, lunging, running at breakneck speed. ``There
was never a more vivid depiction of the American horse,'' <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON>
adds.
   Indeed, <PERSON>Remington</PERSON> once told a drinking companion that if he
could have one thing written on his tombstone, it would be: ``He
knew the horse.''
   His subject was always the horse and its rider _ the
Indian-fighting soldier or the cowboy. But the West of the
homesteader, the farmer and the frontier-ending railroads held no
interest for him.
   ``While the rest of the country spoke of the advance of the
frontier, the `taming of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>,' as a positive force in the
building of American civilization, to <LOCATION>Remington</LOCATION> the frontier was
receding and, in the end, a tragic loss,'' historian <PERSON>David
McCullough</PERSON> writes in the show's catalog.
   Remington was born <DATE>Oct. 4, 1861</DATE>, in <LOCATION>Canton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, the son of a
newspaper proprietor. He grew up in <LOCATION>Canton</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ogdensburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>,
then enrolled in the School of Fine Arts and joined the football
team at <ORGANIZATION>Yale University</ORGANIZATION>.
   He dropped out of <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> after a year and a half when his father
died and, at the age of 21, he headed west to make his fortune,
plunking down part of his inheritance on a sheep ranch near
<LOCATION>Peabody</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan</LOCATION>.
   The sheep ranch failed, and <PERSON>Remington</PERSON> bought into a <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>
saloon, which also failed. His new wife had left him to go back to
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. Remington headed west again to sketch his way through <LOCATION>New
Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>.
   But by <DATE>1885</DATE>, <PERSON>Remington</PERSON> was back in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, reunited with his
wife and establishing himself as a magazine illustrator. In <DATE>1887</DATE>,
<PERSON>Harper</PERSON>'s Weekly carried 39 of his sketches and drawings, and the
next year more than 70.
   Remington's drawings also began to appear in <LOCATION>St. Nicholas</LOCATION> and
Outing magazines. He was commissioned by <ORGANIZATION>Century Illustrated
Magazine</ORGANIZATION> to illustrate a series of articles by a young <PERSON>Theodore
Roosevelt</PERSON>. The series later was made into a book titled ``Ranch
Life and the Hunting Trail.''
   Despite his popular success, <PERSON>Remington</PERSON> was never a critical
success, says <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON>.
   His work was ``just seen as cowboys and Indians,'' he says,
``and there was a belief that cowboys and Indians wasn't serious
subject matter.''
   The exhibit goes next to the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill Historical Center</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Cody</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, the Museum of Fine Arts in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> and closes at the
Metropolitan Museum of Art in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880311-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-11-88 0308EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Remington Bjt   03-11 0677</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Remington, Bjt,0693</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0435 to make slug conform to PM-News Digest.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Remington Artworks Are More Than A Wild West Show</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LORI DODGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Frederic Remington</PERSON>, the painter and sculptor
best known for his depiction of the Wild West, deserves recognition
as an American master, say the curators of a traveling exhibit of
his work that opens here today.
   ``Remington has been seen superficially,'' says <PERSON>Michael Edward
Shapiro</PERSON>, chief curator at the <ORGANIZATION>St. Louis Art Museum</ORGANIZATION>. ``He's been
stereotyped as a cowboy artist when he was a very sophisticated New
Yorker who drew from a lot of sources and created his own style,
which has astonishingly imprinted itself on the conscience of our
country.''
   <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON> and <PERSON>Peter H. Hassrick</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill
Historical Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cody</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, organized ``<PERSON>Frederic Remington</PERSON>:
The Masterworks,'' the first major traveling exhibit of <ORGANIZATION>Remington</ORGANIZATION>'s
work.
   The exhibition consists of 46 paintings and drawings and 20
bronze sculptures Remington created from <DATE>1889</DATE>, when he was 28,
until he died in <DATE>1909</DATE> at age 48 of complications from appendicitis.
   Among the works are ``A Dash for the Timber,'' an <DATE>1889</DATE> painting
acknowledged as <PERSON>Remington</PERSON>'s first masterpiece, and ``The <PERSON>Bronco
Buster</PERSON>,'' possibly the best-known American bronze sculpture of the
<DATE>19th century</DATE>.
   Remington began his art career as an illustrator, with his Wild
West scenes turning up in several popular magazines, including
<PERSON>Harper</PERSON>'s Weekly. His work illustrated what <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON> describes as the
forces of nature and man and the risk of death and danger in the
<LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in the action and energy of <LOCATION>Remington</LOCATION>'s horses and horsemen.
   He was especially successful at capturing the image of the horse
_ bucking, rearing, lunging, running at breakneck speed. ``There
was never a more vivid depiction of the American horse,'' <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON>
adds.
   Indeed, <PERSON>Remington</PERSON> once told a drinking companion that if he
could have one thing written on his tombstone, it would be: ``He
knew the horse.''
   His subject was always the horse and its rider _ the
Indian-fighting soldier or the cowboy. But the West of the
homesteader, the farmer and the frontier-ending railroads held no
interest for him.
   ``While the rest of the country spoke of the advance of the
frontier, the `taming of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>,' as a positive force in the
building of American civilization, to <LOCATION>Remington</LOCATION> the frontier was
receding and, in the end, a tragic loss,'' historian <PERSON>David
McCullough</PERSON> writes in the show's catalog.
   Remington was born <DATE>Oct. 4, 1861</DATE>, in <LOCATION>Canton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, the son of a
newspaper proprietor. He grew up in <LOCATION>Canton</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ogdensburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>,
then enrolled in the School of Fine Arts and joined the football
team at <ORGANIZATION>Yale University</ORGANIZATION>.
   He dropped out of <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> after a year and a half when his father
died and, at the age of 21, he headed west to make his fortune,
plunking down part of his inheritance on a sheep ranch near
<LOCATION>Peabody</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan</LOCATION>.
   The sheep ranch failed, and <PERSON>Remington</PERSON> bought into a <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>
saloon, which also failed. His new wife had left him to go back to
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. Remington headed west again to sketch his way through <LOCATION>New
Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>.
   But by <DATE>1885</DATE>, <PERSON>Remington</PERSON> was back in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, reunited with his
wife and establishing himself as a magazine illustrator. In <DATE>1887</DATE>,
<PERSON>Harper</PERSON>'s Weekly carried 39 of his sketches and drawings, and the
next year more than 70.
   Remington's drawings also began to appear in <LOCATION>St. Nicholas</LOCATION> and
Outing magazines. He was commissioned by <ORGANIZATION>Century Illustrated
Magazine</ORGANIZATION> to illustrate a series of articles by a young <PERSON>Theodore
Roosevelt</PERSON>. The series later was made into a book titled ``Ranch
Life and the Hunting Trail.''
   Despite his popular success, <PERSON>Remington</PERSON> was never a critical
success, says <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON>.
   His work was ``just seen as cowboys and Indians,'' he says,
``and there was a belief that cowboys and Indians wasn't serious
subject matter.''
   The exhibit goes next to the <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill Historical Center</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Cody</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, the Museum of Fine Arts in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> and closes at the
Metropolitan Museum of Art in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911016-0150
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911016-0150.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Theater:
   Scenes From the Wild West
   ----
   By Edwin Wilson
</HL>
<DATE>
10/16/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A14
</SO>
<LP>
   Princeton, N.J. -- Buffalo Bill Cody and Wild Bill Hickok
are at the White House performing a scene from a play for the
president and the first lady. In the scene, written by
19th-century author Ned Buntline, Cody and Hickok play
themselves: It features the two men rescuing an Indian maiden
in distress. Halfway through, Wild Bill rebels: He won't
"play-act" any longer. Suddenly he turns and puts a knife
into Buntline's back, and starts out after the actress who's
playing the maiden, to seduce her himself. The president and
his wife, thinking this is part of the action, are delighted.
   For Buffalo Bill, the chief character in Arthur Kopit's
play "Indians," this is symptomatic of his whole life:
Nothing turns out the way he thought it would. Hired by the
railroads to provide workers with food, he kills 4,280
buffalos, practically wiping out the Indians' supply. "How
did I know buffalo breed so slow?" he moans.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Sitting Bull, who had ignominiously defeated Gen. <PERSON>Custer</PERSON>
at the Little Bighorn, became <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill's friend. After
promising Sitting Bull that he would persuade the president
to come talk to him in person about Indian grievances,
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill can only produce three pompous, insensitive
senators. Attempting, finally, to effect some compromise
between the government and Sitting Bull, he must stand by
helplessly as <ORGANIZATION>Sitting Bull</ORGANIZATION> is brutally assassinated and a few
days later his Sioux Indian followers are massacred at
Wounded Knee.
   After being made a hero by Buntline in novels and plays,
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill, prior to Wounded Knee, produced his own Wild
West show in which he featured not only Wild <PERSON>Bill Hickok</PERSON> and
Sitting Bull, but <PERSON>Annie Oakley</PERSON>, <PERSON>Geronimo</PERSON> and others. It was
playwright <PERSON>Kopit</PERSON>'s inspired idea to use the Wild West
framework to produce a play that moves back and forth from
actual events to scenes from the show. As in real life, there
is a natural affinity between show business and history. We
have the pageantry of Indian ceremonies and mock shoot-outs,
mixed with heartbreaking scenes of betrayal and
Indians.
   In some ways <PERSON>Mr. Kopit</PERSON>'s play was ahead of its time. First
opened on Broadway in <DATE>1969</DATE>, after which it disappeared from
sight. It is one of those underrated, overlooked plays that
not only speaks to an issue still very much alive, but is a
highly charged coup de theatre. "Indians" is just the kind of
play important regional theaters should produce. And now,
<ORGANIZATION>McCarter Theater</ORGANIZATION>, in its recently renovated space, has done
just that.
   That's the good news. The not-so-good news is that
director <PERSON>George Faison</PERSON> has not given it the kind of
production it deserves. The visual elements are there --
stunning scenery, lighting and costumes -- but the show
itself does not do justice to the theatrical nature of the
play. Being part of a Wild West show, we should be caught up
in hoopla and razzle-dazzle; we should rush headlong from one
scene to the next. But <PERSON>Mr. Faison</PERSON>, quite unaccountably, moves
the action at snail's pace. He lets one scene come to a
complete halt, takes a long pause, and painstakingly begins
the next scene. The action should unfold the way <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bill
fells fake buffalo or <PERSON>Annie Oakley</PERSON> shoots clay pigeons: bam,
bam, bam.
   <PERSON>Mr. Faison</PERSON> fares no better with his lead performer, <PERSON>Robert
Joy</PERSON>. Instead of his tepid performance, Buffalo Bill should be
charisma personified, not only to give the play a lift and a
self-assurance, but to provide a contrast with the lost,
bewildered figure who stumbles about the stage at the end.
   Despite these handicaps, there is still much to enjoy at
<ORGANIZATION>McCarter</ORGANIZATION>. The electric scene between Sitting Bull (<PERSON>Mel Duane
Gionson</PERSON>) and the three senators (<PERSON>John Tillotson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Don Perkins</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Gordon Stanley</PERSON>) is theater at its best, and several
performances -- <PERSON>Jay Patterson</PERSON> as Wild <PERSON>Bill Hickok</PERSON>, for
instance -- let us see just how much excitement "Indians" can
produce.
   Meanwhile, the first production of the Broadway season is
also a revival: <PERSON>Paul Osborn</PERSON>'s "On Borrowed Time" at the
Circle in the Square Theater. The chief attraction here is
actor <PERSON>George C. Scott</PERSON>, who has traded in the gruff Gen.
<PERSON>Patton</PERSON> of films and the "Bah, Humbug" Scrooge of television
for lovable Gramps. <PERSON>Mr. Scott</PERSON> not only plays the lead but has
directed the production, assembling a strong cast that
includes <PERSON>Teresa Wright</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bette Henritze</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nathan Lane</PERSON>, <PERSON>Conrad
Bain</PERSON> and a very talented young actor, <PERSON>Matthew Porac</PERSON>.
   "On Borrowed Time" opened on Broadway in <DATE>1938</DATE>, one night
before <PERSON>Thornton Wilder</PERSON>'s "Our Town," with which it has much
in common. Both are set in small-town <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, both rely
heavily on fantasy and both underscore the necessity of
accepting the inevitability of death. In "On Borrowed Time,"
Gramps (<PERSON>Mr. Scott</PERSON>) is taking care of his grandson Pud (<PERSON>Mr.
Porac</PERSON>) when the boy's father and mother, away for the day on
a trip, are killed in an auto accident.
   Death appears in the form of <PERSON>Mr. Brink</PERSON>, played with
tremendous eclat by <PERSON>Mr. Lane</PERSON> dressed in formal <DATE>1930s</DATE> men's
attire. <PERSON>Mr. Brink</PERSON> has come to claim Gramps's wife (<PERSON>Ms.
Wright</PERSON>), who dies during the course of the action, and also
Gramps, who has several sinking spells. Before <PERSON>Mr. Brink</PERSON> can
corner him though, Gramps traps him in a tree, which means
that as long as <PERSON>Mr. Brink</PERSON> remains there, not only Gramps, but
no one on earth can die.
   Despite the emphasis on death, "On Borrowed Time" has
several uproarious scenes, some between Gramps and <PERSON>Mr. Brink</PERSON>
and others between Gramps and the prune-faced maiden aunt
(<PERSON>Ms. Henritze</PERSON>) who wants to get her hands on Pud and raise
him according to the strict precepts of her church. Gramps's
doctor (<PERSON>Mr. Bain</PERSON>) and lawyer (<PERSON>George DiCenzo</PERSON>), who cannot see
<PERSON>Mr. Brink</PERSON>, are convinced <ORGANIZATION>Gramps</ORGANIZATION> is insane and bring the head
of the local mental asylum (<ORGANIZATION>Allen Williams</ORGANIZATION>) to take him away
in a straitjacket. The joke here is that the head of the
asylum is far loonier than any of his patients.
   In the end, Gramps realizes that you cannot forestall
death, that inevitably it must be accepted. At the same time,
death will never be pleasanter, on stage or off, than it is
in "On Borrowed Time."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA092590-0039 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 282693 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 25, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 6; Column 4; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
469 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NO DOUBTING BILLS' THOMAS IN 30-7 VICTORY; 
</P>
<P>
PRO FOOTBALL: HE GAINS 214 YARDS RUSHING -- AND AVERAGES NEARLY 12 YARDS PER 
CARRY -- IN ROMP PAST JETS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills' <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON>, running through the kinds of holes tailbacks 
usually only dream of, rushed for 214 yards <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in a 30-7 victory over 
the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Jets. 
</P>
<P>
Thomas' best rushing total as a pro compares to the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> record of 275 yards by 
<PERSON>Walter Payton</PERSON> in <DATE>1977</DATE> and the Bill mark of 273 by <ORGANIZATION>O.J. Simpson</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1976</DATE>. Thomas 
averaged nearly 12 yards per carry. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't think of it as an individual effort," <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> said. "It truly was team 
play. The offense came out with fire in their eyes, and they just knocked huge 
holes in the defense." 
</P>
<P>
Thomas had several big games as an All-American at <LOCATION>Oklahoma State</LOCATION>, where he 
preceded <PERSON>Barry Sanders</PERSON> as the star running back. This was different. 
</P>
<P>
"I never thought in the NFL I would be 20 yards downfield without ever being 
touched, just me and a safety," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Said Bill tackle <PERSON>Howard Ballard</PERSON>: "We didn't really expect it to be that easy. 
We just blew them out." 
</P>
<P>
The Bills (2-1) wanted to show they are not the same bickering outfit that 
struggled to win the AFC East championship last year. The Jets (1-2) sought to 
show they are a playoff contender. 
</P>
<P>
It was the Bills who were convincing in moving back into first place in the <LOCATION>AFC 
East</LOCATION>, where they stood for 33 weeks before a 30-7 loss at <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE>. 
After that game, star defensive end <PERSON>Bruce Smith</PERSON> was fined for shouting at Coach 
<PERSON>Marv Levy</PERSON> on the sidelines when Levy removed six starters with seven minutes to 
play. 
</P>
<P>
Said Jet Coach <PERSON>Bruce Coslet</PERSON>: "No team should really be allowed to manhandle us 
like that. They dominated the line of scrimmage. We have to play very well to 
have a chance against a playoff team like <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
Was it a step backward for the Jets? 
</P>
<P>
"Probably," <PERSON>Coslet</PERSON> said. "But I'm not concerned about the psyche. This is not 
last year's team. We have a lot of confidence. We stubbed our toe." 
</P>
<P>
The Bills took a 20-7 halftime lead after <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> ran for 146 yards in 10 
carries, two yards short of his career high for a full game, against <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> last 
season. Buffalo had 305 yards and the Jets 87 in the half. 
</P>
<P>
"We established just what we wanted to do in the first half," <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 
quarterback <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON> said. "We took it from there." 
</P>
<P>
It didn't get any better for <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in the second half. Thomas keyed an 
85-yard, nine-play drive with 56 yards rushing, including a 34-yard burst on a 
quick-opener. <PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON>'s 27-yard field goal made the score 23-7 and <PERSON>Keith 
McKeller</PERSON> caught a six-yard touchdown pass from <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The Jets had gone 13 consecutive quarters without a touchdown against <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 
before scoring 4:59 into the game on <PERSON>Brad Baxter</PERSON>'s one-yard run. Their last 
touchdown against the Bills was scored <DATE>Oct. 17, 1988</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Jet wide receiver <PERSON>Al Toon</PERSON> had two receptions before being sidelined because of 
a bruised back. He has caught a pass in 65 consecutive games. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, No stopping him -- Thurman Thomas of the Buffalo Bills gets some of his 
career-high 214 rushing yards in a 30-7 victory over the New York Jets Monday 
night. Story, C6. Reuters 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111990-0068 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 310444 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 19, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 8; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
554 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BILLS SLOWED BUT NOT STOPPED BY PATRIOTS; 
</P>
<P>
AFC: THOMAS SCORES ON 80-YARD RUN IN FOURTH QUARTER AS BUFFALO BEATS NEW 
ENGLAND, 14-0. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ORCHARD PARK, N.Y. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bills</ORGANIZATION> entered their game against the <ORGANIZATION>New England Patriots</ORGANIZATION> with an 
NFL-high 274 points. 
</P>
<P>
Surprisingly, the Patriots held the Bills to 14 points, but that was still more 
than enough against the league's worst team. 
</P>
<P>
Thurman Thomas provided the clinching touchdown on an 80-yard run with under 
two minutes left <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to lead the Bills to a 14-0 victory. 
</P>
<P>
The Bills (9-1), who scored 87 points in their previous two games, won for the 
eighth consecutive time. The Patriots (1-9) lost their eighth game in a row. 
</P>
<P>
"We just got bad breaks," Patriot running back <PERSON>George Adams</PERSON> said. "We took the 
field like we were 8-1, not 1-8. We know what we can do; it's just a matter of 
time." 
</P>
<P>
It was the second shutout in three weeks for the Bills, who blanked <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, 
42-0, two weeks ago. The Patriots had not been shut out since <DATE>Nov. 20, 1983</DATE>, by 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Thomas, who had 22 carries for 165 yards, also scored in the <DATE>first quarter</DATE> on a 
five-yard run. 
</P>
<P>
Buffalo quarterback <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s top-rated passer, completed only five 
of 15 passes for 79 yards as the Bills managed only 288 yards of offense. 
</P>
<P>
Patriot quarterback <PERSON>Marc Wilson</PERSON> completed 21 of 33 passes for 234 yards and had 
two passes intercepted. 
</P>
<P>
The Patriots came closest to scoring early in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE> after driving 
54 yards. 
</P>
<P>
With the Bills leading, 7-0, the Patriots had a first and goal from the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 
one-yard-line. Three plays later, it was fourth-and-goal from the one and the 
Patriots went for it. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Marvin Allen</PERSON>, who ran effectively early in the game, tried to run off the right 
side of the offensive line. But <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> linebacker <PERSON>Ray Bentley</PERSON> shot through and 
stopped him for a one-yard loss. 
</P>
<P>
"About four guys hit me and I shed them all and got in there," <PERSON>Bentley</PERSON> said 
jokingly. "Actually, the guard pulled out of there and I just went in where he 
left and came through untouched." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bentley</PERSON> said he was surprised the Patriots tried to run the ball, but once they 
came to the line of scrimmage, he said he knew what play was coming. 
</P>
<P>
"I didn't necessarily know that the guard would pull, but that's a scheme they 
do have," he said. "We had great penetration on the other side to keep the back 
from bouncing outside so I could get to him." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>New England Coach Rod Rust</ORGANIZATION> said he didn't regret the call. "It was a good 
defense against the play." 
</P>
<P>
The play seemed to inspire the Bills' defense, which kept the Patriots in check 
until <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>'s next-to-last drive. 
</P>
<P>
The Patriots moved from their 14 to the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 38. But the drive ended when 
rookie <PERSON>James Williams</PERSON> intercepted a pass by <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> in the end zone that was 
intended for <PERSON>Irving Fryar</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I had a feeling they were going to try and go toward me because I was a rookie 
out there," said <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>, the Bills' first-round draft choice who was starting 
for injured <PERSON>Kirby Jackson</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Buffalo got the ball on its 20 and the Patriots let Thomas slice through the 
line on the next play. 
</P>
<P>
"We were basically just trying to get a first down," <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> said. "The 
offensive line came off the ball well. Usually, that play doesn't cut back all 
the way to the right, but the hole was so big I just had to do it." 
</P>
<P>
Patriot safety <PERSON>Fred Marion</PERSON> said his team was "cutting down on giving up the 
easy stuff. But he (<PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>) broke right, they made good blocks and we didn't 
get over to make the play." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Buffalo's Thurman Thomas and Kent Hull celebrate after the first of 
Thomas' two touchdowns in the Bills' 14-0 win over the Patriots. Reuters; 
Photo, (Southland Edition) New England kick returner Sammy Martin (82) and the 
rest of the Patriots were unable to escape the Buffalo Bills in a 14-0 loss. 
Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122489-0165 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 153184 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 24, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 11; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
606 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JETS ARE MAT AS BUFFALO ENTERS THE PLAYOFF DOOR; 
</P>
<P>
BILLS: THEY WIN AFC EAST AGAIN, BEATING THE SAME TEAM AS LAST SEASON TO CLINCH 
THE TITLE. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It didn't happen as early as it did last season, but the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills are AFC 
East champions. 
</P>
<P>
The clincher came in Week 12 last season, and this year it was on the <DATE>Saturday</DATE> 
of the <DATE>last weekend</DATE>. Both clinchers, however, were at the expense of the <LOCATION>New 
York</LOCATION> Jets. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON>'s two touchdowns led the Bills to a 37-0 victory, as one-sided as 
last year's divisional race. 
</P>
<P>
"Last year it was early, this year it was struggle, struggle, but we're there 
again," <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> nose tackle <PERSON>Fred Smerlas</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
There was no struggle for the Jets <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, except for the few fans who 
ventured to <ORGANIZATION>Giants Stadium</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The game started with the temperature at 16 degrees and a wind-chill factor of 
minus-11. There were 21,148 in attendance, but there were 55,743 no-shows, 
believed to be an <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> record. 
</P>
<P>
The crowd was the smallest at a non-strike Jet game since 5,826 attended a game 
against <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Polo Grounds</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Dec. 14, 1963</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"It wasn't a real stinging wind," <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Marv Levy</PERSON> said. "It was one of 
the nicer days we've seen in a long time." 
</P>
<P>
The weather and the loss weren't all that made it a bleak day for Jet Coach <PERSON>Joe 
Walton</PERSON>. It has been widely speculated this was his last game as Jet coach after 
taking over for the <DATE>1983</DATE> season. 
</P>
<P>
"If you stay in this business long enough, there are going to be bad times," 
said <PERSON>Walton</PERSON>, who said he wants to return next season. "I'll meet with the team 
tomorrow, thank them and wish them a Merry Christmas and Happy New Year." 
</P>
<P>
The Bills (9-7), who had lost five of seven, ended a three-game losing streak. 
"Is it a relief to win it?" Levy asked, repeating a question. "There's always 
that pressure, but it is sweet. We've struggled hard to get here. We have been 
in first place for 32 straight weeks. It's hard to please people." 
</P>
<P>
The division title was the sixth for the Bills, who lost to <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> in the 
<ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> championship game last season. 
</P>
<P>
"This team deserves a lot of credit," <PERSON>Levy</PERSON> said. "They hung in there and won 
the division by earning it." 
</P>
<P>
The Jets, who lost to <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, 34-3, earlier in the season, finished 4-12, 
their worst record since going 4-12 in <DATE>1980</DATE>. Instead of playoffs, what's next 
for the franchise is a much-awaited meeting <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> between <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dick 
Steinberg</PERSON>, the team's new general manager. 
</P>
<P>
Kelly finished 13 for 21 for 208 yards with <PERSON>Andre Reed</PERSON> catching six passes for 
80 yards. "We were the Bills of the first five games today," <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> said. "Our 
offense was clicking and our defense was clicking." 
</P>
<P>
The Bills opened the scoring with a 26-yard field goal by <PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON> with 
4:26 to play in the <DATE>first quarter</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The Jets, who were shut out by <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> two weeks ago, had one scoring chance 
but it ended when <PERSON>Pat Leahy</PERSON>'s 30-yard field goal attempt was blocked with 8:14 
left in the quarter. 
</P>
<P>
It was all <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> from there. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Larry Kinnebrew</PERSON> ran in from one yard 1:07 before halftime for a 10-0 lead. The 
Bills stretched it out in the third with <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> connecting with <PERSON>James Lofton</PERSON> on 
a 25-yard pass play with 10:49 left in the quarter. It was the same distance on 
the next scoring play, this time a pass to <PERSON>Ronnie Harmon</PERSON> in the left corner of 
the end zone, and the Bills led, 23-0, with 4:39 left in the third. 
</P>
<P>
"That touchdown before the half was big, but the game still wasn't over then," 
<PERSON>Levy</PERSON> said. "Jim played very well. He was a big contributor. Our team has to 
continue to play well, not just <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
The Bills made the score 30-0 on a three-yard run by <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON> shortly 
before the <DATE>third quarter ended</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kenneth Davis</PERSON> ended the scoring with a 17-yard run with 2:44 to play. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kinnebrew</PERSON> had 91 yards in 17 carries, while <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> had 73 in 17 carries. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, (Southland Edition) The Jets' Bobby Humphrey can't hold pass intended 
for the Bills' Andre Reed during first quarter at East Rutherford, N.J. 
Associated Press; Photo, (Southland Edition) The Buffalo Bills' James Lofton 
enters end zone after catching 25-yard touchdown pass from Jim Kelly during 
37-0 victory over the New York Jets. United Press International 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06323194 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06323194 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawings (2); DRAWING: (Bills helmet logo); DRAWING: (Dolphins helmet logo)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; GAME; FORECAST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  BUFFALO BILLS VS. MIAMI DOLPHINS; KICKOFF: 6 p.m., Joe Robbie Stadium, Miami.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TONIGHT'S GAME  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  LINE: <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> is favored by 4 1/2 points.; TELEVISION/RADIO: CH7CH11/KCBS
(740).; RECORDS: <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> is 9-1 and in first place in the <LOCATION>AFC East</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> is
5-5, third in the AFC East.; SERIES: The Dolphins lead the series 35-15-1. In
the season opener, <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> scored 28 points in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE> and defeated
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 35-31. <PERSON>Don Shula</PERSON> has coached more victories against the Bills (32) than
any other team.; BILLS UPDATE: <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> has won 11 consecutive games against
AFC East teams, including three in a row against <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. The Bills are known
for their passing game, but they have passed 311 times and rushed 304 times.
Thurman Thomas (968 yards) is the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s rushing leader. Green Bay scored 24
points last week against the Bills. Unfortunately for the <ORGANIZATION>Packers</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>
scored 34.; DOLPHINS UPDATE: QB <PERSON>Dan Marino</PERSON> is finally getting some protection.
The <ORGANIZATION>Dolphins</ORGANIZATION>' offensive line has allowed only three sacks in the past five
games after yielding 13 in the first five. Dolphins defenders will hope their
offense can control the ball. Buffalo ranks 26th in the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> in run defense,
and RB <PERSON>Sammie Smith</PERSON> is looking for a big game. <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s defense has forced an
AFC-low five fumbles.; KEY INJURIES: Bills -- T Will <ORGANIZATION>Wolford</ORGANIZATION> (back) is
questionable; QB <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON> (back) is probable. Dolphins -- DT <PERSON>Bert Weidner</PERSON>
(shoulder) is questionable; DE <PERSON>Jeff Cross</PERSON> (groin) is probable.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911118  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  255  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, November 18, 1991
00323194,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06281159 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06281159 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; GAME; STATISTIC  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  KICKOFF: 6 p.m., Arrowhead Stadium, Kansas City, Mo.; LINE: Buffalo is favored
by 2 1/2 points.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TONIGHT'S GAME
BUFFALO BILLS VS. KANSAS CITY CHIEFS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The NFL/Week 6  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  TV/RADIO: ch. 7, 11/KCBS (740).; RECORDS: <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> is 5-0, first in the <LOCATION>AFC
East</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> is 3-2, second in the AFC West.; BILLS UPDATE: All-Pro DE
<PERSON>Bruce Smith</PERSON> is making his second start since recovering from knee surgery.
With <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> and NT <PERSON>Jeff Wright</PERSON> out because of injuries, the defense has given
up an average of 137 yards a game rushing -- a big factor in opponents
averaging 23 points per game. <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> did not have a tackle in his first game
back <DATE>last week</DATE>, but in beating the previously unbeaten <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bears 35-20</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> held <PERSON>Neal Anderson</PERSON> to 54 yards rushing and the Bears to 84 rushing
yards. The Bills' powerful offense, led by QB <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON> and RB <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON>,
has averaged an AFC-high 32.4 points per game. No Chiefs opponent has scored
more than 17 points this season, and the Bills have not scored fewer than 17
in any game.; CHIEFS UPDATE: The Chiefs still believe they might have beaten
the Bills in the playoffs last season had their road to <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> not stopped in
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. The Chiefs can run -- the Bills are last in the league in ball control
and are 24th against the rush. Behind <PERSON>Christian Okoye</PERSON> and <PERSON>Barry Word</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Kansas
City</LOCATION>'s rushing game has averaged a respectable 110 yards. With QB <PERSON>Steve DeBerg</PERSON>
off to a slow start, the <ORGANIZATION>Chiefs</ORGANIZATION>' passing game is averaging less than 148 yards.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911007  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  258  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, October 7, 1991
00281159,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06246044 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06246044 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, Chart; Chart: (Game Statistics); PHOTO: Associated Press; Bills Don
Beebe (82) and Miami's Paul Lankford can't reach incomplete pass  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BUFFALO; MIAMI; PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; GAME  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mercury News Staff Writer;   ORCHARD PARK, N.Y. -- When it comes to a Buffalo
Bills-Miami Dolphins matchup, perhaps it would be best to tally up the points
and individual plaudits with a pinball machine, just to keep up with the
darned thing.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  KELLY, THOMAS KEY BILLS
BUFFALO MAINTAINS MASTERY OF DOLPHINS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The NFL/Week 1  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The numbers rattled off with a familiar vengeance <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Running back
<PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON> became the first <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> player with more than 100 yards
rushing and receiving in the same game. Wide receiver <PERSON>Andre Reed</PERSON> caught 11
passes for 154 yards and a touchdown. Quarterback <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON>, overcoming an
ankle injury, threw for 381 yards -- the most in his career -- leading the
Bills to a wild, season-opening 35-31 victory over the Dolphins before 80,252
at Rich Stadium.;   Considering <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s 44-34 loss in the snowy <DATE>Jan. 12</DATE>
playoff game on Rich Stadium's tundra and a 24-14 stumble last <DATE>December</DATE>
against the Bills that erased all hope of home-field advantage in the
playoffs, you could say the Dolphins were primed to wash away the memories of
last season's bad luck against <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>. But the Bills, depleted as they were
on defense without pass-rushing defensive end <PERSON>Bruce Smith</PERSON>, who still is
nursing a surgically repaired right knee, have retained the deed when it comes
to owning <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s number.;   "It's depressing knowing that they knocked us out
of home-field advantage up here and they knocked us out of the playoffs up
here in <DATE>January</DATE> and then to start the year, they do it to us again," said
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Don Shula</PERSON>, whose team is minus 11 starters, four of whom are
contract holdouts.;   The Bills, despite early use of their defense-rattling,
no-huddle attack, had to come back to do it.;   Kicker <PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON>, the goat
of Super Bowl XXV for missing a 47-yard field goal with four seconds
remaining, preserving the <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION>' <DATE>20-19</DATE> victory, choked <DATE>Sunday</DATE> on a
25-yard gimme capping <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>'s opening drive. <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> then took a 7-0 lead as
<PERSON>Dan Marino</PERSON> (17 of 28, 267 yards, three touchdowns) tossed 43-yard flea-flicker
to <PERSON>Mark Clayton</PERSON> for a touchdown -- keeping <PERSON>Clayton</PERSON>'s streak of consecutive
games with at least one reception alive at 64 -- with 8 minutes, 56 seconds
remaining in the first quarter.;   An interception by safety <PERSON>Louis Oliver</PERSON> set
up a 3-yard run by running back <PERSON>Mark Higgs</PERSON>, a return man who rushed for 146
yards in 30 carries filling in for starter <PERSON>Sammie Smith</PERSON>, who's out with a knee
injury. Higgs' touchdown put <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> ahead 14-0.;   By then, though, the
Kelly-Thomas machine was primed to go. On third-and-five from the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>
46-yard line, <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> launched a 54-yard scoring pass to <ORGANIZATION>Reed</ORGANIZATION>, pulling the Bills
closer, 14-7, with 8:45 remaining before halftime.;   <PERSON>Charlie Baumann</PERSON>'s
21-yard field goal at the start of the third period increased <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s lead to
17-7. And the Bills' problems seemed to worsen when <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> came up limping
after Dolphins nose tackle <PERSON>T.J. Turner</PERSON> rolled onto <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>'s left ankle on a
sack attempt.;   <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> left the field, ostensibly for the rest of the game
with a sprain. But three plays later, backup <PERSON>Frank Reich</PERSON> hit tight end <PERSON>Butch
Rolle</PERSON> on a 3-yard play-action fake, pulling <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> closer, 17-14.;   Would
that be it for <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>? Hey, this guy's tough. No way.;   "It's going to take a
lot more than a bum ankle to keep me out of a game," said <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>, who came back
to complete 29 of 39 attempts, with two touchdown passes.;   So back he came
on the next series, driving <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 30 yards to midfield. On second-and-eight,
<PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> threw 30 yards on a post to <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, who blew past safety <PERSON>Jarvis Williams</PERSON>
and sprinted 20 yards down the right sideline for a 50-yard touchdown
reception, giving the Bills their first lead, 21-17, with 2:10 left in the
third quarter.;   Wide receiver <PERSON>Don Beebe</PERSON>'s fumble set up a 5-yard scoring
pass from <PERSON>Marino</PERSON> to <PERSON>Clayton</PERSON> (6 catches, 138 yards two touchdowns), and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>
regained the lead 24-21 with 11:18 remaining.;   But the Bills answered with a
1-yard touchdown run by fullback <PERSON>Carwell Gardner</PERSON> to pull ahead again, 28-24.; 
 Thomas scored from seven yards out to increase the lead to 35-24, and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>
capped the scoring with <PERSON>Marino</PERSON>'s 3-yard touchdown toss to Duper with 2:32
remaining.; BILLS 35, DOLPHINS 31; (box) THE HERO: <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON>
rushed for 165 yards and added 108 yards receiving to become the first Bill to
surpass 100 yards in both categories in one game.;   (box) THE GOAT: Bills
kicker <PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON>, who missed the potential winning field goal in the Super
Bowl in <DATE>January</DATE>, shanked a 25-yard effort with his first kick Sunday.;   (box)
KEY PLAY: Bills QB <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON> hobbled back onto the field after suffering an
ankle injury to toss a 50-yard scoring strike to Thomas to give <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> its
first lead, 21-17.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  NANCY GAY, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910902  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  858  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, September 2, 1991
00246044,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890913-0250 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-13-89 1309EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-WesternCentennials Adv17-2Takes   09-13 1180</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Western Centennials, Adv 17 - 2 Takes,1204</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv17</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Sept. 17, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Much of the American West Celebrates Centennials of Statehood This
Fall</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: This story is accompanied by four profiles of people in the
centennial states, b0619-b0622. Note time element in 7th graf, President
Bush visits Monday and Tuesday; varying spellings of Bighorn and Big Horn
are cq.</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY303 of Sept. 12, others planned; LaserGraphic Logo</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ``In my book a pioneer is a man who turned all the grass upside
down, strung bob-wire over the dust that was left, poisoned the
water and cut down the trees, killed the Indian who owned the land,
and called it progress. If I had my way, the land here would be like
God made it, and none of you SOBs would be here at all.''
   _ <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> artist <PERSON>Charles M. Russell</PERSON> to a group of Great Falls
citizens who threw a celebration in honor of themselves in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By TAD BARTIMUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   ``In my book a pioneer is a man who turned all the grass upside
down, strung bob-wire over the dust that was left, poisoned the
water and cut down the trees, killed the Indian who owned the land,
and called it progress. If I had my way, the land here would be like
God made it, and none of you SOBs would be here at all.''
   _ <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> artist <PERSON>Charles M. Russell</PERSON> to a group of Great Falls
citizens who threw a celebration in honor of themselves in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06282172 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06282172 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; GAME; RESULT; KANSAS-CITY; BUFFALO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Monday night football fans who wondered if those really were the Buffalo Bills
were in good company.;   Kansas City Coach Marty Schottenheimer could hardly
believe it himself.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CHIEFS KNOCK BILLS OFF THEIR PEDESTAL, 33-6
CHIEFS DEMONSTRATE HOW TO KNOCK BILLS OFF PEDESTAL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Monday's Score; CHIEFS 33, BILLS 6; Highlight: Derrick Thomas had four of
Kansas City's six sacks, and Buffalo lost five fumbles.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "We've all been around long enough to know that isn't the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills
football team," <PERSON>Schottenheimer</PERSON> said after the Chiefs romped to a 33-6 victory
over the previously unbeaten AFC champions. "It was one of those nights where
everything fell our way.";   The Bills, averaging more than 32 points and 450
yards in winning their first five games, suffered six sacks, five lost fumbles
and their most lopsided loss in four years. They managed only 211 net yards,
and the Chiefs (4-2), who had only 182 yards the week before in a one-point
victory over <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, rolled to 397.;   "This was not only the best
defensive game I've ever been associated with," said defensive end <PERSON>Bill Maas</PERSON>,
who had two sacks. "It was the greatest game I've ever been associated with.";
  The victory snapped a five-game <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> losing streak for the Chiefs,
who had not played a <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> game in <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> since <DATE>1983.</DATE>;   "There
was a lot of energy, a lot of adrenaline flowing," <PERSON>Maas</PERSON> said. "Our defense
shut down the No. 1 offense. Our offense held the ball and ran and ran and
ran. It was a night to remember.";   <PERSON>Christian Okoye</PERSON>, who rushed for 130 yards
and set a team record with his 13th 100-yard game, turned two <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>
turnovers into two touchdowns less than two minutes apart in the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>
for a 30-6 lead.;   Okoye reached the 100-yard rushing plateau for the 13th
time in his five-year career and passed <PERSON>Abner Haynes</PERSON> as the Chief with the
most 100-yard rushing games.;   Rookie <PERSON>Harvey Williams</PERSON> rushed for 103 yards.; 
 "By the time the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE> rolled around, it was glorious," <PERSON>Maas</PERSON> said.; 
 "We gave them so many gifts, they should be happy until next <DATE>Christmas</DATE>," said
<PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>, who hit 17 of 23 passes for 189 yards.;   The Bills, who hadn't been
held without a TD since <DATE>Dec. 4, 1988</DATE>, suffered their worst defeat since a 47-6
loss to <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> by replacement players during the <DATE>1987</DATE> strike. <PERSON>Derrick
Thomas</PERSON> had four of the <ORGANIZATION>Chiefs</ORGANIZATION>' sacks, with two of them causing fumbles.;   "We
believed in each other," <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> said. "We thought we could get the job done.";
  The Bills still were in the game when <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON> took a pass from <PERSON>Jim
Kelly</PERSON> deep in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> territory and was immediately hit by <PERSON>Lonnie Marts</PERSON>, who
knocked the ball loose for <PERSON>Kevin Ross</PERSON> to scoop up and run 13 yards to the
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 17.;   One play later, <PERSON>Okoye</PERSON> went over for a 23-6 lead with 2 minutes,
52 seconds left in the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>. A moment later, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> sacked <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>,
knocking the ball loose, and <PERSON>Dan Saleaumua</PERSON> recovered on the 11. On
fourth-and-goal from the 2, <PERSON>Okoye</PERSON> knocked a defender backward into the end
zone.;   A fumble by <PERSON>Don Beebe</PERSON> on the ensuing kickoff led to <PERSON>Nick Lowery</PERSON>'s
22-yard field goal. Lowery also kicked a 41-yarder in the <DATE>first quarter</DATE>, a
40-yarder in the second and a 24-yarder in the third.;   <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, the Bills'
leading rusher, left the game late in the quarter with an apparent ankle
injury.;   Even the officiating went against the Bills. Officials placed the
ball 5 yards away from where they should have after replay officials
overturned a <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> pass completion in the third period.;   The Bills were
without All-Pro defensive end <PERSON>Bruce Smith</PERSON>, who is out with a knee injury. But
it was a miserable homecoming for Bills' Coach <PERSON>Marv Levy</PERSON>, who coached the
Chiefs from 1978-82.;   "If a team can succeed in running the ball as well as
they did, you're in for a long night," <PERSON>Levy</PERSON> said. "They just overpowered us. I
hope we're not as bad as we looked. I think most routs -- and this was a rout
-- are not indicative of the difference between the two teams.";   The Chiefs
won with a formula all teams attempt against <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>: Once you get the
football, hold on to it for long drives and eat the clock. <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> led in
plays (38-28) and in possession time (19 minutes 15 seconds to 10:45) as it
built a 13-6 halftime lead.;   The Chiefs scored on the game's first
possession on <LOCATION>Lowery</LOCATION>'s 41-yard field goal.;   Then with 7:40 left in the
<DATE>quarter</DATE>, <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> tight end <PERSON>Jonathon Hayes</PERSON>, after a huge hit by linebacker
<PERSON>Darryl Talley</PERSON>, fumbled at the Chiefs<DATE>' 31</DATE> and cornerback <PERSON>Nate Odomes</PERSON> recovered
for Buffalo.;   But <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> got the ball back with 5:46 left when <PERSON>Maas</PERSON>
knocked <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> down and the ball loose at the <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 23. Marts recovered
and <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> then drove 77 yards in 12 plays, featuring daring play-calling
with play-action passes near the Bills' goal line. Tight end <PERSON>Pete Holohan</PERSON>'s
1-yard catch from <PERSON>Steve DeBerg</PERSON> gave the Chiefs a 10-0 lead with 14:16 left in
the half.;   <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>'s only points came on a 44-yard field goal from <PERSON>Scott
Norwood</PERSON> in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE>, and then a 25-yarder after wasting a first down
on the Chiefs 11 after <PERSON>Okoye</PERSON> fumbled.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Wire Services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Kansas City, Mo.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911008  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  902  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, October 8, 1991
00282172,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900702-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-02-90 2045EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WagonTrain     07-02 0628</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wagon Train,0645</SECOND>
<HEAD>Centennial Wagon Train Ends Its Journey</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JULIA PRODIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CODY, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thirty dusty days on the <ORGANIZATION>Jim Bridger Trail</ORGANIZATION>
ended in rain <DATE>Monday</DATE> as the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming Centennial Wagon Train</ORGANIZATION> rolled
into Cody with modern-day pioneers who relived the past to
celebrate the state's 100th birthday.
   Approximately 200 wagons and 1,600 riders on horseback were
greeted with a great whooping and hollering from several thousand
well-wishers who jammed streets and roof tops to watch the
four-mile-long procession.
   ``I wouldn't have bet there were this many horses in this whole
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,'' lifelong Cody resident <PERSON>Frank McJunkin</PERSON>, 70, said as
he watched the parade of covered wagons, horses and exhausted but
delighted riders ramble by.
   The cavalry led the wagon train to the end of its 260-mile trek
along the <PERSON>Jim Bridger Trail</PERSON>, one of the main pioneer routes
northwest through <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. Riders recreating the <ORGANIZATION>Pony Express</ORGANIZATION>
followed with state centennial flags.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Alan Simpson</PERSON>, in a red Western shirt and beaded vest,
rode the last few miles with the wagon train and predicted that
years from now everyone will claim they rode along.
   ``There'll be as many people saying they rode the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming
Centennial Wagon Train</ORGANIZATION> as said they saw Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s last game at
Yankee Stadium _ about 7 million,'' said <PERSON>Simpson</PERSON>, who grew up in
this frontier town founded by showman <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bill Cody</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Kayne Pyatt</PERSON>, the trail boss who oversaw the journey organized by
a group of enthusiasts, said, ``It's sort of like I've lived a
great childhood adventure, a fantasy. ... If I died tomorrow, I'd
be satisfied.''
   The riders started the day about 16 miles east of Cody and
followed alongside <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 14A, encountering a torrential downpour
about a mile out.
   Simpson and his wife, <PERSON>Ann</PERSON>, were joined on the final leg by
<LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Mike Sullivan</PERSON> and his wife, <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> Rep.
<PERSON>Craig Thomas</PERSON> and his wife, <PERSON>Susan</PERSON>, all on horseback. <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> Gov.
<PERSON>Stan Stephens</PERSON> rode in a red surry.
   The sun broke through as they reached the edge of town, but
distant thunder and lightning added a dramatic backdrop. Horses
reared and bucked, riders waved and hollered and a few wagon
passengers played their fiddles to the Cody crowd.
   ``Cody loves you,'' some spectators yelled. ``Happy birthday
Wyoming!''
   Some of the trail riders welcomed the return to modern
conveniences, while others regretted reaching the end of the line.
   ``In a way, it's sad and in a way I'm glad to roll into <PERSON>Cody</PERSON>,''
said <PERSON>Ken Hagen</PERSON>, 71, of <LOCATION>Roseau</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION> ``The dust was the worst. Some
days, there was so much dust you couldn't see the team ahead of
you. And for six days, we never saw a tree.''
   The final miles brought together past and present, as modern-day
vehicles on the highway buzzed by the rumbling replica wagons.
   ``This is a chance for a person like me to be a part of history,
maybe not a significant part, but a part,'' said <PERSON>Mike Wozniak</PERSON>, of
Casper, who spent two days on the trail. ``This wagon train is not
going to happen again _ maybe not for another 100 years.''
   The train left <LOCATION>Fort Caspar</LOCATION> <DATE>June 2</DATE>. Besides the dust, it was
accompanied by fears the organizers wouldn't be able to pay their
bills.
   Arriving here, the organizers estimated they were about <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY>
shy of the approximately <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> they figured they'd need to pay
for things like hay, water and portable toilets.
   Participating costs ranged from <MONEY>$40</MONEY> a day to just ride along in
your own rig, to <MONEY>$198</MONEY> a day to ride on one provided.
   The organizers also raised money through contests and auctions
along the trail, and plan to raffle off an elk permit donated by
Gov. <PERSON>Mike Sullivan</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06324210 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06324210 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; GAME; RESULT; MIAMI; BUFFALO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  As if Jim Kelly, Thurman Thomas and Andre Reed weren't enough, the Buffalo
Bills added a new scoring weapon Monday night -- their defense.;   Three
turnovers produced 17 points, including a fumble return for a touchdown by
linebacker Cornelius Bennett, and the Bills beat the Miami Dolphins 41-27.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BILLS ROMP 41-27
DEFENSE KEYS WIN OVER MIAMI  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> (5-6) lost to <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> (10-1) for the 10th time in 11 games.;   The
Bills mounted scoring drives of 83, 65, 72 and 89 yards. Thomas rushed for 135
yards and a touchdown in 23 carries. Kelly threw three touchdown passes -- two
to <ORGANIZATION>Reed</ORGANIZATION> and one to Thomas.;   Plenty of points;   The 41 points were the most
by <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> against <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> in a regular-season game since <DATE>1966</DATE>. The Bills won
that one 58-24. Buffalo beat the Dolphins 44-34 in the playoffs last January.;
  <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> is accustomed to such production from its offense, ranked No. 1 in
the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>. Big plays by the Bills' defense, ranked 26th, have been much less
frequent.;   The first and biggest turnover came when a blitzing <PERSON>Bennett</PERSON>
knocked the ball from <PERSON>Dan Marino</PERSON>'s cocked right hand, fell on the fumble at
the 6-yard line, stood up and dashed into the end zone. That gave <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> the
lead for good at 17-10 in the second quarter.;   "It was a huge play," Bills
Coach <PERSON>Marv Levy</PERSON> said. "It really turned the momentum.";   <PERSON>Marino</PERSON> suffered
another costly turnover on the next play when his underthrown pass was
intercepted by <PERSON>Kirby Jackson</PERSON> and returned 12 yards to the <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 24. Seven
plays later, <PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON> kicked a 21-yard field goal.;   Fumble sets up
score;   <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> rookie <PERSON>Aaron Craver</PERSON> fumbled the second-half kickoff, and
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Hal Garner</PERSON> recovered at the 27. Kelly then hit <ORGANIZATION>Reed</ORGANIZATION> with a 5-yard TD
pass.;   The Dolphins finished with five turnovers, <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> none. With such
figures, <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Don Shula</PERSON> said, "there's just no way you're going to win
a game against a team with that kind of talent.";   <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Reed</ORGANIZATION> connected
from 23 yards for the Bills' final TD.;   <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Sammie Smith</PERSON> scored his
first touchdown of the season. Former Stanford tight end <PERSON>Greg Baty</PERSON> caught a
1-yard pass from <PERSON>Marino</PERSON> for his first TD since <DATE>1987</DATE>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Miami  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911119  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  372  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, November 19, 1991
00324210,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-12574</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CAZAFAC9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920125
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 JAN 92 / Sport: Bills seek their place in history - American Football
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PATRICK HARVERSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>MARV LEVY</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> graduate, history buff and poetry lover, talks a mean
game of American football.
The silver-haired head coach of the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills analyses the strategies
and tactics of the sport in a precise, elegant manner. His comments in press
conferences can come laced with literary allusions. He uses words like
'inculcate' and 'salient' in pre-game meetings with his team.
Tomorrow in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, however, the erudite <PERSON>Levy</PERSON> will leave the talking to
his players, who must play a mean game of football if they are to defeat the
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Redskins in Superbowl XXVI.
The Redskins start as favourites, and are expected to win by at least seven
points according to the bookmakers in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>. Yet for those of us who
have enjoyed watching the Bills this season, it is difficult to think of
them as underdogs.
Under <PERSON>Levy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> has set the <ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION> alight in the past
two seasons with a rapid-fire passing and running game which led the team to
a host of high scoring victories.
At the root of their success is the 'no-huddle' offense - a tactic that
dispenses with the huddle before each play and allows the quarterback to
call his own moves. At its best, the no-huddle offense puts points on the
board quickly and leaves opposing defenses scrambling to keep up with the
pace.
At the heart of the Bills attack are two great players, quarterback <PERSON>Jim
Kelly</PERSON> and all-purpose running back <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON>. Kelly is an experienced
leader with a sharp tactical brain and a strong arm, while <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> is a
superb all-rounder, a quicksilver runner and an acrobatic receiver.
Powered by <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> and <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, and supported by receivers <PERSON>James Lofton</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Andre Reed</PERSON>, the Bills topped the statistical tables in a number of key
attacking categories this season, including most total yards gained and most
touchdowns scored.
So with all their offensive firepower, why aren't the Bills favourites to
win?
There are two reasons, and both come down to defense. The Redskins' defense
is strong, against both the running and the passing game, and it ranks third
best in the league for overall effectiveness.
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s defense is especially good at 'blitzing' the quarterback - in
the 16 regular games this season they reached opposing quarterbacks and
sacked them 50 times. <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> has looked vulnerable to the sack in the past,
particularly two weekends ago when the <ORGANIZATION>Denver Broncos</ORGANIZATION>' blitzed relentlessly,
giving <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> insufficient time to get his no-huddle offense into gear.
The fragility of their own defense, which ranked next-to-last in the league
this season, is the second reason why the Bills are not favourites tomorrow.
They have shown an improvement in the playoffs (holding <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> to just seven
points in the AFC Championship game), thanks partly to the return of two
powerful players, slashing defensive end <PERSON>Bruce Smith</PERSON> and bulldozing nose
tackle <PERSON>Jeff Wright</PERSON>.
Yet in the <LOCATION>Redskins</LOCATION>, the Bills defense will be facing one of the toughest
offensive lines in football. This is where the 'Hogs' come in. Hogs is the
collective nickname for the enormous front-line that defends Redskins'
quarterback <PERSON>Mark Rypien</PERSON>.
Not only are the Hogs good at giving <PERSON>Rypien</PERSON> time to throw long passes to
receivers Art Monk, <PERSON>Gary Clark</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ricky Sanders</PERSON> (the protection has been so
effective that <PERSON>Rypien</PERSON> was sacked just nine times all season), but they are
also adept at knocking holes in defensive lines for backs <PERSON>Ernest Byner</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Ricky Ervins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gerald Riggs</PERSON> to run through.
One big advantage the Redskins have is the versatility of their attack. The
Bills rely heavily, perhaps too heavily, on <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>'s all-round skills. Stop
<PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> usually struggles.
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s three running backs possess different strengths and styles
providing a balance of power and precision. The trio of fleet wide receivers
spread defenses and regularly break open for long yardage. The variety of
attacking options available to Redskins coach <PERSON>Joe Gibbs</PERSON> helps explain why
his team was the highest-scoring unit in the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> this season.
Yet, as any fan of sports cliches knows, statistics and history mean little
when it comes to one Big Game. The difference may ultimately lie in
motivation, and how badly each team wants to win.
In this respect, the Bills could have the edge. It has been 363 days since
<PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON>'s potential game-winning kick sailed wide of the right hand
goalpost in the closing seconds of Superbowl XXV against the <ORGANIZATION>New York
Giants</ORGANIZATION>, and the determination of the Bills to avenge that loss burns just as
bright as it did a year ago.
Both teams have prepared thoroughly, but <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> seem to have gone about
their business amid the outrageous hype and publicity of Superbowl week in a
quieter, more purposeful manner.
And while less than half of the Redskins are survivors from the team's last
Superbowl appearance in <DATE>1987</DATE>, the Bills squad is much the same as it was
last year. The memories of that game are still fresh for <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON>, <PERSON>Thurman
Thomas</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Bruce Smith</PERSON>. My money is on <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> to win by three points,
courtesy of kicker <PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XII Photograph Bills head coach Marv Levy (Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111389-0020 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 134024 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 13, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 8; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
323 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COLTS LOSE THREE FUMBLES AND FALL TO BILLS, 30-7 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ORCHARD PARK, N.Y. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Three fumbles in the game's first seven minutes <DATE>Sunday</DATE> gave <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> Colt 
Coach <PERSON>Ron Meyer</PERSON> a mountainous problem. 
</P>
<P>
"As I said coming in, it looks like a very steep hill," <PERSON>Meyer</PERSON> said in reference 
to <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>' playoff chances after a 30-7 loss to the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills. "It 
looks like Mount Everest right now." 
</P>
<P>
The Colts (4-6) are three games behind the first-place Bills (7-3) in the race 
for the AFC East title and two games behind second-place <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It is best when you control your own destiny," Colts' offensive tackle <PERSON>Chris 
Hinton</PERSON> said. "But now we have to win the rest of our games and we also need 
some help from other teams if we are going to catch <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
The game's turning point may have come on the opening kickoff, when <PERSON>Mark Pike</PERSON> 
ripped the ball out of <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> returner <PERSON>James Pruitt</PERSON>'s hands. <PERSON>Mickey 
Sutton</PERSON> recovered for <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> on the Colt 22-yard line. 
</P>
<P>
"That fumble was a big emotional lift for us," <PERSON>Sutton</PERSON> said. "Both teams came 
out all psyched up and that play set the tone for the whole game." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON> took advantage of the mistake, connecting with <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON> for the 
first of <ORGANIZATION>Kelly</ORGANIZATION>'s three touchdown passes on the day with only 2:12 gone in the 
game. 
</P>
<P>
That fumble was forced by a hard hit. The Colts, especially running back <PERSON>Eric 
Dickerson</PERSON>, had no such excuse on the fumbles that ended their next two 
possessions. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Leonard Smith</PERSON> recovered <PERSON>Dickerson</PERSON>'s first fumble, giving <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> the ball at 
midfield, and <PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON> kicked a 42-yard field goal to make it 10-0. 
</P>
<P>
On the first play after the ensuing kickoff, <PERSON>Dickerson</PERSON>, who didn't talk to 
reporters after the game, fumbled again when the ball bounced off his knee. 
</P>
<P>
The Bills turned that into a 40-yard field goal by <ORGANIZATION>Norwood</ORGANIZATION> for a 13-0 lead. 
</P>
<P>
Touchdown passes of 32 and three yards from <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> to <PERSON>Andre Reed</PERSON> in the <DATE>second 
quarter</DATE> made it 27-0 at the half. 
</P>
<P>
The Bills rushed for 232 yards in 51 carries. Thomas had 127 yards in 29 
attempts. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06024473 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06024473 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; CHAMPIONSHIP; PLANNING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The talk of the Super Bowl has been not what the Buffalo Bills do, but what
they don't do: go into a huddle.;    Their no-huddle offense, which thoroughly
befuddled the Los Angeles Raiders at the start of the AFC championship game,
figures to be a significant weapon Sunday in Super Bowl XXV.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BILLS COUNT ON NO-HUDDLE FOR QUICK START  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Sunday's Game
N.Y. Giants vs. Buffalo in Tampa, Fla., 3:18 p.m. PST. TV: CH7 CH11 CH13
Radio: KCBS (740).
See also related article on page 1F and 5F of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The Bills won't use it all the time or even most of the time. Their routine
is to strike quickly, keeping the defense off balance, grabbing control of the
game's tempo. That's what they did in a 51-3 rout of the Raiders on Sunday.;  
 That's exactly what they would like to do against the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> champ <ORGANIZATION>New York
Giants</ORGANIZATION>. After all, scoring early is becoming a habit. The Bills have scored on
their first possession in nine of their past 12 games. Given that jump start,
they have scored a total of 95 points in two playoff games.;    "Once the
opponent sees us score so quickly on the first drive, which we've been doing a
lot lately, I think it gives our defense a psychological advantage," said
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> running back <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON>. "Now the other team is thinking that we
came out in a no-huddle and came right down and scored. It's a big morale
boost. People we play start thinking we can go up and down the field all
day.";    It was used against Bills;  The ironic part of the no-huddle offense
is that it was used effectively by the <LOCATION>Cincinnati Bengals</LOCATION> against the Bills
during the <DATE>1988</DATE> AFC championship game. Buffalo Coach <PERSON>Marv Levy</PERSON> protested
loudly before the game about the propriety of the no-huddle, where plays are
called at the line of scrimmage and defenses are not afforded time to make
adjustments.;    <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> won the game 21-10 and went to the Super Bowl. Now
Levy has used it to reach the Super Bowl.;    "They've been successful with
it," noted Giants defensive lineman <PERSON>Leonard Marshall</PERSON>. "They make you play a
