<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06107135 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06107135 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  OPINION; US; IMAGE; MUSIC  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  LET'S TEST your knowledge of music. Tell me what song these lyrics are from.; 
  1. Oh-dah-lah-hah la-hah-haha-eee-hee-hah-aaaand-uh aaaan-uh uvva-uvva-uvva
fruh-heee-heeeeee.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Editorial  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SING IT WITH RESPECT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Commentary
Mike Royko is a Chicago Tribune columnist.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     2. Anna homma-duh homma-du-du-du hommaaaaaaaaa.;    3.
Dee-uh-dee-hah-hah-hah buh-huheee-buh-huhe-eee-eee-eee-ray-have.;    You say
you don't recognize it? Nonsense. Of course you do. It's likely that you've
heard and sung it dozens or hundreds of times, depending on your age. Your
parents sang it. And probably your grandparents too.;    You still don't know
it? I'll throw out a few hints.;    It's a very old song. The words were
written more than 150 years ago. The melody is even older than that. You still
don't know? Then you don't go to many Opening Days at baseball games.;    Of
course, when <PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> wrote that line, as well as the others that
precede and follow it, he kept the lyrics much simpler: "O'er the land of the
free and the home of the brave." And for many years, that's the way it was
sung.;    But it's no longer done that way. There has developed an informal
competition among singers at ballparks, hockey rinks, basketball stadiums and
other patriotic gathering places to see who can best turn "The Star-Spangled
Banner" into something resembling the howls of a maniac.;    I'm not sure when
these free-form interpretations began, although I vaguely remember some guy
named Jose creating a stir a few years ago by opening a World Series with a
rendition that sounded like the Star-Spangled Cha-Cha-Cha.;    Since then, I
have heard the anthem has been performed as the Star-Spangled Rock, the
Star-Spangled Disco, the Star-Spangled Gospel, the Star-Spangled Blues, the
Star-Spangled Hootenanny and the Star-Spangled Barbershop Quartet.;    A few
weeks ago, a woman who sang it before a <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bulls</ORGANIZATION> game is believed to have
set a record by using a variety of prolonged howls, shrieks, warbles, screams
and other vocal acrobatics to drag it out to more than five minutes.;    A man
who was there told me: "I couldn't understand one word. And, I swear, if I
were a <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> policeman and I heard those sounds coming from a building, I
would radio for backup, then draw my gun and go crashing into the place on the
assumption that a woman was being brutally attacked by a gang of fiends.";   
I think it is time to draw the line. After all, it is our national anthem. As
such, it should be performed with some dignity, rather than sounding as if the
singer has been bitten in the rear by a pit bull.;    It's doubtful that
anyone would stand in center court at <LOCATION>Wimbledon</LOCATION> and sing: "Ga-hah
Say-hey-he-hey-iv ow-ow-owah guh-ray-hey-hey-hey-hey shush
Qwa-hey-qua-hey-heee-eeeen." (That's "God save our gracious queen," ballpark
style).;    And think of the children. Generation after generation of parents
bring their children to ballparks to introduce them to the national pastime.
Do we want these children later standing up in the assembly hall and saying:
"No, teacher, it starts like this: 'Oh-hoh-hey cah-han-you-see-uh-see-uh
by-the daw-haw-hawns err-uh-err-ee-uh-lee-lah-lite?"';    That isn't what
<PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> had in <LOCATION>mind.</LOCATION>;    On the other hand, some musicologists say
that the melody can be traced back to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> where it had different lyrics
and was a drinking song. So maybe it's not totally inappropriate for today's
singers to sound as if they just downed a quart of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Comfort</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MIKE ROYKO  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910416  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  631  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday April 16, 1991
00107135,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891213-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-13-89 0232EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-NationalAnthem     12-13 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-National Anthem,0324</SECOND>
<HEAD>Francis Scott Key's Hometown Riled About Anthem Flap</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FREDERICK, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Legislation that would scrap ``The
Star-Spangled Banner'' as the national anthem has riled people in
the hometown of <PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON>, who wrote the song 175 years ago.
   ``I honestly feel they should leave it be,'' said <PERSON>Harry L.
Decker</PERSON>, <PERSON>Frederick</PERSON>'s historian. ``I think it's more like a hymn than
a song. It brings tears to a lot of people's eyes.''
   Rep. <PERSON>Andrew Jacobs Jr.</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ind.</LOCATION>, has introduced legislation in
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for the ninth time in 12 years to supplant it with
``America the Beautiful.''
   <PERSON>Decker</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he thought the campaign for change was being
fueled by people who believe the song embraces war and by those who
think it's too hard to sing.
   ``If they can't sing it, they can't sing,'' <PERSON>Decker</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>David Maloney Jr.</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Historical Society of
Frederick County</ORGANIZATION>, said he liked ``America the Beautiful,'' but
thinks it's less ``emotionally stirring'' than ``The Star-Spangled
Banner.''
   The proposal to replace the national anthem also has struck a
sensitive chord with the <PERSON>Frederick Keys</PERSON>, the city's new minor
league baseball team.
   ``His monument (in Mount Olivet Cemetery) faces our new
stadium,'' said <PERSON>Mark Zeigler</PERSON>, the team's assistant general manager.
``I've got a lot of pride in this area and the state.
   ``This is something of local significance that is national. It
would take away some of the significance.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Frederick County Arts Council</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>Carole Werking</PERSON> said: ``I
like `America the Beautiful.' I think it is easier to sing, but
<PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> being <PERSON>Frederick</PERSON>'s native son and having a lot of
pride in my community, I don't think we should change it.''
   Gov. <PERSON>William Donald Schaefer</PERSON> has written to <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>'s
congressional delegation, urging them to oppose any change.
   <PERSON>Jacobs</PERSON> said the protests probably are unnecessary because he
doesn't think his bill will pass.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06191229 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06191229 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; Minnesota's Jack Morris starts tonight  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; BASEBALL; CHAMPIONSHIP; GAME; BRIEF  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Scott Erickson will not be the American League's starting pitcher in tonight's
62nd All-Star Game, but there will be a reminder of him on Toronto's SkyDome
mound.;    "I'm wearing the low socks in honor of Scotty," said Jack Morris,
Erickson's elder teammate at Minnesota and his replacement as the starting
pitcher. "I know how much he wanted to be here. He is by far the best pitcher
in the league at this point."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MORRIS GETS TO START TONIGHT IN PLACE OF TWINS TEAMMATE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  All-Star Game Preview;  SETTING THE RECORD STRAIGHT (publ. 7/10/91, pg. 2E); 
Because of an editor's error, the junior college for which Minnesota Twins
pitcher Scott Erickson formerly played was incorrect in Tuesday's editions.
Erickson played for San Jose City College.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Erickson</PERSON>, from <ORGANIZATION>Homestead High</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>De Anza College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cupertino</LOCATION>, was 12-2
with a 1.83 ERA in this, his first full season. He would have started today,
but he was placed on the disabled list recently because of an elbow problem.; 
  <ORGANIZATION>While National League</ORGANIZATION> Manager <PERSON>Lou Piniella</PERSON> chose <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Tom Glavine</PERSON> to
start, counterpart <ORGANIZATION>Tony La Russa</ORGANIZATION> said he chose <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> because he is
right-handed.;    The only two A.L. left-handers are <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>'s Jimmy Key
(10-4) and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> (12-3). There was speculation that Key
might start in front of his home fans, but La Russa said he wants the
left-handers available in later innings. <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> was chosen over <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Roger
Clemens</PERSON> (11-5), who slowed after a sizzling start this season.;    Starting
was an unexpected honor for <PERSON>Morris</PERSON>, but then, this hasn't been the sort of
season that was expected from him. He had been the winningest pitcher of the
<DATE>'80s</DATE>, and seemingly was a <ORGANIZATION>Detroit Tigers</ORGANIZATION> lifer. Many people considered the
small-market Twins foolish for giving him <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> this season as a free
agent. But <PERSON>Morris</PERSON>, 36, won seven in a row at one stretch and is 11-6 with a
3.65 ERA.; Franco pained; by fan voting;  As it turns out, <PERSON>Julio Franco</PERSON> has
had more to worry about than <PERSON>Roberto Alomar</PERSON>'s ability.;    <LOCATION>Franco</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Texas
Rangers</ORGANIZATION>' second baseman and <DATE>last year</DATE>'s All-Star MVP, said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that
<LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Alomar</PERSON>, voted the <ORGANIZATION>A.L.</ORGANIZATION> starter in fan balloting, does not deserve to
start ahead of him at second base. Franco left <LOCATION>Arlington Stadium</LOCATION> after saying
that -- and was checked into a nearby hospital because of chest discomfort.;  
 The diagnosis was that the problem was caused by a combination of the heat
and caffeine; he was discharged <DATE>Monday</DATE> morning.;    <PERSON>Alomar</PERSON> is hitting .284
with 37 RBIs, 27 steals and eight errors.;    "He can keep talking all he
wants," <PERSON>Alomar</PERSON> said of Franco, who is hitting .318 with 40 RBIs, 17 steals and
11 errors. "He's going to have to wait five or six innings before he gets into
the All-Star Game.";    Who says All-Star games aren't exciting anymore?; Like
old times; for <LOCATION>Sanderson</LOCATION>;  <PERSON>Dave Henderson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rickey Henderson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dennis Eckersley</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Scott Sanderson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dave Duncan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rene Lachemann</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tommie Reynolds</PERSON>. Which one of
those names does not belong?;    If you said <PERSON>Sanderson</PERSON>, you're technically
correct. He no longer represents the A's, but those seven lockers are side-by-
side in the <LOCATION>A.L.</LOCATION> clubhouse. For <PERSON>Sanderson</PERSON>, who is 9-3 since the A's let him to
go the <LOCATION>New York Yankees</LOCATION> as a free agent, this is like old times.;    "Any time
I think about my days with the A's, I just have a real good feeling," said
<PERSON>Sanderson</PERSON>, who won 17 games last season but was not re-signed, purely for
economic reasons. "I think I'm a much better player for having played in
<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. A lot of players can go their whole careers and not get a chance to
be on a team like that."; <PERSON>Ripken</PERSON> wins home run battle;   <LOCATION>Cal Ripken</LOCATION>'s 18
homers were the most by a major league shortstop before the All-Star break
since <PERSON>Rico Petrocelli</PERSON> had 23 in <DATE>1969</DATE>. The <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> iron man has been doing it
all this season, so maybe we shouldn't be surprised that he made such sluggers
as <PERSON>Cecil Fielder</PERSON>, <PERSON>Howard Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Joe Carter</PERSON> look like lightweights
Monday.;    <PERSON>Ripken</PERSON> won the <ORGANIZATION>Home Run Derby</ORGANIZATION> with 12 homers in 20 swings, seven
more than the nearest competitor, <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Paul O'Neill</PERSON>. Fielder hit
four.;    <PERSON>Ripken</PERSON> amazed the lunchtime crowd by hitting seven of the first
eight pitches for homers.;    "Lachemann just kept saying, 'Geez,' " <PERSON>Ripken</PERSON>
said of the A's coach, who served as the derby's catcher. "It's funny, I got
to take a few extra swings in (batting practice), and I was going to right
field. I didn't feel I'd be able to take it up a notch. It didn't feel good.";
<PERSON>Carter</PERSON> learns how sweet it is;  After all those 100-RBI seasons, <PERSON>Joe Carter</PERSON>
finally made it to an All-Star Game. The fact that he is playing before his
newest home fans obviously makes it even sweeter.;    "It was a long time
coming, but that's been the way with my entire career," said <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>, who was
traded with <PERSON>Roberto Alomar</PERSON> from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> over the <DATE>winter</DATE> for <PERSON>Fred McGriff</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Tony Fernandez</PERSON>. "People doubted my ability, and that drove me. Hopefully,
people will keep doubting me and I'll keep proving them wrong."; Please
explain that again, <PERSON>Lou;   Piniella</PERSON> tried to explain why he chose <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>'s
<PERSON>Ivan Calderon</PERSON> over <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>George Bell</PERSON> to sub for <PERSON>Darryl Strawberry.</PERSON>;    "We
have two natural left fielders on the team," <PERSON>Piniella</PERSON> said. "Calderon is
having a good season, plus he knows the <ORGANIZATION>A.L.</ORGANIZATION> well. He's faced <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> quite a
few times.";    Didn't <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION> also just come from a long <LOCATION>A.L.</LOCATION> career?; <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> is
his first All-Star appearance, said he holds no grudges against <ORGANIZATION>Giants General
Manager Al Rosen</ORGANIZATION>. Last <DATE>winter</DATE>, <PERSON>Rosen</PERSON> chose to let <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> become a free agent
and signed <PERSON>Willie McGee</PERSON> as his replacement.;    "He's like a father to me,"
<PERSON>Butler</PERSON> said. "Say a father does something his son doesn't understand -- you
still love him. It doesn't mean I don't respect him. . . . I was very close to
Al, and I still am.";    <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> said he wants to talk about the past <DATE>winter</DATE>
with <PERSON>Rosen</PERSON> over dinner but said his schedule has been too busy. "I just want
to hear it," he said. "I just want to know what went through his mind.";    As
for <PERSON>Rosen</PERSON>'s future, <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> predicted, "Al's not going to step away until he's
back. Al <PERSON>Rosen</PERSON> will not step down until that team is back where it should be.
To go from one extreme to the other, they want it back. Roger (<PERSON>Craig</PERSON>) is the
same way. It's more for (<ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> owner) <PERSON>Bob Lurie</PERSON>, because of the man he is."  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910709  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,131  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, July 9, 1991
00191229,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081990-0129 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 264191 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 19, 1990, Sunday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 17; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1039 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BASEBALL / STEVE HENSON; 
</P>
<P>
FRANCO DOING HIS PART TO DELIVER A HIT PERFORMANCE FOR PEORIA 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By STEVE HENSON 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Bing and <PERSON>Lou Russell</PERSON> shifted uncomfortably in their seats, growing ever more 
irate as the heckler, a few rows back, continued his relentless diatribe. The 
target was the first baseman for the visiting <LOCATION>Peoria</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>) <LOCATION>Chiefs</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Hey, number nine, hustle to your position," the man yelled in a thick Latino 
accent. "You're better than that, nine. Stay in the game." 
</P>
<P>
No. 9 happened to be <PERSON>Matt Franco</PERSON>, the Russells' grandson. Finally, they had 
heard enough. Lou turned to confront the loudmouth, then gasped in 
astonishment. It was her son, <PERSON>Kurt Russell</PERSON>, doing one of his better acting 
jobs. 
</P>
<P>
Russell, best known for his roles in such films as "Silkwood," "Escape From New 
York" and "The Best of Times," had only the best of intentions, however. He 
wanted to fire up Franco without revealing his identity. No one knew <PERSON>Kurt</PERSON> was 
at the game in <LOCATION>Rockford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, not even his parents. 
</P>
<P>
"I heard him for a while, and when the inning ended, I looked up and it was 
<PERSON>Kurt</PERSON>," <PERSON>Franco</PERSON> said. "He was dressed to conceal his identity. He's gotta go 
incognito." 
</P>
<P>
Franco, whose mother <PERSON>Jill</PERSON> is <PERSON>Kurt</PERSON>'s sister, rapidly is establishing his own 
identity. A 6-foot-3 left-handed hitter from <LOCATION>Westlake High</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Franco</PERSON> is 
challenging for the <ORGANIZATION>Midwest League</ORGANIZATION> batting title. With 13 games to play, he is 
batting .290, 15 points behind league-leader <PERSON>Scott Cepicky</PERSON> of <LOCATION>South Bend</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Franco has batted .382 the past month for the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Cubs</ORGANIZATION>' Class-A affiliate 
after beginning the season in a horrendous slump. 
</P>
<P>
Like any 20-year-old from <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Franco</PERSON> saw his spirits -- and 
batting average -- rise along with the temperature. 
</P>
<P>
"The first few weeks were ridiculous. Some nights it was 18 degrees with the 
wind-chill factor," <PERSON>Franco</PERSON> said. "Who can hit when your hands are numb?" 
</P>
<P>
Bedeviled: They have used pitches rather than pitchforks, but two former 
<ORGANIZATION>Arizona State Sun Devils</ORGANIZATION> have helped toss former <ORGANIZATION>Camarillo High</ORGANIZATION> right-hander 
<PERSON>Travis Willis</PERSON> from <LOCATION>Peoria</LOCATION>'s starting rotation. 
</P>
<P>
The Cubs assigned <PERSON>Lance Dickson</PERSON>, their <DATE>1990</DATE> No. 1 draft choice out of <ORGANIZATION>Arizona 
State</ORGANIZATION>, to <LOCATION>Peoria</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 4</DATE>. After four starts, <PERSON>Dickson</PERSON> was promoted. He is now 
with the Cubs. 
</P>
<P>
Replacing <PERSON>Dickson</PERSON> at <LOCATION>Peoria</LOCATION> was <PERSON>Troy Bradford</PERSON>, the team's third-round draft 
pick, also out of <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION>. About the same time, Manager <PERSON>Greg Mahlberg</PERSON> 
decided to stick with a four-man rotation after using five starters much of the 
season. All of which left <PERSON>Willis</PERSON> in long relief. 
</P>
<P>
At first glance, <PERSON>Willis</PERSON> seemed an odd choice for banishment to the bullpen. The 
former <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> standout was 8-9 with an earned-run average of 3.18 in 20 starts for 
the Chiefs (49-77), who are last in the <LOCATION>Midwest League</LOCATION>. With five complete 
games he still ranks among league leaders and he has walked only 39 in 154 
innings. 
</P>
<P>
"My control worked against me," <PERSON>Willis</PERSON> said. "They told me I'm a guy they can 
count on to come in and throw strikes. I was a better candidate for the bullpen 
than somebody who can't find the plate." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Willis</PERSON> has been hit hard in relief -- he is now 9-11 with a 3.49 ERA -- and 
<PERSON>Mahlberg</PERSON> might be having a change of heart. <PERSON>Willis</PERSON> got a start against <LOCATION>Waterloo</LOCATION> 
(<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>) on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and gave up one earned run, getting the win in the 
<ORGANIZATION>Chiefs</ORGANIZATION>' 5-2 victory. 
</P>
<P>
Holy Toledo: How <PERSON>Scott Muckey</PERSON> made his professional coaching debut at age 37 is 
basically a travel story. Certainly, it's circuitous. 
</P>
<P>
The manager of the <PERSON>Toledo</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>) Mud Hens, <PERSON>John Wockenfuss</PERSON>, was afraid to fly, 
so he was told to hit the road. The lone coach, <PERSON>Aurelio Rodriguez</PERSON>, had family 
problems in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, so he took off south of the border, never to return. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Tom Gamboa</PERSON>, the new Mud Hen manager, called <PERSON>Muckey</PERSON>, a longtime friend, <DATE>July 18</DATE> 
and asked if he had two months to spare. <PERSON>Muckey</PERSON> was on the next flight to 
<LOCATION>Toledo</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It took me all of a few seconds to make the decision," said <PERSON>Muckey</PERSON>, who had 
planned to spend the <DATE>summer</DATE> in his usual manner -- coaching an <ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION> 
team and helping out at baseball camps. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Muckey</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Crespi High</ORGANIZATION> coach, has been at the high school or junior college 
levels since his playing career ended at <ORGANIZATION>Pepperdine</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1974</DATE>. All of a sudden, 
he found himself pitching batting practice and coaching first base for the 
<ORGANIZATION>Detroit Tigers' triple-A International League</ORGANIZATION> affiliate. 
</P>
<P>
In <PERSON>Muckey</PERSON>'s first game, <LOCATION>Toledo</LOCATION> played <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION>, which coincidentally is 
managed by <PERSON>Steve Smith</PERSON>, a friend of <ORGANIZATION>Muckey's</ORGANIZATION>. "He was kind of surprised to see 
me," <PERSON>Muckey</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The rookie coach trotted out to the first-base coach's box. The first Toledo 
batter singled . . . and was promptly picked off. The next <LOCATION>Toledo</LOCATION> batter 
doubled . . . and was picked off. Two innings later, a <LOCATION>Toledo</LOCATION> batter singled . 
. . and was picked off. 
</P>
<P>
"Old Smitty's over there in the dugout laughing at me," <PERSON>Muckey</PERSON> recalled. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Muckey</PERSON> has earned respect with his understated manner and knowledge of the 
game. Yet he is a mere chick among the <ORGANIZATION>Mud Hens</ORGANIZATION> in terms of professional 
experience. 
</P>
<P>
"I've made all the rookie mistakes. Just trying to keep track of the time 
schedule is hard enough," he said, chuckling. "I was running out there with my 
uniform on when we were supposed to be in batting practice tops." 
</P>
<P>
Another day he forgot his cap. "If they were serious about fining me, they 
could have slapped me for <MONEY>$150</MONEY> for not being in the right place at the right 
time." 
</P>
<P>
The fans have been less forgiving. During a game in <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Muckey</PERSON> 
fielded a foul ball down the first-base line and tossed it to the ball boy. 
</P>
<P>
Oops. 
</P>
<P>
"The crowd was all over me," he said. "I don't know why. But now when a ball 
comes near me, I watch it roll by." 
</P>
<P>
The season itself is flying by. Muckey is enjoying every minute, but after a 
month beating around the bush leagues, he paints a less-than-romantic picture: 
Sit around a hotel room until 3 or <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>, head to the ballpark, try to wind 
down after <TIME>midnight</TIME>. The next day, ditto. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't think the pro life's for everyone," he said. 
</P>
<P>
"Probably a lot of kids looking to be pro players are in for a little bit of a 
surprise." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Muckey</PERSON>, not being much for night life, has used his time in the hotel room to 
prepare for his Crespi teaching duties -- school begins <DATE>Sept. 3</DATE>, one day after 
the <ORGANIZATION>Mud Hens</ORGANIZATION>' season ends. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm studying up on physiology," he said without enthusiasm. "That's what they 
have me teaching this year." 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911129-0021
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911129-0021.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- On Sports:
   Prepping for Albertville
   ----
   By Frederick C. Klein
</HL>
<DATE>
11/29/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A5
</SO>
<LP>

to date, there will be an Olympics, the winter one, in
Albertville, France, beginning in about 10 weeks. And the
U.S. will field a hockey team as usual, although there's been
little fuss about that, either.
   "There's been less hype this time around -- no doubt about
that," affirmed Dave Peterson, the hockey team's coach,
before his charges faced the St. Louis Blues of the National
Hockey League here Monday night in the 35th game of its
60-game pre-Olympic tour.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Peterson</PERSON> thought the lack of attention here to the
<DATE>February</DATE> winter games is "probably because expectations of
our doing well haven't been as high as they were prior to
previous Games." But he made it clear he wasn't complaining:
"If I had my way, it'd be quieter yet. The fewer distractions
we have, the easier it is to prepare a squad. And public
relations isn't exactly the thing I do best."
   Ah, yes, public relations. You'll recall (or, maybe, you
don't) that <PERSON>Peterson</PERSON> coached our last Olympic hockey team, at
<LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> in <DATE>1988</DATE>. And unlike the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>'s "Miracle on Ice" gang
that won a gold medal at <LOCATION>Lake Placid</LOCATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE>, its 3-3
won-lost record, and seventh-place finish in a field of 12,
defined mediocrity. But he enlivened things by answering
questions about the club's performance by questioning his
questioners' motives and intelligence.
   Before he got the job this time around, <ORGANIZATION>USA Hockey</ORGANIZATION>, which
runs this particular show, insisted <PERSON>Peterson</PERSON> take a course in
responding to the news media. The long-time <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> high
school coach obliged, and reports that the experience was
relatively painless.
   "We did some role playing. I even held the notebook for
awhile," he said, smiling. "I think I learned a few things,
but it didn't really change my perspective. As I saw it, the
problem at <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> was that some reporters wanted me to
negatively evaluate individual players, and I wouldn't do it.
Given the same circumstances, I'd probably react the same way
again. But all in all, I enjoyed <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION>, and learned there,
too. And, maybe, the circumstances won't be the same this
time."
   The fact that Team <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> was here, playing the <ORGANIZATION>NHL Blues</ORGANIZATION>,
reflects one thing that <PERSON>Peterson</PERSON> learned in <DATE>'88</DATE>. The '88 team
compiled a gaudy, 37-18-5 pre-Olympic record, but it was
achieved mainly at the expense of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> collegiate teams that
offered little competition or preparation for Olympic-level
hockey. The record of this year's crew after a 6-4 loss to
the Blues <DATE>Monday</DATE> is 14-16-5, but it probably means more
because it comes mostly from a tougher card of NHL or elite
foreign teams.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> defeated a Soviet national team in an <DATE>August</DATE>
tournament in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and holds a 2-2-2 record after two,
three-game sets against the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian Nationals</ORGANIZATION>. Its 3-10-2
mark against <ORGANIZATION>NHL</ORGANIZATION> competition includes wins over the <LOCATION>Minnesota
North Stars</LOCATION> and San Jose Sharks (two) and ties with the
<LOCATION>Philadelphia Flyers</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Sabres</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Peterson</PERSON>'s '88 team was faulted for loose defense,
especially during an Olympics in which it surrendered 31
goals in six outings. The coach says that was partly an
offshoot of a free-wheeling style that produced a lot of
goals as well, and wonders aloud why a 3-1 defeat should be
preferable to one of 7-5. That, not incidentally, was the
score by which <ORGANIZATION>Team USA</ORGANIZATION> fell to the favored Czechs and
gold-medal-winning Soviets at <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION>. And while he admits
his current crew has been "overpowered" on occasion by bigger
NHL outfits, he says "we expect our speed to make us better
defensively this time around" once it gets on the larger ice
surface used in international play.
   Withal, the coach says this team shapes up as faster and
deeper than his last unit, and one that contains a better
blend of youth and experience. Among the younger players
showing early foot are <PERSON>Shawn McEachern</PERSON>, a 22-year-old wing
out of <ORGANIZATION>Boston University</ORGANIZATION> who is its leading scorer with 18
goals and 15 assists in 31 games; <PERSON>Scott Lachance</PERSON>, a speedy,
18-year-old defenseman from the same school; and <PERSON>Ted Drury</PERSON>, a
19-year-old center from <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>. In the experience category,
nobody tops center <PERSON>Scott Fusco</PERSON>. He's a 28-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>
grad who was a member of the <DATE>1984</DATE> and '88 Olympic teams. As
far as he knows, no one else ever played for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> in
three Olympics in the sport.
   Fusco, a smallish redhead, quit hockey after the last
Games and went to work in his family's computer business in
<LOCATION>Winchester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>. Last <DATE>July 4</DATE>, though, he got back on skates,
found he could still stand and liked the feeling, and so
again reported for duty. "A lot of people played sports in
college, and quite a few are pros, but being an Olympian puts
you in a special club," he says by way of explanation.
   Goalie is, probably, the key position in the six- or
eight-game Olympic hockey sprint, and the identity of the man
or men who will protect the nets for <ORGANIZATION>Team USA</ORGANIZATION> is still in
doubt. <PERSON>Scott Gordon</PERSON>, formerly of the <ORGANIZATION>NHL</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Quebec Nordiques</ORGANIZATION>,
and <PERSON>Les Kuntar</PERSON>, out of <ORGANIZATION>St. Lawrence U.</ORGANIZATION>, split the post until
<PERSON>Kuntar</PERSON> suffered a broken jaw. <PERSON>Ray LeBlanc</PERSON>, a veteran minor
leaguer, took <PERSON>Kuntar</PERSON>'s place and gave up but four goals in
three games before <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. The Blues got him for six,
but the number easily could have been nine or 10, and
<PERSON>Peterson</PERSON> later expressed himself as impressed.
   The world has changed since the '88 Games, and in ways
that may improve <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> chances for a hockey medal. Most
obviously, some of the best Soviet players have opted for
capitalism and will be playing for the <ORGANIZATION>NHL</ORGANIZATION>'s lucre while
others maintain the honor of what's left of the <ORGANIZATION>USSR</ORGANIZATION> at
<LOCATION>Albertville</LOCATION>. But people who know about such things say there
are sufficient proficient icemen left to make the Sovs the
choice for their eighth Olympic gold medal in the sport in
the last 10 quadrenniums, with the Swedes, Finns, Czechs and
Canadians not far behind.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> teams have done pretty well in recent international
tournaments, finishing fifth in the last World Championships
and second in the <DATE>1990</DATE> Goodwill Games. The brusque, beefy
<PERSON>Peterson</PERSON> opines that "despite what some people thought, we
weren't all that far out of it" in <DATE>'88</DATE>, and says he expects a
medal this time.
   "That's why we have a team," he says. "If it isn't,
nobody's told me."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900727-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-27-90 1452EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Barr-Anthem 1stLd-Writethru a0483 07-27 0690</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Barr-Anthem, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0483,0709</SECOND>
<HEAD>Critics: Barr's Screeching National Anthem Not Funny, or Patriotic</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 5th graf, `But she...' to UPDATE with
Bush comment. Note language in 20th graf.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto GOS1 of July 26</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS GEORGATOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   O'er the ramparts rained criticism of Roseanne
<PERSON>Barr</PERSON>'s screeching, off-key rendition of the national anthem at a
baseball game, but the comedian defended her conduct even if her
wailing solo struck out.
   ``Geez, gimme a break. I was just trying to sing a song,'' the
caustic star of the <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> sitcom ``Roseanne'' told Los Angeles-area
television station <ORGANIZATION>KCAL</ORGANIZATION> in a telephone interview broadcast <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME>.
   Barr conceded she was ``no <PERSON>Beverly Sills</PERSON>,'' referring to the
famed opera singer. She said she has a naturally shrill singing
voice.
   ``I apologize that people were so appalled,'' she said.
   But she added: ``If this is the worst thing they ever heard,
they've had it really easy.'' <PERSON>Barr</PERSON> said if she ever sang the anthem
again she'd ``want to do it for a hipper crowd.''
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, flying to <LOCATION>Kennebunkport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, for the <DATE>weekend</DATE>,
said <DATE>today</DATE> that <PERSON>Barr</PERSON>'s rendition was ``disgraceful. That's the way
I feel about it and I think a lot of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> fans said the same
thing.''
   Fans at <PERSON>Jack Murphy Stadium</PERSON>, where the <LOCATION>San Diego Padres</LOCATION> were
playing a doubleheader with the <ORGANIZATION>Cincinnati Reds</ORGANIZATION>, booed <PERSON>Barr</PERSON> after
the shrieking performance <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   After screaming the final notes, she grabbed her crotch and spit
on the field.
   Barr told <ORGANIZATION>KCAL</ORGANIZATION> the crotch-grabbing gesture and spitting were
meant to parody mannerisms common among some baseball players, not
to show disrepect for the anthem or booing fans.
   The comedy actress had been invited to sing ``The Star-Spangled
Banner'' by her boss, <PERSON>Tom Werner</PERSON>, the co-creator and executive
producer of ``Roseanne.'' Earlier this year, <PERSON>Werner</PERSON> led a 15-member
investment group that bought the Padres for <MONEY>$75 million</MONEY>. He is now
chairman and managing partner of the team.
   Padres headquarters were deluged by 1,200 calls <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, mostly
complaints. The team issued an apology and said in the statement
that they ``recognize their obligation to ensure the national
anthem is sung with respect and dignity.''
   National League President <PERSON>William D. White</PERSON> said: ``We have
discussed it with the Padres and are in agreement with their
apology. We are satisfied that they will take all necessary steps
to assure it will not happen again.''
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, before their game against the <ORGANIZATION>Houston Astros</ORGANIZATION>,
the Padres played a taped version of the national anthem performed
by the <ORGANIZATION>Marine Corps</ORGANIZATION>. The crowd gave it a rousing ovation.
   Barr's caterwauling rendition was the subject of much of <PERSON>Johnny
Carson</PERSON>'s ``Tonight Show'' monologue <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   ``<PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> must be spinning like a lathe,'' he quipped,
referring to the anthem's composer. ``The closest sound I heard was
when I got my cat neutered.''
   Others leveled more serious criticism.
   ``It was to me like burning of the flag,'' said <PERSON>Robert Merrill</PERSON>,
70, who has been singing the national anthem in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s Yankee
Stadium for 18 years.
   Padres pitcher <PERSON>Eric Show</PERSON> said, ``It's an insult. There are
people who died for that song.''
   About 30,000 people attended the doubleheader promoted as
``Working Women's Night.''
   ``I was embarrassed for the women who showed up,'' said
spectator <PERSON>Jannette Davis</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. ``This was supposed to be a
night of saluting those who worked hard and she made us all feel
like crap.''
   It wasn't the first time <PERSON>Barr</PERSON> achieved notoriety at a baseball
game. In the stands during a World Series game in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> <DATE>last
fall</DATE>, she bared her bottom, revealing a tattoo declaring ``Tom'' _
her husband, <PERSON>Tom Arnold</PERSON>.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <PERSON>Arnold</PERSON> urged critics to lighten up.
   ``They knew what kind of singer she is. She's just an average
singer. She's not an opera singer,'' <PERSON>Arnold</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated
Press</ORGANIZATION> by telephone from their <LOCATION>Malibu</LOCATION> home. ``She did the best she
could.''
   Barr wouldn't come to the telephone, but was troubled by the
criticism, he said.
   ``She's very sorry,'' <PERSON>Arnold</PERSON> said. ``She's very upset that
people think she meant disrespect.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900106-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-06-90 1444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NationalAnthem     01-06 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-National Anthem,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Birthplace of National Anthem Rallies to Its Defense</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER BRANDLON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Oh say, can you sing the national anthem?
   Most people can't, says a congressman from <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> who wants to
scrap ``The Star-Spangled Banner'' as the nation's official song in
favor of the less straining ``<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> the Beautiful.''
   Rep. <PERSON>Andrew Jacobs</PERSON> also says the poem penned by <PERSON>Francis Scott</PERSON>
Key after American troops repelled British forces at <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>'s
<LOCATION>Fort McHenry</LOCATION> in <DATE>1814</DATE> is unsuitable because it celebrates war and
because the tune's origin is an old drinking song _ and an English
one, to boot.
   <PERSON>Jacobs</PERSON>' introduction of a bill to make the change, though
nothing new, has provoked a spirited defense.
   ``Who says you can't sing it?'' demanded <ORGANIZATION>Maryland Historical
Society</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Darlene Frank</PERSON>.
   The society held a contest in <DATE>September</DATE> to commemorate the 175th
anniversary of the writing of the anthem and found ``more than 300
patriotic Americans who loved the song enough to want to sing it in
public ... and a capella, no less,'' <PERSON>Frank</PERSON> wrote in a letter
dismissing <PERSON>Jacob</PERSON>'s proposal.
   The Democrat has introduced the bill nine times in 12 years,
without gaining any appreciable support.
   ``It's not a burning issue in my existence,'' <PERSON>Jacobs</PERSON> said.
   Still, he does not plan to forego the campaign. ``America the
Beautiful'' is gradually eclipsing ``The Star-Spangled Banner'' as
the song of choice at official functions, he said.
   In <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>, Gov. <PERSON>William Donald Schaefer</PERSON> has asked the state's
congressional delegation to oppose <PERSON>Jacobs</PERSON>' bill. The <PERSON>Frederick</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Keys</LOCATION>, a minor league baseball team named for the composer,
also opposes the change.
   <PERSON>Karen Stuart</PERSON>, head librarian at the <ORGANIZATION>Maryland Historical Society</ORGANIZATION>,
said the latest attempt to replace the anthem has prompted more
outcry that in the past.
   The public may be more sensitive because of the emphasis on the
<ORGANIZATION>Pledge of Allegiance</ORGANIZATION> during the <DATE>1988</DATE> presidential campaign and the
<ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>'s ruling last <DATE>summer</DATE> that the burning of the flag is
a protected form of free speech.
   Key wrote the anthem to commemorate the defense of <LOCATION>Fort McHenry</LOCATION>,
where citizen soldiers withstood 25 hours of bombardment from
British ships during the War of <DATE>1812</DATE>.
   Key almost certainly took some poetic liberties in his most
famous verse. Historians say it is unlikely he saw the flag
``gallantly streaming'' because it would have been soggy after a
night of pounding rain. And <PERSON>Stuart</PERSON> said some scholars question
whether the rockets' red glare was sufficient to illuminate the
banner through the smoke and mist from as far away as the truce
ship which Key was aboard.
   Flawed or not, ``The Star-Spangled Banner'' enjoyed immediate
popularity in the young nation. The melody was ``To Anacreon in
Heaven,'' the slightly bawdy theme song of a private men's club in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. The tune became well-known on both sides of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>
but didn't get official recognition until <DATE>1931</DATE>.
   Its rival _ the tribute to spacious skies and amber waves of
grain _ was written in the <DATE>late 19th century</DATE> by a <LOCATION>Wellesley</LOCATION> College
English literature professor, <PERSON>Katherine Lee Bates</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Jacobs</PERSON> said he was impressed by the story of how <PERSON>Bates</PERSON> was
inspired to write ``America the Beautiful,'' not by an armed
conflict, but by the beauty she beheld from the peak of a <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>
mountain.
   But neither song is <PERSON>Jacobs</PERSON>' personal favorite among patriotic
tunes.
   ``I like `This Land Is Your Land,''' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06058267 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06058267 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  US; MUSIC; CHILDREN; FAMILY; LEARNING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THIS SUNDAY, March 3, marks the 60th anniversary of our national anthem, "The
Star-Spangled Banner." I'll bet you thought that the song was more than 60
years old -- and it is. But it was officially adopted as our national anthem
by the U.S. Congress and President Herbert Hoover on March 3, 1931.;    The
words were composed during the War of 1812 by a lawyer from Washington, D.C.
named Francis Scott Key, whose involvement in the whole matter was quite
accidental. Key had been persuaded by several friends of a physician named
William Beanes, who had become a prisoner of war, to negotiate with the
British navy for the release of the doctor. For some reason, Dr. Beanes had
been picked up by soldiers off the streets of Washington during a British
assault on the city that had resulted in the burning of the White House, the
Capitol, and other public buildings. He was taken back to the British naval
ships that had blockaded Chesapeake Bay, and it is there that Key went to
obtain his release.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Peninsula Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ILLUMINATING NATIONAL ANTHEM IS KEY TO CHILD'S
UNDERSTANDING  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Also ran in EAST3, EX4/3, WL3
See also related story on this page
Education
Family LearningDr. William F. Russell's latest book for children is Animal
Families of the Wild.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Well, the talks were courteous and an agreement was reached, but there
happened to be other talks under way at the same time, on that same ship, and
these concerned the battle plans for that night's attack on <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> and on
<LOCATION>Fort McHenry</LOCATION>, which guarded the city. The British didn't know how much of
their plans Key and <PERSON>Dr. Beanes</PERSON> had overheard, and so they detained the
Americans until after the battle had commenced.;    From here on the story is,
or should be, rather well known by all American school children. Key was so
taken by the bombardment he witnessed from the deck of the ship that night
(the British lobbed more than 1,800 bombs and rockets into and around the
fort) and he was so stirred upon seeing the American flag still flying over
the fort at daybreak, that he hastily composed several verses of a poem on the
back of a letter or an envelope he found in his pocket.;    That poem, which
appeared shortly thereafter in a <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> newspaper under the title "The
Defense of <LOCATION>Fort McHenry</LOCATION>," became the words for what we know as "The
Star-Spangled Banner." The war in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> has made the playing and
singing of our national anthem more common and frequent than just at the
beginning of sporting events.;    Many children know the words but have little
understanding of what some of those words mean. Parents can help put some of
the meaning and flavor back into this song by telling their children how the
anthem came to be written. (Be sure they see that the event, and the War of
<DATE>1812</DATE>, took place only about forty years after the Revolution, and so our
fledgling nation could easily have come under British rule once again if Fort
<ORGANIZATION>McHenry</ORGANIZATION> had fallen.) Recite the anthem to them like a poem, and translate for
them the following words and phrases:;    The Star-Spangled Banner: "Spangled"
means adorned with shining or glittering objects; sequins, for example, are
spangles.;    What so proudly we hailed: "Hailed" means cheered for or
applauded.;    O'er the ramparts we watched: "O'er" is the one-syllable,
poetic pronunciation of the word "over"; "ramparts" are protective barriers,
in this case the walls of <LOCATION>Fort McHenry.</LOCATION>;    The bombs bursting in air:
Explosives weren't actually dropped from above until <DATE>1849</DATE> (from balloons), and
so this early use of "bombs" refers to mortar shells that were launched over
the walls from the ground.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  William F. Russell column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910227  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  612  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday February 27, 1991
00058267,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06178292 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06178292 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PERSON; LIFESTYLE; OPINION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AS I WRITE this column, I come across interesting slices of life that may not
develop into a full length article, but offer a glimpse into other people's
lives. Here are some of them:  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  The Weekly  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TRUTH OR DARE IN THE TRI-CITIES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     As <PERSON>Madonna</PERSON> became a singing sensation, there were ripple effects in <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>
in the life of <ORGANIZATION>Madonna Pride</ORGANIZATION>. The phone started ringing in the middle of the
night with callers wanting to talk to Madonna.;    When she ordered food by
phone, clerks often thought the call was a prank. A friend of her family who
works at the pizza parlor heard the following conversation.;    "Hey, <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION>
just placed an order," someone yelled in the restaurant after she had ordered
pizza.;    "Yeah, right," another employee quipped back, "and Elvis called up
for pizza, too.";    <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> is the mother of three and a product of
Catholic schools. Sometimes when she says her name and adds that she works as
a bookkeeper for Sisters of the Holy Family, people think she's a nun.;    In
<ORGANIZATION>Price Club</ORGANIZATION> one day, <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> had just finished paying for her items when the
checker waved the check in the air and yelled to another employee: "Hey Bob,
here's another star." The checker was talking to <ORGANIZATION>Price Club</ORGANIZATION> employee, <PERSON>Bob
Wagoner.</PERSON>;    "My daughter and her friends think it's cool that my name is
Madonna," says <ORGANIZATION>Madonna Pride.</ORGANIZATION>;    On her daughters' field trips if anyone gets
out of line, <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> threatens to sing.;    "I think she's
outrageous, unique, a free spirit," says <ORGANIZATION>Madonna Pride</ORGANIZATION> about her more famous
namesake.;    <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> is not the only one whose name gets attention in her
family. She's been married to Rusty Pride for more than 20 years. At a
marriage encounter follow-up years ago, another couple showed up just to see
what a Rusty Pride looked like.;    "It's just kind of fun," <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> says
about their names. "I don't take it too seriously.";     IN A COLUMN a few
weeks ago about <PERSON>Ed Shannon</PERSON>'s son-in-law, who is an underwater photographer and
writer, I couldn't weave in a comment from Ed about his experience traveling
inland after scuba diving off the coast of <LOCATION>New Guinea.</LOCATION>;    In the highlands
where people still live as they did thousands of years ago with painted faces
and using bows and arrows, Ed asked what the older natives had thought of the
fighter planes that flew overhead during World War II.;    The sound signaled
giant bees droning overhead. The natives ran for cover in the jungles.;     IT
WAS THE car that <PERSON>Bob Wheeler</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> courted <PERSON>Diane</PERSON> in before they were
married. During <PERSON>Bob</PERSON>'s military service, the car was resigned to a chicken barn
on a <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION> ranch <PERSON>Diane</PERSON>'s father owned.;    The <DATE>1956</DATE> Chevy that's been babied
and repainted and is in a never-ending process of being restored is headed for
its longest trip yet. Diane and Bob are driving the car across some of the
western states, as it is being passed from one generation to the next.;   
It's a gift from Dad to son, <PERSON>David</PERSON>, a recent graduate of <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young
University</ORGANIZATION>, who adores the car as much as his father does.;    When she
started graduate work in library science, one of her mentors encouraged <PERSON>Lauren
Teixeira</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> to look for vast resources as she studied the Costanoan
Indians.;    She developed a descriptive guide on "Access to Information on
Costanoan/Ohlone Indians of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Monterey Bay Areas</LOCATION>" as her
thesis and assembled a first of its kind resource guide on tribal organization
and the rancherias in <LOCATION>Mendocino County</LOCATION> in a grant project.;    For <PERSON>Lauren</PERSON>, a
five-year journey through school has ended. She finished two years
undergraduate work and three years of graduate studies to earn her master's
degree in library science from <LOCATION>San Jose State University</LOCATION> this month.;    With
the workload of family and her children's schedules, a job and studies
becoming unwieldy at times, she discovered an equally vast resource within
herself, through children's storytelling and writing of poetry.;    "A Lament:
From One Friend (Married with Children) to Another Friend (Single, No
Entanglements)" is one from her poetry collection that working mothers may
relate to:;    I envy you;    your solitude --;    Your house quietly filled; 
  with the color of your creativity;    flowing into every room;    filling
your universe infinitely you . . .;    While I make appointments;    for
solitude;    late at night;    in a sleeping house;    where I find my
creativity;    in sputters and spurts,;    splotches, splashes;    caught
somewhere between;    exhaustion and dreams.;    Since the two Teixeira
children, <PERSON>Zachary</PERSON> and <PERSON>Laural</PERSON>, are used to having a parent attending college,
their dad will finish his degree, starting full-time this month as he holds
down a full-time job.;     A YEAR OR SO ago, I wrote a column about <PERSON>Ray
Gatchalian</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Fire Captain</ORGANIZATION>, who produced the video "Unheard Voices"
that aired on <ORGANIZATION>PBS</ORGANIZATION> about the children of war-ravaged <LOCATION>El Salvador.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Ray</PERSON>, who
can't sit still, is running across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, having left on Flag Day
from the <PERSON>Francis Scott Key Monument</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Golden Gate Park</LOCATION> with 19 other runners
who plan to hit the <PERSON>Francis Scott</PERSON> Key Bridge in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, D. C. on <DATE>July 2</DATE>.
As they run, <PERSON>Ray</PERSON> and the others carry a replica of the 15-star flag that flew
over <LOCATION>Fort McHenry</LOCATION> when it was being bombarded by the British in <DATE>1814</DATE>,
inspiration for <PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> to write the Star Spangled Banner. The run
across <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> is designed to call attention and contribution to a <PERSON>Francis
Scott</PERSON> Key Memorial to be built at the foot of the bridge by <DATE>July 4</DATE>, 1993.;   
When I talked to <PERSON>Ray</PERSON> last, he was in <LOCATION>Vernal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, having run through the
foothills of the Sierra, the high desert of <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> and heading through the
Rockies.;    "The sunsets, the sunrises, the landscape pastels. The horses and
birds. You get to hear everything come up in that golden hour as the sun
spreads its light," says Ray.;    "It's just incredible. When you're running
down the middle of the highway at one and two in the <TIME>morning</TIME>, with the Milky
Way blazing, it gives you an opportunity to think what <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> is about."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Johnna Laird column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Alameda County/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910626  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,027  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday June 26, 1991
00178292,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881017-0254 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-17-88 0835EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Britain-Elders     10-17 0184</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Britain-Elders,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Australian Brewers Elders IXL Bids For British Brewery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Australian brewers <ORGANIZATION>Elders IXL Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> launched a
takeover bid <DATE>Monday</DATE> for Scottish and <ORGANIZATION>Newcastle PLC</ORGANIZATION>, valuing the
British brewer at the equivalent of <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY>.
   Elders, through its <ORGANIZATION>Courage Holdings PLC</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary, is offering
<MONEY>400 pence</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$7</MONEY> a share in cash for the Scottish-based drinks
company best known for its <ORGANIZATION>Newcastle</ORGANIZATION> brown ale.
   The Australian company, which makes the popular Fosters brand
lager, said it already owns <PERCENT>9.65 percent</PERCENT> of Scottish and
<ORGANIZATION>Newcastle</ORGANIZATION>'s share capital.
   Following the announcement, Scottish and <ORGANIZATION>Newcastle</ORGANIZATION> stock shot
above the Elders offer price in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> to <MONEY>426 pence</MONEY> from <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s
closing price of <MONEY>351 pence</MONEY>.
   Elders already owns Courage, one of the best-known names in
British beer, which it bought in <DATE>1986</DATE> for 1.4 billion pounds.
   It also owns <PERCENT>13.5 percent</PERCENT> of <PERSON>Greene King</PERSON>, another British
brewer, and just under <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of the American company
<ORGANIZATION>Anheuser-Busch</ORGANIZATION>, the world's biggest brewer.
   Elders is best known for its beer and lager, but it also has a
financial services company and interests in agriculture and mining.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112890-0029 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 314363 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 28, 1990, Wednesday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 12; Column 4 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
824 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SOUTHERN SECTION BASKETBALL CAPSULES; 
</P>
<P>
SAN FERNANDO VALLEY LEAGUE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Bell-Jeff 
</P>
<P>
COACH: <PERSON>Steve Wahl</PERSON>, 1st season 
</P>
<P>
LAST SEASON: 9-15; 4th in league, 5-5 
</P>
<P>
PLAYERS TO WATCH: <PERSON>Wahl</PERSON> replaces <PERSON>Joe Dunn</PERSON>, who stepped down after 12 seasons in 
<DATE>August</DATE> because of personal reasons. Three junior starters, swingman <PERSON>Brian Lee</PERSON> 
(6-foot-3), point guard <PERSON>Bryon Camacho</PERSON> (5-7) and guard <PERSON>Ignacio Castro</PERSON> (6-0) 
return. Wahl calls Lee the top all-around player. "He can play forward, guard 
or center and score and rebound," <PERSON>Wahl</PERSON> said. Camacho averaged 11.6 points a 
game last season and is the catalyst for an offense that will play an up-tempo 
game. "He makes everything go," said <PERSON>Wahl</PERSON>, who also coaches the boys' and 
girls' tennis teams. "We have good team speed and we want to take advantage of 
it." Two juniors, forward <PERSON>Damien Scott</PERSON> (6-2) and center <PERSON>Joe Bunning</PERSON> (6-5), 
round out the starting lineup. Scott and <PERSON>Bunning</PERSON> will be the dominant forces 
under the boards. 
</P>
<P>
OUTLOOK: The team, which did not participate in <DATE>summer</DATE> league because of <ORGANIZATION>Wahl</ORGANIZATION>'s 
late hiring, has eight underclassmen on its 12-man roster. "It's been difficult 
just trying to get it going with a new philosophy, but I think we'll come 
around once they catch on," <PERSON>Wahl</PERSON> said. Wahl believes <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>St. Francis</PERSON> 
and possibly <LOCATION>El Segundo</LOCATION> could contend for the league championship, but he 
believes that <PERSON>Bell-Jeff</PERSON> should finish no lower than third. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Harvard 
</P>
<P>
COACH: <PERSON>Greg Hilliard</PERSON>, 6th season 
</P>
<P>
LAST SEASON: 23-3; 1st in league, 10-0 
</P>
<P>
PLAYERS TO WATCH: Seven players return from last season's <LOCATION>San Fernando Valley 
League</LOCATION> championship team, which advanced to the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Section 3-A Division</ORGANIZATION> 
semifinals. Forward Andres Carlo (6-4) and center <PERSON>Spencer Miller</PERSON> (6-8), both 
seniors, are returning starters. Carlo played in all 26 games, averaging 10 
points, 8.8 rebounds, 2.8 steals and 1.5 blocks. Carlo and <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> should be 
strong inside forces, but <PERSON>Hilliard</PERSON> said that <PERSON>Carlo</PERSON> also is an effective outside 
threat. Iheanyi Uwaezouke (6-2), a Division I football prospect, and <PERSON>Marcus 
Puhvel</PERSON> (6-5) received significant playing time as juniors. Newcomer <PERSON>Tarlin Ray</PERSON> 
(6-2), a junior point guard, rounds out the starting five. <PERSON>Hilliard</PERSON> said that 
Puhvel probably is the best outside shooter and that <PERSON>Uwaezouke</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ray</PERSON> are the 
best ballhandlers. Harvard averaged more than 85 points a game last season and 
<PERSON>Hilliard</PERSON> thinks this year's team can duplicate that effort. "We're definitely a 
running team with a full-pressure defense," <PERSON>Hilliard</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
OUTLOOK: "Our strength is our conditioning and we have good athletes that have 
yet to be proven," said <PERSON>Hilliard</PERSON>, who has guided <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> to two league titles 
and four playoff berths in five seasons. "Last year's team was tight and 
cohesive and how well we come together will be the determining factor." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
St. <PERSON>Francis</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
COACH: <PERSON>John Jordan</PERSON>, 4th season 
</P>
<P>
LAST SEASON: 7-15; 5th in league, 2-6 
</P>
<P>
PLAYERS TO WATCH: <PERSON>Kyle Barrett</PERSON> (6-3), <PERSON>Dave Landa</PERSON> (5-3) and <PERSON>Marty Konrad</PERSON> (6-3) 
return and are expected to play key roles. Barrett is the Golden Knights' main 
offensive threat and averaged 16.4 points last season. Landa, who averaged 
eight points and 5.1 assists, will play point guard. Konrad averaged seven 
rebounds last season. Junior Tory <PERSON>Carruthers</PERSON> (6-3) also will start. Four 
sophomores and two juniors with no varsity experience round out the team. 
"Hopefully, we can build around (<ORGANIZATION>Barrett</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Landa</PERSON> and Konrad) and find some other 
kids to help them out," <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
OUTLOOK: <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> believes that the basketball team will benefit from the move 
from the <ORGANIZATION>Del Rey League</ORGANIZATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>San Fernando Valley League</ORGANIZATION> in the same manner as 
the football team, which improved from 1-9 to 7-4. But <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> is unsure of what 
to expect. "I have no idea what we'll do," <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> said. "We're so young. I'm 
not sure what kind of character this team is going to have." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
St. Genevieve 
</P>
<P>
COACH: <PERSON>Scott Smith</PERSON>, 3rd season 
</P>
<P>
LAST SEASON: 2-20; 6th in league, 0-10 
</P>
<P>
PLAYERS TO WATCH: Senior guards Jeff De La O (5-9) and <PERSON>Josh Smith</PERSON> (5-10) 
started last season and are among seven returning players. De La O, who 
averaged 10 points, will be relied upon for his offensive output. Smith will be 
the primary ballhandler. Junior center <PERSON>Pat Rodriguez</PERSON> (6-2) and junior <PERSON>John 
Hoffmann</PERSON> (6-2) and senior <PERSON>Victor Dionisio</PERSON> (5-11), both forwards, also will 
start. <PERSON>Pete Miranda</PERSON> (5-10), <PERSON>Dominic Parero</PERSON> (5-9) and <PERSON>Mike Robinson</PERSON> (6-1), a 
transfer from <LOCATION>Crespi</LOCATION>, also will be given extensive playing time. "We don't have 
any size so everybody is going to have to crash the boards," <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said. "Once 
we get the ball, we'll be all right." <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> says quickness is the team's most 
valuable asset and that he will utilize a motion offense. "We'll set screens 
and try to roll out of them." 
</P>
<P>
OUTLOOK: <ORGANIZATION>St. Genevieve</ORGANIZATION> should be improved, but <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> believes the league, in 
particular <PERSON>St. Francis</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Harvard</LOCATION>, is very strong. "It was a long season and 
we didn't get any wins (last year)," <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said, "but we have only one way to 
go. We don't have any outstanding individual, but we work well as a team." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
List 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890630-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-30-89 1539EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     06-30 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0468</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GRAND RAPIDS, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Paul Kidwell</PERSON> would like to see <PERSON>Manfred
Mann</PERSON> replace <PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> as the man associated with the
national anthem.
   <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON> has formed a group to promote replacing ``The
Star-Spangled Banner'' with ``Do <PERSON>Wah Diddy</PERSON>.''
   ``It's just one of my favorite songs. It was a real hard choice
between that and another of my favorites, `Mack the Knife,''' said
<PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON>, founder and self-appointed president of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, Change the
Anthem Now _ America CAN.
   <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON> said the only good rendition he has ever heard of the
anthem was by <PERSON>Marvin Gaye</PERSON> at a basketball game.
   ``I don't like the song,'' <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON> said of the notoriously
hard-to-sing anthem. ``It's stodgy, staid, not easy to dance to and,
frankly, may be the worst song ever written. I'd give it about a
35.''
   <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON>, who works for a subliminal tapes manufacturer in <LOCATION>Grand
Rapids</LOCATION>, said he doesn't expect his suggestion to survive. ``After
all, the other piece has been around, what, 200 years? But that
doesn't mean I have to like the song,'' he said.
   ``Do <PERSON>Wah Diddy</PERSON>,'' made famous by <PERSON>Mann</PERSON> in <DATE>1964</DATE>, ``embodies the
American dream. You know, boy meets girl, boy falls in love with
girl, boy gets girl,'' <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON> said.
   ``Besides, we need something upbeat.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Paul Kidwell</PERSON> would like to see <PERSON>Manfred
Mann</PERSON> replace <PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> as the man associated with the
national anthem.
   <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON> has formed a group to promote replacing ``The
Star-Spangled Banner'' with ``Do <PERSON>Wah Diddy</PERSON>.''
   ``It's just one of my favorite songs. It was a real hard choice
between that and another of my favorites, `Mack the Knife,''' said
<PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON>, founder and self-appointed president of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, Change the
Anthem Now _ America CAN.
   <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON> said the only good rendition he has ever heard of the
anthem was by <PERSON>Marvin Gaye</PERSON> at a basketball game.
   ``I don't like the song,'' <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON> said of the notoriously
hard-to-sing anthem. ``It's stodgy, staid, not easy to dance to and,
frankly, may be the worst song ever written. I'd give it about a
35.''
   <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON>, who works for a subliminal tapes manufacturer in <LOCATION>Grand
Rapids</LOCATION>, said he doesn't expect his suggestion to survive. ``After
all, the other piece has been around, what, 200 years? But that
doesn't mean I have to like the song,'' he said.
   ``Do <PERSON>Wah Diddy</PERSON>,'' made famous by <PERSON>Mann</PERSON> in <DATE>1964</DATE>, ``embodies the
American dream. You know, boy meets girl, boy falls in love with
girl, boy gets girl,'' <PERSON>Kidwell</PERSON> said.
   ``Besides, we need something upbeat.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA040190-0167 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 198094 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 1, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 10; Column 4; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
680 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AUGMON ACCOMPLISHES TASK: RENDERING WEAPON HARMLESS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHRIS BAKER, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
DENVER 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Forward <PERSON>Stacey Augmon</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nevada Las Vegas</LOCATION> is always assigned to check the 
toughest opposing player. When <ORGANIZATION>UNLV</ORGANIZATION> faced <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> in an <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> tournament 
semifinal game <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, he was assigned to <PERSON>Dennis Scott</PERSON>, the top gun in 
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION>'s Lethal Weapon 3 offense. 
</P>
<P>
"It was a big challenge," <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> said. "I knew he was looking forward to 
playing against me and he took the challenge and came out launching. I couldn't 
stop him in the first half." 
</P>
<P>
Scott scored 20 points in the first 20 minutes as <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> took a 53-46 
lead. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> limited <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> to nine points in the second half as the Rebels won, 
90-81, to advance to the <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> championship game <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> against <ORGANIZATION>Duke</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Stacey played great defense in the <DATE>second half</DATE>," guard <PERSON>Anderson Hunt</PERSON> said. "He 
knew what he had to do." 
</P>
<P>
What <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> had to do was play more aggressively against <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
After making five of eight shots in the first half, including four three-point 
shots, <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> didn't touch the ball in the <DATE>first five minutes of the second half</DATE> 
because of <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON>. "He played great defense on me the <DATE>second half</DATE>," <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> said. 
"He denied me the ball. I think the whole Vegas team was denying us the ball 
and it got us out of our offense." 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> did a good job on <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> in the <DATE>second half</DATE>, he thought he could 
have done a better job in the first half. 
</P>
<P>
"Scott's a great player," <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> said. "You can't take anything from him. He 
still got 29. The thing I tried to do was hold him to the lowest possible 
points. I can't go out and stop anyone. Great players are going to hit shots on 
anyone." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Tarkanian</PERSON> thought <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> was being too modest. 
</P>
<P>
"In all fairness to <LOCATION>Stacey</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> got quite a few of his points when we were in 
our zone," <PERSON>Tarkanian</PERSON> said. "It seemed like every time we went to a zone he hit 
a three-pointer and made us pay for it. I don't know how many he got directly 
off Stacey, but I'm sure half of them came off our zone." 
</P>
<P>
As the Rebels' best defensive player, <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> said he takes more pride in his 
defense than his offense. And he has shut down some of the nation's best 
offensive players, such as <ORGANIZATION>Temple</ORGANIZATION> guard <PERSON>Mark Macon</PERSON>, who had 11 points before 
fouling out in a loss to <ORGANIZATION>UNLV</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Although <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> Coach <PERSON>Bobby Cremins</PERSON> praised the aggressive defense <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> 
played on <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>, he felt <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> stopped himself in the second half. 
</P>
<P>
"I knew <PERSON>Stacey</PERSON> couldn't stop <PERSON>Dennis Scott</PERSON> overall," <PERSON>Cremins</PERSON> said. "He's a heck 
of a defender, but no one can stop <PERSON>Dennis Scott</PERSON>. The only one who can stop 
<PERSON>Dennis Scott</PERSON> is <PERSON>Dennis Scott</PERSON>. But <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> is a good athlete." 
</P>
<P>
After opening the game in a zone defense, <ORGANIZATION>UNLV</ORGANIZATION> switched to a man-to-man defense 
at the start of the second half. The defense seemed to confuse <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION>, 
which shot <PERCENT>66.7%</PERCENT> in the first half. The Yellow Jackets shot just <PERCENT>34.5%</PERCENT> in the 
second half. 
</P>
<P>
"I thought the second half we played really well defensively," <PERSON>Tarkanian</PERSON> said. 
"We got after it real good and we shut down a lot of things. The first half we 
didn't play with the intensity we wanted." 
</P>
<P>
The Rebels opened the second half with a 17-4 run as <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> scored five points. 
While <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> is recognized for his defense, he also is a good offensive player 
as he proved last <DATE>Sunday</DATE> by scoring 33 points against <ORGANIZATION>Loyola Marymount</ORGANIZATION> and 
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> with 22 against <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I take more pride in my defense than my offense," <PERSON>Augmon</PERSON> said. "A lot of 
people say I should take more pride in my offense because it will take me 
farther in life. 
</P>
<P>
"But my role on this team is as the defensive stopper and to put a little 
points on the board and that's what I did. I enjoy playing defense." 
</P>
<P>
While <ORGANIZATION>UNLV</ORGANIZATION>'s defense might have been the key, the Rebels' perimeter offense 
came to the fore after <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> made a run late in the game. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION>'s sagging defense took away <ORGANIZATION>UNLV</ORGANIZATION>'s inside game as forward <PERSON>Larry 
Johnson</PERSON> got into foul trouble. But the Rebels picked up their outside game, 
making 10 of 15 three-point shots. 
</P>
<P>
Hunt, who had 20 points, broke out of a slump by making five of nine 
three-point shots and <PERSON>Greg Anthony</PERSON> made three of four and scored 14 points. 
</P>
<P>
Company: Penalty 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY; UNIVERSITY OF NEVADA AT LAS VEGAS; BASKETBALL PLAYERS; 
DUKE UNIVERSITY; BASKETBALL CHAMPIONSHIPS; AUGMON, STACEY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-14078</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJYD1ADJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941025
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 OCT 94 / Arts: Celebration gives food for thought - William Packer
visits Paris for two exhibitions with very different views on British
painting
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By WILLIAM PACKER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
D'outre-Manche, not quite 'Across', as we have it, but 'Beyond the Channel',
with its faint hint at a somewhat greater psychological barrier, is a
fascinating and even shocking exhibition.
Here is no full and scholarly study of its subject and period - British art
up to the time of Queen <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON> - drawn from the wealth of French public
taste and connoisseurship. But, rather, a parade of historic French
attitudes and assumptions upon the art of our fog-shrouded and barbarous
land, that amounts to a confession.
If that wealth is not drawn upon, it is because that wealth is not there.
The French have never bothered to acquire the art of the British school  -
the distinction between the English, the Irish and the Scots is seldom made,
and ecole Anglais usually stands for all - in any substantial or
comprehensive fashion, for they have never taken our visual culture
seriously. And what they do not take seriously, they do not choose to
understand.
The contrast between our own <ORGANIZATION>National Gallery</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION> in generosity
of interest and critical even-handedness, could hardly be greater.
In <ORGANIZATION>Trafalgar Square</ORGANIZATION> we find an account of the post-Renaissance European
tradition that gives each national school its due, the French along with the
Italian, the Spanish, the Dutch and, yes, the British. What gaps there are,
as in the German and northern schools, they are admitted and, as far as
limited resources allow, addressed.
Never so, it would seem, along the quai du <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION>. 'How did I find the
show?' asked my friend in the <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION>'s service presse, a little anxiously,
and gave at once her own pre-emptive answer: 'il y a beaucoup des trous.'
The show does contain some lovely things, with the magnificent <PERSON>Gainsborough</PERSON>
full-length of Lady <PERSON>Alston</PERSON>, green silk and grey shawl against a darkly
romantic setting, the best of all.
There are some good <PERSON>Reynolds</PERSON>, a decent <PERSON>Stubbs</PERSON> of <PERSON>Lord Curzon</PERSON> and his horse,
the splendid 'Captain Hay of Spott' by <PERSON>Raeburn</PERSON> and any number of <LOCATION>Lawrences</LOCATION> -
<PERSON>Lawrence</PERSON> after all was the painter of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s grandees in the
post-Napoleonic dispensation and was for a generation the best-known English
painter of them all.
But we know, and at heart the French know, that there is more to the British
School than the brief flourish of the late-Georgian swagger portrait.
So where do we begin? Neither with <PERSON>Holbein</PERSON> nor yet with <PERSON>Van Dyck</PERSON>, for they
are foreigners, so a fine full-length of <ORGANIZATION>Edward VI</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>William Scrots</PERSON>, a
Dutchman, will do.
What then of the Elizabethan miniaturists, <PERSON>Hilliard</PERSON> perhaps? But there is,
it seems, no <PERSON>Hilliard</PERSON> in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, and a single, exquisite portrait of the
fated <ORGANIZATION>Earl of Essex</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Isaac Oliver</PERSON>, a Frenchman, must do. Into the <DATE>17th
century</DATE> we go, and to the Cavaliers and the Restoration, so with no <ORGANIZATION>Van
Dyck</ORGANIZATION>, what about <PERSON>Dobson</PERSON>? No <PERSON>Dobson</PERSON>, but a little later there is Lely. Wasn't
he a foreigner, too?
Never mind. The <DATE>18th century</DATE> will sort things out. <PERSON>Philippe Mercier</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Heinrich Fussli</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Fuseli</ORGANIZATION> to us) are in, I see. Odd that. But we shall really
get going with <PERSON>Hogarth</PERSON>, shan't we, surely the first great painter of the
truly English school. Shan't we?
But the French, we find, have this funny idea that <PERSON>Hogarth</PERSON> wasn't really a
painter at all, but an engraver - and indeed this show reveals the curious
fixed idea that it was in the general commercial development of print-making
that our peculiarly English talents were declared.
So there is not a single <PERSON>Hogarth</PERSON> painting in the show, but only the engraved
version of the 'Marriage a la Mode'. <PERSON>Thomas Girtin</PERSON> is represented by a
single acquatint of the 'Porte Saint <PERSON>Denis</PERSON>', <PERSON>Rowlandson</PERSON> by three satirical
etchings among a group by <PERSON>Gillray</PERSON> and <PERSON>Cruikshank</PERSON>. That group is at least
included, bitterly anti-French as its satires are.
What else? A few good water-colours by <LOCATION>Bonington</LOCATION>, Constable, Boys and Cox,
miscellaneous drawings, some good oils including a Bonington 'Doges'
Palace', Constable's '<LOCATION>Weymouth Bay</LOCATION>' and '<ORGANIZATION>Helmingham Dell</ORGANIZATION>', and a late
unfinished Turner landscape, vaporous and magical.
And that, of any substance, is it. This is, indeed, a show which gives us
rather more to think about than actually to see.
The smaller show at the <ORGANIZATION>Musee Carnavalet</ORGANIZATION> is a wonderful corrective, if only
because the prejudice is openly celebrated in terms that are often as hugely
enjoyable as they are grotesque.
A run of post-Napoleonic jokes about French girls finding any excuse to peer
up the kilts of Scottish soldiers gets us off to a good start and there is
no looking back, or down.
Randy rost-bifs and their prim, boot-faced wives on the one hand, seductive
girls and effete 'frogs' on the other, the ancient mutual stereotypes are
funny still.
But jokes apart, the show does make the serious point that the English love
affair with <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> had its cultural aspect, and bore real fruit in the work
of our tourist painters. Thus represented here are not only the better-known
figures of <ORGANIZATION>Turner</ORGANIZATION>, Cox, <LOCATION>Bonington</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Girtin</PERSON> and Boys, but also such
comparatively minor, but still accomplished, artists as <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Wyld</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Callow</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chalon</LOCATION> . . . and we think on to <LOCATION>Whistler</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sickert</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Nicholson</PERSON> . . .
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> to us, and <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> above all, has always been irresistible.
D'outre-Manche - British art in French public collections: Musee du <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> 1e, until <DATE>December 19</DATE>. Les Anglais a <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> au 19e siecle: <ORGANIZATION>Musee
Carnavalet</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> 4e, until <DATE>December 11</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>FRZ  France, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8412 Museums and Art Galleries.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06061147 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06061147 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  OBITUARY; FRANCE; FASHION; DESIGN; PROFESSIONAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Ken Scott, a fashion designer known for his fabric designs and for developing
fashion shows, died Tuesday at his home in Eze, France. He was 72.;    He died
of lymphatic cancer, a family spokesman said.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  KEN SCOTT, 72, EUROPEAN FASHION DESIGNER  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Obituaries  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Mr. Scott</PERSON>, who was born in <LOCATION>Fort Wayne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>, had his boutique in <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, and in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and early '70s was one of the best-known designers in
that country.;    He had a flair with fabrics, and his flowered print suits
for both men and women were often the rage.;    At times, some of his typical
color schemes included dresses in lemon yellow, pumpkin, hot pink and pepper
green or mauve, purple, chalk white, electric pink and black.;    At other
times, his models swirled down the runways wearing flower-print jersey in
every shade of pink imaginable, from begonia, bougainvillea and poinsettia to
lobster, raspberry, strawberry and watermelon. He also inspired flowered
turtlenecks with velvet dinner suits.;    "<PERSON>Ken</PERSON> was doing psychedelic colorings
before anyone even knew what psychedelic was all about," a <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> fashion
illustrator said in a <DATE>1968</DATE> interview in <ORGANIZATION>Time magazine</ORGANIZATION>. "Nobody dares to put
color next to color the way he does.";    <PERSON>Mr. Scott</PERSON> later showed
leopard-printed suits for men and women, and went on to design footwear to go
with some of his creations. His fabrics also became wall coverings and bed
furnishings.;    <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> graduated from the <ORGANIZATION>Parsons School of Design</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> in <DATE>1941</DATE> and worked as a upholsterer and fabric designer before
moving to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE> to be an artist.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910301  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  11B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  256  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday March 1, 1991
00061147,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890720-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-07-20-89 2134EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e AM-APArts:BadHemingway     07-20 0859</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AP Arts: Bad Hemingway,0879</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parodying Hemingway in All Ernest-Ness</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Stands as a 1st Ld-Writethru to b0436, to CORRECT Hemingway's
birthday to July 21 sted July 28. Story is now released for spot use.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GENEVA COLLINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If <PERSON>Ernest Hemingway</PERSON> _ that aficionado of big
guns, feisty bulls, lusty reds and really short sentences _ were
alive today, the pugnacious Papa would be spoiling for a fight.
   The object of his disaffection would be ``The Best of Bad
Hemingway'' (<ORGANIZATION>Harcourt Brace Jovanovich</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$7.95</MONEY>), a compilation of
the best entries to a now-defunct annual competition of Hemingway
parodies. The ersatz <PERSON>Ernest</PERSON> contest was sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>Harry's Bar &amp;
American Grill</ORGANIZATION>, whose ingenious milking of an extremely tenuous
<PERSON>Hemingway</PERSON> connection deserves induction into the Publicists' <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>
of Fame.
   Hemingway, who would have been 90 on <DATE>July 21</DATE>, was no stranger to
parody. His second novel, ``The Torrents of <DATE>Spring</DATE>,'' was a cruel
mimickry of <PERSON>Sherwood Anderson</PERSON>, an early mentor <PERSON>Hemingway</PERSON> thought
was washed up. But when his own prose became well enough known to
be parodied, <PERSON>Hemingway</PERSON> was hardly a sport.
   ``The parody is the last refuge of the frustrated writer,'' he
said after <PERSON>E.B. White</PERSON> spoofed him with a piece called ``Across the
Street and Into the Grill.'' ``The greater the work of literature,
the easier the parody. The step up from writing parodies is writing
on the wall above the urinal.''
   All of the Ernie-wannabees in this collection are long on puns
and short on commas. Among the titles: ``The Snooze of
Kilimanjaro,'' ``In Another Contra,'' ``Hills Like White
Heffalumps,'' ``The Old Man and the Seal,'' ``A Clean Well-Sighted
Ace,'' ``A Lean Well-Tighted Space'' and ``A Clean Well-Lighted
Race.''
   When author <PERSON>George Plimpton</PERSON>, who wrote the introduction to the
book, was asked in a recent interview to select a favorite entry,
he mentioned <PERSON>Daniel Hardy</PERSON>'s ``The Last Good Martini,'' which
mangles more than a half-dozen <PERSON>Hemingway</PERSON> titles in its few short
paragraphs:
   ```Do you want to order dinner?' said <PERSON>Nick</PERSON>. `They still serve
the big two-parted liver.'''
   And later: ```Do you remember <PERSON>George Tell</PERSON>?'
   ```Yes,' said <PERSON>Francis</PERSON>. `He was a swell bowler. For whom does
Tell bowl now?'''
   Plimpton also mentioned the parody by <PERSON>Lee Ewing</PERSON>, ``The Question
Hung in the Air'':
   ``He knew what they must do on this day. It was a month with no
R.
   ```Come,' he said. `It is the day of the running of the
oysters.'''
   Plimpton explains in his introduction that the parody contest
was dreamed up in <DATE>1978</DATE> by an advertising man named <PERSON>Paul Keye</PERSON> for
<ORGANIZATION>Harry's Bar &amp; American Grill</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Century City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Beverly
Hills</LOCATION>.
   The American <PERSON>Harry</PERSON>'s was a replica of <ORGANIZATION>Harry</ORGANIZATION>'s Bar in <LOCATION>Florence</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>. Keye knew <PERSON>Hemingway</PERSON> never went to the <LOCATION>Harry</LOCATION>'s in <LOCATION>Florence</LOCATION>
but was a devotee of the original <PERSON>Harry</PERSON>'s Bar in <LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION> and often
featured it in his stories.
   His copy promoting the competition warned contestants that they
would have to face ``The White Bull That Is Paper With No Words on
It.'' All entries had to be limited to one type-written page and
had to mention <PERSON>Harry</PERSON>'s Bar _ favorably. The winner was flown to
<LOCATION>Florence</LOCATION> for dinner at the other <LOCATION>Harry</LOCATION>'s (lodging was not included).
   The thousands of entries that poured in took the contest
organizers by surprise, and the contest grew bigger every year,
with celebrity judges such as <LOCATION>Plimpton</LOCATION>, novelist <PERSON>Joseph Wambaugh</PERSON>,
science fiction writer <PERSON>Ray Bradbury</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jack Hemingway</PERSON>, the
author's son. Television crews gathered for the reading of the
winning entry. Harry's decided to end the competition after a
decade because it was devoting more time to running it than its
restaurants.
   <PERSON>Plimpton</PERSON> was asked what he looked for when he judged the entries.
   ``It has to be funny; it has to echo the style of author. I
think the skill in copying the primary source would be utmust, then
the imagination in developing the idea,'' he said by telephone from
his office at the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> Review, of which he is editor.
   In later years the entries were pre-screened and the judges read
only the best entries.
   ``The Best of Bad Hemingway'' is rounded out by spoofs of the
author by well-known writers, including <PERSON>F. Scott Fitzgerald</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Raymond Chandler</PERSON> and <PERSON>Plimpton</PERSON> himself, whose ``The Snows of
Studiofiftyfour'' is a skillful mutation of <ORGANIZATION>Hemingway</ORGANIZATION>'s writing
style and a Truman Capote-esque sensibility.
   <PERSON>Gary Piepenbrink</PERSON>, who edited the collection for <PERSON>Harcourt Brace
Jovanovich</PERSON>, said he thought the book was fairly evenly divided
between those who parodied <PERSON>Hemingway</PERSON> because they loved him and
those who did it because they reviled him.
   Hemingway, who was awarded the Nobel Prize in literature in
<DATE>1954</DATE>, put a shotgun in his mouth and committed suicide in <DATE>1961</DATE>.
   ``He's a literary force that everyone will have reckoned with
somehow,'' said <PERSON>Piepenbrink</PERSON> in a telephone interview from his <LOCATION>San
Diego</LOCATION> office. ``His stature is not to be challenged. His place is
secure in modern literature.
   ``I don't think the collection diminishes <PERSON>Hemingway</PERSON>,'' said
<PERSON>Piepenbrink</PERSON>, who reveres the author. ``Some of the parodies are
pretty cruel, but he can take it. A lesser writer couldn't endure
all these punches.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880509-0156 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-09-88 1849EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TonyNominations 1stLd-Writethru a0714 05-09 0778</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tony Nominations, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0714,0789</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Phantom,' `Anything Goes,' `Into the Woods' Lead Tony Nominations</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf ``Glenda Jackson's'' to CORRECT roles to
Blanche Du Bois and Stella Kowalski, sted Blanche and Stella Du
Bois</NOTE>
<HEAD>Laserphoto NY36</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL KUCHWARA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Drama Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``The Phantom of the Opera,'' ``Anything Goes''
and ``Into the <PERSON>Woods</PERSON>,'' three big musicals, dominated the <DATE>1988</DATE> Tony
award nominations <DATE>Monday</DATE> as each show garnered 10 nominations.
   <PERSON>Andrew Lloyd Webber</PERSON>'s ``Phantom,'' the story of a deformed
composer and his love for a young soprano, and ``Into the <PERSON>Woods</PERSON>,''
a reworking of several fairy tales by <PERSON>Stephen Sondheim</PERSON> and <PERSON>James
Lapine</PERSON>, will compete for best musical of the 1987-88 Broadway
season against ``Sarafina!'' a South African show about township
high school students, and ``Romance-Romance,'' two one-act musicals
about love.
   The same four musicals were also nominated for best score.
   ``M. Butterfly,'' the story of a love affair between a French
naval officer and a star of the <LOCATION>Beijing Opera</LOCATION>, topped the
non-musical categories with seven nominations.
   It will compete for best play against ``<PERSON>Joe Turner</PERSON>'s Come and
Gone,'' <PERSON>August Wilson</PERSON>'s drama about the grandchildren of slaves
coming to terms with the past; <PERSON>David Mamet</PERSON>'s ``Speed-the-Plow,'' a
Hollywood morality tale of two movie producers; and ``A Walk in the
Woods'' by <PERSON>Lee Blessing</PERSON>, a two-character play about American and
Soviet arms control negotiators in <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Derek Jacobi</PERSON>, who played the brilliant British mathematican <PERSON>Alan
Turing</PERSON> in ``Breaking the Code,'' was nominated for best actor in a
play. His competition: <PERSON>John Lithgow</PERSON>, of ``M. Butterfly''; <PERSON>Robert
Prosky</PERSON>, the Soviet diplomat in ``A Walk in the <LOCATION>Woods</LOCATION>''; and <PERSON>Ron
Silver</PERSON>, a sleazy Hollywood producer in ``Speed-the-Plow.''
   <PERSON>Glenda Jackson</PERSON>'s portrayal of Lady Macbeth captured a best
actress nomination. She will compete against <PERSON>Joan Allen</PERSON>, a tortured
dancer in <PERSON>Lanford Wilson</PERSON>'s ``Burn This,'' and <PERSON>Blythe Danner</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Frances McDormand</PERSON>, who played <ORGANIZATION>Blanche Du Bois</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Stella Kowalski</PERSON>
in a revival of <ORGANIZATION>Tennessee Williams</ORGANIZATION>' ``A Streetcar Named Desire.''
   <PERSON>Patti LuPone</PERSON>, the ebullient <PERSON>Reno Sweeney</PERSON> in the revival of
``Anything Goes'' was nominated for best actress in a musical. Her
competition: <PERSON>Joanna Gleason</PERSON>, the practical baker's wife of ``Into
the Woods''; <PERSON>Judy Kuhn</PERSON>, the love interest in ``Chess''; and <PERSON>Alison
Fraser</PERSON> of ``Romance-Romance.''
   <PERSON>Michael Crawford</PERSON>, the title character in ``The Phantom of the
Opera,'' was the favorite to win the award for best actor in a
musical. He faces <PERSON>Scott Bakula</PERSON> of ``Romance-Romance''; <PERSON>David
Carroll</PERSON>, the Russian grandmaster in ``Chess''; and <PERSON>Howard McGillin</PERSON>,
an ambitious young stockbroker in <PERSON>Cole Porter</PERSON>'s ``Anything Goes.''
   For the first time in years, more than enough nominees filled
the many categories. Among the people snubbed by the Tony
nominating committee were: <PERSON>Sarah Brightman</PERSON>, the leading lady of
``The Phantom of Opera'' and <PERSON>Lloyd Webber</PERSON>'s wife; pop star <PERSON>Madonna</PERSON>,
making her Broadway debut in <PERSON>Mamet</PERSON>'s ``Speed-the-Plow''; <PERSON>John
Malkovich</PERSON>, the star of ``Burn This,'' which also was ignored;
<PERSON>Bernadette Peters</PERSON> of ``Into the Woods''; <PERSON>Christopher Plummer</PERSON> who
played the title role in ``Macbeth''; and <PERSON>Trevor Nunn</PERSON> who directed
``Chess'' and was last year's big Tony winner with ``Les
Miserables.''
   Besides ``Anything Goes,'' nominated for best revival were ``A
Streetcar Named Desire,'' ``Dreamgirls'' and ``Cabaret.''
   Three performers in ``Cabaret'' _ opera singer <PERSON>Regina Resnik</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Alyson Reed</PERSON> and <PERSON>Werner Klemperer</PERSON>, best known from TV's ``Hogan's
Heroes'' _ received nominations for featured actress and actor in a
musical.
   The other nominees for featured actress in a musical were <PERSON>Judy
Kaye</PERSON> of ``The Phantom of the Opera'' and <PERSON>Leleti Khumalo</PERSON> of
``Sarafina!'' Klemperer faces <PERSON>Robert Westenberg</PERSON> of ``Into the
Woods'' and two actors from ``Anything Goes,'' <PERSON>Bill McCutcheon</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Anthony Heald</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Harold Prince</PERSON>, the director of ``The Phantom of the Opera,'' was
the top contender for best director of a musical. His competition
is <PERSON>Jerry Zaks</PERSON>, ``Anything Goes''; <PERSON>James Lapine</PERSON>, ``Into the Woods'';
and <PERSON>Mbongeni Ngema</PERSON>, ``Sarafina!''
   The battle for best director of a play pits <PERSON>John Dexter</PERSON>, ``M.
Butterfly''; <PERSON>Gregory Mosher</PERSON>, ``Speed-the-Plow''; <PERSON>Lloyd Richards</PERSON> for
``<PERSON>Joe Turner</PERSON>'s Come and Gone'' and <PERSON>Clifford Williams</PERSON>, ``Breaking
the Code.''
   ``<PERSON>Joe Turner</PERSON>'s Come and Gone'' picked up three featured actress
nominations, for <PERSON>Kimberleigh Aarn</PERSON>, <PERSON>L. Scott Caldwell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kimberly
Scott</PERSON>. Also nominated was <PERSON>Kate Nelligan</PERSON> in the scathing British
satire ``Serious Money.''
   ``<PERSON>Joe Turner</PERSON>'' got one nomination for featured actor in a play _
<ORGANIZATION>Delroy Lindo</ORGANIZATION>. The other nominees are <PERSON>Michael Gough</PERSON>, ``Breaking the
Code''; <PERSON>Lou Liberatore</PERSON>, ``Burn This''; and <PERSON>B.D. Wong</PERSON> of ``M.
Butterfly.''
   The winners, selected by some 730 members connected to the
theatrical industry, will be announced <DATE>June 5</DATE> in a nationally
televised show on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>. The Tonys are named for actress-director
<PERSON>Antoinette Perry</PERSON>, who was active in the <ORGANIZATION>American Theater Wing</ORGANIZATION>
during the <DATE>1940s</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06058299 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06058299 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  US; MUSIC; CHILDREN; FAMILY; LEARNING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Some people believe the words to our national anthem are too obscure and too
militaristic; perhaps they should be grateful that only the first verse of
Francis Scott Key's poem is ever sung. Here are the other three verses. Just
for fun, try singing them to the tune we have come to know as "The
Star-Spangled Banner.";    The verses below were copied from the Encyclopedia
Americana and corroborated in a wonderful new collection called The American
Reader: Words That Moved a Nation (Harper/Collins, 1990).  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Peninsula Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TRY THESE WORDS FOR TUNEFUL BLISS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related story on this page  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  On the shore, dimly seen through the mists of the deep,;    Where the foe's
haughty host in dread silence reposes,;    What is that which the breeze, o'er
the towering steep,;    As it fitfully blows, half conceals, half discloses?; 
  Now it catches the gleam of the morning's first beam,;    In full glory
reflected, now shines on the stream.;    'Tis the star-spangled banner -- O
And where is that band who so vauntingly swore,;    That the havoc of war and
the battle's confusion;    A home and a country should leave us no more?;   
Their blood has washed out their foul footsteps' pollution.;    No refuge
could save the hireling and slave;    From the terror of flight or the gloom
of the grave,;    And the star-spangled banner in triumph doth wave;    O'er
freemen shall stand;    Between their loved home and the war's desolation!;   
<ORGANIZATION>Blest</ORGANIZATION> with victory and peace, may the heav'n-rescued land;    Praise the power
that hath made and preserved us a nation!;    Then conquer we must, when our
cause it is just,;    And this be our motto -- "In God is our trust!" And the
star-spangled banner in triumph shall wave;    O'er the land of the free and
the home of the brave!  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910227  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  327  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday February 27, 1991
00058299,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061589-0072 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 70362 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 15, 1989, Thursday, South Bay Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 20; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1230 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PREP NOTES / ROB FERNAS: BISHOP MONTGOMERY LOSES 11 PLAYERS -- BUT NOT SPIRIT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Rob Fernas 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As athletic director of <ORGANIZATION>Bishop Montgomery High</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Steve Carroll</PERSON> does a good job 
of promoting the school's attractive features. He speaks of the rigorous 
academic environment, the emphasis on discipline and the well-rounded sports 
program. 
</P>
<P>
