<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890508-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-08-89 1346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Korea-Princess     05-08 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea-Princess,0518</SECOND>
<HEAD>Last Korean Princess Buried in Ancient Rites</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY TUNNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The last princess of the royal dynasty
of <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> was buried <DATE>Monday</DATE> with musicians blowing conch shells and
honor guards in traditional red, blue and gold robes escorting the
coffin to the royal tombs.
   Prince <PERSON>Yi Pang-ja</PERSON>, a member of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s royal family who married
a Korean prince, died <DATE>April 30</DATE> at age 88, nine days after the death
of Princess Tok-hye, her sister-in-law. The princesses were the
last two royal members of the Yi dynasty that ruled <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> for five
centuries until <DATE>1910</DATE>.
   Hundreds of official mourners dressed in traditional white robes
and tall hats made of hemp followed the princess' only son in a
royal funeral procession from her home at <ORGANIZATION>Changdok Palace</ORGANIZATION> through
crowded downtown streets.
   Other marchers wore the red, blue and gold tunics of palace
guards and court officials of the <ORGANIZATION>Yi Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>. Musicians played a
funeral dirge on long trumpets, bells and conch shells as several
thousand people stood on curbs to watch the procession pass.
   ``Your majesty, your majesty,'' wailed a woman in the crowd who
said she worked at the palace.
   Officials said the ceremony would be <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>'s last royal funeral
since none of the royal family's surviving descendants has a royal
title.
   Princess Pang-ja, whose Japanese name was <PERSON>Masako</PERSON>, was a cousin
of Japanese Empress <PERSON>Dowager Nagako</PERSON>, widow of Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>. She
married Prince <PERSON>Yi Un</PERSON>, a son of <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>King Kojong</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> in
<DATE>1920</DATE>, 10 years after <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> annexed the Korean peninsula as its
colony. King Kojong was the last royal ruler of <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>.
   ``This is the passing of an era,'' said <PERSON>Peter Bartholomew</PERSON>, a
friend of the princess. ``There will never been another royal
funeral. A tradition and an era in history has died.''
   South Korean Prime Minister <PERSON>Kang Young-hoon</PERSON> said the princess
had bridged two cultures to ``become the loving grandmother of our
country. We'll never forget her.''
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Prince Mikasa, youngest brother of <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, and his
wife, Princess Mikasa, attended the services as the representatives
of the Japanese Imperial household and followed the procession in a
motorcade.
   At the services in the palace grounds, Prince Mikasa bowed
toward the traditional white funeral altar, burned incense for a
happy afterlife, then bowed again to the princess' son, <PERSON>Yi Ku</PERSON>, who
was raised in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and lives there.
   The princess was buried, as she wished, beside her husband and
an infant son on a hillside in the royal burial grounds east of
<LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, surrounded by the rice paddies and trees of her adopted land.
   ``I have two fatherlands: <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> has given me
body, while <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> has given me spirit,'' the princess once wrote, a
passage repeated at her funeral.
   She and her invalid husband came to <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> in <DATE>1963</DATE>, and he died
in <DATE>1970</DATE>. Princess Pang-ja devoted herself to philanthropic works,
founding a vocational training center for the handicapped and a
rehabilitation center for the mentally and physically disabled.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890425-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-25-89 0936EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SouthKorea-Princess     04-25 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-South Korea-Princess,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>One Of Korea's Last Royals Buried In Royal Tomb</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SEL9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY TUNNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Princess Tokhye, one of the last
survivors of the ancient Yi Dynasty that ruled <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> for five
centuries, was buried today amid prayers for the woman one mourner
called ``the unhappy princess.''
   Official mourners dressed in traditional white hemp clothes and
tall hats carried the lacquered black coffin to the grave site on a
hillside in the royal burial grounds east of <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>.
   The princess died <DATE>Friday</DATE> at age 77.
   ``She was the most beautiful and most noble of princesses,''
said <PERSON>Alice Kim</PERSON>, who attended the funeral. ``And she was the most
sad.''
   The grave site was chosen by a traditional pungsu, or fortune
teller, who decides the most auspicious location and timing of a
burial. He used a compass to align the casket in keeping with a
Korean belief that a corpses' feet must point south to ensure a
happy afterlife.
   Lee Hae-suk, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Yi Dynasty Association</ORGANIZATION> who helped
arrange the ceremonies, said Princess Tokhye probably wouldn't mind
if her feet didn't quite point due south because her life had been
difficult.
   ``She was a very unhappy princess,'' said <PERSON>Lee</PERSON>. ``She would be
used to being a little off.''
   About 75 people, many of them spectators, attended a traditional
Confucian burial ceremony at <ORGANIZATION>Changdok Palace</ORGANIZATION> in central <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>,
where the princess spent the last years of her life as a recluse.
The body was then taken to the royal burial grounds.
   Princess Tokhye, a daughter of <PERSON>King Kojong</PERSON>, the last Yi king,
was born to a royal concubine named <ORGANIZATION>Yang</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1912</DATE>, two years after
her father was forced to abdicate by the Japanese, who took control
of <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>.
   At age 13, she was sent to school in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and later married a
Japanese nobleman much older than herself. Her mother died before
she could return to <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> and her only child committed suicide.
   In <DATE>1951</DATE>, the princess was divorced from her Japanese husband and
in <DATE>1962</DATE> she returned to her homeland, suffering from diabetes and
aphasia.
   Visitors said she was sometimes heard humming or singing to
herself, but she hadn't spoken for many years.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7369 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas059_c_94037" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-059 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  26 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> North Korea </F>
<H3> <TI>   Preservation of Cultural Relics Reported </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  SK2603230394 Pyongyang KCNA in English 1516 GMT 26 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> SK2603230394 </F>
<F P=104>  Pyongyang KCNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Pyongyang</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 26</DATE> (<ORGANIZATION>KCNA</ORGANIZATION>) -- The building of the 
tomb of Tangun is progressing at fast speed in <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>. 
  Tangun is the father of the Korean nation who was the first 
king of Kojoson (ancient <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>) (3,000 B.C.-108 B.C.). Situated 
in <LOCATION>Kangdong County</LOCATION>, Yongyang municipality, the 22 meter high 
tomb will occupy an area of over 800,000 square metres when 
reconstructed. 
  The great leader President Kim Il-song personally studied 
the 
legend of <PERSON>Tangun</PERSON> and materials about his tomb and saw to it that 
the tomb was excavated. After the remains of <PERSON>Tangun</PERSON> and relics 
were excavated and identified scientifically, President Kim 
Il-song went out to the spot and gave instructions to rebuild 
the tomb splendidly to be handed down to the generations to come. 
  Thus, <PERSON>Tangun</PERSON> who had long been known to be a mythical man 
was 
proved to have been a real man and the history of Kojoson 
distorted by the Japanese imperialists when they occupied <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> 
was established correctly. 
  Under the wise guidance of President Kim Il-song, cultural 
heritages which had been severely destroyed by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and 
Japanese imperialist aggressors have been reconstructed to be 
preserved as treasures of the country and the nation. 
  In recent years, the tomb of <PERSON>King Tongmyong</PERSON>, the founder of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Koguryo Dynasty</ORGANIZATION> (277 B.C.-668 A.D.) which was the strongest 
country in the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>, the tomb of <PERSON>King Wang Kon</PERSON>, the first king 
of Koryo (918-1392) which was the first unified state in <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, 
the tomb of <PERSON>King Kogukwon</PERSON> (a king of <LOCATION>Koguryo</LOCATION> in the middle of 
the 4th century), the tomb of <PERSON>King Kongmin</PERSON> (the 31st king of 
Koryo) and tombs of other kings have been restored to their 
original state. 
  The Kwangbop temple in Mt. Taesong (392), the Pohyon temple 
in Mt. Myohyang (1042) and the Pyohun temple in Mt. Kumgano 
(670), Buddhist temples showing the equisite architecture of the 
Korean nation, and the wall on Mt. Taesong belonging to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Koguryo Dynasty</ORGANIZATION> and the wall on Mt. Ongbang belonging to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Koryo Dynasty</ORGANIZATION> and many other architectural heritages have been 
splendidly rehabilitated. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Songgyungwan Academy of Koryo</ORGANIZATION> (992), one of the first 
universities in the world, was recently rebuilt on an expansion 
basis to be turned into a university training light industrial 
technicians. 
  The chronicles of the <ORGANIZATION>Yi Dynasty</ORGANIZATION> of 900 books in 1,763 
volumes, the world largest governmental diary covering over 500 
years of the feudal state of the <ORGANIZATION>Yi Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>, not omitting a 
single day, has been published in modern Korean language. 
  The bibliographical book (25 volumes) of the "80,000 Blocks 
of Complete Collection of Buddhist Scriptures" of 6,793 volumes, 
a library of Buddhism belonging to the <ORGANIZATION>Koryo Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>, and the 
selected translation of major sutras of the collection have been 
published and a modern house for preserving the collection was 
built in the scenic Mt. Myohyang. 
  Many classical books of history, culture, medical sceince 
and 
other fields such as "Tonguibogam", an encyclopedic book of 
Koryo medicine, "The History of the Three Dynasties" "History of 
the Koryo Dynasty", and "The Tale of Chun Hyang" have been 
collected and arranged. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Korean Central History Museum</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Korean Folklore 
Museum</ORGANIZATION> 
and <ORGANIZATION>Provincial History Museum</ORGANIZATION> are crowded with youth and 
children and working people everyday. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-5342</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFEASAFBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940604
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 JUN 94 / Collecting: Rarities in blue and white - Susan Moore samples
the numerous wares of quality Chinese porcelain
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By SUSAN MOORE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Chinese porcelain takes pride of place at the seasonal Oriental art shows in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> this month. Even the <ORGANIZATION>British Museum</ORGANIZATION> presents highlights from the
Meiyintang Collection, the first public display of one of the largest and
finest private holdings of Chinese ceramics in the west.
Amassed during the last 40 years, this continental collection is remarkable
for the variety, quality and rarity of its pieces which range from Neolithic
pottery and Han and Tang dynasty tomb figures and burial wares to <ORGANIZATION>Ming</ORGANIZATION> and
Qing Imperial porcelains (<DATE>June</DATE> 9-September 9).
<PERSON>Eskenazi</PERSON> has a no less sumptuous feast of market rarities in its exhibition
of early blue and white (10 <PERSON>Clifford Street</PERSON>, W1, <DATE>June</DATE> 7-July 8). From their
first large-scale manufacture in the <DATE>14th century</DATE>, these luxurious white
porcelains painted in underglaze cobalt blue have been highly prized in
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and beyond. Perhaps no ceramic tradition has been more widely imitated
or more enduringly popular.
The <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> appears to have been the destination of a number of these
vessels. Forms are distinctly un-Chinese: there are Islamic emblems, even a
Persian inscription proclaiming a piece the property of one <PERSON>Alamgir Shah</PERSON>.
The star turn, discovered in <LOCATION>Damascus</LOCATION> 30 years ago, is a spectacular and
densely decorated mid-14th century Yuan dynasty dish, 46cm wide. In the
central medallion, reserved in white on a rich blue ground, are cranes and
ducks in a lotus pond, well observed and full of life.
Their liveliness is matched by the dish's surface: one of the delights of
handling blue and white is the way in which the impurities in the cobalt
produce a heaped and piled effect in the glaze and a varying intensity of
blue.
This unique piece is of museum quality and into a museum it may well go  -
given that it was broken and repaired and even hair-line cracks are not
tolerated by the new breed of avid <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> collectors.
The show's other tour de force is not technically blue and white at all.
This large, deep Ming dynasty bowl of the Hongwu period (1368-98) is
decorated with scrolling peonies in underglaze copper red, which firing has
turned into the subtlest of pinks and greys. Dated 1340-1435, the 26 pieces
bear Pounds 45,000-Pounds 400,000 price tags.
At <ORGANIZATION>S. Marchant &amp; Son</ORGANIZATION> (120 Kensington Church Street, W8), the focus is on the
great age of blanc de Chine - <DATE>1640-1710</DATE> - a much more particular taste. As
this show demonstrates, however, the craftsmen of provincial Dehua gave
their glossy white wares an astonishing variety of expression. At one
extreme stands a graceful and superbly modelled Guanyin or goddess of mercy
in flowing robes. Dating around <DATE>1640</DATE>, and 38cm high, the figure bears the
seal mark of the mysterious He Chaozong, the most illustrious name in <LOCATION>Dehua</LOCATION>
porcelain. At the other, a whistle in the form of a European gentleman in a
tricorn hat seated astride a comically grinning tiger. The whole group is
only 4.7cm high. Prices Pounds 200-Pounds 30,000 (<DATE>June</DATE> 3-24).
Early celadon porcelains from <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> are the delicate fare
at Jehanne de Biolley Oriental Art (29 Conduit Street, W1, <DATE>June</DATE> 1-July 1).
Prices Pounds 150-Pounds 20,000. Chinese, Korean and Japanese works of art
are also at <ORGANIZATION>Spink</ORGANIZATION>'s, 5-7 King Street, SW1, <DATE>June 1-17</DATE>. Notable here is a pair
of white jade lotus-shaped drinking cups that unusually bear the mark of the
<PERSON>Qianlong</PERSON> emperor, and an understated white porcelain moon flask from late
Choson dynasty <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>. Prices Pounds 5,000-Pounds 150,000.
The <ORGANIZATION>Oriental Art Gallery</ORGANIZATION>'s wide- ranging exhibition includes Ming and Qing
caladons, blanc de Chine and monochrome porcelains at 4 <ORGANIZATION>Davies Street</ORGANIZATION>, W1,
<DATE>June 7-24</DATE>. Prices Pounds 950-Pounds 55,000, with most objects under Pounds
10,000.
With characteristic theatrical flourish, Christian Deydier of <ORGANIZATION>Oriental
Bronzes Ltd</ORGANIZATION> unveils one extraordinary item for one evening only. This is a
pair of stylised gold tigers dated to 8th century BC <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, their slender,
elongated bodies decorated with cinnabar stripes and formed out of gold
strips wrapped and pinned around a wooden core. Professor <PERSON>Han Wei</PERSON>, an
authority on ancient Chinese gold, has suggested that the 45cm long tiger
mounts flanked a burial pillow. Nothing quite like them is known in gold -
nor any other gold artefact of comparable size and date. Deydier is asking
around Pounds 1.5m. 96 Mount Street, W1. <DATE>June 7</DATE>, 5.30-8pm.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XXI
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870721-0130 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
The Gallery: When Ash and Water Make Bronze and Jade
---
By Pamela J. Macleod</HL>
<DD> 07/21/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> New York  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the <DATE>seventh century</DATE>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> awed the world with its exports of a fine, translucent white porcelain -- the same stuff, in fact, that we now call china. 

   But the roots of that achievement stretch back to the <DATE>15th century B.C.</DATE>, when potters discovered that a coating of ash and water produced an impermeable bronze-and-jade-tinted glaze after firing at high temperatures. 

   Thus celadon porcelain -- named after a character in a 17th-century French play ("L'Astree" by Honore d'Urfe) whose costume was grayish-green -- became the world's first hard-glazed ware. 
Reaching its peak in quality and quantity in the Song dynasty (10th-13th centuries), it didn't fade in popularity until the advent of blue-and-white porcelain in the <DATE>14th century</DATE>. 
It is still made in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> today. 

   Fortunately, you don't have to cross the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> to get a good look at what a ninth-century poet likened to "cracked ice and green clouds." 
The <ORGANIZATION>Indianapolis Museum of Art</ORGANIZATION> has mounted the most complete survey of celadon's 3,000-year history to date, "Ice and Green Clouds: Traditions of Chinese Celadon," at the <ORGANIZATION>Asia Society</ORGANIZATION> through <DATE>Sept. 6</DATE>. 
It then stops at the <ORGANIZATION>Kimbell Art Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> (<DATE>Oct. 17,1987-Jan</DATE>. 3, <DATE>1988</DATE>), and the Art Institute of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> (<DATE>Feb. 4-March 27</DATE>). 

   The exhibit's 87 works from collections around the world were painstakingly tracked down over a five-year period by <PERSON>Yutaka Mino</PERSON>, former curator of Oriental art at the <LOCATION>Indianapolis Museum</LOCATION> and now curator of Chinese and Japanese art at the <ORGANIZATION>Art Institute of Chicago</ORGANIZATION>. 
The 75 works that made the trip to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> are attractively, understatedly displayed in one room, in chronological order. 

   Celadon was rare in the beginning; it accounts for less than <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> of all ceramic discoveries from the Shang dynasty (17th-11th centuries <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>). 
These early vessels were shaped like bronze ware and often decorated with a basketwork or clothlike pattern. 
They had a thin brown or yellow glaze. (The color of the glaze is determined by the amount of iron in the coating and the clay, and by firing techniques.) 
They were used by the ruling classes for ceremonial and funerary purposes. 
One simple widemouthed jar on display exemplifies the earliest known type of celadon, and is the only such vessel now outside <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 

   It wasn't until the <ORGANIZATION>Six Dynasties Period</ORGANIZATION> (third-sixth centuries), that celadon as we know it today was born. 
Then potters stopped imitating bronze ware and began to create wholly new forms and add whimsical touches. 
Vessels took the shape of frogs and lions, sprouted chicken and tiger heads, and were dotted with tiny molded masks representing mythological or religious figures. 
A pair of incised little fish frolic at the bottom of one large basin on display, and a small stand, perhaps for a candle, doubles as a curly maned lion ready to pounce, teeth bared. 

   The celadon of the Tang dynasty (seventh-10th centuries) -- from spittoons to ewers and little covered boxes -- took its inspiration from the silverwork of the period. 
Shapes became more refined and compact, while decoration (such as textile patterns and mythological motifs from <LOCATION>Central Asia</LOCATION>) began to reflect the foreign influences in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> brought about by trade. 
A simple spittoon provides quite a contrast to the ornate pale-green-glazed ewer pictured here. 
It has a seated lion for a spout and is covered with bold relief leaves and flowers. 

   Some features of Tang dynasty ware survived into the Song dynasty, but for the first time celadon reflected "pure Chinese taste," <PERSON>Mr. Mino</PERSON> says, "with no outside influences." 
The most beautiful celadon ever created dates from this period, from the kilns of <LOCATION>Longquan</LOCATION>, south of <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION>. 

   This silky smooth, beautifully shaped celadon, in luminescent shades from seafoam green to robin's-egg blue, is displayed here in three adjoining cases that catch the eye as soon as you enter the room. 
A long, thin dragon winds around the shoulder of one wonderful urn, in pursuit of a shiny pearl, while a rectangular vase (in a case of its own at the beginning of the exhibit) is fashioned after an ancient ritual jade vessel. 

   The Yuan dynasty (13th-14th centuries) is the last period covered by the exhibit, just before celadon went out of fashion. 
Some of these pieces have molded panels that were left unglazed and burned reddish-brown, in nice contrast to the cool greens of the glazes. 
Other vessels are punctuated by dark brown spots created by applying dots of iron oxide before glazing. 

   Celadon of all periods vividly reminds us of the artist behind the work. 
"There is no brush between the artist and the clay," <PERSON>Mr. Mino</PERSON> says, "so we really understand what he was thinking." 
"Unfortunately," he adds, "we don't know who any of these people were, because they didn't sign their names." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890522-0281 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-22-89 1344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-MisnamedCemetery Adv30   05-22 0920</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Misnamed Cemetery, Adv 30,0947</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tue AMs, May 30 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Expert Says Ancient Egyptian Burial Ground `Misunderstood, Misnamed'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VALLEY OF THE QUEENS, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This quiet, bone-dry ravine
of death, overshadowed since antiquity by the Valley of the Kings
just over the hills, slowly is shedding its mystery.
   And with the mystery, its name.
   Ancients called the valley Ta-Set Neferu, the <ORGANIZATION>Place of Beauty</ORGANIZATION>.
To the Arabs it was Gates of the Ladies. Egyptologists and
guidebooks perpetuate the homage to entombed royal women: the
Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>.
   ``It's wrong. This valley has been misunderstood and misnamed by
all Egyptologists,'' said <PERSON>Christian LeBlanc</PERSON>, field director for a
continuing 17-year French-Egyptian project to record and study its
history.
   ``We should be calling it the Valley of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Children</ORGANIZATION>. They
were here first, but the valley became tied only to the queens and
named by tradition rather than history.''
   Season after archaeological season, <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON>'s team has scoured
the sloping, dusty hillsides dotted with cave-like tombs to find
the origins of a sequence of burials that would last almost 2,000
years. Tombs were used repeatedly, as late as the Christian era
when pharaonic designs sometimes were plastered over and crosses
painted on.
   <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said the first burials were princes and princesses of
ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s 18th dynasty, a 243-year renaissance when, after a
period of decline, pharaohs and their kin once again lived and died
like kings.
   That dynasty ended in <DATE>1307</DATE> B.C., and Ramses I, founder of the
19th dynasty, changed tradition by burying his queen Sat-Re here.
   <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said it's unclear why he did or why the practice
continued. In addition to queens, royal children still were buried
here, and concubines who cared for them and pharaohs' mothers.
   Paintings in some of the tombs show <PERSON>Hathor</PERSON>, the goddess of women
and love, emerging from a grotto that dominates the valley. <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON>
said perhaps this indicates that religion brought the ancients
here, because <PERSON>Hathor</PERSON>'s realm also included the cemeteries on what
is called the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION> across the <ORGANIZATION>Nile</ORGANIZATION> from present-day <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION>.
   The 18th dynasty, when the graveyard for royal children began,
was a time when queens traditionally shared their pharaoh's tombs
in the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>. Many of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s greatest rulers
were buried there, along with the young pharoah Tutankhamun, whose
treasure-filled tomb was discovered by <PERSON>Howard Carter</PERSON> in <DATE>1922</DATE>.
   That discovery brought international fame to the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the
Kings</ORGANIZATION>. Hundreds of other royals and officials also were buried on
the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION>. But to the world, the glory of the pharaohs meant
the Valley of the Kings _ not the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>, the Valley
of the Monkeys or the Tombs of the <LOCATION>Nobles</LOCATION>.
   For tourist agencies, the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION> became an
afterthought, a place to fill a half-hour after an exhausting visit
to the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>.
   When the joint expedition began, 78 burial places had been found
in the limestone hillsides enclosing the valley. Today 98 are known.
   ``We couldn't understand the cemetery before, because we were
working tomb-by-tomb,'' <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said. ``Today, we've uncovered all
the major tombs and have returned the valley to the way it would
have looked when burials began.
   ``For the first time, we can write its history.''
   As <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> talked, he and <PERSON>Fathy Hassanein</PERSON>, director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization's National Documentation Center</ORGANIZATION>,
walked through scores of excavators digging toward the valley's
bedrock. The job at hand was almost done, another tomb uncovered
from rubble that has obscured the cemetery for most of its
existence.
   An aim of the project is to restore tombs in the valley so that
more can be opened to tourists. Fewer than six are now.
   The valley's most beautiful tomb, the fabulous burial chambers
of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses II</ORGANIZATION>'s powerful queen <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>, is among those so
deteriorated that they remain off-limits. More than half its
paintings of the elaborately dressed and coiffured queen have been
destroyed by natural forces.
   <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said one source for the valley's history has been
tidbits left by workers who built and decorated the tombs. For
generations they lived in a village inside the valley. Their
records, on papyrus, provided the team not only with answers but
with mysteries.
   Workers recorded the construction of tombs for Queen Isis
<LOCATION>Nefret</LOCATION>, one of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses II</ORGANIZATION>'s many wives, and a queen named
Duat-Iny-Pet.
   <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said they might have been same person, but ``where are
they?''
   He also is intrigued by a lack of burial objects or pieces of
the queens' mummies.
   ``This is strange,'' he said. ``Did those who came afterwards
destroy them?'' He added that it could mean another royal cache
exists, perhaps mummies of queens and children.
   Typical of the tales <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> has faced in rewriting a new
history for the valley is the story of a mummified fetus inside the
tomb of 9-year-old prince Amon-Hir-Khopshef, son of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses III</ORGANIZATION>.
   Local guides tell fascinated visitors that <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON>' queen became
so distraught over the death of their son that she miscarried and
the mummies of both Amon-Hir-Khopshef and the fetus were entombed.
   The story is nonsense, <PERSON>Leblanc</PERSON> said.
   Early this century, the Italian excavator <PERSON>Ernesto Schiaparelli</PERSON>
found the fetus in a rubbish pile outside the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>.
It was <PERSON>Schiaparelli</PERSON>, not ancient priests, who placed it inside the
prince's empty sarcophagus.
   Today, the mummified fetus is so popular a tourist attraction
that it has its own tiny case.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tue AMs, May 30</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061189-0088 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 68754 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 11, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 5; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
907 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ANCIENT EGYPTIAN BURIAL GROUND IS 'MISUNDERSTOOD AND MISNAMED' 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MIMI MANN, Associated Press Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
VALLEY OF THE QUEENS, Egypt 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
This quiet, bone-dry ravine of death, overshadowed since antiquity by the 
Valley of the Kings just over the hills, slowly is shedding its mystery. 
</P>
<P>
And with the mystery, its name. 
</P>
<P>
Ancients called the valley Ta-Set Neferu, the <ORGANIZATION>Place of Beauty</ORGANIZATION>. To the Arabs it 
was Gates of the Ladies. Egyptologists and guidebooks perpetuate the homage to 
entombed royal women: the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It's wrong. This valley has been misunderstood and misnamed by all 
Egyptologists," said <PERSON>Christian LeBlanc</PERSON>, field director for a continuing 17-year 
French-Egyptian project to record and study its history. 
</P>
<P>
"We should be calling it the Valley of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Children</ORGANIZATION>. They were here 
first, but the valley became tied only to the queens and named by tradition 
rather than history." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Hillsides Scoured 
</P>
<P>
Season</ORGANIZATION> after archeological season, <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON>'s team has scoured the sloping, 
dusty hillsides dotted with cave-like tombs to find the origins of a sequence 
of burials that would last almost 2,000 years. Tombs were used repeatedly, as 
late as the Christian era when Pharaonic designs sometimes were plastered over 
and crosses painted on. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said the first burials were princes and princesses of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>18th Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>, a 243-year renaissance when, after a period of decline, Pharaohs 
and their kin once again lived and died like kings. 
</P>
<P>
That dynasty ended in <DATE>1307</DATE> B.C., and Ramses I, founder of the <ORGANIZATION>19th Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>, 
changed tradition by burying his queen Sat-Re here. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said it is unclear why he did or why the practice continued. In 
addition to queens, royal children still were buried here, and concubines who 
cared for them and Pharaohs' mothers. 
</P>
<P>
Paintings in some of the tombs show <PERSON>Hathor</PERSON>, the goddess of women and love, 
emerging from a grotto that dominates the valley. <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said perhaps this 
indicates that religion brought the ancients here, because <PERSON>Hathor</PERSON>'s realm also 
included the cemeteries on what is called the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION> across the <ORGANIZATION>Nile</ORGANIZATION> from 
present-day <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Treasure-Filled Tombs 
</P>
<P>
The 18th Dynasty, when the graveyard for royal children began, was a time when 
queens traditionally shared their Pharaoh's tombs in the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>. 
Many of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s greatest rulers were buried there, along with the young 
<PERSON>Pharaoh Tutankhamun</PERSON>, whose treasure-filled tomb was discovered by <PERSON>Howard Carter</PERSON> 
in <DATE>1922</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
That discovery brought international fame to the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>. Hundreds 
of other royals and officials also were buried on the <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION>. But to the 
world, the glory of the Pharaohs meant the Valley of the Kings -- not the 
Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>, the Valley of the Monkeys or the Tombs of the <LOCATION>Nobles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For tourist agencies, the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION> became an afterthought, a place 
to fill a half-hour after an exhausting visit to the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Kings</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
When the joint expedition began, 78 burial places had been found in the 
limestone hillsides enclosing the valley. Today 98 are known. 
</P>
<P>
"We couldn't understand the cemetery before, because we were working 
tomb-by-tomb," <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said. "Today, we've uncovered all the major tombs and 
have returned the valley to the way it would have looked when burials began. 
</P>
<P>
"For the first time, we can write its history." 
</P>
<P>
As <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> talked, he and <PERSON>Fathy Hassanein</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities 
Organization's National Documentation Center</ORGANIZATION>, walked through scores of 
excavators digging toward the valley's bedrock. The job at hand was almost 
done, another tomb uncovered from rubble that has obscured the cemetery for 
most of its existence. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Restoration Work 
</P>
<P>
An aim of the project is to restore tombs in the valley so that more can be 
opened to tourists. Fewer than six are now. 
</P>
<P>
The valley's most beautiful tomb, the fabulous burial chambers of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses II</ORGANIZATION>'s 
powerful queen <PERSON>Nefertari</PERSON>, is among those so deteriorated that they remain 
off-limits. More than half its paintings of the elaborately dressed and 
coiffured queen have been destroyed by natural forces. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said one source for the valley's history has been tidbits left by 
workers who built and decorated the tombs. For generations they lived in a 
village inside the valley. Their records, on papyrus, provided the team not 
only with answers but with mysteries. 
</P>
<P>
Workers recorded the construction of tombs for Queen Isis <LOCATION>Nefret</LOCATION>, one of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses 
II</ORGANIZATION>'s many wives, and a queen named Duat-Iny-Pet. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said they might have been same person, but "where are they?" 
</P>
<P>
He also is intrigued by a lack of burial objects or pieces of the queens' 
mummies. 
</P>
<P>
"This is strange," he said. "Did those who came afterwards destroy them?" He 
added that it could mean another royal cache exists, perhaps mummies of queens 
and children. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Mummified Fetus 
</P>
<P>
Typical of the tales <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> has faced in rewriting a new history for the 
valley is the story of a mummified fetus inside the tomb of 9-year-old prince 
Amon-Hir-Khopshef, son of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses III</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Local guides tell fascinated visitors that <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON>' queen became so distraught 
over the death of their son that she miscarried and the mummies of both 
Amon-Hir-Khopshef and the fetus were entombed. 
</P>
<P>
The story is nonsense, <PERSON>LeBlanc</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Early this century, the Italian excavator <PERSON>Ernesto Schiaparelli</PERSON> found the fetus 
in a rubbish pile outside the Valley of the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>. It was <PERSON>Schiaparelli</PERSON>, not 
ancient priests, who placed it inside the prince's empty sarcophagus. 
</P>
<P>
Today, the mummified fetus is so popular a tourist attraction that it has its 
own tiny case. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881013-0009 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Art: One From Dynasty A and One From Dynasty B </HL>
<AUTHOR> Amy Gamerman </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> Seattle  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of the most spectacular collections of Chinese art ever to be seen in this country is currently tucked behind an amusement park at the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
But the bumper-cars, carousel and cotton-candy vendors form an appropriate backdrop for "Son of Heaven," a show that seems a cross between a museum exhibit and a three-ring circus. 

   The vast selection of ancient bronzes, porcelains, paintings, sculptures and jewelry spans more than 2,500 years of Chinese history and includes many objects from recently excavated tombs. 
Culled from more than 20 Chinese museums and institutes, <PERCENT>92%</PERCENT> of the artifacts have never been seen before in this country and <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> have never traveled outside of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 

   Despite this and the high quality of the objects, all the museums approached by the private sponsors, <ORGANIZATION>Son of Heaven Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, refused to take the show. 
"There are extraordinary things, wonderful things on show," said <PERSON>Freda Murck</PERSON>, associate curator of Asian art at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s Metropolitan Museum of Art. 
But her museum, like several others, found the costs and logistical difficulties overwhelming. 
With insurance, shipping and underwriting costs, "Son of Heaven" carries a price tag of <MONEY>$5.5 million</MONEY>. 
Heavy temple and mortuary sculpture, eventually omitted, posed nightmarish problems of installation and maintenance. 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> museums were, further, put off by the organizers' commercial approach and lack of professionalism. 
<PERSON>Ms. Murck</PERSON> adds that the Met didn't even try to find corporate sponsors, because the show didn't have "a dazzling list that we were ready to die for." 
Seattle added its own, highly publicized complications, notably the recent firing of the show's director, <LOCATION>Harvey West</LOCATION>. 
Some people here have taken to calling the show "Son of Hell." 

   The exhibit certainly has a bizarre history. 
The Chinese government initially suggested the loan to <PERSON>Norm Swanson</PERSON>, a Spokane-based travel agent who runs organized tours in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Swanson</PERSON> tried to market the exhibit as a commercial venture in partnership with <PERSON>Harvey West</PERSON>, an art administrator known for his impresario-like projects, but they failed to win sufficient backing. 
The project later resurfaced under <PERSON>Mr. West</PERSON>'s directorship in a new, nonprofit guise and was bankrolled through a combination of corporate underwriting and donations. 

   <PERSON>Larry Childs</PERSON>, president of the resulting Son of Heaven company, is a former business executive without museum experience. 
<PERSON>Mr. Childs</PERSON>, who has described himself as being in the "blockbuster business," is trying to maximize the show's popular appeal. 

   "We want the people that might go to a football game," he said. 
"The people who would go see the Seahawks play are the people I'd like to see come to this exhibit." 

   But despite the TV advertisements, 40-foot banners, and an opening gala featuring acrobats, firecrackers and every local celebrity from <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Miss Chinatown</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>'s brother <PERSON>Edward</PERSON>, "Son of Heaven" has failed to take the world or even this town by storm. 
The show has been drawing crowds well under the maximum capacity of 700 people an hour. 
This may be due in part to the stiff entrance fee: <MONEY>$7.50</MONEY> for adults. 
Beyond this, the show hasn't managed to capture the public imagination. 
The organizers themselves seem to lack a clear notion of what they are promoting. 

   "We wanted to be a show that would teach people about <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and the role of the imperial institution," said <PERSON>Robert Thorp</PERSON>, the American curator of the exhibit and an associate professor of art history at <ORGANIZATION>Washington University</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. 

   But at four times the size of the epic "Tutankhamen" exhibit of <DATE>1978</DATE>, which it rivals as pure spectacle, "Son of Heaven's" bulk may be working against its own mystique. 

   "One of the problems is that it spans over 2,500 years and goes all over <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Ms. Murck</PERSON>. 
"It's very ambitious -- and for the man on the street, not easy to grasp." 

   On a recent morning, a cluster of under 100 people with tickets to the exhibit waited patiently under a long green and yellow canopy outside the entrance of the center's <LOCATION>Flag Pavilion</LOCATION>. 
A host of exhibit attendants dressed in brown mandarin-style jackets, clearly prepared for much larger crowds, monitored the entrance with walkie-talkies. 

   Once inside, the group was ushered into one of two auditoriums for a 10-minute sound-and-light show. 
The gongs, bells and flashing pictures of temples and thrones are meant to prepare the spectator for the Altar, the first of five thematically arranged exhibit rooms. 
A glowing jade ritual disc the size of a Frisbee hangs at the dark entrance, the first stop on a dizzying game of hopscotch that leaps back and forth over 26 centuries, six imperial dynasties, and every kind of artistic medium. 

   In a somber atmosphere silent except for the whisper of rented audio headsets, viewers moved from the Altar's <DATE>Sixth century</DATE> B.C. bronzes to the <ORGANIZATION>Outer Court</ORGANIZATION>'s 18th-century Qing brocades and inkstands, and then on to the <ORGANIZATION>Temple</ORGANIZATION> and Eighth-century Tang sculptures. 
By the time they reached the Inner Court many were beginning to look bleary-eyed as they wandered through a sea of glass cases filled with everything from Han jugs to Ming wall-scrolls and jades. 
In the <ORGANIZATION>Tomb</ORGANIZATION>, the final room of the show, most managed a few minutes in front of the four terra-cotta warriors from the famous tomb at <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION> before staggering, with expressions of relief, into the exhibit's mammoth gift shop. 

   "It's a heavy dose," <PERSON>Mr. Thorp</PERSON> admitted. 
"There is a fatigue factor that sets in, probably at the <ORGANIZATION>Inner Court</ORGANIZATION>. 
I'd love it if we could put in benches so people could rest." 

   The non-chronological organization of the exhibit adds significantly to the fatigue. 
Objects from different centuries are placed side by side, creating an atmosphere of visual and historical confusion that the thematic groupings do little to clarify. 
Many recently excavated tombs are well represented here, but the organizers' decision to scatter objects from individual tombs throughout the five rooms detracts from their impact and squanders their romance. 

   But whatever reservations one may have about the exhibit, there are wonderful things to be seen. 
The Altar features a magnificent selection of bronze ritual vessels, including ornately engraved bowls from the tomb of Lady <PERSON>Meng Ji</PERSON>, which have survived from the <DATE>Seventh century B.C.</DATE> without a trace of the blue-green rust of oxidization. 
Other objects, such as a gilt silver phoenix crown (17th century), trembling with dragons, phoenixes and flowers, impress by their sheer material splendor. 
The jade burial suit of <ORGANIZATION>Princess Dou Wan</ORGANIZATION> (200 B.C.) is perhaps the most sensational of all. 
Two thousand jade plaques stitched together with gold thread are deployed to form the body stocking, boots, gloves and mask of a spacesuit-like shroud meant to preserve the body through eternity. 

   "Son of Heaven" will be up in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> until <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>. 
On <DATE>March 1, 1989</DATE>, it moves to a still-unnamed new exhibition hall now being built in the former <ORGANIZATION>Central High School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, where it will stay until <DATE>Sept. 4, 1989</DATE>. 

   In the meantime, <PERSON>Mr. Childs</PERSON> and his marketing team continue their campaign to whip up local enthusiasm. 
With a Chinese "lion dance" scheduled for one of the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Seahawks</ORGANIZATION>' halftime shows, "Son of Heaven" is certain to achieve its share of notoriety. 
But after all the hoopla, it may be remembered as the exhibit that swallowed its own treasures. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Ms. Gamerman</PERSON> is a free-lance writer based in <LOCATION>Larchmont</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA070989-0065 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 79771 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 9, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part 7; Page 8; Column 3; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1542 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CELADON POTTERY LEAVES VISITOR WITH GLAZED LOOK 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MAREN RUDOLPH, Rudolph is a free-lance writer living in Irvington, N.Y. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ICHON, South Korea 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
About 80 years ago a Korean farmer returning from work noticed a curious object 
half-hidden along a red dirt path near his home. He thought the item was a 
piece of jade -- it had the right texture and color. But once he had picked up 
the curio and rubbed it clean, he found a green ceramic duck instead of a 
precious stone. 
</P>
<P>
The duck was in good condition, and its charming shape showed the whimsical 
intent of its maker. 
</P>
<P>
People in the country had no use for such items, so the farmer went to town the 
next day and sold his prize -- a perfect Koryo Dynasty (AD 935-1392) celadon 
water dropper. 
</P>
<P>
Serendipitous discoveries such as this were almost routine in early 
20th-Century <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>. The story of the duck-shaped calligraphy instrument is not 
unique. It was just one of several finds that exposed a cache of ceramics 
unlike anything the art world has ever seen. 
</P>
<P>
Celadon is to <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> what Sevres is to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, Ming to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Delft</LOCATION> to the 
<LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>. Until <DATE>1910</DATE>, however, the grayish-green porcelains, symbolic of 
<LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>'s Golden Age, remained largely forgotten -- buried in aristocratic 
tombs for about 600 years -- until unearthed when occupying Japanese began to 
dig a network of highways throughout the peninsula. 
</P>
<P>
Since their rediscovery Koryo celadons -- items such as water droppers, hair 
ornaments, square pillows, rice bowls, teapots and wine vases -- have delighted 
connoisseurs. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>'s capital of <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, merchants lug wooden carts piled high with 
intricate new inlaid maebyongs (vases with a gourd-shaped top) through crowded 
streets of Insa-dong, <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>'s exclusive antique district, where shops show off 
medieval ceramics from water droppers to wine bottles. 
</P>
<P>
A few blocks south in the deluxe hotel region of Myong-dong, expensive 
galleries in underground arcades lure buyers with one or two flawless Koryo 
Dynasty copies. 
</P>
<P>
For a first-time visitor the concentration is dizzying. After a while, however, 
saturation gives way to appreciation. And before you know it, a love affair 
with the soft green ceramics begins. 
</P>
<P>
Part of what distinguishes <LOCATION>Koryo</LOCATION> celadons is their elegant simplicity. Unlike 
the more flamboyant Mings and Imaris, effects rendered by a celadon maebyong 
are as subtle as a Japanese garden. 
</P>
<P>
The maebyong does not reach out and dazzle the observer as does a Ming; 
instead, it waits. Its appeal stems from an uncontrived balance of color, motif 
and form -- as well as the quiet impression this leaves upon the intellect and 
senses. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>'s antique celadons are rare and expensive. Prices vary according to 
quality and demand, but an authentic Koryo Dynasty bowl, even in poor 
condition, is certain to bring <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> or more. Foreigners can buy flawed but 
charming antique celadons at Insa-dong galleries. 
</P>
<P>
(You must have government approval if you want to take any curio more than 65 
years old home with you.) 
</P>
<P>
But if it is perfection you want, do not despair. Reproductions crafted in 
mountain kilns using the ancient process make fine substitutes. At city 
galleries and even department stores you can buy copies that rival original 
Koryo ceramics found in the <ORGANIZATION>National Museum</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But they do not come cheap. Vases from potters such as Chi Sun-t'aek and Yoo 
Keun-hyeong -- both national living treasures -- could cost <MONEY>$8,000</MONEY> or more. 
</P>
<P>
If your schedule permits, there is a less expensive way to acquire a celadon 
souvenir. For one-third the cost and three times the fun, you can travel to a 
country kiln and discover what <LOCATION>South Koreans</LOCATION> mean by "Chosun" or "Morning 
Calm." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>'s most popular pottery region is this mountain village of Ichon -- 
about 20 miles south of <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, where famous kilns of Koryo-doyo and 
Haegang-doyo, craft splendid Koryo celadon reproductions. 
</P>
<P>
In early fall, country dwellers string red peppers atop roofs in preparation 
for the kimchi festival (when <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>'s staple of hot and spicy pickled cabbage 
is celebrated) as workers push for an abundant celadon harvest before the 
frigid winter sets in. 
</P>
<P>
Ichon's kilns keep busy, and when its storerooms bulge with pots, you can seize 
a masterpiece for a fraction of its gallery value. And better yet, the beauty 
of the Korean countryside is there for the seeing. 
</P>
<P>
Fluffy white clouds cap mountains and pepper hills with shadows as if imitating 
subtle designs on a 12th-Century celadon vase. In the valley, the harvest nears 
and the rice stands tall. 
</P>
<P>
Farmers dressed in white carry heavy loads of produce on their backs and 
gracefully walk red dirt paths as if being carried down terraced hills on a 
wave of grain. 
</P>
<P>
Part of what distinguishes South Korean celadon from that of the Sung Chinese 
lies in these simple pastoral scenes. The graceful lines and sensuous forms 
come from familiar objects -- a melon, a gourd, a bamboo shoot, a reed. The 
spirited motifs -- ducks playing among reeds, cranes soaring through clouds -- 
arise from landscapes lyrical and naive. 
</P>
<P>
Good celadon reproductions follow the same painstaking process of the Koryo 
period. First, the best clays are selected and taken to the kiln site. 
Preparation of the clay is important, for unless a suitably plastic condition 
is achieved, the finished product will appear rough. 
</P>
<P>
Also, without the proper mixture of clays containing kaolin and petuntse, a 
Chinese discovery called the "bones and flesh" of porcelain, celadons would 
crack at the high firing of 1,300 degrees centigrade, and the soft, green glaze 
would never fuse with the body. 
</P>
<P>
Twisting up and down Ichon's mountain roads, you encounter kiln upon kiln. 
</P>
<P>
In one room, an artisan with Popeye-sized forearms throws a slab of gray earth 
onto a spinning wheel and -- presto -- a shape is born. In another, 12-year-old 
apprentices carve intricate designs onto "leather-dried" pots, while older 
artists inlay chiseled crevices with white or black slip, depending upon the 
master potter's whim. The day that storerooms fill with trimmed pots the real 
feat begins -- the glaze. 
</P>
<P>
Of Koryo celadon's three distinguishing features (shape, design and glaze) the 
latter is the most important and the hardest to achieve. It is perhaps the 
delicate serenity of the celadon glaze -- never opaque, always soft and 
transparent -- that most distinguishes the beauty of Koryo pieces. 
</P>
<P>
How a color so lush could emerge from elements as common as flower petals, red 
clay and wood ash is a factory secret. While the precise composition of the 
iron-oxide-based glaze varies from kiln to kiln, all masters share in one 
tradition -- they reveal their formulas only to their heirs. 
</P>
<P>
The best celadons bake in pine-burning kilns that arch like dormers onto 
Ichon's wooded mountainsides. Some reproductions are fired in electric ovens, 
but modern methods, while more predictive, fail to capture the luster of 
medieval Koryo -- especially the soft sparkle caused by melted particles and 
bubbles imprisoned within the glaze. 
</P>
<P>
Master potters preferring ancient ways heat with pine even though only one in 
10 of their intricately prepared pots will survive. Those that do are 
expensive. 
</P>
<P>
If you visit Ichon, you might want to take along a rabbit's foot or two. When 
the kilns begin to smoke, a cloud of superstition wafts across the hills. 
</P>
<P>
Believing that spirits reside not only in humans but in natural forces and 
inanimate objects, Korean potters call on ancient shaman symbols to ensure a 
successful outcome. Some hire mudangs (sorceresses) to perform ceremonies 
(kuts) to shake off demons. Others offer food -- pig's heads on tridents -- to 
get good spirits on their side. 
</P>
<P>
Spells notwithstanding, fall firings are festive occasions. Besides good buys 
(especially on pots judged imperfect for gallery sale), Ichon offers insights 
and experiences not shared in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- -- -- 
</P>
<P>
The best approach to <LOCATION>Ichon</LOCATION>, 35 miles southeast of <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, is via bus tour or 
private car. Your hotel concierge can put you in touch with one of the many 
Korean travel agents who offer day trips to Ichon and nearby <LOCATION>Kwangju</LOCATION> 
(Kyonggi-do province). 
</P>
<P>
If you are not the bus-tour type, a chauffeur-driven car can be arranged 
through your hotel. Most car-rental agencies, such as <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>'s Hertz-affiliated 
<ORGANIZATION>Daehan Rent-a-Car</ORGANIZATION>, provide drivers. The daily rate (10 hours) for driver and 
car is <MONEY>$80</MONEY>, plus tolls for the first 77 miles. After that, the rate changes to 
<MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> a mile, plus <MONEY>$6</MONEY> an hour. 
</P>
<P>
While foreigners can obtain rental cars without drivers, most do not -- 
especially when traveling outside <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. Country road signs are only in Korean, 
so persons not fluent in Hangul are advised to pay the modest chauffeur's fee. 
</P>
<P>
About 40 kilns are spread out along the Kwangju-Ichon highway. Most feature 
showrooms in addition to factories. The most famous are Chi Sun-t'aek's at 409, 
Sugwang-ri Shindun-myon, <LOCATION>Ichon</LOCATION>, and Yoo Keun-hyeong's at 323-4, Sugwang-ri, 
Shindun-myon, Ichon. 
</P>
<P>
In addition to pottery, Ichon is noted for its hot springs. Just off the main 
highway at 313-5-Anhung-ri, Ichon-up, is the town's famous resort spa -- Hotel 
<PERSON>Seol Bong</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Besides offering some of <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>'s best spa facilities, the hotel features both 
Western and Korean cuisine. 
</P>
<P>
For more information on travel to <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, contact the <ORGANIZATION>Korea National Tourism 
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, 510 West 6th St., <ORGANIZATION>Suite</ORGANIZATION> 323, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 90014, (213) 623-1226. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Inlaid celadon porcelain is a celebration of nature's grace. ; Photo, 
The tradition of celadon is being reproduced by potters today. ; Photo, 
Visitors to Korea may find a rich art in folk dance beyond the ancient world of 
celadon porcelain. ; Map, South Korea, LIGAYA GRITZ / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900801-0180 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-01-90 1937EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-China-Archeology 1stLd-Writethru a0589 08-01 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Archeology, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0589,0504</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ancient Burial Site with 40,000 Figurines Found in China</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to ADD details on new find, background. No
pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archeologists have unearthed a 2,000-year-old
burial site containing 40,000 pottery figurines in the ancient
capital of <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION>, said a report seen <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>.
   The site is estimated to contain more than five times the number
of terracotta figurines found buried with the first Chinese
emperor, <PERSON>Qin Shi Huang Di</PERSON>, whose tomb is also in <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Xinmin
Evening News of Shanghai</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The discovery of the ancient army of terracotta warriors
guarding Qin's tomb was one of the great archaeological finds of
modern times. It has turned <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION>, in western <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, into one of the
country's major tourist attractions.
   The newly discovered burial site dates to the Han dynasty, or
between 206 A.D. and 220 B.C.
   Archaeologists have uncovered 11 pits the past two months, the
newspaper said. Each pit measures an average of 13 feet wide, 23
feet deep, and dozens of yards long, the newspaper said.
   The more than 300 figurines excavated so far are all male, naked
and about 24 inches tall, it said. Each was exquisitely crafted
with smooth, flowing lines and attention paid to such details as
eyes, eyebrows, nose, lips, ears, hairstyle and muscles, it said.
   Experts believe that bits of silk cloth that were also found at
the site indicate the figurines originally were clothed in silk,
but their costumes have disintegrated over 2,000 years, the
newspaper said.
   Qin's terracotta army was discovered by peasants from a local
commune who were digging a new well to irrigate their parched soil
in <DATE>March 1974</DATE> following a winter drought.
   Hundreds of thousands of foreign tourists visit <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION> each year
to see the museum built around the pits containing the colorfully
dressed, life-size terracotta figures of archers, infantrymen and
cavalry, which guard the emperor's tomb, about two miles away.
   The terracotta warriors have yielded invaluable clues to the
dress, weaponry, military organization and physical appearance of
the era.
   Pieced together by experts, the armored warriors and their
horses, stand in formation, rank by rank. Each of the sand-colored
statues has a different facial expression and hair style.
   The finds over the years have included bronze and wooden
chariots, a variety of weapons, as well as drums and gongs used to
give command signals to troops in battle.
   The museum is about 20 miles east of <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION>, now the capital of
<LOCATION>Shaanxi Province</LOCATION>, a city of 2.9 million people, about 660 miles
southwest of <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>.
   Starting point of the ancient Silk Road to the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION> and
its environs was the cradle of Chinese civilization under 11
dynasties from the 11 century <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION> to 907 <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION>, when the city was
the largest in the world with more than 1 million people.
   Qin unified scattered Chinese kingdoms into a single nation in
221 B.C. and died a year later.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880422-0237 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-22-88 2200EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Pyramids     04-22 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Pyramids,0509</SECOND>
<HEAD>French Team Discovers Tombs of Pharaoh's Wives</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two small pyramids built for the wives of <PERSON>Pharoah
Pepi</PERSON> I were discovered under mounds of sand by French scientists
who say the find could shed light on a dynasty that ruled <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>
more than 2,000 years before <PERSON>Jesus</PERSON> was born.
   The discovery was announced <DATE>Friday</DATE> by members of the <ORGANIZATION>French
Archaeological Mission</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION> and scientists from <LOCATION>Electricite
de France</LOCATION>, the state-owned utility which conducted a high-tech
exploration at the site about 20 miles south of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION> site contains the step pyramid built by <PERSON>King Zoser</PERSON>,
said to be the first stone structure in history, and other
pyramids. The discovery of the queens' tombs brings to 85 the
number of known pyramids in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.
   One pyramid is in ruins, but the second could contain
subterranean funeral chambers decorated with hieroglyphics, said
<PERSON>Jacques Montlucon</PERSON>, who led the utility's team.
   In the <DATE>19th century</DATE>, the 50-acre <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION> site served as a quarry
from which stone was taken for building in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>. For the last 25
years or so, extensive digging around the pyramid of Pepi I has
left a field of rubble at the site.
   ``It looks like a battlefield there,'' said <PERSON>Montlucon</PERSON>, adding
that the pyramids were covered by ``eight meters (about 26{ feet)
of rubbish.''
   ``In such disturbed land, it would be practically impossible to
find anything, to know where to begin to dig, without our current
technology,'' he said.
   Last <DATE>summer</DATE> Montlucon supervised the conservation of artifacts
retrieved from the wreck of the Titanic.
   He said the electromagnetic tests used at <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION> were developed
by the French utility for conducting geophysical tests at potential
nuclear reactor sites.
   Using test results, the team put together a map pinpointing five
possible pyramid sites. Three sites were then excavated.
   The first hole revealed a highly decorated mastaba, or tomb, of
a dynastic official. Weeks passed before workers finally hit the
stone of a pyramid on <DATE>Feb. 12</DATE>.
   ``I was in the big pyramid when the foreman came running in
shouting `Mabrouk!' (congratulations),'' <PERSON>Montlucon</PERSON> said. ``I felt
so happy I could have cried.''
   Workers dug out a ``buttonhole'' through which they could see a
segment of the pyramid wall, smooth and gold in color. The French
archaeological team will ask permission from the <ORGANIZATION>Eygptian
Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION> to begin full excavation next year on the
pyramid, thought to be 66 feet tall and 66 feet at the base.
   The find is ``a big gain for Egyptology'' and ``will allow us to
know more, possibly a great deal more, about the 6th Dynasty'' that
ruled the <ORGANIZATION>Nile Valley</ORGANIZATION> from <DATE>2420</DATE> to <DATE>2258</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>B.C.</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Montlucon</PERSON> said.
   Archaeologists are hoping the pyramid contains hieroglyphic
inscriptions that can be added to the Pyramid Texts, the oldest
writings known to man. The archaeologists also hope the writing
will reveal the name of the pharaoh's wife, shrouded by the
centuries, who is buried there.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-4201 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi059_k_94010" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-059 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<F P=101> Political &amp; Social </F>
<H3> <TI>   Preserving Minority Cultures Said Urgent Task </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  HK2803091894 Beijing CHINA DAILY in English 28 Mar 94 p 4 </F>
<F P=103> HK2803091894 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing CHINA DAILY </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By staff reporter <PERSON>Zhang Xia</PERSON>: "Successes Mixed With </F>
Anxiety"] 
  [Text] The distinctive cultures of the 55 minority 
nationalities in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> are preserved on paper, stones, wood or 
just plain passed on orally from generation to generation. 
  "This is an indispensable part of the treasure-house of 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s history, and it is urgent to rescue and protect this 
precious heritage," said <PERSON>Li Dongsheng</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>State Nationalities 
Affairs Commission</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>SNAC</ORGANIZATION>). 
  <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has always attached great importance to protecting 
minority culture. 
  As far back as <DATE>1952</DATE>, Premier <PERSON>Zhou Enlai</PERSON> suggested collecting 
and publishing ancient books of ethnic minorities. But due to 
the ensuing political chaos, the work did not start until the 
<DATE>1980s</DATE>. 
  In <DATE>August 1984</DATE>, upon <ORGANIZATION>State Council</ORGANIZATION> approval, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Nationalities Affairs Commission</ORGANIZATION> started to prepare for the 
collection and research of ancient books of minorities published 
before the Qing Dynasty (1644-1911). 
  Offices, research centres and publishing houses were set up 
in 24 provinces and autonomous regions, with money coming from 
regional revenue. 
  Generally, ancient books refer to those written before the 
Qing. Since some minorities have a short history, books written 
in their language before <DATE>1949</DATE> are also included, according to Li. 
  These books cover a wide range of fields: philosophy, 
literature, history, astronomy, medicine, architecture, music 
and painting. 
  Research found that the Yi nationality boasts 10,000 volumes 
of ancient publications. A book on medicine, included more than 
370 prescriptions. Investigations show it was finished 17 years 
earlier than the <ORGANIZATION>Compendium of Materia Medica</ORGANIZATION>, a world-famous 
book on medicine written by <PERSON>Li Shizhen</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Ming Dynasty</ORGANIZATION> 
(1368-1644). 
  <LOCATION>Mongolia</LOCATION> and Man nationalities, founders of the Yuan 
11271-1368) and Qing dynasties, left large numbers of official 
documents in addition to folk tales. These documents have 
far-reaching significance in historical studies of the two 
dynasties. 
  The collection and publication of these books help minority 
nationalities better know their own history. 
  It also signifies the equality of all nationalities. 
  "The work, however, is tough and urgent," said <PERSON>Li Dongsheng</PERSON>. 
  Few people are expert at all minority languages. 
  Naxi nationality, scattered in the <LOCATION>Lijiang</LOCATION> area of <LOCATION>South 
China</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Yunnan Province</LOCATION>, created a hieroglyph called the Dongba 
character. It got its name from its use to record religious 
rites by <ORGANIZATION>Naxi</ORGANIZATION> celebrants, called Dongba in the local language. 
  Only a few old Dongba can read these pictographic 
characters. 
  In <DATE>1981</DATE>, an institute was established in <LOCATION>Lijiang</LOCATION> to rescue 
the precious cultural relics of Naxi nationality. The institute 
invited several old Dongba as instructors and provided 10 
university graduates for them. 
  With it the pronunciation and content of more than 1,000 
Dongba books have been recovered and more than 300 books have 
been translated into Mandarin Chinese. The books also disclosed 
eight Dongba rituals. 
  Some minority nationalities, on the other hand, do not have 
written languages. Their history is passed down orally. 
  In the past decade or so, the <ORGANIZATION>Snac</ORGANIZATION> has invested money and 
manpower to recover their history, legend and folk tales. 
  From <DATE>1986</DATE> to <DATE>1990</DATE>, more than 1,000 books about 30 
nationalities were published, their academic value attracting 
world attention. 
  Research institutes of Chinese minorities have also been 
established in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 
  During the past 10 years, more than 1,000 foreigners have 
visited the Dongba culture research institute in <LOCATION>Lijiang</LOCATION>. Two 
foreign students are studying in the institute for their 
doctor's degree. 
  A national conference on the collation of ancient 
nationality 
books will be held this year, according to Li. At the 
conference, relevant rules and regulations will be worked out to 
provide long-term guidelines for the work. 
  Li said the collection and collation work needs to be 
further 
improved. 
  In the past decade, both the central and local governments 
have provided financial help to the collection and collation of 
these books, <PERSON>Li</PERSON> said. In the future, more money is expected to 
be allocated to meet the increasing need. 
  On the other hand, local research institutes should actively 
tap resources on their own to collect funds, Li suggested. 
  Inner <ORGANIZATION>Mongolia Autonomous Region</ORGANIZATION> set a prime example in this 
regard. In recent years, it has cooperated with the People's 
Republic of <LOCATION>Mongolia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> on minority nationality 
cultural studies. Many books in the Mongolian language were 
jointly published by them. 
  There is a lack of professional personnel in the collection 
and collation work. Until now, no university has set up this 
major. Only short-term training classes have been opened at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Central University for Nationalities</ORGANIZATION>, according to Li. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031389-0094 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 30442 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 13, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1446 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SCIENCE / MEDICINE; 
</P>
<P>
ANSWERS FROM ANTIQUITY; 
</P>
<P>
A SCHOLAR AND A SCIENTIST COMBED THROUGH ANCIENT SCROLLS THAT RESULTED IN NEW 
FINDINGS ABOUT EARTH'S ROTATION AND THE DAWN OF CHINESE CIVILIZATION. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ASHLEY DUNN, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Buried deep in an ancient Chinese book called "The Bamboo Annals" is a passage 
about an unusual double dawn nearly 2,900 years ago: "In the first year of the 
reign of <ORGANIZATION>King Yi</ORGANIZATION>, in the first month of <DATE>spring</DATE>, the sun rose twice in Zheng." 
</P>
<P>
The passage describes what is believed to be a solar eclipse viewed in the <ORGANIZATION>9th 
Century</ORGANIZATION> BC from the now-dead city of Zheng. 
</P>
<P>
For centuries, scholars have seen this terse report as a strange but minor part 
of the annals, an ancient history book discovered by grave robbers 1,700 years 
ago. 
</P>
<P>
But from this passage, <PERSON>Chou Hung-hsiang</PERSON>, a professor of Chinese at <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>, and 
astronomer <PERSON>Kevin D. Pang</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> launched an unusual 
two-year search that has led to a series of findings about the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s rotation 
and the dawn of Chinese civilization. 
</P>
<P>
By matching Chinese astronomical records dating back 3,900 years with computer 
simulations of the movements of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and moon, they have determined the 
rate of the planet's gradually slowing rotation within thousandths of a second. 
</P>
<P>
Their report was published recently in the British journal Vistas in <LOCATION>Astronomy</LOCATION>. 
While other researchers have done similar studies using Arabian and Babylonian 
eclipse records, none have been able to go as far back into history as <ORGANIZATION>Chou</ORGANIZATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Pang</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
According to their research, the length of a day was 22-thousandths of a second 
shorter in AD 532, 42-thousandths of a second shorter in 899 BC, and 
70-thousandths of a second shorter in <DATE>1876</DATE> BC. 
</P>
<P>
Using the same method, the two researchers believe they also have established 
or confirmed the dates of several events in Chinese history. 
</P>
<P>
Their research focused on the period when <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> was divided into the <LOCATION>Shang</LOCATION>, 
<PERSON>Zhou</PERSON> and Xia kingdoms, known collectively as the Three Dynasties. Scholars have 
never been able to determine the exact time of their rule and many question 
whether the Xia Dynasty even existed. 
</P>
<P>
But by matching astronomical records with historical accounts, <PERSON>Chou</PERSON> and Pang 
believe they have determined the reign of several rulers in the Three Dynasties 
period and the beginning of the legendary <ORGANIZATION>Xia Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Chou and <ORGANIZATION>Pang</ORGANIZATION> began their search after hearing about research to determine the 
planet's rotational speed using Arabian and Babylonian eclipse records. 
</P>
<P>
They knew the same could be done with Chinese accounts, and that it would take 
the research much further back into the past. 
</P>
<P>
Out of thousands of eclipses recorded over the centuries, they chose three that 
fell outside of the years covered by Arabian and Babylonian accounts. 
</P>
<P>
The first step was to determine an approximate date for the eclipses, since 
there are no recorded dates in Chinese history before 841 BC. 
</P>
<P>
In the case of the double dawn, the task was easy, since <PERSON>King Yi</PERSON> was only two 
generations removed from that time. By assigning 30 years for each generation, 
they estimated the first year of King Yi's reign to be around 901 BC. 
</P>
<P>
By using <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION>'s computers, they simulated the movement of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and moon 
backward through time toward the double dawn. 
</P>
<P>
While they found hundreds of eclipses within a century of that date, there was 
only one, which occurred on <DATE>April 21</DATE>, 899 BC, whose path was in line with the 
city of Zheng. 
</P>
<P>
"You could go forward 2,000 years and backward 2,000 years and you wouldn't 
find another one," <PERSON>Pang</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
There was one problem: If they assumed each day was exactly 24 hours, the 
eclipse should have occurred 5 hours and 48 minutes later and would have been 
seen in the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> instead of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The discrepancy was caused by a phenomenon that astronomers have long known 
about: that each day, in fact, is not exactly 24 hours long. Because of 
atmospheric friction, tidal action and the movement of molten rock in the 
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s core, the planet's rotation has been gradually slowing, meaning that 
days were slightly shorter in the past. 
</P>
<P>
To put the eclipse over Zheng 2,900 years ago, <PERSON>Chou</PERSON> and Pang calculated that a 
day had to have been 42-thousandths of a second shorter than today. 
</P>
<P>
Using the same method, <PERSON>Chou</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Pang</ORGANIZATION> analyzed an eclipse recorded in the 
1,400-year-old History of the <LOCATION>Northern Wei Kingdom</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"In the first year of the tai-chang reign period (of the reign of <ORGANIZATION>King Chu</ORGANIZATION>), on 
the day xin-you (the 58th day in a 60-day cycle), or the first day of the 10th 
lunar month, the sun from beneath the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> eclipsed and began to wane from the 
southwestern horn." 
</P>
<P>
They set the date of the eclipse at <DATE>Nov. 13</DATE>, AD 532, and calculated that the 
length of the day was 22-thousandths of a second shorter than today. 
</P>
<P>
The final eclipse that <PERSON>Chou</PERSON> and <PERSON>Pang</PERSON> studied is the oldest recorded in Chinese 
history. 
</P>
<P>
According to the <ORGANIZATION>6th Century BC</ORGANIZATION> "Book of Documents," a compilation of 
historical treatises on the Xia, <PERSON>Shang</PERSON> and Zhou dynasties, the eclipse took 
place during the fifth year of the reign of <PERSON>King Zhong Kang</PERSON>, the fourth king of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Xia Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"On the first day of the <DATE>last month of autumn</DATE>, the sun and the moon did not 
meet harmoniously in fang (the fourth lunar mansion). The blind musicians beat 
their drums and the lower-ranked officers and common people bustled and ran 
about." 
</P>
<P>
The passage provided several important clues. The eclipse was seen in a part of 
the sky known as fang, which roughly corresponds to the location of the 
constellation Scorpio. It was viewed in the <DATE>last month of autumn</DATE>, which in the 
Xia calendar is the same as modern month of <DATE>October</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The computer again found hundreds of possible eclipses within a few centuries 
of the estimated date of <PERSON>King Zhong Kang</PERSON>'s reign. 
</P>
<P>
But only one was visible from <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> during <DATE>October</DATE> and located exactly in the 
fourth lunar mansion of fang. "It satisfied all the criteria," <PERSON>Pang</PERSON> said. "It 
was the only one possible." 
</P>
<P>
Pang and Chou set the date of the eclipse at <DATE>Oct. 16, 1876</DATE> BC, which would put 
the beginning of <PERSON>King Zhong Kang</PERSON>'s reign in the year 1881 BC. 
</P>
<P>
There are no other eclipses recorded before <PERSON>King Zhong Kang</PERSON>'s time, but there 
was an unusual clustering of planets that allowed Chou and <ORGANIZATION>Pang</ORGANIZATION> to journey even 
further back in history to the origins of the <ORGANIZATION>Xia Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The five-planet conjunction, described in the <PERSON>Gu Wei Shu</PERSON>, a 2nd Century BC 
compilation of astronomical writings, was of one of the most spectacular in 
recorded history. 
</P>
<P>
"During the reign of King Yu (first king of the Xia Dynasty), five planets 
lined up clearly like a string of pearls, brightly burning like joined jade 
disks." 
</P>
<P>
Chou and <ORGANIZATION>Pang</ORGANIZATION> ran a computer simulation of planetary orbits back through time 
and found that <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION>, Mars and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> did indeed cluster in 
the sky above the Xia capital of Yangcheng on <DATE>Feb. 23, 1953</DATE> BC. 
</P>
<P>
"It has never been that close and never in that straight a line," <PERSON>Pang</PERSON> said. 
"You could put your thumb up and it would block them out." 
</P>
<P>
Their simulation matched a previously published report by <PERSON>David W. Pankenier</PERSON>, 
assistant professor of Chinese at <ORGANIZATION>Lehigh University</ORGANIZATION>, that proposed <DATE>1953</DATE> BC as 
the beginning of the <LOCATION>Xia Dynasty</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It could be very exciting if we finally know the beginning of Chinese 
civilization," said <PERSON>K. C. Chang</PERSON>, professor of Chinese archeology at <ORGANIZATION>Harvard 
University</ORGANIZATION>. "Their findings are of great interest." 
</P>
<P>
Chou and <ORGANIZATION>Pang</ORGANIZATION> believe they will be able to date a few more points in the 
chronology of the Three Dynasties using other Chinese accounts of astronomical 
events. 
</P>
<P>
Pankenier has already used a similar technique to date two other planetary 
conjunctions that he believes establishes the fall of the <ORGANIZATION>Shang Dynasty</ORGANIZATION> shortly 
after <DATE>1059</DATE> BC and the end of the <ORGANIZATION>Xia Dynasty</ORGANIZATION> around 1576 BC. 
</P>
<P>
But modern researchers are far from unanimous in accepting any of these dates. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>David S. Nivison</PERSON>, a retired professor of Chinese philosophy at <ORGANIZATION>Stanford 
University</ORGANIZATION> and an expert on the chronology of the <ORGANIZATION>Three Dynasties</ORGANIZATION>, said that 
using ancient Chinese texts is fraught with problems. 
</P>
<P>
Erroneous words have been copied into the texts, events have been distorted for 
symbolic purposes, and efforts by ancient historians to reconstruct the past 
have created gross errors. 
</P>
<P>
Compounding this problem is that most historians have only a limited 
understanding of astronomy, and most astronomers have little skill in wading 
through the complexities of ancient texts. 
</P>
<P>
But despite the problems, <PERSON>Nivison</PERSON> and others say that using modern astronomical 
techniques to date the past holds enormous promise and, except for the 
discovery of new archeological finds, may be the only way to recover the 
long-lost chronology of the Three Dynasties. 
</P>
<P>
"I think there is going to be a lot more agreement in the future over dates 
because of the use of scientific methods," <PERSON>Nivison</PERSON> said. "But don't 
underestimate the ability of scholars to argue and argue and argue." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, UCLA Professor Chou Hung-hsiang, left, and Jet Propulsion Lab astronomer 
Kevin D. Pang with some of the ancient materials used in their research about 
the earth's rotation. The bamboo screen is a copy of early Chinese writing done 
before the invention of paper. LARRY BESSEL / Los Angeles Times; Map, Shaded 
area shows path of the eclipse of the sun on April 21, 899 BC that created the 
legendary "double dawn" in the now-dead city of Zheng. Los Angeles Times ; 
Drawing, Below, the unusual conjunction of five planets as seen from Yangcheng 
in 1953 BC. In one of the most spectacular astronomical events in recorded 
history, Jupiter, Venus, Mercury, Mars and Saturn appeared in the twilight sky 
"like a string of pearls." Computer simulation of both events helped determine 
that the earth's rotation is slowing. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
EARTH (PLANET); CHINA -- HISTORY; ARCHEOLOGY -- CHINA; SOLAR ECLIPSES; 
ASTRONOMY; GEOLOGY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880830-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-88 0337EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AncientTomb     08-30 0514</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ancient Tomb,0529</SECOND>
<HEAD>4,000-Year-Old Funeral Boat Gently Moved into Elaborate Museum
Tomb Scene</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL A. DRISCOLL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly 4,000 years after it was built, the
funeral boat of one of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s most powerful pharaohs takes another
journey this week.
   The delicate, 32-foot long, wooden craft was gently lifted off
the floor of the <ORGANIZATION>Field Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> and
rotated 180 degrees. Expert riggers who performed the tricky
maneuver kept their hands off, fearing sweat or body oils would
harm the ancient wood.
   Today, the boat used in the funeral of King Sen-wosret III in
about <DATE>1850</DATE> B.C. will be moved inch by inch a few yards to its new
setting in the museum _ a <MONEY>$2.2 million</MONEY> permanent exhibit.
   When the exhibit opens in <DATE>November</DATE>, it will allow visitors to
walk through the eerie world of tombs, mummies, shrines to cat
goddesses and other treasures from ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>. The museum said
the exhibit would give visitors the only opportunity outside <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>
to enter and explore a life-size tomb complex.
   King Sen-wosret's boat _ a graceful, crescent-shaped canoe-like
craft _ is but one of more than a thousand artifacts and treasures
from the museum's collection used to recreate the burial scenes.
   Visitors enter the tomb chambers of the 5th Dynasty pharaoh,
<PERSON>King Unis</PERSON>, dating to <DATE>2400</DATE> B.C. and excavated from <LOCATION>Saqqara</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>,
in <DATE>1908</DATE>.
   Beneath a false door, a 35-foot burial shaft takes visitors into
the dark and eerie burial chamber. The sarcophagus is empty. When
it was excavated, the pharaoh's mummy was gone, stolen by robbers
or destroyed by time.
   Leaving the burial chamber, the visitor passes through a roughly
hewn tomb robbers' tunnel and into another scene depicting a
variety of Egyptian burial rites.
   ``This could well be the most fascinating part of the exhibit,''
said its developer, <PERSON>Janet Kamien</PERSON>. ``It gives them (visitors) a
chance to explore the age-old mysteries of mummies and life after
death.''
   Next month, the museum staff will move 23 mummies into the
exhibit, along with the accouterments their souls were to take with
them to the afterworld.
   Sen-wosret's boat will be displayed nearby.
   No one actually knows if the boat was used to transport the
king's body across the <LOCATION>Nile River</LOCATION> to the burial site, said <PERSON>Frank
Yurco</PERSON>, a scholar on ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Oriental Institute</ORGANIZATION> and a
consultant on the museum project.
   The boat was one of six found at the burial compound in 1893-94
by <PERSON>Jacques DeMorgan</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Welsh Egyptologist</ORGANIZATION>. Two badly deteriorated
ones were left at the site.
   Two of the four DeMorgan saved are at the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Museum</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>.
   Sen-wosret is remembered for military campaigns that extended
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s boundary into the Nubian region of <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Sudan</LOCATION>,
as well as securing control of the <LOCATION>Nile River</LOCATION> to the south, he said.
   He also centralized the Egyptian government, setting the pattern
for several hundred years.
   Sen-wosret is believed to have died when he was about 50, said
Yurco.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880830-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-88 1923EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AncientTomb     08-30 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ancient Tomb,0598</SECOND>
<HEAD>4,000-Year-Old Funeral Boat Gently Moved into Elaborate Museum
Tomb Scene</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BERNARD SCHOENBURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Inch by inch, with the help of expert riggers,
the funeral boat of one of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s most powerful pharoahs
took another journey <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, to a new <MONEY>$2.2 million</MONEY> museum exhibit.
   Hydraulic jacks, dollies and a forklift were used to move the
fragile, 3,847-year-old wooden boat about 50 yards from a display
section of the <ORGANIZATION>Field Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION> to an exhibit
designed to recreate a pharoah's tomb.
   ``It went very well,'' said <PERSON>Suzanne Santos</PERSON>, a museum spokeswoman.
   Before the move, the 32-foot boat _ a graceful craft resembling
a canoe _ was gently lifted off the floor and rotated so it was
pointing south to its new destination, <PERSON>Mrs. Santos</PERSON> said.
   Riggers who performed the tricky maneuver had to keep their
hands off, so no sweat or body oils would harm the ancient wood.
   The boat, used in the funeral of King Sen-wosret III in about
1850 <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>, now becomes part of a new permanent exhibit called
``Inside Ancient Egypt,'' which opens in <DATE>November</DATE>.
   The actual moving of the boat took about an hour, <PERSON>Mrs. Santos</PERSON>
said.
   The ancient craft has been at the museum since <DATE>1900</DATE>, and for at
least a dozen years has been encased in glass in a room with other
Egyptian artifacts.
   ``It was your typical museum collection,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Santos</PERSON> said.
   The new exhibit will give visitors a feel for ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>,
though glass will still prevent any direct contact with the boat,
she said.
   The exhibit will give visitors their only opportunity outside
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> to enter and explore a life-size tomb complex, with two
burial chambers, mummies and a shrine to the cat goddess Bastet,
the museum said.
   King Sen-wosret's boat is among more than 1,000 artifacts to be
displayed.
   Visitors will enter the tomb chambers of Unis-ankh, son of the
5th Dynasty pharaoh Unis. The chambers date to <DATE>2400</DATE> B.C. and were
excavated at <LOCATION>Saqqara</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1908</DATE>.
   Beneath a false door, a 35-foot burial shaft will take visitors
into the dark burial chamber itself. The sarcophagus is empty. When
the tomb was excavated, the mummy was gone, probably stolen by tomb
robbers.
   Leaving the burial chamber, visitors will pass through a roughly
hewn tomb robbers' tunnel and into a series of Egyptian burial
scenes featuring dioramas, 23 mummies and other artifacts.
   ``It gives (visitors) a chance to explore the age-old mysteries
of mummies and life after death,'' said the exhibit's developer,
<PERSON>Janet Kamien</PERSON>.
   Sen-wosret's boat was one of four excavated in <DATE>1894</DATE> from his
tomb at Dashur by <PERSON>Jacques DeMorgan</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Welsh Egyptologist</ORGANIZATION>, the
museum said. Two are at the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> and the other
   No one knows if Sen-wosret's boats were used to transport his
body across the <ORGANIZATION>Nile</ORGANIZATION> to the burial site, or if they was buried near
the tomb for use in the afterlife by the king's soul, said <PERSON>Frank
Yurco</PERSON>, a scholar on ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Oriental Institute</ORGANIZATION> and a
consultant on the museum project.
   Sen-wosret conducted military campaigns that extended <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s
boundary into the Nubian region of <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Sudan</LOCATION>, as well
as securing control of the <LOCATION>Nile River</LOCATION> to the south, he said. He
also centralized the government, setting the pattern for several
hundred years.
   Sen-wosret is believed to have died when he was about 50, <PERSON>Yurco</PERSON>
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890317-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-17-89 1359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Mummy Bjt   03-17 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mummy, Bjt,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Smiling Mummy Found at Base of Great Pyramid</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An ancient mummy of an aristocratic
young woman, her <PERSON>Mona Lisa</PERSON> smile frozen in a plaster death mask, has
been unearthed in a shallow pit at the foot of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Pyramid of
Cheops</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``She's really lovely,'' said <PERSON>Aly Hassan</PERSON>, director of pharaonic
monuments for the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION>. Hassan dated
the mummy as 4,400 years old, one of the earliest ever found in
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.
   Egyptologists expressed surprise at <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s discovery, noting
the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids area has been looted repeatedly since antiquity
and excavated by some of the greatest archaeologists of the last two
centuries.
   Hassan said the seals of the grave were intact when an
antiquities inspector accidentally found the burial shaft.
   Officials who entered the grave found the mummy. She wore a
bronze crown covered with gold leaf on her head and jewelry around
her neck.
   Jewelry, pottery, wooden items, a piece of glass, flint,
obsidian, a clove of garlic and more than a dozen teeth lay nearby.
The wood and garlic may have been placed in the grave to keep
insects away.
   The mummy was not identified, but <PERSON>Hassan</PERSON> said the woman's
nobility was established both by the finery buried with her and the
site of her burial, a cemetery reserved for officials of the ruling
court.
   She was about 22 years old when she died and stood five feet
tall, <PERSON>Hassan</PERSON> said. He said the body dates from the <ORGANIZATION>Fifth Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>,
which lasted from <DATE>2465</DATE> B.C. to <DATE>2323</DATE> B.C. He said he dated her body
from that dynasty because other bodies in the cemetery were from
that period.
   Her body is so dried out that it has been wrapped in foam for
protection and bound beneath the head.
   <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, director general of the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> area, said the new
mummy might have been an important person reburied for safekeeping
in the shaft where she was found.
   Two vast cemeteries lie under <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>, one with royal tombs
to the east of the <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> pyramid. To the west lies the one with the
new mummy, put into use five years into the reign of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> 4,600
years ago.
   Inspectors have identified the owner of the complex in which the
shaft was found as S-ankh Ptah, but his position under the pharaohs
and his relation with the mummy remain mysteries.
   Egyptologists hope the mummy can provide clues into early
mummification, an art of preservation that spanned more than 3,000
years of Egyptian history into Christian times.
   ``Any find in the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> area in such a condition is a great
addition to archaeology,'' said <PERSON>Hassan</PERSON>. ``This mummy changes our
concept of preservation and mummification and provides a new date
for (it).''
   The earliest true mummy is that of Waty, found in the tomb of a
court singer called Nefer at <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION>. Waty's mummy dates from the
late <ORGANIZATION>Fifth Dynasty</ORGANIZATION> and was preserved so well by resin-soaked
bandages that even a callus on the sole of a foot is visible.
   Egyptians mummified their dead for thousands of years and was
refined over the ages using a solution of naturally occurring
preservative compounds.
   An obstacle to unraveling mysteries that still surround the
mummification process is that the ancients left incomplete pictorial
records of the embalming ritual.
   Some say the art of mummification was too sacred to be revealed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-5029</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFFAXAEDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930605
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  05 JUN 93 / Collecting: Jewels from the East - Susan Moore welcomes an
upcoming feast of Oriental art
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By SUSAN MOORE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
ON TUESDAY, <PERSON>Eskenazi</PERSON> unveils the latest in a long line of spectacular and
scholarly Oriental art exhibitions to celebrate the gallery's move from a
first floor in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s Piccadilly to a five-storey 'Flemish Renaissance'
townhouse off Bond Street, at No. 10 Clifford Street. The acquisition and
refurbishment of the building cost in excess of Pounds 5m and is an
expression of confidence all the more striking given that <PERSON>Eskenazi</PERSON> has no
English clients.
The old premises in <ORGANIZATION>Foxglove House</ORGANIZATION> afforded no storage space, no room for
parallel exhibitions and inadequate wall space for the extensive library.
The restored <DATE>1897</DATE> facade of Clifford Street belies an imaginative,
purpose-built interior of some 12,000 sq ft. There are two gallery floors,
divided front and back to offer up to four independent exhibition spaces.
Moveable, free-standing showcases provide maximum flexibility.
A pool of natural light is brought to the heart of a once gloomy, narrow
building by a new atrium. Natural materials have been chosen throughout:
blond sycamore, French limestone, glass. The effect is cool, airy and
meditative.
For the new gallery, <PERSON>Giuseppe Eskenazi</PERSON> envisions more exhibitions (there
have already been 36 in the last decade), including loan shows, and
'symposia or anything which might interest academics'.
For him, the new building is also 'my way of showing my commitment to
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'. When he left <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION> to open a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> office of the family firm of
Oriental art dealers in <DATE>1960</DATE>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> was the undisputed capital of the art
world. Thirty years on, and thanks to the arguably short-sighted policies of
the auction houses which now move objects around the world to offer them in
their primary markets, it has become just one important centre as <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> have come to rival it in the Oriental art market. But <PERSON>Eskenazi</PERSON>
believes <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> still retains the trump card of unrivalled expertise - in
its museums, universities and art trade.
Significantly, <ORGANIZATION>Oriental</ORGANIZATION> art is one of the few markets in which the auction
houses have failed to wrest the biggest business from the hands of a small
group of top international dealers. Eskenazi may have no English clients,
but it claims the third highest turnover of any <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> dealers. In <DATE>1991-92</DATE>
that was some Pounds 18.5m, a huge sum in Oriental terms.
<PERSON>Eskenazi</PERSON>'s inaugural show is 'Early Chinese Art from Tombs and Temples'
(<DATE>June</DATE> 8-July 9). Some 48 works of art, from a Shang bronze of the 12th-11th
century BC to a Song or Jin wood Bodhisattva of the 12th-13th century AD,
have been selected to represent the breadth and quality of the gallery's
holdings. Collectors with deep pockets will be delighted to find that a
number of prize rarities have been extracted from the company collection.
'We are selling things we had no intention of parting with', says <PERSON>Eskenazi</PERSON>.
Notable among the highlights is an unusually large and superbly modelled
recumbent bronze ox of the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Zhou</ORGANIZATION> period (4th-3rd century BC), inlaid
with scrolls of silver. A partial inscription states that it belonged to the
state treasury of an unknown king. From the Tang dynasty comes a sumptuous
silver reliquary, a vigorous glazed earthenware horse biting its knee and an
imposing amphora, 68cm high, streaked with a sancai glaze of cream, green
and chestnut. Most examples are half its size.
'Japanese Netsuke from the <ORGANIZATION>Carre Collection</ORGANIZATION>' also goes on show, <DATE>June 15-July
9</DATE>. The 243 pieces reflect the collector's particular fascination with the
folklore of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, a subject illustrated so effectively by the netsuke
craftsmen.
Another inaugural show also features a single-owner collection. Swiss dealer
<PERSON>Patrick Syz</PERSON>, formerly of Sarzi-Amade in Bond Street, opens as a private
dealer at <ORGANIZATION>No. 94 Eaton Place</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> SW1 (tel: 071-235-4572) with an
admirable if highly specialist show. He presents 92 of the finest examples
of Japanese sword fittings, or tsuba, from the collection of the American
<PERSON>Henry D. Rosin</PERSON>, <DATE>June 10-25</DATE>. 'It is said to be probably the finest, small,
concise collection outside <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>,' Syz says modestly. Prices Pounds 500 to
Pounds 60,000.
