<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062589-0082 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 74492 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 25, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 12; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
610 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ONLY 600 LEFT OF CENTURIES-OLD CULTURE; 
</P>
<P>
NAMIBIA BUSHMEN STRUGGLE FOR SURVIVAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JEAN-PIERRE CAMPAGNE, Agence France-Presse 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
GAUTCHA, Namibia 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
They call themselves the <PERSON>Ju Wasi</PERSON>, meaning "correct people," and survive in 
eastern <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, descendants of the Bushmen who first inhabited the desert 
there 40,000 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
"We were the first, we have become the last. We must do something quickly," 
said <ORGANIZATION>Tsanko Toma</ORGANIZATION>. He heads a farming cooperative and acts as spokesman for 
about 600 Bushmen in the <LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Since <DATE>1981</DATE>, they have gathered in 14 villages like this one south of Tsumkwe, 
one of the n'lore, their term for "the place we belong to," the land around the 
ancestral watering hole. 
</P>
<P>
The South African administration gave them everything they had never had and 
never desired: a school, a clinic, a church and a prison. But they also 
discovered what they were not expecting: malnutrition, alcoholism, despair, 
early death. 
</P>
<P>
Now they call Tsumkwe "the place of death," said <PERSON>Megam Biesele</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Bushman 
Development Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, a private body aiding the 600 Bushmen. 
</P>
<P>
At the end of the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, several thousand were still hunting and gathering in 
the <LOCATION>Kalahari</LOCATION>. But in <DATE>1960</DATE> the <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION> allocated territory on ethnic 
lines, and the Bushmen lost <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of their land. 
</P>
<P>
Living traditionally in groups of 40 to 50, with no practice of central 
organization and leadership to state their case, they were unsuited to 
competitive society, Megam Biesele explained. 
</P>
<P>
Tsumkwe lies at the end of a sandy 125 miles of arrow-straight road, and the 
sight of humans along the isolated road is like an apparition. 
</P>
<P>
There are a few houses for whites, while the Bushmen live in huts, many around 
the military base of the South African army's 203rd Battalion. 
</P>
<P>
The soldiers have been using more than 500 Bushmen as trackers, but by next 
<DATE>November</DATE> the troops will have left under the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> independence plan for 
<LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>. There will be no more wages for the trackers. 
</P>
<P>
"They are all going to starve," warned American anthropologist <PERSON>John Marshall</PERSON>, 
the creator of the <ORGANIZATION>Bushman Foundation</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Tsanko Toma</PERSON>, who said he was born "somewhere around <DATE>1940</DATE>," is emerging as a 
leader in a society that has no hierarchy of its own. 
</P>
<P>
He started the week in <LOCATION>Windhoek</LOCATION>, the territorial capital, meeting South African 
Administrator-General <PERSON>Louis Pienaar</PERSON> to "set out all the problems of the land." 
</P>
<P>
A particular concern was to voice fears that neighboring Herero tribesmen have 
designs on Bushman lands. 
</P>
<P>
Then he did the rounds of the villages, where the once nomadic Bushmen are 
trying to settle down as farmers and stock raisers, to tell them all he had 
heard. 
</P>
<P>
He made a similar tour after talks with <PERSON>Daniel Tjongarero</PERSON>, head of the internal 
branch of the main black nationalist grouping the <ORGANIZATION>South West Africa People's 
Organization</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
SWAPO, whose guerrilla armed wing took up arms against <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>'s presence in 
the territory nearly a quarter of a century ago, is widely expected to win the 
general election scheduled for <DATE>November</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Tsanko did not know which party he will vote for. It will be "a new day" after 
independence, but the <PERSON>Ju Wasi</PERSON> does not yet know how to take part in government, 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
Fellow tribesman Gaishay, from the cooperative in <LOCATION>Naru Na</LOCATION> village, said he felt 
that none of the political parties was ready to give any thought to the future 
of the Bushmen. 
</P>
<P>
Children and old people watched in the village square as he spoke with the 
foreigners. 
</P>
<P>
As evening drew near, some men and women -- the sexes have always been on an 
equal footing among the Bushmen -- went off to do some hunting. 
</P>
<P>
As they have for thousands of years, they used bows and poisoned arrows. 
</P>
<P>
They are not allowed to have rifles. That is a privilege reserved for white 
tourists who come to shoot elephants and lions in <LOCATION>Bushmanland</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890307-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-89 2040EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--DesertRescue     03-07 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Desert Rescue,0188</SECOND>
<HEAD>Family Rescued After Nine Days in the Kalahari Desert</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GABORONE, Botswana (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pregnant woman, her husband and their
2-year-old son were rescued after being stranded in the <LOCATION>Kalahari
Desert</LOCATION> for nine days, a relative said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Jonathan Hayman</PERSON>, his wife, <PERSON>Laura</PERSON>, and their son, <LOCATION>Romano</LOCATION>, were
driving across the <ORGANIZATION>Central Kalahari Game Reserve</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Feb. 23</DATE> when
their truck broke down, said <PERSON>Lawrence Wright</PERSON>, a cousin of <PERSON>Hayman</PERSON>.
   After three days, the <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> family ran out of food and water
and began walking back toward their hometown of <LOCATION>Serowe</LOCATION>, more than
120 miles away, <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> said.
   The mother and child were too weak to continue after three days,
but <PERSON>Hayman</PERSON>, 24, continued and was found by farm workers <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   A <ORGANIZATION>Botswana Defense Force</ORGANIZATION> helicopter located <PERSON>Mrs. Hayman</PERSON> and her
son, <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> said.
   ``I had given up hope,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Hayman</PERSON>, 23. ``I thought we
were both dead.''
   She said she and her son survived by sucking the moisture off
plants during the night. Daytime temperatures in the <LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION>
often reach above 100 degrees time of year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890807-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-07-89 0150EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Namibia-Tribes     08-07 0842</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Namibia-Tribes,0871</SECOND>
<HEAD>Independence Approaches, but National Unity may be Elusive</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WINDHOEK, Namibia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the golden glow of the <LOCATION>Kalahari
Desert</LOCATION>, the Bushmen live in nomadic simplicity virtually unchanged
for thousands of years.
   At the seaside resort of <LOCATION>Swakopmund</LOCATION>, descendants of German
settlers converse in their mother tongue over wiener schnitzel and
beer at sidewalk cafes.
   In the dusty town of <LOCATION>Rehoboth</LOCATION>, virtually all 20,000 residents
are of mixed-race and insist on being called ``Bastards.''
   <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s vast, rugged landscape has only 1.3 million people,
but they make up an anthropological laboratory of 11 ethnic groups
who often put tribe before country and are linked not by culture
nor tradition.
   With independence from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> expected early next year,
Namibians still are searching for a sense of nationhood to bond
people who share little but common boundaries.
   Witchcraft cases are tried under a Western legal system.
Mercedes-Benzes and donkey-drawn carts kick up dust along the same
rural roads. Black women with a week's worth of groceries perched
on their heads shop alongside white women in fur coats in this
modern capital.
   At political rallies arranged by the <ORGANIZATION>South-West Africa People's
Organization</ORGANIZATION>, the faction favored to win <DATE>November</DATE>'s
pre-independence elections, speeches are delivered in English, then
translated into four African languages.
   ``<LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION> is not a nation at this point,'' said <PERSON>Hans Diergaardt</PERSON>,
leader of the <LOCATION>Rehoboth Basters</LOCATION>. ``There are too many different
groups that have been kept apart for too long.''
   Diergaardt and his fellow Basters, the Afrikaans-language word
for ``bastards,'' epitomize the stubborn independence that
permeates <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s multi-tribal society.
   The product of liaisons between whites and blacks in <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Cape Province</LOCATION>, the Basters left that region in search of
farmland and independence in <DATE>1868</DATE> and settled the deserted
missionary village of <LOCATION>Rehoboth</LOCATION>, about 60 miles south of <LOCATION>Windhoek</LOCATION>.
   They identify with neither whites nor blacks and have
steadfastly refused to recognize the authority of the German
colonialists or their South African successors.
   They now oppose <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s planned one-person, one-vote elections.
   ``A unitary state in <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION> is not going to work,'' said
<PERSON>Diergaardt</PERSON>, a husky farmer whose weathered face speaks of years
spent in the African sun.
   Diergaardt has threatened to unilaterally declare Rehoboth an
independent state if the Basters are dissatisfied with <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s
elected government.
   For the past several years the Basters have prepared for such a
move by purchasing land that separates their territory from
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> port of <LOCATION>Walvis Bay</LOCATION>, about 180 miles away. They've bought
250,000 acres and need about <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> to secure enough land for a
corridor to the sea, <PERSON>Diergaardt</PERSON> said.
   Like the Basters, the diminutive Bushmen have found little in
common with other Namibians.
   Entirely self-sufficient, the Bushmen thrive in the seemingly
inhospitable Kalahari with extraordinary hunting and gathering
skills.
   They are among the most primitive people on earth, rarely
building fixed settlements or making regular contact with other
groups.
   Most of <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s 30,000 Bushmen have begun to join the modern
world, including hundreds employed by the South African-led
security forces as trackers in the 23-year-old bush war against
<ORGANIZATION>SWAPO</ORGANIZATION> guerrillas.
   Equally untouched by Western culture are the Himbas of <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s
barren northwest corner, who wear minimal clothing and smear their
bodies with a rancid mixture of butter and ochre that gives them a
distinctive orange tint.
   The Himbas have repeatedly rejected Western missionaries, while
their cousins, the Hereros, accepted them to such an extent that
the women still dress in brightly colored <DATE>19th-century</DATE> Victorian
dresses that seem incongruous in <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s scorching climate.
   Most of the original missionaries and settlers were Germans,
whose influence remains strong.
   The <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> town of <LOCATION>Swakopmund</LOCATION> features turn-of-the-century
German architecture set against the alien terrain of the <ORGANIZATION>Namib
Desert</ORGANIZATION>. Visitors are more likely to be greeted in German than the
official languages of English and <LOCATION>Afrikaans</LOCATION>.
   German descendents, who account for about 20,000 of <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s
75,000 whites, are prominent in business throughout the territory,
but generally stay out of <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s tangled politics, which until
recently included 47 parties.
   Far from <LOCATION>Swakopmund</LOCATION>'s European charm, the Kavango people of
northeastern <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION> remain wedded to tribal customs.
   In one case, a suspected Kavango arsonist received the
traditional punishment from his tribal elders _ he was ordered to
dig his own grave then lie in it, where he was buried alive,
according to court records.
   Three tribal elders were convicted of the killing, but received
only suspended sentences.
   Suspected witches have been thrown into rivers with stones tied
around their necks. If they drown, it is considered proof they were
witches; if they survive, then they were falsely accused, according
to tradition.
   <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION> abandoned most of its segregation laws in the <DATE>late
1970</DATE>'s and early <DATE>1980</DATE>'s, and the racial climate is more relaxed
than in neighboring <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   But under <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> rule, <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s tribal differences were
formalized with the creation of 11 separate ethnic governments that
had considerable autonomy.
   <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>'s first independent government will face the difficult
task of establishing itself as a national authority that remains
sensitive to local customs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-6224</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DH2AOADUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930828
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  28 AUG 93 / Books: Mystic meditations
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By WILLIAM ST CLAIR
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE VOICE OF THUNDER by <PERSON>Laurens</PERSON> van der <ORGANIZATION>Post Chatto &amp; Windus Pounds 15.99</ORGANIZATION>,
229 pages
SIR LAURENS van der <ORGANIZATION>Post</ORGANIZATION> has led a life of adventure - soldier in the
jungles of the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>, explorer of the deserts of <LOCATION>Southern Africa</LOCATION>, great
white hunter. Like a character in a <PERSON>John Buchan</PERSON> novel, he is equally at home
in tent and palace, welcomed, trusted and consulted as sincerely in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>
as in <LOCATION>Belgravia</LOCATION>.
Unlike the predecessors who trampled uncomprehendingly over local cultures,
he was sensitive and sympathetic. He understood that simple technology does
not imply simple minds; that peoples without books may share rich resources
of legendary traditions; and that those whose lives are precariously
balanced retain an understanding of the changing seasons, the vital force of
rain and sun, our kinship with animals, and other aspects of humanity which
are lost or obscured in the comfortable <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
Van der Post wrote marvellous books. He was quick to exploit television when
it was new and to help change old attitudes. To the post-imperial generation
brought up in this country after the war, as well as to recent
environmentalists and conservationists, <PERSON>Laurens</PERSON> van der Post is a modern
hero.
His new book The <ORGANIZATION>Voice of Thunder</ORGANIZATION> brings together two pieces written some
years ago,'The Little Memory' and 'The Great Memory', and a recent essay,
'The Other Journey'. The earlier pieces are classic van der Post, part
autobiography, part good yarn about the desert, interspersed with
observations and speculations about how the bushmen of the Kalahari see the
world and how we can share their wisdom.
The new essay has no narrative, it is an old man's meditation on the story
of the Odyssey, the perpetual cycle of departure, return and departure which
he sees as intrinsic to all lives.
As he has grown older, van der Post's mystical streak has become more
pronounced. He is sure he has a message to pass on, but it is hard to pin
down what exactly it is. The ancient Greeks would have recognised his awe at
the power of nature as a sense of the divine, Pan in the woods, Nereids in
the <LOCATION>Ocean</LOCATION>, without implying a personal deity or an intended discoverable
design. The romantic poets shared his vision of the mountains, the torrents
and the deserts as metaphors of the tempests and aridities of life. Jung,
whom van der Post knew personally, suggested the concept of the collective
unconscious, the cumulative effect of heredity and experience, which is
unique to each individual but of which a good deal is also shared with other
human beings.
Van der <ORGANIZATION>Post</ORGANIZATION> sees a revealed secret in the urge of the unconscious to become
conscious. Perhaps, he suggests elsewhere, everything in the universe is
synchronised. The metaphor of a journey can give shape to recurring patterns
in human lives. Mixing personal experience with fragments of science, myth
and literature, drawing on a quotation here and a famous name there, van der
Post constantly risks appearing banal and confused. He is a remarkable man,
but wonderment and benevolence are not, by themselves, enough to make a poet
or a philosopher.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2731 Book Publishing.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XVI
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880913-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-13-88 1554EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pope Bjt   09-13 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope, Bjt,0558</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Calls On Catholics To Help Discrimination Victims</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GABORONE, Botswana (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Standing on <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s doorstep,
Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> called on the people of this desert nation
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to assist victims of racial discrimination who are
``deprived of their legitimate rights.''
   The pope, on a one-day visit to diamond-rich and bone-dry
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, praised the nation as ``an island of peace in a troubled
sea.''
   <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, a landlocked country of 1.1 million people, has never
fought a battle in its 22 years of independence despite bordering
such turbulent places as <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South-West Africa</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   ``You are a peace-loving and friendly people who believe in the
basic equality and human dignity of every man and woman,'' the
pontiff told about 2,000 people who greeted him at the airport,
including a choir of bare-breasted, teen-age schoolgirls.
   Later, in a speech at the Cathedral of Christ the King, the
pontiff clearly referred to <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and its apartheid policies
of racial segregation, without mentioning the country by name.
   ``You have witnessed the plight of those who are subjected by
law to discrimination,'' the pontiff told the audience in <LOCATION>Gaborone</LOCATION>,
10 miles from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s northern border. ``I gladly support
your desire to be close to those who are unjustly deprived of their
legitimate rights and lack decent living conditions.''
   The pope arrived <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, the first stop on his
five-nation tour of southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.
   He travels <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to <LOCATION>Lesotho</LOCATION>, a mountain kingdom surrounded
by <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, where he is likely to make additional comments on
apartheid. The pontiff is not visiting <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> on this trip
but the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> has said he may do so in the future.
   At an afternoon mass in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s national stadium, <PERSON>John Paul</PERSON>
renewed his call for regional peace to a crowd of 50,000 _ more
than <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s entire Catholic population of 45,000. Several
thousand of those attending were from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, according to
church officials.
   ``What are the causes of humanity's fears?'' the pontiff said.
``It is the absence of justice and peace in our lives, and in the
world, that so often troubles us and arouses our fears.''
   ``Nation still lifts sword against nation. There is much
training for war,'' he said.
   <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> has raided <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> several times in past years
killing alleged guerrillas of the <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   The pope was serenaded by several hundred members of a women's
choir and received gifts from Catholic parishes around the country.
Two parishes from western <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> brought crosses they had carried
by foot and car across the Kalahari desert, which makes up <PERCENT>80
percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> has a Western-style, multiparty democracy, a rarity in
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. Diamond mines make it relatively wealthy on the continent
but it remains heavily dependent economically on <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   On papal matters, the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the pope would return
to <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> next year, with stops in <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> and the island nation
of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>.
   There has been speculation that the trip, expected next <DATE>May</DATE>,
also may include <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Joaquim
Navarrro</PERSON>, traveling with the pope, said neither country was ``on
the program,'' although he confirmed that Angolan bishops had
recently sent an invitation to the pope.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891007-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-07-89 2014EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Botswana-Election     10-07 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Botswana-Election,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Botwana, in the Eye of Africa's Storm, Holds Elections</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GABORONE, Botswana (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters stood in long lines under
pouring rain <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to vote for a new Parliament for <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>,
one of the few African nations with regular, multiparty elections.
   The conservative <ORGANIZATION>Botswana Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> was expected to
retain its comfortable majority. It has governed this diamond-rich
country since independence from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> 23 years ago and supervised
a capitalist economy that has made <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> one of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s most
prosperous states.
   Eight political parties contested the elections. The polls
closed at <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> but final results were not expected until <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   There were no reports of turnout. About 360,000 people over the
age of 21 were eligible to vote.
   It was the sixth general election in this landlocked country in
southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> country since independence in <DATE>1966</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>, now led by President <PERSON>Quett Masire</PERSON>, has won
all the elections. It held 28 of the 34 seats in the former
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>.
   The socialist <ORGANIZATION>Botswana National Front</ORGANIZATION> held five seats and
controls the city council in <LOCATION>Gaborone</LOCATION>, the capital of this nation
of 1.2 million people.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Botswana People's Party</ORGANIZATION> had one parliamentary seat, which it
was expected to lose. The other five parties were not expected to
win any seats.
   Masire's party was expected to maintain its advantage because of
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s booming economy, which has grown at least <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>
annually through the <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   Diamonds from the <LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION>, along with cattle ranching,
provide most of the wealth.
   When <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> gained independence it was among the world's 20
poorest nations with a per capita annual income of less than <MONEY>$100</MONEY>.
Today the average yearly income is more than <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>, one of the
highest in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.
   On a continent crippled by foreign debt, <ORGANIZATION>Botwana</ORGANIZATION>'s government
has spent cautiously. The country has foreign reserves in excess of
<MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>.
   Masire, who has been president since <DATE>1980</DATE>, has avoided large,
expensive public works projects and his administration concentrated
on small-scale development.
   In foreign affairs, his government has been critical of <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>'s policies of racial discrimination, but it has kept close
business ties with its powerful southern neighbor.
   <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s army has never fought a battle, even though the
country is surrounded by such tumultuous lands as <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Botswana National Front</ORGANIZATION> has said it can win seats in larger
towns where jobs and houses are in short supply. The front also
claims <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s wealth has not reached ordinary workers and
declaried it would establish more social welfare programs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880218-0006 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS: TV: Oriental Intrigue, African Fauna, American Music </HL>
<AUTHOR> Martha Bayles </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 20</DATE>, <TIME>8-10 p.m. EST</TIME>, on HBO (repeated <DATE>Feb. 24</DATE> and 29, and <DATE>March 3</DATE>, 6 and 8): "<LOCATION>Baja Oklahoma</LOCATION>." 
In <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, an attractive, 40ish barmaid (<ORGANIZATION>Lesley Ann Warren</ORGANIZATION>) encounters an old flame (<PERSON>Peter Coyote</PERSON>), who expresses his regret for having dumped her 20 years ago and offers to help revive her faded dream of becoming a country-music songwriter. 
Can she trust him? 
The plot, taken from the novel by <PERSON>Dan Jenkins</PERSON>, sounds like typical TV-movie fare. 
But the writing, script, country music and local color (never mind local off-color) are outstanding. 

   <DATE>Sunday-Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 21-24</DATE>, <TIME>9-11 p.m. EST</TIME>, on <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>: "<PERSON>James Clavell</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Noble House</ORGANIZATION>." 
Here are just a few of the stars promised to twinkle in this high-gloss miniseries set in modern <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>: <PERSON>Denholm Elliott</PERSON>, <PERSON>Pierce Brosnan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Deborah Raffin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ben Masters</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Rhys-Davies</PERSON>, <PERSON>Khigh Dhiegh</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gordon Jackson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Nancy Kwan</PERSON>. 

Just south of <PERSON>Victoria Falls</PERSON>, in the <LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION> in northern <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Okavango River</LOCATION> forms an extraordinary inland delta. 
This three-part "Nature" miniseries presents the history of the area and its amazingly rich flora and fauna, including bat-eared foxes, dancing ostriches, shrimp-eating flamingos and leaping bush babies. 

   Tuesdays, <DATE>Feb. 23</DATE> and <DATE>March 1</DATE>, <TIME>8-9 p.m. EST</TIME>, on PBS: "Battles in the War on Cancer." 
Remember Interleukin-2, the miracle cancer drug that made headlines back in <DATE>1985</DATE>? 
The first part of this special edition of "NOVA" examines the mounting costs of testing this (or any) new drug, while the second part brings more heartening news about better detection and treatment of breast cancers. 

   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 24</DATE>, <TIME>8:30-9 p.m. EST</TIME>, on PBS: "Not Your Average Russian: The Pozner File." 
Having grown up in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Vladimir Pozner</PERSON> has spoken to us in fluent media-babble on many occasions calling for "expert" Soviet commentary. 
Until recently, he did so as an official spokesman for Gosteleradio, so it's puzzling to see a <ORGANIZATION>PBS</ORGANIZATION> press release call him "the unofficial voice of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>." 
Perhaps by scrutinizing this documentary, we can figure out whose "Pozner file" the film makers used. 

   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 24, 9-10</DATE><TIME>:30 p.m. EST</TIME>, on PBS: "<PERSON>Billy Galvin</PERSON>." 
Like the <ORGANIZATION>HBO</ORGANIZATION> film mentioned above, this tale of Irish blue-collar <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> has a predictable TV-movie plot: generational conflict between an independent son (<PERSON>Lenny Van Dohlen</PERSON>) and his strong-willed father (Karl Malden). 
But also like the <ORGANIZATION>HBO</ORGANIZATION> film, this "American Playhouse" presentation offers a rich sense of place. 
The language is wonderful, and the actors even rise to the challenge of approximating the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> accent! 

   <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 26</DATE>, 9-10<TIME>:30 p.m. EST</TIME>, on PBS: "Wolf Trap Salutes Dizzy Gillespie." 
<PERSON>Oscar Peterson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Carmen McRae</PERSON>, <PERSON>Benny Carter</PERSON> and other jazz greats gathered last <DATE>June</DATE> to pay tribute, on his <DATE>70th birthday</DATE>, to the man with the rubber cheeks and the tip-tilted horn. 
The show also includes excellent film clips of past performances with the likes of <PERSON>John Coltrane</PERSON> and <PERSON>Charlie Parker</PERSON>. 

   <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 27</DATE>, 10 p.m.-midnight EST, on PBS: "Firing Line Special Edition: The Next First Lady." 
No, the hosts of this interview program -- <PERSON>William F. Buckley Jr.</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Strauss</PERSON> -- do not know who the next First Lady will be. 
But they will be talking with all the possibilities, except <PERSON>Jacqueline Jackson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON>. 

   <DATE>Sunday-Monday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 28-29</DATE>, <TIME>9-11 p.m. EST</TIME>, on CBS: "Bluegrass." 
That graceful filly <PERSON>Cheryl Ladd</PERSON> plays a would-be member of the high-stepping <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> horsebreeding set, only to be thwarted by a colicky, bad-tempered stud played by <PERSON>Wayne Rogers</PERSON>. 
But she's got the right bloodlines and the best training, and soon leaves her dainty hoof prints in all the right places. 

   <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 29</DATE>, <TIME>8-9 p.m. EST</TIME>, on CBS: "Superman's 50th Anniversary: A Celebration of the Man of Steel." 
Muhammad Ali, <PERSON>Hal Holbrook</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jimmy Breslin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lee Salk</PERSON> and many others will sing the praises of this icon of American popular culture, in an extravaganza produced by "<DATE>Saturday</DATE> Night Live" creator <PERSON>Lorne Michaels</PERSON>. 

   <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 29</DATE>, <TIME>9-11 p.m. EST</TIME>, on <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>: "Perfect People." 
In order to star in this confection about "two middle-aged couch potatoes" who strive for physical beauty by embarking on an incredible ordeal of diet, exercise, plastic surgery, hair transplants and liposuction, actors <PERSON>Lauren Hutton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Perry King</PERSON> had to embark on an incredible ordeal of skullcaps, hairpieces, false jowls, makeup and body-altering prosthetics. 

   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 1</DATE>, <TIME>9-11 p.m. EST</TIME>, on CBS: "The 37th Annual Miss USA Pageant." 
Speaking of perfection and incredible ordeals, don't miss these 51 fine young things strutting their stuff in old <LOCATION>El Paso</LOCATION>. 

   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 2</DATE>, <TIME>8-11 p.m. EST</TIME>, on CBS: "The 30th Annual Grammy Awards." 
If you get argumentative about the success of <PERSON>Steve Winwood</PERSON>'s comeback, or about whether <LOCATION>Los Lobos</LOCATION> is more authentic than <PERSON>Suzanne Vega</PERSON>, watch this prestigious music awards show. 
If you never heard of these people, tune in and find out who they are, and what's been happening this year in pop (and a little bit about jazz and classical) music. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891008-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-08-89 1614EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Botswana-Election     10-08 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Botswana-Election,0315</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ruling Party Appears To Have Easy Win</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GABORONE, Botswana (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Botswana Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>, which
has governed this diamond-rich nation since independence in <DATE>1966</DATE>,
retained a comfortable majority in <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION>, according to partial
returns <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The party captured all 19 districts where final results were
available for the elections, and it appeared set to add to its
majority in <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION>. Prior to <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s balloting, the party
held 28 of the 34 seats.
   The left-leaning <ORGANIZATION>Botswana National Front</ORGANIZATION> was expected to retain
at least four of its five seats. The <ORGANIZATION>Botswana People's Party</ORGANIZATION> lost
its lone seat.
   This peaceful, southern African nation is one of only a few on
the continent to hold regular, multiparty elections. <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s
polls were the sixth since <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> gained independence from
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> 23 years ago.
   President <PERSON>Quett Masire</PERSON> and his Democratic Party retained their
comfortable majority on the strength of <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s surging
capitalist economy, which has grown at least <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> annually
throughout the <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   Diamonds from the <LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION>, along with cattle ranching,
account for most of the wealth in this thinly populated desert
nation of 1.2 million.
   When <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> gained independence it was among the world's 20
poorest nations, with a per capita annual income of less than <MONEY>$100</MONEY>.
Today the average yearly income is more than <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>, one of the
highest in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.
   At a time when many African nations are crippled by huge foreign
debts, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s government has spent cautiously and has foreign
reserves in excess of <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>, enough to pay for more than two
years of imports.
   Masire, president since <DATE>1980</DATE>, has avoided expensive public works
projects and concentrated on small-scale development.
   The opposition <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> argued that <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s wealth has
not reached the ordinary workers and called for an increase in
public spending and the creation of more social programs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032590-0066 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 194592 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 25, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 29; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1021 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FINDING YOUR OWN COMFORT ZONE IN ONE GEM OF A COUNTRY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Lyndon Stambler 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> is a peaceful country of 1.2 million people, most of whom live along 
the eastern border with <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
If all you saw was the <DATE>1980</DATE> South African movie "The Gods Must Be Crazy," you 
might think of this country as primitive and backward. Most of <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> is 
blanketed by the <LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION>, where bushmen still hunt with arrows as they 
have for centuries. 
</P>
<P>
because it provides <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> of the world's gem diamonds. 
</P>
<P>
My Okavango excursion was the highlight of a 12-day loop through southern 
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. It began in <LOCATION>Harare</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>. We traveled south to <LOCATION>Francistown</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, northeast to <PERSON>Nata</PERSON> and west to <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION>. After the canoe voyage we headed 
northeast to <ORGANIZATION>Chobe National Park</ORGANIZATION> and on to <LOCATION>Victoria Falls</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
This trip was the rough way to see the <ORGANIZATION>Okavango Delta</ORGANIZATION>, and it's not for 
everyone. There are many more comfortable ways to go. Whether you fly to <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION> 
and stay in a luxury camp or drive in a Land-Rover and camp out, you won't 
likely be disappointed once you get to the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Getting There: If you're driving, you need a four-wheel-drive vehicle; the 
190-mile stretch from <ORGANIZATION>Nata</ORGANIZATION>, which is halfway between <LOCATION>Francistown</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION>, is 
made of a chalky gravel. Coming from <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, as I was, <LOCATION>Francistown</LOCATION> is the 
first major town, about 58 miles southwest of the <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> border. 
</P>
<P>
A good stop-off point is <ORGANIZATION>Nata Lodge</ORGANIZATION> (Private Bag 10, <LOCATION>Francistown</LOCATION>) six miles 
south of <PERSON>Nata</PERSON>. The lodge has good accommodations and a nice restaurant. I 
stayed in the campground behind the lodge for five pula (about <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY>). Thatched 
huts and tented rooms also are available. Tented rooms cost slightly more than 
the campground; the huts are 60 pula (<MONEY>$30</MONEY>) a night. 
</P>
<P>
If you're flying to <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION> you will likely have to go through <LOCATION>Gabarone</LOCATION>, the 
capital of <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>. Carriers serving the area include <LOCATION>Air Botswana</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>British 
Airways</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Zambia Airways</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Air Zimbabwe</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>South African Airways</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Safari Options: Once you reach <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION> there are basically two ways to see the 
delta: the mobile or the fly-in safaris. I took a mobile safari. We took our 
own camping gear and provisions. 
</P>
<P>
Island Safari Lodge (P.O. Box 116, <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> 300) charges 40 pula a day 
for a three-person canoe and 95 pula for a return motorboat trip into the 
<ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>. We stayed in the <LOCATION>Island Safari</LOCATION> campground for five pula, but Island 
Safaris also offers lodging (47.50 pula per person double, 80 pula per person 
single), a restaurant (dinner is 18 pula), a bar, a swimming pool and a little 
movie theater. 
</P>
<P>
Other operators in <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION> are Crocodile Camp (Box 46) and the <LOCATION>Okavango River 
Lodge</LOCATION> (Box 32, <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION>). It's also possible to hire your own poler and mokoro out 
of <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The fly-in safaris offer a more comfortable way to see the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>. These 
companies fly you from <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION> to an exclusive, semi-permanent camp, treat you 
like royalty and take you out on daylong canoe trips. Amenities include 
thatched or tented lodging with comfortable beds, mosquito netting, lighting, 
bathrooms and showers (with hot water), plus a restaurant, bar and movie 
theater. Meals and laundry service are often included. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Gametrackers International</ORGANIZATION> (1000 <PERSON>E. Broadway</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Glendale</LOCATION> 91205, toll-free (800) 
252-0493) offers an eight-day package through northern <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, including a 
stop at <LOCATION>Victoria Falls</LOCATION>, for <MONEY>$2,725</MONEY> (low season, <DATE>March 1</DATE> through <DATE>June 30</DATE>) or 
<MONEY>$2,925</MONEY> (high season, <DATE>July 1</DATE> through <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>). 
</P>
<P>
Desert and <ORGANIZATION>Delta Safaris Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> (16179 E. <LOCATION>Whittier Blvd.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Whittier</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> 90603, 
(213) 947-5100) offers an eight-night itinerary for <MONEY>$2,274.65</MONEY> per person, with 
a minimum of four people. A six-night itinerary costs <MONEY>$1,537.05</MONEY> per person 
(minimum of four). 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Ker Downey Selby</PERSON> (13201 <ORGANIZATION>Northwest Freeway</ORGANIZATION>, Suite 800, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION> 77040, 
(800) 231-6352) offers a nine-day trip for <MONEY>$1,952</MONEY>. The company also does fancy 
mobile safaris for <MONEY>$660</MONEY> a day for two people, or <MONEY>$460</MONEY> a day per person. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Okavango Tours &amp; Safaris</ORGANIZATION> (P.O. Box 39, <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION>) operates <ORGANIZATION>Delta Camp</ORGANIZATION>, an 
exclusive camp with everything provided, and <ORGANIZATION>Oddball</ORGANIZATION>'s, something in between a 
fly-in and a mobile safari. Oddball's flies you into a semi-permanent camp on 
the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> (110 pula for return), but you must take your own food and camping 
gear (7.50 pula a night for camping). For 30 pulas a day you can also hire a 
mokoro through <ORGANIZATION>Oddball's</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
When to Go: I took my trip in <DATE>May</DATE>, a good time to see the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> but perhaps not 
the best time to see animals. The <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> was in full flood, and it was 
beautiful. The end of the dry season, <DATE>September</DATE> and <DATE>October</DATE>, is peak 
animal-viewing season, but also peak tourist season. It's a good idea to make 
reservations well ahead. 
</P>
<P>
Health: Malaria is the main concern. Consult a physician and begin taking 
anti-malaria medication one week before entering the area. Take mosquito 
repellent and netting. Make sure to keep all of your tent flaps closed until 
you go to sleep for the night. 
</P>
<P>
Tsetse flies are in the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>, but they usually aren't a problem, mainly 
because of spraying to reduce their population. There are insect repellents 
that are effective against the flies. 
</P>
<P>
If you drink water straight from the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>, you should boil or filter it. 
</P>
<P>
What to Take: If you're camping, you need to take all of your gear. Most fly-in 
operators will supply everything. You should also take sun block, sunglasses, a 
hat and neutral-colored clothing (to avoid frightening the animals), plus 
binoculars, a good camera with a telephoto lens, and film. 
</P>
<P>
Miscellaneous: <DATE>Last July 1</DATE> Botswana raised fees for non-residents at its 
national parks from 5 pula to 30 pula a day, and as much as 50 pula a day for 
organized tours. 
</P>
<P>
If you're visiting the <ORGANIZATION>Okavango Delta</ORGANIZATION> it would be a shame not to also visit 
<ORGANIZATION>Chobe National Park</ORGANIZATION>. In addition, <PERSON>Victoria Falls</PERSON> is across the border in 
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, and in <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>, and should not be missed. 
</P>
<P>
A good source of invaluable information for traveling on the cheap around 
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> is "Africa on a Shoestring" by <PERSON>Geoff Crowther</PERSON> (Lonely Planet, <MONEY>$24.95</MONEY>). 
</P>
<P>
For more information on travel to <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, contact the <ORGANIZATION>Botswana Embassy</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>4301</DATE> 
<ORGANIZATION>Connecticut Ave. N.W.</ORGANIZATION>, Suite 404, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 20008, (202) 244-4990. 
<PERSON>Lyndon Stambler</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Sidebar 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-13352</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DAXAVAE1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930123
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  23 JAN 93 / Travel Focus - Africa: North Luangwa now open - Practical
Traveller / Safaris
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MICHAEL J WOODS
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   THE TRACKS were very fresh in the off-white talc of the dusty path
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
there was an African hunting dog not far ahead. We set off on foot, treading
silently and hardly daring to breathe. We had barely reached the bend in the
track which led through thick mopane scrub when the wild dog doubled back
and met us face to face. We had walked into the middle of a hunt.
This was one of those chance encounters which turn an African safari from a
holiday into an adventure. One way of maximising the chances of such
encounters is to choose your destination carefully. With more areas opening
up for visitors, opportunities are increasing.
<LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>South Luangwa</LOCATION> national park has long been noted for its walking
safaris and its exciting night drives, while <LOCATION>North Luangwa</LOCATION> has only recently
been opened to visitors, although on a limited scale. <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION> was one of the
pioneers of walking safaris. They are generally well planned and full of
interest.
<ORGANIZATION>Abercrombie &amp; Kent</ORGANIZATION>, Worldwide Journeys and Expeditions, <ORGANIZATION>Twickers World</ORGANIZATION>, and
Art of Travel all go to <LOCATION>Luangwa Valley</LOCATION>, but of these only Art of Travel
specifically includes <LOCATION>North Luangwa</LOCATION>. Expect to pay Pounds 1,855 and up for
14 days.
While the walks in <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION> take you from one fixed camp to another, <PERSON>Richard
Bonham</PERSON>'s walking expeditions into <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION>'s enormous Selous game reserve
are more in the traditional safari mould. Strings of porters are used, and
you sleep under the stars. Worldwide Journeys and Expeditions offers these
safaris from Pounds 3,950.
The traditional theme is repeated elsewhere in <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> where Gibbs Farm
Safaris takes clients into the vast grass seas of the <LOCATION>Serengeti</LOCATION>. Camping in
luxury tents, you will not see another vehicle in spite of the open country.
<PERSON>Nigel Perks</PERSON>, who runs GFS, has an uncanny knack of finding the most elusive
of animals. These safaris can be booked through Art of Travel, while
<ORGANIZATION>Twickers World</ORGANIZATION> has fly-in safaris to the Serengeti from Pounds 2,615 for 17
days.
A destination that has become much more accessible now that <ORGANIZATION>Air Namibia</ORGANIZATION>
operates direct flights from <LOCATION>Heathrow</LOCATION> is <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>. With its good road
network, this southern African country makes an excellent destination for a
fly-drive tour. Etosha national park has plenty of elephant, black rhino and
lions, and a stay at <LOCATION>Okaukuejo</LOCATION>, with its floodlit water hole, is not to be
missed.
One country to rejoin the safari scene recently is <LOCATION>Uganda</LOCATION>, which has
gorillas. The borders of <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rwanda</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Uganda</LOCATION> meet in the volcanic
massif which forms the last stronghold of the mountain gorilla. It is
particularly good to see that gorilla-watching in <LOCATION>Rwanda</LOCATION> is possible again
now, as the continued conservation of these primates depends so much on
western visitors. Twickers World has a 23-day tour including visiting
chimpanzees in <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> from Pounds 1,675, while <ORGANIZATION>Abercrombie &amp; Kent</ORGANIZATION> has a
four-day add-on to a standard safari for around Pounds 1,021.
Mana Pools national park on the banks of the <LOCATION>River Zambezi</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> is
not only excellent for walking but is one of the highlights of a canoe
safari down the <LOCATION>Zambezi</LOCATION>, a leisurely way to see game, especially hippos and
crocodiles, at quite close quarters.
In turn, overland transport comes in many forms. <ORGANIZATION>Abercrombie &amp; Kent</ORGANIZATION> offers a
traditional ox-wagon safari on the shores of <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Lake Naivasha</LOCATION> (two
days, Pounds 480 ex-Nairobi), or a camel safari in northern <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> (three
days, Pounds 307 ex-Nairobi), while there is the opportunity to explore
parts of the Kalahari desert in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> on all-terrain vehicles.
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Okavango delta</ORGANIZATION>, a rich mixture of glittering channels, clear
lagoons, water-lilied pools and sandy, palm-treed islands, has never been
easy to travel around. One way is to take an unhurried safari in traditional
mokoros, dug-out canoes, which are poled through the placid waters of this
enormous labyrinth of waterways by local guides, with an occasional walk on
one of the thousands of islands.
Telephone numbers: <ORGANIZATION>Abercrombie &amp; Kent</ORGANIZATION>, 071-730-7795; Art of Travel:
071-738-2038; British Airways Holidays: 0293-611611; Dragoman: 0728-861133;
Explore Worldwide: 0252-319448; Exodus Overland: 081-675-7996; Guerba
Expeditions: 0373-826611; <LOCATION>Southern Africa</LOCATION> Travel: 0904-692469; Sunvil
Holidays: 081-568-4499; Twickers World: 081-892-8164; Worldwide Journeys and
Expeditions: 071-381-8638.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>XMZ  Africa.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999  Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
    P70  Hotels and Other Lodging Places.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment and Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XI
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881114-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-14-88 1258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Charles Bjt   11-14 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Charles, Bjt,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>Charles Turns 40 with Tongue Tucked Firmly in Cheek</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BIRMINGHAM, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> donned a ``Life Begins
at 40'' button and poked fun at his eccentric image <DATE>Monday</DATE> as he
celebrated his birthday with 1,500 youths he has helped overcome
poverty and unemployment.
   ``You've given me one of the best birthday parties I could ever
have hoped for,'' the heir to the throne declared after a day that
included champagne toasts, birthday cakes, renditions of ``Happy
Birthday,'' and a princely bit of disco dancing with three of his
guests.
   A ball at <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> for friends and family was scheduled
for the evening.
   Charles used his 40th birthday to launch an appeal for <MONEY>$70
million</MONEY> for the Prince's <ORGANIZATION>Youth Business Trust</ORGANIZATION>, a charity that gives
seed money and professional advice to unemployed people aged 18 to
25 who want to start their own business.
   He chose <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s second-largest city, and spent the
day visiting projects partly financed by his various charities.
   He went to <LOCATION>Handsworth</LOCATION>, an inner city district torn by race riots
in <DATE>1985</DATE>, to inspect <ORGANIZATION>Grove Lane Baths</ORGANIZATION>, which is being converted into
a community center.
   Then he continued to the <ORGANIZATION>Old Tram Depot</ORGANIZATION>, which has been made into
a transport museum. It was festooned with flags, balloons and
antique gaslamps. An old double-decker bus bore the number 40 and
the words ``Happy Birthday Prince Charles.''
   In the cavernous tram depot, the prince was serenaded by calypso
and rock bands, and by hundreds of young people singing a specially
composed paean to Charles: ``Thank you for showing where the road
can lead; If we put our mind to it, in time we will succeed.''
   His mother, <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON>, is in good health at 62, and he
expects a long wait before being crowned <PERSON>King Charles III</PERSON>.
Meanwhile, his search for a meaningful role has transformed him into
a compelling spokesman for <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s needy youth, and a critic of
environmental neglect.
   He also has a penchant for alternative medicine, vegetarianism,
talking to his plants and sojourning among the Bushmen of the
<LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION>. He regards this simply as a measure of his
open-mindedness, and is known to be angry at the way some newspapers
here have exploited his foibles to question his sanity.
   His speech in <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> was a carefully crafted riposte,
frequently interrupted by laughter and cheers.
   ``Only the other day I was inquiring of an entire bed of
old-fashioned roses who were forced to listen to my dementing
ramblings on the meaning of the universe as I sat cross-legged in
the lotus position on the gravel path in front of me,'' he said.
   ``And I was inquiring of them what they thought would happen on
my birthday in a <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> tram shed. `A tram shed?' they all
replied, totally aghast at the thought. Yes, I said, a tram shed.
   ``At this point a row of prize Welsh leeks, cocky little things,
which were lurking in a nearby vegetable patch, chipped in to say
that they expected the shed would be filled with groups of
semi-naked Kalahari Bushmen ... and also a troupe or two of Tibetan
Buddhist monks ... armed with advance copies of the tabloid
newspapers which would be strewn in my path in a form of ancient
Buddhist greeting ...
   ``But looking around here, ladies and gentlemen, I see those
idiotic plants have got it wrong again. I knew they would. Instead,
you've given me one of the best birthday parties I could ever have
hoped for.''
   Gesturing to his lapel button, which he said was given to him by
his two small sons, he said, ``I'm not sure I ought to be reminded
of it, but my children reminded me of it just this day.''
   Of the charities he runs, he said: ``I never imagined for one
minute that they would become big enough to start giving expensive
birthday parties like this one. But it's all, I can assure you,
extremely rewarding and encouraging if you can see just one person's
life transformed by this means.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032590-0057 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 194571 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 25, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 1; Column 6; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1957 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WET &amp; WILD; 
</P>
<P>
AFRICA BY CANOE; 
</P>
<P>
GLIDING AMONG THE RICH WILDLIFE OF BOTSWANA'S OKAVANGO DELTA 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LYNDON STAMBLER, Stambler is a Santa Monica free-lance writer. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MAUN, Botswana 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Later I got used to not caring a damn, just to walking and staying put when I 
had walked far enough, at some village of which I didn't know the name, to 
letting myself drift with <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. -- <PERSON>Graham Greene</PERSON>, "Journey Without Maps" 
</P>
<P>
Drifting with the currents on <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Okavango Delta</ORGANIZATION>, gliding through 
channels choked by papyrus and lily pads is like a journey without maps. 
</P>
<P>
I found myself in unfamiliar territory, not caring about anything but sitting 
back and enjoying the sky, the clouds and the birds as our canoe passed red and 
yellow reeds, swamp grasses, sausage trees and fields of maize. 
</P>
<P>
I watched wallowing hippos, heard the screech of baboons and, in the <TIME>evening</TIME>, 
fell asleep to a symphony of swamp sounds. I was not oblivious to the dangers 
of this watery wilderness, but it was hard to feel threatened in such pristine, 
even hypnotic, surroundings. 
</P>
<P>
Before <DATE>1923</DATE> there were no comprehensive maps of the <ORGANIZATION>Okavango Delta</ORGANIZATION>, a lush 
waterway on the edge of the <LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION>. It's nearly impossible to 
accurately map an area that changes so dramatically with the seasons. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Okavango River</LOCATION>, which begins in the <LOCATION>Angola Highlands</LOCATION>, swells during the 
rainy season (<DATE>November</DATE> to <DATE>April</DATE>) and floods over a depression in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, 
forming the world's largest inland delta: 6,500 square miles of inlets, flood 
plains, lagoons and islands. 
</P>
<P>
I went on a four-day water safari last <DATE>May</DATE>. It was a good time to visit. The 
<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> was in full flood, lush with vegetation, and the weather was dry and warm 
but never too hot. 
</P>
<P>
I saw lots of wildlife, though I probably would have seen more at the end of 
the dry season in <DATE>September</DATE> and <DATE>October</DATE> when herds of animals come to the <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> 
in search of water. 
</P>
<P>
Canoes, which are like water taxis, are the only way to get around much of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. They transport people from village to village, to fishing or hunting 
areas. Polers are the taxi drivers, having grown up navigating the channels. 
They stand in the stern, moving the canoe forward with a long forked pole (a 
ngashi). 
</P>
<P>
 My journey began when two friends -- <PERSON>Katie Janssen</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>John Blank</ORGANIZATION> -- showed up 
at my door in <LOCATION>Harare</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>. They had just finished a year teaching in 
Kenyan villages. I was on a six-month trip to <LOCATION>Harare</LOCATION>, visiting a friend who 
works there. 
</P>
<P>
Katie and <PERSON>John</PERSON> were driving through eastern and southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and suggested a 
trip to the <LOCATION>Okavango</LOCATION> -- the "Serengeti of Swamps" they called it. I was game. 
</P>
<P>
It's hard to stick to a timetable when you're traveling in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> in a '67 Land 
Rover. Every time we hit a rut I braced myself to avoid hitting my head on the 
roof. We stalled each time mud splashed on the spark plugs, which was often. 
</P>
<P>
It took three days to make the 700-mile trip to the <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. We passed through 
customs behind a huge bus of Zimbabweans going to <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> to shop. 
</P>
<P>
Later, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> soldiers stopped us at a roadblock. They were apparently making 
a routine check for South African secret agents who conduct undercover 
operations in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, trying to find <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> guerrillas. 
They let us pass. 
</P>
<P>
After a long drive along the northern edge of the surprisingly lush <LOCATION>Kalahari 
Desert</LOCATION> it was a relief to see water. We had reached <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION>, the gateway to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION> is a patchwork of old and new, with posh hotels going up next to 
traditional villages. 
</P>
<P>
Herero women, refugees from <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, wander the streets dressed in colorful 
long dresses adopted from 19th-Century German colonists, but decorated with 
African patterns. 
</P>
<P>
Our home base was 7 1/2 miles north of <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Island Safari Lodge</ORGANIZATION>. We shared a 
campsite with several <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION> speaking <LOCATION>Afrikaans</LOCATION>. They tried to convince 
us that apartheid doesn't exist, and that they weren't such "bad guys." They 
regaled us with tales of traversing the African bush. 
</P>
<P>
But we were more interested in water and canoes than Afrikaner tales. So we 
decided to hire a canoe and poler for four days through Island Safaris, at the 
lodge. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kay Potter</PERSON>, who operates the lodge with her husband <PERSON>Phil</PERSON>, recommends using 
Fiberglas canoes rather than the traditional mokoros, which are carved from 
sausage trees. 
</P>
<P>
"You have to chop down a sausage tree to make a mokoro," she said. "Before long 
the trees will be gone. Besides, you get a wet bum in a mokoro. I guarantee 
it." We were to get "wet bums" anyway. 
</P>
<P>
The next day a speedboat took us into the <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. As we went deeper, the winding 
pathway through the lily pads grew narrower. The boatman moved expertly through 
the tortuous channels at breakneck speed. Every so often he would stop and 
reverse the motor, when the prop became clogged with reeds. 
</P>
<P>
After two hours we reached an island inhabited by polers who were sitting 
around a fire making coffee in tin cans and cooking mielie meal. Mielie meal, 
the staple food in <LOCATION>sub-Saharan Africa</LOCATION>, is like thick grits. It fills you up but 
won't put meat on your bones. A telltale sign: There wasn't an overweight man 
among the polers. 
</P>
<P>
They didn't pay much heed to us when we arrived. But eventually <PERSON>Kenneth Monare</PERSON>, 
a tall, barefoot man wearing shorts and a blue T-shirt, approached us. He would 
be our pilot and guide for the next four days. 
</P>
<P>
We were lucky. Kenneth spoke English and enjoyed practicing it with us. He also 
taught us a few <LOCATION>Setswana</LOCATION> phrases. Although English is the official language of 
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Setswana</LOCATION>, a Bantu language of the <LOCATION>Tswana</LOCATION> tribe, is spoken by <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of 
its population. 
</P>
<P>
Monare's friend Kid, a shorter man wearing a <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> jacket, piloted the other 
canoe in our party, which also included a Canadian couple who were traveling 
around the world. 
</P>
<P>
When the polers were ready, we glided out into a channel bound for Chief's 
<LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>, the main island in <ORGANIZATION>Moremi Wildlife Reserve</ORGANIZATION> (set up by the <LOCATION>Tswana</LOCATION> tribe 
in <DATE>1962</DATE> to protect the animals) and one of the best game reserves in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Kenneth stood in the stern and began rhythmically poling us forward. The prow 
of the canoe parted the reeds that sprouted like stubble from the water. 
Sometimes a spider, while stretching a web between the reeds, would fall into 
our canoe. 
</P>
<P>
The spiders were fat, dark and fuzzy, though non-poisonous. We would either 
toss them out of the canoe or carry them along with us to another part of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. The webs were often so beautiful that I felt sad, as if we had destroyed 
a work of art. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> is a palette of colors: yellow water lilies, white and pink flowers 
against the reeds, tiny green frogs on lily pads. 
</P>
<P>
When we passed another canoe <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> would greet his fellow poler with a hearty 
"dumela!" ("hello" in <LOCATION>Setswana</LOCATION>). I marveled at how he could navigate the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> 
maze in which channels become dead ends clogged by vegetation. Some of the 
channels are kept open only because hippos break through the reeds. 
</P>
<P>
We reached our first campsite on Chief's <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION> after three hours and a bit too 
much sun. Later, we took the canoe out to get water for cooking and to 
photograph the sunsets. The nights, what with the campfires and the stars, 
reminded me of my childhood camping trips. 
</P>
<P>
When we were quiet we were treated to a cacophony of exotic sounds: the screech 
of baboons . . . hippo grunts . . . the plaintive songs of crickets, frogs, 
birds . . . an insect that sounded like the tinkling of a toy piano, and the 
eerie cackling of hyenas. 
</P>
<P>
As we brushed our teeth we saw two yellow eyes of a bush baby, a nocturnal 
primate, staring at us through the trees. 
</P>
<P>
The sounds of mosquitoes were considerably less exciting. I was glad that I was 
wearing mosquito repellent and taking anti-malaria medication. Malaria is the 
main hazard in the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>. It's unlikely that one would be bitten by tsetse 
flies, crocodiles, lions, leopards or poisonous snakes, but anyone who goes 
into the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> and doesn't take precautions against malaria is foolish. 
</P>
<P>
In the morning <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> took us to another spot on the northern part of Chief's 
<LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>, a place that abounds with game. We passed a deep pool where hippos were 
wallowing. Kenneth and Kid kept their distance. I was aware that an angry hippo 
could smash a canoe to bits. But <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON>, with typical African tour guide 
aplomb, said there was little danger. 
</P>
<P>
"They're very frightened," he said, as a snort came up from a hippo. Nine times 
out of 10 he's right. Of course I'd hate to be too close on that occasion when 
a hippo does decide to charge. 
</P>
<P>
As we approached our destination <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> and Kid found that the channel had 
shifted and was only a few inches deep. The thick swamp grasses made it 
impossible to move forward. After a futile effort, <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> gave us the command: 
"Get out!" 
</P>
<P>
We rolled up our pants legs and began to push the canoes through the reeds. We 
splashed through the mushy swamp. Now, I'm not one who particularly enjoys 
sticking his feet into swamp water. I had visions of leeches covering my 
calves. I feared it might be time for the crocodiles to have a picnic. I guess 
I identify more with <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON> than <ORGANIZATION>Indiana Jones</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
We reached our campsite tired but exhilarated. I looked back at the area we had 
just crossed -- a field of tans and yellows fading into the blue sky. 
</P>
<P>
This part of the island was deserted except for the animals. We followed 
<PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> on walking safaris. He led us for hours as he followed smells, tracks 
and droppings through the brown grass and gnarled trees. He had to quiet us 
several times to avoid frightening the animals. 
</P>
<P>
At one point, after hours of walking, he put up his hand to halt us. Several 
zebra, wildebeest, tsesebe antelope and warthogs came out in front of us, no 
more than 10 feet away. 
</P>
<P>
We were on the trail of an elephant. We could smell its musk-like odor but we 
never found it. I had seen elephants before, but always from the safety of a 
vehicle. I feared the possibility of coming face to face with one of the huge 
animals. 
</P>
<P>
But we probably were safe in <LOCATION>Kenneth</LOCATION>'s hands. He had a keen sense of the smells 
and sounds of the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> -- where to go and, perhaps more important, where not 
to go. His calm and self-confidence was reassuring. 
</P>
<P>
On our <TIME>last night</TIME> I realized why <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> wanted Kid to come along. They joked 
and laughed together, making the trip relaxed and fun for all of us. But Kid 
was also a master fisherman. He took a drop line, crouched by the water's edge 
and snared 20 fish. 
</P>
<P>
Kid and <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> used four of the fish to make a stew for themselves, and saved 
the rest for their fellow polers. I feared that perhaps the fish would be the 
appetizer and we would be the main course for some predator -- a leopard, 
baboon or hyena, whose jaws are said to be the strongest of all animals. 
</P>
<P>
Indeed, hyenas are known to attack humans while they sleep, which is why it's 
important to keep your tent flap zipped up. But in the morning the fish were 
still dangling on the line. 
</P>
<P>
Kenneth showed us his calloused hands, which told the story of his years as a 
poler. The lodge pays him 5 pula (about <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY>) a day plus food. (Passengers are 
expected to tip their poler at the end of the trip.) 
</P>
<P>
He told us that someday he would like to own his own mokoro. But you need to 
pay a teacher 200 to 300 pula to show you how to build one. Besides that, 
<PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> had to think about saving enough pulas to someday pay for a bride. 
Payment to the parents of the bride used to be in cattle; now you can pay in 
pulas (or VCRs in some parts of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>). 
</P>
<P>
I was happy I didn't have to worry about a bride's price. Then again, I would 
soon return to a complex world of jumbo jets and grid-locked cities, and 
somehow the life of the poler seemed more civilized and appealing. 
</P>
<P>
As we rode back to the <ORGANIZATION>Island Safari Lodge</ORGANIZATION> in a powerboat at what now seemed 
like a frenetic pace, I hoped that there would always be room in this world for 
the polers, expertly plying the uncharted delta waters. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Above, polers guide visitors through the Okavango Delta,; Photo, 
COLOR, often close to native fauna such as the crocodile.(right); Map, 
Botswana, VICTOR KOTOWITZ / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Main Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-8111</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EEVAPAE9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940521
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  21 MAY 94 / Books: Meditations of the sage for today - JDF Jones reviews
an anthology of the work of Sir Laurens van der Post
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JDF JONES
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
FEATHER FALL: AN ANTHOLOGY by <PERSON>Laurens</PERSON> van der <ORGANIZATION>Post Chatto &amp; Windus Pounds
16.99</ORGANIZATION>, 269 pages
Sir <PERSON>Laurens</PERSON> van der Post is not so far short of 90 but, happily, in full
possession of his powers as he celebrates this 60th anniversary of his
association with the <ORGANIZATION>Hogarth Press</ORGANIZATION> (today subsumed in <LOCATION>Chatto</LOCATION>, and in turn in
<ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>). This attendant anthology, <PERSON>Feather Fall</PERSON>, is a slightly curious
concept because one has to question its function. Is it to commemorate the
occasion? To remind us fans of his qualities? To give to new readers a taste
which will encourage them to buy the real books? Perhaps the model is the
anthology of CG Jung - van der Post's mentor - which has led many casual
readers to tackle Jung's fuller achievement.
After all, it is hard to imagine an anthology from, say, <LOCATION>Conrad</LOCATION>, or <LOCATION>Bellow</LOCATION>,
or <PERSON>Hemingway</PERSON> (successful publishing projects like The Essential <PERSON>Hemingway</PERSON>
are not comparable because they are omnibuses, not anthologies). The
explanation is that van der Post is seen today not so much as a novelist -
although he is a good one - but as a thinker, visionary, philosopher,
mystic. You cannot sensibly anthologise a novelist but you can much more
easily gather together a collection of extracts, often brief, even a single
paragraph, from the life-work of a sage.
The danger is that, as a result of abbreviation, you can finish up with too
many out-of-context mini-extracts which do less than justice to the author:
for instance, 'Never try to go ahead of your spoor. Many a man has died
because he has not observed the discipline of the spoor to the end'. That
sort of example, and there are quite a few of them here, would keep Private
Eye happy for months. As with all van der Post's regular appearances in that
journal, it is very unfair but undeniably funny.
Another problem with a book of this sort is that it cannot - because these
are snippets] - communicate the achievement of a creative writer. It needs
to be insisted that the early van der Post novels - In A Province, The Face
Beside The Fire, <PERSON>Flamingo Feather</PERSON> - are still splendid. The African travel
books - Venture to the Interior, The Lost World of the Kalahari, The Heart
of the <PERSON>Hunter</PERSON> - continue to defy the sneers of the anthropologists. A Story
Like The Wind and A Far-Off Place are a captivating duo about childhood and
much else. Even the food book, <ORGANIZATION>First Catch Your Eland</ORGANIZATION>, is hard to put down.
And that is to leave out The Dark Eye in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, The Seed and the Sower, the
travels to <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, the recent semi-memoirs, and so much more.
The editors of <ORGANIZATION>Feather Fall</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Jean-Marc Pottiez</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jane Bedford</PERSON>, focus on
van der Post not as novelist or traveller, soldier or crypto-diplomat, but
as - to use <PERSON>Rosamond Lehmann</PERSON>'s words about him - 'a great spiritual thinker
and writer'. They correctly see 'a pattern in his writing, a flow and a
continuity' over 60 years, or at least over the 40 years since he resumed
his writing career after returning from the war in the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>. That
pattern is underlined by the fact that he has never hesitated to repeat
himself: again and again his books, whether ostensibly fiction or
non-fiction, return to themes and episodes from his early Afrikaner
childhood, his <PERSON>Bushman</PERSON> nanny, his Huguenot ancestry, his early youthful
visit to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, his experiences as a POW, his subsequent travels in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>,
his acquaintance with <PERSON>Jung</PERSON>, and so on.
Inevitably and properly, these topics are re-visited in this volume,
together with his lifelong meditation on the mighty themes that go with them
 -the dark shadow within ourselves, the function of journey for each of us,
the significance of the <PERSON>Bushman</PERSON> as the 'first man', the religious role of
<ORGANIZATION>Wilderness</ORGANIZATION>, the necessity to forgive, the Jungian sense of 'wholeness', the
mystery of Dream.
Too many of these extracts, in my opinion, are taken from that odd volume A
Walk with a <PERSON>White Bushman</PERSON>, which is not a real van der Post book but a
rambling and disorganised conversation with <PERSON>Jean-Marc Pottiez</PERSON>. I am also
struck by a change in style over the years: I am convinced that at some
point the taut, elegant pace of, say, Venture to the Interior, turned into
the very different rhythm, a tendency to spin words and lose precision, of
the later books. (I assume he started to dictate, which is never a good
thing.)
Van der Post has been active in Southern African affairs for many years
though he has chosen to operate sub rosa. His disdain for apartheid was
never a secret, nor - more controversially - his opposition to the
international sanctions which surely contributed to recent events. I
particularly enjoyed his unwitting reference here to the Afrikaners' history
'which still has a half-Nelson hold on them'. Fresh from a visit to
<LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>, and full of images of inauguration of majority rule, I was
also struck by his understanding - dating back to his years as prisoner of
the Japanese - of the surprising possibility of forgiveness.
'Persons who have really suffered at the hands of others do not find it
difficult to forgive, nor even to understand the people who caused their
suffering,' he once wrote. 'They do not find it difficult to forgive because
out of suffering and sorrow truly endured comes an instinctive sense of
privilege . . .' He went on, in a later novel, 'For if one does not forgive,
one does not understand, and if one does not understand, one is afraid, and
if one is afraid, one hates, and if one hates, one cannot love. And no new
beginning on earth is possible without love . . .'
I should like to think that those two elderly <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Laurens</PERSON> van
der Post and <PERSON>Nelson Mandela</PERSON>, might have something to say to each other when
they are next in the same town.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2731 Book Publishing.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XXIV
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06059234 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06059234 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Knight-Ridder News Service; Hunter Willie Phillips stands at the
buffalo fence, which already has killed many wild animals  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BOTSWANA; GOVERNMENT; POLICY; CHANGE; ANIMAL; ZONING; EQUIPMENT; .....;
CONTROVERSY; ENVIRONMENT; ORGANIZATION; OPPOSE; DAMAGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  SEVERAL HUNDRED feet below, a rust-colored scar cuts like a razor through the
glistening Okovanggo swamps. Willie Phillips taps a leathery finger on the
airplane window.;    "There's the new buffalo fence," the big-game hunter
said. "Come back here next spring, and you'll see dead animals all along it."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BOTSWANA'S GIANT FENCE IS KILLING WILDLIFE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The fence runs along the northwest rim of the Okovanggo, an
8,500-square-mile wilderness teeming with game in <LOCATION>northwest Botswana</LOCATION>, where
the <LOCATION>Okovanggo River</LOCATION> makes a fan-shaped inland delta before dying in the sands
of the <ORGANIZATION>Kalahari Desert.</ORGANIZATION>;    Besides cutting migration routes for some of the
<ORGANIZATION>Okovanggo</ORGANIZATION>'s rarest herds, the "buffalo fence" under construction also places
outside the fence one of the wildest and most remote sections of the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>,
the <LOCATION>Magwegqana</LOCATION> peninsula.;     'It's a paradise';    "It's a paradise, I'm
telling you, a paradise," <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said. "And it'll all be cattle country
now.";    The fence is the latest part of a long-range plan by the government
to cordon this sprawling, desert nation into cattle and wildlife zones.;   
The fences already have opened massive tracts of formerly wild country to
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s cattle industry. They also have killed tens of thousands of wild
animals -- giraffe, springbok, zebra, eland -- that become tangled in the
sharp wires as they follow their centuries-old migrating routes. In the <DATE>last
decade</DATE>, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s population of 300,000 wildebeest was reduced to a little
more than 1,000; they either died in the fences or of thirst in their
water-poor enclaves.;     Government defends fences;    Government officials
defend the program as necessary to <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s lucrative beef trade.
Environmentalists, they say, exaggerate the threat and underestimate the
ability of wildlife to adapt to the fences.;    <PERSON>Ove Nielsen</PERSON>, chairman of the
<ORGANIZATION>Botswana Meat Commission</ORGANIZATION>, complains that foreigners are trying to turn his
country into "a gigantic zoo.";    <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, long considered one of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s
most conservation-minded countries, recently has come under increasing attack
from international environmental groups -- partly because of the new fences
and partly for the proposed dredging of 15 miles of river leading out of the
swamps.;     Dredging draws attention;    The dredging, intended to tap the
<ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>'s precious water, has drawn more international attention in recent
weeks. <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION> threatened to boycott <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s diamond industry if the
dredging isn't stopped. But many people think the buffalo fence poses the
greater threat.;    "As far as I'm concerned, this is worse than the
dredging," said one environmentalist in <LOCATION>Gaborone</LOCATION>, the capital.;    <ORGANIZATION>Coert Van
Hasselt</ORGANIZATION>, a lawyer based in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, represents a coalition of
environmental groups threatening to launch a global boycott of <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s beef
industry because of the fences.;    One concern is the timing of the
construction. Many of the Okovanggo's animals have left the swamp area to
migrate north toward the <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> highlands, where the rains begin in early
<DATE>January</DATE>. If the fence is finished in the next few months, environmentalists
argue, these animals will be caught outside.;     Delay promised;    In
response, the <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> government promised only to plant the tall, wooden
posts for the fence, but to hold off stringing the steel wire until the rains
subside and the animals return to the central Okovanggo.;    But a <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION>
investigator said this month that an inspection showed that the wire was being
put in place and that the new fence's first casualty -- a young giraffe -- had
been found tangled and dead along one completed stretch.;    To
environmentalists, it is as though one of the world's greatest natural
treasures is being sacrificed for the benefit of a handful of major cattle
owners.;    To many Botswanans -- and to many landowners throughout <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> --
it is as though they are being asked to remain primitive and poor so
well-heeled foreigners will have a place to come on vacation.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RICK LYMAN, Knight-Ridder News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Okovanggo Delta, Botswana  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910228  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  638  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday February 28, 1991
00059234,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-4951</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EIFD6ABEFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940906
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  06 SEP 94 / Commodities and Agriculture: De Beers digs deeper into its
resources - The new lease of life for the Jwaneng and Finsch diamond mines
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KENNETH GOODING
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The Jwaneng mine, on the fringes of the Kalahari desert in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, is
known as 'a gem in the world of gems' because it almost certainly is the
richest diamond mine in the world - at least in terms of the value of the
stones it yields. Jwaneng's position is being reinforced by a USDollars 160m
expansion programme at present being completed three months ahead of
schedule and under budget.
Meanwhile, 160km west of Kimberley in the northern <LOCATION>Cape Province</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>, another diamond mine, the <LOCATION>Finsch</LOCATION>, where operations started in <DATE>1964</DATE>,
has been given a new lease of life.
Having dug an open pit 423 metres deep, miners have now gone underground. <PERSON>Mr
Simon Webb</PERSON>, the general manager, says that the underground development has
given it another 35 to 40 years of life.
All this goes to show that De Beers, the South African group that dominates
world trade in rough (uncut) diamonds, still has complete faith in its
ability to maintain stability in the diamond market despite short-term
difficulties such as those the company is experiencing with <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>. It also
remains intent on maintaining its diamond output even though its
100-year-old mines at <ORGANIZATION>Kimberley</ORGANIZATION> are now running down.
The South African group believes that its control of at least <MONEY>50 per cent</MONEY> of
world diamond production gives it a powerful base from which to negotiate
with the other producers who have marketing contracts with De Beers' Central
Selling Organisation,
In <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> De Beers controls half of <ORGANIZATION>Debswana</ORGANIZATION>, the company that owns the
Jwaneng mine, with the government owning the rest. The value of Jwaneng to
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> cannot be overstated.
It, and the country's two other (smaller) diamond mines, between them
account for 50 per cent of the government's revenue and 40 per cent of the
country's gross domestic product. No wonder Jwaneng's company slogan is Re
phtas imisa <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, which translates as 'We make <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> sparkle'.
Production started at Jwaneng in <DATE>1982</DATE>. Now a so-called fourth stream is
being completed which is adding one-third to processing capacity. In turn,
this means a 21 per cent rise in the number of carats produced. Last year
the mine treated 5.8m tonnes of ore which yielded 8.546m carats of diamonds,
well below the <DATE>1992</DATE> output when the 5.77m tonnes treated gave up more than
9m carats.
Jwaneng's open pit has reached a depth of 190 metres. Already it is 2kms
long and 1km wide. <PERSON>Mr Loz Shaw</PERSON>, chief geologist, says drilling down to 600
metres shows there are still plenty of diamonds at that depth and so the pit
will go down at least that far.
<PERSON>Mr Derrick Moore</PERSON>, the general manager, says this indicates mining in the
open pit will last another 35 years - 'and then we might go underground'.
If experience at De Beers' wholly-owned Finsch mine in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> is
anything to go by, planning the underground development at Jwaneng might
already have started.
Planning for the underground mine at Finsch started in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> and the
first work began in <DATE>1979</DATE>. Yet the bottom of the Finsch open pit - 423 metres
 -was not reached until <DATE>1990</DATE>.
Unfortunately, things did not go completely as expected when underground
mining started, to some extent because the development was designed by a
management whose expertise was mainly in open pit mining.
However, <PERSON>Mr Mark Button</PERSON>, mining superintendent, says: 'Finsch has come of
age as an underground mine after two years. Our costs compare with the best
in the group.'
Among the innovations that have helped Finsch achieve its objectives are
some remote-controlled LHD (load-haul-dump) trucks which are similar to
radio-controlled toy vehicles or boats. Using VHF radio signals, a driver
can stand back and send a truck on its own to dig out material from areas
between the old pit wall and the underground development that would not
otherwise be mined because of the dangers involved. When, as occasionally
happens, rock crashes on to the LHD trucks, it is relatively simply to haul
the vehicles out virtually undamaged.
<PERSON>Mr Webb</PERSON> says the objective is to mine down to a depth of 830 metres, at
which point there are not enough diamonds left in the ground to make
recovery viable.
Finsch - named after the discoverers, <PERSON>Messrs Fincham</PERSON> and <PERSON>Schwabel</PERSON>, who
stumbled across the kimberlite pipe containing the diamonds when actually
they were looking for asbestos - is one of the victims of the present
turmoil in the diamond market caused mainly by uncertainties about Russian
exports.
About 500 of its 1,900 employees were laid off in <DATE>August 1992</DATE>. It is mining
only five days a week at present and processing on four days. Last year
Finsch mined 2.68m tonnes and recovered 2m carats of diamonds compared with
4.7m tonnes mined and 3.446m carats in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mr Webb</PERSON> suggests <DATE>1994</DATE> output will be similar to last year's. But when market
conditions improve, production can be brought back up to previous levels in
about six months.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>De Beers Consolidated Mines.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>ZAZ  South Africa, Africa.
    BWZ  Botswana, Africa.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P1499 Miscellaneous Nonmetallic Minerals.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>MKTS  Production.
    MKTS  Market shares.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 32
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901019-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-19-90 0006EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Gulf-SaudiLand     10-19 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Saudi Land,0692</SECOND>
<HEAD>Operation Desert Shield Holding Off Iraqi Soldiers And Sheep</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DHA1, DHA2 sent Oct. 18.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIYADH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Operation Desert Shield, along with
holding off Iraqi soldiers, is also shielding the desert from
another force that each year devastates Saudi rangeland: millions
of Iraqi sheep.
   An inadvertent side effect of impending war, conservationists
say, is that Iraqi herders have ceased their traditional migration
across the border to find pasture for sheep, goats and camels.
   That, they say, is no small windfall to <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>, where a
loss of plant cover threatens to convert arable range into
wasteland across much of the country.
   ``Tanks and jeeps running around up there are nothing compared
to what happens from overgrazing,'' said <PERSON>Graham Child</PERSON>, senior
consultant to the <ORGANIZATION>National Commission for Wildlife Conservation and
Development</ORGANIZATION>.
   Crisis or not, the commission is pressing ahead with a 10-year
plan to protect endangered habitats and restock them with
disease-free gazelle, ostrich and native birds.
   The measures have already brought the Arabian oryx back from
extinction in the wild. Two species of gazelle are being bred by
the hundreds.
   There are also some new houbara bustards, large birds beloved by
Saudis who hunt them with falcons.
   Arabian rangelands, slowly degrading for a thousand years, now
suffer badly from <LOCATION>Saudi Bedouin</LOCATION> now able to use water trucks to
graze their animals on fragile land they could not reach before.
   Under historic accords, Iraqi and Jordanian nomads have crossed
regularly into northern <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION> to find fresh range. They have
benefited from the same generous subsidies allowed the Saudis.
   At the same time, swift rural development in <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>
brought new roads, irrigated farming and other incursions on
natural habitats.
   Saudi leaders realized they faced a crisis in the mid-1980s when
hunters consistently camehome empty-handed. In <DATE>1986</DATE>, the
commission was set up to do something about it.
   Within four years, 57,692 square miles were designated protected
areas. Specialists came in to shape a wildlife research center from
a neglected private zoo on the late <LOCATION>King Khalid</LOCATION>'s farm north of
here.
   At a second center, scientists experimented with ways to breed
enough houbara bustard chicks to save the threatened wild
population.
   ``They've achieved an enormous amount in three years,'' said
<PERSON>Doug Williamson</PERSON>, an English-based biologist who runs the <ORGANIZATION>King
Khalid Wildlife Research Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Things are far from perfect, but there is goodwill and money
is being committed,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Abdul Aziz abu Zinada</PERSON>, the commision's secretary-general, said
his priorities were protecting habitats, seeking environmental
legislation, restocking wildlife and building public awareness.
   Conflict with <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION> has stalled plans for regional cooperation,
he said, but international organizations have continued to help
with data and advice.
   ``Now in the north you can see idmi (sand gazelle) where they
had almost disappeared,'' Abu <PERSON>Zinada</PERSON> said. ``It is thrilling.''
   At the <ORGANIZATION>King Khalid Center</ORGANIZATION>, scientists have all but eliminated
the tuberculosis which, traced back to a gift deer from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, had
crippled herds left for years in a single enclosure.
   Soon the 600 to 700 gazelles now thriving as a result of the
program will be breeding hundreds of kids a year to be released
into the wild, <PERSON>Williamson</PERSON> said.
   The center has two pairs of afri, or Saudi dorcas gazelles,
among the <DATE>last 27</DATE> believed left in the world.
   Altogether, there are 20 species from five continents.
   The animals thrive in separate pens and paddocks and include a
mix of indigenous species and gifts from visitors. There are idmi,
rheem (mountain gazelle), other rare gazelles, Arabian oryx,
zebras, ostriches and assorted extras, including a mad half-goat,
half-ibex that thinks it's a deer.
   Williamson, an antelope specialist who worked in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s
<LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION>, is also conducting research on how gazelle cope
with roasting desert temperatures.
   ``We haven't been affected much by the <LOCATION>Iraq</LOCATION> crisis,'' he said,
echoing remarks by scientists conducting other commission projects.
   ``There is a lot to do still, but we're doing it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-1069</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFZARAEZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940625
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 JUN 94 / Books: African journeys - JDF Jones discovers a
classic-in-waiting
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JDF JONES
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE ELECTRONIC ELEPHANT by <PERSON>Dan Jacobson Hamish Hamilton</PERSON> Pounds 17.99, 373
pages
HAPPY SAD LAND by <PERSON>Mark McCrum Sinclair-Stevenson</PERSON> Pounds 16.99, 455 pages
INNOCENTS IN <LOCATION>AFRICA</LOCATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Drury Pifer Granta Books Pounds</ORGANIZATION> 15.99, 338 pages
<PERSON>Dan Jacobson</PERSON> has taken time off from his crafted and distinguished novels to
go home - home to <LOCATION>Kimberley</LOCATION>, the diamond town, and thence to travel up the
'Missionary Road', that ancient African route which slips between the
Kalahari and the <PERSON>Boers</PERSON> and finishes at the <LOCATION>Zambesi</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Victoria Falls</LOCATION>.
It is not one of the region's finer scenic routes, featuring as it does
countless miles of thorn, sand and scrub, so <PERSON>Jacobson</PERSON> has to explain that he
was attracted to the journey in part by its historical interest, in part by
its personal reference - 'that half-known, half-feared region which had lain
forbiddingly on the very doorstep of the <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> I had grown up in'. We are
to be taken back, then, to the scene of his early - brilliant - novels,
before he graduated to a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> professorial chair and ambitious novels on
Old Testament themes. The best thing in The Electronic Elephant is his
description of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Cape</ORGANIZATION> veld, which sends us back after all these
years to A Dance in the Sun and its images of a furious Afrikaner isolation.
The route to the north was indeed important to the 19th-century
missionaries, who were in the vanguard of colonial conquest. 'The
<ORGANIZATION>Livingstone Liquor Stall</ORGANIZATION>' in <LOCATION>Campbell</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Griquatown</LOCATION>, is a reminder of the
presiding genius of the tale. It is a road, argues <PERSON>Jacobson</PERSON>, littered with
the wreckage of successive ideologies: European imperialism, Boer
nationalism, Victorian racialism, apartheid, African liberation, <PERSON>Marxism</PERSON> -
and Christianity, which alone has survived, and prospered, in its peculiar
African styles. In a lovely scene in the <LOCATION>Kuruman</LOCATION> mission church the
secular-Jewish <PERSON>Jacobson</PERSON> and his atheist wife are the only congregation at
the Easter service: 'Making sense of my presence there was impossible;
impossible also not to feel the strangest mixture of wonder, embarrassment,
mirth, fraudulence, compassion for our hosts, even a kind of protectiveness
towards them'.
This is, as you would expect, a journey informed by the novelist's eye. He
encounters <PERSON>Bushman</PERSON> soldiers brought back for their safety from <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> by the
<ORGANIZATION>South African Defence Forces</ORGANIZATION> whose forebears had massacred them to
near-extinction (it is, as he says, 'surreal'); he meets a group of
far-Right Afrikaners who are preparing for their own ethnic, on-screen
state; he returns, always, to the history of these obscure territories; he
notes that it was platinum as well as tourism which transformed the economy
of President <PERSON>Mangope</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Bophuthatswana</LOCATION>; he has the expatriate white South
African's gentle scepticism of the future ('A 'non-racial' <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>? One
might as well talk of breeding a kosher pig . . .')
When he moves out of the Republic he is less confident: he does not respond
to <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> and is ill at ease in <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>. The single map is inadequate,
the absence of an index is regrettable, and he can't spell <LOCATION>Mmabatho</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mark McCrum</PERSON> has published the story of another journey around <LOCATION>Southern
Africa</LOCATION>. The scheme is simple: <PERSON>McCrum</PERSON> spent time in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> as a teenager in
<DATE>1977</DATE> and liked it; 15 years later he went back. Cue to a pleasantly readable
account of his travels and his undramatic adventures. McCrum has a good ear
for dialogue and does not take himself too seriously. Happy Sad Land makes
an interesting, relaxed, unessential read for anyone interested in that part
of the world. He can't spell Van Zyl Slabbert.
The best of the bunch, the surprise, the curiosity from out of the blue, the
classic-in-waiting, is <PERSON>Drury Pifer</PERSON>'s Innocents in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. Pifer is an
American, a playwright who was brought up in <LOCATION>Southern Africa</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1930s</DATE> as
son of a mining engineer who was employed on the <ORGANIZATION>Rand</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>Kimberley</LOCATION>, in
<LOCATION>South-west Africa</LOCATION>, and then in <LOCATION>Kimberley</LOCATION> again.
<PERSON>Pifer</PERSON> has produced an entrancing memoir of childhood in pre-apartheid days.
This book, written with superb precision and elegance, its recall of detail
based on access to his beloved mother's letters home, is utterly fascinating
about the <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> of those pre-war years, yet it is more than this, it
evokes and recreates the intimacy of the life of a happy family of
half-a-century ago. The fact that they were Americans gives a unique view of
the English-Afrikaner tensions of those formative years, but the deeper
subject is its poetic recapture of the experiences of childhood which most
of us never recall in more than fragments.
The Pifers went back to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> at the end of the war: 'It didn't occur to
us that this journey out of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> was the last time we would find ourselves
together and happy, day after day, perfectly matched in our non-stop prattle
and familiar love . . .' The boy never went back.
Innocents in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> deserves a much longer review: let this be a shorthand
recommendation of a wonderful book. He can't spell Japie.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2731 Book Publishing.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XX
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-7390</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CBVAEACQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920222
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 FEB 92 / How To Spend It: Penny-pinching chic for the recession -
Lucia van der Post goes bargain-hunting and finds that even in these
straitened times it can be fun
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LUCIA VAN DER POST
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THERE IS something about <DATE>February</DATE> that seems to induce in me a fit of
