<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891106-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-06-89 0749EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv15   11-06 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv15,0539</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv15</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday, Nov. 15</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Pikes Peak cq in 6th graf.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE>, the <DATE>319th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 46
   One hundred years ago, on <DATE>Nov. 15, 1889</DATE>, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s monarchy was
overthrown. A republic was proclaimed following the ouster of Dom
Pedro the Second, the country's second and last emperor.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1777</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Continental Congress</ORGANIZATION> approved the Articles of
<ORGANIZATION>Confederation</ORGANIZATION>, a precursor to the Constitution of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1806</DATE>, explorer <PERSON>Zebulon Pike</PERSON> sighted the mountaintop that
later became known as Pikes Peak.
   In <DATE>1926</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Broadcasting Company</ORGANIZATION> made its on-air debut
with a radio network of 24 stations.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, 50 years ago, President <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> laid the cornerstone
of the <ORGANIZATION>Jefferson Memorial</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington D.C.</LOCATION>
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, the first 75,000 men were called to armed forces duty
under peacetime conscription.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, <PERSON>William Lyon Mackenzie King</PERSON> retired as prime minister
of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> after 21 years. He was suceeded by <ORGANIZATION>Louis St. Laurent</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, the flight of Gemini 12 ended successfully as the
capsule _ carrying astronauts <PERSON>James A. Lovell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz''
<PERSON>Aldrin Jr.</PERSON> _ splashed down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1969</DATE>, 250,000 protesters staged a peaceful demonstration in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> against the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   In <DATE>1978</DATE>, 183 people were killed when a chartered <ORGANIZATION>Icelandic
Airlines</ORGANIZATION> DC-8 crashed short of an airport in <LOCATION>Colombo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sri Lanka</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> began a five-day visit to <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION>, becoming the first pontiff in 198 years to visit the
birthplace of the Protestant Reformation.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, funeral services were held in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s Red Square for
the late Soviet President <PERSON>Leonid I. Brezhnev</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> signed an accord giving <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> an
official consultative role in governing the troubled British-ruled
province of <LOCATION>Northern Ireland</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, 28 of 82 people aboard a <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> DC-9,
including the pilot and co-pilot, were killed when the plane
crashed on takeoff from <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Stapleton International Airport</LOCATION>.
   Ten years ago: The British government publicly identified Sir
<PERSON>Anthony Blunt</PERSON>, a respected art historian, as the ``fourth man'' of
a Soviet spy ring that included <PERSON>Guy Burgess</PERSON>, <PERSON>Donald Maclean</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kim
Philby</PERSON>.
   Five years ago: <PERSON>Baby Fae</PERSON>, the month-old infant who had received
a baboon's heart to replace her own congenitally deformed one, died
at a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> medical center almost three weeks after the
transplant.
   One year ago: The <ORGANIZATION>Palestine National Council</ORGANIZATION>, the legislative
Palestinian state at the close of a four-day conference in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>.
The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> launched its first space shuttle, Buran, on an
unmanned, 3{-hour flight.
   Today's Birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>Former White House</ORGANIZATION> Chief of Staff <PERSON>Howard H.
Baker Jr.</PERSON> is 64. Actor <PERSON>Edward Asner</PERSON> is 60. Singer <PERSON>Petula Clark</PERSON> is
57. Actress <PERSON>Joanna Barnes</PERSON> is 55. Actor <PERSON>Sam Waterston</PERSON> is 49.
   Thought for Today: ``He too serves a certain purpose who only
stands and cheers.'' _ <PERSON>Henry Brooks Adams</PERSON>, American historian
(1838-1918).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Wednesday, Nov. 15</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881107-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-07-88 0752EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv15   11-07 0470</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv15,0491</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv15</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Tuesday, Nov. 15</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE>, the <DATE>320th day of 1988</DATE>. There are 46
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Nov. 15, 1777</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Continental Congress</ORGANIZATION> approved the Articles
of <ORGANIZATION>Confederation</ORGANIZATION>, a precursor to the Constitution of the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>. (Ratification of the Articles took more than three years.)
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1806</DATE>, explorer <PERSON>Zebulon Pike</PERSON> sighted the mountaintop that later
became known as ``Pikes Peak.''
   In <DATE>1887</DATE>, artist <ORGANIZATION>Georgia O'Keeffe</ORGANIZATION> was born in <LOCATION>Sun Prairie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wis</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1887</DATE>, poet <PERSON>Marianne Moore</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1926</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Broadcasting Company</ORGANIZATION> made its on-air debut
with a radio network of 24 stations.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, the first 75,000 men were called to armed forces duty
under peacetime conscription.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, <PERSON>William Lyon Mackenzie King</PERSON> retired as prime minister of
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> after 21 years. He was suceeded by <ORGANIZATION>Louis St. Laurent</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1958</DATE>, actor <PERSON>Tyrone Power</PERSON> died of a heart attack while filming
a movie in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>. He was 44.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, the flight of ``Gemini 12'' ended successfully as the
spacecraft -- carrying astronauts <PERSON>James A. Lovell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz''
<PERSON>Aldrin Jr.</PERSON> -- splashed down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1969</DATE>, 250,000 protesters staged a peaceful demonstration in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> against the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> began a five-day visit to <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION>, becoming the first pontiff in 198 years to visit <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>,
birthplace of the Protestant Reformation.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, funeral services were held in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s Red Square for
the late Soviet President <PERSON>Leonid I. Brezhnev</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, <PERSON>Baby Fae</PERSON>, the month-old infant who had received a
baboon's heart to replace her own congenitally deformed one, died at
a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> medical center almost three weeks after the transplant.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> signed an accord giving <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> an
official consultative role in governing the troubled British-ruled
province of <LOCATION>Northern Ireland</LOCATION>.
   Ten years ago: 183 people were killed when a chartered <ORGANIZATION>Icelandic
Airlines</ORGANIZATION> DC-8 crashed short of an airport in <LOCATION>Colombo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sri Lanka</LOCATION>.
Anthropologist <PERSON>Margaret Mead</PERSON> died in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> at age 76.
   Five years ago: Turkish Cypriot leaders in <LOCATION>northern Cyprus</LOCATION>
declared their part of the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> island an independent
republic in a move that was later denounced by the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Security
Council</ORGANIZATION>.
   One year ago: Twenty-eight of 82 people aboard a <ORGANIZATION>Continental
Airlines</ORGANIZATION> DC-9, including the pilot and co-pilot, were killed when
the jetliner crashed seconds after taking off from <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>'s
<LOCATION>Stapleton International Airport</LOCATION>.
   Today's birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>Former White House</ORGANIZATION> Chief of Staff <PERSON>Howard H.
Baker Jr.</PERSON> is 63. Actor <PERSON>Edward Asner</PERSON> is 59. Singer <PERSON>Petula Clark</PERSON> is
56. Actress <PERSON>Joanna Barnes</PERSON> is 54. Actor <PERSON>Sam Waterston</PERSON> is 48.
   Thought for today: ``Friends are lost by calling often and
calling seldom.'' -- Scottish proverb.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901105-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-05-90 0734EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv15   11-05 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv15,0508</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv15</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thursday, Nov. 15</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE>, the <DATE>319th day of 1990</DATE>. There are 46
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>Nov. 15, 1777</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Continental Congress</ORGANIZATION> approved the Articles
of <ORGANIZATION>Confederation</ORGANIZATION>, a precursor to the Constitution of the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1806</DATE>, explorer <PERSON>Zebulon Pike</PERSON> sighted the mountaintop that
later became known as ``Pikes Peak.''
   In <DATE>1889</DATE>, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s monarchy was overthrown. A republic was
proclaimed following the ouster of Dom Pedro II, the country's
   In <DATE>1926</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Broadcasting Company</ORGANIZATION> made its on-air debut
with a radio network of 24 stations.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, President <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> laid the cornerstone of
the <ORGANIZATION>Jefferson Memorial</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington D.C.</LOCATION>
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, 50 years ago, the first 75,000 men were called to armed
forces duty under peacetime conscription.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, <PERSON>William Lyon Mackenzie King</PERSON> retired as prime minister
of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> after 21 years. He was suceeded by <ORGANIZATION>Louis St. Laurent</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, the flight of Gemini 12 ended successfully as the
spacecraft - carrying astronauts <PERSON>James A. Lovell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz''
<PERSON>Aldrin Jr.</PERSON> - splashed down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1969</DATE>, 250,000 protesters staged a peaceful demonstration in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> against the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   In <DATE>1979</DATE>, the British government publicly identified Sir <PERSON>Anthony
Blunt</PERSON>, a respected art historian, as the ``fourth man'' of a Soviet
spy ring that included <PERSON>Guy Burgess</PERSON>, <PERSON>Donald Maclean</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kim Philby</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, funeral services were held in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s Red Square for
the late Soviet President <PERSON>Leonid I. Brezhnev</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, <PERSON>Baby Fae</PERSON>, the month-old infant who had received a
baboon's heart to replace her own congenitally deformed one, died
at a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> medical center almost three weeks after the
transplant.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Palestine National Council</ORGANIZATION>, the legislative body of
state at the close of a four-day conference in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>.
   Ten years ago: Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> began a five-day visit to <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION>, becoming the first pontiff in 198 years to visit the
birthplace of the Protestant Reformation. A two-week series of
fires began breaking out in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> signed an accord giving
<LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> an official consultative role in governing the troubled
British-ruled province of <LOCATION>Northern Ireland</LOCATION>.
   One year ago: Solidarity leader <PERSON>Lech Walesa</PERSON> was cheered by
American lawmakers as he told a joint meeting of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
aid to <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> ``will not be wasted, and will never be forgotten.''
   Today's Birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>Former White House</ORGANIZATION> Chief of Staff <PERSON>Howard H.
Baker Jr.</PERSON> is 65. Actor <PERSON>Edward Asner</PERSON> is 61. Singer <PERSON>Petula Clark</PERSON> is
58. Actress <PERSON>Joanna Barnes</PERSON> is 56. Actor <PERSON>Sam Waterston</PERSON> is 50.
   Thought for Today: ``Psychology, which explains everything,
Explains nothing, And we are still in doubt.'' - <PERSON>Marianne Moore</PERSON>,
American poet (1887-1972).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thursday, Nov. 15</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE>, the <DATE>319th day of 1990</DATE>. There are 46
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>Nov. 15, 1777</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Continental Congress</ORGANIZATION> approved the Articles
of <ORGANIZATION>Confederation</ORGANIZATION>, a precursor to the Constitution of the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1806</DATE>, explorer <PERSON>Zebulon Pike</PERSON> sighted the mountaintop that
later became known as ``Pikes Peak.''
   In <DATE>1889</DATE>, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s monarchy was overthrown. A republic was
proclaimed following the ouster of Dom Pedro II, the country's
   In <DATE>1926</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Broadcasting Company</ORGANIZATION> made its on-air debut
with a radio network of 24 stations.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, President <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> laid the cornerstone of
the <ORGANIZATION>Jefferson Memorial</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington D.C.</LOCATION>
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, 50 years ago, the first 75,000 men were called to armed
forces duty under peacetime conscription.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, <PERSON>William Lyon Mackenzie King</PERSON> retired as prime minister
of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> after 21 years. He was suceeded by <ORGANIZATION>Louis St. Laurent</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, the flight of Gemini 12 ended successfully as the
spacecraft - carrying astronauts <PERSON>James A. Lovell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Edwin</PERSON> ``Buzz''
<PERSON>Aldrin Jr.</PERSON> - splashed down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1969</DATE>, 250,000 protesters staged a peaceful demonstration in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> against the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   In <DATE>1979</DATE>, the British government publicly identified Sir <PERSON>Anthony
Blunt</PERSON>, a respected art historian, as the ``fourth man'' of a Soviet
spy ring that included <PERSON>Guy Burgess</PERSON>, <PERSON>Donald Maclean</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kim Philby</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, funeral services were held in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s Red Square for
the late Soviet President <PERSON>Leonid I. Brezhnev</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, <PERSON>Baby Fae</PERSON>, the month-old infant who had received a
baboon's heart to replace her own congenitally deformed one, died
at a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> medical center almost three weeks after the
transplant.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Palestine National Council</ORGANIZATION>, the legislative body of
state at the close of a four-day conference in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>.
   Ten years ago: Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> began a five-day visit to <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION>, becoming the first pontiff in 198 years to visit the
birthplace of the Protestant Reformation. A two-week series of
fires began breaking out in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> signed an accord giving
<LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> an official consultative role in governing the troubled
British-ruled province of <LOCATION>Northern Ireland</LOCATION>.
   One year ago: Solidarity leader <PERSON>Lech Walesa</PERSON> was cheered by
American lawmakers as he told a joint meeting of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
aid to <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> ``will not be wasted, and will never be forgotten.''
   Today's Birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>Former White House</ORGANIZATION> Chief of Staff <PERSON>Howard H.
Baker Jr.</PERSON> is 65. Actor <PERSON>Edward Asner</PERSON> is 61. Singer <PERSON>Petula Clark</PERSON> is
58. Actress <PERSON>Joanna Barnes</PERSON> is 56. Actor <PERSON>Sam Waterston</PERSON> is 50.
   Thought for Today: ``Psychology, which explains everything,
Explains nothing, And we are still in doubt.'' - <PERSON>Marianne Moore</PERSON>,
American poet (1887-1972).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072990-0023 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 253853 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 29, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 10; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1667 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CLIMB PIKES PEAK FOR FAMOUS VIEW OF A STUNNING AMERICA THE BEAUTIFUL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By T. R. REID, WASHINGTON POST 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
COLORADO SPRINGS, Colo. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
No doubt you know that it bears the best-known name of any mountain in the 
country. 
</P>
<P>
What you probably don't know, unless you've made the spectacular, winding trip 
to the top, is that the snow-capped massif called Pikes Peak also offers the 
most famous vista to be seen from any American mountain. 
</P>
<P>
Looking eastward from the summit of Pikes Peak, 14,110 feet above sea level, 
you see an endless expanse of spacious skies stretching over amber waves of 
grain. 
</P>
<P>
When you turn around and gaze west, you see purple mountain majesties above the 
fruited plain. And as you look over this scenic splendor, you know for certain 
that you have found <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> the beautiful. 
</P>
<P>
If those descriptive phrases sound familiar, they should. For it was here on 
the summit of Pikes Peak, in the Front Range of the <ORGANIZATION>Colorado Rockies</ORGANIZATION> just 20 
miles west of <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, that a <ORGANIZATION>Wellesley College</ORGANIZATION> professor named 
<PERSON>Katharine Lee Bates</PERSON> was moved to write the poem that has become the national 
anthem of our nation's physical grandeur: "America the Beautiful." 
</P>
<P>
Much has changed about <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> since the <DATE>July day in 1893</DATE> when <PERSON>Bates</PERSON> traveled 
to the summit and was instantly inspired to create her moving hymn. Happily, 
though, the view from atop <LOCATION>Pikes Peak</LOCATION> has not changed much at all. 
</P>
<P>
All the wonders that sent <PERSON>Bates</PERSON> scrambling for pen and paper are still here to 
see. The rolling waves of grain fields to the east still glisten a deep amber 
beneath a mid-summer sun. And the imposing mountain majesties off to the west 
-- ridge after ridge of snowcapped ranges -- really do look purple against the 
dark blue <ORGANIZATION>Rocky Mountain</ORGANIZATION> sky. 
</P>
<P>
Thus if you're searching for a travel destination that will prove -- either to 
yourself or to your kids -- that this country is still <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> the beautiful, 
you can't go wrong by planning a trip to southern <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> and a trek to the 
top of Pikes Peak. 
</P>
<P>
There were three ways to get to the top of the Peak when <PERSON>Bates</PERSON> made the trip: 
by foot, by train and by carriage. The same three ways are available today, 
except that the horse-drawn carriage that took <PERSON>Bates</PERSON> and her party up the Pikes 
Peak Highway has been replaced by the family car. 
</P>
<P>
Unless you choose to hike, the trip today is quick and relatively easy. A round 
trip on the Cog Railway that chugs up the mountain's east face takes three 
hours and 10 minutes, including a little less than an hour at the top. 
</P>
<P>
Driving the steep, winding 20-mile highway takes about an hour each way. Which 
means you will probably spend just half a day visiting <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s most famous 
mountain. 
</P>
<P>
Even if it hadn't been lucky enough to be given a memorably alliterative name, 
Pikes Peak would almost certainly have become a famous natural feature. This is 
a simple fact of geography. 
</P>
<P>
Pikes Peak is the easternmost of the "fourteeners" -- the elite category of 
American mountains reaching higher than 14,000 feet. As such, it was the first 
to be "discovered" when the white man began exploring the mountain west nearly 
two centuries ago. 
</P>
<P>
A <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> lieutenant, <PERSON>Zebulon Montgomery Pike</PERSON>, was dispatched in <DATE>1806</DATE> to head 
an exploratory troop mapping the lower reaches of the <LOCATION>Louisiana Purchase</LOCATION> -- 
sort of a southern version of the <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> expedition. 
</P>
<P>
Following the <LOCATION>Arkansas River</LOCATION> west from the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pike</PERSON> and his men spent 
week after redundant week traversing the empty flatlands of the high plains. 
</P>
<P>
Then, on <DATE>Nov. 16, 1806</DATE>, on an eastern <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> meadow about 120 miles from the 
present city of <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pike</LOCATION> looked up to the west and saw "a small 
blue cloud." 
</P>
<P>
As they came closer, the soldiers gradually realized that this spot on the sky 
was really a massive, snow-draped mountain. Thanks to the prerogatives of rank, 
the peak was eventually named for the commanding officer of the troop that 
found it. 
</P>
<P>
That enormous mountain marks an abrupt shift in the topography of the 
continent. Here the flat, featureless meadowland of middle <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> gives way to 
the wrinkled spine of <LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION> that make up the <ORGANIZATION>Continental Divide</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
And the change occurs with dramatic suddenness. With just a few low foothills 
before it, Pikes Peak juts up abruptly from the plains to scratch the sky. 
</P>
<P>
Consequently, the nation's easternmost alp quickly became a powerful symbol of 
the rugged West -- "the most celebrated peak in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>," as the <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> 
puts it. 
</P>
<P>
When the gold seekers of <DATE>1859</DATE> set out from <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, their wagons were 
emblazoned with the famous slogan, "Pikes Peak or Bust." 
</P>
<P>
Over time, railroad interests created a resort city, <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, at the 
base of the mountain to help draw tourists. Hiking trails, the cog railroad and 
a narrow carriage road were constructed on the mountain to carry visitors to 
the peak of the Peak. 
</P>
<P>
Thus it was only natural when <PERSON>Katharine Lee Bates</PERSON> arrived in the <LOCATION>Springs</LOCATION> to 
teach a <DATE>summer</DATE> school course at <ORGANIZATION>Colorado College</ORGANIZATION> -- one of her faculty 
colleagues that <DATE>summer</DATE> of '93 was a political scientist from <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION> named 
<PERSON>Woodrow Wilson</PERSON> -- that she should set aside a day to travel to the summit. 
</P>
<P>
When she alighted from her carriage at the top, <PERSON>Bates</PERSON> wrote later, she stood 
still for "an ecstatic moment" drinking in "the most glorious scenery I ever 
beheld." 
</P>
<P>
"As I was looking out over the sealike expanse of fertile country spreading 
away so far under those ample skies," <PERSON>Bates</PERSON> recalled afterward, "the opening 
lines of the hymn floated into my mind . . . Oh beautiful for spacious skies, 
for amber waves of grain. . . ." 
</P>
<P>
Today, <PERSON>Katharine Lee Bates</PERSON> (1859-1929) is well remembered in the environs of 
<LOCATION>Pikes Peak</LOCATION>. If you stop to visit the campus of <ORGANIZATION>Colorado College</ORGANIZATION>, a lovely green 
oasis near the heart of downtown <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, you can see a mural honoring 
her poem in the school's Shove Chapel. 
</P>
<P>
And in the small gift shop/rest house at the top of the mountain, there's an 
author's holograph of "America the Beautiful" in <PERSON>Bates</PERSON>'s own hand. 
</P>
<P>
If you're traveling from the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> to Pikes Peak, you'll probably stop in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 
and then drive the 70 miles to <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>. If the sky is clear -- a rare 
occurrence in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> these days -- you'll see the Peak poking its snowy face 
skyward due south of <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> airport as your plane comes in to land. 
</P>
<P>
Driving south along Interstate 25, you'll begin to get marvelous vistas of the 
majestic mountain about 20 miles out of <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. For my money, the view from the 
north is the most dramatic way to see Pikes Peak. 
</P>
<P>
The great white mountain (it is snow-covered about 42 weeks of the year) 
hunkers there on the horizon like a great white whale, its long ridge rising 
gradually to the sharp peak. 
</P>
<P>
Just north of <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, I-25 skirts the campus of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force 
Academy</ORGANIZATION>, nestled in against the jagged hills of the <ORGANIZATION>Rampart Range</ORGANIZATION> on the 
eastern slope of the <ORGANIZATION>Rockies</ORGANIZATION>. There's a well-marked overlook here that offers a 
stunning view of the eastern face of the Peak, the face that <PERSON>Zebulon Pike</PERSON> first 
saw from his vantage point out on the plains. 
</P>
<P>
When you reach <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, it's a 10-minute drive westward on Route 24 to 
the little tourist town of <LOCATION>Manitou Springs</LOCATION>, where most of the routes up Pikes 
Peak begin. 
</P>
<P>
Intrepid hikers might choose to trek to the top on the <ORGANIZATION>Barr Trail</ORGANIZATION>, a 
well-marked but extremely demanding hiking route laid out by <PERSON>Fred Barr</PERSON> from 
<DATE>1914</DATE> to <DATE>1918</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
According to the <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION>, thousands of people start the trip every year 
and a few hundred finish it. It's roughly 12 miles of hiking -- no technical 
climbing required -- with some incredibly steep sections and scores of 
switchbacks. 
</P>
<P>
A lot of people turn back early, because the first four miles are quite tough, 
and down there below timberline there's not much view of the peak. Those hikers 
who make it all the way generally plan on a two-day round trip, with a stopover 
at <ORGANIZATION>Barr Camp</ORGANIZATION>, four miles and 4,000 feet below the summit. 
</P>
<P>
Among the regular hikers are the members of <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>' Ad-Am-An (i.e., 
"add a man") Club. This fraternal organization adds one member each year. The 
neophyte must pass initiation by climbing to the top on New Year's Eve, when 
the club sets off an annual fireworks display that can be seen for 50 miles in 
all directions. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Manitou Springs</LOCATION> is the boarding point for the <ORGANIZATION>Pikes Peak Cog Railway</ORGANIZATION>, an 
electric train with two bright red cars that follow a surprisingly straight 
track to the top. Round-trip fare is <MONEY>$17</MONEY> for adults, <MONEY>$8</MONEY> for people between 5 
and 11 years old; preschoolers ride free. 
</P>
<P>
The most popular means of ascent these days is the Pikes Peak Highway, a 
serpentine 20-mile toll road that is paved for the first seven miles and then 
becomes reasonably smooth gravel. This is a steep and occasionally terrifying 
driving experience, but most two-wheel-drive family cars can make it. It's open 
from <DATE>May</DATE> to <DATE>October</DATE> each year. 
</P>
<P>
At the toll gate, you'll be charged <MONEY>$14</MONEY> for a family of four. The rangers there 
offer driving tips: Don't use your air conditioning; it will make hard-working 
engines overheat. Stop now and then on the way down to let your brakes cool 
off. 
</P>
<P>
To enforce that last rule, there is frequently a policeman stationed about five 
miles below the summit to feel each car's wheels and warn motorists whose 
brakes are overheated. The best time to go is in the <TIME>morning</TIME>, because the 
summit can be hazy or completely fogged in on <DATE>summer</DATE> afternoons. 
</P>
<P>
The drive up <LOCATION>Pikes Peak</LOCATION> is one of the loveliest auto trips you can imagine, 
particularly above timberline (11,500 feet in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>), where the views seem 
to spread out forever and the mountainside becomes a vast white sea of snow. 
</P>
<P>
And then you reach the summit, bundle up against the nippy <DATE>summer</DATE> breeze, throw 
snowballs until your hands freeze solid and soak in the 360-degree splendor of 
the mountain view that you've been singing about since your school days. 
</P>
<P>
America! America! From this unequaled vantage point at the very roof of the 
Rockies, it is clear that God really has shed His grace on thee. 
</P>
<P>
For more information on Pikes Peak, call the <ORGANIZATION>Colorado Springs Convention and 
Visitors Bureau</ORGANIZATION> at (800) 888-4748, <DATE>Ext. 20</DATE> or 22. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Towering above the Colorado plains, the mountain majesty of Pikes Peak 
inspired a hymn to America. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06231030 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06231030 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COLORADO; TRAVEL; GUIDELINE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THIS turn-of-the-century Rocky Mountain town offers tourists easy access to an
extraordinary collection of natural wonders -- red rock formations, caverns,
mountains and mineral springs.;    Centuries ago, Ute, Arapahoe, Cheyenne and
other American Indian tribes considered the area sacred. Here, they laid down
their weapons and abandoned thoughts of war for religious ceremonies and
meditation -- and to drink and bathe in the waters flowing from the area's
dozen mineral springs.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DRINK UP! THE SPRINGS FLOW FREE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Destination: Colorado  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The town was founded during the late 1800s, when Victorian-era tourists
were partial to "taking the waters." The enterprising <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> Gen. <PERSON>William J.
Palmer</PERSON>, founder of neighboring <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, developed the region as a
health resort and spa.;    <LOCATION>Manitou Springs</LOCATION> has attracted a brisk tourist
business ever since.;    There are still 10 freely flowing mineral springs
within the town's borders -- each with its unique taste, particular mineral
content and attributed healing properties. Individual springs, it is said,
cure everything from arthritis to rheumatism, from dyspepsia to constipation.;
   The waters are free. Just go up to the tap with a cup or jug and fill 'er
up.;    Better yet, arrange with the local <ORGANIZATION>Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> for a free
one-hour tasting tour of the springs. While you stroll the quaint streets and
drink of the waters at <LOCATION>Cheyenne</LOCATION>, Twin, <PERSON>Wheeler</PERSON>, Soda and other springs, the
guide will regale you with local history and colorful anecdotes about the
town's founders and early residents.;    Be sure to visit Soda <DATE>Spring</DATE>, flowing
from a calcium-encrusted fountain in the center of the lobby of the town's spa
building at 934 <LOCATION>Manitou Ave.</LOCATION> The water is clear, cold and pleasantly bubbly,
with sodium, potassium, calcium and lithium among its contents.;    The
Spanish-style stucco spa, built as the <ORGANIZATION>Manitou Bath House</ORGANIZATION> at the turn of the
century, is now a hotel, where guests may spend the night and bathe in <ORGANIZATION>Soda
Spring</ORGANIZATION>'s waters. The cost is <MONEY>$35</MONEY> per night for two people, including
breakfast.;    Move over source <ORGANIZATION>Perrier</ORGANIZATION>!;    <ORGANIZATION>Ute Chief Spring</ORGANIZATION>, at 1311 <LOCATION>Manitou
Ave.</LOCATION>, spews from the hands of a statue of an Indian chief. <ORGANIZATION>Cheyenne Spring</ORGANIZATION> is
in a red stone <DATE>spring</DATE> house, now being restored, at 934 <ORGANIZATION>Manitou Ave. Twin
Spring</ORGANIZATION>, with its tap outside a shop at 121 <LOCATION>Ruxton Ave.</LOCATION>, is the preferred water
for lemonade.;    Of the natural wonders surrounding <LOCATION>Manitou Springs</LOCATION>, the most
famous is Pike's Peak, rising 14,110 feet on the eastern horizon.;    Although
this ranks only as the 32nd highest summit in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, the ascent is
staggeringly steep. In <DATE>1808</DATE>, explorer <ORGANIZATION>Zebulon Pike</ORGANIZATION> declared the peak
unclimbable. In <DATE>1820</DATE>, <PERSON>Edwin James</PERSON>, set foot on the summit and proved him
wrong.;    Relatively few tourists managed to struggle up the mountain until
<PERSON>Zalmon Simmons</PERSON>, of <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> mattress fame, built a railway to the summit. The
<ORGANIZATION>Manitou &amp; Pikes Peak Railway</ORGANIZATION> was completed in <DATE>October 1890.</DATE>;    West of town
is the Garden of the Gods, a splendid outcropping of gigantic red rock
formations. Manitou means "Great Spirit," and Native Americans believed this
place was created and inhabited by gods. Garden of the <ORGANIZATION>Gods Trading Post</ORGANIZATION>,
established 100 years ago, still sells authentic American Indian crafts.; If
you go . . .; (check) GETTING THERE -- <LOCATION>Manitou Springs</LOCATION> is a pleasant 70-mile
drive from <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. From <ORGANIZATION>Stapleton International Airport</ORGANIZATION>, take <LOCATION>Quebec</LOCATION> Street to
Interstate 70, head east to I-225 then south to I-25 and continue south to the
<LOCATION>Manitou Springs</LOCATION> exit at <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 24. For car rentals, <ORGANIZATION>Dollar Rent-A-Car</ORGANIZATION> currently
has the best rates.;    (check)  WHERE TO STAY -- <LOCATION>Manitou Springs</LOCATION> has a
variety of excellent accommodations, ranging from the Soda Springs Spa (719)
685-1505) to the exclusive Broadmoor Hotel (800) 634-7711) and the intimate
Two Sisters Inn Bed and Breakfast (719) 685-9684).;    (check) INFORMATION --
Call <ORGANIZATION>Manitou Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> (800-642-2567) for information about the
springs. For attractions surrounding the town, call the <ORGANIZATION>Colorado Springs
Convention &amp; Visitors Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, (719) 635-7506.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JENNIFER MERIN, Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manitou Springs, Colo.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910818  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  655  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday August 18, 1991
00231030,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880425-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-25-88 0238EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     04-25 0965</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,970</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dropping Water Table Means Long-term Changes in Plains</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was part of what explorer <PERSON>Zebulon Pike</PERSON> in
<DATE>1806</DATE> called the <ORGANIZATION>Great American Desert</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>High Plains</LOCATION> where grass
was the natural crop and buffaloes roamed far and wide.
   Pike's adventures along the <LOCATION>Arkansas River</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Rocky
Mountains</LOCATION> gave rise to a notion at the time that the huge region of
low rainfall, short grass and few natural water holes was a natural
barrier that would limit <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> westward expansion.
   Farmers tried to tame it with the plow, but often drought and
crop failure dominated the huge region, generally west of the 100th
meridian. Dryland farming, the settlers found, was a precarious
business in the <ORGANIZATION>Great American Desert</ORGANIZATION>.
   It began to change after enterprising farmers tapped underground
water supplies for large-scale irrigation. A huge, invisible lake _
the Ogallala Aquifer _ was a gold mine for parts of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New
Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>.
   But for years the underground water level has been receding,
forcing deeper drilling and greater pumping costs. Already
irrigation has become uneconomical for many.
   ``In order to maintain a viable agricultural economy, this area
must return to a dryland type of production,'' says <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture
Department</ORGANIZATION> economist <PERSON>Wendell Holmes</PERSON> in the current issue of
Farmline magazine. ``How soon the transition will be made depends
somewhat on how willing farmers are to change their irrigation
practices.''
   <PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said ``it seems reasonable to assume'' that some
irrigation will continue for a number of years. New technologies
and more drought-tolerant plants may help for a time.
   ``Whatever the time, though, adjustments must be made in order
to be ready when the wells run dry,'' he said.
   Holmes and a colleague, <PERSON>Mindy Petrulis</PERSON>, in the department's
<ORGANIZATION>Economic Research Service</ORGANIZATION> studied an area of the high plains in
<LOCATION>West Texas</LOCATION>, which included seven irrigated counties and eight
neighboring dryland counties.
   The irrigated counties included <PERSON>Castro</PERSON>, <PERSON>Crosby</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Floyd</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hale</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Lamb</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Parmer</PERSON> and <PERSON>Swisher</PERSON>, while the dryland counties were <LOCATION>Baylor</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Cottle</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Foard</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Haskell</LOCATION>, <PERSON>King</PERSON>, <PERSON>Knox</PERSON>, <PERSON>Stonewall</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Throckmorton</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said the irrigated counties enjoyed an economic boom in
the <DATE>1940s</DATE> and <DATE>1950s</DATE> as irrigation became widespread. A move to
``center pivot'' systems made it possible to nearly triple yields
of cotton, wheat and corn on land previously farmed without
irrigation.
   By <DATE>1960</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> high plains had become one of the most
irrigation-dependent areas of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   But the nearby dryland counties, which lie just to the east of
the Ogallala Aquifer, have never had enough water from surface or
below-ground sources to develop agriculture based on irrigation.
<PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said that has been apparent from their economic performance
beginning in the <DATE>1940s</DATE>.
   ``The economy of the dryland farming area continued to stagnate
and periodically worsen, because of the lack of water for crops,''
<PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said. ``One effect has been a continued heavy outmigration
of rural people.''
   For example, between <DATE>1940</DATE> and <DATE>1984</DATE>, the total population of the
dryland counties was cut in half and employment was reduced by a
fourth.
   In contrast, <PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said, the irrigated counties experienced
rapid economic growth and development during most of the 1940-84
period. Despite a small decline in the last few decades, total
population in the mid-1980s exceeded 100,000 people, a <PERCENT>38 percent</PERCENT>
increase from <DATE>1940</DATE>, and employment at about 41,000 was up nearly <PERCENT>80
percent</PERCENT>.
   Meanwhile, in the dryland counties that weren't blessed with an
abundance of water, farms grew larger and fewer in order to
maintain their incomes, and population dropped by <PERCENT>32 percent</PERCENT> from
<DATE>1940</DATE> to <DATE>1959</DATE>.
   ``Dryland farming does not require a large labor force, nor can
it support a large rural or urban population,'' <PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said.
``Thus, there was little inducement for people to move into the
area or, having been born there, to stay. More and more people
found employment elsewhere.''
   But by <DATE>1960</DATE>, the fast-track development of the irrigated
counties slowed down. From <DATE>1959</DATE> to <DATE>1978</DATE>, he said, the value of farm
products sold increased about <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT>, compared with a tenfold
increase in the previous 19 years.
   And by <DATE>1978</DATE>, almost 2,400 irrigation farmers had gone out of
business and 140,000 acres of cropland had been taken out of
irrigation. Rising costs of energy took a toll.
   The tough times continued among dryland farmers, too. Population
in those counties dropped by more than a fourth from <DATE>1959</DATE> to <DATE>1978</DATE>,
total employment was down more than a tenth, and <PERCENT>31 percent</PERCENT> of the
farm operators went out of business, <PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said.
   In the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, the financial situation for farmers across the
nation deepened as debt piled up, land values declined and interest
rates edged higher.
   Between <DATE>1978</DATE> and <DATE>1984</DATE>, the total value of farm products sold
dropped <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT> in the irrigated counties, while they increased
about <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> in the dryland area.
   <PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said the population of the irrigated counties in <DATE>1978-84</DATE>
declined about <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT>, and total employment decreased for the
first time since the Great Depression of the <DATE>1930s</DATE>.
   The trends were much different in the dryland counties. Farm
income rose <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT>, compared with an <PERCENT>18 percent</PERCENT> decline in the
irrigated counties.
   <PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said that was because the proportion of total farm sales
from wheat in the dryland areas tripled from <DATE>1978</DATE> to <DATE>1984</DATE> because
of government price support programs. And dryland farm operations
cost much less.
   In fact, he said, per capita income in the dryland counties in
<DATE>1984</DATE> was higher than it had ever been in the irrigated counties.
Unfortunately, the long decades of decline in the dryland counties
had resulted in a grim bottoming out.
   ``So many people have left that the economy has finally
stabilized, and most of those who remain are those with the jobs
that are still available,'' <PERSON>Holmes</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA040190-0055 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 197814 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 1, 1990, Sunday, South Bay Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 10; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
734 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PEOPLE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Rancho Palos Verdes resident <PERSON>William A. Baker</PERSON>, a 30-year veteran of the <ORGANIZATION>Los 
Angeles County Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION>, has been promoted to chief of the 
department's <ORGANIZATION>Court Services Division</ORGANIZATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Sheriff Sherman Block</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> and his 
wife, <LOCATION>Pearl</LOCATION>, have lived in Rancho Palos Verdes for 19 years and have two 
children, <LOCATION>Arlyce</LOCATION>, a business administrator with <ORGANIZATION>TRW</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>William</PERSON>, an investment 
banker in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Torrance Mayor <PERSON>Katy Geissert</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mary Furutani</PERSON> of <PERSON>Gardena</PERSON> are among <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 
women honored recently as Women of the Year, a program organized by the Women 
Legislators Caucus of the state Legislature. Geissert, a <ORGANIZATION>Torrance</ORGANIZATION> city 
councilwoman from <DATE>1974</DATE> to <DATE>1982</DATE> and mayor since <DATE>1986</DATE>, was named for the <ORGANIZATION>51st 
Assembly District</ORGANIZATION> by Assemblyman <PERSON>Gerald N. Felando</PERSON> (R-San Pedro). Furutani was 
named Woman of the Year for the <ORGANIZATION>53rd Assembly District</ORGANIZATION> by Assemblyman <PERSON>Richard 
E. Floyd</PERSON> (D-Carson), in recognition of her community service. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Torrance YWCA</ORGANIZATION> has named the following six women as <DATE>1990</DATE> Women of the Year 
Honorees: 
</P>
<P>
Sister <PERSON>Nancy Boyle</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Torrance</ORGANIZATION> has been chairman of the board of <ORGANIZATION>Little Company 
of Mary Hospital</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>1986</DATE>. She has served on the executive board of the 
Medical Explorer Program and was instrumental in instituting the <ORGANIZATION>Mary Potter 
Program for Human Dignity</ORGANIZATION> at the hospital. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Carolin Lott</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Torrance</LOCATION>, community relations manager for <ORGANIZATION>Epson America Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, 
works with numerous nonprofit organizations in the community, such as the <ORGANIZATION>South 
Bay-Harbor-Long Beach Volunteer Center</ORGANIZATION>, the Retired Senior Program, the <LOCATION>South 
Bay</LOCATION> <ORGANIZATION>Advisory Council</ORGANIZATION>, chambers of commerce and local churches. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Nell Mirels</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Rolling Hills Estates</ORGANIZATION> has taken on leadership roles as mayor of 
the city of Rolling <PERSON>Hills Estates</PERSON>, councilwoman and head of numerous committees 
and commissions. She is active in community service organizations. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Joan Moe</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Rolling Hills Estates</ORGANIZATION> is co-founder of the <ORGANIZATION>Norris Theatre</ORGANIZATION> for the 
Performing Arts on the <LOCATION>Palos Verdes Peninsula</LOCATION> and has served there in many 
capacities. She has been chairman of the board of the <ORGANIZATION>Switzer Center</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Torrance</LOCATION> and is past president of the <ORGANIZATION>Rolling Hills Estates Woman's Club</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Janet Smith</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Rancho Palos Verdes</ORGANIZATION> has worked with many community organizations 
and is currently involved with the <ORGANIZATION>Community Assn.</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>Peninsula</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Norris 
Theatre</ORGANIZATION> for the Performing Arts, the <ORGANIZATION>Palos Verdes Library District</ORGANIZATION>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>American Assn. of University Women</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Palos Verdes Art Center</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>League of 
Women Voters</ORGANIZATION>, and others. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>LaVon Sutton</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Redondo Beach</LOCATION>, director of volunteer services at <LOCATION>South Bay 
Hospital</LOCATION> and a leader in the <LOCATION>South Bay Hospital Auxiliary</LOCATION>, has supported many 
projects in the <LOCATION>South Bay</LOCATION>. She coordinates health fairs, senior citizens' 
events, holiday aid to families and house calls to ailing seniors who live 
alone. She is an elected member of the <ORGANIZATION>Salvation Army Advisory Board</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Redondo 
Beach Corps</ORGANIZATION>, and an honorary life member of the <ORGANIZATION>South Bay Hospital Auxiliary</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Virginia Wright</PERSON> will be honored <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for her 50-year membership in the 
<ORGANIZATION>National Society</ORGANIZATION> of the Daughters of the <ORGANIZATION>American Revolution</ORGANIZATION> during a meeting 
of <ORGANIZATION>El Redondo Chapter</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>St. Andrew's Presbyterian Church</ORGANIZATION>. 
Also honored will be fifth- and sixth-grade students from <ORGANIZATION>El Segundo Center</ORGANIZATION> and 
Middle schools for their winning essays on "What the Bill of Rights Means to 
Me." ROTC medals will be presented to Sea Cadets <PERSON>Brett D. Chauncey</PERSON> and <PERSON>Thomas 
W. Henneberg</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>El Segundo High School</ORGANIZATION> seniors. 
</P>
<P>
Members of <ORGANIZATION>Temple Beth El</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Pedro</LOCATION> have elected three people to receive the 
<LOCATION>Zebulon</LOCATION> Award for distinguished service and commitment to the temple and the 
Jewish community. They are <ORGANIZATION>Sharon</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Morris Gross</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Lou Marcus</PERSON>. Marcus, now 
living in <LOCATION>Murietta Hot Springs</LOCATION> with his wife, <PERSON>Esther</PERSON>, took an active part in 
the building of the temple and sanctuary. The Grosses are both active in many 
temple and community activities and helped raise the money for the expansion of 
the temple building. The <ORGANIZATION>Zebulon Award</ORGANIZATION> is named after the ancient seafaring 
tribe of <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>. Zebulon is also the name of the Menorah that adorns the 
temple's sanctuary. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Keith Thompson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Harbor City</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Steven Beamer</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Redondo Beach</LOCATION> have become 
volunteers with <ORGANIZATION>Big Brothers of Greater Los Angeles</ORGANIZATION>. Thompson is an employee of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Torrance Police Department</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Beamer</PERSON> is an employee of <ORGANIZATION>Mobil Oil</ORGANIZATION>. Each man 
will spend half a day each week being a friend and a role model to a fatherless 
boy. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, William A. Baker ; Photo, Katy Geissert Katy Geissert 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890816-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-16-89 1330EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-IowaGamblingTowns Adv20   08-16 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Iowa Gambling Towns, Adv 20,0570</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv20</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Aug. 20, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Dubuque Wants Riverboat Gambling License; So Does Tiny McGregor</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Heartland Gambling</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>McGREGOR, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This town, population 945, will try for a
riverboat gambling license. So will <LOCATION>Dubuque</LOCATION>, with more than 60 times
as many people.
   ``I think there's a possibility of us getting a license, but I
think it's an uphill battle,'' said <ORGANIZATION>McGregor Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>
official <PERSON>Charlie Zahn</PERSON>. ``Personally speaking, I think it stinks.''
   The northeast <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> communities, about 60 miles apart on the
<LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION>, are two of the <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> towns that plan to apply for
licenses from the state Racing and <ORGANIZATION>Gaming Commission</ORGANIZATION> following
approval of riverboat gambling in local referendums last week.
   There is no limit on the number of licenses that could be issued,
but observers expect no more than three _ some say only one _ will
be issued for the first year.
   On paper, <LOCATION>Dubuque</LOCATION> would appear to have an overwhelming edge. The
city boasts many tourism attractions, highlighted by <LOCATION>Mississippi
River</LOCATION> boat tours and the first dog track granted a parimutuel
license when gambling was legalized in <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> four years ago.
   But McGregor officials concede nothing.
   Their own attractions include a 970-acre park named for <PERSON>Zebulon
Pike</PERSON>, a series of 191 preserved prehistoric Indian burial grounds,
and thousands of acres for hunting and camping. Officials felt
confident enough of obtaining a riverboat gambling license to hire a
contractor to build a boat dock for about <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY>.
   McGregor is a half-mile stretch of restaurants, antique shops,
taverns and other stores nestled between forested bluffs overlooking
the river.
   ``Being a smaller community, I think it's only fair that we
should have an opportunity like this, rather than everything going
to the big urban areas,'' said <ORGANIZATION>McGregor City Clerk Norm Lincoln</ORGANIZATION>.
   Dubuque has a different argument for the gaming commission.
   ``There is a point that's reached where there's too many people
in too small a geographic region all trying to do the same thing. I
think a full-fledged operation like we plan in <LOCATION>Dubuque</LOCATION> and a
full-bore operation very close to us, such as <PERSON>McGregor</PERSON>, might be a
little bit much,'' said <PERSON>Don Hess</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Dubuque Racing
Association</ORGANIZATION>, the non-profit group seeking a license.
   <PERSON>Hess</PERSON>, also director of marketing and communications at <LOCATION>Dubuque
Greyhound Park</LOCATION>, said five dog tracks are due to open in neighboring
<LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, potentially cutting attendance and revenue in <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>.
   ``We're hoping to secure a riverboat gambling license to get a
floating casino out on the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> so we can have two major
tourism draws that will allow us to bring back some of these people
that we'll be losing to <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>.''
   A floating casino could mean 300 jobs and an extra <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> a
year to the local economy, <PERSON>Hess</PERSON> said.
   In <PERSON>McGregor</PERSON>, officials feel the state almost owes them a license
to compensate for lost taxes on thousand of acres around town
purchased by the <ORGANIZATION>Iowa Department of Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``McGregor's never going to land the big industry, and the
economics are such that we'll probably never see a dog track or
horse track,'' Mayor <PERSON>Robyn Denning</PERSON> said. ``We just never seem to get
our fair share of what's going on.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Aug. 20</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881128-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-28-88 1400EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--StampPickers ADV11-2Takes   11-28 1000</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Stamp Pickers, ADV 11-2 Takes,1030</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv11</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Dec. 11</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 drawing.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ When it comes to stamps, millions of citizens
seem to have ideas about what should go on them. Pressure and
controversy can get pretty intense (as in behalf of the Elvis
Presley stamp). That's why the committee that decides meets behind
closed doors and never explains its reasoning for picking one
subject over another.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By SID MOODY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ When it comes to stamps, millions of citizens
seem to have ideas about what should go on them. Pressure and
controversy can get pretty intense (as in behalf of the Elvis
Presley stamp). That's why the committee that decides meets behind
closed doors and never explains its reasoning for picking one
subject over another.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ When it comes to stamps, millions of citizens
seem to have ideas about what should go on them. Pressure and
controversy can get pretty intense (as in behalf of the Elvis
Presley stamp). That's why the committee that decides meets behind
closed doors and never explains its reasoning for picking one
subject over another.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911113-0059
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911113-0059.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf:
   Lear in Iowa: Family Farm, Family Trouble
   ----
   By Julia Just
</HL>
<DATE>
11/13/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A14
</SO>
<LP>
   Jane Smiley's latest novel, "A Thousand Acres" (Knopf, 352
pages, $23), is set in Zebulon County, Iowa, where the
farmland is "thicker, richer, more alive with a past and
future than any soil anywhere." The land is also layered with
long-festering intrigues among jealous neighbors, and poisons
blamed for miscarriages and cancer. This is the novel's
overriding metaphor -- a rich but deceptive topsoil yielding
up secrets of the buried past.
   Initially, the story's calm, inviting surface recalls Joan
Chase's lyrical portrait of a family farm in "During the
Reign of the Queen of Persia," as well as Ms. Smiley's own
previous works of fiction, with their almost uncannily
precise depictions of daily life. In her widely praised books
"The Age of Grief" and "The Greenlanders," Ms. Smiley made
the very ordinariness of things the most compelling substance
of her narratives. But "A Thousand Acres" turns out to be
closer in spirit to her ambitious recent novella, "Good
Will," in which seemingly innocent beginnings lead to dark
revelations and unexpected violence.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The novel, set in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE>, is narrated by <PERSON>Ginny</PERSON>,
whose father, <PERSON>Larry Cook</PERSON>, owns the biggest and most
profitable farm around -- a thousand acres. Ginny is an
accommodating, even malleable, sort, although at 36 she has
been bitterly disappointed by a series of miscarriages with
her husband, Ty. She's appealingly levelheaded, but not
immune to deeper impulses; she confesses to harboring vague
desires, "secret, passionate wishes."
   While the youngest sister, <PERSON>Caroline</PERSON>, went to college and
became a tough-talking lawyer in <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ginny</PERSON> and her
sister Rose stayed behind on the farm. It is soon apparent
why. After their mother died, when they were teenagers, their
father became an abusive tyrant who kept the entire family
under his thumb. Later, <PERSON>Rose</PERSON> will force <PERSON>Ginny</PERSON> to remember
just how abusive "Daddy" was; as time goes on, that word
comes to have chilling, Sylvia Plath-like overtones.
   When the father suddenly decides to cede the farm to his
three daughters, it brings the hidden past to the surface and
winds up setting each family member against the other,
irrevocably. Another catalyst is <PERSON>Jess Clark</PERSON>, a neighbor's
prodigal son, back from <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, where he had been since
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. For a while, he's the answer to <PERSON>Ginny</PERSON>'s "passionate
wishes" -- and he convinces her that the farm's runoff in the
groundwater is to blame for her miscarriages.
   <PERSON>Ms. Smiley</PERSON> can describe compounding strains in a marriage
better than anybody, and the confrontations between <PERSON>Ginny</PERSON> and
Ty -- quiet but devastating -- are among the best scenes in
the book. She's superb at depicting the surface effects of
feelings "too complicated . . . to name," the way trust can
"disappear into formality," and she plays off this life of
the emotions beautifully against the daily necessities of the
farm.
   Wonderfully evoked, too, are the pressures of keeping up
appearances in a small town. Ultimately, <PERSON>Ginny</PERSON> concludes,
putting the best face on things in front of the neighbors is
the "broken plank you are left with after the ship has gone
down." Still, as the sisters confront their old father and
his tainted bequest, the unending string of disasters that
follows seems more than strictly necessary, while the
characters' motivations sometimes hover on the outer edges of
plausibility.
   It's pretty clear early on to the reader, for example,
that the erratic old farmer is in the initial stages of
Alzheimer's disease, but <PERSON>Caroline</PERSON> never seems to figure it
out. This is overly convenient, since it's essential to the
story that she blame the rest of the family for everything
that happens. As for <PERSON>Ginny</PERSON>, our sympathetic companion, the
ever-present litany of her household chores ("I spent the
morning shampooing the carpet . . .") will eventually include
preparing a jar of poisoned sausage. We've come a long way
from the stewed pork chops and kitchen-table confidences that
open this book.
   Still, the novel's center holds firm. Its narrative
momentum is undeniable, as is the psychological truth (with
its deliberate nod to "Lear") underlying the mortal combat
between <PERSON>Larry Cook</PERSON> and his daughters, and among the newly
estranged sisters. Indeed, if the grim patriarch dominates
the first half of the book, Rose -- grabby and manipulative
and iron-willed -- dominates the second. Of all the other
illusions of past and future, <PERSON>Ginny</PERSON>'s adoring love for Rose,
her conviction that they were a team "united" against their
father, proves the most traumatic to give up. It is a point
of no return, but also exhilarating:
   "The strongest feeling was that now I knew them all,"
<PERSON>Ginny</PERSON> says of her divided family. "Rather than feeling `not
myself,' I felt intensely, newly, more myself than ever
before." It is the beginning of a new life, far from the old
"ordered, hard-working world."
   As for the thousand-acre farm in <LOCATION>Zebulon County</LOCATION>, one
notices right away that <PERSON>Ms. Smiley</PERSON>'s novel begins in <DATE>1979</DATE> --
on the brink of the <LOCATION>Midwestern</LOCATION> farm crisis, with its falling
land values and rising suicide rates. The timing is an apt
and melancholy touch -- as though <PERSON>Larry Cook</PERSON> foresaw it all,
and wanted no part of it.
   ---
   <PERSON>Ms. Just</PERSON> is on the editorial staff of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Review
of Books</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880617-0123 </DOCNO>
<HL> Investor Seeks to Increase Interest in Home Owners </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> HFS GOVMT </CO>
<IN> BNK TNM </IN>
<DATELINE> MANCHESTER, N.H.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Milo L. Pike</PERSON> said he has applied to the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Home Loan Bank Board</ORGANIZATION> to increase his stake in <ORGANIZATION>Home Owners Federal Savings &amp; Loan Association</ORGANIZATION>'s common stock to <PERCENT>24.9%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>9.9%</PERCENT>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Pike</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Bank Board</ORGANIZATION> has informed him that consideration of the application has been delayed pending receipt of additional information. 

   Even if the application is approved, additional purchases by <PERSON>Mr. Pike</PERSON> may be subject to limits under Home Owners' charter. 
Any additional purchases would be for investment purposes, <PERSON>Mr. Pike</PERSON> said in a statement. 


   As previously reported in a page-one story in yesterday's Wall Street Journal, <PERSON>Mr. Pike</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> investor, has been a key player in an ongoing tug of war between Home Owners shareholders and short-sellers, whose activity has driven the stock down in recent months. 

   <LOCATION>Burlington</LOCATION>, Mass.-based Home Owners couldn't be reached for comment on <PERSON>Mr. Pike</PERSON>'s announcement, which was made after the market closed yesterday. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-15184</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJMCRAC7FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931013
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 OCT 93 / Observer: Pike landed
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Last <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <PERSON>Francis Pike</PERSON> dropped in for a board meeting of <ORGANIZATION>Drayton Far
Eastern Trust</ORGANIZATION>, before heading to <LOCATION>Chelsea</LOCATION> register office to wed Lady <PERSON>Annabel
Goldsmith</PERSON>'s daughter, India-Jane Birley. Pike's new boss, <PERSON>Philip Tose</PERSON>,
chairman of Hong Kong-based investment bank <ORGANIZATION>Peregrine Securities</ORGANIZATION>, flew in
for the day to be best man.
Without further ado, <PERSON>Pike</PERSON> left for <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, where he has 10 weeks before
opening the doors of a joint venture between <ORGANIZATION>Peregrine</ORGANIZATION> and Indian tobacco
company <ORGANIZATION>ITC</ORGANIZATION>.
Pike had spent the <DATE>last 14 years</DATE> at fund managers <ORGANIZATION>Invesco</ORGANIZATION>, 24 per cent of
which is now held by <ORGANIZATION>Peregrine</ORGANIZATION>. When management upheavals at <ORGANIZATION>Invesco</ORGANIZATION> a year
ago made his position uncomfortable, <PERSON>Pike</PERSON>, who has spent much of his time in
the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>, took a call from his old friend <PERSON>Tose</PERSON>.
Having created <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>'s largest independent merchant banking group in
under five years, <PERSON>Tose</PERSON>'s ambitions now stretch to repeating the success
story throughout <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>.
With the help of close associate <PERSON>Li Ka-Shing</PERSON>, lack of capital is not one of
<PERSON>Tose</PERSON>'s problems. Peregrine last year sunk Dollars 30m into <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION> in
another joint venture, with commodities giant Dongbang.
<ORGANIZATION>ITC</ORGANIZATION>, meanwhile, rejected several British merchant banks in favour of the
Asian partner for its foray into financial services.
An adaptable sort, 39-year-old <PERSON>Pike</PERSON> spent his first three months in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>
living in a Zen Buddhist temple before getting stuck into what he calls the
'gaijin ghetto'. But he is far from unworldly, as his blue <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION>, fondly
remembered by Japanese friends, demonstrated.
In taking on the still formidable difficulties of the Indian market, he will
not be stuck for more ways to make his mark.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Peregrine.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>INZ  India, Asia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6211 Security Brokers and Dealers.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891108-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-08-89 0435EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-ELN--ElectionBriefs     11-08 1001</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-ELN--Election Briefs,1036</SECOND>
<HEAD>Racial Slur Triggers Ouster Of Veteran Houston City Councilman</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A political unknown defeated veteran City
Councilman <PERSON>Jim Westmoreland</PERSON>, whose racial slur involving the late
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON> triggered protest.
   For an at-large seat on the 15-member council, <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>
attracted 142,026 votes, or <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>, to 116,244 or <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> for
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Westmoreland</PERSON> said on <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> that <LOCATION>Houston Intercontinental
Airport</LOCATION> should be called ``Nigger International'' to appease council
members pushing to rename the airport after <PERSON>Leland</PERSON>, the black
congressman killed in an <DATE>Aug. 7</DATE> plane crash while aiding famine
victims in <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>.
   Last week, council members approved a resolution censuring
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION> for the comment.
   <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>, 34, is a minority recruiter for the <ORGANIZATION>University
Outreach Program</ORGANIZATION>, a partnership involving the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston,
program helps <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> middle school and high school students
interested in attending college.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Democrat Elected East Orange, N.J., Mayor; Succeeds Indicted</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   A political unknown defeated veteran City
Councilman <PERSON>Jim Westmoreland</PERSON>, whose racial slur involving the late
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON> triggered protest.
   For an at-large seat on the 15-member council, <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>
attracted 142,026 votes, or <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>, to 116,244 or <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> for
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Westmoreland</PERSON> said on <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> that <LOCATION>Houston Intercontinental
Airport</LOCATION> should be called ``Nigger International'' to appease council
members pushing to rename the airport after <PERSON>Leland</PERSON>, the black
congressman killed in an <DATE>Aug. 7</DATE> plane crash while aiding famine
victims in <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>.
   Last week, council members approved a resolution censuring
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION> for the comment.
   <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>, 34, is a minority recruiter for the <ORGANIZATION>University
Outreach Program</ORGANIZATION>, a partnership involving the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston,
program helps <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> middle school and high school students
interested in attending college.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>EAST ORANGE, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A political unknown defeated veteran City
Councilman <PERSON>Jim Westmoreland</PERSON>, whose racial slur involving the late
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON> triggered protest.
   For an at-large seat on the 15-member council, <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>
attracted 142,026 votes, or <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>, to 116,244 or <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> for
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Westmoreland</PERSON> said on <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> that <LOCATION>Houston Intercontinental
Airport</LOCATION> should be called ``Nigger International'' to appease council
members pushing to rename the airport after <PERSON>Leland</PERSON>, the black
congressman killed in an <DATE>Aug. 7</DATE> plane crash while aiding famine
victims in <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>.
   Last week, council members approved a resolution censuring
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION> for the comment.
   <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>, 34, is a minority recruiter for the <ORGANIZATION>University
Outreach Program</ORGANIZATION>, a partnership involving the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston,
program helps <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> middle school and high school students
interested in attending college.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Zebulon, Ga., Mayor Denies Racial Intent in Registration Session</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ZEBULON, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A political unknown defeated veteran City
Councilman <PERSON>Jim Westmoreland</PERSON>, whose racial slur involving the late
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON> triggered protest.
   For an at-large seat on the 15-member council, <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>
attracted 142,026 votes, or <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>, to 116,244 or <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> for
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Westmoreland</PERSON> said on <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> that <LOCATION>Houston Intercontinental
Airport</LOCATION> should be called ``Nigger International'' to appease council
members pushing to rename the airport after <PERSON>Leland</PERSON>, the black
congressman killed in an <DATE>Aug. 7</DATE> plane crash while aiding famine
victims in <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>.
   Last week, council members approved a resolution censuring
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION> for the comment.
   <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>, 34, is a minority recruiter for the <ORGANIZATION>University
Outreach Program</ORGANIZATION>, a partnership involving the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston,
program helps <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> middle school and high school students
interested in attending college.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Twin Brothers Defeated in Salem City Council Race</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SALEM, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A political unknown defeated veteran City
Councilman <PERSON>Jim Westmoreland</PERSON>, whose racial slur involving the late
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON> triggered protest.
   For an at-large seat on the 15-member council, <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>
attracted 142,026 votes, or <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>, to 116,244 or <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> for
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Westmoreland</PERSON> said on <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> that <LOCATION>Houston Intercontinental
Airport</LOCATION> should be called ``Nigger International'' to appease council
members pushing to rename the airport after <PERSON>Leland</PERSON>, the black
congressman killed in an <DATE>Aug. 7</DATE> plane crash while aiding famine
victims in <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>.
   Last week, council members approved a resolution censuring
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION> for the comment.
   <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>, 34, is a minority recruiter for the <ORGANIZATION>University
Outreach Program</ORGANIZATION>, a partnership involving the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston,
program helps <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> middle school and high school students
interested in attending college.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Mayor Masloff Runs Unopposed in Pittsburgh</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A political unknown defeated veteran City
Councilman <PERSON>Jim Westmoreland</PERSON>, whose racial slur involving the late
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON> triggered protest.
   For an at-large seat on the 15-member council, <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>
attracted 142,026 votes, or <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>, to 116,244 or <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> for
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Westmoreland</PERSON> said on <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> that <LOCATION>Houston Intercontinental
Airport</LOCATION> should be called ``Nigger International'' to appease council
members pushing to rename the airport after <PERSON>Leland</PERSON>, the black
congressman killed in an <DATE>Aug. 7</DATE> plane crash while aiding famine
victims in <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>.
   Last week, council members approved a resolution censuring
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION> for the comment.
   <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>, 34, is a minority recruiter for the <ORGANIZATION>University
Outreach Program</ORGANIZATION>, a partnership involving the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston,
program helps <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> middle school and high school students
interested in attending college.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>`Capt. Tony' Elected Elected Mayor of Key West</NOTE>
<DATELINE>KEY WEST, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A political unknown defeated veteran City
Councilman <PERSON>Jim Westmoreland</PERSON>, whose racial slur involving the late
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON> triggered protest.
   For an at-large seat on the 15-member council, <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>
attracted 142,026 votes, or <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>, to 116,244 or <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> for
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Westmoreland</PERSON> said on <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> that <LOCATION>Houston Intercontinental
Airport</LOCATION> should be called ``Nigger International'' to appease council
members pushing to rename the airport after <PERSON>Leland</PERSON>, the black
congressman killed in an <DATE>Aug. 7</DATE> plane crash while aiding famine
victims in <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>.
   Last week, council members approved a resolution censuring
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION> for the comment.
   <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>, 34, is a minority recruiter for the <ORGANIZATION>University
Outreach Program</ORGANIZATION>, a partnership involving the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston,
program helps <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> middle school and high school students
interested in attending college.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Nobody Shows Up To Vote In Rural Town</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PAHAQUARRY TOWNSHIP, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A political unknown defeated veteran City
Councilman <PERSON>Jim Westmoreland</PERSON>, whose racial slur involving the late
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Mickey Leland</PERSON> triggered protest.
   For an at-large seat on the 15-member council, <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>
attracted 142,026 votes, or <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>, to 116,244 or <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> for
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Westmoreland</PERSON> said on <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE> that <LOCATION>Houston Intercontinental
Airport</LOCATION> should be called ``Nigger International'' to appease council
members pushing to rename the airport after <PERSON>Leland</PERSON>, the black
congressman killed in an <DATE>Aug. 7</DATE> plane crash while aiding famine
victims in <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>.
   Last week, council members approved a resolution censuring
<LOCATION>Westmoreland</LOCATION> for the comment.
   <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>, 34, is a minority recruiter for the <ORGANIZATION>University
Outreach Program</ORGANIZATION>, a partnership involving the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston,
program helps <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> middle school and high school students
interested in attending college.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880805-0184 </DOCNO>
<HL> Stake in Portsmouth Bank Shares of 5.2% Acquired by Investor </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> POBS </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<DATELINE> PORTSMOUTH, N.H.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Milo Pike</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> businessman, said he acquired a <PERCENT>5.2%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Portsmouth Bank Shares Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   In a <ORGANIZATION>Securities and Exchange Commission</ORGANIZATION> filing, <PERSON>Mr. Pike</PERSON> said he holds 205,000 of <LOCATION>Portsmouth</LOCATION>'s common shares, including 75,500 shares purchased from <DATE>June 10 through July 27</DATE> at prices ranging from <MONEY>$10.9375</MONEY> to <MONEY>$11.50</MONEY> a share. 

   According to the filing, <PERSON>Mr. Pike</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Pike Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tilton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>, purchased the shares for investment purposes. 

   A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Portsmouth Bank Shares</ORGANIZATION>, a bank holding company located here, declined to comment on the filing. 
The company went public in <DATE>February</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881102-0021 </DOCNO>
<HL> Suffield Financial Corp. Holders Plan to Discuss Buying Coastal Unit </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> SFCP </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two men who own <PERCENT>9.98%</PERCENT> of the shares outstanding of <ORGANIZATION>Suffield Financial Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said they plan to discuss with management acquiring <ORGANIZATION>Suffield's Coastal Savings Bank</ORGANIZATION> susbidiary. 

   <PERSON>Milo L. Pike</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Pike Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Tilton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Henry M. Powers</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>C.H. Sprague &amp; Son Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Portsmouth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>, disclosed the plan in a <ORGANIZATION>Securities and Exchange Commission</ORGANIZATION> filing. 
They said they may sell the subsidiary, based in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, after buying it. 

   In <LOCATION>Suffield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, a spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>Suffield Financial</ORGANIZATION> said the bank holding company didn't have any immediate comment. 

   Messrs. 
<PERSON>Pike</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Powers</ORGANIZATION> reiterated a previous statement that they are looking for a third party to acquire <LOCATION>Suffield</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Pike</PERSON> has been an active investor in <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> bank stocks. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880713-0230 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-13-88 2310EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SchoolTakeover     07-13 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-School Takeover,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Takes Control of Debt-Ridden Pike County Schools' Finances</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FRANKFORT, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The state took control of <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>'s
third-largest school district's finances <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, citing a budget
deficit estimated by consultants to have been as high as <MONEY>$3.3
million</MONEY>.
   The action by the <ORGANIZATION>State Board of Education</ORGANIZATION> means state
Superintendent <PERSON>John Brock</PERSON>'s written approval will be needed for all
hiring and purchases by the <LOCATION>Pike County</LOCATION> district, which has 15,250
students in 30 schools.
   The board acted after two consultants it sent into the
mountainous eastern <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> district reported dozens of management
problems.
   ``Beyond what we see in writing, there are unique political
problems in <LOCATION>Pike County</LOCATION> at the present time,'' <PERSON>Brock</PERSON> said.
   ``I think the (state board) would have to take some
extraordinary action at this time. ... I think they need some
help,'' <PERSON>Brock</PERSON> said.
   He said the state veto over local hiring would relieve the local
board of some political pressure to dole out school jobs _ pressure
that has increased as layoffs increase in the coal industry,
according to the report by consultants <PERSON>Arnold Oaken</PERSON> and <PERSON>James
Melton</PERSON>.
   Brock also said it ``would remove that temptation'' for school
board candidates to promise jobs for votes. Three of the board's
five members are up for re-election in <DATE>November</DATE>.
   The chief reason for the state board's action, however, was <ORGANIZATION>Pike
County</ORGANIZATION>'s third straight year of running a deficit budget.
   On paper, it has been cut from <MONEY>$3.3 million</MONEY> to about <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY>,
but that is illusory, <PERSON>Melton</PERSON> and Oaken told the board.
   The district soon will have to borrow <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> to keep
operating, increasing the debt to near <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> again, and the
purchase of new school buses can be delayed no longer, they said.
   The local board has voted to close one elementary school, but
the report by Oaken and <PERSON>Melton</PERSON> said five should be closed, with 780
pupils redistributed. In the past, when the county has built new
schools, it has declined to close old ones, <PERSON>Melton</PERSON> said.
   It was not immediately known how long the state would manage
<LOCATION>Pike County</LOCATION> schools' finances under the seldom-used statute it
invoked. The action is less severe than a declaration of ``academic
bankruptcy,'' by which the state would take over actual management
of the school system.
   <PERSON>Brock</PERSON> said he would place a lieutenant in <LOCATION>Pike County</LOCATION> to oversee
the school system's finances. <PERSON>Brock</PERSON> said he had a former school
superintendent, whom he would not identify, in mind for the job.
   In <LOCATION>Pikeville</LOCATION>, school board Chairman <PERSON>Alvin Newsome</PERSON> said he
welcomed the state takeover, and 18-year board veteran <PERSON>Gifford
Varney</PERSON> said he hoped the action marked a turning point for the
district. But two other members said they believed the takeover had
been unnecessary.
   If <LOCATION>Pike County</LOCATION> voters were unhappy with board members, they
could elect someone else to do the job, said board member <PERSON>Carl
Biliter</PERSON>. He said the state action surprised him, but added, ``We
don't have no say over it because we were in debt.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881230-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-88 0237EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-30 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0496</SECOND>
<HEAD>On The Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLORADO SPRINGS, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   While a nearly all-male club is
making its annual New Year's Eve trek up 14,110-foot <PERSON>Pike</PERSON>'s Peak, a
group of women will be making a 1,000-foot ascent of a nearby
mountain in jest of the traditional event.
   This year's climb will mark the 66th annual climb of <ORGANIZATION>Pike</ORGANIZATION>'s Peak
by the AdAmAn club, which plans to set off fireworks at the summit.
The group adds a climber each year.
   AdaWoman, a band founded in <DATE>1982</DATE>, will make an ascent on <ORGANIZATION>Pyramid
Mountain</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ute Pass</LOCATION> west of <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, light sparklers, play
<PERSON>Helen Reddy</PERSON>'s song ``I Am Woman,'' down champagne and head home for
the night, organizers said.
   It will be the seventh climb for the AdaWoman club, which was
founded almost as a lark by <PERSON>Rita Randolph</PERSON> and several other woman
who train on <ORGANIZATION>Pyramid Mountain</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It's really beautiful up there, and one morning we had run the
mountain and decided this was the way we should start out the new
year together,'' she said.
   The women also were prodded that year because AdAmAn, for the
first time in its history, was inviting a female guest, veteran
climber Sue <PERSON>Graham</PERSON>.
   ``One of the AdAmAn members said that the reason they hadn't done
it before was they didn't know any women who could make it,'' said
<PERSON>Randolph</PERSON>. ``Well, I and another of our members ran the Pikes Peak
Marathon, so I think we can make it.''
   AdAmAn historian <PERSON>Jim Bates</PERSON> said <PERSON>Graham</PERSON>, still the only woman
invited, will make her fourth climb with the club this year.
   ``Of course, when we started this climb in <DATE>1922</DATE>, you couldn't
have hired a woman to go with us. It wasn't until a few years ago
that women got so they were into this type of thing,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Randolph</PERSON> said AdaWoman may add a man in 50 or 60 years, if one is
found worthy.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   While a nearly all-male club is
making its annual New Year's Eve trek up 14,110-foot <PERSON>Pike</PERSON>'s Peak, a
group of women will be making a 1,000-foot ascent of a nearby
mountain in jest of the traditional event.
   This year's climb will mark the 66th annual climb of <ORGANIZATION>Pike</ORGANIZATION>'s Peak
by the AdAmAn club, which plans to set off fireworks at the summit.
The group adds a climber each year.
   AdaWoman, a band founded in <DATE>1982</DATE>, will make an ascent on <ORGANIZATION>Pyramid
Mountain</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ute Pass</LOCATION> west of <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, light sparklers, play
<PERSON>Helen Reddy</PERSON>'s song ``I Am Woman,'' down champagne and head home for
the night, organizers said.
   It will be the seventh climb for the AdaWoman club, which was
founded almost as a lark by <PERSON>Rita Randolph</PERSON> and several other woman
who train on <ORGANIZATION>Pyramid Mountain</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It's really beautiful up there, and one morning we had run the
mountain and decided this was the way we should start out the new
year together,'' she said.
   The women also were prodded that year because AdAmAn, for the
first time in its history, was inviting a female guest, veteran
climber Sue <PERSON>Graham</PERSON>.
   ``One of the AdAmAn members said that the reason they hadn't done
it before was they didn't know any women who could make it,'' said
<PERSON>Randolph</PERSON>. ``Well, I and another of our members ran the Pikes Peak
Marathon, so I think we can make it.''
   AdAmAn historian <PERSON>Jim Bates</PERSON> said <PERSON>Graham</PERSON>, still the only woman
invited, will make her fourth climb with the club this year.
   ``Of course, when we started this climb in <DATE>1922</DATE>, you couldn't
have hired a woman to go with us. It wasn't until a few years ago
that women got so they were into this type of thing,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Randolph</PERSON> said AdaWoman may add a man in 50 or 60 years, if one is
found worthy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881107-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-07-88 0824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TitanLaunch     11-07 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Titan Launch,0360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Titan Missile Launched, Probably Carries Military Satellites</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VANDENBERG AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Titan 34D rocket
thundered into space with a secret cargo during the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, and one
expert said it probably carried a pair of military communication
satellites into orbit.
   The 16-story-tall booster blasted off <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, said <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> Capt. <PERSON>John Sullivan</PERSON>, a spokesman for the sprawling Vandenberg
military base on the coast 140 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   As usual for military space flights, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> didn't
announce the launch in advance and declined to identify its payload.
   However, it most likely carried two Satellite Data System
satellites, although it also might have carried either a KH-9 or
KH-11 photo reconnaissance satellite, said <PERSON>John Pike</PERSON>, a space policy
expert for the Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>Federation of American Scientists</ORGANIZATION>.
   Pike, who knew about the launch in advance, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> the data
system satellites are used for military communications.
   The satellites provide ``a way for the president to stay in touch
with our nuclear forces ... to give bombers and (silo-based crews
operating) missiles the `go code''' to launch nuclear warheads, he
said.
   <PERSON>Pike</PERSON> said two <ORGANIZATION>SDS</ORGANIZATION> satellites were ``launched five years ago.
They're due for replacement.''
   <ORGANIZATION>SDS</ORGANIZATION> and KH-series satellites are the only types launched from
<LOCATION>Vandenberg</LOCATION> on Titan 34Ds, he said.
   ``The reason I think it's <ORGANIZATION>SDS</ORGANIZATION> is I don't think the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> has
any more KH-9s or KH-11s,'' <PERSON>Pike</PERSON> said.
   The Titan 34D, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s most powerful space booster, will be
supplanted by the Titan 4, due for its maiden launch next year from
<LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   The last launch of a Titan 34D was from <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sept.
2</DATE>, but sources told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> it failed to place its
payload in orbit.
   Pike described that payload as a satellite designed to monitor
Soviet missile tests and radio, telephone, radar and other
electronic communications.
   Two Titan 34Ds were launched successfully in late <DATE>1987</DATE>. Before
then, they were grounded following two straight explosions during
launches on <DATE>Aug. 28, 1985</DATE>, and <DATE>April 18, 1986</DATE>, destroying a KH-11
and a KH-9.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061090-0213 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 231872 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 10, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 10; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1086 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AMERICA'S HEROES: MARBLE AND BRONZE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES HILLINGER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Each year, 1.5 million visitors view the bronze and marble statues that stand 
throughout the Capitol waiting to be recognized. 
</P>
<P>
Some are well-known. Many are not. 
</P>
<P>
Since <DATE>1864</DATE>, each state has been entitled to donate statues of two of its most 
distinguished deceased citizens for permanent exhibit in the <LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Once a state legislature decides who is to be honored, a statue is created and 
accepted by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for a place in the <ORGANIZATION>National Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION> -- <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s 
hall of fame. 
</P>
<P>
"People are always anxious to see the statues from their state. But often 
they're surprised and disappointed because they have no idea who (the people) 
depicted in the statues are," said <PERSON>Barbara Wolanin</PERSON>, 46, curator of <ORGANIZATION>Statuary 
Hall</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>1978</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s statues, both dedicated on <DATE>March 1, 1930</DATE>, are of a minister and a 
priest. It is the only state with two statues of clergy. 
</P>
<P>
Most visitors recognize Father <PERSON>Junipero Serra</PERSON>, the Franciscan priest who 
established nine <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> missions before he died in <DATE>1784</DATE>. Father <PERSON>Serra</PERSON>'s 
bronze likeness holds a little mission in his left hand, and in the right, a 
cross, held high above his head. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Thomas Starr King</PERSON> is not so familiar. "What did he do?" Californians typically 
ask when they see the statue. 
</P>
<P>
King, a Unitarian minister, came to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in <DATE>1860</DATE> from <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> to serve as 
pastor of the <ORGANIZATION>First Unitarian Church of San Francisco</ORGANIZATION>. It was during the Civil 
War and many Californians favored the Confederacy. Of the more than 100 
newspapers in the state, only 24 supported <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"King traveled throughout <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> championing the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> cause. He is 
remembered as the man whose matchless oratory kept <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in the union," 
curator <PERSON>Wolanin</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
King lived in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> only four years before dying at age 40 in <DATE>1864</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Of the 95 statues from 50 states, 14 are of religious leaders, including Father 
<PERSON>Damien</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>), who devoted his life to lepers on <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>; Father <ORGANIZATION>Kino</ORGANIZATION> 
(<LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>), a Jesuit missionary, and <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>), the <ORGANIZATION>Mormon Church</ORGANIZATION> 
leader. 
</P>
<P>
Five states -- <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> -- have 
contributed only one statue each. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>May 2</DATE>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> became the latest state to present its second statue, a 7-foot-7 
bronze likeness of lanky <PERSON>Philo T. Farnsworth</PERSON> (1906-1971), known as the "Father 
of Television." The statue shows <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> holding one of his first 
cathode-ray tubes. He transmitted his first electronic TV picture in <DATE>1927</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Students at <ORGANIZATION>Ridgecrest Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Butler</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, under the guidance of 
Principal <PERSON>Bruce Barnson</PERSON>, led the effort to put the <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> statue in the 
<LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In a statewide poll conducted by students, residents favored <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> over 20 
other Utahans, including <PERSON>Eliza Snow</PERSON>, a poet and wife of <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young; Mormon 
Church</ORGANIZATION> leader <PERSON>Ezra Taft Benson</PERSON>; hotelier <PERSON>J. Willard Marriott</PERSON>, and heavyweight 
boxing champion <PERSON>Jack Dempsey</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Among those present for <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Norman Bangerter</PERSON>'s unveiling of the statue 
was the inventor's 81-year-old widow, <PERSON>Elma</PERSON> (Pem) <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Three statues are of Presidents: <PERSON>George Washington</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Andrew Jackson</PERSON> 
(<LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>James A. Garfield</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>). Four are of vice presidents, 36 of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
senators, 23 of <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> members, 30 of governors and 32 of military heroes. (Some 
held more than one of these titles.) Six statues honor women: <PERSON>Dr. Florence 
Sabin</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>), author of the "Sabin Health Laws" that modernized <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>'s 
public health system; <PERSON>Frances Willard</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>), founder of the Women's <ORGANIZATION>Christian 
Temperance Union</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Marie Sanford</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>), educator and champion of women's 
rights; <PERSON>Jeannette Rankin</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>), the nation's first congresswoman; Mother 
<PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>), a Catholic nun who contributed to the fields of health care, 
education and social work, and <PERSON>Esther Hobart Morris</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>), the first woman to 
hold judicial office in the nation. 
</P>
<P>
six physicians. A king is here -- Kamehameha (<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>), and a famed cowboy 
artist -- <PERSON>Charley Russell</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>). Oklahoma honors two American Indians: 
Sequoya, inventor of the Cherokee alphabet, and <PERSON>Will Rogers</PERSON>, humorist, 
newspaper columnist and movie star. 
</P>
<P>
In keeping with <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON>' famous advice to "Always keep an eye on <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to see 
what they're up to," his statue is the only one facing the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> chamber. 
</P>
<P>
The feet of many of the statues gleam from constant rubbing, "for good luck," 
by visitors. Will <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> has the shiniest feet of all. 
</P>
<P>
There are statues of the president and vice president of the <LOCATION>Confederacy</LOCATION>, 
