<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06190131 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06190131 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  THERE seem to be two schools of thought, neither of which is very large, about
this new photo at the top of my column. Some people tell me they love it.
Others say it makes me look old, because I must be bald if I'm wearing a hat.
Well, I still have my hair, but I am old.;    Meanwhile, there have been
letters on other, more interesting topics:  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  READERS COMPLIMENT, COMPLAIN, COMMENT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Lee Quarnstrom's columns appear on Mondays.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Mr. Lee Quarnstrom</PERSON>, I resent your ignorant view you have of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz
County</LOCATION> . . .;    <PERSON>Dennis Campi</PERSON>; <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION>;    Thanks for sharing, <LOCATION>Dennis.</LOCATION>; We
appreciate the fact that you included our store in your feature article on
shopping in our part of the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Mall</LOCATION>. We have no doubts that your
intentions were good, and that you thought that by describing <PERSON>Anubis Warpus</PERSON> as
a "punk" store, you were helping our business . . . We are writing to you
because we feel that you misrepresented the true character of our store . . .
The store has much more to offer, and "punks" constitute a negligible portion
of our clientele . . . Your article has stirred some negative emotions toward
us, since the word "punk" tends to have negative associations, especially
among people who are older and more conservative than ourselves and people who
shop at Anubis.;    Anubis Warpus; <PERSON>Jacek Lentz</PERSON> and <PERSON>Brian Friedman</PERSON>,; owners;
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>;  You note in your letter that you sell <PERSON>Dr. Martens</PERSON> shoes, those
favored by punks. I guess I could say, if the shoe fits, wear it. But, since
I'm basically a nice guy, let me merely say that your inventory, which
includes black leather clothing, material on tattooing, lava lamps, etc.,
looks dandy, and I'm sure you're correct when you say that your customers
include grandmothers, students and "young people in general with a taste
somewhat out of the ordinary." Let me also say that what you consider
"somewhat out of the ordinary" seems to this "older and more conservative"
<PERSON>Santa Cruzan</PERSON> to be rather banal. Anyway, best of luck. Meanwhile, let's try to
call it "the Avenue" instead of the Mall.; YOUR column indicates that you have
accepted the <ORGANIZATION>Warren Commission</ORGANIZATION>'s canard that <PERSON>Lee Harvey Oswald</PERSON> murdered <PERSON>John
<PERSON>Iain Prentice</PERSON>; <LOCATION>Sunnyvale</LOCATION>;    If you'd have been a newspaper reporter for as
long as I have, you, too, might have serious doubts not only about the ability
of the <ORGANIZATION>CIA</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> or <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military, whom you say you suspect, to pull off such a
conspiracy, but also to keep everyone involved from blabbing during the past
27-plus years. Also, frankly, more than a quarter-century later, I don't
really care anymore who killed JFK. The man is dead, and a lot of good-headed,
good-hearted political concepts died with him.; THE statement that
"<LOCATION>Watsonville</LOCATION> is on the brink of disaster" is totally inaccurate and
reprehensible. This city has made great strides in recovery . . . from the
earthquake and agricultural setbacks.;    <PERSON>Anne Lucero</PERSON>; <LOCATION>Watsonville</LOCATION>;    There
has been a lot of construction on Main Street compared to what's been going on
in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>. But I still believe that <ORGANIZATION>Green Giant</ORGANIZATION>'s pullout to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>,
coupled with the need for much more rebuilding, present some grave problems
for your town -- where, by the way, I worked for nine years and still visit
frequently.; Thank you, thank you, thank you so much for making my day. No, my
month . . . with your article about bees. I have not laughed so hard for so
long . . . You are truly funny.;    <PERSON>Janice Marklein</PERSON>; <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>;  I'm passing
your kind remarks along to my editor.; Are you still writing a column? Here is
a self-addressed, stamped envelope.;    Dad;    It's in the mail.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Lee Quarnstrom column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Santa Cruz/Monterey  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910708  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  643  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday July 8, 1991
00190131,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06176121 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06176121 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  WHILE MANY of their compatriots up the street have yet to return to buildings
that have yet to be rebuilt, the merchants of one stretch at the south end of
Pacific Avenue in Santa Cruz seem to be flourishing.;    The men and women
whose businesses sit in the block between Maple and Laurel streets are
exhibiting a vigor and vitality that should be an inspiration to the rest of
us in Surf City, particularly the sorry nitpickers who are passing the time
fretting about how many feet apart the trees should be when the avenue is
rebuilt.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  A LITTLE BIT OF BOHEMIA  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     People like <PERSON>Ken Stocks</PERSON>, whose <ORGANIZATION>Retrospect Records</ORGANIZATION> fills the space where
<PERSON>Lott</PERSON>'s auto stereo shop sat for decades, have made that one-block stretch of
Pacific a delightful place to hang around. Not only do these business folks
operate some interesting and unique shops, but they also have banded together
to keep their block free of the bums whose besotted presences lurk in some
other parts of town like a bad smell that won't go away.;    Let's take a look
at some of the businesses along the southerly end of <LOCATION>Pacific Avenue</LOCATION>:;   
STOCKS' SHOP features old and rare recordings as well as old posters from the
days of psychedelic rock 'n' roll at the Fillmore, the Avalon and <LOCATION>Winterland</LOCATION>
up in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Anybody my age -- except Republicans -- will have
something approaching a flashback when they see the old posters touting
appearances by <ORGANIZATION>Big Brother</ORGANIZATION> and the Holding Company, the <ORGANIZATION>Quicksilver Messenger
Service</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Jefferson Airplane</ORGANIZATION>, the Grateful Dead, the Siegel-Schwall Blues Band,
the Charlatans, the <ORGANIZATION>Paul Butterfield Blues Band</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>James Cotton</PERSON>, Moby Grape and
even the Peanut Butter Conspiracy.;    Nearby are places like <PERSON>Zachary</PERSON>'s, which
serves the best breakfast in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, bar none; <LOCATION>Tampico Kitchen</LOCATION>, which puts
a tasty <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> black-bean spin on some of its entrees; Haber's, the
classiest furniture store in the county; and <LOCATION>Cognito</LOCATION>, where I look for
Hawaiian shirts whenever I have a couple of bucks to waste.;    New on the
block is Anubis Warpus, which seems to be a supply depot for punks -- a place
where punks can buy the outfits they need in order to hang out up the street,
near the Metro transit center. (You might think that punk, like disco, is long
dead. Not in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>!);    There are other shops as well -- like <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz
Glass Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>PIP</ORGANIZATION> instant printing, <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>'s Barber Shop, like Cotton Tales, for
kids' stuff, <ORGANIZATION>Beat City Records</ORGANIZATION>, for music mostly by bands I can't stand, the
<ORGANIZATION>Free Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, a used-clothing emporium, Gateways, a New Age, spiritual book
outlet -- and they're worth a visit.;    ONE NICE thing about this south end
of <LOCATION>Pacific Avenue</LOCATION> is that the merchants have taken steps to make their
neighborhood attractive by getting the bums out. They've agreed to call the
cops every time they see any illegal activity -- such as panhandling -- and
they're very happy with the response of the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Police Department</ORGANIZATION>.
They've written judges asking that winos and crooks who used to frequent the
area be ordered to stay away from <LOCATION>Pacific Avenue.</LOCATION>;    The result is a
surprisingly bum-free business district, at least for that one end of the main
street.;    "It is hard to keep it hip and artsy and keep out the bad element
at the same time," admits <PERSON>Ken Stocks</PERSON>. "But we're doing it.";    The area
between <ORGANIZATION>Laurel</ORGANIZATION> and, say, the Catalyst has become the bohemian (or hip or chic
or cool or whatever you want to call it) district in a town noted for being a
lot less-than-traditional.;    "Look out there," Stocks, 44, said the other
day, waving his arm at the street outside the shop he's operated for a year.
"It looks like a healthy old town out there.;    "Business is getting better
and better. The stores here are interesting, really interesting.;    "Get the
word out. Let the people know. Tell 'em to come on down."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Lee Quarnstrom column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Santa Cruz/Monterey  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910624  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  659  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday June 24, 1991
00176121,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-13808</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJZDWAC5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941026
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 OCT 94 / Arts: Semi-comic King Kong takes powerful grip - Opera
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By RICHARD FAIRMAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
It is as though an ancient Greek tragedian has completed his trilogy and is
turning his hand to lighter things. <PERSON>Harrison Birtwistle</PERSON>, who dealt so
massively with myth and ritual in The Mask of Orpheus and <PERSON>Gawain</PERSON>, has
returned to cast a wry backward glance over similar material for his new
semi-comic opera.
A year ago it looked as if The Second <PERSON>Mrs Kong</PERSON> might not reach the stage as
intended. The Arts Council had singled out <ORGANIZATION>Glyndebourne Touring Opera</ORGANIZATION> to
lose its subsidy, but after much argument the company won a reprieve - an
outcome which is starting to look as much of a ritual as anything in
<LOCATION>Birtwistle</LOCATION>'s operas. This autumn's GTO tour includes revivals of Yevgeny
Onegin and Il barbiere di <LOCATION>Siviglia</LOCATION>, with this <PERSON>Birtwistle</PERSON> premiere in pride
of place.
The idea of <LOCATION>King Kong</LOCATION> came from the opera's librettist, <PERSON>Russell Hoban</PERSON>. He
had always loved the film and found that the composer had, too. As a
scenario, they envisaged souls meeting in the world of shadows, each
choosing characters according to his own partiality. Hoban was obsessed by
<ORGANIZATION>Vermeer</ORGANIZATION>'s 'Girl with a <ORGANIZATION>Pearl Earring</ORGANIZATION>'. <PERSON>Birtwistle</PERSON> - true to form - wanted
Orpheus and <ORGANIZATION>Eurydice</ORGANIZATION>. Goebbels was going to put in an appearance at one
point, but then they decided against it. Other sundry dead souls include a
Texan film producer and an Indian spiritualist.
There is no logic to the story. Characters from different times and places
are thrown together, merely because their creators want to amuse themselves
seeing what might happen. The girl with the pearl earring from <ORGANIZATION>Vermeer</ORGANIZATION>'s
portrait is soon reclining in a 21st-century living-room, zapping the
channels on her wall-sized television, watching repeats of old films like
Brief Encounter, a British Rail documentary and - yes - <LOCATION>King Kong</LOCATION>.
At first it seems that <PERSON>Birtwistle</PERSON>, tongue-in-cheek, is going to parody
himself. (The scene of the shooting, repeated over and over, satirizes the
ritualistic repetitions of The Mask of Orpheus.) Then the tone falters.
Dense mists of sound build up in the orchestra, submerging any sharpness of
mind and obscuring the words, despite the authoritative presence of <ORGANIZATION>Elgar
Howarth</ORGANIZATION> in the pit. A scene involving a computer search for <ORGANIZATION>King Kong</ORGANIZATION> is
overlong and woefully heavy-handed. A fight scene sinks to the weakest
knockabout humour.
By the interval it looks as though the opera is lost, but come the second
act, composer and librettist unexpectedly nail the right style - mythic
pretension played up one moment, brought down to earth with a comic bump the
next. Setting out in search of the girl with the pearl, <LOCATION>Kong</LOCATION> and Orpheus
encounter first a sphinx with a sharp ear for one-liners and then a
character called the <ORGANIZATION>Death of Kong</ORGANIZATION>, leading to a superhuman struggle of
ideas where the issues slug it out on stage. All this is more entertaining.
It helps, crucially, that now the words can be heard. <PERSON>Philip Langridge</PERSON> is
clarity itself as <LOCATION>Kong</LOCATION>, a bizarre addition to his gallery of operatic
portrayals. <PERSON>Nuala Willis</PERSON> is amusingly dead-pan as the Sphinx. <PERSON>Michael Chance</PERSON>
sings beautifully as the counter-tenor Orpheus, especially after he has been
beheaded (shades of Gawain). <ORGANIZATION>Helen Field</ORGANIZATION> reaches tirelessly for the top
notes as <ORGANIZATION>Vermeer's Pearl</ORGANIZATION>. Among some magical sights in <PERSON>Tom Cairns</PERSON>'
production are two haunting scenes in which Anubis rows the souls back and
forth across the waters of the underworld.
Above all, the music finds its sense of direction in the second act.
Birtwistle shapes the act in a single arc, starting Ring-like from a few
ideas swirling in deep soundwaves, through the comedy of the central scenes,
to a peroration of primeval power underpinning what I take to be the opera's
serious message: that ideas live on, even though people may die. Like so
many new operas, it asks to be seen half a dozen times, but its very
complexity means it is unlikely to get the chance. That is the tragic irony
of the modern opera composer.
Sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>The Baring Foundation</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>John S Cohen Foundation</ORGANIZATION>. GTO at
<LOCATION>Glyndebourne</LOCATION> until <DATE>October 29</DATE>, then on tour to <LOCATION>Oxford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Norwich</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Plymouth</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Woking</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Manchester</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7922 Theatrical Producers and Services.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-15589</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EGHDJADDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940708
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 JUL 94 / Arts: A motley cast for 'Aida' - Opera
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID MURRAY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
There was a motley crew for <ORGANIZATION>Verdi</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Aida</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, motlier than I can
remember seeing at the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Opera</ORGANIZATION> - and that was just the audience, who ran
from American neglige (greying T-shirts, busted chinos) to bold chic
imported from deeply foreign countries. It was a nice touch for the RO to
have imported another motley new cast, unable to communicate with one
another nor even, apparently, with the conductor <PERSON>Edward Downes</PERSON>. I have to
report that by the end, most of the audience were vociferously delighted.
'New cast' is too simple, because the singers successively contracted for
this Aida - <PERSON>Elijah Moshinsky</PERSON>'s new production - have been dropping like
flies. Somebody at the <ORGANIZATION>RO</ORGANIZATION> has had to spend desperate hours on international
phone-lines. <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s Radames, the Icelander <PERSON>Kristjan Johannsson</PERSON> (new to
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>), was flown in on the afternoon of the performance: it was no wonder
that he and his Aida seemed never to have been properly introduced.
Of the ex-Soviet singers - not including the Amonasro of <PERSON>Gregory Yurisich</PERSON>,
who is Australian - <PERSON>Nina Rautio</PERSON>'s Aida sang in even less intelligible
Italian than <PERSON>Paata Burchuladze</PERSON>'s High Priest. Burchuladze, however, lent
imposing power and presence to his faceless role; <PERSON>Miss Rautio</PERSON>, musically
quite effective, kept herself glumly to herself, and her acting to raising
one or both arms heavenward at high notes. It was amusing to watch <PERSON>Dolora
Zajick</PERSON>'s Amneris (a daunting Midwestern hostess), Yurisich's wild <LOCATION>Amonasro</LOCATION>
and <PERSON>Johannsson</PERSON>'s stiff, upstanding Radames trying in turn to get some
dramatic response from her, all in vain.
The <PERSON>Zajick</PERSON> mezzo has too sharp an edge for the crucial Act 2 scene with Aida
 -which I have not seen more crudely played: where was <PERSON>Moshinsky</PERSON>?  - but
came into its own with the Act 4 showdown. <PERSON>Johannsson</PERSON>'s Italian-schooled
tenor has bright metal and force (he must be a stirring Manrico in
Trovatore), but not much grace. '<ORGANIZATION>Celeste Aida</ORGANIZATION>' was brittle, and he kept
rushing his fences - again and again <PERSON>Downes</PERSON> made considerate room for him to
breathe in, but he refused to take it.
Otherwise, <PERSON>Downes</PERSON> himself sounded un-tender with the score, though of course
efficient: grand, noisy ensembles, but no magic in the quieter music. As
usual <PERSON>Moshinsky</PERSON> has built a clean, thrifty production, designed to last; I
thought that recycling <PERSON>Michael Yeargan</PERSON>'s Nile act set, with its tall array
of Anubis-heads, for the Act 4 trial looked too much like parsimony. And why
Aida and her father should belong to a genetically deviant tribe of
Ethiopians (none of them was remotely black) remained a mystery: could this
be a perverse example of pc?
In repertory with a variety of singers until <DATE>July 22</DATE>
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7922 Theatrical Producers and Services.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 15
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022490-0036 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 180691 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 24, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 9; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
567 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PERFORMANCE ART REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
A ONE-SIDED 'PROMETHEUS' RANTS AT HIGHWAYS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CATHY CURTIS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When <PERSON>Keith Antar Mason</PERSON> chose the infamous "wilding" incident that occured last 
year in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Central Park</LOCATION> as the basis for a performance piece, he must 
have realized what he was up against. 
</P>
<P>
How could anyone of any race summon up a shred of sympathy for the pack of 
black youths accused of raping and nearly beating to death a white woman 
jogger? 
</P>
<P>
And yet "Prometheus on a Black Landscape: The Core," which opened <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at 
Highways in <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>, is full of whining and ranting about the history of 
black oppression and the frantic needs of the black libido -- carryings on 
that, at the very least, make a mockery of black men who have not found it 
necessary or amusing to deprive others of their liberty. 
</P>
<P>
The attack itself is suitably horrific, with the five insolent, swaggering 
<ORGANIZATION>Ashanti Bloods</ORGANIZATION> closing in on the jogger (<PERSON>Erika Schickel</PERSON>), "beating" her and 
carrying her away as she screams in all-too-real terror and pain. 
</P>
<P>
But she remains a kind of cartoon figure, reappearing later to sob and droop in 
her downstage corner, comforted by her "spiritual" counterpart, <PERSON>Raina Paris</PERSON>, a 
shriekingly protective good-fairy figure in a blue tulle skirt. We never get to 
know her as a person, and the sole reference to her investment banking career 
-- "Tomorrow I was gonna make a kill" -- is shrilly stereotyped. 
</P>
<P>
As the woodenly paced, two-hour piece lumbers along, the Bloods sometimes hang 
out in front of the stage, staring down members of the audience, or laughing in 
a witless, evil way at occurences on stage. They get to do most of the moving 
too. 
</P>
<P>
Garbed in woolly loincloths, they crumble into doubled-over postures to 
illustrate how they are "the broken people," Outfitted in color-dappled 
jumpsuits, they form a genial chorus line. In slacks and shirts, they prowl 
with scuffing, sliding movements of their shoes. 
</P>
<P>
Crank (<PERSON>Daryl A. Swann</PERSON>), one of the alleged attackers in this version, 
languishes in jail, where he is visited by various folk from his past and 
future. They include his impotently God-fearing father, a chic black woman 
(<PERSON>Alretha Rakel</PERSON>) who falls in love with him, urges him to greater things and 
ultimately gives him up, and Omo/Exu (<PERSON>Lynell Gardner</PERSON>), a wiry, hyperactive 
doomsayer whose body is painted with white letters. 
</P>
<P>
Wafting through the piece for no observable rhyme or reason are figures from 
Greek mythology and Western history. A black Medusa (<PERSON>Meri Danquah</PERSON>) does a 
perfunctory, pelvic-thrusting dance; another Medusa (poet <PERSON>Wanda Coleman</PERSON>) 
recites on a videotape. A white Perseus (<PERSON>Bruce Sanborn</PERSON>) is embarrassed about 
the size of his sexual organ and stabs himself in the foot with his cardboard 
sword. Crank's free-form trial at the end offers the opportunity for cameo 
testimony by <ORGANIZATION>Joan of Arc</ORGANIZATION> (<PERSON>Curtis York</PERSON> cutting a sweet, serpentine figure), an 
impossibly affected <ORGANIZATION>Virginia Woolf</ORGANIZATION> (<PERSON>Roxanne Beckford</PERSON>), <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Angela Davis</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Other personages are apparently <ORGANIZATION>Mason</ORGANIZATION>'s own creations: KaKro (<PERSON>Brian Foster</PERSON>), an 
orotund, justice-meting vulture in a pearl collar and feathers and <PERSON>Drumrock</PERSON> 
(<PERSON>Keith Coleman</PERSON>), a leering, prancing, purple-headdressed spinoff of the 
Egyptian god Anubis. 
</P>
<P>
But the meeting of camp and rage in the piece not only evades the central issue 
of responsibility for crime; it also makes for bad theater in which too much is 
regurgitated and too little is experienced afresh. 
</P>
<P>
"Prometheus" will be repeated tonight and <DATE>March 1-4</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Play Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880223-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-23-88 0749EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--BaboonResearcher Adv4-6   02-23 1016</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Baboon Researcher, Adv 4-6,1041</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv4-6</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Weekend Editions, March 4-6 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Books and Authors: Are Humans Fundamentally Aggressive?</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In <DATE>1972</DATE>, <PERSON>Shirley Strum</PERSON> found herself alone with
a troop of baboons among the spare, scattered acacia trees on the
plains of <LOCATION>East Africa</LOCATION>, a jacket knotted around her waist and a
clipboard in her hand.
California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> had been dispatched to <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> to observe
the baboons. She knew little about them. And she knew less about
survival in the African wilderness.
   ``It was only total ignorance of what I was getting into that
gave me the courage to go,'' she said recently in an interview.
   Strum was supposed to stay in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> for 18 months, just long
enough to collect the data she would need to write a Ph.D. thesis.
Instead, she made <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> her home.
   By <DATE>1976</DATE>, her studies had grown into the <ORGANIZATION>Gilgil Baboon Project</ORGANIZATION>.
She now employs six full-time researchers.
   Strum has written a lively, personal account of the project in
``Almost Human'' (<ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY>). She was in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to
promote the book, which synthesizes the ideas she has developed
during 15,000 hours of watching baboons in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> during the past 15
years.
   In ``Almost Human,'' she compares the behavior of the olive
baboon, Papio anubis, to the behavior of <PERSON>Homo</PERSON> sapiens. Her studies,
vividly recounted in the book, challenge the accepted wisdom that
baboons are brute, aggressive beasts. In so doing, the studies have
changed her thinking about human nature.
   ``If baboons were aggressive, then the killer ape was where we
started from,'' she said. Early baboon studies formed part of the
underpinning for the idea widely popularized in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> by the
writer <PERSON>Robert Ardrey</PERSON> that a ``killer ape'' lurks inside each of us.
Humans are fundamentally aggressive, <PERSON>Ardrey</PERSON> wrote in ``African
Genesis,'' and nothing we do can change that; we can only control
it.
   That is not what <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> found, however. She draws an engaging
picture of baboons as sophisticated creatures who prefer
negotiation and persuasion to aggression.
   The old picture was of a society in which males held all power
and used force to attain dominance. Strum found that males were
transients and that they did not arrange themselves in a hierarchy
with dominant males on top. She found that females were the stable
core of baboon troops, and were ranked in a dominance hierarchy.
Females _ not males _ were the linchpins of baboon society.
   They did not, however, exert their dominance over the males.
``It turns out to be a society where there is a complementarity of
roles,'' <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> said. ``Even if you have dominance and aggression in
the traditional sense, it doesn't explain everything.''
   No one suggests that the hominids, or human-like creatures, that
gave rise to humans resembled baboons. But, said <PERSON>Strum</PERSON>, if baboons
had developed to the point where they no longer relied on naked
aggression, then humanity's early ancestors probably did too.
   ``It's impossible for me to believe that the early hominids were
less sophisticated than baboons,'' she said. Thus our early
ancestors may have abandoned aggressive social practices long ago.
   Strum grew up in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, and she had no plans to become an
anthropologist when she left home in <DATE>1965</DATE> for the <ORGANIZATION>University of
California</ORGANIZATION>. But the turmoil of those years in <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> made a mark
on her.
   ``As I lived through the Free Speech movement and the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
War protests, I found myself confronting, over and over, questions
about human nature, about what was innate and impossible to modify
and what was flexible and worth changing,'' she writes.
   She drifted in and out of the psychology and sociology
departments before fixing on anthropology. She fell under the spell
of <PERSON>Sherwood Washburn</PERSON>, a leading American anthropologist who had
done some of the first observations of baboons in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and
<DATE>'60s</DATE>. It was <PERSON>Washburn</PERSON> who said: ``Go out and watch baboons.''
   That's what she did for six years, keeping careful records of
her observations. In <DATE>June 1978</DATE>, at a conference on baboon behavior
organized by <PERSON>Strum</PERSON>, she presented her findings to her colleagues.
``The 10 worst days of my life followed,'' she writes.
   Other baboon watchers at the conference couldn't accept her
conclusions, or her methods. When she arrived in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>, she decided
to follow baboons on foot, rather than watching from a van, as her
predecessors had done. That was partly what enabled her to learn so
much about baboon society. ``Rival baboon watchers criticized me,''
she writes. ``I was `interfering,' ruining the baboons!''
   It took time, but <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> overcame her disillusionment with her
colleagues and won many of them over. As that crisis resolved,
however, she faced a crisis of a different sort in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>: The
baboons she had come to know so intimately were in danger; the
undeveloped ranch on which they had been allowed to roam had been
sold, and it was being divided into 5-acre and 10-acre parcels. The
baboons' wilderness would soon be farmland.
   Strum and her colleagues made preparations to do the unthinkable
_ to relocate the baboons to another wilderness area. No one had
ever attempted to move a group of non-human primates from one
wilderness area to another.
   The search for a new location proved difficult, but at the last
minute a site was found. The animals were difficult to capture.
They were being moved to an area where they would have to learn to
eat new foods. Would they survive?
   They would. ``It's been a great success,'' <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> said. The
animals adapted well, and with <PERSON>Strum</PERSON>'s help, survived a dry period
shortly after arriving at their new home. The success of the move
has made translocation an option for conservationists, she said.
   ``Unwittingly, the baboons had given me much over the years,
personally and scientifically,'' she writes. ``Now I had been able
to reciprocate by giving them a chance for a better future.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, March 4-6</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   In <DATE>1972</DATE>, <PERSON>Shirley Strum</PERSON> found herself alone with
a troop of baboons among the spare, scattered acacia trees on the
plains of <LOCATION>East Africa</LOCATION>, a jacket knotted around her waist and a
clipboard in her hand.
California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> had been dispatched to <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> to observe
the baboons. She knew little about them. And she knew less about
survival in the African wilderness.
   ``It was only total ignorance of what I was getting into that
gave me the courage to go,'' she said recently in an interview.
   Strum was supposed to stay in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> for 18 months, just long
enough to collect the data she would need to write a Ph.D. thesis.
Instead, she made <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> her home.
   By <DATE>1976</DATE>, her studies had grown into the <ORGANIZATION>Gilgil Baboon Project</ORGANIZATION>.
She now employs six full-time researchers.
   Strum has written a lively, personal account of the project in
``Almost Human'' (<ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY>). She was in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to
promote the book, which synthesizes the ideas she has developed
during 15,000 hours of watching baboons in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> during the past 15
years.
   In ``Almost Human,'' she compares the behavior of the olive
baboon, Papio anubis, to the behavior of <PERSON>Homo</PERSON> sapiens. Her studies,
vividly recounted in the book, challenge the accepted wisdom that
baboons are brute, aggressive beasts. In so doing, the studies have
changed her thinking about human nature.
   ``If baboons were aggressive, then the killer ape was where we
started from,'' she said. Early baboon studies formed part of the
underpinning for the idea widely popularized in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> by the
writer <PERSON>Robert Ardrey</PERSON> that a ``killer ape'' lurks inside each of us.
Humans are fundamentally aggressive, <PERSON>Ardrey</PERSON> wrote in ``African
Genesis,'' and nothing we do can change that; we can only control
it.
   That is not what <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> found, however. She draws an engaging
picture of baboons as sophisticated creatures who prefer
negotiation and persuasion to aggression.
   The old picture was of a society in which males held all power
and used force to attain dominance. Strum found that males were
transients and that they did not arrange themselves in a hierarchy
with dominant males on top. She found that females were the stable
core of baboon troops, and were ranked in a dominance hierarchy.
Females _ not males _ were the linchpins of baboon society.
   They did not, however, exert their dominance over the males.
``It turns out to be a society where there is a complementarity of
roles,'' <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> said. ``Even if you have dominance and aggression in
the traditional sense, it doesn't explain everything.''
   No one suggests that the hominids, or human-like creatures, that
gave rise to humans resembled baboons. But, said <PERSON>Strum</PERSON>, if baboons
had developed to the point where they no longer relied on naked
aggression, then humanity's early ancestors probably did too.
   ``It's impossible for me to believe that the early hominids were
less sophisticated than baboons,'' she said. Thus our early
ancestors may have abandoned aggressive social practices long ago.
   Strum grew up in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, and she had no plans to become an
anthropologist when she left home in <DATE>1965</DATE> for the <ORGANIZATION>University of
California</ORGANIZATION>. But the turmoil of those years in <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> made a mark
on her.
   ``As I lived through the Free Speech movement and the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
War protests, I found myself confronting, over and over, questions
about human nature, about what was innate and impossible to modify
and what was flexible and worth changing,'' she writes.
   She drifted in and out of the psychology and sociology
departments before fixing on anthropology. She fell under the spell
of <PERSON>Sherwood Washburn</PERSON>, a leading American anthropologist who had
done some of the first observations of baboons in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and
<DATE>'60s</DATE>. It was <PERSON>Washburn</PERSON> who said: ``Go out and watch baboons.''
   That's what she did for six years, keeping careful records of
her observations. In <DATE>June 1978</DATE>, at a conference on baboon behavior
organized by <PERSON>Strum</PERSON>, she presented her findings to her colleagues.
``The 10 worst days of my life followed,'' she writes.
   Other baboon watchers at the conference couldn't accept her
conclusions, or her methods. When she arrived in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>, she decided
to follow baboons on foot, rather than watching from a van, as her
predecessors had done. That was partly what enabled her to learn so
much about baboon society. ``Rival baboon watchers criticized me,''
she writes. ``I was `interfering,' ruining the baboons!''
   It took time, but <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> overcame her disillusionment with her
colleagues and won many of them over. As that crisis resolved,
however, she faced a crisis of a different sort in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>: The
baboons she had come to know so intimately were in danger; the
undeveloped ranch on which they had been allowed to roam had been
sold, and it was being divided into 5-acre and 10-acre parcels. The
baboons' wilderness would soon be farmland.
   Strum and her colleagues made preparations to do the unthinkable
_ to relocate the baboons to another wilderness area. No one had
ever attempted to move a group of non-human primates from one
wilderness area to another.
   The search for a new location proved difficult, but at the last
minute a site was found. The animals were difficult to capture.
They were being moved to an area where they would have to learn to
eat new foods. Would they survive?
   They would. ``It's been a great success,'' <PERSON>Strum</PERSON> said. The
animals adapted well, and with <PERSON>Strum</PERSON>'s help, survived a dry period
shortly after arriving at their new home. The success of the move
has made translocation an option for conservationists, she said.
   ``Unwittingly, the baboons had given me much over the years,
personally and scientifically,'' she writes. ``Now I had been able
to reciprocate by giving them a chance for a better future.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870326-0176 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
Time Off: Diversions and Excursions March 26-April 8</HL>
<DD> 03/26/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
      ART
   <ORGANIZATION>National Museum of Women</ORGANIZATION> in the Arts, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>: "American Women Artists, 1830-1930" -- The first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> museum devoted solely to women artists opens with this exhibit of 124 paintings and sculptures from the late 19th and early 20th centuries. 
Included are works by <PERSON>Mary Cassatt</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Georgia O'Keeffe</ORGANIZATION>, and lesser-known talents such as <PERSON>Ellen Day Hale</PERSON> and portraitist <PERSON>Cecilia Beaux</PERSON>. 4590 <ORGANIZATION>MacArthur Boulevard</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>N.W. April</ORGANIZATION> 7-June 14. 
The show travels to the <ORGANIZATION>Minneapolis Institute of Arts</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>July 5-Aug</DATE>. 30; the <PERSON>Wadsworth Atheneum</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, <DATE>Sept. 19-Nov</DATE>. 15; the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Museum of Art, <DATE>Dec. 5</DATE>, 1987-Jan. 31, <DATE>1988</DATE>; and the <ORGANIZATION>Meadows Museum</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 20-April 17, 1988</DATE>. 

   Dallas Museum of Art: "A Century of Modern Sculpture: The Patsy and <PERSON>Raymond Nasher</PERSON> Collection" -- Just over 100 works by 54 artists, including <PERSON>Rodin</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Brancusi</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>. 1717 <LOCATION>North Harwood</LOCATION>. 
<DATE>April 5-May 31</DATE>. 
Selections from the show move to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Gallery of Art</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>June 28</DATE>, 1987-Jan. 3, <DATE>1988</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Alexander F. Millikin Gallery</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>: Birds, flowering branches, snowy landscapes and a butterfly-and-leaf-covered temptress are some of the subjects featured in a rare show of "<LOCATION>Nihonga</LOCATION>" -- traditional Japanese-style paintings done on paper or silk and using only natural pigments and gold hammered so thin it becomes as transparent as a ray of sun. 98 <ORGANIZATION>Prince St. Through April 1</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Diane Brown Gallery</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>: "Fallen Limbs Rising" -- a collage of bronze castings and natural branches of extinct and endangered trees from the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION> pays symbolic homage to the spirit of forests. 100 <ORGANIZATION>Greene St. Through April 8</ORGANIZATION>. 

   DANCE
   <ORGANIZATION>Laura Dean Dancers</ORGANIZATION> and Musicians: This intense, energetic troupe returns to <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> after an eight-year absence with a double dose of Dean -- both choreography and music. 
The program includes the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> premiere of "Magnetic," set to a dramatic synthesizer score. 
Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Ave. (at 19th St.). 
April 7-12. (212) 242-0800. 

   Tibetan Opera, Music and Dance From Lhasa: A colorful spectacle marrying Indian drama with singing, makeup and movement styles reminiscent of Chinese opera -- <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Dinkelspiel Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>March 26-27</DATE>; <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Zellerbach Hall</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>), <DATE>March 28</DATE>; <LOCATION>Mendocino</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> (Cotton Auditorium), <DATE>March 29</DATE>; <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Beckman Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>March 31</DATE>; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Mandeville Auditorium</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>), <DATE>April 1</DATE>; <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> (Performing Arts Theatre, <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>April 4</DATE>. (212) 288-6400, ext. 286. 

   MUSIC
   Metropolitan Opera: <PERSON>Maria Ewing</PERSON> puts on basic black as novice nun <ORGANIZATION>Blanche de la Force</ORGANIZATION> in a revival of <LOCATION>Poulenc</LOCATION>'s "The Dialogues of the Carmelites," while <PERSON>Marilyn Horne</PERSON> wields her shears wearing something more seductive for her role in <ORGANIZATION>Saint-Saen</ORGANIZATION>'s "Samson et Dalila." 
Tenor <PERSON>Jon Vickers</PERSON> sings the biblical hero. 
Lincoln Center, 65th and Broadway, <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. 
"Dialogues" can be seen <DATE>March 27</DATE> and 30; <DATE>April 4</DATE>, 7 and 10. 
"Samson" runs <DATE>March 28</DATE> and 31; <DATE>April 3</DATE> and 8. (212) 799-3100. 

   <PERSON>Naoko Yoshino</PERSON>, a 20-year-old harpist and winner of the <DATE>1985</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Ninth International Harp Contest</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>, makes her <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> debut. 
Her program includes <PERSON>Yuzo Toyama</PERSON>'s "Fantasy," <PERSON>Spohr</PERSON>'s "Fantasie in C minor, Op. 35," and <ORGANIZATION>Prokofiev</ORGANIZATION>'s "Prelude in C Major." 
<ORGANIZATION>Merkin Concert Hall</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Abraham Goodman House</ORGANIZATION>, 129 West 67th St., <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. 
<DATE>March 31</DATE> at <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> (212) 362-8719. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Houston Grand Opera</ORGANIZATION>: A new production of <PERSON>Richard Strauss</PERSON>'s "Salome" offers <PERSON>Josephine Barstow</PERSON>, with the seven veils and sets designed by artist <PERSON>Jim Dine</PERSON>. 
<PERSON>Rosalind Elias</PERSON> is Herodias; <ORGANIZATION>Ingvar Wixell</ORGANIZATION> sings <PERSON>Jochanaan</PERSON> and <PERSON>John DeMain</PERSON> conducts. 
<DATE>March 27, 28, 29</DATE> and 31; <DATE>April 1</DATE> and 3. (713) 227-ARTS. 

   Opera Company of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>: <PERSON>Paata Burchuladze</PERSON>, a bass from <LOCATION>Soviet Georgia</LOCATION>, makes his <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> opera debut as the crazy czar in the original <DATE>1869</DATE> version of <ORGANIZATION>Mussorgky</ORGANIZATION>'s "Boris Godunov." 
The Metropolitan Opera's <PERSON>Max Epstein</PERSON> conducts. 
Academy of Music, Broad and <LOCATION>Locust</LOCATION> streets. 
<DATE>March 30</DATE> and <DATE>April 3</DATE>. (215) 893-1930. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Opera Theater</ORGANIZATION> presents <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s "The Turn of the Screw." 
<PERSON>Claudia Cummings</PERSON>, <PERSON>Glenn Siebert</PERSON> and <PERSON>Diane Ragains</PERSON> star; <PERSON>Steven Larsen</PERSON> conducts. 
Athenaeum Theater, <DATE>2936</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>N. Southport Ave.</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>April 4</DATE>, 5, 8, 10-12 and 15. (312) 663-0048. 

   U2: This Irish rock band's tour is one of the most eagerly awaited on the pop calendar -- <LOCATION>Tempe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Arizona State University</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>April 2</DATE>; <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> (The Summit), <DATE>April 7</DATE>; <LOCATION>Las Cruces</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Pan American Center</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>April 10</DATE>; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Thomas &amp; Mack Arena</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>April 12</DATE>; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> (Sports Arena), <DATE>April 13-14</DATE>; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> (Sports Arena), <DATE>April 17-18</DATE> and <DATE>20-22</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06124135 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06124135 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Arturo Sandoval, May 15-19, Kimball's East, Emeryville.;
PHOTO: Poison spreads to Shoreline Amphitheater, Mountain View, May 16; PHOTO:
Pete Escovedo, Black and White Ball, May 10, S.F.; Performing Arts Center.  </CAPTION>
<LEADPARA>  Prices may not reflect ticket-agency service charge.; Theater  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Weekend  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COMING ATTRACTIONS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  Les Miserables.  <DATE>June 11-16</DATE>, Center for the Performing Arts, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>.
<MONEY>$32.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$38.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Smothers Brothers/Kingston
Trio</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>May 12</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Circle Star Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$21.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415)
762-2277.;    Pop, rock, jazz and folk music; <PERSON>Ernestine Anderson</PERSON>.  May <DATE>17-18</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Koncepts Cultural Gallery</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$13</MONEY>. (415) 763-0682.;    <PERSON>Ray Anderson</PERSON>
Quartet.  May 29-June 1. <PERSON>Kimball</PERSON>'s, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$12</MONEY>-<MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (415) 861-5555.
<DATE>June 3</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Kuumbwa Jazz Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$12</MONEY>. (408) 427-2227.;    The Beach
Boys.  Two shows <DATE>May 19</DATE>, <LOCATION>Great America</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$6</MONEY> plus park admission.
(408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Harry Belafonte</PERSON>.  <DATE>July 23</DATE>, <PERSON>Villa Montalvo</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Saratoga</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$30</MONEY>-<MONEY>$37.50</MONEY>; <MONEY>$100</MONEY> VIP seating and post-concert dessert reception.
Benefit. (408) 741-3428.;    <ORGANIZATION>Boogie Woogie Piano Summit</ORGANIZATION>.  With <PERSON>Charles Brown</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Jay McShann</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dorothy Donegan</PERSON> and tenor saxophonist <LOCATION>Houston Person</LOCATION>. <DATE>June 2</DATE>,
<PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$13</MONEY>-<MONEY>$21.50</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;    <ORGANIZATION>Steve
Erquiaga Group</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>June 10</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Kuumbwa Jazz Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, <MONEY>$10</MONEY>. (408)
427-2227.;    <PERSON>Dizzy Gillespie</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Big Band</LOCATION>.  With <ORGANIZATION>George Cables</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>May 25</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Herbst Theatre</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$18</MONEY>-<MONEY>$24</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;    <ORGANIZATION>Vinny Golia
Quintet</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>May 11</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Koncepts Cultural Gallery</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$10</MONEY>. (415) 763-0682.;   
<PERSON>Scott Hamilton</PERSON> Quartet.  With <PERSON>Richie Cole</PERSON>. <DATE>May 13</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Kuumbwa Jazz Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa
Cruz</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$14</MONEY>. (408) 427-2227.;    <PERSON>Shirley Horn Trio</PERSON>.  May <DATE>22-25</DATE>, <PERSON>Kimball</PERSON>'s, <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$12</MONEY>-<MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (415) 861-5555.;    <LOCATION>Whitney Houston</LOCATION>.  After 7. <DATE>May 11</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Oakland Coliseum</ORGANIZATION> and <DATE>May 13</DATE>, <PERSON>Shoreline Amphitheater</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. Oakland:
<MONEY>$25</MONEY>; Mountain View: <MONEY>$18.50</MONEY> lawn, <MONEY>$25</MONEY> reserved. (408) 998-2277, (415)
762-2277.;    <PERSON>Julio Iglesias</PERSON>.  <DATE>May 17</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Shoreline Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, Mountain View.
<MONEY>$19.50</MONEY> lawn, <MONEY>$25</MONEY> reserved. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Keiko Matsui</PERSON>. 
May <DATE>22-26</DATE>, <PERSON>Kimball</PERSON>'s East, <LOCATION>Emeryville</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$20</MONEY>. (415) 658-2555.;    <ORGANIZATION>Les
McCann/Hank Crawford Quartet</ORGANIZATION>.  May <DATE>22-26</DATE>, <PERSON>Kimball</PERSON>'s East, <LOCATION>Emeryville</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$18</MONEY>.
(415) 658-2555.;    <PERSON>Bobby McFerrin</PERSON> and the <LOCATION>San Jose Symphony</LOCATION>.  May 31-June 2,
<PERSON>Paul Masson Mountain Winery</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Saratoga</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$30</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;  
 <PERSON>Charles Mingus</PERSON>' Epitaph.  West Coast premiere of 18-movement work, 30-piece
jazz orchestra under <PERSON>Gunther Schuller</PERSON>. <DATE>June 7</DATE>, <PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$14</MONEY>-<MONEY>$24</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;    <ORGANIZATION>Hermeto Pascoal</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>June 24</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Kuumbwa
Jazz Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, <MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (408) 427-2227.;    <ORGANIZATION>Courtney Pine Quartet</ORGANIZATION>.  With
<PERSON>Geri Allen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Charnett Moffett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mark Mondesir</PERSON>. <DATE>May 20</DATE>, Kuumbwa Jazz Center,
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, <MONEY>$13</MONEY>. (408) 427-2227.;    Poison.  Slaughter, BulletBoys. <DATE>May 16</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Shoreline Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$18.50</MONEY> lawn, <MONEY>$20</MONEY> reserved. (408)
998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Righteous Brothers</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>May 26</DATE>, Circle Star Center,
<LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$21.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Arturo Sandoval</PERSON>.  May
<DATE>15-19</DATE>. <PERSON>Kimball</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Emeryville</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$12</MONEY>-<MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (415) 658-2555.;    <PERSON>Joe Sharino
Band</PERSON>.  <ORGANIZATION>Beach Party Dance</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>May 26</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Cocoanut Grove Ballroom</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Beach
Boardwalk</LOCATION>, 400 <ORGANIZATION>Beach St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$8</MONEY> door. (408) 423-2053.;    <ORGANIZATION>Marlena
Shaw</ORGANIZATION>.  May <DATE>15-18</DATE>. <PERSON>Kimball</PERSON>'s, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$12</MONEY>-<MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (415) 861-5555.;   
<PERSON>Richard Stoltzman</PERSON> and Friends.  <DATE>June 6</DATE>, <LOCATION>Concord Pavilion</LOCATION> and <DATE>June 7</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Garden
Theater</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Villa Montalvo</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Saratoga</LOCATION>. Concord: <MONEY>$17.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$19.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277,
(415) 762-2277. Montalvo: <MONEY>$26</MONEY>. (408) 741-3428.;    <PERSON>Cecil Taylor</PERSON>.  <DATE>June 16</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Grace Cathedral</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$16</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;    Yes.  <DATE>May 17</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Oakland
Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY> reserved. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    Classical
Music; <PERSON>Luciano Pavarotti</PERSON>.  With the <ORGANIZATION>San Francisco Opera Orchestra</ORGANIZATION> and Chorus.
<DATE>June 17</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$17</MONEY>-<MONEY>$152</MONEY>. 1-(800-552-6168.;    Events; Black and
<LOCATION>White Ball</LOCATION>.  <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pete Escovedo</PERSON> and His Orchestra, Asleep
at the Wheel, <PERSON>Les Brown</PERSON> and His Band of Renown, <PERSON>Joyce Cooling Trio</PERSON>, <PERSON>Xavier
Cugat Orchestra</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Dinos</LOCATION>, Dynatones. <DATE>May 10</DATE>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Performing Arts
Center. <MONEY>$125</MONEY>-<MONEY>$175</MONEY>. Fund raiser for <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION>. (415) 431-5400.;   
Jazz Tap Summit III.  <PERSON>Honi Coles</PERSON>, <LOCATION>M.C.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bunny Briggs</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jimmy Slyde</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lynn Dally</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Sam Weber</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mark Mendonca</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Jazz Tap Ensemble</ORGANIZATION>, Steps Ahead, <PERSON>Wayne Doba</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Marshall Davis Jr.</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Tee Carson Quartet</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>June 8</DATE>, <PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$16.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$28</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;    <ORGANIZATION>Strawberry Festival</ORGANIZATION>.  Benefit for
Eastfield-Ming Quong. Strawberry delicacies, daquiris; two stages of
entertainment (one for children), <DATE>June 1-2</DATE>, <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION> Civic Center. Free
admission. (408) 379-3790.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910503  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  723  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday May 3, 1991
00124135,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06117199 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06117199 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3); PHOTO: Bobby McFerrin, May 31-June 2, Paul Masson Winery,
Saratoga.; PHOTO: Henry Threadgill, May 5, Bach Dancing and Dynamite Society,
Half Moon Bay.; PHOTO: Life Magazine; Whitney Houston, May 11, Oakland
Coliseum; May 13, Shoreline Amphitheater, Mountain View.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ENTERTAINMENT; DATE; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Prices may not reflect ticket-agency service charge.; Theater  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Weekend  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COMING ATTRACTIONS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  <PERSON>Victor Borge</PERSON>.  <DATE>May 10</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Flint Center</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>De Anza College</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cupertino</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$25</MONEY>.
(408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Les Miserables</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>June 11-16</DATE>, Center for
the Performing Arts, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$32.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$38.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;
   Real Women Have Curves.  <ORGANIZATION>Teatro de la Esperanza</ORGANIZATION>. May 9-11, Center for the
Performing Arts, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$20</MONEY>. (415) 903-6000.;    <ORGANIZATION>Smothers
Brothers/Kingston Trio</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>May 12</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Circle Star Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$21.50</MONEY>. (408)
998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Tienanmen</ORGANIZATION>.  Play by Yau-Gene Chan. May 9-10,
<ORGANIZATION>Mayer Theater</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara University</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>, <MONEY>$12</MONEY> students. (408) 249-1748.;   
Pop, rock, jazz and folk music; The Beach Boys.  Two shows <DATE>May 19</DATE>, <LOCATION>Great
America</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$6</MONEY> plus park admission. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;
   <PERSON>Harry Belafonte</PERSON>.  <DATE>July 23</DATE>, <PERSON>Villa Montalvo</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Saratoga</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$30</MONEY>-<MONEY>$37.50</MONEY>; <MONEY>$100</MONEY> VIP
seating and dessert reception. Benefit. (408) 741-3428.;    <ORGANIZATION>Boogie Woogie
Piano Summit</ORGANIZATION>.  With <PERSON>Charles Brown</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jay McShann</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dorothy Donegan</PERSON> and tenor
saxophonist <LOCATION>Houston Person</LOCATION>. <DATE>June 2</DATE>, <PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
<MONEY>$13</MONEY>-<MONEY>$21.50</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;    <PERSON>Roy Clark</PERSON>.  May 4 Paramount Theater, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>;
<DATE>May 5</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Flint Center</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>De Anza College</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cupertino</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$16.50</MONEY> and <MONEY>$19.50</MONEY>. (408)
998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Dizzy Gillespie</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Big Band</LOCATION>.  With <ORGANIZATION>George
Cables</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>May 25</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Herbst Theatre</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$18</MONEY>-<MONEY>$24</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;   
<ORGANIZATION>Vinny Golia Quintet</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>May 11</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Koncepts Cultural Gallery</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$10</MONEY>. (415)
763-0682.;    Grateful Dead.  May 10-12, <ORGANIZATION>Shoreline Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain
View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$19.50</MONEY> lawn, <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY> reserved. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Lee
Greenwood</PERSON>.  <DATE>June 28</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Wente Bros</ORGANIZATION>. Vineyard, <LOCATION>Livermore</LOCATION>. Concert <MONEY>$24.95</MONEY>; concert
and buffet dinner <MONEY>$49.95</MONEY>. (415) 443-1500.;    <PERSON>Julio Iglesias</PERSON>.  <DATE>May 17</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Shoreline Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, Mountain View. <MONEY>$19.50</MONEY> lawn, <MONEY>$25</MONEY> reserved. (408)
998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <LOCATION>Whitney Houston</LOCATION>.  <DATE>May 11</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$25</MONEY>.
<DATE>May 13</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Shoreline Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$18.50</MONEY> lawn, <MONEY>$25</MONEY> reserved.
(408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Salif Keita</PERSON>.  From <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>. <DATE>May 8</DATE>, Slim's,
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$20</MONEY>. (415) 621-3330.;    <PERSON>Bobby McFerrin</PERSON> and the <LOCATION>San Jose
Symphony</LOCATION>.  May 31-June 2, <PERSON>Paul Masson Mountain Winery</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Saratoga</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$30</MONEY>. (408)
998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Charles Mingus</PERSON>' Epitaph.  West Coast premiere of
18-movement work, <PERSON>Gunther Schuller</PERSON>, conductor. <DATE>June 7</DATE>, <PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$14</MONEY>-<MONEY>$24</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;    Poison.  Slaughter, BulletBoys.
<DATE>May 16</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Shoreline Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$18.50</MONEY> lawn, <MONEY>$20</MONEY> reserved.
(408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Righteous Brothers</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>May 26</DATE>, Circle Star
Center, <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$21.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Joe Sharino
Band</PERSON>.  <ORGANIZATION>Beach Party Dance</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>May 26</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Cocoanut Grove Ballroom</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Beach
Boardwalk</LOCATION>, 400 <ORGANIZATION>Beach St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$8</MONEY> door. (408) 423-2053.;    <PERSON>Richard
Stoltzman</PERSON> and Friends.  <DATE>June 6</DATE>, <LOCATION>Concord Pavilion</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$17.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$19.50</MONEY>. (408)
998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Cecil Taylor</PERSON>.  <DATE>June 16</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Grace Cathedral</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$16</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;    <PERSON>Henry Threadgill</PERSON>'s Very Very Circus.  <DATE>May
5</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Bach Dancing</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Dynamite Society</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Half Moon Bay</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (415) 726-4143.;   
Yes.  <DATE>May 17</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY> reserved. (408) 998-2277, (415)
762-2277.;    Classical Music; Musicians from <LOCATION>Marlboro</LOCATION>.  <DATE>May 5</DATE>, Center for the
Performing Arts, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$12</MONEY>-<MONEY>$18</MONEY>. (415) 903-6000.;    <PERSON>Luciano
Pavarotti</PERSON>.  With the <ORGANIZATION>San Francisco Opera Orchestra</ORGANIZATION> and Chorus. <DATE>June 17</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Oakland Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$17</MONEY>-<MONEY>$152</MONEY>. (800) 552-6168.;    Dance; Jazz Tap Summit III. 
<PERSON>Honi Coles</PERSON>, <LOCATION>M.C.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bunny Briggs</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jimmy Slyde</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lynn Dally</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sam Weber</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mark
Mendonca</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Jazz Tap Ensemble</ORGANIZATION>, Steps Ahead, <PERSON>Wayne Doba</PERSON>, <PERSON>Marshall Davis Jr.</PERSON>
and <ORGANIZATION>Tee Carson Quartet</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>June 8</DATE>, <PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
<MONEY>$16.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$28</MONEY>. (415) 431-5400.;    Events; Black and <LOCATION>White Ball</LOCATION>.  <LOCATION>San Francisco
Symphony</LOCATION>, Asleep at the Wheel, <PERSON>Les Brown</PERSON> and His Band of Renown, <PERSON>Joyce Cooling
Trio</PERSON>, <PERSON>Xavier Cugat Orchestra</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Dinos</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Dynatones</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pete Escovedo</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>His
Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>May 10</DATE>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Performing Arts Center. <MONEY>$125</MONEY>-<MONEY>$175</MONEY>. Fund
raiser for <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION>. (415) 431-5400.;    <ORGANIZATION>Palo Alto Black and
White Ball</ORGANIZATION>.  Six bands and orchestras, food, strolling musicians. Benefit for
<ORGANIZATION>Palo Alto Recreation Foundation</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>May 4</DATE>, various <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION> locations beginning
at <ORGANIZATION>City Hall Plaza</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$50</MONEY>. (415) 329-2623.;    <ORGANIZATION>Showcase</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>'91</DATE>.  Twenty-five design
areas featuring work of <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> decorators and artists. Benefit for <ORGANIZATION>San Jose
Symphony</ORGANIZATION>. O'Connor mansion, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. May 4-June 2. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>, <MONEY>$13</MONEY> seniors. (408)
354-0773.;    <ORGANIZATION>Strawberry Festival</ORGANIZATION>.  Benefit for Eastfield-Ming Quong. Two
stages of entertainment (one for children), <DATE>June 1-2</DATE>, <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION> Civic Center.
Free admission. (408) 379-3790.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910426  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  766  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday April 26, 1991
00117199,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06196177 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06196177 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Samplings from 25 restaurants will be available at Menlo Park's
Connoisseur's Marketplace next weekend.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; CHILDREN; ENTERTAINMENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE mid-Peninsula will be alive again today as the second day of the Los Altos
Arts and Wine Festival gets under way. And next weekend Menlo Park will launch
its Connoisseur's Marketplace on Saturday and Sunday. Both events are being
held on the main streets of their respective towns and both have special
events for children, creating a hometown arena for family outings.;    (check)
Jazz is the featured entertainment today at the Los Altos Arts and Wine
Festival, with the San Jose Jazz Society playing from 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. and
the Jazz Workshop from 1 to 3 p.m. on the main stage, between Main and State
streets off of Third Street, Los Altos. A special children's stage provides
continuous entertainment with the Magic Pearl Puppets, Jay the Juggler, and
Bethie, who performs children's songs. A limited supply of free kazoos will be
distributed at 1 p.m. today followed by a sing-along. The children's stage is
at the intersection of Main and State streets, off San Antonio Road, Los
Altos. There will be 360 arts and crafts booths lining Main Street along with
booths featuring Santa Cruz Mountain wines, international cuisine and a
variety of beers. Admission and parking are free.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WINE AND SONG IN THE AIR  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Family Clipboard
Things to do  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     (check) Next weekend two stages of musical entertainment are being planned
for the Connoisseur's Marketplace in <LOCATION>Menlo Park</LOCATION>. Culinary samplings from 25
restaurants and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> wines will be featured. Entertainment starts at <TIME>10
a.m.</TIME> each day at the <ORGANIZATION>El Camino Stage</ORGANIZATION>, corner of <ORGANIZATION>El Camino Real</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Santa Cruz
Avenue</LOCATION>, and the <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> Park Stage, corner of <ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz</ORGANIZATION>
avenues. Two hundred craftspeople will show their creations, and there will be
a barnyard petting zoo, clowns, face painting and art demonstrations. Free
admission and parking.;    (check) If the family feels like a drive to the
country, try the Summer Fine Arts and <ORGANIZATION>Quality Craft Festival</ORGANIZATION> from <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5
p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> in <LOCATION>San Juan Bautista</LOCATION>. Works by 250 artisans will be displayed.
Ventriloquist Skip <PERSON>Hines</PERSON> and his puppet, Dusty, will entertain the kids with
free balloons and face painting while adults enjoy the bands Way Out West and
High Strung. Foods include barbecued spareribs, sausage sandwiches, shish
kebabs and beer and homemade ice cream and fresh-squeezed lemonade. Free
admission.;    (check) Other family activities this week include:;    Events;
Families Arts Day.  This free event <DATE>Saturday</DATE> is designed for all ages. There
will be 10 hands-on arts booths for children, live entertainment (10:30
a.m.-2:30 p.m.) and activities that include musical spoons, silk screening and
origami. Refreshments will be available. Sponsored by the Arts Council of <LOCATION>San
Mateo County</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Redwood City Parks</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Recreation and Community Service</ORGANIZATION>
department. Gates open at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Red Morton</ORGANIZATION> park, behind the Community
Activities Building, 1400 <LOCATION>Roosevelt Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Redwood City.</LOCATION>;    <ORGANIZATION>Obon Festival</ORGANIZATION>. 
This traditional <ORGANIZATION>Japanese Festival of Lanterns</ORGANIZATION> is in its <DATE>second day today</DATE> at
the <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Buddhist Church</ORGANIZATION>, 640 <ORGANIZATION>N. Fifth St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Food booths open at
<TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>, followed by games for both adults and children, a temple program, the
Minyo singing group, <LOCATION>San Jose Taiko</LOCATION> Drum group, <ORGANIZATION>Chidori Band</ORGANIZATION> concert and obon
dancing. The foods include sushi, tempura, teriyaki, barbecued chicken,
skewered teriyaki beef, noodles and strawberry short cake. Because of parking
limitations, festivalgoers are encouraged to use light rail and get off at the
Ayer-Japantown station. Free admission.;    Entertainment; "<PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> and the
Amazing Technicolor Dreamcoat."  This play is presented by the <ORGANIZATION>Palo Alto
Children</ORGANIZATION>'s Theater at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and <DATE>Friday</DATE> and at <TIME>2:30 and 7:30 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the main Theater, <ORGANIZATION>Foothill College</ORGANIZATION>, 12345 <ORGANIZATION>El Monte Road</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Altos
Hills</LOCATION>. Admission is <MONEY>$3</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$2 children</MONEY>. Call (415) 948-4444.;    Mexican
Museum.  Performances and art activities for both children and parents. <TIME>Noon-5
p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Fort Mason Center</ORGANIZATION>, Building D, <LOCATION>Laguna Street</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Marina Boulevard</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Free. (415) 441-0445.;    "Peter Pan."  Presented by <ORGANIZATION>Los Altos
Youth Theater</ORGANIZATION>. <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> and 2 and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Spangenberg
Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Gunn High School</ORGANIZATION>, 780 Arastradero Road, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. Admission is <MONEY>$6</MONEY>
adults; <MONEY>$4</MONEY> children 4-12 and seniors. Reserved seats only. (415) 948-6903.;   
"The Princess and the Magic Pea."  A musical adaptation of a popular fairy
tale. Performers are ages 9-16. Curtain times <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Fridays</DATE> and <DATE>Saturdays</DATE>,
<TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sundays</DATE>. Alameda Children's Musical Theatre, <DATE>1912</DATE> Central Ave.,
<LOCATION>Alameda</LOCATION>. Play runs through <DATE>July 28</DATE>. Admission is <MONEY>$7</MONEY>; <MONEY>$5</MONEY> for seniors, teens,
military personnel and disabled people; <MONEY>$4</MONEY> for children under 12. For
reservations call (415) 521-6965.;    Exhibits;  <ORGANIZATION>Children's Discovery Museum</ORGANIZATION> 
announces new <DATE>summer hours of</DATE> <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> through <DATE>Saturdays</DATE>;
to <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursdays</DATE> and from noon to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sundays</DATE> through <DATE>Aug. 27</DATE>. Tuesdays
the museum is open to pre-booked youth groups only. The museum features
hands-on interactive exhibits and programs. Located at Woz Way and Auzerais
Street, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Admission is <MONEY>$6</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> children ages 4-18; 3 and under
are free. (408) 298-5437.;    Inside Active Volcanoes  is the timely exhibit
at <ORGANIZATION>Lawrence Hall of Science</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, with
demonstrations of Hall-made volcano eruptions, art activities planned for 1-3
p.m. <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Spectacular photographs and video footage of the <ORGANIZATION>Mount St.
Helens</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION> volcanoes will be shown. Admission is <MONEY>$4</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> seniors
and youths ages 7-18, <MONEY>$2</MONEY> ages 3-6. (415) 642-5133.;    Upcoming; "Childhood
Memories"  is the theme for the 47th annual <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION>, <DATE>July 25</DATE>
through <DATE>Aug. 11</DATE>. A special promotion on <ORGANIZATION>Butler Amusements' Carnival Coupon
Books</ORGANIZATION> is available this year. If purchased before <DATE>July 24</DATE>, the book containing
33 ride coupons is on sale for half-price at <MONEY>$10</MONEY>. Season passes, <MONEY>$19.95</MONEY>, also
entitle holders to general fair admission as often as they like through the
run of the fair. Call (408) 998-2277 or (415) 762-2277. Regular admission at
the county fair will be <MONEY>$6.50</MONEY> general (ages 17-59), <MONEY>$4</MONEY> for seniors (60 and
over) and juniors (6-16).;    An All You Can Eat Ice Cream Social  will be
held 1:30 to <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>July 28</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Community School of Music</ORGANIZATION> and Arts, 253
<ORGANIZATION>Martens Ave.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. A family fun afternoon of sweet surprises by
<PERSON>Dreyer</PERSON>'s, <ORGANIZATION>Double Rainbow</ORGANIZATION>, Baskin-Robbins, yogurt from <PERSON>J. Higby</PERSON>'s, toppings
from <ORGANIZATION>Smucker</ORGANIZATION>'s, a children's art exhibit, hands-on activities, a sound sampler
for kids to try out musical instruments are all planned. Advance tickets are
<MONEY>$4</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> children; at the gate, <MONEY>$5</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> children, with family
attendance not to exceed <MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (415) 961-0342.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DOROTHY PRIES, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910714  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4L  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,112  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday July 14, 1991
00196177,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06082051 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06082051 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (4); PHOTO: Edie Brickell and New Bohemians perform at the Santa Cruz
Civic Auditorium and Zellerbach Auditorium, UC-Berkeley.; PHOTO: INXS will
play the Oakland Coliseum on April 2.; PHOTO: Crazy Horse joins Neil Young at
the Cow Palace on April 6.; PHOTO: Shirley MacLaine will be at Circle Star
Center, April 5-7.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ENTERTAINMENT; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Prices may not reflect ticket-agency service charge.; Theater  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Weekend  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COMING ATTRACTIONS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  Culture Clash.  Cabaret, <DATE>April 26</DATE>; "The Mission," <DATE>April 27</DATE>, Center for the
Performing Arts, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$12</MONEY>-<MONEY>$18</MONEY>. (415) 903-6000.;    <ORGANIZATION>Forbidden
Broadway</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>April 18-20</DATE>, Center for the Performing Arts, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$22</MONEY>.
(415) 903-6000.;    <ORGANIZATION>Les Miserables</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>June 11-16</DATE>, Center for the Performing
Arts, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$32.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$38.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    Real Women
Have Curves.  <ORGANIZATION>Teatro de la Esperanza</ORGANIZATION>. May 9-11, Center for the Performing
Arts, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$20</MONEY>. (415) 903-6000.;    <PERSON>Keith Terry</PERSON>.  May 3-4,
Center for the Performing Arts, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$7.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$18</MONEY>, <MONEY>$5</MONEY> children,
students and seniors <DATE>May 3</DATE> only. (415) 903-6000.;    Pop, rock, jazz and folk
music; <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Band of the Golden Gate.  From <ORGANIZATION>Travis Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>. Public
concert. Co-sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>City of San Jose Office of Cultural Affairs</ORGANIZATION> and the
San Jose <ORGANIZATION>Mercury News</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>April 16-17</DATE>, Center for the Performing Arts, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>.
Free, but must present tickets available by clipping coupon from ads appearing
in <ORGANIZATION>Mercury News</ORGANIZATION> near the end of <DATE>March</DATE>. (408) 277-5144.;    <PERSON>Edie Brickell</PERSON> and
<LOCATION>New Bohemians</LOCATION>.  <DATE>April 17</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Civic Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> and <DATE>April 18</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Zellerbach
Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, UC-Berkeley. Santa Cruz: <MONEY>$20.50</MONEY>, UC-Berkeley: <MONEY>$20.50</MONEY> reserved.
(408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>INXS</ORGANIZATION>.  Woup Dragons. <DATE>April 2</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Oakland
Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY> reserved. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Eric Johnson</PERSON>. 
<DATE>April 5</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Event Center</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>San Jose State University</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$19.50</MONEY> reserved. (408)
998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <PERSON>Patti LaBelle</PERSON>.  <DATE>April 19-20</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Circle Star Center</ORGANIZATION>,
<DATE>1717</DATE> Industrial Road, <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$24.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415)
762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Andy Narell Group</ORGANIZATION>.  April 5-6, Center for the Performing Arts,
<ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$18</MONEY>. (415) 903-6000.;    <ORGANIZATION>Nelson</ORGANIZATION>.  <ORGANIZATION>House of Lords</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>April 6</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Berkeley Community Theater</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$16.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Poncho
Sanchez</ORGANIZATION>.  With 8-piece Latin jazz ensemble, <DATE>April 7</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Bach Dancing</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Dynamite
Society</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Half Moon Bay</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (415) 726-4143.;    <ORGANIZATION>Side Street Strutters Jazz
Band</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>April 23</DATE>, Center for the Performing Arts, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$20</MONEY>. (415)
903-6000.;    <PERSON>Frank Sinatra</PERSON>.  <DATE>April 26-28</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Circle Star Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION>.
<MONEY>$39.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$41.50</MONEY>. (415) 366-7100.;    <PERSON>Henry Threadgill</PERSON>.  May 2-4, <ORGANIZATION>Koncepts
Cultural Gallery</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (415) 763-0682.;    <PERSON>Steve Winwood</PERSON>.  <DATE>May 3</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Shoreline Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$19.50</MONEY> lawn, <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY> reserved. (408)
998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Neil Young/Crazy Horse</ORGANIZATION>.  With <ORGANIZATION>Sonic Youth and
Social Distortion</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>April 6</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Cow Palace</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Daly City</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277,
(415) 762-2277.;    World Music; <LOCATION>Los Folkloristas</LOCATION>.  Mexican music and dance.
<DATE>April 11-12</DATE>, Center for the Performing Arts, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$12</MONEY>-<MONEY>$18</MONEY>. (415)
903-6000.;    Imperial Bells of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>.  <DATE>April 26</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>.
<MONEY>$21</MONEY>-<MONEY>$25</MONEY>, <MONEY>$18</MONEY>-<MONEY>$22</MONEY> students. (415) 725-2787.;    <PERSON>Milton Nascimento</PERSON>.  <DATE>April 21</DATE>,
Center for the Performing Arts, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$20</MONEY>. (415) 903-6000.;   
Classical Music;  <PERSON>Julian Bream</PERSON>.  Lute and guitar. <DATE>April 12</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford
University</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$28</MONEY>-<MONEY>$30</MONEY>, <MONEY>$25</MONEY>-<MONEY>$27</MONEY> students. (415) 725-2787.;    <ORGANIZATION>Ensemble Project
Ars Nova</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>April 5</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$16</MONEY>-<MONEY>$18</MONEY>, <MONEY>$13</MONEY>-<MONEY>$15</MONEY> students. (415)
725-2787.;    Musicians from <LOCATION>Marlboro</LOCATION>.  <DATE>May 5</DATE>, Center for the Performing Arts,
<ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$12</MONEY>-<MONEY>$18</MONEY>. (415) 903-6000.;    <ORGANIZATION>Peabody Trio</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>April 19</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford
University</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$14</MONEY>-<MONEY>$16</MONEY>, <MONEY>$11</MONEY>-<MONEY>$13</MONEY> students. (415) 725-2787.;    <ORGANIZATION>Ridge String
Quartet</ORGANIZATION>.  With <PERSON>David Soyer</PERSON>, cello. <DATE>April 7</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$17</MONEY>-<MONEY>$19</MONEY>,
<MONEY>$14</MONEY>-<MONEY>$16</MONEY> students. (415) 725-2787.;    Dance; <ORGANIZATION>American Ballet Theater</ORGANIZATION>.  "La
Bayadere" (<DATE>April</DATE> 5-7); mixed repertory (March 26-April 7), <ORGANIZATION>War Memorial Opera
House</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$65</MONEY>. (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Alvin Ailey
American Dance Theater</ORGANIZATION>.  <DATE>April 2-7</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Zellerbach Hall</ORGANIZATION>, UC-Berkeley. <MONEY>$13</MONEY>-<MONEY>$27</MONEY>.
(415) 642-9988.;    DanceBrazil.  <DATE>April 30</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$14</MONEY>-<MONEY>$20</MONEY>,
<MONEY>$11</MONEY>-<MONEY>$17</MONEY> students. (415) 725-2787.;    Events; <ORGANIZATION>Dinner/Operatic Entertainment</ORGANIZATION>. 
Honoring Metropolitan Opera star <PERSON>Jerome Hines</PERSON> on 50th anniversary of his
debut. By <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Opera</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>April 5</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Hyatt Regency Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$75</MONEY>. (415)
832-0559.;    <PERSON>Shirley MacLaine</PERSON>.  April 5-7, <ORGANIZATION>Circle Star Center</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1717</DATE>
Industrial Road, <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$26.50</MONEY>. (415) 366-7100.;    <ORGANIZATION>Palo Alto Black and
White Ball</ORGANIZATION>.  Six bands and orchestras, food, strolling musicians. <DATE>May 4</DATE>,
various <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION> locations beginning at <ORGANIZATION>City Hall Plaza</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$50</MONEY>.
(415) 329-2623. Benefit for <ORGANIZATION>Palo Alto Recreation Foundation</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910322  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  746  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday March 22, 1991
00082051,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06355007 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06355007 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (6), Drawing; PHOTO: Voice Farm, above, does Bimbo's 365 Club, S.F.;
Taj Mahal, right, plays Slim's, S.F.; and X performs at One Step Beyond, Santa
Clara.; PHOTO: Are the Genuine Diamelles the best band in the Bay Area? See --
and hear -- for yourself; PHOTO: Etta James; PHOTO: Exene Cervenka, X; PHOTO:
Aaron Neville; PHOTO: Kenny G; COVER DRAWING: All dressed up and no place to
go? (Color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  HOLIDAY; ENTERTAINMENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  WE KNOW The Question. It is deceptively simple. And it has dogged us ever
since that first time we got to stay up late and watch from the top of the
stairs as Mom and Dad donned silly hats, blew cardboard horns and indulged in
other mysteriously un-grown-up behavior. Every year, without fail -- somewhere
between the first flying champagne cork of New Year's Eve and the last fizzing
Alka Seltzer of the Tournament of Roses Hangover -- we ask ourselves: "Why do
we do this?";   We do it because after all these years music, dancing,
champagne and people we love are still four of the very best things in life.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HAPPY GROOVE YEAR
BY DAVID PLOTNIKOFF  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  FRONT LINES  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     We do it because hunkering down in front of the tube while others make
merry seems like a slothful, downright cowardly  way to greet a new year full
of possibilities.;   We do it because we want -- and deserve -- to be
unshackled from yesterday's business. Shredding the calendar. Cleaning the
slate. End-ing the inning. Initiating a karma download. Closure, by whatever
name, is a comfort and a joy.;   Goodbye, <LOCATION>Gorby</LOCATION>. So long, <PERSON>Bill Graham</PERSON>. Happy
trails, <PERSON>Johnny Carson</PERSON>. That's a wrap, <PERSON>Willie Smith</PERSON>. Don't slam the door on
your way out, <PERSON>Kevin Mitchell</PERSON>. Thanks for stoppingby, <ORGANIZATION>Anita Hill</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>John Sununu</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Saddam Hussein</PERSON> -- your 15 minutes are up. Please clear the set and make
way for presidential primaries, Olympic heroes and post-Soviet Asia.;   Around
the bay, there are almost as many events as there are reasons to celebrate.
From thrash funk to Viennese opera, classic blues to big-name comedy, here are
some of best places to greet '92:;   Rock 'n' roll connoisseurs looking for
top-flight talent have some easy choices: X, probably <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s greatest
rock 'n' roll band of the <DATE>last decade</DATE>, has a rare reunion show at One Step
Beyond, <DATE>1400</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Martin Ave.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$25</MONEY> advance or at the door.
(408) 982-0555. The Grateful Dead's annual pageant of psychedelia at <ORGANIZATION>Oakland
Coliseum</ORGANIZATION> is sold out. The <ORGANIZATION>Neville Brothers</ORGANIZATION> bring the heartbeat of <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>
to the <ORGANIZATION>Warfield Theater</ORGANIZATION>, 982 Market St., <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$28.50</MONEY> to
<MONEY>$30</MONEY>. (415) 775-7722. The <ORGANIZATION>Red Hot Chili Peppers</ORGANIZATION> top a funk-rockin' triple-bill
with Nirvana and <LOCATION>Pearl Jam</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Cow Palace</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Daly City</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$27.50</MONEY>
advance. (510) 762-2277. The <LOCATION>California Ballroom</LOCATION>, <PERSON>1736 Franklin St.</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>,
has a killer blues-and-soul show featuring <PERSON>Solomon Burke</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dorothy Moore</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sam
Mayfield</PERSON> and the Soul's Alive Orchestra and <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> "Merry Christmas, Baby"
<PERSON>Brown</PERSON>. Tickets are <MONEY>$75</MONEY>. (510) 769-3701. Two other blues gigs worth considering
are local legend Taj Mahal at Slim's, 333 11th St., <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> (<MONEY>$50</MONEY>,
advance or at the door), (415) 255-0333, and hard-rockin'diva <PERSON>Etta James</PERSON> at
the <ORGANIZATION>Great American Music Hall</ORGANIZATION>, 859 <ORGANIZATION>O'Farrell St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> (<MONEY>$55</MONEY>), (415)
885-0750. Latin-music aficionados have a hard call: <PERSON>Dr. Loco</PERSON>'s Rockin'
Jalapeno Band cuts loose at <LOCATION>Longshoremen</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>, 400 <ORGANIZATION>North Point</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$25</MONEY>. (415) 776-8999. Alberto's, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>'s hot new
Latin dance club at 736 <PERSON>Dana St.</PERSON>, has a Brazilian dance party with <ORGANIZATION>Terra Sul</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Samba Time</ORGANIZATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$25</MONEY>. (415) 968-3007.;   For the middle-brow crowd,
there's <PERSON>Huey Lewis</PERSON> and the News at the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Civic Auditorium. Tickets
are <MONEY>$32.50</MONEY> to <MONEY>$75</MONEY>. (510) 762-2277. Y&amp;T, the granddaddies of local heavy metal,
regroup for a one-time-only reunion gig at the Cabaret, 370 <LOCATION>Saratoga Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San
Jose</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$25</MONEY> to <MONEY>$30</MONEY>. (408) 248-0641. The oldies schlockmeisters of
Daddy-O work the <ORGANIZATION>Cocoanut Grove Ballroom</ORGANIZATION> at the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Beach Boardwalk</LOCATION>,
400 <ORGANIZATION>Beach St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$39</MONEY> advance, reservations required.
(408) 423-2053. Blues warhorse <PERSON>Elvin Bishop</PERSON> trots through the Catalyst, 1011
<LOCATION>Pacific Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$9</MONEY> advance, <MONEY>$10.50</MONEY> at the door. (408)
423-1336. Jazz-fusion saxophonist <PERSON>Kenny G</PERSON> has performances slated for <TIME>7:30
p.m.</TIME> and <TIME>12:15 a.m.</TIME> at the <ORGANIZATION>Circle Star Center</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1717</DATE> Industrial Road, <LOCATION>San
Carlos</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$37.50</MONEY>; only single seats are available for the early
show. (415) 366-7100. <ORGANIZATION>Trumpeter Freddie Hubbard</ORGANIZATION> lights up <PERSON>Kimball</PERSON>'s, 300 <ORGANIZATION>Grove
St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$40</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$80</MONEY> with the dinner package. (415)
861-5555. AtKimball's East, 5800 Shellmound St., <LOCATION>Emeryville</LOCATION>, sax-man <ORGANIZATION>George
Howard</ORGANIZATION> holds forth. Tickets are <MONEY>$50</MONEY>, <MONEY>$90</MONEY> with the dinner package. (510)
658-2555.;   The denizens of the hipper-than-thou alternative-rock scene have
four commendable club shows to choose from: Genre-bender <PERSON>Ted Zeppelin</PERSON>
headlines the <ORGANIZATION>Cactus Club</ORGANIZATION>, 417 <ORGANIZATION>S. First St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (408)
280-1435. Across the street at F/X, 400 <ORGANIZATION>S. First St.</ORGANIZATION>, the F/X Players will
stage four musical numbers from "Cabaret" throughout the <TIME>night</TIME>. Disc jockey
<PERSON>Rick Preston</PERSON> will be in the booth. The club also will offer a dinner buffet
catered by <LOCATION>Eulipia</LOCATION>, included in the advance ticket price of <MONEY>$20</MONEY>. Tickets are
<MONEY>$25</MONEY> at the door. (408) 298-9796. Up the street at the <ORGANIZATION>Ajax Lounge</ORGANIZATION>, 374 <ORGANIZATION>S.
First St.</ORGANIZATION>, the jazz ensemble LMNOP will preside over "Casino Royale," which is
billed as a '20s-style speakeasy. Tickets are <MONEY>$10</MONEY> advance, <MONEY>$15</MONEY> at the door.
(408) 298-2529. Lounge king <ORGANIZATION>Bud E. Luv</ORGANIZATION> teams with <PERSON>Josef Brinkman</PERSON> and the
Conspiracy of Equals at the <ORGANIZATION>Paradise Lounge</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1501</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Folsom St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
Tickets are <MONEY>$20</MONEY>. (415) 861-6906. Polkacide and Diablos cut the rug at Bottom
of the Hill, 1233 17th St., <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, <MONEY>$10</MONEY>. (415) 431-7625. The Movie
Stars and the Muskrats team for what should be the best of the double bills,
at <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Coast Brewery</ORGANIZATION>, 906 <LOCATION>Washington St.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$7</MONEY>. (415)
836-2739. The big daddy of the alternative-rock shows -- featuring <ORGANIZATION>Voice Farm</ORGANIZATION>,
the Hesla-RobinsonBig Band, Connie Champagne and the Genuine Diamelles --
unfolds at <ORGANIZATION>Bimbo</ORGANIZATION>'s 365 Club, the venerable <LOCATION>North Beach Art Deco</LOCATION> shrine.
Tickets are <MONEY>$60</MONEY>. (510) 762-2277.;   For the dance-club crew, there's a
low-cost "Black and White Ball" at the Edge, 260 <LOCATION>California Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>,
that is set to run from <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> to <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> Tickets are <MONEY>$18</MONEY> to <MONEY>$23</MONEY> advance. (415)
324-3343. The <PERSON>San Jose Oasis</PERSON>, at 200 <ORGANIZATION>N. First St.</ORGANIZATION>, is planning giveaways of
club <ORGANIZATION>VIP</ORGANIZATION> cards, cash and electronics to round out its evening of <LOCATION>D.J.</LOCATION> dancing.
Ticket are <MONEY>$15</MONEY> advance, <MONEY>$20</MONEY> at the door. (408) 292-3346. The Oasis' northern
sibling, <ORGANIZATION>Club O</ORGANIZATION>, at 11th and <PERSON>Folsom</PERSON> streets in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, is giving away a
vacation for two and club <ORGANIZATION>VIP</ORGANIZATION> cards. Tickets are <MONEY>$19.92</MONEY>, <MONEY>$35</MONEY> per couple. (415)
621-8119.;   <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s 12th Annual Exotic Erotic Fantasy Ball (not for
the meek or the shy; the real entertainment consists of a jolly mob of
scantily clad revelers bent on ogling each other) takes over the <ORGANIZATION>Concourse
Exhibition Center</ORGANIZATION>, Eighth and <PERSON>Brannan</PERSON> streets. Entertainment includes music by
<PERSON>Pete Escovedo</PERSON>, D'Cuckoo, Zulu Spear and Skin 'n' <PERSON>Bonz</PERSON>. Comedian <PERSON>Bobby Salem</PERSON>
will emcee. Tickets are <MONEY>$32.50</MONEY> advance, <MONEY>$40</MONEY> at the door. (510) 762-2277.;   On
the comedy front, <PERSON>Bobby Slayton</PERSON> headlines the Punchline, 444 Battery St., <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$20</MONEY> for the <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> set and <MONEY>$40</MONEY> for the 11 p.m. set.
(415) 397-7573. Will <PERSON>Durst</PERSON>, <PERSON>Greg Proops</PERSON>, <PERSON>Steve Kravitz</PERSON>, <PERSON>Deb &amp; Mike</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ed
Crasnick</PERSON> cut up at <ORGANIZATION>Fort Mason</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Cowell Theater</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Tickets are
<MONEY>$20</MONEY> for the <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> show and <MONEY>$30</MONEY> for the 10 p.m. show. (510) 762-2277. <PERSON>Geoff
Bolt</PERSON>, <PERSON>David Feldman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Michael Meehan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ed Marques</PERSON> trade quips at the Other
Cafe, 5800 <ORGANIZATION>Shellmound St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Emeryville</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$15</MONEY> for the <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> show and
<MONEY>$25</MONEY> for the <TIME>9:30 p.m.</TIME> show. (510) 601-4888. The <ORGANIZATION>Paramount Theater</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>2025
Broadway</DATE>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, hosts a "Black Comedy Explosion" featuring <PERSON>Martin Lawrence</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Jamie Foxx</PERSON>, <PERSON>Chris Thomas</PERSON> and <PERSON>Yvette Wilson</PERSON>. Tickets are <MONEY>$25</MONEY> for the <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>
show, <MONEY>$27.50</MONEY> for the 11 p.m. seating. (510) 762-2277. <PERSON>Rob Schneider</PERSON>, a local
stand-up vet who earned his star as "The Robmeister" on "<DATE>Saturday</DATE> Night Live,"
works the Palace of Fine Arts Theater, 3301 <LOCATION>Lyon St.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, along
with <PERSON>Margaret Cho</PERSON> and impressionist Fran Solomita. Tickets are <MONEY>$20</MONEY> for the <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME> show and <MONEY>$45</MONEY> for the <TIME>9:30 p.m.</TIME> show. (415) 392-4400.;   For those of you
who had a very good year, the <LOCATION>San Francisco Fairmont</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Nob Hill</LOCATION> will present
<PERSON>Joel Grey</PERSON> in the Venetian Room at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> and the Gold Room at <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>
(Tickets are an eye-popping <MONEY>$195</MONEY> for either show, including a four-course
dinner.) For bon vivants on a budget, <PERSON>Dick Bright</PERSON>'s SRO Orchestra holds court
in the <LOCATION>Grand Ballroom</LOCATION> at <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> Tickets are <MONEY>$45</MONEY>. (415) 772-5021. Along the
same lines, the San <PERSON>Jose Fairmont</PERSON>, at 170 S. Market St., is offering a
four-course dinner, with dancing in Club Regent to the <ORGANIZATION>Alfie Dreifuss
Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>, for <MONEY>$100</MONEY>. The <ORGANIZATION>International Show Band</ORGANIZATION> will headline the hotel's
Imperial Ballroom. Tickets for that show, sans dinner, are <MONEY>$45</MONEY>. (Cover charge
to boogie in the hotel's lobby lounge is a mere <MONEY>$35</MONEY>.) (408) 998-1900.;  
<PERSON>Michael Feinstein</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rosemary Clooney</PERSON> take a sentimental journey through the
music of the '20s, '30s and '40s at the <ORGANIZATION>Curran Theater</ORGANIZATION>, 445 <ORGANIZATION>Geary St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. Tickets for the <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> show are <MONEY>$22</MONEY> to <MONEY>$48</MONEY>. (510) 762-2277. <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>'s Theatre on the Square, 450 <ORGANIZATION>Post St.</ORGANIZATION>, has a <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> curtain for the
<ORGANIZATION>American Conservatory Theater</ORGANIZATION>'s production of <PERSON>August Wilson</PERSON>'s Pulitzer
Prize-winning drama "The Piano Lesson." Tickets are <MONEY>$35</MONEY>. (415) 433-9500.
A.C.T. is also producing "Some Enchanted Evening: The Songs of <PERSON>Rodgers</PERSON> and
Hammerstein" at <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Herbst Theater</ORGANIZATION>, 401 Van Ness Ave. Tickets for
the <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> show are <MONEY>$10</MONEY> to <MONEY>$33</MONEY>. A post-performance supper also is available
for <MONEY>$60</MONEY>. (415) 749-2228. For another fond look back to a half-century ago,
consider taking in the <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> screening of "Citizen Kane" at the <ORGANIZATION>Stanford
Theater</ORGANIZATION>, 221 <ORGANIZATION>University Ave.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. (415) 324-3700.;   The <LOCATION>San Francisco
Symphony</LOCATION> teams with guest conductor <PERSON>Julius Rudel</PERSON> and soprano <PERSON>Pamela Coburn</PERSON> for
the annual "A Night in Old <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>" musical gala in <PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Grove
Street</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Van Ness Avenue</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$55</MONEY> to <MONEY>$88</MONEY> for the <TIME>9
p.m.</TIME> performance. In addition to the <ORGANIZATION>Symphony</ORGANIZATION>'s usual assortment of waltzes,
arias, polkas and marches, <PERSON>Don Neely</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Royal Society Jazz Orchestra</ORGANIZATION> and the
jump-blues band <PERSON>Mitch Woods</PERSON> and the Rocket 88s also will perform. (415)
431-5400.;   For gourmets, there are many more events than we could ever list.
Here's just a sampling of the gustatory choices for New Year's: the <ORGANIZATION>Jacqueline
Cafe &amp; Wine Bar</ORGANIZATION>, 185 <PERSON>Castro St.</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>, is offering a five-course prix
fixe dinner of <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> lobster for <MONEY>$45</MONEY> (plus tax and tip). There are seatings at
<TIME>5:30 and 8:30 p.m.</TIME> (415) 964-2075. <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s Ritz-Carlton Hotel on
<ORGANIZATION>Stockton Street</ORGANIZATION> is planning a four-course dinner with drinks and dancing in
the ballroom that will run you <MONEY>$295</MONEY> per couple. Dinner in the Dining Room, the
hotel's French restaurant, will set you back <MONEY>$300</MONEY> per couple, including a
half-bottle of Perrier-Jouet champagne. (415) 296-8559. Square One, at 190
<LOCATION>Pacific St.</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, is offering a four-course, <MONEY>$70</MONEY> prix fixe meal
