<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881208-0148 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-08-88 1328EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SnakeCity     12-08 0407</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Snake City,0417</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pythons Found Moving Into Neighborhood</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLDSMAR, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The seventh large python snake found
slithering around the same neighborhood has officials puzzled, but
not panicked.
   Experts are not sure where the snakes have come from, but say
rodents are in far more danger than residents.
   The latest python to be spotted in the 20-block area was captured
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. All seven snakes have been either full-grown Burmese
pythons or reticulated pythons from <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>, averaging 12 to
15 feet in length and weighing up to 175 pounds, said <PERSON>Debbie Parker</PERSON>
of <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Rescue</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Rehab Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>St. Petersburg</LOCATION> facility that
cares for injured or abandoned wild animals.
   But because they are not aggressive and appear well-fed, <PERSON>Parker</PERSON>
believes they may have been turned loose by their owner.
   ``We're talking about big, big snakes, as big around as my leg,''
<PERSON>Parker</PERSON> said. ``If I lived in the area, I'd be worried. They're big
enough to eat a small child.''
   Pythons are constrictor snakes and suffocate prey, normally small
mammals such as raccoons and opossums.
   Burmese pythons are unlikely to attack people and should flee
when confronted by humans, said <PERSON>Patrick Parisi</PERSON>, president of the
<ORGANIZATION>West Coast Herpetological Society</ORGANIZATION>. He said such a snake would have
to be starving before it would attack a child for food.
   But pythons have small, sharp teeth that can inflict a painful
bite, he said. They also have a natural fear of falling that could
cause them to coil around anyone who attempts to pick them up.
   Reticulated pythons are the world's largest snakes, reaching
lengths of up to 36 feet. Burmese pythons can grow to 24 feet,
<PERSON>Parisi</PERSON> said. Both snakes can live up to 50 years in captivity.
   <PERSON>Parisi</PERSON> said it's possible the pythons may be offspring of snakes
that either escaped or were turned loose by the now-defunct <ORGANIZATION>Tarpon
Springs Zoo</ORGANIZATION>, which closed more than two decades ago. Development may
be forcing the snakes out of woodlands, he speculated.
   All of the snakes have been taken to the <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Rescue</ORGANIZATION>
facility. If they are not claimed within 10 days, they can be
donated to schools, zoos or other educational facilities, said
<PERSON>Vernon Yates</PERSON>, director of the center. Five of the snakes already
have been donated to other institutions, he said.
   ``I don't think there's too many people in this world we have to
tell to stay away from them,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Sheriff's Office</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>John
Bocchichio</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890819-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-89 0029EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GiantSnake     08-19 0222</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Giant Snake,0228</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zoos, Reptile Breeders Bidding For 20-foot Python</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Zoos, exhibits and reptile breeders all over the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> are bidding for a 20-foot python found
under a home after reportedly having slithered around the
neighborhood for years.
   The animal catcher who helped bag the 250-pound snake said <DATE>Friday</DATE>
his prize catch won't necessarily go to the highest bidder.
   ``We want to put it where it will receive the best treatment,''
said <PERSON>Todd Hardwick</PERSON>, owner of Pesky Critters Relocation in suburban
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, who noted the snake will probably go for about <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>.
   Hardwick wouldn't name the bidders, but he said they include four
or five of the biggest zoos in the country. The snake now resides in
a special box built to contain its bone-crushing strength.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> and three other men wrestled the snake from
underneath a <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION> home. Residents say they've seen the
snake gobble down raccoons ``like marshmallows'' in a nearby park.
   <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> believes the snake is the largest ever captured in <LOCATION>South
Florida</LOCATION>, where many exotic pets are illegally released into the wild.
   The reticulate python, a native of southeastern <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, can grow to more than 30 feet. Though not venomous, the
snake coils around its prey to stop the breathing and blood flow of
its victims.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06315162 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06315162 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  UNUSUAL; REPTILE; DRUG; PRODUCT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A narcotics officer found a 10-foot python -- a "guard snake" -- wrapped
around "crack" vials and glassine bags under a mattress during a house raid
last week.;   "The way he was screaming, I thought he'd found a mother lode of
coke," police Lt. John Gallo said of Officer Jimmy Coolen.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DRUG DEALERS USING SNAKES, CROCODILES TO GUARD
STASHES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "But then, I see this huge snake slithering out from under the mattress,
flicking its tongue, heading toward us," <PERSON>Gallo</PERSON> said.;   The snake was seized
along with the crack in <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s raid and taken to an animal shelter.;   The
owner of the raided house fled. Two men were arrested and charged with
possession of heroin, <PERSON>Gallo</PERSON> said.;   The use of large or venomous snakes is
the latest tactic of drug dealers, said <PERSON>David Chiszar</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of
Colorado</ORGANIZATION> herpetologist.;   A few drug dealers favor small crocodiles, he
said.;   "The presence of large or highly venomous serpents or aggressive
crocodilians could certainly be a deterrent to anyone entering a drug
establishment," <PERSON>Chiszar</PERSON> said.;   The reptiles usually are used to dissuade
thieves or rival dealers, rather than to scare away police, <PERSON>Chiszar</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gallo</PERSON>
said.;   <PERSON>Chiszar</PERSON> has heard from herpetologists around the world with tales of
rattlesnakes, cobras and vipers turned over by police after raids.;   His
favorite tale was the one about the haul of six Indian cobras, two <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>
diamondback rattlers, three black-tailed rattlers, four red diamondback
rattlers and one prairie rattler -- all seized at a crack house in <LOCATION>Oxnard</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Philadelphia  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911110  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  16A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  241  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, November 10, 1991
00315162,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090990-0094 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 273534 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 9, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 40; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
508 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BOAS, PYTHONS ON THE CRAWL IN FLORIDA; 
</P>
<P>
SNAKES DUMPED IN FLORIDA GROW INTO BIG PROBLEMS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CATHERINE WILSON, ASSOCIATED PRESS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MIAMI 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In just two years, an exotic snake abandoned in the wild can grow from a cute 
pet into a raccoon-eating monster, and large snakes are becoming a large animal 
control problem in southern <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Big pythons and boa constrictors have been popping up with unwelcome 
regularity, but the capture of 15-, 12- and 10-foot snakes within eight days in 
<DATE>June</DATE> in <LOCATION>Palm Beach County</LOCATION> were evidence the problem is getting bigger. 
</P>
<P>
"A lot of people think it's nifty to have these snakes as pets," said <PERSON>Ron 
Magill</PERSON>, assistant curator of <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s MetroZoo. "Within a few years, that snake 
can exceed 10 feet. . . . They're also escape artists." 
</P>
<P>
But the escapees are only part of the problem in a region that offers an ideal 
climate for the cold-blooded, cold-wary animals. 
</P>
<P>
Wildlife experts believe dozens of snakes have been abandoned in the wild by 
pet owners after the novelty wears off, the feeding gets too expensive, medical 
bills get too high or the snakes become a threat to their owners. 
</P>
<P>
"They release it, evidently unaware or not caring about the impact on the 
natural environment or the human population in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>," said Lt. <PERSON>Jim 
Hoffstodt</PERSON>, spokesman for the state Game and <ORGANIZATION>Fresh Water Fish Commission</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>West 
Palm Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Last <DATE>summer</DATE>, <PERSON>Todd Hardwick</PERSON>, a private trapper of nuisance animals, captured 
20-foot, 250-pound <ORGANIZATION>Big Mama</ORGANIZATION>, a reticulated python that landed him and her on 
"The Tonight Show." A crawl space under a Ft. Lauderdale house was the snake's 
home -- apparently for years. 
</P>
<P>
"I get reports all the time of big snakes down on Old Cutler Road," a suburban 
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> thoroughfare that borders mangrove swamps, <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> said. "Airboaters and 
hunters see big ones in the <LOCATION>Everglades</LOCATION>, so there's a lot more out there." 
</P>
<P>
State officials acknowledge that they don't have a good grasp on the numbers. 
But <PERSON>Magill</PERSON> warned: "Keep in mind, I think for every snake that's found, there's 
10 of them that are never seen." 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE>, the Port of <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> handled imports of 1.26 million reptiles, 
including snakes, turtles and lizards. A total of 18,150 ball pythons, a 
constrictor known to curl up in a ball, cleared customs. 
</P>
<P>
"People don't realize the sheer amounts of animals moving through this country, 
the amounts being imported into the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> for the pet trade," said Lt. 
<PERSON>Tom Quinn</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Custom Service</ORGANIZATION>'s inspections division in <LOCATION>Tallahassee</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
And <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> said he has found baby constrictors at two locations in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s 
<LOCATION>Dade County</LOCATION>, indicating that the big snakes may be mating in the wild. Boas can 
give birth to 60 offspring at a time. 
</P>
<P>
But the biggest may be ahead. A python "as big as Big Mama or bigger yet" is 
being spotted every few months in a rugged, inaccessible area of <LOCATION>Dade County</LOCATION>, 
<PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm waiting for my opportunity to apprehend it," he said, refusing to disclose 
the location. 
</P>
<P>
The state tightened regulation of venomous reptiles <DATE>July 1</DATE> to require one 
year's experience with the species, but non-venomous snakes such as the 
constricting boas and pythons aren't covered. No permit is needed for 
ownership. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Animal trapper Todd Harwick, second from left, and helpers remove 
20-foot-long, 250-pound reticulated python captured under a house in Ft. 
Lauderdale, Fla. The discovery of 10-, 15- and 20-foot snakes in South Florida 
is an animal control problem that seems to grow each year, officials say. 
Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890817-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-17-89 2154EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GiantSnake     08-17 0297</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Giant Snake,0305</SECOND>
<HEAD>Huge Python Wrestled From Under Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto MH6</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A giant python known to gobble down
raccoons ``like they were marshmallows'' was finally captured
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> by four men who tunneled under a home to confront the
20-foot, 250-pound snake.
   ``I got close enough to snare it and then we just attacked,''
said <PERSON>Todd Hardwick</PERSON>, owner of <ORGANIZATION>Pesky Critters Relocation</ORGANIZATION> in suburban
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. ``It showed no fear of us. It's a proud reptile. He could
have broken our ribs in the flash of an eye.''
   <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> believes the python was a pet released years ago in a
nearby park across from <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION> beach. The animal probably
crawled under the house and caught small animals for food.
   ``The homeowners had been calling people for a month, but no one
wanted to go after it,'' said <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON>, whose company traps nuisance
animals in <LOCATION>South Florida</LOCATION>. ``People say they've seen it eat 30-pound
raccoons like they were marshmallows.''
   <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> believes the snake is the largest ever captured in <LOCATION>South
Florida</LOCATION>, where many exotic pets are illegally released into the wild.
   The reticulate python, a native of southeastern <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, can grow to more than 30 feet. The snakes, which are not
venomous, coil around their prey to stop breathing and blood flow.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> and a crew began digging tunnels below the
home. They found the snake about eight feet underground next to a
concrete wall.
   <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> said he hooked the snake around the head with a pole
snare. He and his helpers then wrestled it down and yanked it out of
the tunnel.
   ``It was like it was daring us to challenge him,'' said <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON>.
   He said he hopes to sell the snake to a zoo or serpentarium.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890818-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-18-89 0538EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-GiantSnake     08-18 0358</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Giant Snake,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>Huge Python Wrestled From Under Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's off to the auction block for a
20-foot, 250-pound python known to gobble down raccoons ``like they
were marshmallows'' within the glow of the glitzy <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>
beach strip.
   A veteran animal trapper who helped wrestle the snake from under
a home <DATE>Thursday</DATE> said he hopes to get at least <MONEY>$500</MONEY> from a zoo or
nature preserve.
   The snake, which slithered about the residental seaside
neighborhood for years, was stuffed into a sleeping bag after it was
displayed to curious onlookers and news cameras.
   ``He won't have to eat for about a week,'' said <PERSON>Todd Hardwick</PERSON>,
owner of <ORGANIZATION>Pesky Critters Relocation</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. ``When it is
time, I might feed him a rabbit.''
   ``We saw the head at first and everyone said, `Wow!''' said <PERSON>Bob
Moxley</PERSON>, a park ranger at <ORGANIZATION>Hugh Taylor Birch State Recreation Area</ORGANIZATION>,
where the snake searched for its prey. ``When it all came out,
everybody just screamed.''
   <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> believes the python was a pet released years ago in the
park and probably rested under the house when not hunting for food.
   ``The homeowners had been calling people for a month, but no one
wanted to go after it,'' said <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON>, whose company traps nuisance
animals in <LOCATION>south Florida</LOCATION>. ``People say they've seen it eat 30-pound
raccoons like they were marshmallows.''
   The reticulate python, a native of <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>,
can grow to more than 30 feet. Though not venomous, the snake coils
around prey to stop breathing and blood flow.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Hardwick</PERSON> and a three-man crew began digging tunnels
below the home. They found the snake about eight feet underground
next to a concrete wall.
   ``I got close enough to snare it and then we just attacked,'' he
said. ``It showed no fear of us. It's a proud reptile. He could have
broken our ribs in the flash of an eye.''
   Homeowner <PERSON>David Spalding</PERSON> said he was unafraid of the reptile, but
he was concerned for others. ``The thing that frightened us was that
he could come out and attack a small child,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062989-0033 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 75901 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 29, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 1; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
382 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
RAID NETS A NEST OF EXOTIC SNAKES AT SAN CARLOS HOME 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LORI GRANGE, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Diego County</LOCATION> animal control officers on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> seized 26 nonpoisonous, 
exotic snakes -- some more than 10 feet long and weighing more than 35 pounds 
-- from a <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION> snake breeder, authorities said. 
</P>
<P>
The snakes, the majority of them pythons, were confiscated about <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> from 
<PERSON>Gary Sipperley</PERSON>, at his home in the <DATE>6700</DATE> block of Renkrib Avenue. 
</P>
<P>
Some 500 snakes at the house were not seized, but were catalogued by <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 
Zoo herpetologists -- experts in the study of snakes -- said <PERSON>Sally Hazzard</PERSON>, 
director of the county's animal control department. 
</P>
<P>
Officials seized the snakes along with two poisonous lizards after charging 
Sipperley with violating <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> laws prohibiting the keeping of dangerous or 
poisonous reptiles, including adult boas and pythons more than 3 1/2 feet long 
or weighing more than 15 pounds. 
</P>
<P>
City authorities also are investigating whether Sipperley violated business 
zoning laws. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Potential Danger' 
</P>
<P>
"The snakes were seized for a variety of reasons," <PERSON>Hazzard</PERSON> said. "The rule of 
thumb is (to seize) those that pose potential danger to humans." 
</P>
<P>
Sipperley declined to comment. But a spokeswoman for the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, where 
the snakes and lizards are being housed temporarily, said such reptiles are not 
necessarily dangerous when in the care of expert breeders. 
</P>
<P>
"None of the snakes were venomous, but all the snakes are definitely over 3 1/2 
feet. It was hard to tell their exact length because they were coiled," said 
<PERSON>Georgeanne Irvine</PERSON>, a zoo official. "Boas and pythons are constricting animals, 
so if they're hungry, they could be dangerous. But if someone knows how to 
handle them, they should be OK." 
</P>
<P>
The reptiles will be kept at the zoo until the county <ORGANIZATION>Department of Animal 
Control</ORGANIZATION> conducts a hearing for Sipperley. Officials said it is uncertain 
whether the breeder will get his snakes and lizards back. 
</P>
<P>
Confiscated were one South American boa constrictor, nine <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> king 
snakes, three pythons from <LOCATION>Sri Lanka</LOCATION>, five Australian pythons, eight rare 
albino Burmese pythons and two beaded lizards, <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
The seizure, authorized by a search warrant, occurred several weeks after a 
citizen filed a complaint against <ORGANIZATION>Sipperley</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Hazzard</ORGANIZATION> said. She said the 
citizen, who was not identified, feared that the snakes would escape. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880410-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-10-88 1246EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SnakeConflict     04-10 0518</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Snake Conflict,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rattlesnake Hunters, Environmentalists Square Off</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hunters estimate that 500,000 <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> diamondback
rattlesnakes were harvested last year, fetching about <MONEY>$50</MONEY> apiece,
but naturalists say the booming business in rodent-eating snakes is
leading to an environmental bust.
   Rattlesnakes ``are a natural part of the ecology _ it's not like
the communists let them go to terrorize Texans,'' said <PERSON>David
Barker</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> herpetologist, or one who studies reptiles.
``They've been there for a million years.''
   The snakes are in great demand for medical research and
commercial products ranging from exotic trinkets, earrings, belts
and paperweights to <MONEY>$10-per-pound</MONEY> snakeburgers and <MONEY>$40</MONEY> snakeskin
caps.
   Those cashing in on the snake trade are mainly small-time
operators whose numbers have swelled to several thousand since the
``Urban Cowboy'' craze popularized snakeskin attire in the early
<DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   More recently, the oil bust has made snake-hunting an attractive
source of supplemental income _ about <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> a year for the most
enterprising.
   ``Cowboys, oil wells and snakes are related to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> _ that's
what people up north think,'' said <PERSON>George Wills</PERSON>, who calls himself
the ``world's largest manufacturer of rattlesnake products.''
   He employs 28 people at a rattlesnake slaughterhouse in <LOCATION>Brady</LOCATION>
where diamondbacks are killed in a miniature guillotine, processed
and turned into offbeat products.
   Wills said his best customers are retailers in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> and other <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> states.
   ``Praise the Lord for <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION>, or we couldn't be in the snake
business,'' he told the <ORGANIZATION>Dallas Morning News</ORGANIZATION>.
   But naturalists are warning that the business could be a
disaster for the delicate balance of nature.
   A decrease in their number could lead to an explosion of
disease-carrying rodents and rabbits that cost <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY>
in crop damage, said <PERSON>Jeffrey Black</PERSON>, a professor of biology at
<ORGANIZATION>Oklahoma Baptist University</ORGANIZATION>.
   A decline in the rattlesnake population ``could cause a general
collapse of an ecosystem,'' <PERSON>Barker</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Bill Ransberger</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Sweetwater</LOCATION> snake hunter and handler, has
survived 40 rattlesnake bites. But he says he steers clear of
``those environmentalists.''
   ``You have to be careful with them,'' he said. ``You don't
argue. You just walk away.''
   ``It's hard to get favorable publicity for rattlesnakes,'' said
<PERSON>Jim Seippel</PERSON>, an <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION> engineer who serves as chairman of the legal
affairs committee for the <ORGANIZATION>Greater San Antonio Herpetological
Society</ORGANIZATION>.
   Nonetheless, environmentalists have gone on the offensive. Last
month, 26 <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> animal rights and environmental groups banded
together for the first time to protest a rattlesnake hunt at <ORGANIZATION>Taylor</ORGANIZATION>.
   Two protesters dramatized their concerns by chaining themselves
to a fence. Police responded by throwing a tarp over the
protesters, who soon unchained themselves and went home.
   The consortium of groups is organizing a nationwide
letter-writing campaign directed at the <LOCATION>Texas Parks</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Department</ORGANIZATION>. The group's goal, <PERSON>Seippel</PERSON> said, is to encourage the
department to regulate the number of snakes killed and outlaw the
practice of pouring gasoline into logs and animal holes to force
snakes out into the open.
   Snake hunters say they are rendering a service _ ridding the
state of the dangerous reptile, educating crowds who gather at the
roundups and promoting safety.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880913-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-13-88 2359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Snakes     09-13 0282</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Snakes,0291</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Of Reptiles Will Be Limited To Four Snakes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORT COQUITLAM, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A new law prompted by
<PERSON>Larry Moore</PERSON>'s slithering, squeaking menagerie is forcing him to get
rid of 146 of his snakes.
   Responding to neighbors' complaints about living next door to a
house filled with 150 snakes _ and several hundred rats and mice
needed to feed them _ the municipal council voted <DATE>Monday</DATE> to limit
to four the number of snakes or rodents in a household.
   ``They don't belong in a residential neighborhood; in an urban
setting, 150 of anything is too much,'' said <PERSON>Alderman John Keryluk</PERSON>.
``I wouldn't want to live next door to a house where I know there
are snakes or rodents in large numbers.''
   Keryluk, co-chairman of the council committee that proposed the
bylaw amendment, said <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> keeps his reptiles and rodents in cages.
   ``The concern in the neighborhood is about the rodents or the
snakes breaking loose,'' he said. ``What if an uncaring person were
to break into his house and kick some of the cages apart?''
   <PERSON>Alf Miller</PERSON>, who lives across the street from <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, said he
complained about the snakes 2{ years ago after he found one in his
yard.
   ``It was over 6 feet long and had a head about the size of an
orange,'' <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said. ``It was sunning itself half on the wall of
my patio and half on the ground.''
   <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> has a large variety of snakes, but <PERSON>Keryluk</PERSON> said he
believes none is venomous.
   <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> did not return messages left on his home answering machine.
   The amendment to the animal regulation bylaw, which excludes pet
stores and schools, also prohibits venomous snakes.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011689-0003 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 5963 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 16, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1057 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SCIENCE / MEDICINE; 
</P>
<P>
GUAM'S SILENT ENEMY; 
</P>
<P>
THIS EXOTIC EXTERMINATOR -- THE BROWN TREE SNAKE -- HAS CAUSED A MAJOR 
ECOLOGICAL CATASTROPHE ON AN ISLAND ONCE FILLED WITH THE SOUND OF RARE BIRDS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SY MONTGOMERY, Montgomery is a free-lance writer in Hancock, N.H. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
On <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, the tropical <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> island halfway between <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION>, a 
recent survey of hospital emergency room records reads like a horror show 
script. 
</P>
<P>
Take, for instance, the case of a 2-month-old baby treated and released in 
<DATE>March</DATE>. Her father checked on the sleeping infant at <TIME>1 a.m.</TIME> and found a 5-foot 
snake wrapped around her neck and chewing on her arm. 
</P>
<P>
That same month, a middle-aged woman was treated for a similar problem. Her 
situation rivaled the shower scene in "Psycho": She was sitting on the toilet 
when a snake, entering the house from the septic system, lunged out of the 
water of the toilet bowl and struck her where she least expected it. 
</P>
<P>
Guam's only native snake is a harmless, blind reptile that resembles an 
earthworm. But unbeknown to the military during World War II, ships carrying 
wartime supplies to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Solomon Islands</LOCATION> 
also brought unwanted stowaways: brown tree snakes native to those areas that 
grow to 13 feet long. 
</P>
<P>
Without the natural enemies like the predatory birds found in its native lands, 
the snake's numbers on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> have exploded to more than 6,000 per square mile, 
according to <PERSON>Thomas Fritts</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> fish and wildlife specialist in reptiles. 
And in the space of a few decades, the snakes have eaten almost all of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s 
birds. 
</P>
<P>
"By the time we discovered there was a problem, the snakes were totally out of 
control," said <PERSON>Fritts</PERSON>, who has been studying the snakes in an effort -- 
fruitless so far -- to control their numbers. 
</P>
<P>
Because the brown tree snake is not highly venomous, most people quickly 
recover from bites. But doctors see only part of the problem caused by the 
reptiles. The agile climbers slither up power lines and short-circuit wires, 
causing frequent blackouts that cost <MONEY>Guam millions of dollars</MONEY> a year. Young 
snakes pop out of automobile air-conditioning vents and scare drivers; some of 
the island's 121,000 residents have awakened to find the snakes in their beds. 
</P>
<P>
But worst of all, the nocturnal snakes eat almost anything and can slither 
almost anywhere, including along branches where birds and fruit bats roost, 
into holes where lizards hide and deep into hollow tree crevices where many 
bird species once laid eggs unmolested. 
</P>
<P>
The snakes' victims include two species that existed nowhere else on earth, the 
<LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> flycatcher and the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> rail, both of which were once so abundant they 
were legally hunted. 
</P>
<P>
"The whole time I was on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, I never heard a bird sound," said <ORGANIZATION>University of 
Connecticut</ORGANIZATION> ornithologist <PERSON>Robert Craig</PERSON>, who is studying the bird life of the 
<LOCATION>Marianas Islands</LOCATION>, which include <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. It was, he recalls, reminiscent of <PERSON>Rachel 
Carson</PERSON>'s book, "Silent Spring": "not a song, not a sound." 
</P>
<P>
Of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s 18 species of native birds, at least six have been wiped off the 
island since <DATE>1970</DATE>; <PERSON>Julie Savidge</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Nebraska</ORGANIZATION> ecologist, has 
watched several of these species disappear during the course of her six-year 
study, while most others have become increasingly rare. "I was shocked at the 
decline," she said. "This is an example showing just how rapidly extinction can 
occur and the devastating effects exotic species can have." 
</P>
<P>
Because of their tree-climbing, night-traveling habits, the snakes went mostly 
unnoticed for the first few decades after they arrived. But today they are so 
numerous and so widespread that "eradication is way out of reach now," <PERSON>Fritts</PERSON> 
said. He estimates that in some areas, there may be as many as 12,000 tree 
snakes per square mile. "But control is possible," <PERSON>Fritts</PERSON> said. "First, we have 
to learn everything we can about the snake to find its weak point." 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Savidge</PERSON> began her study in <DATE>1982</DATE>, no one really thought the snakes were a 
problem. No introduced reptile has been implicated in causing the extinction of 
a native animal. But that the snakes were at fault became quickly apparent as 
<PERSON>Savidge</PERSON> observed the secretive reptile's night feeding habits: She found that 
the snakes eat birds, bird eggs, lizards and small mammals -- even puppies, 
gripping them with powerful constricting muscles and then chewing on them until 
their flesh reaches the back of the snake's mouth, where its venomous fangs 
lie. 
</P>
<P>
Wildlife researchers are struggling for a solution. Savidge went as far as to 
pass out recipes for snake to people on the streets -- sweet and sour snake, 
snake adobo -- but they never caught on. Besides, <PERSON>Fritts</PERSON> said, the snakes are 
so numerous that even a bounty program probably won't help. 
</P>
<P>
Fritts hopes that further studies of the snake will yield an attracting 
chemical (to use in mass traps), repellent or fumigant. Eventually he hopes to 
establish some snake-free reserves for threatened species. 
</P>
<P>
A few of the rails and kingfishers were removed from the wild before they 
became extinct and are now being bred in zoos in hopes of reintroducing them to 
such reserves on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> some day. But at the moment, efforts are focused on 
preventing the snakes' spread, like a malignant disease, from <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> to other 
islands. 
</P>
<P>
Ornithologist <PERSON>Craig</PERSON> is particularly worried about the birds on the other 14 
islands of the <LOCATION>Marianas</LOCATION> chain. Each island he's visited hosts bird species 
found nowhere else. If the tree snakes arrived on these islands, he said, "the 
loss to science would be devastating." 
</P>
<P>
It's not an unlikely scenario. Within the <DATE>last 10 years</DATE>, <PERSON>Fritts</PERSON> said, the 
snakes have shown up twice on <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, and also on Kwajalein, an island 1,000 
miles east of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, as well as <PERSON>Diego Garcia</PERSON>, an atoll in the <LOCATION>Indian Ocean</LOCATION>, and 
the islands of <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> and Ponapi. All these snakes, which apparently found 
their way onto cargo ships, have either been killed or failed to establish a 
breeding population on these islands. 
</P>
<P>
Fritts and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> colleagues have begun offering technical briefings at 
Micronesian and <LOCATION>Marianas</LOCATION> ports to teach inspectors how to look for the snakes 
in high-risk cargo like junk cars, lumber and government surplus property, 
where the snakes can easily hide. Such inspectors are already trained to look 
for agricultural pests and contraband, <PERSON>Fritts</PERSON> said, "but they aren't trained to 
look for snakes." No one envies them the job, "but somebody has got to do it." 
</P>
<P>
Some of the native island birds that are now considered extinct or near 
extinction: 
</P>
<P>
1. The <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> broadbill 
</P>
<P>
2. Bridled white eye 
</P>
<P>
3. Guam kingfisher 
</P>
<P>
4. Guam rail 
</P>
<P>
5. Rufus-footed fantail. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Drawing, The Guam broadbill, MICHAEL HALL / Los Angeles Times ; Drawing, 
Bridled white eye, MICHAEL HALL / Los Angeles Times ; Drawing, Guam kingfisher, 
MICHAEL HALL / Los Angeles Times ; Drawing, Guam rail, MICHAEL HALL / Los 
Angeles Times ; Drawing, Rufus-footed fantail, MICHAEL HALL / Los Angeles Times 
; Drawing, Brown tree snake, MICHAEL HALL / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ECOLOGY; SNAKES; ENDANGERED SPECIES; BIRDS; GUAM; EXTINCTION; WILDLIFE 
MANAGEMENT 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA033089-0077 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 37411 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 30, 1989, Thursday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 20; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
531 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LIZARD LADY LIKES TO RUN WITH PARTY ANIMALS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY LOUISE KAZMIN, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In search of entertainment for the young guests at her 4-year-old son's 
birthday party, <PERSON>Ann Shapiro</PERSON> wanted something different. 
</P>
<P>
"I have an older daughter, so I've gone through all the clowns and different 
things. The kids don't always appreciate the clowns. I wanted something I knew 
he would really enjoy," <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> Parent magazine, she saw an ad for the Lizard Lady -- <PERSON>Melanie Pickrell</PERSON>, 
36, of <PERSON>Van Nuys</PERSON>, who brings an entourage of snakes and lizards to children's 
parties -- and <PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON> knew she had found the perfect entertainment for her 
dinosaur-obsessed son. 
</P>
<P>
At the party, about 12 children sat enthralled for an hour as <PERSON>Pickrell</PERSON> showed 
them a 7 1/2-foot-long Burmese python, a Dumerils lizard, skinny brightly 
colored milk snakes, corn snakes, tortoises, a chameleon and other reptiles. 
</P>
<P>
"Chameleons are white when they are sick, green when they are relaxed, and 
green and black when they are nervous. Now watch as she changes colors," 
<PERSON>Pickrell</PERSON>, a part-time preschool teacher, instructed the children. The tiny 
triceratops-shaped creature's skin, initially a pure bright green, transformed 
into a black-and-green circular pattern. 
</P>
<P>
The children, crowding close to see and touch each reptile, oohed and aahed 
appreciatively at each new discovery. "They're beautiful!" birthday boy <PERSON>Michael</PERSON> 
cried in delight. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Pickrell</PERSON> said her hourlong snake display, which costs <MONEY>$100</MONEY>, has elicited 
similar responses at each of the nearly 30O children's parties where she has 
performed since she began in <DATE>August</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"The kids love it," <PERSON>Pickrell</PERSON> said. "They don't have the preconceived ideas 
about snakes that we do. They love dinosaurs, and reptiles are like dinosaurs." 
</P>
<P>
Pickrell works part time at <ORGANIZATION>All Children Great and Small</ORGANIZATION> preschool in <LOCATION>Los 
Feliz</LOCATION>, where she came up with the idea for the Lizard Lady when she saw how 
much the youngsters loved studying reptiles. 
</P>
<P>
At first, <PERSON>Pickrell</PERSON> borrowed most of the animals for her show from <LOCATION>Slither City</LOCATION>, 
a Van Nuys pet shop specializing in snakes, lizards, bugs and other unusual 
pets. Eventually, she decided to buy her own because the store kept selling off 
her favorites. She has been known to borrow an occasional reptile at a client's 
request. 
</P>
<P>
Despite some parents' laughing speculation ("What would happen if she forgets 
something and leaves it in your house?"), <PERSON>Pickrell</PERSON> said the snakes are not a 
threat to the children. She has not had a snake bite nor had a snake slither 
out of sight. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Really Tame' 
</P>
<P>
"There is a difference between a tame animal and a wild animal, and these are 
really tame," <PERSON>Pickrell</PERSON> said. "Snakes don't bite to eat people, they bite to 
defend themselves, and these snakes know that people aren't going to hurt them. 
They are used to people feeding them, being around them." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Shapiro</PERSON> said she was not concerned that some of her son's friends could have 
been afraid of the creatures, and she did not give advance warning on the 
invitations. 
</P>
<P>
"Younger kids have a lot of animals in their classrooms, so they are used to 
different animals," she said. "I didn't want to tell them too far in advance 
because then they might get wound up about it. I wanted to let it happen 
naturally and let them enjoy it." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Melanie Pickrell and one of her party pals, a Burmese python. ; Photo, 
Pickrell drapes a Burmese python over Michael Shapiro, 4. JOE VITTI / Los 
Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890522-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-22-89 2248EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--DisplacedSnakes     05-22 0152</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Displaced Snakes,0154</SECOND>
<HEAD>Residents Disturbed By Snakes Driven Out By Floods</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Flooding forced many snakes into populated areas,
but experts asked residents to restrain their fears and spare the
reptiles, many of which eat rodents.
   ``There's a lot of harmless species in the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> area. The ones
that are left alone will return to their homes as soon as they can
because they tend to live in the same place all their lives,'' said
<PERSON>Ardell Mitchell</PERSON>, reptile supervisor at the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Zoo.
   And experts say the snakes may be doing homeowners a favor,
since <DATE>last week</DATE>'s flooding, caused by heavy rainstorms, may also
have forced a few rodents to higher ground.
   Harmless <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> rat snakes, diamondback and blotched water
snakes, which can grow to more than 3 feet long, are the most
common species in the area. But some areas of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> have venomous
copperheads and diamondback rattlesnakes.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881016-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-16-88 1237EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MissingSnakes     10-16 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Missing Snakes,0246</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thieves Pilfer Pythons, Boost Boas</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thieves who stole eight snakes from the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> zoo
picked the most valuable snakes and the easiest to handle,
authorities said.
   The snakes, worth about <MONEY>$8,000</MONEY>, were reported missing <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
<TIME>morning</TIME>. Workers found no sign of forced entry at the Bird and
Reptile Building and lids still covered the snakes' cages, some of
which were found latched, suggesting the snakes did not escape.
   ``The thing is it's just these specific snakes that were
taken,'' said <PERSON>Victoria Furber</PERSON>, zoo spokeswoman. ``We figure that
somebody knew what they were doing and just went after some of the
most valuable snakes in that section.''
   Gone were three ringed pythons, three carpet pythons and two
endangered <ORGANIZATION>Dumeril</ORGANIZATION>'s ground boas.
   <PERSON>Ardell Mitchell</PERSON>, animal care manager for the zoo's reptile
department, said the snakes probably were taken for resale to
underground pet traders or collectors.
   ``These little snakes that were taken may bite, but it wouldn't
hurt at all. So they took the easy ones to handle,'' <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> said.
The stolen snakes were between 2 and 3 feet long.
   The loss of the boas, which were brother and sister, especially
worried zoo officials, <PERSON>Ms. Furber</PERSON> said. The snakes came from
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> and are listed as an endangered species because their
forest habitat is being destroyed.
   ``They're pretty valuable animals,'' <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> said. ``I'd hate
for them to go off and sit in someone's garage somewhere.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901222-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-22-90 0418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-ViperVittles     12-22 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Viper Vittles,0477</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter in Hong Kong Means It's Time For Snake Soup</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto TOK2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WONG SAU-YING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some people's idea of Yuletide fun is to watch
the waiter bite the head off a live viper and pluck out the
still-squirming serpent's bladder. The slippery green organ is then
eaten raw.
   Sure, not everyone will cotton to that bitter flavor, but they
say snake enhances sexual prowess, so what's not to like?
   For one thing, snakes may be threatened with extinction, <LOCATION>Hong
Kong</LOCATION>'s government has declared.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the government adopted a law that requires snake
dealers to apply for import and export licences for king cobras,
Asiatic cobras and Oriental rat snakes. Failure to comply could
bring fines of up to <MONEY>$3,200</MONEY> and up to six months in jail.
   Chan Ping-kwong, spokesman for the Agriculture and <ORGANIZATION>Fisheries
Department</ORGANIZATION>, said the government would collect data on snake imports
to make sure the reptiles aren't in danger of extinction.
   More than 100,000 snakes are imported by <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> each year,
mostly from <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chan</PERSON> said.
   Serpent eating is a feature of social life in the British
colony, especially during <DATE>winter</DATE> when the vipers are reportedly
tastiest, having gorged themselves to prepare for hibernation.
   Snake soup is a staple of business banquets this time of year,
and trade unions are organizing year-end snake feasts to kick off
an election campaign for the legislature and other local offices
next year.
   The most common snake dish is a soup, cooked with mushrooms,
bamboo shoots and dried orange peels. The potion is reputed to
speed the metabolism and improve male sexual performance.
   Another favorite, snakes' skin soaked in malt wine, is believed
to have calming effects similar to that of tranquilizers.
   Perhaps the most spectacular way of eating snake is swallowing
raw bladders. The dark green organ is extremely slippery and has an
intensely bitter taste.
   To show how fresh their product is, <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> vendors bite the
snake's head off in front of customers, who get to watch the body
of the reptile wriggle through the vendor's fingers as he searches
for the organ.
   The conservation organization World Wide Fund For Nature said it
supported the government's licensing decision.
   ``If unrestricted trade continues, snakes will one day become
endangered,'' said <PERSON>Amy Lau</PERSON>, the fund's conservation officer in <LOCATION>Hong
Kong</LOCATION>.
   Snake trader <PERSON>Tam Sun</PERSON>, who runs a small shop in downtown <LOCATION>Hong
Kong</LOCATION> that sells snake soup, said he has no choice but to pass on
the cost of the new import license to his customers, who now pay <MONEY>$2</MONEY>
for a bowl.
   ``Our profit margin is already pretty narrow,'' <PERSON>Tam</PERSON> said, after
biting off the head of a green snake. ``Prices of snake soup will
go up <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870707-0123 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
Rounding Up Rattlers: A Town Tradition
---
By Michael Pearce</HL>
<DD> 07/07/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> Okeene, Okla.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three men moved slowly along the lip of the canyon, their shadows falling below them, stretching long and dark across a long meadow carpeted in lush green grass and dotted with crimson <ORGANIZATION>Hereford</ORGANIZATION> cattle grazing peacefully in the early morning sun. 

   Eyes on the ground, each man peered into the crevices and recesses of the white, porous gypsum boulders and into the inner depths of the scattered scrub brush that sprouts near the break where canyon meets plateau. 

   <PERSON>Anthony Felder</PERSON>, the leader of the three, parted the leaved branches of a stubby wild plum and was the first to find the object of their quest. 
"There's one here," announced <PERSON>Mr. Felder</PERSON>, "but I doubt we'll get it. 
All I can see is about the last six inches sticking out of a hole." 

   The three converged on the spot, planned a strategy and went to work. 
Using yard-long metal rods equipped with controllable, grasping tongs, each hunter scrambled to grasp his prey. 

   The battle went undecided for several tense minutes before <PERSON>Virgil Pugh</PERSON> announced, "I've got him. . . . 
Everybody stand back." 
<PERSON>Mr. Pugh</PERSON> lifted hard, swinging his catch over his head. 
Turning, he deposited 3 1/2 feet of wrist-thick, enraged diamondback rattlesnake onto a slab of ivory gypsum. 

   The men stood for a few minutes and admired the coiled snake. 
<PERSON>Mr. Pugh</PERSON> took time to show the newcomer of the three the clear yellow venom that streaked down his catcher from the snake's repeated strikes. 

   Eventually, <PERSON>Mr. Pugh</PERSON> pinned the diamond's head to the rock with the metal instrument, grasped it between his thumb and forefinger and barehanded the twisting snake into a pillowcase. 
The excitement behind them, the hunt went on. 

   "This is my 24th year," said <PERSON>Mr. Pugh</PERSON>, a speech pathologist from <LOCATION>Colwich</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan</LOCATION>. 
"I started it as a dare but you can get hooked. 
I take a week's vacation and come down here to hunt with friends. 
It's kind of like a class reunion. 
But I guess the thrill of it is what attracts me. 
These things can be hazardous to your health." 

   But rattlesnake hunting is more than just a sport for a courageous few around this tiny central <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> town. 
It is a tradition. 

   "I guess I've been hunting rattlesnakes for 46 years, since I was 14, and that's probably true of about every kind around," said <PERSON>Mr. Felder</PERSON>, a lifelong resident. 
"It's part of a tradition. 
Big brother did it, Dad did it and most kids naturally want to get out and try to find a snake bigger than they did." 

   According to <PERSON>Mr. Felder</PERSON>, the gypsum canyons that lie in the petroleum and ranching country west of town offer optimum habitat for Western diamondback rattlesnakes. 
The poisonous reptiles thrive thanks to the little caverns that sound hollow underfoot and reach far back from the lips of the canyons. 

   Local hunters, such as <PERSON>Mr. Felder</PERSON>, know the locations of such dens and hunt the area around their usually small openings. 
During the course of a year the best dens produce an amazing number of snakes. 

   "During the average day it's not too uncommon not to catch any snakes but it's not uncommon to catch as many as 14 or 15," said <PERSON>Mr. Felder</PERSON>. 
"I've had days when two of us have caught as many as 40 from just a few dens. 
The most I know of coming from one den, at one time, is somewhere over 30. but you can go to these same dens the next day and still catch more snakes." 

   A new season begins with the first tepid afternoons of <DATE>January</DATE> when the rattlers slither to the surface to warm in the sun, and lasts until the heat of <DATE>summer</DATE> forces the cold-blooded creatures to be nocturnal. 

   The town that locals affectionately refer to as "Okeene America" remains mostly ambivalent toward the hunts most of the year. 

   On a recent <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, regulars gathered at The Galvanized Palace, talking of things common to towns of 1,300. 
Outside the tavern teen-agers, fresh from school, cruised the three-block business district, exchanging waves with friends and strangers alike. 

   And things would be the same the following <DATE>Monday</DATE>, but not so during the two days in between. 
Two blocks of Main Street would be roped off, concessionaires would line the sidewalks and an estimated 5,000 people would come to attend the 47th Okeene Rattlesnake Round-Up. 
Sponsored by the local Jaycees, the Round-Up draws people from nearly two dozen states as well as an occasional foreign country. 

   Some come for hunting, renting equipment and following local guides into the canyon country where they search for, and usually find, rattlesnakes. 
But more than <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of those who attend come only as spectators drawn by the unusual. 

   For them there are the stands, selling an assortment of rattlesnake products ranging from <MONEY>$1</MONEY> rattles to <MONEY>$300</MONEY> boots, and the carnival-like snake shows. 
And there are the cornmeal-coated "snake steaks" that one newcomer rated as having "a good flavor but not much meat," as she rolled the bony skeleton between her fingers. 

   Admittedly, many come for the mystery and the danger that surround the creatures. 
People stand seemingly spellbound as handlers measure and auction off the largest of the entries, snakes that come from both local dens and from across the South, routinely measuring five and six feet in length. 

   At times spectators pack "the butcher shop" where Jaycees turn live rattlesnakes into packaged meat as well as souvenir heads, skins and rattles. 

   The main event of the Round-Up is officially billed "The Den of Death," but locals call it "the pit." 
They're talking about an enclosure made from eight sheets of plywood and filled with several hundred rattling snakes. 
Spectators line the perimeter, watching handlers such as Messrs. 
<PERSON>Felder</PERSON> and <PERSON>Pugh</PERSON> pick up and show off the reptiles. 
It is here where most of the danger lies. 

   "Nearly all of the bites that occur happen in the pit," said <PERSON>Mr. Felder</PERSON>, taking a break from a turn with the snakes. 
"You say it'll happen to somebody else but it's inevitable. 
I've been bitten twice but some guys get it a lot more than that. 

   "Our wives have to be super ladies to put up with what we do," continued <PERSON>Mr. Felder</PERSON>, a religious and dedicated family man. 
"Now I know how my parents must have felt. 
My 18-year-old son has been getting into the pit for two years. 
There were three bites at a roundup in <LOCATION>Sweetwater</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, this year. 
One of them died -- he was only 20 years old." 

   Later that day the younger <PERSON>Felder</PERSON> did get hit by a striking snake. 
Luckily, the venomous fangs didn't penetrate the legs of his jeans. 
"That's probably the best thing that could have happened to him," commented the father. 
"It'll give him a whole new respect for the snakes. 
It's probably postponed his getting bit for another five years." 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Pearce</PERSON> is a free-lance outdoor writer based in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122889-0005 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 154351 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 28, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 6; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
672 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ABANDONED SNAKES POSE A MYSTERY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHRIS KRAUL, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Describing the reptilian horde as a "scene out of an <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Jones movie," <LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION> Zoo officials <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> were trying to identify the 225 nonpoisonous 
snakes impounded at a vacant Vista residence. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, county officials wondered why the owner apparently abandoned the 
valuable creatures. 
</P>
<P>
Officers from the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego County Department of Animal Control</ORGANIZATION> seized the 
snakes <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> on <ORGANIZATION>Lado de Loma Drive</ORGANIZATION> after neighbors complained of a stench to 
the county <ORGANIZATION>Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION>. Deputies entered the house, found several dead 
snakes among the poorly tended live ones, and called in animal control 
officers. 
</P>
<P>
While neither the county nor the <ORGANIZATION>Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION> could identify the 
snakes' owner as of <DATE>late Wednesday</DATE>, a former owner of the house said he sold 
the residence in early <DATE>December</DATE> to <PERSON>James R. King</PERSON> of <LOCATION>El Cajon</LOCATION>, who reportedly 
described himself to a real estate agent as a "reptile wholesaler." 
</P>
<P>
Efforts to reach King at an <ORGANIZATION>El Cajon</ORGANIZATION> telephone listing were unsuccessful 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The haul included 225 live snakes, about a dozen dead ones, 20 exotic species 
of frogs and a handful of lizards, said <PERSON>Sally Hazzard</PERSON>, county animal control 
director. The animals, which apparently had not been given food or water for 
some time, were turned over to the temporary custody of the zoo <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> 
<TIME>morning</TIME> for veterinary care and identification. 
</P>
<P>
Some of the snakes were found <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night in plastic foam cups and plastic 
containers, zoo spokesman <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON> said. The reptiles "were all extremely 
thirsty and went immediately to the water when it was put in their pens" at the 
zoo, he said. Jouett described some of the baby snakes as dehydrated. 
</P>
<P>
Notations were made on some of the snakes' pens that indicated to zoo officials 
that the animals may have last been fed and watered <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The owner may face criminal charges if the county determines that the snakes 
were mistreated, <ORGANIZATION>Vista Assistant City</ORGANIZATION> Manager <PERSON>Jeanette Farris</PERSON> said. The owner 
may be in misdemeanor violation of a Vista law that prohibits homeowners from 
keeping more than 25 snakes or from owning pythons or boa constrictors longer 
than 3 1/2 feet or weighing more than 15 pounds, she said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said the haul of snakes included a crate full of "20 or more" pythons 
and boa constrictors that range from 5 to 12 feet in length. 
</P>
<P>
Although the snakes "appeared to be abandoned," Deputy <PERSON>Sheriff Larry van Dusen</PERSON> 
said law enforcement officials would not try to identify or locate the snakes' 
owner unless the animal control department determines that there may have been 
criminal neglect of the animals. 
</P>
<P>
Hazzard said her department is awaiting the zoo's medical evaluation and 
identification of the animals before fully assessing the case. 
</P>
<P>
Zoning laws that govern what kinds of animals may be kept in given areas and 
the required "methods of containment" must also be evaluated by the county, she 
said. 
</P>
<P>
"No one knows how long the animals have been abandoned," <PERSON>Hazzard</PERSON> said. "But 
there is criminal liability, in general, if an owner does not provide adequate 
food, water and shelter for their animals." 
</P>
<P>
In the meantime, animal control officers posted a notice at the <ORGANIZATION>Vista</ORGANIZATION> house 
saying that the reptiles' owner must come forward within five days to claim the 
animals or forfeit ownership. After that, the county would be free to sell the 
snakes at auction, or dispose of them to zoos or the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> 
and Game, <ORGANIZATION>Hazzard</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
Although the zoo has not yet finished identifying the reptiles, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> 
described them as all nonpoisonous. The snakes identified include rare, 
12-foot-long albino Burmese pythons and albino king snakes, as well as a 
variety of king snakes, rat snakes, garter snakes and rosy boa constrictors. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Gary Sipperley</PERSON>, owner of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Reptile Breeders, said adult albino Burmese 
pythons could be worth up to <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> each. The albino pythons "are a fairly new 
genetic strain that's become available in the last five years. That's why 
they're so valuable. There aren't that many available at this point." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Some of the snakes that were taken from vacant house in Vista. ; Photo, 
Zoo reptile keeper Robin Greenlee holds a boa found in Vista house. BOB GRIESER 
/ Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010789-0119 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 3134 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 7, 1989, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 2; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
397 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ORANGE COUNTY DIGEST : LOCAL NEWS IN BRIEF; 
</P>
<P>
IRVINE; 
</P>
<P>
THIEVES CAN'T STEAL LIFE OUT OF SCIENCE CLASS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KIMBERLY L. JACKSON, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Seventh-graders at <ORGANIZATION>Rancho San Joaquin Intermediate School</ORGANIZATION> have been fascinated 
by life science instructor <PERSON>Bill W. Anderson</PERSON>'s "teaching tools" -- animals of 
all kinds, including a 15-foot python, caged cockateels, wild deer mice, exotic 
fish and more in two rooms used to expose his pupils to wildlife. 
</P>
<P>
But in one corner, next to a wall covered with clippings from science 
magazines, a glass aquarium marked "Haitian Boa" sits empty. The two specimens 
that had lived there were among <MONEY>$2,200</MONEY> worth of reptiles stolen from the <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> 
classroom earlier this week. 
</P>
<P>
"They took some really unusual king snakes that you can't legally buy in 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> said. An albino corn snake and a western hognose snake 
also were among the 23 snakes, 3 turtles and 2 lizards stolen <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, he said. 
Only about 15 of the reptiles remain. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Irvine Police</ORGANIZATION> Lt. <PERSON>Pat Rodgers</PERSON> said the suspects pried the classroom door open 
with a blunt object sometime between <TIME>midnight</TIME> and <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Officers were 
unable to find any usable fingerprints <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, but they are still 
investigating the case. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> said he had bought many of the missing reptiles with his own money. 
Others he had found under rocks while on trips or morning runs. He added that 
he spends much of his free time collecting and caring for the animals that 
bring "life" to his science classes. 
</P>
<P>
"This is what I love, and I put <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> into what I do," he said. 
</P>
<P>
The reason for the elaborate exhibit, he said, is that most of his students, 
about age 12, aren't really interested in "the booky stuff." But if they can be 
made interested by looking at the actual creatures, "that's when they'll read," 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
Anderson's approach seems to work. On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, students were planning a "snake 
dance" and a candy sale to replace some of the stolen animals, school officials 
said. 
</P>
<P>
During class <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> lifted one of the remaining snakes, a 15-foot 
python, from its temporary home -- a green garbage pail, for about 35 wide-eyed 
students. 
</P>
<P>
"If you look inside his mouth," he said, holding the snake by its neck, "you'll 
see a little hole. That's his breathing tube." 
</P>
<P>
"Hey <PERSON>Mr. Anderson</PERSON>," one pupil called out. "What does that guy eat?" 
</P>
<P>
Rabbits and chickens and such, <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> responded. But watching the reptiles 
eat is an experience he reserves for his advanced students. "A lot of the kids 
couldn't handle it," he explained. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Bill Anderson uses some of his "teaching tools" in class:at right, a 
reticulated python, and lower right, a caged mouse. Lower left, Anderson gets 
students involved. DON TORMEY / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ROBBERIES -- ORANGE COUNTY; REPTILES; TEACHERS -- ORANGE COUNTY; SCIENCE; 
SNAKES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911212-0005
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911212-0005.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   It's Man vs. Snake
   In Guam. For Now,
   Bet on the Snake
   ---
   Millions of Slithering Serpents
   Frustrate Control Efforts;
   Will Sex Do the Trick?
   ----
</HL>
<DATE>
12/12/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<IN>
ENVIRONMENT (ENV)
</IN>
<NS>
ENVIRONMENTAL NEWS (ENV)
</NS>
<GV>
AGRICULTURE DEPARTMENT (AGD)
CONGRESS (CNG)
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF)
INTERIOR DEPARTMENT (INR)
</GV>
<RE>
FAR EAST (FE)
GUAM (GU)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   GUAM -- Tourist advisory: While in Guam, keep your toilet
seat down when not in use.
   Snakes like to come in through the toilets.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   At night, they hang from trees like fat, brown strands of
cooked spaghetti. They attack <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military bases. They
slither up power poles. They wipe out entire bird
populations, attack children and crawl into homes looking for
food. Some are 10 feet long. And they're so tough they
actually can bump up against an electrified fence and keep
coming back for more.
   This is really gross.
   There are as many as three million snakes here on a land
mass of 212 square miles. That's an average of 14,000 snakes
per square mile, or 22 snakes for every man, woman and child.
Now, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government, armed with <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> from
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, is mounting a counterattack. Wildlife biologist
<PERSON>Thomas Fritts</PERSON> and a team of researchers have been zapping the
snakes silly in experimental electric corrals, luring them
into traps, testing fumigants and trying to figure out if, in
the case of snakes, sex can kill. If all else fails, they
figure maybe at least they can establish some "snake-free
zones."
   What makes this research work so difficult is the nature
of the foe. "Boiga irregularis" -- known as a brown tree
snake -- lives in trees but is equally adept on the ground,
so it's difficult to keep the snake in or out of any large
area. The snakes are hard to starve out because they will
dine on any small critter.
   Indigenous to the <LOCATION>Solomon Islands</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION> and northern
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, the snakes first turned up in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> shortly after
World War II, apparently as stowaways on a cargo ship. They
proliferate maddeningly fast because they have no natural
predators on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. For decades, the snakes were mostly
unnoticed, content to devour lizards and birds. But by the
early <DATE>1980s</DATE> local biologists discovered the snakes had wiped
out nine of 12 native birds species, critically depleted the
rest and had run so low on lizards that they began foraging
in homes for more varied food.
   "Two snakes came through the commode of my home the other
day," says <PERSON>Marilyn D.A. Manibusan</PERSON>, a territorial senator. "I
threw boiling water at them." A lot of people put screens
over their sewer vents to keep the snakes from entering via
the toilet.
   By day, the nocturnal snakes seem to disappear. Indeed,
many people in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> say they've never seen one. But the
snakes, which are mildly poisonous, have been found coiled
around screaming infants, their mouths locked on tiny hands
in vain attempts to swallow the babies. Though no known
deaths have resulted, 53 emergency room cases of snakebites
were reported in the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Memorial Hospital</ORGANIZATION> between <DATE>1986</DATE> and
<DATE>1989</DATE>, including four in which doctors said infant victims
came perilously close to death.
   The problem finally drew widespread public attention after
the snakes began crawling over power lines and electrocuting
themselves, knocking out power in the process. Between <DATE>1978</DATE>
and <DATE>1990</DATE>, <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> was hit by an estimated 680 snake-related
outages, in some cases blacking out the entire island.
Exasperated, the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Power Authority</ORGANIZATION> wound up turning off
from dusk to dawn a utility pole that had suffered 17 faults,
effectively ceding it to the snakes.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military soon found out itself that the reptile
is a resourceful opponent. At one base, commanders ordered
the bottoms of power poles wrapped with sleeves of slick
metal in hopes of keeping the snakes off. They were chagrined
to later discover the snakes don't even go up the poles; they
prefer the supporting guy wires. So the next tack was to
erect screen-wire barriers around the guy wires. The snakes
simply climbed over.
   So, what to do?
   <PERSON>Gordon Rodda</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>Arizona Cooperative Fish</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Research Unit</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, tried to build a better snake trap.
He tried using lizards, chicken litter and quail as bait, but
found that white mice work best. "If you put out 100 traps
with quail bait, you find six snakes in them, but with white
mice you find 25 snakes out of 100 traps," he says.
   The downside: "We don't really want to import a million
white mice to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>," says <PERSON>Mr. Fritts</PERSON>. So <PERSON>Mr. Fritts</PERSON> says the
researchers hope to come up with an artificial white mouse
that can be used in its place.
   In fact, just about every solution seems to have a catch.
Officials considered importing mongooses or paying a bounty
on dead snakes. But mongooses hunt by day and sleep by <TIME>night</TIME>
-- opposite of the snakes -- and <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> officials concluded
that a bounty would only encourage enterprising entrepreneurs
to start raising snakes commercially.
   <PERSON>Earl Campbell</PERSON>, a researcher with the <ORGANIZATION>Ohio Cooperative Fish</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Research Unit</ORGANIZATION>, has designed electrified snake
fences that carry 8,000 volts. He says he has sat up <TIME>night
after night</TIME> watching surrounded snakes zap themselves -- and
then zap themselves again. In the long run, though, "the
mortality rate is <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT>," he says. But the fences are expensive
and can only be used in small areas, perhaps such as the
airport and port. They could also be used to create a few
snake-free <PERSON>Edens</PERSON>.
   Great hopes are also being placed on work being done by
<PERSON>Peter Savarie</PERSON>, a Denver-based research pharmacologist with
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>. He says methyl bromide,
in appropriate doses, kills the snakes. But that also could
only be used in small areas, and requires trained personnel.
   A snake-killing virus is one idea, but no one knows yet
which virus would do the trick. Another possibility is using
sex pheromones to attract snakes into a designated "poison
station," where they could be killed off. Great idea, except
no one knows for sure that the snakes are actually attracted
by such sex lures.
   As biologist <PERSON>Fritts</PERSON> says: "Each line of research may have
some place, but no one of them is going to solve the
problem."
   Meanwhile, <ORGANIZATION>Guam's Division of Aquatic</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Resources</ORGANIZATION> is pushing its own modest proposal: recipes for
brown tree snake, such as snake meat in coconut milk,
deep-fried snake and sweet-and-sour snake. "I haven't eaten
it personally," says wildlife biologist <PERSON>Michael McCoid</PERSON>, "but
people who have say it's tasty, like" -- you guessed it --
"chicken."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900803-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-03-90 0249EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SlitherStudy Bjt   08-03 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Slither Study, Bjt,720</SECOND>
<HEAD>'S Tough to Slink and Slither, Snake Scientists Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's harder work being a snake than scientists
once believed.
   <ORGANIZATION>Three University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>, scientists studying the
energy cost of locomotion report that it takes as much energy for a
snake to undulate along the ground as does for an animal with legs
to walk.
   This, says <PERSON>Bruce Jayne</PERSON>, a coauthor of a study published <DATE>today</DATE> in
Science, is contrary to what scientists have long believed.
   ``Our findings do not support the widely held notion that the
energetic cost of terrestrial locomotion by limbless animals is
less than that of limbed animals,'' he said.
   In plain language, it is as hard to wiggle along as it is to
walk along. Or it takes as much energy to slither as it does to
stroll.
   To find out how hard a snake has to work to get from one place
to another, <PERSON>Jayne</PERSON> and his colleagues got a group of black racer
snakes and figured out a way to put them through an aerobic workout.
   First, the three-foot-long snakes were fitted with little clear
plastic masks. Leading from each mask was a hose that would collect
the exhaled reptilian breath.
   Then the snakes, one by one, were put on a treadmill _ or,
perhaps, it was a slithermill.
   Anyway, once placed on the device a snake crawled like crazy to
keep up with the surface moving under it. As it worked, the snake's
exhaled breath was drawn through the hose and into a machine that
measured the oxygen content.
   How much oxygen was depleted from the breath, said <PERSON>Jayne</PERSON>, was a
measure of the amount of energy the snake needed to slither along.
   The scientists then compared the results with similar studies of
limbed animals, such as lizards, of the same mass, or weight. The
energy used by both the footed and the fanged was about the same,
they discovered.
   <PERSON>Jayne</PERSON> said the study casts doubt on a long-held notion about the
evolution of limbless land animals, such as snakes and some legless
lizards.
   ``One explanation for the evolutionary loss of limbs has been
that it was energetically less expensive,'' he said. Scientists,
said <PERSON>Jayne</PERSON>, have suggested that being legless gave some animals an
advantage because it was thought to require less energy to move
like a snake than to walk on legs.
   Now, he said, that theory no longer seems valid.
   <PERSON>Jayne</PERSON> said the undulating motion of a snake on a flat surface is
only one of several ways the reptile can move.
   Another method is used when a snake crawls through a tunnel
wider than its body, but not wide enough to slither.
   For such a place, snakes use what is called a concertina motion.
   This movement involves bunching up the lower body and then
extending the head forward. Then the upper body is bunched up and
the tail pulled forward.
   To test the energy need for this motion, <PERSON>Jayne</PERSON> and his team
built a tunnel treadmill and the snakes worked out as before with
their exhaled breath measured.
   ``Concertina locomotion is very expensive (in energy use),''
said <PERSON>Jayne</PERSON>. He said it was ``far and away more expensive than
virtually all other kinds of locomotion.''
   <PERSON>Jayne</PERSON> said the black racers used in the experiments lived up to
their names. In a short bursts, he said, the snakes were able to
slither at more than four miles an hour. Typically, though, they
worked at a speed of half a mile an hour, or less. For the
concertina locomotion, the typical speed dropped to less than 200
feet an hour.
   The scientists got their test subjects from an animals supply
house, but black racers are common snakes in the southeastern
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. They eat small rodents, birds and lizards and
typically keep away from humans. They are not poisonous, but, as
<PERSON>Jayne</PERSON> learned, they can bite.
   ``Sometimes when I would get them out of their cages, they would
nip me,'' he said.
   How do you get a snake to start a treadmill workout?
   ``You could just touch their tail or wave your hand and off
they'd go,'' said the scientist.
   Jayne's coauthors in the study were <PERSON>Albert Bennett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael
Walton</PERSON>. Science, which published the study, is the journal of the
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111589-0022 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 134812 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 15, 1989, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
346 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SNAKE BITES THE HAND THAT'S FREEZING IT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MICHAEL GRANBERRY, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Aveteran snake handler at the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> was bitten <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by a venomous 
mole viper, the first such incident in the zoo's history, officials said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Charles W. Radcliffe</PERSON>, 48, who has worked at the zoo three years and previously 
handled snakes at zoos in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> and Ft. Worth, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, was listed in good 
condition <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night in the intensive care unit of <ORGANIZATION>UC San Diego Medical 
Center</ORGANIZATION>. Hospital officials said they expect <ORGANIZATION>Radcliffe</ORGANIZATION> to be released <DATE>today</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Zoo spokesman <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON> said <PERSON>Radcliffe</PERSON> was about to put the mole viper into a 
freezer in preparation for feeding it to a poisonous red-headed krait from 
<LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> when he was bitten at <TIME>9:50 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Kraits feed on other 
snakes, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said, noting that the mole viper is one of 20 "feeder" snakes 
that had arrived in a shipment from a private dealer from out of state. 
</P>
<P>
"Our curator of snakes had never seen a mole viper in 29 years," <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. 
"He had to get a magnifying glass and count the scales on its stomach to be 
able to make a positive identification. The 20 snakes, including the mole 
viper, were not identified as to species or whether or not they were venomous. 
In fact, the mole viper looks exactly like two or three other species of 
nonpoisonous snakes." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said <PERSON>Radcliffe</PERSON> was bitten on the index finger of his right hand, which 
began to "swell and hurt immediately after the bite." <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said the zoo keeps 
a well-stocked supply of anti-venom for most poisonous snakes, but has no such 
serum for the mole viper. 
</P>
<P>
Coincidentally, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said the zoo was notified <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by officials at the 
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> Zoo that one of their handlers was bitten by an African puff adder, 
necessitating a shipment of puff adder anti-venom from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Mexico 
City</LOCATION>, via the <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> airport. He said <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> police rushed the anti-venom 
to <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> for the flight out. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said <PERSON>Radcliffe</PERSON>'s was the second bite a poisonous reptile had inflicted 
on a handler, the first occurring in <DATE>1984</DATE>, when a Gila monster bit two 
handlers. But it was the first time a venomous snake had bitten a handler. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890311-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-11-89 1322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Snake-aholic     03-11 0800</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Snake-aholic,0820</SECOND>
<HEAD>When Viper Bit William Haast, The Viper Died</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto upcoming</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILARY ISRAELSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first time <PERSON>William Haast</PERSON> brought home
poisonous snakes, his horrified mother left home for three days. She
came back only because she realized her son's interest wasn't about
to slither away.
   At 78, <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> remains a self-described ``snake-aholic,'' who has
kept his energy and enthusiasm though he just weathered his 148th
snake bite. It is not surprising it was the viper, not <PERSON>Haast</PERSON>, who
passed on.
   Haast is founder and director of the <ORGANIZATION>Miami Serpentarium
Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>, which he started in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> in <DATE>1946</DATE>. He relocated the
lab to Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION> five years ago to concentrate on venom
research and production.
   Haast claims to be the first to standardize snake venom and
produce it for research use. His clients include <ORGANIZATION>Wyeth Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>,
the only producer of antivenins in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, and almost every
university in the country. He also has helped foster research into
the use of venom against such diseases as polio, multiple sclerosis
and AIDS.
   Haast was in his lab collecting venom from a Pakistani pit viper
<DATE>Feb. 28</DATE> when the serpent bit his left thumb. Not overly concerned,
he waited to see if the weekly venom injections he has given himself
for 40 years would provide immunity to the poison.
   When the bite was still bleeding after 24 hours, he took himself
to the hospital and was diagnosed in critical condition, the venom
robbing his blood of the ability to clot. Doctors said he could have
bled to death from a bump or fall.
   ``I guess I excited every hematologist (blood doctor) in town,''
he said. ``They dug up all the information they had on snake bites.''
   Haast, who was released from the hospital <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, praised the
extraordinary efforts in his behalf to obtain antivenins from
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and even from private sources
in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>. A <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> aide helped contact foreign sources and ease
passage of the medicines through Customs.
   ``Those people involved in getting the antivenins are the heroes
of the story,'' he said. ``All I am is the result of an accident.''
Haast's condition started improving after he received the serum from
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, and doctors in the end opted not to use the foreign
serums.
   The night before <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> was bitten, he and <PERSON>Nancy Harrell</PERSON>, who
helps direct the lab, went to a local steak house for what she
called ``anything goes day.''
   Sometimes at the end of the month <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION> abandons a strict routine
that includes eating animal protein only on even-numbered days and
never touching refined sugar. <TIME>This night</TIME>, he consumed four chocolate
sundaes.
   ``When I let myself go, I really let go,'' he said.
   The next day, <PERSON>Harrell</PERSON> said, <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> was a little hastier than usual
in his work. ``He was really buzzing around the lab that day,'' she
said.
   He believes his strict regimen _ which also includes always
walking up the 11 flights to his condominium _ helped him overcome
the viper's venom and to cleanse his system. It wasn't until nine
days after the bite that he ate solid food. Meantime, the snake had
died of natural causes.
   Haast, first bitten in <DATE>1926</DATE>, says his interest in snakes dates
back nearly 70 years to when he collected garter snakes out of
canals in <LOCATION>Paterson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   In <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION>'s serpentarium near the highway to the <LOCATION>Florida
Keys</LOCATION> was as much a tourist attraction as a laboratory. Visitors
could watch from a glass-enclosed amphitheater while <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION> extracted
venom from hundreds of different species of snakes.
   He and <PERSON>Harrell</PERSON> moved the facility to <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE> to
focus more on research. He declines to say just how well the
business is faring except to say it's ``holding its own.''
   Haast collects venom from each snake about once a week, at the
same time they are fed a high-protein formula he mixes himself.
Harrell helps with the feedings; feeding and venom collection are
done at the same time to minimize trauma to the snakes.
   Nearly 50 years ago, <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> had a hunch that snake venom may be
valuable in treating polio and was proved right. Later, he had the
same feeling about multiple sclerosis and more recently has explored
the possibility of using venom in the fight against AIDS.
   Haast and <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> businessman <PERSON>Alan Glanville</PERSON> have organized AIDS
experimental treatment and research in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. Both hesitate to
discuss the project, saying it is in its infancy and the hospitals
and researchers involved require anonymity.
   Even after his latest brush with death, <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> says there is
little chance he will retire. In fact, he plans to start giving
himself booster shots to create an immunity to the species of viper
that bit him.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111590-0173 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 308353 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 15, 1990, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
North County Focus; Page 6; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1103 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
A PET SHOP WHERE THE SQUEAMISH GO FOR CURE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MAURINA SHERMAN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It's a scene out of your worst nightmare. Thousands of snakes, lizards -- 
reptiles of all kinds -- crawling and writhing and slithering about in a space 
the size of a living room. It's enough to make <LOCATION>Indiana Jones</LOCATION>, or any 
ophidiophobe, go down for the count. 
</P>
<P>
There are albino Burmese pythons. And seven-foot green anacondas. And 
Colombian, Brazilian, and Argentine rainbow boas. There are tree boas, milk 
snakes, rat snakes, corn snakes, Carpet pythons and Baja rosey boas. Iguanas, 
monitors, skinks and chameleons are also scattered about. Any cold-blooded 
little crawly thing that your warm-blooded heart could desire. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>'s Reptile Haven, <LOCATION>2205 E. Valley Parkway</LOCATION>, is one of only a handful of 
reptile "pet" stores in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. It specializes in more than 100 
species of snakes, tortoises, turtles, lizards and amphibians. At second glance 
(if you make it to second glance, that is), it is apparent that all of these 
beguiling beasts are safely behind glass or in aquariums -- save a 
less-than-frightening tortoise or two -- making it possible for visitors to 
browse the aisles and keep a comfortable distance while feigning bravery. 
</P>
<P>
It is just this discomfort and fear that brings many of Reptile Haven's patrons 
to its doors for the first time. 
</P>
<P>
"A lot of people come in to get over their phobia," says owner <PERSON>Chris Estep</PERSON>. "A 
couple of months ago two little old ladies came in. They were shaking at the 
door. They have 20 snakes now. They're really into it." 
</P>
<P>
Reptile Haven has gotten downright educational about this phobia. It has taken 
some of its specimens to psychology classes at <ORGANIZATION>Palomar College</ORGANIZATION> at which 
students overcome their fears by handling the animals. 
</P>
<P>
"We start out real slow," said <PERSON>Estep</PERSON>. "First, they look at (the reptiles) for a 
while, and then someone else holds (the reptiles) in front of them, and then 
they start at the tail and pet them, and, before you know it most of them are 
holding them and they feel good with them." 
</P>
<P>
Estep insists that, once people overcome their fear, reptiles can be wonderful 
pets. What, exactly, are some qualities that make snakes good pets? 
</P>
<P>
"They hold onto you and constrict around your arm," said <PERSON>Estep</PERSON>. "They're real 
slow moving, so they don't run away from you." 
</P>
<P>
Perhaps some people find a constricting snake endearing. For those who wish it 
were a little faster-moving so it could run away from them, there are other 
options. Like iguanas or tortoises. 
</P>
<P>
"Tortoises are my No. 1 love," <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> said. "We have a huge breeding colony set 
up in <LOCATION>Lakeside</LOCATION> for super-rare tortoises. They're great." They're so great, in 
fact, that <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> is looking for another location to expand his enterprise. 
</P>
<P>
"They have a way of looking right into your eyes," he said. "They're really 
personable." 
</P>
<P>
"Tortoises definitely have a lot of character, and are really smart. They'll 
come out of their hiding places in the back yard to see what you're doing." 
Estep points out that tortoises eat mostly vegetation, and they're not 
aggressive when they eat. "They don't seem as bloodthirsty as snakes -- not so 
cold-blooded. They're really docile. Very few people have been hurt by them," 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> doesn't have any pet reptiles at home, he maintains they make 
better pets than cats or dogs. 
</P>
<P>
"They're low-maintenance pets," he said. "You can leave your pet snake for a 
month if you fill his water bowl before you leave, and, when you come back 
he'll be the same way, other than the droppings in the cage. You can't do that 
with a dog." 
</P>
<P>
This low maintenance was one of the draws for <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> to open Reptile Haven. When 
he opened the doors in <DATE>June, 1987</DATE>, <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> also owned A Bird Haven, a few doors 
down. 
</P>
<P>
"With the bird shop, I had to do a lot of work every day," he said. "Here, I 
can take off for three or four days, and, when I come back, other than it being 
a little messier, they're going to be alive." 
</P>
<P>
Reptiles' low susceptibility to virus and disease is another advantage. 
</P>
<P>
"The bird shop got wiped out three times. Everything in the whole shop died" 
because of a severe and fast-moving virus, <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> said. With snakes, however, 
viruses are rarely transmitted between species. 
</P>
<P>
As far as personality goes, however, reptiles fail miserably. "Snakes have the 
least personality," <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> said. "Most people have a snake for a year or so, 
then switch over to a lizard or a tortoise." 
</P>
<P>
Lizards are the most congenial of the lot. "If you raise an iguana from a baby, 
he'll follow you around the house and react to you more than a snake will," 
<PERSON>Estep</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Everything sold at <ORGANIZATION>Reptile Haven</ORGANIZATION> is legal to own. But the manner in which you 
handle and display your acquisition is a little tricky if you want to remain 
within the bounds of the law. Take the case of a 17-foot python. If a minor 
takes it out of its cage, it's illegal. If it is in your house, but out of its 
cage, it's illegal. And, the cage must have a padlock. 
</P>
<P>
"When people have pythons around their necks at the beach -- that's illegal," 
<PERSON>Estep</PERSON> said. "There's a ferocious beast law that covers it." 
</P>
<P>
Until last year, it was illegal in the city of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to own any snake that 
reached over 4 feet. "They don't have that law anymore, because there are very 
few snakes that don't get over 4 feet," <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> said. "Even the king snakes get 4 
1/2 feet." 
</P>
<P>
Estep acknowledges the argument of environmentalists that snakes should be left 
in the wild, rather than kept in captivity. But he maintains that the trade in 
snakes as pets is less of a threat than other demands on the species. In <DATE>1988</DATE> 
over half a million Salvator monitor lizards were killed for the skin trade, he 
said, contrasted with the 1,300 sold in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> as pets. 
</P>
<P>
Most of Reptile Haven's snakes are bred in captivity. 
</P>
<P>
Some are imported from <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. 
Reptile Haven exports some of its inventory, as well. This makes for a lot of 
paperwork, especially in the case of endangered species like the <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> 
tree boa, which sell for <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> a pair. 
</P>
<P>
"In order to sell them out of state, you have to fill out forms with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Department of the Interior</ORGANIZATION> so they can OK the sale," <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> said. "Normally, I 
don't like to do that because the paper work is not worth it. If you sell in 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, all you have to do is give the people you sell to the same paper 
work you have. The government stuff takes about 40 days." 
</P>
<P>
And 40 days can make a big difference in shipping costs when you're dealing 
with live animals. 
</P>
<P>
"A couple years ago, we sold some stuff to <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Estep</PERSON> said. "When I 
bought the snakes, they were 6 pounds, and when we shipped them they were 20 
pounds." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, A young Argentine horned frog rests comfortably atop a 6-year-old frog 
at Reptile Haven, one of the few stores of its type. ; Photo, Kathy Hester 
wrangles with an Arizona mountain king snake. ; Photo, Visitors browse among 
the collection of turtles, some of which are bred at a colony in Lakeside. ; 
Photo, A dwarf chameleon nabs a fly with its long tongue. Iguanas, monitors, 
skinks and other cold-blooded creatures can be found around the shop. DON 
BARTLETTI / Los Angeles Times; Photo, COLOR, FINDS A shop with all the crawly 
little things a heart could desire 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881021-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-21-88 0552EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-AsianSnakeCure ADV26   10-21 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Asian Snake Cure, ADV 26,0663</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv26</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Wed AMs, Oct. 26, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Snake Blood Sold As Cure-all</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARI S. MANIAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BIDOR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's snake blood, not snake oil, but the
Bidor Snake Shop says it cures the same aches, arthritis, asthma,
acne and mysterious maladies of a sexual nature.
   The proprietor, <PERSON>Loi Chee Long</PERSON>, sells the blood of cobras and
other poisonous snakes to those who find his shop in this jungle
town 90 miles north of <LOCATION>Kuala Lumpur</LOCATION> and can pay the fee of up to
<MONEY>$120</MONEY>.
   Customers buy the snake, then Loi kills it and drains the blood,
mixing it with brandy for taste and wallop.
   Most of his customers are from <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>, but some
tourists drop in from <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> and there
is the occasional Western curiosity-seeker.
   ``The white man comes, but I think it is all too disgusting to
him,'' said <PERSON>Loi</PERSON>, 27. ``He inquires about the whole thing with great
enthusiasm, but when we ask him to have a drink he says `Not for
me, thanks.'''
   As he spoke, Loi had a firm grip on the neck of a cobra longer
than he was. Loi is about 5 ft. tall and the reptile's tail
thrashed the ground.
   The commotion continued while he explained calmly that people
drink snake blood because it can cure ``rheumatism, body aches and
skin diseases, improve the eyesight and increase your sexual
prowess, among other things.''
   He said a snake's venom is in its mouth and the blood contains
no poison.
   Loi explained the procedure like a surgeon conducting class:
   ``I hold the snake by the neck, find the main blood vessels on
the underside, slit them with a sharp knife and gather the blood in
the glass.
   ``Pieces of the snake's gallbladder are thrown in and an equal
amount of brandy is added. The brandy is to give the whole thing a
kick as you drink it. Beer and stout won't give that.
   ``This drinking cobra blood is nothing new. The Chinese have
been doing it for years.''
   With his free hand, he plucked a snake from another cage.
   ``Am I scared?'' he said. ``No. I have been catching snakes
since I left school at the age of 16.
   ``At first I used to creep quietly behind the snake, hold its
head with a stick and grab it by the neck and dump it into a cage.
Now I just grab it by the neck. After so many years, it would be
amateurish to use the stick.''
   He has never been bitten, <PERSON>Loi</PERSON> said, because he is a professional
snake catcher whose rule is: ``Your hand grabbing the neck has to
be quicker than the cobra's head to bite you.''
   Other professional catchers in Bidor include <PERSON>Wai Kwan Yang</PERSON>, his
partner in the shop, and Lim Ah Ha, who was listening to the
interview, <PERSON>Loi</PERSON> said.
   They take no antidote with them on hunting forays ``because the
doctor says it is illegal for us to carry such medicine around,''
he said, but ``we carry a small knife. If I am bitten I would cut
the area, drain the blood and rush to a doctor.
   ``We catch only poisonous snakes like the cobra, black cobra,
king cobra and pit vipers because only their blood will have the
proper effect.''
   About 30 to 50 people come to the shop for blood every month,
which <PERSON>Loi</PERSON> said was healthy traffic considering the price.
   ``To buy a cobra or some other poisonous snake ... would cost
between 100 and 300 ringgits (<MONEY>$40</MONEY> to <MONEY>$120</MONEY>), and that is a lot of
money considering that a long snake would only yield about six to
eight tablespoons of blood,'' he said. ``One snake is enough only
for one drink.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed AMs, Oct. 26</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890302-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-02-89 1355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--SnakeBite     03-02 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Snake Bite,0174</SECOND>
<HEAD>Venom Researcher Bitten By Snake For 148th Time</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A researcher who maintains 1,000 venomous
snakes for scientific purposes was in serious but stable condition
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> after being bitten by a deadly <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> pit viper, his
148th snake bite.
   <PERSON>William E. Haast</PERSON>, 78, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Miami Serpentarium
Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>, was extracting venom from the viper <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> when it
bit his thumb, said <PERSON>John Dwan</PERSON>, spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>University of Utah
Health Sciences Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   Haast drove himself to the hospital, but doctors were not
immediately able to administer anti-venin because <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> was allergic
to the stock on hand. Another type was flown in from the <LOCATION>San Diego
Zoo</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> told him it was the 148th time he'd been bitten
by a snake.
   The 40-year-old <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> Serpentarium originated the concept of
importing snakes from around the world to collect their venom. Its
customers include the <ORGANIZATION>National Institutes of Health</ORGANIZATION> and hundreds of
research and medical laboratories, which use the venom to
manufacture anti-venins.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901015-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-15-90 0805EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SnakeAlert     10-15 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Snake Alert,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snake Expert: They Believe Me Now</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KILEY ARMSTRONG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maybe there was something amiss in the hiss.
   Maybe it was viperous vibes.
   Whatever the serpentine signal he received, <PERSON>Tom Robertson Jr.</PERSON>
deemed things were not as they ssssssssseemed.
   <PERSON>Robertson</PERSON>, 36, a self-taught snake expert and former zoo
employee, walked into a pet store on <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Upper West
Side</LOCATION> about a week ago to buy some fish food.
   When he glanced at a tank that supposedly held harmless garter
snakes, he recognized similar-looking, Asian water snakes known as
Redneck Keelbacks. The snake's bite, in rare instances, can be
fatal.
   ``I told a guy in the store,'' said <PERSON>Robertson</PERSON>. ``He said he knew
they weren't poisonous. I told him I could bring them some proof;
he got real arrogant. I brought back a book, but they still didn't
believe me. ... I called the police, the <ORGANIZATION>ASPCA</ORGANIZATION>, Fish and <PERSON>Wildlife</PERSON> -
I called a lot of places, trying to find out what to do.''
   Finally, someone at the city <ORGANIZATION>Health Department</ORGANIZATION> took him
seriously.
   The department's inspectors called a <ORGANIZATION>New York University</ORGANIZATION>
biologist who confirmed <PERSON>Robertson</PERSON>'s suspicions.
   The inspectors learned that a wholesaler had sold <ORGANIZATION>Petland
Discount</ORGANIZATION> stores about 50 supposedly harmless snakes - and that some
had been distributed to the chain's 50 stores in the metropolitan
area.
