<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-38623 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu024_h_94009" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> GERMANY </F>
<H3> <TI>   Spokesman Describes Visit </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0402100694 Delhi All India Radio Network in English 0830 
GMT 4 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0402100694 </F>
<F P=104>  Delhi All India Radio Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> have agreed to take all necessary 
steps to boost India-German cooperation in industrial and 
technical fields. The two countries have agreed to set up an 
India-Germany joint mechanism to monitor progress in scientific 
cooperation. An official spokesman summing up the prime 
minister's visit to <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> said both the countries have also 
agreed to review the avoidance of double taxation treaty and 
pursue efforts to sign bilateral investment guarantees. Our 
correspondent Sudarshnam reports from <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>: 
  [Begin Sudarshnam recording] The Federation of German 
Industry and <ORGANIZATION>India-German Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> have sent 54 
proposals to intensify the economic relationship between the two 
countries. These relate to general and financial issues, 
pharmaceuticals and chemical industries, private sector and air 
traffic. As many as 40 ministries and departments in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> 
examined these proposals. Several of these have been 
implemented. Decision in respect of some are awaited. [end 
recording] 
  In another development, leading political parties of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> 
have assured <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> that the <LOCATION>New Asia</LOCATION> concept initiated by 
Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> making <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as a target country for 
intensified bilateral cooperation will be honored whichever 
party comes to power in this year's German elections. The 
assurance was conveyed to the prime minister, <PERSON>Mr. P.V. Narasimha 
Rao</PERSON>, when important German political leaders called on him in 
<LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> yesterday. An official spokesman said that there is a 
multiparty support to Chancellor <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>New Asia</LOCATION> concept, as 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has willingly recognized that <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in 
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> will be important political and economic powers in the 
years to come. The chief of the German Agency for Aid has 
shown his willingness to open a second window for soft credit to 
finance infrastructure projects in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. The projects include 
power and telecommunications sector. Meanwhile, the minister 
of state for external affairs, <PERSON>Mr. Salman Khurshid</PERSON>, who is 
accompanying the prime minister, has reiterated <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 
willingness to improve bilateral relations with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>. He 
made it clear that <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION> has no locus standi in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, and 
it is not in a position to advise <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in this matter. The 
minister said <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has no problems regarding protection of 
human rights, and it is always ready to be open with 
  As reported, the prime minister is leaving for <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> today. 
He will meet the German president and address the <ORGANIZATION>Humboldt 
University</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> is also scheduled to have meeting 
with German business leaders and inaugurate the <ORGANIZATION>Indian Cultural 
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>. On <DATE>Sunday</DATE> [6 <DATE>February</DATE>], <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> is 
returning home. Our correspondent Karuppaswamy reports that his 
meeting with German indologists and business leaders will be 
continuation of his earlier exprience in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> to reassure 
Germans that the reform process in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is irreversible. The 
visit of the prime minister is the first official visit from 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to the reunited <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> -- the upcoming capital of the 
united <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-38598 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu024_g_94009" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> GERMANY </F>
<H3> <TI>   Spokesman Describes Visit </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0402100694 Delhi All India Radio Network in English 0830 
GMT 4 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0402100694 </F>
<F P=104>  Delhi All India Radio Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> have agreed to take all necessary 
steps to boost India-German cooperation in industrial and 
technical fields. The two countries have agreed to set up an 
India-Germany joint mechanism to monitor progress in scientific 
cooperation. An official spokesman summing up the prime 
minister's visit to <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> said both the countries have also 
agreed to review the avoidance of double taxation treaty and 
pursue efforts to sign bilateral investment guarantees. Our 
correspondent Sudarshnam reports from <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>: 
  [Begin Sudarshnam recording] The Federation of German 
Industry and <ORGANIZATION>India-German Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> have sent 54 
proposals to intensify the economic relationship between the two 
countries. These relate to general and financial issues, 
pharmaceuticals and chemical industries, private sector and air 
traffic. As many as 40 ministries and departments in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> 
examined these proposals. Several of these have been 
implemented. Decision in respect of some are awaited. [end 
recording] 
  In another development, leading political parties of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> 
have assured <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> that the <LOCATION>New Asia</LOCATION> concept initiated by 
Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> making <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as a target country for 
intensified bilateral cooperation will be honored whichever 
party comes to power in this year's German elections. The 
assurance was conveyed to the prime minister, <PERSON>Mr. P.V. Narasimha 
Rao</PERSON>, when important German political leaders called on him in 
<LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> yesterday. An official spokesman said that there is a 
multiparty support to Chancellor <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>New Asia</LOCATION> concept, as 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has willingly recognized that <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in 
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> will be important political and economic powers in the 
years to come. The chief of the German Agency for Aid has 
shown his willingness to open a second window for soft credit to 
finance infrastructure projects in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. The projects include 
power and telecommunications sector. Meanwhile, the minister 
of state for external affairs, <PERSON>Mr. Salman Khurshid</PERSON>, who is 
accompanying the prime minister, has reiterated <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 
willingness to improve bilateral relations with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>. He 
made it clear that <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION> has no locus standi in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, and 
it is not in a position to advise <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in this matter. The 
minister said <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has no problems regarding protection of 
human rights, and it is always ready to be open with 
  As reported, the prime minister is leaving for <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> today. 
He will meet the German president and address the <ORGANIZATION>Humboldt 
University</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> is also scheduled to have meeting 
with German business leaders and inaugurate the <ORGANIZATION>Indian Cultural 
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>. On <DATE>Sunday</DATE> [6 <DATE>February</DATE>], <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> is 
returning home. Our correspondent Karuppaswamy reports that his 
meeting with German indologists and business leaders will be 
continuation of his earlier exprience in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> to reassure 
Germans that the reform process in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is irreversible. The 
visit of the prime minister is the first official visit from 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to the reunited <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> -- the upcoming capital of the 
united <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-38468 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu023_h_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-023 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> GERMANY </F>
<H3> <TI>   Rao Views Economic Cooperation </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0302121094 Delhi All India Radio Network in English 0830 
GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0302121094 </F>
<F P=104>  Delhi All India Radio Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpts] <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has assured <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> that it will continue 
to take a neutral stance on the <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> issue and not make any 
value judgments. Kashmir figured prominently in the talks 
between the prime minister and the German leaders in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. 
Narasimha Rao</PERSON> explained to them the problems faced by <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> 
because of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s abetment of terrorism in <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Punjab</LOCATION>. [passage omitted] 
  Earlier, <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> held talks with the German 
Carl-Dieter Spranger</PERSON>, and reaffirmed <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s commitment to 
closer cooperation with <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> also told German 
leaders that <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> is keen on enhanced trade and investment 
flow from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. He emphasized that the theme of the Asian 
partnership choice and strategic partnership should be made a 
reality [sentence as heard]. 
  Our correspondent <PERSON>S. Sudarshanam</PERSON> adds from <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> that <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 
line of thinking is in tune with <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s new <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> policy which 
seeks to widen its cooperation with the Asian countries like 
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. The German minister told the prime 
minister that he would lead a 20-member delegation to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> soon 
to explore further cooperation in trade, investment, and joint 
venture in technical and technological fields. The signing of 
aid protocol for this year will also come up during his visit. 
  Meanwhile, the new foreign secretary, <PERSON>Mr. K. Srinivasan</PERSON>, 
told 
newspersons at <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> that the German leaders emphasized greater 
cooperation in trade, science, and technology. He said <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> 
is a major trading partner with <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and two German ministers 
in charge of economic development and foreign affairs are 
planning to visit <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> before <DATE>June this year</DATE>. 
  The chairman of the German multinational corporation, <ORGANIZATION>Bayer</ORGANIZATION>, 
held talks with the prime minister and indicated that <ORGANIZATION>Bayer</ORGANIZATION> is 
to set up a pharmaceutical plant at <LOCATION>Manali</LOCATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Tamil Nadu</ORGANIZATION>. This 
afternoon, the prime minister will have talks with the German 
chancellor, <PERSON>Dr. Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, on strengthening economic and trade 
relations. <PERSON>Dr. Kohl</PERSON> will host a working lunch. Cooperation in 
scientific, technical, and cultural fields and issues of mutual 
interests are likely to figure in the talks. The prime 
minister, now on a four-day official visit, will leave for 
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> tomorrow. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881223-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-88 2021EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-China-Gandhi 1stLd-Writethru a0668 12-23 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Gandhi, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0668,0457</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gandhi Returns to India After Patching Up Ties With China</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 2 grafs to UPDATE with Tibetan protest. Pickup 3rd
graf `Gandhi told...'; SUBS 9th graf `New Delhi...' with graf to ADD
communique details on Tibet. Pickup 10th graf `India has...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RAJU GOPALAKRISHNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON> came home
<DATE>Friday</DATE> after five days in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and said his visit restored the
friendly Indian-Chinese relations of the early <DATE>1950s</DATE>.
   Also <DATE>Friday</DATE>, about 100 Tibetan students outside Parliament set
fire to a Chinese flag and denounced <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s recognition of <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION> as
part of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. Police with bamboo canes watched the rally but did
generally not interfere.
   Gandhi told a news conference at <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>'s international
airport, ``I believe this visit will be a new beginning for both
countries.''
   A border dispute has strained relations between <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>,
the world's two most populous countries, for nearly three decades.
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has more than 1 billion people, and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has about 800
million.
   Gandhi's visit to <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> was the first by an Indian prime
minister since his grandfather, <PERSON>Jawaharlal Nehru</PERSON>, visited <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in
<DATE>1954</DATE>.
   The two countries issued a communique in <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> earlier <DATE>Friday</DATE>,
agreeing to set up a joint working group to take up the territorial
dispute, which led to war in <DATE>1962</DATE>. <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> said the group would set a
time frame in which to resolve the issue.
   The communique also said Chinese Premier <PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON> has accepted an
invitation to visit <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, but no date was set.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> claims 36,000 square miles of mountainous frontier that
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> says is part of its Arunachal Pradesh state. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> also says
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> illegally occupies 14,500 square miles in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>
state.
   Gandhi also told reporters that Chinese leaders respected <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
views on <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>, another sore point in relations. <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> invaded
mountainous <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION> in <DATE>1949</DATE> and annexed it a year later.
   The communique noted that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> ``expressed concern over
anti-China activities by some Tibetan elements in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>,'' and that
the Indian side had repeated its policy of recognizing <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION> as a
part of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and banning Tibetans from carrying out anti-Chinese
political activities on Indian soil.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has granted asylum to the <ORGANIZATION>Dalai Lama</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>'s religious
leader, and thousands of his followers who fled <ORGANIZATION>Tibet</ORGANIZATION> after an
abortive uprising against Chinese rule in <DATE>1959</DATE>. <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> blames
supporters of the <ORGANIZATION>Dalai Lama</ORGANIZATION> for pro-independence activities that
led to clashes with police in the last 14 months.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> signed three agreements _ a civil
aviation accord calling for direct flights between <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, a three-year cultural agreement, and a science and
technology pact.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-34197 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes024_r_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> India </F>
<H3> <TI>   Rao Discusses Bilateral Ties With Kohl in Berlin </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0402062494 Delhi All India Radio Network in English 0245 
GMT 4 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0402062494 </F>
<F P=104>  Delhi All India Radio Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> have expressed concern at the 
dangers posed by religious extremism. The prime minister, <PERSON>Mr. 
Narasimha Rao</PERSON>, and Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> called for immediate 
steps to check the spread of this threat. Briefing newsmen on 
the one-to-one talks between <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dr. Kohl</PERSON>, an official 
spokesman said in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> that the two leaders discussed 
Indo-Pakistan relations. The prime minister reiterated that 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is in favor of peaceful relations with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON>, 
however, regretted that despite <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>'s efforts, the 
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> prime minister, <PERSON>Ms. Benazir Bhutto</PERSON>, has taken a 
strident view. Referring to the package of proposals offered by 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> following the recent foreign secretary-level talks, <PERSON>Mr. 
Rao</PERSON> expressed the hope that continuance of worthwhile dialogue 
will yield positive results. During the talks, <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> promised to 
take steps to speed up access of German technology to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. 
The German chancellor, <PERSON>Dr. Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, said bottlenecks, if 
any, will be removed. He promised to support <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in its 
dealings with the <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has a prominent place 
in the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION>. Our correspondent, <PERSON>S. Sudarshanam</PERSON>, understands 
that <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> spoke about human rights environment in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and 
the steps taken to protect and promote the human rights 
aspirations of the people. Earlier, the German foreign affairs 
minister, <PERSON>Dr. Klaus Kinkel</PERSON>, called on the prime minister. 
  The prime minister is visiting <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> later today. Our 
special correspondent, <PERSON>Karuppaswamy</PERSON>, reports: 
  [Begin Karuppaswamy recording] <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> is one of the very big 
cities in the world outside <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> with a full-fledged museum 
dedicated exclusively to Indian art. There are several streets 
named after <PERSON>Ravindranath Tagore</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jawaharlal Nehru</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Indira 
Gandhi</PERSON>. And <PERSON>Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose</PERSON> visited the city for 
the possible assistance during freedom struggle. <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha 
Rao</PERSON> will be received by the federal president, <PERSON>Dr. Richard Von 
Weizsacker</PERSON>. His engagements during his two days of visit to 
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> include a meeting with the governing mayor of the city, 
the German indologists, and representatives of the industry and 
commerce. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881223-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-88 0434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-Gandhi     12-23 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-Gandhi,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gandhi Visit To China Ends On High Note</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> ended a visit
to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> today with the two nations expressing a common desire to
improve ties after nearly three decades of strained relations.
   Gandhi, accompanied by his wife, <PERSON>Sonia</PERSON>, departed for home from
<LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION> after his five-day visit, the first by an Indian head of
government since his grandfather, <PERSON>Jawaharlal Nehru</PERSON>, visited in <DATE>1954</DATE>.
   Both sides said the visit ushered in a new era of good will
between the world's most populous nations. <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> said his trip
marked a ``new beginning'' for the two countries.
   During the visit, the countries agreed to set up a joint working
group to take up their most divisive issue, a territorial dispute
that broke out into a short border war in <DATE>1962</DATE>.
   ``The leaders of the two countries held earnest, in-depth
discussions on the India-China boundary question and agreed to
settle this question through peaceful and friendly consultations,''
a joint communique said.
   It added, ``They also agreed to develop their relations actively
in other fields and work hard to create a favorable climate and
conditions for a fair and reasonable settlement of the boundary
question.''
   It said <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>'s talks with Chinese Premier <PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON> were held
``in an atmosphere of friendship, candidness and mutual
understanding.'' Gandhi also met with senior leader <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> head <PERSON>Zhao Ziyang</PERSON> and President <PERSON>Yang Shangkun</PERSON>.
   The border issue, <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> said, is ``very complicated'' and a
quick solution is unlikely.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> claims 36,000 square miles of mountainous frontier in what
<LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> says is northeast <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s Arunachal Pradesh province.
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> says <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> illegally occupies 14,500 square miles on its
western border.
   The communique said <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> ``expressed concern over anti-China
activities by some Tibetan elements in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>,'' and that the Indian
side repeated its policy of recognizing <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION> as a part of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and
banning Tibetans from carrying out anti-Chinese political activities
on Indian soil.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has been the home of <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>'s religious leader, the <ORGANIZATION>Dalai
Lama</ORGANIZATION>, and thousands of his followers who fled <ORGANIZATION>Tibet</ORGANIZATION> after an
abortive anti-Chinese uprising in <DATE>1959</DATE>. <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> blames supporters of
the <ORGANIZATION>Dalai Lama</ORGANIZATION> for pro-independence activities that have led to
violent clashes with police the past 14 months.
   Gandhi on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> presided over the signing of three bilateral
agreements _a civil aviation accord calling for direct flights
between <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, a three-year cultural agreement and a
science and technology agreement.
   The communique said Premier Li accepted an invitation to visit
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, but no date was set.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, grappling with economic problems at home, has made a
commitment to improving relations with its neighbors.
   Soviet President <PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON> is expected to visit <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>
next year, becoming the first Soviet leader to do so in 30 years.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> will likely normalize relations with the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>
during the visit. The two countries fought a border war in <DATE>1969</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881220-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-88 0920EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-Gandhi     12-20 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-Gandhi,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gandhi Says India Will Not Interfere in Tibet</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s
president, <PERSON>Yang Shangkun</PERSON>, today discussed <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s troubled region of
<LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> said his country will not interfere in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s
internal affairs.
   The Indian leader spent much of his second day in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>
   The official <ORGANIZATION>Xinhua News Agency</ORGANIZATION> said Yang explained <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s
position on <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Gandhi</LOCATION> during a one-hour meeting at the <PERSON>Great
Hall</PERSON> of the People.
   Yang, 81, who has held the largely ceremonial post of president
since <DATE>April</DATE>, stressed that the <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> government provides
assistance to the Tibetan region, one of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s most backward areas.
   ``We respect the religious beliefs and customs and habits of the
Tibetan people, and they enjoy the freedom of religious belief,''
<PERSON>Yang</PERSON> said.
   Gandhi repeated <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s position that <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION> is an autonomous
region of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and that <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> will not interfere in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s
internal affairs, <ORGANIZATION>Xinhua</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The Tibetan issue has long been a source of tension between the
two countries because <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has provided refuge to the Tibetan
religious leader, the <ORGANIZATION>Dalai Lama</ORGANIZATION>, and his followers, who have
demanded independence for <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Dalai Lama</ORGANIZATION> fled to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in
<DATE>1959</DATE> after he led a failed uprising against Chinese military forces.
   At least one Tibetan monk was shot and killed by Chinese security
forces during a demonstration in the Tibetan capital of <LOCATION>Lhasa</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Dec. 10</DATE>. It was the third outbreak of anti-Chinese violence in <LOCATION>Lhasa</LOCATION>
in the past 14 months.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> are trying to restore friendly ties after <DATE>a
quarter century</DATE> of soured relations, which hit bottom during a
21-day border war in <DATE>1962</DATE>.
   The border question was the main topic during talks <DATE>Monday</DATE>
between <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s Premier <PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> claims 36,000 square miles of what <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> says is part of
its northeast state of <LOCATION>Arunachal Pradesh</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> claims 14,500 square
miles of land seized by <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in <DATE>1962</DATE>.
   Gandhi and Li, however, vowed not to let the border problem
interfere with efforts to improve the strained bilateral ties.
   Gandhi is the first Indian leader to visit <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> since his
grandfather, former Prime Minister <PERSON>Jawalharlal Nehru</PERSON>, came in <DATE>1954</DATE>.
   Accomapnied by his Italian-born wife, <PERSON>Sonia</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> today
traveled about 37 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> to the Badaling section
of the Great Wall, the 3,720-mile-long barrier built over a
2,000-year period to keep out invaders.
   The Indian leader also visited the <ORGANIZATION>Temple of Heaven</ORGANIZATION>, a 15th
century structure where <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s emperors once prayed for good
harvests and performed sacrificial rituals.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> is scheduled to meet 84-year-old senior
leader <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party General</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Zhao
Ziyang</PERSON>.
   The two sides are expected to sign agreements on civil aviation,
border trade, science and technology and the exchange of consular
offices in <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-38622 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu024_h_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> GERMANY </F>
<H3> <TI>   Rao Says Industrial Climate `Extremely Good' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0402001394 Delhi All India Radio Network in English 1530 
GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0402001394 </F>
<F P=104>  Delhi All India Radio Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The prime minister has invited German businessmen 
to invest in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Addressing the <ORGANIZATION>Indo-German Economic 
Conference</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> today, <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> described the 
industrial climate in the country as extremely good and 
favorable for investment. Making it clear that his government 
has absolutely no hesitation in going ahead with the economic 
liberalization process, <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> asserted that <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> will step up 
the reform process. He assured the German industry that there 
will be no constraints coming in the way. He added that 
constraints if any will be resolved by him and the German 
chancellor, <PERSON>Dr. Helmut Kohl</PERSON>. 
  Opening the conference, the chancellor, <PERSON>Dr. Kohl</PERSON>, assured 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> of all possible assistance for the development of the 
industrial and technological cooperation. He said the economic 
policies of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> are on the right path. He told the conference 
that <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> with its reform-oriented economic policy is one of 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s most important partners on the Asian continent. <PERSON>Dr. 
Kohl</PERSON> announced that both the countries have agreed to establish 
a high-level India-German commission for science and technology. 
The president of the <ORGANIZATION>Confederation of Indian Industry</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. N. 
Godrej</PERSON>, asked <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> to remove the constraints and controls on 
technology transfer. 
  Our correspondent, <LOCATION>Sudarshanam</LOCATION>, reports from <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> that 
German 
industry has drawn up certain proposals for deregulating and 
liberalizing <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s economy. These proposals have been 
forwarded to the <ORGANIZATION>Indian Government</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Indian Government</ORGANIZATION> after 
a study has sent certain recommendations. These are being 
examined to strengthen the economic and trade cooperation. Our 
correspondent understands that a German festival in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> will 
be held as soon as possible. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> was given a formal ceremonial welcome in the 
forecourt of the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Chancellor's Office</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> 
inspected a guard of honor by the <ORGANIZATION>German Air Force</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Here is a report from our special correspondent A. 
Karuppaswamy: [Begin Karuppaswamy recording] The opening of the 
first India-German economic conference in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> by the German 
chancellor and <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> is another successful step 
towards the India-German cooperation. The event follows the 
successful dialogue between Indian and German industrialists 
since the prime minister's last visit in <DATE>1991</DATE>. The exchange of 
view and suggestions between the two delegates at the conference 
largely reflects the compelling necessity of both the nations to 
come closer to strengthen their bilateral ties in global 
interests. Modern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is viewed by Germans as a very valuable 
strategic partner in economic and scientific development because 
of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s ongoing reform-oriented economic policies aimed at 
liberalization offering one of the biggest markets in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. [end 
recording] 
  That was a report from our special correspondent in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. 
  Earlier, <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> held talks with the German 
Carl-Dieter Sprangar</PERSON>, and reaffirmed <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s commitment to 
closer cooperation with <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> also told German 
leaders that <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> is keen on enhanced trade and investment 
flow from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 
  <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has assured <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> that it will continue to take a 
neutral stance on the <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> issue. Kashmir figured 
prominently in the talks between the prime minister and the 
German leaders in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> explained the 
problems faced by <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> because of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s abetment of 
terrorism in <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Punjab</LOCATION>. He said, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> is 
deliberately creating conditions to obstruct a meaningful 
dialogue. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-38597 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu024_g_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> GERMANY </F>
<H3> <TI>   Rao Says Industrial Climate `Extremely Good' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0402001394 Delhi All India Radio Network in English 1530 
GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0402001394 </F>
<F P=104>  Delhi All India Radio Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The prime minister has invited German businessmen 
to invest in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Addressing the <ORGANIZATION>Indo-German Economic 
Conference</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> today, <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> described the 
industrial climate in the country as extremely good and 
favorable for investment. Making it clear that his government 
has absolutely no hesitation in going ahead with the economic 
liberalization process, <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> asserted that <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> will step up 
the reform process. He assured the German industry that there 
will be no constraints coming in the way. He added that 
constraints if any will be resolved by him and the German 
chancellor, <PERSON>Dr. Helmut Kohl</PERSON>. 
  Opening the conference, the chancellor, <PERSON>Dr. Kohl</PERSON>, assured 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> of all possible assistance for the development of the 
industrial and technological cooperation. He said the economic 
policies of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> are on the right path. He told the conference 
that <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> with its reform-oriented economic policy is one of 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s most important partners on the Asian continent. <PERSON>Dr. 
Kohl</PERSON> announced that both the countries have agreed to establish 
a high-level India-German commission for science and technology. 
The president of the <ORGANIZATION>Confederation of Indian Industry</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. N. 
Godrej</PERSON>, asked <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> to remove the constraints and controls on 
technology transfer. 
  Our correspondent, <LOCATION>Sudarshanam</LOCATION>, reports from <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> that 
German 
industry has drawn up certain proposals for deregulating and 
liberalizing <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s economy. These proposals have been 
forwarded to the <ORGANIZATION>Indian Government</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Indian Government</ORGANIZATION> after 
a study has sent certain recommendations. These are being 
examined to strengthen the economic and trade cooperation. Our 
correspondent understands that a German festival in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> will 
be held as soon as possible. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> was given a formal ceremonial welcome in the 
forecourt of the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Chancellor's Office</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> 
inspected a guard of honor by the <ORGANIZATION>German Air Force</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Here is a report from our special correspondent A. 
Karuppaswamy: [Begin Karuppaswamy recording] The opening of the 
first India-German economic conference in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> by the German 
chancellor and <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> is another successful step 
towards the India-German cooperation. The event follows the 
successful dialogue between Indian and German industrialists 
since the prime minister's last visit in <DATE>1991</DATE>. The exchange of 
view and suggestions between the two delegates at the conference 
largely reflects the compelling necessity of both the nations to 
come closer to strengthen their bilateral ties in global 
interests. Modern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is viewed by Germans as a very valuable 
strategic partner in economic and scientific development because 
of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s ongoing reform-oriented economic policies aimed at 
liberalization offering one of the biggest markets in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. [end 
recording] 
  That was a report from our special correspondent in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. 
  Earlier, <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> held talks with the German 
Carl-Dieter Sprangar</PERSON>, and reaffirmed <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s commitment to 
closer cooperation with <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> also told German 
leaders that <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> is keen on enhanced trade and investment 
flow from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 
  <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has assured <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> that it will continue to take a 
neutral stance on the <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> issue. Kashmir figured 
prominently in the talks between the prime minister and the 
German leaders in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> explained the 
problems faced by <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> because of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s abetment of 
terrorism in <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Punjab</LOCATION>. He said, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> is 
deliberately creating conditions to obstruct a meaningful 
dialogue. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-21429 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpnea015___94031" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-NEA-94-015 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Near East &amp; South Asia 

</HEADER>

<ABS> </ABS>
<DATE1>     5 February 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> INDIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Papers Report Rao Visit to Germany </TI></H3>
<H4>   Reply to Memo </H4>
<F P=102> 94AS0223C Bombay THE TIMES OF INDIA in English 5 Feb 94 p 17 </F>
<F P=103> 94AS0223C </F>
<F P=104>  Bombay THE TIMES OF INDIA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:<ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [All quotation marks as published] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, <DATE>February 4</DATE>--The Indian government is 
"seriously considering" doing away with the situation that 
foreign equity should cover the foreign exchange requirement for 
import of capital goods under the automatic approval category, 
as part of ongoing liberalisation process, <ORGANIZATION>UNI</ORGANIZATION> reports. 
  This has been conveyed by the Prime Minister, <PERSON>Mr P.V. 
Narasimha Rao</PERSON>, in the Indian government's reply to the "Kohl 
memorandum" sent to <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> after the German Chancellor, Dr 
<PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>'s visit to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <DATE>February last year</DATE>. 
  The memorandum, entitled `Proposals on Economic Policies and 
Procedures of the <ORGANIZATION>Government of India</ORGANIZATION>', was forwarded by the 
Chancellor in <DATE>July last year</DATE>. 
  Some of the other proposals for further liberalisation, made 
in the memorandum and under active consideration of the 
government, are: 
  --Liberalisation of the pharmaceutical and chemical 
industry; 
  --Removal of the phased manufacturing programme obligations 
for units established prior to the new industrial policy; 
  --Increasing the prescribed payment limits for automatic 
approvals of technical collaborations; 
  --Amendment of the Industrial Disputes Act. 
  The government's reply to the memorandum also states that on 
some other issues, such as enforceability of foreign awards, the 
government had an "open mind" and was willing to consider the 
matter. 
  The Indian reply to the memorandum was given to the German 
government a few days before <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON>'s arrival on a state visit 
here. 
  The Indian reply states that it must be appreciated as a 
fundamental point relating to the issues raised in the "Kohl 
memorandum" that since the process of reforms was initiated 
several policy changes had been progressively made and 
procedures increasingly streamlined to improve the business 
environment in the country. 
  The reply adds that several of the proposals made in the 
memorandum were already under implementation. They were 
identified as: 
  --To decrease the number of industries reserved for the 
public sector; 
  --Faster clearance for applications under the <ORGANIZATION>EPCG</ORGANIZATION> [Export 
Promotion Capital Goods] scheme; 
  --Negotiation of more favourable double-taxation agreement; 
  --More liberal procedures for payment of foreign 
technicians; 
  --Long duration purchase agreements for power and secured 
fuel supplies for such projects; 
  --Equal opportunities for manufacturers in the telecom 
sector. 
  Under six broad classifications, the memorandum put forward 
suggestions on a vast range of areas and subjects such as 
desirability of a "negative" list; speeding up of state 
governments' proposals; uniform industrial policy in the states; 
remittance facilities for foreign nationals; disinvestment 
procedures; and governing law and arbitration for contracts 
entered into with foreign parties. 
  PTI adds: Leading political parties in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> 
have assured <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> that the new `<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> concept' unveiled by the 
Chancellor, Dr <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, with <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as a target country for 
intensified bilateral cooperation and embracing a wide range of 
fields, would be honoured irrespective of which party came to 
power in this year's elections there. 
  This assurance was conveyed to <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON>, when a series of 
important German political leaders called on him here yesterday. 
  An official spokesman said that by and large there was "a 
multi-party support" to Dr <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON>'s new `<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> concept', as <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> 
has willingly recognised that <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> 
would be the important political and economic powers in the 
coming years. 
  The important German leaders who called on <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON> included 
<PERSON>Mr 
Hans Ulrich Klose</PERSON>, chairman of the parliamentary group of 
<ORGANIZATION>Socialist Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>, Dr <PERSON>Wolfgang Schauble</PERSON>, chairman of 
the parliamentary group of the <ORGANIZATION>Christian Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>, and 
Dr <PERSON>Hermann Otto Solms</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Free Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Meanwhile, <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON> reached the historic city of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> <TIME>this 
afternoon</TIME> on the last leg of his six-day tour to <LOCATION>Davos</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 
  <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON> is scheduled to meet the German President, <PERSON>Mr Richard 
von Weizsaecker</PERSON>, besides opening the cultural festival programme 
at the Indian cultural centre there tomorrow. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881217-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-88 1035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GandhiVisit Bjt   12-17 0748</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gandhi Visit, Bjt,0768</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gandhi In China: First Visit Of Indian Leader In 34 Years</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN POMFRET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON> comes to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE> for the first
visit by an Indian prime minister since his grandfather, <PERSON>Jawalharlal
Nehru</PERSON>, made the trip 34 years ago.
   For <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>'s nation and his political future, the stakes appear
high. For <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, little seemingly can go wrong.
   During a week long on symbolism but short on substance, <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>
will be feted in the capital, tour the ancient city of <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION> and
visit <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION>.
   The visit, <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> recently said, will be ``very important ... for
this globe, for <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and for both of us.''
   The two nations _ the world's most populous _ will probably sign
agreements on civil aviation, border trade and science and
technology, Indian and Western diplomats said, speaking on condition
of anonymity. <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> also may agree to establish consular
offices.
   But no substantial progress is expected on the critical issue of
their 2,400-mile border, over which the two countries fought a brief
war in <DATE>1962</DATE>.
   The two countries began border talks in <DATE>1981</DATE> but have made little
progress. <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> claims 36,000 square miles of Indian territory.
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> rejects the claim and demands that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> return the 15,200
square miles it took in the <DATE>1962</DATE> war.
   Since then, relations have improved, but only slightly. The
border remains heavily guarded on both sides and bilateral trade,
which resumed in <DATE>1977</DATE> but amounted to only <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY> last year,
is limited.
   Both <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> say <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>'s visit is intended to create an
atmosphere for greater communication and not to resolve the border
question. But Western diplomats said pressures on Gandhi could make
him more willing to compromise than his Chinese counterparts.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> is moving quickly to improve relations with the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION> after nearly three decades of hostility. A summit between
Soviet President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON> and Chinese leader <PERSON>Deng
Xiaoping</PERSON> may be held next year.
   Better Chinese-Soviet relations will eliminate <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s need to
cultivate <LOCATION>New Dehli</LOCATION> as a foil against <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>. And by removing
tensions along its northern border, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> will be under less
pressure to accomodate <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> on its southern flank.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> continues its close relationship with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
traditional enemy. <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s new prime minister, <PERSON>Benazir Bhutto</PERSON>, is
expected to visit <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in <DATE>January</DATE> on her first official trip abroad.
   ``For <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>, the whole visit has an air of him running along so
he doesn't get left out in the cold,'' said a Western diplomat in
<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> who recently returned from <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>. ``For the Chinese, the
visit can't possibly go wrong.''
   A society that speaks with one voice when it comes to foreign
affairs, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has watched with apparent enjoyment as the Indian
press has pressured Gandhi to make progress on the border issue,
Western diplomats said.
   ``The prime minister has decided to stick yet another label to
his travel bags,'' wrote the normally pro-government Times of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>
in an editorial <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. ``The more important question, however,
is, what is the prime minister going to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> for?''
   Gandhi also faces an election next year in which victory is far
from certain. Diplomats say he must convince his public that simply
establishing goodwill with the Chinese _ and not achieving a
dramatic breakthrough _ is a worthy goal.
   ``If he feels that he is failing at that, he might be persuaded
to do something rash,'' the Western diplomat said.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> could use the <ORGANIZATION>Dalai Lama</ORGANIZATION>, the exiled Tibetan leader who has
taken refuge in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> since <DATE>1959</DATE>, to embarrass the Chinese. The
Tibetan refugees' parliament-in-exile on <DATE>Friday</DATE> called on <ORGANIZATION>Gandhi</ORGANIZATION> to
raise the issue of <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION> with Chinese leaders.
   But <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s hand is weakened by <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s apparent willingness to
crush dissent in <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>, regardless of international opinion. On <DATE>Dec.
10</DATE>, police shot and killed at least one monk in <LOCATION>Lhasa</LOCATION>, the capital
of <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>, during an anti-Chinese demonstration. In addition, <LOCATION>New
Delhi</LOCATION> also has backed <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s claims to the region.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> was one of the first non-socialist countries to recognize
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in the early <DATE>1950s</DATE>. Relations soured in the early <DATE>1960s</DATE> over
the border question and political disagreements.
   Relations improved slightly in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE>. <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> invited an
Indian leader to visit as early as <DATE>1979</DATE>, but <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> agreed to come
only in <DATE>November</DATE> of last year.
   Western diplomats say the timing of the acceptance was
significant because it came well after Sino-Soviet relations had
begun to improve.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881219-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-88 0628EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-Gandhi 1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0664</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-Gandhi, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0468,0686</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thorny Border Issue Dominates Talks</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS spelling of New Delhi in grafs 3,5</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN POMFRET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and Chinese
leaders spent most of their time together today discussing their
troubled border, the main issue dividing the world's most populous
nations, Indian journalists said.
   Gandhi also discussed <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION> and trade with his Chinese hosts.
   Gandhi and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s premier, <PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON>, met for two hours in the
morning following <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>'s arrival from <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>. They continued
meetings after lunch, said the journalists who attended a news
briefing closed to non-Indian reporters.
   Gandhi's five-day visit marks the first time an Indian leader has
come to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> since <DATE>1954</DATE>, when his grandfather <PERSON>Jawalharlal Nehru</PERSON>
came to <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>.
   The last time Chinese and Indian leaders met was in <DATE>1960</DATE>, when
Premier <PERSON>Chou Enlai</PERSON> went to <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>. Two years later, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> fought a war over the border and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> occupied a large chunk
of Indian territory.
   Gandhi flew into <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> accompanied by about 100 top officials
and the two nations were expected to sign agreements on civil
aviation, border trade and science and technology.
   Consular offices in <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> may also be established.
   Little progress was expected on the 2,400-mile border.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Xinhua News Agency</ORGANIZATION> and Indian journalists said <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> and
Li agreed that the two nations had to find a way of settling the
border question peacefully.
   ``We should work now toward resolution of the border issue while
we work at the same time to expand and strengthen our bilateral
relations,'' the journalists quoted <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> as saying.
   Li said the border problem was hindering the two countries'
relations, <ORGANIZATION>Xinhua</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   Xinhua also said <PERSON>Li</PERSON> expressed ``admiration'' for <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s position
on <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>, a Chinese province bordering <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has reiterated that <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION> is part of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and forbids
Tibetan refugees in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> from engaging in political activities. In
<DATE>1959</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Dalai Lama</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>'s leader, and thousands of Tibetan
refugees fled to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> after an abortive, anti-Chinese uprising.
   On <DATE>Dec. 10</DATE>, at least one monk was killed in the Tibetan capital
of <LOCATION>Lhasa</LOCATION> during a clash between Chinese troops and Tibetans who seek
an end to 38 years of Chinese rule. It was the third bloody clash in
<LOCATION>Lhasa</LOCATION> in 14 months.
   Earlier <DATE>Monday</DATE>, at the <PERSON>Great Hall</PERSON> of the People in downtown
<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> was given a 19-gun salute and met by Premier LI.
   Indian and Chinese flags lined <LOCATION>Tiananmen Square</LOCATION>, colored flags
lined the city's main boulevard, Changanjie.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> was one of the first non-socialist countries to recognize
Communist <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> soon after <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1949</DATE> revolution. In the early
<DATE>1960s</DATE>, relations deteriorated over the border question and personal
and political disagreements between Chinese leader <PERSON>Mao Tse-tung</PERSON> and
<ORGANIZATION>Prime Minister Nehru</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> now claims 36,000 square miles of Indian land. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>
rejects the claim and demands that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> return the 15,200 square
miles it took in the war.
   In the late <DATE>1970s</DATE>, relations improved slightly when <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> began
emphasizing traditional state-to-state relations instead of
exporting socialist revolution.
   Direct trade resumed in <DATE>1977</DATE> but it amounted to just <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY>
in <DATE>1986-87</DATE> with few prospects for growth.
   The two countries began border talks in <DATE>1981</DATE> but have made little
progress in eight rounds.
   Interviews with Chinese scholars over the weekend found them
pessimistic about the possibility for good Sino-Indian ties. For
one, they said, the economies of the two countries are too similar
to allow for much trade.
   ``They export textiles and we export textiles. They want high
technology and we want high technology,'' said <PERSON>Zhang Minqiu</PERSON>, deputy
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute of South and Southeast Asian Studies</ORGANIZATION> at
<ORGANIZATION>Beijing University</ORGANIZATION>. ``We're competitors so we lack cooperative
spirit.''
   In addition, Chinese researchers said the border question appears
intractable.
   ``In some of the areas that we claim, the Indian government has
made big investments and has registered good economic growth,'' said
<PERSON>Ms. Zhang</PERSON>. ``It's very hard to see them giving it up.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881221-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-88 0258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-Gandhi 1stLd-Writethru   12-21 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-Gandhi, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0454,0706</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gandhi Meets Deng, Agrees to Restore Friendly Ties</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS 10 grafs with Gandhi speech. Picks up graf 7 pvs,
`Chinese-Indian relations ...' CORRECTS population figure in last
graf.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN POMFRET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and Chinese
leader <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON> agreed today to restore friendly ties between
the world's most populous countries despite a long-standing border
dispute.
   ``Welcome, my young friend,'' the 84-year-old senior Chinese
leader said to <LOCATION>Gandhi</LOCATION>, 44, as the two leaders met in the <PERSON>Great Hall</PERSON>
of the People.
   ``Beginning with your visit we can restore our relationship as
friends,'' <PERSON>Deng</PERSON> said. ``The two countries' leaders will become
friends, the countries will become friends, the people will become
friends.''
   ``I agree and would like to thank you for your warm welcome,''
<PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> said.
   Deng said he knew <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>'s grandfather, <PERSON>Jawaharlal Nehru</PERSON>, who
came to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in <DATE>1954</DATE>, the last Indian prime minister to do so.
   ``In the considerable period of time in between, there was
unpleasantness with each other,'' <PERSON>Deng</PERSON> said. ``But let us forget it.
We should be looking forward.''
   Later at a speech at presitigious <ORGANIZATION>Qinghua University</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>
summed up the goal of his five-day trip.
   ``I have every hope that during this visit we will, together with
our Chinese friends, build a better political climate for the
solution of the border issue,'' he said.
   In the past, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has said it would only improve bilateral ties
once progress was made on the border.
   ``I am heartened that the Chinese leadership is more than
prepared to put behind us past rancor and past prejudices,'' <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>
said. ``I am heartened that we are both prepared not to be mired in
the past.''
   Chinese-Indian relations were good in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> but a boundary
dispute led the two countries into war in <DATE>1962</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> claims 36,000 square miles of Indian land. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> rejects
the claim and demands <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> return the 15,200 square miles it took
in the <DATE>1962</DATE> war.
   During <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>'s visit, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> are expected to sign
agreements on civil aviation, border trade and science and
technology. Consular offices in <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> may also be
established.
   Little progress is expected on the border.
   Gandhi arrived in <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> and spent most of the day
meeting with Premier <PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON>. His visit marked the first time Indian
and Chinese leaders have met since <DATE>1960</DATE>, when then-Premier <PERSON>Chou
Enlai</PERSON> went to <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>.
   Gandhi and Li discussed the border problem and <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> called for
a renewal of friendship between the two nations.
   ``It is now time to look beyond the past,'' <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> said at a
banquet <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. ``It is now time to look forward to the
future. It is now time to restore the relationship between our two
countries.''
   In the past, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has said it would only improve bilateral ties
once progress was made on the border.
   Gandhi also discussed <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>, trade and the Cambodian conflict
with his Chinese hosts in talks his official spokesman described as
``warm, cordial and very friendly.''
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> met with <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s president, <PERSON>Yang Shangkun</PERSON>, and
again talked about <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s troubled region of <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> said his country will not interfere in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s internal
affairs. The issue is sensitive because <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>'s spiritual leader,
the <ORGANIZATION>Dalai Lama</ORGANIZATION>, fled to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <DATE>1959</DATE> after an abortive,
anti-Chinese uprising.
   Gandhi was to meet tonight with <PERSON>Zhao Ziyang</PERSON>, general secretary of
the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>. On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, he is to fly to the
ancient city of <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION> and <DATE>Friday</DATE> he will go to <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> was one of the first non-socialist countries to recognize
Communist <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> soon after <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1949</DATE> revolution. In the early
<DATE>1960s</DATE>, relations deteriorated over the border question and political
disagreements.
   Relations began to improve in the late <DATE>1979s</DATE> but the border
remains heavily guarded. The two countries began border talks in
<DATE>1981</DATE> but have made little progress in eight rounds, the last of
which was held in <DATE>November 1987</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has more than 1 billion people. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, the world's largest
democracy, has a population of about 800 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-21427 </DOCNO>
<HT>      "jpnea015___94029" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-NEA-94-015 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Near East &amp; South Asia 

</HEADER>

<ABS> </ABS>
<DATE1>     4 February 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> INDIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Papers Report Rao Visit to Germany </TI></H3>
<H4>   3 Feb Activities, Talks </H4>
<F P=102> 94AS0223A Bombay THE TIMES OF INDIA in English 4 Feb 94 pp 
1, 13 </F>

<F P=103> 94AS0223A </F>
<F P=104>  Bombay THE TIMES OF INDIA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:CSO 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, <DATE>February 3</DATE>--The German Chancellor, <PERSON>Dr Helmut 
Kohl</PERSON>, today assured the Prime Minister, <PERSON>Mr P.V. Narasimha Rao</PERSON>, 
that his country would do everything in its power to boost 
industrial and technological co-operation with <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and 
announced that a high-level Indo-German commission on science 
and technology would be set up soon, report <ORGANIZATION>PTI</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>UNI</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Addressing the Indo-German economic conference along with <PERSON>Mr 
Rao</PERSON>, the German Chancellor said <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s economic development was 
on the "right course" and acknowledged that there was scope for 
further increasing German investments in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. 
  <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON>, declaring there was "absolutely no hesitation or 
dilution in the commitment to liberalisation," urged German 
industrialists to take "one more determined step" to increase 
the flow of investments, in view of the "ideal opportunity" 
provided by the reforms process in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. 
  The Prime Minister assured both Indian and German 
industrialists at the conference that he and Dr <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON> would solve 
"any problem, if it comes to our level." 
  The two leaders told the delegates that both <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> were aware of the vast and untapped potential for 
further deepening and strengthening bilateral economic relations. 
  The federal government and German industry were following 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s policy of reforms with close attention and sympathy and 
"modern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, with its reform-oriented economic policy aimed at 
liberalisation, is one of our most important partners on the 
Asian continent," the German leader told <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON>. 
  <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON> said further liberalisation to cover some more items 
was on the anvil. The items to be liberalised were those which 
one could think of, he said and added that he could not say a 
syllable more because the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> budget was only three weeks away. 
  <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON> welcomed the <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> offensive of the German 
industrialists who are increasingly turning towards the 
Asia-Pacific region for investments. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> have 
been identified as major thrust areas by the newly-launched 
<ORGANIZATION>Asia-Pacific Association</ORGANIZATION> (APA). 
  In his observations, the president of the <ORGANIZATION>Confederation of 
Indian Industry</ORGANIZATION> (CII), <PERSON>Mr Jamshed N. Godrej</PERSON>, announced the 
(the German federation of industry). 
  <PERSON>Mr Godrej</PERSON> said <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION> could enter into 
trilateral partnership to exploit the complimentaries and 
individual advantages in areas of skilled manpower, technology 
and industrial sophistication. 
  Meanwhile, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has told <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> that it would continue to 
adopt a neutral stance on the <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> issue and avoid making any 
value judgment in the matter. 
  The issue figured prominently during the talks <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON> had 
with German leaders, during which he voiced serious concern over 
the problems his country faced with regard to <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s aid to 
terrorists in the Indian border states of <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Punjab</LOCATION>. 
  The issue also figured during the foreign secretary-level 
talks where the Indian foreign secretary, <PERSON>Mr K. Srinivasan</PERSON>, 
briefed his German counterpart on the outcome of the recent 
foreign secretary level talks in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION> and the subsequent 
six proposals mooted by <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>." 
  <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> urged <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to sign the nuclear non-proliferation 
treaty (NPT), which <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> has refused to comply with, 
arguing that the existing global non-proliferation regimes were 
discriminatory against the developing countries. 
  The German Chancellor reiterated his strong commitment to 
nuclear non-proliferation which he has been consistently and 
resolutely pursuing at all international fora. 
  The German leader told <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON> that strengthening the 
existing 
global non-proliferation regimes must take "absolute priority" 
and reiterated his government's resolve for an indefinite 
unconditional extension of the <ORGANIZATION>NPT</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1995</DATE>. 
  The two countries have been engaged in a comprehensive 
dialogue on the issue of nuclear non-proliferation and other 
political matters of mutual concept at the foreign office-level 
talks for quite some time. The two sides have already held three 
rounds and the fourth round is due to commence shortly. 
  Three high-level ministerial delegations from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> will 
visit <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in the first half of the current year. 
  An official spokesman today said these high-level visits, 
which will follow <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON>'s current visit, were in line with 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s "new-look" <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> concept unfolded by the Chancellor, Dr 
<PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>. 
  The spokesman said the German development co-operation 
minister would visit <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> next month, followed by the visit of 
the German economic co-operation minister in <DATE>April</DATE>. 
  The German vice-chancellor and foreign affairs minister, <PERSON>Mr 
Klaus Kinkel</PERSON>, is expected to come in <DATE>May</DATE>. 
  The new German perception was that it had put too many eggs 
in the European basket. It now wanted to expand its influence in 
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> as well and had identified <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> for 
cementing ties, the spokesman said. 
  <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON>'s visit, his second to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> in less than three 
years, was extremely important because <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> had already 
declared <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> "a partner of choice in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>." <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> had also 
described its relationship with <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as a "strategic" one. 
  <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s number one and the world's third largest 
economy, till recently used to be the second largest investor in 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, after the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, but had gone down to the tenth 
position after <DATE>1990</DATE>. 
  However, trade volume between <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> had been 
growing steadily and touched nearly 5.5 billion <ORGANIZATION>Deutsche Mark</ORGANIZATION> 
(DM) in <DATE>1992</DATE>. It was anticipated to cross the DM <MONEY>6 billion mark</MONEY> 
in the current financial year. 
  Indian exports to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> have been getting more and more 
sophisticated and diversified. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06347276 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06347276 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; A Tibetan protesting Li's visit is carried away  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  CHINA; LEADER; TRIP; INDIA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Chinese Prime Minister Li Peng arrived in India on Wednesday for a six-day
visit aimed at improving relations between the world's two most populous
nations at a time when both are struggling to define their places in the
rapidly changing international order.;   Li's visit, the first by a Chinese
premier in 31 years, is being described by officials of both countries as an
important step in a continuing effort to thaw a relationship that has remained
chilly since the two countries fought a Himalayan border war in 1962. The
recent warming trend began when former Indian Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi
visited Beijing three years ago.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CHINESE PREMIER BEGINS INDIA VISIT
OFFICIALS SEEK CLOSER TIES AFTER YEARS OF DISTRUST  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     This week's talks are expected to produce agreements on bilateral
cooperation in space exploration and improved trade ties, including the
reopening of consulates in <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION>. But Indian and Chinese
officials say they do not expect any breakthroughs on the main border dispute
between the two countries, which involves unresolved claims to thousands of
square miles of largely uninhabited territory in the Himalayas.;   In
interviews published before <PERSON>Li</PERSON>'s arrival, both the Chinese premier and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
prime minister, <PERSON>P.V. Narasimha Rao</PERSON>, emphasized that their countries shared an
interest in asserting themselves internationally at a time when an ascendant
West is moving to shape the post-Cold War order.;   In an apparent gesture to
<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, Indian officials arrested about 20 Tibetan democracy advocates before
<PERSON>Li</PERSON>'s arrival and imposed tight security in the capital. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has for decades
provided safe haven to Tibetan exiles, including <LOCATION>Tibet</LOCATION>'s spiritual leader, the
<LOCATION>Dalai Llama</LOCATION>, but had never arrested activists. A number of Tibetan protesters
demonstrated in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> but were unable to get near the
visiting premier.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Washington Post  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New Delhi, India  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911212  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  22A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  292  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, December 12, 1991
00347276,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-21430 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpnea015___94032" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-NEA-94-015 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Near East &amp; South Asia 

</HEADER>

<ABS> </ABS>
<DATE1>     5 February 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> INDIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Papers Report Rao Visit to Germany </TI></H3>
<H4>   More on Memo, 4 Feb Activities </H4>
<F P=102> 94AS0223D Madras THE HINDU in English 5 Feb 94 p 1 </F>
<F P=103> 94AS0223D </F>
<F P=104>  Madras THE HINDU </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:<ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>Alok Mukherjee</PERSON>: "<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, A Priority Area for </F>
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>"] 
  [Text] <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 4</DATE>--The Prime Minister, <PERSON>Mr. P.V. 
Narasimha Rao</PERSON>, today began the last leg of his <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> visit. 
Flying into <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> in a German Government plane, the 
Prime Minister's major programme for the day was a meeting with 
the German President, <PERSON>Mr. Richard von Weizsacker</PERSON>. <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON> also 
had a luncheon meeting with eminent Indologists here, when a 
number of issues to facilitate studies on <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> were brought to 
the notice of the Prime Minister. 
  With <PERSON>Mr. Weizsacker</PERSON>, the discussions were general in nature, 
it being basically a courtesy call. The German President is well 
acquainted with <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, having been there in <DATE>1991</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr. Weizsacker</PERSON> 
was in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> at the height of its political crisis when the 
minority <PERSON>Chandra Shekar</PERSON> Government was in power and its 
continuance in office was under doubt. This aspect was 
highlighted by the German authorities on many occasions as a 
measure of their commitment to maintain high political relations 
with <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, irrespective of the <ORGANIZATION>Government</ORGANIZATION> in power. 
  In fact, the importance that <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> attaches to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has 
been confirmed to the Prime Minister not only by the present 
Government in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, but by the host of Opposition leaders as 
well, who called on <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> during his two-day stay in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. 
<H5>  `<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> policy' </H5>
  The leaders of the coalition parties in the present 
Government, as well as those from other political parties, have 
also told <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> that the new "<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> policy" of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> had a 
national consensus and would be pursued by any Government that 
comes to power after the federal elections in <DATE>October</DATE> this year. 
The "<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> policy" of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> focuses on the entire Asian region 
as the priority area for trade and economic concentration as 
well as for high political contacts. Almost all the countries of 
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> have been included in the priority list, including <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, but three countries have been identified for 
intensive co-operation--<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. 
  Parallel meetings conducted by the members of the <ORGANIZATION>Prime 
Ministerial</ORGANIZATION> delegation had also indicated that the <ORGANIZATION>German 
Government</ORGANIZATION> has sent out the signal to its industrialists that 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is now a priority area for investment and that 
concentration should begin. The process has been facilitated by 
the fact that just a few days before <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON>'s visit, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Government of India</ORGANIZATION> relied to a detailed memorandum that was 
submitted by the German Chancellor, <PERSON>Mr. Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, after his 
return from <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <DATE>February last year</DATE>. This memorandum listed 
out the various irritants that were obstructing German 
investment in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and the response of the Government of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> 
had been sought to the points raised. 
  The proposals submitted by the Germans were broadly divided 
into six categories covering the financial sector, the 
pharmaceutical and chemical industry, the power sector, 
telecommunications, air traffic and general issues. The Indian 
response too has been fairly detailed with areas listed out 
where decisions have already been taken. The pending areas 
include liberalisation of the pharmaceutical and chemical 
industry, removal of phased manufacturing programme obligations 
for units established prior to the new industrial policy, 
increase in the prescribed payment limits for automatic 
approvals of technical collaborations, amendments to the 
Industrial Disputes Act and removal of the condition that 
foreign equity should cover the foreign exchange requirement for 
import of capital goods under the automatic approval category. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Government</ORGANIZATION> has also indicated that it is not in a 
position to agree to the suggestion for a negative list of 
imports, an uniform industrial policy in all the States, 
abolition of octroi and automatic adoption of environmental 
standards prescribed in advanced countries. 
<H5>  Joint Ventures </H5>
  Individual interactions between the Prime Minister and chief 
executive officesr of multinational corporations too have 
confirmed that German industry was now positive about investment 
in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. For instance, the representative of <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes Benz</ORGANIZATION> said 
that a passenger car project was being finalised with the <ORGANIZATION>Tata</ORGANIZATION> 
group which would make the project one of the major investments 
by <ORGANIZATION>Benz</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Similarly, the <ORGANIZATION>Siemens</ORGANIZATION> group will be setting 
up two power projects in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>--one at Jayamkondan with a 
capacity of 1,500 MW [megawatts] and another at <LOCATION>Gandhar</LOCATION> of 600 
MW capacity. Another multinational, <ORGANIZATION>BASF</ORGANIZATION> is setting up a 
chemicals factory in <LOCATION>Mangalore</LOCATION> for the manufacture of dyestuff. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-33722 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes020_r_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-020 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  31 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> India </F>
<H3> <TI>   Prime Minister Rao Leaves for Switzerland, Germany </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK3101104994 Delhi All India Radio Network in English 0930 
GMT 31 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK3101104994 </F>
<F P=104>  Delhi All India Radio Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The prime minister left <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> <TIME>this afternoon</TIME> on 
a six-day visit to <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. He was seen off at 
the airport by cabinet colleagues and senior officials. <PERSON>Mr. 
Narasimha Rao</PERSON> has been invited by the <ORGANIZATION>World Economic Forum</ORGANIZATION> to 
address the closing plenary of the symposium at <LOCATION>Davos</LOCATION> tomorrow. 
The prime minister is expected to apprise the world business 
community of the liberalization process in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. The theme for 
this year's <LOCATION>Davos</LOCATION> meet is redefining the basic assumptions of 
the world economy. The meeting of the forum, which began on 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, is being attended by more than 20 heads of government 
and state. In all 800 company chief executives and 150 
government representatives are attending the deliberations. 
  From <LOCATION>Davos</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Rao</PERSON> will go on to <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> on the 
second leg of his visit. He will hold talks with the German 
chancellor, <PERSON>Dr. Helmut Kohl</PERSON>. Both the leaders will address the 
Indo-German Business Conference. The prime minister will later 
go to <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> where he will meet the German president. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-21385 </DOCNO>
<HT>      "jpnea014___94028" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-NEA-94-014 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Near East &amp; South Asia 

</HEADER>

<ABS> </ABS>
<DATE1>     8 February 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> INDIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Results of Rao Visit to Germany Told </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  94AS0197O Hyderabad DECCAN CHRONICLE in English 8 Feb 94 p 12 </F>
<F P=103> 94AS0197O </F>
<F P=104>  Hyderabad DECCAN CHRONICLE </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:CSO 

  [Text] <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 7</DATE>--<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has responded favourably 
to the Indian request for greater access to German technology 
and to its middle-level industry for partnership. 
  The Germans have also reassured the Prime Minister, <PERSON>Mr P.V. 
Narasimha Rao</PERSON>, during his just-concluded visit to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> of 
clear political support for German programmes aimed at expanding 
Indo-German economic cooperation. The German Chancellor, <PERSON>Dr 
Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, has conveyed his intention to nominate one of his 
ministerial-level colleagues to monitor the progress of economic 
cooperation and to remove obstacles, if any, in the process. 
  Both the countries have also agreed to synchronise their 
efforts for further democratisation of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, to 
reflect the existing ground realities, including expansion of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Security Council</ORGANIZATION> by increasing the number of permanent 
members with veto. Both <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> are keen for a place 
in the extended <ORGANIZATION>Security Council</ORGANIZATION> with veto power. 
  In the next few months three high-level delegations from 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, each headed by a minister such as the Minister for 
Development, Minister for Economic Cooperation and Foreign 
Minister are slated to visit <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to provide fresh impetus to 
growing Indo-German cooperation in various fields. 
  According to official sources in the <ORGANIZATION>External Affairs 
Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, in the context of German view of playing an important 
role in world affairs, <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> has formulated a priority programme, 
"<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> concept policy," for opening itself up towards "high 
growth" Asian countries like <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. The market 
in <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> was not considered to be sufficient to meet 
the growing German capabilities in fields like science, 
technology, economic, investment abroad. 
  These sources are quite optimistic that in the near future 
large-scale German investments could be expected in various 
spheres of cooperative economic interaction for mutual benefit 
and advantage, though it is "very difficult to quantify" the 
outcome of the visit so early. 
  However, <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON> himself said that he was satisfied with the 
outcome of his German visit. 
  These sources further pointed out that the reception the 
Prime Minister received in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> was much warmer and greater 
than the one he received during his first visit in <DATE>September 
1991</DATE>. 
  These sources asserted that during the Prime Minister's 
talks 
with German leaders at no point the issue of nuclear 
non-proliferation treaty (NPT) figured. Thus a report circulated 
by some news agency to say that the issue figured during the 
talks was totally baseless. The sources further stated that the 
German official sources also denied having given any such 
briefing at all. 


</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-38469 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu023_h_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-023 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> GERMANY </F>
<H3> <TI>   Bonn Assures `Neutrality' on Kashmir </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0302070794 Delhi All India Radio Network in English 0630 
GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0302070794 </F>
<F P=104>  Delhi All India Radio Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has assured <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> that it will continue to 
adopt a neutral stance on <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and avoid making any value 
judgments in the matter. Kashmir figured prominently during the 
talks the prime minister, <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON>, had with the German 
leaders in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. The prime minister explained to them the 
problems faced by <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> due to <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s abetment of terrorism 
in <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Punjab</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Narasimha Rao</PERSON> also 
apprised the German leaders of the serious threat posed to the 
country's unity and integrity from cross-border terrorism. The 
prime minister said <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> is deliberately creating conditions 
for not having a meaningful dialogue. He also informed them 
about the confidence-building measures his government had taken 
in the past toward good neighborly relations with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>. 
  The issue also figured prominently during the foreign 
secretary-level talks in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. The Indian side told the Germans 
about the setting up of the commission to look into the 
allegations of human rights abuses and permission given to the 
Amnesty International to visit the country. Attention was also 
drawn to the threat by <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> to move an anti-India resolution 
at the <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> session on human rights. <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> sought 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s help to thwart the attempt. Bonn assured that the 
anti-Indian motion on <ORGANIZATION>Kashmir</ORGANIZATION> will not serve any useful purpose. 
Both countries also called for wider representation in the <ORGANIZATION>UN 
Security Council</ORGANIZATION> to ensure the political effectiveness of the 
collective will of international community. Both <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> are aspirants of a permanent seat in the council. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881222-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-88 1033EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-India     12-22 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-India,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>India, China Agree To Set Up Group To Discuss Border Dispute</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> have agreed to establish a group
to take up their thorny border dispute following discussions with
visiting Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>
announced today.
   Ministry spokesman <PERSON>Li Zhaoxing</PERSON>, speaking at the end of <ORGANIZATION>Gandhi</ORGANIZATION>'s
visit to the Chinese capital, also said good will fostered by the
trip could lead to a solution to the border issue ``in the near
future.''
   Gandhi, the first Indian head of government to visit <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> since
his grandfather <PERSON>Jawaharlal Nehru</PERSON> in <DATE>1954</DATE>, left <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> for the
ancient capital of <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION> <TIME>this afternoon</TIME> following three days of talks
with <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s top leaders.
   Both sides declared the visit a triumph and declared that the
boundary question should not stand in the way of a new course of
expanded ties that will end the two countries' decades-long cold war.
   The border dispute, which exploded into a short war in <DATE>1962</DATE> and
since has poisoned relations between the world's two most populous
nations, was the most pressing topic in <LOCATION>Gandhi</LOCATION>'s talks with Premier
<PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON> and other senior leaders.
   Spokesman Li, speaking at a news conference, said:
   ``Thanks to the visit, the Sino-Indian history of relations now
ushers in a new period. Leaders of the two countries conducted
sincere and in-depth discussions on the border question between
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, which are conducive to reaching a solution on the
boundary question in the near future.''
   He declined comment on the makeup of the working group, but
Indian sources said it will be at the vice foreign minister-level
and will be like a joint commission.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> have held eight rounds of talks in the past seven
years on the border, but there has been no formal structure to the
meetings, which have achieved little or no progress.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> claims 36,000 square miles of mountainous frontier in what
<LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> says is northeast <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s Arunachal Pradesh province.
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> says <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> illegally occupies 14,500 square miles on its
western border.
   Gandhi and the Chinese apparently did not try to negotiate the
boundary question. ``The border issue is very complicated,'' <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>
said at a <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> news conference. ``We can't expect instant
solutions.''
   The symbolic restoration of friendly ties dominated the <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>
trip, although the two sides added some substance today by signing a
civil aviation agreement calling for direct flights between <LOCATION>New
Delhi</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> and two other accords.
   The two sides also signed a three-year cultural exchange
agreement and a science and technology accord promoting contacts
between their scientific communities.
   Gandhi also is to tour <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION> before returning to <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Friday</DATE>. The two sides are to issue a joint communique when he
departs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881222-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-88 1410EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Gandhi     12-22 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Gandhi,0504</SECOND>
<HEAD>India, China To Discuss Border Dispute</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that it and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> will
establish a group to tackle a border dispute that flared into a
brief war in <DATE>1962</DATE> and has poisoned relations between the world's
most populous nations ever since.
   The agreement was announced at the end of Indian Prime Minister
<PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON>'s historic visit to the Chinese capital. Foreign
Ministry spokesman <PERSON>Li Zhaoxing</PERSON> also said good will fostered by the
<PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> visit could lead to a solution to the border issue ``in the
near future.''
   Gandhi, the first Indian head of government to visit <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> since
his grandfather <PERSON>Jawaharlal Nehru</PERSON> in <DATE>1954</DATE>, left <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> for the
ancient capital of <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> following three days of talks
with Chinese leaders.
   Both sides declared the visit a triumph, and declared the
boundary question should not stand in the way of a new course of
expanded ties that will end the two countries' decades-long cold war.
   The border dispute exploded into a short war 26 years ago and has
since kept the nations apart. It was the most pressing topic in
<LOCATION>Gandhi</LOCATION>'s talks with Premier <PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON> and other senior leaders.
   <PERSON>Li Zhaoxing</PERSON>, speaking at a news conference, said, ``thanks to the
visit the Sino-Indian history of relations now ushers in a new
period. Leaders of the two countries conducted sincere and in-depth
discussions on the border question between <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, which
are conducive to reaching a solution on the boundary question in the
near future.''
   He said the two sides ``agreed to establish a joint working
group, which is specially devoted to the boundary question.''
   He declined comment on the makeup of the working group, but
Indian sources said it will be at the vice foreign minister level.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> have held eight rounds of talks since <DATE>1981</DATE> on the
border issue, but there has been no formal structure to the
meetings, which have achieved little progress.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> claims 36,000 square miles of mountainous frontier in what
<LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> says is northeast <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s Arunachal Pradesh province.
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> says <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> illegally occupies 14,500 square miles on its
western border.
   Gandhi and the Chinese apparently did not try to negotiate the
boundary question. ``The border issue is very complicated,'' <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>
said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. ``We can't expect instant solutions.''
   Gandhi's trip to <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> brings a new era of detente to
Sino-Indian relations that is likely to be followed next year by a
visit by Soviet President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>. The <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> visit
will formally end 30 years of political strain and distrust between
the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>.
   The symbolic restoration of ties dominated the <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> trip,
although the two sides added some substance <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by signing a
civil aviation agreement calling for flights between <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> and accords for cultural and technological exchanges.
   Gandhi also is to tour <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION> before returning to <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Friday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-38549 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu024__a94025" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-024-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Germany </F>
<H3> <TI>   Indian Prime Minister Arrives for 4-Day Visit </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU0202172394 Hamburg DPA in German 1211 GMT 2 Feb 94--FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0202172394 </F>
<F P=104>  Hamburg DPA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> German </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpt] <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> (DPA) -- On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [2 <DATE>January</DATE>] <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 
head of government, <PERSON>P.V. Narisimha Rao</PERSON>, arrived in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> for a 
four-day visit to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and for talks on expanding relations. 
Rao is returning a visit by Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, who visited 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> last <DATE>February</DATE> and thus introduced a new stage of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s 
policy toward <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. 
  A few hours after his arrival <PERSON>Rao</PERSON>, who will meet with Kohl, 
Foreign Minister <PERSON>Klaus Kinkel</PERSON> (Free Democratic Party of 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>), as well as high-ranking representatives of German 
industry and the leaders of the coalition parties this <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, 
had an appointment with Development Aid Minister <PERSON>Carl-Dieter 
Spranger</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Christian Social Union</ORGANIZATION>). The minister will go to 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> on 10 <DATE>February</DATE> to take a look at the projects of 
German-Indian cooperation in situ. On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Fraunhofer 
Society</ORGANIZATION> for the <ORGANIZATION>Promotion of Applied Research</ORGANIZATION> and the "Council 
of Scientific and Industrial Research" signed an agreement on 
cooperation in the fields of, among others, microelectronics and 
environmental research. 
which has 900 million inhabitants, and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> will be the focus 
of all of <PERSON>Rao</PERSON>'s meetings in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>. On <DATE>Friday</DATE> 
President <PERSON>Richard von Weizsaecker</PERSON> will receive Rao in <LOCATION>Bellevue 
Palace</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>
