<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881219-0209 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-88 1339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-APN--Madagascar'sEcology ADV01-2Takes   12-19 0731</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Madagascar's Ecology, ADV 01-2 Takes,0752</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv01</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Jan. 1</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 2 b&amp;w
photos. ColorFoto subscribers get 2 35mm slides.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ The island of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> split from the African
mainland more than 150 million years ago and went on its own
evolutionary course. But the island's many animals and plants which
are found no place else in the world are now threatened with
extinction by the encroachment of man. As smoke continues to rise
from the dwindling forests, environmental groups are digging in to
do battle.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ The island of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> split from the African
mainland more than 150 million years ago and went on its own
evolutionary course. But the island's many animals and plants which
are found no place else in the world are now threatened with
extinction by the encroachment of man. As smoke continues to rise
from the dwindling forests, environmental groups are digging in to
do battle.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT WELLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PERINET, Madagascar (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ The island of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> split from the African
mainland more than 150 million years ago and went on its own
evolutionary course. But the island's many animals and plants which
are found no place else in the world are now threatened with
extinction by the encroachment of man. As smoke continues to rise
from the dwindling forests, environmental groups are digging in to
do battle.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010889-0078 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 2761 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 8, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 2; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1098 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MANKIND POSES GRAVE THREAT TO MADAGASCAR'S UNIQUE FLORA AND FAUNA 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ROBERT WELLER, Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
PERINET, Madagascar 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
This island off the East African coast is to today's naturalists what the 
<LOCATION>Galapagos Islands</LOCATION> off <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> were to <PERSON>Charles Darwin</PERSON>, a study in 
evolution. 
</P>
<P>
But the island's unique and diverse plant and animal life is under grave threat 
as man continues to torch the forest to clear the land in what one newspaper 
calls a kind of "national pyromania." 
</P>
<P>
As a result, heading off the destruction of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s fragile habitat has 
become the premier goal of many international environmental groups. 
</P>
<P>
After <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> split from the African mainland more than 150 million years 
ago, its plants and animals went on their own evolutionary course. 
</P>
<P>
Some became extinct, like the pygmy hippopotamus, elephant bird and giant 
lemurs. 
</P>
<P>
"There was a tremendous explosion of different forms from very, very few 
ancestors," said <PERSON>Dr. Martin Nicoll</PERSON>, a zoologist who represents the World 
Wildlife Fund here. "<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> lets you look at the limits of adaptability. 
</P>
<P>
"You can make really nice biological comparisons. What do plants have to do, 
for example, to live in a desert?" 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s terrain ranges from rain forests to prairie to desert. 
</P>
<P>
Ninety percent of the plant and animal species on the 226,658-square mile 
island are found nowhere else: from the lovable lemurs to hundreds of species 
of orchids and more than 350 species of amphibians and reptiles. 
</P>
<P>
There are 29 species of lemurs, primates whose name comes from the Latin word 
for ghosts because of their largely nocturnal habits. The closest living 
descendants of the common ancestor of humans, monkeys and apes, lemurs were 
displaced by monkeys elsewhere in the world. Here they had a chance to survive 
in isolation. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s equivalent of the woodpecker is a lemur called an aye-aye. It 
detects insect larvae moving in decaying trees with its sharp ears and then 
uses a skinny middle finger to reach in and pull them out. 
</P>
<P>
The largest lemur is the indri, a black-and-white creature that weighs about 15 
pounds at adulthood and can leap 20 feet from treetop to treetop. 
</P>
<P>
The indris, whose haunting calls are reminiscent of sounds emitted by great 
whales, are the main attraction for the small but growing number of tourists 
who visit this small reserve about 60 miles east of the capital of 
<LOCATION>Antananarivo</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
A short walk through a rain forest, led by a guide, inevitably turns up a 
family of the indris, staring down with their Teddy bear-like faces, bemused 
but not much interested in their visitors. 
</P>
<P>
The humans, whose slash-and-burn agricultural methods now threaten wildlife and 
the nation's watershed, are late arrivals, coming from <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Malay 
Archipelago</LOCATION> only 1,500 years ago. Fourteen species of lemurs have become 
extinct since humans arrived, and ecologists fear that others are in danger of 
joining them. 
</P>
<P>
The island's population has more than doubled since <DATE>1950</DATE>, and now exceeds 11 
million. Farmers are so desperate for land they are felling trees on 70-degree 
slopes. Four-fifths of the island's land is barren, and its forests have been 
reduced by half in the <DATE>last three decades</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The government's agriculture department long encouraged farmers to cut trees 
and burn the stumps to clear the ground for cash crops. The savanna is burned 
to produce tender shoots for an estimated 10 million zebu cattle. 
</P>
<P>
"In the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and in the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>, not far from the capital, the fires continue to 
burn," said <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Ambassador <PERSON>Patricia Gates Lynch</PERSON>. "Sometimes you see the smoke 
trapped right here in the city." 
</P>
<P>
The government and environmental organizations are working together now to 
discourage slash-and-burn land clearing, though the education process is slow. 
</P>
<P>
"It's primarily a human problem," Prime Minister <PERSON>Victor Ramahatra</PERSON> said. "We 
must teach people that the natural environment is their principal source of 
wealth." 
</P>
<P>
The government has shifted course from the policies adopted in a <DATE>1975</DATE> socialist 
revolution and now follows the advice of Western donors on economic policy. But 
a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> economic report says no economic reforms will work in the long 
run "without corrective action against <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s single greatest 
self-inflicted problem: the destruction of its environment." 
</P>
<P>
The government also has broken out of the virtual self-imposed isolation since 
President <PERSON>Didier Ratsiraka</PERSON> came to power in <DATE>1975</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Nicoll</PERSON> says the government has cooperated with environmental groups since the 
end of <DATE>1985</DATE>. "It is our No. 1 conservation priority," he said. 
</P>
<P>
A recent issue of the daily newspaper <PERSON>Midi</PERSON> said an average of 3.7 million acres 
of land was being burned each year. Midi, an independent journal, likened the 
burning to "national pyromania." 
</P>
<P>
Some peasants reportedly continue to burn the land to show their displeasure 
with the steady decline in the nation's economy since the revolution. Per 
capita income declined <PERCENT>24%</PERCENT> between <DATE>1979</DATE> and <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Destructive Erosion 
</P>
<P>
The denuded hillsides are no match for heavy rains and occasional cyclones. 
Great holes are carved in the landscape by erosion. The Indian Ocean north of 
the island is red from the red clay soil washed out to sea. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> is organizing an international effort to halt the degradation, 
which it estimates will cost from <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> over the <DATE>next 15</DATE> 
to 20 years. 
</P>
<P>
Already 11 major projects aided by Western environmental groups, universities 
and governments are under way. They include efforts to save existing reserves 
and plans to create new reserves or national parks. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Nicoll</PERSON>, whose <ORGANIZATION>WWF</ORGANIZATION> is managing projects covering 10 reserves, said efforts have 
to take into consideration the needs of the people who live nearby. 
</P>
<P>
"The people don't want to cut down the forest just because it's there," said 
<ORGANIZATION>Yale University</ORGANIZATION> anthropologist <PERSON>Eleanor Sterling</PERSON>, who is studying the aye-aye. 
"They truly need the wood for firewood or for land for agriculture. Many of 
them understand the problems in the environment and would like to do something 
to help, but they have to feed their children." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
People Accept Change 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Nicoll</PERSON> says the success of the Perinet reserve proves people can be persuaded 
to change. 
</P>
<P>
"I was there in <DATE>1985</DATE>, during my first long-term stay in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>," he said. 
"When you'd go into the reserve you'd meet people walking along with an ax. 
Just about every day you'd hear the chop, chop of an ax. You never hear that 
now. Tourism has done that. Tourism has put that place into a sort of protected 
status. Nobody would dare go in there now with an ax." 
</P>
<P>
Western organizations are pushing tourism, which up to now only brings a few 
thousand people to the island, many of them bird watchers or naturalists. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, A large chameleon perches on limb in forest in Madasgascar, an island 
off East Africa where nature has taken its own course. Associated Press; Photo, 
Cattle represent wealth for the peasants of Madagascar. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA073089-0110 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 88692 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 30, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 26; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
630 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FUTURE BLEAK FOR MADAGASCAR'S LEMURS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARTIN BAUMGAERTNER, Deutsche Presse-Agentur 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
TANANARIVE, Madagascar 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The first rays of sunlight pierce the swatches of mist above the leafy green 
roof of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s eastern rain forests. 
</P>
<P>
The cacophony of twittering birds mingles with a penetrating howling that 
appears to come from the lush treetops in the distance. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Maurice</PERSON>, the 24-year-old son of the local gamekeeper, recognizes the odd call 
immediately. "Those are the indris, the largest woolly lemurs on the island," 
he explains. 
</P>
<P>
Suddenly, a family of four indris answers a call from another group of the 
species about a mile and a half away. The indris, known by the natives as 
babakoto or amboanala, have the loudest call of the lemur family. 
</P>
<P>
"There are mating calls or hedging-off cries designed to show whose territory 
it is," said <PERSON>Maurice</PERSON>, who compared the lemur utterances to the jungle calls of 
Asiatic gibbons. 
</P>
<P>
The gray and black indri, with its long hind legs, short tail and doglike head, 
measures about 2 feet long and belongs to a family of prosimians found only on 
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> and the neighboring <LOCATION>Comoro Island</LOCATION> to the northwest. 
</P>
<P>
The future for the indris looks bleak. People here are gradually destroying the 
lemurs' natural habitat by chopping down the trees on whose leaves the 
creatures feed. 
</P>
<P>
In spite of a ban, the local population is chopping down the rain forest to 
provide grazing land for their herds of Zebu African cattle. 
</P>
<P>
The percentage of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s 342,000 square miles given over to the rain 
forest has declined from 72,000 square miles (<PERCENT>21%</PERCENT>) in the last century to 
41,000 square miles or <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> now. 
</P>
<P>
As the branches vanish, so do many unique species that are only to be found on 
the island. Here <PERCENT>86%</PERCENT> of flowering plants, <PERCENT>65%</PERCENT> of birds and <PERCENT>99%</PERCENT> of reptiles are 
native to the island. 
</P>
<P>
The forefathers of the indri probably drifted from mainland <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> to the 
world's fourth-largest island on natural craft made of driftwood more than 40 
million years ago. 
</P>
<P>
The lemurs had the place largely to themselves, since only a few other mammals 
managed to make the journey. 
</P>
<P>
There are currently 30 types of woolly lemur on <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>. An estimated 12 
species are thought to have died out since human beings began settling the 
island 1,500 years ago, including two lemur species whose representatives 
weighed up to 200 pounds each. 
</P>
<P>
Survivors are the dwarf lemurs such as the mausmaki, or the bizarre-looking 
aye-aye, which uses its bony middle finger to pry insect larvae from tree bark. 
</P>
<P>
The indri remains the most impressive of the lemurs. Its bushy ears, cut-off 
tail and howling cry have earned it an important place in Madagascan folklore. 
</P>
<P>
Maurice tells the story: A young man called Koto who climbed a tree in order to 
collect honey was attacked by a swarm of bees and could not get away. 
</P>
<P>
An indri came along and carried the youngster on his back to a safe forest 
clearing. Since then, the natives have dubbed the lemurs babakoto, or father of 
<ORGANIZATION>Koto</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Frenchman <PERSON>Pierre Sonnerat</PERSON> chose the scientific name indri after discovering the 
creatures at the end of the <ORGANIZATION>18th Century</ORGANIZATION>. He was the first European to set eyes 
on them but made the mistake of christening his find after the words used by a 
local guide, meaning simply, "There he is." 
</P>
<P>
Not a great deal is known about the indri, whose feeding habits have not been 
researched by zoologists. No zoo has succeeded in keeping an indri in 
captivity. 
</P>
<P>
Eight indris were taken to the Jardin de Plantes in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>1939</DATE>, but all of 
them died within a month, and not even the zoo here in the Madagascan capital 
has been able to keep an Indri alive and well behind bars. 
</P>
<P>
The indri's life style still puzzles animal behaviorists, who know for sure 
only that the female of the species assumes the leading role in the family 
groups of two to eight animals. Such female dominance is seldom found among 
primates. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910117-0078
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910117-0078.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- The Mobile Guide:
   Leeches, Lemurs and Very Long Names
   ----
   By Roger Thurow
</HL>
<DATE>
01/17/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A9
</SO>
<CO>
   AFRIC
</CO>
<LP>
   Antananarivo, Madagascar -- In four years of African
travels, I have seen some pretty weird things.
   In Zanzibar, I stared down at the ruins of the would-be
World's Largest Swimming Pool, which surely would have
received that distinction if it hadn't been built on a swamp.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, at the height of the great light-bulb
shortage, I checked into the <ORGANIZATION>Dom Carlos Hotel</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> and
was handed one 60-watt bulb. The idea, the desk clerk
demonstrated, was to move the bulb from one light fixture to
another while stumbling around the room in the dark. "Enjoy
your stay," he said.
   In <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>, a group of boys waving sticks ambushed our car.
They were hawking mousekebabs: whole mice, skewered on a
stick, lightly grilled. My wife took one horrified look and
rolled up the windows as we sped off. That <DATE>December</DATE>, an
American friend in <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION> sent us a picture of the young
vendors with their wares. "Merry Crispmouse," he wrote.
   In <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, you get used to weird.
   Then I went to <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>.
   On the world's fourth largest island, I saw a three-foot
long earthworm, a gigantic moth yellower than the sun, and
several species of lemurs. I met a man whose name was one
letter shorter than the entire alphabet. I sat in a traffic
jam while a funeral procession crossed the road, not to bury
someone but to raise him, turn his bones, give him a clean
shroud, show him what's new in town and put him back in the
ground. I also donated blood to a legion of rain-forest
leeches.
   Perhaps <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> is the weirdest normal country I have
visited (the "normal" qualifier eliminates <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> under
<PERSON>Ceausescu</PERSON> and <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> under apartheid) because it broke
away from <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> some 160 million years ago and drifted out
into the Indian Ocean to become weird all on its own. Most of
the animals, insects and plants on the island are found
nowhere else in the world. Most notable are the lemurs,
primates that never evolved like the rest of us. Generally,
they are furry and cute with big eyes and long tails. But
one, the aye-aye, is hairy and ugly with big ears and long,
boney fingers: the Grim Reaper in lemur's clothing.
   The Malagasy, an exotic mix of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,
are an equally unusual species. They give each other
humongous names. Their lives are governed by a series of
fady, or taboos, and the mystical powers of dead relatives.
They eat more rice per capita than the Chinese. They are very
friendly.
   Our first night in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, my wife, <PERSON>Anne</PERSON>, and I had
just finished dinner when the wine steward offered cigars. He
opened the fine wooden box and there, amid the stogies, were
a couple of large carrots. I said I'd take a carrot if he
could show me which end to light. He shook his head and said,
"No, monsieur, zee carrots are for zee humidity." C'est la
vie.
   The next morning I interviewed one of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s most
successful businessmen and possessor of the longest
unhyphenated name I have ever had the pleasure of foisting on
my editors. Charles Andriantsitohaina: 25 characters in all
(including the space), marching majestically across his
crowded business card. The last name, with 17 letters, is
just one short of the legal limit for racehorse names.
(Thoroughbred names are to be no longer than 18 characters,
including spaces, which explains why so many horses have
names that run together, like <LOCATION>Itsallgreektome</LOCATION>.) <PERSON>Mr.
Andriantsitohaina</PERSON> (pronounced Andrian-su-TWINE, or something
like that) modestly said his name was short by Malagasy
standards.
   I then became obsessed with finding a longer one, counting
letters of everyone I interviewed. While waiting 30 minutes
for a call to come through in the post office of a small
village, I feverishly checked all the pages of the phone book
for <LOCATION>Antananarivo</LOCATION>, the capital, which the locals mercifully
call Tana. There were some marvelous specimens.
Ravonitsoamaholizanany, first name Lalao.
Andrianaivoravelona, Andrianavalona. But it was while touring
the old royal palace that we found a name truly worth
mounting and hanging above the fireplace: King
Andrianampoinimerinandriantsimitoviaminandriampanjaka. His
subjects, the tour guide explained, called him plain old
Andrianampoinimerina.
   A Malagasy journalist named <PERSON>Olivier Ramahatra</PERSON>, who kept
calling me "ThurowRoger," explained that <PERSON>Andrian</PERSON> and Ra, the
two most-common prefixes, are noble salutations. Intimidating
as they may be, the names give <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> its hospitable
flavor. Strangers quickly advance to first-name footing.
Charles was <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> from the moment I first mangled
Andriantsitohaina. After a few days in <LOCATION>Tana</LOCATION> observing the
world's current No. 1 tourist attraction, the ruins of
Marxism, we headed to the rain forest in search of lemurs. On
the way, <PERSON>Anne</PERSON> studied the "Guide to <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>," a must for
tourists, to make sure we didn't violate any local fady. "In
Imerina," she read, "it is fady to hand an egg directly to
another person -- it must first be put on the ground." The
book didn't say if this meant all eggs, including scrambled
and fried. Better to stick to cereal for breakfast, we
figured, than to risk an international incident.
   The eight-hour drive south from <LOCATION>Tana</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>Ranomafana
National Forest</ORGANIZATION> is an ecological heartbreaker. Along the way,
smoke curls up from charred tree stumps, the haunting legacy
of the peasants' slash-and-burn agriculture, which has made
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> the most eroded place on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Just outside the
small village of <LOCATION>Ranomafana</LOCATION>, however, the smoke stops and the
road follows the descent of a spectacular waterfall. Here,
<ORGANIZATION>Duke University</ORGANIZATION> is coordinating a unique
conservation-development project that aims to save both lemur
and man from man's destruction.
   Our lemur safari began at the <ORGANIZATION>Duke</ORGANIZATION> cabin in the rain
forest. Before we set out, <PERSON>Emil</PERSON>, our Malagasy guide, told us
to tuck our pant legs into our boots as protection against
leeches. Leeches] The mere mention of the word conjured up
visions of <ORGANIZATION>Humphrey Bogart</ORGANIZATION> frantically pulling the slimy
things off his body in African Queen. But <PERSON>Emil</PERSON> quickly
reassured us: "When no rain, not many leeches." The sun was
shining. Off we went.
   About 15 minutes into our hike, the forest darkened from
the gathering clouds. A light rain began to fall, but we
continued. Then there was a clap of thunder, followed by a
downpour. Emil turned us back toward the cabin, muttering,
"When much rain, many leeches." I looked down, and there, on
one of my fingernails, was a tiny, thread-thin worm flailing
about for a piece of flesh. My first leech. I flicked it off
and alerted Anne. We stopped looking up into the trees for
lemurs and concentrated on our leech-ridden selves. We walked
and flicked, walked and flicked. Back at the cabin, we did a
Bogart. We each had a dozen leeches sucking away, mainly on
our feet and ankles, though one was working on my waist and
<PERSON>Anne</PERSON> had one on her back. (<ORGANIZATION>Emil</ORGANIZATION>, alas, was clean.) They had
penetrated our clothes through some kind of hideous osmosis.
A sharp flick of a finger is all it takes to remove them, but
the result is a rather dramatic stream of blood. When the
leeches attach themselves, they inject an anti-coagulant to
keep the blood flowing. You have to admire their ingenuity.
   We saw several species of lemurs on leech-free hikes over
the next few days. But that afternoon, we contented ourselves
with the age-old practice of primate grooming, inspecting
each other for leeches we may have missed. I imagined the
lemurs, the least-evolved primates, looking down from the
treetops at us and laughing. How weird, they must have
thought.
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Thurow</PERSON> was based for four years in <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>, and now is a correspondent in <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION> for the Journal.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910110-0092
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910110-0092.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Man and Lemurs
   Strike a Good Deal
   On Island Off Africa
   ---
   An Ecological Plan May Save
   Both From Extinction;
   A Woman Brings Schools
   ----
   By Roger Thurow
</HL>
<DATE>
01/10/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<CO>
   AFRIC
</CO>
<LP>
   RANOMAFANA, Madagascar -- It is a good morning in the rain
forest. The drizzle is light, the leeches are few and the
lemurs, bounding from tree to tree, are as happy as ever. So,
too, is their guardian, primatologist Patricia Wright, as she
returns to her cabin with two mouse lemurs, captured in small
metal boxes.
   The measuring begins. Left ear, three-quarters of an inch.
Tail, four inches. Right testicle, 0.4 inch. The littlest
lemur squirms in the palm of his inspector's hand. He is put
in a bag attached to a scale. Weight, 1 1/2 ounces.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "They're the smallest primates in the world," says <PERSON>Ms.
Wright</PERSON>, her voice full of wonder.
   No sooner are the mouse lemurs sent scampering back to the
forest than a short, thin man with a big, wide smile enters
the cabin. He is <ORGANIZATION>Nala Edouard</ORGANIZATION>, the barefoot president of
Ambatolahy, a village of 31 peasant families on the edge of
the forest. His people, along with those in other villages,
have agreed to stop cutting down the trees, which amounts to
putting a hold on their agricultural expansion, in return for
development aid -- and a school. Now he has come to collect.
Again, <PERSON>Ms. Wright</PERSON> takes out her tape-measure, this time to
outline the foundation of the school she has promised them.
   "I walk into the forest and then into politics and then
back into the forest again," laughs the primatologist, a
professor at <ORGANIZATION>Duke University</ORGANIZATION>. "It's hard to even get my
clothes straight." The day before, she showed up at a meeting
with local officials in her knee-high mud boots. "I forgot,"
she says with slight embarrassment, "to change into my
shoes."
   So it goes in the quixotic quest to strike a balance
between conservation and development, in a country that
doesn't have enough money for either.
   <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, an achingly beautiful island off the southeast
coast of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, is a land of sweeping distinctions: It is at
once one of the world's richest countries and one of its
poorest. It is also the most eroded spot on earth.
   The island's wealth is in its unique biological diversity.
Scientists estimate that 150,000 of the 200,000 identified
living things on <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, which broke off from the African
mainland 160 million years ago, are found nowhere else. This
is true of its 13 species of lemurs -- ranging from the teddy
bear-faced indri, which begins and ends each day with a wail
that sounds like someone learning to play the clarinet, to
the tiny microcebus, a furry Kewpie doll with <PERSON>Bette Davis</PERSON>
eyes. The rosy periwinkle, a plant that produces the most
effective agent in combating childhood leukemia, is a native.
So are two-thirds of the world's chameleons and most of its
orchids.
   Yet <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> is pitifully poor, ranking among the
world's 10 most impoverished countries. Its 11 million
people, most of them farmers, have an average annual income
of <MONEY>$210</MONEY>. The government, in contrast, owes its international
creditors <MONEY>$283</MONEY> per person. Women live an average of 55 years,
men 52. Of every 1,000 babies born, 122 die before their
first birthday. Still, the population grows by <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> a year. To
keep up, the Malagasy relentlessly push back the forest to
expand rice production.
   Through generations of such slash-and-burn agriculture,
the Malagasy have in effect been committing national suicide.
Eighty percent of the island's original forest is gone. From
the air, <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> looks as if is bleeding to death; its
rivers, red with eroded topsoil, spill into the Indian Ocean.
Already, 14 species of lemurs have become extinct, along with
the legendary "elephant bird" that reportedly stood 10 feet
tall, two giant turtles, an aardvark, a pygmy hippopotamus
and an unknown number of plants. Scientists say that if the
current pace of deforestation continues, in 20 to 40 years
the Malagasy themselves will be added to the list.
   "Yes, the lemurs are important. But the major species
under threat in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> is the Malagasy," says <PERSON>Jose
Bronfman</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> representative here. "Their major
source of life, the soil, is going into the sea."
   But from these barren hillsides and gaping gullies has
emerged an African rarity: Man and nature -- and their First
World surrogates, development experts and conservationists --
have become allies.
   "The environment will be saved if we reduce poverty," <PERSON>Mr.
Bronfman</PERSON>, a developmentalist, tells the conservationists.
"And poverty will be reduced if you save the environment."
   This elementary equation is the foundation of an ambitious
15-year environmental action plan drawn up by the Malagasy
government and a consortium of donor agencies from around the
world. Stamped on every page is an equally simple and
neglected principle: The Malagasy must be involved in their
own salvation.
   With the help of colleagues in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ms. Wright</PERSON>
persuaded the Malagasy government to set aside 103,000 acres
of rain forest as the <ORGANIZATION>Ranomafana National Park</ORGANIZATION>. But, with <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT>
of the local peasants' income coming from the forest -- from
freshwater crayfish and eels, wild fruit, honey, reeds for
weaving and from jobs as timber porters for the logging
companies -- laws wouldn't be enough to keep them out.
   "Our parents and grandparents taught us where to go in the
forest to make our living," says <PERSON>Jean Rafidison</PERSON>, a
29-year-old park guide who sells nuts and beans from the
forest on the side. "If you want us to stay out of the
forest, you must teach us, little by little, how to do things
differently."
   Little by little, Prof. <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> and her team of
researchers, backed with <MONEY>$3.4 million</MONEY> from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Agency
for International Development</ORGANIZATION>, are succeeding. Amid the
cluster of mud huts at the entrance to the park stands a
bamboo snack bar, where local peasants serve <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION>. They
are learning that tourists, attracted by the forest and the
lemurs, bring money.
   While some researchers count lemurs and birds, others
count malnourished children. Some measure snails and geckos,
while others plan dams for irrigation and hydroelectricity. A
scientist from the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution</ORGANIZATION> identifies 40,000
different insects in three weeks; a student from Duke hands
out conservation cartoons to the children.
   Up at the cabin, Prof. <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> slips into a pair of dress
loafers. It is time to visit the villagers at <LOCATION>Sahavondronona</LOCATION>.
   The elders are waiting on the hillside. They don't
understand the fuss over the lemurs -- "Don't you have them
in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>?" asks one with a toothless grin -- but they trust
the woman who is bringing them a school.
   <PERSON>Pierre Rakotomanga</PERSON>, the village leader, says his people,
all 154 of them, are looking forward to a visit from the
American experts who can teach them to raise chickens and
pigs, and to extend the life of their rice paddies.
   His people have stopped pushing back the forest, he says,
but the need for food grows. <PERSON>Philomene Ravaoarisoa</PERSON>, mother of
11 children, steps forward to demonstrate. She rolls back the
frayed sleeves of her orange sweater and picks up the loose,
wrinkled skin of her boney right arm. "I'm getting thinner,"
she says. "My family is growing but the rice is the same."
   Still, when it came to picking a top development priority,
the villagers voted for a school. "We cannot eat a school,"
jokes <PERSON>Mr. Rakotomanga</PERSON>, "but it will educate our children.
They will learn how to live with the forest."
   Prof. <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> leaves with a broad smile. "We will furnish
the school, and put up posters of lemurs," she says
excitedly, bouncing down a gravel road on her way back to the
forest. "When you see lemurs when you are five, you remember
them all your life."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900321-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-21-90 0301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-LostLemur Bjt   03-21 0658</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lost Lemur, Bjt,0675</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientist: Long-Lost Relative of Humans and Apes Found in Remote
Forest</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY26, LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A field biologist who trudged through a soggy,
leech-infested forest in search of a long-lost relative of humans
and apes returned with malaria, blood poisoning and the first
photographs of an animal no scientist had ever seen alive.
   ``For a week, I couldn't move,'' <PERSON>Bernhard Meier</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Ruhr
University</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>Bochum</DATE>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, said in a telephone interview
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   But he recovered, and his sighting of the hairy-eared dwarf
lemur in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> has been described as one of the most important
rediscoveries of a mammal in the last decade.
   ``I went three times to that forest to find that animal,
although I already knew it was there,'' he said.
   An old man in a nearby village had told him about it.
   To get to the forest, near <LOCATION>Mananara</LOCATION> in northern <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, an
island country off the east coast of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, ``you need to hike
three days, long and strong,'' <PERSON>Meier</PERSON> said. ``Nothing is dry after a
few kilometers because you need to cross many big rivers and
creeks'' containing leeches.
   ``The leeches are not dangerous. Most people say, `Oh, leeches,
I don't want these plum-sized, ugly, satisfied leeches on me.' ...
But the mosquitoes are dangerous. They transmit malaria.''
   Five preserved specimens, the first collected 115 years ago, are
held in museums. But until <PERSON>Meier</PERSON>'s discovery, researchers had no
idea whether the creature still existed.
   The first complete description of the animal, known to
scientists as Allocebus trichotis, will be published shortly in
<LOCATION>Folia Primatologica</LOCATION>, a scientific journal. Meier made the discovery
<DATE>last April</DATE>, but it is only now being reported.
   The rediscovery of the lemur (pronounced LEE-mur) is important
because it is the only surviving species of an entire genus of
lemurs that have disappeared, said <PERSON>Russell Mittermeier</PERSON>, president
of <ORGANIZATION>Conservation International</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, and a primate
specialist.
   ``If you lose a species, there are close relatives around,'' he
said. ``If you lose a genus, that's worse.'' The discovery of the
hairy-eared dwarf lemur is ``one of the two most important
rediscoveries of mammals in a decade,'' <PERSON>Mittermeier</PERSON> said.
   The other was the rediscovery of the soft-spined porcupine in
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, he said.
   The lemur is brown and shaped like a mouse, with a body 5 inches
long and a 7-inch, furry tail. It weighs no more than 3{ ounces.
   ``Allocebus is the smallest primate species in existence, except
during the dry season when the mouse lemur is not fat and is
smaller,'' <PERSON>Meier</PERSON> said.
   The lemurs of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> are scientifically important because
they are a group of primates that evolved in isolation during the
millions of years that the other primates _ monkeys, apes and
humans _ were evolving elsewhere.
   ``In effect, <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> is a giant experiment in alternative
evolution,'' the New Scientist, an English journal, has said.
   <PERSON>Meier</PERSON> has an enviable record as a lemur hunter. Within the last
few years he discovered and described a lemur new to science, the
golden bamboo lemur, in collaboration with <PERSON>Patricia Wright</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Duke
University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>. He also rediscovered the greater
bamboo lemur, which biologists feared had become extinct.
   Meier emphasized that the importance of the discovery also lies
in the attention it focuses on preserving the forest where the
lemur dwells. About 57,000 acres of the forest have been designated
as a biosphere reserve by the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations Educational</ORGANIZATION>,
Scientific and <ORGANIZATION>Cultural Organization</ORGANIZATION>.
   That part of the forest is protected, but a surrounding area of
forest about 10 times that size is under increasing pressure from a
burgeoning local population, <PERSON>Meier</PERSON> said.
   ``It is one of the last patches of virgin, lowland rain forest,
with huge trees you can't imagine, 50 meters (about 160 feet)
tall,'' <PERSON>Meier</PERSON> said. ``This forest is a very special ecosystem and
can't be substituted by importation of other things.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051389-0024 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 56363 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 13, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 1; Column 1; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
2084 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AN URGE TO BURN; 
</P>
<P>
MADAGASCAR: RARE ISLAND UP IN SMOKE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MICHAEL A. HILTZIK, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ANDASIBE, Madagascar 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> is burning. 
</P>
<P>
The evidence is everywhere: in the haze of smoke that drapes itself into the 
steep dales of the capital, <LOCATION>Antananarivo</LOCATION>, in the evening; in acres of hillside 
blackened with fire that line the road on the three-hour drive from there to 
this forest glen near the east coast, leaving nothing but a stubble of tree 
stumps. 
</P>
<P>
It is visible in the appearance from the air of the great island's central 
highlands, its once-deep forests burned away, leaving only a threadbare 
coverlet of green, as thin as the felt of an old billiard table, through which 
the rich red of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s soil bleeds. 
</P>
<P>
Blessed with a bounty of plant and animal life almost unique on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, thanks 
to 165 million years of geographical isolation from the African mainland, 
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> is cursed with a human population of pyromaniacs. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Centuries-Old Habit 
</P>
<P>
The result of their fires is that this fourth-largest island in the world is 
also the most heavily eroded. Compounded by a population explosion, the 
residents' centuries-old habit of slash-and-burn agriculture today menaces the 
island's future. 
</P>
<P>
The story is told here of a visiting Soviet cosmonaut who told his hosts that 
their island is the only land mass he could never fail to identify from space. 
It is always surrounded by a halo of bright red sea, he explained, the color of 
the soil relentlessly scrubbed off its denuded surface by the wind and rain. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s prized lemurs, the squirrel-tailed, dog-muzzled, monkey-like 
primates of which 23 species are unique to the island, have been pushed out of 
their accustomed habitats into progressively smaller strips of forest. 
</P>
<P>
Its precious rice fields, which feed the world's heaviest per capita consumers 
of rice, are fouled by soil eroded off the bare hills. Its best west coast port 
is all but useless today, so full is it of silt carried off the hills by its 
river. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Spreading Malnutrition 
</P>
<P>
As the forests dwindle and the soil is degraded, charcoal and rice alike become 
more expensive, and malnutrition spreads among <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s children. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Martin Nicoll</PERSON>, a World Wildlife Fund official here, observed: "Virtually 
everyone in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> is dependent on an endangered ecosystem." 
</P>
<P>
That ecosystem is one of the world's wonders. The island may not have lions, 
elephants or giraffes, but not one of its more than 400 species of primates, 
rodents, carnivores and insects is seen anywhere else on the globe. About <PERCENT>95%</PERCENT> 
of its reptile species and <PERCENT>46%</PERCENT> of its birds are also unique. 
</P>
<P>
Its outstanding diversity and sheer strangeness often have naturalists talking 
of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> as if it were the product of a fabulist's imagination. 
</P>
<P>
"Butterflies as big as birds, and birds as colorful as the rainbow" were among 
the wonders listed by British environmentalists <PERSON>Gerald</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lee Durrell</PERSON> in their 
keynote address to a <DATE>1985</DATE> scientific conference marking the start of worldwide 
concern over the island's environment. 
</P>
<P>
Mammals here have retained traits that their mainland cousins lost in 
prehistoric times, such as the ultrasonic alarms and signals that tenrecs -- 
small, burrowing insectivores -- produce by vibrating their quills. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Unusual Ecological Niches 
</P>
<P>
Others have filled ecological niches left vacant by the vagaries of evolution. 
For instance, the nocturnal aye-aye, perhaps the strangest of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s 
lemurs, fills the role of the rest of the world's woodpeckers by digging under 
tree bark for grubs with its spindly, "E.T"-like middle finger. 
</P>
<P>
But the Malagasy love affair with fire is increasingly at odds with this 
otherworldly population of animals and plants. 
</P>
<P>
The Malagasy burn for many reasons. They burn the hillsides to clear land for a 
form of rice culture known as tavy. They burn the flatlands to bring up new 
shoots of grass for their cattle to graze. They burn irreplaceable forest to 
make charcoal. 
</P>
<P>
"And sometimes," said <PERSON>Voara Randriamasolo</PERSON>, director of the national zoo in 
<LOCATION>Antananarivo</LOCATION>, "when they're unhappy with the government, they burn." 
</P>
<P>
The fires set in pastureland eat away at the edges of the rain forest, drying 
them up until they flake away like the pages of a yellowing book. "The fires 
get out of hand because the people set them and let them burn until they just 
die out," said <PERSON>Sheila O'Connor</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Cambridge University</ORGANIZATION> biologist working in the 
south of the country. 
</P>
<P>
Unprotected by forest, the rolling hills of the highlands are scarred by 
crescent-shaped earthslides and eroded gullies, so common that the Malagasy 
have a word for them in their quasi-Polynesian language: lavaka. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Conservation Effort 
</P>
<P>
Yet for all that, <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> has today become the focus of one of the world's 
most ambitious conservation programs. Development agencies, including the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. 
over the last three years made the environment their prime focus. 
</P>
<P>
In the same period, the government has awakened to the threat. After an 
international conference in <DATE>1985</DATE>, the government approved a program to improve 
management of its 22 preserves and to add 14 sites to protect such delicate 
ecosystems as coral reefs and mangrove swamps. 
</P>
<P>
"Today, there's often no staff in some preserves, or sometimes one nominal 
guide, with no transport, no training," said <PERSON>Nicoll</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
With foreign help, the government is prepared to spend as much as <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> per 
year to train and equip wardens for each of 14 particularly important reserves 
selected for intensive management. The programs will include rural development 
schemes aimed at providing local farmers with alternatives to the ancient 
destructive practices. 
</P>
<P>
In some ways, <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> is a test of environmental preservation programs in 
the Third World. Where environmentalism is no luxury, such programs must have 
their own justification. Farmers cannot simply be instructed not to burn; they 
must be told how to find alternatives. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Why Should We Stop?' 
</P>
<P>
"The difficulty," said <PERSON>Randriamasolo</PERSON>, "is the chiefs say, 'We've been burning 
for 100 years. . . . Why should we stop now?' " 
</P>
<P>
Complicating the process here has been a history of political, not just 
geographical, isolation. For 10 years beginning in <DATE>1975</DATE>, the Malagasy 
government barred all foreign researchers from the island. When they were 
permitted to return, the government itself was just beginning to realize the 
seriousness of the decline. 
</P>
<P>
Even today, some Malagasy, just like many other <LOCATION>Africans</LOCATION>, bristle at the 
suggestion that foreign help is crucial to preservation of the island's 
ecosystem. 
</P>
<P>
"It must be the Malagasy themselves who take matters in hand," said <PERSON>Bartholom 
Voahita</PERSON>, chairman of the World Wildlife Fund's local office. "The British or 
Americans wouldn't allow their patrimony to be taken over by Tanzanians, would 
they? So, why should we let ours be taken over by them?" 
</P>
<P>
Yet, the pace of destruction is so great, and the rate of discovery so slow, 
that scientists are convinced that countless species are going extinct without 
ever having been known. 
</P>
<P>
"Since the arrival of man on the island (1,500 years ago), two species of 
tortoise, three of birds and 11 of lemurs have disappeared," the <PERSON>Durrells</PERSON> told 
the <DATE>1985</DATE> conference. At least 238 others are endangered. 
</P>
<P>
"I think you'd have to conclude that there have been extinctions here in the 
<DATE>last 20 years</DATE>," said <PERSON>George Schatz</PERSON>, a botanist from the <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> Botanical 
Gardens in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> who has been helping the government chart a proposed 
reserve. "Sometimes a species is localized to just the side of a hill. When the 
hill goes, the species goes." 
</P>
<P>
At the same time, new species are constantly being discovered in the island's 
newly explored areas. 
</P>
<P>
Not too long ago, botanists discovered a new palm -- not just a new species, 
but a new genus. It wasn't that the palm was so inconspicuous that no one 
noticed it before. Rather, it is a majestic tree, 100 feet high and crowned 
with a red crest that proclaims its presence from half a mile away. 
</P>
<P>
"It was in a place where people had never gotten to," said <PERSON>Schatz</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I know that one of every 20 plants I collect here is probably a new species," 
he added. "In my preserve, there might be 500 new species altogether." 
</P>
<P>
The decline of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s ecosystem began, if at a leisurely pace, with man's 
arrival from the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION> about 1,500 years ago. At that time, much of the 
island was covered with virgin rain forest. 
</P>
<P>
Since then, the forest has receded to a thin strip along the island's eastern 
coast and clumps in the isolated northern and southern tips, and the Malagasy 
have perfected their slash-and-burn methods of cultivation. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Population Explosion 
</P>
<P>
Destructive as they are, the impact of these techniques was limited when 
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> was relatively thinly populated and the land plentiful. But in the 
<DATE>last 20 years</DATE>, the population has nearly doubled, to about 11 million from 6.2 
million in <DATE>1966</DATE>. The pace of destruction has grown proportionately. 
</P>
<P>
"The farmers might get 400 to 500 kilograms of rice per hectare the first year 
(of slash-and-burn cultivation)," said the World Wildlife Fund's <PERSON>Nicoll</PERSON>. "The 
second year, they only get half as much. The third year, they get a tremendous 
infestation of pests and weeds because the soil is dying. So, it's abandoned. 
They pull out and leave it fallow for 11 to 15 years." 
</P>
<P>
That's long enough for the land to recover. But the population explosion has 
forced the Malagasy to telescope this cycle. 
</P>
<P>
"There is so little land now that the cycle is three to five years," said 
<PERSON>Nicoll</PERSON>. "That's not enough time for anything but grass and bamboo, so the cycle 
spirals downhill. They go into more difficult areas -- steeper hills, poorer 
climates." The destruction builds geometrically. 
</P>
<P>
Conservationists say the government's emphasis on preservation has borne some 
fruit in recent times, particularly by halting the commercial exploitation of 
endangered forest land for timber and by controlling the poaching of lemurs. 
</P>
<P>
Some local people have discovered that conservation pays more directly, too, in 
guide fees and jobs in tourist lodges. 
</P>
<P>
Perhaps one of the greater successes is a small reserve known as Perinet, about 
50 miles east of the capital and just outside the railroad stop of Andasibe. 
Tree cutting and lemur hunting have all but ceased in the reserve, said <PERSON>Maurice 
Bedo</PERSON>, a young guide who explained that he grew up inside the forest of Perinet. 
</P>
<P>
"I spent all my childhood hours in here because I love nature," he said. Being 
a guide is so lucrative here that <PERSON>Maurice</PERSON>'s brother, <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON>, recently gave up 
on his college preparation because no job he could aspire to with a college 
education would pay more than he gets now. 
</P>
<P>
In his patched blue jogging suit, <PERSON>Maurice</PERSON> leads a troop of researchers deep 
into the woods. Tree roots interlock in a sort of ladder up the steep 
hillsides. He stops frequently to point out the peculiar characteristics of the 
plants lining the path. This one is an anodyne for a scorpion bite, he 
explains, showing how one crumples the leaf and rubs the moisture on the skin. 
</P>
<P>
Perinet is dedicated to the preservation of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s largest lemur, the 
indri, a tailless brown-and-white teddy bear of a primate. 
</P>
<P>
The indri's most appreciated feature is its call. "A Callas among the lemurs," 
is the description of one naturalist, "who composes and performs its own 
operas." 
</P>
<P>
Presently, <PERSON>Maurice</PERSON>'s brother, <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON>, emerges from a thicket with the news he 
has tracked down an indri family of five. Suddenly, they are spotted flinging 
themselves, limbs outstretched, across the wedge of sunlight coming through the 
treetops. Two can be seen folded together in the crook of a tree. 
</P>
<P>
Silence. 
</P>
<P>
Then with the abruptness of a foghorn comes a symphony of pentatonic sound, a 
song of greeting, alarm or awakening in five harmonizing pitches. The calls 
continue for perhaps five minutes. Then they end as suddenly as they began. 
</P>
<P>
All over <PERSON>Madagasgar</PERSON>, the Malagasy and foreign visitors alike have been 
discovering those hitherto-hidden qualities of the island's wildlife. But 
resistance to changing the old ways still thrives. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Cambridge University</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> was confronted by resistance just last year, 
after she and some colleagues emerged in their Land Rover from the depths of a 
forest preserve they were helping to chart. 
</P>
<P>
"We came across a huge plot on fire," she recalled. "Later, one of the 
villagers told us they had done it to display annoyance at our not having made 
contact with them before going into the forest. It may or may not have been 
true, but they never did cultivate it." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Woman on St. Marie Island, part of Madagascar, with a basket of twigs to 
be used for cooking. MARISSA ROTH; Map, Madagascar 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Non Dup 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MADAGASCAR -- AGRICULTURE; FIRES -- MADAGASCAR; ENDANGERED SPECIES; ECOLOGY; 
FORESTS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900713-0213 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-13-90 0743EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Debt-Conservation     07-13 0606</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Debt-Conservation,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>Debt-for-Nature Swap To Help Save Lemurs And Forests of Madagascar</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: also on general news wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A novel deal called a debt-for-nature swap will
pay for a <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> conservation program in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, where
destruction of exotic forests threatens wildlife found nowhere else.
   Among the forests' inhabitants are 43 varieties of lemurs,
tree-dwelling human relatives that live only on <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, an
island off the southeast coast of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.
   <PERCENT>Eighty percent</PERCENT> of their habitat has been wiped out.
   <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>D.C.-based Conservation International</ORGANIZATION>, which
negotiated the debt swap, has pledged to pay off <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> of
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s debt to commercial banks, said spokesman <PERSON>Roderic Mast</PERSON>.
   ``We consider <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> to be one of the highest conservation
priorities in the world,'' <PERSON>Mast</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   A first-ever combination of debt reduction and trade credits
will enable the environmental group to get better than double value
for the cash it pays.
   <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s end of the bargain is to begin a five-year
conservation and protection program staffed by its own people under
the direction of <ORGANIZATION>Conservation International</ORGANIZATION>.
   Madagascar is an island about <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> larger than <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
It contains some of the world's most threatened wild habitat.
   <PERCENT>Eighty percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s forests have been lost to
encroachment by poor farmers struggling to eke out a living. The
remaining forest contains 150,000 to 200,000 species of plants and
animals. About three-quarters are found only in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>.
   Last year, the World Wildlife Fund negotiated a <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY>
debt-for-nature swap with <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s first such
agreement. The first debt-for-nature swap was negotiated by
<ORGANIZATION>Conservation International</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION> in <DATE>July 1987</DATE>.
   ``The government of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> has shown its commitment to
saving its own wildlife,'' <PERSON>Mast</PERSON> said. ``They're taking a real
leadership role, in terms of African countries, in showing this
strong commitment to preserving their natural heritage.''
   The new agreement is unusual for two reasons. The <ORGANIZATION>United Nations
Development Program</ORGANIZATION> is considering providing much of the money, the
first time the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> has joined in a debt-for-nature swap. And the
agreement may let <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> reduce its debts to foreign companies
as well as its commercial bank debt.
   Under the accord, foreign companies that have sold goods to
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> and haven't been paid could be paid off in exchange for
further government commitments to conservation.
   Conservation International officials are hoping that some
companies will agree simply to forgive the debts, in effect
donating the money to the conservation effort in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>.
   ``This is the first ever debt-for-nature swap that I'm aware of
involving trade credits as well as bank debt,'' said <PERSON>Steven Rubin</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Conservation International</ORGANIZATION>'s director of business and legal
affairs. ``We're effectively bringing private companies into the
cause of ecosystem preservation in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>.''
   Debt-for-nature swaps have appeared only in the last few years.
The legal and financial underpinnings of the swaps are complex, but
their intent is to get conservation groups more bang for the buck.
   In this swap, for example, <ORGANIZATION>Conservation International</ORGANIZATION> will use
money it raises from the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> or elsewhere to pay off portions of
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s foreign debt and trade deficit at less than face value.
   At current rates, <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> in debt can be paid off for about
<MONEY>$400,000</MONEY>. Banks are willing to accept less than what they are owed
so they can close the books on their loans.
   For each <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> paid off, the government agrees to use <MONEY>$1
million</MONEY> worth of its own currency _ which banks generally won't
accept as payment _ to finance conservation.
   The result is that <MONEY>$400,000</MONEY> raised by an environmental group
results in <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> worth of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s currency spent on
conservation.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890501-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-01-89 0953EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Pope 1stLd-Writethru a0461 05-01 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pope, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0461,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede ANTANANARIVO</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pope Reaffirms Church Position on Birth Control</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to update with today's Mass, pope's departure. Changes
byline. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEPHEN R. WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FIANARANTSOA, Madagascar (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> celebrated an
open air Mass in an impoverished farming region today and said that
despite tough economic times the faithful should not use artificial
birth control.
   ``While it appears necessary to be aware of family planning,
couples...should use natural methods,'' the pope told the 100,000
people who gathered for the <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> approves only what it calls natural
family planning, or abstinence during a woman's fertile period.
   Many Western nations have pressured Third World countries to
control their population explosions, which hinder economic growth
and are a chief factor in environmental degradation.
   The pope said that although the church's teachings seem
difficult, natural methods will work and the faithful should reject
``contraceptive imperialism.''
   <PERSON>John Paul</PERSON> arrived 90 minutes late for his last Mass on this
<LOCATION>Indian Ocean</LOCATION> island. Fog had closed the airport 240 miles south of
the capital of <LOCATION>Antananarivo</LOCATION>.
   After the Mass, the pope flew back to the capital and boarded an
<ORGANIZATION>Air Madagascar Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 737 for the hour's flight to the French
island of <ORGANIZATION>Reunion</ORGANIZATION>, the second of four stops on his fifth African
tour. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he travels to <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION> then <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>.
   President <PERSON>Didier Ratsiraka</PERSON> called the pope's visit ``a source of
comfort for those who are suffering'' in this impoverished country.
   In <LOCATION>Fianarantsoa</LOCATION>, the pope blessed 100 lepers who kneeled in a
sandy field near the airport before saying Mass from a raised,
wooden altar covered by a canopy.
   The pope today spoke of the serious environmental problems
facing <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> and other developing countries and reaffirmed his
call <DATE>Sunday</DATE> for an international effort to safeguard the
environment.
   ``From the north to the south of your great island, I have been
able to admire the beauty, diverse richness of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and its
fruit. And yet the way it is being used risks its degradation and
sterilization.''
   Saving this 225,000-square-mile island that split from the
African mainland more than 150 million years ago has become a
priority of many international environmental groups.
   Ninety percent of the island's plants and animals are found
nowhere else, including hundreds of species of orchids and 29
species of lemurs, small primates whose name derives from the Latin
word for ghost because of their nocturnal habits.
   The destructive farming methods of the island's population,
constantly seeking fresh terrain to plant rice and other crops, has
caused widespread deforestation.
   The <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> channel, off the island's west coast, is so red
from the infusion of soil washed in by erosion that it is clearly
recognizable to astronauts circling the globe.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the pope spoke on the environmental threat to a
gathering of foreign diplomats. He said he supports international
efforts to halt the dumping of toxic wastes in poor countries and
development that endangers the world's remaining rain forests.
   Also <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the pontiff beatified a Malagasy woman credited
with keeping the faith alive 100 years ago after the queen had
banned all Roman Catholic services. Beatification is a first step
toward possible sainthood.
   The church has been openly critical of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s government.
Since a communist revolution in <DATE>1975</DATE>, the country's economy has
declined and recently, the government made policy alterations to
assure foreign aid.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06196185 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06196185 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Jose Luis Villegas -- Mercury News; At his home, Jean-Marie
"James" de La Beaujardiere entertains visiting Malagasy dignitaries.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PALO-ALTO; MAN; PUBLIC; RELATION; MADAGASCAR  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  As you make your way down Garland Drive, a curvy, tree-shaded road in south
Palo Alto, you'll come upon a house that's a little different from the rest.; 
  At the tip of a cul-de-sac sits a simple white home with a bronze plaque at
the entrance, and a grand red, white and green flag flying above the garage.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  P.A. MAN PROMOTES MADAGASCAR
HIS HOME IS HIS CONSULATE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Shorter version ran P. 5B Morning Final Edition  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Welcome to 867 <ORGANIZATION>Garland Drive</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Honorary Consulate</ORGANIZATION> of the Democratic
Republic of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>'s only consulate, otherwise known as the
home of Jean-Marie "James" de La Beaujardiere and his family.;    With only
eight native Malagasy known to be living in the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION> may seem a
strange site for such a consulate. It's here because de La Beaujardiere, a
native of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, lives and works in <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. And when the <ORGANIZATION>Madagascar
Embassy</ORGANIZATION> wanted help, he volunteered to promote his island homeland, off the
southeast coast of Africa.;    <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, a 24-hour airplane ride from here,
is not well known in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. De La Beaujardiere is used to that.;    "It's
true. Almost everybody has no idea where it is or what it looks like," said de
La Beaujardiere, 54, who coined the nickname "James" after consulate
officials, seeing his first name, thought he was a woman and kept seating him
between two men at official dinners.;    Since de La Beaujardiere turned his
home into a consulate seven years ago, neighbors have gotten used to having a
built-in conversation piece next door.;    "After a while, you don't even
notice it," said <PERSON>Barbara Murray</PERSON>, who lives across the street. "In fact, I
didn't know anything about <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> before it opened, and I still don't know
much now.";    De La Beaujardiere opened the consulate when relations between
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> improved after a tense eight years in the
late <DATE>1970s</DATE> when rumors, later discounted, spread that the <ORGANIZATION>CIA</ORGANIZATION> was supplying
aid to <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>'s opposition party.;    De La Beaujardiere works for free as
a consul, when he is not earning a living as a programmer at the <ORGANIZATION>Xerox Palo
Alto Research Center</ORGANIZATION>. He issues visas, provides information about tourism and
trade, lectures at schools, compiles a computer index of literature on
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> and acts as official host for visiting Malagasy dignitaries.;   
Above all, he said, he wants people in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> to learn that "<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> is a
beautiful country with extremely unusual plants and animals found nowhere
else," a place where nature lovers would feel right at home.;    The world's
fourth-largest island, 1 1/2 times the size of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> boasts
hills, deserts and rain forests, which are being depleted by farmers who burn
down the trees to grow rice, the country's main staple.;    The largely rural
country is known for baobab trees, with their distinct rootlike branches; rich
coffee beans; lemurs, exotic primates with glowing eyes; and for the world's
largest variety of chameleons.;    <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, which gained its independence
from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>1960</DATE>, is home to 10 million people, most of whom who are
farmers or herders of either black African or Indonesian descent. It is one of
the world's poorest countries, with an average per capita income of <MONEY>$250</MONEY> a
year, de La Beaujardiere said.;    De La Beaujardiere grew up in the capital
of <LOCATION>Antananarivo</LOCATION>. One grandfather was an architect there, and designed many of
the country's elegant churches. Another grandfather started a print shop that
is still operating.;    De La Beaujardiere moved to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> because there was
no university in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> at the time, he said. After graduating from
college, he worked as a physicist before moving to <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION> 20 years ago with
his wife, <PERSON>Odile</PERSON>, also a physicist, and three sons.;    De La Beaujardiere
maintains that "my flesh is French, my head is American, but my heart is
Malagasy.";    And he hopes that one day, his beloved homeland won't seem
quite so mysterious to those in his new-found land.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  CAROLYN JUNG, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910714  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  678  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday July 14, 1991
00196185,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06036143 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06036143 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SEX; MEDICAL; SCIENCE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  CONSIDER the life of the top baboon: He appears to call all the shots for his
troop; and he rules a "harem" of females. Young males can stay in the troop,
but they're not permitted to mate.;    Aha! thought the scientists studying
baboon behavior. There must be something biological, something genetic, that
dictates male dominance over females, at least among primates.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Science &amp; Medicine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DOMINANCE ISN'T ALWAYS WHAT IT SEEMS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Biology  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Too bad those scientists didn't study the lemurs of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> instead,
says <PERSON>Sarah Nelson</PERSON>, chairwoman of the <ORGANIZATION>Anthropology Department</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Denver.</ORGANIZATION>;    Among lemurs, the females wear the pants, as is true in many
societies, says Nelson.;    <ORGANIZATION>Nelson</ORGANIZATION> currently is leading a series of discussion
groups on the topic of gender differences and how they've been perceived
through history.;    These female lemurs, <PERSON>Nelson</PERSON> said, grab food from the
males, hit them and shove them away. "I'm not putting this forward as ladylike
behavior, but it is an example of a primate where the females are dominant
over the males," she said.;    The males of a different group of lemurs in
<LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> are the primary child care-givers.;    "As soon as the baby is
born, the mother gives it to a waiting male, who carries it around," <PERSON>Nelson</PERSON>
said. "It hangs onto the male's fur. When the baby gets restless and wants to
nurse, he gives it to the mother. It nurses, then she gives it right back.";  
 And perhaps it's wrong to think of those baboons as the male's harem, <PERSON>Nelson</PERSON>
said. Perhaps it's that the females do the really important work of bearing
young, and they choose to keep just one male around merely to meet their
reproductive needs.;    <ORGANIZATION>Nelson</ORGANIZATION> cites all these monkey-related anecdotes to
prove her point: Males aren't always the dominant sex.;    Among humans, "The
diminishment of women's role seems to come with warfare," <PERSON>Nelson</PERSON> said. "In
those agricultural societies that are peaceful, women seem to be at least
equal with men."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Scripps Howard News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910205  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  320  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday February 5, 1991
00036143,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06079028 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06079028 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawing; DRAWING: Philippine flying lemur  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PHILIPPINES; ANIMAL; BEHAVIOR; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Home: Forest of Philippines.; Habits: Agile climber. Eats shoots, buds,
flowers and fruit from many forest trees. Its main enemy is the Philippine
eagle, which feeds almost exclusively on flying lemurs.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Science &amp; Medicine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PHILIPPINE FLYING LEMUR
(CYNOCEPHALUS VOLANS)  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Creature Feature  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  Claim to fame: A membrane called the patagium stretches from neck to wrists,
ankles and tip of tail. It allows the lemur, which is about a foot long, to
glide through trees for up to 450 feet. The lemur is almost helpless on the
ground.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Nancy Ross-Flanigan, Knight-Ridder News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910319  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  83  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday March 19, 1991
00079028,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06098177 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06098177 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: (Adams)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BOOK; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  LAST CHANCE TO SEE; By Douglas Adams  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Arts &amp; Books  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WITH HUMOR AND COMPASSION, AUTHOR TRACKS
VANISHING SPECIES
GETTING A LAST LOOK AT ENDANGERED ANIMALS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Books
Blake Edgar is assistant editor of Pacific Discovery, the natural history
magazine of the California Academy of Science.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  and <PERSON>Mark Carwardine</PERSON>; Harmony Books/Crown, 220 pp., <MONEY>$20</MONEY>; BECAUSE his
Animals, <PERSON>Douglas Adams</PERSON>' boyhood home sheltered many "badly damaged dogs." But
<PERSON>Adams</PERSON> says he never developed an interest in animals.;    So he was baffled
when a British magazine decided to send him, a best-selling author of comic
science fiction novels, to <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE> to join zoologist <PERSON>Mark
Carwardine</PERSON> on a search for a rare and elusive lemur. This animal, the aye-aye,
made a brief appearance on a tree branch during a downpour, and <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> was
moved to join Carwardine on a second journey to find other endangered
species.;    "Last Chance to See" relates their <DATE>1988</DATE> trip to a handful of
places where some of the world's rarest animals survive, for the moment.
Alternately uplifting and depressing, the book affirms the need to preserve
other species and their habitats, and reveals what a necessary and difficult
task that is.;    Fans of <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' "The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy" and
its sequels, or his <ORGANIZATION>Dirk Gently</ORGANIZATION> detective novels, will recognize the author's
wit and offbeat perspective in his first non-fiction work. There are hilarious
accounts of actually reaching the increasingly unremote spots, as <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' sense
of intrepid adventure consistently gets dashed.;    <ORGANIZATION>Adams</ORGANIZATION> brings sensitivity
and curiosity to his encounters with the animals themselves. He also takes the
opportunity to comment and ruminate on the state of his species -- the monkeys
that mastered astounding feats of "twig technology" as they evolved.;    For
instance, while staring into the eyes of a silverback mountain gorilla in a
Zairean cloud forest, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> ponders the futility of teaching language to apes.
"There are many members of our own species who live in and with the forest and
know it and understand it. We don't listen to them. What is there to suggest
we would listen to anything an ape could tell us?";    <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' and <ORGANIZATION>Carwardine</ORGANIZATION>'s
quest takes them to <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> to search for the kakapo, "the world's
largest, fattest and least-able-to-fly parrot," to Komodo for its legendary
10-foot dragon ("though it doesn't actually breathe fire, it does have the
worst breath of any creature known to man"), to <LOCATION>Mauritius</LOCATION> where the extinct
dodo lived and where a host of other unique birds barely exist.;    Many of
these locales share a feature that makes them logical settings for a book on
endangered species: They are islands. Evolution assumes amazing forms on
islands, including flightless birds, giant lizards and dwarf mammoths. But
when an island's isolation is broken by exotic predators and colonizing
people, its animals and fragile habitats are quickly overrun.;    <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> and
Carwardine do see all of their selected species in the wild except one, the
baiji, a half-blind dolphin threatened by barbed fishing nets and blaring boat
propellers on <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Yangtze River</LOCATION>. But their success is incidental to the
story of how each of these animals became rare and of the sometimes
extraordinary steps being taken to save them.;    Take the kakapo, for
example. Fewer than 50 of these large, khaki parrots exist, confined to three
tiny islands. Saving the kakapo has become the top priority for the <ORGANIZATION>New
Zealand Department of Conservation.</ORGANIZATION>;    Rats, cats, dogs, ferrets and weasels
arrived with settlers and decimated kakapo eggs and chicks in their
ground-level nests. <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> remains unsafe for kakapos, and
conservationists killed feral animals on two smaller islands before turning
them into carefully guarded kakapo refuges.;    Perhaps the bird's biology
presents the biggest obstacle to its future. Female kakapos breed once every
four years and then they lay just one egg.;    Meanwhile, the male kakapo
builds a bowl-shaped stage and emits a deep, booming mating call each night
for months. The only problem is that it's difficult for the prospective mate
to locate the source of the call.;    As <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> writes, "One conservation
worker we met said he sometimes wonders if the mating call of the male didn't
actively repel the female, which is a sort of biological absurdity you
otherwise find only in discotheques.";    Although the animals are the main
characters in "Last Chance to See," <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> does not neglect the dedicated and
hopeful biologists. They include <PERSON>Don Merton</PERSON>, who deposits sweet potatoes at
former courtship sites in <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Fiordland</LOCATION> in case a kakapo or two
persist there; and <PERSON>Professor Zhou</PERSON>, the founder of a "semi-nature reserve" for
the Yangtze river dolphin.;    <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> also peppers the book with curious cameo
characters. There is the Australian venom specialist who's bored with
poisonous animals and whose only advice is "don't get bitten." There is Arab,
the scruffy free-lance kakapo tracker and his kakapo-tracking dog, Boss. Plus
hordes of obnoxious tourists and inept officials.;    One drawback is the
book's focus on conspicuous, flashy species that can easily inspire awe,
admiration and action. Obviously, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Carwardine</ORGANIZATION> could choose but a few
species to seek, and in his insightful epilogue, Carwardine points out, "It is
often not the big and beautiful creatures, but the ugly and less dramatic
ones, that we need most.";    "Last Chance to See" offers a poignant portrait
of some scattered patches in our shredded natural tapestry and of the people
rushing to mend what they can. (box)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  BLAKE EDGAR  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910407  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  24  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  907  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 7, 1991
00098177,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880525-0309 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-25-88 0757EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-LondonZooFun Adv02   05-25 0633</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-London Zoo Fun, Adv 02,0654</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv02</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thurs AMs, June 2, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>London Zoo Official Wants Animals to Have Fun, Too</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAGGIE JACKSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>David Shepherdson</PERSON>'s job is to take the boredom out
of life for the animals at the <LOCATION>London Zoo</LOCATION>, putting something more
into their day than sleeping, eating and watching humans.
   He has piped gibbon music into the the gibbon cage.
   For the mongooses, he has provided pieces of hollow wood filled
with crickets for the animals to try to catch. ``Cricket
dispensers,'' he calls them.
   He plans a light-and-sound show for the orangutans.
   The lanky 28-year-old Englishman, whose doctoral thesis had him
tracking wild badgers by radio at night, became behavioral
enrichment officer six months ago at the <LOCATION>London Zoo</LOCATION>, the first
British zoo to have one.
   Believing a little work for the animals is healthy, too,
<PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> is making some species work for their dinners.
   ``Zoos should show the animal as it behaves in the wild,'' he
said. ``For example, in the wild, most species spend more than <PERCENT>50
percent</PERCENT> of their time foraging for food. ... In the zoo, they get
fed once a day.
   ``You have a choice _ either change the environment, or you
don't keep the animals properly.''
   <PERSON>Trevor Paul</PERSON>, director of research at the <ORGANIZATION>Universities Federation
for Animal Welfare</ORGANIZATION>, the independent body co-sponsoring
<PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON>'s post, says the project also works well for people who
visit the zoo.
   ``There isn't a great deal of point in them seeing an animal
sitting in a corner behind bars,'' he said.
   He and <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> say that while zoos in many countries are
making cages more natural, few have spent much time studying animal
behavior in relation to their habitats.
   The 161-year-old <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> Zoo's gibbon monkeys never did much
loafing in their tree-lined outdoor enclosure, but with the change
in their zoo habitat they've become much more feisty.
   Gibbons usually have one mate for life and assert their
territory by singing. <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> Zoo's pair weren't as musical as they
should have been until <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> hung stereo speakers near their
cage and played taped gibbon duets twice a day.
   Thinking they have neighbors, the gibbons now sing, too.
   Shepherdson is also working on a computer keyboard to produce
sounds, food or even slide shows when orangutans operate it.
   <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> said an electronic organ failed to excite the apes, ``so
we'll try to get a keyboard which does more things than produce
sound.''
   Simple toys, often involving food, are best for most animals,
<PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> said.
   He had praise for <PERSON>Hal Markowitz</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> behavioral enrichment
pioneer who installed a machine to toss meatballs into a serval's
cage, but added that he believes more naturalistic tools should be
explored.
   Recently <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> equipped the ring-tailed lemurs' cage with
poles that sway like the trees in the primates' native <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> said one of the best ways to simulate natural behavior ``is
to make an animal work for its food (and) spend normal amounts of
time foraging.''
   In the kinkajous' cage, carrots, bananas and apples hang from
the ceiling, some tantalizingly out of reach for the weasel-like
creatures.
   Before getting the snacks, the female paced for hours _ one of
the first signs of boredom, said <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON>, watching as she
pursued a banana just beyond nose-reach.
   ``Even tortoises pace, I'm told,'' <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> added. ``It's not
a lack of space, it's what you have in that space that's
important.''
   After a cage is outfitted, zoo workers watch the animals for
hours to see how they respond.
   ``In every case so far, there's been a beneficial effect,'' said
<PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON>. ``If every zoo in the country did these things, it
would be a great step forward in animal welfare.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thurs AMs, June 2</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06350064 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06350064 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Chart; DRAWING: Wes Killingbeck - Mercury News (color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  COMPUTER; SOFTWARE; ENVIRONMENT; GAME; CHILDREN  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  FOR PARENTS who want their kids to save the planet instead of shooting up the
place, software publishers have finally begun to offer more environmentally
sensitive products.;    Computer literacy and environmental awareness have
come together in recent years to produce a growing body of "greenware" --
several dozen game-oriented educational titles that embody sound ecological
principles.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Computing  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PLAYING WITH PLANET EARTH
GREENWARE TEACHES CHILDREN ECOLOGY THROUGH GAMES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cover Story;  Additional information attached to the end of this article.; 
(box) FINDING A NICHE: Merchandise at KidTech is strictly child's play. Page 3F  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Even The <ORGANIZATION>Nature Company</ORGANIZATION>, a trendy retailer of eco- paraphernalia, has begun
to offer a few software titles in its catalog.;    One of the recent arrivals,
Eco-Adventures in the Rain Forest, is typical of this genre. The program
provides a computer simulation of a rain forest. It asks aspiring forest
rangers to complete a series of assignments that require exploration of the
habitat.;    For example, one assignment might be to locate and photograph a
lemur. To complete the task, the adventurer must learn the lemur's habits and
preferences. The search may be complicated by extensive clear-cutting of the
forest, unfavorable weather, the unexpected appearance of other species or
threats from poachers. Indians or anthropologists encountered along the way
might provide more information about the rain forest and its inhabitants.;   
Each assignment ends with a "press conference" back at the ranger station,
where reporters ask questions about the situation.;    Another recent arrival,
Eco-Saurus, is intended to teach conservation to kids in the early elementary
grades. An alien is stranded on a befouled island. The objective is to help
the alien repair his spaceship by finding trash that can be recycled into
essential components and by conserving sufficient water and energy.;   
Although school systems have been using personal computers as instructional
tools for more than a decade, much of the older educational software was
intended to provide drill and practice on academic material. Such programs --
clearly developed for use by captive audiences -- can seem dreadfully dull in
comparison with recent computer games.;    Developers of greenware have relied
heavily upon the game format and the techniques of arcade game developers to
produce products that are less overtly instructional.;    When <PERSON>Bob Stevens</PERSON> and
<PERSON>David Smith</PERSON> designed <DATE>Earthquest two years ago</DATE>, they tied together basic
information about the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in a format that allowed a user to explore more
detailed material on its land, air, water, animals and people. Individual
frames, for example, showed where volcanoes were found, how they erupted and
when significant eruptions occurred.;    Earthquest seemed to be a
computerized reference book, enlivened at points by small games and quizzes
that provided incentive for exploring more of the program.;    In designing
their second product, <ORGANIZATION>Earthquest Explores Ecology</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Stevens</PERSON> and <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> made far
greater use of the game format. "Much more effort went into the fun side,"
<PERSON>Stevens</PERSON> said. Their new program functions more like a large game that
frequently requires exploration of a reference work.;    "The game has become
the principal method for stimulating interest in the information," <PERSON>Stevens</PERSON>
said.;    Another recent release, SimAnt from <ORGANIZATION>Maxis Software</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Orinda</LOCATION>,
creates an electronic ant colony. The objective of the game is for the black
ants to defeat the red ants, their competitors for food and territory. After
taking over the entire back yard, the black ants can invade the adjacent home
and drive out human inhabitants. Along the way, the black ants are decimated
by such hazards as insect predators, rainstorms, human feet, lawn mowers and
insecticides.;    To compete successfully in this brutal environment, it is
necessary to learn a good deal about ant castes, breeding and other essentials
of ant citizenship.;    "There's no reason kids can't be learning and having
fun at the same time," said <PERSON>Jeffery Silverman</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Tanager Software
Productions</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Leandro.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Silverman</PERSON>'s company recently released The
Secret Codes of C.Y.P.H.E.R. -- Operation Wildlife.;    The program puts kids
in the role of an undercover agent responsible for finding and deciphering
secret messages. To find these "cyphergrams," users must learn some basic
information about mammals and locate them in their proper habitat.;   
Developers of greenware must strike a balance between the extraordinary
variation of nature and the limitations of the personal computer. There's a
paradox in trying to represent ecosystems and illustrate environmental
phenomena through a medium that is so far removed from the natural world,
<PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> said.;    <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> had to combine elements from widely separated
parts of the world into a single generic computerized rain forest. Although
information on any single species is accurate, the result is an improbable
world where an Asian species might coexist with a South American species.;   
"Nature is extremely complex," <PERSON>Silverman</PERSON> said. "We can only go so far in
simulating it."; ECO-SOFTWARE; Here's a sampling of environment-related
programs.; (box)Eco-Adventures in the <LOCATION>Rainforest</LOCATION>. Published by <ORGANIZATION>Chariot
Software</ORGANIZATION>. Available in <LOCATION>Macintosh</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>DOS</ORGANIZATION> versions. Recommended ages: 9-14.
List Price: DOS or Mac (B&amp;W), <MONEY>$49.95</MONEY>; Mac (color), <MONEY>$59.95</MONEY>.; (box)Eco-Saurus.
Published by <ORGANIZATION>First Byte</ORGANIZATION>. Available in <ORGANIZATION>DOS</ORGANIZATION> version only. Recommended ages: 4-9.
List price: <MONEY>$39.95</MONEY>.; (box)<LOCATION>Earthquest</LOCATION>. Published by <ORGANIZATION>Earthquest Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Available
in <LOCATION>Macintosh</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>DOS</ORGANIZATION> versions. Recommended ages: 10 and up. List price: DOS,
<MONEY>$59.95</MONEY>; Mac, <MONEY>$69.95</MONEY>.; (box)<ORGANIZATION>Earthquest Explores Ecology</ORGANIZATION>. Published by
<ORGANIZATION>Earthquest Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Available in Macintosh version only (DOS version to be
released in <DATE>March</DATE>). Recommended ages: 10 and up. List price: <MONEY>$59.95</MONEY>.;
(box)SimAnt. Published by <ORGANIZATION>Maxis Software</ORGANIZATION>. Available in Macintosh version only
(DOS version to be released in <DATE>January</DATE>). Recommended ages: 7 and up. List
price: <MONEY>$59.95</MONEY>.; (box)The Secret Codes of C.Y.P.H.E.R. -- Operation Wildlife.
Published by <ORGANIZATION>Tanager Software</ORGANIZATION>. Available in DOS version only (Macintosh
version to be released in <DATE>March</DATE>). Recommended ages: 8 and up. List price:
<MONEY>$49.95</MONEY>.; (box)Eco-Adventures in the <LOCATION>Ocean</LOCATION>. Published by <ORGANIZATION>Chariot Software</ORGANIZATION>. This
is the second in a series that began with Eco- Adventures in the Rain Forest.
The objective is to complete a series of oceanographic research assignments.
Available in Macintosh version only. (DOS version to be released in <DATE>January</DATE>.)
Recommended ages: 9-14. List Price: Mac (B&amp;W), <MONEY>$49.95</MONEY>; Mac (color), <MONEY>$59.95</MONEY>.;
(box)Balance of the Planet. Published by <PERSON>Chris Crawford</PERSON> Games. This simulation
offers an opportunity to run the world as "Commissioner of the Environment,"
juggling the need for industrial and food production against problems such as
global warming, acid rain and other pollution. Recommended ages: 15 and up.
Available in <ORGANIZATION>DOS</ORGANIZATION> and Mac versions. List price: <MONEY>$59.95</MONEY>.; (box)<LOCATION>SimEarth</LOCATION>.
Published by <ORGANIZATION>Maxis Software</ORGANIZATION>. Another opportunity to rule the world. For those
tired of fine-tuning ocean temperatures and insect populations, <ORGANIZATION>SimEarth</ORGANIZATION>
offers options such as catastrophic meteors, nuclear accidents and ice ages to
upset the balance. Recommended ages: 12 and up. Available in <LOCATION>Macintosh</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>DOS</ORGANIZATION>
versions. List price: <MONEY>$69.95</MONEY>.; (box)Audubon Wildlife: Whales. Published by
<ORGANIZATION>National Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>. This is an older and slower-moving, but highly
regarded program. It offers a chance to research migration of whales in the
<LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> or extinction of manatees in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, rescue stranded whales or
explore a <DATE>19th century</DATE> whaling village. Available in <ORGANIZATION>DOS</ORGANIZATION> and Apple II
versions. Recommended ages: 8-17. List price: <MONEY>$49.95</MONEY> (includes trial
membership in <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>).; (box)Audubon Wildlife: <ORGANIZATION>Grizzly Bears</ORGANIZATION>.
Published by <ORGANIZATION>National Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>. Become a biologist trying to locate
grizzlies and investigate the mysterious death of a bear, or become a park
ranger trying to prevent conflicts between bears and people. Available in <ORGANIZATION>DOS</ORGANIZATION>
and Apple II versions. Recommended ages: 8-17. List price: <MONEY>$49.95</MONEY> (includes
trial membership in <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>).; -- <PERSON>Ron Wolf</PERSON>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RON WOLF, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911215  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,241  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, December 15, 1991
00350064,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880708-0197 </DOCNO>
<HL> Environmentalists in Brazil Mobilize In Bid to Save Once-Vast Atlantic Forest </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> LATAM </CO>
<IN> ENV </IN>
<DATELINE> RIO DE JANEIRO (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Environmentalists are mobilizing to save what is left of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s once-vast <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> forest, the nation's picture-postcard front door. 

   One of the species of trees near extinction is the brazilwood, or pau-Brazil, which gave the country its name. 

   When Portuguese explorers discovered <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in <DATE>1500</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> forest covered about 170,000 square miles along a 3,000-mile coastal strip. 

   Today, with 80 million of the country's 143 million people and most of its heavy industry crowded into the coastal zone, only about <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> of the original primary forest remains -- in scattered patches. 

   Some of the forest's rare monkeys, birds and trees, many found nowhere else in the world, face extinction. 

   "We are in the process of destroying an entire ecosystem, but there's still time to save what's left and prevent total tragedy," said <PERSON>Rodrigo Lara Mesquita</PERSON>, the chairman of a group called the <ORGANIZATION>S.O.S. Atlantic Forest Foundation</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The foundation has strong economic and political influence. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Mesquita</PERSON> is an heir of the family that for a century has controlled the influential O Estado de S. Paulo newspaper and media group. 
Others running S.O.S. include two multimillionaire industrialists, the president of the country's largest university and a retired admiral. 

   Since <DATE>1986</DATE>, the foundation has raised the equivalent of more than <MONEY>US$4 million</MONEY> for nationwide newspaper and television publicity. 
It intends to collect more, for the satellite mapping of the forest zone and for conservation programs where the remaining forest is thickest. 

   "This group is powerful and well organized," said <PERSON>Russell A. Mittermeier</PERSON>, international vice chairman of the Washington-based World Wildlife Fund and a consultant to the <LOCATION>Atlantic Forest</LOCATION> organization. 
"It's not radical, as unfortunately was the case with many well-meaning but ineffective environmental groups that sprang up in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>. 
I'm very optimistic." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Mittermeier</PERSON> has been traveling to <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> since <DATE>1971</DATE>, principally to work with the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> forest's endangered monkey species. 

   He said in an interview in <LOCATION>Rio de Janeiro</LOCATION> that <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> probably has the best chance for success of the "three highest-priority ecological problems in the world" -- the tropical South American Andes in <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>; the African island of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>; and the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> forest. 

   "Here in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> forest, it really is possible to save the remnants," <PERSON>Mr. Mittermeier</PERSON> said. 
He mentioned specifically the muriqui, <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>'s largest primate, of which fewer than 100 remain; the <LOCATION>Golden Lion Tamarin</LOCATION>, another endangered monkey, with about 400 left; the increasingly scarce red-tailed parrot; the rare and valuable jacaranda tree; and the almost extinct pau-Brazil. 

   "Today, with few exceptions, the only place you can still see pau-Brazil is in a botanical garden," <PERSON>Mr. Mesquita</PERSON> said. 

   Early Portuguese pioneers chopped down all the brazilwood they could find to extract dye. 
Later settlers hacked away the coastal forest to make way for sugar cane and coffee plantations and for settlements. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>S.O.S. Atlantic Forest Foundation</ORGANIZATION>'s logotype is a stylized green, yellow and blue Brazilian flag, but with part of the green ripped away. 

   A foundation poster shows a map of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> with an outline of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> forest as it existed in <DATE>1500</DATE>, with the words, in Portuguese, "I Used to Be Like This." 
Then there is a map showing the scattered forest pockets left <DATE>today</DATE> and the words, "I Wound Up Like This." 

   The foundation's first specific project is to be in a still relatively untouched forest zone covering 3,500 square miles along the coasts of the southeastern states of <LOCATION>Sao Paulo</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Parana</LOCATION>. 
It intends to set up two ecological bases and buy a patrol-type boat to sound the alarm against illegal tree cutting and the banned netting of coastal fish, shrimp and oysters. 

   "Invasion of that region has long gone unpunished," S.O.S. Chairman <PERSON>Mesquita</PERSON> said. 
"But we think we can stop it. 
We're organized, we've got money, and we have access to the authorities and the media." 
