<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890612-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-12-89 1148EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-MissingPlane 1stLd-Writethru a0501 06-12 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Missing Plane, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0501,0476</SECOND>
<HEAD>Search Launched for Missing Hawaii Tour Plane With 11 Aboard</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout with location of Coast Guard search today, details,
police finding nothing in ground search, similar plane crash in 1987. No
pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A twin-engine plane with 11 people aboard
disappeared on what was to have been an hourlong tour of the
<LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION>, and searchers used helicopters and boats to look
for the plane, the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast Guard Cutter Point Harris</ORGANIZATION> searched overnight
through the channel separating <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maui Island</LOCATION> for the
<ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tour Hawaii</ORGANIZATION> plane that disappeared <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> was concentrating its search for the plane off
the northeast coast of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, the last confirmed location of
the airplane, said <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> spokesman Petty Officer <PERSON>Robert
Bennett</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Bennett</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> received information from <ORGANIZATION>Federal
Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION> radar tapes confirming the twin-engine
Beechcraft had left <LOCATION>Hilo International Airport</LOCATION> on the east side of
<LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> and headed up the island's northeast coast.
   The last communication with the pilot was when he radioed an <ORGANIZATION>FAA</ORGANIZATION>
ground station that he had taken off from <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION> for <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kahului
Airport</LOCATION>, said the <ORGANIZATION>FAA</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>George Harvey</PERSON>.
   The plane was to have toured <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, including erupting
<LOCATION>Kilauea Volcano</LOCATION>, before flying on to <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>David Tom</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Scenic
Air Tours Hawaii</ORGANIZATION> reservationist in <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>.
   Tom, who declined to identify the pilot, said the 10 passengers
aboard the plane had set out earlier <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Oahu
Island</LOCATION>. He said they were probably tourists.
   Search efforts <DATE>Sunday</DATE> included a <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> C-130 search and
rescue plane and a helicopter, two helicopters provided by the <ORGANIZATION>Maui
Fire Department</ORGANIZATION> and four Scenic Air Tour <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> planes, said <PERSON>Bennett</PERSON>.
   Civil <ORGANIZATION>Air Patrol</ORGANIZATION> planes and a <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> helicopter were to join
the search when it resumed <TIME>this morning</TIME>, <PERSON>Bennett</PERSON> said.
   <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> police were also asked to check a section of the island
the pilot was known to fly over during tours, <PERSON>Bennett</PERSON> said. Hilo
police Sgt. <PERSON>Prentiss Morino</PERSON> said ground searches <DATE>Sunday</DATE> turned up
nothing and police were to resume looking later today.
   Air strips on the neighboring island also were checked in case
the pilot made a landing without informing the <ORGANIZATION>FAA</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON> said.
   No rains were reported on the two islands <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, which had party
sunny skies with low scattered clouds and 15 to 20 mph winds, the
<ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> office said. Alenuihaha Channel, which the
plane would have had to cross to get to <LOCATION>Maui Island</LOCATION>, had 5- to
6-foot seas, it said.
   In <DATE>December 1987</DATE>, a twin-engine <ORGANIZATION>Panorama Air Tours</ORGANIZATION> plane with
eight people aboard disappeared on flight from <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Molokai
Island</LOCATION>. No trace of the plane or those aboard was found.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890613-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-89 0009EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MissingPlane 2ndLd-Writethru a0698 06-13 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Missing Plane, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0698,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Search Continues for Missing Hawaii Tour Plane With 11 Aboard</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with emergency signal detected,
details. Picks up 3rd graf pvs, `A Coast...'</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   SUBS grafs 8, `The
sky...,' to end to edit to conform, ADD that most aboard were
Americans.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By STEVE ELLIOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   SUBS grafs 8, `The
sky...,' to end to edit to conform, ADD that most aboard were
Americans.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061289-0107 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 69404 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 12, 1989, Monday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 2; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
173 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NATION; 
</P>
<P>
PLANE WITH 11 ABOARD MISSING; 
</P>
<P>
SIGHTSEEING PLANE WITH 11 ABOARD MISSING OVER HAWAIIAN ISLANDS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times wire services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HONOLULU 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A twin-engine plane with 11 people aboard disappeared on what was to have been 
an hourlong tour of the <LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION>, and searchers used helicopters and 
boats to look for the plane, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard Cutter Point Harris</ORGANIZATION> searched overnight through the channel 
separating the islands of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> for the <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tour Hawaii</ORGANIZATION> plane 
that vanished <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> was concentrating its search for the plane off the northeast 
coast of the island of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, the last confirmed location of the twin-engine 
Beechcraft. 
</P>
<P>
The last communication with the pilot was when he radioed an <ORGANIZATION>FAA</ORGANIZATION> ground station 
that he had taken off from <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION> for <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kahului Airport</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>FAA</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>George 
Harvey</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The plane was to have toured <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, including erupting <LOCATION>Kilauea Volcano</LOCATION>, 
before flying on to <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>David Tom</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tours Hawaii</ORGANIZATION> 
reservations clerk in <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Tom</PERSON> said the 10 passengers aboard the plane had set out earlier <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from 
<LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> on the island of <LOCATION>Oahu</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061489-0060 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 69924 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 14, 1989, Wednesday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 17; Column 5; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
166 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WRECKAGE OF HAWAII TOUR PLANE FOUND 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HONOLULU 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The wreckage of a sightseeing airplane that had disappeared with 11 people 
aboard was found <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> strewn over a rugged cliff-side in a remote valley on 
</P>
<P>
There was no immediate sign of survivors. 
</P>
<P>
The crew of a <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County Fire Department</ORGANIZATION> helicopter spotted the <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air 
Tours</ORGANIZATION> plane above <LOCATION>Waipio Valley</LOCATION> on the island's northeast coast, <LOCATION>Hawaii County</LOCATION> 
Fire Battalion Chief <PERSON>James Higashida</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The twin-engine Beechcraft disappeared without indication of trouble <DATE>Sunday</DATE> 
afternoon during a planned hourlong flight from <LOCATION>Hilo Airport</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> to 
<LOCATION>Kahului Airport</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
An 18-member <ORGANIZATION>Marine Corps</ORGANIZATION> reconnaissance team equipped with mountaineering 
equipment was lowered onto a plateau at the 2,000-foot elevation, 700 feet 
above the crash site, and rappelled down ropes to the wreckage, <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County 
Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Bruce Butts</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"They have spotted bodies at the site. At this point, there is no indication 
there are any survivors," Butts said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890614-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-14-89 0452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MissingPlane     06-14 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Missing Plane,0469</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rescue Team Recovers Seven Bodies, Find Four Other Victims of Crash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOKAA, Hawaii (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescue workers descended down ropes from a
helicopter to recover the bodies of seven of the 11 people who died
when a sightseeing plane crashed into a steep valley wall.
   County firefighters and national park rangers found the bodies of
the other four passengers, but the recovery was suspended at
nightfall <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. They planned to return to the remote site <TIME>this
morning</TIME>.
   The twin-engine Beechcraft slammed into an 1,800-foot high wall
at the back of <LOCATION>Waipio Valley</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, shortly after taking
off <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Hilo Airport</LOCATION> en route to <LOCATION>Kahului</LOCATION> on the island of
<LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>. There were no survivors.
   The wreckage of the plane was spread over a 300-foot-long,
fire-scarred swath in the thick vegetation. It was found just after
dawn <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by helicopters that tracked the signal from the plane's
emergency locator transmitter.
   Heavy rains and low clouds had prevented aircraft from searching
the area <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``Most of it was all disintegrated,'' said <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> County Deputy
Fire Chief <PERSON>Edward Bumatay</PERSON>. ``The biggest part they could find was
the engine down in the bottom of the valley.''
   The bodies were taken <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> to <LOCATION>Hilo Hospital</LOCATION>, where work
was to begin on identification, said <PERSON>Bruce Butts</PERSON>, operations officer
for the county <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense Agency</ORGANIZATION>.
   Eight of the 10 passengers were identified <DATE>late Tuesday</DATE> as <PERSON>Peter
Spillane</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ann Herbert</PERSON>, both of <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Jack Merle</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Shirley Merle</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Russellville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>; a <PERSON>Ms. Statler</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Blue Mound</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Sylvie Martel</PERSON> and <PERSON>Nicole Beland</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>; and <PERSON>Robert Wren</PERSON>,
61, an English professor at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston</ORGANIZATION>.
   Two women whose names were withheld pending the notification of
their families were from <LOCATION>Torrance</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, said
<PERSON>T.C. Campbell</PERSON>, operations manager for <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tours Hawaii</ORGANIZATION>, the
carrier.
   The plane's pilot, <PERSON>Pascal Meric</PERSON>, 28, of <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>, had about 4,000
hours flying experience, said <PERSON>Doug Rogers</PERSON>, chief pilot for <ORGANIZATION>Scenic
Air Tours</ORGANIZATION>.
   The crash was the first in the company's nine-year history.
an investigation today into the cause of the crash.
   It was <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s fourth major airline accident in two years.
   In <DATE>December 1987</DATE>, a twin-engine <ORGANIZATION>Panorama Air Tours</ORGANIZATION> plane with
eight people aboard disappeared during a flight from <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Molokai Island</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>April 1988</DATE>, a flight attendant died and dozens were injured
when the front third of the top section of an <ORGANIZATION>Aloha Airlines</ORGANIZATION> jet's
passenger cabin blew away in flight.
   In <DATE>February</DATE>, nine passengers were hurled to their deaths when a
cargo door and a huge chunk of fuselage tore off a <ORGANIZATION>United Airlines</ORGANIZATION>
jumbo jet some 100 miles south of <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890613-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-89 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-MissingPlane 4thLd-Writethru a0618 06-13 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Missing Plane, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0618,0404</SECOND>
<HEAD>Searchers Find Wreckage of Plane</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with Marine saying wreckage was
strewn over wide area; PICKS UP 7th graf pvs, `Heavy rain ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE DUNFORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A rescue helicopter searching a remote valley
early today spotted the wreckage of a sightseeing plane that
vanished <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with 11 people aboard, authorities said. There were
no signs of survivors.
   Pieces of the twin-engine Beechcraft were strewn over the face of
a cliff on <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>'s northeast coast, three miles from where
aircraft had pinpointed an emergency radio signal on <DATE>Monday</DATE>,
authorities said.
   Marines lowered themselves by ropes in an attempt to reach the
crash site, said <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>David Santos</PERSON>.
   ``Debris is spread out over a 200- to 300-meter area,'' said
<ORGANIZATION>Marine</ORGANIZATION> spokesman Maj. <PERSON>Kerry Gershaneck</PERSON>. ``There's nothing that our
people see that would identify the wreckage as an aircraft. There is
no sign of survivors.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tours</ORGANIZATION> plane disappeared without indication of
trouble <DATE>Sunday</DATE> during what was supposed to be an hour-long flight
from <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Maui Island</LOCATION>. The plane had left under partly
sunny skies, carrying a pilot and 10 tourists.
   Heavy rain and strong winds on <DATE>Monday</DATE> prevented helicopters from
searching the valley. A <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> helicopter had picked up the
emergency signal from the <LOCATION>Waimanu Valley</LOCATION> region on the northeast
side of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>.
   The valley is about four miles long with several major side
valleys and has a 320-foot-high waterfall. It cuts deep into the
5,480-foot <LOCATION>Kohala Mountain</LOCATION> and is thick with vegetation.
   The plane's last reported position was 10 miles north of <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION> and
flying at 2,000 feet, according to <ORGANIZATION>Federal Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION>
spokesman <PERSON>George Harvey</PERSON>. The plane passed out of radar contact at
that point and would not have re-emerged on radar until it passed
the island's northern tip.
   The names of those aboard, eight Americans and two Australians,
will not be released until all their families have been notified,
said <PERSON>David Tom</PERSON>, the tour company's operations manager.
   The plane's 28-year-old pilot had about 4,000 hours flying
experience and had flown the around-the-island tour about 50 times,
according to <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tours</ORGANIZATION> chief pilot, <PERSON>Doug Rogers</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, a twin-engine <ORGANIZATION>Panorama Air Tours</ORGANIZATION> plane with eight people
aboard disappeared without a trace on a flight from <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Molokai Island</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890614-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-14-89 1803EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MissingPlane     06-14 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Missing Plane,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investigation Begins Into Tour Plane Crash That Killed 11</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOKAA, Hawaii (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescuers worked to recover the last four
bodies <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> from a remote <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> valley where a tour
airplane crashed, killing 11 people.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tours Hawaii</ORGANIZATION> plane slammed into an 1,800-foot high
wall <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> at the back of <LOCATION>Waipio Valley</LOCATION>. There were no
survivors.
   The twin-engine Beechcraft was on a flight from <LOCATION>Hilo Airport</LOCATION> on
<LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Kahului</LOCATION> on the island of <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>.
travel to <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> to meet with officials in charge of recovery
effort, said <PERSON>Bruce Butts</PERSON>, operations officer for the <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County
Civil Defense Agency</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Barry Trotter</PERSON>, leader of the <ORGANIZATION>NTSB</ORGANIZATION> team, said that in addition to
examining the crash site the team would investigate Scenic Air
Tours' crew training procedures and how the company selects its
pilots.
   The plane's pilot, <PERSON>Pascal Meric</PERSON>, 28, of <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>, had about 4,000
hours flying experience, said <PERSON>Doug Rogers</PERSON>, chief pilot for <ORGANIZATION>Scenic
Air Tours</ORGANIZATION>. The crash was the first in the company's nine-year
history.
   Rescue workers descended on ropes from a helicopter to recover
seven bodies <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Those remains were found upslope from the main
portion of wreckage.
   ``The remains of the others, from what I understand, are in and
around the main wreckage itself, and that wreckage is hanging
precariously on the side of a steep valley wall,'' Butts said.
   Butts said <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> officials, firefighters and national
park rangers were trying to minimize the risk to rescue workers
working to recover the remaining bodies.
   The twin-engine Beechcraft struck a sheer valley wall, and its
wreckage cut a 300-foot-long, fire-scarred swath as it slid downhill
through thick vegetation.
   <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County Police</ORGANIZATION> Chief <PERSON>Victor Vierra</PERSON>, who visited the crash
site <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, said the impact left a burn mark ``that was the
perfect outline of the aircraft.''
   The seven bodies were taken to <LOCATION>Hilo Hospital</LOCATION>, where work was to
begin on identification, Butts said.
   Scenic Air Tours on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> released the name of a ninth
passenger: <PERSON>Delphine Clemenz</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Torrance</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   Eight other passengers were identified as <PERSON>Peter Spillane</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ann
Herbert</PERSON>, both of <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Jack Merle</PERSON> and <PERSON>Shirley Merle</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Russellville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Mary Statler</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Blue Mound</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Sylvie Martel</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Nicole Beland</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>; and <PERSON>Robert Wren</PERSON>, 61, an English
professor at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Houston</ORGANIZATION>.
   The name of a <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> woman was being withheld pending
notification of relatives, according to company owner <PERSON>Doris Tom</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061589-0089 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 70403 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 15, 1989, Thursday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 25; Column 3; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
173 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HAWAII PLANE CRASH SITE YIELDS 11 DEAD, ONE A CALIFORNIAN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HONOKAA, Hawaii 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Emergency crews descended by ropes from helicopters <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to recover the 
last four bodies from the steep terrain where a tour airplane crashed over the 
<DATE>weekend</DATE>, killing all 11 people aboard. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Delphine Clemenz</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Torrance</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, was identified <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> as one of those 
on the <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tours</ORGANIZATION> flight. 
</P>
<P>
The twin-engine Beechcraft was en route <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Hilo Airport</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> to 
<LOCATION>Kahului</LOCATION> on the island of <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> when it slammed into the 1,800-foot-high 
escarpment at the back of remote <LOCATION>Waipio Valley</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> to meet with officials in charge of the recovery effort, <PERSON>Bruce 
Butts</PERSON>, operations officer for the <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County Civil Defense Agency</ORGANIZATION>, said. 
</P>
<P>
An <ORGANIZATION>NTSB</ORGANIZATION> team member said that in addition to examining the crash site the team 
would investigate crew training procedures and how the tour company selects 
pilots. 
</P>
<P>
Seven of the dead were removed by helicopter <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and taken to <LOCATION>Hilo 
Hospital</LOCATION>, where identification work was under way, Butts said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901128-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-28-90 2126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CDC-DeathRates 1stLd-Writethru a0703 11-28 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CDC-Death Rates, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0703,0609</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Finds Hawaii Has Lowest Rate of Preventable Deaths</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS three grafs after 8th graf, `Teutsch said ...' with
researcher's explanation ff possible reasons for varying death
rates. Pick up 9th graf, `Researchers figured ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Death Rates-List</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURAN NEERGAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> has the nation's lowest rate of
preventable deaths from chronic diseases and <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> has the
highest, the federal <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> found that the 50 states and the <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION>
could have prevented at least <PERCENT>26 percent</PERCENT> of their deaths from nine
leading chronic diseases in <DATE>1986</DATE> by reducing such risks as smoking
and cholesterol levels.
   ``The bottom line is there are a lot of these deaths that are
potentially preventable,'' said <PERSON>Steven M. Teutsch</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION>
epidemiologist who helped research the study.
   ``What we are hoping states do is look at where they fall in
terms of these chronic disease deaths and then examine the specific
problems in their states.''
   The study found that <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> had the lowest rate of preventable
deaths, with <PERCENT>26.4 percent</PERCENT> of 2,817 deaths that year labeled as
preventable. <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, both with <PERCENT>33.2 percent</PERCENT>, tied
for the second lowest rate. <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, with <PERCENT>37.2 percent</PERCENT>, and
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, with <PERCENT>37.7 percent</PERCENT>, rounded out the lowest five.
   <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> had the highest rate - <PERCENT>53.5 percent</PERCENT> - followed by <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION>'s <PERCENT>53.3 percent</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <PERCENT>52.6 percent</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>'s <PERCENT>52.1
percent</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>'s <PERCENT>52 percent</PERCENT>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study, published in this week's Journal of the <ORGANIZATION>American
Medical Association</ORGANIZATION>, found that if each state reduced a risk for
its most prevalent disease, the national life expectancy of 73.7
years would increase by four years.
   <PERSON>Teutsch</PERSON> said the study was the first federal effort to track
preventable deaths, which it considered stroke, coronary heart
disease, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, chronic
liver disease and lung, breast, cervical and colorectal cancers in
<DATE>1986</DATE>, the latest year data were available.
   <PERSON>Teutsch</PERSON> said the differences in rates of preventable deaths are
``potentially explainable'' by isolating various factors.
   For instance, he said <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s high rate may be attributable
to it being a highly industrialized state with high minority
populations where knowledge about risk of disease is low.
   In <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, on the other hand, the diet leans strongly toward
seafood and vegetables, which contributes to lower cholesterol
rates and less heart disease.
   Researchers figured out which state had the lowest mortality
rate of each of the diseases and added those rates to create a
mythical ``utopian state'' with the lowest death rate in all nine
diseases - about 224 per 100,000 population. Then they compared
each state to the ideal.
   <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> came the closest to the ``utopian state,'' with 304.7
deaths per 100,000, or 80.34 above the ideal. Thus <PERCENT>26.4 percent</PERCENT> of
its deaths were considered preventable.
   <PERSON>Teutsch</PERSON> said researchers have found that reducing even one of
the known risks for these diseases - such as smoking for lung
cancer and cholesterol for heart disease - dramatically lowers
chances of developing the illnesses.
   ``What we've seen is what's been achieved in some state,''
<PERSON>Teutsch</PERSON> said, pointing out that <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> has the nation's low heart
disease rate. ``If that's been achieved in some state, it
presumably can be achieved in another state.''
   The study found cigarette smoking contributed to the most deaths
from the nine diseases, <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT>. Obesity, a sedentary lifestyle,
high cholesterol, hypertension and diabetes followed.
   It also found that use of mammography and <ORGANIZATION>Pap</ORGANIZATION> screening for
breast and cervical cancers could lower deaths from those diseases.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061389-0145 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 69984 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 13, 1989, Tuesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 2; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
112 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NATION; 
</P>
<P>
HAWAII PLANE FOUND, 11 FEARED DEAD 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times wire services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WAIMEA, Hawaii 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A search helicopter today found the wreckage of a sightseeing plane carrying 10 
tourists and a pilot in a valley on the northeastern tip of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> island. 
Authorities said there were no survivors. 
</P>
<P>
The crashed orange Scenic Air Tours twin-engine Beechcraft C-18 was sighted in 
the vicinity of an 1,800-foot-high waterfall in the picturesque <LOCATION>Waipio Valley</LOCATION> 
at <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME>, the <ORGANIZATION>Hilo Fire Department</ORGANIZATION> said. It had been missing since <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"From aerial survey, there seemed to be no known survivors," Fire Department 
Battalion Chief <PERSON>James Higashita</PERSON> said. "The helicopter crew is trying to find 
the nearest open terrain, road and trails so a ground crew can reach the site." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901129-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-29-90 0504EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CDC-DeathRates     11-29 0361</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-CDC-Death Rates,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Finds Hawaii Has Lowest Rate of Preventable Deaths, Michigan
Highest</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Death Rates List</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURAN NEERGAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s seafood-rich diet may have helped give
it the nation's lowest rate of preventable deaths from nine major
diseases, while <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s industrial lifestyle was blamed in part
for its having the highest.
   The rankings of all 50 states and the <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> came
from a <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> study published <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   It looked at deaths from stroke, lung cancer, coronary heart
disease, breast cancer, diabetes, cervical cancer, chronic liver
disease, colorectal cancer and chronic obstructive pulmonary
disease in <DATE>1986</DATE>, the latest year data were available.
   The study found that <PERCENT>26.4 percent</PERCENT> of the 2,817 deaths in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>
from those nine diseases could have been prevented - the lowest
rate in the nation. <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, both with <PERCENT>33.2 percent</PERCENT>,
tied for the second lowest rate.
   <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> had the highest rate - <PERCENT>53.5 percent</PERCENT> - followed by <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>53.3 percent</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>52.6 percent</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>52.1
percent</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>52 percent</PERCENT>.
   The differences depended on several variables but could be
explained, at least partially, with a little guesswork, said <PERSON>Steven
M. Teutsch</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> epidemiologist who worked on the study published
   <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s high rate may be because it is highly industrialized
and has large minority populations that might know little about
disease risks, he speculated.
   In <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, people tend to eat more seafood and vegetables; that
contributes to lower cholesterol rates and less heart disease, he
said.
   Researchers arrived at their figures using a model based on
combining the lowest death rates for each disease to create a
``utopian state'' with an overall, combined death rate for the nine
diseases of about 224 per 100,000 people.
   Then they compared each state to the ideal.
   <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> came the closest, with 304.7 deaths per 100,000, or 80.34
deaths above the ideal. Thus <PERCENT>26.4 percent</PERCENT> of its deaths were
considered preventable.
   The study found smoking contributed to the most deaths from the
nine diseases, <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT>. Obesity, a sedentary lifestyle, high
cholesterol, hypertension and diabetes followed.
   <PERSON>Teutsch</PERSON> said researchers have found that reducing even one of
the known risks for each disease - such as smoking for lung cancer
and cholesterol for heart disease - dramatically lowers chances of
developing the illnesses.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890617-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-89 1713EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--MissingPlane     06-17 0127</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Missing Plane,0130</SECOND>
<HEAD>Recovery Effort Ends; Not All Bodies Found</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOKAA, Hawaii (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities ended their search of a remote
<LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> valley after finding the bodies of all but one of the
11 people killed when a sightseeing plane crashed.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tours Hawaii</ORGANIZATION> plane slammed into an 1,800-foot
cliff on <DATE>June 11</DATE>, killing all 11 people aboard.
   The bodies of two or three victims were discovered <DATE>Friday</DATE>, and
seven sets of remains were found <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Rain and fog in the rugged <LOCATION>Waipio Valley</LOCATION> forced authorities to
give up the effort, said <PERSON>Bruce Butts</PERSON>, deputy administrator of the
<ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County Civil Defense Agency</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The weather conditions have turned bad again and we just have
to figure we've gotten all we can,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061389-0034 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 69512 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 13, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 18; Column 2; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
150 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HAWAII TOUR PLANE MISSING WITH 11 MAY HAVE SENT EMERGENCY SIGNAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HONOLULU 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A sightseeing plane that vanished between the islands of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> with 
11 people aboard may have sent out an emergency signal <DATE>Monday</DATE>, but foul weather 
prevented rescuers from searching for it. 
</P>
<P>
"There's an emergency signal coming from a valley, and we think it could be the 
plane," said <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Keith Spangler</PERSON>. "But the weather's so bad 
helicopters can't go in, and otherwise it's about a 10-hour hike." 
</P>
<P>
A <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> helicopter picked up the emergency transmitter's signal from the 
remote <LOCATION>Waimanu Valley</LOCATION> region of the island, which is on the northwest end and 
within the flight path of the missing <ORGANIZATION>Scenic Air Tours Hawaii</ORGANIZATION> plane, <PERSON>Spangler</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
The plane disappeared <DATE>Sunday</DATE> on what was to have been an hourlong flight. 
</P>
<P>
"We're getting all our information together and seeing if the weather will let 
up," <PERSON>Spangler</PERSON> said. Heavy rain and low clouds persisted in the area <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
AIRPLANE ACCIDENTS -- HAWAII; RADIO SIGNALS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881013-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-13-88 0621EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-GraveDiscovery     10-13 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Grave Discovery,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>Maui Boat Missing Nearly 10 Years Found in Marshalls</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG SMALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A grave discovered on a small, uninhabited atoll
in the <LOCATION>Marshall Islands</LOCATION> was believed to contain the remains of one
of five <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> fishermen who disappeared nearly 10 years ago,
authorities said.
   The grave and what remained of the men's 17-foot fiberglass
boat, the <PERSON>Sarah Joe</PERSON>, were found on <LOCATION>Sibylla Island</LOCATION> last month by a
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. National Marine Fisheries</ORGANIZATION> worker and an archaeologist studying
green turtles and sea birds, <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> Capt. <PERSON>Jim Cushman</PERSON> said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Two forensics experts and a 27-member <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> shore group
were sent to the island, located 2,054 nautical miles from <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>,
after officials in <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> were notified late last month, <PERSON>Cushman</PERSON>
said.
   ``It (the grave) was located some yards above the high water
mark,'' he said. ``It was a cairn of rocks with a crude cross on
top of it.''
   The partial remains, comprising about <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of a skeleton,
including a lower jawbone, were found in the shallow grave, <PERSON>Cushman</PERSON>
said. A skull was not recovered, he said.
   A 2{-day search of the island, measuring about three miles by
less than half a mile, and nearby islands turned up no other human
artifacts, <PERSON>Cushman</PERSON> said.
   The island was described as uninhabitable, with no water or
vegetation, he said.
   The remains were transported last week to the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Central
Identification Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>, where an attempt to make a
positive identification will be made once medical records of the
five men are obtained, said Capt. <PERSON>Paul Bethke</PERSON>. It is possible the
remains might not be associated with the <PERSON>Sarah Joe</PERSON>, he said.
   The <PERSON>Sarah Joe</PERSON> was reported missing <DATE>Feb. 11, 1979</DATE>, after it
failed to return from a one-day fishing trip off Hana, <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>.
   A search for the boat was suspended after five days following a
56,000-square-mile search involving aircraft from the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Marine Corps</ORGANIZATION>, civil air patrol and commercial and private
aircraft.
   Registration numbers on the boat's hull and the boat's
manufacturer's number were used to identify the <PERSON>Sarah Joe</PERSON>, said
<ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Keith Spangler</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA071590-0039 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 247312 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 15, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 17; Column 2; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
306 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AWAY FROM IT ALL ON THE BIG ISLAND 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JERRY HULSE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Sightseeing: Scenery on the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION> from lush tropical growth to desert-like 
terrain. Recommended visits: the bay south of <LOCATION>Kailua-Kona</LOCATION>, where Capt. <PERSON>James 
Cook</PERSON> met his <LOCATION>Waterloo</LOCATION> and the orchid farms at <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Kona Arts Center, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 272, <LOCATION>Holualoa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96725, (808) 322-2307. 
</P>
<P>
Tours of the <LOCATION>Waipio Valley</LOCATION> are available through <ORGANIZATION>Waipio Valley Shuttle &amp; 
Tours</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 5128, <LOCATION>Kukuihaele</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96727, (808) 775-7121. 
</P>
<P>
For information on volcanoes, contact <ORGANIZATION>Volcanoes National Park</ORGANIZATION>, Box 52, <LOCATION>Hawaii 
National Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96718, (808) 967-7311. 
</P>
<P>
For additional details, contact the <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii Visitors Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, 180 <ORGANIZATION>Kinoole St.</ORGANIZATION>, 
<LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96720, (808) 961-5797. In <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, contact the <ORGANIZATION>HVB</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>3440</DATE> 
<ORGANIZATION>Wilshire Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>, Suite 502, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 90010, (213) 385-5301. 
</P>
<P>
Little Hotels and B&amp;Bs: <ORGANIZATION>Holualoa Inn</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 222, <LOCATION>Holualoa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96725, 
(808) 324-1121. Possibly the finest B&amp;B in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. Four rooms, a swimming 
pool, fireplace, billiards room. Rates: <MONEY>$60/$125</MONEY> with a <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> discount for guests 
remaining a week. 
</P>
<P>
Kona Hotel, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 342, <LOCATION>Holualoa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96725, (808) 324-1155. Eleven rooms, 
shared baths. A bit ramshackle but plenty of old <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> atmosphere. Rates: <MONEY>$15</MONEY> 
single, <MONEY>$23</MONEY> double. 
</P>
<P>
Manago Hotel, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 145, <ORGANIZATION>Captain Cook</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96704, (808) 323-2642. 
Forty-two rooms, an informal restaurant with tasty, inexpensive fare. Rates: 
<MONEY>$18/$32</MONEY> single, <MONEY>$21</MONEY>/<MONEY>$35</MONEY> double. Japanese style: <MONEY>$46</MONEY> single, <MONEY>$49</MONEY> double. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jacqueline Horne</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Waipio Wayside Inn</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> 840, <LOCATION>Honokaa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96727, (808) 
775-0275. Four rooms (one with private bath). Rates: <MONEY>$45/$65</MONEY>. Call (800) 
833-8849. 
</P>
<P>
Waipio Hotel, <LOCATION>Waipio Valley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. Contact <PERSON>Tom Araki</PERSON>, 25 <ORGANIZATION>Malama Place</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96720 (no telephone). Five rooms. Rates: <MONEY>$15</MONEY> per night. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Linda Beech</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Tree House</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 5086, <LOCATION>Honokaa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96727, (808) 775-9518. 
Rates: <MONEY>$125</MONEY>. <PERSON>JERRY HULSE</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Sidebar 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891029-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-29-89 1049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-MissingPlane 1stLd-Writethru a0681 10-29 0396</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Missing Plane, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0681,0400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Commuter Plane With 20 Aboard Disappears In Hawaii</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New throughout with search continuing, last radar fix on plane,
origin of passengers; CORRECTS style on Aloha IslandAir. No pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A search continued <DATE>Sunday</DATE> for a commuter plane
with 20 people aboard that disappeared <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> on a
scheduled 35-minute flight from the island of <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> to the island of
<LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>, officials said.
   The Aloha IslandAir DH6 Twin Otter failed to reach <LOCATION>Molokai
Airport</LOCATION> after leaving <LOCATION>Kahului Airport</LOCATION> at <TIME>6:25 p.m.</TIME> (<TIME>12:25 a.m. EDT</TIME>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>), said <PERSON>Don Early</PERSON>, air traffic manager for the <ORGANIZATION>Federal
Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION> at the <LOCATION>Honolulu Airport</LOCATION>.
   There was no distress call from the plane's two-member crew and
no signals have been detected from an emergency locator transmitter
aboard the plane, said Sgt. <PERSON>William Bowker</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Rescue
Coordination Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   The last radar fix on the plane was when it was two miles off
the northeast shore of <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>, officials said.
   Two <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> C130 search planes, two helicopters and two
cutters were dispatched to search the 3,000-square-mile area of the
Pailolo Channel between the two islands, said Chief Petty Officer
<PERSON>Dennis Hubbard</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> spokesman.
   By <DATE>early Sunday</DATE>, the two helicopters and one C130 had been
recalled from the search area to await first light before rejoining
the search, said Petty Officer First Class <PERSON>Francesca Bozem</PERSON> at the
rescue center.
   Two <ORGANIZATION>Civil Air Patrol</ORGANIZATION> planes also were to join the search, she
said. Aloha IslandAir planned to send two aircraft to join in the
search at daylight, said <PERSON>Stephanie Ackerman</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for
<ORGANIZATION>Aloha IslandAir</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Kahului</LOCATION> is about 100 miles southeast of <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>.
   Searchers reported rain in the area was limiting visbility,
<PERSON>Hubbard</PERSON> said. The weather service said there were only scattered
clouds and 18 mph winds during the scheduled time of the flight.
   The plane, owned by a subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>Aloha Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, was carrying
18 passengers and a crew of two, <ORGANIZATION>Early</ORGANIZATION> said. Thirteen passengers
are from <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>, one is from <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>, two are from <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> and
two are from <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Ackerman</PERSON>. The names of the passenger and
crew were not released.
   About 10 police officers searched the coastlines of <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION> and the island of <LOCATION>Lanai</LOCATION> ``looking for flares or any kind of
distress signal,'' said officer <PERSON>Peter Akuna</PERSON> at the <ORGANIZATION>Maui Police
Station</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wailuku</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06112059 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06112059 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Rodney N. Smith -- Special to the Mercury News; Aboard a
Hawaiian cruise, time passes in sunny leisure(color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  HAWAII; BOAT; TRAVEL; TRIP  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A VACATION in Hawaii is an experience most visitors never forget, and one of
the best ways to discover it all is with the unique cruising opportunities the
islands offer.;    The SS Constitution and SS Independence, grand ships from
bygone days and the only major American-flagged liners operating in the world,
sail from Honolulu in opposite directions weekly.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WESTERN WATERS
WHETHER REACHING OUT TO A GLACIER IN THE
INSIDE PASSAGE OR SOAKING UP SUN OFF HAWAII'S
COAST, OPTIONS ARE PLENTIFUL
HAWAII
HISTORIC SHIPS SAIL FROM HONOLULU TO CAPTURE
THAT ISLAND MAGIC OF BEACHES, FIERY VOLCANOES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Summer Cruise Special
See also related stories on page 1T &amp; 6T-10T in this section
Free-lance writer Rodney N. Smith lives in Kailua, Hawaii.
Additional information attached to the end of this article.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     They make stops at <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. Visitors can
fly in from the mainland and just hop on board.;    The Independence was built
in <DATE>1950</DATE> and was the first of the sister ships to re-enter the trade after
American ocean cruises had stopped. Bought in <DATE>1978</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>American Hawaii Cruises</ORGANIZATION>,
the ship started sailing <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> waters in <DATE>1980.</DATE>;     The Constitution entered
service in <DATE>1951</DATE> with voyages between <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, and took <PERSON>Grace Kelly</PERSON>
to her wedding to <ORGANIZATION>Prince Rainier</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Monaco</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Princess Grace</ORGANIZATION>
rechristened the vessel for <ORGANIZATION>American Hawaii Cruises</ORGANIZATION> when it joined the
Independence.;    Both ships have undergone <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> in renovations in the
past 18 months, and both have occupancy rates greater than <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT> in
<DATE>summer</DATE>, since young families book vacations then with children in tow.;   
Along the <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> waterfront, the Independence and the Constitution have
become heirs to the long tradition of American shipping. Each week as the
ships depart majestically, a bit of the magic of "Boat Day" is recaptured, and
it is easy to sense the years of tradition that the vessels continue.;    Time
aboard passes leisurely, Hawaii-style. Visitors spend hours lounging in the
sun, walking the decks, exercising in the fitness spas, relaxing in the
refurbished lounges and dining on the succulent Hawaiian fare.;    The
American registry of the sister ships means that they are staffed with all
American crews. "Passengers frequently find neighbors to share the hometown
news with," says Capt. <PERSON>Lawrence W. Kelley</PERSON>, master of the Independence.;   
Reaching all islands;  All the major islands are accessible by <ORGANIZATION>American Hawaii
Cruises.</ORGANIZATION>;    <LOCATION>Oahu</LOCATION>, "The Gathering Place," is ringed by protective coral reefs,
its legendary beaches stretching as far as the eye can see. At its heart is
world-famous <LOCATION>Waikiki Beach</LOCATION>, yet just a few miles beyond are pineapple and
coconut groves and ancient fishing villages.;    <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> may be the only place in
the world where humpback whales cause traffic jams. That is because so many
drivers stop to watch along the Honoapiilani Highway during the <DATE>November-May</DATE>
migrating season, when two-thirds of the <LOCATION>North Pacific</LOCATION> giants, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s
biggest visitors, stop by.;    <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> is <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s second-largest island, and
also ranks No. 2 in visitors. <LOCATION>Lahaina</LOCATION>, the old whaling port where humpbacks
sing and cavort for visitors, is still the center of the action, but the
narrow, dusty streets <PERSON>Herman Melville</PERSON> walked are brightly lined with shops,
art galleries, restaurants and night spots.;    <DATE>Today</DATE>, the ships anchor
offshore, and visitors are taken by tender to <LOCATION>Lahaina</LOCATION>. Strolling its streets
and beaches is an easy way to kick back in paradise.;    <LOCATION>Haleakala</LOCATION>, the mighty
volcano called the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> of the Sun, which stretches 10,000 feet out of the
sea, is the not-to-be-missed sight on <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>. Once visitors have seen it at
sunrise, they understand why <PERSON>Mark Twain</PERSON> called it "the sublimest spectacle I
ever witnessed.";    Sunshine on <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION>;  <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION>, the resort of ancient kings
and modern filmmakers, is the third-largest island, and ranks third in
visitors because of its gorgeous beaches, dependable sunshine and wonderful
sunsets. The ancient kings knew how to pick resorts, and visitors are
following in their footsteps to <LOCATION>Poipu Beach</LOCATION> on its south shore.;    The ships
tie up in <LOCATION>Nawiliwili</LOCATION>, but it is easy to arrange any ground tour desired. The
port itself is a working harbor, and not a great place to spend a day.;    In
addition to <LOCATION>Poipu</LOCATION>, many visitors choose the visually dramatic recreational
resort at <LOCATION>Princeville</LOCATION>. The unsurpassed sight at <ORGANIZATION>Puupoa Point</ORGANIZATION>, with its post
card perfect vista of <LOCATION>Hanalei</LOCATION>, was the sight for shooting the <LOCATION>Bali</LOCATION> Hai scene
in "South Pacific.";    Near the northernmost point of the <LOCATION>Big Island of
Hawaii</LOCATION>, there is a special place called <LOCATION>Waipio Valley</LOCATION>. The 2,000-foot gouge in
the earth is one of the great panoramas of the islands, and the two waterfalls
at the head are silver ribbons in the lush greenery.;    Towering above the
little valley is the snow-capped peak of <LOCATION>Mauna Kea</LOCATION>, home of the world's
greatest concentration of space-age telescopes. This may be the only place on
earth where it is possible to drive in a single day from an orchid-lined road
through a rain forest to a scene of lunar-like desolation high above the
clouds.;    The ships tie up off <LOCATION>Kailua-Kona</LOCATION>, where visitors can spend the day
or arrange day tours. Hilo is the other <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION> port of call, where
organized tours are a lot better idea than spending the day wandering the old
town.;    <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s not-to-be-missed spectacle is <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION>, the world's only
"drive-in" volcano, which offers the thrill of frequent, easily accessible
eruptions. The ride around Crater Rim Drive gives visitors the feeling they
can reach out and almost touch the volcano.;    As usual, <PERSON>Twain</PERSON> probably put
it best when he wrote of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>: "No other land could so longingly and
beseechingly haunt me sleeping and waking through half a lifetime, as that one
has done."; IF YOU'RE INTERESTED; (box) ITINERARIES -- Both the Independence
and the Constitution depart every <DATE>Saturday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>. The Constitution
offers 3- and 4-day packages as well as week-long cruises; the Independence
has only 7-day cruises. Both ships sail to <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kona</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION> on
the Big Island.; (box) RATES -- The packages offered by the Constitution
include either three or four nights at hotels on the various islands. Prices
for both ships (cruise only) start at <MONEY>$1,095</MONEY> per person for an inside cabin.
The top end price (outside two-room suite) is <MONEY>$3,695</MONEY> per person. The company
also has air fare add-ons.; (box) SPECIALS -- A honeymoon/anniversary package
combines a two-day resort stay with a four-day cruise. Rates start at <MONEY>$989</MONEY> per
person for stays at the Hawaiian Regent in <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> and <MONEY>$1,069</MONEY> per person for
stays at the <LOCATION>Hawaii Prince</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Maui Prince</LOCATION>. Champagne,
ocean-view rooms are among the amenities.; The cruise line is offering a <PERCENT>50
percent</PERCENT> discount off its seven-day inter-island cruises to active and active
reserve military as well as military dependents. The discount applies to the
first two passengers in cabin categories "A through G" for <DATE>April, May, July
27</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>, <DATE>Nov. 9-23</DATE> and <DATE>Dec. 14</DATE> sailings. Reservations may be made by
calling <ORGANIZATION>American Hawaii's Group Department</ORGANIZATION> at (800) 765-5555. Ask for the
military desk.; (box) <LOCATION>ETC.</LOCATION> -- For information and reservations, contact
<ORGANIZATION>American Hawaii Cruises</ORGANIZATION>, 550 <LOCATION>Kearny St.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 94108; (800) 765-7000.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RODNEY N. SMITH, Special to the Mercury News  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910421  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,202  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 21, 1991
00112059,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900918-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-18-90 0642EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Marie     09-18 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Marie,0286</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Marie Closes in on Hawaii Island</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm <PERSON>Marie</PERSON>, downgraded from a
hurricane, moved today toward <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. Residents were advised to
prepare for winds of up to 73 mph.
   Hurricane <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> was downgraded late <DATE>Sunday</DATE> after its top
sustained winds fell from 85 mph to 70 mph. A storm must have
sustained winds of 74 mph to be classified a hurricane. Marie's
winds still gusted to 85 mph, the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Marie storm was 210 miles southeast of <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>,
heading for <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> at 9 mph, forecasters said. If it stays on the
same course, the storm center would pass 130 miles south of <LOCATION>South
Point</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, known as the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION>, <TIME>this afternoon</TIME>,
forecasters said.
   A tropical storm warning, meaning winds of 39 mph to 73 mph were
possible, was posted for <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>. A tropical storm watch was
posted for <LOCATION>Maui County</LOCATION>, including the islands of <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Lanai</LOCATION>. There were no warnings for <LOCATION>Oahu Island</LOCATION>, where <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> is
located.
   Gale-force winds, ranging from 39 to 54 mph, extend 140 miles
from the center, the weather service said.
   High surf kicked up by the storm hammered the east and south
shores of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, prompting the closing of <LOCATION>Punaluu Beach
Park</LOCATION> with surf on <DATE>Monday</DATE> ranging from 8 to 10 feet where it
normally averages 1 to 2 feet, said <ORGANIZATION>County Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION>
Administrator <PERSON>Harry Kim</PERSON>.
   The southeast section of the island was already experiencing
some strong gusty winds <DATE>Monday</DATE>, blowing debris onto some roadways,
<PERSON>Kim</PERSON> said.
   There were no reports of any property damage related to the surf
or wind, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891031-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-31-89 0040EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HawaiiCrash     10-31 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hawaii Crash,0568</SECOND>
<HEAD>Island Grieves Over Airplane Crash that Killed all 20 Aboard</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KAUNAKAKAI, Hawaii (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High school students on <LOCATION>Molokai Island</LOCATION>
wept and prayed <DATE>Monday</DATE> for classmates and educators who were among
20 people killed in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s worst commuter airplane crash.
investigate <ORGANIZATION>Aloha IslandAir</ORGANIZATION> Flight 1712, which slammed into a ridge
near <LOCATION>Halawa Valley</LOCATION> on the island's eastern end <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> en
route from neighboring <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>. There were no survivors.
   Rescuers recovered 20 bodies <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from the charred wreckage of
the DH6 Twin Otter.
   The victims included eight members of <ORGANIZATION>Molokai High School</ORGANIZATION>'s
volleyball teams, the coach of the girl's team and the school's
athletic director. Three other island residents also were killed.
   The crash stunned <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>, a rural island with 6,000 residents.
Many drivers attached green and white streamers to their car radio
antennas <DATE>Monday</DATE>. Molokai High's colors are green and white.
   ``It's small enough here so that everybody knows each other,''
said the Rev. <PERSON>Robb Kojima</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Kalaiakamanu Hou Congregational
Church</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's almost like the feeling when the (space shuttle)
Challenger blew up. In the same sense, we all feel the grief.''
   Students at <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION> High gathered for a morning assembly. State
psychologists and psychiatrists and two sent by Aloha IslandAir
were on hand to help students cope with the tragedy.
   The school will establish a special counseling center as well,
Principal <PERSON>Clifford Horita</PERSON> said.
   State Health Director <PERSON>Dr. John Lewin</PERSON> said a six-member <ORGANIZATION>Mental
Health Division</ORGANIZATION> crisis team will be available to counsel families
and friends of the victims.
   Fire rescue teams used helicopters to ferry the bodies back to
<LOCATION>Kahului Airport</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>. State crisis team workers were on hand to
assist relatives who were flown to the island.
   The twin-engine plane was 16 years old and had made 28,000
flights, <PERSON>Peter Dudgeon</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Aloha IslandAir</ORGANIZATION>'s vice president and
general manager, said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. It was rebuilt in <DATE>1986</DATE> and had no
significant maintenance problems, he said.
   The plane left <LOCATION>Kahului Airport</LOCATION> at <TIME>6:25 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> for a
scheduled 35-minute flight, said <PERSON>Don Early</PERSON>, air traffic manager for
the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Honolulu Airport</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> launched a search shortly after <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> when the
airline reported the plane missing, officials said. The plane was
sighted at <TIME>5:45 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Wreckage was found over a 300-foot
area.
   There was no distress call from the crew and no signals were
detected from an emergency locator transmitter aboard the plane,
said Sgt. <PERSON>William Bowker</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Rescue Coordination Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   The pilot of the plane, Captain <PERSON>Bruce Pollard</PERSON>, 30, had flown for
the airline for two years, <PERSON>Dudgeon</PERSON> said. He and First Officer <PERSON>Phil
Helfrich</PERSON>, 27, were from <LOCATION>Oahu Island</LOCATION>, which includes <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>.
   Aloha IslandAir said the passenger list included <PERSON>Peter</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Elizabeth Wiley</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>John Craig</PERSON> and <PERSON>Christina Batura</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Hank Gabriel</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>. The airline earlier identified
<PERSON>Ms. Batura</PERSON> as <PERSON>Christina Craig</PERSON>, which is how she checked in with the
carrier. Her real name was released <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION> passengers were identified by the airline as girl's
volleyball team coach Odetta Rapanot; athletic director <PERSON>John Ino</PERSON>;
<PERSON>Leilani Ahina</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jared Elia</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lea Dunnam</PERSON>, <PERSON>Colette Kekalia</PERSON>, <PERSON>Natalie
Helm</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nancy Pierce</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nancine Mahiai</PERSON>, <PERSON>Aloma Spencer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rodrigo Senica</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Jovencio Ruiz</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Testa Ku</ORGANIZATION>. No ages were given.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890719-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-19-89 2002EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HurricaneDalilia     07-19 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hurricane Dalilia,0396</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dalilia Weakens to Tropical Storm; Still Heading Toward Hawaii</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVE ELLIOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Dalilia weakened to a powerful tropical
storm <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and continued on a track that would take it just
south of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, forecasters said.
   <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> residents were stocking up on batteries, canned
goods and other emergency supplies as the storm approached from the
southeast.
   Dalilia surprised forecasters <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by turning to the north,
putting it on track to pass 70 miles south of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>,
southernmost in the chain, late <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   A tropical storm watch _ meaning wind up to 73 mph and heavy rain
were possible _ remained in effect for <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>.
   At <TIME>8 a.m. HST</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the hurricane was about 230 miles
southeast of <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION>, on <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, moving west-northwest at about
13 mph, the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said. Its maximum sustained
wind speed was 70 mph; a storm is classified a hurricane when that
speed reaches 74 mph. Wind gusted to 85 mph.
   <PERSON>Clarence Lee</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Central Pacific Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION>, said
<PERSON>Dalilia</PERSON> was expected to weaken but remain a tropical storm for a few
days.
   In Naalehu, the southernmost community in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, many
residents were buying emergency supplies.
   ``They've been buying lots of batteries and canned goods _
candles and lamps too,'' said <PERSON>Janice Javar</PERSON>, a cashier at <ORGANIZATION>Naalehu
Food Center</ORGANIZATION>. ``Almost everyone mentions the hurricane.''
   Naalehu, with about 5,000 residents, is the closest community to
<LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>'s south tip.
   <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> beach parks were closed for the second day as surf
surged to more than 15 feet on the southeast coast.
   <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> officials closed several seldom-used roads along
<LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>'s south shore.
   ``The purpose is to keep campers out so when the storm hits we
don't have to go in and rescue them,'' said <PERSON>Neil Gyotoku</PERSON>, a
spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION>.
   There were no immediate plans for evacuation, he said.
   Although there were reports of waves washing up on coastal roads,
<LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION> police said no injuries or damage were reported as of late
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The last major storm to hit <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> was Hurricane Iwa, which
brushed the island of <LOCATION>Oahu</LOCATION> and roared over of <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> with wind up to
117 mph in <DATE>November 1982</DATE>, causing <MONEY>$234 million</MONEY> damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900918-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-18-90 1605EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StormMarie     09-18 0276</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Storm Marie,0336</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Veers Away From Hawaiian Islands</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> headed farther south of the
<LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION> than previously expected <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, but forecasters
cautioned residents to prepare for effects of the storm.
   High surf kicked up by the storm hammered the eastern and
southern shores of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, prompting the closing of <LOCATION>Punaluu
Beach Park</LOCATION>. Surf there ranged from 8 to 10 feet, up from a normal
average of 1 to 2 feet, <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> Administrator
<PERSON>Harry Kim</PERSON> said.
   The southeastern section of the island also experienced some
strong, gusty wind that blew debris onto some roads, <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> said.
   There were no reports of any property damage caused by the surf
or wind, he said.
   The storm was expected to pass about 250 miles south of the
<LOCATION>South Point</LOCATION> area of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> predicted the storm
would come within 130 miles of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION>, but
the storm began veering from a westerly course to the southwest.
   At <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME>, the storm was about 235 miles south southeast of
<LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION>, on <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>'s east coast, and was moving to the
southwest at 9 mph.
   The storm, downgraded from a hurricane <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, had a maximum
sustained wind speed of 65 mph with 85 mph gusts. Gale force wind
extended 125 miles out from the center.
   The storm's intensity was expected to change little until the
same time <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the weather service said.
   A tropical storm warning remained in effect for <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>
and a tropical storm watch was in effect for the islands of <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Lanai</LOCATION>. No storm warnings were issued for <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oahu</LOCATION>
islands; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> is located on <LOCATION>Oahu</LOCATION>.
   A tropical storm warning means wind blowing at a sustained speed
of 39 mph to 73 mph is possible within 24 hours or less. A watch
means there is a threat of tropical storm conditions within 36
hours.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890719-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-19-89 1315EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-HurricaneDalilia 2ndLd-Writethru a0577 07-19 0431</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hurricane Dalilia, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0577,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hurricane Expected to Pass Close to Hawaii</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 4 grafs after 5th graf, `At 2 a.m. ...' to UPDATE with
new quotes from forecaster, civil defense official, no plans for evacuations;
Picks up 6th graf pvs, `Hawaii residents ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTINE DONNELLY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Dalilia surprised forecasters and
turned north, putting it on course to pass close to <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> <DATE>late
today</DATE> and prompting authorities to warn residents anew to stock up
on emergency items.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the storm appeared to be turning away from the
islands, but it shifted to a northwesterly direction and forecasters
said <PERSON>Dalilia</PERSON> could come closer than they initially expected.
   Forecasters said <ORGANIZATION>Dalilia</ORGANIZATION>'s new track would bring its center to
within 70 miles of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>'s south coast late today.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Central Pacific Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> expected to upgrade a
tropical storm watch _ meaning wind up to 73 mph and heavy rain were
possible _ to a hurricane warning for <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, southernmost in
the Hawaiian chain.
   At <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, the hurricane was about 310 miles southeast of
<LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION>, on <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, moving west-northwest at about 13 mph, the
<ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said. Its maximum sustained wind speed was
75 mph; a storm is classified a hurricane when that speed reaches 74
mph. Wind gusted to 90 mph.
   <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> forecaster <PERSON>Dick Sasaki</PERSON> said <PERSON>Dalilia</PERSON>'s
hurricane-force winds extend to 25 miles from its center.
   ``The storm's center would have to pass very close or right over
any of the islands to bring any hurricane-force winds,'' <PERSON>Sasaki</PERSON> said.
   ``Right now our main concern is high surf,'' said <PERSON>Neil Gyotoku</PERSON>, a
spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION>. ``High tide is this
afternoon and they're expecting bigger surf to hit about then.''
   There were no immediate plans for evacuation, <PERSON>Gyotoku</PERSON> said.
   Hawaii residents were urged to stock up on batteries, canned
goods and other emergency supplies.
   <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> beach parks were closed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> when surf surged to
more than 15 feet on the southeast coast of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>.
   ``We're going to be keeping these beaches closed as a
precautionary measure,'' said <PERSON>Bruce Butts</PERSON>, a spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii
County Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION>.
   Although there were reports of waves washing up on coastal roads
in some spots, <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION> police said there were no reports of injury or
damage as of late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The last major storm to hit <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> was Hurricane Iwa, which
brushed the island of <LOCATION>Oahu</LOCATION> and roared over of <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> with wind up to
117 mph in <DATE>November 1982</DATE>, causing <MONEY>$234 million</MONEY> damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091690-0022 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 276852 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 16, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 16; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
767 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE MATURE TRAVELER: TOURS MAKE EDUCATION A MOVING EXPERIENCE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By HANK KOVELL 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Mature travelers who enjoy combining travel with education will appreciate the 
program offered by <ORGANIZATION>ElderFolk</ORGANIZATION>, a fast-growing program founded in <DATE>1984</DATE> by the 
<ORGANIZATION>Oregon-based Folkways Institute</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
ElderFolk is designed for adults age 55 and older, and is described as a 
"school without walls" because, unlike many study programs for seniors that 
take place on college campuses in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and abroad, ElderFolk 
provides on-site lectures, discussions and individual exploration in the 
countries visited. 
</P>
<P>
Programs are designed to be economical while still providing participants the 
opportunity to explore other cultures by direct contact with local citizens. 
</P>
<P>
ElderFolk programs vary in length and do not require any specific education 
level or previous knowledge of the areas visited. There are no textbooks, 
homework or study preparation. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Folkways Institute</ORGANIZATION> has scheduled more than 15 tours for the remainder of 
<DATE>1990</DATE> and through <DATE>1991</DATE>, with other destinations to be added. 
</P>
<P>
A sampling of the types of tours and subject matter includes: "Discover the 
Agean" (<LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>), emphasizing the region's influence on the modern 
world, <DATE>May 3-24, 1991</DATE>, <MONEY>$2,160</MONEY>; "Back Country <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>," devoted to an ecological, 
cultural and geological overview of the <LOCATION>Big Island of Hawaii</LOCATION>, <DATE>Jan. 11-20</DATE>, <DATE>1991</DATE>, 
<MONEY>$1,260</MONEY>, and "<LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Burma</LOCATION>), <LOCATION>Rangoon</LOCATION> to Inle Lake," focusing on the natural 
and cultural wonders of the Republic of <LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 6-22, 1991</DATE>, <MONEY>$2,325</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The free ElderFolk catalogue contains details of the philosophy and background 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Folkways Institute</ORGANIZATION> and a brief description of all of the tours scheduled 
for 1990-91. 
</P>
<P>
For the listing of tours or a copy of the catalogue, write <ORGANIZATION>Folkways Institute</ORGANIZATION>, 
14600 <ORGANIZATION>S.E. Aldridge Road</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 97236-6518, or call (800) 225-4666. 
</P>
<P>
Mature travelers make up a high percentage of passengers on freighters, 
according to a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Cruise &amp; Freighter Travel Assn</ORGANIZATION>. 
Flexibility is the key to freighter travel since the vessels' schedules are 
dictated by the cargo on board and any that might be picked up along the way. 
</P>
<P>
Newer freighters are being constructed with the express intent of carrying 
passengers, too, and cabins are increasingly more spacious and better 
decorated. One new freighter, <ORGANIZATION>Ivaran Lines</ORGANIZATION>' Americana, can book 88 passengers, 
although most freighters offering service from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> carry a 
maximum of 12. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Cruise &amp; Freighter Travel Assn.</ORGANIZATION> has published a free booklet entitled, 
"35 Most Commonly Asked Questions About Freighter Travel." It tells about 
length of trips, shipboard activities, possible destinations, food service, 
language problems on foreign carriers, accommodations, health requirements, 
fares and discounts, booking procedures and other subjects. 
</P>
<P>
For a free copy of the booklet, write to the <ORGANIZATION>Cruise &amp; Freighter Travel 
Assn.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 218, <LOCATION>Flushing</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 11358, or call (800) 872-8584 during normal 
business hours. 
</P>
<P>
Mature travelers who are considering a trip to the <LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION> <DATE>this year</DATE> 
can benefit from what are called "Prime Time Perks" -- fringe benefits offered 
by <ORGANIZATION>Island Holidays Tours</ORGANIZATION> to persons over age 60. Bonus features may include 
tours, special amenities or upgrades at certain properties. 
</P>
<P>
Island Holidays is a large tour operator that specializes in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> and offers 
cruises, tours and resort hotel rooms and condominium rentals throughout the 
state. 
</P>
<P>
For travelers who wish simply to book room reservations in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Island 
Holidays</LOCATION> has arrangements with 35 hotels in <LOCATION>Waikiki</LOCATION>, as well as with resorts 
and condominiums on <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION>. The company is able to 
supplement room rentals with discounted air transportation, airport transfers, 
day-tours and car rentals. 
</P>
<P>
Also offered are so-called "supersavers" that include one or more islands. For 
example, the Super Saver Waikiki/Oahu provides round-trip air transportation 
from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, airport transfers, flower lei greeting, seven nights' hotel 
and a welcome breakfast for <MONEY>$512</MONEY> per person, based on two persons in a room, 
effective <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> to <DATE>March 31</DATE>. From <DATE>April 1</DATE> to <DATE>Dec. 14</DATE>, deduct <MONEY>$40</MONEY> per person. 
</P>
<P>
A three-island trip includes <LOCATION>Oahu</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> for nine days and provides 
round-trip air from the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>, lei greeting, three-day car rental on both 
<LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Kaui</PERSON> and inter-island transportation. Cost for this package begins at 
<MONEY>$814</MONEY> per person, double occupancy, and will vary according to the type of hotel 
or condo desired and the season selected for travel. 
</P>
<P>
For more information, contact your travel agent or Island Holidays, <LOCATION>2222 
Kalakaua Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 96815, (800) 448-6877. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06070049 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06070049 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Add-on land excursions include a trip to Rainbow Falls.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  TRAVEL; BOAT; HAWAII  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE first Polynesian settlers reached the Hawaiian Islands by sea about 500
B.C. and British explorer Capt. James Cook sailed there in the 18th century,
so it seemed odd to me on my first visit to Hawaii 15 years ago that I
couldn't travel from island to island by sea. Not only the Polynesians and
Captain Cook had done it, but Yankee whalers and missionaries in the 19th
century. But in the 20th century, I couldn't.;    Instead, I hopped on and off
planes for a 30-minute flight from Honolulu to Kauai, about 100 miles away,
and to Maui, another 100-mile, half-hour flight. When I was in Honolulu, there
was Molokai in the distance just 26 miles away. From Molokai to Maui, the
channel is only nine miles wide. But by sea there was no getting there from
here.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CRUISE PASSENGERS CAN MAKE LIKE CAPTAIN COOK  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Hawaii Special
See also related stories on P. 1, 5, 6, 7 and 8T of this section  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     But <DATE>10 years ago</DATE>, two former transatlantic passenger ships, the
Constitution and the Independence were refurbished to cruise the <LOCATION>Hawaiian
Islands</LOCATION>. And last <DATE>spring</DATE> I joined 790 other passengers in <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> for a
weeklong American-Hawaii Line cruise of these waters that the Polynesians, the
explorers, the whalers and the missionaries had sailed.;    Skies lowered and
rain fell almost constantly as the Constitution made her way from <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION>. To go ashore in <LOCATION>Kona</LOCATION> on the <LOCATION>Big
Island</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> I wore a bathing suit. There was no point in getting other
clothes that wet. And I opted for a submarine fish-seeing tour figuring that,
under water, I would be in the right company. It didn't really matter, though,
as the 46-passenger mini Atlantis submarine took us down 150 feet to a coral
reef in the harbor where schools of zebra-striped fish and surgeon fish and
blue-striped snappers swarmed around a diver feeding them stale bread and
lettuce.;    Of course the American-Hawaii Cruise Line cannot be blamed for
the weather, but the season to avoid in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> -- the inviting warmth of the
climate notwithstanding -- is the <DATE>December</DATE> to <DATE>February</DATE> rainy season. Even
then, the rain comes in quick, heavy showers and is gone again just as
quickly.;     In <LOCATION>Kona</LOCATION>, after my submarine outing, I spent an hour indoors at
<ORGANIZATION>Hulihee Palace</ORGANIZATION>, a <DATE>summer</DATE> palace for some of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s last royalty. (An
advantage of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, in any weather, is its large number of well maintained
historic houses, palaces and museums -- many operated by <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s equivalent
of the <ORGANIZATION>DAR</ORGANIZATION>, the Daughters of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, descendants of missionaries interested in
preserving old <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s heritage.) The palace was rich in Hawaiian antiques
and royal memorabilia (including a 180-pound exercise ball that 18th-century
King Kamehameha the Great is said to have used and a hatbox made from a
hollowed-out coconut tree trunk.);    In <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION>, on the other side of the
island, I saw the early-morning <DATE>Monday</DATE> through <DATE>Saturday</DATE> Suisan Fish Auction
where hotel buyers poked with their umbrellas at the fish they wanted -- red
snapper, blue marlin, yellowfin tuna and wahoo. The taxi driver who had picked
me up at the ship also had provided a brief tour of other waterfront sights --
the Japanese Garden with miniature pagodas and stone bridges and lanterns and
bamboo.;    A land excursion from the ship took passengers to <ORGANIZATION>Rainbow Falls</ORGANIZATION>
where mist from the 125-foot falls and sun commingle to make the rainbows;
ferns grow as tall as trees; elephant ear leaves are carried as umbrellas;
philodendron and trumpet flowers grow.;    Another possible excursion was to
<LOCATION>Hawaii Volcanoes National Park</LOCATION> where <LOCATION>Kilauea Volcano</LOCATION> lava is oozing like black
tar toward the ocean and one can walk out on the lava flow, feel the heat
beneath it; see the destruction it has wrought.;    Sailing from <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Kona</LOCATION>
we watched the burning lava -- like a stream of lights -- descend the mountain
side and splash -- with a further explosion of lights -- into the black sea.; 
  On <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Garden Island</LOCATION> where "South Pacific" was filmed,
fellow-passengers and I rented a car to drive through little tin-roofed
villages, past taro fields to the beauty spots of its North Shore where the
blue seas thunder in on white sand and rock and ironwood trees grow tall. Had
the weather been better, another option would have been a view from a Zodiac
raft of this northern <LOCATION>Na Pali</LOCATION> coast, or from a helicopter.;    I spent the
afternoon of my <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> visit wandering the over-manicured, over-fancified
grounds of the <LOCATION>Westin Kauai</LOCATION> at <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> Lagoons resort, whose mammoth high-rise
bulk I had seen looming alongshore as the Constitution pulled into <LOCATION>Nawiliwili
Harbor.</LOCATION>;    On a post-cruise excursion on the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION>, I spent time on the
still grander similar resort, the <LOCATION>Hyatt Regency Waikoloa</LOCATION> where the waterfalls
and lagoons and canals are artificial. Trams take one from the registration
desk to one's accommodation (or it is possible, instead, to travel on a
canopied boat along one of the canals). Guests can swim in a pool with
dolphins.;    On <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>, the land excursions included a bus trip through green
hills and effulgent valleys where plumeria and orange African tulips bloom to
the <LOCATION>Iao Needle</LOCATION>, a rock spearing 1,200 feet from the valley floor.
Unfortunately, again, rain impeded seeing it with clarity.;    Land excursions
from the Independence or the Constitution are an expensive add-on to a
Hawaiian Islands cruise (they range from <MONEY>$15</MONEY> to <MONEY>$125</MONEY>).;    As for shipboard
time, there are hula, lei-making and ukulele lessons to take take free of
charge; nightly cabaret entertainment; good, if not exceptional meals
pleasantly served in pretty dining saloons. Cabins are well decorated and well
tended.;    And I was right. It feels better, somehow, to be sailing through
an island chain rather than flying through it.;    (check) IF YOU GO --
American-Hawaii cruises leave <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturdays</DATE> year round with double
cabin prices for a seven-day cruise starting at <MONEY>$895</MONEY> per person for an inside
or <MONEY>$1,095</MONEY> for an outside cabin, plus port and cruise taxes of about <MONEY>$50</MONEY>.
Alternatives include a three- or four-day cruise combined with three or four
days at a resort. Information: (800) 765-7000.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PHYLLIS MERAS, Providence Journal  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910310  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,053  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday March 10, 1991
00070049,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880401-0292 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-88 0205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Hawaii-LaborCrunch Bjt   04-01 0771</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hawaii-Labor Crunch, Bjt,0794</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hawaii Labor Pool Shrinks as Tourism, and Demand for Services,
Grows</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTINE DONNELLY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Magdalena Barut</PERSON> didn't need the money, but she
was bored; tired of ``just chasing the chickens around the yard''
of the <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> home she has lived in since <DATE>1954</DATE>.
   So, on a whim, the 67-year-old Barut applied for a job at
<ORGANIZATION>McDonald's</ORGANIZATION>, figuring she would be rejected because of her age.
   But not only has <ORGANIZATION>McDonald's</ORGANIZATION> hired Barut and other senior
citizens like her, the nationwide hamburger chain also lets them
pick their own shifts, gives them 20 hours of training for just one
task _ Barut learned to make french fries _ and in some cases
drives them to and from work.
   ``I don't know I was worried about getting turned down,'' said
<PERSON>Barut</PERSON>, who has been promoted to running a cash register. ``I guess
we just didn't figure how desperate they are for workers around
here.''
   <ORGANIZATION>McDonalds</ORGANIZATION> _ which traditionally hires high school students for
part-time, minimum-wage jobs _ is only one of the many companies
facing a labor crunch in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>.
   Businesses on the islands of <LOCATION>Oahu</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>,
especially those dependent on the ever-burgeoning tourist industry,
are scrambling for workers as the state's unemployment rate falls
to record lows and soon-to-open luxury resorts compete for the
existing work force.
   The state department of <ORGANIZATION>Labor and Industrial Relations</ORGANIZATION> reported
a statewide unemployment rate of just <PERCENT>3.3 percent</PERCENT> for <DATE>February</DATE>, the
most recent data available.
   ``Basically, everybody's got a job who wants one,'' according to
a spokeswoman from the <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii Visitors Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, who said the state's
reputation could suffer if hotels, restaurants and other
tourist-related businesses could not hire enough people to serve
their guests.
   ``The aloha spirit is one of the prime attractions of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>,''
said the spokeswoman, who asked not to be named. ``If that begins
to change because there are not enough people to fill all the jobs,
we could have a serious problem.''
   A report by the labor department's Tourism and <ORGANIZATION>Training Council</ORGANIZATION>
projected an average of 6,400 workers would be needed each year to
meet job openings forecast for <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> counties
through <DATE>1995</DATE>. But the study found that after this year, only about
1,600 people _ or one-fourth the demand _ would enter the job
market each year until then.
   Those dim projections helped convince <ORGANIZATION>McDonalds</ORGANIZATION> to turn to
senior citizens to fill its employee gaps. Other companies have
taken more drastic measures.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Westin Maui Hotel</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Kaanapali</LOCATION>, in a joint venture with the
state, helps ferry workers from the nearby island of <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>, where
a declining pineapple industry led to a <PERCENT>5.8 percent</PERCENT> unemployment
rate in <DATE>February</DATE>. Other businesses followed suit.
   ``<LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> had a low unemployment rate and <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION> had a high one,
so we decided to work together,'' said <PERSON>Lindsey Geyer</PERSON>, the director
of human resources at the <LOCATION>Westin Maui</LOCATION>.
   Although many are basking in the glow of the state's ``full
employment,'' others say the prevalence of tourist-related jobs _
which account for about one third of the employment in the state _
means many residents earn less than they would in other industries.
Since <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s cost of living is about <PERCENT>26 percent</PERCENT> higher than the
national average, many people struggle to make ends meet.
   ``The islands may be paradise, but there also very expensive,''
said <PERSON>Geyer</PERSON>. Educators in the state are also concerned; they say
that because of the proliferation of jobs, young people who would
otherwise go to college are lured away to the work world.
   And economists say that full employment could trigger higher
inflation, because when businesses compete for employees _ offering
more pay and better fringe benefits _ the cost is ultimately passed
on to the consumer.
   Then, of course, there are the tourists.
   <DATE>1987</DATE> was a record year for tourism in the state, with about 5.7
million people visiting the islands, <PERCENT>3.3 percent</PERCENT> more than the year
before, according to the visitors bureau.
   ``Today's traveler and tomorrow's traveler want more service,
and that's labor intensive,'' said <PERSON>Dorothy Bremner</PERSON>, employment
analyst for the labor department's Tourism and <ORGANIZATION>Training Council</ORGANIZATION>.
   An obvious cure _ enticing more people to work and live here _
could be painful.
   ``Bringing people in presents plenty of other problems, and our
infrastruture is already overloaded,'' <PERSON>Bremner</PERSON> said. ``You'll find
very few people interested in making it any more crowded here.''
   A better solution, she says, is to upgrade the skills of the
people who already live here, and make jobs in the tourist industry
career opportunities rather than just average-wage occupations.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06259252 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06259252 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  HAWAII; TRAVEL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  HAWAII is an accessible safari, even for those of us who usually only daydream
of adventure. Let your friends return from a Hawaiian vacation to say they
have been to the famous places. You can come back with the kind of amazing
stories of nature that most people expect to find only on television
documentaries.;   That was what we discovered on a recent trip to two of the
Aloha State's most accessible islands: the Valley Island of Maui and the Big
Island of Hawaii.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE BIG ISLAND IS A WORLD OF WONDER IN ONE FINE
SPOT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Hawaii Special: Fire &amp; Water  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     You can watch active volcanoes ooze orange fire. Or experience the
mysterious way that black and lifeless lava deserts lie right next to lush
rain forests filled with thundering waterfalls. You can marvel at mountains
capped with snow -- then drive half an hour to sweltering, secluded beaches
made of black, red and even green sand. The ocean's crashing waves can tease
your senses as, just yards away, you soak quietly in natural pools of clear,
still and soothing water.;   Wide open spaces; The <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION> is often
overlooked by tourists -- but we found it amazing in its sheer volume of
natural wonders.;   They do not call it the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION> just to distinguish it
from the state name itself. It's big -- all the other islands would fit on it
together with no problem. But it is open -- fewer than 100,000 people are
scattered through its 4,000 square miles -- and it is manageable. We drove 350
miles around its circumference in one very long but immensely satisfying day.;
  That is how we discovered that <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, the island, holds a little of just
about everything that <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, the state, has to offer. Actually, everything
the planet has to offer. Of Earth's 37 climate zones, 31 can be found on this
island.;   In <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> Volcanoes National Park you can view huge, lunar-like
volcanic craters (not to mention active <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION>), and then moments later be
hiking in surprisingly lush rain forests.;   Only the hardiest hikers can
reach <ORGANIZATION>Mauna Loa</ORGANIZATION>, at 13,677 feet the island's second-highest mountain. But
anyone can drive up <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s tallest peak, <PERSON>Mauna Kea</PERSON>, in the midst of a forest
reserve north of the national park. The world's largest observatory -- holding
10 huge telescopes -- takes advantage of the unspoiled atmosphere atop its
13,796 feet. The height also brings snow in the <DATE>winter</DATE> months; expert skiers
can make an expensive four-wheel-drive haul up to find untouched powder.;  
The road less traveled; The real appeal of the Hawaiian islands lies in the
sum total of dozens of small delights, the ones that can only be savored by
taking those detours down spur roads that look appealing and hiking up some
muddy trail just to see where it might lead.;   We learned this valuable
lesson in our earlier stop on <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>. You are likely to have heard of some of
its main attractions -- like the "road to Hana," a three-hour drive from the
resort towns over some of the twistiest, windiest coastal two-lanes imaginable
to an isolated little village on <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>'s windward side. It is inevitable that
you go, but you must think of it as a journey on the Hana Highway, not a road
to a place.;   Take the time to stop and savor its many nooks and crannies --
dozens of waterfalls, some creating ponds suitable for swimming; family fruit
stands offering reasonably priced refreshments and homemade souvenirs;
roadside mini-trails through bamboo forests and wild gardens of blazing exotic
flowers; quaint missionary churches from the <DATE>19th century</DATE>. We stumbled on a
grove of "rainbow" eucalyptus trees whose trunks were streaked with an amazing
array of bright pastel colors -- lavender, pink, chartreuse and orange.;  
Despite conventional wisdom, you do not absolutely have to backtrack from
<LOCATION>Hana</LOCATION>, either, although it is true that <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION>'s paved roads run out pretty
quickly around the far side. We forged ahead a few miles to the much-touted
Seven Sacred Pools, which we learned were not considered sacred and are
considerably more than seven, stepping down from a stunning waterfall to the
ocean in quick succession down a rock gorge. It is almost a religious
experience, however, to take a dip in them, especially the final one, which is
protected from the raging ocean only by a short wall of stones.;   When we got
back to the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> with two dozen rolls of landscape
pictures and stories of all those remote wonders of nature that we had managed
to discover, our friends said in amazement that it sounded like we had seen it
all.;   Gee, we thought -- we felt as though we had barely scratched the
surface.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DIANE WERTS, Newsday  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910915  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  10T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  775  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, September 15, 1991
00259252,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891029-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-29-89 0227EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MissingPlane     10-29 0107</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Missing Plane,0108</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Commuter Plane With 20 Aboard Disappears In Hawaii</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A commuter plane with 20 people aboard
disappeared <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> on a scheduled 20-minute flight from the
island of <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> to the island of <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>, officials reported.
   The Aloha Islandair DH6 Twin Otter failed to reach <LOCATION>Molokai
Airport</LOCATION> after taking off from <LOCATION>Kahului Airport</LOCATION> at <TIME>6:25 p.m.</TIME>, said
<PERSON>Don Early</PERSON>, air traffic manager for the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Aviation
Administration</ORGANIZATION> at the <LOCATION>Honolulu Airport</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> launched a search for the plane after
determining it had not landed at any other airport, said Sgt.
<PERSON>William Bowker</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Rescue Coordination Center</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA020490-0193 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 171611 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 4, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 22; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1137 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TRAVEL VIDEOS: A TRIP TO HAWAII WITHOUT LEAVING YOUR CHAIR 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BETTY MARTIN, Martin is a former staff member of the Travel Section. Her 
column on travel videos appears monthly. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Switch on your VCR and join us on a journey to <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> that could take days in 
person. 
</P>
<P>
On this armchair trip we'll eavesdrop on the major islands and sneak a glimpse 
of developing attractions on <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
So roll the tape. 
</P>
<P>
"HAWAII" (<PERSON>Rand McNally VideoTrips</PERSON>, Best Films and <ORGANIZATION>Video Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, 55 minutes, 
<DATE>1986</DATE>). This is a noble effort to show the highlights of the four major islands 
