<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-13390</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DGTCCABDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930720
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 JUL 93 / Belize suspends territorial pact with Guatemala
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>BELIZE</LOCATION>'S new government is to suspend legislation approving an agreement
between the previous administration and neighbouring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> to settle a
130-year-old territorial dispute. <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> has also asked the Guatemalan
government for a review of the pact.
<PERSON>Mr Manuel Esquivel</PERSON>, prime minister of the former British colony, said the
aim was to get <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> to renounce all claims on Belizean territory. <PERSON>Mr
Esquivel</PERSON> took office a fortnight ago after a narrow general election
victory.
The pact ending the dispute was reached by <PERSON>Mr George Price</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mr Esquivel</PERSON>'s
predecessor, and <PERSON>Mr Jorge Serrano</PERSON>, former president of <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>.
'Too many concessions were made by the previous government in order to reach
a speedy conclusion of the matter. We will not allow this to happen,' <PERSON>Mr
Esquivel</PERSON> said.
'Our concern, basically, is that <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> has given up rights it has under
Belizean law. We say that it is not for the government alone to make this
decision. Ultimately, it will have to be by a referendum.'
At the heart of the settlement between <PERSON>Mr Price</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr Serrano</PERSON> are changes
to <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s maritime boundaries to satisfy Guatemalan desires for access to
the <LOCATION>Caribbean Sea</LOCATION>. The changes allow Guatemalan ships use of a navigation
channel in the <LOCATION>Gulf of Honduras</LOCATION>, bordered by <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>.
The agreement was ratified by Belizean legislators and <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s
constitutional court.
Repeated indications over the past two decades that the Guatemalan military
might invade <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> in pursuit of the territorial claim led to the
stationing of a 1,500-member British garrison in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. Two months ago the
<ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> said it intended to withdraw the garrison. During the election campaign
<PERSON>Mr Esquivel</PERSON> claimed that <PERSON>Mr Price</PERSON>'s administration had no plans for the
defence of the country.
Guatemalan conservatives and sections of the military have objected to any
agreement which does not satisfy Belizean territorial claims.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GTZ  Guatemala, Central America.
    BZZ  Belize, Central America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-14974</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJNDKABQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931014
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 OCT 93 / Belize to seek UK military support
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PORT OF SPAIN
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
MR <PERSON>Manuel Esquivel</PERSON>, prime minister of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, is to ask <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> for further
assurances of military support if the Central American country is threatened
by neighbouring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Esquivel</PERSON>, who will visit <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> between <DATE>Sunday</DATE> and <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of next
week for discussions with government officials, said he was increasingly
concerned at continued instability in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, where the congress and the
supreme court have rejected a demand from President <PERSON>Ramon de Leon Carpio</PERSON>
that they resign.
'All this could provide an opportunity for those elements in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> which
always want to raise the issue of Guatemalan claims to <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>,' <PERSON>Mr Esquivel</PERSON>
said. 'All this concerns us as it could result in the overturning of former
President <PERSON>Jorge Serrano</PERSON>'s recognition of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>.'
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s 130-year-old territorial claim to <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> was ended last year by
a pact between the then-president <PERSON>Serrano</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr George Price</PERSON>, the former
premier of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, in which <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> recognised <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> as an independent
nation.
Worries that the Guatemalan military might invade <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> in pursuit of the
territorial claim led to the stationing of a 1,500-strong UK garrison in
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. Earlier this year the British government said it intended to
withdraw the garrison, but would use the facilities for military training.
The garrison has contributed significantly to the economy of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr
Esquivel</PERSON> said a new budget next month would take account of the impending
loss of income, as well as under-estimated expenditure and overstated
revenue in the previous budget.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BZZ  Belize, Central America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50428 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat001_g_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-001 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   UK Confirms Withdrawal of Troops From Belize </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0101002894 Paris AFP in Spanish 1805 GMT 31 Dec 93 </F>
<F P=103> PA0101002894 </F>
<F P=104>  Paris AFP </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION>, 31 Dec (AFP) -- The <ORGANIZATION>UK Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> today confirmed that the <ORGANIZATION>Belizean Government</ORGANIZATION> will 
assume responsibility for its own defense as of 1 <DATE>January 1994</DATE>, 
and announced that it had started the "immediate" withdrawal of 
the UK troops stationed in that country located in the Central 
American isthmus. 
  <PERSON>Lourdes Taylor</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>UK Embassy</ORGANIZATION>'s cultural attache, asserted 
that the process will be completed by <DATE>September 1994</DATE>. She 
added, however, that a small UK military detachment would remain 
in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> to operate a jungle training installation. "This 
action (the troop withdrawal) reflects the <ORGANIZATION>UK Government</ORGANIZATION>'s trust 
in the much-improved relations between <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and 
the determination of the governments of both countries to 
resolve their bilateral differences peacefully," <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> asserted. 
  The official's statements alluded to <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s historic 
claims to Belizean territory. The tone of those claims eased 
after former Guatemalan President <PERSON>Jorge Serrano</PERSON> recognized 
Belizean independence in <DATE>1991</DATE>. 
  AFP talked on the phone to the spokesperson of Prime 
Minister 
<PERSON>Manuel Esquivel</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Belmopan</LOCATION>, and he explained that the UK troop 
withdrawal will be a gradual process, which was planned over the 
past seven months. It will be "a change of style in UK 
assistance" to <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Carlos Perdomo</PERSON>, who is <PERSON>Esquivel</PERSON>'s private 
secretary, asserted. The official added that after the 
approximately 1,800 soldiers leave Belizean territory, the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> 
will maintain 100 military advisers to operate a special 
training school and that a changing number of UK soldiers will 
come to be trained at that school. 
  Last week, Prime Minister <PERSON>Esquivel</PERSON> stated that the frequent 
raids by Guatemalan soldiers on Belizean territory could be "a 
bad sign" and indicative of a possible invasion. Guatemalan 
authorities denied this possibility. Perdomo disclosed that 
there is no "immediate" fear that the <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Army</ORGANIZATION> will take 
advantage of the UK troop withdrawal to take their demands by 
force. 
  The prime minister's statements, explained his secretary, 
were triggered by the fact that Guatemalan opposition sectors 
have insisted on disavowing all the actions taken by former 
President <PERSON>Serrano</PERSON>, including his agreements with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, and 
declared them as unconstitutional. "If an opposition government 
sets in, it is possible that it will act differently from 
Presidents <PERSON>Serrano</PERSON> and (current President) De <PERSON>Leon Carpio</PERSON> have 
acted. This was the reason for the prime minister's 
statements," he added. 
  <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> obtained its independence from the UK in <DATE>1981</DATE>, but UK 
troops have remained on the territory as guarantors of its 
territorial integrity. <DATE>Ten years later</DATE>, when it recognized 
Belizean independence, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> renounced a large part of its 
demands for the territory of the young nation. It, however, 
maintains its intentions to negotiate a passage to the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> 
sea through the <ORGANIZATION>Belizean Province of Toledo</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> already 
has access to the sea in the extreme southeastern part of its 
territory. Negotiations for the opening can only be initiated 
when the recognition of Belizean independence is ratified by a 
referendum in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-10123 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat041_g_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-041 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  2 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Ministry To Send Note to UN Secretary on Belize </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0203032994 Hamburg DPA in Spanish 0220 GMT 2 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0203032994 </F>
<F P=104>  Hamburg DPA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION>, 1 Mar (DPA) -- It was officially 
reported today that the <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> will send a 
formal note to <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> Secretary General Butrus Butrus-Ghali 
expressing <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s interest in solving the 100-year-old 
territorial dispute with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> through negotiations or 
international legal procedures. 
  Guatemalan Foreign Minister <PERSON>Gladys Marithza Ruiz de Vielman</PERSON> 
said that "in order to safeguard <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s rights regarding 
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>," the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry</ORGANIZATION> decided to send the note to the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> 
secretary general, "with the appropriate reservations regarding 
the territorial sea, the exclusive economic zone, and 
continental shelf, so that it can be circulated as an official 
document of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>." 
  The government of Guatemalan President <PERSON>Ramiro de Leon Carpio</PERSON> 
maintains claims over the territory of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> (23,000 square 
km), which <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> unilaterally granted independence on 21 
<DATE>September 1981</DATE>. <PERSON>Jorge Serrano Elias</PERSON>, the previous president who 
was ousted on 1 <DATE>June 1993</DATE>, recognized <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and established 
diplomatic relations. Various Guatemalan sectors, including 
Human Rights <PERSON>Ombudsman Jorge Mario Garcia</PERSON> <LOCATION>Laguardia</LOCATION>, have said 
this was unconstitutional. 
  Moreover, because the border between the two countries has 
not been well defined, some incidents have occurred. The 
<ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> reported that the <ORGANIZATION>Belizean 
Government</ORGANIZATION> has affirmed that a group of Guatemalans allegedly 
settled in Belizean territory. This is being investigated by the 
<ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Government</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Human Rights <PERSON>Ombudsman Garcia</PERSON> <LOCATION>Laguardia</LOCATION> has asked for the 
immediate intervention of the <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Army</ORGANIZATION> to protect 
Guatemalan territory, after he personally learned of the threats 
that Belizean soldiers have issued against 35 families in the 
town of <LOCATION>Rio Hondo</LOCATION> in northern <ORGANIZATION>Peten Department</ORGANIZATION>, on the border 
with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. The ombudsman met with local peasants who provided 
details of the threats. Garcia <LOCATION>Laguardia</LOCATION> called for strict 
control and surveillance of the border area by the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> to 
guarantee the rights of the Guatemalans. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-10202 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat042_g_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-042 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Further on Foreign Minister's Note to UN </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0303045294 Guatemala City SIGLO VEINTIUNO in Spanish 2 Mar 
94 p 4 </F>

<F P=103> PA0303045294 </F>
<F P=104>  Guatemala City SIGLO VEINTIUNO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] On 1 <DATE>March</DATE> at a news conference, Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Marithza Ruiz Vielman</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> has decided to send a 
formal note to <ORGANIZATION>UN Secretary General Butrus-Ghali</ORGANIZATION> in order to 
protect <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s rights regarding <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. She explained that 
the note will contain relevant considerations regarding 
territorial waters, the economic exclusive zone, and the 
continental shelf, with the goal of being distributed as an 
official UN document. 
  <PERSON>Vielman</PERSON> said that reference is made in the note to 
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s unrestricted compliance to <ORGANIZATION>UN Charter</ORGANIZATION> principles 
and, consequently, to <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s interest in resolving the 
dispute with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. Vielman noted that the solution would be 
attained through negotiation or international jurisdictional 
procedures when she announced that the letter will be sent soon 
and that it will be disclosed to the media as soon as it is. 
  Regarding Guatemalan families' complaints of threats and a 
Belizean military ultimatum to make them leave their lands, 
which are allegedly in Belizean territory, she said the presence 
of settlers has been confirmed "to the east of the historic 
monuments that are being used as a reference point with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>." 
She pointed out that "in case they prove the settlement is 
located in the protected Mayan biosphere area and that it was 
established illegally, the settlers will have to leave the area, 
but the <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Government</ORGANIZATION> will see to it that their rights 
are respected and that they are able to take the products of 
their harvest and their personal goods." 
  Vielman also clarified that <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s interest in seeking 
a 
solution causing the least possible damage to the settlers 
should not be viewed as a renunciation of its rights in the 
territorial claim. She said that <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> have not 
recognized the mentioned monuments as a demarcation line, which 
was confirmed by the 31 <DATE>July 1992</DATE> Joint Declaration. Vielman 
stated that "while the territorial dispute has not been resolved 
and with the sole purpose of avoiding a confrontation, the 
monuments have been used as a reference point by authorities 
from both countries." 
  Vielman added that if the settlers must be removed, no 
deadline will be stipulated because, with the protection of 
Guatemalan authorities, they will determine the time they need 
to prevent losing their crops. She refused to accept that this 
is a threat by the <ORGANIZATION>Belizean Government</ORGANIZATION>, and instead called the 
Belizean statement "a message to withdraw from there," in 
accordance with the Guatemalan ambassador in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. 
  The official argument for the removal of the settlers from 
the place is that it pertains to the Mayan biosphere, and this 
is why, when de <PERSON>Vielman</PERSON> was asked about the reasons why this 
policy is not followed with other people in similar conditions, 
she only replied that it concerns the organizations in charge. 
Finally, <PERSON>Vielman</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Belizean Commission</ORGANIZATION> will be in charge 
of drafting the mechanisms to be followed in the territorial 
claim case, and she could not venture to express her view in 
that regard. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-56444 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat086_g_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-086 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Wants To Resume Belizean Border Talks </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Government Wants To Resume Belizean Border Talks </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA0405014394 Panama City ACAN in Spanish 2100 GMT 3 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0405014394 </F>
<F P=104>  Panama City ACAN </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Excerpt] <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION>, 3 <DATE>May</DATE> (ACAN-EFE) -- Today, 
Foreign Relations Minister <PERSON>Maritza Ruiz de Vielman</PERSON> said the 
<ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Government</ORGANIZATION> is interested in resuming the stalled 
negotiations on the more than 150-year-old territorial dispute 
between <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>. 
  The negotiations were interrupted in the aftermath of the 
failed 26 <DATE>May 1993</DATE> coup d'etat by former President <PERSON>Jorge 
Serrano</PERSON>, who recognized the Belizean state, a British colony 
until <DATE>1981</DATE>, for the first time in Guatemalan history and 
established diplomatic relations. President <PERSON>Ramiro de Leon 
Carpio</PERSON> upheld the <PERSON>Serrano</PERSON>'s decision (1991-93), although many 
political sectors and citizens have demanded he change his 
position. 
  Today, Minister <PERSON>Vielman</PERSON> told foreign correspondents the 
following: "As the executive branch, we have no jurisdiction" in 
recognizing <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> as an independent state. She failed to say, 
however, whose jurisdiction such a decision would fall under. 
  She pointed out that the "<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> Council," a new council 
comprising lawyers and other experts on the subject, must deal 
with this issue. The council, which will serve an advisory 
role, will revise the previous legislation and will recommend to 
the government what to do next. The <ORGANIZATION>Belize Council</ORGANIZATION>, whose 
appointment will be announced next week, will make 
recommendations that will be reviewed by the executive branch 
"in accordance with foreign policies before acting upon them." 
  The foreign minister insisted this is a legal conflict, but 
said she trusts the territorial dispute will have a negotiated 
solution and avoid arbitration within the international courts. 
[passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-208</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EC4C0ABAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940331
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  31 MAR 94 / Fears revive in Belize
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> says neighbouring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> has revived its claim to Belizean
territory, despite an interim agreement reached two years ago between the
two Central American countries, <PERSON>Canute James</PERSON> reports from <LOCATION>Kingston</LOCATION>.
The Belizeans say <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s 130-year-old claim was revived in a letter
sent this month by the government to <PERSON>Mr Boutros Boutros Ghali</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION>
secretary general, saying that an end to <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s claim on the former
British colony would come only with a final treaty.
The latest Guatemalan statement coincides with the dismantling of a
1,500-strong British garrison which had been stationed in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> to
discourage the Guatemalan military from invading in pursuit of the
territorial claim.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BZZ  Belize, Central America.
    GTZ  Guatemala, Central America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 5
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-9714 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat063aa_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-063 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Belize Leaves Central American, EU Summit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Belize Leaves Central American, EU Summit </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA3103040994 Mexico City NOTIMEX in Spanish 1254 GMT 29 Mar 
94 </F>

<F P=103> PA3103040994 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City NOTIMEX </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Lucia Perez Moreno</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>, 29 Mar (NOTIMEX) -- <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> today abandoned 
the 10th Central American and <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>] Foreign 
Ministers' Meeting after <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, the host country, withdrew its 
observer status. 
  The incident occurred after the Guatemalan delegation asked 
<PERSON>Theodoros Pangalos</PERSON>, current chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>European Council of 
Ministers</ORGANIZATION>, to withdraw <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s status as observer at the 
ministerial meeting. 
  "<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s participation in the <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> meetings will depend 
on the context of negotiations on the territorial dispute," it 
was stated to NOTIMEX by Guatemalan Foreign Minister <PERSON>Gladys 
Marithza Ruiz de Vielman</PERSON>. 
  <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> established diplomatic relations in 
<DATE>1981</DATE>, although the two countries have yet to settle a 
territorial dispute. 
  "We were invited by the council's chairman. We do not 
consider this the place to discuss differences between <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Ursula Brown</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s ambassador to the 
<LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION>, shortly before her departure. 
  A participant in the meeting said <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> made "a mistake in 
formalities" when it invited <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> as an observer without first 
consulting with the Central American country. 
  The problem arose when the Belizean representative stood 
close to the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> and Central American foreign ministers when 
posing for a group picture of the meeting, which is currently 
being held at an elegant hotel on the outskirts of the Greek 
capital. 
  <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, with a population of 200,000, achieved its 
independence from the <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, and <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> has 
demanded the return of part of their common border since then. 
  Although <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> had been invited to participate as an 
observer in other international forums on <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>, this 
was the first time it had been invited to participate in the <LOCATION>San 
Jose Summit</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-56829 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat090_g_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-090 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Ministry Proposes Referendum on Belize </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Foreign Ministry Proposes Referendum on Belize </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA0905005494 Guatemala City PRENSA LIBRE in Spanish 6 May 94 
p 3 </F>

<F P=103> PA0905005494 </F>
<F P=104>  Guatemala City PRENSA LIBRE </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Yesterday, in an appearance before the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> of 
the <LOCATION>Republic</LOCATION>, Foreign Relations Minister <PERSON>Maritza Ruiz de Vielman</PERSON> 
confirmed that <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> still maintains its territorial claims 
over <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and plans to allow the people to voice their opinion 
on the issue by means of a referendum. 
  During a meeting with the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Relations Committee</ORGANIZATION>, the 
minister explained that no unexpected readjustments to the 
guidelines of the dispute with the Belizean people are expected 
to take place during her term as minister and that they are 
prepared to resort to any legal means in order to resolve the 
dispute. 
  As established by the Constitution, after the <LOCATION>Belize Council</LOCATION> 
has been established, one of the points to be put on its agenda 
will be to request the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Electoral Tribunal</ORGANIZATION> to call the 
Guatemalan people to a referendum so they may voice their 
opinion on the issue. 
  Even though the minister indicated that the <ORGANIZATION>Belize Council</ORGANIZATION> 
will be directly responsible for negotiating the territorial 
dispute, she also explained that at any given moment it could 
expressed interest in the problem. 
  In addition, the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> will be made aware of the 
objectives sought by the proviso submitted a few months ago. 
  With respect to the extradition of [former President] <PERSON>Jorge 
Serrano Elias</PERSON>, the minister indicated that the court responsible 
for the case has not yet forwarded any [extradition] request to 
the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. 
<H5>  <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> Council To Be Established in 10 Days </H5>
  The foreign minister stated that the <ORGANIZATION>Belize Council</ORGANIZATION> will be 
established in no less than 10 days. She also abstained from 
identifying the candidates selected to become members of the 
aforementioned council and indicated that there are still talks 
to be held with some of them in order to confirm their 
disposition to participate. 
  According to the foreign minister, a preliminary list of 
candidates has already been discussed with President <PERSON>Ramiro de 
Leon Carpio</PERSON>, and, if there are no objections, she would proceed 
to forward invitations to the citizens named as possible council 
members. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-56815 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat198_g_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-198 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Ministry Proposes Referendum on Belize </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Foreign Ministry Proposes Referendum on Belize </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA0905005494 Guatemala City PRENSA LIBRE in Spanish 6 May 94 
p 3 </F>

<F P=103> PA0905005494 </F>
<F P=104>  Guatemala City PRENSA LIBRE </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Yesterday, in an appearance before the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> of 
the <LOCATION>Republic</LOCATION>, Foreign Relations Minister <PERSON>Maritza Ruiz de Vielman</PERSON> 
confirmed that <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> still maintains its territorial claims 
over <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and plans to allow the people to voice their opinion 
on the issue by means of a referendum. 
  During a meeting with the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Relations Committee</ORGANIZATION>, the 
minister explained that no unexpected readjustments to the 
guidelines of the dispute with the Belizean people are expected 
to take place during her term as minister and that they are 
prepared to resort to any legal means in order to resolve the 
dispute. 
  As established by the Constitution, after the <LOCATION>Belize Council</LOCATION> 
has been established, one of the points to be put on its agenda 
will be to request the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Electoral Tribunal</ORGANIZATION> to call the 
Guatemalan people to a referendum so they may voice their 
opinion on the issue. 
  Even though the minister indicated that the <ORGANIZATION>Belize Council</ORGANIZATION> 
will be directly responsible for negotiating the territorial 
dispute, she also explained that at any given moment it could 
expressed interest in the problem. 
  In addition, the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> will be made aware of the 
objectives sought by the proviso submitted a few months ago. 
  With respect to the extradition of [former President] <PERSON>Jorge 
Serrano Elias</PERSON>, the minister indicated that the court responsible 
for the case has not yet forwarded any [extradition] request to 
the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. 
<H5>  <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> Council To Be Established in 10 Days </H5>
  The foreign minister stated that the <ORGANIZATION>Belize Council</ORGANIZATION> will be 
established in no less than 10 days. She also abstained from 
identifying the candidates selected to become members of the 
aforementioned council and indicated that there are still talks 
to be held with some of them in order to confirm their 
disposition to participate. 
  According to the foreign minister, a preliminary list of 
candidates has already been discussed with President <PERSON>Ramiro de 
Leon Carpio</PERSON>, and, if there are no objections, she would proceed 
to forward invitations to the citizens named as possible council 
members. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-5364</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CK0B0AA4FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921127
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 NOV 92 / Guatemala-Belize accord backed
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>GUATEMALA</LOCATION>'S <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> has cleared the way for the resolution of a
130-year-old territorial dispute with <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, in which <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>
was claiming the former British colony with which it has a common border,
writes <PERSON>Canute James</PERSON>.
Guatemalan legislators have ratified a recent ruling by a constitutional
court supporting the decision of President <PERSON>Jorge Serrano</PERSON> to recognise
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s political independence and to establish diplomatic ties between the
two countries.
The decision by the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is likely to end the dispute, although a
referendum must be held in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> before the treaty is ratified.
Repeated indications over the past two decades that the Guatemalan military
might invade <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> in pursuit of their territorial claim led to the
stationing of a 1,500-member British garrison in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>.
However, the 78-24 vote by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is likely to anger sections of the
Guatemalan military and political right.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 5
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-5611</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFCCOABGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930603
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 JUN 93 / Belize PM calls snap general election
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
MR <PERSON>George Price</PERSON>, prime minister of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, has called a general election for
<DATE>June 30</DATE>, 15 months before it was constitutionally due.
The announcement came a few hours after the resignation of <PERSON>Mr Jorge Serrano</PERSON>
as president of neighbouring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>. He and <PERSON>Mr Price</PERSON> had reached an
accord to end <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s 130-year-old territorial claim on the former
British colony in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>.
The Belizean opposition is claiming that the government has no plans to
defend the country against any invasion by <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> announced last month that it is to withdraw its 1,400-strong
garrison in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. British troops had been stationed there to deter
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> from military action to pursue its claim.
Mr <ORGANIZATION>Price's People's United</ORGANIZATION> party has a comfortable parliamentary majority,
and the election is expected to keep it in power at the expense of the main
opposition <ORGANIZATION>United Democratic</ORGANIZATION> party.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BZZ  Belize, Central America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9199 General Government, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-1582</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CIVBVAEGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920922
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 SEP 92 / Survey of Belize (6): Political bridge - Foreign relations
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
VISITORS arriving at the international airport see an immediate and graphic
illustration of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s relations with its neighbours.
On either side of the runway and around the airport are camouflage netting,
anti-aircraft guns, helicopters and fighter aircraft ready for action.
The trappings of the British military garrison in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, they represent a
passing phase in the country's foreign policy. The garrison's purpose had
been to deter aggression by <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> which had threatened to invade in
pursuit of a 130-year-old territorial claim.
Now, however, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> are heading towards a diplomatic solution
of their differences. <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is also hoping to make friends of other Central
American countries which had backed <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s claim. The role of the
British troops will then change: they are likely to stay for training
purposes.
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is both <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and Central American. It sits between two regions
which have been economically, politically and culturally poles apart.
Once the dispute with <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> is settled, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> should be able to act as
an economic and political bridge between its immediate neighbours and the
archipelago to the east.
It is a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Caribbean Economic Community</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Caricom</ORGANIZATION>) which is
struggling to create a customs union, a monetary union and a common market.
It shares with its antillean neighbours many of the economic difficulties
and uncertainties of small economies. <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> might even become involved in
other efforts at economic integration, such as the emerging common market in
<LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr George Price</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s prime minister, and his predecessor in office, <PERSON>Mr
Manuel Esquivel</PERSON>, have attended summits of the <ORGANIZATION>Caribbean Community</ORGANIZATION>. Recently,
<PERSON>Mr Price</PERSON> was invited to observe summits of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s Latin neighbours.
'<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is now is a position to do more in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> because we have
minister. 'There have been two meetings of <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and Central American
ministers to discuss bananas. <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> has also attended two Central American
summits.'
The <ORGANIZATION>West Indian Commission</ORGANIZATION>, which has been studying ways of increasing the
level of integration of Caribbean economies, also concluded that <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> can
play a pivotal role in bridging the gap between the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Central
America</LOCATION>.
'A further objective of <ORGANIZATION>Caricom</ORGANIZATION> policy must be the exploration of possible
levels of economic relationships with the Central American countries,' the
<ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> concludes. 'Here, in fact, are the makings of a system of
competition between the two sub-groupings of the <LOCATION>Caribbean Basin</LOCATION>  .. in
industrial and agricultural exports.'
It says that thanks to its location and its political inclinations <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is
naturally at the forefront of co-operation between the two regions. But <PERSON>Mr
Esquivel</PERSON> feels that too much is being made of the role which <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> can play
in bringing the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> closer together.
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, he says, cannot be an effective bridge between the two regions
because it has no influence in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>. 'Because of the Guatemalan
claim we have been ostracised by <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> and we have kept out of
Central American affairs, so we cannot claim any influence in <LOCATION>Central
America</LOCATION>,' he concludes.
'Our political and economic influence in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> is minimal as well
because of our geography. Rather than being a bridge, we are desperately
trying to straddle two regions to keep our balance.' There is one very real
and seemingly intractable problem which divides the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> islands and
<LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>, and which could determine the value of a friendship with
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>.
The creation of a single European market in <DATE>January</DATE> has put a question mark
over the preferential market for bananas which <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> islands
and other developing countries have in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> is struggling with a
formula which satisfies the desires of the traditional suppliers, such as
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, to maintain preferential access, while meeting the demands of the
tendency towards freer international trade, as being demanded by Latin
American producers, including <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s immediate neighbours.
The disagreement threatens to abort any hopes of meaningful co-operation
between the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>. Mr Price has attempted to close
the gap on bananas through meetings of government officials and ministers
from the two regions.
Inevitably, there has been effective technical co-operation between <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>
and its Central American neighbours. Matters such as dealing with <LOCATION>Latin
America</LOCATION>'s cholera epidemic, a common approach to the problems of refugees in
the region, and restoration and preservation of Amercan Indian artefacts,
have provided ground for <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s integration into the region in the wake of
better relations with <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Ismael Garcia</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s ambassador to <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>, has concluded that
there is now an opportunity for meaningful co-operation in trade and
agriculture. <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> once gained substantially from transhipment of exports
and imports for southern <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
'<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> could prosper from the fact that it is English-speaking and could be
an entrepot such as <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> was,' says <PERSON>Mr Geoffrey Hart</PERSON>, the manager of
<ORGANIZATION>Barclays Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. 'This country could, for example, warehouse
material for distribution to <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>. There are opportunities for
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> to be <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s gateway to <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Area</ORGANIZATION>.'
The next stage in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s efforts at being a good neighbour, however, will
be determined by others. The Guatemalan government's proposals for resolving
the territorial dispute are being contested in a constitutional court. Much
hangs on the court's decision. <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s relations with its Central American
neighbours still hinge on its ties with <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 33
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-10764 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat049_g_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-049 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  14 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Ministry Reasserts Territorial Claim on Belize </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA1203021994 Panama City ACAN in Spanish 2241 GMT 11 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA1203021994 </F>
<F P=104>  Panama City ACAN </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION>, 11 Mar (ACAN-EFE) -- Today, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> asserted in a letter to <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> Secretary 
General Butrus Butrus-Ghali that the country has signed no 
agreement establishing borders with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, and it adds that 
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> maintains a territorial claim on the former British 
colony. 
  Foreign Minister <PERSON>Marithza Ruiz de Vielman</PERSON> asked the <ORGANIZATION>United 
Nations</ORGANIZATION> to inform its member states about the <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan 
Government</ORGANIZATION>'s territorial claim, which includes an area of land 
in Belizean territory and maritime areas on the <LOCATION>Caribbean Ocean</LOCATION>. 
Ruiz de <PERSON>Vielman</PERSON> said the joint declaration signed by the two 
states on 31 <DATE>July 1992</DATE> does not recognize the definition of 
their territorial and maritime limits. She recalled that 
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> recognized <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> as an independent state in <DATE>September 
1992</DATE> without relinquishing its claim, which dates back 150 years. 
  The diplomat's letter to <PERSON>Ghali</PERSON> emphasized that the 
government 
respects the free determination of nations and believes the 
settlement of controversies between states should be reached 
through peaceful means. She added that the <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Government</ORGANIZATION> 
is prepared to continue direct discussions with the former 
British colony to reach a definite solution to the dispute. 
  "<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> formally rejects anything which violates its 
sovereignty, continental shelf, control of its territorial seas, 
or exclusive economic zone, both those defined in the past and 
those which may result when the dispute is settled," the text 
added. The document said <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s territorial sea is 12 
maritime miles (more than 18 km) wide. 
  "Until the dispute is settled, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> cannot accept nor 
does it accept boundaries that are equidistant to states, 
adjacent coasts, or coasts that face each other if they 
negatively affect its sovereign right to 12 maritime miles," she 
emphasized. Ruiz said the government is willing to adopt control 
measures to prevent the violation of its laws and its customs, 
immigration, and health regulations. 
  She confirmed that the country's economic zone comprises an 
area beyond its territorial sea and adjacent zones, which extend 
200 maritime miles beyond the boundaries used to measure the 
width of its territorial sea. Also, the continental shelf 
extends 200 miles with exclusive sovereignty rights to exploit 
its natural resources, she said. 
  She emphasized that <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> will not recognize the 
charters 
or lists of geographic coordinates prepared by <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> until they 
reach a definite agreement that is satisfactory to the two 
parties. The foreign minister asked the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> to inform 
its member states about <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s position on <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-16764</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DGBCVAA4FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930702
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 JUL 93 / Government loses close election in Belize
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>MR Manuel Esquivel</PERSON>, a 53-year-old businessman, is to be sworn in by the
weekend as prime minister of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, following a narrow victory by his
<ORGANIZATION>United Democratic</ORGANIZATION> party in the general election on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
Preliminary results yesterday gave the <ORGANIZATION>UDP</ORGANIZATION> 15 of the 29 seats in the Central
American state's assembly, with 13 for the <ORGANIZATION>People's United</ORGANIZATION> party of <PERSON>Mr
George Price</PERSON>, the long-serving prime minister. A recount was under way in
one constituency.
The result suggests a miscalculation by <PERSON>Mr Price</PERSON>, who called the election 15
months before it was due. He had hoped to be returned to office on the basis
of steady economic growth in the former British colony. Also, the <ORGANIZATION>PUP</ORGANIZATION> had
done well in recent by-elections.
In the month-long campaign, however, <PERSON>Mr Esquivel</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>UDP</ORGANIZATION> closed the gap,
arguing that <PERSON>Mr Price</PERSON>'s administration was corrupt. He charged the
government with having given Belizean citizenship and voting rights to
thousands of refugees from neighbouring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>El
Salvador</ORGANIZATION>,in a bid to win the election.
<PERSON>Mr Esquivel</PERSON> also proposed free education, from primary school to university,
as well as income tax concessions.
The PUP's loss has raised questions over the political future of <PERSON>Mr Price</PERSON>,
who has dominated the politics of the country of 200,000 people for 40
years, and has been its political leader for all but five years since <DATE>1954</DATE>.
If Mr Price steps down as PUP leader, he is likely to be succeeded by <PERSON>Mr
Said Musa</PERSON>, foreign minister, or <PERSON>Mr Florencio Marn</PERSON>, a former deputy prime
minister.
<PERSON>Mr Esquivel</PERSON>, who was prime minister in <DATE>1984-1989</DATE>, is not expected to bring
any great political changes to Belizean domestic affairs.
During the campaign, however, he accused the Price administration of making
too many concessions to <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> in an effort by the government to bury for
good a 130-year-old Guatemalan territorial claim on <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, which <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>
recently declared that it had relinquished.
The opposition leader suggested the suspension of legislation which grants
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> access to the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> through Belizean territory.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BZZ   Belize, Central America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9199 General Government, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-8758</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DERDAAAXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930518
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  18 MAY 93 / UK sparks worries in Belize
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE opposition in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> has accused the government of having no alternative
plans for the country's defence after British troops leave. Local economists
are also expressing concern about the impact of the pull-out, announced by
the British government last week.
The garrison of 1,400 troops was stationed in the central American country
to deter neighbouring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, which threatened many times to invade the
former British colony in pursuit of a 130-year-old territorial claim. The
overall responsibility for defence will pass to the 600-strong <ORGANIZATION>Belize
Defence Force</ORGANIZATION>.
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> said it was closing the garrison, but would leave 150 soldiers in
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and use the facilities for training. The move follows agreements
between <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> in the past two years which have cleared the
way for a diplomatic end to the dispute.
The contingent is a significant contributor to the <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> economy.
Maintaining the garrison in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> costs the British government about
Dollars 40m (Pounds 26m) a year. Economists say the country earns Dollars
35m a year (about a fifth of the country's gross domestic product) from the
presence of the garrison.
The government denied it was unprepared for the British decision.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BZZ  Belize, Central America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9711 National Security.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-56830 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat090_g_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-090 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Belizean Envoy Cited on Willingness To Negotiate </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Belizean Envoy Cited on Willingness To Negotiate </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA0905231794 Guatemala City SIGLO VEINTIUNO in Spanish 6 May 
94 p 5 </F>

<F P=103> PA0905231794 </F>
<F P=104>  Guatemala City SIGLO VEINTIUNO </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Passages in italics as published] </F>
  [Text] <PERSON>Henry W. Anderson</PERSON>, Belizean ambassador to <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, 
yesterday said his government is prepared to begin negotiations 
on the territorial dispute with <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>; adding that a 
commission has been created for this purpose and only the final 
details must be settled. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Government</ORGANIZATION> has recognized <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s 
independence; therefore, we have accepted the fact that a border 
dispute prevails between the two countries, a situation we hope 
will be handled cordially, he said. Regarding the 
organization of a <ORGANIZATION>Belizean Council</ORGANIZATION>, the ambassador said this is 
considered positive because it is a sign the <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan 
Government</ORGANIZATION> is prepared to begin negotiations to settle the 
dispute. 
  <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is interested in establishing trade, cultural, 
and sports relations, not only with <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> but with all of 
<LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>; and that is one of the reasons that prompt us 
to be prepared to negotiate what is negotiable, <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> 
said. The ambassador also said he cannot release the names of 
the persons who make up the Belizean commission that will 
participate in the negotiations, because he does not have them. 
  He also referred to the role played by the media in the 
case, 
which is important, to establish the objective atmosphere 
necessary to settle relations between the States of <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. The diplomat added that <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s recognition as an 
independent state by the media, and the illustration of this on 
the region's maps, will represent a great step forward. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-56816 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat198_g_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-198 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Belizean Envoy Cited on Willingness To Negotiate </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Belizean Envoy Cited on Willingness To Negotiate </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA0905231794 Guatemala City SIGLO VEINTIUNO in Spanish 6 May 
94 p 5 </F>

<F P=103> PA0905231794 </F>
<F P=104>  Guatemala City SIGLO VEINTIUNO </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Passages in italics as published] </F>
  [Text] <PERSON>Henry W. Anderson</PERSON>, Belizean ambassador to <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, 
yesterday said his government is prepared to begin negotiations 
on the territorial dispute with <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>; adding that a 
commission has been created for this purpose and only the final 
details must be settled. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan Government</ORGANIZATION> has recognized <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s 
independence; therefore, we have accepted the fact that a border 
dispute prevails between the two countries, a situation we hope 
will be handled cordially, he said. Regarding the 
organization of a <ORGANIZATION>Belizean Council</ORGANIZATION>, the ambassador said this is 
considered positive because it is a sign the <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan 
Government</ORGANIZATION> is prepared to begin negotiations to settle the 
dispute. 
  <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is interested in establishing trade, cultural, 
and sports relations, not only with <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> but with all of 
<LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>; and that is one of the reasons that prompt us 
to be prepared to negotiate what is negotiable, <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> 
said. The ambassador also said he cannot release the names of 
the persons who make up the Belizean commission that will 
participate in the negotiations, because he does not have them. 
  He also referred to the role played by the media in the 
case, 
which is important, to establish the objective atmosphere 
necessary to settle relations between the States of <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. The diplomat added that <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s recognition as an 
independent state by the media, and the illustration of this on 
the region's maps, will represent a great step forward. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-35090 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat125_g_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-125 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   De Leon Cited on Relocation of Settlers in Belize </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    De Leon Cited on Relocation of Settlers in Belize </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2906034694 Guatemala City LA REPUBLICA in Spanish 25 Jun 
94 p 3 </F>

<F P=103> PA2906034694 </F>
<F P=104>  Guatemala City LA REPUBLICA </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] President <PERSON>Ramiro de Leon Carpio</PERSON> yesterday 
acknowledged that there are Guatemalan settlers residing in 
Belizean territory; however, he explained that no pressure has 
ever been exerted on the peasants by <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> to get them to leave 
the area. Land is being sought to transfer them into those 
protected areas, he added. [sentence as published] 
  De <PERSON>Leon Carpio</PERSON> explained that his government's plan is to 
have the families living in the <LOCATION>Chiquibul</LOCATION> region leave the area, 
because it is a nature reserve. He added that studies are being 
conducted with the authorities of the <ORGANIZATION>National Institute of 
Agrarian Reform</ORGANIZATION> (INTA) to transfer these people to an area that 
meets their basic living requirements. 
  Nevertheless, he reiterated that Belizean troops are not 
driving these people out, as had previously been reported. He 
also said there is no final deadline for the withdrawal of the 
settlers. 
  "The government is taking all necessary measures for those 
peasants to settle in lands that will enable them to raise their 
crops. It is necessary for them to withdraw from <LOCATION>Chiquibul</LOCATION>, 
because this is a national park. But certainly, it is not 
because <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is pressuring them to leave," De <PERSON>Leon Carpio</PERSON> 
noted. 
  In light of the situation, <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman 
<PERSON>Antonio 
Monzon</PERSON> assured that the Guatemalans will be transferred in 
<DATE>September</DATE> to the Dolores municipality in <LOCATION>Peten</LOCATION>, located several 
kilometers from where they are currently settled. He explained 
that the trip will be sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>INTA</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Peten Land 
Committee</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>National Fund for Peace</ORGANIZATION>. 
  This issue caused several reactions last week when <PERSON>Carlos 
Asturias</PERSON>, former governor of the northern department of <LOCATION>Peten</LOCATION>, 
disclosed that Belizean troops had set a 25 <DATE>June</DATE> deadline for 
the settlers to withdraw from the area. 
  Asturias recently said the report had been received by a 
parish priest in the region, explaining that a group of soldiers 
who patrol the border area "are threatening them constantly." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-33849 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat113_g_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-113 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   President Creates Council on Belizean Issue </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    President Creates Council on Belizean Issue </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1006171094 Guatemala City PRENSA LIBRE in Spanish 8 Jun 94 
p 3 </F>

<F P=103> PA1006171094 </F>
<F P=104>  Guatemala City PRENSA LIBRE </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] The <ORGANIZATION>National Council</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> [<ORGANIZATION>Consejo Nacional</ORGANIZATION> de 
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>], <ORGANIZATION>CNB</ORGANIZATION>, was formally constituted yesterday after President 
<PERSON>Ramiro de Leon Carpio</PERSON> signed a decree creating this consultative 
and advisory organization under the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Foreign Minister <PERSON>Maritza Ruiz de Vielman</PERSON> will chair the <ORGANIZATION>CNB</ORGANIZATION>, 
and its members are: Fernando Andrade Diaz-Duran, <PERSON>Roberto 
Bermejo Gonzalez</PERSON>, <PERSON>Eduardo Castillo Carriola</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edwin Fernando 
Guzman Ovalle</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alberto Herrarte Gonzalez</PERSON>, <PERSON>Roberto Herrera 
Ibarguen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Carlos Larios Ochaita</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jorge Lujan Munoz</PERSON>, <PERSON>Oscar 
Clemente Marroquin Godoy</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gabriel Orellana Rojas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jorge Skinner 
Klee</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Francisco Villaran Kramer</PERSON>. These 12 individuals will 
be sworn in shortly. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>CNB</ORGANIZATION> was created by government Decree 259-94 that asserts 
that the territorial difference with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and the search for a 
solution that conforms to the Constitution's precepts is a 
matter of national interest. The purpose is to modernize and 
reorganize the <ORGANIZATION>CNB</ORGANIZATION> as a study, planning, consultative, and 
advisory office of the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> for everything related 
to the territorial disagreement with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. 
  According to the decree, the <ORGANIZATION>CNB</ORGANIZATION> will be authorized to 
appoint permanent or temporary commissions or sub-commissions as 
well as take the necessary measures to regulate their work. The 
decree will take effect when it is published in the official 
daily. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-51724 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat016__a94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-016-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Belize </F>
<H3> <TI>   Military Strengthened Against Potential Guatemalan Threat </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA2201000194 Havana PRENSA LATINA in Spanish 1431 GMT 20 Jan 
94--FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> PA2201000194 </F>
<F P=104>  Havana PRENSA LATINA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>, 20 Jan (PL) -- The Belizean Armed 
Forces this year allotted <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> to strengthen its military 
so it will be prepared to defend national sovereignty, 
government sources disclosed today. 
  This announcement is related to a statement made last 
<DATE>November</DATE> by Prime Minister <PERSON>Manuel Esquivel</PERSON>, who said that the 
imminent withdrawal of British troops from this state would 
probably encourage its Guatemalan neighbors to reclaim this 
territory, a former colony of the <ORGANIZATION>United Kingdom</ORGANIZATION> until <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
  According to reports received in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, spokesmen for the 
<ORGANIZATION>Belizean Government</ORGANIZATION> assured that the government is planning to 
gradually increase its troops in response to the withdrawal of 
the British, who defended the country until <DATE>last 31 December</DATE>. 
  The withdrawal of 1,200 men and combat equipment, including 
several squadrons of planes of various models, practically 
concluded on 1 <DATE>January 1994</DATE>. 
  According to official data, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> has 1,000 armed men, 
while 
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> has an army of 30,000 soldiers. 
  A representative of the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> said the objective was 
to add 1,500 men in <DATE>1994</DATE> and attract more recruits in the 
following years, depending on the state budget, while making 
structural changes in the corps. 
  Diplomatic sources in <LOCATION>Belmopan</LOCATION> said the internal situation 
was calm, even though <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> has on previous occasions tried 
to annex the territory. 
  <PERSON>Julio Roberto Herrera</PERSON>, Guatemalan vice consul in the 
neighboring Mexican city of <LOCATION>Chetumal</LOCATION> (southern state of <ORGANIZATION>Quintana 
Roo</ORGANIZATION>), said that from the times of the administration of <PERSON>Jorge 
Serrano Elias</PERSON>, his country has ruled out a military intervention 
in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. 
  After pointing out that <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> has other priorities, the 
diplomat said: "We respect the sovereignty of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, and even 
though we claimed that territory at one time, it doesn't mean we 
are planning an invasion." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-218</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DGABBABEFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930630
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 JUN 93 / Security the key to Belize poll
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>BELIZE</LOCATION> holds a general election today with the ruling party trying to play
down concerns that the country's security is threatened by political
uncertainty in neighbouring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and a planned pull-out by British
forces.
The election was called by the prime minister, <PERSON>Mr George Price</PERSON>, 15 months
before it was constitutionally due. The election follows the removal from
office of Guatemalan president <PERSON>Mr Jorge Serrano</PERSON>, with whom <PERSON>Mr Price</PERSON> had
reached an accord - yet to be ratified - ending the 130-year-old Guatemalan
claim on <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>.
In a bid to calm fears over <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s attitude to the agreement, <PERSON>Mr
Antonio Castellanos</PERSON>, ambassador to <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, issued a statement at the weekend
saying that 'the new Guatemalan government will respect and honour all
international agreements.'
Mr <ORGANIZATION>Price's People's United Party</ORGANIZATION> is expected to retain a majority in the
assembly, but to be closely challenged by main opposition <ORGANIZATION>United Democratic
Party</ORGANIZATION> led by <PERSON>Mr Manuel Esquivel</PERSON>. The opposition accuses the government of
having no plans to defend the country following <DATE>last month</DATE>'s British
decision to withdraw a 1,400-strong garrison.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BZZ  Belize, Central America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9199 General Government, NEC.
    P8651 Political Organizations.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-34572 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat120_g_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-120 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> CENTRAL AMERICA </F>
<F P=101> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Council on Belize To Study Border Dispute </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Council on Belize To Study Border Dispute </PHRASE></F></HT>

1900 GMT 21 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=104>  Guatemala City Teleonce Television </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "Telepress" newscast] </F>
  [Text] The <ORGANIZATION>National Council</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, which will be in 
charge of conducting a general and thorough evaluation of the 
dispute over that territory, was officially installed today. 
  An agreement to update and reorganize the <ORGANIZATION>National Council</ORGANIZATION> 
on 
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> specifies that the entity will do studies and planning 
and will advise the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> on all matters related to 
the territorial dispute with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Council</ORGANIZATION> will be headed by Foreign Minister <PERSON>Gladys 
Maritza 
Ruiz de Vielman</PERSON> and will be made up of the following persons, 
who will work without compensation: <PERSON>Fernando Andrade Diaz 
Duran</PERSON>, <PERSON>Roberto Bermejo Gonzalez</PERSON>, <PERSON>Eduardo Castillo Arriola</PERSON>, <PERSON>Erwin 
Fernando Guzman Ovalle</PERSON>, (<PERSON>Alberto Errarte Gonzalez</PERSON>), <PERSON>Roberto 
Herrera Ibarguen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Carlos Larios Ochaita</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jorge Lujan Munoz</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Oscar Clemente Marroquin Godoy</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gabriel Orellana Rojas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mario 
Quinonez Amezquita</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jorge Skinner Klee</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Francisco Villagran 
Kramer</PERSON>. 
  The 8 <DATE>June</DATE> agreement states that the territorial dispute 
with 
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and the search for a solution within the framework of the 
Constitution and the principles of international law are matters 
of national interest. The document recognizes the 
appropriateness of the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> receiving the advice of 
qualified citizens who, based on their knowledge and 
capabilities, can help formulate an adequate policy to resolve 
the territorial dispute with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890903-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-03-89 2049EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Belize     09-03 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Belize,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>Belize Holding National Elections Monday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELIZE CITY, Belize (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Manuel Esquivel</PERSON> and
former leader <PERSON>George Price</PERSON> conducted a flurry of campagining on the
eve of the nation's general elections <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   All campaigning, including television and radio commercials,
officially ended at <TIME>midnight</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> _ seven hours before the polls
open for 11 hours.
   Voters will cast ballots for the 28 seats in the lower house of
the legislature and the party that wins the most seats will name the
prime minister. Terms of office are for five years.
   Esquivel, of the conservative <ORGANIZATION>United Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>, said
during the campaign that his administration brought economic
recovery to <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and efficient government.
   Price, leader of the centrist People's <ORGANIZATION>United Party</ORGANIZATION>, was defeated
by <PERSON>Esquivel</PERSON> in the <DATE>1984</DATE> election. His campaign slogan was
``Belizeans first,'' and he accused <PERSON>Esquivel</PERSON> of giving too much to
foreigners to gain investments and tourism.
   Price was the top Belizean official when the country was a
self-governing British colony before it became independent in <DATE>1981</DATE>.
   No public opinion polls were taken but political observers said
they belived <PERSON>Esquivel</PERSON> held a slight edge.
   His party holds 21 seats in the lower house and the <ORGANIZATION>United
Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> the remaining seven.
   Elections officials say 82,589 of the country's 160,000 residents
are eligible to vote.
   Initial results are expected about <TIME>midnight</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   In his criticism of alleged foreign influence, Price attacked a
program that allows foreigners to purchase <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> bonds and then
apply for citizenship. If the applicants don't qualify for
citizenship they can redeem the bonds but if they do they can become
citizens and the bond is to be repaid without interest in 10 years.
   The plan is aimed mainly at residents of <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>, a British
colony that is to revert to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in <DATE>1997</DATE>. Many <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> residents
are expected to flee the colony rather than accept control by
communist <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>.
   Esquivel has said that during the past five years prices for
sugar, fruits and other major exports have been stable and foreign
investments and tourism have doubled.
   <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> has a bicameral legislature with an elected <ORGANIZATION>House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION> and appointed <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. The house determines which
party will form a new government.
   <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, smaller than <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, is on the Central American
mainland but maintains closer cultural ties with other
English-speaking former British colonies in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> than with
its Spanish-speaking neighbors.
   Neighboring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> maintains a territorial claim against
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, formerly British <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>, and British troops are stationed
in the country in case of hostilities with <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-10200 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat042_g_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-042 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Ombudsman Requests Protection on Belize Border </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0203212794 Guatemala City PRENSA LIBRE in Spanish 1 Mar 94 
p 2 </F>

<F P=103> PA0203212794 </F>
<F P=104>  Guatemala City PRENSA LIBRE </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] Human Rights Ombudsman <PERSON>Dr. Jorge Mario Garcia 
Laguardia</PERSON> requested the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s and the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>'s 
intervention to protect the nation's territorial integrity and 
the lives of Guatemalans settled along the Belizean border. 
During his visit to the region, the ombudsman personally 
learned about the threats that Belizean soldiers issued against 
35 families who live at the border town of <LOCATION>Rio Blanco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Dolores</LOCATION>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Peten Department</ORGANIZATION>. The high-ranking official met with peasants 
of the aforementioned town and the mayor of Dolores who gave a 
detailed account of the threats issued by the Belizean military. 
  <PERSON>Sebastian Tux</PERSON>, a peasant, asked the ombudsman to clearly 
demarcate the boundary with <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, because last year Belizean 
soldiers also forced them to abandon their land, where they left 
behind a crop of approximately 2,500 quintals of beans and 2,000 
quintals of corn. He added: If necessary we, the peasants, 
offer our labor to build a boundary along the border. We have 
looked for another place to relocate, but have not found one. 
He said they would rather stay than emigrate from the lands 
they have tilled for many years. 
  Moreover, Ombudsman <PERSON>Garcia Laguardia</PERSON> said it all began when 
former President <PERSON>Jorge Serrano</PERSON> accepted <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s independence 
unconstitutional act that would have never been accepted by the 
Guatemalans if a referendum had been held on the issue. 
  However, he added, two key institutions have to intervene: 
the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. Besides, the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> 
are duty bound to maintain strict control of the border, which 
it has apparently neglected; and the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> has to 
mediate with the <ORGANIZATION>Belizean Government</ORGANIZATION> through diplomatic channels 
to prevent these actions. Referring to this, he asked the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> 
to permanently protect the border zone and guarantee Guatemalan 
rights; and he asked the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> to mediate 
diplomatically to put an end to hostilities and provide 
guarantees to the Guatemalan citizens, so they may live in their 
country and exercise their rights. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-205</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EC4C0ABDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940331
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  31 MAR 94 / Fears revive in Belize
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> says neighbouring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> has revived its claim to Belizean
territory, despite an interim agreement reached two years ago between the
two Central American countries, <PERSON>Canute James</PERSON> reports from <LOCATION>Kingston</LOCATION>.
The Belizeans say <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s 130-year-old claim was revived in a letter
sent this month by the government to <PERSON>Mr Boutros Boutros Ghali</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION>
secretary general, saying that an end to <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s claim on the former
British colony would come only with a final treaty.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BZZ  Belize, Central America.
    GTZ  Guatemala, Central America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 5
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-9929 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat039_g_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-039 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Rejects Belizean `Ultimatum' to Border Residents </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA2702223594 Panama City ACAN in Spanish 1823 GMT 27 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA2702223594 </F>
<F P=104>  Panama City ACAN </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION>, 27 Feb (ACAN-EFE) -- The Guatemalan 
Government and <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> today rejected the "ultimatum" given by the 
Belizean authorities to 18 Guatemalan families who have been 
ordered to withdraw from lands they are occupying. 
  According to the <ORGANIZATION>Belizean Embassy</ORGANIZATION>, the peasants, who have 
established themselves in the "Chiquibul" national park, have 
been given 15 days to clear the area with a deadline that 
expires on 10 <DATE>March</DATE>. 
  Guatemalan Foreign Minister <PERSON>Maritza Ruiz</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> does 
not acknowledge the <ORGANIZATION>Belizean Government</ORGANIZATION>'s authority to give 
alleged "ultimatums" to Guatemalan families living in border 
areas. 
  Guatemalan Defense Minister General <PERSON>Mario Rene Enriquez</PERSON> 
asserted that the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> will not tolerate any "meddling" on 
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s part in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s national sovereignty, much less the 
"intimidation" of Guatemalan citizens. 
  Enriquez added that the Belizean authorities are "being 
unreasonable" and that they cannot set deadlines for families to 
abandon the area in question because <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> still disputes 
ownership of that territory. 
  <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> gained its independence from <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> in 
<DATE>September 1981</DATE>, and the administration of deposed Guatemalan 
President <PERSON>Jorge Serrano</PERSON> (1991-1993) recognized it as a state. 
However, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> has maintained its claim on the region for 
over a century and a half. 
  The defense minister said the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> is prepared to support 
the 
Guatemalan families living in the "Chiquibul" national park, 
where they have built their homes. Enriquez dismissed the 
possibility of clashes with Belizean soldiers. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-1586</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CIVBVAECFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920922
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 SEP 92 / Survey of Belize (3): A dominating personality - Politics
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By STEPHEN FIDLER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
FOR MORE than 40 years, the politics of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> has been dominated by one man
and one party. <PERSON>Mr George Price</PERSON> helped to form the <ORGANIZATION>People's United Party</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1949</DATE>. This move - a response to the devaluation of the British <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>
dollar which hit the pockets of Belizeans - established an anti-colonialist
party which the British originally viewed with suspicion.
This suspicion lifted over the next 15 years, and <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> would undoubtedly
have claimed full independence in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> were it not for the Guatemalan
claim over <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1964</DATE>, the country became self-governing, except for
foreign policy, defence and internal security. Full independence was gained
on <DATE>September 21, 1981</DATE>.
The PUP won the six general elections held from <DATE>1954</DATE> to <DATE>1979</DATE>, losing to the
opposition <ORGANIZATION>United Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>. Against the odds, it narrowly
won the <DATE>1989</DATE> general election - with a narrow 15-13 majority in the <ORGANIZATION>House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION>. Its majority was strengthened after one opposition deputy
switched to the government benches.
Unmarried, austere and a devout Catholic, <PERSON>Mr Price</PERSON>, 73, is seen as likely to
fight the next election, which must be held by <DATE>1994</DATE>. The prime minister, the
last of the generation of post-independence commonwealth leaders, has no
obvious successor within the party. Those seen as most likely to succeed him
are <PERSON>Mr Said Musa</PERSON>, foreign minister, and <PERSON>Mr Florencio Marin</PERSON>.
Although the party rhetoric would suggest otherwise, the policies of the two
main parties have proved hard to distinguish. Although ostensibly more
populist than the pro-market <ORGANIZATION>UDP</ORGANIZATION>, the PUP in government has followed similar
policies in favour of privatisation and continued investment.
This has calmed the disquiet among investors following the <DATE>1989</DATE> election
which the <ORGANIZATION>PUP</ORGANIZATION> won by appealing to nationalist sentiment with the slogan
'Belizeans first' and charges that the <ORGANIZATION>UDP</ORGANIZATION> had allowed foreign speculators
to dominate the economy. The <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> embassy's assessment of the investment
climate in the country remains 'excellent'.
<PERSON>Mr Manuel Esquivel</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>UDP</ORGANIZATION> leader and former prime minister, agrees the
'PUP were more effective in fighting the election than we were'.
Since the election the opposition has split over the aimed-for settlement
with <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, which <PERSON>Mr Esquivel</PERSON>'s party has supported. A faction, led by
<PERSON>Mr Philip Goldson</PERSON>, a respected senior politician, has ceded from the <ORGANIZATION>UDP</ORGANIZATION> and
formed a new party, the <ORGANIZATION>National Alliance</ORGANIZATION> for Belizean Rights.
<PERSON>Mr Esquivel</PERSON> says his party sacrificed 'party integrity in favour of national
integrity' in supporting the government over the Guatemalan settlement. 'We
felt this was an opportunity to end this problem once and for all by making
a minor concession to solve a major problem.'
This may add to his problems in fighting the municipal elections in <DATE>March</DATE>.
But he says that in the the long run the <ORGANIZATION>UDP</ORGANIZATION> will not be hurt, since the
<ORGANIZATION>NABR</ORGANIZATION> is a one-issue party.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 32
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881125-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-25-88 0651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Britain-Guatemala     11-25 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Britain-Guatemala,0197</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Navy Vessel Confronted by Guatemalan Gunboat</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Guatemalan gunboat fired a shot after a British
naval vessel refused its order to halt off the Central American
country of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Office</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   A spokesman said the government will bring up <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s incident
with the Guatemalan authorities, but he could not say whether a
protest would be filed.
   ``We'll have it taken up with them. What form that will take,
frankly I don't know,'' the spokesman said on condition of
anonymity. ``We'll have to talk with them first.''
   He said the <ORGANIZATION>HMS Fawn</ORGANIZATION>, an 800-ton inshore survey vessel, was in
the territorial waters of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> when the Guatemalan gunboat ordered
it to stop.
   When the Fawn ignored the order, the gunboat fired a shot. Two
<ORGANIZATION>Royal Air Force Harrier</ORGANIZATION> jet fighters flew to the area, and the
Guatemalans agreed to withdraw their ship after telephone contact
with British authorities, said the official.
   <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, a former British colony, gained independence in <DATE>1981</DATE> but
requested British troops to remain until a territorial dispute with
neighboring <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> is resolved. About 2,000 British troops are
stationed in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-1614</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CIVBVADHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920922
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 SEP 92 / Survey of Belize (1): A bridge to the future - Belize is a
richer and more just society than many of its South American neighbours. Its
judicial, political and educational systems work reasonably well. In spite
of growing social problems, Stephen Fidler says it is possible to be
optimistic about tomorrow
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By STEPHEN FIDLER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
WHILE civil war ravaged the rest of central <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>
remained an oasis of calm. As heavy debt and economic crisis engulfed <LOCATION>Latin
America</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> achieved high growth and single-digit inflation. In a zone
with a history of military regimes and political instability, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> offered
democracy and respect for the rule of law.
Belizeans are proud of what differentiates them from their neighbours; but
their destiny will probably lie as much with the Hispanic countries
surrounding them as it does with their traditional allies in the
English-speaking <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is becoming, ethnically at least, more like its neighbours. An
estimated 40,000 people - a fifth of the population - have arrived from
neighbouring states over the past decade, fugitives from civil war or
economic deprivation. The influence of the creoles - the Afro-European group
that has traditionally dominated Belizean society - has meanwhile weakened
because of emigration.
This has caused tension: the newcomers have provided the manpower for
agriculture, the engine for growth in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. But they have put pressure
on health services and schools.
The prime minister, <PERSON>Mr George Price</PERSON>, who with his <ORGANIZATION>People's United Party</ORGANIZATION> has
dominated Belizean politics for 40 years, has spoken of the country as a
bridge between central <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. This is a long way from
reality, but it is part of a growing recognition among the mini-states of
the two sub-regions of the costs of isolation.
Until last year, practical co-operation with the rest of central <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> was
impossible because of <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s claim over the territory of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. The
claim delayed independence of <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> - known until <DATE>1973</DATE> as British <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>
 -until <DATE>1981</DATE> and was the reason for <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s maintenance of a garrison of
1,800 men and a squadron of Harrier jets.
Following guidelines hammered out between the two sides, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> last year
recognised <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s independence. A final settlement will require further
steps, including ratification in a referendum in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and concessions to
guarantee <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> access through the <LOCATION>Gulf of Honduras</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
These moves have allowed a lifting of the veto on <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s membership of the
<ORGANIZATION>Organisation of American States</ORGANIZATION>, to which it acceded in <DATE>January 1991</DATE>. <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>
will also join the <ORGANIZATION>InterAmerican Development Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>November</DATE>.
The garrison still provides 8-10 per cent of the country's GDP, but its
departure will not necessarily mean an end to the British military presence.
As a training ground, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s jungle terrain is excellent.
A withdrawal would anyway have less economic impact now than in the past
thanks in large part to the growth of agriculture. Agriculture and
agro-processing account for a quarter of GDP, 40 per cent of employment and
nearly 70 per cent of exports. However, four-fifths of all <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>'s exports
benefit from preferential market arrangements, some of which are threatened.
As a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> exports to <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> markets at low tariffs
under the Lome convention. Its agricultural products also have tariff-free
access to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> under the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> Basin Initiative (CBI), and the country
also belongs to the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> common market, <ORGANIZATION>Caricom</ORGANIZATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> between the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> is
one threat. It may encourage <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> to become a big citrus producer. A
further extension of <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> free trade agreements to other countries in <LOCATION>Latin
America</LOCATION>, proposed under President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>'s Enterprise for Americas
Initiative, would also erode the special position of CBI countries.
According to <PERSON>Mr Ralph Fonseca</PERSON>, minister of state in the ministry of finance:
'The main tenet of our trade policy has been gradualism. We are saying give
us to the <DATE>year 2000</DATE> and we can take on anybody.'
This approach recognises the country's still heavy dependence on a few
export products and its chronic trade deficits. Remittances from overseas -
estimated to bring in USDollars 15m to Dollars 17m a year - help balance
this. So does tourism, which has grown to become the country's second most
important source of foreign exchange.
Tourist attractions - rain forest, long expanses of coral reef and important
Mayan sites - have potential for further development. <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> has, however,
neither the desire, the labour force nor the beaches necessary to become a
mass tourist destination.
The country also provides a positive reception for foreign investment. There
are constraints such as a small labour force and mixed infrastructure: good
telephones but poor roads and no access for large ships. Electricity is
costly: <MONEY>21 US cents</MONEY> per kilowatt-hour, almost three times that of the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.
It can also offer stability. Government handovers of power in <DATE>1984</DATE> and <DATE>1989</DATE>
were achieved without big shifts in policy. The <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> dollar has been fixed
since <DATE>1976</DATE> at two to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> dollar and inflation has been low. The
government is fairly free of corruption. According to one businessman: 'The
worst thing you can say is that occasionally it favours its friends.'
However, the bureaucracy is often slow. One businessman describes it as
'expert in procrastination' and <PERSON>Mr Fonseca</PERSON> says the government recognises a
need to modernise it.
The government is also selling commercial assets. The telephone company has
been privatised, although the government retains a significant stake, and
plans to sell the electricity company are being finalised. The privatisation
programme has critics. <PERSON>Mr Manuel Esquivel</PERSON>, leader of the opposition, says
that it risks being dominated by one company: <ORGANIZATION>Belize Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, controlled by
<PERSON>Mr Michael Ashcroft</PERSON>, the controversial chairman of the British car auction
and security group, <ORGANIZATION>ADT</ORGANIZATION>.
The government has also attempted to speed up development by increasing
capital spending. This and its pay award to public sector workers of an
annual 10 per cent for the next three years have increased anxieties that
the government is forgetting its traditional fiscal conservatism.
<PERSON>Mr Keith Arnold</PERSON>, the central bank president, is worried that the
government's revenues are falling behind its spending: 'The government has
sufficient funds for the next two to three years, but beyond that it will
have to take care.'
This will accelerate talk of fiscal reform. Although legislation has been
passed to enable imposition of a value added tax, the government has been
reluctant to implement it. Yet the tax system is outdated: most revenue is
raised through taxing international trade.
The government also faces growing social problems. As migrants put pressure
on health and education services, emigration to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> is tearing at the
social fabric. Into this environment, cocaine has found its way. <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> has
resolved one drugs problem - in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> it was one of the top five
suppliers of marijuana to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>; now most of the plantations have been
eradicated. But it has developed another: on a line between <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is used for cocaine trans-shipment. The Belizean middle men are
paid in kind and they have seen to it that a cocaine habit has developed. As
a result, crime, particularly in <LOCATION>Belize City</LOCATION>, is on the increase.
Yet, in spite of these problems, it is possible to be optimistic about the
future. With per capita income of USDollars 2,000 a year and a reasonable
income distribution, <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> is a richer and more just society than many of
its neighbours. Its institutions - its judicial, political and educational
systems - work reasonably well. As <PERSON>Mr Geoffrey Hart</PERSON>, manager of <ORGANIZATION>Barclays
Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>, says: 'This country is not going to be a <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>. It's no
tiger but it has a lot going for it.'
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 31
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-33916 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat114_g_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-114 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Guatemala </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Minister Views Nonaligned Movement Summit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Foreign Minister Views Nonaligned Movement Summit </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1006183194 Guatemala City SIGLO VEINTIUNO in Spanish 9 Jun 
94 p 3 </F>

<F P=103> PA1006183194 </F>
<F P=104>  Guatemala City SIGLO VEINTIUNO </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Carlos Castanaza</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] Foreign Minister <PERSON>Maritza Ruiz de Vielman</PERSON> reported 
yesterday on her participation in the 11th Nonaligned Movement 
[NAM] Ministerial Conference held recently in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>. She 
explained that she had stopped the organization from accepting 
inaccurate proposals that attempted to obtain statements of 
thus, ignoring the existence of the territorial dispute. 
  Confronted with such attempts, her delegation acted to 
safeguard the country's interests and was able to get the <ORGANIZATION>NAM</ORGANIZATION> 
Declaration to be more balanced, limiting it to calling upon 
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> to discuss and resolve the dispute, which 
had not been achieved at this forum previously. She asserted 
that the government agreed with the <ORGANIZATION>NAM</ORGANIZATION> statement because 
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s position had not been omitted. To the benefit of 
both parties, the declaration backed the negotiations and, by 
not polarizing the situation, established the necessary climate 
for it, she added. 
  She highlighted as special achievements her participation as 
vice president of the conference and <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s selection to 
chair the next <ORGANIZATION>NAM</ORGANIZATION> presidential summit of member countries to be 
held in <DATE>1998</DATE>. Above all, we managed to get a special 
pronouncement in favor of <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> -- something that is 
uncommon -- to support the efforts being made by De <PERSON>Leon Carpio</PERSON> 
to further the democratization and peace processes, she 
emphasized. 
  On ending, <PERSON>Vielman</PERSON> stated that the officials who attended 
the 
<ORGANIZATION>NAM Ministerial Conference</ORGANIZATION> had attempted to redefine the 
movement's role in the new international context and had 
reaffirmed its objective of furthering the developing countries' 
struggle to advance. 
  The meeting was attended by 130 delegates, of which 109 were 
from member countries. We took advantage of this situation and 
held bilateral meetings with most of the representatives at the 
meeting, she added. 

</TEXT>
