<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Portugal-Discoveries Bjt   12-31 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Portugal-Discoveries, Bjt,0854</SECOND>
<HEAD>Is Small Beautiful For Portugal's 500-Year Discoveries Celebrations?</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LISBON, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s plans to stage a
headline-grabbing 500th birthday party for <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> in <DATE>1992</DATE> have
stirred up a storm of controversy over how <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> is celebrating
its own discoverers, who were charting the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> before
<PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON> was born.
   <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> were archrivals in the push in the 15th and
16th centuries to sail off the end of known maps and find new
worlds. Both succeeded.
   But now, many Portuguese fear their neighbors are stealing the
limelight for the <DATE>1992</DATE> fiesta.
   At the center of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s celebrations is <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>'s Expo <DATE>'92</DATE>, a
530-acre international fair that is set to end a six-month run <DATE>Oct.
12, 1992</DATE>, 500 years to the day after <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> reached the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>
island of <LOCATION>San Salvador</LOCATION>.
   Also making <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> hot property in <DATE>1992</DATE> will be the excitement of
the Summer Olympic games in <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>. And the <ORGANIZATION>European Economic
Community</ORGANIZATION> has chosen <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> as its cultural capital on the eve of
the trading bloc's deadline to create a single European market.
   Compared with all that, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1992</DATE> celebrations seem
lackluster.
   <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s government-appointed <ORGANIZATION>National Discoveries Commission</ORGANIZATION> is
promoting research, exhibitions and the publishing of more history
books about the era.
   It has commissioned American composer <PERSON>Philip Glass</PERSON> to write an
opera for <DATE>1992</DATE> release, based probably on the Lusiads _ an epic
poem about <PERSON>Vasco da Gama</PERSON>'s voyages that was written by <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s
16th century roving bard, <PERSON>Luis de Camoes</PERSON>.
   But the Spaniards got there first by casting Catalan soprano
<ORGANIZATION>Montserrat Caballe</ORGANIZATION> and tenor <PERSON>Jose Carreras</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Cristobal Colon</LOCATION>, an
opera based on trials and tribulations of the Genoese captain. It
sold out when it premiered in <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   News media, executives and even historians here have called for
more glamour to promote <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s past glories and to show that it
is a rapidly modernizing European country.
   ``I'm ashamed at how my country is celebrating the
discoveries,'' said <PERSON>Waldemar de Abreu</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> publisher and
editor of ``The Portuguese Christopher Columbus _ Secret Agent of
<PERSON>King Dom Joao II</PERSON>,'' a 600-page book that claims proof the explorer
was Portuguese.
   ``<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> could easily have pooled resources with <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and
staged an Iberian discoveries exhibition in <DATE>1992</DATE>,'' de <PERSON>Abreu</PERSON> said.
   While admitting <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> ``is pegging all the force of its
modernization on <DATE>1992</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Vasco Graca Moura</PERSON>, head of the
<ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION>'s executive board, makes no apologies for not going
overboard in that year.
   ``The main difference is that <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> is only commemorating one
date and a short journey _ <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' voyage in <DATE>1492</DATE> to the <LOCATION>West
Indies</LOCATION>,'' he said.
   ``Our celebrations began last year with <ORGANIZATION>Bartolomeu Dias</ORGANIZATION> and will
only end in <DATE>2000</DATE>, with <PERSON>Pedro Alvares Cabral</PERSON>.''
   Spurred by their pioneering Prince <PERSON>Henry</PERSON> the Navigator's studies
of astronomy and cartography, Portuguese seafarers had claimed the
island of <LOCATION>Madeira</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>mid-Atlantic Azores</LOCATION> archipelago by <DATE>1430</DATE>.
   Dias took his ship around the <LOCATION>Cape</LOCATION> of Good Hope in <DATE>1488</DATE>, leaving
da <LOCATION>Gama</LOCATION> to open up the sea route to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> <DATE>10 years later</DATE>.
   Cabral discovered <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in <DATE>1500</DATE>, the Portuguese went east of
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Fernao de Magalhaes</PERSON> _ better known as <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
_ closed the Discoveries circle in <DATE>1520</DATE> by commanding the first
expedition to sail around the world.
   ``Our commemorations match our dimension _ we're smaller than
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, so honestly we can't be as elaborate,'' said the
commission's <PERSON>Antonio Mega Ferreira</PERSON>, though adding <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> still
has a few tricks up its sleeve.
   <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE> submitted its candidacy to the Paris-based
<ORGANIZATION>International Exhibitions Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, to hold Expo '98 _ a three-month,
international fair, only about a tenth the size of <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>.
   Instead of trying for the Olympics, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> is expected to bid
in <DATE>January</DATE> to hold soccer's World Cup in <DATE>1998</DATE>.
   Expo <DATE>'98</DATE>'s theme will be East meets West, its hero _ Vasco da
Gama. Graca Moura argues da <PERSON>Gama</PERSON>'s trips to the Orient were as
important as <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' discovery in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   Mega <PERSON>Ferreira</PERSON>'s plans for Expo '98 include a subway train
connecting the undeveloped left bank of the Tagus estuary with
<LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s historic <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION> district.
   <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION> is already the site of three ornate monuments to the
discoveries _ <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION> tower and Jeronimos monastery, and former
dictator <PERSON>Antonio Oliveira Salazar</PERSON>'s colossal, caravel-shaped
``Padrao'' _ a pillar that navigators used to leave behind them on
land to mark the spread of the Portuguese empire.
   Salazar in <DATE>1940</DATE> organized an exhibition called ``O Mundo
Portugues'' _ the Portuguese world, that glorified the country's
discoveries and African empire to distract attention from its
isolation in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and World War II that was going on around it.
   ``The (center-right) government has a complex of being linked to
<PERSON>Salazar</PERSON>. They're frightened they'd be accused of nationalism, if
they did more to glorify our history,'' de <PERSON>Abreu</PERSON> said. ``But
nobody's accusing <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s socialist government of anything, and
what is <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> if not a glorification of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s colonial past?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891122-0268 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-22-89 1209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-PortuguesePark Adv26   11-22 0742</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Portuguese Park, Adv 26,0764</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday Nov. 26 and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Portugal Seeks Fair Wind for Theme Park Success</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL AMES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LISBON, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vasco da <PERSON>Gama</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand Magellan</ORGANIZATION> may
seem unlikely rivals for <ORGANIZATION>Donald Duck</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mickey Mouse</ORGANIZATION>. But under an
ambitious plan by a group of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> businessmen, the 15th-century
Portuguese explorers could vie with Walt Disney stars as major
European theme park attractions.
   A U.S.-owned company, backed by the Portuguese government, is
planning an <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> theme park near <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>,
based on the pioneering Portuguese sea voyages to <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and
the New World some 500 years ago.
   The Lusolandia park is set for a <DATE>1993</DATE> opening, one year after
the scheduled launch of a <ORGANIZATION>Euro Disneyland</ORGANIZATION> park in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Lusolandia Holdings</ORGANIZATION>' chairman <PERSON>Edward Kane</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> native, said
the project sprang from <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>'s rejection five years ago of an
idea from then Portuguese Prime Minister <PERSON>Mario Soares</PERSON> to locate a
European Disneyland in <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>.
   As <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> representative of the Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>International
Trade and Guarantee Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a company advising <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> businesses
abroad, <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> had been asked by Soares _ currently Portuguese
president _ to approach <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Walt <ORGANIZATION>Disney Enterprises</ORGANIZATION> basically said no way, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> is too
small potatoes for them,'' said <PERSON>Kane</PERSON>.
   Disney decided to locate closer to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s more affluent and
densely populated ``golden triangle'' formed by <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>. Their French amusement park program foresees costs of up
to <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> to <DATE>1997</DATE>.
   After <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>'s refusal, <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> turned to <ORGANIZATION>Management Resources</ORGANIZATION>, an
<LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, company specialized in creating and running theme
parks and formed by ex-Disney employees.
   ``I had the idea of ... instead of <PERSON>Mickey Mouse</PERSON> and Donald Duck
... let's make it a Portuguese historical theme park, let's replace
<PERSON>Donald Duck</PERSON> with <ORGANIZATION>Bartolomeu Dias</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Mickey Mouse</PERSON> with <PERSON>Vasco da
Gama</PERSON>,'' said <PERSON>Kane</PERSON>, a retired <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> foreign service officer.
   Portuguese authorities backed the plan, and <ORGANIZATION>Mangagement
Resources</ORGANIZATION> enthusiastically joined the project. Feasibility studies
predicted 2.15 million first-year customers from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s 10
million inhabitants and foreign visitors to <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> who last year
topped 16 million.
   The park is to be built near the town of <LOCATION>Azambuja</LOCATION>, some 28 miles
northeast of <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> along the main north-south freeway to <LOCATION>Oporto</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s second city.
   <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> said the park will also have good road links to <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s
main tourist destination _ the southern Algarve region _ and to
neighboring <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>. The site proposed for a new <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> international
airport is 7 miles to the east of the park location.
   Visitors will enter the 247-acre park into a mock-up of
<LOCATION>Renaissance Lisbon</LOCATION>, complete with castle and 15th century main
street.
   From a reconstructed quayside, replicas of the explorers'
caravels will carry would-be Magellans on a voyage of discovery
across an artificial lake to ``theme areas'' representing Brazilian
jungles, mysterious African kingdoms and the glittering
civilizations of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> said the latest technology will be used to create a
fun-as-you-learn environment for adults and children. The park
publicity brochure promises ocean storms and Amazonian canoe trips
as well as cultural exhibitions highlighting lands along the
Portuguese sea routes.
   Portuguese historians will advise on the park's authenticity and
experts from other countries will be contacted to set up Japanese
tea houses and African dance displays.
   <ORGANIZATION>Lusolandia Holdings</ORGANIZATION> is registered in <LOCATION>Bermuda</LOCATION> and owned 50-50 by
<ORGANIZATION>Management Resources and International Trade and Guarantee Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   Soon, <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> said, they will be joined by a Portuguese partner and
create a Portuguese company _ Lusolandia Empreedimentos Turisticas.
   Private financing for the project is being sought mainly in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Kane also hopes to gain Portuguese government funding and
is discussing loan prospects with the Luxembourg-based <ORGANIZATION>European
Investment Bank</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Portuguese government has created a special task force of
officials from four ministries to steer the project through
<LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s bureaucratic maze.
   Inspired by the ideas of Prince <PERSON>Henry</PERSON> the Navigator, Portuguese
14th and 15th century mariners undertook a series of voyages that
expanded <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s perception of the world and opened contacts with
the people of other continents.
   Dias became the first man to sail beyond the shores of <LOCATION>North
Africa</LOCATION> down the West African coast to the <LOCATION>Cape of Good Hope</LOCATION> in
<DATE>1488</DATE>, da <PERSON>Gama</PERSON> discovered the sea route to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <DATE>1499</DATE> and <PERSON>Pedro
Alvares Cabral</PERSON> first landed in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in <DATE>1500</DATE>. Sailing under
Spanish colors, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> began the first circumnavigation of the
globe in <DATE>1519</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv Sunday Nov. 26</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122089-0137 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 151311 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 20, 1989, Wednesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 8; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
757 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MICKEY IS OUT, MAGELLAN IS IN AT PORTUGAL'S HISTORICAL THEME PARK; 
</P>
<P>
DEVELOPMENT: UNDER AN AMBITIOUS PLAN BY U.S. BUSINESSMEN, 15TH-CENTURY 
EXPLORERS WILL STAR IN AN AMUSEMENT ATTRACTION TO OPEN IN 1993 NEAR LISBON. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
LISBON, Portugal 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Vasco da <PERSON>Gama</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand Magellan</ORGANIZATION> may seem unlikely rivals for <ORGANIZATION>Donald Duck</ORGANIZATION> 
and <ORGANIZATION>Mickey Mouse</ORGANIZATION>. But under an ambitious plan by a group of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> businessmen, 
the 15th-Century Portuguese explorers could vie with Walt Disney stars as major 
European theme park attractions. 
</P>
<P>
A U.S.-owned company, backed by the Portuguese government, is planning an 
<MONEY>$80-million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$100-million</MONEY> theme park near <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>, based on the pioneering 
Portuguese sea voyages to <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and the New World some 500 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
The Lusolandia park is set for a <DATE>1993</DATE> opening, one year after the scheduled 
launch of a <ORGANIZATION>Euro Disneyland</ORGANIZATION> park in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Lusolandia Holdings</ORGANIZATION> chairman <PERSON>Edward Kane</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> native, said the project 
sprang from <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>'s rejection five years ago of an idea from then-Portuguese 
Prime Minister <PERSON>Mario Soares</PERSON> to locate a European Disneyland in <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
As <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> representative of the Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>International Trade and 
Guarantee Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a company advising <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> businesses abroad, <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> had been asked 
by Soares -- currently Portuguese president -- to approach <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Walt <ORGANIZATION>Disney Enterprises</ORGANIZATION> basically said no way, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> is too small potatoes 
for them," <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Disney decided to locate closer to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s more affluent and densely populated 
"golden triangle" formed by <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>. Their French amusement 
park program foresees costs of up to <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> to <DATE>1997</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
After <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>'s refusal, <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> turned to <ORGANIZATION>Management Resources</ORGANIZATION>, an <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> company 
specializing in creating and running theme parks and formed by ex-Disney 
employees. 
</P>
<P>
"I had the idea of . . . instead of <PERSON>Mickey Mouse</PERSON> and Donald Duck . . . let's 
make it a Portuguese historical theme park, let's replace <PERSON>Donald Duck</PERSON> with 
<ORGANIZATION>Bartolomeu Dias</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Mickey Mouse</PERSON> with <PERSON>Vasco da Gama</PERSON>," said <PERSON>Kane</PERSON>, a retired <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
foreign service officer. 
</P>
<P>
Portuguese authorities backed the plan, and <ORGANIZATION>Mangagement Resources</ORGANIZATION> 
enthusiastically joined the project. Feasibility studies predicted 2.15 million 
first-year customers from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s 10 million inhabitants and foreign 
visitors to <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> who last year topped 16 million. 
</P>
<P>
The park is to be built near the town of <LOCATION>Azambuja</LOCATION>, 28 miles northeast of <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> 
along the main north-south freeway to <LOCATION>Oporto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s second largest city. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kane</PERSON> said the park will also have good road links to <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s main tourist 
destination -- the southern Algarve region -- and to neighboring <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>. The 
site proposed for a new <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> international airport is seven miles to the east 
of the park location. 
</P>
<P>
Visitors will enter the 247-acre park into a mock-up of <LOCATION>Renaissance Lisbon</LOCATION>, 
complete with castle and 15th-Century main street. 
</P>
<P>
From a reconstructed quay, replicas of the explorers' caravels will carry 
would-be Magellans on a voyage of discovery across an artificial lake to "theme 
areas" representing Brazilian jungles, mysterious African kingdoms and the 
glittering civilizations of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kane</PERSON> said the latest technology will be used to create a have-fun-as-you-learn 
environment for adults and children. The park publicity brochure promises ocean 
storms and Amazonian canoe trips as well as cultural exhibits highlighting 
lands along the Portuguese sea routes. 
</P>
<P>
Portuguese historians will advise on the park's authenticity and experts from 
other countries will be contacted to set up Japanese teahouses and African 
dance displays. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Lusolandia Holdings</ORGANIZATION> is registered in <LOCATION>Bermuda</LOCATION> and owned 50-50 by <ORGANIZATION>Management 
Resources and International Trade and Guarantee Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Soon, <PERSON>Kane</PERSON> said, they will be joined by a Portuguese partner and create a 
Portuguese company -- Lusolandia Empreedimentos Turisticas. 
</P>
<P>
Private financing for the project is being sought mainly in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Kane also 
hopes to gain Portuguese government funding and is discussing loan prospects 
with the Luxembourg-based <ORGANIZATION>European Investment Bank</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Portuguese government has created a special task force of officials from 
four ministries to steer the project through <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s bureaucratic maze. 
</P>
<P>
Inspired by the ideas of Prince <PERSON>Henry</PERSON> the Navigator, Portuguese 14th- and 
15th-Century mariners undertook a series of voyages that expanded <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s 
perception of the world and opened contacts with the people of other 
continents. 
</P>
<P>
Dias became the first man to sail beyond the shores of <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION> down the 
West African coast to the <LOCATION>Cape of Good Hope</LOCATION> in <DATE>1488</DATE>, da <PERSON>Gama</PERSON> discovered the sea 
route to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <DATE>1499</DATE> and <PERSON>Pedro Alvares Cabral</PERSON> first landed in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in <DATE>1500</DATE>. 
Sailing under Spanish colors, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> began the first circumnavigation of the 
globe in <DATE>1519</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
AMUSEMENT PARKS; PORTUGAL -- HISTORY; UNITED STATES -- FOREIGN INVESTMENTS -- 
PORTUGAL 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-13121</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJ1D8AGHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941028
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  28 OCT 94 / Survey of Portugal (8): Facelift for an anniversary / A look
at preparations for Expo '98
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By TOM BURNS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> has every right to be proud of its illustrious past, and the manner
in which it recalls events in its history that the rest of the world ignores
is nothing short of endearing.
Few outside <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, for example, are aware that <DATE>1991</DATE> was the 500th
anniversary of the first Portuguese mission to the kingdom of the <LOCATION>Congo</LOCATION>, or
that <DATE>2000</DATE> will mark the the 500th anniversary of the colonisation of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>,
or that this year celebrates the 600th anniversary of the birth of Prince
<PERSON>Henry</PERSON> the Navigator whose intellectual stimulus and deep pockets made such
milestones possible.
The world outside <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> may, however, become aware of the significance of
<DATE>1998</DATE> as the year marking 500th anniversary of <ORGANIZATION>Vasco da Gama</ORGANIZATION>'s voyage to
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. If it does it will be because of <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s Expo <DATE>'98</DATE>, an international
exposition which hopes to attract 115 participants, countries, multinational
companies and international organisations, and 10m visitors.
Expo <DATE>'98</DATE>, has chosen an attractive theme: under the title The Oceans, a
<ORGANIZATION>Heritage</ORGANIZATION> for the Future, it will focus on conserving the oceans and also on
realising the sustainable assets that the two thirds of planet earth
represented by the oceans can provide. The question is whether it can
deliver this appealing package.
<PERSON>Antonio Cardoso e Cunha</PERSON>, a former <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> commissioner and now commissioner for
Expo <DATE>'98</DATE>, brushes the doubters aside. The world fair will happen as planned
because much more than being an occasion to wave the <LOCATION>Vasco</LOCATION> da Gama flag,
more even than providing a platform for ecological correctness, Expo '98 is
the excuse for a significant urban facelift that <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> can no longer delay.
Already the state-owned Expo '98 consortium is beginning to decontaminate
and to level a 300-hectare industrial garbage area on <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s eastern
suburbs, upriver and alongside the river Tagus estuary, that was formerly
occupied by a succession of petroleum refineries and factories.
It is an undertaking comparable to the renewal of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s Docklands or to
<LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>'s decision to uproot a similar rust belt to construct an Olympic
village. <PERSON>Mr Cardoso</PERSON> believes that <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> is not only 'fit to meet' such an
undertaking but 'desperately needs to do so'.
The stimulus is all-important. 'If the objectives are not foolish, if they
are reasonable, then societies need this sort of psychological challenge,'
says Expo <DATE>'98</DATE>'s commissioner and his views echo those of <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> mayor
<PERSON>Pascual Maragall</PERSON> in the run up to the <DATE>1992 summer</DATE> games.
Expo '98 will not, however, be a repeat of the Expo '92 jamboree in <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>
that marked the 500 years of <PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON>'s first voyage to the New
World. That was a 'universal' exposition, a higher rank than the
'international' exposition accolade awarded to <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>BIE</ORGANIZATION>, the
Paris-based organisation which monitors world fairs. With hindsight, <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>
perceives Expo '92 as having been too costly, too ambitious and, ultimately,
too wasteful.
'One of our main concerns is not to be <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> mark two,' says <PERSON>Mr Cardoso</PERSON>.
The <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> event will be shorter - <DATE>four months, June</DATE> to <DATE>September</DATE>, instead
of <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>'s six - the exhibition space will be much smaller and, hopefully,
it will pay for itself by selling off its real estate to the private sector.
If all goes as Expo '98 plans it, <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> will be making a giant leap forward
over the next three years. It will acquire:
A second fixed link over the <LOCATION>Tagus</LOCATION>, a 15-kilometre six-lane highway thrown
across the estuary that will relieve pressure on the saturated existing
suspension bridge, down river, which dates from <DATE>1966</DATE>.
A transport interchange centre serving buses, the city's metro system and
the main national railway traffic moving north-south and east towards the
Spanish border.
A big exhibition centre, a large multi-purpose indoor sports and music
stadium and the biggest oceanarium in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
A new residential, office and commercial area, housing some 25,000 and,
scenically situated by the Tagus estuary's bulge, reminiscent in its
location of lakeside <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
'Everybody has got his feelings at least a little mixed about such
ambitions,' says a <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> property developer. 'Clearing all that needs to be
cleared (the Expo '98 site extends along 5km of river front) and then
building all the complex things that are planned in under four years seems a
bit far-fetched.' The doubters point to the fact that <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> has only
recently scrapped its own plans to have an Expo '96 because of time and
financing difficulties.
<PERSON>Mr Cardoso</PERSON> appears untroubled and he harks back to <PERSON>Vasco da Gama</PERSON> who was
'not a navigator' but a clear-sighted businessman. Getting to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> was a
'trade-driven act' and by the same token the world fair on the 500th
anniversary of that voyage is a sound commercial venture moulded to the
city's requirements.
Indeed, <PERSON>Mr Cardoso</PERSON> seems intent on leaving nothing to chance as he preaches
the need to be 'hard, demanding and accurate' in the Expo '98 quest. He has
a poster of <ORGANIZATION>Murphy</ORGANIZATION>'s Law - If things can go wrong they will - framed in his
office and he says that he has it hanging there to remind him and his staff
that 'everything has to be covered'.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>PTZ  Portugal, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
    P65   Real Estate.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    RES  Facilities.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 34
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0201 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0809EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   12-18 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <DATE>Dec. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>358th day of 1989</DATE>. There are seven
days left in the year. This is <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION>.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>Dec. 24, 1814</DATE>, the War of <DATE>1812</DATE> officially ended as the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> signed the <ORGANIZATION>Treaty of Ghent</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>. However,
because of the slowness of communications at that time, the
countries fought the Battle of <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> the following month.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1524</DATE>, Portuguese navigator Vasco da Gama _ who had discovered
a sea route around <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> _ died in <LOCATION>Cochin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1851</DATE>, fire devastated the <ORGANIZATION>Library of Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington
D.C.</LOCATION>, destroying about 35,000 volumes.
   In <DATE>1865</DATE>, several veterans of the <ORGANIZATION>Confederate Army</ORGANIZATION> formed a
private social club in <LOCATION>Pulaski</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, called the <PERSON>Ku Klux Klan</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1871</DATE>, <PERSON>Giuseppe Verdi</PERSON>'s opera ``Aida'' had its world premiere
in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, to celebrate the opening of the <ORGANIZATION>Suez Canal</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1906</DATE>, Canadian physicist <PERSON>Reginald A. Fessenden</PERSON> became the
first person to broadcast a music program over radio, from <LOCATION>Brant
Rock</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1920</DATE>, <PERSON>Enrico Caruso</PERSON> gave his last public performance, singing
the role of Eleazar in <PERSON>Jacques Halevy</PERSON>'s ``La Juive'' at the
Metropolitan Opera in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1943</DATE>, President <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> appointed Gen. <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON>
supreme commander of Allied forces as part of Operation Overlord.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, the Apollo 8 astronauts, orbiting the moon, read
passages from the Old Testament Book of Genesis as part of a
Christmas Eve television broadcast to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, Americans remembered the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> hostages in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> by
burning candles or shining lights for 417 seconds _ one second for
each day of captivity.
   In <DATE>1986</DATE>, French hostage <PERSON>Aurel Cornea</PERSON>, held in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> for 9{
months, was released by his pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem captors.
   Ten years ago: Four clergymen from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> were
allowed to meet with some of the American hostages in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> to hold
Christmas services.
   Five years ago: The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> held funeral services for its
late defense minister, <PERSON>Dmitri F. Ustinov</PERSON>. The absence of President
<PERSON>Konstantin U. Chernenko</PERSON> fueled rumors of serious illness.
   One year ago: President-elect <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> nominated <PERSON>Elizabeth H. Dole</PERSON>,
onetime transportation secretary during the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration,
to be his secretary of labor.
   Today's Birthday: Actress <PERSON>Ava Gardner</PERSON> is 67.
   Thought for Today: ``Christmas is the season when people run out
of money before they run out of friends.'' _ Anonymous.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901217-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-17-90 1046EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   12-17 0368</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0432</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Monday, Dec. 24</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>Dec. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>358th day of 1990</DATE>. There are seven
days left in the year. This is <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION>.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>Dec. 24, 1814</DATE>, the War of <DATE>1812</DATE> officially ended as the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> signed the <ORGANIZATION>Treaty of Ghent</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>. (However,
because of the slowness of communications at that time, both
countries fought the Battle of <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> the following month.)
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1524</DATE>, Portuguese navigator Vasco da <PERSON>Gama</PERSON> - who had discovered
a sea route around <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> - died in <LOCATION>Cochin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1851</DATE>, fire devastated the <ORGANIZATION>Library of Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
destroying about 35,000 volumes.
   In <DATE>1865</DATE>, several veterans of the <ORGANIZATION>Confederate Army</ORGANIZATION> formed a
private social club in <LOCATION>Pulaski</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, called the <PERSON>Ku Klux Klan</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1871</DATE>, <PERSON>Giuseppe Verdi</PERSON>'s opera ``Aida'' had its world premiere
in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, to celebrate the opening of the <ORGANIZATION>Suez Canal</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1906</DATE>, Canadian physicist <PERSON>Reginald A. Fessenden</PERSON> became the
first person to broadcast a music program over radio, from <LOCATION>Brant
Rock</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1920</DATE>, <PERSON>Enrico Caruso</PERSON> gave his last public performance, singing
the role of Eleazar in <PERSON>Jacques Halevy</PERSON>'s ``La Juive'' at the
Metropolitan Opera in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1943</DATE>, President <PERSON>Franklin Roosevelt</PERSON> appointed Gen. <PERSON>Dwight D.
Eisenhower</PERSON> supreme commander of Allied forces as part of
``Operation Overlord.''
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Apollo VIII</ORGANIZATION> astronauts, orbiting the moon, read
passages from the Old Testament Book of Genesis as part of a
Christmas Eve television broadcast to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1986</DATE>, French hostage <PERSON>Aurel Cornea</PERSON>, held in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> for 9{
months, was released by his pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem captors.
   Ten years ago: Americans remembered the American hostages in
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> by burning candles or shining lights for 417 seconds, one
second for each day of captivity.
   Five years ago: The government of <ORGANIZATION>El Salvador</ORGANIZATION> announced it had
accepted a <DATE>10-day Christmas</DATE> holiday truce with leftist rebels.
(However, both sides accused the other violating the cease-fire.)
   One year ago: Ousted Panamanian ruler <PERSON>Manuel Noriega</PERSON>, who had
succeeded in eluding <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces, took refuge at the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION>'s
diplomatic mission in <LOCATION>Panama City</LOCATION>.
   Today's Birthdays: Actress <PERSON>Jill Bennett</PERSON> is 59. Author <PERSON>Mary
Higgins Clark</PERSON> is 59. Federal health administrator <PERSON>Anthony S. Fauci</PERSON>
is 50.
   Thought for Today: ``To perceive Christmas through its wrapping
becomes more difficult with every year.'' - <PERSON>E.B. White</PERSON>, American
author and journalist (1899-1985).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday, Dec. 24</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>Dec. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>358th day of 1990</DATE>. There are seven
days left in the year. This is <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION>.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>Dec. 24, 1814</DATE>, the War of <DATE>1812</DATE> officially ended as the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> signed the <ORGANIZATION>Treaty of Ghent</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>. (However,
because of the slowness of communications at that time, both
countries fought the Battle of <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> the following month.)
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1524</DATE>, Portuguese navigator Vasco da <PERSON>Gama</PERSON> - who had discovered
a sea route around <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> - died in <LOCATION>Cochin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1851</DATE>, fire devastated the <ORGANIZATION>Library of Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
destroying about 35,000 volumes.
   In <DATE>1865</DATE>, several veterans of the <ORGANIZATION>Confederate Army</ORGANIZATION> formed a
private social club in <LOCATION>Pulaski</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, called the <PERSON>Ku Klux Klan</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1871</DATE>, <PERSON>Giuseppe Verdi</PERSON>'s opera ``Aida'' had its world premiere
in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, to celebrate the opening of the <ORGANIZATION>Suez Canal</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1906</DATE>, Canadian physicist <PERSON>Reginald A. Fessenden</PERSON> became the
first person to broadcast a music program over radio, from <LOCATION>Brant
Rock</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1920</DATE>, <PERSON>Enrico Caruso</PERSON> gave his last public performance, singing
the role of Eleazar in <PERSON>Jacques Halevy</PERSON>'s ``La Juive'' at the
Metropolitan Opera in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1943</DATE>, President <PERSON>Franklin Roosevelt</PERSON> appointed Gen. <PERSON>Dwight D.
Eisenhower</PERSON> supreme commander of Allied forces as part of
``Operation Overlord.''
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Apollo VIII</ORGANIZATION> astronauts, orbiting the moon, read
passages from the Old Testament Book of Genesis as part of a
Christmas Eve television broadcast to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1986</DATE>, French hostage <PERSON>Aurel Cornea</PERSON>, held in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> for 9{
months, was released by his pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem captors.
   Ten years ago: Americans remembered the American hostages in
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> by burning candles or shining lights for 417 seconds, one
second for each day of captivity.
   Five years ago: The government of <ORGANIZATION>El Salvador</ORGANIZATION> announced it had
accepted a <DATE>10-day Christmas</DATE> holiday truce with leftist rebels.
(However, both sides accused the other violating the cease-fire.)
   One year ago: Ousted Panamanian ruler <PERSON>Manuel Noriega</PERSON>, who had
succeeded in eluding <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces, took refuge at the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION>'s
diplomatic mission in <LOCATION>Panama City</LOCATION>.
   Today's Birthdays: Actress <PERSON>Jill Bennett</PERSON> is 59. Author <PERSON>Mary
Higgins Clark</PERSON> is 59. Federal health administrator <PERSON>Anthony S. Fauci</PERSON>
is 50.
   Thought for Today: ``To perceive Christmas through its wrapping
becomes more difficult with every year.'' - <PERSON>E.B. White</PERSON>, American
author and journalist (1899-1985).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881212-0227 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-12-88 0801EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   12-12 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0481</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Saturday, Dec. 24</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<HEAD>By The Associated Press</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <DATE>Dec. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>359th day of 1988</DATE>. There are
seven days left in the year. This is <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>Twenty years ago</DATE>, on <DATE>Dec. 24, 1968</DATE>, the ``Apollo Eight''
astronauts, orbiting the moon, read passages from the Old Testament
Book of Genesis as part of a Christmas Eve television broadcast to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1524</DATE>, Portuguese navigator Vasco da Gama _ who had discovered
a sea route around <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> _ died in <LOCATION>Cochin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1814</DATE>, the War of <DATE>1812</DATE> ended as the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>
signed the <ORGANIZATION>Treaty of Ghent</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1851</DATE>, fire devastated the <ORGANIZATION>Library of Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, destroying about 35,000 volumes.
   In <DATE>1865</DATE>, several veterans of the <ORGANIZATION>Confederate Army</ORGANIZATION> formed a
private social club in <LOCATION>Pulaski</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, called the <PERSON>Ku Klux Klan</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1871</DATE>, <PERSON>Giuseppe Verdi</PERSON>'s opera ``Aida'' had its world premiere
in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, to celebrate the opening of the <ORGANIZATION>Suez</ORGANIZATION> canal.
   In <DATE>1906</DATE>, Canadian physicist <PERSON>Reginald A. Fessenden</PERSON> became the
first person to broadcast a music program over radio, from <LOCATION>Brant
Rock</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1920</DATE>, <PERSON>Enrico Caruso</PERSON> gave his last public performance, singing
the role of Eleazar in <PERSON>Jacques Halevy</PERSON>'s ``La Juive'' at the
Metropolitan Opera in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1943</DATE>, President <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> appointed Gen. <PERSON>Dwight D.
Eisenhower</PERSON> supreme commander of Allied forces as part of Operation
``Overlord.''
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, Americans remembered the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> hostages in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> by
burning candles or shining lights for 417 seconds _ one second for
each day of captivity.
   In <DATE>1986</DATE>, French hostage <PERSON>Aurel Cornea</PERSON>, held in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> for 9{
months, was released by his pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem captors.
   Ten years ago: In <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>, about 200 anti-shah demonstrators
shouting, ``Go home, Yankee'' and ``Down with the American <PERSON>Shah</PERSON>,''
tried to storm the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION>, but were driven away by <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Marines</ORGANIZATION> who fired tear gas at the protesters.
   Five years ago: <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Marine peacekeepers in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>, ate
a Christmas dinner of turkey and baked ham one day early for what
were described as security reasons.
   One year ago: In <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>, the kidnappers of <PERSON>Terry Anderson</PERSON>
released a videotape in which the <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> correspondent
told his family he was in good health, and said to President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>,
``Surely by now you know what must be done and how you can do it.''
   Today's Birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>Journalist I.F. Stone</ORGANIZATION> is 81. Actress <PERSON>Ava
Gardner</PERSON> is 66.
   Thought for today: ``If Christmas didn't already exist, man would
have had to invent it. There has to be at least one day in the year
to remind us we're here for something else besides our general
cussedness.'' _ <PERSON>Eric Sevareid</PERSON>, American journalist and commentator.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-13838</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EGRD8AB9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940718
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  18 JUL 94 / Business Travel: City for explorers - Peter Wise offers tips
on getting around and staying in Lisbon - and the etiquette of doing deals
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PETER WISE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The Portuguese, with self-deprecating humour, like to describe <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> as a
city of the developing world, rather than a European capital. The country's
historical involvement with <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and the Arab world is evident in
the city's architecture, culture and cuisine - but on a technical level, it
functions almost on a par with the most modern of its European counterparts.
Doing business in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> is rarely arduous and the hospitality of the
Portuguese usually makes it a pleasure. The city from where discoverers such
as <ORGANIZATION>Vasco de Gama</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Fernao de Magalhaes</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>) set out in the 15th and
16th centuries enjoys being discovered by newcomers.
Lisbon will be welcoming more and more foreign businessmen over the next few
years, as the host to Expo '98 and the promoter of important infrastructure
projects, including new road and rail crossings over the Tagus river.
Visitors will discover that taxis are the best way to travel. They are
cheap, reliable and plentiful in the city centre. Except at rush hours,
nowhere is much more than 20 minutes away. Unless you are travelling to the
country's interior, it is not worth hiring a car (but if you do, it is often
cheaper to book outside <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>).
There are good reasons for hailing a cab. First, it is virtually impossible
to park in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>. Second, public transport is crowded and uncertain. The
yellow trams are fun but slow. Third, driving in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> can be frightening.
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> has the highest road-accident rate in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. US soldiers at a <ORGANIZATION>Nato</ORGANIZATION>
base on one of the most dangerous roads out of <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> have had T-shirts
printed saying 'I survived the Marginal'.
The few sharks among <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> taxi drivers wait around the airport. The most
frequent trick is to clear the meter when you reach your destination and ask
for a higher fare. There is a 50 per cent surcharge for heavy luggage, but
it should be registered on the meter. Tolls are not shown, and are charged
double to cover the driver's return.
Company headquarters, banks, financial markets and government departments
are scattered around <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>. But most are within easy reach of the main
hotels.
The <ORGANIZATION>Tivoli</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Ritz</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Meridien</ORGANIZATION> and Sheraton offer the best five-star
accommodation. However, businessmen are increasingly staying at new three-
and four-stars hotels. The <LOCATION>Sol Lisboa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Dom Rodrigo Lisboa</PERSON>,
which offers self-catering apartments for longer stays, provide good service
and ample space.
Most Portuguese businessmen speak English and French. A single foreign
visitor is enough for a meeting of 20 Portuguese executives to be held
entirely in English. A few words of Portuguese from a foreigner are taken as
a compliment, but not expected. It is not advisable to try out your Spanish.
The Portuguese do understand it, but pride themselves on the individuality
of their own language.
Punctuality is prized in <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, but rarely practised. As a foreigner,
however, you are expected to be on time.
The Portuguese are not overly formal. But the Anglo-Saxon habit of quickly
adopting first names can affront some sensibilities. Women wear skirts; men
wear suits or jackets and ties.
Lunch is a vital part of doing business. It begins at 1pm or 1.30pm and
lasts a minimum of 90 minutes, more often two hours. The city is teeming
with good restaurants, but a few are especially favoured for business
meetings. They include the <LOCATION>Veranda</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Hotel Ritz</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Gambrinus</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Hotel da
Lapa</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Casa da Comida</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Chester</PERSON>. The latter attests to the penchant of
<LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> businessmen for traditional British styles, from oak-panelled rooms
to tweed jackets. The Portuguese do not take a siesta and dinner starts no
later than 9pm.
Breakfast is a non-event, and it is unwise to organise business meetings
around it.
The most frequent business journey out of <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> is to the northern city of
<LOCATION>Oporto</LOCATION>. The aircraft is faster and more reliable than the train. <ORGANIZATION>Portugalia</ORGANIZATION>,
a small private airline, tends to be more efficient on this route than the
national carrier, TAP-Air <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>.
On a free day, visit the romantic palaces of <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> or the rolling plains of
the <LOCATION>Alentejo</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> is this year's <ORGANIZATION>European Capital of Culture</ORGANIZATION>, making it a fertile city
for night life. The medieval <LOCATION>Bairro Alto</LOCATION> is a lively district of Fado music
houses, boxing clubs, boutiques, bars, restaurants, discotheques and
bordellos. Over the past three years, the clubs along the Avenida 24 de
Julho, beside the Tagus, have become the most fashionable. The action goes
on until dawn. No one has yet worked out when the young professionals who
dance the night away there actually sleep.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>PTZ  Portugal, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900731-0119
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900731-0119.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Somebody Send Them a Fat Lady
   So They'll Know When It's Over
   ----
   By Thomas Kamm
</HL>
<DATE>
07/31/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<LP>
   RIO DE JANEIRO -- Brazilians don't play baseball, so they
worry little about who's on first. But they're passionate
about soccer, and they wonder who's in first. First place,
that is.
   "In the end, who is the champion?" asked the headline in
Monday's Jornal do Brasil. Perplexed fans asked the same
question Sunday after watching both Botafogo and Vasco da
Gama run victory laps after their game at Maracana Stadium,
the 200,000-seat temple of soccer.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   On the face of it, it was simple. Botafogo won the game,
1-0, and has more points overall this season than <LOCATION>Vasco</LOCATION>.
   But this is <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, and nothing is ever that simple. Rules
are rules and, apparently, the rules say Botafogo may have
been the best team overall and won the final, but it didn't
win the championship. That's if you believe the rules that
were adopted in midseason, which aren't the same as the rules
that were enforced at the beginning of the season.
   Under the old rules, the soccer season is divided into two
legs, one won by <PERSON>Vasco</PERSON> and another won by a third team,
<ORGANIZATION>Fluminense; Vasco</ORGANIZATION> won the playoff between the two. On top of
that, however, if another team has more overall wins than the
two champions when the two legs of the season are combined,
it also has a right to dispute the prestigious championship
of the state of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>. That was <ORGANIZATION>Botafogo</ORGANIZATION>'s case, so
it had to play <LOCATION>Vasco</LOCATION> to determine the championship.
Botafogo's victory <DATE>Sunday</DATE> sealed the matter, so far as its
players and fans were concerned.
   But the rules were changed during this season's recess for
the World Cup, when the <ORGANIZATION>Soccer Federation</ORGANIZATION> decided that the
winner would be determined by a point system. Under that
system, <LOCATION>Botafogo</LOCATION> and Vasco were tied with one victory apiece
at the end of regulation time in <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s game and should
have played an overtime period to determine the overall
winner.
   Botafogo refused and left the field after a victory
celebration, so Vasco dubbed itself "the legal winner"
despite its defeat. "The rules exist and we complied with
them," proclaims <PERSON>Eurico Miranda</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Vasco</ORGANIZATION>'s vice president.
   Which leaves the championship a matter for a court
decision, and <ORGANIZATION>Botafogo</ORGANIZATION> faces expulsion for refusing to comply
with the rules. A ruling is expected within 20 days, but
soccer fans may have to be patient: The last time there was a
dispute over the title was in <DATE>1907</DATE>, and the final decision on
that didn't come until <DATE>1989</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890320-0264 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-20-89 0641EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Travel:WithGuidebooks-Books     03-20 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Travel: With Guidebooks-Books,0179</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Travel: With Guidebooks-Books</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Often fascinating are new and reprinted accounts of people's
travels.
   <PERSON>Bruce Chatwin</PERSON>, in ``Songlines,'' seeks out the traditional
ancestral paths of aborigines in the Australian Outback, and <PERSON>Mary
Morris</PERSON> travels alone and offbeat in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in ``Nothing to Declare''
(both Viking-Penguin).
   Freya Stark visits Turkish spots that <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON> the Great visited
in the years before the Christian era and thinks of his experiences
as she jolts and rides along ``Alexander's Path'' (<ORGANIZATION>Overlook Press</ORGANIZATION>).
   <PERSON>Geoffrey Moorhouse</PERSON> sets out with some trepidation to cross the
Sahara by himself by camel, as recounted in ``The Fearful Void''
(<PERSON>Griffin</PERSON>).
   <PERSON>Eric Newby</PERSON>'s apparently insatiable interest in other people's
travels has led to a fat collection, ``A Book of Travellers' Tales''
(Viking-Penguin), with brief excerpts of writings by travelers
ranging from the unknown diarist who was on Portuguese navigator
<PERSON>Vasco de Gama</PERSON>'s 1497-1499 voyage, in which he discovered the sea
route to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> around the <LOCATION>Cape of Good Hope</LOCATION>, to novelist <PERSON>Evelyn
Waugh</PERSON>, looking at <ORGANIZATION>Mt. Etna</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-1235</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CFXBMAARFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920624
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  24 JUN 92 / World News in Brief: Lisbon wins 1998 world fair
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>, proposing a salute to Portuguese explorer <PERSON>Vasco da Gama</PERSON>, has been
chosen ahead of <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> to host an international fair in <DATE>1998</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 1
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022689-0154 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 23762 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 26, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part 7; Page 5; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1267 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
RETRACING BYRON'S STEPS IN 'GLORIOUS EDEN' 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BETTY LOWRY, Lowry is a Wayland, Mass., free-lance writer. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SINTRA, Portugal 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Of all the words spoken and sung about <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION>, poet <PERSON>George Gordon Noel Byron</PERSON>'s 
had the most lasting effect. When he put this flowering mountain town in 
"Childe Harold" he put <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> on the map. "Glorious Eden," he called the city. 
</P>
<P>
Wherever he stayed <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> was taken with <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION>. He wrote his mother: "<LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> . 
. . contains beauties of every description, natural and artificial. Palaces and 
gardens rising in the midst of rocks, cataracts and precipices; convents on 
stupendous heights, a distant view of the sea and the Tagus." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION>, 17 miles north of <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>, hasn't changed much from that description. 
Open are castles, convents, botanical gardens and <ORGANIZATION>Pena Palace</ORGANIZATION>, the wedding-cake 
structure that crowns the Serra de <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Looks Like <ORGANIZATION>Balmoral 
</P>
<P>
Pena Palace</ORGANIZATION> was built by a cousin of <ORGANIZATION>Queen Victoria</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Albert</PERSON> and resembles 
<LOCATION>Balmoral</LOCATION> on the inside, although it is more like <LOCATION>Bavaria</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Neuschwanstein</LOCATION> on 
the outside. 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> visited the mountain was topped by a monastery built by Manuel I in 
gratitude for the safe return of <ORGANIZATION>Vasco da Gama</ORGANIZATION>. The king was hunting on the 
mountain when the fleet was spied entering home waters. Monastery ruins include 
a chapel, an alabaster altar and a cloister. 
</P>
<P>
Farther down <ORGANIZATION>Pena Ridge</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> undoubtedly walked the parapets of Castelo dos 
Mouros, an 8th-Century Arab stronghold later occupied by Norsemen. In the clear 
mountain air, views are still amazing. 
</P>
<P>
We know he hiked to Capuchos to see the <ORGANIZATION>Convento de Santa Cruz</ORGANIZATION>, a Capuchin 
monastery carved in the rock and insulated -- as well as furnished -- with 
cork. 
</P>
<P>
St. Honorius, a hermit who lived in a cave nearby, gets credit lines in <LOCATION>Byron</LOCATION>'s 
poem. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Capuchos Monastery 
</P>
<P>
Capuchos is still a dark warren. Visitors are shown where eight penitents at a 
time lived in discomfort, despite such facilities as an infirmary, a dining 
room, a kitchen and an indoor bathroom. 
</P>
<P>
Byron probably strode on to Colares, a town of vineyards and villas, pausing 
for bread, cheese and claret in a small taverna. 
</P>
<P>
An English merchant, <PERSON>Francis Cook</PERSON>, 40 years later claimed that <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> inspired 
him to import eminent horticulturists to the old monastery grounds at 
<ORGANIZATION>Monserrate</ORGANIZATION> to oversee exotica from <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> as well as <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Cook then built a bizarre neo-Oriental mansion for which he could blame no one 
but himself. 
</P>
<P>
Still later, another Englishman acquired <PERSON>Monserrate</PERSON>, sold the antique 
furnishings at a profit and proposed to divide the property into house plots. 
As shudders ran down the mountain, the Portuguese government stepped in and 
declared the place a national treasure. 
</P>
<P>
Today the gardens of <PERSON>Pena</PERSON> and <PERSON>Monserrate</PERSON> feature more than 3,000 plants. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Twin Chimneys 
</P>
<P>
The distinctive twin chimneys of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Palace</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> reminded <PERSON>Hans 
Christian Andersen</PERSON> of champagne bottles when he visited in <DATE>1866</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Byron ignored them in "Childe Harold." 
</P>
<P>
The palace began as the home of a Moorish potentate, was taken by <PERSON>Alfonso 
Henriques</PERSON>, the first king of <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1147</DATE>, and early in the 15th Century 
was rebuilt as a <DATE>summer</DATE> palace for <ORGANIZATION>King Joao</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
A century later more additions were made by Manuel I, who lived there and was 
called "the Fortunate King." 
</P>
<P>
The romantic interior has a Swan Room that commemorates the wedding of Princess 
<LOCATION>Isabela</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Philip of Burgundy</LOCATION>, and a Magpie Room -- to reprimand palace 
gossips after the king was caught kissing a lady-in-waiting. 
</P>
<P>
Sintra's highland setting has always drawn those wilted by the <DATE>summer</DATE> heat of 
<LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>, but it has remained a serene place. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Casinos and Beaches 
</P>
<P>
Casinos and condos belong to <LOCATION>Estoril</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Cascais</LOCATION> at the foot of the mountain, a 
short trip by auto or bus. Equally convenient for today's visitor are the 
<LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> beaches and such seaside villages as <LOCATION>Ericeira</LOCATION>, where lobsters 
are bred in nurseries. 
</P>
<P>
The Serra de <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> ends in a spectacular cliff at <ORGANIZATION>Cabo da Roca</ORGANIZATION>, the 
westernmost point of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and a great place to watch the sunset. 
</P>
<P>
Mafra, the combination Franciscan monastery and royal palace, was the object of 
a day's hike for <PERSON>Byron</PERSON>. The 800-room edifice included a 35,000-volume library, 
the pride of <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Byron afterward told of the monk who guided them through and who asked politely 
if there were "any books in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>?" 
</P>
<P>
Byron does not mention fog or mists, so he must have been as fortunate as we in 
having clear skies. It can be damp and gloomy at times, especially around 
Capuchos and Castelo dos Mouros. Byron would have appreciated the ghost 
stories. 
</P>
<P>
Displaced European nobility and expatriate Britishers still own the country 
estates -- the quintas -- of <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Several quintas have become country-house hotels at which the line between paid 
and invited guests is casually drawn and the bedrooms are full of 
museum-quality antiques. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Swimming Pools 
</P>
<P>
Swimming pools and tennis courts dapple the manicured grounds. The horses and 
flower gardens are cloned from Kent. 
</P>
<P>
In <PERSON>Byron</PERSON>'s eyes no place on the grand tour matched <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION>. He would write from 
<LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> of a town "in the most beautiful situation (always excepting <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> in 
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>) I ever beheld." 
</P>
<P>
He was not alone in praise. <PERSON>Robert Southey</PERSON>, English poet and historian, and 
<PERSON>William Beckford</PERSON>, an English author, also enticed British tourists to undertake 
what was then a rough ocean voyage. Portuguese poets would sing of it as "a 
garden of earthly Paradise" and claim "here is Spring enthroned." 
</P>
<P>
Andersen observed that some aspect of <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> inevitably reminded the visitor of 
home. He saw in <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> flashes of <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> as we see <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> compared to <LOCATION>New 
England</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Andersen also said that <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> had stayed in "a private house now the Hotel 
Lawrence" on the Setais-Monserrate road. No hostelry of that name survives. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Actually Three Towns 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> is really three towns rising one after another on the mountain, with the 
oldest at the summit. 
</P>
<P>
On a second or fourth <DATE>Sunday</DATE> you can attend the street market in <LOCATION>Sao Pedro</LOCATION> de 
<LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION>. Curio and antique shops are open in the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION> section of town 
every day. 
</P>
<P>
It may not be that the cheese tarts known as Quejadas de <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> were invented 
in <LOCATION>Byron</LOCATION>'s day, nor that the cooks of <DATE>1809</DATE> added a mound of sauteed shrimp to 
the fresh-fried mountain trout "in the <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION> manner." 
</P>
<P>
In any event, <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> visited only four days, <DATE>July 12-16</DATE>, then went to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>. Even <ORGANIZATION>Eden</ORGANIZATION> didn't hold the 21-year-old <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> for long. 
</P>
<P>
 -- -- -- 
</P>
<P>
Car rentals at the <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> airport begin at <MONEY>$124</MONEY> a week plus <PERCENT>16%</PERCENT> tax for a 
<ORGANIZATION>Citroen Visa</ORGANIZATION> with unlimited mileage. 
</P>
<P>
Hotel Palacio dos Seteais, 2700 <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION>, has 18 rooms, including two suites. 
It's a five-star hotel, <MONEY>$120</MONEY> and up, double occupancy, including continental 
breakfast. 
</P>
<P>
Hotel <ORGANIZATION>Tivoli Sintra</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>2710 Sintra</LOCATION>, has 70 rooms. It's a four-star hotel on the 
<LOCATION>Praca da Republica</LOCATION>, about <MONEY>$50</MONEY> double. 
</P>
<P>
Quinta <LOCATION>Sao Thiago</LOCATION>, 2710 <LOCATION>Sintra</LOCATION>, a private manor house, has seven doubles and 
two singles. It's about <MONEY>$70</MONEY> for two with breakfast. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Condos for Rent 
</P>
<P>
Guest houses and B&amp;Bs may be booked at the tourist office. There are condos 
for rent in <LOCATION>Cascais</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Estoril</LOCATION>, and hotels in all classes. 
</P>
<P>
The nearest pousada (government inn) is Pousada do Castelo, a nine-room castle 
on the coast at Obidos. 
</P>
<P>
Palacio dos <PERSON>Seteais</PERSON> has a notable dining room. Dinner for two costs about <MONEY>$40</MONEY>. 
Reservations are essential. 
</P>
<P>
Galeria Real, <LOCATION>Sao Pedro</LOCATION>, in a building full of antique shops and history, 
serves dinner for two for <MONEY>$45</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
A Tiborna, opposite the Royal Palace, is a small cafe with good service and 
inexpensive food. 
</P>
<P>
For more information on travel to <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, contact the <ORGANIZATION>Portuguese National 
Tourist Office</ORGANIZATION>,, 548 Fifth Ave., <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 10036, or call (212) 354-4403. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Convento de Santa Cruz in Capuchos is a monastery carved in the rock and 
insulated with cork. ; Photo, Pena Palace is a wedding-cake structure atop the 
Serra de Sintra. BETTY LOWRY 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-19869 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu056_k_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-056 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  5 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> PORTUGAL </F>
<H3> <TI>   Chief of Staff on Modernization of Armed Forces </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PM2203142894 Lisbon EXPRESSO in Portuguese 5 Mar 94 p 2 </F>
<F P=103> PM2203142894 </F>
<F P=104>  Lisbon EXPRESSO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FP=106> [Interview with <ORGANIZATION>Admiral Fuzeta da Ponte, Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> chief </F>
of staff, by <PERSON>Jose Manuel Saraiva</PERSON>; place and date not given] 
  [Excerpt] [passage omitted] [<PERSON>Saraiva</PERSON>] The EMGFA [Armed 
Forces General Staff] is a very bureaucratic structure. What 
will you do to make this body effective, open, and perhaps more 
modern? 
  [Fuzeta] In the first place, I will have to concern myself 
with a rigorous assessment of the degrees of readiness and 
maintenance of the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>. Over the past few years we 
have witnessed profound changes in the Armed Forces, ranging 
from the initiation of new laws governing the body to the new 
personnel recruitment and pay systems, with a view to the 
greater effectiveness of the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>. The changes in the 
EMGFA form part of a broader plan that I wish to implement and 
whose aim is to assess the final outcome of those changes. 
  [Saraiva] Do you believe that the material and human 
resources of the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> are sufficient to implement that 
plan? 
  [Fuzeta] No military chief anywhere in the world deems the 
available resources sufficient. In the first place, the needs 
are always very great. We must acknowledge that a great deal 
has been done in <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> to improve the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>. This is 
a fact that must be acknowledged, but we must also remember that 
the recovery of the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> started from a very low 
point.... 
  [<LOCATION>Saraiva</LOCATION>] What do you mean by that? 
  [Fuzeta] I mean that our Armed Forces were already obsolete. 
Their modernization depends on the level of investment, which 
means that the greater the resources allocated to the <ORGANIZATION>Armed 
Forces</ORGANIZATION>, the more rapidly they will be able to achieve their 
aims. We are never satisfied. 
  [<LOCATION>Saraiva</LOCATION>] How do you explain young people's enormous lack of 
motivation to serve the Armed Forces? 
  [Fuzeta] This is a very serious matter. Over the years, the 
Portuguese people have always known how to defend the 
fatherland. They have always found considerable motivation to 
that end. Hence the motivation to serve the Armed Forces 
depends to some extent on the perception of the threats 
surrounding society at a given time. An individual immersed in a 
society over which looms a threat of disruption of peace is more 
motivated to serve the country than in the contrary situation. 
Moreover, it is important that it be said that something has 
been done to improve the motivation of the personnel serving in 
the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>. For instance, for career professionals the 
modernization of the new resources is a highly motivating 
factor. Any <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> professional likes to have his M-60's, any <ORGANIZATION>Air 
Force</ORGANIZATION> man eagerly awaits the F-16's; naturally, any sailor is 
pleased with the Vasco da Gama-class frigates. With respect to 
the contract and volunteer personnel, in addition to these 
aspects we are also motivating them through accelerated 
vocational training, so that, after serving in the ranks, they 
will be reintegrated into civilian life. However, it is in 
education that the values that lead the Portuguese people to 
love their fatherland are instilled, and it is imparted in the 
schools and at home. 
  [<PERSON>Saraiva</PERSON>] With respect to the so-called performance of 
military duties, which system do you prefer -- compulsory 
military service or the volunteer and contract system? 
  [Fuzeta] The matter is eminently political. This is an 
important debate that should be conducted in the proper forum. 
Technically, there are Armed Forces that have opted for the 
volunteer system -- for instance, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> -- and others that 
have chosen the compulsory system, such as <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, and have not 
lost effectiveness on that account. I mean by this that it is 
possible to have effective Armed Forces both with the volunteer 
system and with the conscript system. In any event, no system 
is pure. All are hybrids. Right now, we have a roster of 
volunteers, but in the event of a crisis or war, we would still 
have to resort to general mobilization. 
  [<LOCATION>Saraiva</LOCATION>] You referred to vocational training aimed at the 
contractees and volunteers. Does the setting up of these 
institutes have any parallel in the armed forces of other 
countries? 
  [Fuzeta] There are similar measures in several European 
countries -- specifically, in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. 
  [<LOCATION>Saraiva</LOCATION>] But in <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> this is a recent innovation whose 
sole aim seems to be to attract less-qualified young people to 
join up. 
  [Fuzeta] This is in the tradition of the great services to 
the nation performed by the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>. For many years, 
compulsory military service to some extent compensated for the 
basic education that was not given in the schools. It is well 
known that many young people from the poorest families who came 
from the most disadvantaged regions found a basic education in 
the forces, but now that tradition in the Armed Forces is 
exercised in a more sophisticated way. 
  [<LOCATION>Saraiva</LOCATION>] But there are those actually within the Armed 
Forces who say that the fighting military component could be 
disadvantaged for the benefit of a vocational training for which 
the forces are not, at first sight, designed? 
  [Fuzeta] On the contrary. We can only have fighting forces 
in <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> if they are very well trained. We must have small, 
but good forces. There can be no good fighter without good 
training. So the vocational training process helps modernize the 
<ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>, and if that training can be projected outside, so 
as to benefit those whom have performed military service, I can 
see no harm in our civilianizing the training that we currently 
give young people. 
  [<LOCATION>Saraiva</LOCATION>] What role should the Armed Forces have in the 
prevailing international situation? 
  [Fuzeta] It is, of course, different from what it was <DATE>five 
years ago</DATE>, owing to the reduction in intensity of the <ORGANIZATION>East-West</ORGANIZATION> 
conflict. At that time, there was still a large number of 
forces settled on various fronts and with little flexibility. 
Today, the scene is completely different. In the current 
multipolar system we are witnessing several regional conflicts 
that require limited but well-trained and more flexible <ORGANIZATION>Armed 
Forces</ORGANIZATION>. In <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> we must transform the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>, 
precisely so that we can use them strictly in <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s 
interest on the international scene. 
  [Saraiva] Do you believe that <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> should participate 
more in international crises? For instance, during the Gulf 
war, some military men argued that the Portuguese Armed Forces 
should have taken part more actively in the conflict. 
  [Fuzeta] That is a political matter. It is the political 
power that decides on involvement of the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>. However, 
I will simply say that <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> should act in the just defense 
of its interests. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-19660 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu054_k_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-054 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> PORTUGAL </F>
<H3> <TI>   Relationship With UK Reviewed </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  94P20532B </F>
<F P=103> 94P20532B </F>
<F P=104></F>



<TEXT>
Article   Type:<ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

  [Editorial Report] The "old alliance" established 600 years 
ago between <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> was a 
political-diplomatic agreement against the Spaniards, writes 
<PERSON>Jose Vegar</PERSON> in the 5 <DATE>March Lisbon</DATE> weekly SEMANARIO. Noting that 
"things are not much different today," it is still in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s 
strategic interest to align itself with the <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION> in 
the field of European construction, he contends. Vegar cites 
<PERSON>Carlos Gaspar</PERSON>, adviser to President <PERSON>Mario Soares</PERSON>, as saying that 
"it is necessary to choose the lesser of two evils, between 
those who wish to preserve <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s transatlantic vocation and 
the <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>) and those who opt for subregional 
integrations that obviate the existence of the Community." In 
<PERSON>Gaspar</PERSON>'s opinion, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> profits from aligning itself with 
<LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> within the framework of the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>, for this 
"reinforces the tripartite center (<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>United 
Kingdom</LOCATION>)...so enlargement will not negatively affect it." Vegar 
cites <PERSON>Gaspar</PERSON>'s concern about a possible fragmentation of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> through the formation of subregional Scandinavian, 
Iberian, or German blocs. 
  On the other hand, <PERSON>Vegar</PERSON> also cites <PERSON>Andre Goncalves Pereira</PERSON>, 
former minister of foreign affairs, as saying that "there is no 
privileged relationship between <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>." An 
alliance made sense when <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> first entered the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>, given 
the somewhat parallel Portuguese and English positions on 
federalism at that time. However, following <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> assistance to 
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s present stance is much closer to the official 
<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> position, which collides with <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s traditional 
antifederalism, <PERSON>Goncalves Pereira</PERSON> is cited as saying. Vegar then 
cites <ORGANIZATION>Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION> (PS) luminary and former Minister of 
Foreign Affairs <PERSON>Jaime Gama</PERSON>, who notes that "it is to our 
advantage to maintain an intense relationship with the <LOCATION>United 
Kingdom</LOCATION> because we are partners in <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>." 
Nevertheless, <PERSON>Gama</PERSON> continues, the object of this alliance "was 
transferred from <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, which 
unfortunately never occupied this vacuum because it has a 
different awareness of international issues." Finally, <PERSON>Gama</PERSON> is 
cited as claiming that the "old theory of <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> versus 
continental nations" cannot justify <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s interest in 
favoring a close relationship with <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, for "the world 
is presently regulated by multipolarity, and a specific response 
to each problem is needed." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880923-0159 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS: Rare Operas by Meyerbeer and Rossini </HL>
<AUTHOR> Manuela Hoelterhoff </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> San Francisco  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strong man could have rowed around the world more than once in the time it took <PERSON>Giacomo Meyerbeer</PERSON> to finish his opera about the explorer <ORGANIZATION>Vasco da Gama</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Finally, in <DATE>1864</DATE>, after 25 years and who knows how many revisions, he thought he was just about done with "L'Africaine." 
And before he could change his mind again and add another country, a few more trills and two more ballets to his 4 1/2-hour extravaganza featuring four soloists and three elephants, death took the well-worn quill out of the hand of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s most applauded composer. ("Meyerbeer's mother is the second woman in history to see her son accepted as divine," snickered <PERSON>Heinrich Heine</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>'s other famous German Jew.) 

   So any production of this once overrated, now underrated composer is of interest. 
Admittedly this interest flickered on and off at the <LOCATION>San Francisco Opera</LOCATION> <DATE>last weekend</DATE> when the company revived this opera rarity after 16 years. 

   There was little to complain about when the stage offered <ORGANIZATION>Placido Domingo</ORGANIZATION>, all booted up and becomingly bearded as <LOCATION>Vasco</LOCATION>, or <PERSON>Shirley Verrett</PERSON>, in an attention getting hairdo (huge looped braids that looked like extra ears) as the slave queen Selika. 
But when they were out of sight, who was there to keep us awake and entertained? 
Not even a baby elephant. 

   You can't skimp with <ORGANIZATION>Meyerbeer</ORGANIZATION>. 
He knew this himself and took great care to place his cardboard characters in the most distractingly lavish productions money could buy. 
But this fabulously rich man is no longer around to push and pay for them, and the <ORGANIZATION>SFO</ORGANIZATION>'s scenery was rather underwhelmingly modest, with the exception of <ORGANIZATION>Selika</ORGANIZATION>'s tropical paradise, which is not in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, despite the title, for reasons known only to <ORGANIZATION>Meyerbeer</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Coherence was not furthered by the cuts, necessary I know, but clumsily done and in any event vitiated by the conductor <PERSON>Maurizio Arena</PERSON>, who took everything so slowly you wondered whether he might be composing some extra little bits as he went along. 

   Characters drop in from the oddest places, sometimes boarding ships from who knows where in the middle of a storming ocean. 
Very often they sing pretty tunes -- the most famous being <PERSON>Vasco</PERSON>'s "O paradis" -- tunes that float above shimmering orchestrations but rarely are imbedded in a dramatic situation. 

   The best scene was the last, with the abandoned Selika sitting sadly on a seashore inhaling the poisonous fumes of a local tree, but getting off a lovely and long song before she goes. 
As <PERSON>Ms. Verrett</PERSON> poured her heart out, you had a vague notion why <ORGANIZATION>Meyerbeer</ORGANIZATION>'s death was an occasion for national mourning. 

   "Weep! 
Weep! 
Sublime Muse," chanted a somber chorus to a mournful accompaniment of taps and drum rolls at <ORGANIZATION>Meyerbeer</ORGANIZATION>'s funeral. 
This "chant funebre" was written by another neurotic, <PERSON>Gioachino Rossini</PERSON>, whose indolence was as legendary as <ORGANIZATION>Meyerbeer's</ORGANIZATION>. 
After a prolific youth, <ORGANIZATION>Rossini</ORGANIZATION> wrote no operas during the <DATE>last 39 years</DATE> of his life, partly to avoid competing with <ORGANIZATION>Meyerbeer</ORGANIZATION>, though he had more talent in his fat fingers than ever coursed through the German's sickly body. 

   This was pretty clear <DATE>last weekend</DATE> when the fearless <ORGANIZATION>SFO</ORGANIZATION> plunged even deeper down the memory hole to give <ORGANIZATION>Rossini</ORGANIZATION>'s "opera seria" "Maometto II" its first staging in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> since the premiere in <DATE>1820</DATE>. 

   Rossini specialists deem "Maometto" a purer and better opera than a later revision called "The Siege of <LOCATION>Corinth</LOCATION>" (which, revised even further, served as <PERSON>Beverly Sills</PERSON>'s Metropolitan Opera debut in <DATE>1975</DATE>). 
And there is indeed much to be said for it despite a dopey libretto that bears passing resemblance to "The Student Prince" (except that <PERSON>Rossini</PERSON>'s disguised is not some German princeling, but the ruler of half the world). 
The opera's glorious trios develop with the pulsating energy that invariably eluded the bloodless Meyerbeer. 

   But for all that, this seems to be another opera that should be heard, not seen, at least not in a production this dreary (the Met's "Siege" sets, bought for a song, I hope). 
The walk-in tomb looked like the Fuhrer bunker. 
Maometto's tent at least was properly grand, if oddly furnished with a tilted bed that made you wonder how the famed conquerer conquered anything but vertigo. 

   Dressed in golden pantaloons, <PERSON>Simone Alaimo</PERSON> was quite a swaggering sultan, even if his coloratura technique wasn't nearly as polished as the teeth he flashed so menacingly at one point that a retainer fell down in dazzled dread. (<PERSON>Sonja Frisell</PERSON>'s direction had some inspired moments.) 
I myself cowered whenever <PERSON>Marilyn Horne</PERSON> appeared on stage as the Venetian hero, <LOCATION>Calbo</LOCATION>, all decked out in a plumed helmet and large blanket that suggested a crossing of a <ORGANIZATION>Valkyrie</ORGANIZATION> and a horse. 
She didn't sound any better than she looked. 
The end of her convoluted aria was a happy moment. 

   With the fleet-voiced <PERSON>Chris Merritt</PERSON> stuck in the small role of the foolish governor, <PERSON>June Anderson</PERSON> pretty much had the <TIME>evening</TIME> to herself, as <PERSON>Anna</PERSON>, a grim Venetian maiden who commits suicide in a taxing 30-minute scene with a pensive prayer and coloratura finale that left no doubt that the American soprano has few rivals in the high-note-studded bel canto repertoire. 
Pure of voice, physically graceful, she made this impossible character come alive, though even she could not work the miracle of rousing the conductor, <PERSON>Alberto Zedda</PERSON>. 
This was another long evening. 
Listeners bolting for the <ORGANIZATION>SFO</ORGANIZATION>'s bar and buffet broke the sprinting records set the night before at "L'Africaine." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880910-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-10-88 1122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OperaOpening     09-10 0362</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Opera Opening,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Glitterati Attend SF's 66th Opera Season Opening</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Opera star <ORGANIZATION>Placido Domingo</ORGANIZATION> wowed the fans
watching celebrities arrive for the glittering opening of <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>'s 66th formal opera season.
   ``I could have fainted dead away,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Lisa Snow</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, as <ORGANIZATION>Domingo</ORGANIZATION> walked by wearing a tuxedo jacket over blue
jeans. ``He's so wonderful ... not stuck up at all.''
   Domingo starred with <PERSON>Shirley Verrett</PERSON> in a 3{-hour performance
<DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> of <ORGANIZATION>Meyerbeer</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>19th century</DATE> romance, ``L'Africaine.''
   The <LOCATION>San Francisco Chronicle</LOCATION> applauded the stars' passionate
performances, but questioned the ``improbable'' choice of the opera
for the opener. It is the story of the love of a presumed African
woman for Portuguese explorer Vasco da Gama. At the end, she turns
out to be an East Indian queen.
   But for those unwilling to pay the opening night ticket prices,
ranging from standing room at <MONEY>$15</MONEY> to <MONEY>$350</MONEY> for a box seat, the show
was outside.
   Some 100 people _ including one who brought along a 10-foot
python for company _ lined the street outside the <ORGANIZATION>Opera House</ORGANIZATION> to
watch the arrival of men in black tie and tails and jeweled women
in <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> gowns.
   ``Isn't this an evening,'' marveled longtime first-nighter <PERSON>John
McGuire</PERSON>.
   Among those entering the <ORGANIZATION>Opera House</ORGANIZATION> were <PERSON>Gordon</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ann Getty</PERSON>,
heiress <PERSON>Patricia Hearst Shaw</PERSON> and designer <PERSON>Paloma Picasso</PERSON>.
   People who bought standing room tickets started lining up early
in the day.
   <PERSON>Ingrid Sumeri</PERSON> and seven friends among the standees marched into
the Opera <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>, across from <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION>, to party in the lobby before
the show.
   ``This is our third opening,'' she said. ``We always bring a
picnic and have dinner _ cold salmon, baklava, champagne, lots of
good things.''
   After they entered, the big-money crowd arrived after pre-opera
parties that included a museum supper at <MONEY>$175</MONEY> a head, and the <ORGANIZATION>Opera
Guild</ORGANIZATION>'s ball, in a large white tent, at <MONEY>$400</MONEY> each. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> jeweler
<PERSON>Stan Silberstein</PERSON> was on hand for the guild's <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> bash.
   ``There isn't anything I could think of in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> that would
be a reason to be in black tie in the afternoon,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-37225 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes118_d_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-118 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  17 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Libya </F>
<H3> <TI>   Visit by Presidents of Mali, Niger, Burkina Faso </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Visit by Presidents of Mali, Niger, Burkina Faso </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Al-Qadhdhafi Addresses Banquet </H4>

<F P=102> LD1706165794 Tripoli Voice of Greater Arab Homeland in 
Arabic 1139 GMT 17 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD1706165794 </F>
<F P=104>  Tripoli Voice of Greater Arab Homeland </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FP=106> [Address by Libyan leader Colonel Mu'ammar al-Qadhdhafi at a </F>
banquet held in honor of the visiting presidents of <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, and <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Tripoli</LOCATION> on 16 <DATE>June</DATE> -- recorded] 
  [Excerpts] In the name of God. I warmly welcome our 
brothers and neighbors, the leaders of the African-Muslim 
countries: <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> in the same manner as 
we welcomed our friend <PERSON>Museveni</PERSON>, the Ugandan president, and 
before him our brother <PERSON>Deby</PERSON>, the president of <LOCATION>Chad</LOCATION>. 
  The Libyan people welcome and appreciate such solidarity 
from 
their brothers because it will consolidate the Libyan people's 
position in its confrontation with the conspiracy led by three 
colonialist-Western countries. [passage omitted] 
  The Libyan people feels comfortable after the effort it 
extended to the neighboring fraternal peoples and deems that the 
patriots have assumed power in these countries and the agents 
have fallen. 
  The Libyan people has undertaken numerous responsibilities 
toward these peoples. The victory of the will of the peoples of 
<LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, and <LOCATION>Chad</LOCATION>, and the consolidation of 
freedom and democracy....[pauses] On the other hand, from the 
viewpoint of the Western imperialist countries, what the Libyan 
people were doing was considered support for international 
terrorism, and considered the training camps for those leaders 
and peoples, who were carrying out a liberation war, as 
terrorist camps. This pretext has now been exposed, and this 
Western propaganda, which they used so frequently in the 
aggression against <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>, has fallen. But, it seems that the 
colonialists will not let the Third World achieve stability and 
build itself in order to progress. 
  After these national movements won in these countries, we 
see 
that the colonialist countries work toward creating trouble and 
problems for them. The material evidence that condemn the 
countries of Western colonialism are obvious. They accuse us of 
all untrue accusations and refuse to be confronted with the 
facts that condemn them. Regrettably, this will not lead to an 
understanding between us. 
  We all know that these peoples now, in <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Burkina Faso</PERSON>, 
and <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>, who aspire for stability and construction, are today 
the target of a new plot. The role of the old type of 
colonialism has been concretely confirmed. This implicit and 
flagrant interference in the domestic affairs of these peoples 
contradicts the statements and declarations made by these 
countries. 
  In the past they accused <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> of being behind the 
destabilization of African states. Yet, it transpired that 
<LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> was behind the cause of liberation and people's democracy. 
Now, the very states who used to accuse <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> are the ones who 
are trying fervently to destabilize the African continent. 
  These are inhuman ethics and a flagrant injustice. The 
Western states are constantly pursuing these states; they are 
trying to sow instability in them; they deny them a chance to 
prove themselves. Psychologically speaking, we feel as if we are 
facing groups who are enemies of humanity. We are facing a 
mentality used to arrogance and the enslavement of others. This 
is not an accusation, but a reality. 
  Who on earth can belittle a person who happens to have a 
black skin? Who in the world introduced the words racial 
discrimination to the dictionary? They are the Western 
colonialist states. 
  Regrettably, we are facing peoples who are defying the whole 
of mankind. We are in confrontation against arrogant states, 
who impose their wrath against us; they use a veto against our 
future. When we raise our voice and resist, they accuse us of 
being warmongers, and against peace. 
  What kind of peace are they talking about? They are talking 
about surrender and that <ORGANIZATION>Third World</ORGANIZATION> people should surrender 
without making a stand. We have decided, nonetheless, to 
resist. A fact that they must understand. 
  Africa should not be destined to face poverty and misery 
until doomsday merely because of its skin, which was God's 
creation. They have begun a new flagrant interference. 
Regrettably they have meddled with the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, which 
used to be the refuge of peoples seeking peace and protection. 
They have torn up the <ORGANIZATION>UN Charter</ORGANIZATION>. They had no right to tear up 
a charter that was written by the people. 
  They have trodden on international law; they have no right 
to 
do so. It is an international law and not an internal one. 
They have been using the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> for a purpose 
completely different from the one that was intended for it. 
They are using the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> as a vehicle for 
neo-colonialism. 
  Before, they used the <ORGANIZATION>League of Nations</ORGANIZATION> to impose their 
protectorate on the colonized Third World countries. As soon as 
they fiddled with it the <ORGANIZATION>League of Nations</ORGANIZATION> fell. 
  Today, the Western powers are accused of working seriously 
for the fall of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>. The best proof is the fact 
that they have been using the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> for their 
manipulation; they have transformed it into an instrument in 
their hands. They have trodden on its charter. 
  Today, they are carrying out their own work in the name of 
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>. They are using the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> outside 
its Charter. Thus, they have decided to kill the <ORGANIZATION>United 
Nations</ORGANIZATION>. This attitude is a serious one that can be very 
harmful to people of the world. This means that we will face a 
new form of chaos. The world will be transformed into a jungle; 
and the Western states will be responsible for the outcome. 
  What is happening these days in a number of Third World 
countries is clear proof of what I have just said. They believe 
that the <ORGANIZATION>Third World</ORGANIZATION> is made up of children and duped people; 
this is in addition to their inferior attitude toward <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>; 
they think that the African people are mere gorillas living in a 
jungle; they do not believe that the inhabitants of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> are 
human beings. Even <PERSON>Dr. Barnard</PERSON>, the heart surgeon who succeeded 
in performing the first heart transplant operation used to hold 
this way of thinking; i.e., black people are not human beings, 
consequently, one should carry out tests on them unreservedly. 
Consequently, he carried out numerous tests on black people, 
like the test performed in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> on mice and rabbits. 
  After having killed a large number of people and destroyed 
their hearts, he succeeded in perfecting the right heart 
transplant technique. All this stems from their attitude of 
inferiority toward the black race. They think that we do not 
understand this. 
  Their behavior is aimed at undermining our will, our desire 
to live, and our right to our land. Now, they are interfering 
in the internal affairs of every state; they believe that we are 
children and duped to the extent that they create problems, then 
they claim that they have to send military forces to solve these 
problems. 
  We are aware that they are the ones who created these 
problems so that they have a pretext to intervene and solve 
them; they think that we are naive and ignorant and imbeciles to 
be fooled by this game. Their mentality is still that of <LOCATION>Vasco 
de Gama</LOCATION>; they think that <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> still resembles the one 
discovered by <ORGANIZATION>Vasco de Gama</ORGANIZATION> when he gave Africans shells and 
beads and took raw material and land in return. All Western 
states are like <LOCATION>Vasco de Gama</LOCATION>; they share the same mentality as 
that of <ORGANIZATION>Vasco de Gama</ORGANIZATION>; they still perceive and consider us as 
the same people who were discovered by <ORGANIZATION>Vasco de Gama</ORGANIZATION>. These are 
the matters that incite revolution, and force us to accept the 
challenge. Why do they not leave <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION> alone, and stop their 
interference? They should let this poor country rebuild itself 
and live. Why do they not leave <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chad</LOCATION> alone? All the 
suffering of these countries is due to this policy. 
  They must understand that while we meet at this level we are 
fully aware of their conspiracies. It is our right to fight and 
we have decided to fight so that they respect us and recognize 
that we are people like them, at least like them, even if we 
believe that we are better than them because we do not commit 
the acts they are committing. Therefore, our mentality is more 
noble than theirs. We do not have the mentality of absurdity, 
human disdain, race, and color segregation. They take pleasure 
in the suffering of the African peoples and laugh at the 
backwardness of the African that they imposed on them in the 
first place. 
  They consider <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> as a jungle, a place for hunting, a 
source for raw materials, and a garden where you can pick 
fruits, but they consider its inhabitants as gorillas. Thus is 
the Western culture that led to colonialism, and world wars, and 
it is the one we are facing nowadays under various names. 
  In <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>, they confronted us in the <LOCATION>Gulf of Sirte</LOCATION>. When the 
world condemned them and this problem was over, they invented a 
problem called al-Rabitah. When it became clear that al-Rabitah 
was a pharmaceutical plant, and the world condemned them and 
showed solidarity with <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>, they created the so-called 
<LOCATION>Lockerbie</LOCATION> issue. 
  In this context, the Libyan people hails your stance during 
the <ORGANIZATION>OAU</ORGANIZATION> [Organization of African Unity] summit meeting. The 
Libyan people hails its brothers and neighbors, as well as all 
the African leaders who stood with the Libyan people. 
  The world condemned them in the <LOCATION>Gulf of Sirte</LOCATION> and al-Rabitah 
cases, and is now condemning them in the <LOCATION>Lockerbie</LOCATION> case. 
Despite all this, we hear astonishing things. They say that 
<LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> is defying the international community. Who is defying 
the international community? 
  For them, the international community means the Western 
colonialist countries. As for the others, they are not at the 
level of the international community. 
  The conspiratorial memorandum handed by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> was considered as the 
will of the international community. They ignore the will of 
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. 
  What do they have to say about the <ORGANIZATION>OAU</ORGANIZATION> summit meeting held 
yesterday in <LOCATION>Tunis</LOCATION> that expressed support to <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> and the 
proposals it made. Are the African countries considered out of 
the international community? 
  The Nonaligned Movement expressed support for <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>, the ICO 
[<ORGANIZATION>Islamic Conference Organization</ORGANIZATION>] expressed support for <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>. 
