<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-10579</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DHCCXAEVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930803
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 AUG 93 / International Company News: Amax/Cyprus mining link hits
snag
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KENNETH GOODING, Mining Correspondent
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE PROPOSED merger between <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> mining groups <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus Minerals</ORGANIZATION> has
run into problems with the authorities. The <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> justice department is using
anti-trust regulations to request more information about their molybdenum
businesses.
Both groups said they were willing to work with the deparment to resolve any
anti-trust difficulties, but <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> said that 'there can be no assurance that
the companies will be able to satisfy any objections the department of
justice may have to the merger'.
Molybdenum, is a versatile and cost-effective alloying agent in special
steels, cast irons, nickel, cobalt and titanium-based alloys. In the
chemicals sector, molybdenum is used in catalysts, lubricants and pigments.
Cyprus owns the <ORGANIZATION>Thompson Creek</ORGANIZATION> molybdenum mine in <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, which produced 40m
lb last year, and the mothballed <LOCATION>Tonopah</LOCATION> mine in <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> has two mines
in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>: the <LOCATION>Henderson</LOCATION>, which produced 33m lb in <DATE>1992</DATE>, and the <LOCATION>Climax</LOCATION>,
also mothballed.
Amax and <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> announced in <DATE>May</DATE> that they wanted to merge their core
operations into a group with assets worth Dollars 5bn and revenues of
Dollars 2.8bn. This would be the second-largest copper producer and the
second-largest coal producer in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.
However, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s aluminium operations would be spun off to shareholders as a
separate company. Amax hoped to clear regulatory hurdles and obtain
shareholder approvals by the end of this year.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Amax Inc.
    Cyprus Minerals Co Inc.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P1021 Copper Ores.
    P3334 Primary Aluminum.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870122-0068 </DOCNO>
<HL> Cyprus Minerals Says
It Earned $4 Million
In The Fourth Quarter</HL>
<DD> 01/22/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CYPM
DOW JONES INTERVIEW (CEO) </IN>
<DATELINE> DENVER  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>

   For the <DATE>year-earlier fourth quarter</DATE>, the mining company reported a loss of <MONEY>$415.8 million</MONEY> on revenue of <MONEY>$218.7 million</MONEY>. 
The loss included a charge of <MONEY>$432.5 million</MONEY> from a write-down of assets. 

For <DATE>1985</DATE>, the company reported a loss of <MONEY>$452.1 million</MONEY>, including the <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> charge, on revenue of <MONEY>$706 million</MONEY>. 

   The company, which mines coal, industrial minerals and metals, has "recovered nicely" from several financial blows since it was spun off by <ORGANIZATION>Amoco Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>July 1985</DATE>, the executive said. 
The setbacks included the cancellation of its major metallurgical coal contract by <ORGANIZATION>LTV Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which filed for protection under Chapter 11 of the federal Bankruptcy Code in <DATE>July 1986</DATE>, and declines in prices and demand for industrial minerals, coal and metal, he said. 

   Contributing to the mining company's move to profitability in <DATE>1986</DATE> were the acquisition of the Sierrita copper and molybdenum mine in <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> at the <DATE>end of the first quarter</DATE>, cost reductions at its <ORGANIZATION>Thompson Creek</ORGANIZATION> molybdenum mine in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and the company's success at setting a floor under its molybdenum price despite industry overcapacity, <PERSON>Mr. Barr</PERSON> said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880208-0079 </DOCNO>
<HL> Amax Inc. Posts Widened Loss For Fourth Period </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> AMX </CO>
<IN> ERN MIN </IN>
<DATELINE> GREENWICH, Conn.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax Inc.</ORGANIZATION> reported a loss of <MONEY>$280.8 million</MONEY> for the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE> after large write-downs to restructure its molybdenum business. 

   The minerals and energy concern had a loss of <MONEY>$49.7 million</MONEY> in the <DATE>year-earlier quarter</DATE>. 


   The write-downs include the closing of the company's Kitsault mine in <LOCATION>Prince Rupert</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>, and the closing of underground operations at its Climax mine in <LOCATION>Climax</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo</LOCATION>. 

   The company also announced that it formed an operating unit, <ORGANIZATION>Climax Metals Co.</ORGANIZATION>, to consolidate its molybdenum and tungsten buinesses. 

   For the full year, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> earned <MONEY>$51.2 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>53 cents</MONEY> a share, up sharply from the <MONEY>$14.3 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>five cents</MONEY> a share, earned in <DATE>1986</DATE>. 

   In addition to the large molybdenum write-downs, the <DATE>1987</DATE> results include a <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY> write-down of some domestic oil and gas properties and gains of <MONEY>$279.1 million</MONEY> from the sale of the concern's <PERCENT>47%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Australian Consolidated Minerals Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a gold mine operator; <MONEY>$43.9 million</MONEY> from an overfunded pension plan, and <MONEY>$38.3 million</MONEY> from the sale of oil and gas properties in the <LOCATION>Dutch North Sea</LOCATION>. 

   The <DATE>1986</DATE> results included a charge of <MONEY>$80.9 million</MONEY> for discontinued operations and a gain of <MONEY>$80.1 million</MONEY> from an overfunded pension plan. 


</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-9401</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CKEB7ADMFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921105
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  05 NOV 92 / Commodities and Agriculture: Molybdenum mine to close
temporarily
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   DENVER
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>CYPRUS MINERALS Company</ORGANIZATION> will temporarily shut its <ORGANIZATION>Thompson Creek</ORGANIZATION> primary
molybdenum mine in <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> because of weak demand for steel, reports Reuter
from <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>.
The company said the mine's sales had fallen in <DATE>1992</DATE>. It will reopen the
mine when it sees improvement in molybdenum prices, which have remained at a
20-year low.
Cyprus said during the shutdown it would meet molybdenum demand from
by-product output at its Sierrita and <LOCATION>Bagdad</LOCATION> copper mines in <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 32
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910201-0136
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910201-0136.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Magma Copper Has
   Surge in Profit;
   Cyprus Shows Drop
   ----
   By Marj Charlier
</HL>
<DATE>
02/01/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A5B
</SO>
<CO>
   MCU CYM
</CO>
<IN>
NON-FERROUS METALS (ONF)
EARNINGS (ERN)
</IN>
<LP>
   Copper producer Cyprus Minerals Corp. reported
fourth-quarter earnings dropped to 12 cents a share from 88
cents a share a year earlier, primarily because of a $40
million after-tax write-down on a molybdenum mine.
   In contrast, Magma Copper Co. said its fourth-quarter
earnings more than tripled to 49 cents a fully diluted share
from 14 cents a share as productivity improved and production
costs declined.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Cyprus said in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> that it earned <MONEY>$8.4 million</MONEY> on
revenue of <MONEY>$478.5 million</MONEY>, compared with <MONEY>$37.4 million</MONEY> on
revenue of <MONEY>$437.3 million</MONEY> in the <DATE>1989 fourth quarter</DATE>. For the
year, the company reported earnings of <MONEY>$111 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$2.38</MONEY>
a share, after asset write-downs on coal, copper, molybdenum,
silver and beryllium facilities totaling about <MONEY>$63 million</MONEY>
after taxes. Revenue was <MONEY>$1.87 billion</MONEY>. In <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus</ORGANIZATION>
earned <MONEY>$164.9 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$3.87</MONEY> a share, on revenue of <MONEY>$1.79
billion</MONEY>. Results for <DATE>1989</DATE> have been restated for a
tax-accounting change.
   Cyprus said <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> operating earnings rose in its
copper-gold-molydbenum group and its coal operations as
higher copper prices helped offset increased production
costs. Molybdenum prices and demand, however, declined
significantly, leading the company to decide to mothball its
<LOCATION>Tonopah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, mine this month.
   Magma, based in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, reported net income of
earnings of <MONEY>$5.9 million</MONEY> on sales of <MONEY>$190 million</MONEY>. Copper
sales declined, but prices increased slightly in the quarter.
Productivity rose as the company's copper smelter reached
capacity and production costs were cut, in part by increasing
the amount of copper refined by energy-saving solvent
extraction methods.
   For the year, the company had net of <MONEY>$84.4 million</MONEY>, or
<MONEY>$2.02</MONEY> a fully diluted share, up <PERCENT>44%</PERCENT> from <DATE>1989</DATE> earnings of
million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$650 million</MONEY>. During the year, the company
increased its cash to <MONEY>$133.6 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$49.4 million</MONEY> while
paying off bank debt of <MONEY>$37.5 million</MONEY> and spending <MONEY>$20.7
million</MONEY> to buy mining property in <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880304-0087 </DOCNO>
<HL> Who's News: Cyprus Minerals' Unit Breaks Into 3 Concerns </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> CYPM WNEWS </CO>
<DATELINE> DENVER  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus Minerals Co.</ORGANIZATION> said it will form three new operating companies out of its <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus Metals Co.</ORGANIZATION> unit and named executives to head them. 

Cyprus acquired <PERCENT>82%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Foote</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>February</DATE>. 

   The company said it will also form a metals development group to identify and develop metals properties in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>C.W. Reno</PERSON>, formerly general manager of the company's Sierrita copper mine near <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, will be executive vice president of that group. 

   Cyprus said it is setting up the operating units because its business is growing rapidly. 
Over the past year, the company has purchased several new mining properties and has increased its gold production. 
Operating earnings for the metals unit more than doubled to <MONEY>$31.9 million</MONEY> for <DATE>1987</DATE> from <MONEY>$15.8 million</MONEY> for <DATE>1986</DATE>. 

   The company produces gold, copper, coal, molybdenum and industrial minerals. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880303-0028 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Cyprus Minerals Co. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> CYPM </CO>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus Minerals Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, said its <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus Twin Buttes Corp.</ORGANIZATION> unit has signed a 15-year lease for the Twin Buttes copper mine near <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, from closely held <ORGANIZATION>Park Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>. 
Terms weren't disclosed. 

   Cyprus, which produces gold, coal, molybdenum, copper and industrial minerals, also said it is purchasing some equipment and plant facilities at the mine from <LOCATION>Park</LOCATION>. 

   Cyprus said the operation of the mine will complement its mining activities at <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>'s nearby Sierrita copper and molybdenum mine, and will enable the company to take advantage of strengthening copper markets. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-6600</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DE0B8AGKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930527
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 MAY 93 / International Company News: Amax deal enriches Cyprus
Minerals' core - Laurie Morse examines prospects of a new power in the coal
and copper industries
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LAURIE MORSE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>MR Milton Ward</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus Minerals</ORGANIZATION>, has enhanced his reputation as
something of a corporate fox. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, he snapped up the assets of
undervalued <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> mining group, at a point when analysts believe
copper and aluminium markets could be close to the bottom.
<PERSON>Mr Ward</PERSON> and his <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> counterpart, <PERSON>Mr Allen Born</PERSON>, agreed to a merger as <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>
struggled with Dollars 2.54bn in long-term debt, declining revenues from
sagging metals prices, and lack of sufficient capital to expand its core
business.
Both men are respected veterans of the mining business, and their alliance,
analysts say, show they are taking a realistic view of world competition and
market conditions.
'We are going to see more of these strategic alliances within the mining
industry, as companies cope with the globalisation of the business and the
effect the collapse of the <ORGANIZATION>CIS</ORGANIZATION> has had on world commodity prices,' says <PERSON>Mr
Vahid Fathi</PERSON>, analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Kemper Securities</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>. 'Mining is in a very
dynamic situation right now.'
<PERSON>Mr Ward</PERSON>, who moved to <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> a year ago after nearly two decades at the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
natural resource company <ORGANIZATION>Freeport McMoRan</ORGANIZATION>, has earned a reputation as an
effective cost-cutter.
He and <PERSON>Mr Born</PERSON>, who went to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> from <ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome</ORGANIZATION>, will share the new
company's chairmanship, but <PERSON>Mr Ward</PERSON> will be chief executive officer.
In acquiring <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> and creating <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus-Amax</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr Ward</PERSON> has continued to focus
on two primary businesses - coal and copper. The deal involves the exchange
of one <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> share for two <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>, subject to adjustments for price
fluctuations in <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> stock.
The new company will be <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s second-largest copper producer, with
reserves of 2.6bn tons of mineable ore. Last year, <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> produced 660m
pounds of copper, and has a Dollars 200m capital expenditure programme under
way to reduce copper production costs.
From <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus</ORGANIZATION> will get 1bn tonnes of new coal reserves and, combined,
the two companies will produce about 60m tons of coal annually. Cyprus will
add its new 40 per cent interest in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>McIlwraith McEacharn</ORGANIZATION> to the
deal. That company, whose markets are mainly Pacific Rim countries, produces
11m tons of coal a year.
<ORGANIZATION>Cyprus-Amax</ORGANIZATION> will also have a 40 per cent stake in <ORGANIZATION>Amax Gold</ORGANIZATION>, which has
annual production of about 250,000 ounces and reserves of about 8.6m ounces.
Cyprus has shed some gold operations in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, but gold
will be included in the combined company's commodity portfolio. Cyprus is
already in talks to acquire several high grade gold deposits in locations
around the world.
The new company will also have dominant positions in lithium, which is used
in aluminum smelting, and molybdenum, used as an alloy in steelmaking.
<ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s oil and natural gas subsidiary will be part of the merger, but <PERSON>Mr
Ward</PERSON> admits the business is not a good fit with his commodity strategy.
Notably, the new company will not have aluminium operations. <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s large
<ORGANIZATION>Alumax</ORGANIZATION> arm will be spun off independently to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> shareholders before the
merger.
'It is a very nicely structured deal. Cyprus didn't have to take the
aluminum business,' says <PERSON>Mr Tom Hess</PERSON>, research analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Northern Trust
Co</ORGANIZATION>.
With most metals markets in the middle of a 13-year decline, analysts say
the Cyprus/Amax deal has substantial potential once metals prices begin to
recover. In the meantime, Dollars 100m in immediate cost savings are
projected, through staff redundancies and closing <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> office.
The merger will also allow a fresh look at <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s remaining businesses,
which <PERSON>Mr Ward</PERSON> is expected to streamline, aiming to be a lowest cost
producer, as he has done at <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>.
'<PERSON>Milton Ward</PERSON> is going to have huge potential to the upside over the next
several years, and very little potential for downside. If metals prices go
lower, other companies, with higher costs, will be forced to curtail
production first,' notes <PERSON>Mr Hess</PERSON>.
<ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Alumax</ORGANIZATION> spin-off is receiving close Wall Street scrutiny. 'It will be
a pure aluminum play,' says <ORGANIZATION>SG Warburg</ORGANIZATION> metals analyst <PERSON>Mr. Victor Lazarovici</PERSON>.
'It has more primary metal to sell in proportion to its size than any other
company.' While the company recorded an operating loss in <DATE>1992</DATE> because of
expenses related to the start up of its new <LOCATION>Quebec</LOCATION> smelter, <ORGANIZATION>Alumax</ORGANIZATION>, which
turned in Dollars 2.4bn in sales last year. is one of the world's lowest
cost aluminium producers.
It is valued at around Dollars 850m. If aluminium prices rise 30 per cent,
that valuation could jump to about Dollars 1.6bn, analysts say, and such
market responsiveness could, they add, make it a popular bet on the
direction of the world economy.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Cyprus Minerals.
    Cyprus-Amax.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P1099 Metal Ores, NEC.
    P1222 Bituminous Coal-Underground.
    P1021 Copper Ores.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    RES  Facilities.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 32
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920305-0165
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920305-0165.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Corporate Focus:
   Cyprus Minerals Changes Strategy, Returns to Basics
   ---
   Company Refocuses on Copper and Coal
   After 5 Years of Diversification
   ----
   By Marj Charlier
</HL>
<DATE>
03/05/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B4
</SO>
<CO>
   CYM
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
ENERGY (ENE)
</MS>
<IN>
COAL PRODUCERS (COA)
ALL NON-FERROUS METALS (NFR)
COPPER, OTHER NON-FERROUS METALS (ONF)
CORPORATE PROFILE (PRO)
STOCK MARKET, OFFERINGS (STK)
</IN>
<NS>
ANALYSTS COMMENTS ON STOCKS, INDUSTRIES &amp; COMPANIES (ANL)
CORPORATE PROFILES (PRO)
STOCK &amp; OTHER MARKET NEWS (STK)
</NS>
<RE>
COLORADO (CO)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   DENVER -- By the time Cyprus Minerals Co. moved into its
brand new, copper-colored office building here three years
ago, it had already outgrown the space. The copper and coal
company's five-year diversification program had led it into
the gold, zinc, talc, iron ore and lithium businesses,
requiring more staff and more room.
   Now, it turns out, the building may be the right size
after all.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   After struggling with a myriad of mineral and metal
ventures that didn't pan out, <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> says it is returning to
basics and concentrating on copper and coal. "We're going to
refocus on our core businesses," said <PERSON>Calvin A. Campbell Jr.</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>'s chairman, when he was named to the additional posts
succeeding <PERSON>Chester B. Stone</PERSON>, who retired suddenly in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   The change in strategy comes none too soon if <PERSON>Mr. Campbell</PERSON>
is to rescue the company's reputation as a shining example of
the rejuvenation of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mining industry. Spun off from
<ORGANIZATION>Amoco Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>July 1985</DATE>, the company overcame high labor and
operating costs, low-quality mines and a dependence on a big
contract with troubled <ORGANIZATION>LTV Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to report record profit of
<MONEY>$164.9 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1989</DATE>. But since then, rising costs,
declining ore grades, aging facilities and some hurried
acquisitions have eroded <DATE>earnings quarter after quarter</DATE>.
   Recent efforts to streamline costs and unload
underperforming assets haven't been enough. Cyprus's copper
production costs have crept higher, to <MONEY>80 cents</MONEY> a pound in
<DATE>1991</DATE> from <MONEY>70 cents</MONEY> a pound in <DATE>1989</DATE>. Attempts to convert small
zinc and gold operations into large, viable businesses have
failed, leaving those operations with high overhead. And
troubled acquisitions have required big write-offs. "Whenever
they seem to be resolving the problem, another problem comes
in," says <PERSON>Vahid Fahti</PERSON>, analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Kemper Securities Group
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>.
   As a result, some observers believe <PERSON>Mr. Stone</PERSON>'s surprise
retirement after less than a year at the helm wasn't entirely
voluntary. Although the company says the move was <PERSON>Mr. Stone</PERSON>'s
decision, the swift departure indicated the board was eager
for a speedier turnaround. The directors believe the company
needs a clearer long-term focus, leaner operations and more
accountability from lower-level managers, <PERSON>Mr. Campbell</PERSON> said
in a recent interview. Mr. Stone couldn't be reached for
comment.
   Some analysts support this strategy. "The company now has
to move from making acquisitions to internal growth," said
<PERSON>Anthony Rizzuto</PERSON>, analyst at <ORGANIZATION>First Boston Corp.</ORGANIZATION> "It's not
going to be able to diversify its way out of its problems."
Nonetheless, <PERSON>Mr. Rizzuto</PERSON> lowered his opinion on the stock to
hold from buy, citing concern about its short-term prospects.
   Even with the management change, a turnaround isn't likely
to occur this year. In <DATE>1991</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus</ORGANIZATION>' net income fell <PERCENT>61%</PERCENT> to
<MONEY>$42.7 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$111 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE>, including a <MONEY>$26
million</MONEY> write-down on the sale of its talc unit to <ORGANIZATION>RTZ Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
company is predicting <DATE>1992</DATE> will be even worse because it
won't be able to refine copper concentrates until <DATE>June</DATE>, when
it finishes rebuilding its copper smelter, which caught fire
last <DATE>November</DATE>. "It ain't going to be a good year," <PERSON>Mr. Stone</PERSON>
said in summing up the situation in an interview just before
his resignation.
   The troubles are quite a change for <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>, which enjoyed
a few heady years after the spinoff. Back then, the company
quickly collected some 20 bargain-basement acquisitions,
including copper mines, smelters and copper-rod plants that
others didn't want, and turned the castoffs into good
producers. The first <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> in acquisitions has already
returned about <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY> in profits, some analysts
estimate. Meanwhile, the company improved its labor contracts
and labor relations and sold off some poorly performing coal
properties and other assets.
   But some of <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>'s later acquisitions outside the copper
area defied the company's apparent Midas touch. A <LOCATION>Tonapah</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, molybdenum property acquired in <DATE>1988</DATE> proved to have
lower grades of ore than the company expected, which became
particularly problematic when molybdenum prices fell. A coal
mine at <LOCATION>Kanawah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>W.Va.</LOCATION>, bought in <DATE>1989</DATE>, had several problems,
including deeper coal seams than anticipated. The company
wrote down the value of both in <DATE>1990</DATE>, for a charge of about
<MONEY>$65 million</MONEY>. "They weren't always sufficiently careful in
these later acquisitions," says <PERSON>Kenneth Friedman</PERSON>, an analyst
at <ORGANIZATION>R.G. Dickinson &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>.
   Also plaguing the company have been weak metals prices:
zinc prices have fallen <PERCENT>33%</PERCENT> in four years; molybdenum is down
<PERCENT>32%</PERCENT>. Copper prices declined to <MONEY>$1.06</MONEY> a pound in <DATE>1991</DATE> from
<MONEY>$1.20</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE>.
   Some analysts have reported long lists of challenges for
the company, including finding more reserves, lowering costs
and getting out of unprofitable businesses. But other
analysts aren't all negative: Stronger prices would minimize
<LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>'s high-cost disadvantage, says <PERSON>Mr. Friedman</PERSON>, who
thinks metals prices will rise as the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and world
economies improve. In addition, says <PERSON>Peter Ingersoll</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman Bros</ORGANIZATION>. Inc., the rebuilt copper smelter could
significantly lower costs, and the company has invested
heavily in equipment that has increased productivity at its
coal operations, readying them for a time when prices rise
again.
   <PERSON>Mr. Campbell</PERSON> isn't going to wait for rising prices to pull
<LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> out of its doldrums, though. A former <ORGANIZATION>Exxon</ORGANIZATION> executive,
he left his most recent post as president of <ORGANIZATION>Chicago-based
Goodman Equipment Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a mining-equipment manufacturer, to
run <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>. He has been on the board since the spinoff in
<DATE>1985</DATE> and was named chairman in <DATE>May 1990</DATE> when <PERSON>Kenneth Barr</PERSON>
retired as president and chairman at <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>'s mandatory
retirement age of 65.
   <PERSON>Mr. Campbell</PERSON> says the company's most immediate problem is
getting costs under control. That will require "reductions in
people and things," he said, declining to elaborate on how
many jobs would be eliminated or what might be sold. The gold
operations, which many mining experts thought would be sold
first, won't go, he said. He said he couldn't comment on
whether the company's molybdenum, zinc or iron ore operations
will stay.
   One thing that's certainly destined for cuts is corporate
staff. To trim costs, <PERSON>Mr. Campbell</PERSON> said he will decentralize
<LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>, leaving fewer people in the new <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> office
building and making mine managers more accountable for
operating results. "We're going to be taking a tougher
approach than we had," said <PERSON>Gerald Malys</PERSON>, chief financial
officer.
   Another priority: improving marketing with better customer
service. Every sales contract will be examined to determine
if there are better delivery schedules, different payment
plans, new packaging or other changes that customers would
like. "You aren't just selling a ton of coal," <PERSON>Mr. Campbell</PERSON>
said. "You're selling a whole relationship."
   Meanwhile, the company will focus its <MONEY>$18 million</MONEY>
exploration effort this year on finding additional copper and
coal reserves, and it is ready to spend the money to acquire
the right properties. New copper reserves will probably come
from outside of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, he said, and the company is
currently looking at a large coal deposit in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr.
Campbell</PERSON> said.
   Cyprus needs higher-grade copper ore reserves to help
reduce production costs, and the company needs to at least
double its coal production in order to be cost-competitive,
he said. "Cyprus spent its early years being very, very
clever in spotting a good deal," he said. Likewise, "we want
to be fortuitous now."
   ---
            <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus Minerals Co.</ORGANIZATION> by the Numbers
                                                                                                       

                     The Fundamentals
                                                                                                       

                                       <DATE>1991      1990</DATE>
                                                                                                       

   SALES (<MONEY>$ bil</MONEY>.)                     <MONEY>$1.68     $1.87</MONEY>
   NET INCOME (<MONEY>$ mil</MONEY>.)               <MONEY>$42.70   $111.00</MONEY>
   EARNINGS PER SHARE                 <MONEY>$0.72     $2.38</MONEY>
                                                                                                       

   MAJOR PRODUCT LINES:
                                                                                                       

   Commodity producer of copper rod and cathodes, gold,
molybdenum, coal, zinc, lithium and iron ore.
                                                                                                       

   MAJOR COMPETITORS:
                                                                                                       

   <ORGANIZATION>Asarco Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Phelps Dodge Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Magma Copper Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>RTZ
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Kennecott Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870211-0126 </DOCNO>
<HL> Amax Estimates
A Narrower Loss
For 4th Quarter</HL>
<DD> 02/11/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> AMX </IN>
<DATELINE> GREENWICH Conn.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
    <ORGANIZATION>Amax Inc.</ORGANIZATION> estimated that its
<DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> net loss narrowed to <MONEY>$49.7 million</MONEY> from a <MONEY>$103
million</MONEY> loss a year earlier.
   For all of <DATE>1986</DATE>, the metals and minerals concern said it had net income of <MONEY>$14.3 million</MONEY>, the company's first full-year profit since <DATE>1981</DATE>, including a gain of <MONEY>$110 million</MONEY> related to pension-plan accounting changes. 
<ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> said its "modest" <DATE>1986</DATE> profit is equivalent to <MONEY>five cents</MONEY> a share after preferred dividends. 

   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> had a full-year loss of <MONEY>$621 million</MONEY>, which included a provision of <MONEY>$360 million</MONEY> for losses on properties and investments. 

   The company didn't give any sales figures. 

<PERSON>Mr. Born</PERSON> attributed the <DATE>1986</DATE> profit in part to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s disposal of "non-core businesses" such as iron ore, lead, copper mining and refining, nickel and most of the agricultural-chemical business. 

   The company's core businesses are aluminum, coal, gold and molybdenum. 
"We're now concentrating our resources and technology in businesses where <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> has relatively low production costs and sustainable competitive advantages," <PERSON>Mr. Born</PERSON> said. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Born</PERSON> said that in addition to generating <MONEY>$450 million</MONEY> in cash from asset sales, the company has trimmed corporate costs, lowered interest expense and reduced the work force. 

   The estimate of the most recent <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> loss includes a charge of <MONEY>$45 million</MONEY> for a reduction in the book value of the <ORGANIZATION>El Mochito</ORGANIZATION> mine in <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION> and a <MONEY>$44 million</MONEY> tax benefit from the elimination of some taxes that had been anticipated. 

   The <DATE>1985 fourth-quarter</DATE> loss included a charge of <MONEY>$45 million</MONEY> for losses on tungsten and base-metal properties and investments, a loss of <MONEY>$45 million</MONEY> on the anticipated disposition of the agricultural-chemicals business, and a net gain of <MONEY>$45 million</MONEY> from the sale of the iron-ore business. 


</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870625-0116 </DOCNO>
<HL> Amax Slates Cutbacks at Mine</HL>
<DD> 06/25/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> AMX </IN>
<DATELINE> GREENWICH, Conn.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said it will cut production and the work force at its <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> molybdenum mine near Empire, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>, citing weaker-than-anticipated demand and a continuing excess supply of molybdenum. 

   In the latest series of reductions over the past five years, the minerals and energy concern said it will cut more than 200 workers, reducing employment to about 400 by the end of <DATE>August</DATE>. 
Production will drop to an annual rate of 18 million pounds from 30 million. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911127-0018
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911127-0018.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Business Brief -- Unocal Corp.:
   Molybdenum Work to End,
   Idling About 200 Employees
</HL>
<DATE>
11/27/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C9
</SO>
<CO>
   CHV UCL
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
ENERGY (ENE)
</MS>
<IN>
CHEMICALS, PLASTICS (CHM)
OIL-INTEGRATED MAJORS (OIL)
PETROLEUM (PET)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<NS>
EARNINGS PROJECTIONS (ERP)
PETROLEUM MARKET (PET)
ACQUISITIONS &amp; MERGERS, TAKEOVERS, BOARD BATTLES (TNM)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NEW MEXICO (NM)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
WASHINGTON (WA)
</RE>
<LP>
   Unocal Corp. said it will close its Molycorp Inc.
molybdenum mining operations in Questa, N.M., and expects to
incur a pretax loss on the business of more than $18 million
this year.
   The closure will idle about 200 people in Questa, where
the unit has been in operation for almost 70 years.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Unocal</ORGANIZATION> said it plans to buy most of <ORGANIZATION>Chevron
Chemical Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s nitrogen fertilizer operations. The price
wasn't disclosed. <ORGANIZATION>Chevron Chemical</ORGANIZATION> is a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Chevron Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Unocal</ORGANIZATION> blamed the mining closure on weakness in the
molybdenum market world-wide. The metal is used as a
hardening agent in steel, and <PERSON>R. Gene Dewey</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Molycorp</ORGANIZATION>'s
president, said future demand appears weak. Current spot
prices for molybdenum are <MONEY>$2.10</MONEY> and <MONEY>$2.15</MONEY> a pound, compared
with <MONEY>$3.60</MONEY> a pound in <DATE>1989</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Chevron</ORGANIZATION> agreement includes two fertilizer
manufacturing and storage facilities in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and a
toll-processing agreement for products made at the <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, plant. <ORGANIZATION>Unocal</ORGANIZATION> expects to offer jobs to 70 of the
facilities' 170 employees, and completion of the sale is
expected in early <DATE>1992</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871216-0113 </DOCNO>
<HL> Cyprus Set to Pay
About $90 Million
For Foote Mineral
---
By Marj Charlier
<DD> 12/16/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CYPM FTE NEM
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus Minerals Co.</ORGANIZATION> said it has agreed in principle to buy <ORGANIZATION>Foote Mineral Co.</ORGANIZATION> for about <MONEY>$90 million</MONEY>. 

   Foote is <PERCENT>82%</PERCENT>-owned by <ORGANIZATION>Newmont Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which has said it would seek to sell some businesses to reduce the huge debt incurred in its successful effort to squelch a takeover bid by <ORGANIZATION>Ivanhoe Partners</ORGANIZATION>, an investment group led by <PERSON>T. Boone Pickens</PERSON>. 
The sale of <ORGANIZATION>Foote</ORGANIZATION> would be <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION>'s first sale under that plan, although the company has also said it is considering selling its <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Newmont Australia Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a gold mining concern. 

   The Foote sale, however, will make only a small dent in <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$2.1 billion</MONEY> long-term debt. 
The company borrowed about <MONEY>$2.1 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>September</DATE> to pay a <MONEY>$33</MONEY> a share special dividend to stockholders. 
<PERSON>Mr. Pickens</PERSON> then dropped his bid for <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION>, but still holds about a <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> stake. 

   For <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>, on the other hand, the deal represents a new ingredient in its minerals production mix. 
Foote, based in <LOCATION>Exton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, produces lithium carbonate, which is used as an alloy in aluminum, as an ingredient in lubricants and in the manufacture of batteries. 
Most of the metals and minerals <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> produces are subject to cyclical price swings, but lithium has had very few price decreases in the past two decades, and demand for the metal is growing. 

   Currently, Denver-based Cyprus mines gold, molybdenum, copper, coal and a number of industrial minerals. 

   In the past six months, <PERSON>Foote</PERSON> has restructured its business, selling and closing its ferro-alloy facilities and its hard-rock lithium production facilities, leaving only the operations that produce lithium from brine. 

   In <DATE>1986</DATE>, <PERSON>Foote</PERSON> had a loss of <MONEY>$8.1 million</MONEY> on revenue of <MONEY>$106 million</MONEY>. 
However, its lithium division earned <MONEY>$6.2 million</MONEY> before taxes on sales of <MONEY>$42 million</MONEY>. 

   Under terms of the proposed acquisition, <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus</ORGANIZATION> would pay about <MONEY>$10.32</MONEY> a share for <ORGANIZATION>Foote</ORGANIZATION>'s 7.3 million common shares outstanding. 
Preferred stock holders will receive cash equal to 3.5 times the amount paid for common stock, <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus</ORGANIZATION> said. 
There are 396,454 preferred shares outstanding. 

Foote rose <MONEY>$2.75</MONEY> a share to close at <MONEY>$8.50</MONEY> on the <ORGANIZATION>American Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>$35.50</MONEY> a share, down <MONEY>$2.625</MONEY> on the <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Cyprus said it would use its current lines of credit to purchase the lithium producer. 
The company said it would merge <PERSON>Foote</PERSON> with an newly formed <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> unit. 
The acquisition is subject to approvals by the boards of <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Foote</PERSON> and shareholders of <ORGANIZATION>Foote</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-22820 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust008___94022" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-008 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   31 March 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> CHEMICAL SCIENCES </F>
<F P=101> CHEMICAL INDUSTRY </F>
<H3> <TI>   Increasing Hydrogenation Activity of Industrial Selective </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Increasing Hydrogenation Activity of Industrial Selective </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Hydrocracking   Catalysts 

<FÊP=102> 947M0018A <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> KHIMIYA I TEKHNOLOGIYA TOPLIV I MASEL in 
Russian No. 11, Nov 93 pp 9-12 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947M0018A </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> KHIMIYA I TEKHNOLOGIYA TOPLIV I <ORGANIZATION>MASEL </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>N.S. Khashagulgova</PERSON>, <LOCATION>L.L. Freyman</LOCATION>, Yu.N. </F>
Zelentsov, <PERSON>B.K. Nefedov</PERSON>, and I.Ye. Gorbatkina, <ORGANIZATION>All-Russian 
Scientific Research Institute of Petroleum Refining</ORGANIZATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Angarsknefteorgsintez Production Association</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 
66.097.3:665.654.2] 
  [Abstract] Zeolites with a pentacyl structure, such as 
TsVK, TsVM, TsVM, and ultrasil, are the main catalysts used in 
hydrodeparaffinization or selective hydrocracking of n-paraffin 
hydrocarbons. To produce high-quality transformer oils from 
paraffin raw materials, these catalysts must possess not only a 
high splitting activity but also a sufficient hydrogenating 
activity. Most hydrogenating heterogeneous catalysts contain 
either noble or rare earth metals or else group VI metals. 
Catalysts containing a nickel-molybdenum complex have a higher 
hydrogenating activity than do catalysts into which metals have 
been added by coextrusion or impregnation. Deposition of a 
nickel-molybdenum complex on solid carriers (aluminosilicates or 
zeolites) helps increase their hydrogenating activity and thus 
helps decrease the content of hydrogenating metals in the 
catalyst. A catalyst's isomerizing activity and its ability to 
redistribute hydrogen (thereby reducing the yield of unsaturated 
compounds) increases in the presence of small quantities of 
wide-pore zeolites (mordenite or ultrastable Y). Tungsten helps 
increase a catalyst's hydrogenating activity in relation to 
polycyclic aromatic compounds, and zinc and chromium reduce 
metals' migration and thereby increase their dispersion and the 
stability of a catalyst's operation. Zinc facilitates 
aromatization of paraffins, and chromium compounds possess an 
independent hydrogenating activity. These and other laws were 
used to develop a new catalyst, SGK-5, which is designed to 
replace the combination SGK-1 plus type <ORGANIZATION>AKM</ORGANIZATION> hydrogenating 
catalyst. SGK-5 contains nickel and molybdenum as its 
hydrogenating components. SGK-5 is simpler to use than the SGK-1 
+ AKM combination; however, it has not been possible to fully 
hydrogenate unsaturated compounds in the presence of SGK-5 
(despite the fact that it has a higher hydrogenating activity 
than the SGK-1 + AKM combination). For this reason, studies were 
undertaken to increase the hydrogenating activity of SGK-5. 
Eight different versions of SGK-5 were produced and compared. 
The comparative tests established that catalysts containing 16 
to <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> (wt) nickel-molybdenum complex have a high 
hydrogenating activity coupled with a high yield of target 
fraction. When the nickel-molybdenum complex exceeds <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>, 
the zeolite content decreases, which has an unfavorable effect 
on the product pour point. Catalysts based on type TsVN zeolite 
were found to result in a target fraction with a low pour point. 
Type TsVM-III zeolite and wide-pore zeolites resulted in 
somewhat of an elevation of the product pour point; however, the 
addition of dealuminized mordenite had a favorable effect on 
yield of the target fraction. Roasting just at 340?C did not 
result in adequate activation of the zeolite component of the 
catalyst or (consequently) the necessary product pour point. 
Staged roasting at 340 and 500?C proved optimum. Tables 2; 
references 18: 14 Russian, 4 Western. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920127-0124
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920127-0124.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Cyprus Minerals
   Had $32 Million
   4th-Period Loss
   ----
   By Marj Charlier
</HL>
<DATE>
01/27/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   CYM
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
</MS>
<IN>
DOW JONES INTERVIEW (CEO)
ALL NON-FERROUS METALS (NFR)
COPPER, OTHER NON-FERROUS METALS (ONF)
</IN>
<NS>
EXCLUSIVE INTERVIEW WITH CHIEF EXECUTIVES (CEO)
EARNINGS PROJECTIONS (ERP)
</NS>
<RE>
COLORADO (CO)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   DENVER -- Cyprus Minerals Corp. expects to report its
operations broke even in the fourth quarter after a fire at
its smelter in Miami, Ariz., shut down the company's refining
Stone Jr. said in an interview.
   Cyprus will report a loss of about $32 million for the
quarter. The loss will reflect a $26 million write-down on
the pending sale of its talc business to RTZ Corp., a
provision for future reclamation costs at a coal mine in
Kentucky and smaller writeoffs.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   For the year, the mining company will report net income of
about <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> on revenue of about <MONEY>$1.7 billion</MONEY>. In <DATE>1990</DATE>,
the company earned <MONEY>$111 million</MONEY>, after <MONEY>$63 million</MONEY> in
write-offs, on revenue of <MONEY>$1.87 billion</MONEY>. For the <DATE>1991 fourth
quarter</DATE>, revenue will be more than <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY>, <PERSON>Mr. Stone</PERSON>
said. In <DATE>1990</DATE>, the mining company reported <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> net
of <MONEY>$8.4 million</MONEY>, or about <MONEY>12 cents</MONEY> a share, on revenue of
<MONEY>$478 million</MONEY>.
   But <DATE>1992</DATE> will probably be an even tougher year for the
company, <PERSON>Mr. Stone</PERSON> said, as <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> won't be able to refine
its copper concentrates for at least the first six months of
the year while it builds a new smelter at <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.
   The company realized a copper price of about <MONEY>$1.06</MONEY> a pound
in <DATE>1991</DATE>, compared with <MONEY>$1.19</MONEY> a pound in <DATE>1990</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Stone</PERSON> said.
   Cyprus's <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> smelter caught fire in <DATE>November</DATE>. The timing
of the fire and closing of the smelter put the company at a
disadvantage because rates charged for smelting copper at
toll smelters have increased to <MONEY>40 cents</MONEY> a pound from about
<MONEY>15 cents</MONEY> a pound in the past year because of a world-wide
shortage of smelter capacity.
   As a result, the company will stockpile its mine
production for the next six months rather than pay high tolls
to have it refined at other smelters, <PERSON>Mr. Stone</PERSON> said. That
will cut income from copper sales in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   In addition, the company expects costs of copper
production to increase in <DATE>1992</DATE> because it anticipates mining
lower-grade ore at all three of its copper mines and it
expects higher stripping costs at two of the mines.
   Also affecting earnings were soft coal prices, depressed
by the recession, the chairman said. Cyprus closed its Empire
Mine in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> this month because of weak demand.
   Iron ore and molybdenum prices are also soft, and the
company's goal for <DATE>1992</DATE> is to have break-even cash flow at
those operations, <PERSON>Mr. Stone</PERSON> said. The company's lithium
business, however, has bucked the downward trend in other
businesses. Earnings from lithium production rose to about
<MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> before tax in <DATE>1991</DATE> from about <MONEY>$17 million</MONEY> in
<DATE>1990</DATE>.
   The company will be looking for more global opportunities
and joint ventures, such as the coal exploration agreement
Cyprus signed with <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s state-owned oil company,
<ORGANIZATION>Petroleos de Venezuela S.A.</ORGANIZATION>, in <DATE>December</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Stone</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880526-0134 </DOCNO>
<HL> Inspiration Plans Sale of Unit to End U.S. Copper Output </HL>
<AUTHOR> Lee Berton (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> IRC CYPM </CO>
<IN> TNM MIN </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Inspiration Resources Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it signed a letter of intent to sell its <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> copper producing and smelting unit for <MONEY>$125 million</MONEY> to <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus Mineral Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Englewood</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo</LOCATION>. 

   Inspiration's move follows the action of other nonferrous metal producers in recent years to leave the copper business because prices until recently had been so depressed. 
It also signals the company's intent to sharply reduce its bank debt and concentrate more on distribution of agricultural chemicals, analysts said. 

   "It's a smart move for <ORGANIZATION>Inspiration</ORGANIZATION>'s shareholders because it puts the company into a good position to reduce debt and recognize profit on other assets," said <PERSON>Daniel A. Roling</PERSON>, senior mining analyst for <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Capital Markets</ORGANIZATION> unit. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Roling</PERSON> noted that Inspiration is one of the biggest <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> agricultural products distributors, with more than 250 retail operations of its <ORGANIZATION>Terra International</ORGANIZATION> unit in the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>South and Southeast</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Reuben F. Richards</PERSON>, Inspiration chairman, said the sale would reduce the company's debt to less than <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> of capitalization from <PERCENT>42%</PERCENT> at the end of <DATE>1987</DATE>. 
<PERSON>James Simon</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Inspiration</ORGANIZATION>'s director of corporate affairs, said the sale would provide a after-tax gain of <MONEY>$45 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> in the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>. 
The sale is subject to a final agreement and regulatory approvals by <DATE>July 1</DATE>. 


   In <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said the purchase will make it the nation's second-largest copper producer, giving it total annual production of more than <MONEY>525 million pounds</MONEY> a year. 
It also will give <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> its first smelter and rod plant, allowing it to better control its copper costs. 

   The minerals concern recently has sold or agreed to sell portions of its industrial minerals unit for a total of <MONEY>$125 million</MONEY> so that it can concentrate on copper, molybdenum and gold. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Inspiration Consolidated Copper Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the subsidiary, employs about 980 people. 
In addition to the smelter, and rod plant, the unit has pit mines, a dump leaching operation, two concentrators, an acid plant, and a tankhouse in <LOCATION>Claypool</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>. 
In <DATE>1987</DATE>, it produced 105.6 million pounds of refined copper, or more than <PERCENT>53%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Inspiration Resources</ORGANIZATION>' total refined copper output. 

   If the sale is completed, <ORGANIZATION>Inspiration Resources</ORGANIZATION> would retain its <ORGANIZATION>Hudson Bay Mining &amp; Smelting</ORGANIZATION> unit in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, which mines copper and other metals. 
Cyprus has been a major supplier of copper concentrates to <ORGANIZATION>Inspiration</ORGANIZATION>'s smelter, <ORGANIZATION>Inspiration</ORGANIZATION> said. 

   Metals analyst <PERSON>Mr. Roling</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Inspiration</ORGANIZATION>'s departure from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> copper-producing business would leave <ORGANIZATION>Phelps Dodge Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Asarco Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>BP America Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>BP Minerals America</ORGANIZATION> unit, formerly <ORGANIZATION>Kennocott Copper Corp.</ORGANIZATION>; and <ORGANIZATION>Magma Copper Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Manuel</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, as major <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> copper producers. 
In <DATE>March 1987</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Newmont Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> spun off <PERCENT>85%</PERCENT> of the stock of <ORGANIZATION>Magma Copper</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> shareholders, retaining <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> ownership. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Roling</PERSON> said the average price of copper rose to <MONEY>76 cents</MONEY> a pound last year from <MONEY>60 cents</MONEY> in <DATE>1986</DATE> and <MONEY>61 cents</MONEY> in <DATE>1985</DATE>. 
Last <DATE>December</DATE>, copper was selling for as much as <MONEY>$1.46</MONEY> a pound, but has since dropped to less than <MONEY>$1</MONEY> a pound. 

   Inspiration's <PERSON>Mr. Simon</PERSON> noted that at the end of the <DATE>first quarter</DATE>, the company had long-term debt of <MONEY>$242.5 million</MONEY> with <MONEY>$84.6 million</MONEY> in current debt. 
"Our aim in this sale is to reduce our exposure to base metals and single commodities and strengthen our balance sheet," he said. 
"Then we can focus on extending our expertise in manufacturing and distribution in other areas." 

   (Revised WSJ <DATE>May 31, 1988</DATE>)
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900426-0050
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900426-0050.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Business Brief -- Cyprus Minerals Co.:
   Net Fell 63% in 1st Period;
</HL>
<DATE>
04/26/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   CYM
</CO>
<IN>
EARNINGS (ERN)
NON-FERROUS METALS (ONF)
</IN>
<LP>
   Cyprus Minerals Co. reported net income fell 63%, on a
1.4% decline in revenue, due to lower copper and molybdenum
prices and higher costs at some of its mines.
   For the first quarter, net income declined to $30.1
$1.96 a share, in the year-earlier period. Year-ago earnings
included a $5 million gain from the sale of clay operations.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Denver-based <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION> said it is seeing improvement in
copper production costs, but the mining company doesn't
expect <DATE>1990</DATE> earnings to be higher than <DATE>1989</DATE> earnings. For all
of <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Cyprus</ORGANIZATION> earned <MONEY>$250.1 million</MONEY> on revenue of <MONEY>$1.79
billion</MONEY>.
   The large earnings drop indicates how vulnerable the
company's earnings still are to fluctuations in copper
prices, despite efforts to diversify into other kinds of
mining ventures over the past five years. Each <MONEY>one cent</MONEY>
increase in copper production costs, or <MONEY>one cent</MONEY> decrease in
the price of copper, results in a 10-cent a share decline in
annual earnings for <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>R. Wayne Atwell</PERSON>, analyst at
<ORGANIZATION>Goldman Sachs &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890803-0040 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890803 </DD>
<AN> 890803-0040. </AN>
<HL> Amax Agrees
@  To Purchase
@  Falconbridge
@  ---
@  Acquisition for $2.42 Billion
@  Would Thwart Noranda,
@  Form Giant Metals Firm
@  ----
@  By Gary Lamphier and Randall Smith
<DD> 08/03/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> AMX FALCF T.NOR N </CO>
<IN> TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
MINING, METALS (NON-PRECIOUS) (MIN)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax Inc.</ORGANIZATION> agreed to acquire <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> under a proposed tender offer valued at <MONEY>2.85 billion Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>US$2.42 billion</MONEY>), or <MONEY>C$36.125</MONEY> a share. 
The move would make <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> one of the world's six largest base-metal producers. 

   The surprise pact between <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>, a big <LOCATION>Greenwich</LOCATION>, Conn.-based aluminum, coal, and gold mining concern, and <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>, a large producer of nickel, copper, and zinc, appears designed to thwart a yearlong creeping takeover of <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Noranda Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a resource giant indirectly controlled by <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> financiers <PERSON>Edward</PERSON> and <PERSON>Peter Bronfman</PERSON>. 

   In over-the-counter trading yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>'s shares soared on the news, closing at <MONEY>US$31.125</MONEY> each, up <MONEY>US$5.50</MONEY> on volume of 561,200 shares. 
In heavy <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> trading, <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>C$36.625</MONEY>, up <MONEY>C$6.375</MONEY>. 

   The <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> closing price, <MONEY>50 Canadian cents</MONEY> above <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s bid price, reflected some investors' expectations that <ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION> might make a counteroffer, alone or with another company. 
But <ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION>, which was told of <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s bid, gave no indication of its intent. 

   "We're reviewing the options," said <PERSON>Alfred Powis</PERSON>, chairman and chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION>, which currently owns 18.8 million, or about <PERCENT>24.9%</PERCENT>, of <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>'s 75.8 million common shares outstanding and has said it seeks control of <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Powis</PERSON> said a counteroffer "may be a possibility," though <ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION> also has "the option of laughing all the way to the bank" by tendering shares to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s bid, which he said would give <ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION> a profit of about <MONEY>C$221 million</MONEY> on its shares. 
Most analysts described <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s offer as fair, and at least one large <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> holder said he expects the offer to succeed. 
"I think it's a fair price. 
If I had to bet, I'd say they {<ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION>} will tender their stock," said <PERSON>William Harnisch</PERSON>, president of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Forstmann-Leff Associates</ORGANIZATION>, an investment management firm that owns about 10 million <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> shares, or <PERCENT>13.2%</PERCENT> of its common. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Harnisch</PERSON> said "There's another <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> out there who I can think of, without blinking an eye," who will likely tender to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s offer. 
<ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s hand is further strengthened by the block of 9.2 million <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> shares that Toronto-based <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> bought back last year. 
<ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman, president, and chief executive officer, <PERSON>William James</PERSON>, himself a former <ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION> executive, said the shares will be tendered to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s bid. 

   "It's a great offer, it's for all the shares, and it's all cash," said <PERSON>Mr. James</PERSON>, who began talks with <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman and chief executive officer, <ORGANIZATION>Allen Born</ORGANIZATION>, in late <DATE>June</DATE>. 
People familiar with the deal said <PERSON>Mr. James</PERSON> "had been looking for somebody" to help fend off the advances of <ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION>, which is mainly interested in acquiring <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Kidd Creek</LOCATION> zinc, copper, and silver operations in northern <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>. 

   In announcing the <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> offer, which is subject to approval by regulators as well as holders of at least two-thirds of <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>'s common shares, <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> also invoked a shareholder rights plan, or "poison pill," effectively blocking <ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION> from adding more than <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> to its existing stake unless it makes a competing bid to all shareholders. 
<ORGANIZATION>Noranda</ORGANIZATION> said it hasn't yet decided whether it will fight the "pill" in the courts. 

   The deal helped fuel speculation in other publicly-traded metal and mining company stocks. 
<ORGANIZATION>Inco Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a big nickel company, was the most actively traded stock on the <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, rising <MONEY>$1.625</MONEY> to <MONEY>$33.75</MONEY> on volume of 3.4 million shares. 
Much of the <ORGANIZATION>Inco</ORGANIZATION> volume occurred when a Canadian securities firm, <ORGANIZATION>Gordon Capital Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, traded a 2.8 million-share block at <MONEY>$33.75</MONEY>. 
"We are not aware of who the ultimate owner is, or the seller," said an <ORGANIZATION>Inco</ORGANIZATION> spokesman. 
"We don't have reason to believe right now that it isn't for passive investment." 

   Analysts said the purchase would be a good fit for <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>, which relies on aluminum for much of its earnings. 
<PERSON>Mr. Born</PERSON>, who took over as president and chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>, has instituted a major restructuring of the once-ailing company, shifting its focus from copper, iron ore, lead and nickel, among other metals, to aluminum, coal and gold, plus molybdenum. 

   If acquired, <PERSON>Mr. Born</PERSON> said, <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> wouldn't be likely to add anything to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s earnings this year, but it could add as much as <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> next year. 
He estimated annual interest charges for the proposed purchase at about <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Born</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> doesn't plan to sell any <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> assets to help finance the purchase, which would raise <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s debt level to about <MONEY>$3.5 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>, or to <PERCENT>56%</PERCENT> of total capital from the current level of about <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Born</PERSON> said permanent financing isn't yet in place, but <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> has received commitments from backers, and it doesn't expect to require a <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> loan guarantee that <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s capital markets group -- dealer manager for the offer in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> -- has agreed to provide. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Born</PERSON> said he doesn't yet know what role the feisty and independent-minded <PERSON>Mr. James</PERSON> would play in the combined company, but he noted that <PERSON>Mr. James</PERSON> is 61 years old. 
"Hopefully, he'll play a strong role," he said. 

   Under the accord, <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> also granted an option to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> to acquire debentures convertible to 9.875 million <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> shares at the bid price, subject to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> acquiring <PERCENT>56%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>'s stock under its offer. 

   At least one analyst was skeptical about the <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> announcement. 
"I don't see why anybody would buy a nickel company at the top of the market," said <PERSON>Ronald Shorr</PERSON>, metals analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Bear Stearns &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> "Even producers are admitting this might be the first year in several years that inventories will increase. 
I don't know where additional demand is going to come from." 

   He said "smart managements made acquisitions three years ago, when things were at their bottoms. 
Amax looks like they've done the opposite. 
I haven't been recommending the stock, but if I had been, I think I'd have egg on my face." 
The transaction, he added, contradicts <PERSON>Mr. Born</PERSON>'s efforts to improve the company's capital structure. 

   ---

   <PERSON>Robin G. Blumenthal</PERSON> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> contributed to this article. 

   ---
@ <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> 
@ <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto 

   Western</LOCATION> world's second-biggest nickel producer; also major producer of zinc, copper, plus some gold and silver. 
@ <DATE>1988</DATE> Results 
@ (Year ended <DATE>Dec. 31, 1988</DATE>, in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars) 
@Revenues .............................. <MONEY>$1.81 billion</MONEY> 
@Net earnings .......................... <MONEY>$289.9 million</MONEY> 
@Earnings per share .................... <MONEY>$3.88</MONEY> 
@Assets ................................ <MONEY>$2.22 billion</MONEY> 
@Shares outstanding .................... 69.8 million basic, 
@ 88.9 million fully 
@ diluted* 
@ <ORGANIZATION>Amax Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Greenwich</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn</LOCATION>. 

   Fourth-biggest North American aluminum producer, third-largest <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> coal producer, one of top 10 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> gold producers; also produces molybdenum. 
@ <DATE>1988</DATE> Results (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars) 
@Revenues .............................. <MONEY>$3.94 billion</MONEY> 
@Net earnings** ........................ <MONEY>$740.9 million</MONEY> 
@Earnings per share .................... <MONEY>$8.42</MONEY> 
@Assets ................................ <MONEY>$4.08 billion</MONEY> 
@Shares outstanding .................... 84.4 million 
@*Includes option granted to <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>, under terms of the bid, to purchase <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> debenture convertible into 9.875 million common shares 
@**Includes special gains 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890802-0296 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-02-89 2014EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Amax-Falconbridge 2ndLd-Writethru f0317 08-02 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Amax-Falconbridge, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0317,0673</SECOND>
<HEAD>Amax To Buy Candaian Mining Company for $2.4 Billion</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 6th graf pvs, `Amax earned ...,' to ADD
closing stock prices. Picks up 7th graf pvs, `In the ...'.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEAN GOLEMBESKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GREENWICH, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax Inc.</ORGANIZATION> announced plans <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to
acquire <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> for <MONEY>$2.4 billion</MONEY> in cash,
capping a complete financial turnaround for the worldwide mining
company.
   If approved by shareholders, the deal will expand <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s mining
operations and mark its return to nickel production. Toronto-based
<ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> is the world's second-largest nickel producer.
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>, the nation's third-largest coal and aluminum producer,
said it has secured financing needed to pay <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY>, or
<MONEY>$36.12</MONEY>{ a share, in Canadian currency for <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>.
   The offer is worth about <MONEY>$2.4 billion</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$30.50</MONEY>, in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
dollars, an <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman said. The acquisition is subject to
approval by Canadian regulatory authorities.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> is an excellent organization with quality people
and assets. Its acquisition will complement <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s current metals
businesses and position the company well to serve growing
markets,'' said <PERSON>Allen Born</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman, chief executive and
president.
   Amax earned <MONEY>$741 million</MONEY> on revenue of <MONEY>$4.2 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1988</DATE>. In
the <DATE>first six months of this year</DATE>, the company reported <MONEY>$245.1
million</MONEY> in profits on revenue of <MONEY>$2.06 billion</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> shares closed up <MONEY>12{ cents</MONEY> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at <MONEY>$25.50</MONEY> in
consolidated <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> trading. Trading in
Falconridge shares was delayed until after the <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> announcement.
The stock shot up after it began trading, closing at <MONEY>$36.62</MONEY>{, up
<MONEY>$6.37</MONEY>{, on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>.
   In the <DATE>last year</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> sought to expand operations and <PERSON>Born</PERSON> said
it was interested in acquiring natural gas properties.
   The possibility of expansion seemed unlikely in <DATE>1985</DATE>, when <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>
ended four years with <MONEY>$1.7 billion</MONEY> in losses.
   In addition to ill-advised ventures into silver and energy, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>
rejected lucrative takeover offers from <ORGANIZATION>Standard Oil of California</ORGANIZATION>,
now <ORGANIZATION>Chevron Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Its interest payments on debts totaled <MONEY>$200
million</MONEY> a year.
   Born was hired in <DATE>1985</DATE> from a Canadian mining company to help
turn the company. Amax then sold about half the subsidiaries
contributing to its <DATE>1984</DATE> losses, pulling out of iron ore, nickel
and agricultural chemicals production. The work force was cut to
nearly half its <DATE>1981</DATE> peak of 20,385 workers.
   In <DATE>1986</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> began making new acquisitions, particularly in
coal and aluminum. The combination of cuts and purchases returned
<ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> to profitability in <DATE>1987</DATE> and its work force has grown again to
about 20,000 worldwide.
   <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> is an international resource corporation that
explores for, develops, mines, processes and markets metals and
minerals. Its major product is nickel, but it also mines
ferronickel, copper and zinc.
   <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> has 9,500 employees with major operations in
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>, a supplier of metals and energy, has as its major products
aluminium, coal, gold and molybdenum.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> deal is conditioned on acceptance of <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION>'s
offer by at least two-thirds of <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> shareholders. No
deadline has been set for tendering the company's 79 million fully
diluted shares, the <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman said.
   If the deal goes through, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> has agreed to make an additional
offer to acquire all untendered shares. Amax recently moved its
headquarters from <LOCATION>Greenwich</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, but maintains corporate
offices here.
   Falconbridge immediately implemented a shareholder rights plan
to defend against hostile offers. The measures would give existing
shareholders the right to purchase additional stock at a bargain
rate if another party acquires at least <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>
stock.
   The so-called ``poison pill'' plan will expire in 120 days if
the deal is not approved by shareholders, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>
said in a joint statement.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman said the company abandoned the nickel
business because it was only a refiner and not a miner. She said
<ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> presented <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> with a ``quality position'' in which it
will both mine and refine nickel.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890802-0266 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-02-89 1157EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Amax-Falconbridge     08-02 0133</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Amax-Falconbridge,0140</SECOND>
<HEAD>Amax Buys Canadian Metals Company</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREENWICH, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE> that it agreed to
purchase <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> for <MONEY>$2.4 billion</MONEY> in cash.
   The deal is conditioned upon approval by at least two-thirds of
<ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION>'s shareholders.
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> said it also agreed to make an additional offer for all
untendered shares.
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Allen Born</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> will fit well with
his company's metals business.
   <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge</ORGANIZATION> is an international resource corporation that mines
and processes metals and minerals. Its major products are nickel,
ferronickel, copper and zinc. Its major operations are in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> is a worldwide supplier of metals and energy. Its major
products are aluminium, coal, gold and molybdenum. It earned <MONEY>$741
million</MONEY> on revenue of <MONEY>$4.2 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880212-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-12-88 1137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-MiningMuseum Adv17   02-12 1096</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mining Museum, Adv 17,1124</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv17</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Wed PMs, Feb. 17, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Leadville Hopes for Federal Nod to Help Museum Lure More Tourists</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TAD BARTIMUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEADVILLE, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Past glories and future dreams of this
economically depressed mining town two miles up in the <LOCATION>Rocky
Mountains</LOCATION> are pinned to a bill now inching its way through <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   The measure aims to bless the <ORGANIZATION>National Mining Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> and
Museum, now housed in the old <LOCATION>Lake County</LOCATION> junior high school here
in <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>, with a federal charter.
   Such a charter brings no bucks but would qualify the museum for
inclusion on lists of national historical sites and maps and other
official documents _ and museum boosters believe that will lure
thousands of mining buffs.
   Tourist dollars are badly needed in <LOCATION>Lake County</LOCATION> where
unemployment stands at <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT>, the highest in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>. The
state's average unemployment rate was <PERCENT>6.4 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>October</DATE>, the
last month tallied.
   <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> is the highest town in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> and an historic
mother lode of legends and lore from the bygone silver and gold
rush days.
   ``We think having the hall of fame and mining museum will
provide a cornerstone for revitalizing <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>,'' said state Rep.
<PERSON>Ken Chlouber</PERSON>. ``We may be one of the richest six cubic miles on
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> because of our minerals, but we have to diversify.''
   Fifty-four mining museums are scattered around the country,
according to the industry. They range from one-room displays to the
new <MONEY>$1.1 million</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>New Mexico Museum of Mining</ORGANIZATION> at Grants, which
spotlights uranium; the <ORGANIZATION>World Museum of Mining</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Butte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>,
which showcases copper; the <ORGANIZATION>American Mining Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, and an exhibition coal mine at <LOCATION>Beckley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>W.Va</LOCATION>.
   But none claims a national designation, say backers who want The
<ORGANIZATION>National Mining Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> and Museum to become an educational
center for the entire industry.
   The museum, set up as a non-profit corporation, was chartered by
<LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE> and has members in 31 states. Industry giants such
as <ORGANIZATION>AMAX</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Phelps Dodge Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>ASARCO</ORGANIZATION> support the idea, and many
mining executives serve on the board of trustees.
   Bills designating the <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> site as the nation's official
mining museum were introduced in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> a year ago.
   On <DATE>Feb. 4</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION> unanimously approved
one version and sent it to the full <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> with 40 co-sponsors.
   An identical resolution is stalled in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> with only half
the 218 co-sponsors required to move it through the legislative
process.
   Museum advocates are chomping at the bit, counting on the
federal charter to help them raise <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> to construct
initial exhibits.
   For more than a century <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> has been synonymous with
mining. In the <DATE>1800s</DATE>, thousands of adventurers dug gold and silver,
found in the town's namesake veins of lead, from surrounding
mountains.
   Legendary characters such as gambler and gunfighter <PERSON>Doc
Holliday</PERSON>, suffragette <PERSON>Susan B. Anthony</PERSON>, the ``unsinkable'' <PERSON>Molly
Brown</PERSON> and English writer <PERSON>Oscar Wilde</PERSON> were attracted to the boom
town 100 miles west of <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, then a nondescript little frontier
settlement.
   In this century, <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s sought-after metal was molybdenum,
used to strengthen steel. <ORGANIZATION>AMAX</ORGANIZATION>'s Climax mine north of town, which
provided steady paychecks through two world wars and the Great
Depression, employed 3,200 people in <DATE>1981</DATE>.
   But <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s mining collapsed in <DATE>1982</DATE> because of declining
steel-making and a world molybdenum glut. Climax now keeps just 48
men on a skeleton maintenance force.
   Town leaders, accustomed to <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s boom-bust history, at
first didn't believe large-scale commercial mining was finished.
But as <LOCATION>Lake County</LOCATION>'s unemployment soared and For Sale signs
sprouted like weeds, committees were formed to plot economic
strategy.
   <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> is 60 miles east of <LOCATION>Aspen</LOCATION>, 40 miles south of <LOCATION>Vail</LOCATION>, and
surrounded by some of the nation's most spectacular scenery,
including two of <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>'s highest peaks, <LOCATION>Mount Elbert</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mount
Massive</ORGANIZATION>.
   One campaign that fizzled over time was ``Operation Bootstrap,''
aimed at coaxing more tourists to the town of 3,300 people, half
the county's population.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Mining Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> and Museum was nothing but an
idea looking for a home when a search committee received
<LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s application in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   ``We heard there was a national competition for the mining
museum, and this community went after it,'' said <PERSON>Chlouber</PERSON>. ``That
effort marked the first time everybody in this town really came
together and forgot about their little turf battles.
   ``Being out of work will do that to you,'' said <PERSON>Chlouber</PERSON>, a
former shift boss at the Climax mine but now unemployed except for
his legislative job, which pays just <MONEY>$11,500</MONEY> a year. ``When we're
all unemployed we support each other.''
   To lure the museum, the school board offered the old junior high
and its 71,000 square feet of space for <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> rent a year. The
county donated parking and free utilities for two years. The town
offered office space, snow removal and improved traffic routing.
<ORGANIZATION>Colorado Mountain College</ORGANIZATION> volunteered to make promotional films,
supply audio-visual help for exhibits and lend its local campus for
mining seminars.
   ``We need this museum,'' said <PERSON>Carol Luoma</PERSON>, who owns the Golden
Burro Restaurant with her husband, <PERSON>Jack</PERSON>. Both lost their jobs when
the Climax mine closed. They gambled their life savings to buy the
cafe on <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s main street.
   ``We've got to all pull together to bring new businesses and
attractions here. This is a great place to live, full of wonderful
people, and I hate to see many of them leaving because there aren't
any jobs,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Luoma</PERSON>. ``The museum can be our showpiece and
help make <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> famous again.''
   <PERSON>Robert Reeder</PERSON>, the museum's executive director, said the
Victorian-style junior high building would eventually be converted
to house a library, geology hall, lecture auditorium and rooms
detailing the history of American mining. The Hall of Fame plans to
periodically pick a person who's made a major contribution to
mining.
   ``We want to show visitors there's virtually nothing you can
look at that mining doesn't have some impact on,'' said <PERSON>Reeder</PERSON>.
``Did you know 17 minerals go into making newsprint? That 14
minerals are needed to manufacture basic cosmetics?
   ``College enrollment in mining engineering is down in this
country from 4,000 students in <DATE>1977</DATE> to 616 this academic year,''
said <PERSON>Reeder</PERSON>. ``We want this museum and hall of fame to stimulate
people's awareness of how important this industry is, both its
past, its present, and its future.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Past glories and future dreams of this
economically depressed mining town two miles up in the <LOCATION>Rocky
Mountains</LOCATION> are pinned to a bill now inching its way through <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   The measure aims to bless the <ORGANIZATION>National Mining Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> and
Museum, now housed in the old <LOCATION>Lake County</LOCATION> junior high school here
in <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>, with a federal charter.
   Such a charter brings no bucks but would qualify the museum for
inclusion on lists of national historical sites and maps and other
official documents _ and museum boosters believe that will lure
thousands of mining buffs.
   Tourist dollars are badly needed in <LOCATION>Lake County</LOCATION> where
unemployment stands at <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT>, the highest in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>. The
state's average unemployment rate was <PERCENT>6.4 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>October</DATE>, the
last month tallied.
   <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> is the highest town in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> and an historic
mother lode of legends and lore from the bygone silver and gold
rush days.
   ``We think having the hall of fame and mining museum will
provide a cornerstone for revitalizing <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>,'' said state Rep.
<PERSON>Ken Chlouber</PERSON>. ``We may be one of the richest six cubic miles on
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> because of our minerals, but we have to diversify.''
   Fifty-four mining museums are scattered around the country,
according to the industry. They range from one-room displays to the
new <MONEY>$1.1 million</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>New Mexico Museum of Mining</ORGANIZATION> at Grants, which
spotlights uranium; the <ORGANIZATION>World Museum of Mining</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Butte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>,
which showcases copper; the <ORGANIZATION>American Mining Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, and an exhibition coal mine at <LOCATION>Beckley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>W.Va</LOCATION>.
   But none claims a national designation, say backers who want The
<ORGANIZATION>National Mining Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> and Museum to become an educational
center for the entire industry.
   The museum, set up as a non-profit corporation, was chartered by
<LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE> and has members in 31 states. Industry giants such
as <ORGANIZATION>AMAX</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Phelps Dodge Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>ASARCO</ORGANIZATION> support the idea, and many
mining executives serve on the board of trustees.
   Bills designating the <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> site as the nation's official
mining museum were introduced in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> a year ago.
   On <DATE>Feb. 4</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION> unanimously approved
one version and sent it to the full <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> with 40 co-sponsors.
   An identical resolution is stalled in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> with only half
the 218 co-sponsors required to move it through the legislative
process.
   Museum advocates are chomping at the bit, counting on the
federal charter to help them raise <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> to construct
initial exhibits.
   For more than a century <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> has been synonymous with
mining. In the <DATE>1800s</DATE>, thousands of adventurers dug gold and silver,
found in the town's namesake veins of lead, from surrounding
mountains.
   Legendary characters such as gambler and gunfighter <PERSON>Doc
Holliday</PERSON>, suffragette <PERSON>Susan B. Anthony</PERSON>, the ``unsinkable'' <PERSON>Molly
Brown</PERSON> and English writer <PERSON>Oscar Wilde</PERSON> were attracted to the boom
town 100 miles west of <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, then a nondescript little frontier
settlement.
   In this century, <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s sought-after metal was molybdenum,
used to strengthen steel. <ORGANIZATION>AMAX</ORGANIZATION>'s Climax mine north of town, which
provided steady paychecks through two world wars and the Great
Depression, employed 3,200 people in <DATE>1981</DATE>.
   But <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s mining collapsed in <DATE>1982</DATE> because of declining
steel-making and a world molybdenum glut. Climax now keeps just 48
men on a skeleton maintenance force.
   Town leaders, accustomed to <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s boom-bust history, at
first didn't believe large-scale commercial mining was finished.
But as <LOCATION>Lake County</LOCATION>'s unemployment soared and For Sale signs
sprouted like weeds, committees were formed to plot economic
strategy.
   <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> is 60 miles east of <LOCATION>Aspen</LOCATION>, 40 miles south of <LOCATION>Vail</LOCATION>, and
surrounded by some of the nation's most spectacular scenery,
including two of <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>'s highest peaks, <LOCATION>Mount Elbert</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mount
Massive</ORGANIZATION>.
   One campaign that fizzled over time was ``Operation Bootstrap,''
aimed at coaxing more tourists to the town of 3,300 people, half
the county's population.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Mining Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> and Museum was nothing but an
idea looking for a home when a search committee received
<LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s application in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   ``We heard there was a national competition for the mining
museum, and this community went after it,'' said <PERSON>Chlouber</PERSON>. ``That
effort marked the first time everybody in this town really came
together and forgot about their little turf battles.
   ``Being out of work will do that to you,'' said <PERSON>Chlouber</PERSON>, a
former shift boss at the Climax mine but now unemployed except for
his legislative job, which pays just <MONEY>$11,500</MONEY> a year. ``When we're
all unemployed we support each other.''
   To lure the museum, the school board offered the old junior high
and its 71,000 square feet of space for <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> rent a year. The
county donated parking and free utilities for two years. The town
offered office space, snow removal and improved traffic routing.
<ORGANIZATION>Colorado Mountain College</ORGANIZATION> volunteered to make promotional films,
supply audio-visual help for exhibits and lend its local campus for
mining seminars.
   ``We need this museum,'' said <PERSON>Carol Luoma</PERSON>, who owns the Golden
Burro Restaurant with her husband, <PERSON>Jack</PERSON>. Both lost their jobs when
the Climax mine closed. They gambled their life savings to buy the
cafe on <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION>'s main street.
   ``We've got to all pull together to bring new businesses and
attractions here. This is a great place to live, full of wonderful
people, and I hate to see many of them leaving because there aren't
any jobs,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Luoma</PERSON>. ``The museum can be our showpiece and
help make <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> famous again.''
   <PERSON>Robert Reeder</PERSON>, the museum's executive director, said the
Victorian-style junior high building would eventually be converted
to house a library, geology hall, lecture auditorium and rooms
detailing the history of American mining. The Hall of Fame plans to
periodically pick a person who's made a major contribution to
mining.
   ``We want to show visitors there's virtually nothing you can
look at that mining doesn't have some impact on,'' said <PERSON>Reeder</PERSON>.
``Did you know 17 minerals go into making newsprint? That 14
minerals are needed to manufacture basic cosmetics?
   ``College enrollment in mining engineering is down in this
country from 4,000 students in <DATE>1977</DATE> to 616 this academic year,''
said <PERSON>Reeder</PERSON>. ``We want this museum and hall of fame to stimulate
people's awareness of how important this industry is, both its
past, its present, and its future.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed PMs, Feb. 17</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880421-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-21-88 0247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--China-Toxic     04-21 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--China-Toxic,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Killed As Toxic Waste Escapes Reservoir</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two people were killed and the livelihoods of
40,000 were threatened when a reservoir holding toxic chemical
waste burst last week in central <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Shaanxi</LOCATION> province, the
official <ORGANIZATION>China Daily</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   The newspaper said that on <DATE>April 14</DATE> a gate collapsed of a
molybdenum waste reservoir of the <ORGANIZATION>Jinduicheng Molybdenum Mining
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, sending poisoned water surging into the nearby Liyu River.
Molybdenum is a metallic substance used chiefly in strengthening
steel.
   The deluge also flowed into two other rivers, washing away
137,000 trees, swamping 52 wells, toppling 25 wooden bridges and
damaging 15 miles of river embankment, the paper said.
   Two villagers drowned when caught in the flood while crossing a
river.
   The daily said villagers were warned not to drink from
contaminated rivers and wells.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870302-0146 </DOCNO>
<HL> Amax Slates Closures
At 2 Colorado Mines</HL>
<DD> 03/02/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> AMX
MINING, METALS (NON-PRECIOUS) (MIN) </IN>
<DATELINE> GREENWICH, Conn.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Amax Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said it will suspend operations at a <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> molybdenum mine and close another for a week, and will cut 220 employees from its workforce to bring supply and demand for the metal into closer balance. 

   The metal and minerals concern said its Climax mine near <LOCATION>Leadville</LOCATION> will be closed <DATE>Friday</DATE> for an indefinite period. 
The weeklong closure of the <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> mine near <ORGANIZATION>Empire</ORGANIZATION> will begin <DATE>March 23</DATE>. 

   By the end of <DATE>March</DATE>, the Climax workforce of 200 will be reduced to about 50, required for security and maintenance, <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> said. 
The <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> workforce will be cut to 620 from 690, including managers and hourly workers. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Amax</ORGANIZATION> had a <DATE>1986</DATE> loss of <MONEY>$65.8 million</MONEY> on sales of <MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-4558</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DCJCTAGHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930310
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 MAR 93 / Commodities and Agriculture: India opens door to private
mining investors
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KUNAL BOSE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   CALCUTTA
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
IN A dramatic policy U-turn, the Indian federal government has decided to
allow private sector participation in the exploration for and mining of 13
minerals hitherto reserved to public sector operations. The minerals are
iron ore, manganese, chrome, sulphur, gold, diamond, copper, lead, zinc,
molybdenum, tungsten, nickel and the platinum group.
Under the new order, Indian public and private sector mining companies will
be allowed 50 per cent foreign equity participation on an automatic basis.
But the government will be ready to sanction higher foreign capital
participation depending on the merits of each case. However, mineral and
metal processing units with any level of foreign equity will now be allowed
to develop captive mines (mines tied to metal processors).
While the new national mineral policy is part of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s economic reform
programme, it is also a response to the need to introduce foreign technology
and funds to develop 'world grade mines to produce minerals at
internationally competitive rates'.
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has had success in recent years in discovering new mineral deposits
through modern exploration techniques, but the public sector, in many cases,
could not mobilise resources to develop mines. For example, <ORGANIZATION>Hindustan
Copper</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s only copper producer, was forced to postpone the development
of Malanjkhand underground copper ore mine with estimated reserve of 275m
tonnes because of lack of finance.
Things may now look up for Hindustan Copper and other public sector
undertakings. According to <PERSON>Mr Balram Singh Yadav</PERSON>, minister of state for
mines, the government has received a good number of enquiries for mineral
exploration from leading mining companies in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
The government is hoping that joint ventures with foreign companies as
partners will focus on the exploitation of those minerals in which the
country is deficient or does not have exportable surpluses. An objective of
the new policy is to promote the export of Indian minerals with as much
value added as possible.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>INZ  India, Asia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P10   Metal Mining.
    P9512 Land, Mineral, Wildlife Conservation.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Natural resources.
    GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 36
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-21228 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpjst011__l94025" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-JST-94-011L </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Japan </ABS>
<DATE1>   25 March 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> Advanced Materials </F>
<H3> <TI>   Matsushita Electric Develops High Strength, High Toughness, Corrosion Resistant Ceramics/Metal Nano Composites </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  94FE0102B Tokyo NIKKEI MATERIALS &amp; TECHNOLOGY in Japanese 
Oct 93 pp 18-19 -- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> 94FE0102B </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo NIKKEI MATERIALS &amp; TECHNOLOGY </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Japanese </F>
Article Type:<ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> 
