<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880223-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-23-88 0311EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Bahamas-Drugs     02-23 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bahamas-Drugs,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bahamian Official Blames US For Failed Interdiction Efforts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior official of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> is angered by
a <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> charge that ``systemic corruption'' in his
government is undermining a combined campaign against illicit drug
trafficking there.
   <PERSON>Paul L. Adderley</PERSON>, attorney general of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, also disputed
recent testimony of an admitted marijuana smuggler that he paid
Prime Minister <PERSON>Lynden Pindling</PERSON> <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> to protect
operations in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> country.
   ``What offends us the most is the judgment that if it were not
for corruption and indifference in this country, the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> would
not and could not be used as a transit route for the smuggling of
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> cocaine and marijuana to <LOCATION>South Florida</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Adderley</PERSON> told a
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> hearing <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``If the corruption and indifference that is perceived were to
magically disappear, the rate of smuggling might not diminish at
all simply because I regret to say the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has not put
the personnel, equipment and operating funds into doing what needs
to be done in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>,'' he said.
   He said it was ``untrue, unfair and distorts the real facts'' to
suggest that the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> is not doing enough to halt the flow of <PERCENT>60
percent</PERCENT> of the cocaine and marijuana that enters the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
through his country.
   But <PERSON>Sen. Alfonse D'Amato</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-N.Y.</LOCATION>, said he still might vote to
deny further <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> assistance to the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> when the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> deals
with the question of drug interdiction efforts by foreign countries
in the next few weeks.
   ``We already have too much rhetoric and empty promises,''
<PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> said.
narcotics matters, combined criticism with praise for the <ORGANIZATION>Bahamas</ORGANIZATION>'
impressive narcotics seizures and cooperation with <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> authorities.
   She said the joint interdiction of 24,860 pounds of cocaine and
146.5 tons of marijuana in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> was ``not equaled
in any other country in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.''
   Nonetheless, she said: ``Narcotics-related corruption remains a
serious problem in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>. The Bahamian government has not
dealt effectively with systemic corruption, which continues to make
the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> attractive to drug traffickers.''
   D'Amato and <PERSON>Sen. Dennis DeConcini</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ariz.</LOCATION>, questioned Adderley
closely about American marijuana smuggler <PERSON>George Baron</PERSON>'s testimony
last week at the drug trial of Colombian cocaine kingpin <PERSON>Carlos
Lehder</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   Baron said he paid <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> from <DATE>1979</DATE>
to <DATE>1981</DATE> in exchange for Bahamian protection for his activities.
Baron also quoted <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> as saying he himself had paid <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>
<MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> a month in bribes.
   <PERSON>Baron</PERSON> said he once paid Pindling <MONEY>$400,000</MONEY> at a gambling casino
on <LOCATION>Paradise Island</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> in the <DATE>fall of 1980</DATE>, which
<PERSON>Adderley</PERSON> said was ``a totally incredible story, an unbelievable
story.''
   Adderley said he intended to investigate <PERSON>Baron</PERSON>'s allegations.
But he also said that for <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> to accept a bribe in a crowded
casino ``would be like the president of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> taking a
bribe in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880521-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-21-88 0401EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lehder     05-21 0635</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lehder,0653</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bahamian Government Says It Will Confiscate Lehder's Property
Itself</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bahamian government has its own
ideas about the property of <PERSON>Carlos Lehder Rivas</PERSON>, whose conviction
on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cocaine-smuggling charges led to a jury ruling that the
Colombian should forfeit his Bahamas assets to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The Bahamas _ whose leader reportedly is a potential target of
the <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> trial prosecutor _ plans to move to confiscate <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s
property itself, according to a statement released <DATE>Friday</DATE> by the
<ORGANIZATION>Bahamas Information Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> has laws that allow it to confiscate the land of
those convicted of drug trafficking outside the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> and it will
use these provisions to confiscate <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s Bahamian assets, the
statement said.
   The statement lauded <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s conviction <DATE>Thursday</DATE> of charges
that he smuggled about 3.3 tons of cocaine from <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> to the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> via the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   A week ago, the Bahamian government took out full-page
advertisements in several major <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> newspapers rebutting charges
by some <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials and news media that it hasn't done enough to
stop drug smuggling and that its officials were bribed by smugglers.
   A federal jury found <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> guilty of all 11 counts, ranging
from conspiracy to import cocaine to engaging in a continuing
criminal enterprise. Lehder has been identified as a leader of the
violent <ORGANIZATION>Medellin Cartel</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>.
   The panel deliberated another 10 hours <DATE>Friday</DATE> on a second phase
of the trial that resulted in the forfeiture of <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s Bahamian
assets.
   The convicted drug smuggler owned a large portion of <PERSON>Norman's
Cay</PERSON>, a Bahamian island about 40 miles southeast of <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>. His
holdings included a 3,000-foot airstrip, three homes on <ORGANIZATION>Norman's
Cay</ORGANIZATION> and a condominium in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>. Lehder, 38, paid about <MONEY>$1.3
million</MONEY> for the property in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE>, and prosecutors said
<PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> used <PERSON>Norman's Cay</PERSON> as his smuggling base. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney
<PERSON>Robert W. Merkle</PERSON> called it ``an aircraft carrier of cocaine.''
   ``The island is wrecked. But that is not to say it would not be
of some future value,'' <PERSON>Merkle</PERSON> said after the verdict on forfeiture.
   Assistant <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Ernst Mueller</PERSON> had urged the jury to
require <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> to forfeit all his Bahamian assets.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Howell W. Melton</PERSON> set sentencing for <DATE>July 20</DATE>.
Lehder faces up to life plus 150 years in prison and <MONEY>$350,000</MONEY> in
fines. Co-defendant <PERSON>Jack Carlton Reed</PERSON>, who was found guilty on one
count of conspiracy, faces a maximum of 15 years behind bars and
<MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> in fines.
   But <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> attorney <PERSON>Edward Shohat</PERSON> told <PERSON>Melton</PERSON> after the jury was
dismissed that under the U.S.-Colombia treaty in existence at the
time of <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s extradition, his client should face a maximum of
only 30 years in prison. Merkle disagreed, and the judge asked both
sides to submit briefs on the question.
   Merkle refused to comment on reports that Bahamian Prime
Minister <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON> _ who trial witnesses said received
million-dollar bribes from <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> _ is his next target.
   Pindling and his aides have denied the allegations, but have
said they understand a <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> grand jury is investigating the
matter.
   Lehder was extradited to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> after a
firefight and his arrest by the Colombian army at a <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION>
mansion.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> drug enforcement officials have warned that while <PERSON>Ledher</PERSON>'s
conviction is important, it alone will not stop the narcotics flow.
   ``You've got an awful lot of heads on the Hydra you have to cut
off,'' <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> Lt. Cmdr <PERSON>Jim Simpson</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE>. ``<PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>
was one of them.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Medellin Cartel</ORGANIZATION> still ships up to <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cocaine
imports. The <ORGANIZATION>DEA</ORGANIZATION> considered <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> one of the four managers of the
cartel until his arrest early last year. The others have evaded _
and sometimes defied _ Colombian and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> justice.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880430-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-30-88 1750EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LehderTrial 1stLd-Writethru a0590 04-30 0808</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lehder Trial, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0590,0826</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Case Against Lehder Paints Bahamas As Linchpin Of Drug
Traffic</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf pvs, `Carlos Lehder ...' to RESTORE dropped
first reference to Merkle.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prosecutors at the trial of alleged
drug lord <PERSON>Carlos Lehder Rivas</PERSON> produced more than 100 witnesses over
22 weeks to show that he operated a multimillion-dollar smuggling
business centered on the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   While the prosecution tried to draw a noose around <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>, it
also presented evidence of the key role of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> island
chain, and a federal grand jury reportedly is looking into the
activities of Bahamian Prime Minister <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON>.
   Lehder, 38, is accused of conspiring to smuggle 3.3 tons of
cocaine into the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> through his private island in the
<LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Norman's Cay</PERSON>, from <DATE>1978</DATE> to <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   The Colombian is charged with conspiracy, possession of cocaine
with intent to distribute, importation of cocaine and operation of
a continuing criminal enterprise. His co-defendant, <PERSON>Jack Carlton
Reed</PERSON>, 57, of <LOCATION>San Pedro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, is charged only with conspiracy.
   The prosecution rested its case against the two <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The
defense is expected to begin <DATE>Monday</DATE> and to last at least two weeks.
   ``The issue in this case is not whether <PERSON>Mr. Lehder</PERSON> was a drug
smuggler but whether <PERSON>Mr. Lehder</PERSON> as an individual committed the 11
crimes charged,'' <PERSON>Ed Shohat</PERSON>, one of <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s attorneys, said last
week.
   When the jury selection started in <DATE>October</DATE>, attorneys said they
expected the trial to last from six weeks to three months. But,
counting jury selection and a two-week Christmas recess, the trial
has ended its 30th week.
   ``<PERSON>Carlos Lehder</PERSON> pursued a singular dream, a singular vision: to
be the king of cocaine transportation,'' <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Robert
Merkle</PERSON> said in his opening statement in mid-November. ``He was to
cocaine transportation what <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION> was to cars.''
   While in federal prison during the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> began hatching
his plans to form a cocaine-smuggling empire, prosecutors said.
   The Colombian first began smuggling small amounts of the drug
inside the lining of suitcases, using young women as couriers,
according to testimony. The smuggling, witnesses testified, became
bolder as time progressed.
   Key prosecution witness <PERSON>Ed Ward</PERSON>, an admitted smuggler, described
<PERSON>Norman</PERSON>'s Cay, about 45 miles southeast of <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>, as the perfect
transshipment point. The island was sparsely populated, had a
3,000-foot airstrip and no police or customs officials.
   Ward testified that he flew 10 loads of Colombian cocaine into
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> for <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>, whom he met in <DATE>1979</DATE>.
   The trial also has touched on alleged payoffs to Bahamian
officials, including allegations from numerous witnesses that
<PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> filled his pockets with bribes from smugglers such as
<PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>.
   Ward testified that he gave former Bahamian Agriculture Minister
<PERSON>George Smith</PERSON> <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> that was ``supposed to go directly to the
prime minister, Prime Minister <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>.''
that <PERSON>Merkle</PERSON> has been presenting evidence about <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> to a
federal grand jury in <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, including reams of material first
presented at the Lehder trial.
   Other news reports have said that the grand jury investigation
was located in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION>, rather than <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>.
   Merkle, when asked last week about whether a grand jury was
investigating <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>, said, ``I can't comment on that.''
   Pindling's name has frequently been mentioned in relation to
drug investigations, but in <DATE>1984</DATE>, a royal commission of inquiry in
the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> found that <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> had more money than known income,
but none of that appeared to be drug-related.
   Pindling won re-election a year ago by invoking the fear common
to small nations in this hemisphere that the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is
meddling in their affairs.
   <PERSON>Bill Kalis</PERSON>, <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>'s spokesman in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> he had
heard reports of grand jury investigations in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> or
<LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION>, but that <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> didn't expect to be indicted.
   ``Most of the testimony at the <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> trial is recycled from the
commission of inquiry,'' <PERSON>Kalis</PERSON> said. He added that the grand jury
``might be hearing some of the same plea-bargaining witnesses that
are appearing at the Lehder trial.'' Much of the testimony in the
trial has come from convicted drug smugglers granted immunity from
prosecution or awaiting sentencing.
   At one point in <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s trial, defense attorneys reminded
prosecutors and jurors that <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> was not on trial.
   But in his opening statement, <PERSON>Merkle</PERSON> had told jurors, ``You also
will hear evidence that <PERSON>Carlos Lehder</PERSON> was making payoffs directly
the prime minister of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, still the prime minister now,
<PERSON>Lynden Pindling</PERSON>.''
   Lehder is also charged in separate indictments in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> indictment accuses him of being one of the leaders of
the so-called <ORGANIZATION>Medellin Cartel</ORGANIZATION>, believed to be responsible for <PERCENT>80
percent</PERCENT> of the cocaine smuggled into <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> _ a drug
operation worth <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY> each year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-60156 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jptdd004__l94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TDD-94-004-L </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Narcotics 

<DATE1>  26 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> LATIN AMERICA </F>
<F P=101> BAHAMAS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Decline in Cocaine Traffic Linked to Antidrug Cooperation </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  FL2301221494 Bridgetown CANA in English 2007 GMT 23 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> FL2301221494 </F>
<F P=104>  Bridgetown CANA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, <DATE>Jan 23</DATE>, <LOCATION>CANA</LOCATION> -- <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> has 
recorded a definite decline in trafficking of illegal drugs 
through a new anti-drug effort between the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, Turks and 
<LOCATION>Caicos Islands</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, says <ORGANIZATION>Public Safety and 
Transport Minister Arlington Butler</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Operation Bahamas Turks and <ORGANIZATION>Caicos Islands</ORGANIZATION> (OPBAT), a 
cooperative effort involving the three territories, was started 
in <DATE>April 1992</DATE> to stamp out the drug trade. 
  And already, 18 months later, <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> says cocaine 
trafficking through the islands has dropped. 
  The public safety minister added that the <DATE>1993</DATE> total for 
cocaine seizure, though not yet official, was expected to be 
just about 700 kilos. 
  "This is an 86 per cent decline from the 4.85 metric tons 
seized in <DATE>1992</DATE> and it is the lowest annual seizure total since 
<DATE>late 1970</DATE>," he said. 
  The minister explained that another first for the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> in 
<DATE>1993</DATE>, was that there was not a single interception of cocaine at 
an airstrip in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>. 
  "The fact that only two airdrops were intercepted in 
Bahamian territorial waters compared to six in international 
waters show great respect for the OPBAT and an obvious decline 
in the traffic." 
  Butler noted that for the 18 months OPBAT has been in 
operation--from <DATE>April, 1992</DATE>, through <DATE>December 31, 1993</DATE>--only 
1.59 metric tons of cocaine was seized in <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>. 
  And 1.85 metric tons were seized in international waters, 
much of it close to the north coast of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. 
  "I think we can conclude that our remarkable joint OPBAT 
programme has brought the traffic of cocaine from <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> to 
<LOCATION>South Florida</LOCATION> through the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> down to irreducible minimum 
during this 18 month period." 
  The public safety minister also reported a fall by more than 
half, in the number of cocaine addicts seeking treatment, as a 
direct result of the anti-drug programme. 
  This, he said, indicated that the drug problem was 
"receding" or "stable." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890322-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-22-89 1216EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Cartel-Bahamas     03-22 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cartel-Bahamas,0611</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Cartel Leaders, Associate Of Bahamian Prime Minister Indicted</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An associate of Bahamian Prime Minister
<PERSON>Lynden Pindling</PERSON> and reputed leaders of <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cocaine
cartel were charged with drug trafficking in a federal indictment
unsealed here today.
   The indictment also accuses alleged cartel leader <PERSON>Pablo Escobar
Gaviria</PERSON> of organizing the assassination of <ORGANIZATION>Colombian Justice
Minister Lara Bonilla</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   Other major figures among the 30 indicted were <PERSON>Everette
Bannister</PERSON>, a close friend of <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>'s, as well as reputed cartel
kingpins <PERSON>Jose Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jorge Ochoa Vasquez</PERSON>, <PERSON>Fabio
Ochoa Vasquez</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gonzalo Mejia</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Robert W. Genzman</PERSON> said the indictment covers <DATE>1974</DATE>
to the present and involved the importation of 44,000 pounds of
cocaine.
   The prosecutor refused to answer questions about continuing
allegations that <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> himself was involved in the drug operation.
   The document charges that <PERSON>Barry Seal</PERSON>, an informant for the <ORGANIZATION>Drug
Enforcment Administration</ORGANIZATION>, was killed at the direction of <PERSON>Fabio
Ochoa</PERSON>, <PERSON>Escobar</PERSON> and other cartel members.
   Also indicted today was <PERSON>Jack Carlton Reed</PERSON>, co-defendant of cartel
leader <PERSON>Carlos Lehder Rivas</PERSON>. They were convicted here last year of
conspiring to import cocaine, and <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> is serving a life sentence.
   ``The case was investigated after the trial of <PERSON>Carlos Lehder</PERSON>, who
is named as a co-conspirator in the indictment as a follow-up to the
trial,'' said <PERSON>Genzman</PERSON>.
   The indictment accuses many of the defendants of running a
continuing criminal enterprise _ punishable by a maximum life
sentence _ and conspiracy to import drugs.
   <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON>, who lives in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>, is charged with receiving bribes
to allow the cartel to use islands just off <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> as a way station
for drug shipments.
   <PERSON>Genzman</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> would seek extradition of
<PERSON>Bannister</PERSON>. As for the cartel leaders, he noted it had taken six
years to get <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and expressed belief the
others would eventually be brought to justice.
   <PERSON>Gorman Bannister</PERSON>, <PERSON>Everette Bannister</PERSON>'s son, is a protected
federal witness who testified the Lehder trial.
   During the trial, <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON> characterized his father, chairman of
<ORGANIZATION>Bahamas World Airlines</ORGANIZATION> and a consultant to <ORGANIZATION>Resorts International</ORGANIZATION>, as
an influence-peddler who took protection payoffs from drug smugglers
and regularly supplied Pindling with money.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, the younger <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON>, wearing a hood, testified before
a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee about drug-related corruption in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   Bannister testified at <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s trial that his father took money
from <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> and former <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> marijuana and cocaine smuggler
<PERSON>Edward Hayes Ward</PERSON> to help protect them from law enforcement.
   ``My father said he made a deal with Carlos to get <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> a
month to make <PERSON>Norman</PERSON>'s Cay operational,'' <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON> testified in
<DATE>February 1988</DATE>, referring to <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s island trans-shipment point in
the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, 40 miles from <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Gorman Bannister</PERSON> said that his father, who had access to police
intelligence information, also had warned <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> about impending
raids on <ORGANIZATION>Norman's Cay</ORGANIZATION>.
   Several witnesses in the <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> trial testified that they had
made payoffs to high Bahamian officials.
   The chief prosecution witness, <PERSON>Edward Ward</PERSON>, said he gave Bahamian
cabinet minister <PERSON>George Smith</PERSON> and <PERSON>Everette Bannister</PERSON> <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> that
was supposed to go to <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>George William Baron III</PERSON> testified in <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s trial that he paid
bribes to <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>. He said he handed a briefcase containing
<MONEY>$400,0000</MONEY> in a crowded casino lounge in <DATE>September</DATE> or <DATE>October 1980</DATE> to
<PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>.
   Pindling has since denied the allegation. In <DATE>1984</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Royal
Bahamian Commission</ORGANIZATION> cleared him of any wrongdoing concerning
allegations that he took payoffs from drug smugglers. Pindling,
first elected in <DATE>1967</DATE>, was re-elected in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890322-0256 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-22-89 2037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Cartel-Bahamas 1stLd-Writethru a0760 03-22 1004</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cartel-Bahamas, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0760,1028</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Indicts Colombia Drug Cartel, Bahamian Connection</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 5-6, `The indictment ..., to CORRECT spelling of
Ochoa, sted Ocho, and to reflect that the Ochoas are brothers; INSERTS
1 graf after 17th graf, `The Bahamian..., to UPDATE with NBC report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leaders of <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Medellin Cartel</ORGANIZATION>
were indicted <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> on charges of cocaine trafficking and
masterminding the slayings of the Colombian justice minister and a
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> drug informant.
   The sweeping indictment alleges that both <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> were used as way stations for <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> in drug imports to
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. Among those charged is a close associate of
Bahamian Prime Minister <PERSON>Lynden Pindling</PERSON>.
   The case ``once again shows that the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is not going
to let up our efforts to catch these individuals who are supplying
drugs to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,'' <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Robert W. Genzman</PERSON> said.
``We feel that the pressure has got to be kept on regardless of how
many indictments come out in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> against members of
the cartel.''
   In all, 30 people were charged in the ``second wave'' of
indictments resulting from last <DATE>May</DATE>'s conviction of <PERSON>Carlos Lehder
Rivas</PERSON>, one of the leaders of the cartel, which officials say is
responsible for up to <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the cocaine imported into the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The indictment accuses cartel leader <PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON> of
organizing the assassination of Colombian Justice Minister <PERSON>Rodrigo
Lara Bonilla</PERSON> on <DATE>April 29, 1984</DATE>, and says <PERSON>Escobar</PERSON> and <PERSON>Fabio Ochoa
Vasquez</PERSON> directed the <DATE>Feb. 19, 1986</DATE>, slaying of former <ORGANIZATION>Drug
Enforcement Administration</ORGANIZATION> informant <PERSON>Barry Seal</PERSON>.
   Other major figures indicted included cartel kingpins <PERSON>Jose
Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON>'s brother <PERSON>Jorge Ochoa Vasquez</PERSON>, and
<PERSON>Gonzalo Mejia</PERSON>.
   None of the cartel members has been taken into custody, although
most have already been indicted in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. They are believed to be in
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, officials said.
   <PERSON>Genzman</PERSON> noted that it took the government six years to get <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>
to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. ``I am confident that in some point in time we
will be able to obtain custody of the others,'' he said.
   Also indicted was <PERSON>Jack Carlton Reed</PERSON>, who was <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s
co-defendant at last year's trial.
   Lehder and <ORGANIZATION>Reed</ORGANIZATION> were convicted here last <DATE>May 19</DATE> of conspiring to
import cocaine. Lehder _ an unindicted co-conspirator in the new
indictment _ is serving a life sentence and <ORGANIZATION>Reed</ORGANIZATION> is serving a
15-year term.
   <PERSON>Genzman</PERSON> said the indictment covers a 15-year period from <DATE>1974</DATE> to
the present, and involves the importation of 44,000 pounds of
cocaine worth <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   ``The indictment contains 205 snapshots of a long-term drug
conspiracy in action,'' <PERSON>Genzman</PERSON> said.
   ``The indictment traces <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s development into a primary
overseas transporter of cocaine for other <ORGANIZATION>Medellin Cartel</ORGANIZATION> members,
and his continued assocation with these members after they developed
their own tranportation operations,'' <PERSON>Genzman</PERSON> said.
   The indictment accuses <PERSON>Escobar</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rodriguez</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mejia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> and the
two Ochoas of running a continuing criminal enterprise _ punishable
by a maximum life sentence _ and conspiracy to import drugs.
   The indictment alleges that after the slaying of <LOCATION>Bonilla</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> the top cartel leaders fled <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, and eventually
traveled to <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>. Lehder and others paid Nicaraguan officials
to allow them to stay in that country and use it as a base to
smuggle cocaine to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, the indictment says.
   They allegedly stored 1,400 kilograms of cocaine at <ORGANIZATION>Los Brasiles
Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> before flying it into the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The Bahamian charged in the indictment, <PERSON>Everette Bannister</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>, is charged with receiving bribes to allow the cartel to use
the islands just off <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s shores as a way station for drug
shipments.
   <ORGANIZATION>NBC News</ORGANIZATION>, citing unidentified federal law enforcement officials,
reported that an early draft of the indictment said <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON> shared
the alleged payoffs with <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> and other Bahamian officials.
Pindling's name was dropped from the indictment after it was
reviewed by the <ORGANIZATION>Justice and State Departments</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>
said. The network did not say whether the early draft named <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>
as a defendant.
   Bannister's telephone in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION> was busy <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and he could
not be reached for comment. <PERSON>Bill Kalis</PERSON>, a spokesman for <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>'s
office, said the government of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> would have no comment on
the indictment.
   <PERSON>Genzman</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has an extradition treaty with the
<LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, and would seek custody of <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON>. He refused to answer
questions about continuing allegations that <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> himself was
involved in the drug operation.
   <PERSON>Gorman Bannister</PERSON>, <PERSON>Everette Bannister</PERSON>'s son, is a protected
federal witness who testified in Lehder's <DATE>1988</DATE> trial.
   In the trial, <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON> characterized his father, chairman of
<ORGANIZATION>Bahamas World Airlines</ORGANIZATION> and a consultant to <ORGANIZATION>Resorts International</ORGANIZATION>, as
an influence peddler who took protection payoffs from drug smugglers
and regularly supplied Pindling with money.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, the younger <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON>, wearing a hood, testified before
a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee about drug-related corruption in the
<LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   Bannister testified in <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s trial that his father took money
from <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> and former <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> marijuana and cocaine smuggler
<PERSON>Edward Hayes Ward</PERSON> to help protect them from law enforcement efforts.
   ``My father said he made a deal with Carlos to get <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> a
month to make <PERSON>Norman</PERSON>'s Cay operational,'' <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON> testified in
<DATE>February 1988</DATE>, referring to <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s island transshipment point in
the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, about 40 miles southeast of <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>.
   Several witnesses in the <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> trial testified that they had
made payoffs to high Bahamian officials, including <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>, who has
denied the allegations.
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Bahamian Commission</ORGANIZATION> cleared <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> of any
wrongdoing concerning allegations that he took payoffs from drug
smugglers. Pindling, first elected in <DATE>1967</DATE>, was re-elected in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   Aside from <ORGANIZATION>Reed</ORGANIZATION>, who was already in prison, only five of those
indicted <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> were immediately arrested, authorities said. They
were identified as <PERSON>Yemel Nacel</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, who is <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s
former wife; <PERSON>Barry Kane</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Hyannis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, attorney; <PERSON>Jeffrey Edward
Lewis</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Diane Helen Thornhill</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Southern
California</LOCATION>; and <PERSON>Donald Gary Podesto</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Rafael</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870513-0119 </DOCNO>
<HL> Corruption Threatens Bahamian Leader's 20-Year Rule
---
Prime Minister Pindling Calls
June Election as New Drug Charges Swirl
---
By Charles F. McCoy
<DD> 05/13/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> LATAM </IN>
<DATELINE> NASSAU, Bahamas  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Corruption helped sweep Prime Minister <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON> into power 20 years ago in this sun-drenched chain of 700 islands. 
Now, it may finally be about to sweep him out. 

   Yesterday, <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON> dissolved <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and scheduled an election for <DATE>June 19</DATE>. 
The race will be the fiercest political battle he and his Progressive Liberal Party, or <ORGANIZATION>PLP</ORGANIZATION>, have faced since <DATE>1967</DATE>, when he helped expose a crooked white-minority government and launched the movement that won independence from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and made him a national hero. 

   Unemployment is high and drug abuse rampant, but the issue that threatens <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON> most is an old one with a new twist: A corruption scandal simmering for more than three years has boiled over again because of fresh charges that he and other top officials have been on the payrolls of international drug lords. 

   He denies the accusations. 
But the flare-up has heaped more pressure on his government and given the <ORGANIZATION>Free National Movement</ORGANIZATION>, or FNM, the opposition party mainly made up of former <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> backers from the black middle class, its first real crack at unhorsing the charismatic leader. 

   Both sides predict landslide victories; most observers rate the race a toss-up. 
"<PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> and his friends have gone too far, at long last," says <PERSON>Kendal Isaacs</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>FNM</ORGANIZATION>'s leader who would become prime minister if his party wins. 
Even some members of <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON>'s party are nervous. 
"It doesn't look so great at the moment," acknowledges <PERSON>Arthur Hanna</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>PLP</ORGANIZATION> member of <ORGANIZATION>Parliment</ORGANIZATION> and former deputy prime minister, who is frequently at odds with the prime minister. 

   Though both parties are basically conservative and pro-Western, the elections could put a new spin on the often prickly relations between the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>. 
Some <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials believe fighting drug smugglers would be easier with <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON> out of power. 
A Pindling triumph, many here feel, could signal that corruption has become an officially sanctioned standard procedure in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>. 

   About <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of the cocaine and much of the marijuana pouring into the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> comes through the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Drug Enforcement Administration</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> estimates. 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials say Bahamian cooperation in combating traffickers has improved in recent years, but some grumble that it hasn't improved enough. 
American officals have been considering whether to take the drastic step of barring some of <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON>'s closest confidants -- including some candidates for Parliament -- from entering the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> because of suspected involvement in drug running. 

   Scandal has been part of the lore of this smuggler's paradise since the days of <ORGANIZATION>Blackbeard</ORGANIZATION>, but the current corruption mess is setting records for duration and damage. 
A <DATE>1984</DATE> report by a government-appointed commission found that dozens of policemen, customs officers and public officials -- some of them <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON>'s closest friends and political allies -- took payoffs from dope smugglers. 

   The report showed <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON> spent eight times what he earned as prime minister over a six-year period, but he wasn't linked directly to any bribes. 
He has branded as "lies" all allegations that he was ever involved with drug traffickers. 

   Since then, <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON> has fought off demands for an early election and survived a palace revolt in which five of his 13 cabinet ministers either quit or were fired. (Under Bahamian law, he had to call a national vote by the end of <DATE>July</DATE>.) 

   But he has done little to distance himself from the corruption imbroglio. 
He recently shocked <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials and some of his own backers by resurrecting two cabinet ministers who were forced to resign in <DATE>1984</DATE> under a cloud of accusations about their ties to drug traffickers. 
Both men will run for <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> with his blessing. 

   "That is outrageous," says <PERSON>Mr. Hanna</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>PLP</ORGANIZATION> member, who some say wants to be prime minister himself. 
"<PERSON>Mr. 
Pindling</PERSON> has refused to make himself accountable to the Bahamian people." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>' first black prime minister, apparently has been counting on his popularity to win him a fifth five-year term. 
The strategy seemed to be working -- until <PERSON>Gorman Bannister</PERSON> showed up in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, suffering from cocaine burnout and loose lips. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Bannister</PERSON> is the son and former business partner of <PERSON>Everette Bannister</PERSON>, a lifelong friend of <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON> known on the islands as a political fixer. 
For the past few weeks, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> law-enforcement officials say, he has been giving them rich detail on his father's alleged dealings with traffickers. 
His most serious accusation: <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON> was the ultimate recipient of some protection money paid by <PERSON>Carlos Lehder</PERSON>, the Colombian cocaine czar who is in federal prison in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> awaiting trial on charges of shipping tons of cocaine into the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> from an isolated Bahamian islet. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON>'s supporters dismiss the younger <PERSON>Mr. Bannister</PERSON>'s stories as ravings. 
Nonetheless, they have invigorated the <ORGANIZATION>FNM</ORGANIZATION>'s campaign. 
"We've picked up enough votes since {the <DATE>1982</DATE> vote} to swing the election," says <PERSON>Arthur Foulkes</PERSON>, spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>FNM</ORGANIZATION>. 
"The Bahamian people are sick of all this foolishness." 

   If graft alone carried much weight in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON> might have been sunk long ago. 
But other problems are fueling discontent with the government. 
Though the tourist trade is still booming and the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>' estimated <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT> growth in gross domestic product last year was the region's best, unemployment is stuck at roughly <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT>. 

   And a lot of cocaine passing through on its way to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> never gets there. 
The islands appear to be in the grip of a drug epidemic. 
"Cocaine is wiping out our young people," says <PERSON>David Allen</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Drug Council</ORGANIZATION>, an anti-drug group partly funded by the government. 

   In a cramped hut that reeks of sweat and urine in a ragged neighborhood called the <LOCATION>Grove</LOCATION>, seven ghostly faces hover around a sputtering candle, smoking "cokome" -- powerful, free-base cocaine. 
This is a "base house," one of an estimated 100 in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>. 
Kids plunk down as little as <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> for a hit. 

   A red-eyed youth pulls on a ceramic pipe, smoke swirling around his head. 
Something is wrong. 
He is yelling, furious -- there's too much noise. 
"This is serious here, man," he snarls, quivering hands jabbing the air. 
"You're not here to talk, you're here to do drugs." 
After tense seconds of silence, he turns his attention back to his pipe. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON>'s supporters say he's honest and that the opposition harps on the corruption issue because it has nothing else to offer. 
They credit the prime minister for the country's relative prosperity. 
"The Bahamian people know <PERSON>Mr. Pindling</PERSON> as a great and honorable leader," says <PERSON>Sean McWeeney</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>PLP</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman. 

   Recently, the prime minister has stepped up attacks on drug abuse and dusted off a proposal to boost the economy by developing tourism. 
In speeches, he rips his critics as "stooges" and "nincompoops," and says he's committed to working with the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> to stem the drug torrent. 

   Some people think if he wins this time he will be politically invincible. 
"It would be a tragedy for the nation," says <PERSON>Eileen Carron</PERSON>, editor of the nation's largest newspaper, the <ORGANIZATION>Tribune</ORGANIZATION>. 
"It would signal to undesirables everywhere that the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> is where corruption is accepted, and where honor and integrity do not count." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880505-0222 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-05-88 2039EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pindling-Bribes     05-05 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pindling-Bribes,0344</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bahamian Prime Minister Attacks Drug Allegations as `Fairy Tales'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASSAU, Bahamas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON>
attacked allegations that he accepted bribes from drug traffickers
as ``absolutely untrue'' and said his government will stand up for
its sovereign rights.
   ``We will take our case to the world. We are citizens of the
world, and we have a right to be heard,'' <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> told a rally
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at a government schoolhouse.
   Earlier, <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> released a statement denouncing the
allegations against him made in testimony during the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> drug
trial of reputed Colombian cocaine kingpin <PERSON>Carlos Lehder Rivas</PERSON>, and
news reports in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> that federal grand juries are
investigating him.
   Pindling, who led the archipelago of 700 islands and 225,000
people to independence after defeating the white-minority
government in <DATE>1967</DATE>, was overwhelmingly re-elected last year in the
aftermath of a <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Royal Commission of Inquiry</ORGANIZATION> that studied
corruption in the Bahamian government and law enforcement. The
probe stopped short of linking <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> directly to drug bribes.
   <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> said in his statement he wasn't surprised by the
allegations that have been made at <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s trial, but would be
surprised if any of the grand juries reportedly investigating his
affairs indicted him.
   ``This is so because the testimony given concerning me is
totally and absolutely untrue,'' <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> said. ``I have never been
offered a bribe and have never accepted a bribe.
   ``For any grand jury anywhere to produce indictments of the kind
speculated about in the press I would regard as a gross miscarriage
of justice and a serious breach of faith on the part of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
government,'' his statement said.
   Several prosecution witnesses testified at <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s trial in
<LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, that <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> took money from smugglers such as
<PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>, who allegedly used <PERSON>Norman</PERSON>'s Cay in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> as a key
transfer point for Colombian cocaine bound for <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> drug officials have estimated some <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of all South
American cocaine reaches the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> from Bahamian transfer
points.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-6897</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CHYAUABJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920821
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  21 AUG 92 / Bahamas lawyer unseats Pindling
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
MR <PERSON>Hubert Ingraham</PERSON>, a 45-year-old lawyer, is to be sworn in as prime
minister of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> following victory, in a general election on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, over Sir <PERSON>Lynden Pindling</PERSON>, the archipelago's premier for the past
25 years.
Provisional results give <PERSON>Mr Ingraham</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Free National Movement</ORGANIZATION> at least 31 of
the 49 seats contested, with the remainder going to Sir <PERSON>Lynden</PERSON>'s Progressive
Liberal party.
<PERSON>Mr Ingraham</PERSON> had focused his campaign on attacking Sir <PERSON>Lynden</PERSON>'s handling of
the economy, which is based on tourism and offshore financial services. He
promised to sell off state-owned enterprises, including several hotels.
The prime minister-elect was a senior member of Sir <PERSON>Lynden</PERSON>'s party until his
dismissal in <DATE>1984</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr Ingraham</PERSON> claimed he was fired because he had advocated
the sacking of officials who were publicly linked to narcotics trafficking.
<PERSON>Mr Ingraham</PERSON> will be faced with a need to restore local and foreign
confidence in the economy. He has promised to turn initially to problems in
the tourism sector, which has suffered from the international recession.
He pledged to 'heal' the nation, encouraging blacks and whites to
participate in the economy. 'You removed from office the longest-serving
elected leader in the <LOCATION>Commonwealth</LOCATION>, perhaps anywhere, and you have done it
peacefully through the electoral process. And for that I congratulate the
<LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>,' <PERSON>Mr Ingraham</PERSON> told supporters.
Sir <PERSON>Lynden</PERSON>, 62, was one of the longest-serving prime ministers in the
<LOCATION>Commonwealth</LOCATION>, and has been a colourful and controversial figure.
Advocating increased economic opportunities in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> for black people,
who make up 85 per cent of the population, Sir <PERSON>Lynden</PERSON> has always argued that
he was seeking economic justice for all Bahamians.
However, his administration had been accused of being corrupt. In <DATE>1983</DATE>,
there were allegations in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> that senior officials of the Bahamian
government, including Sir <PERSON>Lynden</PERSON>, were involved in drug smuggling. He axed
several officials and denied that he was involved.
The charges appeared to have had little effect on his popularity, as the <ORGANIZATION>PLP</ORGANIZATION>
won elections in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 5
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890919-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-89 2346EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Hugo-Bahamas     09-19 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hugo-Bahamas,0544</SECOND>
<HEAD>Residents of Bahamas Brace for Hugo's Passage</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASSAU, Bahamas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Islanders boarded up their homes and
bought supplies <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as Hurricane Hugo, blamed in at least 25
deaths, swept along the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> after leaving an estimated 50,000
people homeless in the eastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
   Weather officials said the hurricane would begin affecting the
British colony of Turks and <LOCATION>Caicos Islands</LOCATION> southeast of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>
chain on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. The storm was moving on a parallel course
east of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   ``All of the islands at some time or another are going to get
some effects (from Hugo),'' said <PERSON>Noel Risnychok</PERSON>, specialist with the
<ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   Weather officials in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> feared Hugo could drift westward
toward more populated islands, including <LOCATION>New Providence</LOCATION>.
   That island, which includes the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> capital city of <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>,
is the most populated with an estimated 135,000 people.
   The government of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> downgraded the hurricane
watch for the central <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> to a tropical storm warning. A
tropical storm warning remained in effect for the southern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>,
though it was discontinued for the Turks and <LOCATION>Caicos Islands</LOCATION>.
   At <TIME>10:30 p.m. EDT</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the hurricane's center was near
latitude 23.8 degrees north and longitude 69.5 west, about 190 miles
east northeast of <LOCATION>Grand Turk Island</LOCATION> in the southern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>,
   Hugo was moving in a northwesterly direction at about 12 miles
per hour with its highest sustained winds at 105 mph.
   Government officials in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION> were monitoring the hurricane but
had not made any special preparations <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> for Hugo, said <PERSON>Bill
Kalis</PERSON>, press secretary for the government's information office.
   Residents were told to monitor weather advisories but could go
about their daily businesses, he said.
   ``They were telling everybody to get the water, the lamps
handy,'' said <PERSON>Dorothea Seymour of Naussau</PERSON>, who has a stall at The
<ORGANIZATION>Straw Market</ORGANIZATION> on Bay Street. ``We never had a storm here for some
years. We're always hearing about storms, but they never come.
   ``Some people worry, some people don't,'' she said.
   ``Although the indications are that it's going to move east of
the more populated areas, no one is relaxing their vigil because it
can change direction,'' <PERSON>Kalis</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Kalis</PERSON> said residents were gathering supplies in preparation.
   ``The stores have reported brisk sales of supplies such as
flashlight batteries and lumber for boarding up windows,'' he said.
   Weather officials in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> said Hugo's threat to the
northwestern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> has intensified because of the
west-northwestern drift that the hurricane is expected to take.
   ``This westward drift can spell trouble for the northwestern
Bahamas which includes the bulk of the population,'' said <PERSON>Ken
Lightbourne</PERSON>, chief meteorological officer for the government's
weather agency in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>.
   Officials with <ORGANIZATION>Paradise Island Airlines</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>,
said they had not changed flight schedules yet, but were monitoring
the hurricane's path.
   ``We're just keeping a close eye on it like everybody else,''
said <PERSON>Hugh Riesdorph</PERSON>, director of flight operations for the airlines.
   He said the company makes 11 round-trip flights daily from <LOCATION>Fort
Lauderdale</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paradise Island</LOCATION>, which is linked by a bridge
to <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890323-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-23-89 0300EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Cartel-Bahamas Bjt   03-23 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cartel-Bahamas, Bjt,0783</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alleged Drug Cartel Leaders, Associate Of Bahamian Prime Minister
Indicted</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leaders of a Colombian drug cartel
bribed Nicaraguan officials for use of a military base as a way
station for 3,000 pounds of cocaine before smuggling it into this
country, according to a federal indictment.
   Leaders of the <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cartel masterminded the slayings of the
Colombian justice minister and a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> drug informant, according to
the <ORGANIZATION>federal District Court</ORGANIZATION> indictment unsealed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The indictment accuses 30 people, including an associate of the
Bahamian prime minister, of participating in a ring that imported 22
tons of cocaine _ <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> worth _ into the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   ``This is an encompassing indictment that talks about the whole
system of importing cocaine from <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> through the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> to the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> beginning in about <DATE>1974</DATE> and continuing into <DATE>1989</DATE>,''
said <PERSON>Jack Hook</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>DEA</ORGANIZATION> spokesman.
   Those indicted are tied to <PERSON>Carlos Lehder Rivas</PERSON>, the Colombian
drug kingpin who was convicted in <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> of
smuggling cocaine into the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   ``This prosecution will further dismantle the <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cartel and
its distribution network in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,'' <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney
<PERSON>Robert W. Genzman</PERSON> said of the latest indictments.
   The cartel, named for the Colombian city where it is based, is
considered the world's largest cocaine trafficking ring. It's said
to be responsible for up to <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the cocaine imported into
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The indictment accuses reputed cartel leader <PERSON>Pablo Escobar
Gaviria</PERSON> of organizing the <DATE>1984</DATE> assassination of Colombian Justice
Minister <PERSON>Rodrigo Lara Bonilla</PERSON>. Escobar and <PERSON>Fabio Ochoa Vasquez</PERSON> also
directed the <DATE>1986</DATE> slaying of former <ORGANIZATION>Drug Enforcement Administration</ORGANIZATION>
informant <PERSON>Barry Seal</PERSON>, the indictment charges.
   After the minister's slaying, cartel leaders fled the South
American country and eventually traveled to <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>, the
indictment said. They stored 3,000 pounds of cocaine at <ORGANIZATION>Los Brasiles
Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in the leftist-ruled country before flying it into
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, the indictment said.
   In <DATE>May 1984</DATE>, <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> and other cartel leaders arranged to pay
Nicaraguan officials large sums of money to allow them to remain in
the Central American nation and to use it as a base for smuggling
cocaine to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, the indictment said. In addition, in
<DATE>July 1984</DATE>, a <ORGANIZATION>Piper Navajo</ORGANIZATION> owned by <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> was given to the
Nicaraguan government as a gift, the indictment said.
   Also indicted was <PERSON>Everette Bannister</PERSON>, a close associate of
Bahamian Prime Minister <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON>. Bannister was accused of
taking money from the cartel to allow the island nation off
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s shores to be used as a way station for drug imports.
   Bannister's telephone in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION> was busy during repeated calls
from <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Bill Kalis</PERSON>, a spokesman for <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>'s
office, said the Bahamian government would have no comment on
<PERSON>Bannister</PERSON>'s indictment.
   <ORGANIZATION>NBC News</ORGANIZATION>, citing unidentified federal law enforcement officials,
reported that an early draft of the indictment said <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON> shared
the alleged payoffs with <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> and other Bahamian officials.
Pindling's name was dropped from the indictment after it was
reviewed by the <ORGANIZATION>Justice and State</ORGANIZATION> departments in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>
said. The network did not say whether the early draft named <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>
as a defendant.
   Genzman refused to answer questions about continuing allegations
that <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> was involved. He did say that the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has an
extradition treaty with the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> and would seek <PERSON>Bannister</PERSON>'s
extradition.
   Other major figures indicted were reputed cartel kingpins <PERSON>Jose
Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON>'s brother <PERSON>Jorge Ochoa Vasquez</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Gonzalo Mejia</PERSON>. Most of the cartel members were earlier indicted in
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> but have not been arrested.
   Also indicted was <PERSON>Jack Carlton Reed</PERSON>, a pilot who is serving a
15-year prison sentence for his conviction with <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>.
   Escobar, <PERSON>Rodriguez</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mejia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> and the <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON> brothers are
accused of running a continuing criminal enterprise _ punishable by
a maximum life sentence _ and conspiracy to import drugs.
   Lehder, an unindicted co-conspirator in the indictment, is
serving a life sentence.
   Only five of those indicted were arrested: <PERSON>Yemel Nacel</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New
York City</LOCATION>, who is <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s former wife; <PERSON>Barry Kane</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Hyannis</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, attorney; <PERSON>Jeffrey Edward Lewis</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>;
<PERSON>Diane Helen Thornhill</PERSON> and <PERSON>Donald Gary Podesto</PERSON> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
authorities said.
   Last <DATE>April</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Columbian Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> negated a <DATE>1979</DATE>
extradition treaty with the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> on a constitutional
technicality.
   <PERSON>Genzman</PERSON> noted that it took the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government six years to get
Lehder to this country.
   ``I am confident that in some point in time we will be able to
obtain custody of the others,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880510-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-10-88 2010EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lehder-Bahamas     05-10 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lehder-Bahamas,0492</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bahamian Government Claims It Fights Drugs</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Lehder Trial Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASSAU, Bahamas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bahamian government took out a
full-page advertisement <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> newspapers in
an attempt at ``setting the record straight'' about new allegations
of corruption and lack of anti-drug efforts.
   The Bahamas decided to buy the ads as part of its response to
charges of Bahamian drug corruption raised in various quarters,
including the federal trial of <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s reputed drug kingpin,
<PERSON>Carlos Lehder Rivas</PERSON>, government spokesman <PERSON>Bill Kalis</PERSON> said.
   The ad in <ORGANIZATION>The New York Times</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Post, <LOCATION>Miami Herald</LOCATION> and
other newspapers was addressed to ``the people of the <LOCATION>United States
of America</LOCATION>'' and signed by Bahamian Attorney General <PERSON>Paul L.
Adderly</PERSON>.
   It says the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> has devoted much of its
limited resources to fighting drugs and needs more <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> aid.
   Specifically, the ad cites the need for ``more air search radar
installations, more joint bases strategically located with
helicopter strike force teams, more air reconnaissance patrols,
more sea patrols and intensified joint undercover and conspiracy
investigations.''
   It says the archipelago of 700 islands and keys and 250,000
people spends <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT> of its national budget on law enforcement,
mostly fighting drugs produced in <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> and bound for users
in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   Published reports have said grand juries in <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> are
investigating Prime Minister Sir <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON>. And reports in
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> have raised doubts about Bahamian drug-fighting efforts.
   ``He started thinking about this during these latest allegations
at the Lehder trial,'' <PERSON>Kalis</PERSON> said.
   ``As you know, the position was not to respond while the
testimony was being heard. Now that the testimony is over, the
prime minister wanted to take an opportunity to make the Bahamian
position better known.''
   During <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s trial in <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Robert
Merkle</PERSON> had produced testimony that <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> was receiving drug
payoffs of up to <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY>. Lehder allegedly used <ORGANIZATION>Norman's Cay</ORGANIZATION> in
the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> as a key transfer point for Colombian cocaine bound for
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>.
   Adderly's advertisement <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> called attention to a <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Royal
Commission of Inquiry</ORGANIZATION> report in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> that criticized lack of
cooperation by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> authorities during its probe into official drug
corruption. That commission found evidence of drug corruption in
some levels of the Bahamian government and law enforcement, but did
not tie Pindling to drug payoffs.
   Last week, <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> issued a statement to the news media and at
a rally flatly denying taking drug payoffs.
   <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> said he was not surprised by the allegations at
<PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s trial but would be surprised if any of the grand juries
reportedly investigating his affairs indicted him.
   Pindling was re-elected last year after criticizing the
corruption allegations, which first surfaced in a <DATE>1983</DATE> report. He
has been in power since breaking the hold of the white-minority
government in <DATE>1967</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880531-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-31-88 0445EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Pindling-Probe     05-31 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pindling-Probe,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bahamas Helps US Anti-Drug Efforts as Pindling Indictment Seems
Less Likely</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> has become more cooperative with the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in an anti-drug effort, while chances are diminishing
that the islands' prime minister will face a drug indictment in
this country, a newspaper reports.
   The Bahamian government has joined the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in combined
drug raids and allowed a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Customs base on Gun Cay south of
<LOCATION>Bimini</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>The Miami Herald</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``We're at a very high level of cooperation at this point,''
said <ORGANIZATION>Customs</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Michael Sheehan</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.
   Sheehan's statement was echoed by <PERSON>Jack Hook</PERSON>, spokesman for the
<ORGANIZATION>Drug Enforcement Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   But chances that the prime minster, Sir <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON>,
could be prosecuted on drug-related charges appear remote because
of obstacles in an ongoing probe of an overseas drug-smuggling
network.
   First, the shaky status of federal drug indictments in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> against <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> has raised doubts
about whether the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> would want to indict a foreign head
of state. The <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration reportedly has offered to drop
the indictments in a deal in which <ORGANIZATION>Noriega</ORGANIZATION> would step down from
power.
   ``I find very little incentive indicting foreign potentates if
the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> can negotiate them right out from under my
feet,'' said <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Robert Merkle</PERSON>, who has indicated he'll
quit if the indictment against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> is dropped.
   Merkle, of <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, has refused to comment on the reported probe
of Pindling.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> said a grand jury in <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION> is hearing testimony
against <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>, the Bahamian leader since <DATE>1967</DATE> who was re-elected
last year after his government was rocked by a drug-corruption
scandal.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>, citing a ``well-placed source,'' said a <DATE>July 4</DATE>
deadline has been set for an indictment of Pindling.
   Another major obstacle, The <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> said, is the statute of
limitations. Pindling's probe stemmed from testimony given by
prosecution witnesses in the <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> federal trial of
convicted Colombian drug kingpin <PERSON>Carlos Lehder Rivas</PERSON>.
   Most of the allegations raised against <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> in the <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>
trial involved incidents in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE> and <DATE>1980</DATE>, which would
put them past the five-year statute of limitations.
   Merkle prosecuted <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>, who was accused of using the private
Bahamian island of <PERSON>Norman</PERSON>'s Cay as a cocaine trans-shipment point
and was convicted on all drug counts he faced.
   During <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s trial, <PERSON>Merkle</PERSON> called <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> ``a
co-conspirator.'' Prosecution witness <PERSON>George Baron</PERSON> said Bahamian
police were guarding the prime minister when he delivered a
suitcase with <MONEY>$400,000</MONEY> to Pindling in <DATE>1980</DATE> for alleged protection
of <PERSON>Baron</PERSON>'s marijuana-smuggling through the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   Pindling, in a <DATE>May 4</DATE> statement, denied <PERSON>Baron</PERSON>'s story and charges
of corruption and bribe-taking. The Bahamian government ran
full-page ads <DATE>May 10</DATE> in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> newspapers stressing its commitment to
fighting drugs and protesting what they called old allegations.
   A <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Royal Commission of Inquiry</ORGANIZATION> detailed corruption in lower
levels of the Bahamian government and law enforcement, but stopped
short of linking <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> to the drug corruption.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890510-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-10-89 1840EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DrugIsland     05-10 0678</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Island,0696</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Officials Say Drug Smugglers Took Over Bahamian Island</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD COLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Drug traffickers have all but taken over the
Bahamian island of <LOCATION>South Bimini</LOCATION>, chasing off <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> patrol boats with
gunfire and intimidating the Bahamian military, say <ORGANIZATION>Customs Service</ORGANIZATION>
reports and law enforcement officials.
   A Bahamian police lieutenant on the island even removed a
suspected drug smuggler from a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> boat and freed him, says a <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Customs Service</ORGANIZATION> report obtained <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Customs Service</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Michael Sheehan</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION>
spokesman Lt. <PERSON>Jeff Karonis</PERSON> refused to give details of the case,
saying the matter is being handled by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>,
the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   Bahamian government spokesman <PERSON>Edward Ellis</PERSON> said he could not
comment immediately on the incidents.
   Drug officials are reluctant to talk on the record about the
situation for fear of endangering joint U.S.-Bahamian drug
interdiction efforts, but said privately that the island is out of
control.
   ``The situation in <LOCATION>South Bimini</LOCATION> is near anarchy,'' a federal law
enforcement official said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, speaking on condition of
anonymity. ``The drug smugglers alone control the island, and
police corruption is obvious.''
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> drug officials have long complained of high-level
protection of drug smugglers and a <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Royal Commission of Inquiry</ORGANIZATION>
found low-level corruption. The Bahamian government strenuously
denies any wrongdoing by current leaders, however.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> defeated 57-40 a resolution by <PERSON>Sen.
John Kerry</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, to revoke President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s certification that
the government of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> has fully cooperated in the war on
drugs. Decertification could have cost the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> nearly all of
its <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> foreign aid and other privileges.
   <LOCATION>South Bimini</LOCATION>, only about 45 miles from <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, was finally
raided <DATE>May 7</DATE> by Bahamian troops who made at least one arrest and
seized six pounds of marijuana and two weapons. <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION>
officials point to the raid by the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Bahamian Defense Force</ORGANIZATION> to
show good faith by the nation's government.
   ``They sent in about 50 RBDF people _ that's a major raid for
here. I don't think that's any evidence of lack of cooperation,''
said <PERSON>Martin Cheshes</PERSON>, charge d'affaires at the embassy in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>.
   But drug agents here say they are not impressed with the
Bahamian raid, complaining that such actions are rare and usually
late.
   ``It is gotten to the point that our people are being shot at by
snipers using machine guns,'' the law enforcement source said.
``The Bahamian government is closing its eyes to what's going on,
allowing <LOCATION>Bimini</LOCATION> to be used as a thoroughfare for drugs.''
   The raid was staged five days after <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard and Customs
Service</ORGANIZATION> officials, assisted by the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Bahamian Defense Force</ORGANIZATION>,
responded to an apparent air-drop of drugs on <LOCATION>South Bimini</LOCATION>'s coast
and were thwarted by angry crowds.
   Cheshes said the delay was caused by the time it took reports to
get to <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>, and the difficulty of mounting a major operation in
the small country.
   Two boats believed involved in the drop were intercepted and
three people taken into custody. But when the group docked outside
the <LOCATION>South Bimini</LOCATION> Hotel to allow the Bahamian soldiers to search for
drugs, about 75 people gathered, according to the Customs report.
   ``The angry crowd would not let the RBDF on shore to search for
the contraband,'' the report said.
   The task force withdrew and then intercepted another vessel
carrying two Cuban-Americans and two Bahamians.
   The two Bahamians insisted repeatedly on being taken to the
<LOCATION>South Bimini</LOCATION> police station instead of RBDF headquarters on another
island.
   One Bahamian jumped overboard and swam to shore. When the
Customs boats headed to shore to rearrest him, a Bahamian police
lieutenant took the second Bahamian off the boat and freed him at
the hotel while another crowd gathered.
   The Bahamian soldiers threatened to fire on the crowd, but
members of the mob said they would shoot back and the task force
again decided to withdraw. The following day, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Customs vessel
returned to the island and came under small arms fire, the report
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA092989-0108 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 113944 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 29, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 11; Column 5; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
403 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BAHAMAS PRIME MINISTER SAYS U.S. FAILS TO BACK UP DRUG-WAR PLEDGE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DOUGLAS JEHL, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Bahamian Prime Minister <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON> charged <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>, while complaining about poor anti-drug cooperation from <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> 
nations, for five years has failed to back up promises to provide a 
high-technology radar balloon for detecting cocaine shipments through the 
archipelago. 
</P>
<P>
The forceful criticism of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> drug interdiction efforts came as <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>, 
whose government has been implicated in cocaine-trafficking activities, mounts 
a new campaign to position himself in the forefront of mounting international 
anti-narcotics efforts. 
</P>
<P>
In a breakfast session with reporters and editors of The Times' <LOCATION>Washington 
Bureau</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> urged the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to expand its war on drugs by ordering 
the immediate recall of all large-denomination currency to hamper drug lords 
who must deal in cash. 
</P>
<P>
"This would convert rich traffickers and their helpers into paupers overnight," 
the Bahamian leader says. 
</P>
<P>
Pindling also endorsed a proposed multilateral anti-drug task force that would 
dispatch troops around the world to help nations eradicate illegal drug crops. 
</P>
<P>
Asked about what the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> has called the disparity between such 
"public pronouncements" and the extent of corruption in his government, 
<PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> freely conceded that the indictments of several of his associates on 
drug charges have taken a toll on him. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON> associates indicted in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> earlier this year were 
<PERSON>Kendal W. Nottage</PERSON>, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Bahamian Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Everette Bannister</PERSON>, 
a longtime business associate of the prime minister. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Nottage</PERSON> was charged in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> in a federal tax conspiracy indictment alleging 
that he and others conspired to conceal the illegal drug profits of organized 
crime figure <PERSON>Salvatore M. Caruana</PERSON> from the <ORGANIZATION>Internal Revenue Service</ORGANIZATION>. Bannister 
was charged in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> in an indictment alleging that he conspired with the 
Colombian Medellin drug cartel to move drugs through the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In the his interview <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the prime minister insisted that the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> 
"never has been" a haven for drug traffickers. He accused the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> of 
adopting a double standard in singling out the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> for criticism. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm not saying that all of our fellows are angels," he said, "but don't you 
try and make out to me that all of yours are angels. 
</P>
<P>
"Don't apply a yardstick abroad in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> that you aren't prepared to 
apply at home," the prime minister warned. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
DRUG SMUGGLING -- BAHAMA ISLANDS; UNITED STATES -- FOREIGN AID -- BAHAMA 
ISLANDS; COCAINE; NOTTAGE, KENDALL W 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880520-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-88 1621EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Lehder     05-20 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lehder,0585</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Says Government Can Confiscate Lehder Property</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Lehder Cartel Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jurors in the case of <PERSON>Carlos Lehder
Rivas</PERSON> decided <DATE>Friday</DATE> that the government can confiscate <MONEY>millions of
dollars</MONEY> in real estate on a Bahamian island, as well as several
planes and other items owned by the convicted drug dealer.
   ``The island is wrecked. It is trashed. But that is not to say
it would not be of some future value,'' <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Robert Merkle</PERSON>
said.
   The same jury had found the 38-year-old Colombian guilty on all
11 drug-trafficking counts <DATE>Thursday</DATE> after seven days of
deliberations. Co-defendant <PERSON>Jack Carlton Reed</PERSON>, 57, was found guilty
on one count of conspiracy.
   The issue of property forfeiture has to be considered separately
under federal law.
   During <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s hearing on that, Assistant <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Ernst
Mueller</PERSON> urged the jurors to allow the government to confiscate a
large portion of <PERSON>Norman's Cay</PERSON>, an airstrip, a marina, three homes,
a condominium and several planes. The island was <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s smuggling
base from <DATE>1978</DATE> to <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   ``If you prosecute a drug smuggler without taking his property,
only part of the job has been accomplished,'' said <PERSON>Mueller</PERSON>.
   According to <ORGANIZATION>Internal Revenue Service</ORGANIZATION> figures, <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> earned an
estimated <MONEY>$250 million</MONEY> in the cocaine business.
   After 10 hours of deliberations the jury agreed <DATE>Friday</DATE> to all
the forfeitures. But the question of how the government could take
control of property in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> was not clear.
   Lehder faces up to life plus 150 years in prison and <MONEY>$350,000</MONEY> in
fines when he is sentenced <DATE>July 20</DATE>. Reed faces a maximum of 15
years and <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> in fines.
   Lehder's attorney, <PERSON>Edward Shohat</PERSON>, told <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge
Howell W. Melton</PERSON> after the jury was dismissed <DATE>Friday</DATE> that under the
U.S.-Colombia treaty in existence at the time of <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s
extradition, his client might face a maximum of only 30 years in
prison. Merkle disagreed, and the judge asked both sides to submit
briefs on the question.
   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Merkle</PERSON> refused again <DATE>Friday</DATE> to confirm reports that
Bahamian Prime Minister <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON> _ who trial witnesses
said received million-dollar bribes from <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> _ is his next
target.
   Pindling and his aides have denied taking bribes, but have said
they understand a <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> grand jury is investigating the matter.
   <PERSON>Merkle</PERSON> said he could not confirm the existence of such an
investigation.
   Although <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> was only on trial for smuggling 3.3 tons of
cocaine from <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> via <ORGANIZATION>Norman's Cay</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> into deserted
airstrips in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, the government presented
testimony that <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> smuggled 18,000 kilos.
   Lehder has been identified as being one of the leaders of the
violent <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cartel, the Colombian organization also reputedly
headed by <PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jorge Ochoa Vasquez</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jose
Rodriguez Gacha</PERSON>.
   The seven-month trial included 22 weeks of testimony from 115
government witnesses, along with mounds of documents. Lehder was
extradited to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> following a firefight and
his arrest by the Colombian army at a <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> mansion.
   During the trial, <PERSON>Merkle</PERSON> called <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> the <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION> of drug
trafficking, the man who turned cocaine smuggling into a modern,
high-tech operation, using airdrops and speed boats.
   Lehder also is under indictment in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> for his role in the
cartel and a sealed indictment in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, but officials said
it is unlikely that he can be tried for those offenses.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-21343 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jptdd018___94009" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TDD-94-018-L </AU>
JPRS 
Narcotics 

<DATE1>  14 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> LATIN AMERICA </F>
<F P=101> BAHAMAS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Deputy Prime Minister Comments on Cut in U.S. Funds for Drug </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Deputy Prime Minister Comments on Cut in U.S. Funds for Drug </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Programs 

<FÊP=102>   94WD0316A <ORGANIZATION>Nassau THE TRIBUNE</ORGANIZATION> in English 14 Jan 94 1 </F>
<FÊP=103> 94WD0316A </F>
<FÊP=104>  Nassau THE TRIBUNE </F>
<FÊP=105>  English </F>
CSO 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>Maryann Burrows</PERSON>: "<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> To Cut Back <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> in </F>
Drug War Funds"] 
  [Text] The <ORGANIZATION>International Narcotic Matters</ORGANIZATION> [INM] grant that 
supported many drug programmes in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> will be cut by 
half a <MONEY>million dollars</MONEY> this year, Deputy Prime Minister <PERSON>Orville 
Turnquest</PERSON> announced at a joint Bahamas/United States drug 
interdiction meeting today. 
  And while it has been indicated that Operation-BAT and the 
Aerostat would not be affected, it will take great ingenuity to 
ensure that the loss of <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> does not significantly impair 
the effectiveness of the Bahamas/U.S. cooperative efforts, <PERSON>Mr. 
Turnquest</PERSON> said. 
  "It will be most unfortunate that the successes which we 
have 
achieved <DATE>today</DATE> over the last seven years, should be reversed in 
any way by a reduction of this kind in our financial resources. 
  We state on other occasions the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> is unable to 
increase its resources which are allocated to drug control 
activities. A budgetary allotment into this area is now 15 per 
cent of our total national budget," he said. 
  <PERSON>Mr. John Ford</PERSON>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Charge d'Affaires to the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> said 
that the cut in the INM budget for <ORGANIZATION>Nassau</ORGANIZATION> is also regretted. But 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials are commitment to OPBAT in terms of money, 
resources and personnel. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Ford</PERSON> said that the corporation between the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> and 
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, continues to shine as an example for other 
bilateral and multi-lateral efforts. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Orville Turnquest</PERSON> said that the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> joint task force 
exercise has become a singularly successful and unique 
continuing enterprise against the scourge of drug trafficking. 
  He said he was delighted that the results to date seem to 
indicate that while "we may not yet have won the war," the 
battle has been continuing. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Turnquest</PERSON> said good news stem from the statistics 
indicating the successful results of the joint enterprise 
between the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
  "The amount of cocaine seized in Bahamian waters during the 
first three quarters of <DATE>1993</DATE>, has returned downwards to <DATE>1980</DATE> 
level. We are told that a mere 520 pounds of cocaine or 240 
kilos, were seized in Bahamian territory in the <DATE>first three 
quarters of 1993</DATE>," said <PERSON>Mr. Turnquest</PERSON>. 
  "Of those totals the largest seizure in Bahamian territory 
for <DATE>1993</DATE>, was an air drop retrieved by OPBAT in <DATE>July</DATE>. This, I 
believe, is proof of the success of this cooperative effort 
between our two countries. 
  OPBAT was also successful in seizing 2,546 pounds of cocaine 
in international waters. This reflects in my mind the reduction 
in the trend of drug trafficking activities in <DATE>1992</DATE>, when the 
bulk of cocaine seizures occurred in Bahamian waters." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880721-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-21-88 0346EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-LehderSentence Bjt   07-21 0634</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lehder Sentence, Bjt,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge: Harsh Sentence A Signal From Society To Drug Traffickers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By IKE FLORES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge says <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> was
sending a signal to drug traffickers when he sentenced <PERSON>Carlos
Lehder Rivas</PERSON> to life imprisonment without parole for smuggling tons
of cocaine into the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   ``Cocaine is viewed as a national tragedy in this country,''
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Howell W. Melton</PERSON> told the Colombian drug dealer
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. ``Those who profit from this are the worst kinds of
offenders.''
   The harsh sentence, life plus 135 years in prison and fines
totaling <MONEY>$350,000</MONEY>, was ``a signal of our society'' that it will
strongly punish those fueling ``this cancer'' of drugs, <PERSON>Melton</PERSON> said.
   The judge also said <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s criminal motivation was greed,
adding that he showed ``no concern for the destruction of others.''
   There was no visible reaction from <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>, who wore a gray
business suit.
   Lehder, 38, a reputed leader of <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s violent <PERSON>Medellin
Cartel</PERSON>, was sentenced for smuggling 3.3 tons of cocaine from his
homeland via the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> to rural airstrips in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>.
   He was convicted on 11 counts of conspiracy, importation of
cocaine and possession with intent to distribute. <PERSON>Melton</PERSON> also
ordered the confiscation of <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s possessions in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>:
three homes, an airstrip, hotel, condominium and marina.
   The seizure is in dispute, with the Bahamian government
contending the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has no right to the property and that
it intended to assume possession.
   Lehder contended he had been ``a hostage'' to prosecutor <PERSON>Robert
Merkle</PERSON>, who resigned as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> attorney for central <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> shortly
after the seven-month trial to run for the <ORGANIZATION>Republican U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION>
nomination.
   Lehder claimed <PERSON>Merkle</PERSON> used him as a symbol of evil to generate
``free publicity for his <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> campaign.''
   He charged he had been kidnapped and illegally brought to the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> because he had been a political leader in <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>,
working to overthrow the U.S.-Colombia extradition treaty.
   Outside the courtroom, <PERSON>Merkle</PERSON>'s replacement, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Joe
Magri</PERSON>, dismissed <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s allegations.
   He said the judge had ``fairly, justly and appropriately socked
it to a hoodlum.''
   The heavy sentence ``sends a clear message that we're serious
about stopping narcotics traffic,'' <PERSON>Magri</PERSON> said, calling <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> a
``cocaine narco-terrorist.''
   The defendant, who said he had dual citizenship in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, asked <PERSON>Melton</PERSON> to deport him to <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> or
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
   Defense attorneys <PERSON>Edward Shohat</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jose Quinon</PERSON> had asked the
judge to impose a 20-year sentence at most, which they said would
be four times longer than the terms being served by the smugglers
who testified against <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>.
   They said <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON> would appeal the conviction and sentence.
   After listening to almost four hours of arguments and objections
from <PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s attorneys to pre-sentence reports, <PERSON>Melton</PERSON> told the
defendant that the government had presented ``monumental amounts of
incriminating evidence against you.''
   Testimony during the lengthy trial alleged that Bahamian
officials, including Prime Minister <PERSON>Lynden O. Pindling</PERSON>, helped
<PERSON>Lehder</PERSON>'s drug ring smuggle more than 20 tons of cocaine into the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   Pindling and his aides have repeatedly denied the allegations.
   Lehder was arrested and extradited to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <DATE>last
year</DATE> after a gunbattle at his mansion in <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION>.
   He also is under indictment in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> for his role in the cartel,
and there is a sealed indictment against him in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. But
officials have said it is highly unlikely that he will be tried on
those charges.
   Co-defendant <PERSON>Jack Carlton Reed</PERSON>, 57, of <LOCATION>San Pedro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, a
pilot in the drug-smuggling ring, stood silently earlier in the day
conviction on a single conspiracy count. Government witnesses had
testified that he ferried 2,500 pounds of cocaine on at least seven
flights from the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32091 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat022_b_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-022 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  2 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Inter-Caribbean Affairs </F>
<F P=101> The Bahamas </F>
<H3> <TI>   Opposition Files No-Confidence Motion Against Ingraham </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  FL0102222894 Bridgetown CANA in English 1619 GMT 1 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> FL0102222894 </F>
<F P=104>  Bridgetown CANA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, 1 Feb, <LOCATION>CANA</LOCATION> -- Opposition leader 
Sir <PERSON>Lynden Pindling</PERSON> and his Progressive Liberal Party [PLP] 
<DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> tabled a motion of no confidence against Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Hubert Ingraham</PERSON>, over the recent resignation of <ORGANIZATION>Justice 
Ira Rowe</ORGANIZATION> from the <ORGANIZATION>Bahamas Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION>. 
  He also tabled a resolution condemning the justice minister 
and the attorney general. Pindling claimed that new evidence had 
surfaced in the abrupt resignation of the Jamaican judge. 
Additional information, he claimed, has convinced the opposition 
that the 17-month-old government, through Justice Minister <PERSON>Janet 
Bostwick</PERSON>, interfered with the judicial process. 
  Pindling, former prime minister of 25 years, also claimed 
that Attorney General <PERSON>Orville Turnquest</PERSON> presented a misleading 
position in a television interview, and that Ingraham misled 
parliament in a communication on the matter. 
  Ingraham branded <PERSON>Pindling</PERSON>'s allegation an "outright lie." He 
said he had no problem with such a debate and offered to change 
the <ORGANIZATION>House of Assembly</ORGANIZATION>'s agenda on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to 
accommodate the <ORGANIZATION>PLP</ORGANIZATION>. 
  "It is dead wrong for Sir <PERSON>Lynden Pindling</PERSON> to seek to mislead 
the Bahamian public and bring into contempt the judicial 
system," <PERSON>Ingraham</PERSON> said. The government, he continued, was 
completely satisfied that it acted in the best interest of the 
people and consistent with its oath of office to uphold the laws 
of <ORGANIZATION>The Bahamas</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Rowe resigned in <DATE>December</DATE> after the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Justice</ORGANIZATION>, 
through the registrar of the supreme court, told him that it was 
not prepared to facilitate his presence in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION> to hear an 
appeal challenging the lawfulness of a commission of inquiry 
appointed to investigate allegations of misuse of public funds 
under the former Pindlng regime. The appeal was lodged by 
<PERSON>Maurice Glinton</PERSON>, lawyer for <PERSON>Phillip Herman Bethel</PERSON>. The inquiry 
was told that <LOCATION>Bethel</LOCATION> indirectly received a substantial amount of 
maoney that had been paid by <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> as commission on 
the sale of Dehavilland aircraft to the state-owned <LOCATION>Bahamasair</LOCATION>. 
<LOCATION>Bethel</LOCATION> is the son of <LOCATION>Philip Bethel</LOCATION>, a former <ORGANIZATION>Bahamasair</ORGANIZATION> chairman 
and <ORGANIZATION>PLP</ORGANIZATION> minister. During the recent hearing, <PERSON>Justice Vincent 
Melville</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>The Bahamas Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION>, stated that 
he was telephoned by <ORGANIZATION>Justice Rowe</ORGANIZATION> last <DATE>December 4</DATE>. Justice <PERSON>Rowe</PERSON> 
informed the president that he had an application for <PERSON>Glinton</PERSON>. 
  Justice <PERSON>Melville</PERSON> said he informed Justice <PERSON>Rowe</PERSON> not to deal 
with the matter as there was someone in <LOCATION>The Bahamas</LOCATION> who could 
deal with it. <PERSON>Glinton</PERSON> had flown to <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION> to get <ORGANIZATION>Justice Rowe</ORGANIZATION> 
to entertain his application. Ingraham said that the chief 
justice of <ORGANIZATION>The Bahamas</ORGANIZATION> has always dealt with applications of 
appeal since the court of appeal was established in <LOCATION>The Bahamas</LOCATION> 
<DATE>28 years ago</DATE>. 
  Ingraham said that his government was sworn to uphold the 
laws of The Bahamas and not to allow anyone "under any cloak" to 
subvert the laws of the country. 

</TEXT>
