<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890411-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-11-89 0828EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Southwest-Report     04-11 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Southwest-Report,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Southwest Airlines Report Features Punch-Out Fun</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In addition to the facts and figures formally
found in a firm's annual report, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Airlines Co.</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>1988</DATE>
features fun, in the form of a paper airplane.
   ``This was one of those wonderful years when we made a lot of
money and it seemed to be we made a lot of money by getting back to
the basics. ... and we translated that to what we thought was the
most basic of all airplanes, the paper airplane,'' said <PERSON>Tim
McClure</PERSON>, executive creative director of <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION> advertising agency
<ORGANIZATION>GSD&amp;M</ORGANIZATION>, which designed the report.
   The booklet, besides reporting on <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s record <MONEY>$57.95
million</MONEY> in profit, traces the construction of a paper airplane from
the first folding of the paper to the final painting to resemble
<ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s ``flying whale'' jet rolled out <DATE>last year</DATE>
during the airline's promotion of <ORGANIZATION>Sea World</ORGANIZATION> theme parks in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   ``You think every pre-schooler and first grader in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> will
want one?'' asked <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <ORGANIZATION>Charlotte Goddard</ORGANIZATION>. ``Or all
the CEOs?''
   Besides a picture of Chairman <PERSON>Herb Kelleher</PERSON> throwing a paper
airplane, the middle of the report features a four-page foldout
picture of <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>.
   On the back page, there's the punch-out version of the unusually
painted plane, with assembly instructions and this ``helpful hint:''
   ``Herb attaches a paper clip to the nose for longer flights
(<ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>'s, not his).''
   Even though <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> previously has taken a light approach to
its reports, <PERSON>McClure</PERSON> said it was a little difficult this year to
sell the idea of a punch-out airplane because, ``once someone
punches it out, you have an annual report with holes in the back.''
   He said he persuaded <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> that the unusual idea would
become enticing. ``Everybody's going to pick it up ... and call up
for one.''
   ``I think it's a delightful brochure and something that really
shows the personality that <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> is,'' <PERSON>McClure</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>, a regional airline that employs almost 6,500 people,
is based at <LOCATION>Love Field</LOCATION> near downtown <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> and operates a
distinctive fleet of gold, rust and orange jets.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890411-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-11-89 1450EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     04-11 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The annual report of <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Airlines Co.</ORGANIZATION>
contains something that could raise a flap, or at least a couple
wings _ a paper airplane.
   ``This was one of those wonderful years when we made a lot of
money and it seemed to be we made a lot of money by getting back to
the basics, said <PERSON>Tim McClure</PERSON>, executive creative director of <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>
advertising agency <ORGANIZATION>GSD&amp;M</ORGANIZATION>, which designed the <DATE>1988</DATE> report.
   ``And we translated that to what we thought was the most basic
of all airplanes, the paper airplane.''
   The booklet, besides reporting on the regional airline's record
<MONEY>$57.95 million</MONEY> in profit, traces the construction of a paper
airplane from the first folding of the paper to the final painting
to resemble <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s ``flying whale'' jet rolled out
<DATE>last year</DATE> during the airline's promotion of <ORGANIZATION>Sea World</ORGANIZATION> theme parks
in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   ``You think every pre-schooler and first grader in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> will
want one?'' asked <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <ORGANIZATION>Charlotte Goddard</ORGANIZATION>. ``Or all
the CEOs?''
   Besides a picture of Chairman <PERSON>Herb Kelleher</PERSON> throwing a paper
airplane, the middle of the report features a four-page foldout
picture of <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>.
   On the back page, there's a punch-out version of the plane, with
assembly instructions and this ``helpful hint'':
   ``Herb attaches a paper clip to the nose for longer flights
(<ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>'s, not his).''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The annual report of <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Airlines Co.</ORGANIZATION>
contains something that could raise a flap, or at least a couple
wings _ a paper airplane.
   ``This was one of those wonderful years when we made a lot of
money and it seemed to be we made a lot of money by getting back to
the basics, said <PERSON>Tim McClure</PERSON>, executive creative director of <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>
advertising agency <ORGANIZATION>GSD&amp;M</ORGANIZATION>, which designed the <DATE>1988</DATE> report.
   ``And we translated that to what we thought was the most basic
of all airplanes, the paper airplane.''
   The booklet, besides reporting on the regional airline's record
<MONEY>$57.95 million</MONEY> in profit, traces the construction of a paper
airplane from the first folding of the paper to the final painting
to resemble <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s ``flying whale'' jet rolled out
<DATE>last year</DATE> during the airline's promotion of <ORGANIZATION>Sea World</ORGANIZATION> theme parks
in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   ``You think every pre-schooler and first grader in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> will
want one?'' asked <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <ORGANIZATION>Charlotte Goddard</ORGANIZATION>. ``Or all
the CEOs?''
   Besides a picture of Chairman <PERSON>Herb Kelleher</PERSON> throwing a paper
airplane, the middle of the report features a four-page foldout
picture of <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>.
   On the back page, there's a punch-out version of the plane, with
assembly instructions and this ``helpful hint'':
   ``Herb attaches a paper clip to the nose for longer flights
(<ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>'s, not his).''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880517-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-17-88 2322EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CessnaCrash     05-17 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cessna Crash,0376</SECOND>
<HEAD>Single-Engine Airplane Crashes; Five Killed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANNE BUCKLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A single-engine airplane crashed
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> into a ditch beside a dirt road on the outskirts of
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>, killing all five people aboard, authorities said.
   Four adults and one child died in the crash, which witnesses
said occurred about <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>, when it was raining, <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> police
Sgt. <PERSON>R.C. Porter</PERSON> said.
   The airplane was attempting to land at nearby <LOCATION>Coronado Airport</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Porter</PERSON> said. It aborted its first attempt and was coming in for a
second try when it crashed, he said.
   State police said the red-and-white <ORGANIZATION>Cessna</ORGANIZATION> P210, which seats six
people, was from <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION>.
bodies were taken to the Office of the Medical Investigator in
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Walter Ramazzini Jr.</PERSON>, 17, of <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>, said he was sitting
about 100 yards from the airplane when it crashed.
   ``He was going east, making a left turn from the airport,''
<ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION> said. ``A gust of wind hit him from right to left.
   ``He did three banks. The wind made him bank to the left 30
degrees or so. To correct for that, he banked right and he kept
going and passed level flight as if to turn right,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``To correct again for that, he went again to the left ... and
went nose-first into the ground,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION>, a student pilot.
``He hit the ground and cartwheeled over.
   ``All I saw was a puff of smoke,'' he said.
   The airplane ``wasn't very high _ maybe 100 feet,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION>
said. ``The weather was gusty and showery. It was sprinkling.''
   He said he was among the first four people at the crash site.
   ``We went up there and there was nobody alive,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION> said.
``You could smell fuel. We were looking for fire extinguishers.''
He said the witnesses thought the airplane might blow up, so they
retreated.
   Firefighters arrived later and sprayed the crumpled airplane
with water before rescue crews removed the bodies from the craft.
to the crash site to conduct an investigation with the <ORGANIZATION>Federal
Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880518-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-18-88 0601EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AirplaneCrash     05-18 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Airplane Crash,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Die In Single-Engine Airplane Crash</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANNE BUCKLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A student pilot who witnessed an
airplane crash that killed five people said the aircraft's lone
engine appeared to stall moments before it plunged nose first into
the ground.
   ``All I saw was a puff of smoke,'' said <PERSON>Walter Ramazzini Jr.</PERSON>,
17, who was sitting about 100 yards from the ditch where the plane
crashed on the outskirts of <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>.
   ``He was going east, making a left turn from the airport,''
<ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION> said. ``A gust of wind hit him from right to left.''
   Police Sgt. <PERSON>R.C. Porter</PERSON> said it was raining when the plane
crashed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> afternoon several miles south of <LOCATION>Coronado Airport</LOCATION>.
   The pilot of the six-seat <ORGANIZATION>Cessna</ORGANIZATION> P210 aborted his first landing
attempt and was coming in for a second try when it crashed, <PERSON>Porter</PERSON>
said.
   State police identified the victims as <PERSON>Gary Brown</PERSON>, 31, his wife,
<PERSON>Melissa</PERSON>, 26, and their 2-year-old daughter, <PERSON>Lindsey</PERSON>, all of
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>; and his parents, <PERSON>Wayne Brown</PERSON>, 60, and <PERSON>Joyce Brown</PERSON>, 58,
Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION> were investigating the crash.
   After the wind hit the plane, the pilot appeared to try to
straighten out the craft, <ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION> said
   ``The wind made him bank to the left 30 degrees or so. To
correct for that, he banked right and he kept going and passed
level flight as if to turn right,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``To correct again for that, he went again to the left ... and
went nose-first into the ground,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION>. ``He hit the
ground and cartwheeled over. It seemed like the engine stalled.''
   The airplane ``wasn't very high _ maybe 100 feet,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ramazzini</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   Three fire trucks sent to the scene sprayed the crumpled
airplane with water and rescue crews removed bodies from the craft,
authorities said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881019-0286 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-19-88 2029EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-NewPlane     10-19 0231</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Plane,0239</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boeing Allows a Look at Secret Unmanned Plane</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: also on general news wires.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SE5</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Co.</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> released a photo of a
secret unmanned airplane it said made its first flight <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> released few details about the experimental aircraft,
other than to say it successfully completed its first flight and
would undergo further flight tests ``to characterize the
capabilities of this type of vehicle.''
   The airplane has a long, skinny fuselage with narrow, flexible
wings. It is powered by two propeller-driven engines, described by
the trade publication <ORGANIZATION>Aviation Week and Space Technology</ORGANIZATION> as
<ORGANIZATION>Teledyne Continental</ORGANIZATION> liquid-cooled piston engines.
   In <DATE>April 1986</DATE>, a similar plane was photographed outside a hanger
at the <LOCATION>Grant County Airport</LOCATION> in <PERSON>Moses Lake</PERSON>, in central <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> declined to comment on that aircraft.
expressed interest in the aircraft and has provided some money to
participate in flight evaluation. The agency has classified certain
aspects of the aircraft design and performance, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The plane resembles <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION>'s Compass Cope remotely piloted
vehicle, an unmanned aircraft powered by a single jet engine.
<ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> built two of the planes for the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Compass Cope was 40 feet long with a 90-foot wingspan. It
made its first flight at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in
<DATE>July 1973</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890530-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-30-89 1252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--Whitehead'sFlight Adv11   05-30 1119</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Whitehead's Flight, Adv 11,1151</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv11</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, June 11</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo,
1 graphic.)</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ Two engineers, convinced that a <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>
inventor beat the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers into the air by more than two
years, have drawn up blueprints for an engine they believe is
almost identical to the ones that powered that first flight. The
next step, they hope, is to build working replicas of the engines
in an attempt to prove that <PERSON>Gustave Whitehead</PERSON> may have been cheated
out of his proper place in history.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ Two engineers, convinced that a <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>
inventor beat the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers into the air by more than two
years, have drawn up blueprints for an engine they believe is
almost identical to the ones that powered that first flight. The
next step, they hope, is to build working replicas of the engines
in an attempt to prove that <PERSON>Gustave Whitehead</PERSON> may have been cheated
out of his proper place in history.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>By DEAN GOLEMBESKI</NOTE>
<NOTE>Associated Press Writer</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CROMWELL, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ Two engineers, convinced that a <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>
inventor beat the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers into the air by more than two
years, have drawn up blueprints for an engine they believe is
almost identical to the ones that powered that first flight. The
next step, they hope, is to build working replicas of the engines
in an attempt to prove that <PERSON>Gustave Whitehead</PERSON> may have been cheated
out of his proper place in history.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, June 11</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891006-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-06-89 1618EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WrightBrothers     10-06 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wright Brothers,0351</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wright Brothers Sites to Get Federal Preservation Study</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES HANNAH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DAYTON, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The federal government will study sites
where the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers lived and worked in a move that could
lead to a national park in the birthplace of aviation, officials
said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Rep. <PERSON>Tony Hall</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ohio</LOCATION>, said the <ORGANIZATION>National Park Service</ORGANIZATION> study,
expected to take 12 to 15 months, will help <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> decide whether
to confer national park status on the sites.
   A committee headed by <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>Judge Walter Rice</PERSON> was
formed to preserve the heritage of <PERSON>Orville</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wilbur Wright</PERSON>, who
developed the first heavier-than-air flying machine.
   ``Over the years ... we have lost many of the buildings, many of
the historic sites involved in the birth of aviation either to the
wrecking ball or to just plain indifference,'' <PERSON>Rice</PERSON> said. ``That
time is over.''
   The sites to be studied include <PERSON>Huffman Prairie</PERSON>, scene of the
<PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers' first flying experiments, and buildings that
housed the Wrights' airplane company, bicycle shop and printing
business.
   Also on the list are <PERSON>Hawthorne Hill</PERSON>, home of <PERSON>Orville Wright</PERSON>;
<ORGANIZATION>Carillon Park</ORGANIZATION>, home of the <ORGANIZATION>Wright Flyer III</ORGANIZATION>, known as the world's
first practical airplane; and <ORGANIZATION>Dunbar House</ORGANIZATION>, home of <PERSON>Paul Lawrence
Dunbar</PERSON>, poet and friend of the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers.
   <PERSON>William Gibson</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>National Park Service</ORGANIZATION> official based in
<LOCATION>Chillicothe</LOCATION>, said the agency will study options for managing the
sites, including oversight by the state or local government, the
private sector, or the federal government in the form of a national
park.
   ``We are impressed,'' said <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON>. ``The historic resources
associated with the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers that remain in <LOCATION>Dayton</LOCATION> are truly
impressive.''
   The city of <LOCATION>Dayton</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montgomery County</LOCATION> plan to contribute
<MONEY>$35,000</MONEY> apiece toward the study. Private contributions will also be
sought, officials said.
   While the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers constructed their early aircraft at
their bicycle shop in <LOCATION>Dayton</LOCATION>, they also are connected historically
with <PERSON>Kitty Hawk</PERSON>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, where on <DATE>Dec. 17, 1903</DATE>, they made the first
controlled, sustained flights in a power-driven airplane.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06092199 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06092199 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; Herb Kelleher: 'Having fun on the job has a
lot of benefits'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  AVIATION; TRAVEL; TRANSPORTATION; SERVICE; COMPANY; EMPLOYMENT; HUMOR  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Whether it's painting airplanes to resemble killer whales, or dressing like
Elvis to greet passengers, Southwest Airlines is serious about having fun.;   
The off-beat approach by the airline, once dubbed the "Cattle Call" carrier,
comes from the top. And it's made a difference on the bottom line: Southwest
was one of only two major airlines to make a profit in 1990, earning $47.1
million, or $1.10 a share, on $1.19 billion in revenue.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NO KIDDING, MAKING MONEY IS FUN  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <ORGANIZATION>United Airlines</ORGANIZATION> was the other profitable carrier.;    "Having fun on the
job has a lot of benefits connected with it," said Chairman <PERSON>Herb Kelleher</PERSON>, who
has been known to dress like Elvis to greet passengers and play practical
jokes on his employees. "You don't have to surrender your individuality to
work for <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Airlines</ORGANIZATION>.";    <PERSON>Kelleher</PERSON> believes the breezy corporate
culture of the nation's eighth-largest airline -- from cash-register style
tickets to golf shirt-clad flight attendants -- has helped make the airline
more efficient.;    In fact, speedy ground crews turn around half of
<ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s flights in 15 minutes.;    <PERSON>Kelleher</PERSON> has even had closets removed
from the front of <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 737s when he noticed passengers dawdled
by it.;    <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> offers few frills. There are no meals, and until recently
only beverages and peanuts were served. Cookies have been added to the longer
flights.;    Passengers aren't assigned seats, but are handed reusable,
numbered, plastic boarding passes when they check in. They then board on a
first-come, first-served basis, hence the cattle-call moniker.;    Such
measures have made <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s cost per passenger mile <MONEY>6.73 cents</MONEY>, one of the
lowest in the business.;    Marketing savvy also has helped. The airline's
frequent flier program is based on the number of flights taken instead of
mileage.;    The airline drew some snickers in <DATE>1988</DATE> when it painted a plane
like a killer whale to promote a joint venture with <ORGANIZATION>Sea World</ORGANIZATION> parks in <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. But it drew even more customers and now has three
"Shamu" planes.;    <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> also has painted a plane to look like a furling
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> flag -- Lone Star One -- to commemorate its 20th anniversary year this
year.;    "No matter what <PERSON>Herb Kelleher</PERSON>'s title is . . . he is a marketing
genius," said <PERSON>Roy Spence</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>GSD&amp;M</ORGANIZATION> Advertising in <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>, the airline's lead
agency.;    Analysts expect <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s success to continue despite the
economic downturn because it has carved a niche as a short-haul carrier with
low fares.;    "<LOCATION>Southwest</LOCATION> has shown incredible resiliency during this period
of industry losses," said <PERSON>Paul Karos</PERSON>, an airline analyst with <ORGANIZATION>First Boston
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>;    <PERSON>Karos</PERSON> predicts higher profits for <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1991.</DATE>;    <ORGANIZATION>Airlines</ORGANIZATION>
have been hurt in the past several months by higher fuel prices, the
recession's effect on consumer spending and fear of terrorism stirred by the
war.;    <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> has managed to overcome those obstacles. During <DATE>January</DATE>,
for example, it had <PERCENT>13.1 percent</PERCENT> more flights and added <PERCENT>17.6 percent</PERCENT> more
passengers over a year ago. Last month it filled slightly more seats, <PERCENT>62
percent vs. 61 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>February 1990.</DATE>;    Nonetheless, <PERSON>Kelleher</PERSON> remains
cautious. "We're not recession-proof. We've suffered from the sparsity of
traffic, too," he said.;    In fact, the Dallas-based carrier has had its
troubles since its inception.;    When <PERSON>Kelleher</PERSON> and business partner <PERSON>Rollin
King</PERSON> mapped out <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s original routes -- between <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> -- on a cocktail napkin in <DATE>1966</DATE>, they had no idea how hard it would be
for business to take off.;    <ORGANIZATION>Braniff</ORGANIZATION> and Trans-Texas airlines mounted
challenges in court and before aviation regulators to keep the upstart
grounded. <PERSON>Kelleher</PERSON>, a successful <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> attorney before starting the
airline, eventually argued <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s case in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>. Its
first flight was on <DATE>June 20, 1971.</DATE>;    Then came the work of convincing
customers that <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> was for real.;    "With the definition of commuter
airline then, you would have not thought of larger planes with seasoned
captains," said <PERSON>Camille Keith</PERSON>, the airline's first public relations chief.;   
And the airline has had to fend off fierce competition. In <DATE>1973</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Braniff</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> fought a pricing battle on flights between <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> that
became known as "The <MONEY>$13</MONEY> War" and is now written about in business textbooks.;
   <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s biggest competitive challenge now is in <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, expected to be
its largest service point by the mid-<DATE>'90s</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>America West Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, based there,
cut ticket prices in half in <DATE>January</DATE>, bringing some one-way fares to <MONEY>$20.</MONEY>;   
<ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> matched <LOCATION>America West</LOCATION>'s prices with fewer restrictions. "Being able
to respond quickly and responsibly is the key to security and survival,"
<PERSON>Kelleher</PERSON> said.;    From the triangle of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' three largest cities, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>
has grown to 31 cities and 33 airports throughout the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Dallas  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910401  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  11E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  796  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 1, 1991
00092199,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900929-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-29-90 1758EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FutureFighter     09-29 0430</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Future Fighter,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Second Competitor for Advanced Tactical Fighter Contract Gets
Airborne</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EDWARDS AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s prototype
of a 21st century fighter jet made its first flight <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in a
winner-take-all competition for the <ORGANIZATION>multibillion-dollar Advanced
Tactical Fighter</ORGANIZATION> contract.
   The YF-22 was airborne just 18 minutes, taking off from <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> Plant 42 in <LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION> and ending 25 mile away at this desert
flight test center.
   The flight was a milestone in a high-stakes contest between an
aerospace team headed by <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> and a team led by <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
for 1,250 <ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION> jets, to be built at a projected cost of <MONEY>$51 million</MONEY>
per plane.
   The winner must produce a jet that is highly maneuverable, uses
radar-evading stealth technology and can fly twice the speed of
sound for long periods of time. The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> wants 750 of the new
planes and the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> needs 500.
   Pilot <PERSON>Dave Ferguson</PERSON> said the YF-22 flew as expected although the
flight was shortened by 42 minutes because of problems at ground
telemetry stations.
   The jet burned so much fuel while sitting on the runway waiting
for takeoff that there wasn't enough left for the scheduled
one-hour flight.
   ``It was a very easy airplane to fly,'' said <PERSON>Ferguson</PERSON>, adding,
``I would be happy to put fuel in it and fly it this afternoon.''
   The jet reached an altitude of 12,500 feet and a speed of about
280 mph. The two-tone gray jet with stubby wings and a V-shaped
tail touched down smoothly in a light rain.
   The YF-22 was built by <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>General Dynamics Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Boeing Co</ORGANIZATION>. It was unveiled in <LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION> <DATE>Aug. 29</DATE>, two days after the
YF-23, built by <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>McDonnell Douglas Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, made
its first flight.
   Lockheed Vice President <PERSON>Sherman Mullin</PERSON>, head of the YF-22
project, said he could not compare the two planes because he didn't
have enough information about the YF-23.
   Each team has spent about <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> producing two prototype
jets each.
   ``It's obviously an extremely important program to us,'' said
<PERSON>Mullin</PERSON>. ``(But) it's not a program that's going to make or break
the <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Corp.</ORGANIZATION>''
   Both planes are built of advanced composite materials. The
<ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> aircraft has stubby wings. The <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> fighter has a
longer, cigarlike fuselage and a wingspread that looks like a kite.
   ``This is a great day from a technological perspective,'' said
<PERSON>Gary L. Denman</PERSON>, who heads an <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> research division. ``I can
assure you, what's out there in the airplane is the best in the
world.''
   Survival of the advanced fighter program was threatened by
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> until <LOCATION>Iraq</LOCATION>'s <DATE>Aug. 2</DATE> invasion of <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION>. The crisis has
enhanced prospects for approval of major defense contracts.
   If <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>McDonnell Douglas</ORGANIZATION> win the contract, the YF-23
would be built in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. The Lockheed-General Dynamics-Boeing
team plans to build YF-22s in <LOCATION>Marietta</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, if it wins. The
selection is due in <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   The <MONEY>$51 million</MONEY> cost of each jet is about twice that of the <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION>'s present top fighter, the F-15 Eagle.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890310-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-10-89 1638EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-StealthBomber 620   03-10 0616</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stealth Bomber, 620</SECOND>
<HEAD>B-2 Flight Delayed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NORMAN BLACK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The B-2 stealth bomber, unveiled last fall
after more than a decade of secret work, will not fly for the first
time before late <DATE>spring</DATE> or <DATE>summer</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Acknowledging recent reports that the schedule for the first
flight was in jeopardy, the service said that because of ``an
aggregation of minor system checkout problems, the B-2's first
flight is now expected to be in the late <DATE>spring</DATE> or early <DATE>summer</DATE> time
frame.''
   ``Routine systems checkout of the first B-2 Advanced Technology
Bomber is continuing ...,'' the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> added. ``After first
flight, the B-2 will undergo extensive testing at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force
Base</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>''
   When the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> made its first announcement last <DATE>summer</DATE> about
an unveiling for the unusual ``flying wing'' plane, it confidently
predicted the aircraft would be ready for its first flight in the
<DATE>fall of 1988</DATE>.
   The plane was ultimately shown to the public for the first time
<DATE>Nov. 22</DATE> at an <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> plant in <LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> officials said at the time they were not
going to rush the initial checkouts of the sophisticated flight
systems, but that they still expected the plane to fly before the
end of the year.
   Maj. <PERSON>Pat Mullaney</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> spokesman, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> the
problems encountered by technicians all had been relatively minor,
but that it took time to prepare a plane for its first flight.
   ``We have said all along that we're going to fly this airplane
when it's ready, and not according to some calendar schedule,'' said
<PERSON>Mullaney</PERSON>.
   The spokesman added the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> decided to release <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s
statement after encountering a problem with the bomber's
``environmental control,'' or air conditioning, system, within the
past week or so.
   A component of that system failed during a high-pressure test,
<PERSON>Mullaney</PERSON> said. Even though the system was purposely overloaded <PERCENT>50
percent</PERCENT> beyond its design limit at the time, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> decided
to fix the component to ensure an extra margin of safety.
   ``The fix for that is straightforward and corrective action is
underway,'' he said.
   The disclosure of checkout problems comes three months after the
<ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> announced the B-2 would carry a price tag _ including
research and development costs _ of <MONEY>$516 million</MONEY> per plane. That
will make it the most expensive airplane ever.
   According to the latest <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> estimate, the design,
development and construction of 132 planes will cost <MONEY>$68.1 billion</MONEY>
by the time production ends in mid-1995. Even if research and
development expenses are excluded, each plane still will cost <MONEY>$305
million</MONEY> to produce on the assembly line.
   The B-2, built primarily by <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, resembles a huge,
tailless manta ray, with wide sweeping wings blending smoothly into
rounded cockpit and engine housings on the top side.
   The stealth gets its name from the claim that it will be almost
invisible to enemy radar, due to the extensive use of exotic
composite materials, some of which absorb rather than reflect radar
waves; its lack of sharp surface angles; and a cross-section that
offers a very small profile to radar.
   The plane is a ``flying wing,'' a design resurrected from the
<DATE>1940s</DATE> that steers with flaps on the rear of the wings rather than
with a tail. The B-2 is described as an all-altitude penetration
bomber, as opposed to the B-1 bomber, which is designed to penetrate
enemy air defenses at low altitudes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> says the plane is 69 feet long, about the length of
an F-16 fighter plane. Its wingspan, at 172 feet, is almost as wide
as the aging B-52.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880815-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-15-88 2359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DoubleEagleAnniversary     08-15 1018</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Double Eagle Anniversary,1055</SECOND>
<HEAD>Balloonist Recounts Historic Flight On 10th Anniversary</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ARNOLD STAPLETON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a cramped gondola dangling beneath
an 11-story helium balloon, with clouds obstructing any view below,
the disembodied voice of the radar operator seemed scarcely to be
believed.
   ``You have crossed the coast of <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>,'' the voice told three
American balloonists on that still-dark early morning 10 years ago.
<PERSON>Larry Newman</PERSON> asked if the message was indeed that which had eluded
others for 105 years.
   Silence.
   Then, crisply, ``Sir, my radar is never wrong.''
   Newman, along with <PERSON>Ben Abruzzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON>, whooped with
joy. Sunburned and weary after five days aloft, the
businessmen-adventurers had made the first trans-Atlantic crossing
in a balloon.
   The three landed their black-and-silver Double Eagle II later
that day, <DATE>Aug. 17, 1978</DATE>, in a wheat field west of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Today, <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> is the only one of the three still alive.
   <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> was killed in <DATE>1983</DATE> at age 48 when his balloon crashed
in a West German forest during a race. Abruzzo, then 53, died in
<DATE>1985</DATE> when his twin-engine airplane crashed shortly after takeoff in
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>, now 40 and a commercial airline pilot in <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>,
said he has no specific plans to celebrate <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s anniversary.
   But he said his thoughts often drifted back to that <DATE>summer 10
years ago</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> recalled that after the initial jubilation, <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> went
to sleep while he and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> looked down through the clearing
clouds on the lights of <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>.
   The silent 112-foot balloon 15,000 feet up caught sounds that
drifted skyward. <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> could hear dogs barking and
trains rumbling along tracks nearly 3 miles below.
   ``Tears came to my eyes,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``I put my arm around
<PERSON>Ben</PERSON> _ he'd always been somewhat like a father to me. I hadn't felt
that close to another human being for as long as I can remember.''
   The men began the flight six days earlier when the <ORGANIZATION>Double Eagle
II</ORGANIZATION> lifted up from <LOCATION>Presque Isle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, and headed toward <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
more than 3,000 miles away.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> says the flight was not without problems, including a
clash of personalities.
   ``<PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON> later stated that he wished he could have flown
the flight by himself,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``I don't know what <PERSON>Ben</PERSON>'s
feelings were, but I wanted someone to share this with. I didn't
want to be <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>.''
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said conflicts arose when <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> both began
making key decisions.
   ``Any aircraft can only have one captain, and we had two: <PERSON>Ben
Abruzzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON>,'' he said.
   But <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said conflicts were overshadowed by the hardships of
the flight in the 12-by-6-foot living space crowded with TV cameras
and navigational equipment. Newman's hang glider dangled beneath
the gondola and 5,500 pounds of sand and lead for ballast hung over
the sides in bags.
   ``There were many times the flight was in question,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>
recalled. ``But how close it came to failure at each moment was
interpreted different by each of us.''
   They lost altitude rapidly at one point when ice chunks crusted
the top of the balloon. They jettisoned valuable ballast. When they
dropped to 4,000 feet the ice melted.
   Later in the flight they dumped more ballast, including an
expensive navigation system that had failed on the second day. They
tossed oxygen bottles, anything they could.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said that at one point, a bit delirious from the
altitude, he chucked a <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> radio _ and only later noticed a jar
of peanut butter that weighed as much.
   Plans were for <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> to fly the glider down once they made it
to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   But 400 miles from <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, it came down to a choice of dropping
the glider, their last oxygen and food, or a propane tank for a
heater to battle <ORGANIZATION>Abruzzo</ORGANIZATION>'s frostbite. The glider went.
   Radios also failed during the flight, and the men had to
communicate by ham radio.
   ``The first guy I talked to wouldn't talk because I didn't have
a license,'' said <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>. ``And he didn't believe I was in a
balloon over the middle of the ocean.''
   Finally, <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> reached an old man confined to a wheelchair in a
home for the elderly somewhere in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   ``His call sign was `G4JY.' I don't think I'll ever forget
that,'' he said. ``He talked to me until the <DATE>last day</DATE> of the
flight. He was like the Good Shepherd.''
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said the rough times were offset by the excitement.
   A high point, he said, came over <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> when a jumbo jet
relayed a message from the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution</ORGANIZATION>. The museum had
asked to display the gondola and balloon in the <ORGANIZATION>National Air</ORGANIZATION> and
Space Museum that houses the Apollo 11 moonship, <ORGANIZATION>Lindbergh's Spirit
of St. Louis</ORGANIZATION> and the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers' plane.
   In the final few hours the men believed they would make it to
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> had landed 51 years before after the first
solo trans-Atlantic airplane flight. But over <LOCATION>Evreux</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, they
realized they could not go on.
   The last of the ballast was gone, save for a bottle of
champagne. They were 60 miles west of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, 3,107 miles and 137
hours from <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> where the helium-packed balloon had taken off.
   The swiftly draining balloon envelope carcass and its gondola
settled gently to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as cheering spectators abandoned their cars
along a nearby highway and rushed to the balloon.
   Hundreds tried to take a piece of history.
   ``It's hard to chew rubberized cloth,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``People
were trying to tear little shreds off, but I think they were
probably losing their teeth more than damaging the balloon.''
   The French press dubbed them the ``new Lindberghs.''
   But <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> says the only time he thought about <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> was
when the adventurers drew straws that evening to see which would
sleep in <LOCATION>Lindbergh</LOCATION>'s bed at the American ambassador's residence in
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> and his wife won.
   ``And I ended up on the floor after 30 minutes because I
couldn't sleep,'' he said. ``The bed was like a banana. The springs
were shot.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880707-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-07-88 2044EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-BoeingOrder     07-07 0220</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boeing Order,0229</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quantas Orders Three Boeing Planes for About $380 Million</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Australian airline <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> has ordered two
<ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 747-400s and one 767-300 with extended range capability,
<ORGANIZATION>Boeing Commercial Airplanes</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The planes will be delivered between <DATE>September</DATE> and <DATE>December 1989</DATE>
and will cost about <MONEY>$380 million</MONEY>, including spare parts and
support, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> said in a news release.
   Qantas Chairman <PERSON>J.B. Leslie</PERSON> said the new planes, which will give
<ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> a 43-plane fleet, will serve the growing tourist market to
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. The airplanes will be financed by <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION>' foreign
exchange earnings and by overseas borrowings, he said.
   The order gives <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> six of the advanced-technology 747-400s,
the world's largest commercial jetliner, and five extended-range
767-300s.
   The four-engine 747-400, which made its first flight this
<DATE>spring</DATE>, can carry up to 660 passengers. With a more typical
configuration for 412 in two classes, the plane can fly more than
7,300 nautical miles, or from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>.
   The twin-engine 767-300 is capable of hauling up to 375
passengers, but can fly more than 7,000 miles with 210 aboard.
   So far this year, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> has had orders for 401 jetliners worth
<MONEY>$18.2 billion</MONEY>, compared with 366 jets worth a record <MONEY>$19.9 billion</MONEY>
in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> now has 148 orders for 747-400s and 103 orders for
767-300s.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880812-0245 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-88 0707EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-DoubleEagleAnniversary Adv16   08-12 1032</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Double Eagle Anniversary, Adv 16,1068</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv16</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Tue AMs, Aug. 16, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Balloonist Recounts Historic Flight on 10th Anniversary</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ARNOLD STAPLETON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a cramped gondola dangling beneath
an 11-story helium balloon, with clouds obstructing any view below,
the disembodied voice of the radar operator seemed scarcely to be
believed.
   ``You have crossed the coast of <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>,'' the voice told three
American balloonists on that still-dark early morning 10 years ago.
<PERSON>Larry Newman</PERSON> asked if the message was indeed that which had eluded
others for 105 years.
   Silence.
   Then, crisply, ``Sir, my radar is never wrong.''
   Newman, along with <PERSON>Ben Abruzzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON>, whooped with
joy. Sunburned and weary after five days aloft, the
businessmen-adventurers had made the first trans-Atlantic crossing
in a balloon.
   The three landed their black-and-silver Double Eagle II later
that day, <DATE>Aug. 17, 1978</DATE>, in a wheat field west of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Today, <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> is the only one of the three still alive.
   <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> was killed in <DATE>1983</DATE> at age 48 when his balloon crashed
in a West German forest during a race. Abruzzo, then 53, died in
<DATE>1985</DATE> when his twin-engine airplane crashed shortly after takeoff in
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>, now 40 and a commercial airline pilot in <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>,
said he has no specific plans to celebrate <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s anniversary.
   But he said his thoughts often drifted back to that <DATE>summer 10
years ago</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> recalled that after the initial jubilation, <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> went
to sleep while he and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> looked down through the clearing
clouds on the lights of <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>.
   The silent 112-foot balloon 15,000 feet up caught sounds that
drifted skyward. <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> could hear dogs barking and
trains rumbling along tracks nearly 3 miles below.
   ``Tears came to my eyes,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``I put my arm around
<PERSON>Ben</PERSON> _ he'd always been somewhat like a father to me. I hadn't felt
that close to another human being for as long as I can remember.''
   The men began the flight six days earlier when the <ORGANIZATION>Double Eagle
II</ORGANIZATION> lifted up from <LOCATION>Presque Isle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, and headed toward <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
more than 3,000 miles away.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> says the flight was not without problems, including a
clash of personalities.
   ``<PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON> later stated that he wished he could have flown
the flight by himself,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``I don't know what <PERSON>Ben</PERSON>'s
feelings were, but I wanted someone to share this with. I didn't
want to be <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>.''
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said conflicts arose when <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> both began
making key decisions.
   ``Any aircraft can only have one captain, and we had two: <PERSON>Ben
Abruzzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON>,'' he said.
   But <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said conflicts were overshadowed by the hardships of
the flight in the 12-by-6-foot living space crowded with TV cameras
and navigational equipment. Newman's hang glider dangled beneath
the gondola and 5,500 pounds of sand and lead for ballast hung over
the sides in bags.
   ``There were many times the flight was in question,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>
recalled. ``But how close it came to failure at each moment was
interpreted different by each of us.''
   They lost altitude rapidly at one point when ice chunks crusted
the top of the balloon. They jettisoned valuable ballast. When they
dropped to 4,000 feet the ice melted.
   Later in the flight they dumped more ballast, including an
expensive navigation system that had failed on the second day. They
tossed oxygen bottles, anything they could.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said that at one point, a bit delirious from the
altitude, he chucked a <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> radio _ and only later noticed a jar
of peanut butter that weighed as much.
   Plans were for <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> to fly the glider down once they made it
to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   But 400 miles from <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, it came down to a choice of dropping
the glider, their last oxygen and food, or a propane tank for a
heater to battle <ORGANIZATION>Abruzzo</ORGANIZATION>'s frostbite. The glider went.
   Radios also failed during the flight, and the men had to
communicate by ham radio.
   ``The first guy I talked to wouldn't talk because I didn't have
a license,'' said <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>. ``And he didn't believe I was in a
balloon over the middle of the ocean.''
   Finally, <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> reached an old man confined to a wheelchair in a
home for the elderly somewhere in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   ``His call sign was `G4JY.' I don't think I'll ever forget
that,'' he said. ``He talked to me until the <DATE>last day</DATE> of the
flight. He was like the Good Shepherd.''
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said the rough times were offset by the excitement.
   A high point, he said, came over <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> when a jumbo jet
relayed a message from the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution</ORGANIZATION>. The museum had
asked to display the gondola and balloon in the <ORGANIZATION>National Air</ORGANIZATION> and
Space Museum that houses the Apollo 11 moonship, <ORGANIZATION>Lindbergh's Spirit
of St. Louis</ORGANIZATION> and the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers' plane.
   In the final few hours the men believed they would make it to
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> had landed 51 years before after the first
solo trans-Atlantic airplane flight. But over <LOCATION>Evreux</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, they
realized they could not go on.
   The last of the ballast was gone, save for a bottle of
champagne. They were 60 miles west of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, 3,107 miles and 137
hours from <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> where the helium-packed balloon had taken off.
   The swiftly draining balloon envelope carcass and its gondola
settled gently to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as cheering spectators abandoned their cars
along a nearby highway and rushed to the balloon.
   Hundreds tried to take a piece of history.
   ``It's hard to chew rubberized cloth,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``People
were trying to tear little shreds off, but I think they were
probably losing their teeth more than damaging the balloon.''
   The French press dubbed them the ``new Lindberghs.''
   But <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> says the only time he thought about <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> was
when the adventurers drew straws that evening to see which would
sleep in <LOCATION>Lindbergh</LOCATION>'s bed at the American ambassador's residence in
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> and his wife won.
   ``And I ended up on the floor after 30 minutes because I
couldn't sleep,'' he said. ``The bed was like a banana. The springs
were shot.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tue AMs, Aug. 16</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900228-0268 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-28-90 1842EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-BoeingDelivery     02-28 0160</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boeing Delivery,0168</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Boeing 737-500 Delivered</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 737-500, the latest version of
the world's top-selling commercial jetliner, was delivered
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Airlines</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> said the 104-passenger plane was flown to <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, where
the regional carrier is based, 16 days after receiving flight
certification from the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   Nineteen customers have ordered a totak 193 737-500s, which cost
roughly <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> each.
   As of <DATE>last Thursday</DATE>, total orders for all models of the
twin-engine 737, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION>'s smallest jetliner, amounted to 2,771
planes, said <PERSON>T. Craig Martin</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Commercial Airplane Group</ORGANIZATION>.
   The more quiet, efficient and technologically advanced 737-500
replaces the 737-100 and 737-200 versions, which made their first
flights in <DATE>1967</DATE>, <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said.
   Production of the first two models ended after 1,144 were
delivered, the last a 737-200 for <ORGANIZATION>Xiamen Airlines</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug.
8, 1988</DATE>, said <PERSON>Martin</PERSON>.
   Other versions still in production are the 128-passenger 737-300
and 146-passenger 737-400.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900622-0106
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900622-0106.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Classic Planes on the Block
   ----
   By Joe Morgenstern
</HL>
<DATE>
06/22/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A6
</SO>
<LP>
   Santa Monica, Calif. -- At a recent auction of classic
aircraft here, I climbed onto the wing of a Curtiss P-40K
Warhawk to check out the cockpit. My pulse was racing, but
not from the climb. As a schoolboy during World War II, I'd
thrilled to newsreel footage of P-40 Flying Tigers shooting
down Japanese Zeros, doodled P-40s in class, even built a
solid -- i.e. non-flying -- model of a P-40, with a tiny
celluloid canopy and, pasted on either side of the nose,
red-and-white decals of the Flying Tigers' fearsome
dentition.
   This P-40 was flyable, as well as buyable by any bidder
with an itch to own a 47-year-old warplane that looked as if
it had just rolled out of the factory. The propeller-driven
fighter had been found in the Aleutian Islands in 1974 --
"the pilot's body was intact," a fact sheet noted -- and
restored to apparent perfection, right down to the rear-view
mirror above the canopy and the rudimentary gun sight, with
which the pilot -- still intact, for all I know, but not
included -- aimed the airplane to aim the guns.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   As I jumped from the wing back down to the ground, a young
woman who had been admiring the P-40 smiled and said hello.
She was Japanese, perhaps in her mid-20s, and, according to
her press badge, a writer for a Japanese aviation magazine.
"Excuse me," she said in careful English. "Do you know why
those small Japanese flags are there?" Her eyes went first to
six little rising suns stenciled on the fuselage below the
cockpit, then to my face, which must have revealed my
astonishment. "Each one," I answered very carefully,
"represents one airplane . . . uh . . . shot down."
   "Shot down," she repeated slowly. "Shot . . . down. Oh, I
see. Thank you very much."
   A sense of history wasn't obligatory at the auction, but
it helped. And not just military history -- though that was
evoked by such works of martial art as a British Spitfire and
a twin-engined, twin-tailed Lockheed P-38 Lightning -- but
the history of aviation, which has produced some of the most
beautiful mechanical objects since the Industrial Revolution.
   A sense of wonder helped too, in the face of time-warping
treasures such as a gorgeous two-seater <DATE>1938</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Curtiss Falcon</ORGANIZATION>
(serial No. 1) with red leather upholstery and intricate
patterns of riveted stitchery on dazzlingly polished aluminum
skin; a <DATE>1941</DATE> Ryan trainer, with sculptured wheel pants and a
birch-and-maple propeller; a <DATE>1918</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Curtiss Jenny</ORGANIZATION> biplane, its
canvas wings held together by wire and hope; and a pristine
red-and-white Fairchild 24, first owned in <DATE>1939</DATE> by <PERSON>Mary
Pickford</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Buddy Rogers</ORGANIZATION> and hardly flown since.
   The auction, organized for the benefit of <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>'s
superb new Museum of Flight, was the brainchild of <PERSON>David
Price</PERSON>, a 57-year-old industrialist and pilot who also doodled
warbirds as a kid in school, and who grew up half a block
from the airport, which was then called <ORGANIZATION>Clover Field</ORGANIZATION> (after a
World War I hero named Clover; so much for bucolic
resonances). Recently <PERSON>Mr. Price</PERSON> built the Supermarine
complex, a huge aviation service facility at the airport that
houses the museum plus a chic restaurant called DC-3. (<ORGANIZATION>Clover
Field</ORGANIZATION> was the home of <ORGANIZATION>Douglas Aircraft</ORGANIZATION> during the war.)
   "So far <PERSON>David</PERSON> has been carrying this museum," said <PERSON>Donald
Douglas Jr.</PERSON>, who attended the auction. "Now we've gotta get
it off his back."
   The two-day affair, which moved more than <MONEY>$7 million</MONEY> of
airplanes and memorabilia, went a long way toward relieving
<PERSON>Mr. Price</PERSON>'s back strain; by every reasonable measure,
including fun, it was a resounding success. Fun may have been
the most sensible measure for many buyers. <PERSON>Jim Mills</PERSON>, an
<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> aircraft-engine installer who bought <PERSON>Mary Pickford</PERSON>'s
Fairchild for <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> (a record price for the model and also
a steal) extolled the pleasures of flying slow, rolling down
the window and sticking your elbow out into the slipstream.
"That's all these things are any good for anyway, havin' a
good time with."
   Flying slow sounded equally good to <PERSON>Morgan Merrill</PERSON>, an
entrepreneur who lives in <LOCATION>Aspen</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo</LOCATION>. He lusted after the
<PERSON>Jenny</PERSON>, which sold to someone else for <MONEY>$175,000</MONEY>, even though
he loves flying his own British-made, fire-engine red <ORGANIZATION>Folland
Gnat</ORGANIZATION>, a modern-day supersonic jet trainer, at speeds up to
<ORGANIZATION>Mach</ORGANIZATION> 1.3.
   Fun for other people at the auction involved the calmer
pursuits of connoisseurship and stewardship. <PERSON>Delford Smith</PERSON>,
chairman of the board of <ORGANIZATION>Evergreen International</ORGANIZATION>, a large
aviation holding company, bought the P-40 for <MONEY>$750,000</MONEY>; a
DC3-built in <DATE>1936</DATE>, and the oldest still flying -- for
<MONEY>$165,000</MONEY>; and a Corsair fighter, with inverted gull wings,
for a record <MONEY>$750,000</MONEY>. (<ORGANIZATION>Corsairs</ORGANIZATION> are comers in this market.)
Then, prompted by associates and advisers who knew of his
love for bare-metal airplanes, he bid on the glittering
Falcon and got it, for <MONEY>$335,000</MONEY>.
   "We believe in preserving this heritage," said <PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON>,
who plans to find homes for his new acquisitions in various
museums. He also urged the <ORGANIZATION>Falcon</ORGANIZATION>'s former owner, <PERSON>Richard
Durand</PERSON>, to call him any time he wanted to visit the airplane,
or even to use it. The gesture was appreciated by <PERSON>Mr. Durand</PERSON>,
who runs an aviation service company in <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>,
and who had sold because of what he called a "pretty rough
business climate for us now." But it didn't make the parting
any less sorrowful. "Don't leave it out in the rain," <PERSON>Mr.
Durand</PERSON> told <PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON> on the flight line, while his wife
fought back tears.
   The high point of the auction was the sale of the P-38
Lightning, one of six still flying throughout the world. For
one thing, this illustrious airplane, newly painted in attack
black, had been bought and restored by the Museum of Flight,
and was the museum's main chance for earning big bucks. Most
importantly, the Lightning seemed an irresistible symbol of
this country's sovereignty and creativity at a time when
foreign competition has been calling both into serious
question.
   When the bidding began, the crowd rooted for <PERSON>William Lyon</PERSON>,
a 67-year-old retired <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> general who'd made his
fortune in real estate and airlines, and against an
unidentified rival, represented, via telephone hookup, by
<ORGANIZATION>City National Bank of Los Angeles</ORGANIZATION>. The rival might have been
from <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Staten Island</LOCATION>, but was instantly assumed to
be Japanese, so the crowd cheered when the bidding finally
ended with <PERSON>Mr. Lyon</PERSON> taking the trophy for a record <MONEY>$1.55
million</MONEY>. They cheered for the general, for the museum and for
the nation, which had brought the Lightning into this world
in <DATE>1939</DATE> and could now, by God, hang onto it.
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Morgenstern</PERSON> is a writer in <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900618-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-18-90 1940EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Osprey-EmergencyLanding     06-18 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Osprey-Emergency Landing,0304</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tilt-Rotor V-22 Osprey Makes Emergency Landing</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ARLINGTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An experimental tilt-rotor aircraft
designed to hover like a helicopter and fly like an airplane made
an emergency landing <DATE>Monday</DATE> after one of two engines failed, a
spokesman said.
   The V-22 Osprey lost power in its left engine, but was able to
return safely to <LOCATION>Arlington Municipal Airport</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Terry Arnold</PERSON>,
spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Bell Helicopter Textron Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   No injuries or damage to the prototype aircraft were reported
after the <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> malfunction in the skies about 40 miles southwest
of downtown <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Arnold</PERSON> said.
   ``Actually, we're pleased, because the aircraft did what it was
supposed to do,'' <PERSON>Arnold</PERSON> said. ``The other engine engaged the shaft
and drove both rotor systems and we landed without incident. It was
designed to do just that.''
   Arnold said it was the first emergency landing on record for the
V-22. The cause of the malfunction was not immediately known.
   The Osprey can hover and land like a helicopter but also flies
at up to 340 mph as a fixed-wing airplane _ much faster than a
helicopter. Large rotors on the ends of the wings tilt up for
vertical flight and rotate forward for the long haul.
   Arnold said the aircraft, one of four Osprey prototypes, was in
``airplane mode'' when the engine failed.
   It flew in ``airplane mode'' back to the airport, where it
swooped down and landed like a helicopter, said <PERSON>Bob Leder</PERSON>, another
<ORGANIZATION>Bell Helicopter Textron</ORGANIZATION> spokesman.
   The four prototypes are among six Ospreys for which the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>
has contracted.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> has spent <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> to develop the V-22
Osprey and its predecessor, the XV-15, for military use. But
<ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Dick Cheney</PERSON> wants to end funding in favor of
conventional helicopter development.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900329-0252 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-29-90 0009EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-First747     03-29 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-First 747,0336</SECOND>
<HEAD>First 747 Retired to Museum</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first 747 jumbo jet, which changed the look
of jet travel with its huge size and distinctive upper-deck hump,
has flown into retirement, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Commercial Airplane Group</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The red-and-white jumbo jet rolled off the assembly line near
<LOCATION>Everett</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sept. 30, 1968</DATE>, made its first flight on <DATE>Feb. 9, 1969</DATE>,
and won certification on <DATE>Dec. 30</DATE> that year.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> has used the aircraft as a test plane for 21 years. Now,
the ``City of Everett'' is being donated to the Museum of Flight in
<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Pan American World Airways</ORGANIZATION> signed the first contract for 747s,
ordering 25 for a total of <MONEY>$525 million</MONEY>. Today, that amount would
buy four of the jets, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The test plane's only break in service was from <DATE>October 1983</DATE> to
<DATE>August 1986</DATE>, when it was in storage in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>. It was then sent
to <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>, where it was used as a mock-up for two 747-200s
that the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> will use to carry the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> president and his
staff.
   The plane had only 5,208 hours of flight time. That's very low,
considering a jet in normal commercial service flies 3,000 to 4,000
hours every year, company spokesman <PERSON>Tom Cole</PERSON> said.
   ``But it was tough stuff. They were always putting it into dives
and stalls,'' he said.
   The plane, officially known as RA001, had a short final flight
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>: about 25 miles from <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Field</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paine
Field</LOCATION>, where 747s are built near <LOCATION>Everett</LOCATION>.
   There, its engines will be taken off and returned to <ORGANIZATION>Pratt &amp;
Whitney</ORGANIZATION>, which owns them, followed by some restoration work.
   Eventually, the plane will be displayed at the museum's
restoration facility or at a new large-aircraft interpretive center
the museum hopes to build at <LOCATION>Paine Field</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Cindy Upthegrove</PERSON>,
the museum's special events manager.
   About 800 747s are in service around the world, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881105-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-05-88 0624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Boeing-Poland     11-05 0436</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boeing-Poland,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>In Breakthrough, LOT Polish Airlines To Acquire 3 Boeing Jets</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER COY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>'s national airline established two firsts
by ordering advanced <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> aircraft and planning to offer two classes
of service in the new jets.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Co.</ORGANIZATION> will sell three 767 wide-body jets to <ORGANIZATION>LOT Polish
Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, marking the first time a Soviet bloc nation has purchased
modern, American jets. The deal, announced <DATE>Friday</DATE>, is worth <MONEY>$220
million</MONEY> to <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>General Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the engine supplier.
   LOT also said it would offer business- and economy-class service
on the jets. Only one class of service currently is offered on the
Soviet-made aircraft that make up LOT's 45-plane fleet.
   The state-owned airline said the three jets would be used on
flights linking <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> with the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>. It said
they should help double its traffic between <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> as early as next year.
   The moves were seen as the first attempt by an <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> bloc
airline to compete with Western concerns for Western passengers,
particularly business travelers, who pay higher fares but also
demand a high level of service.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> officials said they hoped the deal, though relatively
small, would lead to more deals with <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> and other Soviet bloc
nations.
   ``We're very proud and pleased that we were selected. It's a
major breakthrough for us,'' said <PERSON>Rudy Hillinga</PERSON>, director of sales
for Central and <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION> for <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Commercial Airplanes Co</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> said it will be the first to deliver modern, wide-body
jets made in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> to a Soviet bloc nation because it will
deliver its first two planes to <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> before <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Airbus</ORGANIZATION>
consortium delivers two A-310s to <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> under a previously
announced deal.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> will deliver two 767-200s in <DATE>April</DATE> and <DATE>May 1989</DATE> and one
767-300 in <DATE>June 1990</DATE>. All will be extended-range models, powered by
<ORGANIZATION>General Electric</ORGANIZATION> CF6-80C2 engines. <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> declined to specify how
the <MONEY>$220 million</MONEY> price was split between <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION>.
   Although <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> has a desperate shortage of hard currency to buy
Western goods, the airline is an exception because it brings in hard
currencies every time it flies to the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. That made the financing
relatively easy.
   In a deal financed by unspecified Western banks, LOT will lease
the airplanes and engines for 12 years, at the end of which it will
own them, <PERSON>Hillinga</PERSON> said. <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION> will be paid by the banks.
   LOT said it will use the jetliners on its routes between <LOCATION>Warsaw</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>. Later, <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> will be added.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-21048 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpest007___94045" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-EST-94-007 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Europe/International </ABS>
<DATE1>   20 January 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> WEST EUROPE </F>
<F P=101> DEFENSE R&amp;D </F>
<H3> <TI>   Sweden: Saab 340 AEW Makes First Flight </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  94WS0218D Paris AFP SCIENCES in French 20 Jan 94 p 16 </F>
<F P=103> 94WS0218D </F>
<F P=104>  Paris AFP SCIENCES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FP=105> French </F>
Article Type:CSO 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>--<ORGANIZATION>Saab Aircraft AB</ORGANIZATION> announced 17 <DATE>January</DATE> in 
<LOCATION>Linkoeping</LOCATION> that its new, radar-carrying Saab-340-AEW had made 
its first test flight, which lasted two hours. 
  The structure of the new Airborne Early Warning (AEW) model, 
which is based on a twinjet commercial airplane with a Saab-340 
type propellor, was reinforced to carry a 900-kg radar made by 
the Swedish company <ORGANIZATION>Ericsson Radar Electronics</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The rear of the aircraft was altered to hold an auxiliary 
electrical power system (APU - <ORGANIZATION>Auxiliary Power Unit</ORGANIZATION>) to supply 
the radar, its cooling device, and the equipment for cooling its 
computers. 
  <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Defense Equipment Office</ORGANIZATION> (FMV) ordered six of the 
aircraft for surveillance of national land and sea territory. A 
spokesperson for <ORGANIZATION>Saab Aircraft AB</ORGANIZATION> said that construction of the 
craft, excluding radar, would cost just over <MONEY>500 million Swedish 
crowns</MONEY> (a little over <MONEY>365 million French francs</MONEY> [Fr], give or 
take). 
  The new Saab-340-AEW, which the British have nicknamed "the 
poor man's <ORGANIZATION>AWAC</ORGANIZATION>", has attracted the notice of international 
specialists. This, says the company spokesperson, "is a very 
good sign for future exports." The first <ORGANIZATION>AEW</ORGANIZATION> will be delivered 
to <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s defense forces during the <DATE>first quarter of 1995</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881012-0246 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-12-88 1123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-747Delays     10-12 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-747 Delays,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jumbo Jet Deliveries Delayed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Deliveries of some of <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s new 747-400
jumbo jets will be delayed by a month or so, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Commercial
Airplanes</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Dean <PERSON>D. Thornton</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> operating company,
said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that of the 161 747-400s ordered by 21 customers, 20
planes will be delivered an average of one month past the
previously agreed upon date.
   ``We intend to obtain <ORGANIZATION>Federal Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION>
certification of the 747-400 in <DATE>December</DATE>, to deliver the first two
aircraft that month and to be back on our original schedule by
mid-1989,'' <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON> said.
   Two deliveries will be pushed back from <DATE>December to early 1989</DATE>,
and there will be a substantial reduction in <DATE>first-quarter 1989</DATE>
deliveries, the company said in a news release. Most of the
deliveries will be made up in the <DATE>second quarter of 1989</DATE>, it said.
   <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON> said far more orders for the new jet were received from
customers on an earlier schedule than anticipated when the program
was launched in <DATE>October 1985</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON> said the delays are due to the increase of 747
production rates at <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION>'s Everett plant from two planes to five
a month and to customers seeking a wider variety of plane
configurations than on earlier programs.
   The delays also stem from the 747-400s being offered with three
different engine types, with each being introduced and certified in
a record four months.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> is doing its best to minimize the impact of the delays on
customers, <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON> said, including working overtime and
reassigning additional experienced workers to the 747 plant.
   The new jet, which made its first flight earlier this year, is
the largest commercial jet in production. The plane will be able to
carry 412 passengers more than 8,000 miles, and greater passenger
loads on shorter trips.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900828-0054
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900828-0054.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Jet Makes Maiden Flight
   In Air Force Job Rivalry
</HL>
<DATE>
08/28/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<CO>
   NOC MD UTX LK BA GD
</CO>
<IN>
AEROSPACE (ARO)
</IN>
<GV>
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF)
</GV>
<LP>
   EDWARDS AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. -- A version of the Air
Force's next-generation fighter jet, built by Northrop Corp.
and McDonnell Douglas Corp., took to the skies for the first
time yesterday, setting the stage for a showdown with another
version of the aircraft built by a rival team of aerospace
companies.
   The twin-engine YF-23, with a Northrop test pilot, Paul
Metz, at the controls, climbed to 25,000 feet, and functional
checks of basic subsystems were performed during the
early-morning, 50-minute flight. United Technologies Corp.'s
Pratt &amp; Whitney division made the engines on the YF-23.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "The airplane flies very clean, much cleaner than we
expected," <PERSON>Mr. Metz</PERSON> said. "During the climb-out, I was using
considerably less power than I expected, and the chase
airplanes were on afterburners just to stay with me -- with
my landing gear down."
   The other team, composed of <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Co.</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>General Dynamics Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, is scheduled to roll out its Advanced
Tactical Fighter, the YF-22, tomorrow at a <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> site in
<LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. The first flight of that plane is expected
to be next month.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>, which wants 750 of the jets to replace the
aging F-15 fighter, is scheduled to choose the winning team
in <DATE>April</DATE> and award the full-scale development contract three
months later. A second YF-23, which was delivered to a test
facility here in <DATE>June</DATE>, will fly with <ORGANIZATION>General Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION>
engines.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891118-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-18-89 2229EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StealthBomber     11-18 0204</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stealth Bomber,0212</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stealth Bomber Undergoes Seventh Test Flight</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EDWARDS AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The B-2 Stealth bomber
completed its seventh test flight <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, including an in-flight
shutdown and startup of its four engines, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The bomber took off from <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in the Mojave
desert at <TIME>7:14 a.m.</TIME> and returned at <TIME>2:31 p.m</TIME>. The 7-hour, 17-minute
flight included two aerial refuelings.
   Each of the aircraft's four <ORGANIZATION>General Electric</ORGANIZATION> F118 engines were
deliberately stopped, then restarted about midway through the
flight, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The bomber's crew also conducted normal and alternate landing
gear extensions.
   <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> test pilot Lt. Col. <PERSON>John Small</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
chief test pilot <PERSON>Bruce J. Hinds</PERSON> were in the cockpit of the advanced
technology bomber.
   The bomber was designed to reduce radar detection through the
use of composite materials and countoured surfaces, which absorb
radar signals instead of reflecting the signals.
   The strategic bomber made its first flight <DATE>July 17</DATE>.
   The B-2, which is capable of delivering nuclear and conventional
weapons, is intended to replace the nation's aging B-52 strategic
bomber fleet.
   With an estimated price <MONEY>$530 million</MONEY> per airplane, the B-2 is
considered the world's most expensive aircraft.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890319-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-19-89 2241EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewAircraft     03-19 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Aircraft,0295</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prototype Of Unique Aircraft Successful In First Test Flight</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ARLINGTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two test pilots took a successful
15-minute test flight <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in a prototype of a revolutionary
aircraft designed to perform like both a helicopter and an airplane,
officials said.
   The V-22 Osprey, the world's first production tilt-rotor
aircraft, remained in helicopter mode throughout the flight,
according to officials of <ORGANIZATION>Bell Boeing</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION>, a consortium of
two companies which built the craft.
   Bell <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> officials described tests in aircraft mode as ``a
milestone soon to be accomplished.''
   The V-22 Osprey performed both a slow taxi liftoff and a vertical
takeoff during the landmark maneuvers and made conventional
``run-on'' landings, the officials said. Its top speed during the
tests was limited to 20 knots, less than 25 mph.
   The aircraft combines the operational capabilities of a
helicopter with those of a fixed-wind turboprop. With its engines
and prop-rotors vertical, the V-22 takes off, hovers and lands like
a helicopter.
   With its prop-rotors in forward position, the Osprey would become
a fast, fuel-efficient, high-altitude turboprop airplane capable of
reaching speeds of more than 345 mph.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Helicopters</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Don Chesnut</PERSON> said the Osprey gives
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military ``the ability to develop new missions and tactics
that cannot be accomplished by any existing helicopter or airplane.''
   Six flight-test prototypes are being built by <ORGANIZATION>Bell Helicopter
Textron Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Helicopters</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, a
division of <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Co.</ORGANIZATION>, under a <MONEY>$1.8 billion</MONEY> full-scale development
contract issued by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Naval Air Systems Command</ORGANIZATION>.
   The versatile Osprey is the first modern weapons system designed
from conception to meet requirements of all four <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> armed
services, with deliveries expected to begin in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890714-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-14-89 0511EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StealthTest Bjt   07-14 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stealth Test, Bjt,0539</SECOND>
<HEAD>Air Force Says B-2 Ground Tests Successful</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PALMDALE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The B-2 stealth bomber is ready to fly
after successfully completing ground tests, and takeoff could come
as early as <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> says.
   The bat-winged aircraft sped down a desert runway <DATE>Thursday</DATE>,
hitting a top speed of 132 mph and lifting its nose wheel off the
tarmac, said Brig. Gen. <PERSON>Richard Scofield</PERSON>, director of the B-2
program.
   ``We've completed all the taxi tests prior to going to first
flight,'' <PERSON>Scofield</PERSON> said. ``The airplane is in good shape.''
   The bomber, in development for more than a decade, has been
subjected to extensive computer-simulated flights but has never
actually lifted off a runway.
   It incorporates revolutionary technologies and the use of
lightweight composite material to elude radar by absorbing radar
energy, rather than reflecting it as conventional aircraft do.
   But although the bomber appears ready to fly, congressional
opposition to the costly defense program threatens to ground the B-2
just as it is rising to prove its secret capabilities.
   Congressmen warned <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> officials earlier this week that
they face a tough uphill fight with the B-2, which recent estimates
indicate would be the most expensive aircraft in history.
   ``Put it in perspective or there's a real possibility that the
B-2 will become a museum piece,'' said Rep. <PERSON>Les Aspin</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>,
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House Armed Services Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Dick Cheney</PERSON> pleaded with <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
not to ``nickel and dime to death'' the B-2, saying the bomber is
essential for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces to ``penetrate improving Soviet air
defenses.''
   Testifying before the <ORGANIZATION>House Armed Services Committee</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Cheney</PERSON>
urged lawmakers to try to overcome ``sticker shock'' at the <MONEY>$500
million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$750 million</MONEY> price for each plane and to restore <MONEY>$800
million</MONEY> the panel cut from the B-2 budget last month.
   At <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Plant 42</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Scofield</PERSON> refused to be drawn
into the political debate, telling reporters: ``I'm working on the
airplane end of the thing _ and the airplane is doing just fine.''
   <PERSON>Scofield</PERSON> said engineers from <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which designed and
built the B-2, and <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> officials would spend at least one day
evaluating data gathered during <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s ground tests.
   ``We will have to see what the data tells us,'' the general said.
``We'll be working on a number of issues.''
   Nevertheless, he made clear that <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> officials
believe they have all the data they need to send the bomber airborne.
   After maintaining for years that the B-2 didn't exist, the <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> invited the media and dignitaries to a coming-out ceremony
last <DATE>November</DATE>.
   Last week, the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> announced the first flight tests of the
bomber _ 18 months behind schedule _ would be held during the next
two weeks.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> is proposing a <MONEY>$4.7 billion</MONEY> budget in fiscal <DATE>1990</DATE>
for the B-2. Manufactured by <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION>, the plane will
cost about <MONEY>$24 billion</MONEY> over a three-year peak period beginning in
<DATE>fiscal 1992</DATE>, according to <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> figures.
   The department has invested about <MONEY>$22.4 billion</MONEY> in the plane so
far.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880523-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-23-88 2050EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Tilt-Rotor     05-23 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tilt-Rotor,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Production Tilt-Rotor Aircraft Unveiled</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DN2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY JORDEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ARLINGTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first non-experimental aircraft that
flies both like a helicopter and an airplane rolled into the
spotlight <DATE>Monday</DATE>, hailed as an aviation milestone by legislators
and top military brass.
   The V-22 Osprey, a tilt-rotor craft that takes off and hovers
like a helicopter and flies like an airplane, received a standing
ovation from a crowd of 1,600. The crowd watched as the camouflaged
craft was towed onto the tarmac at <ORGANIZATION>Bell Helicopter Textron Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Flight Research Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first flight of the V-22, which has been in development for
30 years, is scheduled for <DATE>Aug. 15</DATE>. An advanced experimental model,
the XV-15, has been flying since <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   Fort Worth-based <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Helicopter Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>
are jointly developing the V-22 for the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Marines</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION>. The three services plan to buy 682 of the twin-engine
aircraft at an estimated cost of <MONEY>$16.6 million</MONEY> each.
   ``It's kind of awesome,'' Marine Corps Commandant <PERSON>Alfred M. Gray
Jr.</PERSON> told the crowd.
   ``It works, it's ahead of schedule and will be a sound
investment for taxpayers' money,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>William L.
Ball III</PERSON>, comparing the tilt-rotor's production to the jet engine's
development as aviation milestones.
   ``You are proving every day that a great country can still
outthink, out-design and out-produce all comers,'' <PERSON>Ball</PERSON> said.
   The three military services plan to use the V-22 for combat
assault, search and rescue, medical evacuation and special-forces
missions. Other uses, including anti-submarine warfare, also are
being studied. The cabin can carry 24 combat-equipped troops in
addition to a crew of three.
   ``On our abortive rescue attempt made in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> a few years ago,
think what could have happened if they'd had an Osprey,'' said
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> Speaker <PERSON>Jim Wright</PERSON>, referring to the failed <DATE>1980</DATE> rescue of 44
American hostages from <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>.
   The Osprey, about the size of a medium transport aircraft, has a
stocky 57.3-foot-long fuselage and twin engines mounted on thick,
stubby wings. Its engines point upward during takeoff and landing,
with 38-foot diameter rotor blades that parallel the ground.
   The engines rotate, or ``tilt,'' forward once the V-22 is
airborne. Rotors lock into place and act like oversized propellers,
pulling the Osprey through the air like a conventional aircraft.
   The tilt-rotor can fly with the speed and range of a turboprop
plane _ more than 360 mph _ but doesn't require an airport or
runway. It also can hover like a helicopter.
   ``I'm convinced that in the <DATE>next 20 years</DATE> there will be
thousands of these in use,'' said Bell President L.M. ``Jack''
<PERSON>Horner</PERSON>.
   Bell has talked with <ORGANIZATION>American Airlines</ORGANIZATION> and several commuter
companies about civilian uses for the craft, a spokesman said.
   ``The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> (and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>) Port Authority is a strong
supporter of this concept,'' said <PERSON>Horner</PERSON>. ``We could build a lot of
V-22s for the cost of one airport.
   The British-designed Harrier jump-jet also takes off and lands
vertically, but using jet-propulsion rather than a rotor system.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060489-0230 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 66382 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 4, 1989, Sunday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
661 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PEGASUS RISES ON THE WINGS, UH LEGS, OF PILOTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARY LOU FULTON, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It was about <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> when eight UC <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> engineering students 
converged on a campus athletic field to assemble the human-powered airplane 
they worked all year to perfect. 
</P>
<P>
By the light of fluorescent lamps powered through yards of orange extension 
cords, the students joined the tail boom to the fuselage, attached the 
propeller, assembled six wing sections and covered most of the aircraft with 
transparent Mylar. 
</P>
<P>
Before daybreak, there it was: <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION>, its 100-foot-long single wing suspended 
like a giant white ruler against a backdrop of trees. And despite a soggy 
morning and a series of mechanical failures, the ungainly aircraft powered by a 
fast-pedaling cyclist actually got off the ground. 
</P>
<P>
"You hear the wheels on the ground and then all of a sudden there's nothing 
between you and the ground," said team member <PERSON>Jeanne Pandes</PERSON>, 22, who piloted 
the plane on its first short flights. "You're cruising." 
</P>
<P>
Pegasus is the third and most successful attempt by UC <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> mechanical 
engineering students to construct a human-powered airplane as a senior project. 
The <DATE>1987</DATE> airplane, dubbed the UC Medfly, crashed almost immediately after 
leaving the ground. Last year's 
</P>
<P>
plane, UC-ME-FLY ("you see me fly"), succeeded in making flights of close to 
300 feet. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> team used wing sections from UC-ME-FLY, but built a new, more 
aerodynamic fuselage that reduced the airplane's weight from 135 pounds to 120 
pounds, said project leader <PERSON>Greg Hill</PERSON>, 23. 
</P>
<P>
The 35-foot-long aircraft is made of balsa wood, sturdy carbon fiber tubing and 
transparent Mylar, a plastic coating. 
</P>
<P>
Pegasus is one of eight senior projects in the mechanical engineering 
department, whose students also designed a human-powered car and a 
human-powered hydrofoil, both of which are scheduled to make their debut <DATE>Monday</DATE> 
<TIME>morning</TIME> in <LOCATION>Newport Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
About <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the weather was a major source of anxiety for the 
<ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> team. An infrequent drizzle covered the wings with a film of water, 
which one student patiently scraped off with a yellow squeegee. Because of the 
wing's large surface area, Hill estimated that the drizzle added about 10 
pounds to the airplane's weight. 
</P>
<P>
Wearing black tights, white tennis shoes and a <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> T-shirt, Pandes crawled 
into the triangular cockpit and experimented with the pedals. The covered 
cockpit bore the advertising logos of the dozen companies that donated about 
<MONEY>$8,000</MONEY> to build <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The team positioned itself for the takeoff, one student holding up the end of 
each wing and several more supporting the fuselage and tail. Pandes began 
pedaling and <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> quivered unsteadily from nose to tail. 
</P>
<P>
"Let's go, <PERSON>Jeanne</PERSON>," one student urged the pilot. 
</P>
<P>
The aircraft lifted off the ground, traveling perhaps 15 feet, then one of the 
wires holding the wings to the fuselage snapped. The students repaired the wire 
and tried again. Pandes piloted the airplane for four more flights, the longest 
of which was about 40 feet. 
</P>
<P>
 Pegasus needed more power. So the second pilot, amateur cyclist <PERSON>Arcadio 
Biboso</PERSON>, was called in. 
</P>
<P>
Clad in yellow and black Spandex, Biboso's powerful legs lifted <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> on a 
60-foot flight. But he reported a problem with the pedaling mechanism -- the 
chain linking the pedals to the propeller shaft kept jerking, causing the 
airplane to lose momentum. 
</P>
<P>
The team discussed ways to correct the problem and, in a last-ditch effort, 
attached a chain-tightening device with quick-drying epoxy glue and some 
string. 
</P>
<P>
A few minutes later, with Biboso at the controls, <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> made its longest 
flight ever: nearly 300 feet. 
</P>
<P>
The next attempt was even more successful, with the airplane staying aloft for 
more than 300 feet. 
</P>
<P>
But as <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> was landing, the right wing hit the ground and snapped in the 
middle. 
</P>
<P>
In a post-mortem of <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION>' flight, Hill mourned that "these wings are so 
long, so fragile . . . but that the plane has stayed together through all these 
rough landings says something for us, I guess." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, UC-Irvine students accompany Pegasus as it lifts off the ground. Pilot 
Jeanne Pandes provides the leg power. ADRIENNE HELITZER / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT IRVINE; ENGINEERS; ENGINEERING; CONTESTS; HUMAN 
POWERED FLIGHT; AIRPLANES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060489-0152 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 65914 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 4, 1989, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 13; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
713 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IT'S UP, UP AND AWAY -- IF ONLY FOR SHORT TIME; 
</P>
<P>
INVENTIVE STUDENT MINDS, STRONG LEGS COMBINE IN UNENDING QUEST FOR 
HUMAN-POWERED FLIGHT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARY LOU FULTON, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
IRVINE 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It was about <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> when eight UC <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> engineering students 
converged on a campus athletic field to assemble the human-powered airplane 
they worked all year to perfect. 
</P>
<P>
By the light of fluorescent lamps powered through yards of orange extension 
cords, the students joined the tail boom to the fuselage, attached the 
propeller, assembled six wing sections and covered most of the aircraft with 
transparent Mylar. 
</P>
<P>
Before daybreak, there it was: <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION>, its 100-foot-long single wing suspended 
like a giant white ruler against a backdrop of trees. And despite a soggy 
morning and a series of mechanical failures, the ungainly aircraft powered by a 
fast-pedaling cyclist actually got off the ground. 
</P>
<P>
"You hear the wheels on the ground and then all of a sudden there's nothing 
between you and the ground," said team member <PERSON>Jeanne Pandes</PERSON>, 22, who piloted 
the plane on its first short flights. "You're cruising." 
</P>
<P>
Pegasus is the third and most successful attempt by UC <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> mechanical 
engineering students to construct a human-powered airplane as a senior project. 
The <DATE>1987</DATE> airplane, dubbed the UC Medfly, crashed almost immediately after 
leaving the ground. Last year's plane, UC-ME-FLY ("you see me fly"), succeeded 
in making flights of close to 300 feet. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> team used wing sections from UC-ME-FLY, but built a new, more 
aerodynamic fuselage that reduced the airplane's weight from 135 pounds to 120 
pounds, said project leader <PERSON>Greg Hill</PERSON>, 23. 
</P>
<P>
The 35-foot-long aircraft is made of balsa wood, sturdy carbon fiber tubing and 
transparent Mylar, a plastic coating. 
</P>
<P>
Pegasus is one of eight senior projects in the mechanical engineering 
department, whose students also designed a human-powered car and a 
human-powered hydrofoil, both of which are scheduled to make their debut <DATE>Monday</DATE> 
<TIME>morning</TIME> in <LOCATION>Newport Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
About <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the weather was a major source of anxiety for the 
<ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> team. An infrequent drizzle covered the wings with a film of water, 
which one student patiently scraped off with a yellow squeegee. Because of the 
wing's large surface area, Hill estimated that the drizzle added about 10 
pounds to the airplane's weight. 
</P>
<P>
Once the wires and propeller had been checked, the students pushed <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> 
across the soggy sod to the end of the field. 
</P>
<P>
Wearing black tights, white tennis shoes and a <ORGANIZATION>Pegasus</ORGANIZATION> T-shirt, Pandes crawled 
