<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900913-0250 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-13-90 1806EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-SAS-Continental     09-13 0280</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAS-Continental,0305</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scandinavian Airlines Closes Continental Deal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION> completed a <MONEY>$50
million</MONEY> deal <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that makes it the largest shareholder of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and puts <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> out as
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> chairman.
   Lorenzo will get <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> through the arrangement, approved a
day earlier by the <ORGANIZATION>Transportation Department</ORGANIZATION>, but a <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
spokesman said the money is not all coming from the <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> purchase.
   ``<PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> is paid out over a period of time
through the company,'' spokesman Art <PERSON>Kent</PERSON> said. ``It's not like
he's getting a lump sum.''
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> said it paid Lorenzo <MONEY>$17 million</MONEY> to buy out his employment
contract and to obtain vested options he had in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> stock,
although <LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION> retains options on 783,333 shares. Lorenzo remains
as a <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> director.
   As part of the deal, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> purchased <ORGANIZATION>Jet Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which
<PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> and partners used as a holding company for their shares of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> also bought 2.25 million newly issued shares of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$14</MONEY> per share.
   <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>, based in
<LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, issued a joint statement <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> that
also announced several appointments to the 15-member <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
board.
   As previously announced, the former president of <ORGANIZATION>Delta Airlines</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Hollis L. Harris</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, becomes president and chief executive
of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> also joins the board.
   Long-time <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> director <PERSON>Carl Pohlad</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, was
elected chairman. <PERSON>Robert Garrett</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, was elected chairman
of the executive committee.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> said it would appoint three members to the <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
board, including <PERSON>Jan Carlzon</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>, president and chief
executive of <ORGANIZATION>SAS Group</ORGANIZATION>. The other <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> appointees are <PERSON>Lars Bergvall</PERSON>,
of <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>, chief operating officer of <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>; and <PERSON>Roberto Mendoza</PERSON>,
of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, vice chairman of <ORGANIZATION>J.P. Morgan</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901128-0250 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-28-90 2020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-ContinentalLawsuit     11-28 0194</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Continental Lawsuit,0251</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Throws Out Lawsuit Filed by Continental Shareholder</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge threw out a lawsuit
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that alleged <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> illegally sold his position as
chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> when <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> paid four times the going
price for stock in the airline.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge H. Lee Sarokin</PERSON> ruled that he did not have
jurisdiction in the case.
   Continental stockholder <PERSON>M. Barnett Gillman</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Lauderdale Lakes</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, had asked the judge to declare the deal void.
   Named in the suit were <LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, Scandinavian Airline System e
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge threw out a lawsuit
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that alleged <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> illegally sold his position as
chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> when <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> paid four times the going
price for stock in the airline.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge H. Lee Sarokin</PERSON> ruled that he did not have
jurisdiction in the case.
   Continental stockholder <PERSON>M. Barnett Gillman</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Lauderdale Lakes</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, had asked the judge to declare the deal void.
   Named in the suit were <LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, Scandinavian Airline System e
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900912-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-12-90 2110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-ContinentalSale     09-12 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Continental Sale,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>SAS Acquisition of Continental Stake Approved</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Transportation Department</ORGANIZATION> will allow
<ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION> to buy out most of <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON>'s
interest in <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the department said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The move will nearly double <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s stake in the parent company of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> through a <MONEY>$52.5 million</MONEY> stock purchase.
   Under the deal approved by the department, <ORGANIZATION>Scandanavian Airlines</ORGANIZATION>
will own <PERCENT>16.8 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> and <PERCENT>18.4 percent</PERCENT> of its voting
stock, and will be given three seats on the holding company's
15-member board.
   However, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> agreed to not buy more than <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT> of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s voting stock for three years. It cannot own more than
<PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> because of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> laws requiring that domestic airlines be
controlled by Americans. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> already owned <PERCENT>9.9 percent</PERCENT> of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s voting stock.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> agreed to buy 2.25 million shares of newly issued
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> stock for <MONEY>$31.5 million</MONEY> and will pay another <MONEY>$21
million</MONEY> to buy <ORGANIZATION>Jet Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which owns another 2.1 million
shares of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> stock. The Jet Capital stock was owned by
<LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION>.
   Lorenzo, who continues to own some 800,000 shares of the
company, resigned last month as chief executive officer of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> and has been replaced by <PERSON>Hollis Harris</PERSON>, former
president of <ORGANIZATION>Delta Airlines</ORGANIZATION>.
   Some <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> shareholders have filed lawsuits in <ORGANIZATION>Delaware
Chancery Court</ORGANIZATION> asking that the transactions among <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, Jet
Capital, <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> be blocked. They argued the deals were
``entered into in breech of fiduciary duties owed to <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> shareholders.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900815-0079
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900815-0079.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Continental Air
   Holders Sue to Stop
   Buy-Out of Lorenzo
   ----
   By Bridget O'Brian
</HL>
<DATE>
08/15/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B8
</SO>
<CO>
   CTA K.SAI JTC
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
AIRLINES (AIR)
</IN>
<LP>
   Several Continental Airlines Holdings Inc. shareholders
sued to stop the proposed purchase of Frank Lorenzo's stake
in the airline company by Scandinavian Airlines System.
   In addition to Mr. Lorenzo, who stepped down as chairman
plaintiffs also sued that company, its directors and Jet
Capital Corp., the tightly controlled holding company that
owns a special class of Continental Holdings stock. SAS was
not named in the suits.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The suits -- three of them filed in <ORGANIZATION>Delaware Chancery
Court</ORGANIZATION> and a fourth filed in <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>
-- allege that <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> directors breached their fiduciary
duty by agreeing to a buy-out in which <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> and Jet
Capital's other shareholders receive <MONEY>$14</MONEY> to <MONEY>$18</MONEY> apiece for
yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> shares closed at <MONEY>$5.25</MONEY>, down
<MONEY>87.5 cents</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> agreed last week to sell all his stock in
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> and to vacate his management
posts at both the holding company and its <ORGANIZATION>Continental
Airlines</ORGANIZATION> unit, although he will remain a director. <PERSON>Mr.
Lorenzo</PERSON> would receive more than <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY>, including <MONEY>$10.8
million</MONEY> for his shares in Jet Capital, and <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> would buy most
of his stock options, also at a premium. The transaction
would boost <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s equity stake to <PERCENT>16.8%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>9.8%</PERCENT>.
   The <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION> suits charge that <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> would receive
amounts vastly exceeding the value of his stock options and
his employment contract. Similarly, the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> suit
claims <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> is paying <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> four times the value of his
equity. The <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> suits ask for unspecified damages and
all the suits seek to stop the transaction.
   A <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said the company believes
the transaction to be proper, and that it was scrutinized by
attorneys and financial advisers for all the parties
involved. "We are confident the directors will be absolved of
any wrongdoing," he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900810-0031
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900810-0031.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Successor to Continental Air's Lorenzo
   Predicts Profitability but Gives No Date
   ----
   By Bridget O'Brian and Carolyn Phillips
</HL>
<DATE>
08/10/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A2
</SO>
<CO>
   CTA K.SAI LABOR EUROP DAL
</CO>
<IN>
AIRLINES (AIR)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
BANKRUPTCIES (BCY)
</IN>
<GV>
TRANSPORTATION DEPARTMENT (TRN)
</GV>
<LP>
   Hollis L. Harris, who succeeded Frank Lorenzo as head of
Continental Airlines, said the carrier will achieve the
consistent profitability that has eluded it, but he wouldn't
predict when.
   "You look at a carrier that has $5.5 billion in revenue,"
said Mr. Harris about Continental, "its service is a good
product and it has among the lowest relative seat-mile costs.
That airline, if we operate efficiently, ought to be able to
make a profit."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The 58-year-old <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> resigned the presidency of
<ORGANIZATION>Delta Air Lines</ORGANIZATION> earlier this week to become president and
chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION>
and head of its airline unit.
   "My goal is to aggressively move forward on a more
streamlined and simplified basis," said <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON>, who
wouldn't be more specific. Asked when the carrier will see
consistent quarterly profit, he simply smiled. "In the
future," he said.
   <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>, an airline executive who spent much of the
past decade embroiled in high-profile, bitter disputes with
labor, agreed to sell most of his stake in <ORGANIZATION>Continental
Holdings</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION> and to step down as
chairman and chief executive officer of the Houston-based
airline holding company and as head of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>.
   "I personally have become a lightning rod for many steps
that were required to build this company to what it is
today," <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> said at a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> news conference.
   Word that <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> had vacated his <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>
posts boosted the company's stock price to <MONEY>$6.25</MONEY>, up <MONEY>$1.75</MONEY>,
on volume of 2.4 million shares in trading on the <ORGANIZATION>American
Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. The stock has suffered tremendously as the
holding company sustained massive losses, even during some of
the industry's most profitable quarters ever.
   <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jan Carlzon</PERSON>, president and chief executive
of <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>, said the transaction would take this form: <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> would
acquire, for <MONEY>$21 million</MONEY> -- <MONEY>$10.8 million</MONEY> to <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> --
all the stock outstanding in Jet Capital, a closely-held
investment vehicle that controls <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> through
a special class of stock. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> also will pay <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> <MONEY>$17
million</MONEY> for various other holdings and options, as well as
three years' salary, or another <MONEY>$2.7 million</MONEY>. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> also will
pay <MONEY>$31.4 million</MONEY> to buy 2,250,000 <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>
shares.
   All told, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> will increase its equity stake in
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> to <PERCENT>16.8%</PERCENT> from the current <PERCENT>9.9%</PERCENT>. Its
voting control will be <PERCENT>18.4%</PERCENT>. Federal law bars foreign
ownership of a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> airline of more than <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT>.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> would increase its representation on the 15-member
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> board to three from one. <PERSON>Mr. Carlzon</PERSON>
would remain on the <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> board, and said he is
considering a post as its chairman, but with no operational
duties.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Transportation Department</ORGANIZATION>, which must approve the
transaction, has already requested additional financial
information. Securities analysts, however, expressed optimism
that the transaction will be cleared. They suggested that
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s case is helped by <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s unpopularity in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, where he has been denounced by a number of
congressmen for his acriminous relations with labor unions.
   <PERSON>Richard Hillman</PERSON>, vice president, flight operations, at
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, confirmed for the carrier's pilots early
yesterday a story in The Wall Street Journal that said <PERSON>Mr.
Lorenzo</PERSON> was leaving. He added that <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> "decided the
future of the company would be better served if he got his
name out of it."
   In the recorded message for the carrier's pilots, <PERSON>Mr.
Hillman</PERSON> suggested <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s absence might mean a "better
shot" at financing for <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s multi-billion dollar
plane orders. "We've been having a little trouble getting
some financing for our airplanes," he added.
   A <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> spokesman wouldn't comment specifically on
what <PERSON>Mr. Hillman</PERSON> told the pilots.
   <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON>'s defection from <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> surprised many. That
carrier prides itself on a family-like atmosphere that keeps
employees from jumping ship as they often do at other
airlines. All but one of <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>'s senior executives have spent
more than 20 years at the company. Under <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> had seven presidents in as many years.
   <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> spent 36 years at <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, rising from gate agent
to president, with stops along the way in engineering,
facilities and flight operations.
   Neither, however, has he been so publicly vilified by
organized labor as was <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>. Labor difficulties pushed
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, then a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>'
predecessor, <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, into a crippling strike that
put the carrier into Chapter 11 bankruptcy proceedings. A
bankruptcy court judge subsequently took control of <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>
from <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> and his management team, appointing a
trustee.
   Union leaders who watched as <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> successfully
vaporized thousands of jobs and slashed wages and benefits to
the tune of <MONEY>hundreds of millions of dollars</MONEY> were celebratory
yesterday. The <ORGANIZATION>International Machinists Union</ORGANIZATION>, taking note of
a non-compete clause with <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> that keeps <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> out of
the airlines business for seven years, offered "our
condolences to whatever industry he stalks next."
   ---
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900809-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-09-90 1643EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Lorenzo 3rdLd-Writethru a0534 08-09 0635</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lorenzo, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0534,0651</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lorenzo Selling Most of Continental Airlines Stake</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with quotes from Lorenzo and why
he decided to resign; picks up 3rd graf, `His departure ...' SUBS
grafs 9-10, `The Wall ...,' with 1 graf to CORRECT total
compensation to $29.8 million, sted $15 million, DELETE outdated
material; picks up 11th graf, `SAS, which ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON>, a central figure during a
tumultuous period in the airline industry and the bane of organized
labor, announced today he was getting out of the business.
   Lorenzo's <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said he was selling
most of his stake in the company, formerly known as <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, to <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION>. He also will quit as
chairman and chief executive but will walk away with nearly <MONEY>$30
million</MONEY> in severance payments and sale proceeds.
   Lorenzo told reporters at a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> news briefing that he
decided to resign partly because the barrage of negative publicity
about his management practices was hurting the company's overall
performance.
   ``It's been obvious to me that I've become a lightning rod for
many of the attacks the company's taken,'' <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> said. ``This
transaction allows me to step aside.''
   His departure marks the end of an era in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> airline
industry, which has undergone sweeping changes since deregulation
more than a decade ago.
   Using <MONEY>billions of dollars</MONEY> in borrowed money, cheap fares and
bankruptcy laws to restructure high-cost airlines <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> expanded his company to the nation's biggest
airline operator with about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the domestic market.
   But <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> has been bitterly criticized by airline unions,
which were driven from <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> and waged a bitter strike at
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>.
   Both airlines are under extreme financial pressure, and doubts
are widespread about <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>'s ability to survive.
   Lorenzo, 50, said he will be replaced as chief executive by
<PERSON>Hollis L. Harris</PERSON>, president of rival <ORGANIZATION>Delta Airlines</ORGANIZATION>. He called
<PERSON>Harris</PERSON> ``one of the industry's most experienced and highly regarded
executives.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> confirmed today that <PERSON>Harris</PERSON>, 58, left the company,
effective <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, to assume a position with <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>
said <PERSON>Ronald W. Allen</PERSON>, its chairman, would take on <PERSON>Harris</PERSON>' duties.
   Lorenzo will immediately get about <MONEY>$17.13 million</MONEY> in cash. He
also will get <MONEY>$2.7 million</MONEY> over three years and <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> from
<ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> for his stake in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. But the <MONEY>$29.8 million</MONEY> total is
still only a franction of what he was worth a few years ago when
his airlines were in better shape.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>, which first bought a stake in <LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION>'s business a few
years ago, said it was spending <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> on the transaction,
which already was approved by <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>' board of
directors.
   Lorenzo became one of the most despised figures among union
groups in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> because of what they called his brutal
treatment of organized labor.
   The most dramatic result: a strike at <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>March
1989</DATE> that prompted the carrier to seek Chapter 11 bankruptcy court
protection from creditors while it reorganized.
   Lorenzo lost control of <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>April</DATE> when federal bankruptcy
judge <PERSON>Judge Burton Lifland</PERSON> placed the airline in the hands of a
trustee, <PERSON>Martin Shugrue</PERSON>.
   Following that move, <LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION>'s company changed its name from
<ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, borrowing the name of
the airline that <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> acquired in <DATE>1982</DATE> and continues to run.
   The sale of <LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION>'s stake would boost <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s interest in
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> to <PERCENT>16.8 percent</PERCENT> in terms of equity and <PERCENT>18.4
percent</PERCENT> in terms of voting control. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> already holds <PERCENT>9.8 percent</PERCENT>
of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> and has a seat on the board.
   The transaction will require approval of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of
Transportation</ORGANIZATION>. It does not appear to violate laws limiting foreign
carriers to no more than a <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> stake in a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> airline.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890828-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-28-89 1052EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Continental-SAS 1stLd-Writethru   08-28 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Continental-SAS, 1st Ld-Writethru,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scandinavian Airline Reportedly Interested in Continental</HEAD>
<UNK>Eds: SUBS 4th graf with 3 grafs from Texas Air spokesman; Picks up
5th pvs ``Texas Air ...''</UNK>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scandinavian Airline Systems and an unidentified
partner reportedly are involved in advanced talks with <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> about buying all or part of the <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> company's <ORGANIZATION>Continental
Airlines</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary.
   The parties have been discussing the form of a possible sale and
terms for some time, and now they have reached the point of trying
to draft a letter of intent, the Wall Street Journal reported today.
   Late last week, <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> said the company
may consider selling a minority or controlling interest in
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. He said <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> officials had talked to interested
parties, but he gave no details.
   Art Kent, a spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>, said this morning he could
not confirm or deny the report.
   ``It's inappropriate to comment on anything like this,'' <PERSON>Kent</PERSON>
said.
   He said if discussions with an interested party ``reach a serious
point and a letter of intent is appropriate, there will be an
appropriate disclosure.''
owns strikebound <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION>. The Miami-based carrier, which is
in the midst of bankruptcy reorganization, wouldn't be involved in
any transaction involving <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>, which currently has a 9.9 percent stake in <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> as part
of a marketing agreement, wouldn't be able to buy <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
outright because of <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Transportation Department</ORGANIZATION> rules that
prevent foreign companies from having more than a <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> share
in a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> carrier.
   Talks between the parties are an outgrowth of meetings that began
between <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> officials in <DATE>June 1988</DATE>, when the two
began work on the joint marketing agreement. Those talks turned to
<ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> possibly buying a stake in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, and that aspect has been
pursued with new seriousness in the past 30 days, an unidentified
source told the Journal.
   The talks apparently heated up because of signs that
Houston-based <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> could remain profitable after massive
losses in <DATE>1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE> and the soaring value of airline stocks.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> is <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> owned by the governments of <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>. In <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, its hub is <LOCATION>Copenhagen</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920213-0088
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920213-0088.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Continental Airlines Holdings' Creditors
   Seek to Sue Former Chairman Lorenzo
   ----
   By Bridget O'Brian
</HL>
<DATE>
02/13/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   CTA K.SAI LABOR
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
AIRLINES (AIR)
BANKRUPTCIES (BCY)
CDS, INTEREST RATES, COMMERCIAL PAPER (FIN)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<NS>
BANKRUPTCY DECLARATIONS AND PROCEEDINGS (BCY)
LABOR, UNIONS, STRIKES, WAGES, RECRUITMENT (LAB)
ACQUISITIONS &amp; MERGERS, TAKEOVERS, BOARD BATTLES (TNM)
</NS>
<GV>
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT (FDL)
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS)
</GV>
<RE>
DENMARK (DA)
EUROPE (EU)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
SCANDINAVIA (SCA)
TEXAS (TX)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   The unsecured creditors of Continental Airlines Holdings
Inc. asked a bankruptcy court to let them sue Frank Lorenzo,
the former chairman who built the carrier with acquisitions
and debt, then sold his stake months before the company
sought bankruptcy-law protection.
   The creditors group charges that Mr. Lorenzo knew or
should have known that Continental Holdings was nearly
insolvent when he and another executive agreed to sell their
shares to Scandinavian Airlines System. The two executives
received $40 million in connection with that August 1990
transaction, the creditors said. Houstonbased Continental
stumbled into Chapter 11 protection the following December.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In their motion, made to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Bankruptcy <PERSON>Judge Helen S.
Balick</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, the creditors said they would seek <MONEY>$180
million</MONEY> in compensatory and punitive damages from <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>
and former <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> director <PERSON>Robert Snedeker</PERSON>, who also
sold his shares. Also named was <ORGANIZATION>Jet Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a company
through which Messrs. <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Snedeker</PERSON> held most of their
stake. The creditors' motion said they also want the
transaction voided. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> wasn't named in the motion.
   The creditors also contend that the two men shaped the <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>
transaction so that the foreign carrier bought their stake
when it decided to double its <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> stake. That
deprived <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> of an opportunity to raise capital by
selling equity to <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>, the creditors said.
   Messrs. <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Snedeker</PERSON>, in a statement, denied the
creditors' allegations. "The transactions that the creditors
are complaining about were perfectly appropriate and in the
best interests of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>," said <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>. He said he
and <PERSON>Mr. Snedeker</PERSON> have been advised by their attorneys that
the proposed creditor committee action is without merit.
   The creditors' move signals more of a "hardball" phase in
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s 14-month bankruptcy saga. It comes a week after
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> and its unsecured creditors' committee proposed a
consensual reorganization plan that would wipe out
shareholder equity and eliminate about <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> in debt.
   The creditors' group yesterday also asked <PERSON>Judge Balick</PERSON> for
permission to recover <MONEY>$124 million</MONEY> from the <ORGANIZATION>Pension Benefit
Guarantee Corp</ORGANIZATION>. The creditors maintain that <ORGANIZATION>Continental
Holdings</ORGANIZATION>' transfer of that sum to the pension plans of
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION> was an insider transaction that should be
voided under bankruptcy court rules. At the time, <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> was
a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, and its underfunded pension
plan was an obligation of the parent company. A <ORGANIZATION>Pension
Benefit Guarantee</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman said the federal agency is
prepared to take aggressive legal action against the
creditors' motion. "This money belongs to <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>'s retirees
and the <ORGANIZATION>PBGC</ORGANIZATION>," she said.
   The proposed action against Messrs. <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Snedeker</PERSON>
had been expected. The creditors' group had been seeking
since <DATE>December</DATE> to force the company itself to sue the two
men, and it twice altered its deadline to await <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s
response. The last deadline was <DATE>last Thursday</DATE>, when according
to yesterday's filing <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s board voted against
instituting such a suit but said it wouldn't oppose a
creditors' attempt to bring one. A <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> spokesman
declined to comment.
   In the motion, the creditors contended that Messrs.
<PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Snedeker</PERSON> breached their fiduciary duty when they
negotiated the <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> transaction and presented it to
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s board "as a fait accompli" in early <DATE>July 1990</DATE>.
Under the agreement, announced in <DATE>August</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> agreed to buy
2,250,000 newly issued shares of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> common
for about <MONEY>$31 million</MONEY>. It also agreed to buy <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> of the
stock of Jet Capital, which held a substantial block of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> common, for about <MONEY>$21 million</MONEY>.
   At the time, <PERSON>Messrs. Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Snedeker</PERSON> were "consummate
insiders," holding positions as officers and directors at
both <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> and Jet Capital, the filing said,
and they owned <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the latter company. As part of the <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>
transaction, <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> paid lump sums of <MONEY>$17.1
million</MONEY> to <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> and <MONEY>$3.5 million</MONEY> to <PERSON>Mr. Snedeker</PERSON>, the
filing said, as well as unpaid salary, insurance, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
passes and other benefits. Messrs. <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Snedeker</PERSON>
agreed to step down from their <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> positions as part
of their agreement.
   A hearing on the matter is scheduled for <DATE>March 11</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900809-0008
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900809-0008.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Bailing Out:
   Lorenzo Plans to Sell
   Continental Air Stake
   To Scandinavian Air
   ---
   He Would Step Out as Chief,
   And SAS Would Install
   Delta's Harris in the Post
   ---
   Sale Proceeds to Be $17 Million
   ----
   By Bridget O'Brian
</HL>
<DATE>
08/09/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<CO>
   JTC CTA WNEWS K.SAI
</CO>
<IN>
AIRLINES (AIR)
BANKRUPTCIES (BCY)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
CORPORATE PROFILE (PRO)
</IN>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Frank Lorenzo, who seized on deregulation to
build one of the nation's largest airline companies in a
series of controversial mergers, is leaving the industry that
he helped transform.
   Beaten by waves of bad publicity that have swept his
latest endeavors, Mr. Lorenzo is expected to announce as
early as today that he is selling most of his stake in
Continental Airlines Holdings Inc. (formerly Texas Air Corp.)
to Scandinavian Airlines System and stepping down as chairman
and chief executive officer, say people with knowledge of the
proposed move.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Under the agreement, <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> would walk away with at
least <MONEY>$17 million</MONEY>, a large sum but a fraction of what he was
worth when his airlines were flying high. Industry sources
say he didn't want to sell his stake, but believed his
continued association with the company, and criticism of his
operating style, were hurting <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s hopes for
recovery.
   <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> has been a pioneer in the post-deregulation
airline industry, helping lead the way in merging carriers,
cutting fares and using bankruptcy protection to reorganize
and break up high-cost airlines. But his innovations brought
on debilitating labor strife, crippling debt loads and
another feature of the modern-day airline industry: service
problems.
   Now <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s latest airline deal appears to be his
last, at least for years to come. The proposed purchase would
raise <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s interest in <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> to <PERCENT>16.8%</PERCENT> in
terms of equity and <PERCENT>18.4%</PERCENT> in terms of voting control. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>
already owns <PERCENT>9.8%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, and has a seat on
the company's board.
   SAS is said to be spending about <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> on the
transaction, and is planning to install <PERSON>Hollis Harris</PERSON>, 58,
the president of <ORGANIZATION>Delta Air Lines</ORGANIZATION>, as president and CEO of
both <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Jan
Carlzon</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman and a <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> director, would
become nonexecutive chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>. The
transaction requires approval from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of
Transportation</ORGANIZATION> but doesn't violate laws governing how big a
piece a foreign carrier may own of a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> airline. That limit
currently is <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT>.
   A <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> spokesman declined to comment on the
proposed transaction. <PERSON>Lars Bergvall</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s chief operating
officer, said he had no comment.
   Under the agreement, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> will buy out <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s
five-year employment contract, which calls for a base salary
of <MONEY>$365,000</MONEY> a year plus bonuses and deferred compensation of
at least <MONEY>$570,000</MONEY>. SAS is also buying all the shares of <ORGANIZATION>Jet
Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a personal investment company owned by <PERSON>Mr.
Lorenzo</PERSON> and two other investors, who are selling their stakes
as well. Jet Capital's chief investment is in <ORGANIZATION>Continental
Holdings</ORGANIZATION> shares. Since there is no public market for Jet
Capital shares, their value lies in the voting power they
exert over <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>.
   Finally, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> plans to purchase, at a premium, <PERSON>Mr.
Lorenzo</PERSON>'s options to buy two million or more <ORGANIZATION>Continental
Holdings</ORGANIZATION> shares. <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> will retain some of those
options and will remain on the board of directors. Under a
non-compete clause in his employment contract, <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> is
obliged to stay out of the airline business for at least
seven years.
   The transaction has already received approval from the
board of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, sources familiar with the
transaction say.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> is paying <MONEY>$14</MONEY> a share for 2.25 million <ORGANIZATION>Continental
Holdings</ORGANIZATION> shares, almost all of which come from <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>
and his two Jet Capital partners. That price is sure to sting
other common holders who have watched <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>
shares slide to yesterday's close of <MONEY>$4.50</MONEY> a share on the
<ORGANIZATION>American Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, down from about <MONEY>$23</MONEY> a year ago. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>
apparently chose to pay the premium in order to get the
additional voting rights that Jet Capital holds. There are
about 40 million <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION> shares outstanding.
   Controversy is certainly nothing new to <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> where
airlines are concerned. Over the last three years, the
50-year-old executive has been routinely vilified by <ORGANIZATION>Eastern
Airlines</ORGANIZATION> unions as they mounted a tough campaign to fight his
attempts to lower labor costs at that former unit. The result
was a bruising strike begun in <DATE>March 1989</DATE> that virtually
grounded <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> and sent that carrier careening into Chapter
11 bankruptcy proceedings, from which it still hasn't
emerged.
   Last <DATE>April</DATE>, the bankruptcy court judge, <PERSON>Burton R. Lifland</PERSON>,
took control of <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> from <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>, placing the carrier
in the hands of a trustee, <ORGANIZATION>Martin Shugrue Jr</ORGANIZATION>.
   That entire episode so demoralized the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> empire
that it sought to distance itself from its past, changing its
name and severing all ties to <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>. The body blows from
the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> affair also led to <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s decision to
leave the airline business, according to people who know him.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> episode, which included critical headlines and
pickets outside <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s exclusive River Oaks home in
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, took a considerable toll on the intensely private
man and his family. He took to hiring bodyguards.
   That was in marked contrast to the <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> who
wrested control of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1982</DATE> in the nation's first
hostile takeover of an airline. <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>, a graduate of
<ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION>'s business school, had been looking for
ways to expand his <ORGANIZATION>Texas International Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, a small
regional carrier. At the time, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> was a staid
carrier and money-loser.
   Within four years, <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> had thrust the airline into
bankruptcy court, abrogated its union contracts and lowered
labor costs. He built back its operations until, in <DATE>1986</DATE>, it
emerged from Chapter 11 protection having turned a profit.
   With low costs, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> lured flyers by offering lower
fares, and a new generation of travelers took to the skies.
   But the growth of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> itself has been anything but
steady, and <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> discovered it was easier to build an
airline than to run it. <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s top management has been
in constant turmoil, with seven chief executives in as many
years.
   But that didn't stop the acquisition-minded <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>.
Riding high on deregulation, he and his <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp.</ORGANIZATION> went
on to acquire <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Frontier</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>, all of
which were financially troubled. <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> already owned <ORGANIZATION>New
York Air</ORGANIZATION>. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> folded all the airlines,
except for <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>, into <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, a merger that became
one of the airline industry's most difficult and costly.
   <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s expansion, funded by junk bonds, was driven
by an ever-growing mound of debt, and was shaky at best. With
his new holdings, <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>'s empire -- briefly the largest
airline in the free world -- began to feel the full weight of
its debt: <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> rolled up . . . the airline industry's
largest losses ever in <DATE>1988</DATE> and <DATE>1989</DATE> -- <MONEY>$718.6 million</MONEY> and
<MONEY>$885.6 million</MONEY>, respectively.
   <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> eventually broke the strike at <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>, but
lost the airline. The labor action, mounted by <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>'s
machinists and supported by flight attendants and pilots, not
only forced <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> into Chapter 11 protection but kept <PERSON>Mr.
Lorenzo</PERSON> in the spotlight: Angry strikers picketed the
nation's airports, handing out buttons and bumper stickers
emblazoned with the words, "Stop Lorenzo."
   But unlike his experience with <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>
would not ride <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> out of bankruptcy. After listening to
ever-smaller offers of repayment, <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>'s creditors ousted
<PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> from day-to-day control of <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> changed its name to <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines
Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>June</DATE>. But the parent still is on the hook
for <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>'s pension debt, which could total nearly half a
<MONEY>billion dollars</MONEY>. While <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> has made a dramatic
financial turnaround from last year and the year before, much
of its net income comes from one-time gains such as lawsuit
settlements and asset sales. Its debt service costs remain
high, and eat up much of its operating profits.
   For its part, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> is <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> owned by the governments of
<LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s initial purchase of a <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>
stake in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, as well as a marketing agreement with
the carrier back in <DATE>October 1988</DATE>, has yielded many benefits.
Passenger traffic between <DATE>May</DATE> and <DATE>December 1989</DATE> was up <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT>
out of <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION> and <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> out of <LOCATION>Oslo</LOCATION>, mostly because of
transfers at <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION> hub.
   The company in recent years has undertaken a broad
expansion program, of which <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> is just a part.
   It now has equity stakes in <ORGANIZATION>Inter-Continental Hotels Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
(<PERCENT>40%</PERCENT>), <ORGANIZATION>Finnair</ORGANIZATION> (estimated <PERCENT>6%</PERCENT>) and <ORGANIZATION>Swissair</ORGANIZATION> (<PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>, to be
finalized by the end of <DATE>1991</DATE>). It bought a <PERCENT>24.9%</PERCENT> stake in
<ORGANIZATION>Airlines of Britain PLC</ORGANIZATION> and <PERCENT>35%</PERCENT> in <LOCATION>LAN Chile</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> also is in
the market for as many as 126 new MD-90s or A-320/A-321s
airplanes.
   Like other European carriers in highwage home markets, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>
is having problems with costs. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> has a hiring freeze and
has sold some ancillary businesses. Now its ambitious
expansion plans are being scaled back. <PERSON>Lars Bergvall</PERSON>, the
chief operating officer, said planned additions to the
airline's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> routes will be
scrapped, as will some other proposed route additions. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>
has frozen its European fleet at its current size, and three
DC-9s are being sold earlier than planned.
   ---
   <PERSON>Carolyn Phillips</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Susan Carey</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>
contributed to this article.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900913-0115
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900913-0115.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   SAS Plan to Buy Holding
   In Continental Is Cleared
</HL>
<DATE>
09/13/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   K.SAI CTA
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
AIRLINES (AIR)
</IN>
<GV>
TRANSPORTATION DEPARTMENT (TRN)
</GV>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- The Transportation Department approved
Scandinavian Airlines System's proposal to purchase Frank
Lorenzo's stake in Continental Airlines Holdings.
   SAS and Continental, which is the parent company of
Continental Airlines, announced SAS's proposed acquisition of
Mr. Lorenzo's stockholdings on Aug. 9. The transaction would
boost SAS's equity stake to 16.8%.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The department said that, upon completion of the
transaction, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> would continue to be "fit" to
operate an airline. In addition, it said the transaction
complies with federal laws requiring that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> carriers
remain under the control of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> citizens.
   <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> would receive more than <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> for his
shares.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-8986</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CBNB3ACNFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920214
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 FEB 92 / International Company News: Continental Air creditors file
suit against Lorenzo
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
CREDITORS of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, the fifth largest <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> carrier and one in
bankruptcy since <DATE>late 1990</DATE>, have filed a suit against <PERSON>Mr Frank Lorenzo</PERSON>, the
airline's former chairman and chief executive. The suit, brought by the
official creditors' committee, claims Dollars 180m in damages.
<PERSON>Mr Lorenzo</PERSON>, known as a pugnacious union-buster and wily deal-maker, quit as
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s boss in <DATE>August 1990</DATE>, although he remained a director. At that
stage, he also sold the privately-owned Jet Capital company - in which he
and other Jet Capital directors had an 80 per cent stake - to <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian
Airlines System</ORGANIZATION>.
Jet Capital, in turn, held a big stake in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> ended up with
18.4 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s voting rights.
However, before the end of <DATE>1990</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> had sought protection under
Chapter 11 of the US Bankruptcy Code - a situation which still exists,
although the airline has now filed a reorganisation scheme with the courts.
Under this proposed plan, ordinary shareholders in the airline would get
nothing - rendering <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s equity stake worthless.
The creditors' lawsuit alleges that <PERSON>Mr Lorenzo</PERSON>, Jet Capital and <PERSON>Mr Robert
Snedeker</PERSON>, another <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> director, received Dollars 41.6m as a result
of the series of transactions with <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August 1990</DATE>. It suggests that the
payments were made when <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> was already insolvent, breaching <PERSON>Mr
Lorenzo</PERSON>'s and <PERSON>Mr Snedeker</PERSON>'s duties as directors of the company. It also
argues that <PERSON>Mr Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr Snedeker</PERSON> benefited from a preferential
transfer which preceded the <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> deal.
The creditors' committee stressed that <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> was not a defendant in the suit.
Lawyers said the suit alleged a mixture of fraudulent conveyance, breaches
of fiduciary duty and preferential transfer.
<PERSON>Mr Lorenzo</PERSON>'s Houston-based investment company said the businessman believed
the actions cited in the creditors' complaint were 'perfectly appropriate
and in the best interests of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'. It added that <PERSON>Mr Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr
Snedeker</PERSON> has been advised by lawyers that the suit was 'totally without
merit'.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900809-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-09-90 1834EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Lorenzo Bjt   08-09 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lorenzo, Bjt,0839</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tough Guy in the Airline Business Says He's Out of There, For Now</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICK GLADSTONE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Airline boss <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> he's
quitting the flying empire he built in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, hurt by a barrage
of bad publicity and labor bitterness about his tough-guy
management style.
   The 50-year-old entrepreneur, who came to symbolize a tumultuous
decade of airline deregulation, is selling most of his stake in
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION>.
The leading foreign carrier has held a small stake in Houston-based
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> for two years.
   Lorenzo also is resigning as chairman and chief executive, to be
replaced by <ORGANIZATION>Delta Air Lines Inc</ORGANIZATION>. President <PERSON>Hollis L. Harris</PERSON>.
<PERSON>Harris</PERSON>, a highly respected manager, was lured to <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> after
a discreet search that started four months ago.
   Lorenzo will receive nearly <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> in severance, retain a
small interest in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s stock options and keep a seat on
the company's board of directors.
   But <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON>'s influence in running the company virtually will
disappear and his compensation reflects a fraction of the value the
airline operation used to have in better times.
   Houston-based <ORGANIZATION>Continental Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, formerly known as <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, once commanded <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the domestic airline market
through its ownership of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> airlines.
   But its business has been severely crimped by heavy debts and a
debilitating strike at <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> that's now 17 months old. Last year
the parent company lost <MONEY>$885.6 million</MONEY>, an industry record.
   ``It's been perfectly obvious to me that I personally have
become a lightning rod for many of the attacks that the company has
taken in the process of making the changes that have been
required,'' <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> said.
   ``This transaction allows me to step aside and allows the
company to have a new management,'' he said. Asked what he would do
now, <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> said, ``Take a little time to catch my breath. I
haven't had much time to do that.''
   He spoke to reporters at a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> news briefing, flanked by
<PERSON>Hollis</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Jan Carlzon</PERSON>. All three called the
arrangement a strategic move that would strengthen <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> into
a global airline for the <DATE>1990s</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>, which is spending a total of <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> in the deal, will
roughly double its stake to <PERCENT>18.4 percent</PERCENT> of the company's voting
stock. <PERSON>Carlzon</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> had no interest in gaining control of the
airline. Federal law already limits foreign ownership is limited to
<PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT>.
   ``We think <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> has an interesting future,'' <PERSON>Carlzon</PERSON>
said. ``It's better to have <PERCENT>18.4 percent</PERCENT> than 9.9 percent.''
   Wall Street reacted positively to the announcement, reflecting
investor optimism that the change would help <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s business
improve.
   Its stock, which traded as high as <MONEY>$23.75</MONEY> a share over the past
year but recently traded in the <MONEY>$4-5</MONEY> range, rose <MONEY>$1.75</MONEY> on the
<ORGANIZATION>American Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in active trading to <MONEY>$6.75</MONEY>.
   Lorenzo's exit from the airline world marks the end of an era
that in many ways was shaped by him. From his initial plunge into
the flying business in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> as an analyst for <ORGANIZATION>Trans World
Airlines</ORGANIZATION> and later as an executive of a small <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> airline
company, <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> helped pioneer innovations ranging from cut-rate
fares to the industry's first hostile takeover.
   But <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> aroused labor hatred because of what unions called
his brutal tactics to cut employee costs, one of the biggest
expenses in the industry besides fuel.
   Lorenzo called his strategies necessary to stay profitable in
deregulated skies that allowed airlines to set their own fares and
fly wherever they wished _ enormous changes in an industry unused
to competition.
   His war with labor began after he won <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> in a
takeover bid in <DATE>1981</DATE>. Two years later he plunged the airline into
bankruptcy court, scrapped union contracts and hired low-cost
replacements for striking workers.
   Lorenzo's reputation among unionists worsened after he bought
unprofitable <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Three years later angry
unions struck, accusing Lorenzo of gutting the airline.
   He responded by placing <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> in bankruptcy court, but its
enormous debts and enduring strike crippled the carrier and made
creditors increasingly edgy. Last <DATE>April</DATE> an irritated federal
bankruptcy judge gave control of <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> to a trustee, which many
strikers regarded as vindication.
   Unionists reacted to <LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION>'s announcement <DATE>Thursday</DATE> with a mix
of satisfaction and resentment. The <ORGANIZATION>International Association of
Machinists</ORGANIZATION>, which has led the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> strike from the start, said
he was largely responsible for the problems in his company.
   ``<PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> demolished <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, wreaked havoc on
thousands of workers' lives and severely devalued <ORGANIZATION>Continental
Airlines</ORGANIZATION>,'' said <PERSON>John Peterpaul</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>IAM</ORGANIZATION> general vice president.
``Those facts dampen our elation at seeing Lorenzo finally leaving
the industry. He is the epitome of what is wrong with corporate
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> today.
   ``Our condolences to whatever industry he stalks next.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-9093</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CBMA5AFRFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920213
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 FEB 92 / International Company News: Continental Air creditors file
suit against Lorenzo
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
CREDITORS of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, the fifth largest <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> carrier and one in
bankruptcy since <DATE>late 1990</DATE>, have filed a suit against <PERSON>Mr Frank Lorenzo</PERSON>, the
airline's former chairman and chief executive. The suit, brought by the
official creditors' committee, claims Dollars 180m in damages.
<PERSON>Mr Lorenzo</PERSON>, known as a pugnacious union-buster and wily deal-maker, quit as
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s boss in <DATE>August 1990</DATE>, although he remained a director of the
airline.
At that stage, he also sold the privately owned Jet Capital company - in
which he and other Jet Capital directors had an 80 per cent stake - to
<ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION>. Jet Capital, in turn, held a big stake in
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> ended up with 18.4 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s voting
rights.
However, before the end of <DATE>1990</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> had sought protection under
Chapter 11 of the US Bankruptcy Code - a situation which still exists,
although the airline has now filed a reorganisation scheme with the courts.
Under this proposed plan, ordinary shareholders in the airline would get
nothing - rendering <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s equity stake worthless.
The creditors' lawsuit alleges that <PERSON>Mr Lorenzo</PERSON>, Jet Capital and <PERSON>Mr Robert
Snedeker</PERSON>, another <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> director, received Dollars 41.6m as a result
of the series of transactions with <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August 1990</DATE>. It suggests that the
payments were made when <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> was already insolvent, breaching <PERSON>Mr
Lorenzo</PERSON>'s and <PERSON>Mr Snedeker</PERSON>'s duties as directors of the company. It also
argues that <PERSON>Mr Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr Snedeker</PERSON> benefited from a preferential
transfer which preceded the <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> deal.
The creditors' committee stressed that <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> was not a defendant in the suit.
Lawyers said the suit alleged a mixture of fraudulent conveyance, breaches
of fiduciary duty and preferential transfer.
<PERSON>Mr Lorenzo</PERSON> <TIME>last night</TIME> was unavailable for comment.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 26
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890828-0257 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-28-89 2149EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-TexasAir-Continental 1stLd-Writethru f01derstorm.Highsaround80.Lightwinds.
08-28 0667</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Texas Air-Continental, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0164,0687</SECOND>
<HEAD>SAS Reportedly Interested in Buying Continental</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 10 grafs to UPDATE with analyst, union comment on possible
Continental sale.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which is considering a sale of
part or all of its <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary, reportedly is
involved in advanced talks about such a transaction with
<ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION> and an unidentified partner.
   Talks about the form of a possible sale and the terms have been
going on for some time, and the parties have reached the point of
trying to draft a letter of intent, the Wall Street Journal reported
in <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s editions.
   A <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> spokesman, however, would not confirm that any such
talks have taken place.
   ``I can't confirm or deny anything,'' spokesman Art Kent told <ORGANIZATION>The
Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's inappropriate to comment on anything like
this.''
   Kent said if discussions with an interested party ``reach a
serious point and a letter of intent is appropriate, there will be
an appropriate disclosure.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> announced last <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that the
Houston-based airline company _ the largest in the nation _ may
consider selling a minority or controlling interest in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Strikebound Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION> is <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>'s other airline
subsidiary, but it would not be involved in any <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
transaction.
   Lorenzo said <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> officials have spoken to parties
interested in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, but he has not provided any details about
the talks.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> already has a <PERCENT>9.9 percent</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> as part of a
marketing agreement.
   If <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> is interested in buying part of Houston-based <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>,
the transaction would have to be structured in such a way that <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>
would get a minority holding. <ORGANIZATION>Department of Transportation</ORGANIZATION> rules
prevent foreign companies from having more than a <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> stake
in a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> carrier.
   Talks that began in <DATE>June 1988</DATE> concerning the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> marketing
agreement apparently turned to <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> possibly buying part of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. That aspect has been pursued with new seriousness in
the past 30 days, an unidentified source told the Journal.
   Signs that <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> could remain profitable after massive
losses in <DATE>1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE>, as well as the soaring value of airline
stocks, apparently heated up the discussions.
   Lorenzo's surprise announcement came a week after a <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>
investment firm disclosed that it holds <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Loomis, Sayles &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> portfolio management company, has
said its <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> stake was held for investment because it
believed <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> would show a profit in <DATE>1990</DATE>.
   The possible sale of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> could doom <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>, according to
securities analysts and labor leaders.
   Miami-based <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> is in the sixth month of a strike by
<ORGANIZATION>Machinists</ORGANIZATION> union members, pilots and flight attendants, and is
flying about a third of its pre-strike 1,100 daily flights.
   ``We've always believed that the plan was to shrink <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> and
roll it into <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>,'' said <PERSON>Louis A. Marchesano</PERSON>, an analyst
with the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> brokerage <ORGANIZATION>Janney Montgomery Scott Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The sale of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> would mean <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> would have to make
it on its own,'' <PERSON>Marchesano</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE>, ``and the risk of a
shrunken <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> not making it is substantial.''
   Eastern, which filed for Chapter 11 protection from bankruptcy
shortly after the walkout began in <DATE>March</DATE>, is losing more than <MONEY>$1.5
million</MONEY> a day.
   The sale of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, according to <PERSON>Marchesano</PERSON>, would mean
Lorenzo ``might be leaving the airline business.''
Cole</PERSON>, agreed, saying that the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> chairman ``may be cutting
and running.''
   A <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> without <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Cole</PERSON> said, would have only two
options _ continued liquidation of <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> assets or the outright
sale of the carrier.
   Striking <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> employees have repeatedly charged that <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON>
has been transferring <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> assets to <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, weakening
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> and strengthening <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Now that the bankruptcy has thrown a net around <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>'s
assets and stopped the upstreaming of cash,'' <PERSON>Cole</PERSON> said, ``Lorenzo
has to admit that <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> can't go it alone, that it can't
survive without sponging off Eastern.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-1546</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEEAAABQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910504
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 MAY 91 / International Company News: Continental Air seeks extra
Dollars 3bn
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PAUL BETTS
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   HOUSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
CONTINENTAL AIRLINES, one of the five largest <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> carriers, is seeking more
than Dollars 3bn in fresh equity and cash to restructure its debt-burdened
balance-sheet and help it out of bankruptcy in the next eight to 12 months.
<PERSON>Mr Hollis Harris</PERSON>, the new chairman of the airline which filed for protection
said he was seeking the conversion of about Dollars 2bn of unsecured debt
into equity.
The airline currently has total unsecured debts of Dollars 2.5bn and secured
debts of Dollars 4.5bn.
<PERSON>Mr Harris</PERSON>, the former <ORGANIZATION>Delta Airlines</ORGANIZATION> president brought in to rescue
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, said it was planning to raise an additional Dollars 600m in new
equity from three or four investor groups.
The company has had discussions with business representatives at its three
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION> hubs of <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>.
At the same time, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> is in advanced talks to sell a controlling
interest in its <LOCATION>Air Micronesia</LOCATION> operation in the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> for about Dollars
300m. But <PERSON>Mr Harris</PERSON> emphasised <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> would continue to be closely
involved in the operation in which it intended to retain a 49 per cent
interest.
The airline is also expecting to raise about Dollars 80m this year from the
sale of its Chelsea air catering company. It has already sold its <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> route to <ORGANIZATION>American Airlines for Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 150m.
All these transactions coupled with the restructuring of the company
aircraft operating and capital leases are designed to reconstruct the
company's balance sheet and provide additional capital to expand the
airline.
<PERSON>Mr Harris</PERSON> stressed that <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> had to find a way not to shrink its
operations. The airline has 350 aircraft in its fleet and has 190 new <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Airbus</ORGANIZATION> jets on order.
'We must grow the airline as we come out of Chapter 11 (protection). We
cannot cut back. We have to grow and maintain market share if we are to
compete with the other big carriers,' he said.
But he acknowledged that the financial restructuring if successful was
likely to dilute significantly current shareholders' equity. This would
include <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION> (SAS) which currently owns 16.8 per
cent of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> shares and 18.3 per cent of voting rights.
'Their holding will automatically be reduced significantly under the
restructuring,' <PERSON>Mr Harris</PERSON> said. But he added that he expected <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> to invest
additional funds in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. 'We have a good relationship and I believe
they want to be a partner with us,' <PERSON>Mr Harris</PERSON> said.
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> reported this week a sizeable <DATE>first-quarter</DATE> loss of Dollars
194.8m compared with a Dollars 21.3m profit in the same quarter last year.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 12 Photograph Hollis Harris, wants to convert debt to equity
(Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901204-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-04-90 0042EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Continental-Chronolog     12-04 0523</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Continental-Chronology,0599</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Continental Airlines, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key events in the evolution of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines
Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, formerly known as <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which filed for
protection from creditors <DATE>Monday</DATE> under Chapter 11 of federal
bankruptcy laws.
   <DATE>1934</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Varney Speed</ORGANIZATION> lines is formed in <LOCATION>El Paso</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, with four
<ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Vega</ORGANIZATION> aircraft flying round trips to <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. Earnings in
the first two weeks total <MONEY>$261.69</MONEY> from nine paying customers.
   <DATE>1937</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Varney</ORGANIZATION> is renamed <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION>. Its eight
employees relocate to <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>1968</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> opens routes to the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION>.
   1972 - Airline entrepreneur <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON>, future boss of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, acquires <ORGANIZATION>Texas International Airlines</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>1976</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Texas International</ORGANIZATION> offers ``Peanut Fares,'' the
precursor to the discount fares that would spread throughout the
industry after deregulation in <DATE>1978</DATE>.
   <DATE>1980</DATE> - <LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION> creates <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, parent of <ORGANIZATION>Texas
International</ORGANIZATION>, headquartered in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>1981</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> gains control of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>1983</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> employees strike, accusing Lorenzo of unfair
tactics to drive down costs. The airline, losing <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> a day,
bankruptcy laws. Employment drops from more than 12,000 a year
earlier to 4,000.
   <DATE>1984</DATE> - Using nonstrikers and new hires, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> resurrects
much of its pre-strike operations. Lorenzo builds reputation as
anti-union manager.
   <DATE>1985</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> begins first European service. Lorenzo loses
a bid to buy <ORGANIZATION>Trans World Airlines</ORGANIZATION> as its employees, fearing his
union hostility, support takeover by investor <PERSON>Carl Icahn</PERSON>.
   <DATE>1986</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> re-emerges from bankruptcy with a plan to
fully repay all debts. Employment reaches 14,500 and aircraft fleet
totals 200, double the pre-bankruptcy level. Parent <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>
acquires <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION> as well as remnants of <ORGANIZATION>People Express</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Frontier</ORGANIZATION>, making it the largest airline operator in the country
with <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the market.
   <DATE>1987</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s employment reaches 24,500 and fleet totals
more than 300 jets serving 140 destinations. Lorenzo introduces
``Maxsaver'' discount fares and announces plans to cut labor costs
at <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>1988</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> undertakes joint venture with <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian
Airline System</ORGANIZATION>, the beginning of a growing relationship between the
two companies. <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> also shows the effects of fare-cutting and
debt-financed spending spree, losing <MONEY>$466.2 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE> vs.
earnings of <MONEY>$72.7 million</MONEY> a year earlier.
   <DATE>1989</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Lorenzo</ORGANIZATION> rejects <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> union demands in contract
negotiations, workers strike, <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> puts <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> under
bankruptcy-court protection and begins to sell many of its assets.
Parent company loses <MONEY>$885.6 million</MONEY> for the year, an industry
record. Lorenzo insists he'll remain in the airline business
despite speculation he might get out.
   <DATE>January-February 1990</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> drastically reduces proposal
for repaying <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> creditors and faces increased trouble in
bankruptcy court.
   <DATE>April 1990</DATE> - <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> loses control of <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> to court-appointed
trustee. <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> is renamed <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>August 1990</DATE> - <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> resigns as chairman and chief executive
and sells most of his <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> holdings to <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines
System</ORGANIZATION>. He remains a board member.
   <DATE>November 1990</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> denies speculation it will file for
bankruptcy but concedes the board considered the move. Airline puts
some prized routes up for sale to raise cash. Lorenzo predicts that
trouble in the airline industry could leave just three or four
carriers dominating within a few years.
   <DATE>Dec. 3, 1990</DATE> - <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> files for protection from creditors
under Chapter 11 of federal bankruptcy laws, blaming the move on
excessive debt and high fuel costs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890828-0052 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890828 </DD>
<AN> 890828-0052. </AN>
<HL> SAS, Partner
@  Seek Part or All
@  Of Continental
@  ---
@  Scandinavian Line's Talks
@  On Texas Air Unit Said
@  To Be at Advanced Stage
@  ----
@  By Bridget O'Brian and Randall Smith
<DD> 08/28/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> K.SAI TEX EUROP LATAM </CO>
<IN> TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
AIRLINES (AIR) </IN>
<TEXT>
   Scandinavian Airline Systems and an unidentified partner are the investors interested in buying all or part of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> from <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, and talks are at an advanced stage, according to those familiar with the situation. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> chairman <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> disclosed late last week that he would consider selling a stake in the <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> unit, but didn't give any details. 

   A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION> refused to comment, as did a spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Houston-based Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>. 

   It's still not known who <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s partner is, how much money may be involved or what percentage of ownership in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> is being discussed. 

   But the parties have been discussing the form of a possible sale and terms for some time, and now have reached the point of trying to draft a letter of intent, according to one source. 
Currently, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> holds a <PERCENT>9.9%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> as part of the marketing arrangement with <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> announced last fall. 

   The talks are an outgrowth of meetings that began between <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> officials in <DATE>June 1988</DATE>, when the two began work on the joint marketing agreement. 
Those talks turned to <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> and its partner possibly buying a stake in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, and that aspect has been pursued with new seriousness in the past 30 days, the source said. 

   It is understood that the talks heated up of late because of signs that <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> could remain profitable after massive losses in <DATE>1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE> and the soaring value of airline stocks. 
Most airline stocks have taken off this year in the wake of a <MONEY>$3.5 billion</MONEY> buy-out of <ORGANIZATION>NWA Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Northwest Airlines</ORGANIZATION>' parent, and a <MONEY>$6.19 billion</MONEY> offer for <ORGANIZATION>UAL Corp</ORGANIZATION>, parent of <ORGANIZATION>United Airlines</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>'s stock price has doubled since <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>, but Wall Street appeared to react cautiously to the disclosure that <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> might sell a piece or all of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>'s other airline unit, now in bankruptcy proceedings, wouldn't be involved in any <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> transaction. 
From time to time there has been speculation that <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> might eventually try to merge <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> with ailing <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>, which is trying to revive its flight operations after a bitter strike that led to its bankruptcy filing in <DATE>March</DATE>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> itself wouldn't be able to buy <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> outright because of <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Transportation Department</ORGANIZATION> rules that prevent foreign companies from having more than a <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> stake in a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> airline. 
So, any transaction that might come of current talks would have to be structured in a way that <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> has a minority holding. 

   That means if a deal is pursued, its structure might be similar to the sale last month of <ORGANIZATION>NWA</ORGANIZATION>, according to someone familiar with the SAS-Texas Air talks. 
The two foreign airlines came out with less than <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> of the voting interest in the new company because most of their stake is held in preferred stock. 

   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s purchase of its <PERCENT>9.9%</PERCENT> stake in parent <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> was a friendly transaction. 
SAS paid <MONEY>$56 million</MONEY> for the stock, and agreed to pay <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> an additional <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> over several months as the agreement goes into effect. 
<ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> chairman <PERSON>Jan Carlzon</PERSON> also sits on <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>'s board. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Carlzon</PERSON> apparently believes he made the right decision to link up with <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, according to one person who discussed the move with him recently. 
But, that source said, in the same conversation <PERSON>Mr. Carlzon</PERSON> conceded that he was concerned about the negative view many people have of the tough-minded <PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON>, his <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> empire, and <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>. 
Separating <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> from <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> might solve part of that problem for <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> is <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT>-owned by the governments of <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>. 
In <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, its hub is <LOCATION>Copenhagen</LOCATION>. 
Since purchasing the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> stake last <DATE>October</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> has operated in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> out of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s new terminal at <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION> international airport in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>. 
The two airlines coordinate schedules, frequent-flier programs and sales forces. 
<ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> also runs a training program for <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. 

   SAS is preparing for the competition expected in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> after market barriers come down there in <DATE>1992</DATE>. 
Anticipating a frenzy of activity similar to what occurred in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> after deregulation, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> is seeking alliances that may bring it passengers. 
Since <DATE>October</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> has bought <PERCENT>24.9%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Airlines of Britain PLC</ORGANIZATION>, owner of four <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> carriers and <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Intercontinental Hotels Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Seibu/Saison Group</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> also is backing an investor group trying to buy <PERCENT>51%</PERCENT> of Chilean flag carrier LAN <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> from the Chilean government. 
<ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> options could give it <PERCENT>35%</PERCENT> of that carrier by <DATE>1991</DATE>. 
<ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> has loose marketing agreements with <ORGANIZATION>Thai Airways International and All Nippon Airways</ORGANIZATION> and owns <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> of the European Amadeus computer reservations system. 

   ---


</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890830-0250 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-89 1422EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-TexasAir-Trump     08-30 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Texas Air-Trump,0587</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lorenzo Trying to Persuade Trump to Buy Continental</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Eastern, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Chairman <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> has met
with <PERSON>Donald J. Trump</PERSON> in an effort to persuade the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> developer
to buy <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> associate said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``<PERSON>Mr. Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON> have spoken,'' said <PERSON>Bruce Nobles</PERSON>,
president of <ORGANIZATION>Trump Shuttle</ORGANIZATION>, which the developer purchased from
<LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION> <DATE>last June</DATE> for <MONEY>$365 million</MONEY>.
   But <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> has concerns about a potential purchase of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>,
a subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Nobles</PERSON> said, noting that <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> is
concerned about <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY> debt, its small cash
reserves and the need to refurbish many of its planes.
   While <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> remains interested and believes his name would help
the Houston-based carrier win passengers, he has not been convinced
that the risks are acceptable, <PERSON>Nobles</PERSON> said in a telephone interview.
   ``His (<ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>'s) concerns are well put,'' said <PERSON>Nobles</PERSON>, a former
<ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am Corp.</ORGANIZATION> official.
   Trump was unavailable for comment <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, a spokesman said.
Art Kent, a <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> spokesman in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> had no
comment on the matter.
   In talks with <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>, said to have been held over the past month,
<PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> said his negative image has hurt <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>, according to
sources quoted in <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s editions of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION>.
   Lorenzo announced last <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that Houston-based <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>, the
nation's largest airline company, may consider selling a minority or
controlling interest in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Strikebound Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION>'s other airline
subsidiary, apparently would not be involved in any <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
transaction.
   Last week, <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> that one reason he
was considering selling a stake in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> was that the bitter
struggle with <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>'s unions had hurt traffic at <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> is also involved in talks about selling a major stake
in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION> and an unidentified
partner, The Wall Street Journal reported <DATE>Monday</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> declined
to comment on the report.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> already has a <PERCENT>9.9 percent</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> as part of a
joint marketing agreement.
   Sources were quoted by the Times as saying that <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> was
impressed with the way traffic on the former <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Air Shuttle</ORGANIZATION> in
the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> picked up since <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> bought it.
   Trump's share of the lucrative <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION> shuttle market, split
with <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am</ORGANIZATION>, has ``approximately doubled since we took over,''
<PERSON>Nobles</PERSON> said. Although he declined to give precise figures, he said
<ORGANIZATION>Trump Shuttle</ORGANIZATION>'s market share has jumped from around <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> when
it started operations in <DATE>early June</DATE> to about <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> currently.
   ``I think being separated from <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> is a positive; having the
<PERSON>Trump</PERSON> name is a positive; having better service is a positive,''
<PERSON>Nobles</PERSON> said.
   But rival <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am</ORGANIZATION> disputed <PERSON>Nobles</PERSON>' estimate of current market
share. <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Pamela Hanlon</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am Shuttle</ORGANIZATION>'s
share, at around <PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> when <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> started up, is now holding at
roughly <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT>.
   ``We're quite pleased with the clientele that we think we've been
able to keep since they started,'' she said.
   The Times quoted its sources as saying that <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> favored a deal
with <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> involving <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> board member <PERSON>Kaj Ikast</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that the carrier was not
near a decision on taking a stake in <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>. Ikast told the
Times there have been talks with <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> about buying such a stake.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901023-0285 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-23-90 2309EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Continental-Changes 1stLd-Writethru   10-23 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Continental-Changes, 1st Ld-Writethru,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Lawyers Prepared Chapter 11 Filing For Continental, Board
Split</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with report that company
considered Chapter 11, transition; PICKUP second graf pvs, The
board . . .</NOTE>
<HEAD>PRECEDE HOUSTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A team of lawyers spent the weekend preparing a
Chapter 11 bankruptcy filing for <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, but the
carrier's board is split on how to deal with its financial
troubles, according to a published report.
   In its <DATE>early Wednesday</DATE> edition, The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> quotes an
attorney, who spoke on condition of anonymity, as saying the papers
were ready to be filed in bankruptcy court <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>.
   The airline denied the report.
   ``The company has no intention of filing for bankruptcy
protection,'' said <PERSON>Art Kent</PERSON>, a spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> suffered losses during the normally busy <DATE>summer</DATE>
travel season and has been hurt by higher fuel prices since the
Iraqi invasion of <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION>, the newspaper said.
   <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON>, who recently stepped down as chairman of
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> but remains on the board, opposes a Chapter 11 filing
by the airline, the <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said. Also, <PERSON>Jan Carlzon</PERSON>, chairman of
<ORGANIZATION>Scandavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION>, which owns <PERCENT>16.8 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
stock, opposes filing for bankruptcy, the newspaper quoted the
lawyer as saying.
   A filing would reduce the value of <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>'s holdings.
   The newspaper said it was not clear which board members support
filing for bankruptcy protection.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> said it has moved to cut costs by
restructuring its senior management team, cutting five top
executives.
   The board of directors for the Houston-based airline approved
the restructuring plan on <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``With radically higher fuel costs, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> must become a
stronger competitor in the global marketplace,'' said <PERSON>Hollis
Harris</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman and chief executive officer. ``We
have reaffirmed our intention to become a preferred airline among
frequent travelers around the world.''
   <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> was given the additional role of president, replacing
<PERSON>Mickey Foret</PERSON>, who is leaving the company to pursue other interests,
officials said.
   Also leaving the carrier will be <PERSON>Neal Neehan</PERSON>, senior vice
president-customer services; <PERSON>Clark Omstad</PERSON>, senior vice
president-properties and government affairs; <PERSON>Jim Arpey</PERSON>, senior vice
president-aircraft programs; and <PERSON>Elliott Seiden</PERSON>, vice president and
associate general counsel for <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines Holdings, Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> named <PERSON>Thomas Kalil</PERSON> senior vice president-customer
service and announced <PERSON>Lewis Jordan</PERSON>, executive vice president and
system general manager, was given the additional responsibility for
managing the company's international division.
   ``These actions position <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> with a lean and efficient
management structure that reflects the realities of operating
during this fuel crisis,'' <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102490-0036 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 296901 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 24, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 3; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
264 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PEOPLE: 5 EXECUTIVES RESIGN AT CONTINENTAL AIR 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> announced the resignation of five top executives in what 
appeared to be a major housecleaning at the Houston-based carrier. 
</P>
<P>
In a statement, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> said the action was a "cost-efficiency measure" 
intended to make <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> more competitive worldwide. 
</P>
<P>
The action came two months after controversial former Chairman <PERSON>Frank Lorenzo</PERSON> 
quit and sold his <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> stake to <ORGANIZATION>Scandinavian Airlines System</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION>, which 
owns <PERCENT>18.4%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s stock, was instrumental in hiring <ORGANIZATION>Delta Air Lines</ORGANIZATION> 
President <PERSON>Hollis Harris</PERSON> as <LOCATION>Lorenzo</LOCATION>'s replacement. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> would be given the additional role as 
president, replacing <PERSON>Mickey Foret</PERSON>, who is leaving the company to pursue other 
interests, officials said. 
</P>
<P>
Others who plan to leave include <PERSON>Neal Neehan</PERSON>, senior vice president-customer 
services; <PERSON>Clark Omstad</PERSON>, senior vice president-properties and government 
affairs; <PERSON>Jim Arpey</PERSON>, senior vice president-aircraft programs, and <PERSON>Elliott 
Seiden</PERSON>, vice president and associate general counsel for <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines 
Holdings Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> named <PERSON>Thomas Kalil</PERSON> senior vice president-customer service and said 
<PERSON>Lewis Jordan</PERSON>, executive vice president and system general manager, was given 
the additional responsibility for managing the company's international 
division. 
</P>
<P>
"With radically higher fuel costs, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> must become a stronger 
competitor in the global marketplace," said <PERSON>Harris</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman and 
chief executive. "We have reaffirmed our intention to become a preferred 
airline among frequent travelers around the world." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920312-0057
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920312-0057.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Continental Air Creditors
   Are Cleared to Sue Lorenzo
</HL>
<DATE>
03/12/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A3
</SO>
<CO>
   CTA K.SAI
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
AIRLINES (AIR)
BANKRUPTCIES (BCY)
</IN>
<NS>
BANKRUPTCY (BCY)
</NS>
<RE>
DENMARK (DA)
DELAWARE (DE)
EUROPE (EU)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
SCANDINAVIA (SCA)
TEXAS (TX)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   WILMINGTON, Del. -- A bankruptcy judge ruled that the
unsecured creditors of Continental Airlines Holdings Inc. can
sue former Chairman Frank Lorenzo and another executive to
recover money they received for selling their shares four
months before the company's bankruptcy-law filing in late
1990.
   U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Helen S. Balick's action wasn't a
ruling on the merits of the case, merely the green light
necessary under bankruptcy court rules to proceed with it.
The action stems from Scandinavian Airlines System's purchase
of Continental shares owned by Mr. Lorenzo and Robert
Snedeker, another director.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The creditors claim the transaction deprived <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
of an opportunity to sell equity to <ORGANIZATION>SAS</ORGANIZATION> at a time when the
company needed additional equity. In addition, they claim
that Messrs. <PERSON>Lorenzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Snedeker</PERSON> knew, or should have known,
that <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> was technically insolvent when it paid them
about <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> to buy out their employment contracts.
   The creditors are seeking <MONEY>$180 million</MONEY> in compensatory and
punitive damages from the two men and <ORGANIZATION>Jet Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>,
