<DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870225-0166 </DOCNO>
<HL> International Corporate Report:
News Corp. Is Returning
To Australia's TV Sector</HL>
<DD> 02/25/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> NWS
TELECOMMUNICATIONS, BROADCASTING, TELEPHONE, TELEGRAPH (TEL)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's NEWS CORP.</ORGANIZATION>, which sold its television interests in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> just <DATE>two weeks ago</DATE> so it could take over the country's biggest media company, is returning to the television business there. 

   Transactions announced yesterday would give <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> a <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> holding in television stations in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> -- the country's two biggest cities -- and in the smaller cities of <LOCATION>Lismore</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Coffs Harbor</LOCATION>. 

   Earlier this month, <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> sold its television stations in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, plus some small newspapers, radio stations and a recording concern, to <ORGANIZATION>Westfield Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION> for the equivalent of <MONEY>$561.3 million</MONEY>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Westfield</ORGANIZATION>, in turn, plans to sell the media interests to a company controlled by its <ORGANIZATION>Northern Star Holdings Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Northern Star plans to put its current television operations in <LOCATION>Lismore</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Coffs Harbor</LOCATION> into this unit, keep a <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> stake, and sell <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> of the unit to <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> for an undisclosed sum. 

   <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said its <ORGANIZATION>Twentieth Century Fox Film Corp.</ORGANIZATION> unit will "enjoy a close association" with <ORGANIZATION>Northern Star</ORGANIZATION>'s television company. 

   In order to buy <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> earlier this month, <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> was forced to sell his television stations in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> because foreigners aren't allowed to own more than <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> of an Australian television station. 
<ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest media group, owned television and radio stations, as well as newspapers and magazines. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870727-0147 </DOCNO>
<HL> International Corporate Report:
John Fairfax of Australia
Sells TV Stations to Qintex</HL>
<DD> 07/27/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
TELECOMMUNICATIONS, BROADCASTING, TELEPHONE, TELEGRAPH (TEL) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s third national commercial-television network was formed when <ORGANIZATION>QINTEX LTD.</ORGANIZATION> acquired TV stations in the nation's three biggest cities from <ORGANIZATION>JOHN FAIRFAX LTD.</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>780 million Australian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$554 million</MONEY>). 

   <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION>, one of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest publishers, will retain an interest in the network by acquiring as much as <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Qintex</ORGANIZATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Qintex</ORGANIZATION>, a media, resorts and property concern, already owned some smaller TV stations. 

   The agreement, in which <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> is selling its stations in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>, follows an accord earlier this year in which <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> sold its TV stations to <ORGANIZATION>Northern Star Holdings Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> and acquired <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Northern Star</ORGANIZATION>. 
Also this year, the entrepreneur Alan Bond formed the country's first commercial network by acquiring several stations from <PERSON>Kerry Packer</PERSON>, another Australian businessman. 

   The transactions followed a liberalization of government curbs on media ownership. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-4572</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFHCQAFUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930608
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 JUN 93 / International Company News: IEL sells undertaker business
for ADollars 102m
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By BRUCE JACQUES and REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
INDUSTRIAL Equity (IEL), the Australian investment group, has sold <LOCATION>Pine
Grove</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest undertaker, for ADollars 102m (USDollars 69.3m).
The buyer is <ORGANIZATION>Service Corp</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> funeral company.
<ORGANIZATION>IEL</ORGANIZATION>, which is part of the <ORGANIZATION>Adsteam</ORGANIZATION> group, said the sale would yield a book
profit of about ADollars 25m, and the proceeds could be used for payments to
shareholders.
The purchase is the first outside <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Service Corp</ORGANIZATION>, estimated
to be the world's largest funeral company. It will add about ADollars 47m to
its revenue. Pine Grove controls between 13 and 16 per cent of the
Australian funeral market.
<PERSON>Mr R. Waltrip</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Service Corp</ORGANIZATION>, said the acquisition represented
the beginning of a truly global company. The deal is subject to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Foreign Investment Review Board</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>IEL</ORGANIZATION> is also in the throes of selling its <ORGANIZATION>Woolworths</ORGANIZATION> supermarket chain, which
is the subject of a planned ADollars 2.45bn public flotation.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac Banking</ORGANIZATION>, the big Australian bank, plans to sack 12 per cent of the
staff at its head office for <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> operations, <ORGANIZATION>Reuter</ORGANIZATION> reports from
<LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>. Westpac currently employs 700 people at the <LOCATION>Wellington</LOCATION> office.
The decision to make staff redundant follows a review of the bank's
operations by an independent consultant.
The review 'identified a number of activities and structures that are no
longer necessary for the current market environment and have been dispensed
with', the bank said.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Industrial Equity.
    Service Corp of America.
    Grove Memorial Park.
    Westpac Banking Corp.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    AUZ  Australia.
    NZZ  New Zealand.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6719 Holding Companies, NEC.
    P7261 Funeral Service and Crematories.
    P6081 Foreign Banking and Branches and Agencies.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Disposals.
    PEOP  Labour.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 24
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-5902</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CE1BHACOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920528
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  28 MAY 92 / International Capital Markets: Australia's banks reveal
diverse results - The ripples from Westpac's property write-offs are
spreading
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By BRUCE JACQUES
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Seldom has an Australian bank reporting season produced such a diversity of
results. In the space of a few days, six-month results have cast <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> as
the poor relation, ANZ as the battling improver and the <ORGANIZATION>National Australia
Bank</ORGANIZATION> as a comfortable top performer.
The banks' experiences with <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s crop of failed entrepreneurs have
been well-chronicled. The big banks, including the 70 per cent federal
government-controlled <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth Bank</ORGANIZATION>, were naturally the most injured by
corporate failures and falling asset values.
But the stock market did not begin to suspect until a few months ago that
one bank out of the big four had performed substantially worse than its
rivals. Its worst fears were confirmed last week when <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> reported a
thumping ADollars 2.65bn (USDollars 2bn) bad debt write-off.
That pushed <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> into the first loss in its 175-year history, a ADollars
2.3bn pre-tax deficit and forced the bank to turn to shareholders with
potentially <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s largest share issue, aimed at raising ADollars
1.2bn.
Worse still, it appears the bank needs the funds to avoid falling below the
<ORGANIZATION>Reserve Bank</ORGANIZATION>'s prescribed capital adequacy ratios later this year when about
ADollars 700m in future tax benefits can no longer be counted as assets for
prudential purposes.
The drama of <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s losses, which mainly reflected an overhaul of its
extensive property portfolio, is likely to place the bank at a competitive
disadvantage against its peers for some time to come.
It was a drama singularly lacking from the National and <ORGANIZATION>ANZ</ORGANIZATION> earnings
reports, which had a strong 'business as usual' flavour. The <ORGANIZATION>ANZ</ORGANIZATION> and the
<ORGANIZATION>National</ORGANIZATION> did however appear to react to the <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> shocks by making a point
of detailing their own more modest property exposures.
The ripples have spread quickly from <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s property write-offs, with
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest home builder <ORGANIZATION>Jennings Industries</ORGANIZATION> effectively placing
itself at the mercy of its bankers earlier this week following a total
write-off of its stake in a ADollars 650m <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> property development.
Ownership of the project has reverted 100 per cent to <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>, but the
<PERSON>Jennings</PERSON> write-offs, among other factors have caused its major shareholder,
<LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>'s biggest company <ORGANIZATION>Fletcher Challenge</ORGANIZATION>, to foreshadow a NZDollars
400m (USDollars 215m) property write-down in the current year.
And yesterday, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s second biggest life office, the <ORGANIZATION>National Mutual</ORGANIZATION>,
had the long-term rating of its finance company lowered from A1 to A3 by
<ORGANIZATION>Moody's Investor Services</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> credit rating agency.
'The oversupply of commercial real estate throughout <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> will likely
result in additional property write-downs, further affecting <ORGANIZATION>National
Mutual</ORGANIZATION>'s reserve position,' <ORGANIZATION>Moody</ORGANIZATION>'s analysts said.
While <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> remains <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest bank measured by total assets, the
accompanying table indicates its position is far inferior to its rivals on
almost all important counts.
Most notably, the bank's large ADollars 8.19bn problem loan portfolio - more
than the <ORGANIZATION>ANZ</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>National</ORGANIZATION> combined - poses the danger that its
write-offs will remain larger for the next few years.
The <ORGANIZATION>National</ORGANIZATION>'s superior position has resulted largely from its ability to
control its finance offshoot. The National was the only bank whose finance
arm was in the black for the half-year, with its Custom Credit operation
turning a ADollars 68m loss into a ADollars 6.4m profit.
Finance offshoots are where much of the big banks' problems have resided.
Witness <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s ADollars 850m capital injection into its <ORGANIZATION>Australian
Guarantee Corporation</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary which lost ADollars 719m. ANZ's <ORGANIZATION>Esanda</ORGANIZATION>
operation lost almost ADollars 34m.
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
                        HOW THE BANKS COMPARE
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
                              <ORGANIZATION>Westpac        NAB         ANZ</ORGANIZATION>
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
Total assets at end-March   ADollars bn  ADollars bn  ADollars bn
                              107.4         95.2        99.2bn
                           (ADollars bn    ADollars m  ADollars m
First-half net profit           1.67)      405.6       135.5
                            ADollars bn    ADollars m  ADollars m
Bad debt write-offs            2.65       412.6       382.6
                            ADollars bn    ADollars m  Dollars bn
Problem loans                  8.19         4.25        3.53
Problem loans as %
of risk weighted assets       10.6          5.4         4.5
Capital adequacy ratio (%)     8.4         11.7        10.8
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 31
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-1301</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CLRBYAE3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921218
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  18 DEC 92 / International Company News: Westpac facing new uncertainty
as MD is fired
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
WESTPAC Banking Corp-oration, the troubled Australian bank, was yesterday
facing further uncertainty after the board fired <PERSON>Mr Frank Conroy</PERSON>, managing
director, after only 14 months in the job.
<PERSON>Mr John Uhrig</PERSON>, who took over as chairman following an earlier board
reshuffle in <DATE>October</DATE>, said a new managing director would be appointed from
outside the bank within a month.
<PERSON>Mr Uhrig</PERSON> said that <PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON> had resigned following agreement among
directors that the bank's restructuring programme needed to be controlled by
'someone who comes fresh to the task'.
This contrasts starkly with the strong support for <PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON> expressed by <PERSON>Mr
Uhrig</PERSON> and the rest of the board when the bank's restructuring plan was
announced last month.
Yesterday's board meeting was the first attended by <PERSON>Mr Kerry Packer</PERSON>, the
publishing entrepreneur, who acquired a 10 per cent stake in <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>November</DATE> through <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Press Holdings</ORGANIZATION> (ConsPress), his private
company.
Analysts said it was clear that <PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON> had refused to bow to pressure
from <PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr Al Dunlap</PERSON>, ConsPress managing director, for bigger
cuts in staffing and assets.
Similar suggestions have been made by the <ORGANIZATION>AMP Society</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest
financial institution, which owns <MONEY>15 per cent</MONEY> of <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> and also has two
seats on the board.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>, once <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest bank, has faced growing problems over the
<DATE>last two years</DATE> as a result of bad debts which culminated in a loss of
ADollars 1.56bn (USDollars 1.07bn) for the year to the end of <DATE>September</DATE>.
The bank was humiliated by the failure of a ADollars 1.2bn rights issue in
<DATE>October</DATE>, which closed 72 per cent under-subscribed, leaving nearly 300m
unwanted shares in the hands of sub-underwriters.
Five directors resigned shortly after the rights issue debacle, including
Sir <PERSON>Eric Neal</PERSON>, chairman.
<PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON>'s frank approach to the bank's problems appeared to have won the
support of the markets, reflected in an improvement in the share price from
a low of ADollars 2.39 in <DATE>November</DATE> to ADollars 3.03 on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
However, the shares rose <MONEY>1 cent</MONEY> to ADollars 3.04 after the announcement of
<PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON>'s resignation, suggesting that investors share <PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON>'s view
that restructuring could be accelerated.
The programme announced by <PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON> included cutting costs and increasing
revenue by ADollars 300m this year; cutting the expenses-to-income ratio
from <MONEY>70 per cent</MONEY> to <MONEY>58 per cent</MONEY> over three years; and reducing corporate
risk assets by ADollars 10bn by <DATE>1995</DATE>.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> has confirmed that the cost-cutting programme could include a
reduction of up to 60 per cent in head office staff.
The bank is also reviewing its regional operations in the south <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-16571</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DGBCVAGJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930702
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 JUL 93 / International Company News: Kmart acquires stake in
Australian grocer
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By BRUCE JACQUES and NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY, NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
KMART, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> retailer, has put itself into the forefront of the battle to
rationalise the Australian grocery industry by paying ADollars 20.5m
(USDollars 13.7m) for a 10.8 per cent stake in <ORGANIZATION>Independent Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, the
South Australian wholesaler.
<ORGANIZATION>Kmart</ORGANIZATION>, which controls just over 20 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Coles Myer</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s
biggest retailer, revealed itself yesterday as the buyer of a parcel of 3.2m
Independent shares traded at ADollars 6.45 earlier this week.
The <ORGANIZATION>Kmart</ORGANIZATION> move follows the recent purchase of a 19.9 per cent stake in
Independent by <ORGANIZATION>Davids Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, the privately-controlled Australian grocery
wholesaler. <ORGANIZATION>Foodland Associated</ORGANIZATION>, another big Australian grocery group, also
controls 18.5 per cent of Independent.
The <ORGANIZATION>Kmart</ORGANIZATION> purchase was seen yesterday by analysts as a move friendly to
<ORGANIZATION>Coles Myer</ORGANIZATION>, which has recently moved to block acquisitions in the grocery
industry which is one of its major supply sources.
Earlier this year, <PERSON>Coles</PERSON> acquired a <MONEY>15 per cent</MONEY> stake in <ORGANIZATION>QIW</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION>
grocery group, helping to thwart a hostile take over attempt by <ORGANIZATION>Davids
Holdings</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Trade Practices Commission</ORGANIZATION> said yesterday it would hold an
inquiry into <ORGANIZATION>Kmart</ORGANIZATION>'s acquisition of Independent shares.
At its <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> headquarters, <ORGANIZATION>Kmart</ORGANIZATION> remained tight-lipped about the share
purchase. Although the company has been putting increased emphasis on
international opportunities recently, and purchased stores in the <LOCATION>Czech
Republic</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Slovakia</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>, it described the Independent stake was a
'non-strategic investment'.
Kmart declined to say whether it had discussed the share purchase with <ORGANIZATION>Coles
Myer</ORGANIZATION>.
In the context of <ORGANIZATION>Kmart</ORGANIZATION>, one of the largest retailers in sales terms in the
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, the funds involved in the purchase are extremely modest. <ORGANIZATION>Kmart</ORGANIZATION>'s assets
at end-January, for example, were put at almost Dollars 19bn.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Independent Holdings.
    Kmart Corp.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ   United States of America.
    AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P5411 Grocery Stores.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Shareholding.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 26
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861226-0049 </DOCNO>
<HL> 
 </HL>
<SO>  </SO>
<IN> FREST NWS
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
PUBLISHING (PUB) </IN>
<DATELINE> SYDNEY, Australia  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch</ORGANIZATION>, whose takeover bid for <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> faces a higher offer from <PERSON>Robert Holmes</PERSON> a Court, is likely to either sweeten his bid or negotiate with <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court to divide the assets of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest media group, analysts said. 

   Moreover, <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> apparently can block <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a <ORGANIZATION>Court</ORGANIZATION>'s bid in its current form. 
<PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a <ORGANIZATION>Court</ORGANIZATION>'s bid, which is being made through his <ORGANIZATION>J.N. Taylor Holdings Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, is contingent on receiving acceptances representing <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION>'s stock. 
But <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> already holds <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> of the media concern. 

   As previously reported, <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> offered the equivalent of <MONEY>$8.58</MONEY> a share, or a total of <MONEY>$1.32 billion</MONEY>, converting the Australian dollar at its current rate, for <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION>. 
That topped an offer made earlier this month by <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> that at the current exchange rate is valued at <MONEY>$7.92</MONEY> a share, or <MONEY>$1.19 billion</MONEY>. 

   Both men, who are two of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s best-known takeover specialists, have failed in earlier bids for the media group, <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> in <DATE>1979</DATE> and <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court in <DATE>1982</DATE>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> officials said they hadn't yet decided whether to recommend the Holmes a Court bid to shareholders. 
<ORGANIZATION>J.N. Taylor Holdings</ORGANIZATION> said its bid won't proceed unless the <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> board recommends it. 
It added that any material changes in the structure or assets of <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> would make its offer invalid. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> board recommended the <PERSON>Murdoch</PERSON> bid on the day it was announced, but only on the condition that a higher offer didn't materialize. 
Officials of <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said that they were studying the Holmes a Court offer and that it was too early to comment. 
In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it would respond in a week or two. 

   But in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>David Fayle</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s company secretary, noted that the <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> stake <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> holds in <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> would prevent <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court from proceeding under the <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> requirement that his bid includes, unless <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> chose to tender its stock to <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court. 
<PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> acquired the <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> stake on <DATE>Dec. 12</DATE> from <ORGANIZATION>Industrial Equity Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a New Zealand-controlled investment company. 

   If <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> does sweeten his bid, analysts said, he might raise it to as much as <MONEY>$9.24</MONEY> a share. 
On the <ORGANIZATION>Sydney Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> rose as high as <MONEY>$8.58</MONEY> -- matching <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court's offer -- before closing at <MONEY>$8.51</MONEY>, up <MONEY>26.4 cents</MONEY> on the day. 
The exchange was closed yesterday for <DATE>Christmas</DATE>. 

   In addition to a cash offer, the Holmes a Court bid includes two alternatives. 
Under one, <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> holders may exchange every four of their shares for seven <ORGANIZATION>J.N. Taylor Holdings</ORGANIZATION> <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> convertible notes. 
Under the other, they may exchange every four shares for seven <ORGANIZATION>J.N. Taylor Holdings</ORGANIZATION> convertible preference shares. 
The preference shares are convertible into ordinary shares five years after they are issued but don't carry voting rights. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s bid also contains alternatives to his cash offer. 
<ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> holders may choose to receive two <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> shares for every three <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> shares held. 
Alternatively, they can exchange every three <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> shares for two <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> five-year notes that are convertible into <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> stock. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s offer marks the first time that he is willing to dilute his hold on <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to make an acquisition. 
If all the <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> holders opted for the share portion of the offer, his stake in <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> would be diluted to <PERCENT>33%</PERCENT> from the current <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT>. 

   If <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s takeover succeeds, he will control about <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> of daily newspaper circulation in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and, if regulators don't intervene, will have a monopoly on daily papers in several major cities. 
Although <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has legislation regulating broadcast holdings, including recently proposed laws prohibiting cross-ownership of broadcast and print media in the same market, it doesn't have any laws specifically governing print media ownership. 

   Under broadcasting rules, television stations can't be controlled by a foreign national. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Federal Court</ORGANIZATION> already is looking at ownership of <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s two stations in light of the Australian-born <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s change to American citizenship last year to comply with <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> media-ownership regulations. 
<PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> also will have to sell the two <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> TV stations if his takeover bid is successful, because he will own newspapers in the same market. 

   By contrast, <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a <ORGANIZATION>Court</ORGANIZATION>'s Australian media interests are modest. 
They include a weekly newspaper and a television station in <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>, another television station in <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>, some radio stations, and some suburban and regional papers. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891002-0105 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891002 </DD>
<AN> 891002-0105. </AN>
<HL> International:
@  Two Big Australian Banks
@  Buy Shares in One Another
@  ----
<DD> 10/02/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> NAB A.ANZ WBK FREST </CO>
<IN> TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
BANKS (BNK) </IN>
<DATELINE> MELBOURNE, Australia  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910606-0022
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910606-0022.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   International Brief -- Westpac Banking Corp.:
   `Strategic Alliance' Formed
   With Big Australian Insurer
</HL>
<DATE>
06/06/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A14
</SO>
<CO>
   CMB WBK
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
MAJOR MONEY CENTER BANKS (BAN)
ALL BANKS, BANKING NEWS AND ISSUES (BNK)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<NS>
ACQUISITIONS &amp; MERGERS, TAKEOVERS, BOARD BATTLES (TNM)
</NS>
<RE>
AUSTRALIA (ASA)
FAR EAST (FE)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   SYDNEY -- Australian Mutual Provident Society, the biggest
insurance and investment concern in Australasia, announced a
"long-term strategic alliance" with Westpac Banking Corp.
   Among the arrangements, AMP will buy Westpac Life Ltd.,
Westpac's life insurance unit. In turn, Westpac will buy the
consumer-banking business of Chase AMP Bank Ltd., a
commercial bank owned by AMP and Chase Manhattan Bank of the
U.S. The Chase Manhattan Corp. unit eventually will acquire
full ownership of Chase AMP's wholesale banking operation.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Exact prices haven't been set, but preliminary indications
are that the two major elements of the agreement will involve
the payment by <ORGANIZATION>AMP</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> of <MONEY>200 million Australian
dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>US$152.2 million</MONEY>) for <ORGANIZATION>Westpac Life</ORGANIZATION> and the payment
by <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Chase AMP</ORGANIZATION> of about <MONEY>A$30 million</MONEY> for <ORGANIZATION>Chase AMP</ORGANIZATION>'s
consumer-banking business.
   Separately, the government declined to permit AMP to
increase its shareholding in <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> to <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT>. Australian
government regulations limit shareholdings in banks to <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>,
although the treasurer can give an exemption to go as high as
<PERCENT>15%</PERCENT>. AMP, a mutual concern owned by policyholders, now has a
stake of about <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> in <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>.
   The link between <ORGANIZATION>AMP</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> is part of a trend for
Australian banks and insurance companies to form alliances
amid a tough, recessionary Australian market.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861229-0023 </DOCNO>
<HL> Media Group Bids
In Australia Face
A Likely Delay
---
By Geraldine Brooks
<DD> 12/29/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> NWS FREST
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
PUBLISHING (PUB) </IN>
<DATELINE> SYDNEY, Australia  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The duel between <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Robert Holmes</PERSON> a Court for <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest media company, <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, is likely to be delayed by a combination of regulators' demands and the year-end holidays. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a <ORGANIZATION>Court</ORGANIZATION>'s Christmas Eve bid, equivalent to <MONEY>$8.65</MONEY> a share, or a total of <MONEY>$1.33 billion</MONEY>, converting the Australian dollar at its current rate, was announced just before the nation's stock market closed for the rest of the week. 
It has triggered a fresh inquiry by the <ORGANIZATION>Trade Practices Commission</ORGANIZATION>, which has been scrutinizing the <MONEY>$7.98-a-share</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$1.19 billion</MONEY>, offer by <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> earlier this month. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court is thought to be more interested in the television assets of <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> than its newspapers. 
Before he made the bid, he unsuccessfully approached <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> about buying <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION>'s TV stations. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a <ORGANIZATION>Court</ORGANIZATION>'s bid, through his <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> unit's <ORGANIZATION>J.N. Taylor Holdings Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, won't proceed unless the <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> board recommends it. 
The board earlier recommended the <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> bid, provided a higher offer didn't emerge. 

   Both bids also are conditional on <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> acceptance. 
However, <ORGANIZATION>Industrial Equity Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a New Zealand-controlled investment concern, agreed to sell its stake of about <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> to <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> before <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a <ORGANIZATION>Court</ORGANIZATION>'s bid. 
But <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court has said he might waive the <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> condition if that stake were the only obstacle to his winning the company. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said directors will meet "in due course" for the purposes of making a recommendation, "but such a meeting would be delayed by the difficulty of getting all the directors together during the holiday period." 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Australian Journalists Association</ORGANIZATION> has called for an independent inquiry into the bid for <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION>. 
The government, however, has signaled its reluctance to intervene in the battle. 

   Although <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a <ORGANIZATION>Court</ORGANIZATION>'s existing Australian media interests aren't as extensive as <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s, they pose potential problems under the government's recently proposed restrictions on the holding of broadcast and newspaper interests in the same market. 
It is likely <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court would have to restructure the holdings of <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> if his bid is successful. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880930-0211 </DOCNO>
<HL> Bond Increases Stake to 11.08% Of Allied-Lyons </HL>
<AUTHOR> John Marcom Jr. (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> T.ALY </CO>
<IN> TNM FOD BVG </IN>
<DATELINE> LONDON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Holdings Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> raised its stake in <ORGANIZATION>Allied-Lyons PLC</ORGANIZATION> to <PERCENT>11.08%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT>, and <ORGANIZATION>Allied-Lyons</ORGANIZATION> said Bond's intentions appear "questionable." 

   Bond, a <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>, Australia-based group that has become the world's fifth-largest brewer through acquisitions, declined to comment. 
Allied-Lyons, a big British food and drink maker, said it regarded further purchases as "unfriendly," and added that it "regrets that <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> has decided to take this action without explanation of its intentions." 

   Allied-Lyons made its announcement late yesterday. 
Its shares were quoted in late <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> trading at <MONEY>468 pence</MONEY> (<MONEY>$7.88</MONEY>), up four pence. 

   The verbal jousting could signal yet another battle for control of valuable food and drink brand names. 
Alan Bond, the entrepreneur who controls about <PERCENT>53%</PERCENT> of the Australian company, has said he wants <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to be at least the No. 2 brewer in the world within five years. 

   But a takeover of <ORGANIZATION>Allied-Lyons</ORGANIZATION> would be a big bite. 
The British company is valued at <MONEY>#3.41 billion</MONEY> (<MONEY>$5.74 billion</MONEY>) at its current stock price, and the company has aggressively promoted its image and operations to the public and shareholders since <ORGANIZATION>Elders IXL Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, Bond's big Australian brewing rival, made an unsuccessful bid for <ORGANIZATION>Allied-Lyons</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>. 

   Allied-Lyons also said yesterday that it had proposed "and brought close to conclusion" a joint venture with Bond -- which would be <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> owned by <ORGANIZATION>Allied-Lyons</ORGANIZATION> and <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> by the Australian company -- to buy certain Bond brands and develop their sales in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
It didn't say what <PERSON>Mr. Bond</PERSON>'s response had been, or what would happen now that he had raised his holding in <ORGANIZATION>Allied-Lyons</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-15773</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJBCAADYFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921002
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 OCT 92 / International Company News: Westpac running out of time to
get its act together - The difficulties still facing the troubled Australian
bank after the latest upheavals
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
WESTPAC, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest bank, is not known for its sense of irony. But
there must have been a few wry grins in the bank's <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> headquarters on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> when <ORGANIZATION>National Australia Bank</ORGANIZATION> (NAB) announced it had completed
precautionary checks on the books of <ORGANIZATION>Bank of New Zealand</ORGANIZATION>.
The announcement confirmed <ORGANIZATION>NAB</ORGANIZATION> will proceed with its proposed NZDollars
1.48bn (Dollars 796m) acquisition of BNZ, which will propel it past <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>
as <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest bank in terms of global assets. Westpac directors,
meanwhile, were wondering how many of them would have to fall on their
swords to satisfy the markets' lust for boardroom blood.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> has a special place in Australian banking history as the country's
oldest bank. But it has paid a heavier price than the other leading banks
for the ill-considered dash for growth in which they indulged in the mid to
late <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s problems came to a head in <DATE>May</DATE>, when it wrote off ADollars 2.65bn
(Dollars 1.91bn) against bad debts, of which ADollars 2.1bn reflected a
revaluation of its ADollars 6.3bn property portfolio. The write-offs left
the bank with pre-tax losses of ADollars 2.2bn for the six months to <DATE>March</DATE>,
compared with profits of ADollars 313m a year earlier.
Mr <PERSON>Frank Conroy</PERSON>, managing director, expected the substantial write-off to
ease investors' fears about <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s exposure to corporate failures and the
weak property market. At the same time, <PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON> sought to strengthen the
bank's balance sheet by raising ADollars 1.2bn through a 3-for-10 rights
issue at ADollars 3 per share.
However, the rights issue merely compounded <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s difficulties.
Executives watched in horror as the bank's share price slid from ADollars
3.87 on the day it was announced to ADollars 2.99 on the day it closed. Not
surprisingly, the issue fell ADollars 880m short of target after investors
took up rights to only 111m of 405m shares on offer, leaving <ORGANIZATION>CS First Boston</ORGANIZATION>
and its sub-underwriters to take up the shortfall.
On a wider front, <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> has been taking a public relations beating as
Australian newspapers and television stations have relentlessly pursued
allegations of fraud by bank officials in connection with a controversial
foreign exchange loans scheme which left many borrowers heavily indebted
after the Australian dollar collapsed in the late <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
Westpac strongly denies criminal activity by any of its staff in relation to
foreign loans. But the bank has also been identified by the <ORGANIZATION>New South Wales
insurance companies which illegally trafficked in confidential government
information on customers.
Against this background, <PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON> admitted earlier this week that the bank
was aware of concern among institutional investors about the composition of
the board. But until mid-morning yesterday, both <PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON> and Sir <PERSON>Eric
Neal</PERSON>, chairman, resolutely refused to say whether resignations could be
expected.
Sir <PERSON>Eric</PERSON>, deputy chairman since <DATE>1987</DATE> and chairman since <DATE>1990</DATE>, was the main
target for a dissident shareholders' group led by <PERSON>Mr Gavin Solomon</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>
solicitor, which has gained credibility as <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s problems have worsened.
The group also sought the departure of Sir <PERSON>Neil Currie</PERSON>, a director since
<DATE>1987</DATE> and deputy chairman since <DATE>1991</DATE>, and several other long-serving
directors. However, there was no pressure for the departure of <PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON>.
In the event, the board surprised the markets by announcing the resignation
of five directors, a third of the total, including both Sir <PERSON>Eric</PERSON> and Sir
<PERSON>Neil</PERSON>.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> shares rose <MONEY>1 cent</MONEY> on the announcement, to close at ADollars 2.86.
However, few observers expect a significant improvement in the short term
because of the large volume of shares overhanging the market and continuing
worries about the bank's exposure to the deteriorating commercial property
market.
<PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON> has forecast improved profits in the <DATE>second half</DATE>, and conceded
that the markets will need to see at least three successive good half-year
results from <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> before the crisis of confidence in the bank can be said
to be over. However, analysts say there is still a chance that <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> may
be forced into further large write-offs.
<PERSON>Mr Scott Hawker</PERSON>, an analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Salomon Brothers</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, says: 'There is a
view emerging that while <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> was conservative in <DATE>May</DATE> when it made those
big write-offs, market conditions have undoubtedly deteriorated since then.
'There is at least a chance (of further major write-offs) because they will
look very bad, having said they have taken all the pain, if ANZ or another
bank comes out with further write-offs. At the least, <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s solid level
of provisioning will have to continue. There is little room for them to cut
back.'
<PERSON>Mr John Uhrig</PERSON>, who replaces Sir <PERSON>Eric</PERSON> as chairman, had little to say about
future strategy yesterday, preferring to concentrate his fire on the media,
which many <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> officials blame for precipitating the crisis. <PERSON>Mr Uhrig</PERSON>
also had no answer to awkward questions about why other long-serving
directors were remaining on the board.
However, <PERSON>Mr Uhrig</PERSON> has built a solid reputation as chairman of <ORGANIZATION>CRA</ORGANIZATION>, the
largely British-owned mining group, and the consensus among analysts was
that he and <PERSON>Mr Conroy</PERSON> should be able to convince investors that enough blood
has been shed to demonstrate the board's contrition for past mistakes.
That will not be good enough for <PERSON>Mr Solomon</PERSON>, who made clear that he would
continue his campaign for a vote on the continued incumbency of all
directors at the next annual meeting, due in <DATE>January</DATE>. However, he is
unlikely to persuade the institutions who own most of <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s shares to
support a further upheaval.
The only other bright spot for <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> is that federal government
regulations prevent any other financial institution mounting a takeover
attempt to take advantage of its weakness. But that will change if, as
expected, the conservative opposition parties win the next federal election,
due by mid-1993.
If that happens, <ORGANIZATION>NAB</ORGANIZATION> may be sorely tempted to double its asset base by
bidding for its erstwhile big brother. Which gives <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> about a year to
get its house in order.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 31
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861208-0074 </DOCNO>
<HL> Murdoch's Bid
For Media Firm
May Hit Snags
---
A Wall Street Journal News Roundup</HL>
<DD> 12/08/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> NWS FREST
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
PUBLISHING (PUB)
TELECOMMUNICATIONS, BROADCASTING, TELEPHONE, TELEGRAPH (TEL)
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON)
STOCK MARKET, OFFERINGS (STK) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch</ORGANIZATION>'s takeover offer for <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest media group, encountered potential obstacles from another possible bidder and the Australian government. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> directors met with the Australian takeover specialist <PERSON>Robert Holmes</PERSON> a Court on <DATE>Friday</DATE> amid speculation that he would launch a counteroffer, even through the board of the Melbourne-based media group <DATE>last Wednesday</DATE> approved a bid, equivalent to <MONEY>$1.18 billion</MONEY>, by <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>News Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Meanwhile, the government's <ORGANIZATION>Trade Practices Commission</ORGANIZATION> said it is investigating the ramifications of a successful takeover by <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>, which would make <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> by far the largest media group in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Bob McComas</PERSON>, the commission chairman, said that if the bid succeeds, <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> may have to sell some of his newspaper interests in the states of <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> has said he will sell <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> television stations in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION> to satisfy government regulations if his bid succeeds. 

   But the threat of an offer by <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court seems the more formidable opposition to <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court, who failed in a <DATE>1982</DATE> takeover effort for <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION>, said the talks were preliminary and would continue. 
He wouldn't rule out a counteroffer but said he agreed with the board to keep the talks confidential. 
<PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court, who is known for his long-runnning pursuit of <ORGANIZATION>Broken Hill Proprietary Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s largest concern, recently sold a stake in <ORGANIZATION>USX Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> after fueling heavy trading in the company's shares. 

   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said, "We'd heard rumors of an impending offer and we'll have to see what our position will be if the offer materializes." 
He noted that while the <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION> board accepted <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s bid, the acceptance was contingent on no better offer for the company coming forward. 

   In another development, the chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Industrial Equity Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, an Australian company that holds an <PERCENT>11.6%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s offer of <MONEY>$7.85</MONEY> a share appeared inadequate. 
Industrial Equity has also been considered a possible contender for the company. 

   <PERSON>Ron Brierly</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Industrial Equity</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman, said: "A bid is always an option, but we are not going to rush into an offer of that magnitude." 

   Separately, in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Moody's Investors Service Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said it is considering downgrading its Ba-2 ratings on two <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> issues, citing the bid for <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times</ORGANIZATION>. 
One issue under review is <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY> of exchangeable redeemable preference shares of <ORGANIZATION>Newscorp Finance N.V.</ORGANIZATION> 
The other is the increasing-rate exchangeable guaranteed preferred stock of <ORGANIZATION>Fox Television Stations Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Moody's</ORGANIZATION> is examining the mix of debt and equity that would be used to make the acquisition, as well as the company's plan to sell assets for regulatory reasons. 

   <PERSON>Richard Sarazen</PERSON>, chief financial officer of <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said the company believes a downgrading isn't in order. 
He noted that the purchase would be made with stock and notes convertible into <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> stock. 
"This transaction will be funded in the final analysis with equity, and should in fact strengthen the company rather than weaken it," he said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870205-0149 </DOCNO>
<HL> Fairfax Makes Bid
For TV Stations
Owned by Herald
---
By Tony Patrick
<DD> 02/05/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> FREST NWS
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
TELECOMMUNICATIONS, BROADCASTING, TELEPHONE, TELEGRAPH (TEL) </IN>
<DATELINE> SYDNEY, Australia  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>John Fairfax Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, attempting to establish a second television network in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, offered the equivalent of <MONEY>$239.8 million</MONEY> for the television interests of <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Last month, <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> paid <MONEY>$666.1 million</MONEY> for the television operations of privately owned <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Press Holdings Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, making it the first company to set up a network covering most major Australian cities. 

   <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION>'s offer is the second it has made to <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>, which is <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest media company, with interests in newspapers, magazines, television and radio. 
Fairfax earlier offered <MONEY>$1.67 billion</MONEY> for all of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>, in competition with <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which is offering <MONEY>$1.53 billion</MONEY>. 
<ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> has made provisional agreements to sell <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s television stations if its bid succeeds. 

   The separate <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> offer for the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> television stations was viewed by analysts as an attempt by <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> to ensure that it comes out of the battle with at least some of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s assets. 

   The moves have been sparked in part by a proposed liberalization in government regulations that up to now have restricted a single company from owning more than two television stations. 
The government proposes instead to limit the ability of companies to own both newspaper and television operations in any major city. 
The proposals haven't been approved by parliament and might be changed before they become law. 

   <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION>, which already owns television stations in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> as well as newspapers and magazines in several states, said it is prepared to pay <MONEY>$179.8 million</MONEY> for <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> television station and <MONEY>$59.9 million</MONEY> for its <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION> station. 
As an alternative to the offer for the <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION> station, <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> said it would pay <MONEY>$76.6 million</MONEY> for that station plus <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> radio operations in the states of <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Australia</LOCATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman, <PERSON>John Dahlsen</PERSON>, said after the <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> offer was received that the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> board decided to call for tenders for its radio and television operations, and that an additional offer from a company he didn't identify already had been received for the <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> station. 

   Fairfax's group general manager, <PERSON>G.J. Gardiner</PERSON>, said the company would be prepared to reconsider its offers for the television operations if other companies make higher bids. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880803-0163 </DOCNO>
<HL> Australian Firm Buys 11.4% Stake In Bell Resources </HL>
<AUTHOR> (WSJ Special) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> FREST BHP </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<DATELINE> SYDNEY, Australia  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Adelaide Steamship Co.</ORGANIZATION>, an Australian investment and trading concern, joined the fight over the assets of financier <PERSON>Robert Holmes</PERSON> a <ORGANIZATION>Court</ORGANIZATION>'s former corporate empire. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Adelaide Steamship</ORGANIZATION> told the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> late yesterday it has acquired an <PERCENT>11.4%</PERCENT> holding in <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> through stock-market purchases. 
It didn't disclose the price it paid or the reasons for the investment, and company officials weren't available for comment. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION> is <PERCENT>43%</PERCENT>-owned by <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court's former flagship that is the target of a takeover bid by Australian entrepreneur Alan Bond. 
<PERSON>Mr. Bond</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Holdings bought <PERCENT>19.9%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>April</DATE> and last month announced it was bidding for the rest of the company, except for a <PERCENT>19.9%</PERCENT> stake held by the <ORGANIZATION>State Government Insurance Commission of Western Australia</ORGANIZATION>. 
It estimated the cost of the offer at <MONEY>$520 million Australian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$417 million</MONEY>). 

   Also last month, <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> disclosed plans to merge <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION> companies to form <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s second-biggest stock-exchange-listed company, which could control assets of more than <MONEY>A$11 billion</MONEY> (<MONEY>US$8.82 billion</MONEY>). 

   Early yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it has acquired slightly more than <PERCENT>45%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION>, mainly through stock-market purchases, and had won two seats on the <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION> board. 

   Analysts say <ORGANIZATION>Adelaide Steamship Managing</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>John Spalvins</PERSON>, one of the country's most active entrepreneurs, wants to be dealt into the split-up of <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a <ORGANIZATION>Court</ORGANIZATION>'s assets. 

   His move conceivably could block <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s proposed merger with the <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION> companies, analysts say. 
Speculating on possible outcomes of <PERSON>Mr. Spalvins</PERSON>'s move, they say <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> might opt to buy <ORGANIZATION>Adelaide Steamship</ORGANIZATION> out of <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION>. 
Or, <ORGANIZATION>Adelaide Steamship</ORGANIZATION> might try to negotiate to acquire some <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION> assets, such as its <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> stake in British bank <ORGANIZATION>Standard Chartered PLC</ORGANIZATION>, or its shares in <ORGANIZATION>Broken Hill Proprietary Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest company, they say. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s plans for <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION>, which must be approved by shareholders in the companies, also have run into resistance among institutional investors. 
They want a cash offer rather than stock in <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> that they would get through a share-exchange proposal. 

   <PERSON>Kerry Packer</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s richest man, and Sir <PERSON>Ronald Brierley</PERSON>, a millionaire <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> investor, already have made a joint run at <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION> and been bought out by <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> at a large profit. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-15754</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJBCAAEHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921002
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 OCT 92 / Westpac chairman and four directors quit after criticism
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE chairman and four directors of <ORGANIZATION>Westpac Banking Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s
biggest bank, resigned yesterday in the face of criticism from the markets
and financial institutions.
Sir <PERSON>Eric Neal</PERSON>, chairman, Sir <PERSON>Neil Currie</PERSON>, deputy chairman, and three other
long-serving directors had accepted responsibility for heavy losses and bad
debts which had halved the bank's share price.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s problems came to a head last week when a ADollars 1.2bn (Pounds
488m) rights issue closed 72 per cent undersubscribed, forcing the
underwriters to take up shares worth about ADollars 860m. This followed a
disastrous first half in which the bank incurred pre-tax losses of ADollars
2.2bn after writing off ADollars 2.65bn against bad debts, including a
ADollars 2.1bn write-down of its property portfolio.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> said Sir <PERSON>Eric</PERSON> would be replaced by <PERSON>Mr John Uhrig</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>CRA</ORGANIZATION>,
the mining group 49 per cent owned by <ORGANIZATION>RTZ</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>. Sir <PERSON>James Balderstone</PERSON>,
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>AMP Society</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest financial institution, was
appointed deputy chairman.
None of the departing directors was available for comment. <PERSON>Mr Uhrig</PERSON> said
they had resigned voluntarily 'on the basis of the need to demonstrate board
responsibility'. He would not comment on why a number of other long serving
directors had not resigned.
<PERSON>Mr Uhrig</PERSON> said there would be no immediate change in the bank's strategy of
cutting costs, improving efficiency and resuscitating its battered public
image.
Analysts said the resignations would help stimulate market support for
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s shares, which have collapsed from ADollars 3.87 in <DATE>August</DATE> to less
than ADollars 3, about half the level of two years ago.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> has suffered deteriorating losses for the last two years as falling
asset prices have exposed the poor quality of many loans and property
investments made during a period of rapid expansion in the late <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
The mass resignation follows strong private pressure for tough action from
institutional investors, and a campaign against the bank by dissident
shareholders and much of the media.
The <ORGANIZATION>Australian Financial Review</ORGANIZATION> yesterday called for the resignation of the
entire board.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> shares closed one cent higher at ADollars 2.86 on the <ORGANIZATION>Australian
Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>.
Background, Page 31; Observer, Page 23
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 25
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-7764</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CEPANABHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920516
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 MAY 92 / International Company News: Foster's wooed in ADollars 5.7bn
merger
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
SA BREWING, the Australian drinks and manufacturing group, yesterday
proposed an ADollars 5.7bn (USDollars 4.3bn) merger with <ORGANIZATION>Foster's Brewing</ORGANIZATION>,
the brewing, pastoral and finance group formerly controlled by <PERSON>Mr John
Elliott</PERSON>.
The merger would create <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s fifth biggest company, and largely
resolve the financial problems of <PERSON>Mr Elliott</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>International Brewing
Holdings</ORGANIZATION> (IBH), a private company which owns 38 per cent of Foster's.
<PERSON>Mr Ross Wilson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>SA Brewing</ORGANIZATION> chief executive, said he had 'initiated and
developed' the proposal, which is conditional on the appointment of <ORGANIZATION>SA
Brewing</ORGANIZATION> nominees as chairman and chief executive of the merged group.
However, the merger also forms the central element of a debt rescheduling
plan presented yesterday by <ORGANIZATION>IBH</ORGANIZATION> to its banks. <ORGANIZATION>IBH</ORGANIZATION> has debts of about
ADollars 2.5bn, acquired to finance the purchase of Foster's shares now
worth ADollars 1.6bn.
The board of Foster's said it would consider the offer, but is almost
certain to reject it. The board is understood to have turned down a similar
approach from <ORGANIZATION>SA Brewing</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>March</DATE>.
The offer will also face scrutiny by the <ORGANIZATION>Trade Practices Commission</ORGANIZATION>, which
indicated that it was concerned about the possibility of a further reduction
of competition in the highly concentrated beer market.
The plan provides for a new holding company to issue one share for each <ORGANIZATION>SA
Brewing</ORGANIZATION> share, and one for each 1.5 shares in Foster's. There would be no
cash alternative.
The offer values Foster's shares at a premium of <MONEY>three cents</MONEY> to <TIME>last night</TIME>'s
closing price of ADollars 1.90. <ORGANIZATION>SA Brewing</ORGANIZATION> shares would be worth ADollars
2.90, compared to the market price of ADollars 3.07.
However, <ORGANIZATION>SA Brewing</ORGANIZATION> believes the deal would unlock substantial extra value
for shareholders by removing the uncertainty about <ORGANIZATION>IBH</ORGANIZATION>'s financial position,
which has depressed Foster's share price for the <DATE>last two years</DATE>.
This would be achieved through the reduction of the <ORGANIZATION>IBH</ORGANIZATION> stake in the merged
company from an initial <MONEY>28 per cent</MONEY> to 7.5 per cent.
<ORGANIZATION>IBH</ORGANIZATION> would exchange its rights to about 14.5 per cent of the merged group for
perpetual convertible notes, exchangeable for shares after two years. The
merged group would then underwrite the sale by <ORGANIZATION>IBH</ORGANIZATION> of about 6 per of its
remaining holding.
If its bankers approve, the deal would provide <ORGANIZATION>IBH</ORGANIZATION> with about ADollars 345m
in cash for immediate payment of overdue interest, and allow it to secure
the bulk of its debt against the convertible notes and remaining shares. <ORGANIZATION>IBH</ORGANIZATION>
would also gain a reliable stream of dividend and interest payments.
<ORGANIZATION>SA Brewing</ORGANIZATION> said the 'significant financial strength' of the merged group
would provide 'substantial benefits' to shareholders of both companies. <PERSON>Mr
Wilson</PERSON> said the deal was expected to take at least five months to conclude.
The merger is dependent on the approval of the directors and shareholders of
both companies, and the creditors of <ORGANIZATION>IBH</ORGANIZATION>, led by <ORGANIZATION>Hongkong Bank Australia</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>BHP</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest company.
<ORGANIZATION>SA Brewing</ORGANIZATION> is a diversified Adelaide-based company, which dominates the
south Australian beer market, and has substantial interests in home
appliances and packaging.
Foster's, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest brewer, owns Courage in the UK and half of
<ORGANIZATION>Molson Breweries</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
The group has been in turmoil since losing a record ADollars 1.3bn in
<DATE>1989/90</DATE>, largely as a result of write-offs connected with non-brewing
activities acquired during <PERSON>Mr Elliott</PERSON>'s reign as chairman and chief
executive.
The group has since sought to refocus itself as a pure brewing operation,
but has been unable to dispose of non-core assets worth about ADollars
2.8bn. The board warned last week it may be forced to write-down the value
of non-core assets again this year, which could affect its ability to pay a
dividend.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 12
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871104-0017 </DOCNO>
<HL> Australia's Holmes a Court Might Face
Cash Squeeze as Result of Global Crash
---
By S. Karene Witcher
<DD> 11/04/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> BHP TX
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
CONSTRUCTION, MATERIALS (CON)
RETAILING (RET)
BANKS, THRIFT INSTITUTIONS (BNK)
SECURITIES INDUSTRY (SCR) </IN>
<DATELINE> SYDNEY, Australia  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The global stock-market crash could be pushing <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s richest man, international takeover artist <PERSON>Robert Holmes</PERSON> a Court, into a cash bind. 
Despite his troubles, though, the usually tight-lipped <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court is hinting he is more inclined to buy than sell. 

   The price collapse has slashed hundreds of millions of dollars off the market capitalization of <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court's major listed companies, <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 
An announcement early last week that <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> was withdrawing as lead manager of a one <MONEY>billion-Australian-dollar</MONEY> (<MONEY>$679 million</MONEY>) bond issue for <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION>, which was to have reduced the company's interest bill, has further shaken investor confidence. 

   Though prices of both <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION> companies recovered slightly this week in a stronger Australian stock market, the two are significantly below their <DATE>1987</DATE> peaks. 
Moreover, prices have fallen far more than the market average and than several other high-flying entrepreneurial stocks. 
Alan Bond's <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>John Elliott</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Elders IXL Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, Australian-born <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Larry Adler</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>FAI Insurances Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, for instance, haven't been hit nearly as hard. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court, who earlier this year became <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s first billionaire, has watched his personal wealth sag; some estimates put his paper losses at more than <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court controls about <PERCENT>45%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION>, which, in turn, owns <PERCENT>42.5%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION> closed yesterday at <MONEY>3.05 Australian dollars</MONEY>, down <PERCENT>73%</PERCENT> from its <DATE>1987</DATE> peak of <MONEY>11.30 dollars</MONEY>. 
Since <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE>, when the world stock crash began, the price of <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION> stock has plunged <PERCENT>69%</PERCENT>, nearly twice as fast as the <PERCENT>36%</PERCENT> decline in the All Ordinaries index. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION> shares have also tumbled, closing yesterday at <MONEY>1.67 dollars</MONEY> -- <PERCENT>79%</PERCENT> below the year's high of <MONEY>eight dollars</MONEY> and <PERCENT>67%</PERCENT> below on its pre-crash price. 

   Investor speculation has focused on <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION>, and its biggest assets -- a <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Broken Hill Proprietary Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> in <ORGANIZATION>Texaco Inc.</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>BHP</ORGANIZATION> is <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest company in terms of market capitalization; the big <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> oil concern is currently in bankruptcy proceedings.) 

   Because many of <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION>' assets are stakes in other listed companies, which provide dividends but no access to cash flow, investors are speculating that the Great Acquirer, as <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court is known, is heading for a cash squeeze in <DATE>1988</DATE>. 
"The group is asset-rich but isn't obtaining a high operating cash flow from its assets," said <PERSON>John Bartley</PERSON>, an analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Potter Partners</ORGANIZATION>, a Melbourne-based brokerage. 

   While <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION>' <DATE>1987</DATE> pretax earnings of about <MONEY>400 million dollars</MONEY> should be enough to cover this year's interest bill, which some analysts expect to exceed <MONEY>200 million dollars</MONEY> on debt of more than <MONEY>3.6 billion dollars</MONEY>, next year could tell a different story. 
If share prices remain depressed, profits from stock-trading operations -- a big contributor to earnings -- aren't likely to be as buoyant. 
That is putting pressure on <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court either to reduce his debt load through sales of assets or to acquire a cash cow. 

   Ian Story, an analyst at <ORGANIZATION>BZW Meares</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, estimated <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION>' <DATE>1988</DATE> interest bill at <MONEY>300 million dollars</MONEY> and the company's earnings, based on its current structure without any share-trading profits, at <MONEY>248 million dollars</MONEY>. 
He said the proposed <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch</ORGANIZATION> bond issue would have trimmed the <DATE>1988</DATE> interest bill by about <MONEY>80 million dollars</MONEY> before tax. 

   Despite all this, <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court has indicated he will use his ample access to credit to shop around for yet more acquisitions. 
In the just-released <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION> annual report, written after the <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> crash, he seeks to reassure shareholders that he is still on the prowl. 
Bell has "held substantial lines of credit in place over the <DATE>last 12 months</DATE> which will allow us to actively pursue our goals," he says. 

   Already, rumors are swirling in the stock market about what <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court may go after next. 
Speculation is that <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION>, whose holdings include media, gold and insurance interests, will seek the rest of <ORGANIZATION>Pioneer Concrete Services Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, an Australian building-products and resources group in which <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION> acquired a <PERCENT>17%</PERCENT> interest in <DATE>August</DATE>. 
A cash bid probably would have to be made at <MONEY>four dollars</MONEY> a share and would cost <ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION> about <MONEY>two billion dollars</MONEY>. 

   As for <ORGANIZATION>Bell Resources</ORGANIZATION>, some analysts think it unlikely <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court will put up the <MONEY>eight billion dollars</MONEY> needed to acquire the remaining shares. 

   Abroad, <ORGANIZATION>BZW Meares</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Mr. Story</PERSON> said <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court may shed some British holdings. 
<ORGANIZATION>Bell Group</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Standard Chartered PLC</ORGANIZATION> may be put on the block, providing <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court could recoup his investment, originally <MONEY>340 million dollars</MONEY>. 

   But he might bid for the British retailer <ORGANIZATION>Sears PLC</ORGANIZATION> -- paying an estimated <MONEY>three billion dollars</MONEY> to acquire the <PERCENT>92%</PERCENT> he doesn't already own -- and sell <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION>'s low-yielding property interests, some analysts said. 
A full bid for <ORGANIZATION>Morgan Grenfell Group PLC</ORGANIZATION>, the British investment bank, could also be in the wings. 
Mr. Story also said <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court might be looking for a buyer for his <ORGANIZATION>Texaco</ORGANIZATION> stake, though he doesn't think the Australian investor would take a loss. 
He paid an average <MONEY>$37</MONEY> a share; <ORGANIZATION>Texaco</ORGANIZATION> fell <MONEY>$3.25</MONEY> on the <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> yesterday to close at <MONEY>$31</MONEY>, one day after the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> affirmed <ORGANIZATION>Pennzoil Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$10.3 billion</MONEY> judgment against the company. 

   Those who have been on the other side of transactions with <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court, however, warn of red herrings. 
"The only thing predictable about <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> is when he's normally trying to indicate one thing, he's going to do another," said an investment banker. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-3763</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CLFAYACQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921205
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  05 DEC 92 / World Stock Markets: Australian bulls pay for misplaced
hopes - The economy let them down
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
It has not been a good year for bulls in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. Time and again, brokers
have forecast a sustained rally, only to retreat hurriedly as the <ORGANIZATION>All
Ordinaries</ORGANIZATION> index resumed its downward trend.
At yesterday's close of 1,435.2, the index was 13.1 per cent lower than at
the end of <DATE>last year</DATE>, and down more than 37 per cent since the all-time high
of 2,300 in <DATE>October 1987</DATE>.
The bulls have reason to feel hard done by. Most of the misplaced optimism
was based on slowly improving economic fundamentals following <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s
emergence from recession in the <DATE>last quarter of 1991</DATE>.
As the federal government keeps pointing out, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s economic cycle is
ahead of most of the rest of the world, and its annualised GDP growth rate
of 2.1 per cent is now one of the fastest in the <ORGANIZATION>OECD</ORGANIZATION>.
But the market has remained stubbornly unmoved, in spite of three cuts in
official interest rates and a substantial fiscal boost delivered in two
expansionary economic statements earlier this year.
With the benefit of hindsight, the lack of response suggests that the market
had fully discounted the prospects of a return to economic growth by the end
of last year.
Investors may have been disappointed by the slower-than-forecast pace of
recovery, and disturbed by the signs of impending currency and current
account difficulties which have accompanied it.
They may also have been put off by the sea of red ink which has spilled from
the books of most of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s big companies as the impact of the 18-month
recession works its way through the accounts.
Hardly a corner of the economy has emerged unscathed. Of the 24 sectoral
indices quoted by the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, only three are higher than
at the end of <DATE>last year</DATE>. And two of those - chemicals and property trusts -
have barely moved.
The only real success story has been the media index, which is up more than
50 per cent, mainly because of a spectacular improvement in the share price
of <ORGANIZATION>News Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr Rupert Murdoch</PERSON>'s newspapers, film and broadcasting
group.
The media index has also been helped by the performance of <PERSON>John Fairfax</PERSON>, the
newspaper group controlled by <PERSON>Mr Conrad Black</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Daily Telegraph</ORGANIZATION> group, and
Nine Network, the television group controlled by <PERSON>Mr Kerry Packer</PERSON>.
Significantly all three groups are recovering from earlier reverses.
However, the media index makes up only about 9 per cent of the <ORGANIZATION>All
Ordinaries</ORGANIZATION> index, and its performance has been overshadowed by the collapse
elsewhere in the market.
The gold index is down more than 11 per cent, diversified resources 26 per
cent, developers and contractors 26 per cent, building materials 23 per
cent, transport 23 per cent, banking and finance 25 per cent, and alcohol
and tobacco 37 per cent.
There are some hopeful signs for the future. The Australian dollar has
declined by more than 13 per cent this year on a trade weighted basis, which
makes local stocks cheaper for overseas buyers.
Corporate net profits increased by 26 per cent in the <DATE>three months to the
end of September</DATE>, to a level 37 per cent above the low point of the
recession in mid-1990.
However, earnings before interest, tax and depreciation rose by only 6.4 per
cent, suggesting that most of the improvement in net profits flowed from
lower interest rates and cost cutting, rather than higher sales or margins.
Apart from the media groups, few major companies made an unambiguous return
to the good financial health in the full-year reporting season which ended
last month.
Exceptions included <ORGANIZATION>Broken Hill Proprietary</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest company;
<ORGANIZATION>Amcor</ORGANIZATION>, the packaging and paper group; <ORGANIZATION>CSR</ORGANIZATION>, the sugar and building materials
producer; and <ORGANIZATION>Mayne Nickless</ORGANIZATION>, the transport, security and health group.
But many big companies continued to disappoint, including <ORGANIZATION>TNT</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Brambles</ORGANIZATION>,
the transport groups; the miners <ORGANIZATION>CRA</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>North Broken Hill Peko</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Goodman
Fielder Wattie</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Australasia</LOCATION>'s largest food producer; and <LOCATION>Pacific Dunlop</LOCATION>, the
diversified manufacturer.
Worst of all, the banking sector is still showing the strains of recession
and falling property prices. The conservatively-managed <ORGANIZATION>National Australia
Bank</ORGANIZATION> produced an improvement, but <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>ANZ</ORGANIZATION> all reported
disappointing or disastrous results.
The market was also badly hit in <DATE>October</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s ADollars 1.2bn
fully-underwritten rights issue, which closed 72 per cent undersubscribed,
leaving millions of unwanted shares overhanging the market.
In the absence of an unexpected acceleration of economic recovery, the
market is likely to mark time over the next few months in the hope of
improved results in the interim reporting season beginning in <DATE>February</DATE>.
The more optimistic bulls are still forecasting the long-delayed rally,
which some claim could take the index to 1,800 by the middle of next year.
But nervous investors should be aware that bears are tipping a floor of
1,250 before a sustained recovery begins.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-6687</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CEVA2ACLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920522
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 MAY 92 / International Company News: National Australia Bank net
profits ahead at midterm
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By BRUCE JACQUES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
NATIONAL <LOCATION>Australia Bank</LOCATION>, one of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s four major national trading
banks, has reversed two years of falling earnings to achieve a 12.3 per cent
increase in net profits to ADollars 405.6m (USDollars 307.2m) for the six
months ended <DATE>March, 1992</DATE>.
The Melbourne-based group, which is holding its interim dividend at <MONEY>22 cents</MONEY>
a share, says doubtful debt charges fell from ADollars 455.7m to ADollars
412.6m.
<PERSON>Mr Don Argus</PERSON> managing director, points to 'some tentative signs of economic
recovery'.
National's report was in marked contrast to <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s half-year results
from <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest trading bank, which declared a ADollars
1.67bn loss following huge property portfolio write-offs.
The major point of contrast was the performance of the two banks' finance
offshoots. National's Custom Credit turned a ADollars 68.7m loss into a
ADollars 6.4m profit, but <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Australian Guarantee Corporation</ORGANIZATION>
incurred a ADollars 719m loss, mainly as a result of property exposure.
National's UK and Irish banking operations acted as the main brake on
earnings with a contribution declining by almost 28 per cent to ADollars
120.1m. The operations include the <ORGANIZATION>Clydesdale</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Northern Yorkshire</LOCATION> and
National Irish groups.
National's Australian trading and savings banks incurred a modest 0.3 per
cent earnings fall to ADollars 279.8m following a 3.1 per cent rise in bad
loan charges to ADollars 212.1m.
The UK and Irish banks bore the brunt of the bad loans with write-offs
rising from ADollars 97.5m to ADollars 201.4m. The biggest contributor was
<ORGANIZATION>Yorkshire Bank</ORGANIZATION> where charges jumped from ADollars 62.9m to ADollars 156.2m.
The most tangible sign of pessimism in <ORGANIZATION>National</ORGANIZATION>'s result was an increase in
problem loan provisions from ADollars 3.86bn to ADollars 4.25bn on the
widest definition.
But <PERSON>Mr Argus</PERSON> did address the matter of property valuations in the wake of
the <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> shock. He said the continued decline in property values in
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> remained a major influence on the group's provisioning and
write-offs.
<PERSON>Mr Argus</PERSON> indicated that <ORGANIZATION>National</ORGANIZATION>'s Tier 1 capital ratio stood at 7.9 per
cent at <DATE>March</DATE>, against a reserve bank minimum requirement of 4 per cent.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-8352</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EETCSAGDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940520
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 MAY 94 / International Company News: Australian banks show
improvement
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>National Australia Bank</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>, two of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s largest commercial
banks, yesterday reported interim figures which emphasised the continuing
improvement in bad debt experience. They also demonstrated some pick-up in
the business lending market.
NAB, reckoned to be the strongest of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s big four banks, announced a
profit of ADollars 868.8m (USDollars 634.2m) after tax for the six months
until the end of <DATE>March</DATE>. This included a ADollars 63.8m abnormal item
relating to a disposal, but still represented a sharp increase on last
time's ADollars 507.3m, which also included a ADollars 32.9m abnormal
surplus.
NAB attributed the improvement to a higher level of business loan demand in
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, a decline in operating expenses, and a further
'significant' reduction in the charge for bad and doubtful debts.
The two biggest geographical divisions - Australian operations and
businesses in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> (which include the Clydesdale, <ORGANIZATION>Northern</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Yorkshire</LOCATION> and National Irish banks) - posted net profits of ADollars 509.9m,
against ADollars 325.9m last time, and ADollars 233.6m against ADollars
157.2m, respectively. The <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> group made ADollars 37.9m.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> reported a ADollars 320.9m profit after tax, against a loss of
ADollars 204.6m a year earlier. In its case, the drop in the bad and
doubtful debts charge was more marked, although the figure remains much
higher than at <ORGANIZATION>NAB</ORGANIZATION>. The charge in the half-year was ADollars 379m compared
with ADollars 799.7m.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s gross problem assets stood at ADollars 5.5bn at the end of <DATE>March</DATE>,
compared with ADollars 8.57bn a year earlier.
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> said restructuring at the bank had helped to push its expense/income
ratio down to 60 per cent in the six months. It said it was 'well-placed' to
achieve its target of 58 per cent in the <DATE>1995</DATE> financial year.
Westpac is increasing the interim dividend by <MONEY>33 per cent</MONEY> to <MONEY>8 cents</MONEY> a
share. NAB has declared a full-franked interim dividend of <MONEY>35 cents</MONEY> a share,
up from <MONEY>24 cents</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>National Australia Bank.
    Westpac Banking Corp.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6081 Foreign Banking and Branches and Agencies.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>FIN  Interim results.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 25
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-5223</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CK0B0AFCFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921127
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 NOV 92 / International Company News: ConsPress takes 8.27% stake in
Westpac Banking
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
CONSOLIDATED <ORGANIZATION>Press Holdings</ORGANIZATION> (ConsPress), <PERSON>Mr Kerry Packer</PERSON>'s privately-owned
publishing group, yesterday emerged as the buyer of an 8.27 per cent stake
in <ORGANIZATION>Westpac Banking Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, the troubled Australian bank.
The shareholding, worth ADollars 434m (USDollars 299.3m) at <TIME>last night</TIME>'s
closing price of ADollars 2.99, is close to the 10 per cent ceiling placed
on individual shareholdings by <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s deed of settlement and federal
banking law. ConsPress could move to 15 per cent ownership of <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>, but
only with the approval of both the board and <PERSON>Mr John Dawkins</PERSON>, the treasurer
(finance minister).
<PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON>, who is travelling abroad, was not available for comment. <PERSON>Mr Al
Dunlap</PERSON>, managing director of <ORGANIZATION>ConsPress</ORGANIZATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> was 'a very good
company, with great potential'. <PERSON>Mr John Uhrig</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> chairman, said the
bank was very pleased to have <PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON> as a shareholder. He said the
ConsPress holding would add stability to the share register.
<PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON> was also welcomed by the <ORGANIZATION>AMP Society</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest
financial institution, which owns 15 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr Ian Salmon</PERSON>,
managing director, said <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> was 'a strong company with an excellent
future, and it is pleasing that <PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON> shares that view'.
ConsPress said it had acquired the rights to 145.16m <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> shares since it
began buying in <DATE>mid-October</DATE>. The stake comprises 4.61 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION>'s
ordinary shares and 3.66 per cent in the form of options.
Buying by <ORGANIZATION>ConsPress</ORGANIZATION> pushed <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> shares briefly above ADollars 3
yesterday, for the first time in two months. The shares fell back in later
trading to close <MONEY>1 cent</MONEY> higher on the day.
ConsPress has been rumoured to be acquiring <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> shares since the failure
in <DATE>October</DATE> of the bank's ADollars 1.72bn rights issue. The issue closed 72
per cent undersubscribed, leaving many sub-underwriters holding unwanted
shares.
Analysts said <PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON>'s investment was likely to provide a significant
lift for the shares, which fell to a low of about ADollars 2.65 last week
after the group announced a record net loss of ADollars 1.5bn for the year
to <DATE>September</DATE>. The shares were trading at about ADollars 4.50 at the start of
the year.
ConsPress gave no indication of its motives in buying <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> shares.
Analysts said <PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON> would probably seek a seat on the board, but would
be prevented from seeking control by the law and the bank's deed of
settlement.
<PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON> may be counting on a takeover bid for <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> by one of the other
three Australian banks, <ORGANIZATION>National Australia Bank</ORGANIZATION> (NAB), <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New
Zealand</LOCATION> banking Group (ANZ) and <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth Bank</ORGANIZATION>.
The banks are excluded from the legal restriction on bank shareholdings, but
are prevented from bidding for each other by a separate government policy
which bans mergers between the six largest financial institutions.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881022-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-22-88 0559EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Australia-DrugBust     10-22 0178</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Australia-Drug Bust,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Seize 96 Pounds Of Heroin In Australia's Biggest Drug Bust</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police said <DATE>today</DATE> they found nearly 100
pounds of heroin in the water tanks of a yacht and broke up a Hong
Kong-based drug ring by employing police officers as crew members.
Authorities said it was <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest heroin bust.
   In simultaneous raids overnight <DATE>Friday</DATE>, police arrested 21
people in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> and seized 96 pounds of high-grade
Thai heroin with an estimated street value of <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY>.
   Seven people were arrested in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and 14 others in raids on
60 premises in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>, Detective Inspector <PERSON>Cliff Foster</PERSON> said.
   In the ruse, two police officers were able to get jobs as crew
members aboard a 50-foot ketch that authorities suspected was being
used to ferry drugs, said Detective Inspector <PERSON>Mike Howard</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Royal Hong Kong Police Force Drug Squad</ORGANIZATION>.
   Foster said the probe began in <DATE>June</DATE> after authorities were
tipped off that a large quantity of heroin was en route from <LOCATION>Hong
Kong</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920207-0160
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920207-0160.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Westpac to Allot Shares
</HL>
<DATE>
02/07/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   A.ABA A.CMU WBK
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
MAJOR MONEY CENTER BANKS (BAN)
ALL BANKS, BANKING NEWS AND ISSUES (BNK)
INSURANCE (INS)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<NS>
ACQUISITIONS &amp; MERGERS, TAKEOVERS, BOARD BATTLES (TNM)
</NS>
<RE>
AUSTRALIA (ASA)
FAR EAST (FE)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
</RE>
<LP>
   SYDNEY, Australia -- Westpac Banking Corp., as part of a
strategic alliance formed last year, said it will allot
Australian Mutual Provident Society 73,146,000 new Westpac
common shares.
   The move will expand AMP's share in Westpac to about 15%
from 10%. The allotment to AMP, Australia's biggest insurance
and investment concern, is valued at A$4.13 (US$3.09) a
share, or A$302 million for the entire parcel. The allotment
is expected to be completed in about two weeks.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In trading yesterday on the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> shares rose four <MONEY>Australian cents</MONEY> to <MONEY>A$4.22</MONEY>.
   Australian regulations limit shareholdings in banks to
<PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>, unless the treasurer makes a concession, which he did in
the case of the strategic alliance. However, Treasurer <PERSON>John
Dawkins</PERSON> ruled yesterday that <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>AMP</ORGANIZATION> may hold
combined stakes of only as much as <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> in other banks. He
said the two organizations must reduce their combined
shareholdings in other banks within six months.
   <ORGANIZATION>Advance Bank Australia Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> had sought clarification on
the <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> limit in the case of <ORGANIZATION>Westpac</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>AMP</ORGANIZATION>. Earlier this
week, <ORGANIZATION>Advance Bank</ORGANIZATION> said the two have a combined shareholding
of <PERCENT>15.9%</PERCENT> of its ordinary shares.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900924-0010
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900924-0010.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Australia Is Producing
   About 90% of Its Oil Needs
   ----
</HL>
<DATE>
09/24/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   FREST
</CO>
<IN>
PETROLEUM (PET)
</IN>
<LP>
   CANBERRA, Australia -- Australia is producing nearly 90%
of its oil needs and, despite the Middle East conflict, is
"well placed" to meet its requirements, the government said.
   Alan Griffiths, minister for resources, said Australia's
oil self-sufficiency rate is up from 65% in 1983, when the
Labor Party government took office. He contended that
government deregulation of crude-oil marketing and strategies
to increase exploration have helped improve self-sufficiency.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Production from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest fields in <LOCATION>Bass Strait</LOCATION>
is declining, while output from northern offshore fields is
rising. <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> imports some oil, but overall is a net
exporter of energy, because it is the world's biggest coal
exporter and sells liquefied natural gas, uranium and
light-crude oil.
   The price of domestically produced crude is kept close to
international levels. <PERSON>Mr. Griffiths</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> can't
artificially restrict prices for crude, because such controls
would cause producers to export more crude, reduce
exploration and force up oil imports.
   But <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> has insisted that oil companies slow the rise
in retail prices of gasoline since the <ORGANIZATION>Gulf</ORGANIZATION> conflict boosted
world prices. Yet gasoline prices could rise four <MONEY>Australian
cents</MONEY> a liter next week, the <ORGANIZATION>Service Station Association</ORGANIZATION>
said. Gasoline already costs more than <MONEY>80 cents</MONEY> (66 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
cents) a liter in some parts of the country. A liter is equal
to 0.26 gallon.
   <PERSON>Mr. Griffiths</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has relatively low taxes on
gasoline, and cited data showing Australian gasoline users
have been paying about <MONEY>74 Australian cents</MONEY> a liter, compared
with the equivalent of <MONEY>1.62 Australian dollars</MONEY> (US$1.34) in
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> and A$1.31 in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-1243</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CCYA1ADAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920325
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 MAR 92 / International Company News: Takeover drive puts TNT on road
to profit - The Australian transport group is winning back investors'
confidence
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
SIR <PERSON>Peter Abeles</PERSON>, chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>TNT</ORGANIZATION>, the Australian transport and
express mail group, has a message to the markets: after a year of hectic
deal-making, the group has sorted out its problems and is on track for a
return to profit.
Sir <PERSON>Peter</PERSON>, 68, flew back to <ORGANIZATION>TNT</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> headquarters from <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> this week
with three deals in his pocket. He believes these will put an end to
investors' concerns about the group's profitability and liquidity.
He also made clear his intention to go on managing the company, which he
transformed during the <DATE>1970s</DATE> and <DATE>1980s</DATE> from a small haulier into an
international shipping, aviation and trucking conglomerate.
'I have no plans to retire; I have not got time for it,' he said in response
to rumours that he intended to hand over management to one of <ORGANIZATION>TNT</ORGANIZATION>'s younger
executives.
Under Sir <PERSON>Peter</PERSON>'s guidance, <ORGANIZATION>TNT</ORGANIZATION> expanded rapidly through the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, from
revenues of ADollars 1.7bn (USDollars 1.29bn) in <DATE>1984</DATE> to ADollars 4.5bn in
<DATE>1990</DATE>. At their peak, the shares were worth well over ADollars 4 on the
<ORGANIZATION>Australian Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>.
However, the group ran into trouble early last year when institutional
investors began to worry about the high level of debt incurred to finance
growth.
With bank debt and subordinated loans totalling ADollars 2.2bn, compared
with shareholders' funds of ADollars 1.1bn, <ORGANIZATION>TNT</ORGANIZATION> looked vulnerable to the
growing recession in its main markets in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>.
There were also worries about the group's entrepreneurial nature and its
close relationship with <ORGANIZATION>Mr Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, which was then
struggling to cope with severe financial problems.
Like <PERSON>Mr Murdoch</PERSON>, Sir <PERSON>Peter</PERSON> had shown himself willing to take big risks. In
the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, for example, <ORGANIZATION>TNT</ORGANIZATION>'s big breakthrough came when its trucks carried <PERSON>Mr
Murdoch</PERSON>'s newspapers through the picket lines at <ORGANIZATION>News Corp</ORGANIZATION>'s non-union
