<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890810-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-10-89 1620EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-Corvette Adv13   08-10 0742</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Corvette, Adv 13,0771</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv13</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday Aug. 13 and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Next Generation of 'Vette: GM's Answer to the Ferrari Crowd</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Chairman <PERSON>Roger B. Smith</PERSON> is
among the first in line for one. Aerobics instructor <PERSON>Abbie Miller</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>St. Paul</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, has her order in. Former <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Bill
Janklow</PERSON> says no thanks.
   They're talking about the newest generation of the <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet
Corvette</ORGANIZATION>, the ZR-1 with an engine that puts more punch into
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s original two-seat muscle car than ever before.
   <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>'s automotive press has been gushing praise for the car,
calling it <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s high-tech answer to the <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> without
their higher pricetags.
   But don't expect to see thousands of ZR-1s screaming down the
interstates at top speed with youthful joyriders at the wheel.
Chevrolet marketing experts anticipate buyers will be predominantly
college-educated males in their 40s with household incomes of at
least <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY>.
   With a production schedule of 3,000 for the <DATE>1990</DATE> model year and
a price between <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> and <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY>, the car ZR-1 is aimed at
luring at least some would-be customers of the European luxury
performance cars.
   ``We've clearly got enough interest in this thing to sell out
this year once we set the price and get on with it,'' said
<ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Ralph Kramer</PERSON>.
   The final price is to be determined late this month, when the
ZR-1 begins rolling off the assembly line in <LOCATION>Bowling Green</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky</LOCATION>.
   Its 5.7-liter, 32-valve, V-8 engine with 375 horsepower can
propel the car from 0 to 60 mph in 4.2 seconds, less time than it
takes a phone to ring three times.
   The car also comes with a special switch that shuts off half the
valves, commonly called a ``valet key'' that temporarily tames the
monster engine and prevents hot-dogging car jockeys from roaring
around the parking lot.
   The ZR-1 doesn't have the most horsepower of any assembly-line
production Corvette _ a <DATE>1967</DATE> model with 435 horsepower did _ but it
does have the highest top speed of any Corvette at about 180 mph.
It has fuel economy ratings of 16 mpg in city driving and 25 mpg on
the highway, good enough to avoid the federal government's
``gas-guzzler'' tax.
   It's the latest in a long line of Corvettes, dating to the
original 300 produced in <DATE>1953</DATE>. Since then, more than 900,000 have
been made and they've created a cult with its own magazines, clubs
and rallies devoted to the car's ground-hugging bullet appearance.
   ``I guess it's the excitement, it's like a dream car,'' said
<PERSON>Mrs. Miller</PERSON>, 49, who owns two other Corvettes and has had her order
in for a ZR-1 since <DATE>July 24</DATE>.
   As head of <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> gets first dibs. He's had his order in
since late last year.
   The ZR-1 originally was planned as a <DATE>1989</DATE> car, but engineering
and marketing decisions pushed the introduction back to this month,
making it a <DATE>1990</DATE> in the automotive industry's calendar year.
   Despite the car's power, highway patrol officers evidently
aren't too worried about an outbreak of ZR-1 speed-mania.
   ``I think that irresponsible people can't afford that car, and
those people who can afford it aren't likely to risk their
investment by driving dangerously on the highway,'' he said.
``Aside from that, regardless of how fast they are, they aren't
faster than a radio.''
   Janklow, governor of <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> from 1978-86, is one <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>
owner who's had some experience with law enforcement officers on
highways. He owns a <DATE>1969</DATE> T-top 427 Corvette, a car he's unafraid to
push to its limit.
   ``I was notorious for my speeding,'' said <PERSON>Janklow</PERSON>, who has
received about 100 speeding tickets. ``It's just a great
automobile. It's <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s one unique touch of freedom.''
   He talks enthusiastically about his <DATE>1969</DATE> Corvette, but the ZR-1
evidently packs too much muscle for him _ <PERSON>Janklow</PERSON> said he doesn't
plan to buy one.
   Even <PERSON>Joe Pike</PERSON>, a retired Chevrolet merchandising manager and
former editor of the Corvette News magazine, said he has some
reservations about the newest model's power.
   ``I don't think there's half of <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of the people who buy
that car who are capable of driving it,'' he said. ``I don't think
I could drive it anymore even if you could find a place to drive it.
   ``It's the kind of car that belongs on the Autobahn in
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday Aug. 13 and thereafter</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911111-0078
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911111-0078.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Gm Says Future
   Of ZR-1 Corvette
   Is Now in Doubt
   ---
   Touted Model Is the Latest
   In a String of Image Cars
   To Stumble in Market
   ----
   By Neal Templin
</HL>
<DATE>
11/11/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A6
</SO>
<CO>
   GM HMC
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
ADVERTISING, MARKETING, PUBLIC RELATIONS (ADV)
AUTOMOBILES (AUT)
</IN>
<RE>
FAR EAST (FE)
JAPAN (JA)
MICHIGAN (MI)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   DETROIT -- General Motors Corp. is considering killing its
highly touted ZR-1 Corvette because of sputtering sales for
the 375-horsepower sports car.
   A Chevrolet spokesman confirmed reports by suppliers and
Auto Week magazine that the future of the $65,000 Chevrolet
model is "under review." Chevrolet is looking at alternatives
to killing the ZR-1, including boosting the power of its
high-tech, eight-cylinder engine to rekindle its appeal, he
said.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   But by acknowledging that the ZR-1's future is in doubt,
<ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> risks turning a car that was supposed to burnish the auto
maker's image into another emblem of disappointment.
   "The ZR-1 came into being for one reason only," says the
Chevrolet spokesman. "And that was to add luster to the
Corvette line and, by extension, to the entire Chevrolet
line."
   Instead, the ZR-1, nicknamed "King of the Hill," is the
latest in a string of heavily promoted <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> image cars to
stumble in the market. In <DATE>1988</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> was forced to kill its
Pontiac Fiero after the plastic-bodied car's propensity to
catch fire killed demand. Earlier this year, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> pulled the
plug on its slow-selling <ORGANIZATION>Buick Reatta</ORGANIZATION> two-seater. <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>
continues to produce the <ORGANIZATION>Cadillac Allante</ORGANIZATION>, a two-seater
designed to compete with exclusive <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION>
roadsters. But <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> has heavily discounted the <MONEY>$57,000</MONEY> Allante
in the past because of disappointing sales.
   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> isn't alone in having trouble selling high-priced,
exotic cars in the recessionary auto market. <ORGANIZATION>Honda Motor
Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s aluminum-bodied <ORGANIZATION>Acura NSX</ORGANIZATION> sports car, which came out a
year ago to rave reviews, now appears to be struggling. Honda
sold just 86 <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> models in <DATE>October</DATE>, down from 270 cars a year
ago. A <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> spokesman conceded that demand is soft, although
he said the drop in <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> sales also reflects a slow launch of
<DATE>1992</DATE> models.
   But many of the Corvette ZR-1's problems appear to be of
<ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s making. Like the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>, the ZR-1 started out red hot when
it was introduced in <DATE>1989</DATE>, with some dealers charging
premiums of thousands of dollars above its <MONEY>$58,995</MONEY> list price
back then. "It was absolutely wild in the beginning,"
remembers <PERSON>Dan Bischof</PERSON>, general manager of <ORGANIZATION>Ed Morse Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION>
near <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION> "People were calling us from all
over the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>"
   But a year ago, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> changed the rear end of the standard
Corvette so that it looked like the ZR-1. Then, <ORGANIZATION>Mercury
Marine</ORGANIZATION>, which makes the ZR-1's 32-valve, eight-cylinder
motor, stopped production for more than three months to fix a
design flaw that was causing some ZR-1 engines to self
destruct. When production started again in <DATE>April 1990</DATE>, demand
for the car had chilled.
   The crowning blow came this <DATE>fall</DATE>, when <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> put a more
powerful motor in the regular <DATE>1992</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>. The base
<ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>, priced at about <MONEY>$34,000</MONEY>, now accelerates to 60
miles per hour in just five seconds, only a step slower than
the sizzling 4.3-second zero-to-60 time of a ZR-1 that costs
nearly twice as much.
   The result: Dealers are now heavily discounting the ZR-1,
bad news for collectors who bought early models in hopes they
would appreciate. "We have them in stock and we've got
relatively few buyers," says <PERSON>Ed Morse Chevrolet</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Mr.
Bischof</PERSON>.
   Without giving specific figures, <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> says ZR-1 sales
are down, even though overall Corvette sales rose <PERCENT>9%</PERCENT> in
<DATE>October</DATE> from a year ago. Moreover, production of the ZR-1 is
being scaled back. <ORGANIZATION>Mercury Marine</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Stillwater</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>,
factory is producing just six ZR-1 engines a day, a third of
capacity. <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> had expected the ZR-1 would account for <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of
total Corvette production this year, but the company
spokesman says the actual percentage is less.
   Mercury Marine workers, meanwhile, want to save the car.
They even rigged up experimental engines that produce over
500 horsepower, says <PERSON>James Skalitzky</PERSON>, a manager in the
factory. However, those engines don't meet federal pollution
standards, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880817-0038 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sea-Horsepowered Corvette to Cruise At Lots of Knots --- Mercury Marine to Produce All-Aluminum Engines For Special Version of Car </HL>
<AUTHOR> Melinda Grenier Guiles and Judith Valente (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> BC GM </CO>
<IN> AUT </IN>
<TEXT>
   Chevrolet is turning to an unusual supplier for the high-performance engine on a new Corvette sports car -- the <ORGANIZATION>Mercury Marine</ORGANIZATION> engine division of <ORGANIZATION>Brunswick Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> unit said <ORGANIZATION>Mercury Marine</ORGANIZATION> will manufacture about 2,000 a year of the all-aluminum, 32-valve, 5.7-liter engines for the Corvette ZR1, a special-version model that will debut by early next <DATE>spring</DATE>. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> spokesman acknowledged the agreement was unusual, but added that under the circumstances, "Mercury is the best business alternative." 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> is expert at getting "very high horsepower and long life from small-displacement, lightweight engines" -- an important factor in boat racing. 
Mercury, <ORGANIZATION>Brunswick</ORGANIZATION>'s largest division with <DATE>1987</DATE> sales in excess of <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>, is a dominant force in that field, where its MerCruiser stern drives and inboard engines have set numerous speed records. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> has an exclusive license to adapt the Corvette engine for marine use, effective about one year from the car's introduction. 
That agreement is more in keeping with the companies' traditional business relationship, under which <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> has purchased GM-made marine engines and engine blocks. 

   Brunswick said inboard boat engines aren't all that different from car engines, since both have four cycles and share the same functions. 
But the <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION> engine will have a better power-to-weight ratio than normal boat engines. 
That means once it's adapted for boats, it will have more power and weigh less than comparable engines, <ORGANIZATION>Brunswick</ORGANIZATION> said. 

   The new Corvette engine was developed and designed by <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Group Lotus</ORGANIZATION> division, of <LOCATION>Hethel</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, in conjunction with <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION>. 
The engine will be capable of delivering as much as 390 horsepower, which could mean top speeds nearing 200 miles an hour for the ZR1. 
A lofty top speed wasn't the objective in designing the new engine, however, said the Chevrolet spokesman, adding that the car's exact performance specifications haven't been determined yet. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> sold about 25,000 Corvettes in <DATE>1987</DATE>. 
The <DATE>1989</DATE> models, other than the ZR1, will go on sale at the end of <DATE>September</DATE> with a base price of <MONEY>$31,545</MONEY>. 
Industry watchers estimate the ZR1 will cost more than <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>, but the <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> spokesman wouldn't discuss its price. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890810-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-10-89 1632EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-CorvettePlant Adv13   08-10 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Corvette Plant, Adv 13,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv13</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday Aug. 13 and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bowling Green Plant Produces World's Corvettes</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Corvette</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBBIE NEWBY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOWLING GREEN, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Jack Taylor</PERSON> has a saying: You don't
drive a <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>, you wear it.
   ``If you've ever sat in one, you kind of have that feeling,''
said <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>, director of manufacturing engineering at the <ORGANIZATION>General
Motors Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Corvette plant at <ORGANIZATION>Bowling Green</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's a statement of
people's success in life.''
   Taylor calls his <DATE>1966</DATE> blue <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION> ``an adult pacifier.''
   The cars, introduced to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> in <DATE>1953</DATE>, pacify such well-known
adults as <PERSON>Mike Love</PERSON> of the Beach Boys; members of the singing group
<LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, who own four; basketball great <PERSON>Michael Jordan</PERSON> and
entertainer <PERSON>Sammy Davis Jr</PERSON>.
   The car also is the choice of such renowned speedsters as <PERSON>Al
Unser</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mario Andretti</PERSON> and <PERSON>Chuck Yeager</PERSON>. Signed photographs of their
Corvettes hang on walls in the plant's visitors' area and the snack
bar.
   This year, <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> will make 26,411 cars at the only plant
that assembles the Corvette, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first two-seat sports car.
Of these, 3,000 will be the souped up ZR-1 model.
   Corvette assembly moved to <ORGANIZATION>Bowling Green</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> in
<DATE>August 1979</DATE>. The first car rolled off the <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> line in <DATE>1981</DATE>.
The 1-million-square-foot plant, about the size of 22 football
fields, houses more than a mile of railroad track and 7{ miles of
conveyor track.
   About 1,250 workers and 65 robots produce 14 cars an hour _ a
piddling line speed in a world where many factories crank out a car
a minute.
   ``We want to make our quality the best it can be,'' said <PERSON>Jim
Case</PERSON>, a trim utility auditor. ``A person who owns a Corvette is
proud of his car. He knows everybody looks at it and wants one.''
   The price of <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION> is pushing it farther from reach.
   The standard coupe now sells for about <MONEY>$34,000</MONEY>; the convertible
for <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY>. The ZR-1, which begins production later this month,
will cost <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY>.
   Nonetheless, the Corvette plant tour is popular, even among
people who could never afford to buy the car. <PERSON>Jane Bowlin</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>
spokeswoman, said about 40,000 people toured the plant <DATE>last year</DATE>,
making it one of <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>'s most crowded tourist attractions.
   The plant also is a shrine among Corvette owners. Some leave
their calling cards.
   Corvette club patches fill a display case outside the visitors'
area. They're from the Thunder Basin Corvettes in <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>;
the Vette Set from <LOCATION>Decatur</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Flood City Corvettes</ORGANIZATION> from
<LOCATION>Johnstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa</LOCATION>.
   ``Some people take their vacation to come here,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Bowlin</PERSON>
said, pointing out patches from <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>.
   Inside the Corvette plant, some things are done a little
differently from others.
   During the painting process, the outside of the car is covered
in plastic wrap and workers apply a flat black paint to hidden and
hard-to-reach parts, including the firewall and the inside of the
hood.
   ``We want to cover all the places only <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION> nuts would
look,'' paint supervisor <PERSON>Bob Breeding</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for Sunday Aug. 13 and thereafter</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06027232 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06027232 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; This long, sleek Corvette may look like a car, but it's really a legacy
and a lifestyle -- at least that's what its owners proclaim  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  KENTUCKY; AUTO; MUSEUM  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  WHEN it comes to Corvettes, there are true believers and then there are all
the rest.;    And it is in a rather unlikely looking storefront in a cloned,
artless mini-mall just off Interstate 65 here that the truly faithful have
begun to gather.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CORVETTE FAITHFUL PEEL RUBBER TO GET TO MUSEUM
ANNEX  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Destination: Kentucky
Jerry Huston is a reporter for The Commercial Appeal in Memphis, Tenn.
Additional information attached to the end of this article.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     It's the <ORGANIZATION>National Corvette Museum Annex</ORGANIZATION>, barely a month old and already
becoming a shrine for 'Vette owners and adulating wanna-bees, a mecca for
legions of devotees. Museum officials say it's the first and only facility
devoted exclusively to the Corvette.;    Situated a few miles from the
museum's permanent site and near <LOCATION>Chevrolet</LOCATION>'s Corvette plant -- the only place
that Corvettes are built -- the museum annex is quickly becoming assimilated
in the local 'Vette montage.;    "When you buy a Corvette, you're not just
buying a car. You're buying a lifestyle, a heritage, a legacy. It's a lot more
than just owning a car," said <PERSON>Owen Bugnaski</PERSON>, 28, who cruised down from <LOCATION>Monroe</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, with a friend to visit the plant and museum.; Open within a year;  The
museum, which will be on a 32-acre site across the street from the Corvette
plant, is expected to open in late <DATE>1991</DATE> or early <DATE>1992</DATE>, said museum manager
<PERSON>Judi Hollander</PERSON>. Its <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY> initial construction cost is to be paid by
individual contributions and corporate sponsors, said <PERSON>Darrel Bowlin</PERSON>, a member
of the museum's board of directors.;    On the drawing board are a 250-seat
auditorium that will regularly feature a video history of the <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>, an
auction room with a revolving floor and a library featuring technical data
books, trade journals, professional papers and car manuals.;    Also planned
is a 700-seat convention hall for car displays and exhibits, a full kitchen
for catered affairs, a visitor's restaurant and a minimum of 30 vintage,
collector-quality Corvettes.;    The storefront "mini-museum" annex has four
cars on display and a lot of <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION> souvenirs for sale.;    All this hoopla,
just for a car?;    Ah, yes, but not just a car, the faithful would say. It's
a <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>. Introduced in <DATE>January 1953</DATE>, the two-seat, fiberglass-body roadster
has emerged as among the most cherished of all automobiles.;    Ironically, a
slow drive train and some corny design features in the early models nearly
killed the Corvette in its infancy.;    But by <DATE>1957</DATE>, the car had been given
the looks, speed, power and handling that have been its trademark ever since.;
   The <DATE>1991</DATE> Corvette ZR-1 with a high performance engine can top 190 mph and
holds several international and world speed records, <PERSON>Bowlin</PERSON> said. It begins at
<MONEY>$65,000</MONEY>. Other <DATE>1991</DATE> 'Vettes, without the high performance engine, list at
about <MONEY>$38,000</MONEY>.;    <ORGANIZATION>Maserati</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Lamborghini</LOCATION> -- none strike a
chord in the American car lover's heart like the Corvette -- a slicked-back,
torqued-up, distinctly American machine that has often left the hoity-toity
foreign jobs trailing in its dust.;    Lining the walls of the annex are more
than a dozen different <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION> posters, some priced over <MONEY>$50</MONEY>, that depict the
actual engineers' designs of some of the cars.;    But to get the best sense
of where Corvette fans are coming from, it's best to talk with them, watch
them together, see them around the objects of their passion.;    "I love these
cars. I always have," said <PERSON>Clarence Long</PERSON>, gazing lovingly at the sleek,
two-toned <DATE>1967</DATE> L88 LeMans Racer housed at the museum.; One of the family; 
Long has owned six different Corvettes, including a beautiful late '50s model
that a friend cracked up in an accident.;    "Oh, it was terrible. It was just
like losing a family member. I mean, the insurance company can pay you for the
life, but you can never get it back," said Long, an employee at the Corvette
plant.;    "It's the feel of the car that gets you, the speed, the feel of the
gears as you take off -- it's that vroom, vroom, vroom-vroom, VROOOOM,"
growled Long, a gleam in his eye, as his wife watched her 53-year-old husband
make odd sounds in front of a stranger.;    True believers speak in their own
language.;    They talk about prototypes and engine specifications and the
aerodynamics of the cars as if they designed the cars themselves. If it were
not for the venue, the adjectives they tossed around might have led a
passer-by to think they were discussing a beautiful woman.;    "So sleek and
smooth, yet voluptuous. Every curve is perfect, yet not obtrusive," said
visitor <PERSON>Jeff Gutschow</PERSON>, speaking in the hushed tones expected in a shrine.; 
(check) IF YOU GO -- For information about the <ORGANIZATION>National Corvette Museum Annex</ORGANIZATION>,
call (502) 781-7973.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JERRY HUSTON, Scripps Howard News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Bowling Green, Ky.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910127  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  817  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday January 27, 1991
00027232,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051890-0016 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 220414 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 18, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 1; Column 4; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1293 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BEHIND THE WHEEL: HYBRID TURBOCHARGES ITS WAY TO CALIFORNIA 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PAUL DEAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The galloping <ORGANIZATION>Callaway Twin Turbo</ORGANIZATION> -- barred from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> since creation 
because its builder chose not to chase state emission standards -- has cleaned 
up its act and has been cleared to sell locally. 
</P>
<P>
Watch out. 
</P>
<P>
Here's a 190-m.p.h. pacemaker to the heartbeat of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, a private-sector 
mutagenesis of a Chevrolet Corvette that accelerates faster than a <ORGANIZATION>Lamborghini 
Countach</ORGANIZATION> or a <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> 911 Turbo. 
</P>
<P>
With twin turbochargers building almost 400 horsepower, the <LOCATION>Callaway</LOCATION> can outrun 
a <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari Testarossa</ORGANIZATION> -- and the terminal velocity of that particular Italian 
redhead just happens to be faster than liftoff speed of an F-16. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Callaway Twin Turbo</ORGANIZATION> is also relatively affordable, undisputedly exclusive 
and a hot rod in sheep's cladding that may be ordered alongside Luminas and 
Corsicas at your neighborhood Chevrolet dealer. 
</P>
<P>
This assigning of an RPO (Regular Production Option) designation to the 
<PERSON>Callaway</PERSON> says a lot for <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s tolerance and acceptance of an after-market hybrid 
clearly competing in price, performance and enthusiast appeal with <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION>'s 
super fast (but still slower) Corvette ZR-1. 
</P>
<P>
And by tacit endorsement of the <LOCATION>Twin Turbo</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> obviously is putting its 
reputation (also its 12-month and 12,000-mile powertrain warranty) behind a 
product that meets cherished standards of reliability for sports cars that -- 
like the thirtysomething Corvette and the yearling ZR-1 -- are docile enough 
for the 'burbs yet become absolute thrashers on interstates. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Callaway Twin Turbo</ORGANIZATION> rose from a <DATE>1985</DATE> misfit -- a turbocharged, experimental 
Corvette built for Chevrolet by an outside contractor. 
</P>
<P>
Chevrolet wasn't much thrilled by the prototype. But <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> engineer <PERSON>Ely 
Reeves Callaway III</PERSON>, former Formula Vee racer, descendant of <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Baptist</ORGANIZATION> 
preachers and <ORGANIZATION>Callaway Vineyards</ORGANIZATION>, saw it as the greatest potential for blinding 
motion since the <MONEY>$25</MONEY> firecracker. 
</P>
<P>
A year later, with <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION>'s blessing, <PERSON>Callaway</PERSON> was in limited production. 
Today there are some 400 Twin Turbos blowing off doors throughout 49 states. 
But not until last month's certification and satisfaction of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s 
bulletproof smog standards has the brute that purrs been available here. 
</P>
<P>
"Frankly, there's a limited market in the rest of the country for a high 
performance car such as this, and selling in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> was the next logical 
step," said <PERSON>Roger Smith</PERSON>, managing director of <ORGANIZATION>Callaway Cars of Old Lyme</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Conn</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Also, we are seeing the rest of the country moving towards adopting 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s (emission) standards. So we thought we might as well do it 
(comply) and get it over with." 
</P>
<P>
Every Twin Turbo starts life as a stock Corvette equipped with the venerable 
but trusted small block Chevy V-8. The car is shipped to <LOCATION>Callaway</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> 
skunk works where moving parts are magnafluxed and balanced. Main bearings are 
worked over. Stainless steel valves, a forged crank and pistons and a new cam 
with hydraulic lifters are added. 
</P>
<P>
Then comes the heart transplant -- the addition of twin, intercooled 
turbochargers that boost the <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>'s standard 245 horsepower to 390 
horsepower, which actually is more like a stampede. 
</P>
<P>
The ultimate proof of power, however, is this thing called torque -- the engine 
force that produces wheel rotation and vehicle motion. Torque is measured in 
terms of maximum oomph produced to move poundage over footage. 
</P>
<P>
The torque-feet of a <ORGANIZATION>Toyota Celica GT</ORGANIZATION>, for example, is 140 pounds-feet. The 
5.0-liter <ORGANIZATION>Ford Mustang</ORGANIZATION> puts out a very respectable 300-pounds-feet. But the 
<ORGANIZATION>Callaway Twin Turbo</ORGANIZATION> transmits a thumping 562-pounds-feet to its rear wheels and 
that's enough to leave divots in your driveway. 
</P>
<P>
For the discreet who do not wish to advertise, the <ORGANIZATION>Callaway Twin Turbo</ORGANIZATION> may be 
purchased as a coupe or convertible that externally is only a badge and a 
plaque removed from a stock <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But the brash might choose an <MONEY>$8,500</MONEY> Aerobody option that gives the car a row 
of flared nostrils and straked body ducts. It includes a new, slick, rounded, 
aerodynamic nose and a sculptured rear end that looks for all the world like a 
grown-up Miata with a ducktail. The whole is awfully handsome. Especially with 
the Dymag magnesium wheels. 
</P>
<P>
The interior of the car is pure <DATE>1990</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
It also is an abomination. 
</P>
<P>
In their semicircular, Pac-Man setting, essential instruments are a mix-up of 
needles and digital readouts. Warning gauges, numbered to show only the 
extremes of their operating range, confuse before they inform. 
</P>
<P>
And then there is dash lettering that's a squint even for those with vision 
only one diopter removed from 20/20. Is this a radio we see before us? Or the 
climate control panel? Either way, the display is a litter of toy knobs and 
pitiful symbology. And the radio doesn't scan. 
</P>
<P>
On a happier note, the cockpit cuddles nicely, the seats feel rugged and hold 
well during spirited cornering, and like all Corvettes, the car comes with an 
air bag. 
</P>
<P>
Yet there is no doubting that this is a <LOCATION>Callaway</LOCATION>. It says so on a dash plaque 
(and in the true spirit of adventure and high-speed risk, the production number 
of the test car was 007) and a boost gauge for monitoring the twin 
turbochargers. 
</P>
<P>
The suspension remains untouched and stock <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>. So does the car's 
six-speed manual transmission. Together, they give a surplus of performance 
management that does not diminish as speed builds but actually seems to improve 
with pace. 
</P>
<P>
But then the <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION> always has been a flat, determined, obedient ride. It has 
brakes (13-inch discs) to spare for late dives into interesting corners. More 
important, there's power aplenty to boot through and out of the turns. 
</P>
<P>
Today's Corvettes come with selective ride control (Tour-Sport-Performance) and 
at no time -- even if fishtailing, overcorrecting or losing some other portion 
of the car's geometry -- is there a shadow of suspension floats or steering 
dithers. 
</P>
<P>
To all of this, add a power plant designed and tuned to do little else but 
convert a two-place car into a drill boring 190-m.p.h. holes through the air. 
</P>
<P>
But forget that speed. It isn't important. It would also be fair to state that 
nobody who owns a <LOCATION>Callaway</LOCATION> has ever driven it at that speed. Or will. Then why 
have it? 
</P>
<P>
Because an inordinately quick top end is simply the byproduct of searching for 
a stupendous mid-range where most mortals live. And it is here -- entering 
freeways, pulling clear of tailgaters, moving around the blind idiot cutting 
across our bows -- where the <LOCATION>Callaway</LOCATION> is simply astounding. 
</P>
<P>
It takes five seconds to accelerate from 60 m.p.h. to 100 m.p.h. It rockets 
from rest to 100 m.p.h. in a sniff over 10 seconds. And it is raw speed in a 
gentle hurtle where the power seems endless. 
</P>
<P>
Indeed, smoothness is the pleasant surprise of the <ORGANIZATION>Twin Turbo</ORGANIZATION>. In town, in 
traffic, it's an easy drive. Shifting is a click and the clutch no heavier than 
a <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>. On the open road it's an enormous dose of docile power where the 
rear-view mirror can be forgotten because no other car will be fast enough to 
sneak up. 
</P>
<P>
That's not a <ORGANIZATION>Chevy</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
That's a <LOCATION>Callaway</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1990</DATE> CALLAWAY TWIN TURBO 
</P>
<P>
COST: 
</P>
<P>
Base: <MONEY>$62,834</MONEY> for coupe. 
</P>
<P>
As tested: <MONEY>$76,619</MONEY> for convertible (with Aerobody). 
</P>
<P>
ENGINE: 
</P>
<P>
Twin turbo, 5.7 liter, V-8 developing 390 horsepower. 
</P>
<P>
TYPE: 
</P>
<P>
Limited production, rear-wheel-drive sports car. 
</P>
<P>
PERFORMANCE: 
</P>
<P>
0-60 m.p.h. (as tested) 5.2 seconds. 
</P>
<P>
Top speed (manufacturer's estimate, coupe) 190 m.p.h. 
</P>
<P>
Fuel economy (<ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> city-highway average) 17.2 m.p.g. 
</P>
<P>
CURB WEIGHT: 
</P>
<P>
3,403 pounds. 
</P>
<P>
THE GOOD: 
</P>
<P>
Astounding performance with decorum of daily driver. 
</P>
<P>
Best-handling American car. 
</P>
<P>
Full-blooded competition for <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> and Lamborghini at half the price. 
</P>
<P>
THE BAD: 
</P>
<P>
Exhaust note tuned to extinction. 
</P>
<P>
Disappointing interior styling. 
</P>
<P>
THE UGLY: 
</P>
<P>
Instrument display by <ORGANIZATION>Nintendo</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Nostrils, ducts for feeding air to turbochargers and radiator 
separate Callaway Twin Turbo with Aerobody styling from standard Corvette. ; 
Photo, Callaway Twin Turbo's intercooled turbochargers boost the Corvette's 
standard 245 horsepower to 390 horsepower; top speed is 190 m.p.h. ; Photo, The 
three-quarter rear view of the Callaway Twin Turbo convertible shows off the 
hybrid's sporty lines. RANDY LEFFINGWELL / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910409-0107
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910409-0107.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   GM Halted Output
   Of Its Corvette ZR1
   Over Engine Flaw
   ---
   Production Has Resumed
   On High Priced Model
   After 3-Month Inspection
   ----
   By Gregory A. Patterson
</HL>
<DATE>
04/09/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A5
</SO>
<CO>
   GM
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
AUTOMOBILES (AUT)
</IN>
<RE>
MICHIGAN (MI)
</RE>
<LP>
   DETROIT -- General Motors Corp. had to stop building its
most expensive car, the $64,138 Chevrolet Corvette ZR1, for
three and a half months while engineers tracked a flaw that
caused some of the 370 horsepower engines in the cars to
self-destruct, company officials confirmed yesterday.
   The ZR1, nicknamed "King of the Hill," has been the object
of considerable hyperbole from GM's Chevrolet division and
the automotive press. Car and Driver magazine called the ZR1
the "Corvette from Hell. . . so good it's scary." And dealers
cheerfully accepted offers well above sticker price from
collectors.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The ZR1 costs <MONEY>$31,683</MONEY> more than the <MONEY>$32,455</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>.
That's mainly because of the ZR1's 32-valve, eight-cylinder
aluminum engine, which can fling the car from 0 to 60 miles
per hour in just 4.3 seconds. The regular <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION> has a cast
iron eight-cylinder engine that produces 245 horsepower and
takes an additional 1.4 seconds to get from 0 to 60 miles per
hour.
   But in <DATE>December</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> officials quietly halted production
and sales of the car, after a vexing engine problem surfaced.
The company resumed building and selling the cars last month.
   Engineers found the problem in a defectively manufactured
camshaft, the component that regulates fuel flow into the
engine. The defect caused the engines to overheat and
ultimately "seize," a <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said. In other
words, the engines self-destructed.
   Chevrolet officials say they checked an entire batch of
500 ZR1 engines manufactured by <ORGANIZATION>Mercury Marine</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Stillwater</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Okla</LOCATION>. They found 17 engines with the problem, which they
dismantled in their search for the solution.
   But more importantly, <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> officials say, none of the
defective engines got into the hands of buyers. "I guess the
proof of the pudding is that there haven't turned out to be
any more problems," the <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said.
   Analysts say Chevrolet handled the ZR1 problem well by
halting sales and production until they fixed it. "This is a
sign of how customer-driven manufacturers have become," says
<PERSON>Chris Cedergren</PERSON>, an industry expert with the <LOCATION>Agoura Hills</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, consulting firm <ORGANIZATION>J.D. Power &amp; Associates</ORGANIZATION>. "Things have
radically changed from 10 or 15 years ago" when manufacturers
might sell the cars anyway and later try to fix problems at
dealerships, he said.
   But <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION> customers may still end up paying more than
the sticker price. Production cutbacks caused a shortage of
ZR1s, which is likely to encourage dealers to demand high
prices, <PERSON>Mr. Cedergren</PERSON> says.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890824-0224 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-24-89 0925EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-NewCars     08-24 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-New Cars,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>1990 Chevrolets Introduced; New Lincoln Town Car Rolls Off Line</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DT1, DT3 of Aug. 23</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A distinct identity for <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION>'s Geo line of
small vehicles still hasn't been developed, nearly a year after the
first of the cars were introduced, a company executive says.
   Chevrolet General Manager <PERSON>Jim Perkins</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>
division is about halfway through its process of developing its Geo
franchise.
   The company is walking a narrow path between selling and
servicing the three Geo cars and one truck at Chevrolet dealers and
fostering a separate image for the nameplate.
   Geo cars were introduced in <DATE>January</DATE>. Since then, one model, the
Spectrum, has been dropped and two, the Metro and Storm, have been
added.
   Separate Geo signs are going up at dealerships and some Chevrolet
dealers are taking out space in commercial telephone books in the
G's to encourage the brand distinction.
   Also, <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION>'s well-known ``Heartbeat of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'' advertising
theme, going into its fourth year, will not be used in Geo ads.
Instead, those ads feature the theme, ``Getting to know Geo,'' to
the tune of ``Getting to Know You,'' from the play ``The King and
I.''
   ``The Geo imagery is going to become more focused than it has
been in the past,'' <PERSON>Perkins</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Perkins</PERSON>, speaking during the introduction of the Chevrolet lineup
for <DATE>1990</DATE>, also said <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> is ready to give Chevrolet dealers a hand in
marketing the Geo and will boost the potential dealer profit margin
on Geo cars and trucks.
   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> has been criticized for failing to give consumers a clear
picture of its new line of cars. For the coming model year, there
will be three Geo cars _ the Storm, Prizm and Metro and one
sport-utility vehicle _ the Tracker.
   The Metro is made by <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co</ORGANIZATION>. Ltd. in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>; the Tracker
is made in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> by the GM-Suzuki joint venture <ORGANIZATION>Canadian-American
Manufacturing Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; the Prizm is made in <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, at the
GM-Toyota joint venture <ORGANIZATION>New United Motor Manufacturing Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; and the
Storm is made in <ORGANIZATION>Fujisawa</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, by <ORGANIZATION>Isuzu Motors Ltd</ORGANIZATION>.
   Eighty-four percent of the 4,800 Chevrolet dealers have agreed to
sell Geos. <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> denied reports earlier this year that some dealers
were pressured into taking on Geo in return for getting a crack at
selling the new Corvette ZR-1, production of which begins later this
month in <LOCATION>Bowling Green</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Perkins</PERSON> said the ZR-1, with a 370-horsepower engine that can push
the car from 0 to 60 mph in 4.2 seconds, will sell for <MONEY>$58,995</MONEY>.
About 3,000 of the cars will be available in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
during the <DATE>1990</DATE> model year, mainly because of restraints by the
engine maker, <ORGANIZATION>Mercury Marine</ORGANIZATION>.
   An undetermined number of ZR-1 Corvettes will be sold in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Perkins</PERSON> said.
   Separately <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> rolled the first <DATE>1990</DATE>
Lincoln Town Car off the assembly line in <LOCATION>Wixom</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, with a
ceremony complete with a cake the shape of a <DATE>1989</DATE> Town Car. The new
version, which will be introduced formally <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE>, is a longer,
slightly rounded version of the <DATE>1989</DATE> model.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081090-0041 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 259781 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 10, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 1; Column 3; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1868 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BEHIND THE WHEEL / ACURA NSX: A $100,000 HONDA? 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PAUL DEAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall has crumbled to paperweights, reading presidential lips 
suddenly became as unreliable as reading minds, and <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> real 
estate is no longer a platinum hedge. 
</P>
<P>
Yet here's the absolute shocker of an audacious year: a <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> that costs 
<MONEY>$60,000</MONEY>. Or <MONEY>$64,000</MONEY> with automatic. 
</P>
<P>
But only if you own the dealership. 
</P>
<P>
Tightly limited supplies of the new, pivotal, radical and very rapid 
Honda/Acura <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> sports car already have created a scalper's market. Only 5,000 
of the cars will be made this year, and only 3,000 of those will come to the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
So offers of <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> are being whispered. A physician in <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, according 
to <ORGANIZATION>AutoWeek magazine</ORGANIZATION>, is offering his first place on a dealer's <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> waiting 
list for <MONEY>$33,000</MONEY>. A <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> broker is ready to pay dealers <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> above their 
sticker prices. 
</P>
<P>
It's a repeat of <ORGANIZATION>Miata Mania</ORGANIZATION> -- yet a display of frantics that will surprise 
only those who still believe Japanese automobile manufacturers make unemotional 
motorcycles, build super gasoline generators and really know how to recycle 
lawn mowers into commuter cars. 
</P>
<P>
The truth of this matter: 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>'s maiden vehicle exports were two motorcycles shipped to <LOCATION>Okinawa</LOCATION> in <DATE>1957</DATE>. 
That was three years before <ORGANIZATION>Nissan</ORGANIZATION> came to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In the short generation since: 
</P>
<P>
* Of all new automobiles sold in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> are imported. When it comes to 
reliable, thrifty, pretty, zippy, little imported cars, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> owns the 
showroom. 
</P>
<P>
* Lexus and Infiniti have grabbed the luxury performance car market by the 
lapels. Mercedes, <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> aren't exactly shaking in their Connelly 
leather britches, but the big dogs are reducing prices or introducing less 
expensive entry-level vehicles. 
</P>
<P>
* Now comes a hefty sports car, the fastest, most expensive Japanese car ever, 
to raid and plunder the stables of <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>, builders of lusty 
exotics that offer performance close to the speed of thought. 
</P>
<P>
And the <ORGANIZATION>Acura NSX</ORGANIZATION>, this car that will be king of <ORGANIZATION>Acura</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>'s upscale 
division, is offering easily in its first year what others have struggled to 
deliver after more than four decades of development. 
</P>
<P>
The competition are gladiators all. From <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, weighing in at <MONEY>$103,000</MONEY>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> 348. From <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, where the motor car was born a century ago, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> 911 Carrera at <MONEY>$72,000</MONEY>. From the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, wearing skinned 
knuckles and drinking Budweiser from the can, comes the Corvette ZR-1 at 
<MONEY>$60,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
In earlier cultures, these cars would be considered talismans to be buried 
alongside their masters. Top speeds usually exceed a driver's weight. They are 
useless for anything but going fast and reminding the self-indulgent of their 
limitations. They certainly do not kiss back. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> snarls with the baddest. 
</P>
<P>
Yet it doesn't roar louder than the toughest. 
</P>
<P>
Externally, from any view, whether seeing styling or examining aerodynamic 
design, the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> is superb and doubtless one of the most handsome cars ever. 
</P>
<P>
The cabin-forward design starts with a short nose and a gentle slope reserved 
for high-performance vehicles built to slide beneath and shove aside 
obstructive air. Just like a Group C racing car. 
</P>
<P>
Amidships -- and for the full length of the doors -- twin horizontal lines 
leading to rear fuselage air scoops visually lower the car and accent its 
Nutra-Slim look. 
</P>
<P>
The roof line resembles a canopy, and the rear rises to an aerofoil; the 
profile is of a jet fighter's vertical stabilizer. That's no accident: In its 
search for the optimum silhouette of speed and purpose, <ORGANIZATION>Acura</ORGANIZATION> researched 
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s aeronautical designs, in particular <ORGANIZATION>General Dynamics</ORGANIZATION>' F-16 Fighting 
Falcon. 
</P>
<P>
From an engineering standpoint, the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> is probably a decade ahead of its time. 
Here is a car with an all-aluminum monocoque body and subframe, and at 460 
pounds, the chassis weighs less than a sumo wrestling tag team. 
</P>
<P>
The suspension is cast aluminum (mounted on a nice piece of walnut, the 
wishbones would make sensational bookends), with a unique, additional strut to 
prevent the front wheels from kicking out of true when riding road bumps. 
</P>
<P>
The engine uses lighter, stronger (and frightfully expensive) titanium 
connecting rods. There's also something called a <ORGANIZATION>Variable Valve Timing</ORGANIZATION> and Lift 
Electronic Control System (VTEC), an automatic orchestration of cams and 
valves. In essence, it creates a 20-horsepower reserve that is uncorked only 
when the car's performance must graduate from serious to competitive. On 
fighter aircraft, it used to be called combat boost. 
</P>
<P>
The interior is five-star and flawless. Leather-covered seats are closer to 
custom chairs with a full, but unobtrusive shoulder support for tighter turns. 
These are better than the most expensive custom seats by <ORGANIZATION>Recaro</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Vision would only be better if your head were inside a goldfish bowl. There's 
even clear sighting to back corners and directly behind the car, a weak spot 
among mid-engined cars that traditionally have had gun slits for rear windows. 
</P>
<P>
The engine note is a ripper. The shifter couldn't be smoother in buttermilk. 
Headroom is just enough for anyone 6-foot-4. There's sufficient luggage space 
for a weekend away with even overdressed beloveds, although the trunk is set 
against the engine, so be prepared for hot baggage. Or it may be used to warm 
take-out lasagna. 
</P>
<P>
Only one fault: Lighting is dim on digital displays telling the driver what the 
radio and climate controls are supposed to be doing. In sunlight, they 
disappear entirely. 
</P>
<P>
But with its thinner air bag fabric (for a smaller lump in the steering wheel) 
to automatic traction control (which completely tames the overcontrol buffoon 
in all of us), the car is a technological marvel. 
</P>
<P>
If only Honda/Acura had moved a little faster. 
</P>
<P>
For the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> was conceived in <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Its announced targets at that time were the <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> 911, the <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet Corvette</ORGANIZATION> 
and the <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> 328. And the <ORGANIZATION>Acura NSX</ORGANIZATION> clearly is superior to all three. 
</P>
<P>
But they were cars of seven years ago, and in the development cycle since, 
<ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> has produced the all-wheel drive Carrera 4. Chevrolet built a day of 
thunder it called the ZR-1. And Ferrari recently began selling the 348ts. 
</P>
<P>
We have driven them all. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> generally is superior in engineering, design and technology, but only a 
peer in performance. 
</P>
<P>
In the hands of the average to better driver, nothing corners sweeter, flatter 
and safer than the all-wheel Carrera 4. The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> is only a rear-wheel drive 
vehicle. 
</P>
<P>
No sports car offers more muscle for the buck than the Corvette ZR-1. The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> 
isn't quite so quick from zero to 60 m.p.h. and has a slightly slower top 
speed. 
</P>
<P>
The Ferrari 348ts can claim an identical edge at the top end. And in its maiden 
year, the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> cannot possibly match the 40-year racing heritage, mystique, 
exclusivity and visceral appeal of <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1983</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Acura</ORGANIZATION>'s 3-liter engine and 270 horsepower were a significant threat to 
the opposition. 
</P>
<P>
But in <DATE>1990</DATE>, that engine has lightened a little alongside the 3.4 liters (290 
horsepower) of <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION>, the 3.6 liters (247 horsepower) of <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> and the 3.5 
liters (375 horsepower) of the Corvette ZR-1. 
</P>
<P>
Acura officials have heard the comparisons, express no concerns and counter 
with some acceptable arguments. 
</P>
<P>
The ZR-1, they said, survives only on brute strength. Handling is coarse, and 
the fit and finish barely American average. 
</P>
<P>
Porsche Carrera? A tired, 25-year-old design, they said, on the life-support 
system of modern technology. Also more expensive than the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Ferrari 348ts? A purist's car and a hard drive. And twice as expensive as the 
<ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Would that our road test could have produced an honest conclusion. Or, at the 
very least, some understanding of the near-total canonization of the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> by 
automotive magazines. 
</P>
<P>
But our test car had been their test car. 
</P>
<P>
It was production prototype 007 that had been ridden hard and put away wet by 
motoring journalists from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. Even dealers got 
to lap this one at 150-m.p.h. So, at 4,400 miles, the car was close to the end 
of its career as a performance punching bag. 
</P>
<P>
But we took the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Willow Springs Raceway</ORGANIZATION> anyway. 
</P>
<P>
Enough of its heart remained to be impressive on some smart laps of the 
facility's secondary circuit, the tight, often tortuous Streets of <LOCATION>Willow 
Springs</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The car has grip and balance, and when its ends get loose, the wagging is both 
predictable and correctable. 
</P>
<P>
Even adjusting to the car's oversteer snap-roll (created when over-correcting a 
drifting tail, failing to catch lateral forces and blushing when stored energy 
whips the car in the opposite direction), quickly becomes a reflex because the 
buildup and release is so constant. 
</P>
<P>
The steering, which is unassisted, seemed a little on the thick side, and that 
created a heavy turn-in. And there was a constant understeer. 
</P>
<P>
But on the highway, lightness and feel return, and the register is perfect. 
</P>
<P>
Track. Highway. Those dual personalities, and the broad division between polite 
jogger and Olympic athlete, is the enormous gift of the <ORGANIZATION>Acura NSX</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In traffic, around town, harumphing through clotted freeways or settled down on 
a pleasant and legal run along the coast to <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> is relaxed 
and terribly smooth. It is a touring car. 
</P>
<P>
But when the going gets tough and the tough get rambunctious, quick shifts and 
a heavy foot unleash that extra horsepower in the higher engine ranges. And the 
<ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> becomes a race car. 
</P>
<P>
Then that mid-engine sets up serious wails behind a driver's right ear and the 
moment rises to a breathtaking blur in search of a checkered flag. It is pure 
performance, even <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> pace, and certainly with <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>'s poise. 
</P>
<P>
In truth, being a <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> for the masses most certainly isn't a bad place to 
occupy. Especially when one considers that <ORGANIZATION>Acura</ORGANIZATION> has earned that heady spot in 
the Major Leagues from its first at bat. 
</P>
<P>
Honda officials acknowledge that with huge development costs and limited 
production numbers, the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> -- which goes on sale <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> -- will not be a 
money maker. But they do expect it to be an image-enhancer for the Acura line. 
</P>
<P>
It also is worth noting that <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> and Chevrolet are not known for 
nimbleness of product development. 
</P>
<P>
Japanese car builders are. 
</P>
<P>
And senior types at <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> are not reluctant to discuss tomorrow's NSX, 
enlarging that V-6, adding turbocharging and all-wheel drive -- and noting how 
quickly they can bring a second generation NSX to market. 
</P>
<P>
Then watch out. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
1991 ACURA NSX 
</P>
<P>
COST : 
</P>
<P>
* Base: <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY> 
</P>
<P>
* As tested <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY> (with automatic, <MONEY>$64,000</MONEY>) 
</P>
<P>
ENGINE 
</P>
<P>
* 3 liter, 24-valve V-6, developing 270 horsepower 
</P>
<P>
TYPE 
</P>
<P>
* Two-seat, mid-engined, high-performance sports car. No convertible available. 
</P>
<P>
PERFORMANCE 
</P>
<P>
* 0-60 m.p.h. (as tested), 5.9 seconds. 
</P>
<P>
* Top speed, (manufacturer's estimate) 168 m.p.h. 
</P>
<P>
* Fuel economy, <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> city-highway, 21 and 31 m.p.g. 
</P>
<P>
CURB WEIGHT 
</P>
<P>
* 2,985 pounds. 
</P>
<P>
THE GOOD 
</P>
<P>
* Handsome, fighter-plane looks. 
</P>
<P>
* Superb appointments, perfect ergonomics amid total comfort. 
</P>
<P>
* <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> for everyone. 
</P>
<P>
* Smooth, effortless, genuine high performer. 
</P>
<P>
* Or gentle street car. 
</P>
<P>
THE BAD 
</P>
<P>
* Does not outperform the competition. 
</P>
<P>
* Tendency to understeer. 
</P>
<P>
* Slightly heavy low-speed steering. 
</P>
<P>
THE UGLY 
</P>
<P>
* Still looking. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Acura NSX, a "Ferrari for the masses," is aimed directly at 
high-performance market. RANDY LEFFINGWELL / Los Angeles Times; Photo, Acura 
NSX interior 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Profile; Infobox 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06101238 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06101238 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  US; AUTO; MANUFACTURING; DELAY; PRODUCT; DEFECT; CAUSE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  General Motors Corp. is making only half as many of its sleek $64,000 Corvette
ZR1s after stopping production for nearly four months due to a faulty engine
part.;    The Bowling Green, Ky., assembly plant is building just nine ZR1s a
day because of a shortage of corrected camshafts, a component that regulates
fuel flow into the engine, Chevrolet spokesman Tom Hoxie said Monday.;    The
original oversized camshaft caused the engines to overheat under certain
conditions.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FLAW DELAYS CORVETTE PRODUCTION  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The problem was discovered in <DATE>November</DATE> when seven of the car's
370-horsepower engines broke down as workers revved the engines at the
assembly plant's shipping yard, <PERSON>Hoxie</PERSON> said.;    Chevrolet located the entire
batch of 500 ZR1s with engines made by <ORGANIZATION>Mercury Marine</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Stillwater</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>,
all at dealerships and in the shipping yard, and found that 17 had defective
engines, <PERSON>Hoxie</PERSON> said.;    There was no official recall as production was halted
from early <DATE>December</DATE> through <DATE>March 16</DATE>. The plant makes all types of Corvettes
and there were no layoffs due to the defect, he said.;    If it were not for
the production halt, about 1,500 cars would have been built in that time. The
normal production is 3,600 a year.;    "It's taking a while to catch up,"
<PERSON>Hoxie</PERSON> said. "Obviously it's going to affect the annual production.";    The
shortage may cause dealerships to raise the prices, an auto analyst said.;   
<PERSON>Chris Cedergren</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>J.D. Power &amp; Associates</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Agoura Hills</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, said the
No. 1 automaker handled the situation well by correcting the problem at the
assembly plant level, rather than selling the cars anyway and letting the
dealerships handle recalls.;    The ZR1 has a 32-valve, eight-cylinder
aluminum engine that can zoom from zero to 60 mph in 4.3 seconds.;    They
discovered the engines' camshafts were slightly oversized, but found that the
breakdowns were due to a combination of situations. The engines that blew out
had never been started up before and were stored in below-freezing
temperatures, <PERSON>Hoxie</PERSON> said.;    "There are a series of circumstances that had to
exist for it to happen," <PERSON>Hoxie</PERSON> said.;    <PERSON>John Harris</PERSON>, sales manager at <ORGANIZATION>Vermont
Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that his business was not affected by
the stopped production.;    "I didn't have a single one in stock," he said.
"Not a lot of people can afford those."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Detroit  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Home  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910410  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  384  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday April 10, 1991
00101238,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890925-0231 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-25-89 0217EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Cars:NewModels 4Takes   09-25 1014</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Cars: New Models, 4 Takes,1039</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Cars: New Models</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A sizzling hot <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>, a quartet of new
Japanese luxury cars, federally mandated safety devices and an
influx of four-door trucks from overseas top the new car and truck
news for the <DATE>1990</DATE> model year.
   While consumers are admiring all the new sheet metal and
technological changes for the new vehicles, they may find
themselves hit with a dose of sticker shock. Prices for <DATE>1990</DATE> cars
are higher, and part of the reason is safety.
   The federal government ruled that cars manufactured after <DATE>Sept.
1, 1989</DATE>, must have either supplemental air bags or automatic seat
belts on the driver's side.
   Cars with air bags also must have manually operated lap and
shoulder belts. By the <DATE>1994</DATE> model year, passive restraints _ either
air bags or automatic belts _ must be standard for the front-seat
passenger, too.
   All <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> models built in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, about <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of the
<ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION> fleet and just less than half of <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s will have
standard air bags this year.
   Costs of the systems, which manufacturers often decline to
reveal, could add hundreds of dollars to the price of a <DATE>1990</DATE> car.
Each of the <ORGANIZATION>Big Three</ORGANIZATION> has blamed air bags for part of its price
increases.
   In the truck market, importers were shaking in their boots in
<DATE>January</DATE> and <DATE>February</DATE>, worrying about whether the <ORGANIZATION>Treasury
Department</ORGANIZATION> would classify their sport-utility vehicles as cars,
with a 2{ percent tariff, or as trucks, with a duty 10 times
stiffer.
   The department ruled, in effect, that four-door vehicles are
primarily for passenger use, making them cars, and two-door
versions are mostly for commercial purposes, making them trucks.
   That ruling had a direct impact on the prices of the imported
trucks, which already had been hurt by a currency exchange rate
that ballooned prices of their vehicles. The number of two-door
sport-utility vehicles from overseas will drop substantially.
   In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> is making just 3,000 of its new
Corvette ZR-1 cars, which have engines packing 370 horsepower to
push the sports car from 0 to 60 mph in 4.2 seconds. The consumer
is going to pay the price for all that power, though. The sticker
on the ZR-1 carries a base price of <MONEY>$58,995</MONEY>.
   The much-publicized entry of two Japanese luxury car lines,
<ORGANIZATION>Nissan</ORGANIZATION>'s Infiniti and <ORGANIZATION>Toyota</ORGANIZATION>'s Lexus, has occurred. The cars, two
from each division, first were shown during <DATE>January</DATE> on the
auto-show circuit. They will be marketed through dealers separate
than those franchised by their parent companies, as are <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>'s
Acura cars now.
   Here's a nameplate-by-nameplate look at major manufacturers'
offerings for the <DATE>1990</DATE> model year in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>GENERAL MOTORS CORP.</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   A sizzling hot <ORGANIZATION>Corvette</ORGANIZATION>, a quartet of new
Japanese luxury cars, federally mandated safety devices and an
influx of four-door trucks from overseas top the new car and truck
news for the <DATE>1990</DATE> model year.
   While consumers are admiring all the new sheet metal and
technological changes for the new vehicles, they may find
themselves hit with a dose of sticker shock. Prices for <DATE>1990</DATE> cars
are higher, and part of the reason is safety.
   The federal government ruled that cars manufactured after <DATE>Sept.
1, 1989</DATE>, must have either supplemental air bags or automatic seat
belts on the driver's side.
   Cars with air bags also must have manually operated lap and
shoulder belts. By the <DATE>1994</DATE> model year, passive restraints _ either
air bags or automatic belts _ must be standard for the front-seat
passenger, too.
   All <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> models built in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, about <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of the
<ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION> fleet and just less than half of <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s will have
standard air bags this year.
   Costs of the systems, which manufacturers often decline to
reveal, could add hundreds of dollars to the price of a <DATE>1990</DATE> car.
Each of the <ORGANIZATION>Big Three</ORGANIZATION> has blamed air bags for part of its price
increases.
   In the truck market, importers were shaking in their boots in
<DATE>January</DATE> and <DATE>February</DATE>, worrying about whether the <ORGANIZATION>Treasury
Department</ORGANIZATION> would classify their sport-utility vehicles as cars,
with a 2{ percent tariff, or as trucks, with a duty 10 times
stiffer.
   The department ruled, in effect, that four-door vehicles are
primarily for passenger use, making them cars, and two-door
versions are mostly for commercial purposes, making them trucks.
   That ruling had a direct impact on the prices of the imported
trucks, which already had been hurt by a currency exchange rate
that ballooned prices of their vehicles. The number of two-door
sport-utility vehicles from overseas will drop substantially.
   In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> is making just 3,000 of its new
Corvette ZR-1 cars, which have engines packing 370 horsepower to
push the sports car from 0 to 60 mph in 4.2 seconds. The consumer
is going to pay the price for all that power, though. The sticker
on the ZR-1 carries a base price of <MONEY>$58,995</MONEY>.
   The much-publicized entry of two Japanese luxury car lines,
<ORGANIZATION>Nissan</ORGANIZATION>'s Infiniti and <ORGANIZATION>Toyota</ORGANIZATION>'s Lexus, has occurred. The cars, two
from each division, first were shown during <DATE>January</DATE> on the
auto-show circuit. They will be marketed through dealers separate
than those franchised by their parent companies, as are <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>'s
Acura cars now.
   Here's a nameplate-by-nameplate look at major manufacturers'
offerings for the <DATE>1990</DATE> model year in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901114-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-14-90 1523EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-AcuraNSX Adv18   11-14 0607</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Acura NSX, Adv18,0812</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv18</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Sunday, Nov. 18, and thereafter</NOTE>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto DT1 of Nov. 13</NOTE>
<HEAD>Acura's `Little Ferrari': An Eye- and Money-Catcher</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   While some car buyers are drawn to big rebates,
others can't resist paying <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> over list price for a new set of
wheels.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Acura NSX</ORGANIZATION> is commanding that kind of money from those who
want an exotic car without a Ferrari or Lamborghini price tag.
   ``It's a bargain,'' said sales manager <PERSON>Betsy Volaric</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Sunshine
Acura</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Farmington Hills</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>, which looks a bit like a shrunken <PERSON>Ferrari Testarosa</PERSON>,
carries a list price of <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY> with a manual transmission and
<MONEY>$63,000</MONEY> for one with an automatic.
   But since <ORGANIZATION>Acura</ORGANIZATION>, the luxury division of <ORGANIZATION>Honda Motor Co</ORGANIZATION>. Ltd. of
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, plans to import just 3,000 of them a year, demand is far
outpacing supply.
   That pumps up the price.
   Premiums on cars are nothing new to the auto industry. Last
year, buyers shelled out up to <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> for the hard-to-get <ORGANIZATION>Mazda
Miata</ORGANIZATION>, which carried a base price of <MONEY>$13,800</MONEY>.
   Volaric said her dealership, one of 300 Acura dealers in the
country, is tacking <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> onto the price of the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>,
because that's what the market will bear.
   ``Anybody who is familiar with the exotic car market realizes
that <MONEY>$85,000</MONEY> is a bargain,'' she said. Ferraris and Lamborghinis
begin at more than <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> and stretch past <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> each, before
any premium.
   Acura spokesman <PERSON>Mike Spencer</PERSON> said dealers in markets with high
exotic-car interest, such as <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, are getting up
to <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> for an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> - <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> over sticker price.
   ``Legally, we can't tell the dealers what to sell the cars
for,'' he said. ``At the same time, they look at this as `Geez, if
Isell the car to a speculator for <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY> and he turns around and
sells it for <MONEY>$80,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$90,000</MONEY>, who's the fool here?'''
   A fool has no place behind the wheel of an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>. The sleek,
two-seater packs a 3-liter, V-6 engine which puts out 270
horsepower. It's top speed is rated around 165 mph, and it can go
from a standing start to 60 mph in about 5.5 seconds.
   Tooling around <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> freeways in an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> causes normally vacant
highway stares to come alive. Even at highway speeds, motorists
hover around the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> for a closer look.
   In a recent test drive:
   -The driver of a <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> RX-7 on the right looked for a minute,
dropped back for a different view, came up on the left for another
peek and moved to the front to take a look at the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> in his
rearview mirror.
   Afterwards, he dropped back to the right, nodded his head up and
down vigorously and flashed a thumbs-up sign.
   -A load of what appeared to be teen-agers in an Oldsmobile
pulled alongside and accelerated, appearing to dare a highway race.
The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> is a conspicuous car and the offer was ignored.
   Parked at a local mall, the car was a magnet for nearly everyone
who walked by, including car crazies and store clerks.
   ``I thought it was a Ferrari,'' said <PERSON>Denise DiDonato</PERSON>, of
<LOCATION>Rochester Hills</LOCATION>, a cosmetics clerk at <ORGANIZATION>Saks Fifth Avenue</ORGANIZATION> in a
suburban <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> shopping mall. ``It's cute, very cute.''
   She owns a <DATE>1990</DATE> Lincoln Town Car - 56.8 inches longer and 1,000
pounds heavier than an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Kevin Corcoran</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Franklin</LOCATION>, could have been doing an
advertisement for the car: ``It's extraordinarily flashy and
reasonably priced as far as these things go. There's a lot of
Italian in it.''
   Corcoran owns a pickup, in which he spends most of his highway
time, and a <PERSON>McLaren</PERSON>, an extremely low-volume exotic sports car.
   With a target volume of 3,000 annually, the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> doesn't pose a
significant volume threat to any car now being sold in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.
   It's priced somewhere around a <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> 911, the <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION>
300-series, a <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> 7-series or a Chevrolet Corvette ZR-1, the
hottest car made by a major American manufacturer.
   The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> doesn't look nearly as muscular as the ZR-1, and it
isn't. The ZR-1's 5.7-liter, V-8 engine produces 375 horsepower,
nearly <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> more than the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>.
   The all-aluminum <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> makes up for some of that difference in
weight, coming in at 3,010 pounds compared with the ZR-1 at 3,465
pounds.
   Canadian visitor <PERSON>Craig Donnelly</PERSON> is an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> fan. He said he had a
poster of a black one back home in <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION>, where he also has a
Pontiac Sunbird.
   ``It's got the same size engine as that,'' he said nodding to
the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>, ``but it doesn't go like that.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Nov. 18</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   While some car buyers are drawn to big rebates,
others can't resist paying <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> over list price for a new set of
wheels.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Acura NSX</ORGANIZATION> is commanding that kind of money from those who
want an exotic car without a Ferrari or Lamborghini price tag.
   ``It's a bargain,'' said sales manager <PERSON>Betsy Volaric</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Sunshine
Acura</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Farmington Hills</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>, which looks a bit like a shrunken <PERSON>Ferrari Testarosa</PERSON>,
carries a list price of <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY> with a manual transmission and
<MONEY>$63,000</MONEY> for one with an automatic.
   But since <ORGANIZATION>Acura</ORGANIZATION>, the luxury division of <ORGANIZATION>Honda Motor Co</ORGANIZATION>. Ltd. of
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, plans to import just 3,000 of them a year, demand is far
outpacing supply.
   That pumps up the price.
   Premiums on cars are nothing new to the auto industry. Last
year, buyers shelled out up to <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> for the hard-to-get <ORGANIZATION>Mazda
Miata</ORGANIZATION>, which carried a base price of <MONEY>$13,800</MONEY>.
   Volaric said her dealership, one of 300 Acura dealers in the
country, is tacking <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> onto the price of the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>,
because that's what the market will bear.
   ``Anybody who is familiar with the exotic car market realizes
that <MONEY>$85,000</MONEY> is a bargain,'' she said. Ferraris and Lamborghinis
begin at more than <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> and stretch past <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> each, before
any premium.
   Acura spokesman <PERSON>Mike Spencer</PERSON> said dealers in markets with high
exotic-car interest, such as <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, are getting up
to <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> for an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> - <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> over sticker price.
   ``Legally, we can't tell the dealers what to sell the cars
for,'' he said. ``At the same time, they look at this as `Geez, if
Isell the car to a speculator for <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY> and he turns around and
sells it for <MONEY>$80,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$90,000</MONEY>, who's the fool here?'''
   A fool has no place behind the wheel of an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>. The sleek,
two-seater packs a 3-liter, V-6 engine which puts out 270
horsepower. It's top speed is rated around 165 mph, and it can go
from a standing start to 60 mph in about 5.5 seconds.
   Tooling around <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> freeways in an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> causes normally vacant
highway stares to come alive. Even at highway speeds, motorists
hover around the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> for a closer look.
   In a recent test drive:
   -The driver of a <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> RX-7 on the right looked for a minute,
dropped back for a different view, came up on the left for another
peek and moved to the front to take a look at the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> in his
rearview mirror.
   Afterwards, he dropped back to the right, nodded his head up and
down vigorously and flashed a thumbs-up sign.
   -A load of what appeared to be teen-agers in an Oldsmobile
pulled alongside and accelerated, appearing to dare a highway race.
The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> is a conspicuous car and the offer was ignored.
   Parked at a local mall, the car was a magnet for nearly everyone
who walked by, including car crazies and store clerks.
   ``I thought it was a Ferrari,'' said <PERSON>Denise DiDonato</PERSON>, of
<LOCATION>Rochester Hills</LOCATION>, a cosmetics clerk at <ORGANIZATION>Saks Fifth Avenue</ORGANIZATION> in a
suburban <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> shopping mall. ``It's cute, very cute.''
   She owns a <DATE>1990</DATE> Lincoln Town Car - 56.8 inches longer and 1,000
pounds heavier than an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Kevin Corcoran</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Franklin</LOCATION>, could have been doing an
advertisement for the car: ``It's extraordinarily flashy and
reasonably priced as far as these things go. There's a lot of
Italian in it.''
   Corcoran owns a pickup, in which he spends most of his highway
time, and a <PERSON>McLaren</PERSON>, an extremely low-volume exotic sports car.
   With a target volume of 3,000 annually, the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> doesn't pose a
significant volume threat to any car now being sold in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.
   It's priced somewhere around a <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> 911, the <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION>
300-series, a <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> 7-series or a Chevrolet Corvette ZR-1, the
hottest car made by a major American manufacturer.
   The <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> doesn't look nearly as muscular as the ZR-1, and it
isn't. The ZR-1's 5.7-liter, V-8 engine produces 375 horsepower,
nearly <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> more than the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>.
   The all-aluminum <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> makes up for some of that difference in
weight, coming in at 3,010 pounds compared with the ZR-1 at 3,465
pounds.
   Canadian visitor <PERSON>Craig Donnelly</PERSON> is an <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION> fan. He said he had a
poster of a black one back home in <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION>, where he also has a
Pontiac Sunbird.
   ``It's got the same size engine as that,'' he said nodding to
the <ORGANIZATION>NSX</ORGANIZATION>, ``but it doesn't go like that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900515-0253 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-15-90 1609EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Viper     05-15 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Viper,0659</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chrysler Ready To Announce New, Pumped-Up Sports Car</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DT4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler Corp.</ORGANIZATION> has decided to produce its
proposed Viper sports car featuring a 10-cylinder engine, a source
said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, a move apparently designed to polish the image of the
struggling carmaker.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Dodge Viper</ORGANIZATION>, equipped with an engine originally designed for
truck use, will go into extremely low-volume production late next
year for the <DATE>1992</DATE> model year, said a company source speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   ``Anything that shows people that <ORGANIZATION>Dodge</ORGANIZATION> is back in the
performance business is good news,'' said <PERSON>David Slone</PERSON>, general
sales manager of <PERSON>Lynn Hickey Dodge</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION>.
   A Viper prototype was introduced last year at an annual auto
show in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> and drew huge crowds. The two-seat convertible is a
throwback to the era of sleek, muscular sports cars with few
electronic gadgets.
   The prototype has been part of a six-city tour this <DATE>spring</DATE>
during which <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> executives have touted the quality of the
company's vehicles, comparing them favorably with those made by
Japanese automakers.
   The tour winds up <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, where <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> Chairman
<PERSON>Lee Iacocca</PERSON> is expected to announce that the Viper will go into
production.
   Such an announcement would come as <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> car sales and
profits slip and as the company struggles to carve <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY>
from its annual <MONEY>$26 billion</MONEY> budget.
   The cost of the Viper project hasn't been pinpointed. Despite
that expense at a time when the company is trimming back, analysts
and dealers on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> were enthusiastic about the project, not
only because of the exotic nature of the car, but because of the
traffic it can draw to dealerships.
   <PERSON>Slone</PERSON> said he already has noticed an increase in traffic through
his showroom just because of media attention the Viper has received.
   ``We've had people wanting to put deposits down on it,'' he said.
   The car's price won't be announced until just before it hits the
showrooms. AutoWeek magazine said it could be in the <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> range.
   The Viper would be entering the exotic sports-car market,
broadly comprised of the Corvette ZR-1, some BMWs and Porsches.
   No firm performance statistics were available, but AutoWeek
magazine reported that with the V-10 engine, the Viper could go
from a standing start to 100 mph in less than 10 seconds. The ZR-1,
the hottest Corvette ever, takes 11.5 seconds to get to 100 mph,
according to a <ORGANIZATION>Road &amp; Track</ORGANIZATION> magazine road test.
   ``There is an enthusiasts' market out there,'' said auto analyst
<PERSON>Mary Anne Sudol</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Fitch Investors Service Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. ``I
think there is room in the market for it (Viper). I think the hot
cars carry fairly nice (profit) margins and you wouldn't have to
put an incentive on them.
   ``I think it will make people sit up and notice <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> even
though there aren't many (Vipers) around. It's what they can do in
styling and performance.''
   The prototype has distinctive door panels with chrome-plated
exhaust pipes running below them. A spy photo appearing in the <DATE>June</DATE>
issue of Car and Driver magazine shows a Viper without the
side-mounted pipes.
   The source said all major components of the car would be made by
<ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION>. The source declined to reveal the final assembly site,
but said it would be an existing <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> factory.
   Production figures weren't available, but it could be as low as
a few hundred a year. By contrast, <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> sold about
24,000 Corvettes last year, before the introduction of the ZR-1
model.
   <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> has said that the Viper was the first project to result
from the carmaker's conceptual design and rendering system. The
computer-driven system could cut by <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> the amount of time
needed to bring a totally new car to market, <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> officials
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910521-0057
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910521-0057.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   AUTOMOBILES
   ----
   By Krystal Miller
</HL>
<DATE>
05/21/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<CO>
   C GM
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
AUTO PARTS AND EQUIPMENT INCLUDING TIRES (AUP)
AUTOMOBILES (AUT)
CHEMICALS, PLASTICS (CHM)
ENVIRONMENT (ENV)
</IN>
<NS>
ENVIRONMENTAL NEWS (ENV)
</NS>
<RE>
MICHIGAN (MI)
</RE>
<LP>
   Rain Poses Acid Test
   For Auto Exteriors
                                                                                                       

</LP>
<TEXT>
   ACID RAIN threatens lakes and forests, many scientists
say, but what about cars?
   An <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Protection Agency</ORGANIZATION> study finds that acid
rain etches dull-looking spots into a car's paint. That's
because the acids in rainwater don't evaporate, but instead
become more concentrated as the raindrops dry. Heat from the
sun or engine increases the damage.
   The spots are hard to detect on light-colored vehicles but
are easily found on darker cars, especially black ones. The
spots are also easier to see under fluorescent lights than in
sunlight.
   Car owners living on the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION> are most likely to see
the dull spots on their cars, because the region's rain is
more acidic than in the rest of the country. However, people
living elsewhere will probably detect spots if they examine
their cars closely.
   "There is little doubt that the problem is widespread,"
says <PERSON>Edward Edney</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> researcher who has studied the
effects of acid rain and fog. The only cure is prevention:
keeping cars out of rain or fog, or drying them immediately
after exposure.
   Some auto makers are working with paint suppliers to find
a solution. <ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION>, for example, each
have developed a clear protective coating to go on top of
paint. <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> says its coating, developed about two years ago, is
effective at spot prevention even though it wasn't developed
specifically to combat acid rain. The coating is currently
being used on about half of its vehicles, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> says, and will
be put on more in the future.
   <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION>, which introduced its coating in <DATE>February</DATE>, says
it was designed to protect against acid rain and works well
in most regions of the country. <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> uses it in three
assembly plants and expects to use it in most of its
facilities by <DATE>July</DATE>.
                                                                                                       

   They Help You to Pick
   Peaches, Not Lemons
                                                                                                       

   THE HIGH PRICE of new cars has many buyers looking for
used ones, but how do you avoid getting taken? Try calling an
expert.
   A growing number of firms will, for a fee, inspect used
cars and tell potential buyers how much they're actually
worth. Car Checkers of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, for example, inspects 3,500
electrical and mechanical components of used cars. The
company also determines whether a car has been involved in an
accident and whether it's starting to rust. The inspection
costs between <MONEY>$75</MONEY> and <MONEY>$100</MONEY>, and takes about an hour.
   "Just listening and looking isn't enough anymore," says
<PERSON>Lee S. Geller</PERSON>, vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Car Checkers</ORGANIZATION>, in
<LOCATION>Bridgewater</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION> Business has jumped <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> since the recession
began, he says. Auto Critic of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, performs a
90-point inspection for between <MONEY>$54</MONEY> and <MONEY>$79</MONEY>, grading such
components as the battery, air conditioner and transmission
on a scale of A (high quality) to F (poor quality). <PERSON>Patrick
A. Ludwick</PERSON>, president, expects the two-year-old company to
earn its first profit this year.
   Most companies that inspect used cars send technicians to
the vehicle's location, even if it's a dealer's lot. While it
seems this might irk dealers, the companies claim they're
welcome. "Many dealers pay us" to determine the quality and
value of used-car trade-ins, <PERSON>Mr. Geller</PERSON> says.
   "These companies can serve a purpose," says <PERSON>Marion Gorton</PERSON>
of the <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> attorney general's office. "The inspection
gives consumers the opportunity to find out what's obviously
wrong with the car." The companies don't do repairs, and most
require customers to sign a disclaimer releasing the firms of
liability in case a highly rated car turns out to be a lemon.
                                                                                                       

   It's Very, Very Fast,
   But It Isn't Moving
                                                                                                       

   GENERAL MOTORS' highly touted Corvette ZR-1 once fetched
as much as <MONEY>$80,000</MONEY> -- a whopping <MONEY>$15,862</MONEY> above its suggested
retail price. But now, some dealers are having trouble
selling the car -- even below retail.
   The ZR-1, nicknamed King of the Hill, was a hit with
auto-enthusiast magazines. They loved the 32-valve,
eight-cylinder, 370-horsepower aluminum engine that zips the
car from 0 to 60 miles per hour in a bone-jarring 4.3
seconds. <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> won't disclose the number of ZR-1 models -- as
opposed to regular Corvettes -- it has sold this year, but
concedes that sales have slowed.
   So why has demand for <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s most exotic and expensive car
cooled? The auto maker's <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> division contends that
after a year on the market, the ZR-1 is no longer a new, hot
item. "It's a natural thing in the marketplace," says a
spokesman for the division, who also cites the effects of the
recession.
   But a mechanical snafu also may have damped consumer
enthusiasm. <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> had to stop selling the car for 3 1/2 months
while correcting a problem -- it turned out to be some
defective camshafts -- that caused some engines to overheat
and "seize," or self-destruct.
                                                                                                       

   Buy a Trendy Couch
   And Get a Car to Match
                                                                                                       
