<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881118-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-18-88 1956EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MedicineVolcano     11-18 0672</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Medicine Volcano,0688</SECOND>
<HEAD>USGS Finds Hints Of Renewed Activity Beneath Medicine Lake Volcano</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MENLO PARK, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A swarm of microearthquakes and
discovery of a possible underground pool of molten rock provide
hints that <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s dormant Medicine Lake Volcano might be
reawakening, scientists said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   However, there is no evidence an eruption is likely, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Geological Survey scientists said.
   ``It's suspicious enough to put in a new network (of seismic
monitors) but not suspicious enough to cause alarm,'' said <PERSON>John R.
Evans</PERSON>, a seismologist at the agency's western regional headquarters.
   ``If you identify a zone of molten magma beneath a volcano, that
obviously increases the potential for some future activity,'' said
geologist <PERSON>Bob Tilling</PERSON>, who headed the agency's response to the <DATE>1980</DATE>
eruptions of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>. ``There's no evidence now for any
eruption at all. The only prudent thing is to keep monitoring it.''
   The evidence is ambiguous, so it's ``premature to suggest it
represents a reawakening of the volcano,'' said <PERSON>C. Dan Miller</PERSON>, a
geologist with the <ORGANIZATION>USGS Cascades Volcano Observatory</ORGANIZATION>.
   Medicine Lake Volcano is a gently sloped volcano, about 20 miles
in diameter, in the southern <ORGANIZATION>Cascade Range</ORGANIZATION> about 35 miles northeast
of <LOCATION>Mount Shasta</LOCATION>, 60 miles north of Lassen Peak and roughly 280 miles
northeast of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Medicine Lake, a recreational lake, sits
at an elevation of 6,674 feet on the floor of the volcano's
four-by-seven-mile crater, called a caldera.
   The nearest town, <LOCATION>Tulelake</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, is 25 miles to the northeast.
   The volcano last erupted about 850 to 875 years ago, forming
small lava flows and cinder cones around several volcanic vents,
<PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said. Between 1,200 and 875 years ago, it had several
explosive eruptions, he said.
   <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said the recent quakes, detection of the possible magma
chamber and a slight drop in the elevation of the caldera floor in
recent months may indicate magma is moving inside the mountain. But
<PERSON>Miller</PERSON> and <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> agreed the quakes also could have been caused by
non-volcanic stretching of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s crust.
   The <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> installed six new seismometers after the single previous
seismometer detected a swarm of about 200 earthquakes <DATE>Sept. 29</DATE> and
30, <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said. Before then, only one earthquake, in <DATE>October 1986</DATE>,
had been detected at the volcano since the agency started monitoring
in <DATE>1981</DATE>, geologist <PERSON>Steve Walter</PERSON> said.
   The <DATE>September</DATE> quakes were shallow and most were microearthquakes
measuring less than 2 on the Richter scale. Four exceeded magnitude
3, including one jolt that reached 4.2, <PERSON>Walter</PERSON> said. Three other
small quakes occurred <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE> and <DATE>Nov. 11</DATE> and 12, he added.
   Evidence for the small magma chamber just northeast of the lake
was found by <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> and geophysicists <PERSON>H. Mahadeva Iver</PERSON> and <PERSON>Phil
Dawson</PERSON>, using the shock xwaves of small explosions to make a picture
of the inside of the volcano.
   They found an area in which shock waves moved slowly, suggesting
they had moved through magma, <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said. However, <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said it
also is possible the waves were slowed by porous rock permeated by
hot water.
   The quakes ``may have recorded the intrusion of new magma into
this part of the volcano,'' <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, <PERSON>Iyer</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dawson</PERSON> said in a study
presented at their agency's Geohazards '88 symposium
   The possible magma pool is small, measuring only about two cubic
miles, compared with a volume of about 200 cubic miles for the magma
chamber believed to be beneath the <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION> caldera near <LOCATION>Mammoth
Lakes</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said.
   Walter and <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> scientist <PERSON>Dan Dzurisin</PERSON> measured the
elevation of benchmarks on the volcano before the quakes, and found
the mountain had ``deflated'' by seven inches since the last
measurements in <DATE>1954</DATE>. After the <DATE>September</DATE> quakes, it had fallen an
additional one-third inch.
   Such deflation suggests magma may have moved outward into cracks
in surrounding rocks, <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said.
   A much higher level of such activity at <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION>, along with
much bigger swarms of quakes in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, failed to result in
any eruption there, <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> and Tilling said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06163112 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06163112 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; OUT OF HARM'S WAY -- Two mothers and their
children await aid after evacuation Monday. The tribal refugees from the
impending disaster were among thousands of Filipinos living near the volcano,
as well as most Americans at Clark Air Base, who have been forced to flee.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; FORECAST; PHILIPPINES  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mount Pinatubo, the Philippine volcano that erupted Saturday after six
centuries of quiet, is likely to explode in the next few days or weeks with
force comparable to the Mount St. Helens explosion, a U.S. government
scientist said Monday.;    "I think we could see a major explosive eruption
any time," said Peter Lipman, a volcanologist at the U.S. Geological Survey
office in Menlo Park. Lipman is in daily contact with five USGS scientists in
the Philippines who have been studying the volcano since April, when it first
stirred.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HUGE ERUPTION LIKELY IN PHILIPPINES 'ANY
TIME'  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     A huge cloud of ash-laden steam rose up to 11,500 feet above the volcano
today, spreading ash over a six-mile radius, the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute of
Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology said.;    If it does erupt, the deadly hot ash
produced by the volcano could sweep across adjoining <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, he said.
Also in peril are the 350,000 residents of <LOCATION>Angeles City</LOCATION>, where the air base is
located, about 50 miles north of Manila.;    Even if the volcano does not
erupt, the threat of eruption is likely to keep the base closed for weeks at
least, <PERSON>Lipman</PERSON> said.;    Scientists doubt it's more than coincidence that the
eruption is occurring at the same time as the Mount Unzen volcano in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, he
said.;    The five <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> scientists are among the few remaining people at <ORGANIZATION>Clark
Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, which was evacuated along with thousands of Filipinos living near
the volcano.;    The researchers, along with 10 Filipino scientists and their
equipment, today  moved to a bunker on the east edge of the air base, 12 miles
from the volcano, where they should be safe from ash avalanches.;    <LOCATION>Mount
Pinatubo</LOCATION> is typical of hundreds of volcanoes that make up the "Ring of Fire"
on the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> coasts of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Americas</LOCATION>. (These volcanoes -- including
<LOCATION>Mount Lassen</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Shasta County</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Mount Rainier</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, all in the <ORGANIZATION>Cascade Range</ORGANIZATION> -- arise where one of the earth's immense
crust plates is slowly diving beneath another.);    <ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION>'s last eruption,
600 years ago, is thought to have yielded at least as much molten rock -- half
a cubic kilometer -- as <LOCATION>Mount St. Helens</LOCATION> did when it erupted in <DATE>1980</DATE>. Until
volcanologists' attention was drawn to it by a cluster of earthquakes beneath
the volcano this <DATE>spring</DATE>, it had not been studied well.;    Other recent
volcanoes that erupted on the same scale were <LOCATION>El Chichon</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE> and
<ORGANIZATION>Nevado del Ruiz</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985.</DATE>;    If it does have a massive eruption,
<ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION>'s primary means of causing death and destruction would be hellish
avalanches of hot ash -- 1,000 degrees or more, flowing and billowing at up to
100 mph, engulfing and searing all in their path.;    "In the worst case, a
really big eruption, all of <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> could be covered" with
glowing ash, <PERSON>Lipman</PERSON> said.;    Just being caught in a cloud of ash blowing off
the avalanche is fatal. That is what killed 38 people in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> last week.;   
Such ash also would wreak havoc with the engines of planes at the air base,
<PERSON>Lipman</PERSON> said.;    Planes flying through clouds of volcanic ash --
indistinguishable on radar from rain clouds -- run the risk of having their
engines stalled by the grit.;    So far, the winds have blown ash away from
the base. But winds of the <DATE>summer</DATE> monsoon weather pattern, expected to begin
any day, would send ash directly toward the base.;    The volcano's activity
-- measured by seismometers detecting slight earthquakes in its molten rock
plumbing system -- is increasing in a way that suggests a large eruption is
imminent, <PERSON>Lipman</PERSON> said.;    The scientists also are monitoring tiltmeters on
the volcano's slopes, to watch it swell as magma builds inside. On clear days
they fly above the crater to measure sulfur emissions.;    Their predictions
might be a false alarm -- the volcano may have done its worst already. But it
would take several weeks of declining quakes and sulfur emissions before
scientists would be reasonably confident that the military could return to the
base.;    Volcanologists know of no reason the volcano's activity could be
linked to the volcano in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, which is of comparable size.;    "No reputable
scientist I know of" is drawing a connection between the two, <PERSON>Lipman</PERSON> said.;   
More than 500 volcanoes have erupted in historical time, he noted. "Two out of
500 is no big deal."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DAVID ANSLEY, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910611  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  773  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday June 11, 1991
00163112,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06163095 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06163095 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Map; MAP: Mercury News. Source: Seattle Times, World Book Encyclopedia; The
Pacific 'Ring of Fire'; Volcanoes that ring the Pacific Ocean rise from the
same fundamental process: Sections of the earth's surface, called plates, are
constantly moving over a layer of partially melted rock. Volcanic activity
occurs when plates collide or move apart, and the tremendous pressures in the
earth's interior melt the rock and push it toward the surface.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PHILIPPINES; VOLCANO; FORECAST; EARTH; SCIENCE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mount Pinatubo, the Philippine volcano that erupted Saturday after six
centuries of quiet, is likely to explode in the next few days or weeks with
force comparable to the Mount St. Helens explosion, a U.S. government
scientist said Monday.;    "I think we could see a major explosive eruption
anytime," said Peter Lipman, a volcanologist at the U.S. Geological Survey
office in Menlo Park. Lipman is in daily contact with five USGS scientists in
the Philippines who have been studying the volcano since April, when it first
stirred.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PHILIPPINE VOLCANO SET TO BLOW
EXPERT PREDICTS BLAST TO MATCH MOUNT ST. HELENS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See related story page 10A of this section.;  SETTING THE RECORD STRAIGHT
(publ. 6/12/91, pg. 2A);  Because of an editor's error, a story in Tuesday's
editions may have been misleading about the location of Mount Lassen. It is in
the Cascade Range, a continuation of the Sierra Nevada.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     If it does erupt, the deadly hot ash produced by the volcano could sweep
across adjoining <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, he said. Also in peril are the 350,000
residents of <LOCATION>Angeles City</LOCATION>, where the air base is located, about 50 miles north
of Manila.;    Even if the volcano does not erupt, the threat of eruption is
likely to keep the base closed for weeks at least, <PERSON>Lipman</PERSON> said.;    Scientists
doubt it's more than coincidence that the eruption is occurring at the same
time as the Mount Unzen volcano in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, he said.;    The five <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION>
scientists are among the few remaining people at <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, which was
evacuated along with thousands of Filipinos living near the volcano.;    The
researchers, along with 10 Filipino scientists and their equipment, today 
moved to a bunker on the east edge of the air base, 12 miles from the volcano,
where they should be safe from ash avalanches.;    <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION> is typical
of hundreds of volcanoes that make up the "Ring of Fire" on the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> coasts
of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Americas</LOCATION>. (These volcanoes -- including <LOCATION>Mount Lassen</LOCATION> in the
<LOCATION>Sierra Nevada</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Mount Rainier</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> in the <ORGANIZATION>Cascade Range</ORGANIZATION> --
arise where one of the earth's immense crust plates is slowly diving beneath
another.);    <ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION>'s last eruption, 600 years ago, is thought to have
yielded at least as much molten rock -- half a cubic kilometer -- as <LOCATION>Mount St.
Helens</LOCATION> did when it erupted in <DATE>1980</DATE>. Until volcanologists' attention was drawn
to it by a cluster of earthquakes beneath the volcano this <DATE>spring</DATE>, it had not
been studied well.;    Waves of hot ash;  Other recent volcanoes that erupted
on the same scale were <LOCATION>El Chichon</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Nevado del Ruiz</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985.</DATE>;    If it does have a massive eruption, <ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION>'s primary
means of causing death and destruction would be hellish avalanches of hot ash
-- 1,000 degrees or more, flowing and billowing at up to 100 mph, engulfing
and searing all in their path.;    "In the worst case, a really big eruption,
all of <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> could be covered" with glowing ash, <PERSON>Lipman</PERSON> said.; 
  Just being caught in a cloud of ash blowing off the avalanche is fatal. That
is what killed 38 people in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> <DATE>last week.</DATE>;    Risk to planes;  Such ash
also would wreak havoc with the engines of planes at the air base, <PERSON>Lipman</PERSON>
said.;    Planes flying through clouds of volcanic ash -- indistinguishable on
radar from rain clouds -- run the risk of having their engines stalled by the
grit.;    So far, the winds have blown ash away from the base. But winds of
the <DATE>summer</DATE> monsoon weather pattern, expected to begin any day, would send ash
directly toward the base.;    The volcano's activity -- measured by
seismometers detecting slight earthquakes in its molten rock plumbing system
-- is increasing in a way that suggests a large eruption is imminent, <PERSON>Lipman</PERSON>
said.;    The scientists also are monitoring tiltmeters on the volcano's
slopes, to watch it swell as magma builds inside. On clear days they fly above
the crater to measure sulfur emissions.;    No link to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>;  Their
predictions might be a false alarm -- the volcano may have done its worst
already. But it would take several weeks of declining quakes and sulfur
emissions before scientists would be reasonably confident that the military
could return to the base.;    Volcanologists know of no reason the volcano's
activity could be linked to the volcano in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, which is of comparable
size.;    "No reputable scientist I know of" is drawing a connection between
the two, <PERSON>Lipman</PERSON> said.;    More than 500 volcanoes have erupted in historical
time, he noted. "Two out of 500 is no big deal."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DAVID ANSLEY, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910611  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  819  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, June 11, 1991
00163095,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901027-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-27-90 1401EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SierraVolcano     10-27 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sierra Volcano,0745</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quakes Gets Subdued Response From Neighbors of Long Valley Volcano</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eight years after a volcano scare incited
fear, anger and economic gloom in Sierra resorts, residents are
nonchalant about renewed underground lava movement that is
triggering thousands of tiny earthquakes.
   Scientists say there is a very small chance of a volcanic
eruption. But most of the quakes are too small to be felt, so ``you
don't really think about it,'' said <PERSON>Pam Murphy</PERSON>, spokeswoman for
Mammoth Mountain Ski Area.
   ``You can get hit by a car,'' she said. ``You can be in a plane
crash. The chances of those are a lot higher than the chance of
being killed by an earthquake or a volcano.''
   ``People who are frightened left long ago. I don't believe it's
a conscious concern of anyone in the community,'' said Mammoth
Lakes Mayor <PERSON>Gordon Alper</PERSON>.
   The resort town's 4,700 permanent residents live in <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION>,
a 19-mile-long, 9-mile-wide volcanic crater known as a caldera. It
is located on the east slope of the <LOCATION>Sierra Nevada</LOCATION> range 250 miles
north of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. The <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s crust is being stretched apart in
the region, allowing molten rock to fill half-mile-wide chambers
under the caldera.
   The valley was created 730,000 years ago by one of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s most
powerful eruptions, a blast that spewed 600 times more material
than the <DATE>May 1980</DATE> eruption of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state.
   Eruptions somewhat smaller than <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>' happened 550
years ago at the Inyo craters, which span <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION>'s north rim,
and 650 years ago at the Mono craters, several miles north of the
caldera.
   Despite the current activity, the probability of a major
earthquake or a volcanic eruption in the area is ``less than <PERCENT>1
percent</PERCENT> each year,'' said <PERSON>David Hill</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>
geophysicist in charge of research at <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION>.
   Mono County <PERSON>Sheriff Martin Strelneck</PERSON> called such estimates ``a
scientific guessing game,'' and said area residents rarely discuss
the latest swarm of earthquakes, which started in <DATE>May 1989</DATE>.
   That low-key attitude contrasts with feelings of anxiety, denial
and hostility when thousands of quakes - some exceeding 6 on the
Richter scale - rocked the area from <DATE>1979</DATE> to <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   During that period, subterranean molten rock pushed upward,
lifting the caldera's floor. As a result, the <ORGANIZATION>Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>
issued a ``notice of potential volcanic hazard'' for <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION> in
<DATE>May 1982</DATE>.
   That warning, coupled with jarring earthquakes, damaged tourism
and aggravated a recession in the once-booming real estate market.
   ``The community overreacted,'' <PERSON>Murphy</PERSON> said. Residents accused
journalists of sensationalizing the possibility of an eruption and
denounced scientists for scaring people.
   ``Initially we thought this was a big ploy for them to get
funding from <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>,'' <PERSON>Alper</PERSON> said.
   The hazard notice was rescinded in <DATE>1984</DATE> after the beleaguered
<ORGANIZATION>Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> changed its warning system and seismic activity
diminished, reducing the possibility of an eruption.
   Swarms of thousands of small quakes resumed 18 months ago and
continue to rattle <ORGANIZATION>Mammoth Lakes</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>June Lake</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lee Vining</PERSON> and other
<LOCATION>Mono County</LOCATION> resort towns. The temblors, most measuring 1 to 3 on
the Richter scale, started beneath <ORGANIZATION>Mammoth Mountain</ORGANIZATION>. In <DATE>September
1989</DATE>, they shifted to the caldera, where five to 10 small quakes
now happen daily.
   A quake estimated at 5 to 5.8 on the Richter scale shook the
region <DATE>last Tuesday</DATE>, tumbling rocks onto <ORGANIZATION>Yosemite National Park</ORGANIZATION>'s
roads. It was eastern <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s largest quake since <DATE>1984</DATE>, but
wasn't related to volcanic activity that causes the quake swarms,
<PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said.
   <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION>'s floor continues to bulge upward as molten rock
moves inside two or three chambers about four miles under the
caldera, he said. The caldera floor rose about 2 feet since <DATE>1979</DATE>,
including 3 inches in the past year.
   While Long Valley ``is clearly an area that's showing unrest,
large calderas can do these kinds of things over years to decades
without necessarily erupting,'' <PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said.
   The floor of a caldera near <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, rose 9 feet between
<DATE>1970</DATE> and <DATE>1984</DATE> but didn't erupt. Comparable uplift inside a <LOCATION>New
Guinea</LOCATION> caldera also failed to produce volcanic disaster.
   Nevertheless, <PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said, eastern Sierra residents are addressing
the volcanic threat by developing or revising emergency plans and
helping the <ORGANIZATION>Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> prepare a new system to issue a
warning if an eruption appeared likely.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112590-0024 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 312914 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 25, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 44; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
838 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VOLCANIC ACTIVITY SLOWLY BUILDING A PIECE OF REAL ESTATE IN THE PACIFIC; 
</P>
<P>
GEOLOGY: A NINTH HAWAIIAN ISLAND IS LIKELY TO RISE FROM THE SEA. BUT DEVELOPERS 
WILL HAVE TO WAIT THOUSANDS OF YEARS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MICHAEL WOODS, NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
VOLCANO, Hawaii 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The mysterious geologic forces behind the current eruptions of <LOCATION>Mt. Kilauea</LOCATION> are 
quietly creating the newest piece of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Climbing with agonizing slowness from the warm tropical waters just southeast 
of the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> is an undersea mountain named <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION>. Volcanologists 
believe <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> eventually could emerge as the ninth Hawaiian island. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> has grown about 10,100 feet from the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> floor," <PERSON>Thomas L. Wright</PERSON>, 
scientist-in-charge of the <ORGANIZATION>Hawaiian Volcano Observatory</ORGANIZATION>, said. "It seems to be 
tapping the same source of magma (lava still underground) as <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION>. Loihi 
needs about 3,100 more feet to break the surface." 
</P>
<P>
The observatory, on the rim of <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION>'s summit caldera, or lava lake, is 
operated by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Volcanoes have been creating and modifying the environment over eons of 
geologic time. More than <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s surface is of volcanic origin. Volcanic 
eruptions have formed fertile soils and sculpted mountains, plateaus and other 
majestic landscapes. Gaseous emissions from volcanic vents helped to form the 
early atmosphere and oceans where scientists believe life first emerged. 
</P>
<P>
The volcanic machine powering <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION> and building <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> may represent the most 
visible and most persistent example of this little-known facet of volcanoes. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION> has been in the news time and again since it resumed erupting on <DATE>Jan</DATE>. 
3, <DATE>1983</DATE>. Lava oozing at the rate of 635,000 cubic feet each day has traveled 20 
miles east to the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Lava flowing from the eruption, 50 feet thick in some places, already has 
torched 140 houses and caused more than <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY> in damage. Last <DATE>May 5</DATE>, a 
2,000-foot-wide flow cut off an entire village on the island's southeast coast, 
and Gov. <PERSON>John D. Waihee</PERSON> declared the town a disaster area. 
</P>
<P>
These highly publicized lava flows, and those silently lifting <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> toward the 
surface, result from the peculiar form of volcanic activity occurring in 
<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Most of the 500 active surface volcanoes on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> straddle the margins of 
continents and the huge plates of rock that fit together like pieces of a 
jigsaw puzzle to make up the planet's surface. 
</P>
<P>
There are about a dozen of these plates, each of which is about 50 miles thick. 
The plates move relative to each other a few inches a year. Active volcanoes 
tend to occur in zones of under-thrusting, or "subduction," where one plate is 
slipping beneath another. 
</P>
<P>
How can volcanic activity occur in the <LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION>, which are more than 
2,000 miles from the nearest plate margin? 
</P>
<P>
Hawaiian volcanoes are believed to result from a different phenomenon termed 
"hot spot" volcanism. Geologists theorize that deep under the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> plate is 
an exquisitely hot, stationary region termed the "Hawaiian hot spot." 
</P>
<P>
Like a propane torch placed under a moving sheet of plastic, the hot spot melts 
rock in the overriding <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> plate. The molten rock, or magma, is less dense 
than surrounding solid rock and rises through fractures to spill onto the 
surface or ocean floor. 
</P>
<P>
Over about 70 million years, the continuous movement of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> plate over 
this stationary "fountain of fire" left a trail of more than 80 big volcanoes 
over the floor of the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>. Called the Hawaiian Ridge-Emperor Seamount 
Chain, the islands and undersea mountains, or seamounts, stretch northwestward 
about 4,000 miles, from the <LOCATION>Big Island of Hawaii</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Kamchatka Peninsula</LOCATION> in 
Soviet territory. 
</P>
<P>
The five main Hawaiian islands are the tops of volcanic mountains that were 
formed as the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> plate moved over the Hawaiian hot spot. 
</P>
<P>
A scientific record of the plate's movement to the northwest is evident in the 
age of solidified lava left on each of the islands. The age decreases from 
northwest to southeast. <LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION>, in the extreme northwest, is 5.6 million years 
old; <LOCATION>Oahu</LOCATION> is 3.4 million; <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION> is 1.8 million, <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> is 800,000, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> is 
under 700,000 years old. Lava ages even decrease in the same 
northwest-to-southeast fashion on each individual island. 
</P>
<P>
Continued movement of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> plate promises to give the goddess Pele a new 
home and <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> a new island. 
</P>
<P>
If theories about hot spot volcanism are correct, plate movement eventually 
will carry the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION> off the Hawaiian hot spot. The two active volcanoes 
on the island, <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mauna Loa</ORGANIZATION>, will become extinct. The hot spot then 
will pour molten rock onto the surface through the next volcano in the Hawaiian 
chain. 
</P>
<P>
Experts do not know exactly when <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> will emerge as a new island. Assuming 
<LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION>'s growth continues at current rates, it could take from a few thousand to 
a few tens of thousands of years. 
</P>
<P>
But other fates also may await the infant volcano. 
</P>
<P>
Infusions of molten rock from the hot spot, for instance, may cease 
unexpectedly. Loihi's growth would be stunted, leaving it just another seamount 
in the chain. The ninth Hawaiian island thus may form in an entirely different 
place. 
</P>
<P>
There is also the possibility a sudden major undersea eruption could raise 
<LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> to the surface sooner than anyone expects. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Molten rock sprays from Hawaii's Kilauea volcano. Scientist believe that 
the same fires deep in the Earth that burst forth here are behind the formation 
of an undersea mountain named Loihi, which in time could break the surface to 
become the 50th state's ninth island. National Geographic 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06111037 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06111037 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Map; MAP: Ron Coddington - Mercury News; Mammoth Lakes  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MAMMOTH-LAKES; EARTHQUAKE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A "swarm" of nearly 1,200 earthquakes is rattling a Sierra ski resort town
that sits inside a giant volcanic crater, but there is little chance of an
eruption, the U.S. Geological Survey said Friday.;    The stepped-up seismic
activity near Mammoth Lakes started March 23, with as many as 60 quakes each
hour, some measuring up to magnitude 3.6 on the Richter scale but most too
tiny to be felt.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GEOLOGISTS, MAMMOTH LAKES PEOPLE UNFAZED
BY LATEST 'SWARM' OF QUAKES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  California News.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     By this week, the number of quakes diminished to an average of five daily.
That is still two to three times as many as during previous months, according
to a weekly report issued by the <ORGANIZATION>Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Menlo Park.</LOCATION>;    Mammoth
Lakes -- with about 4,700 permanent residents and thousands of tourists -- is
located inside the <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION> caldera, a volcanic crater 19 miles long and 9
miles wide. The area is 150 miles east of <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>;    The volcano "continues
to show unrest and has the potential of erupting at some point," said <PERSON>David
Hill</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> geophysicist in charge of research at <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION>. "But we see
no reason to worry over the short run.";    <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION> and other volcanic
calderas around the world go through decades of episodic quake activity
without erupting.;    "From that, and based on our knowledge of the geological
history of eruptions in the area, we think the chances of an eruption in any
given year are very small, less than a tenth of a percent or so," <PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said
during a telephone interview.;    Between <DATE>March 23</DATE> and <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, 1,122 quakes
were detected near <LOCATION>Mammoth Lakes.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said the quakes probably are caused
by increased pressure inside one of the chambers of molten rock, called magma,
located beneath the caldera.;    The increased pressure could be caused either
because more molten rock is being injected into the magma chamber or because
some of the molten rock is crystallizing as it cools, releasing steam and
other gases, he added.;    <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s five-year drought hurt the area's ski
business. The quake swarm started just after heavy snow in <DATE>March</DATE> brought an
influx of skiers to the resort town. However, most residents and visitors "are
taking it in stride," Hill said.;    "If you're skiing, you probably don't
feel a thing," said <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> geophysicist <PERSON>John Langbein.</PERSON>;    The <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION>
caldera was created about 730,000 years ago by one of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s most powerful
eruptions. The blast spewed 600 times more volcanic debris and ash than the
<DATE>May 18, 1980</DATE>, eruption of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state.;    Eruptions
somewhat smaller than <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>' occurred about 650 years ago at the
Mono craters, several miles north of the caldera, and about 550 years ago at
the Inyo craters, which span the caldera's north rim.;    Scientists believe
two or three chambers of molten rock, each perhaps 1 1/2 miles wide, are now
located beneath the caldera and the Inyo-Mono craters, at depths ranging from
4 miles to 6 miles.;    From <DATE>1979</DATE> to <DATE>1984</DATE>, the area was rocked by thousands of
quakes, including several strong jolts exceeding magnitude 6 on the Richter
scale. Molten rock pushed upward, making the caldera's floor bulge.;    The
activity prompted the Geological Survey to issue a "notice of potential
volcanic hazard" for <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION> in <DATE>May 1982</DATE>, drawing harsh criticism from
local business people who blamed the scare for aggravating a recession in
tourism and real estate.;    The hazard notice was rescinded in <DATE>1984</DATE> when
quake activity diminished and the agency revised its warning system.;    Quake
swarms resumed under the Mammoth Mountain ski area, on the west edge of the
caldera, in <DATE>May 1989</DATE>. The quake activity shifted to the caldera's southern
edge in late <DATE>1989</DATE> and has continued sporadically since then.;    The swarm
that started last month is the biggest since <DATE>1989</DATE>, <PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said.;    But it
hasn't been accompanied by any increase in upward bulging of the caldera's
floor. The floor has bulged upward about two feet since <DATE>1979</DATE>, but is now
rising at a rate of only three-quarters of an inch annually, <PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said.;   
<PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said scientists are confident they would recognize signs of an imminent
eruption: a sharp increase in bulging and quakes that generate "harmonic
tremor," which indicates large-scale underground movement of molten rock.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910420  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  713  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday April 20, 1991
00111037,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900705-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-05-90 1135EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Why-Volcano Adv09   07-05 0694</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Why-Volcano, Adv09,0709</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv 09</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Thursday, July 9, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>`Hot Spot' Forms Hawaii Islands</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BEN DIPIETRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hawaiian folklore tells of the movements of the
volcano goddess Pele from one island to another. Without knowing
it, the tellers of these tales were chronicling the scientific
process that formed the Hawaiian archipelago.
   Legend has it that Pele was being chased from island to island
by her sister and nemesis, <PERSON>Na Maka o Kahai</PERSON>, goddess of the sea. In
reality, the ``chase'' was the formation of the islands, part of a
900-mile string of volcanoes that have been active on the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>
plate for 70 million years.
   These volcanic islands were formed after passing over a ``hot
spot'' in the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s mantle that remains in a fixed location under
the plate, said <PERSON>Reggie Okamura</PERSON>, who has studied volcanoes at the
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Hawaiian Volcano Observatory</ORGANIZATION> for 32 years.
   This hot spot remelts the portion of the rock passing over it,
creating magma. The intense heat forces the magma to rise through
the crust. The new magma builds on the previous eruptions in a
layered fashion to form massive undersea mountains whose tips
eventually rise above sea level and become islands, he said. These
are known as shield volcanoes because of their gently sloping
contours.
   ``The process that's happening now pretty much is what happened
earlier to form the other islands,'' <PERSON>Okamura</PERSON> said.
   The <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> plate is moving northwesterly at a rate of about
four inches a year, <PERSON>Okamura</PERSON> said. Each island _ beginning with
<LOCATION>Kauai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Niihau</LOCATION> and followed by <ORGANIZATION>Oahu</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Lanai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maui</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> _ were active volcanoes at one time.
   A large portion of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>, the youngest in the chain,
currently sits over the hot spot. It is the island's location that
presently accounts for the volcanic activity at <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION>, which has
been in continuous eruption since <DATE>1983</DATE>. About 160 acres of new land
have been created as a result, <PERSON>Okamura</PERSON> said.
   Three of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>'s five volcanoes have been active in the
last 200 years. The other two, which already have passed over the
hot spot, have been dormant for 3,000 and 6,000 years, respectively.
   Scientists say a new seamount is forming southeast of <LOCATION>Hawaii
Island</LOCATION> and is about 600 feet below the surface. When it breaks sea
level, thousands of years from now, <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> will be the newest
Hawaiian island, <PERSON>Okamura</PERSON> said.
   The process that forms <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s volcanoes is different from the
one that forms volcanoes on the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, such as
<ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>, which blew its top off in a spectacular eruption
in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   The Cascade range that includes <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> was formed by
the subduction of the <ORGANIZATION>Juan de Fuca</ORGANIZATION> plate with the <ORGANIZATION>North American
Continental</ORGANIZATION> plate. As the <ORGANIZATION>Juan de Fuca</ORGANIZATION> plate is pushed deeper into
the earth, the friction melts the rock to form highly pressurized
magma that can be released with explosive force, <PERSON>Okamura</PERSON> said.
   While lava from <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s volcanoes sometimes shoots hundreds of
feet into the air, it's unlikely enough pressure could be built up
to cause such a violent eruption as the one at <LOCATION>Mount St. Helens</LOCATION>, he
said.
   Magma _ called lava only after it reaches the surface _ moves
through the island's volcanoes via a series of tubes and vents. The
tubes are formed when the crust over a lava flow cools, thickens
and stops moving. The rest of the lava continues to pass under it.
   The tubes and vents are created by a system of dykes and sills.
Most of these are found in fractured areas of the volcano known as
rift zones. Lava also can flow over the volcano's crater, or
caldera, <PERSON>Okamura</PERSON> said.
   There are two kinds of lava _ pahoehoe and a'a _ identical in
chemical composition. Pahoehoe lava is black and smooth and
swift-moving. A'a lava is rougher, more fragmented and
slower-moving. Most lava erupts as pahoehoe, with some changing to
a'a as its temperature and gas content decrease. The lava mainly is
composed of silica, iron, magnesium, calcium, potassium, sodium and
other minerals, <PERSON>Okamura</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance for July 9</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900108-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-08-90 0940EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StHelens     01-08 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-St Helens,0490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Checking Mount St. Helens for Clues to Future Activity</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VANCOUVER, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists took samples of gritty ash
from the flanks of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> in hopes of learning whether
the volcano's latest burst will bring more explosive activity.
   Three scientists got within 12 miles of the crater on the east
flanks of the 8,366-foot mountain <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to gather ash from the
largest explosion in nearly four years.
   <PERSON>Dan Dzurisin</PERSON>, acting scientist in charge of the <ORGANIZATION>Cascades Volcano
Observatory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, said the ash appeared to be pulverized
material from previously erupted lava.
   If an examination by microscope shows the ash is from a new
surge of magma or molten rock beneath the volcano, however, it
could be a sign of more explosions to come, <PERSON>Dzurisin</PERSON> said.
   Scientists also planned to fly in a helicopter over the crater
to determine whether there was an avalanche from the lava dome in
the eruption <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>. Dense clouds prevented a flight
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>Dzurisin</PERSON> said.
   The latest eruption, which came without preceding earthquakes,
sent ash as far as 90 miles to the east and destroyed two
seismometers and two tilt meters in the crater. No injuries were
reported.
   Seismographs and other equipment recorded the two-minute
explosion beginning at <TIME>5:37 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. After a couple of hours
of small earthquakes beneath the volcano, seismic activity subsided
to normal levels, <PERSON>Dzurisin</PERSON> said.
   In the past few months, there have twice been lesser bursts from
the volcano. On <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, there was a minor eruption with no ashfall
detected. On <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE>, ashfall was limited to the crater.
   An eruption like <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s, without the small earthquakes in
advance to give a warning, is ``relatively new to us,'' <PERSON>Dzurisin</PERSON>
said.
   It was the most significant explosion since a series of small
explosions spit ash in the <DATE>spring of 1986</DATE>, he said.
   <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Wapato</PERSON> police officials received dozens
of calls <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, reporting light dustings of a fine, gritty,
gray-white ash in and around <LOCATION>Yakima</LOCATION> in the south-central part of
the state. Yakima is about 80 miles from the volcano.
   The volcano's last significantly large eruption was on <DATE>March 19,
1982</DATE>, when mud flowed from the crater six miles to the north fork
of the <LOCATION>Toutle River</LOCATION>, he said.
   The last dome-building eruption, a more quiet process in which
molten rock pushes upward to swell the huge mound of cooling lava
in the crater, was in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   Studying the recent ashfall could indicate whether the eruption
was part of a ``last gasp'' or the start of a more explosive phase
in the volcanic activity that began in <DATE>March 1980</DATE>, <PERSON>Dzurisin</PERSON> said.
   The cataclysmic explosion of <DATE>May 18, 1980</DATE>, leveled 230 square
miles, killed 57 people and sent up an ash cloud that circled the
globe. It also blew off the top 1,300 feet of the peak.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901205-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-05-90 1658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-UnderseaObservatory     12-05 0598</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Undersea Observatory,0713</SECOND>
<HEAD>Underwater Observatory to Watch Gradual Birth of Next Hawaiian
Island</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists plan to install a <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY>
observatory on an underwater volcano, complete with cameras,
microphones and seismometers to monitor the gradual birth of the
next Hawaiian island.
   University of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> researchers hope the Hawaiian Undersea
Geo-Observatory, or HUGO, will be in place on <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> seamount within
two years, using its instruments to study earthquakes and
eruptions, geology and geophysics professor <PERSON>Fred K. Duennebier</PERSON> said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``It's a good idea to monitor undersea volcanoes,'' said <PERSON>Bob
Tilling</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> volcanologist. ``More than half
the world's volcanoes are on the sea floor. The challenge is to
capture one of these erupting because we haven't done that yet.''
   <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> is a rugged, steep-sided submarine volcano about 22 miles
southeast of the <LOCATION>Island of Hawaii</LOCATION>. It rises roughly 11,200 feet
above the surrounding sea floor. Its cratered summit is now about
3,300 feet beneath the surface of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Duennebier</PERSON> said.
   Volcanologists are certain it is active but haven't actually
observed an eruption. Intense earthquake activity suggests
eruptions happened in <DATE>1986</DATE>, <DATE>1988</DATE> and early this year, <PERSON>Duennebier</PERSON>
said during the <ORGANIZATION>American Geophysical Union</ORGANIZATION>'s fall meeting.
   ``It will be the next Hawaiian island in about 50,000 years or
so'' once eruptions build the summit above the ocean's surface, he
added. ``I wouldn't buy real estate yet.''
   The observatory will be a network of 20 or more cameras and
instruments plugged into electrical boxes located on a system of
electro-optical cables draped across <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION>'s summit and slopes -
like TVs, lamps and stereo equipment linked by extension cords in
someone's living room.
   HUGO will be connected to the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION> by another cable that
will provide power and also carry data from the observatory to a
recording station and scientists on shore.
   Duennebier said that once a ship lays the cable and boxes,
unmanned remote-controlled submarines and manned submersible
vehicles will plug cameras, microphones, seismometers and heat and
chemical sensors into the network.
   Scientists who study the sea floor now usually use instruments
that are dropped off ships, fall to the ocean floor, record
scientific data on tape and then are recovered by ships.
   Duennebier said <ORGANIZATION>HUGO</ORGANIZATION>'s instruments will have the advantage of
being able to collect data on quakes and eruptions and send the
information to land immediately. If a camera or instrument breaks
down or becomes obsolete, a submersible vehicle or
remote-controlled submarine can retrieve it and install a new one.
   The observatory will be able to collect pictures and information
for at least 10 years unless it is buried by undersea lava flows or
landslides, <PERSON>Duennebier</PERSON> said. He said the instruments would be
placed in areas where they are least likely to be damaged.
   During the apparent eruption of <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, the university
installed seven temporary seismometers on <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION>'s slopes. They
detected thousands of earthquakes at the rate of about three daily,
while seismometers on land detected only three per month.
Duennebier said that shows the value of installing a permanent
observatory like HUGO.
   The Hawaiian Islands were created by a ``hot spot,'' a plume of
molten rock that rises from deep inside the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. As a giant plate
of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s crust was dragged over the hot spot, volcanic eruptions
from the hot spot formed each of the islands in succession.
   <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> is now over the hot spot, which also has branches feeding
<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mauna Loa</ORGANIZATION> volcanoes.
   The network of cables and electrical plug-in boxes for the
observatory will cost roughly <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY>, although about two-thirds
of that cost has been donated by <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T Co.</ORGANIZATION> in the form of 25 miles
of undersea cable and the use of a cable-laying ship to install it.
   The university also got <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> of <MONEY>$2.5 million</MONEY> it requested
for the project from the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>. Duennebier
and his colleague, oceanographer <PERSON>Alexander Malahoff</PERSON>, hope to use
that money to start buying cameras and monitoring instruments for
the observatory.
   Because the observatory will be equipped with numerous plug-in
boxes, many other researchers will be able to install their own
instruments on <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Duennebier</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06170171 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06170171 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawing, photo, diagram; DRAWING: (Drawing shows 4 men doing 1. Surveying, 2.
Pick and shovel, 3. Seismometer and 4. Spectrometer) (Color); Reporting by
Glennda Chui, graphic by Jenny Anderson and Kevin Boyd - Mercury News.;
Diagram: Under the volcano.; The eruptions of Mount Pinatubo in the
Philippines and Mount Unzen in Japan are not directly related. However, both
are the result of a process called subduction.; Near the edge of a continent,
one plate of the earth's crust dives beneath another.; The plate descends
about 60 miles, where temperatures and pressures are high enough to melt the
crustal rock. This molten rock, or magma, is light and buoyant. It rises
through cracks, collects in chambers and eventually erupts to the surface.;
(Diagram shows what is happening under volcano) (Color); Sources: Robert
Tilling and Steven Brantley, U.S. Geological Survey: " The Earth," by Peter J.
Smith.; Reporting by Glennda Chui, graphic by Jenny Anderson and Kevin Boyd -
Mercury News.; (Attached Map shows Mount Unzen and Mount Pinatubo and
direction of subduction) (Color); The 1980s: A decade of volcanic violence;
The years following the eruption of Mount St. Helens in 1980 were the most
disastrous period for eruptions since 1902, when three volcanoes killed more
than 36,000 people worldwide in a single year.; (box) Mount St. Helens,
Washington, 1980. Worst volcanic disaster in U.S. history; 57 dead and $1
billion in damage. Triggered a renaissance in volcano hazards research.; (box)
El Chichon, Mexico, 1982. Thought long dead, it erupted without woarning,
killing more than 2,000; (box) Galunggung, West Java, Indonesia, 1982-'83. No
deaths but 80,000 people evacuated and 35,000 left homeless.; (box) Nevado del
Ruiz, Colombia, 1985. Despite warnings, people not evacuated: more than 22,000
died in mudslides after lava melted glaciers.; (box) Redoubt Volcano, Alaska,
1989-'90. Monitoring led to successful forecast. No deaths; more than $100
million in damage; Sources: Robert Tilling and Steven Brantley, U.S.
Geological Survey: " The Earth," by Peter J. Smith.; Reporting by Glennda
Chui, graphic by Jenny Anderson and Kevin Boyd - Mercury News.; PHOTO:
Associated Press; Hotel employees in Subic, about 30 miles from Pinatubo, dig
out cars buried in volcanic ash  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FORECAST; VOLCANO; RESEARCH; MAJOR-STORY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE FIRST THREATS were subtle:;    Steam curling from a fissure. A flurry of
small earthquakes, too faint to be felt.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Science &amp; Medicine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FORECASTING VOLCANOES
SCIENTISTS HAVE LEARNED MUCH IN THE PAST
DECADE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Additional information attached to end of article.
See related article on page 3E  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The Mount Pinatubo volcano was slowly rousing from 600 years of sleep.;   
Two months ago, when the drama began, scientists knew almost nothing about
this drowsy Philippine giant, swaddled in thick jungle and ignored by the
hundreds of thousands of people living around its flanks.;    They didn't know
it had a habit of exploding with a force twice as great as the <DATE>1980</DATE> eruption
of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> -- or that the debris from these eruptions
had covered much of what was now <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base.</ORGANIZATION>;    But with the first small
signs of trouble, researchers went on alert, throwing a network of instruments
around the restless mountain. And in a few frenzied weeks of investigation,
they learned enough to recommend evacuation of some 84,000 people.;    The
warning came just in time. A series of violent eruptions has rocked the
mountain since <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, blowing ash and pumice 80,000 feet in the air and
sifting volcanic grit over villages 90 miles away. At least 101 people have
been killed, 150,000 Filipinos have crowded into refugee centers in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> and
20,000 American military dependents and civilian workers are being evacuated
from the country. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said the damage may lead them to permanently
close <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base.</ORGANIZATION>;    On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, scientists said much of the pressure
inside the volcano had dissipated and the worst may be over.;    Although
Pinatubo never erupted into the cataclysmic blow-up that some had feared, the
damage and death toll from related earthquakes, mudslides and falling ash and
pumice could have been far higher had scientists not recommended evacuation.
The successful forecast points up just how far the science of volcanoes has
come in the past decade.;    The basics are the same. Researchers still use
seismometers and other instruments to measure the trembling, quaking and
bulging of the ground that often spell danger.;    But the technology has
improved immensely:;    (check) Instruments are cheaper and more expendable,
so they can be deployed where they will do the most good -- right in the path
of the volcano's fury.;    (check) The instruments continually beam data to
scientists who are waiting a safe distance away. Before, they had to visit
their instruments and collect the data by hand.;    (check) Information is
routinely analyzed by computer, allowing researchers to assess a situation
quickly -- and to develop computer models for predicting the behavior of
volcanoes.;    Researchers have also made strides in interpreting what they
see. "Our biggest improvement has been in our own heads," said <PERSON>Peter Lipman</PERSON>, a
volcanologist with the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Menlo Park.</LOCATION>;    These skills
were honed in a series of volcanic disasters that rocked the world over the
past decade.;    "The <DATE>1980s</DATE> was a very interesting decade because of the
number of eruptions that have occurred for which we have good monitoring
information," said <PERSON>Steven Brantley</PERSON>, a geologist with the survey's <ORGANIZATION>Cascades
Volcano Observatory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION> "It was a rather remarkable decade,
really.";    Scientists say the eruption of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>, which killed 57
people and caused <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> in property damage, triggered a renaissance in
volcano research.;    It alerted the American public to volcano hazards and
prompted a tenfold increase in government spending for volcano research and
monitoring, said geologist <PERSON>Robert Tilling</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Menlo Park.</LOCATION>;    As a
result, the survey opened two new volcano observatories. One, in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
keeps track of active volcanoes in the <LOCATION>Cascades Range</LOCATION> of the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>, including <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mount Rainier</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mount
Hood</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mount Baker</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mount Shasta</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mount Lassen</ORGANIZATION>. The second is in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>,
where Redoubt Volcano put on a spectacular show in <DATE>1989</DATE> and <DATE>1990</DATE>. A third
observatory has been operating in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> since 1912.;    American scientists
have since responded to a number of volcanic awakenings throughout the world,
from Galunggung in <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nevado</LOCATION> del Ruiz in <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, improving their
ability to quickly evaluate volcano hazards. Such a quick response is crucial
because only a few dozen of the world's 500 active volcanoes have been
adequately investigated and monitored.;    "Now," <PERSON>Tilling</PERSON> said, "we can go in
there and literally overnight set up a seismic network, and start getting data
within a day or two.";    The blossoming research has in turn spurred
development of cheaper and more rugged instruments.;    Take tiltmeters.;   
Like glorified carpenters' levels, they are used to measure the bulging and
tilting of the ground as magma muscles its way toward the surface.;    A
decade ago they cost thousands of dollars each. But after <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>
blew, scientists looked for cheaper models. One was developed by <PERSON>James
Westphal</PERSON>, a well-known astronomer and gadgeteer at the <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of
Technology</ORGANIZATION>, who patterned it after an idea used in missile guidance systems.
Now tiltmeters are inexpensive enough to place in areas likely to get wiped
out in eruptions.;    The humble seismometer has also grown more useful as
scientists learn to better interpret what it's saying.;    "Volcanoes are
probably the most complex structures you can find on this planet," said
<PERSON>Bernard Chouet</PERSON>, a seismologist at the <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Menlo Park.</LOCATION>;    It's not unusual
for them to produce thousands of small earthquakes -- but those quakes can
have a variety of causes. Most are innocuous, caused by the cracking of rock
above pools of magma that, for the moment, aren't going anywhere. But others
are ominous, reflecting the surge of magma toward the surface in preparation
for an eruption.;    In the past few years, <PERSON>Chouet</PERSON> said, seismologists have
learned to recognize distinctive tremors that mean an eruption is on its way.
These patterns were successfully used to forecast the <DATE>1989</DATE> eruption of <ORGANIZATION>Redoubt
Volcano</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, as well as the current eruptions at Pinatubo.;    But even
though volcano warnings have proved far more accurate than earthquake
forecasts, they're far from foolproof.;    Some volcanoes give virtually no
warning. Even when they do, the decision to evacuate is difficult and
expensive. In the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, for instance, vandals looted parts of <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air
Base</ORGANIZATION> that were left unguarded. Factories and businesses shut down; crops and
livestock were left unattended.;    This time the evacuation paid off,
possibly averting a number of deaths. But it won't always. In the end, every
volcano is a rugged individualist, with its own distinct patterns of activity.
Some wake up, make threatening noises for weeks or months, then drift back to
sleep.;    The burden of deciding whether to warn the public weighs heavily on
scientists.;    <PERSON>Randall White</PERSON>, another seismologist with the <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Menlo
Park</LOCATION>, recalled how he felt while working near the freezing summit of
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s Nevado del Ruiz six years ago.;    Struggling to hear their
instruments above the noise of nearby broadcast towers, he and his colleagues
warned local officials that an eruption was on its way. But their warnings
were vain. For reasons that are still unclear, the officials did not order an
evacuation, and 22,000 people died after lava spewed from the volcano, melting
glaciers and forming devastating mudslides.;    "I found it nerve-racking,"
White said. "We were literally afraid to go to sleep at night, thinking that
some technician would get the interpretation (of the incoming data) wrong, and
a lot of people would die.";  Tools give clues that can save lives;    The
basic tools of volcano monitoring are cheaper and more portable than they were
10 years ago. Scientists can move in fast and set up instruments that
continually broadcast readings, which are then analyzed by computer. This
allows quicker evaluation of volcano hazards -- and forecasts that can save
lives.; 1. Surveying: Researchers measure the volcano, with optical
instruments or high-tech laser tools, to see if it is bulging or stretching as
a result of magma rising inside. They also put tiltmeters near the volcano's
vent to record changes in the slope of the ground.; 2. Pick and shovel:
Geologists dig through layers of old ash and lava to determine how often a
volcano erupted in the past -- a clue to what it might do in the future. The
thicker and more extensive the deposit, the bigger the eruption.; 3.
Seismometer: Measures ground shaking. Volcanoes often produce swarms of small
earthquakes. Researchers are learning to distinguish ordinary earthquakes from
those caused by magma rising toward the surface -- a sign of impending
eruption.; 4. Spectrometer: First developed to measure pollutants from factory
smokestacks, it is now also used to measure sulfur dioxide in the smoke
belched by volcanoes. Increasing levels of the gas may signal an impending
eruption. The amount of gas reflects the amount of magma beneath the volcano,
and thus the potential size of the eruption.;    Sources: <PERSON>Robert Tilling</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Steven Brantley</PERSON>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Geological Survey: " The Earth," by <PERSON>Peter J. Smith.</PERSON>;
Reporting by <PERSON>Glennda Chui</PERSON>, graphic by <PERSON>Jenny Anderson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kevin Boyd</PERSON> - <ORGANIZATION>Mercury
News.</ORGANIZATION>; (3 Drawings showing Laser, Pick, Seismometer and Spectrometer)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  GLENNDA CHUI, Mercury News Science Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910618  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING; DIAGRAM; PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,846  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday June 18, 1991
00170171,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891205-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-05-89 0221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SierraVolcano     12-05 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sierra Volcano,0398</SECOND>
<HEAD>Molten Rock Triggers Quakes Under Volcano, But Eruption Unlikely</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Molten rock moving beneath <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s
Mammoth Mountain ski resort triggered thousands of small
earthquakes since <DATE>May</DATE>, but the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> says the old
volcano is unlikely to erupt.
   ``We still see occasional bursts of quake activity, but it's
much more sporadic'' in recent weeks than in <DATE>June</DATE>, when hundreds of
tiny jolts each day rattled the 11,053-foot mountain in the <LOCATION>Sierra
Nevada</LOCATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> geophysicist <PERSON>Dave Hill</PERSON>, the scientist in charge
of monitoring the situation.
   In a statement issued <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the federal agency said: ``While
eruptive activity as a consequence of this current earthquake swarm
cannot be ruled out, observations at many volcanoes in the world
suggest the most likely outcome ... is a return to an extended
period of relative quiescence.''
   Hill discussed the ``swarm'' of quakes under <ORGANIZATION>Mammoth Mountain</ORGANIZATION>
during a <DATE>Monday</DATE> session at the <ORGANIZATION>American Geophysical Union</ORGANIZATION>'s fall
meeting.
   Only four of the thousands of quakes that started <DATE>May 4</DATE> measured
more than 3 on the Richter scale, so most were too small to be
felt. Some of the quakes were only 1.5 miles deep and often came in
rapid-fire bursts.
   Mammoth Mountain has bulged upward about one-half inch since
<DATE>May</DATE>, <PERSON>Hill</PERSON> said.
   The most likely explanation for the quakes and bulging is that
molten rock, or magma, is being squeezed into a vertical crack that
extends from 3.5 miles to 6 miles below Mammoth Mountain's south
flank, he said.
   This sheetlike intrusion is called a dike, and excavations at
many old volcanoes reveal that most dikes never erupt to the
surface, Hill explained.
   Mammoth Mountain, now covered with ski runs, last erupted
explosively about 50,000 years ago and is located just outside the
southwest rim of <LOCATION>Long Valley</LOCATION> caldera. The caldera is a
20-by-10-mile oval-shaped crater created 730,000 years ago by one
of the world's greatest eruptions.
   That blast spewed at least 600 times more material than the <DATE>May
18, 1980</DATE>, eruption of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>.
   The resort town of Mammoth Lakes sits inside the caldera a few
miles east of <ORGANIZATION>Mammoth Mountain</ORGANIZATION>. Hill cautioned against undue
volcano phobia, saying it is ``more dangerous to drive up on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
395 than to spend time skiing or living near Mammoth Lakes.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890713-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-13-89 1137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Volcano 1stLd-Writethru a0537 07-13 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Volcano, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0537,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Volcano Erupts In Region of Japan Plagued By Earthquakes</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 2 grafs for 5th, ``Many people...'' to UPDATE with residents
calling local officials, second eruption not ruled out. Pickup 6th, ``More
than...''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A volcano erupted near an uninhabited island today,
spewing plumes of steam and smoke into the air and raising concerns
about a region of the nation where thousands of earthquakes have
occurred recently.
   The eruption happened at <TIME>6:30 p.m.</TIME> about 1{ miles northeast of
the island of <LOCATION>Teishijima</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Central Meteorological Agency</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   The island is just off the coast of Ito city on the <LOCATION>Izu
peninsula</LOCATION>, 60 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. The extent of the volcanic
activity several hundred yards beneath the ocean's surface was not
   There were no immediate reports of injuries, and a tsunami, or
seismic wave caused by earthquakes or volcanic activity, was not
expected, the agency said. However, it issued a navigation warning
to ships operating in the area.
   Many people in <LOCATION>Ito</LOCATION>, a seaside spa known for its many hot springs,
were seen leaving their homes, but no evacuation order was issued,
the <ORGANIZATION>Japan Broadcasting Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said. Hundreds of people called local
officials asking about the volcano.
   ``Right now, we don't know if this will lead to another, larger
eruption and can only tell people there to watch for further
warnings,'' said a <ORGANIZATION>Central Meteorological Agency</ORGANIZATION> official who
requested anonymity. ``Obviously, there could be danger to <PERSON>Ito</PERSON> if a
larger eruption occurs.''
   More than 20,000 earthquakes have been recorded around <LOCATION>Izu</LOCATION> over
the past two weeks, and officials from the <ORGANIZATION>Construction Ministry</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Geographical Survey Institute</ORGANIZATION> began today to check movement of the
earth's crust at <LOCATION>Ito</LOCATION>, the town nearest the epicenter. Ito has a
population of 72,000.
   Also seismologists from the <ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> started surveying
the movements of underground magma with monitoring equipment in <LOCATION>Ito</LOCATION>.
   The stepped-up investigations followed an emergency meeting late
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of the government's <ORGANIZATION>Coordinating Committee for Earthquake
Prediction</ORGANIZATION>, which called for ``careful monitoring'' of the
continuing earthquakes.
   The 16-member committee, led by Professor <PERSON>Daisuke Shimozuru</PERSON> of
the <ORGANIZATION>University of Tokyo</ORGANIZATION>, said in a statement that the successive
minor quakes occurring since <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> ``may be caused by
activities of underground magma, and there is a need to monitor them
carefully.''
   Two million people visited <DATE>Ito last year</DATE>, where there are 450
inns and hotels for visitors, <PERSON>Hidekatsu Takei</PERSON>, acting director of
the <ORGANIZATION>Hot Spring Tourist Cooperatives</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ito</LOCATION>, told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated
Press</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900323-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-23-90 1040EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-AnotherLook:MountSt.Helens Adv26   03-23 1255</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Another Look: Mount St. Helens, Adv 26,1282</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv26</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Mon PMs, March 26, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Quake 10 Years Ago Was First Sign Mount St. Helens' Fuse Was Lit</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Donal is cq in 25th graf, ``For Crandell...'</NOTE>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JIM KLAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At 4.1 on the Richter scale, the earthquake on
the <TIME>afternoon</TIME> of <DATE>March 20, 1980</DATE>, was no great shakes. It knocked
snow off the north face of <LOCATION>Mount St. Helens</LOCATION> but went virtually
unnoticed in the surrounding counties of southwestern <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Nearly 130 miles to the north, the line traced by a wandering
pencil on a seismograph at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Washington</ORGANIZATION> was first
interpreted as evidence of a tremor 75 miles southeast of the
dormant volcano.
   But on closer inspection, seismologists determined the quake had
occurred under the mountain, and relatively close to the surface.
   It was the first recorded sign that <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>' volcanic
fuse was lit. One week later, on <DATE>March 27</DATE>, the volcano belched
steam and ash in its first eruption in 123 years. The accompanying
4.7-magnitude quake sent seismic needles skittering.
   Fifty-two days after that, on <DATE>May 18, 1980</DATE>, the mountain
exploded spectacularly. The eruption killed 57 people and sent ash
around the world. In an instant, 1,300 feet of the mountain
disappeared, fully a fifth of its towering majesty simply blown
away.
   The smoking, raw-edged crater left behind stunned residents of
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> used to gazing out at a symmetrical,
snowcapped peak.
   ``It woke people up to the fact that having a volcano in your
back yard can be dangerous,'' said <PERSON>Dwight Crandell</PERSON>, retired from
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>. In <DATE>1978</DATE>, <PERSON>Crandell</PERSON> helped write a report
that predicted an eruption at <LOCATION>Mount St. Helens</LOCATION> <DATE>this century</DATE>.
   The blast was also a wake-up call for volcanologists around the
world. In the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, only two countries with volcanic mountains
were examining the dangers of nearby human settlements. Today 16
countries have active studies under way, <PERSON>Crandell</PERSON> said by telephone
from his home in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>.
   ``It's clear that the <DATE>1980</DATE> eruption was a sensation for the
science of volcanology,'' said geologist <PERSON>Steve Brantley</PERSON>, stationed
at the <ORGANIZATION>USGS Cascade Volcano Observatory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, about
45 miles southwest of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>. About 80 scientists work at
the observatory, built after the eruption.
   UW seismologist <PERSON>Steve Malone</PERSON> said the <DATE>March 20</DATE> earthquake was
strong enough to draw attention to the area but not so unusual as
to make scientists suspicious that molten rock was squeezing into
crevices deep under the earth.
   ``Earthquakes at the volcano are not unheard of,'' <PERSON>Malone</PERSON> said.
``They generate a bit of interest but not immediate alarm.''
   But quakes kept coming, increasing in number and strength. Three
days after the initial quake, <ORGANIZATION>UW</ORGANIZATION> seismologists warned the <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION>
about a ``potentially serious situation.''
   ``This was when we first suspected we might be on to something
other than just a small earthquake swarm,'' <PERSON>Malone</PERSON> said.
   Teams of geologists arrived to set up equipment to monitor
ground movement and the gases emitted each time the volcano burped.
Seismologists stayed close to their machines. The <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION>
began warning people to stay clear of the mountain because of
avalanches.
   But the scientists were not working in isolation. Scores of
eager newspaper and broadcast reporters joined the crush.
Researchers accustomed to working in geologic time, in a science
where more is unknown than known, were being asked to provide
instant answers for that evening's news and the next morning's
newspapers.
   ``I remember ... being a bit overwhelmed by the media interest
this was already generating,'' <PERSON>Malone</PERSON> said. ``All we had was data
and some possibilities and a lot of questions.''
   Meantime, the ground was moving at postcard-perfect Spirit Lake,
at the mountain's foot. <PERSON>Chuck Tonn</PERSON>, who ran the <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> desk
at the lake, hung a pencil from a string to show the faint shaking.
The lake was evacuated <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, <DATE>March 25</DATE>.
   ``I was glad to leave that morning,'' <PERSON>Tonn</PERSON> said. ``That <TIME>last
night</TIME>, I don't think any of us slept. ... It seemed like there was
always some movement going on.''
   Not everyone left. <PERSON>Harry Truman</PERSON>, the 83-year-old owner and
keeper of rustic <ORGANIZATION>Spirit Lake Lodge</ORGANIZATION>, dug in his heels. <PERSON>Truman</PERSON> said
he would stay on the mountain that had been his home for 50 years,
the mountain that eight weeks later would kill him. In the media
catering to the nation's rising anticipation, <PERSON>Truman</PERSON> became a
cantankerous folk hero.
   Another local, <PERSON>Stan Lee</PERSON>, 67, owner of the <ORGANIZATION>Kid Valley Store</ORGANIZATION> about
20 miles from the peak, snorted at talk of a possible eruption and
accused the <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> of plotting to squelch development. Two
days later, the mountain blew.
   That first eruption shot a black plume almost a mile and a half
high. By mid-April, the stark gray and brown hollow of a crater had
replaced the mountain's snowy point, once 9,677 feet above sea
level. Ashfalls in the region were commonplace, with fickle winds
determining who got dusted next.
   <DATE>May 18, 1980</DATE>, the day the mountain finally blew its top, is now
designated Eruption Day in <ORGANIZATION>Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> books. On those who
were there and experienced the power and awe and terror, <ORGANIZATION>Mount St.
Helens</ORGANIZATION> has left its mark as clearly as the eruption scarred the
landscape.
   ``I feel fortunate to have been at <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> from the
beginning all these 10 years,'' said <PERSON>Tonn</PERSON>, who now manages the
<ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION>'s visitors' center west of the 110,000-acre <ORGANIZATION>National
Volcanic Monument</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It (eruption) kind of puts me in my place. It puts me in awe
of what can happen.''
   For <PERSON>Crandell</PERSON> and fellow <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> geologist <PERSON>Donal Mullineaux</PERSON>, the
eruption was right on time. After studying dormant <ORGANIZATION>Cascade Range</ORGANIZATION>
volcanoes in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and <DATE>1970s</DATE>, they predicted in <DATE>1978</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>Mount
St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> would likely erupt relatively soon.
   ``Everything we found indicated it was a very young volcano, and
a very explosive volcano, and a frequently active volcano,'' which
last erupted in <DATE>1857</DATE>, <PERSON>Crandell</PERSON> said. ``We felt almost sure the
volcano would erupt, and sooner rather than later. That is what the
history told us.''
   While some public officials greeted their hazard report
seriously, there were also snickers, the two scientists said. ``A
lot of people made fun of it, of course,'' <PERSON>Mullineaux</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Crandell</PERSON> said he was gratified that many countries with
volcanoes have since made use of their work in hazard assessment,
including <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Equador</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>.
   The eruption of <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Nevado del Ruiz</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>November 1985</DATE>
provides an example of how hazard assessment could have helped,
<PERSON>Crandell</PERSON> said. An assessment had been completed, and hazard zones
had been laid out, including likely flood and mudflow zones at the
town of <LOCATION>Armero</LOCATION>. But word never reached local officials. There were
no evacuations and 25,000 people perished.
   Mount <LOCATION>St. Helens</LOCATION> prompted gains in both volcanology and
seismology. Since <DATE>1980</DATE>, scientists have learned to better predict
volcanic eruptions by studying earthquake activity, including the
``harmonic tremors'' that indicate movement of molten earth.
   Other volcanic mysteries are also better understood, <PERSON>Crandell</PERSON>
said. These include the devastating sideways force of the <DATE>May 1980</DATE>
eruption, the fast-moving and deadly mixtures of matter and gas
known as pyroclastic flows and surges, and the mudflows that let
loose in minutes after vibrations turn snowfields into walls of
water.
   Mullineaux and <PERSON>Crandell</PERSON> retired in the mid-1980s, but both
remain active in research on <LOCATION>Mount St. Helens</LOCATION>.
   ``I can't leave it alone,'' <PERSON>Crandell</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Mon PMs, March 26</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901221-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-21-90 0535EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MountStHelens     12-21 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mount St Helens,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Plume of Steam, Ash from Mount St. Helens</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A giant ash plume belched from <LOCATION>Mount St. Helens</LOCATION>,
but scientists said it didn't appear to portend a new eruption of
molten rock.
   Wind carred the ash toward <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 53 miles to the
southwest, prompting <ORGANIZATION>United Airlines</ORGANIZATION> to cancel 21 flights in and
out of that city <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. Normal service was to resume <TIME>this
morning</TIME>, <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> customer service supervisor <PERSON>Fred Von Pegert</PERSON> said.
   Port of <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION> spokesman <PERSON>Darrel Buttice</PERSON> said the airport
remained open <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and the 11 other airlines were flying.
   The 8,366-foot mountain blew a column of light gray ash and
steam 23,000 feet into the air <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, about 30 minutes
after a small explosion occurred on the lava dome in the volcano's
crater, said <PERSON>Michael Doukas</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> geologist at
its <ORGANIZATION>Cascade Volcano Observatory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Doukas</PERSON> said it was similar to the latest volcanic ``burp,'' on
<DATE>Nov. 5</DATE>, when a plume of steam and ash rose 30,000 feet into the
sky. Similar bursts occurred last <DATE>December</DATE> and <DATE>January</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Doukas</PERSON> said those bursts are significant only in underscoring
that <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> remains an active volcano.
   Scientists have theorized such bursts come from either gases
bubbling out of solution in molten rock beneath the mountain, or
from rain and snowmelt percolating down to hot areas and bursting
into steam.
   The volcano's last significant eruption was on <DATE>March 19, 1982</DATE>,
when mud flowed from the crater six miles to the north fork of the
<LOCATION>Toutle River</LOCATION>. Since then, the mountain has had a series of
``dome-building'' eruptions in which the mountain quietly adds lava
to the heap in its crater. The last of those was in <DATE>October 1986</DATE>.
   The mountain's cataclysmic <DATE>May 18, 1980</DATE>, eruption killed 57
people and blew off the top 1,300 feet of the once-symmetrical
peak, a lava dome dating to about the <DATE>16th century</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890627-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-27-89 0057EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HawaiiEarthquake 1stLd-Writethru a0655 06-27 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hawaii Earthquake, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0655,0402</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strongest Quake in Six Years Strikes Hawaii Island</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 7th, `The quake...,' to UPDATE with aftershocks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VOLCANO, Hawaii (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The strongest earthquake to hit <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> in
six years shook a sparsely populated area of <LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION> already
ravaged by lava, destroying two homes and generating a small tidal
wave.
   No serious injuries were reported.
<DATE>Monday</DATE>, said <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii County Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> Administrator <PERSON>Harry Kim</PERSON>.
   ``Our first priority this morning is to check certain remote
areas to make sure no one is trapped in their homes,'' <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> said.
``Early reports we are getting indicate no one is trapped.''
   The temblor, caused by the 6{-year-old eruption of <LOCATION>Kilauea
Volcano</LOCATION>, struck <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> and measured 6.1 on the Richter
scale, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> said.
   It was centered west of <LOCATION>Kalapana</LOCATION>, a small coastal town on the
south flank of the volcano, said <PERSON>Bruce Turner</PERSON>, a geophysicist at the
<ORGANIZATION>Pacific Tsunami Warning Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>.
   The quake was triggered by the release of pressure generated by
the movement of underground magma, or molten rock, said <PERSON>Bob
Koyanagi</PERSON>, a seismic analyst at the <ORGANIZATION>Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Hawaiian
Volcano Observatory</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Reggie Okamura</PERSON>, a spokesman for the observatory, said scientists
had recorded numerous aftershocks. The strongest, measuring 4.0 on
the Richter scale, was recorded <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, he said.
   <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION> lava has destroyed 68 homes in the <LOCATION>Kalapana</LOCATION> area since
its latest eruption began <DATE>Jan. 3, 1983</DATE>. Four homes were destroyed in
<DATE>May</DATE>, and <DATE>last Thursday</DATE> a <ORGANIZATION>Hawaii Volcanoes National Park</ORGANIZATION> visitor
center burst into flames as lava crept beneath the wooden structure.
   <PERSON>Koyanagi</PERSON> said pressure became too great within the world's most
active volcano, causing its south flank to move and triggering the
earthquake.
   The tidal wave, which measured 22.8 inches high at <LOCATION>Honuapo</LOCATION>, 8.4
inches at Kapoho and 5.6 inches at <LOCATION>Hilo</LOCATION>, caused no damage, <PERSON>Turner</PERSON>
said.
   Five people were injured by falling debris inside homes, but none
required hospitalization, <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> said. Crews were working to repair
downed power lines.
   It was the strongest earthquake to hit the state since <DATE>Nov. 15,
1983</DATE>, when a 6.6 temblor caused <MONEY>several million dollars</MONEY> damage on
<LOCATION>Hawaii Island</LOCATION>.
   The Richter scale is a measure of ground motion as recorded on
seismographs. Every increase of one number means a tenfold increase
in magnitude.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890714-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-14-89 1530EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Volcano     07-14 0447</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Volcano,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quakes, Volcano Eruption Scare Tourists Away From Resort Town</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TETSUO JIMBO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ITO, Japan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Yusaku Inoue</PERSON>, sitting quietly <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the
stairs in front of his tiny beachfront restaurant, sighed deeply and
said, ``It looks like my <DATE>summer</DATE> is over.''
   The 85-year-old restaurant owner was among hundreds of shop
owners, hotel managers and restaurant operators in <LOCATION>Ito</LOCATION>, 60 miles
southwest of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, whose business has been hurt by thousands of
earthquakes and the eruption of an undersea volcano.
   ``I have been running this place for over 40 years and business
was never this bad,'' he said.
   Since <DATE>June 30</DATE>, more than 22,000 quakes have jolted the hot
springs resort, including more than 585 strong enough to be felt by
humans. Twenty-one people suffered minor injuries when two
earthquakes registering 5.5 on the Richter scale hit Ito on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>, a volcano onthe ocean floor off Ito erupted,
spewing white steam into the air.
   The hundreds of hotels in the area are virtually empty, although
some of the rooms are being filled by reporters.
   ``The irony is that this town earned its fame from its rich hot
springs derived from volcanic activity,'' said one middle-aged shop
owner, speaking on condition of anonymity. ``Now, the volcanic
activity is hurting the tourism industry.''
   More earthquakes and volcanic tremors jolted the Ito area on
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, but no injuries were reported. Scores of dead fish and
volcanic stones were scattered along the shore.
   ``On an ordinary <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, this beach is always packed
and most restaurants around here are full,'' said <PERSON>Inoue</PERSON>. ``But I've
only had one customer so far today.''
   News reports <DATE>Friday</DATE> said two undersea mounds were found near the
eruption site, a few miles from <PERSON>Ito</PERSON>. One was about 80 feet high and
the other about 30 feet, the reports said.
   Most of the 200 people who left their seaside houses after the
eruption to spend the night in four Buddhist temples and schools
returned home <DATE>Friday</DATE>, but 43 schools in <LOCATION>Ito</LOCATION> remained closed, said
<PERSON>Masaaki Mitsuhashi</PERSON>, a spokesman for the city.
said another eruption was highly likely to occur, not only at the
same spot but possibly at other locations.
   When the 72,000 residents began to experience temblors in recent
weeks, its 916 hotels and inns began receiving a stream of
cancellations. After the eruption <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, more than <PERCENT>95 percent</PERCENT> of
hotel reservations were canceled, said <PERSON>Hiroyuki Yamashita</PERSON> of <PERSON>Ito</PERSON>'s
tourist bureau.
   The Japanese archipelago, which is of volcanic origin, is
believed to have about 80 active volcanoes. In <DATE>January</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Mount
Tokachi</ORGANIZATION>, on <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s northern island of <LOCATION>Hokkaido</LOCATION>, erupted several
times.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901206-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-06-90 0312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-UnderseaObservatory     12-06 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Undersea Observatory,0381</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists to Rig Deep-Sea Volcano with Cameras and Sensors</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A volcano at the bottom of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> that
is destined to be the next Hawaiian island is going high-tech with
a <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY> network of cameras and seismic sensors to document its
deep-sea rumblings.
   ``We would love to catch an eruption,'' <PERSON>Fred K. Duennebier</PERSON>, a
professor of geology and geophysics at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Hawaii</ORGANIZATION>,
said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of the Hawaiian Undersea Geo-Observatory.
   The observatory will be installed on <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> seamount, an
underwater volcano 22 miles southeast of the island of <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> rises about 11,200 feet above the ocean floor, but its
cratered summit is still 3,300 feet beneath the waves.
   ``It will be the next Hawaiian island in about 50,000 years or
so,'' <PERSON>Duennebier</PERSON> said at a meeting the <ORGANIZATION>American Geophysical Union</ORGANIZATION>.
``I wouldn't buy real estate yet.''
   The observatory, which scientists hope to have in operation
within two years, will be a network of 20 or more cameras and
instruments draped across <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION>'s summit and slopes.
   HUGO will be connected to the <LOCATION>Big Island</LOCATION> by a power cable that
will also carry data from the observatory to scientists on shore.
   A ship will lay a network of electro-optical cable and outlet
boxes, then remote-controlled submarines and manned submersible
vehicles will plug in cameras, microphones, seismometers and heat
and chemical sensors.
   It will work for at least 10 years unless it is buried by lava
flows or landslides, <PERSON>Duennebier</PERSON> said.
   Scientists are sure <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> is active but haven't actually
observed an eruption. Intense earthquake activity suggests
eruptions happened in <DATE>1986</DATE>, <DATE>1988</DATE> and early this year, <PERSON>Duennebier</PERSON>
said.
   The Hawaiian Islands were created by a ``hot spot,'' a plume of
molten rock that rises from deep inside the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Loihi</LOCATION> is now
over the hot spot, which also has branches feeding <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s active
<LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mauna Loa</ORGANIZATION> volcanos.
   Roughly <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the world's volcanos are on
the sea floor.
   ``We have no idea how these volcanos are built up from the ocean
floor,'' <PERSON>Duennebier</PERSON> said. ``We don't know how the lava actually
makes it to the top of the volcano.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900109-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-09-90 2157EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Volcanoes     01-09 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Volcanoes,0505</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Work On Seismic Equipment at Alaskan Volcano</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RETRANSMITTING a0735 to fix spelling of `volcanoes' in
slugline.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists spent <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> installing new
seismic devices on the flanks of Redoubt Volcano and repairing a
monitor damaged in an eruption last week. Schools were closed
because of an eruption <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The mountain remained active, but there were no significant
eruptions ollowing <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s blasts, which pushed ash and steam
eight miles into the air. The ash plume turned daylight to darkness
and blanketed parts of the nearby <LOCATION>Kenai Peninsula</LOCATION> with up to
three-quarters of an inch of ash.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state, scientists monitoring <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>
detected little seismic activity <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, but said they're not
ready to declare the volcano has returned to its slumber following
weekend earthquakes.
   Mount Redoubt's latest eruption occurred with little warning.
Scientists at the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Volcano Observatory</ORGANIZATION> said their most
sensitive monitor was damaged in a violent eruption last week, so
they may have missed the telltale increase in earthquake activity
which signalled previous eruptions.
   Unlike previous eruptions, there was no dome built up over the
eruptive vent prior to <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s eruption. That prompted scientists
to warn that similar violent eruptions could continue to occur
without warning.
   The volcano 115 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> had been dormant
for more than two decades before the latest sequence of eruptions
began <DATE>Dec. 13</DATE>.
   <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s ash plume mostly missed the major population
concentrations around Kenai and Homer, but the grit was heavy
enough for officials to close schools <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Kenai</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Soldotna</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Nikiski</LOCATION> and Sterling.
   No deaths or injuries were reported as a result of the volcanic
activity, but air travel and holiday mail have been snarled by the
almost continuous eruptions.
   At <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>, the weekend earthquakes sent a plume of ash
90 miles to the east, surprising scientists.
   ``It looks quiet right now, but I can't say it's going to stay
calm,'' said <PERSON>Chris Jonientz-Trisler</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Washington
Geophysics Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, 100 miles north of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It doesn't look at the present time like any eruption is
imminent,'' she said. ``One thing we've learned, though, is
anything can change.''
   Bad weather again prevented flights over the mountain, said
<PERSON>Cliff Hall</PERSON>, an operations staffer with the <ORGANIZATION>Cascade Volcano
Observatory</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We're unable to look at what's happened because of the rain
and wind and clouds,'' <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> said.
   Scientists speculated that steam emissions seen coming from the
volcano were caused by groundwater reaching superheated rock
beneath the volcano and turning to steam, or from gas released by
cooling molten rock.
   Ash expelled by the volcano over the weekend was tested and
found to be pulverized rock from previous eruptions rather than
freshly erupted matter.
   The volcano's last major eruption occurred on <DATE>March 19, 1982</DATE>. A
cataclysmic explosion on <DATE>May 18, 1980</DATE>, killed 57 people, devastated
230 square miles and sent up an ash cloud that circled the globe.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06165101 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06165101 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Special to the Mercury News; 'GUERRILLA SEISMOLOGIST' -- David
Harlow of the U.S. Geological Survey in Menlo Park and his wife, Pauline Lord,
on a visit to Mount Kilauea in Hawaii.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; RESEARCH; EARTH; SCIENCE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The cool-headed "guerrilla seismologist" from Menlo Park whose accurate
predictions of the eruptions of Mount Pinatubo helped save thousands of lives
in the Philippines is right where he wants to be -- a cramped bunker a dozen
miles from the exploding volcano.;    One of only a handful of volcano
seismologists in the world, David Harlow, 47, is known as an Indiana Jones of
volcanoes, jumping at the chance to get close enough to pick up the bumps and
tremors that signal an impending eruption and thriving on the high-pressure
decision-making that goes with making predictions.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EXPERT AN INDIANA JONES OF VOLCANOES
MENLO PARK MAN THRIVES ON PRESSURE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related story on page 1A of this section.
See also related story on this page.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "He's someone who eats it up," said <PERSON>Randy White</PERSON>, <PERSON>Harlow</PERSON>'s friend and
colleague at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Menlo Park</LOCATION>. "He's able to totally
concentrate in those sorts of situations.";    The eruptions at <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>
finally gave <PERSON>Harlow</PERSON> the chance to put his skills and experience to work saving
lives. When <PERSON>Harlow</PERSON> went to <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state in <DATE>1980</DATE>,
geologists were still learning how to read the telltale earthquakes.
Bureaucratic delays kept <PERSON>Harlow</PERSON> from arriving at <ORGANIZATION>Nevado de Ruiz</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>
until a day after its <DATE>1985</DATE> eruption. Harlow and his team predicted the <DATE>1989</DATE>
eruption of Redoubt Volcano in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, but few lives were threatened in the
