<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06320113 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06320113 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: John Adams' 'El Dorado' drew a 29-minute standing ovation  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-FRANCISCO; MUSIC; SHOW; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  COMPOSER John Adams' "El Dorado" ("The Golden One") was unveiled in a
shimmering world premiere Wednesday night at the San Francisco Symphony, with
Adams conducting.;    This was, in effect, the Berkeley composer's Christopher
Columbus piece, coming just before the 500th anniversary of Columbus' arrival
in the New World. Instead of focusing on the controversial discoverer,
however, Adams explored the dream of finding a gilded paradise here,
implicitly contrasting that dream with the current ravaging of our planet, one
of Adams' stated concerns.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  'EL DORADO' LEADS THE WAY TO PARADISE IN DAVIES
HALL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  REVIEW;  PERFORMANCE;  SETTING THE RECORD STRAIGHT (publ. 11/16/91, pg. 2C); 
Because of an editor's error, a caption in Friday's eye was incorrect. It
should have stated that John Adams' 29-minute "El Dorado" received a standing
ovation from the San Francisco Symphony audience.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     His 29-minute work got a standing ovation from many of the <ORGANIZATION>Davies Hall</ORGANIZATION>
patrons. It is so beautifully crafted in a style that is both familiar and
monumental that it likely will be performed and recorded often.;    Snobs may
scoff at <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' tried-and-true writing. There's the familiar crescendoing
pulse in the opening movement ("Bolero," anyone?), and the closing movement
forays into Sibelius-tinged orchestration, New Age sounds, and the <PERSON>Steve Reich</PERSON>
style of phase-shift music begun a generation ago.;    But <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>, 44, remains
one of the champion colorists of the <DATE>late 20th century</DATE>. His minimalism for
maximum orchestra is awe- inspiring, and in "El Dorado" he creates gilded
pyramids of thoroughly consonant sound.;    While most symphonic composers are
still uncomfortable with electronic music, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> is as much at ease with it as
with the full instrumental array on stage, which, for "El Dorado," included an
army of eight percussionists and heavy brass.;    His signal breakthrough in
this piece is the idiomatic integration of two synthesizers into the
orchestral texture. They spray their fine mist of exotic timbres and pitches
through the hall via 10 loudspeakers.;    Clearly <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> has broken through the
computer-phobia rampant at symphonies around the country, and it is high time.
Now any young symphonic composer who doesn't learn to use the synthesizer will
be ill prepared to create 21st-century music.;    The rest of the program
consisted of an Adams orchestration of a piece by <ORGANIZATION>Liszt</ORGANIZATION>, and two Stravinsky
works. I was far more impressed with <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' version of Liszt's "The Black
Gondola" this week than in hearing it at the <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo Music Festival</ORGANIZATION> three
months ago. The funereal piece shone <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, illuminated by the expert
players and a more vibrant hall.;    The original Liszt composition was for
cello and piano. Adams' orchestration incorporates a lot of low instruments --
English horn, violas and bass clarinet -- and does so exquisitely. Toward the
end, it employs a celestial choir of cellos. This highly sophisticated,
pictorial piece contrasts markedly with some vacuous Liszt works heard all too
often. It was deliciously chromatic -- and moving, too.;    As a conductor,
<PERSON>Adams</PERSON> has his strong and weak points. "El Dorado" seemed by far the most
successful effort <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. In the two Stravinsky pieces, he blunted the
accents and sapped much of their energy.;    In the prickly <ORGANIZATION>Stravinsky Violin
Concerto</ORGANIZATION>, however, soloist <PERSON>Stephanie Chase</PERSON>, formerly of the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>, gave a
more exciting reading than I have ever heard. I'm baffled why Chase has not
soloed with more of our major orchestras. After melting the hall with the
soulful "Aria II," she gave a masterful version of the tricky finale.;    The
hall needed all the melting it could get. Apparently cool to contemporary
music this <DATE>fall</DATE>, patrons stayed away in droves, just as they did for the
"Pulcinella" program conducted by visiting <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> Symphony music director
<PERSON>David Zinman</PERSON> two weeks ago.;    The other Stravinsky work, the whimsical opera
excerpt "The Song of the Nightingale," opened the program. But this time the
nightingale was sedate, with no punch.;    The concert will be broadcast <DATE>Nov.
26</DATE> at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> on KKHI radio.;  <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION>; World premiere of <PERSON>John
Adams</PERSON> '<LOCATION>El Dorado</LOCATION>,' conducted by the composer; Where: <PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>, Van
Ness Avenue at <ORGANIZATION>Grove Street</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; When: 8:30 tonight-Saturday;
Tickets: <MONEY>$22</MONEY>-<MONEY>$48</MONEY>; Call: (415) 431-5400  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PAUL HERTELENDY, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911115  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  22  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  695  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, November 15, 1991
00320113,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06209175 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06209175 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Sylvan  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE Cabrillo Music Festival is off and running again with what sounds like a
broken record: a new hall, expressive premieres, impressive symphonic music
and depressing acoustics.;    The festival's chancy firsts in soloists,
composer-in-residence, conductor and repertory came off resoundingly at the
prelude concert Thursday, though the new symphony hall is anything but
resounding.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  IMPRESSIVE WORKS, DEPRESSIVE ACOUSTICS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Music Review  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Composer-conductor <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>' docu-operas "Nixon in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>" (<DATE>1987</DATE>) and "The
Death of Klinghoffer" (<DATE>1991</DATE>) rank as the most talked-about in decades. He
changed styles between them, from a synthesizer-led minimalism in the first to
a diaphanous, non-synthesized orchestration prevalent in the second. In both,
the vocal lyricism, the unambiguous tonality and the importance of understood
text were hallmarks.;    <DATE>Thursday</DATE> provided the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> premieres of two arias
from "Klinghoffer," featuring the title-role protagonist <PERSON>Sanford Sylvan</PERSON>
repeating his triumph. Baritone Sylvan soared with a voice that dripped
honeyed richness in nonpareil abundance; he sounds like this generation's
<ORGANIZATION>Dietrich Fischer-Dieskau</ORGANIZATION>, but one with an unmistakable made-in-the-USA stamp,
once again signaling our American singers' coming of age.;    The pieces
offered a modern-day surrealism, whether in the soliloquy of the dying <PERSON>Leon
Klinghoffer</PERSON> during his slow-motion fall from the hijacked cruise ship, or the
strangely poetic "Bird Aria" of the Palestinian killer-terrorist Mamoud,
wistfully reflecting on the beauty of birds overhead.;    In both arias, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>
laid out a spacious, comfortable vocal line for <ORGANIZATION>Sylvan</ORGANIZATION>'s adagios with the
simplicity of a <PERSON>Purcell</PERSON>, committed to spotlighting the text's content rather
than any musical elaborations. Often the orchestra offered little more than
violin-dominated "halos" to encircle and embrace the voice, neatly rendered by
<PERSON>Adams</PERSON> himself on the podium. No hint of his earlier minimalism was evident.;  
 The conclusion is that <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> has again defied pigeonholing. He has entered
many styles with gusto, from chugging chordal repetition to modality to
near-Wagnerian romanticism to honky-tonk to a new post-minimalist
American-folk-like clarity. This versatility is a characteristic of a
tremendously inventive mind having many worlds yet left to conquer at the age
of 44, not all of them operatic.;    One non-operatic foray was his own
orchestration of Liszt's "La lugubre gondola" No. 2 ("The Black Gondola"),
which received its <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> premiere <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Writing late in life, Liszt
prophetically foresaw the death and funerary gondola trip of his son-in-law
<PERSON>Richard Wagner</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION> and wrote programmatic music to fit. Though there are
Wagnerian harmonies, and glints of themes recalling the chillingly haunting
<ORGANIZATION>Shepherd</ORGANIZATION>'s Horn solo from "Tristan und Isolde," <ORGANIZATION>Liszt</ORGANIZATION>'s treatment was almost
skeletal, whether in the piano version or in the alternate cello-piano version
played movingly beforehand by cellist <PERSON>Lee Duckles</PERSON> and pianist <PERSON>Emily
Wong-George.</PERSON>;    <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> transferred it, I think, too literally to orchestra,
with the string section taking most of the cello part, using almost no
harmonic filling out. The effect was too understated. Apart from Liszt
himself, no one short of <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON> should have carried out the orchestration. And
<PERSON>Wagner</PERSON> would have colored it so powerfully, so richly, that he'd have been
denounced as vehemently as <PERSON>Ted Turner</PERSON> is for his colorized movie classics.;   
The <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> Cruz Civic Auditorium, looking like a near-clone of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>'s, is a
Spartan half-century-old site better known for basketball than <ORGANIZATION>Beethoven</ORGANIZATION> and
<PERSON>Brahms</PERSON>. It lacks warmth on all fronts, but it offers capacity (900 seats for
this festival configuration), visibility and proximity. The most distant seat
sold is less than 80 feet from the podium, which is near center court on the
raised temporary stage.;    The auditorium sound for orchestra is pale and
distant. Future pressure will certainly come to amplify the orchestra as in
years past, despite all the (justified) kicking and screaming about sound
systems that have hardly proven state-of-the-art.;    The auditorium's big
plus is for chamber music, when the acoustic shell is drawn close to the
audience. The results then are downright gratifying, and no microphones need
to intrude.;    In addition, this 29th reprise of the fest born in <LOCATION>Aptos</LOCATION> is
offering pre-concert festivities out in the blocked-off street, with al fresco
dinners along with free local musical groups playing 75 minutes before curtain
time.;    There's even a booth selling numerous recordings made by Music
Director <PERSON>Dennis Russell Davies</PERSON> (who is on sabbatical), but so far none of the
many CDs of his internationally toasted <DATE>1991</DATE> fill-in, <LOCATION>Adams.</LOCATION>;    That should
change quickly if <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' impressive opening concert is any guide.;    CABRILLO
NOTES -- Tickets remain for all festival concerts except for the two San <PERSON>Juan
Bautista</PERSON> "run-out" concerts <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. . . . <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' "Klinghoffer" opera makes its
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> debut in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> this <DATE>fall</DATE>, coming to the <LOCATION>San Francisco Opera</LOCATION> in
<DATE>November 1992</DATE>. . . . <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' Liszt orchestration is featured at the <LOCATION>San
Francisco Symphony</LOCATION>, along with his (as yet incomplete) world premiere "El
Dorado" <DATE>Nov. 13-17</DATE>, with the composer conducting. . . . The festival received
a <MONEY>$105,000</MONEY> grant from the <PERSON>Daniel</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Flora Hewlett Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, plus another
<MONEY>$35,000</MONEY> in grants through the county Cultural Council for setting up the Civic
Auditorium with a suitable central stage and lighting grid. . . . Concert
patrons got a big scare <DATE>Thursday</DATE> with an auditorium-wide power failure toward
the end of intermission <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Fortunately, power and music were both
restored soon after.; <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo Music Festival</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> and <PERSON>JoAnn Falletta</PERSON>,
guest conductors; Where: <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Civic Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, Center and Church
streets; When: Thursdays-Sundays through <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>, plus weekend matinees. Also
this <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at San <PERSON>Juan Bautista</PERSON> (sold out). No repeat concerts.; Tickets:
<MONEY>$15.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$23.50</MONEY>; Call: (408) 429-3444.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PAUL HERTELENDY, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910727  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  945  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday July 27, 1991
00209175,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-1062</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFZARAE6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940625
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 JUN 94 / Arts: Sizzler in the concert hall
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Paul Driver</ORGANIZATION> reviews <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>' new concerto conducted by <ORGANIZATION>Ken Nagano
The London Symphony Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>'s concert under <PERSON>Kent Nagano</PERSON> at <ORGANIZATION>Barbican Hall</ORGANIZATION>
on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> was designed to be sizzling and balletic: <ORGANIZATION>Ravel's La Valse</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Prokofiev</ORGANIZATION>'s Romeo and <PERSON>Juliet</PERSON> ballet suite and the European premiere of the
Violin Concerto by the American <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> (born <DATE>1947</DATE>), a composer renowned
for heady minimalist rhythmic intensities. <LOCATION>Nagano</LOCATION> is a leading exponent of
<ORGANIZATION>Adams</ORGANIZATION>'s work, having launched (and latterly recorded) his opera The Death of
<PERSON>Klinghoffer</PERSON> and performed many of his other pieces.
He is also a guaranteed sizzler in the concert hall. His account of <ORGANIZATION>Ravel</ORGANIZATION>'s
bewitching yet brutally vivid 'choreographic poem', that strangely extrovert
threnody for the old <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, which begins in the ballroom to end on the
battlefield, made one feel the truth of all those epithets and brought home
the sheer sonorous power of the <ORGANIZATION>LSO</ORGANIZATION>, especially in the lower and darkly
rumbling registers. No matter how dark and rumbling the sounds, they were
always precisely focussed: little curling counterpoints took on chilling
force.
Adams's concerto, written in <DATE>1993</DATE> and premiered in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> in <DATE>January</DATE>
(with soloist <PERSON>Jorja Fleezanis</PERSON>) is also a kind of choreographic poem, having
been jointly commissioned not only by two orchestras (<LOCATION>Minnesota Orchestra</LOCATION>;
LSO) but by the <LOCATION>New York City Ballet</LOCATION>. Adams's strict, often motoric rhythmic
manner and colourful (but often inwardly complex) imagery lend themselves
readily to dance.
His <DATE>1988</DATE> score Fearful Symmetries has been choreographed no less than six
times, most recently by <PERSON>Ashley Page</PERSON>, whose Royal Ballet version opened at
Covent Garden last week.
But it was out of the experience of opera composing, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> writes, that the
present concerto sprang. To him it illustrates a melodic and harmonic
flexibility and a contrapuntal richness alien to the minimalist rigour of
his earlier work but called for by <ORGANIZATION>The Death of Klinghoffer</ORGANIZATION> and now the
basis of what he calls a 'post-Klinghoffer', or post-minimalist, language.
Actually, few minimalist composers besides the soporific <ORGANIZATION>Philip Glass</ORGANIZATION> have
tended to keep matters truly minimalist for long; but there is no mistaking
the opulent melodic and contrapuntal intentions of this new work, even if
the part-writing is heavily dependent on flurrying scale passages, and the
rhapsodising does not quite throw up tunes.
The orchestra used is small (double winds), but a large assortment of
percussion and a pair of synthesisers make up the odds. When the latter are
not spending time perversely imitating the harp, they contribute some novel,
ethereal effects. There are the three movements, fast-slow-fast, traditional
to a concerto: the second a gently musing and attractive Chaconne with the
curious subtitle 'Body through which the dream flows'; the third an
exceptionally lively Toccata with extra bite supplied by claves and cowbell.
The solo part, brilliantly despatched by <PERSON>Gidon Kremer</PERSON>, is full of
traditional figurations and devices. With likeable impunity and verve, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>
has produced a virtuoso vehicle in something like the grand romantic manner.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7922 Theatrical Producers and Services.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XXII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06208120 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06208120 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO:; cp,11 Adams is the closet thing we have today to a star composer  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IN THE heyday of Verdi, Rossini and Puccini, opera houses vied to perform the
star composers' latest works before the clamoring public.;    One man commands
that kind of attention today: Berkeley's John Adams, whose 1991 opera "The
Death of Klinghoffer" was booked by six opera houses before the first
rehearsal started.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  OPERA'S YOUNG BRIGHT HOPE TO TAKE BOWS AT
CABRILLO  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  PERFORMANCE  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Earlier this month the low-key, local-boy-turned-star <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> was back home
briefly between conducting the <LOCATION>Cleveland Orchestra</LOCATION> and recording his opera
with the <ORGANIZATION>Opera de Lyon</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. It's that kind of life now: commissions,
major engagements, jet commutes, 15-hour days.;    At 44, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> still manages
the aw-shucks, pebble-kicking quality that has endeared him to the Bay Area
musical community since joining the <ORGANIZATION>San Francisco Conservatory of Music</ORGANIZATION>
faculty in <DATE>1972.</DATE>;    Music macabre;  Now it's Cabrillo's turn. In the biggest
coup since engaging Music Director <PERSON>Dennis Russell Davies</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo Music
Festival</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> has <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> on the podium for two weeks during <PERSON>Davies</PERSON>'
sabbatical year.;    The kind of audacity marking <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' guest-conducting
programs around the country is being carried over to <LOCATION>Cabrillo</LOCATION>. Few
composer-conductors have the panache to open their festival with such morbid
morsels as their own "Aria of the Falling Body," and close with <ORGANIZATION>Mahler</ORGANIZATION>'s
"Songs on the Death of Children" and <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s "Sinfonia da requiem," after
several equally lugubrious selections.;    The edge of the new;  While <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Mahler</PERSON> and <PERSON>Britten</PERSON> all get attention, the Cabrillo focus is on newer music, in
which the composer-conductor offers special insights, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> points out.;   
"It's helpful on both sides. My composing informs my conducting. When doing
music of other composers, I have a different intuition.;    "Also my
conducting informs my composing -- I'm aware of necessities, of what
instruments can and cannot do, and what can be done in limited rehearsal
time.";    The <DATE>1991</DATE> Cabrillo sojourn getting into full swing tonight could be
termed a season of mystical horizons. It offers <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s songs on <PERSON>William
Blake</PERSON>, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' stunning vocal concert piece "The Wound-Dresser," his own
orchestration of Liszt's "The Black Gondola" (a preview of his
premiere-studded <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Symphony program in the fall), part of
<PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s "Kingdom of the Pagodas," and <PERSON>Milhaud</PERSON>'s "The Creation of the World"
(danced by <ORGANIZATION>Tandy Beal &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>).;    Overriding it all is the shadow of <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>'
opera, "The Death of Klinghoffer," a work based on the Palestinian hijacking
of the "Achille Lauro" cruise ship in the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>. The work will
not reach the <LOCATION>San Francisco Opera</LOCATION> until <DATE>November 1992</DATE>, but Cabrillo scheduled
excerpts and offers performances by its title-role singer, baritone <PERSON>Sanford
Sylvan.</PERSON>;    Because of the opera, a <ORGANIZATION>Middle Eastern</ORGANIZATION> theme overlays the concerts
the <DATE>second weekend</DATE>, with <PERSON>Nazim Ozel</PERSON> on Turkish flute and "semi-civilized tree"
(a custom-made, plucked musical instrument) <DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>, and a collaboration by
<ORGANIZATION>Group Parvaneh</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ballet Afsaneh</ORGANIZATION> with Turkish and Persian music and dance
<DATE>Aug. 4.</DATE>;    Modern melodies;  But nothing is a one-man show, not even with
<PERSON>Adams</PERSON> around. Music Director <PERSON>Davies</PERSON> collaborated via long distance in the
programming decisions. <PERSON>JoAnn Falletta</PERSON> leads the juried concert of music by
living <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> composers <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, with pieces by <PERSON>Ross Bauer</PERSON>,
<PERSON>David Jaffe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Stefan Carow</PERSON>, <PERSON>Allen Shearer</PERSON> and "the other" <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>, <PERSON>John
Luther</PERSON> Adams.;    This Cabrillo season features prominent soloists such as
violinist <PERSON>Stephanie Chase</PERSON> and pianist <PERSON>Richard Goode</PERSON>, and finally what may be
an end to the nomadic Cabrillo life: an entry into the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Civic
Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, thanks to a <MONEY>$35,000</MONEY> renovation. The face-lift instantly converts
the 1,950-seat hall into a 970-seat concert site with new lighting, sound
system, grid and proscenium. All the concerts (except <DATE>Aug. 28</DATE>) are being held
at the auditorium.;     <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo Music Festival</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> and <PERSON>JoAnn
Falletta</PERSON>, guest conductors; Where: <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Civic Auditorium</LOCATION>; When: Nightly
Thursdays-Sundays through <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>, with weekend matinees. Also this <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at
<LOCATION>San Juan Bautista</LOCATION>. No repeat concerts.; Tickets: <MONEY>$15.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$23.50</MONEY>. (408) 429-3444.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PAUL HERTELENDY, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910726  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  47  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  673  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday July 26, 1991
00208120,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06099044 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06099044 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: John Adams will lead several of his own compositions;
PHOTO: Bernstein  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  COMPOSER John Adams will take over the baton from music director Dennis
Russell Davies for the 1991 Cabrillo Music Festival, which will run July
25-Aug. 4 at a new home in Santa Cruz County.;    Davies is on sabbatical for
the festival's 29th season, though he helped Adams plan its repertoire.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CABRILLO MUSIC FESTIVAL HAS NEW LEADER, NEW
HALL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Classical Music  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     'Klinghoffer' heard;    The programs will feature the first American
hearing of an excerpt from <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' new opera, "The Death of Klinghoffer" (<DATE>July
25</DATE>), as well as his cantata "The Wound Dresser" (<DATE>July 28</DATE>), an anti-war piece
with text by <PERSON>Walt Whitman</PERSON>, who dressed wounds as a medical orderly during the
Civil War. The American premiere of <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' "Eros Piano" will be given <DATE>Aug. 2.</DATE>;
   Guest artists include baritone <PERSON>Sanford Sylvan</PERSON>, for whom the title role in
"Klinghoffer" was written; pianist <PERSON>Richard Goode</PERSON>; violinist <PERSON>Stephanie Chase</PERSON>;
soprano <PERSON>Dora Ohrenstein</PERSON>, a longtime member of the <ORGANIZATION>Philip Glass Ensemble</ORGANIZATION>; and
conductor <PERSON>JoAnn Falletta</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Bay Area Women</LOCATION>'s Philharmonic.;    The
festival will include its first-ever dance program, featuring <ORGANIZATION>Tandy Beal &amp;
Company of Santa Cruz</ORGANIZATION> and live orchestra (<DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>). Traditional Persian music
and dance will be performed by <ORGANIZATION>Group Parvaneh</ORGANIZATION> and Ballet Afsaneh (<DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>).;   
<ORGANIZATION>Nazim Ozel</ORGANIZATION> will play a Turkish flute called a ney and "the amazing 500-string
Semi-Civilized Tree" (<DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>). And the festival will present a concert in
<LOCATION>Mission San Juan Bautista</LOCATION> by the Oakland-based gospel choir Elements of Praise
(<DATE>July 28</DATE>).;    After <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>, the most-heard composer will be <PERSON>Benjamin Britten</PERSON>,
with performances scheduled of his "Phantasy Quartet" for oboe and strings
(<DATE>July 25</DATE>); "The Arrival and Adventures of <ORGANIZATION>Belle Rose</ORGANIZATION> in the Kingdom of the
Pagodas" (<DATE>Aug. 2</DATE>), an excerpt from the ballet "The Prince of the Pagodas";
"Songs and Proverbs of <PERSON>William Blake</PERSON>" (<ORGANIZATION>Sylvan</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Goode</PERSON>, <DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>); and the
powerful "Sinfonia da Requiem" as the festival finale (<DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>).;    The
complementary repertoire will be heavily neo-romantic, acknowledging <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>'
roots in 19th-century music. Among the major works to be heard: the late
<PERSON>Leonard Bernstein</PERSON>'s "Serenade," a "Platonic dialogue" for violin and orchestra
(<DATE>July 26</DATE>); two versions of <PERSON>Franz Liszt</PERSON>'s "The Black Gondola," for solo piano
(<DATE>July 25</DATE>) and orchestrated by <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> (<DATE>July 28</DATE>); "Kindertotenlieder" ("Songs on
the Death of Children") by <PERSON>Gustav Mahler</PERSON> (<DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>); and the <DATE>1947</DATE> version of
<ORGANIZATION>Stravinsky</ORGANIZATION>'s "Petrouchka.";    On <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE>, <PERSON>Ohrenstein</PERSON> will perform "Urban
Diva," an original cabaret piece that includes contemporary vocal showpieces
such as <PERSON>John Cage</PERSON>'s "Aria.";    <ORGANIZATION>The Cultural Council of Santa Cruz County</ORGANIZATION> has
raised <MONEY>$35,000</MONEY> to turn <PERSON>Santa Cruz</PERSON>'s barn-like Civic Auditorium from a
1,950-seat arena to a 970-seat concert hall, defined by an acoustical shell
and other technical assistance.;    The festival, which has performed under
increasingly cramped conditions in the <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo College</ORGANIZATION> theater and an array
of local churches, as well as a problematic tent on the <ORGANIZATION>University of
California</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz</ORGANIZATION> campus, will become one of the auditorium's two
principal tenants. The <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz County Symphony</ORGANIZATION> (which <ORGANIZATION>Falletta</ORGANIZATION> directs) is
the other.;    The tradition of San <PERSON>Juan Bautista</PERSON> Day (<DATE>July 28</DATE>) will be
maintained. Two concerts are scheduled for <DATE>July 28</DATE> in the mission: a <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>
orchestral program and the gospel singers at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>; IFYOU'RE INTERESTED; To
receive a festival brochure, call (408) 662-2701. Single tickets will be on
sale <DATE>June 1</DATE> from (408) 429-3444.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JUDITH GREEN, Mercury News Arts Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910408  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  16B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  571  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 8, 1991
00099044,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-12365</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CA0BDADFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920127
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 JAN 92 / Arts: American symphonists - Andrew Porter reviews much
noisy, angry, well meaning music and has to cover his ears
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW PORTER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
According to a recent survey by the <ORGANIZATION>American Symphony Orchestra League</ORGANIZATION>,
covering five years of programmes by the leading orchestras, <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> (the
composer of the operas <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and The Death of Klinghoffer) is the
living American composer most often played. <PERSON>Kurt Masur</PERSON> began his
directorship of the <LOCATION>New York Philharmonic</LOCATION> with <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>'s Short Ride in a Fast
Machine and <PERSON>Tromba Lontana</PERSON>, two short works, one loud and one soft. El
Dorado, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>'s latest orchestra piece, was given its premiere recently by
the <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION>, which commissioned it. It's about 'the greed of
the eighties', we are told, with a first movement, angry and violent, that
is 'my own response to the Gulf War'.
I've not heard <LOCATION>El Dorado</LOCATION>, but last month in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> there were two
symphonies containing much angry, noisy music. <PERSON>John Corigliano</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>First
Symphony</ORGANIZATION> was inspired by the sight of the AIDS Memorial Quilt, those
thousands of commemorative panels for those who have died. Each movement
recalls a lost musician friend. The first, 'Of Rage and Remembrance', begins
'ferociously' and includes pages on end of slashing chords marked 'tutti as
loud as possible', but in a quiet episode a distant piano is heard playing
the <ORGANIZATION>Albeniz Tango</ORGANIZATION>, a favourite piece of the pianist friend remembered.
The central movement, a <LOCATION>Tarantella</LOCATION>, recalls a friend in the music business,
famed for his wit, who became mad; a trivial tarantella tune is put through
increasingly horrible distortions. Corigliano found the motto theme of the
finale, 'Giulio's Song', while listening to 30-year-old tapes of himself and
a cellist friend improvising. Played by a solo cello, it begins with the
whole-tone ascent that in <ORGANIZATION>Berg</ORGANIZATION>'s Violin Concerto spells 'Es ist genug'.
Other themes join it; in the score they are named, and the names are those
of musician friends who have died. The music mounts to a battering funeral
march, with the clash and clamour of bells; in a quiet coda earlier themes
are recalled.
The work was commissioned by the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Symphony</ORGANIZATION>, which gave the first
performance, under <PERSON>Barenboim</PERSON>. It was recorded (<ORGANIZATION>Erato</ORGANIZATION>); the disc has stayed
for months in Billboard's Classical Top Ten; <PERSON>Corigliano</PERSON> won the Grawemeyer
Award, music's 'Nobel Prize'. (<PERSON>Birtwistle</PERSON>, for The Mask of Orpheus; <PERSON>Ligeti</PERSON>,
for the piano Preludes; and <ORGANIZATION>Chinary Ung</ORGANIZATION>, for <ORGANIZATION>Spiral</ORGANIZATION>, were earlier winners.)
At the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> premiere, which was given by the <ORGANIZATION>Philharmonic</ORGANIZATION> under <PERSON>Leonard
Slatkin</PERSON>, panels of the Quilt hung in the lobby of <PERSON>Fisher Hall</PERSON>, and the
audience was invited to inscribe the names of dead loved ones on a new
panel. The emotional charge was high. The critic must steel his heart to say
that, for all the pain and grief and love that it expresses, the musical
means of expression are undistinguished, conventional, obvious. The <ORGANIZATION>New York
Times</ORGANIZATION> went so far as to call the result 'vulgar'.
Aaron <PERSON>Jay Kernis</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Second Symphony</ORGANIZATION>, which was given its first performance by
the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Symphony</ORGANIZATION> under <PERSON>Hugh Wolff</PERSON>, addresses even more 'the endless
violence of the Gulf War, the subtle and unsubtle encroachment upon women's
and minority rights, the hovering threat of censorship of artists along with
the economic, social, and medical disasters that plague us daily'. Adams is
45, <PERSON>Corigliano</PERSON> is 54; <PERSON>Kernis</PERSON> is a younger composer, born in <DATE>1960</DATE>, who has
become very prominent. He wrote some good, exuberantly inventive works in
his youth: Dream of the Morning Sky (<DATE>1983</DATE>), for soprano and orchestra; Love
Scenes (<DATE>1987</DATE>), for soprano (Dawn Upshaw) and cello. But now, as work after
work after work pours out, he seems content to press the conventional
response triggers.
His first symphony, Symphony in Waves, had its premiere earlier this season
from the <ORGANIZATION>New York Chamber Symphony</ORGANIZATION>, and has been recorded. It included
Adams-like passages of minimalism. The movements of the <ORGANIZATION>Second Symphony</ORGANIZATION> are
entitled 'Alarm' 'Air/Ground', and 'Barricade'. The first, marked
'aggressively', contains wave upon wave of noisy climax underpinned by
ostinato. In the second, simple melodies wander over 'grounded' harmonies.
While writing the third, <PERSON>Kernis</PERSON> says, 'a recurring image was the building
full of innocent Iraqi civilians under siege which was mistakenly bombed and
obliterated nearly a year ago'; it ends with the loudest noise I have ever
heard in a concert hall - four tam-tams whacked 'at maximum volume' for five
long seconds. Audience and orchestra players covered their ears.
Crash-bang - alternating (but not always) with episodes soft, sentimental,
and soupy - has become the mode of the successful American orchestra works
taken up in city after city. <ORGANIZATION>Del Tredici</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> screams at the top of her
voice; he himself describes his Steps, composed for the <LOCATION>Philharmonic</LOCATION>, as
'violent and raucous . . . clattering . . . Godzilla battling Megalon'. This
is music for people already half-deafened, responsive only to high-decibel
assault. And he is not the only composer who writes it.
Poster-art is in vogue. American orchestras (and their conductors) -
shunning <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>, Sessions, <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON> - embrace it. When not strident, it's
'nostalgic'. In the programme that brought the <PERSON>Kernis</PERSON>, there was a 'new'
Flute Concerto, by <PERSON>Joseph Turrin</PERSON>, in sub-Prokofiev vein. In the <ORGANIZATION>Philharmonic</ORGANIZATION>
programme after the one that brought the <PERSON>Corigliano</PERSON>, <PERSON>Slatkin</PERSON> championed
<PERSON>Claude Baker</PERSON>'s Shadows, a 'Japanese' piece such as many composers have
written: a flower arrangement of exquisite sounds - scratch, patter, tinkle
and ting - based on four haiku but also (with full acknowledgement and
near-quotation) on movements by <ORGANIZATION>Mahler</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>, and <ORGANIZATION>Stravinsky</ORGANIZATION>. Dainty
working, no harm it in at all - and no sustenance. We might as well have
been listening to <PERSON>Takemitsu</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06087055 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06087055 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Herbert Blomstedt will move the S.F. Symphony to the Civic
Auditorium for two weeks next season, while renovation work is done on Davies
hall.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE San Francisco Symphony announced plans for its 80th season (1991-92)
Tuesday, and with the announcement came news that major acoustic renovations
at the orchestra's home, Davies Symphony Hall, will cause disruptions at
season's end.;    Because of the Davies reconstruction, the symphony will move
into the Civic Auditorium during its last two subscription weeks (May 20-29,
1992).  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DAVIES WORK DISRUPTS S.F. SYMPHONY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Classical Music  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "That is why we want to give the <ORGANIZATION>Verdi 'Requiem</ORGANIZATION>' then -- it's the place for
a big sound," explained Music Director <PERSON>Herbert Blomstedt</PERSON> yesterday from his
home in <LOCATION>Lucerne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland.</LOCATION>;    Recording postponed;    The annual May
recordings with <ORGANIZATION>London Records</ORGANIZATION> will have to be postponed until <DATE>fall 1992</DATE>. And
for one week in <DATE>May</DATE> the orchestra will be silent, right after its three-week
Asian tour.;    <ORGANIZATION>Blomstedt</ORGANIZATION> will be on the podium for 15 instead of the usual 16
weeks because of that <DATE>May week</DATE> without programs. Three of his weeks on the
podium will be during the Asian tour.;    The ambitious program, <PERSON>Blomstedt</PERSON>
says, serves his goal "to give everybody a new and fresh experience" in the
concert hall.;    Some highlights:;    (box) The season opens with a gala
<DATE>Sept. 4</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Davies</ORGANIZATION>, with coloratura soprano <PERSON>Kathleen Battle</PERSON> singing <PERSON>Richard
Strauss</PERSON> and works by <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON> and Berlioz.;    (box) Guest conductor <PERSON>David
Zinman</PERSON>, who is looking more and more like a fixture here, will return for two
weeks. Other guest conductors include <PERSON>Roger Norrington</PERSON>, <PERSON>Eduardo Mata</PERSON>, <PERSON>Christof
Perick</PERSON>, composer <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>, <PERSON>Iona Brown</PERSON>, <PERSON>Michael Tilson Thomas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kent Nagano</PERSON>,
<PERSON>John Nelson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Neal Stulberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Silvain Cambreling</PERSON>. Conducting during two weeks
of subscription concerts, each, are <PERSON>Semyon Bychkov</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gunther Herbig</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Alasdair Neale.</PERSON>;    (box) <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> audiences will hear the large-scale <PERSON>Charles
Ives Symphony</PERSON> No. 4. This American answer to <ORGANIZATION>Mahler</ORGANIZATION>'s symphonies, which dates
back to the World War I era, will be given under <PERSON>Michael Tilson Thomas</PERSON>, <DATE>Nov.
20-23</DATE>, with the symphony chorus.;    (box) <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>' podium week <DATE>Nov. 13-16</DATE>
will feature the commissioned world premiere of his own "El Dorado.";    (box)
Other commissioned world premieres include <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> composer <PERSON>Charles
Wuorinen</PERSON>'s 35-minute-long "Genesis" on Christian texts, written for chorus and
orchestra, and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> composer <PERSON>Wayne Peterson</PERSON>'s "The Face of <TIME>Night</TIME>, the
Heart of the Dark.";    (box) Other music by living composers includes various
pieces by <PERSON>Henri Dutilleux</PERSON>, <PERSON>Christopher Rouse</PERSON>'s "Iscariot," <PERSON>Alfred Schnittke</PERSON>'s
"(K)ein Sommernachtstraum," <PERSON>Joan Tower</PERSON>'s "Sequoia," <PERSON>George Perle</PERSON>'s "Dance
Fantasy" and excerpts from Sir <PERSON>Michael Tippett</PERSON>'s "The Midsummer Marriage.";   
(box) Other unusual repertoire features a program consisting entirely of
<ORGANIZATION>Manuel de Falla</ORGANIZATION>'s music, with "Homenajes" and the opera "La Vida Breve";
<ORGANIZATION>Stravinsky</ORGANIZATION>'s complete "Pulcinella," with voices; <PERSON>Honegger</PERSON>'s "Christmas
Cantata"; <ORGANIZATION>Barber</ORGANIZATION>'s Cello Concerto; <ORGANIZATION>Corigliano</ORGANIZATION>'s Symphony No. 1; and <PERSON>Francaix</PERSON>'s
"The Flower Clock.";    (box) The recording repertory next season with <ORGANIZATION>London
Records</ORGANIZATION> is not all traditional either, with <PERSON>Schubert</PERSON>'s "Great C Major"
Symphony (No. 9), <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON>'s "Siegfried Idyll," <PERSON>Franz Berwald</PERSON>'s "Symphonie
Serieuse," <PERSON>Schubert</PERSON>'s Overture in the Italian Style, and <PERSON>Strauss</PERSON>' tone poem
"Ein Heldenleben" on the agenda.;    (box) Performances of <PERSON>Berlioz</PERSON>'
vocal-dramatic symphony "Romeo et Juliette," under <PERSON>Roger Norrington.</PERSON>;    (box)
Star soloists include pianists <PERSON>Mitsuko Uchida</PERSON>, <PERSON>Horacio Gutierrez</PERSON>, <PERSON>Garrick
Ohlsson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Peter Serkin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Andre Watts</PERSON>; violinist Cho-Liang Lin; and sopranos
<PERSON>Jessye Norman</PERSON>, <PERSON>June Anderson</PERSON> and Dawn Upshaw.;    Special events;    (box)
Special events, guest ensembles and recitals will feature pianist <PERSON>Maurizio
Pollini</PERSON>; the Soviet Philharmonic under <PERSON>Gennady Rozhdestvensky</PERSON>; the <LOCATION>Cleveland
Orchestra</LOCATION> under <PERSON>Christoph von Dohnanyi</PERSON>; the <LOCATION>Minnesota Orchestra</LOCATION> under Edo de
Waart; and the Academy of St. Martin-in-the-Fields.;    (box) The violinists
<PERSON>Itzhak Perlman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Isaac Stern</PERSON> will be back for their near-annual
appearances.;    (box) The symphony will also present the Joffrey Ballet
again, <DATE>June 29-July 12, 1992</DATE>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PAUL HERTELENDY, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910327  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5G  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  633  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday March 27, 1991
00087055,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06212100 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06212100 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW; SAN-JUAN-BAUTISTA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  HAS any performance in Mission San Juan Bautista ever started on time?;    The
mission is still a working church, and its calendar of weddings and
christenings bumps up against the Cabrillo Music Festival, El Teatro Campesino
and other users. On Sunday afternoon, Cabrillo's concert was delayed about 20
minutes by an annual ceremony in which local Indians forgive the church for
crimes committed against them in the name of Christianity. (Pretty generous of
them, considering.)  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DARK VISIONS, BEAUTIFUL MUSIC AT CABRILLO
FEST  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Music Review  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The concert was a beauty, despite being upset by the abrupt departure of
its Franco-Romanian concertmaster, <PERSON>Romuald Tecco</PERSON>, to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> for his mother's
funeral.;    'Klinghoffer' aria substituted; Instead of the <PERSON>Shostakovich</PERSON>
violin concerto he was to have played, <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>, guest music director for
the <DATE>1991</DATE> season, substituted "The Bird Aria" from his own opera, "The Death of
Klinghoffer." (It is scheduled for <LOCATION>San Francisco Opera</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1992</DATE> season.);    The
aria is sung by the Palestinian Mamoud as he watches the birds from the deck
of the doomed ship <PERSON>Achille Lauro</PERSON>: "Messengers of God . . . angels free to
marry and die," he calls them (in <PERSON>Alice Goodman</PERSON>'s lovely text).;    Its winged
imagery was complemented by "The Black Gondola," a barcarolle for piano (1882)
by <PERSON>Franz Liszt</PERSON>, transcribed by <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> in the dark colors of French and English
horns and massed cellos.;    Civil War horrors;  The second half grew even
darker with "The Wound-Dresser," a tableau for baritone and orchestra by
<ORGANIZATION>Adams</ORGANIZATION>, to a text by <PERSON>Walt Whitman</PERSON>. This prose-poem, based on <ORGANIZATION>Whitman</ORGANIZATION>'s
experiences as a medical orderly during the Civil War, describes the horrors
of war's aftermath in unflinching terms. Whitman faced gangrene and amputated
limbs, infected wounds and unstoppable bleeding as bravely as any more
celebrated war hero, and his compassion for the dying soldiers makes the poem
bearable.;    It's not a likely subject for the concert hall, but <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> has
made it into a powerful piece of musical painting. It was written for <PERSON>Sanford
Sylvan</PERSON>, an American baritone with an exceptionally resonant and lustrous
voice. (He also sang the "Klinghoffer" excerpt.) He's so compelling that even
depressing sentiments became things of beauty in his voice. He sings again at
<TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>: a cycle of songs by <PERSON>Benjamin Britten</PERSON>, to poems of <LOCATION>William
Blake.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> filled out the program with <PERSON>Haydn</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Symphony No.</ORGANIZATION> 83, subtitled
"La Poule" or "The Hen" because of an oboe tune that supposedly sounds like
clucking) and <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON> (Symphony No. 39). These were performed with zest and
even brilliance, despite a few orchestral slips. The <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON> got a big,
generous performance, making one appreciate <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' gifts as a legit (as
opposed to a strictly new music) conductor.;    Amplified gospel suffers; 
With its thick adobe walls and plain box shape, the mission is kind to
classical music. The Cabrillo orchestra sounds like the <LOCATION>Vienna Philharmonic</LOCATION>
here, yet preserves the agility of a chamber ensemble.;    The Elements of
Praise, a contemporary gospel choir from <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, were not so fortunate. These
lively acoustics took their amplified arrangements, chewed them up and spit
them out as gibberish. However, the evangelical arm-twisting that connected
their songs came through loud and clear and offensive.;    The festival moves
back to <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Civic Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> for its second weekend of performances.;  
  <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo Music Festival</ORGANIZATION>; Through: <DATE>Sunday</DATE>; Where: Civic Auditorium, 301
Center St., <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>; Tickets: <MONEY>$15.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$23.50</MONEY>. (408) 429-3444; Parking: Street  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JUDITH GREEN, Mercury News Arts Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Juan Bautista  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910730  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  562  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday July 30, 1991
00212100,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-11095</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DBDCDAFXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930204
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 FEB 93 / Arts: Born in the USA - Concert
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW CLEMENTS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
In the <DATE>1970s</DATE> <PERSON>George Crumb</PERSON> was the most performed of contemporary American
composers, a success founded on his knack of offering all the exotic
textural trappings of the avant garde within a friendly sugar-coated shell.
Twenty years on it is <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> who occupies a similar position of eminence
in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>. Adams's confections may be sugar-free yet they have their own
surface allure, even if in keeping with the spirit of the <DATE>1990s</DATE> it is a far
more astringent one.
On <DATE>Monday</DATE> Adams himself conducted the <LOCATION>London Sinfonietta</LOCATION> in a programme of
contemporary American works, three of them UK premieres, which ended with
<ORGANIZATION>Crumb's Ancient Voices of Children</ORGANIZATION>. The song cycle was beautifully delivered
by the mezzosoprano <PERSON>Christine Whittlesey</PERSON> and treble <PERSON>Sam Pay</PERSON>, yet sounds now
a museum piece, the thin musical substance sustained only by its web of
cultural references and the undimmed beauty of the <LOCATION>Lorca</LOCATION> text.
There just might be more magic left in the sounds than was obvious here, for
<ORGANIZATION>Adams</ORGANIZATION> conducts rather as he composes, with bold poster colours and bracing
rhythmic energy which leave precious little room for subtlety or magic.
Certainly <PERSON>Peter Lieberson</PERSON>'s nimble Raising the Gaze would have benefitted
from more air and awareness of light and shade than <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> and the
Sinfonietta instrumentalists suggested, while <PERSON>Tod Machover</PERSON>'s Song of Penance
seemed over-insistently eloquent.
<PERSON>Machover</PERSON>'s was, though, an intriguing construction, with a solo
computer-linked 'hyperviola' (played by <PERSON>Paul Silverstone</PERSON>) set against dense
textures which combined live and pre-recorded instruments and voices. A
specially commissioned poem serves as thematic backbone; it appears in both
spoken and sung form throughout the work, usually embedded deep in the
textures, while the hyperviola alternates keening chromaticism with ripe
romantic harmonies. The mixture is beguiling and repellent by turns like
latter day Skryabin; the sheer density of the sound world is seductive in
itself.
There was some new Adams too, a Chamber Symphony completed <DATE>last year</DATE> which
was receiving its first British performance. The Schoenbergian echoes of the
title belie the musical substance. There are three movements with
calculatedly memorable titles  - '<ORGANIZATION>Mongrel Airs</ORGANIZATION>', 'Aria with Walking Bass',
'Roadrunner'  - and plenty of spiky stylistic allusions along the way.
The first movement jumbles Soldier's Tale Stravinsky with <PERSON>Threepenny Opera
Weill</PERSON>, the second unfolds an increasing elaborate skein of lyrical lines
over a constantly mobile bass, while the finale is an extrovert romp, highly
virtuosic (brilliantly played by the Sinfonietta) and propelled by a
rock-like rhythmic pulse. It is artfully put together, undeniably attractive
and ultimately, I suspect, totally specious.
Barbican <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> Radio 3
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7929  Entertainers and Entertainment Groups.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment and Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06072002 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06072002 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: John Adams  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  CANDIDATES for San Jose Symphony's music directorship are being aggressively
courted by rival organizations, just as though they were the most eligible
bachelors at the prom.;    Leonid Grin, the Soviet emigre who scored such a
vibrant success with critics and audiences when he was guest conductor in
February, looked like the front-runner for a similar vacancy at the Spokane,
Wash., Symphony. Spokane reps even traveled to hear him in San Jose, and Grin
went to Spokane to conduct some audition rehearsals.;    But now, amid great
sighs of relief by local symphony-watchers, Spokane has named another Soviet
emigre -- Vakhtang Jordania -- as its music director. So Grin remains in the
running for San Jose -- at least until the next offer pops up on his fax
machine.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GRIN WON'T BE GOING TO SPOKANE
SOVIET STILL IN S.J. SYMPHONY RACE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Classical Music  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     San Jose already has lost candidate <PERSON>John Mauceri</PERSON>, another preseason
favorite, at least in this critic's view, until his cancellation and
withdrawal last month.;    <LOCATION>BERKELEY</LOCATION> MINIMALIST composer <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>' upcoming
opera may be too political for its own good. Even with the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> war
now over, the work is being treated with extreme caution and special security
measures.;    "The Death of Klinghoffer" is based on the <DATE>1985</DATE> Palestinian
terrorist attack on the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> cruise ship <PERSON>Achille Lauro</PERSON>, which
resulted in the death of one passenger, an escape by air, an interception by
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> jets, and a trial in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> in which the terrorists were found guilty.;   
The opus may prove as politically sensitive as classics of the genre such as
"The Marriage of Figaro," "Rigoletto" and "Un ballo in maschera.";    Next
week's world premiere in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, of this operatic collaboration
between composer <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> and stage director <PERSON>Peter Sellars</PERSON> is being orchestrated
with a news brownout. There are no interviews, and, until two weeks before the
<DATE>March 19</DATE> opening, there were no press releases, either.;    The work, coming
to the <LOCATION>San Francisco Opera</LOCATION> in the <DATE>fall of 1992</DATE>, opens in the <ORGANIZATION>Monnaie Opera
House</ORGANIZATION> with <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> in attendance.;    The unsettled world situation is also a
factor in the cancellation of upcoming tours to <LOCATION>Western Europe</LOCATION> by the <LOCATION>New York
Slatkin</PERSON>. The Philharmonic was to make an Easter tour, while the <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>
orchestra was to have gone in February.;    THE COMPUTER-MUSIC studio at
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION> has aroused controversy over a concert coming <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME> to <ORGANIZATION>Dinkelspiel Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, because Norwegian composer Per <PERSON>Landa</PERSON> insists
on passing out earplugs for those who will be hearing his high-volume music.; 
  "That (high a sound level) is utterly against my philosophy, but I can't be
tyrannical," says studio director <PERSON>John Chowning</PERSON>. The concert also features
composers from <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and Stanford.;    On a more harmonious note, <PERSON>Chowning</PERSON>
is working to bring over from the <ORGANIZATION>USSR</ORGANIZATION> the legendary <PERSON>Leon Theremin</PERSON>, who
invented one of the first electronic instruments (named the theremin) around
<DATE>1924</DATE>. Chowning met him on his recent Soviet visit and found him spry and
active at 95, eager to return to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, where he had lived for a
time until <DATE>1938</DATE>. Theremin once met with <PERSON>Lenin</PERSON> himself to demonstrate his
instrument and apparently left the Red leader impressed with his revolutionary
device.;    THE DEATH of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> composer <PERSON>Elie Siegmeister</PERSON> at 82 deprives the
music world of a live-wire author, raconteur, educator, and prolific composer
on American themes. He studied abroad with <PERSON>Nadia Boulanger</PERSON> and had his music
played by <PERSON>Arturo Toscanini</PERSON>, who was never known to be a champion of American
music. Five seasons ago the <LOCATION>San Jose Symphony</LOCATION>, under <PERSON>George Cleve</PERSON>, played
<PERSON>Siegmeister</PERSON>'s "Ozark Set."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Paul Hertelendy column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910312  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  601  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday March 12, 1991
00072002,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06218131 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06218131 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  DANCE; REVIEW; SANTA-CRUZ  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE 29th annual Cabrillo Music Festival finally engaged Santa Cruz's own Tandy
Beal &amp; Company to present a program Saturday afternoon. Banding with Beal
produced a world premiere choreography, as well as that marvelous
Genesis-in-rewind-mode dance called "La creation du monde" (The Creation of
the Earth).;    The pairing was a congenial one, echoed by a ballet-inspired
orchestral program given Friday night, also under John Adams' baton.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TANDY BEAL'S CHOREOGRAPHY BRINGS QUIRKINESS
TO CABRILLO  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Concert Review  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Dancer-choreographer <PERSON>Beal</PERSON> is bursting in quirky moves and instant
Chaplin-like humor, mixing mimic fun with sight-gag theater, using the arms
more than legs for the center of attention.;    In her new piece "Sequenza V,"
named after <PERSON>Berio</PERSON>'s solo-trombone avant-garde composition, she turned musician
<PERSON>Daniel Livesay</PERSON> into an actor, and surrounded him with masked figures hidden in
Picasso-like cubisms -- cone shapes, zany paste-on eyes and "wrong-place"
facial features.;    She feeds the creative furnaces by putting musical notes
into a giant music machine, and ends it all with an action-painting sequence
leaving the scene as wildly color-splotched as the music itself. I think
<PERSON>Luciano Berio</PERSON> would enjoy <PERSON>Beal</PERSON>'s responsiveness to his music and like the
novelty of those paste-on noses, mouths and ears.;    An imaginative Beal; 
We've already had do-it-yourself. It took <ORGANIZATION>Beal</ORGANIZATION> to dream up glue-it-yourself.; 
  <ORGANIZATION>Beal</ORGANIZATION> tore up the original scenario for "La creation du monde," the
pioneering <DATE>1923</DATE> dance score by composer <PERSON>Darius Milhaud</PERSON>. Her view now has the
Creation in reverse -- an idea very appealing philosophically to us troubled
modern urban-dwellers. The couples dancing in ballrooms undergo a transition
of decay and disruption. Plant life runs amok, supplants the architecture, and
creates an <ORGANIZATION>Eden</ORGANIZATION> with the dancers becoming restored <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> and Eves. The piece
is a marvelous reflection on our civilization, further allowing set designer
<PERSON>Kevin</PERSON> Constant to produce verdant vines as if out of a Rousseau primitive
painting.;    <PERSON>Beal</PERSON>'s six dancers stood aside for her rapid-fire solo
"Mysterious Barricades," a funny invention of limbs turning into mirrors, of
twitches, of snaky undulations, and of hands that grab where they shouldn't,
all at such a wild pace that it's almost over before it starts.;    Live music
was used throughout -- a welcome luxury for <ORGANIZATION>Beal</ORGANIZATION>, allowing <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' festival
orchestra to shine in the <LOCATION>Milhaud</LOCATION> piece. <PERSON>William Trimble</PERSON>'s alto sax solo
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> was delicious.;    <PERSON>Milhaud</PERSON> always insisted this was the first jazz
used in serious concert music. Its recurrent oboe solo also apparently
inspired a major theme of <PERSON>George Gershwin</PERSON>'s "Three Preludes" (<DATE>1926</DATE>) for solo
piano.;    "I don't really like new music," composer-conductor <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>
insists publicly. He made an exception for <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> when he programmed
"Eros Piano" (<DATE>1989</DATE>) by -- surprise! -- <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> himself. The orchestral part
is almost non-existent. The piano part <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> was turned over to <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>'
longtime friend <PERSON>Mack McCray</PERSON>, who recreated this tribute to that new-age
classicist among composers, the late <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> Feldman.;    This is a nostalgic
mood piece, conjuring up visions of late-night clouds of cigarette smoke, as
wispy as the limpid jazz harmonies clinging around the keyboard during this
14-minute <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> premiere.;    <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' concert programming was effective. Two
ballet scores complemented each other with their sonic zing and percussive
sparkle. Adams unearthed a long swatch of act-two music from <PERSON>Benjamin
Britten</PERSON>'s exotic fairy tale "The Prince of Pagodas" (<DATE>1957</DATE>). Most of it follows
the soft-focus Holst-Delius strain common in English music. But one magical
number has the most astute orchestral-percussion simulation of the highly
volatile Balinese gamelan (traditional percussion orchestra) that you'll ever
hear.;    <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s effect;  The short gamelan section rings with the "beats"
of nearly attuned pairings, with the serene tootling of high flute, and with
the highly agitated explosions of metallic sounds. This was all a result of a
single <DATE>1956</DATE> Balinese visit by the brilliantly adventurous <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>, who
assimilated one of the richest and most complex musical traditions in that
brief exposure.;    His uneven story ballet -- all about a Cinderella in an
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> land of magic -- offers several instrumental solos, and a bracing
musical "collision" of orchestra with off-stage trumpets doing their own
thing.;    <ORGANIZATION>Stravinsky</ORGANIZATION>'s revolutionary <DATE>1911</DATE> ballet score "Petrouchka" was an
apt companion piece, even with <ORGANIZATION>Conductor Adams</ORGANIZATION> whittling down its exclamation
points and irreverent outbursts in his interpretation.;    Once again the
orchestra under <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> showed indifferent polish and accuracy. But these two
opuses offered some colossal solo work by principal players like <PERSON>William
Winant</PERSON> (percussion), <PERSON>Adam Gordon</PERSON> (trumpet), <PERSON>Emily Wong-George</PERSON> (piano) and the
remarkable concertmaster <PERSON>Elizabeth Baker</PERSON>. <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> was subbing superbly on
emergency basis for <PERSON>Romuald Tecco</PERSON>, who had a death in the family.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PAUL HERTELENDY, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  SANTA CRUZ  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910805  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  777  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday August 5, 1991
00218131,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910827-0078
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910827-0078.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Cabrillo Festival: New Music in Garlic Land
   ----
   By Mark Swed
</HL>
<DATE>
08/27/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A10
</SO>
<LP>
   Santa Cruz, Calif. -- The most dramatic way to approach
Santa Cruz is by driving west, entering the coastal region
through Gilroy, the garlic capital of the world. The aroma of
a dozen Little Italys penetrates a car's closed windows. The
radio suddenly seems overrun by new-age music stations and
earnest '60s-style Berkeley radicals. When the ocean appears,
its spectacular beauty takes your breath away.
   It's a particularly appropriate route to take if you
happen to be headed for the Cabrillo Music Festival, where
pre-concert pastries include such local specialties as
garlic-bread pudding, where a Saturday-night concert can pair
a fine performance of a Benjamin Britten song cycle with the
work of a tedious new-age Turk, and where a pervasive '60s
informality can be both endearing and infuriating.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The Cabrillo festival was begun 29 years ago by the dean
of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> composers, the wonderfully lyric and
unpredictably multicultural <PERSON>Lou Harrison</PERSON>, as a quirky
chamber-music series in a coffee-house hangout for <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo
College</ORGANIZATION> students in nearby <LOCATION>Aptos</LOCATION>. It grew quickly, moving to
the college itself and later to a convivial circus tent on a
thrilling site at the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> campus of the <ORGANIZATION>University of
California</ORGANIZATION>, overlooking the sparkling bay.
   In <DATE>1974</DATE>, it hired an up-and-coming young conductor, <PERSON>Dennis
Russell Davies</PERSON>, then music director of the <ORGANIZATION>St. Paul Chamber
Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Davies</PERSON> put together a first-rate small
orchestra, invited world-class composers each year,
commissioned and premiered important work and created
arresting programs. One year, for instance, he featured works
in every concert by <ORGANIZATION>Ravel</ORGANIZATION>, the American eclecticist <PERSON>William
Bolcom</PERSON> and the eccentric Estonian minimalist Arvo Part.
   Meanwhile, however, the festival has fallen on leaner
times. For the first time in 17 years, <PERSON>Mr. Davies</PERSON> -- who is
now music director of the city of <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, as well as of the
<LOCATION>Brooklyn Philharmonic</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>American Composers Orchestra</ORGANIZATION> --
took a sabbatical, leaving his future involvement with the
festival uncertain.
   The festival itself has the same economic troubles every
small-scale arts organization has these days, and it has
hired new management to address the situation. No longer able
to afford its sensational site, it has moved to the unwieldy
and acoustically unflattering Civic Auditorium in depressing
downtown <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>.
   But the festival's spirit survives, and it continues to
offer two of the most thoughtful and original <DATE>summer</DATE> musical
weekends anywhere in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
   Actually, this year's festival looked, on paper,
considerably more conventional than it generally does when
<PERSON>Mr. Davies</PERSON> programs it. But, thanks to a brilliant stroke, it
wasn't. By inviting the composer <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> as guest
director, <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo</ORGANIZATION> ensured that however common the
repertoire, it would be filtered through the sensibility of a
controversial composer who is also proving to be an
interesting conductor. He is best known for his operas "Nixon
in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>" and the new "The Death of Klinghoffer," which
reaches the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> next month at the <ORGANIZATION>Brooklyn Academy of Music</ORGANIZATION>.
Often cast as a minimalist, <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON> employs minimalist
repetition as only one facet of his multistylistic approach,
which can include everything from American swing to
Schoenbergian dissonance. At <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo</ORGANIZATION>, he showed himself to
be simply uncategorizable.
   He began the festival's second and more elaborate weekend,
the one I attended, with the American premiere of his "Eros
Piano," a moving short elegiac score for piano and chamber
orchestra that sounds a little bit like the '50s jazz of <PERSON>Bill
Evans</PERSON> meeting the mystical sweetness of <PERSON>Olivier Messiaen</PERSON>. He
followed that with the ravishing second act of <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s
seldom-played ballet, "The Prince of the Pagodas," with its
glamorous orchestral imitation of Balinese gamelan. He wound
up the program with a performance of <ORGANIZATION>Stravinsky</ORGANIZATION>'s
"Petroushka" that emphasized the music's rhythmic bite and
brash orchestral colors, unlike most glossy modern orchestral
accounts.
   It was a canny Cabrillo evening. <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON> bowed toward
the multicultural impulses that have always characterized the
festival -- much of <PERSON>Mr. Harrison</PERSON>'s music is inspired by the
gamelan. He offered a fresh look at <LOCATION>Britten</LOCATION>, a composer who,
like <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON>, spent his career coming to his own individual
terms with modernism. And he presented some insight into his
own striking musical personality, which vacillates from the
gloomy to the glitzy in fascinating ways.
   Occasionally <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON>'s instincts went awry, however, as
they did in a big way on his weirdly devised Saturday-night
program. The first half consisted of a terrific performance
of <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s stern, seldom-heard "Songs and Proverbs of
<PERSON>William Blake</PERSON>," sung with a riveting sensitivity to every
word by the baritone <PERSON>Sanford Sylvan</PERSON> and accompanied with
wondrous fluidity by the pianist <PERSON>Richard Goode</PERSON>. But it was
followed by nearly an hour's worth of needless noodling from
the Turkish-born <PERSON>Nazim Ozel</PERSON>, who plucks away on all 400
strings he has strung on a branch of a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> live oak he
calls the "Semi-Civilized Tree."
   Earlier that day there was a delightfully noncondescending
family concert featuring the witty <ORGANIZATION>Tandy Beal &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the
local choreographer collaborating with <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON> for a
mysterious and mildly risque version of <ORGANIZATION>Milhaud</ORGANIZATION>'s "La
Creation du Monde." The next evening was mixed: <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON> led
a driving, properly disturbing account of <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s "Sinfonia
da Requiem"; <PERSON>Mr. Sylvan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON> became emotionally
overwrought in Mahler's "Kindertotenlieder"; <PERSON>Mr. Goode</PERSON>
offered one of his typically nuanced renditions of <ORGANIZATION>Mozart</ORGANIZATION>'s
Piano Concerto No. 25, with <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON> accompanying solidly.
   Missing, for the first time in memory, was anything by <PERSON>Mr.
Harrison</PERSON>, who still reigns as the informal paterfamilias of
the festival. But a CD of <PERSON>Mr. Harrison</PERSON>'s gorgeous <ORGANIZATION>Third
Symphony</ORGANIZATION>, performed by <PERSON>Mr. Davies</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo Music
Festival Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>, was just released on <ORGANIZATION>Music Masters</ORGANIZATION>. No
one else today writes orchestral music as rapturous as this,
or combines musical cultures as effectively. And no place is
better for producing such music as <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06319155 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06319155 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Elizabeth Knighton Printy: concussion, broken pelvis, four
broken ribs.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  SOPRANO Elizabeth Knighton Printy barely escaped disaster in the scary suicide
scene at the end of a Minnesota Opera production of "Tosca.";   When she
jumped through the window for Tosca's suicide plunge, she missed the bed that
was supposed to catch her, hit her head, and fell off a platform to the floor
22 feet below.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TOSCA'S SUICIDE LEAP NEARLY DOES IN ONE SOPRANO  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Classical Music  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Undaunted, she expects to perform a stint with the San <PERSON>Jose Symphony</PERSON> next
spring.;   "It was a miracle that I didn't kill myself," she said. The fall
resulted in four broken ribs, a concussion, a broken pelvis and a week in the
hospital.;   After that <DATE>Oct. 24</DATE> mishap at <ORGANIZATION>St. Paul's Ordway Theater</ORGANIZATION>, the
anguished epilogue to her otherwise successful debut as <LOCATION>Tosca</LOCATION>, she is on
crutches but glad there was "no irreparable damage.";   The determined singer
plans to resume her performance schedule in <DATE>January</DATE>, singing the songs of
death in <ORGANIZATION>Shostakovich</ORGANIZATION>'s Symphony No. 14 in <LOCATION>New York City.</LOCATION>;   Now a resident of
<LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Knighton Printy</PERSON> lived in the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> <DATE>from 1976</DATE> to <DATE>'84</DATE>. She sang
in the <ORGANIZATION>Verdi</ORGANIZATION> "Requiem" with the San <PERSON>Jose Symphony</PERSON> last <DATE>spring</DATE> and will return
for the <ORGANIZATION>Mahler Second Symphony</ORGANIZATION>, under <PERSON>George Cleve</PERSON>, in <DATE>June 1992.</DATE>;  
Appropriately, the Mahler symphony is subtitled "Resurrection.";   In other
news of the orchestra, the lineup of vocalists for the <DATE>Dec. 7-8</DATE>
"Messiah"-<PERSON>Mozart Requiem</PERSON> package is superlative: <PERSON>Lorraine Hunt</PERSON>, <PERSON>Wendy
Hillhouse</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robert Tate</PERSON> and <PERSON>William Parker.</PERSON>;   The symphony has also signed
Mexican-born conductor <PERSON>Jorge Perez-Gomez</PERSON> for the <DATE>May 14</DATE> flamenco program at
<ORGANIZATION>Flint Center</ORGANIZATION>. Guitarist Anita Sheer will give the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> premiere of the
"Suite flamenca" by her teacher, <PERSON>Carlos Montoya</PERSON>. She describes it as a
concerto for guitar and orchestra. Choreographer <PERSON>Patri Nader</PERSON> will prepare the
local performers of <ORGANIZATION>Bailes de Espana</ORGANIZATION> in four selections featuring composers
Bizet, <ORGANIZATION>Albeniz</ORGANIZATION>, de Falla and Gimenez.;   <LOCATION>UNITED OPERA</LOCATION> -- The <LOCATION>San Francisco
Opera</LOCATION> wants to do something special for the weeklong celebration in <DATE>June 1995</DATE>
of the 50th anniversary of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> charter. A new opera, perhaps.
The company's general director, <PERSON>Lotfi Mansouri</PERSON>, explained: "We hope we can
stimulate a new opera from <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> Rim countries" with a commission.;   NEW
FACES -- The <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION> has announced an adventurous appointment:
Precocious British composer <PERSON>George Benjamin</PERSON>, 31, will lead Wet Ink, a
new-music series featuring six <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> premieres, from <DATE>Feb. 7</DATE> to <DATE>Feb. 28</DATE>. The
series will replace the New and Unusual Music series, which was led by
composer-in-residence <PERSON>George Perle</PERSON>, 76.;   The symphony may also be
cultivating a special relationship with frequent guest conductor <PERSON>David Zinman</PERSON>.
After prolonged stints this year and last, <PERSON>Zinman</PERSON> is scheduled to return again
<DATE>June 18-27</DATE> to lead an entire Beethoven festival. The orchestra could name
<PERSON>Zinman</PERSON> principal guest conductor, which would make him a prime candidate to
succeed <PERSON>Herbert Blomstedt</PERSON>, music director since <DATE>1985</DATE>, should <PERSON>Blomstedt</PERSON> decide
to move on. Zinman is music director of the <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> Symphony.;   MUSICAL
NOTES -- KUSP-FM radio (88.9) in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> got a leg up on the competition by
acquiring the exclusive <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> premiere broadcast rights for <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>' new
opera, "The Death of Klinghoffer." A recording of the world premiere in
<LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> <DATE>last March</DATE> will be broadcast <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> . . .;   Also at <LOCATION>Santa
Cruz</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz's McHenry Library</ORGANIZATION> is holding a
free public reception at <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> to mark the acquisition of the archives
of local composer-conductor <PERSON>George Barati</PERSON>, 78. At the event, held in the
Special Collections area, the <ORGANIZATION>Porter String Quartet</ORGANIZATION> will give the world
premiere of <PERSON>Barati</PERSON>'s String Quartet No. 3.;   Artistic director and composer
<ORGANIZATION>Robert Greenberg of Composers Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> complied fully with a
request from his publicity-minded board of directors. "They said, 'We need a
<LOCATION>South Bay</LOCATION> angle,' " <PERSON>Greenberg</PERSON> explains. He wrote a new work for violin and
piano called -- "South Bay Angle.";   <PERSON>James Mobberley</PERSON>, featured at last
month's <ORGANIZATION>Composers Inc.</ORGANIZATION> concert, explained how he became a composer. Camping
out in <LOCATION>Bodega Bay</LOCATION> years ago, he found he couldn't sleep. "There were two
foghorns. I noticed that they were blowing a minor ninth (interval) apart, (in
a regular pattern of) 12 beats against 17.;   "I decided then that I had to
become a composer."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Paul Hertelendy column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911114  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  723  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, November 14, 1991
00319155,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011090-0041 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 159891 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 10, 1990, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 5; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
826 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COMPOSER GETS 1 SHOT TO WIN OVER LISTENERS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KENNETH HERMAN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
LA JOLLA 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Composer <PERSON>Charles Wuorinen</PERSON> is confident that avant-garde music only needs 
adequate exposure to win over reluctant listeners. 
</P>
<P>
"The question of acceptance depends on familiarity," he said. "After all, <PERSON>Bach</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Beethoven</PERSON> wrote demanding music, but because it is played by devoted 
performers and taught in schools that value the music, ultimately, the complex 
and demanding becomes familiar. Their music is loved, even if it may not be 
understood." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON> has but a single opportunity, however, to make his case to the <LOCATION>San 
Diego Symphony</LOCATION> audience <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>UC San Diego</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Mandeville 
Auditorium</LOCATION>. In the inaugural concert of the symphony's Pulitzer Series, the 
51-year-old <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> composer will conduct a pair of his recent works as well 
as two Stravinsky compositions. 
</P>
<P>
At the expense of cultivating an adoring and understanding public, <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON>, 
who is often described as a second-generation 12-tone composer, has made 
"complex and demanding" his musical credo. Despite a prolific output -- about 
160 works in almost every musical medium -- he has never attracted the 
attention of such minimalist media darlings as <ORGANIZATION>Philip Glass</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"Those of us who write real music do not do it for the immediate satisfaction, 
but in the hope that it will last. That which is wildly popular will not last 
-- the more popular they are, the shorter their works will be around," <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Not that he wishes to be known as a minimalist basher. 
</P>
<P>
"Minimalism is not the issue," he said. "My problem is this: A lot of music 
that is essentially pop music is now being declared to be serious music and 
played on programs with <ORGANIZATION>Beethoven</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON> and yours truly. Entertainment is 
healthy in its place, but I object to confusing it with the higher arts." 
</P>
<P>
It is possible that <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON>'s non-stop flow of awards and prizes, starting at 
age 16 with the <ORGANIZATION>New York Philharmonic Young Composers Award</ORGANIZATION>, has forged such 
unwavering self-confidence. In <DATE>1970</DATE>, while in his early 30s, he was the 
youngest composer to be awarded a Pulitzer Prize (and the first to receive one 
for a composition of electronic music), and in <DATE>1986</DATE> he won a megabuck <ORGANIZATION>MacArthur 
Foundation Fellowship</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
If <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON> has been loathe to cultivate a personal following, he has regularly 
collaborated with major orchestras to keep his music before the public. Last 
year, <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON> completed a four-year residency with the <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION>, 
where he also served as the orchestra's new-music adviser. He showered music 
director <PERSON>Herbert Blomstedt</PERSON> with praise for giving his compositions thorough 
preparation and first-rate performances. 
</P>
<P>
The orchestra also made a compact disc of <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON>'s "The Golden Dance" and 
<ORGANIZATION>Third Piano Concerto</ORGANIZATION>, with <PERSON>Garrick Ohlsson</PERSON> as soloist. In <DATE>January, 1989</DATE>, the 
composer's only opera, "The W. of Babylon," was given its sole performance in a 
concert setting by the <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION>. Subtitled a "Baroque Burlesque," 
the lascivious (according to local music critics) and satirical opera had been 
sitting on the shelf since its completion in <DATE>1975</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"It was a happy relationship. I had a very good time while I was there, and our 
relationship will continue. I'm putting the final touches on a work for chorus 
and orchestra that <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> will be playing in <DATE>March</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
In spite of the time spent in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> working with the symphony, the <LOCATION>New 
York</LOCATION> native did not discover a distinctly <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> school of composition. 
</P>
<P>
"There are so many different approaches -- the range of compositional style is 
so great. How would you put, say, <PERSON>Lou Harrison</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> and a <PERSON>Roger Reynolds</PERSON> 
in the same category? The cultural scene is so adrift, you begin to ask, 'Does 
anything mean anything?' " 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON> ascends the <LOCATION>Mandeville Auditorium</LOCATION> podium to conduct "Bamboola 
Squared" for orchestra and quadraphonic tape, the piece will finally have come 
home. 
</P>
<P>
"The tape for 'Bamboola Squared' was produced and realized at the university's 
Center for Music Experiment laboratory. The piece was written for the <LOCATION>New York 
Philharmonic</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Horizons Festival</ORGANIZATION>, which (<ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION> professor) <PERSON>Roger Reynolds</PERSON> 
and I co-produced." (<ORGANIZATION>Reynolds</ORGANIZATION>' music will be featured on the <LOCATION>San Diego 
Symphony</LOCATION>'s next Pulitzer Series program on <DATE>Feb. 15</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION>.) 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON> asked the center to retool the tape portion of "Bamboola 
Squared" in the latest electronic technology -- magneto-optical hard disc -- 
for this performance with the <LOCATION>San Diego Symphony</LOCATION>, the center's wizards could 
not comply. 
</P>
<P>
"The new technology is not as reliable in performance, say, as a clarinet," 
said the centerspokesman, <PERSON>John Lauer</PERSON>. "But we did recompute the file that 
<PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON> left when he first made the tape in '84 and freshened it up a bit." 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s program, <PERSON>Wuorinen</PERSON> will also conduct his <DATE>1988</DATE> "Machault, mon 
chou," one of the works written for the <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION> and dedicated to 
<PERSON>Blomstedt</PERSON>. The Stravinsky pieces will be "Dumbarton Oaks" Concerto and 
"Monumentum pro Gesualdo di Venosa." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Wuorinen 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06219183 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06219183 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Pianist Richard Goode gave one of the finest readings in this
Mozart-saturated year  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE signature of a music festival is its echo in the mind -- the sonic
impression that lingers after the last bouquet of roses has been handed to the
last soloist.;    By that criterion, the Cabrillo Music Festival went out with
flying colors on Sunday night.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CABRILLO'S ECHO WILL BE A PLEASANT ONE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Music Review  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Forget the unsuccessful new compositions heard in its two-week run. Forget
the deficits. Forget the peccadilloes of the orchestra. Forget the worries
about whether the festival's in absentia music director, <PERSON>Dennis Russell
Davies</PERSON>, will keep his word and return in <DATE>1992.</DATE>;    <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s finale was
brilliant. Everything came together to tie up the season with a golden bow.;  
 <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s and <ORGANIZATION>Mahler</ORGANIZATION>'s eloquence on the theme of death and <ORGANIZATION>Mozart</ORGANIZATION>'s eloquence
on life furnished music with provocative polarities.;    <PERSON>Pianist Richard Goode</PERSON>
was exceptional in his articulate, propulsive reading of <ORGANIZATION>Mozart</ORGANIZATION>'s Piano
Concerto No. 25 in C Major (K. 503), one of the finest readings I've
encountered in this <DATE>Mozart-saturated year.</DATE>;    The long, grandiose concerto,
which anticipates <ORGANIZATION>Beethoven</ORGANIZATION>, is a marvel of architecture, articulation,
allusion and affection. The main piano theme of the opening, for instance, is
an upbeat reworking of <ORGANIZATION>Papageno</ORGANIZATION>'s coda of lament from the end of <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON>'s
opera "The Magic Flute.";    <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON> left only a couple of cadenzas (solo
display segments) for his late concertos, and none for No. 25. So <PERSON>Goode</PERSON> wrote
his own, and it comes as close to <ORGANIZATION>Mozart</ORGANIZATION>'s style as any I've encountered,
including <PERSON>Daniel Barenboim</PERSON>'s likable recorded one.;    Even more to my liking
were <PERSON>Goode</PERSON>'s seamless lines, his way of caressing the notes, and his singing
tone.;    <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> conducted capably, keying closely to <PERSON>Goode</PERSON>'s reading.;   
This was the hit-or-miss Cabrillo orchestra's finest evening of the season.
The group was more responsive and richer texturally than in other
performances.;    In <PERSON>Britten</PERSON>'s "Sinfonia da Requiem" and <PERSON>Mahler</PERSON>'s
tragic-romantic "Kindertotenlieder" ("Songs on the Death of Children"), the
renditions were often stirring and the solos in the latter work often stellar,
thanks to <ORGANIZATION>Yvonne Powers</ORGANIZATION> (oboe), <PERSON>Patricia Barry</PERSON> (English horn) and <PERSON>Fred
Bergstone</PERSON> (horn).;    In the Mahler work -- the saddest piece I ever hope to
hear -- baritone <PERSON>Sanford Sylvan</PERSON> was not at his best vocally, and his lyric
instrument is too light for this song cycle. But his musical intelligence and
his command of German are so refined that the poems were devastating in their
understatement.;    The "Sinfonia da Requiem" (<DATE>1940</DATE>) is a piece of fire and
ice, in which composer Britten meets the dual tragedies of a death in the
family and the growing devastation of World War II with a stiff upper lip.;   
Composer-conductor <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> offers engaging program annotations, but this year's
festival seemed fixated on death, with nine performances over two weekends
presenting death-related music.;    <PERSON>Adams</PERSON>' own compositions were welcome,
though they barely hinted at his stylistic versatility.;    The acoustic
limitations of the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Civic Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> are something <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> and music
director <PERSON>Davies</PERSON> simply have to bear. The <DATE>Sunday</DATE> concert benefited from removal
of the hall's sound-absorbent curtains.;    Despite the problems, the <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo
Festival</ORGANIZATION> is an asset to be cherished. The friendliness at <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo</ORGANIZATION> is
legendary, from the crowd around the tostada stand in the street to the folks
schmoozing (and not snoozing) in the hall.;    There's a jaunty reveling here
in symphonic programs of 20th-century music that would terrify marketing
directors at many big-city orchestras. There's a bucolic informality, with
musicians in rehearsal togs and conductor <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> in clothes that had a rumpled,
slept-in look. But all were totally engaged in their music-making. It's the
ambiance that opens the door to musical adventurousness.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PAUL HERTELENDY, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910806  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  615  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday August 6, 1991
00219183,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06211075 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06211075 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Chase  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CRUZ; MUSIC; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The Cabrillo Music Festival's opening weekend took its listeners through
adventurous modern terrain, with JoAnn Falletta conducting two programs at the
Santa Cruz Civic Auditorium.;    The modern scores dealt out in saturation to
the music stands reached a climax at the Saturday matinee, and it proved too
much for some. One fast-wilting out-of-town music critic dashed out to the
intermission refreshment stand gasping, "Double espresso!"  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CABRILLO FESTIVAL TREADS SUCCESSFULLY ON
MODERN GROUND  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Music Review  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The recession also dampened the impact, with attendance far below past
norms. The biggest of the first three concert crowds was 400 -- less than half
a house.;    But there was recurrent excitement and renewal, especially in
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s new music by emerging <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> composers born between <DATE>1943</DATE> and
<DATE>1957</DATE>, selected by a six-member jury.;    Imaginative use of ritual;  Upstaging
all the Californians was the Alaskan composer <PERSON>John Luther Adams</PERSON> -- no relation
to the <PERSON>John</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Coolidge</ORGANIZATION>) <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> conducting other parts of the festival. Adams had
a flair for timeless ritual, with bass-drum tattoos suggesting Inouit
ceremonies. Brass stationed around the higher echelons of the auditorium
played an insistent, mystical music using the ambiguous notes and chords from
the string players' so-called open strings. The hypnotic spatial music
entitled "The Far Country of Sleep" at a quarter-hour was the matinee's
longest, yet it seemed the shortest on the program.;    Two of the five
composers were associated with <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Ross Bauer</PERSON> showed a
complex organization in his "Neon" (<DATE>1988</DATE>), yet it was very easy to listen to,
with its sonic brilliance and soothing textures. The busy piece was like a
platter with a lot of good seasonings. The work was an ebullient
curtain-raiser, with many solos and uncommon sounds in bass clarinet, tuba,
piccolo and other exotica.;    <PERSON>David Jaffe</PERSON>'s "Whoop for Your Life!" (<DATE>1987</DATE>)
struck me as a bundle of shards trying to find their place within some
structural whole. Jaffe seemed to make a conscious attempt to avoid idiomatic
gestures of orchestral writing, and he showed some of the uninhibited nature
of an action painter, but without all the glue needed to make his eclectic
piece stick together. He seemed uncomfortable with string writing, and he got
his best effects with haunting, heavily muted low brass outpourings.;    Two
others showed an extra-serious bent, such as you'd expect to find around
university composers. The German immigrant <PERSON>Stefan Carow</PERSON>'s "Five Pieces for
Orchestra" (world premiere) was an austere, atonal, post-Schoenbergian work of
sparse ingredients, like a Kandinsky painting. The <PERSON>Schoenberg</PERSON> clue lay not
just in the texture, but in the title, which <PERSON>Schoenberg</PERSON> himself had used in
<DATE>1909.</DATE>;    <PERSON>Allen Shearer</PERSON>'s Fantasy for Piano and <ORGANIZATION>Orchestra</ORGANIZATION> was a stoical
eight-minute opus, with <PERSON>Barbara Shearer</PERSON> providing the pristine structures of
the solo part.;    Inspired by traditional songs; The night before, <PERSON>Falletta</PERSON>
-- a conductor more notable for her diplomatic, no-nonsense efficiency than
moving performances -- had introduced "Due Ye No. 2" (<DATE>1987</DATE>) by the <ORGANIZATION>Cantonese
Chen Yi</ORGANIZATION>. Chen Yi had been inspired by the traditional songs and dances of
<LOCATION>Guangxi Province</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, and harnessed them into a tremendous, uplifting
outburst of both power and sophistication, offering both changes of meter as
well as musical "gates" adroitly separating segments of the seven-minute
span.;    <LOCATION>The East Coast</LOCATION> violinist <PERSON>Stephanie Chase</PERSON> had made a forceful impact
playing "Serenade," the most platonic of <PERSON>Leonard Bernstein</PERSON>'s creations.
<PERSON>Bernstein</PERSON> tied his unusually neoclassical score to <PERSON>Plato</PERSON>'s "Symposium," each
of the five sections making allusions to the many faces of love.;   
Considering the theme of love, <ORGANIZATION>Chase</ORGANIZATION>'s approach, like that of conductor
<PERSON>Falletta</PERSON>, was needlessly severe, meeting the considerable rhythmic obligations
with technique and virtuosity. They managed the syncopated jazzy finale well,
but more heart from all the forces, including the unusual orchestra of strings
and percussion, would have been welcome.;    Splashy ending;  <PERSON>Falletta</PERSON> closed
that concert with the splashy Mussorgsky-Ravel "Pictures at an Exhibition,"
indifferently played apart from <PERSON>Tony Clements</PERSON>' marvelously squishy tuba solo.;
   Despite able conductors and some of the most imaginative programs on the
coast, the <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo Music Festival</ORGANIZATION> remains below its potential. The orchestra
is widely recruited -- only 30 of the 67 players are from <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>
-- but it remains short of national-festival norms in its responsiveness,
rhythmic acuity and pitch. I have not heard a really good ensemble here,
commensurate with the festival's high national repute, since <DATE>1988.</DATE>;    For
future hirings, the festival would be well advised to hold musician auditions,
even in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> if necessary, and forget word-of-mouth from current
players, which is the commonest hiring method currently used.;  <ORGANIZATION>Cabrillo Music
Festival</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> guest conductor.; Where: <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Civic Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, at
<ORGANIZATION>Center and Church Streets.</ORGANIZATION>; When: Nightly Thursdays-Sundays through <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>,
plus weekend matinees. No repeat concerts.; Tickets: <MONEY>$15.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$23.50</MONEY>. (408)
429-3444.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PAUL HERTELENDY, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  SANTA CRUZ  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910729  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  796  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday July 29, 1991
00211075,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06082140 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06082140 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: John Adams  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  LIKE "Nixon in China" but in more incendiary fashion, "The Death of
Klinghoffer" transmutes contemporary history into operatic poetry.;    Unlike
the earlier work by composer John Adams, librettist Alice Goodman, director
Peter Sellars and choreographer Mark Morris, the new opera, which received its
world premiere Tuesday at the Theatre Royal de la Monnaie, needs some
refinement. But the potential for eventual triumph is there.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FROM FRONT PAGE TO STAGE
ACHILLE LAURO TRAGEDY IS SOURCE OF POETIC
OPERA  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Opera Review  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     After seven performances in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, it will travel over the next year to
<LOCATION>Lyons</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> (for its American premiere Sept. 5); <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>; and <LOCATION>Glyndebourne</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England.</LOCATION>;    The subject of "The Death
of Klinghoffer" is the seizure of the Italian cruise ship <ORGANIZATION>Achille Lauro</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>October 1985</DATE> by four Palestinian terrorists and the murder of a
wheelchair-bound <ORGANIZATION>American Jew</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Leon Klinghoffer.</PERSON>;    The hatreds of Jews and
Palestinians surface here and there, sometimes violently. But the opera, laid
out in two acts of approximately 80 minutes each, deliberately cools passions
into meditations from afar.;    The action, which alternates choruses and solo
