<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-9036 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu076__a94054" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-076-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  19 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Dutch Prime Minister Arrives on Official Visit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Dutch Prime Minister Arrives on Official Visit </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1904172194 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1420 GMT 19 Apr 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1904172194 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 19/4/1994 -- A government 
delegation from the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> headed by Prime Minister <PERSON>Ruud 
Lubbers</PERSON> arrived in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> on <DATE>Tuesday, April 19</DATE>, for a two-day 
official visit. The Dutch guests were greeted at the <LOCATION>Otopeni 
Airport</LOCATION> by Romanian Prime Minister <PERSON>Nicolae Vacaroiu</PERSON>, Foreign 
Minister <PERSON>Teodor Melescanu</PERSON>, Minister of State <PERSON>Dan Mircea Popescu</PERSON>, 
the Dutch ambassador in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Monique Frank</PERSON>, and other 
officials. 
  Shortly after his arrival, Premier <PERSON>Ruud Lubbers</PERSON> said that 
his 
visit in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> would further substantiate the cooperation 
between the two countries. The <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> is located on the 
other side of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and considers that transports and trade are 
especially important, said the Dutch prime minister and added 
that the <LOCATION>Rhine</LOCATION>- Main-Danube watercourse would ease the bilateral 
ties, as <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> is located on the other end of the road and 
therefore the bilateral cooperation was extremely necessary, not 
only in the economic field but also in the political one and 
perhaps also in tourism. The Dutch premier mentioned the 
Latin-rooted language spoken by Romanians as a very special 
trait of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>central Europe</LOCATION>. 
  On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [20 <DATE>April</DATE>], Premier <PERSON>Ruud Lubbers</PERSON> is scheduled 
to 
meet <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Senate</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Oliviu Gherman</PERSON>, Chamber of 
Deputies' Speaker <PERSON>Adrian Nastase</PERSON>, the presidential adviser <PERSON>Misu 
Negritoiu</PERSON>, and the governor of the <ORGANIZATION>National Bank of Romania</ORGANIZATION>, 
<PERSON>Mugur Isarescu</PERSON>. 
  Today <PERSON>Ruud Lubbers</PERSON> was received by Romanian President <PERSON>Ion 
Iliescu</PERSON>, at <ORGANIZATION>Cotroceni Palace</ORGANIZATION>. The Dutch guest was accompanied 
by Dutch Foreign Affairs Minister <PERSON>Peter Kooijmans</PERSON>. The visit of 
the high Dutch officials is the first of its kind since 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s <DATE>December 1989</DATE> revolution. 
  The interview was attended by <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Minister of Foreign 
Affairs Teodor Melescanu</ORGANIZATION>, Minister of State <PERSON>Dan Mircea Popescu</PERSON>, 
presidential advisers <PERSON>Misu Negritoiu</PERSON> and <PERSON>Traian Chebeleu</PERSON>, the 
Romanian ambassador to the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Marin Buhoara</PERSON>. 
  After the official talks, the Romanian president gave his 
guests lunch. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-55123 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu090__a94034" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-090-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Iliescu Receives Germany's Spranger </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Iliescu Receives Germany's Spranger </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU0605195194 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1735 GMT 6 May 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0605195194 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 6/5/1994 -- <PERSON>Carl-Dieter Spranger</PERSON>, 
German minister of economic cooperation, who has been in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
for a few days now and had multiple contacts, was received by 
Romanian President <PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> on 6 <DATE>May</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>. 
  At the close of the interview President Iliescu termed the 
Romanian-German relations as increasingly good, saying <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> 
was the country that understood the best <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s difficulties 
caused by the processes of transformation that resembled those 
of the former GDR. "We have found with <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> a more exact 
perception of our problems in the process of transition," the 
Romanian head of state said. 
were concerned, the president pointed to the existence of mutual 
interests, explaining that both <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> were located 
"on the Rhine-Main-Danube trans-European axis, with two 
terminals, <LOCATION>Rotterdam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Constanta</LOCATION>, and with the German economy 
at the center, which will be the engine of the general process 
of the European integration." 
  The German guest noted the good level of the bilateral 
relations. "I believe the reforms these last few years in 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, and especially the situation after <DATE>1993</DATE> can stir the 
interest of foreign investors," he said. 
  The German minister of economic cooperation, <PERSON>Carl-Dieter 
Spranger</PERSON> met on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, 6 <DATE>May</DATE>, in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> with the Romanian 
minister of state, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Council for Economic 
Coordination</ORGANIZATION>, Strategy, and Reform, <PERSON>Mircea Cosea</PERSON>. 
  Within his presentation of the Romanian economy, <PERSON>Mircea 
Cosea</PERSON> 
said that <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> was giving a very special attention to its 
relations with <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, because there existed a tradition of 
German industry presence in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> in the sectors of railroads, 
iron and steel industry, and telecommunications. The Romanian 
minister expressed hope that <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> would benefit from German 
aid of capital and technology in the process of reform. <PERSON>Cosea</PERSON> 
said that the German business mentality could be a very 
important factor in the process of reform. 
  The German minister <PERSON>Carl-Dieter Spranger</PERSON> said his visit was 
a 
signal for the extending of the relations with <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. The 
signing of the agreement on the non-reimbursable economic 
assistance granted to <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> is a relevant sign, said the 
German minister. 
  Minister <PERSON>Spranger</PERSON> said that <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> would send in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
experts in privatization, banking system updating, stock 
exchanges, industrial restructuring, and social protection. 
  <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> is interested in developing a proper collaboration 
framework with <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, that should allow for the presence of 
German businessmen here, the setting up of joint ventures, as 
well as the intensification of the actions of cooperation and 
commercial exchanges, said Romanian Prime Minister <PERSON>Nicolae 
Vacaroiu</PERSON> on 6 <DATE>May</DATE>, during his interview with <PERSON>Carl-Dieter 
Spranger</PERSON>, federal minister of economic cooperation of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 
The Romanian premier assessed that the signing of the technical 
assistance agreement between the two countries was part of the 
preoccupations to improve the management of the commercial 
companies and update and retool the industrial units, especially 
those built with German technology. 
  Minister <PERSON>Spranger</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> would further back <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
efforts in the <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>OECD</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>Organization for 
Referring to the German minority in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Spranger</PERSON> said the 
Romanian state's policy with respect to that community was 
favorably regarded in his country. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-32720 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu125__a94040" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-125-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Controversy Over Cluj Excavation Plan Noted </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Controversy Over Cluj Excavation Plan Noted </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU2806132294 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1154 GMT 28 Jun 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2806132294 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 28/6/1994 -- For a week the 
city of Cluj-Napoca (North-West of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, inhabited by a large 
Hungarian minority) has been living in a state of tension 
created by the conflict between the public authorities and the 
(<ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>). 
  The conflict, which is not something new, because such 
situations arose several times in the capital of the historical 
Romanian province of <LOCATION>Transylvania</LOCATION>, was sparkled by the intention 
of the local authorities to authorize, at the request of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Transylvanian History Museum</ORGANIZATION>, archaeological diggings in the 
central square of the city where the monument to Hungarian King 
of Romanian descent <PERSON>Matthias Corvinus</PERSON> is located. The local 
branch of <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> is accusing the <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION>, and Mayor <PERSON>Gheorghe 
Funar</PERSON> in the first place, of using the digs as a pretext to move 
<ORGANIZATION>Corvinus</ORGANIZATION>'s statue to another location. 
  "The archaeological diggings planned to start in the <LOCATION>Union 
Square of Cluj-Napoca</LOCATION> are about 100 meters away from the statue 
of King Matthias Corvinus," the city mayor <PERSON>Gheorghe Funar</PERSON> told 
<ORGANIZATION>CRONICA ROMANA</ORGANIZATION>. 
  "The <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> misleads its members, supporters, and the whole 
world, pretending that the unearthings pursue to create a state 
of conflict in the town," <PERSON>Gheorghe Funar</PERSON> also says. His opinion 
is that the tension aroused in the past few days is 
"artificially created, has a political connotation and was 
generated by the <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>'s actions intended to prevent the 
archaeological investigations in the <LOCATION>Union Square</LOCATION>." He specified 
that the initiative comes from the <ORGANIZATION>History Museum of 
Transylvania of Cluj Napoca</ORGANIZATION>, which has obtained the approval of 
all the competent fora, and has allotted 10 million lei to the 
project. The mayor himself suggested the local council to 
approve another 30 million lei to sustain the project. 
  Despite assurances from local authorities that <PERSON>Matthias 
Corvinus</PERSON>'s statue will have nothing to suffer, "the <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> 
representatives said they would stage demonstrations and urge to 
civic disobedience, and termed the matter a political issue," 
<PERSON>Gheorghe Funar</PERSON> said. Should any acts of civic disorder appear 
in the town, <PERSON>Gheorghe Funar</PERSON> said he would be the advocate of 
"firm enforcement of the law." 
  The daily <ORGANIZATION>ORA</ORGANIZATION> carries a commentary in its yesterday's issue 
qualifying the case as part of "the Hungarian concerted strategy 
aimed at having the <ORGANIZATION>Trianon Treaty</ORGANIZATION> canceled or revised." The 
<ORGANIZATION>Treaty of Trianon</ORGANIZATION> permitted <LOCATION>Transylvania</LOCATION> to reunite with the 
mother country after <PERSON>Habsburg</PERSON> and Hungarian occupation was 
abolished. The article in question remarked that "the plan is 
absolutely the same for all the countries having a Hungarian 
minority," and that "from this point of view, <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> is one of the 
spearheads of this intelligent plan, obstinately followed by 
<LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION>." 
  The archaeological investigations due to start next week in 
<LOCATION>Cluj-Napoca</LOCATION> intend to bring to light the forum of the ancient 
city of <LOCATION>Napoca</LOCATION>, a Roman colony on the territory of ancient 
<ORGANIZATION>Dacia</ORGANIZATION>, the cradle of the Romanian people and language. The city 
of Napoca used to be the capital of the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Province of Dacia 
Porolisensis</ORGANIZATION>, and <LOCATION>Cluj-Napoca</LOCATION> is celebrating <DATE>this year 1870</DATE> 
years from its first documentary attestation. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-31767 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu114__a94030" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-114-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Defense Official Views Security Issues </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Defense Official Views Security Issues </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1306144394 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 0933 GMT 13 Jun 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1306144394 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, ROMPRES, 13/6/1994 -- The transition 
process has inevitably diminished <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s capacity to ensure 
its own security. <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> does not have, as at now, allies and 
firm security guarantees. The main danger lies in having its 
own domestic weaknesses exploited. There is a direct 
relationship between the reform and the national security. 
These are some of the main ideas <PERSON>Ioan Mircea Pascu</PERSON>, secretary 
of state in the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Ministry of National Defense</ORGANIZATION>, 
elaborated on in the comprehensive interview for the <ORGANIZATION>CURIERUL 
NATIONAL</ORGANIZATION> of 13 <DATE>June</DATE>. 
  Speaking of the integrated concept of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s national 
security, a recently issued document, <PERSON>Pascu</PERSON> says the study ends 
with the basic conclusion that for now and for a while to come, 
"<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> cannot rely on allies and firm security guarantees." 
Besides, the transition from one type of society to another has 
diminished its capacity to ensure security by its own means, 
"particularly as we are located in an area characterized by a 
high degree of conflict potential." 
  In <PERSON>Mr. Pascu</PERSON>'s opinion, the most important sign of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
insecurity since <DATE>December 1989</DATE> is the very fact that threats are 
no longer mostly external, and that "the main danger is posed by 
the possibility of having its domestic weaknesses exploited." 
And among the main internal risk factors he listed the economic 
situation, the social costs required by the changes brought 
about by the transition period, a diminished social cohesion etc. 
  To face the domestic risk factors this country needs to 
ensure the continuity of the reform process: "the success of the 
reform, however cannot be obtained in the absence of security, 
and to have security, we need to take the reform to the end 
successfully." 
  The defense official also mentioned some of the external 
risk 
factors for <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s security, such as the appearance and 
worsening of certain conflicts, the existence of zones with a 
high potential of political and military instability close to 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. 
  As directly concerning <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s security, Secretary of 
State 
<PERSON>Mircea Pascu</PERSON> names international developments like the recent 
stability plan adopted in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, the agreement for the reduction 
of the conventional armaments and troops in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, the 
Partnership for Peace plan, <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s geopolitical position, the 
relations with <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>. 
  Concluding, the dignitary predicted about the future of 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s security in the following terms: "If we ignore the 
unpredictable, which, unfortunately, will continue to be there 
both in the near and medium future, I think we can be optimistic 
about <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s long- term chances of integration in the 
European and Euro-Atlantic security systems." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-8131 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu043__a94019" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-043-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Spokesman on Moldovan Vote, B-H Accord </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU0203182994 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1704 GMT 2 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0203182994 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpts] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 2/3/1994 -- Foreign 
Ministry Spokesman <PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON> announced at the today's news 
conference President <PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON>'s unofficial visit to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> on 
11-14 <DATE>March this year</DATE> at the invitation of the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese 
Government</ORGANIZATION>. The Romanian president will be shown the special 
economic zones in the <LOCATION>South of China</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Shen Zhen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Zhu Hai</PERSON>, the 
<LOCATION>Quandong Canton Province</LOCATION> where, the Romanian delegation will 
meet with the local administration. The president will be 
accompanied by a group of Romanian businessmen, executives of 
state and private companies, and will examine the prospects of 
cooperation between the two countries. [passage omitted] 
  The spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> read a communique at 
a 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 2</DATE>, press conference, saying that the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian 
Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> has taken note with satisfaction of the 
agreement on the creation of a <ORGANIZATION>Croatian-Muslim Federation</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Bosnia</LOCATION>- <LOCATION>Herzegovina</LOCATION> and of a confederation made up of the said 
federation and <LOCATION>Croatia</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Ministry of Foreign 
Affairs</ORGANIZATION> considers that the putting in place of the provisions of 
this accord would represent an important step in finding a 
political solution to the crisis in <LOCATION>Bosnia-Herzegovina</LOCATION>, in 
parallel with solutions for the other problems under 
negotiation. The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> expresses hope that this 
favorable moment will be made good use of in the interest of all 
the parties, of stability and security in the region, reads the 
communique. 
  The relations between <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION> are not function 
of 
the electoral cycle, which was already proved when elections 
were held in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> Spokesman <PERSON>Mircea 
Geoana</PERSON> at his <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 2</DATE>, press conference, speaking 
about the elections held in the Republic of <LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION> on <DATE>February 
27</DATE>. 
  The results of the polls reflect the state of mind of the 
population and they can be interpreted in terms of the economic 
and social difficulties confronting the Republic of <LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION>, of 
the way in which the electorate took those aspects of the 
programmes of the parties running for seats in parliament that 
refer to the current situation of the country, mentioned the 
spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. An evaluation of the 
results has to take into account the conditions specific to the 
Republic of <LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION>, the tensions appeared in consequence of the 
situation in <LOCATION>Dniester</LOCATION> and the districts inhabited by <LOCATION>Gagauz</LOCATION>, the 
general evolutions in the former Soviet space. "That is how the 
option for the left can be explained, the relative high percent 
of vote got by the bloc formed of the <ORGANIZATION>Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION> (the 
former <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>) and the "unity" party. It is 
interesting to mention, nevertheless, that the Democratic 
Agrarian Party had the biggest number of seats in the previous 
parliament and it has preserved its position, added <PERSON>Geoana</PERSON>. 
  At the 2 <DATE>March</DATE> weekly news conference of the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian 
Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, Spokesman <PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON> referred to 
the statement of 28 <DATE>February</DATE> of the <ORGANIZATION>Council of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Democratic Union of Romania</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>), issued as a 
follow-up and in response to a letter sent to this body by 
Bishop <PERSON>Laszlo Tokes</PERSON>. The spokesman said that the letter 
confirms, once again, the extremist and anti-Romanian angle from 
which <PERSON>Pastor Tokes</PERSON>, encouraged by some <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> leaders and 
political persons in <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, approaches his relations with the 
Romanian state and with <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> itself. 
  "We express the hope that the <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> leaders will distance 
themselves from the positions of the honorary president of their 
party, in whose view at present in <LOCATION>Romania Ceausescu</LOCATION>'s policies 
on minorities are being continued. It is only to be regretted 
that the declaration issued by the <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Council of 
Representatives</ORGANIZATION> practically reiterates all the accusations 
listed in the instruction-letter of Pastor Tokes. <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>'s 
declaration is accusing the Romanian authorities of lacking the 
political will to implement the amendments of the <ORGANIZATION>Council of 
Europe</ORGANIZATION>. We think it is high time <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> understood that the 
addressee of these amendments is the Romanian society as a whole 
and that the observance of the commitments made before the 
<ORGANIZATION>Council</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s admission to it is a matter of national 
interest," the spokesman said. He also stressed that the 
withdrawal of <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> from the <ORGANIZATION>Council for Ethnic Minorities</ORGANIZATION> -- the 
place where it would be but natural that such problems were 
debated -- reveals the lack of both real interest and pragmatism 
in solving them, and lack of consideration for the interests and 
role of the other ethnic minorities in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. 
  "The <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION> expresses the confidence 
that, joining the competent institutions in the rapid 
finalization of this process, all the forces interested in 
proving the democratic propensity and realities of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> will 
bring a constructive and sincere contribution," the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign 
Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman concluded. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-9036 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu053__a94033" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-053-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  16 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Press Condemns 15 Mar Hungarian Festivites </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU1603121094 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 0949 GMT 16 Mar 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1603121094 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the 16 March Romanian press review] </F>
  [Excerpt] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 16/3/1994 -- "Irredentist 
Fangs in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> and in <LOCATION>Transylvania</LOCATION>" is the headline in daily 
ADEVARUL of the set of reports on the observance of the 
anniversary of the <DATE>1848</DATE> revolution by the ethnic Hungarian in 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. The matter is covered by all newspapers that emphasize 
[<ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>] Deputy <PERSON>Imre Borbely</PERSON> to make an address in Hungarian in 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>. "To speak Hungarian before the <ORGANIZATION>Chamber of 
Deputies</ORGANIZATION> means an official offense to the country and to the 
fellow parliamentarians," writes daily <PERSON>CRONICA ROMANA</PERSON>, noting 
that "this characteristic rudeness of <PERSON>Mr. Borbely</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> 
hardliner, (...) serves only those accused of nationalism (...) 
and we must admit that in such situations they are right, 
because one needs not be a nationalist to feel offended in one's 
own home, in one's own country, and in one's own parliament." 
  Daily <ORGANIZATION>ORA</ORGANIZATION> covers the visit paid to <LOCATION>Transylvania</LOCATION> by high 
state 
officials of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> in order to celebrate together with the 
Hungarian minority there the memory of the <DATE>1848</DATE> revolution. 
"The <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Government</ORGANIZATION>'s gesture to celebrate at high level 
the event that was a happy one for them and a tragical one for 
us, is impolite and this is an understatement (...). It is 
offending the Romanians' feelings" daily ORA writes. "The 
Hungarian revisionism is behaving as if the Hungarian empire 
existed, temporarily subjected to different, unjust laws, but 
still an empire, consequently the government has to participate 
in the festivities in its eternal provinces, irrespective of the 
present situation (...) The Hungarian revisionism tries in 
every possible way [to achieve] <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s isolation from the 
community of European states. In an isolated <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, subject 
to the quarantine of civilization, the difficult mission has 
been assumed by the <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>. In <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> there is a 
party hostile to <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, that despises the Romanian nation." 
[passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-30315 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu021__a94023" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-021-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  1 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Melescanu, Moroccan Officials View Cooperation </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU2901181294 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1455 GMT 29 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU2901181294 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, ROMPRES, 29/1/1994 -- <PERSON>Teodor Melescanu</PERSON>, 
the Romanian minister of foreign affairs, was on an official 
visit to <LOCATION>Morocco</LOCATION> on 26-28 <DATE>January</DATE> in response to an invitation 
from his Moroccan counterpart. 
  Foreign Minister <PERSON>Melescanu</PERSON> had talks with <PERSON>A. Filali</PERSON>, 
minister 
of state and foreign minister of the Kingdom of <LOCATION>Morocco</LOCATION> about 
the present stage and the prospects of the Romanian-Moroccan 
relations, and about international and regional matters of joint 
interest. Minister <PERSON>Melescanu</PERSON> met with the president of <LOCATION>Morocco</LOCATION>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>Chamber of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>, with the Moroccan ministers of 
mining and energy, public works, and cultural affairs. 
  The talks with the Moroccan personalities gave the two sides 
the opportunity to express their wish that partnership be the 
basic principle of the future development of their bilateral 
relations. To this effect the possibility was examined of taking 
actions apt to render the Romanian-Moroccan relations a 
privileged nature. 
  The exchange of opinions on international and regional 
issues 
revealed similitude or closeness in assessing the developments 
in the areas in which the two countries are located and on a 
wider international plane. 
  Concomitantly with the visit to <LOCATION>Morocco</LOCATION> of the Romanian 
minister of foreign affairs, the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian-Moroccan Joint 
Governmental Committee for Economic</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Technical and Scientific 
Cooperation</ORGANIZATION> held its 8th session under the chairmanship of the 
two countries' foreign ministers. The committee agreed on 
cooperation projects in port facility development, drilling, 
energy, mining, agriculture, professional training. Both sides 
admitted that the trade exchanges had been below their economic 
potential and agreed to favor direct contacts between public and 
private businesses, between medium and small ventures. 
  At the end of the official visit to <LOCATION>Morocco</LOCATION> and of the 8th 
session of the joint committee, the Romanian and Moroccan 
foreign ministers signed several bilateral juridical documents: 
the convention for the mutual guaranteeing of investments, the 
statement on establishing regular consultations between the two 
foreign ministries, the programme of the cultural accord for the 
years <DATE>1994</DATE> and <DATE>1995</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-31487 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu112__a94027" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-112-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Air Traffic Control Center Inaugurated in Arad </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Air Traffic Control Center Inaugurated in Arad </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU0906183594 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1701 GMT 9 Jun 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0906183594 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 9/6/1994 -- A regional center 
for air traffic control was inaugurated in <LOCATION>Arad</LOCATION>, western 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, as the first in a set of five such up-to-date centers 
designed to ensure coverage for the entire national territory. 
The inauguration ceremony was attended along with the Romanian 
authorities by representatives of the <ORGANIZATION>Eurocontrol</ORGANIZATION>, the body 
concerned in air traffic control in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> which assisted 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> in building the center. 
  The Arad center equipment employs the latest technologies. 
The center is endowed with an over-fly radar and other 
automatic equipments enabling the pilot to locate any time the 
position of the center and to know the flight-angle of his 
plane. The center is furnished also with a computer system 
securing a swift information coordination. 
  Beside the Arad center, other four similar centers for air 
traffic control are being built in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cluj</LOCATION>, <DATE>Bacau</DATE> and 
<LOCATION>Constanta</LOCATION>. The Arad center has been recently visited by a <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> 
delegation that showed interest in the cooperation relations 
between the civilian and the military flights monitoring. The 
<ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> delegation said that the development and upgrading of the 
traffic control of the civilian and military flights would 
speed-up <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s integration in the European and Euro-Atlantic 
structures. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-55378 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu093__a94023" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-093-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Affairs Spokesman on Hungarian Elections </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Foreign Affairs Spokesman on Hungarian Elections </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1105191194 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1618 GMT 11 May 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1105191194 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, ROMPRES, 11/5/1994 -- Referring to the 
first round of the elections recently held in <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, the 
spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mircea 
Geoana</PERSON> told a press conference on 11 <DATE>May</DATE> that "in order to have 
a complete and definitive picture of the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Parliament</ORGANIZATION>'s 
composition, and, consequently, of the government to be 
appointed, we need to see the results of the second round. It 
is obvious however that the Socialist Party is heading for 
victory." 
  About the Romanian-Hungarian relations once socialists 
accede 
to power, the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said the 
socialists' statements in the pre-election period were already 
known. "They voiced a constructive approach the Socialist Party 
intended to have if, elections over, they gained access to the 
ruling structures," <PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON> said. He also said that the 
Romanian side received such statements with interest and that 
"the Romanian authorities are waiting to see the outcome of the 
electoral process in <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, with a view to identifying, 
jointly with the new <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Government</ORGANIZATION>, the concrete means to 
continue the negotiations on the framework political treaty, and 
on the bilateral relations as a whole." 
  According to information furnished by the spokesman for the 
<ORGANIZATION>Romanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON>, the 
president of the <ORGANIZATION>European Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Egon Klepsch</ORGANIZATION> is expected 
on an official visit to <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> on <DATE>16-17 May this year</DATE> at the 
invitation of the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Parliament</ORGANIZATION>. The head of the <ORGANIZATION>European 
Parliament</ORGANIZATION> will have meetings with the speakers of the two 
houses of the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, with members of the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign 
Policy Committees</ORGANIZATION>, and with the Romanian parliamentary 
delegation to the <ORGANIZATION>European Parliament</ORGANIZATION>. He will also meet with 
leaders of the parliamentary groups, the chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Council 
for Economic Coordination</ORGANIZATION>, Strategy and Reform, and the <ORGANIZATION>Minister 
of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION>. Egon Klepsch will deliver a speech before a 
joint sitting of parliament, and will be received by the 
president of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman also informed the press that 
the president of the <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Jacques Delors</PERSON>, will 
be the guest of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> on 2-4 <DATE>June</DATE>, at the invitation of Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Nicolae Vacaroiu</PERSON>. 
  In the same line, the spokesman announced that the <ORGANIZATION>European 
Parliament</ORGANIZATION> approved in its plenary meeting the recommendation of 
the <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION> for a ECU 125,000,000 credit to <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, 
representing the quota underwritten by the <ORGANIZATION>European Union</ORGANIZATION> from 
the <MONEY>$300,000,000</MONEY> loan officially applied for by the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian 
Government</ORGANIZATION> to the G-24 with the purpose of compensating the 
balance of payments and financing the economic reform over 
1993-1994. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-31015 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu106__a94027" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-106-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  31 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Greek Opposition Leader Urges Balkan Agreement </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Greek Opposition Leader Urges Balkan Agreement </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU0106101394 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1425 GMT 31 May 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0106101394 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 31/5/1994 -- Romanian President 
<PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> received at <ORGANIZATION>Cotroceni Palace</ORGANIZATION> on 31 <DATE>May</DATE> <PERSON>Miltiades 
Evert</PERSON>, president of the New Democracy Party of the <ORGANIZATION>Hellenic 
Republic</ORGANIZATION>, leader of the opposition in <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>. 
  After recalling the fine relations between <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, even at the time when the two countries belonged to 
differing social systems, the Hellenic politician pleaded in a 
press statement for the necessity of establishing a climate of 
peace in the <LOCATION>Balkans</LOCATION>. "<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bulgaria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> are spaces 
of stability and these countries have to take over the 
initiative of pacifying the <LOCATION>Balkans</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Miltiades Evert</PERSON> said. 
  He mentioned he proposed to the Romanian president "the 
signing of an agreement on existing frontiers intangibility" by 
the Balkan countries, as well as the passage to concrete 
measures for such a document to be signed the soonest. "The 
signing of such an agreement would be the first great step 
toward peace in the <LOCATION>Balkans</LOCATION>, that should be ensured first of all 
by the Balkan peoples," he added. 
  In the same context, <PERSON>Miltiades Evert</PERSON> said that the signing 
of 
the proposed agreement would be difficult at this moment for 
<LOCATION>Serbia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Croatia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bosnia</LOCATION>, countries that are at war now, but 
the other states in the zone, he said, were bound to do it 
"precisely in order to prevent the expansion of the conflict and 
to ensure welfare and economic development in the <LOCATION>Balkans</LOCATION>." 
  The conclusion of treaties to guarantee the current 
frontiers 
can be a first step toward securing peace in the <LOCATION>Balkans</LOCATION>, 
assessed <PERSON>Miltiadis Evert</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>New Democracy Party 
of Greece</ORGANIZATION>, during an interview with <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Minister of Labour</ORGANIZATION> 
and Social Protection <PERSON>Dan Mircea Popescu</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, on 31 
<DATE>May</DATE>. 
  The interview occasioned a survey of the stage of the 
bilateral relations which, they assessed, had to be increased 
and diversified, as well as the approach of stability and 
cooperation in the <LOCATION>Balkans</LOCATION>. 
  Minister <PERSON>Dan Mircea Popescu</PERSON> outlined to the guest the 
<ORGANIZATION>Romanian Government</ORGANIZATION>'s current priorities, emphasizing among them 
the securing of an adequate social protection and an increasing 
living standard of the population. He considered the 
difficulties <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> was going through at this time could be 
eased only through good-quality work, an efficient management 
and steady international economic cooperation, which, between 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, could be achieved on multiple planes. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50022 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu014__a94028" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-014-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Judge Condemns UDMR Talks on `Self-Governing' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU1801073294 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1217 GMT 17 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU1801073294 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, ROMPRES, 17/1/1994 -- "It was an attempt 
against the constitutional democracy in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>," said Romanian 
Constitutional Court <PERSON>Judge Antonie Iorgovan</PERSON>, cited by the daily 
ADEVARUL, referring to the news broadcasted by the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Television</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <DATE>January 14</DATE>, informing that the Hungarian 
Democratic Union of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> [<ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>], the ethnic party of the 
Hungarian minority, had met with mayors of several localities to 
discuss the issue of "self-governing." 
  <PERSON>Judge Antonie Iorgovan</PERSON>, who is also professor of 
constitutional law of the <ORGANIZATION>Bucharest University</ORGANIZATION>, reminds that 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s constitution does not provide such a concept because 
of the simple reason that there is only one government in a 
unitary state, politically responsible in front of the single 
parliament as the representative body of the Romanian nation." 
  <PERSON>Antonie Iorgovan</PERSON> reminded also that the "self-governing" 
wording was not stipulated by any unitary state's constitution 
in <LOCATION>Western Europe</LOCATION> as they consecrated a regional system of local 
administration and not a departmental system." <PERSON>Antonie Iorgovan</PERSON> 
draws attention also to the fact that even though only a 
departmental system of administrative-territorial organization 
in counties exists in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and not one recognizing regions, 
lands, provinces or communities, "there are political forces who 
employ such wording." Judge Iorgovan cites the Article 31, 
Paragraph 7, of the constitution as saying: "Any defamation of 
the country and the nation, instigation to a war of aggression, 
to national, racial, class or religious hatred, any incitement 
to discrimination, territorial separatism, public violence as 
well as an obscene conduct contrary to morality are prohibited 
by law." 
  The public opinion in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> has repeatedly showed in the 
recent years, its concern with regard to the statements made by 
several <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> leaders questioning directly or in a dissimulated 
way the issue of <LOCATION>Transylvania</LOCATION>, ancient Romanian territory, 
temporarily under the rule of the Austro-Hungarian <PERSON>Habsburg</PERSON> 
empire, till <DATE>1918</DATE>. 
  According to the <DATE>January 1992</DATE> census, the population of the 
counties of the historic province of <LOCATION>Transylvania</LOCATION> is made up by 
Romanians with <PERCENT>72.3 percent</PERCENT>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-8293 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu070__a94061" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-070-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Defense Council Examines Documents </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Defense Council Examines Documents </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1204075094 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1749 GMT 11 Apr 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1204075094 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 11/4/1994 -- <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s President 
<PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> presided on <DATE>April 11</DATE> a meeting of the country's 
<ORGANIZATION>Supreme Defence Council</ORGANIZATION>. Two drafts were examined and initialed 
on the occasion, namely "The Integrated Outlook of Romanian 
National Security" and "<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Military Defence Doctrine</ORGANIZATION>." 
  The former includes the fundamental tenets, objectives and 
trends defining the general policy of security of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. The 
latter has been drafted with observance of the provisions of 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s Constitution and laws, the basic principles, 
objectives and guiding lines of the security policy of the 
Romanian state, the current stage and the tendencies of the 
political-military affairs at a world, continental and regional 
scale, risks and threats that appear as likely against <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
national interests, the short- and middle-term evolution of the 
country's military integration with the European and 
Euro-Atlantic security structures. 
  The country's <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Defense Council</ORGANIZATION> decided that the two 
documents be referred to parliament for endorsement. 
  The agenda included debates and approval of a draft 
"Presentation Document: <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>," written by the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian 
Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of National 
Defence</ORGANIZATION>, in consequence of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s joining the "Partnership 
for Peace" plan. The document includes the measures proposed by 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, necessary for fulfilment of the political objectives of 
the Partnership and the aspects of military character or of 
other type that <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> can made available for <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION>, which is 
going to be forwarded the draft. 
  <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> reasserts in the document its determination to be 
faithful to all the principles and targets of the "Partnership 
for Peace" to the assertions in the "Declaration of the Heads of 
States and Governments Who Attended the Sitting of the 
<ORGANIZATION>North-Atlantic Council Held</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> on <DATE>January 10-11</DATE>, <DATE>1994</DATE>." 
  Political and organisation measures have been enlisted in 
the 
document intended to secure a democratic control on the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> and 
facilitate transparency in planning national defence and 
drafting the budget, fields of cooperation, human and logistic 
resources that <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> can contribute to the <ORGANIZATION>Partnership for 
Peace</ORGANIZATION> plan. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-9266 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu078__a94042" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-078-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  20 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Ministry Spokesman Cited on Treaties </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Foreign Ministry Spokesman Cited on Treaties </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU2004181394 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1620 GMT 20 Apr 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2004181394 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 20/4/1994 -- Foreign Ministry 
Spokesman <PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON> made a few points on news items in the 
Romanian media on the Romanian-Hungarian treaty, during a news 
conference he held in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> on 20 <DATE>April</DATE>. The news items 
claimed that "sources at the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> and the presidency 
said that, pursuant to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> pressures, the basic 
Romanian-Hungarian political treaty will be signed by 1 <DATE>July, 
1994</DATE>." 
  <PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON> denied the existence of such an understanding 
and said that as far as <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> was concerned, it was interested 
to conclude the political treaty with <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> the soonest. 
"Even before the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> conference or <DATE>26-27 May</DATE>, when the 
`stability' pact initiated by <PERSON>Balladur</PERSON> is launched, we would 
like to do it," said <PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON>. He added that <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> has 
not stated its stand on the proposals advanced long ago by the 
<ORGANIZATION>Romanian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> regarding the outstanding issues. "If 
we got an answer and were able to agree on a new round of 
negotiations, this would be a positive element in the actuation 
of the Romanian-Hungarian political dialogue," he said. 
  Regarding the issue of lifting the embargo against the 
<ORGANIZATION>Federal Republic of Yugoslavia</ORGANIZATION>, "from what we know this is not 
envisaged for now" -- Foreign Ministry Spokesman <PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON> 
said, referring to the "official launch" of the joint demarche 
of <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bulgaria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> in this respect. The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign 
Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said such a demarche ought to be made at the 
right time, when the process of political negotiations reaches a 
congenial stage. "In keeping with the evolution of the 
negotiations between the Bosnian conflicting parties, a decision 
will be analyzed and made by all parties concerned", he said, 
adding that <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> showed interest in the demarche, while 
<LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> did not state its stand. 
  The idea of a joint demarche of <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bulgaria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
for the lifting of the embargo on the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Republic of 
Yugoslavia</ORGANIZATION> was launched during the <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> visit by the Greek 
foreign minister a few weeks ago. The initiative pursues the 
easing of the negative effects emerged following the application 
of the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> sanctions by the countries neighbouring <LOCATION>ex-Yugoslavia</LOCATION>. 
  The prime minister of the Grand Duchy of <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jacques 
Smiter</PERSON>, will make an official visit in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> over <DATE>April 24-26</DATE> 
at the invitation of the Romanian Prime Minister <PERSON>Nicolae 
Vacaroiu</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman also said. 
  The agenda of the visit includes official talks with the 
Romanian premier, interviews with Romanian President <PERSON>Ion 
Iliescu</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Oliviu Gherman</PERSON>, Chamber of Deputies 
Speaker <PERSON>Adrian Nastase</PERSON>. 
  On the occasion of the visit, an inter-governmental 
agreement 
of cooperation in the fields of culture, education, science and 
sport will be signed. 
  The postponement of the signing of the basic political 
treaty 
between <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Republic</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>, first 
scheduled to take place while Yugoslav Federal President <PERSON>Zoran 
Lilic</PERSON> was in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> for the <ORGANIZATION>Crans Montana Forum</ORGANIZATION>, stirred the 
interest of the journalists who attended the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> 
briefing on 20 <DATE>April</DATE>. Confirming President <PERSON>Lilic</PERSON> would not 
attend the Forum because of the tense situation in <LOCATION>Bosnia</LOCATION>, 
<PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON> said the official document would be signed only 
after the two parties agreed on all issues. "It is an important 
political document with a neighbour state, that has to fall in 
line with the whole of the political treaties <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> is 
concluding with other states of the world," he added. "It is 
not to be achieved upon conjunctural bases, statuting instead 
the format of bilateral relations in all spheres." 
  Referring to the conflict in <LOCATION>Gorazde</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Foreign 
Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman reiterated <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s constant stand relying 
upon the principle of using the whole range of 
political-diplomatic means to induce the conflicting parties to 
go on negotiating. "We follow with worry the events in <LOCATION>Gorazde</LOCATION> 
and see the high rate of contacts and statements by all parties 
concerned, which leaves room for optimism," <PERSON>Geoana</PERSON> said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-8297 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu070__a94065" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-070-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   U.S. General Continues Visit, Talks on NATO </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    U.S. General Continues Visit, Talks on NATO </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Talks With Tinca Reported </H4>

<F P=102> AU0604153794 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1202 GMT 6 Apr 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0604153794 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 6/4/1994 -- <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, 6 <DATE>April</DATE>, 
the talks started between Romanian Defense Minister <PERSON>Gheorghe 
Tinca</PERSON> and General <PERSON>George Joulwan</PERSON>, supreme commander of the 
allied forces in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, who is now on a documentation visit in 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. The agenda, <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Army</ORGANIZATION> sources say, includes 
matters related to the participation of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and other East 
European countries in the Partnership for Peace program, the 
evolution of the democratic process in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and the parallel 
reform of the army, to matters concerning European and 
international security. 
  Attending the talks are <PERSON>Dumitru Cioflina</PERSON>, secretary of state 
at the <ORGANIZATION>National Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> and chief of the general staff, 
<PERSON>Ioan Mircea Pascu</PERSON>, secretary of state for defense policies and 
external relations of the <ORGANIZATION>National Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, and other 
military officials accompanying the guest. 
  In the morning of 6 <DATE>April</DATE> General <PERSON>George Joulwan</PERSON> was 
received 
by the president of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ion Iliescu</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-50016 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu014__a94022" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-014-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Ministry `Welcomes' Ukrainian Disarmament </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU1901215094 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1700 GMT 19 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU1901215094 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpt] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 19/1/1994 -- The spokesman 
for the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mircea Geoana</PERSON>, 
read to the press at the 19 <DATE>January</DATE> news briefing a statement by 
which the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> takes note with interest and 
satisfaction of the signing in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> by the presidents of the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Russian Federation</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> of the 
documents by which the <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> renounces the nuclear strategic 
missiles deployed in its territory. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION> reasserts <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
firm attachment to the aims and principles of non-proliferation 
of nuclear arms and welcomes this important decision made by the 
<LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION>, a decision apt to contribute to strengthening security, 
stability and confidence in our geographical zone, in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and 
the whole world. <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, while duly appreciating the signing 
of the <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> documents as an important example of nuclear 
disarmament, expresses its hope that other countries holding 
nuclear armament in their possession will take new steps towards 
liquidating their arsenals, the statement concludes. 
  Other subjects mentioned at the news briefing: Scheduled for 
<DATE>27-28 January 1994</DATE> in <LOCATION>Rabat</LOCATION>, the proceedings of the eighth 
session of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Romanian-Moroccan Intergovernmental 
Commitee for Economic and Technical Cooperation</ORGANIZATION> will be chaired 
by the two countries' foreign ministers. This will occasion 
<PERSON>Teodor Melescanu</PERSON> an official visit to <LOCATION>Morocco</LOCATION> at the invitation 
of state minister in charge with the external affairs and 
cooperation <PERSON>Abdellatif Filali</PERSON>. 
  The two sides will tackle and establish concrete measures 
and 
actions apt to lead to the relaunch of the bilateral political 
dialogue, to boost commercial relations and favour the 
furtherance of economic cooperation in fields of joint interest, 
such as port facilities, road building, drilling, technical 
assistance, professional training. The sides also propose to 
negotiate and sign an agreement to guarantee and promote 
investment, as well as a cooperation protocol between the two 
foreign ministries and the programme reflecting the 1994-1996 
cultural agreement. 
  <DATE>Friday</DATE>, 21 <DATE>January</DATE>, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Melescanu</PERSON> will have an 
interview with <PERSON>Joseph Kruzel</PERSON>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> deputy assistant secretary of 
defence for European and <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> policies, who is heading the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
delegation to the meeting of the U.S.-Romania bilateral working 
group on matters regarding political-military cooperation 
relations. 
  Spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry Mircea Geoana</ORGANIZATION> also told 
the 19 <DATE>January</DATE> briefing that the message of <PERSON>Mrs. Madeleine 
Albright</PERSON>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ambassador to the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, special envoy 
of American President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>, who paid a visit in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
<DATE>Saturday, January 15</DATE>, was considered, alongside recent 
statements by President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> and Vice President <PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON>, 
to substantially back <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s efforts to reinforce its 
stability and security in a troubled regional framework and in a 
larger context, in order to consolidate the Romanian democratic 
society. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-8291 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu070__a94059" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-070-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Chebeleu on Ties With Hungary, Other Issues </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Chebeleu on Ties With Hungary, Other Issues </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU0804185794 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1530 GMT 8 Apr 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0804185794 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 8/4/1994 -- <PERSON>Geza Entz</PERSON>, member of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Government</ORGANIZATION>, paid his Romanian visit in spite of 
the fact that the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> was emphatic about 
abstaining from this until Romanian authorities agreed. "It is 
regrettable that the Hungarian dignitary chose to ignore the 
Romanian authorities", said Ambassador <PERSON>Traian Chebeleu</PERSON> during a 
news conference on 8 <DATE>April</DATE>, in answering a ROMPRES question. 
  Referring to the same aspect, the presidential spokesman 
showed that the Romanian authorities were worried by that 
gesture "that accounts for a very serious brake in the efforts 
to normalize the Romanian-Hungarian relations and conclude the 
basic treaty between the two countries," as the <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> 
official's behaviour defied the principles of inter-state 
relations. 
  Referring to the pardoning of the ethnic Hungarians involved 
in the crimes at <LOCATION>Zetea</LOCATION> and Dealu, <LOCATION>Harghita County</LOCATION>, presidential 
spokesman <PERSON>Traian Chebeleu</PERSON> said it was not complete. It was made 
in such a way as to have the convicts eligible for parole while 
the final decision would be made in keeping with the existing 
procedures by the local court. 
  As regarded the treaty envisaged to be concluded with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Federal Republic of Yugoslavia</ORGANIZATION>, Ambassador <PERSON>Chebeleu</PERSON> said it was 
part of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s policy of equal treatment of all states in the 
territory of former <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>. 
  The statement of Moldovan Prime Minister <PERSON>Andrei Sangheli</PERSON>, 
who 
did not name <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> among the countries that gave the Republic 
of <LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION> support, accusing it instead of failure to fulfil its 
obligations, was termed as "ununderstandable" by <PERSON>Traian Chebeleu</PERSON> 
who said the Romanian authorities waited for "the necessary 
explanation" that would be requested through the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian 
Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chisinau</LOCATION>. 
  The spokesman also said President <PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> was 
represented 
at the funeral of playwright <PERSON>Eugen Ionesco</PERSON> by <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
Ambassador in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Anton Vatasescu</PERSON>. 
  Requested to deny or confirm an alleged meeting between 
President <PERSON>Slobodan Milosevic</PERSON> and American General <PERSON>George Joulwan</PERSON> 
during the Serb head of state's stay in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, Ambassador 
<PERSON>Traian Chebeleu</PERSON> definitely denied it: "The meeting did not and 
could not occur because of President <PERSON>Milosevic</PERSON>'s very busy 
schedule, he said. [no closing quotation mark as received] 
  Romanian President <PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> will pay a state visit to 
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> over <DATE>14-11 April, 1994</DATE>, presidential spokesman <PERSON>Traian 
Chebeleu</PERSON> also announced in his news conference. 
  The schedule of the visit includes, apart from talks with 
President <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON>, an interview with Prime Minister <PERSON>Edouard 
Balladur</PERSON>, meetings with <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Rene Monory</PERSON> and 
President of the National Assembly <PERSON>Philippe Seguin</PERSON>, with other 
politicians. 
  He is also expected to meet at the <ORGANIZATION>National Council</ORGANIZATION> of the 
French Employers with representatives of business circles and to 
visit the <ORGANIZATION>GEC-Alsthom</ORGANIZATION> works. 
  The presidential spokesman assessed the visit was "a natural 
moment in the evolution of the Romanian-French relations after 
the revolution and at the same time it is meant to boost them." 
Stressing that in the four years after the revolution <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> has 
given <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> decisive support in its efforts for rapprochement 
and integration in the bodies of the European democratic states, 
Ambassador <PERSON>Traian Chebeleu</PERSON> highlighted that <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s president 
attached great importance to the forthcoming political 
consultations with <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, that would cover a wide area of 
issues, from ways to further develop the bilateral relations and 
the speeding up of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s integration in the European 
institutions to the current questions of security in our zone 
and in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> generally. 
  The visit will have also an important economic dimension, 
the 
result of which we hope to be an ever more significant presence 
of the French companies in the Romanian economy, the 
presidential spokesman said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-30869 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu027__a94030" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-027-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Poland </F>
<H3> <TI>   Comments by Moldova's Snegur Draw Reaction </TI></H3>
<H4>   Party Officials Comment </H4>
<F P=102> AU0702172694 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1400 GMT 7 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0702172694 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 7/2/1994 -- <PERSON>Dumitru Paslaru</PERSON>, 
spokesman of the ruling party of Social Democracy of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
(<ORGANIZATION>PDSR</ORGANIZATION>), said developments in the Republic of <LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION>, the 
reconsideration of the stands of important political 
personalities there and their statements rendered delicate the 
continuation of the political relations and the rapprochement 
between <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and that state. In an interview with ROMPRES, 
<PERSON>Paslaru</PERSON> added that the <ORGANIZATION>PDSR</ORGANIZATION> considered the statements made by 
<PERSON>Snegur</PERSON> [president of the Republic of <LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION>] and <PERSON>Motpan</PERSON> 
[president of the <ORGANIZATION>Agrarian Democratic Party of Moldova</ORGANIZATION>] to be 
inciting, offending the Romanians everywhere, an attempt at the 
country's national integrity, an obvious disconsideration of 
public opinion of the Romanian majority in the present Republic 
of <LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION>. "We however hope these statements are just a 
temporary element in the political climate of the Republic of 
<LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION>. These statements should better not turn into ruling 
theses and the optimistic tone of our relations of so far should 
be resumed," the <ORGANIZATION>PDSR</ORGANIZATION> spokesman also said. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Romanian National Unity Party</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>PUNR</ORGANIZATION>] Vice-President 
<PERSON>Cornel Brahas</PERSON> assesses as a mistake the fact that the Romanian 
authorities recognized officially "this shadow state in 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s historical territory. It is an open attempt at our 
integrity and a tragical betrayal of the Romanian nation. No 
matter what eastern or western chancellories encouraged <PERSON>Snegur</PERSON> 
to assume this terrible burden, we must not give in to 
defeatism," <PERSON>Cornel Brahas</PERSON> said. 
  "I have not been taken by surprise by this statement made by 
<PERSON>Mr. Mircea Snegur</PERSON>, a good Romanian speaker but not an equally 
good Romanian. It was prepared by other political actions which 
we ignored when we did not encourage," said Professor <PERSON>Ion Coja</PERSON>, 
an outstanding member of the <ORGANIZATION>Agrarian Democratic Party of 
Romania</ORGANIZATION> (PDAR). "What's even worse is that, in a concerted 
manner, some sort of declaration of annexation of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
territory to the former <ORGANIZATION>USSR</ORGANIZATION> is also launched. It is high time 
that the president of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, the parliament and government 
took at long last a stand that should not be criticized by the 
future generations of Romanians on either bank of the Prut," 
Professor <PERSON>Ion Coja</PERSON> said. 
  "The <ORGANIZATION>National Council of Reintegration</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Party 
of Reintegration</ORGANIZATION> have decided to `back' <PERSON>Mircea Snegur</PERSON>, 
organizing the participation in the referendum of the more than 
one million refugees or their descendants, either Romanians, 
Jews, Germans, Poles," said <PERSON>Mircea Druc</PERSON>, former prime minister 
of the Republic of <LOCATION>Moldova</LOCATION>, now president of the <ORGANIZATION>National Party 
of Reintegration</ORGANIZATION>. "A referendum of all those who were forced to 
leave their native land following the Soviet invasion. In a 
near future, we will convene also a world congress of all 
refugees because we too, want to be a part of `<PERSON>Snegur</PERSON>'s people' 
summoned to the referendum," <PERSON>Mircea Druc</PERSON> said. 
  "<PERSON>Mircea Snegur</PERSON> has proved he has remained a cent [as 
received] percent communist and no longer thinks, even for a 
moment, that he is Romanian," said <PERSON>Ion Diaconescu</PERSON>, 
Party</ORGANIZATION>. 
  "For him, the notion of Romanian is completely subordinated 
to the political creed for which he has campaigned for a 
lifetime. His theses are communist, they were <ORGANIZATION>Stalin</ORGANIZATION>'s as well 
and he keeps them because he grew up with them. 
  "Nobody imposes <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s union with <LOCATION>Bessarabia</LOCATION> by force, 
but 
to go as far as declaring that Romanians and Moldovans are 
different peoples is a nonsense launched by communists which 
<PERSON>Mircea Snegur</PERSON>, as a truthful disciple, has adopted." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-32403 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu122__a94023" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-122-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  23 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   UDMR Says Education Bill `Unacceptable' </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    UDMR Says Education Bill `Unacceptable' </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU2306185794 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1457 GMT 23 Jun 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2306185794 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

Union of Hungarians in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>] sees itself compelled to 
reassess the role and aim of its representation to parliament, 
because <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> does not accept to act just as a stand-in in the 
country's legislative body," runs a statement made by this 
party's parliamentary group leader <PERSON>Gyula Vida</PERSON> at the end of the 
debates on the education act. 
  In the group's opinion, the "education act in its present 
form is absolutely unacceptable for the Hungarian community. It 
(the law) enacts an obvious and unspeakable discrimination 
against the ethnic minorities in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, and at the same time, 
a flagrant violation of the constitution." 
  The main objections <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> has against the draft law is the 
restriction of the constitutional right to learn in the native 
tongue in all the objects of study, the abolition of the 
existing structures of specialized education in minority 
languages, the interdiction to train in higher education 
institutions specialists in social and economic sciences, the 
inacceptance to have the confessional schools reorganized and 
re-established. 
  "The ruling (Social Democracy Party of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> -- <ORGANIZATION>PDSR</ORGANIZATION>) is 
visibly the prisoner of extremist political forces. The 
government's lack of political will to solve these problems 
hampers the building of a climate of social peace, destabilizing 
the Romanian society," says the <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> lower house group statement. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-49151 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu004__a94029" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-001-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> ROMANIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Iliescu Receives South Korean Business Group </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU0401184994 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1751 GMT 4 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0401184994 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> ROMPRES 4/1/1994 -- <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s President 
<PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> received on <DATE>January 4, 1994</DATE>, a delegation of the 
North [as received] Korean Daewoo group, led by <PERSON>Kim U-chung</PERSON>, 
chairman of the administration board. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Daewoo</ORGANIZATION> group intends to explore ways for large-scale 
investments in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> in the car-making industry, 
ship-building, refineries, electronics, tourism and the 
financial-banking sector. 
  President <PERSON>Iliescu</PERSON> saluted the interest of South Korean 
businessmen in cooperation actions in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and told his guest 
about the potentialities of the Romanian economy, the 
opportunities created for foreign investors by the Romanian 
legislation. The Romanian president encouraged the 
representives of the <ORGANIZATION>Daewoo</ORGANIZATION> group to have contacts with Romanian 
businessmen in view of making mutually advantageous transactions. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-49109 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu001__a94029" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-001-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> ROMANIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Iliescu Receives South Korean Business Group </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU0401184994 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1751 GMT 4 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0401184994 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> ROMPRES 4/1/1994 -- <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s President 
<PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> received on <DATE>January 4, 1994</DATE>, a delegation of the 
North [as received] Korean Daewoo group, led by <PERSON>Kim U-chung</PERSON>, 
chairman of the administration board. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Daewoo</ORGANIZATION> group intends to explore ways for large-scale 
investments in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> in the car-making industry, 
ship-building, refineries, electronics, tourism and the 
financial-banking sector. 
  President <PERSON>Iliescu</PERSON> saluted the interest of South Korean 
businessmen in cooperation actions in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and told his guest 
about the potentialities of the Romanian economy, the 
opportunities created for foreign investors by the Romanian 
legislation. The Romanian president encouraged the 
representives of the <ORGANIZATION>Daewoo</ORGANIZATION> group to have contacts with Romanian 
businessmen in view of making mutually advantageous transactions. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-9351 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu056__a94035" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-056-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   UDMR Walks Out of Senate Over Veterans' Bill </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU2203143494 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1230 GMT 22 Mar 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU2203143494 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, ROMPRES 22/3/1994 -- The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> resumed 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 22</DATE>, the debates of the bill on war veterans and 
widows. The parliamentary group of the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian Democratic 
Union</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>, asked for permission to make a political 
declaration on part of the articles of the said bill. Submitted 
to vote, the request was rejected. Consequently the members of 
the <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> parliamentary group walked out of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Hall</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> passed in its <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>March 21</DATE> sitting an 
amendment to an article of the bill on war veterans and widows 
saying that the residents of Romanian territories occupied over 
1940-1945, that were called to arms fight in the Armies of other 
states are considered to be war veterans only "if they did not 
fight against the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Army</ORGANIZATION>." The members of the <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> group 
opposed the amendment. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-49482 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu007__a94028" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-007-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Spokesman on Iliescu's Efforts To Join NATO </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU0801191094 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1708 GMT 7 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0801191094 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 7/1/1994 -- At the press 
conference of 7 <DATE>January</DATE> given by Ambassador <PERSON>Traian Chebeleu</PERSON>, 
spokesman for the Presidency of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, the following points 
were made about the steps taken by the head of the Romanian 
state for <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s adherence to <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION>: 
  "It is not incidental that the president [Ion Iliescu] paid 
an official visit to <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>February 1993</DATE>. Availing himself of 
this opportunity, President <PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> said before the <ORGANIZATION>NATO 
Council</ORGANIZATION>: `As a true partner, <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> wishes to work ever closer 
with <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> and to strengthen its ties with the structures of the 
alliance, to draw closer to them, by taking part in any form of 
cooperation open to the Central European countries. Besides the 
immediate positive effects, all this would be of a nature to 
contribute to creating the prerequisites for reaching the 
strategic aim which is <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s joining the <ORGANIZATION>North Atlantic 
Alliance</ORGANIZATION>. This would offer the necessary guarantees for a 
normal evolution of the irreversible process of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
democratization.' 
  "Subsequent to these official efforts made by the president, 
which were among the first statements of this kind on the topic 
of permitting the countries in this part of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> access to 
<ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION>, messages were addressed on two different occasions -- in 
<DATE>September</DATE> and <DATE>December 1993</DATE> -- to <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> heads of state and <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> 
Secretary General <PERSON>Woerner</PERSON>, including President <PERSON>Iliescu</PERSON>'s 
considerations on the role of <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> in maintaining security in 
<LOCATION>Central</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>East Europe</LOCATION>, and the official position relative to 
the inclusion in the alliance of the countries in this part of 
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
  "Those messages were well received by the member states of 
the alliance and found by the greatest part of their 
representatives as most welcome, straightforward, and clearly 
worded," the presidential spokesman said. 
  On receiving the letter from the president of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, the 
representatives of several (<ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION>) states made a point of showing 
that they would support <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> in its strive for integration in 
<ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> and other Euro-Atlantic structures, knowing that <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
was resolutely committed to the course of democratization and 
the rule of law, and therefore it should stay in the family of 
the democratic European states. 
  It was also shown that <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s security interests would be 
considered, as well as its readiness to assume responsibilities 
in ensuring security in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
  A positive assessment was made of the way <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> responded 
to the initiative of <ORGANIZATION>Partnership for Peace</ORGANIZATION>, which several member 
countries see as a transitional stage in the gradual extension 
process of the alliance. 
  The message of the Romanian president was unanimously 
appreciated as a significant signal for the priority <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
gives to enlarging its political, economic, and security 
relations with the Western countries, the spokesman for the 
presidency said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-49932 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu009__a94029" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-009-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Turkey Favors Nation's Admission to NATO </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU1201195994 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1813 GMT 12 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU1201195994 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 12/01/1994 -- <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
President <PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> received a letter of reply from <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>'s 
President <PERSON>Suleyman Demirel</PERSON> saying that <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION> favours <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
application to joint <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> and will back the alliance's decisions 
meeting these aspirations. 
  The letter stresses <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>'s admiration of the progress 
marked by <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> since <DATE>1990</DATE> and the satisfaction at the fine 
and close collaboration within the <ORGANIZATION>North-Atlantic Cooperation 
Council</ORGANIZATION>, as well as the interest confirmed by <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> in the 
collaboration with that forum that has brought <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
closer. 
  "We see the Partnership for Peace initiative as an 
operational formula in this period of transition and believe it 
will help enhancing the security, stability and fertile 
cooperation in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and around it," the <DATE>January 5, 1994</DATE> letter 
by <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>'s president reads. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-8410 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu046__a94025" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-046-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Talks With Senate President </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AU0703202594 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1627 GMT 7 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0703202594 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, ROMPRES, 7/3/1994 -- The president of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Oliviu Gherman</PERSON>, received <DATE>Monday</DATE>, 7 <DATE>March</DATE>, a 
delegation of the Alliance of the Free Democrats of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> 
[SZDSZ], led by <PERSON>Gabor Kuncze</PERSON>, leader of a parliamentary faction 
and its candidate for premiership. 
  The sides talked about the necessity to strengthen the 
bilateral parliamentary ties as a basic element for the 
improvement of the Romanian-Hungarian relations. 
  <PERSON>Oliviu Gherman</PERSON> termed the inexistence of interparliamentary 
relations of the ruling party and the opposition forces in 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> with their counterparts in <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> as "illogical and 
contrary to bilateral interests" and said that as long as <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> 
with representation to <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s Parliament -- e.n.) is the sole 
parliamentary representative of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>Hungarian 
Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, the progress in the bilateral parliamentary 
relations will be "insignificant". <PERSON>Gabor Kuncze</PERSON> remarked that, 
given the short time lying before the present Hungarian 
legislative, the bilateral parliamentary relations between the 
two countries could be intensified after the new legislative 
assumes duties. 
  Both sides agreed that all possibilities should be used to 
improve Romanian-Hungarian relations, and that keeping up false 
tensions is to the interest of neither party. The president of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Senate</ORGANIZATION> gave assurances to the Hungarian guests 
that, before its term is over, the Romanian legislative body 
will ratify the Romanian-Hungarian agreement for the mutual 
protection of investments. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-9034 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu076__a94052" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-076-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  19 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Holds Talks With Iliescu </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Holds Talks With Iliescu </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1904171994 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1248 GMT 19 Apr 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1904171994 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 19/4/1994 -- The minister of 
foreign affairs of the Republic of <LOCATION>Armenia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Vahan Papazyan</PERSON>, was 
received on <DATE>Tuesday, April 19</DATE>, at the <ORGANIZATION>Cotroceni Palace</ORGANIZATION>, by 
Romanian President <PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON>. 
  In a statement to the press made at the end of the 
interview, 
the Armenian chief diplomat underscored the necessity of 
developing the bilateral relations as the main subject of his 
dialogue with the Romanian head of state along with an analysis 
of several issues of the international life, especially the 
situation in <LOCATION>Nagorno</LOCATION>- <LOCATION>Karabakh</LOCATION> and in <LOCATION>Bosnia-Herzegovina</LOCATION> as 
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Armenia</LOCATION> were equally interested in their settlement. 
The Armenian minister of foreign affairs delivered to the 
Romanian president a message from the part of the Armenian 
president together with the invitation to visit <LOCATION>Armenia</LOCATION>. 
  The interview was attended also by Romanian Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Teodor Melescanu</PERSON>, Presidential Adviser <PERSON>Traian Chebeleu</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Varujan Vosganian</PERSON>, deputy in the Romanian Parliament 
representing the Armenian minority of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. 
  Armenian ambassador <PERSON>Guergui Kazinyan</PERSON> [name as received] 
presented on <DATE>Monday, April 18</DATE>, his credentials while the 
<ORGANIZATION>Armenian Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> is going to be officially opened 
within the following days. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-54791 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu087__a94036" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-087-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   German Parliamentary Delegation To Assess Aid </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    German Parliamentary Delegation To Assess Aid </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU0405181094 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1410 GMT 4 May 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU0405181094 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 4/5/1994 -- The parliamentary 
secretary of state of the <ORGANIZATION>German Ministry of the Interior</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Horst 
Waffenschmidt</PERSON>, in charge with the affairs of the Germans abroad, 
started on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> a three-day visit in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> accompanied by 
a delegation comprising deputies in the <LOCATION>Bundestag</LOCATION>, the 
presidents of the associations of the Swabians and the Saxons of 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, representatives of charity institutions, government 
dignitaries, said <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesperson <PERSON>Simona 
Miculescu</PERSON> at a press conference on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. The visit is 
meant to assess the aid granted by the German Government to the 
German nationals of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> in order to decide over new measures 
of aid in the economic, cultural, social and education fields. 
The German delegation will be received by Romanian President 
<PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> and will have talks with members of the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian 
Government</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesperson said also that the German 
minister for economic cooperation Carl-Dieter Spranger would 
visit <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> on <DATE>May 6-7</DATE> at the invitation of the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian 
Government</ORGANIZATION> in order work out new actions of German support to 
the economic restructuring process in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> especially in the 
industrial sector. On that occasion, a governmental 
frame-agreement will be signed concerning the technological 
cooperation between <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-9042 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu076__a94060" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-076-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Defense Official on Danger of `Subversion' </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Defense Official on Danger of `Subversion' </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1604154494 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1543 GMT 15 Apr 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1604154494 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 15/4/1994 -- The main danger 
threatening <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> is not coming from outside, but rather from 
inside, subversion being one of its forms, <PERSON>Ion Mircea Pascu</PERSON>, 
secretary of state in charge of defense and international 
relations of the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Ministry of Defense</ORGANIZATION>, told a news 
conference <DATE>Friday, 15 April</DATE>. Subversive acts can be 'canvassed' 
in many ways, he said, by those who pursue such aims. <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 
does not exclude extraneous danger, although this is less 
poignant at the moment. He said <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s option is for 
integration in the European structures, and that the Partnership 
for Peace is one step towards that goal. <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s ultimate 
target in its strive for integration is the forging of a 
European security system comprising all the actors on the 
European political stage, the <ORGANIZATION>Russian Federation</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION>, 
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, inclusively. 
  Related to the problems the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Army</ORGANIZATION> is confronted 
with, 
the secretary of state said its endowment and equipment shall be 
done as the budget allocation permits. Although modest, this 
provides for certain growths which will enable the army to 
upgrade medical assistance and housing conditions for the 
military. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-32006 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu117__a94027" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-117-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  16 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   PDSR, UDMR Debate Education Draft Bill </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    PDSR, UDMR Debate Education Draft Bill </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1606154294 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1337 GMT 16 Jun 94 
-- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> AU1606154294 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 16/6/1994 -- For several weeks 
the <ORGANIZATION>Chamber of Deputies</ORGANIZATION> has debated the Education Act, seen as 
the second most important law of this country after the 
Constitution. The law will pass when key provisions, such as the 
ones regulating education in minority languages, are solved. To 
many objections in their draft form. 
  The chapter in question, the thirteenth, being the most 
difficult to adopt, a Parliament member came the other day with 
the idea that the chapter should be skipped over and remanded to 
a special group formed of the senior members of the [<ORGANIZATION>Chamber of 
Deputies] Education Committee</ORGANIZATION> and the leaders of the 
parliamentary groups, while the plenum goes on with the debates 
on the following chapters. 
  So, while the chamber tackled other sections of the draft, 
negotiations took place in what the daily newspaper ADEVARUL 
calls "the less transparent corners of the <ORGANIZATION>Education Committee</ORGANIZATION> 
and the chamber's permanent bureau," and "maybe even between the 
ruling Social Democracy Party of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> [<ORGANIZATION>PDSR</ORGANIZATION>] and the <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>." 
  The bone of contention are two articles of this Chapter 13, 
namely the one stipulating that at all school levels the history 
and geography of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> should be taught in Romanian language, 
and the other says that objects of study specific for the 
technical, medical, agricultural, juridical, and economic 
streams, whatever the level, should be taught in Romanian. 
According to press news, the ruling party is reportedly 
favoring the provisions above for various reasons, one of them 
being the insistent request by some of its political allies (the 
<ORGANIZATION>National Unity Party</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Greater Romania Party</ORGANIZATION>), and 
some independent members of parliament, namely that "the history 
and geography of <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> be taught exclusively in the official 
language of the Romanian state," that is, in Romanian. 
  Commenting the first round of talks on this issue, <ORGANIZATION>CRONICA 
ROMANA</ORGANIZATION> remarks that "it ended with an agreement on the teaching 
of geography and civic education in the languages of minorities, 
and of teaching only history in Romanian language." A second 
and a third round of consultations have failed so far to bring 
the sides' positions any nearer. 
  With the consultations going on until late, the following 
morning (<DATE>Thursday</DATE>, 16 <DATE>June</DATE>), the plenum debates started <DATE>two 
hours later</DATE> than scheduled. 
  The same morning, a <ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION> press release informed that its 
presidium had reached the conclusion, at its latest meeting, 
that the articles so far adopted from the draft of the education 
act "do not help solve the problem to the effect desired by the 
<ORGANIZATION>UDMR</ORGANIZATION>," and that the still valid education law, enacted during 
the communist regime, was "more permissive than the draft 
currently under debate." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-30872 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu027__a94033" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-027-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Poland </F>
<H3> <TI>   Comments by Moldova's Snegur Draw Reaction </TI></H3>
<H4>   Press Condemnation Reported </H4>
<F P=102> AU0802173594 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1400 GMT 8 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU0802173594 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 
