<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-12574</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CAZAFAC9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920125
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 JAN 92 / Sport: Bills seek their place in history - American Football
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PATRICK HARVERSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>MARV LEVY</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> graduate, history buff and poetry lover, talks a mean
game of American football.
The silver-haired head coach of the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills analyses the strategies
and tactics of the sport in a precise, elegant manner. His comments in press
conferences can come laced with literary allusions. He uses words like
'inculcate' and 'salient' in pre-game meetings with his team.
Tomorrow in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, however, the erudite <PERSON>Levy</PERSON> will leave the talking to
his players, who must play a mean game of football if they are to defeat the
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Redskins in Superbowl XXVI.
The Redskins start as favourites, and are expected to win by at least seven
points according to the bookmakers in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>. Yet for those of us who
have enjoyed watching the Bills this season, it is difficult to think of
them as underdogs.
Under <PERSON>Levy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> has set the <ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION> alight in the past
two seasons with a rapid-fire passing and running game which led the team to
a host of high scoring victories.
At the root of their success is the 'no-huddle' offense - a tactic that
dispenses with the huddle before each play and allows the quarterback to
call his own moves. At its best, the no-huddle offense puts points on the
board quickly and leaves opposing defenses scrambling to keep up with the
pace.
At the heart of the Bills attack are two great players, quarterback <PERSON>Jim
Kelly</PERSON> and all-purpose running back <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON>. Kelly is an experienced
leader with a sharp tactical brain and a strong arm, while <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> is a
superb all-rounder, a quicksilver runner and an acrobatic receiver.
Powered by <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> and <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, and supported by receivers <PERSON>James Lofton</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Andre Reed</PERSON>, the Bills topped the statistical tables in a number of key
attacking categories this season, including most total yards gained and most
touchdowns scored.
So with all their offensive firepower, why aren't the Bills favourites to
win?
There are two reasons, and both come down to defense. The Redskins' defense
is strong, against both the running and the passing game, and it ranks third
best in the league for overall effectiveness.
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s defense is especially good at 'blitzing' the quarterback - in
the 16 regular games this season they reached opposing quarterbacks and
sacked them 50 times. <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> has looked vulnerable to the sack in the past,
particularly two weekends ago when the <ORGANIZATION>Denver Broncos</ORGANIZATION>' blitzed relentlessly,
giving <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> insufficient time to get his no-huddle offense into gear.
The fragility of their own defense, which ranked next-to-last in the league
this season, is the second reason why the Bills are not favourites tomorrow.
They have shown an improvement in the playoffs (holding <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> to just seven
points in the AFC Championship game), thanks partly to the return of two
powerful players, slashing defensive end <PERSON>Bruce Smith</PERSON> and bulldozing nose
tackle <PERSON>Jeff Wright</PERSON>.
Yet in the <LOCATION>Redskins</LOCATION>, the Bills defense will be facing one of the toughest
offensive lines in football. This is where the 'Hogs' come in. Hogs is the
collective nickname for the enormous front-line that defends Redskins'
quarterback <PERSON>Mark Rypien</PERSON>.
Not only are the Hogs good at giving <PERSON>Rypien</PERSON> time to throw long passes to
receivers Art Monk, <PERSON>Gary Clark</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ricky Sanders</PERSON> (the protection has been so
effective that <PERSON>Rypien</PERSON> was sacked just nine times all season), but they are
also adept at knocking holes in defensive lines for backs <PERSON>Ernest Byner</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Ricky Ervins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gerald Riggs</PERSON> to run through.
One big advantage the Redskins have is the versatility of their attack. The
Bills rely heavily, perhaps too heavily, on <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>'s all-round skills. Stop
<PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> usually struggles.
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s three running backs possess different strengths and styles
providing a balance of power and precision. The trio of fleet wide receivers
spread defenses and regularly break open for long yardage. The variety of
attacking options available to Redskins coach <PERSON>Joe Gibbs</PERSON> helps explain why
his team was the highest-scoring unit in the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> this season.
Yet, as any fan of sports cliches knows, statistics and history mean little
when it comes to one Big Game. The difference may ultimately lie in
motivation, and how badly each team wants to win.
In this respect, the Bills could have the edge. It has been 363 days since
<PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON>'s potential game-winning kick sailed wide of the right hand
goalpost in the closing seconds of Superbowl XXV against the <ORGANIZATION>New York
Giants</ORGANIZATION>, and the determination of the Bills to avenge that loss burns just as
bright as it did a year ago.
Both teams have prepared thoroughly, but <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> seem to have gone about
their business amid the outrageous hype and publicity of Superbowl week in a
quieter, more purposeful manner.
And while less than half of the Redskins are survivors from the team's last
Superbowl appearance in <DATE>1987</DATE>, the Bills squad is much the same as it was
last year. The memories of that game are still fresh for <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON>, <PERSON>Thurman
Thomas</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Bruce Smith</PERSON>. My money is on <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> to win by three points,
courtesy of kicker <PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XII Photograph Bills head coach Marv Levy (Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-12481</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CAZAFAFUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920125
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 JAN 92 / Markets: It is all go for the Superbowl predictor - Wall
Street
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PATRICK HARVERSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE <LOCATION>WASHINGTON</LOCATION> <ORGANIZATION>Redskins</ORGANIZATION> will defeat the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills in the Superbowl
tomorrow, and US stock markets will remain bullish all year. No, a
combination of the cold weather and Superbowl hype has not gone to my head.
I am only paying heed to one of Wall Street's most effective forecasting
tools: the Superbowl Predictor.
The theory is simple. Victory for a team from the old <ORGANIZATION>National Football
League</ORGANIZATION> forecasts a year of rising stock prices, while victory for a team
from the old <ORGANIZATION>American Football League</ORGANIZATION> (the two leagues merged in <DATE>1970</DATE>)
heralds a year of falling prices. The Redskins are favoured to win in
<LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> tomorrow, and because they are an old <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> team, Wall Street
believes it is in for a good year.
You may scoff, but since the first Superbowl in <DATE>1967</DATE>, the Predictor has
worked 22 out of 25 times, a success rate of 88 per cent. There is no other
leading indicator that comes close to matching it.
The theory can also work in reverse. The stock markets have started <DATE>1992</DATE> in
buoyant mood, and should continue to enjoy solid gains throughout the year,
if you believe the consensus. Thus, the bulls predict the Bills will lose
and the Skins win. Confused?
Investors certainly are. This was a difficult week for the markets, which
posted some of the first significant losses since the rally began in
<DATE>mid-December</DATE>. There was a 32-point gain midweek, but that owed more to
late-session program trading than it did to renewed demand from investors.
Profit-taking was the dominant factor, with traders and investors taking the
opportunity to book some of the gains earned in the month-long rally. At the
same time, buyers have been scanning the market for sectors that could offer
a good ride over the next few weeks.
Technical trading aside, investors appear uncertain as to what to do next. A
vast amount of money has flooded into the market since the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve</ORGANIZATION>
slashed interest rates at the end of <DATE>last year</DATE>, most of it from
lower-yielding short-term assets such as bank certificates of deposit and
money market funds.
That initial energy is probably now spent. Since the last rate cut on
<DATE>December 20</DATE>, the Dow has risen more than 10 per cent and the <ORGANIZATION>Standard &amp;
Poor</ORGANIZATION>'s 500 8.6 per cent, and it is difficult to justify adding to those
gains until some fresh stimulus other than lower interest rates
materialises.
This means any advance in the market from now on must come either from
better economic fundamentals or an improvement in the outlook for corporate
earnings. On the economic front, the news has remained gloomy. This week
contained little that pointed to a brighter future, while one set of
backward-looking figures, the final count for housing starts in <DATE>1991</DATE>,
testified to the depth of the recession last year.
Despite a modest rebound in housing starts in <DATE>December</DATE> (they rose 2.6 per
cent), over the full year they posted a 1.1 per cent decline, the worst
showing since <DATE>1945</DATE>. Although stock markets should only pay attention to
leading economic indicators, the housing numbers for <DATE>1991</DATE> show just how much
ground one of a key sector of the economy has to reclaim before the recovery
can be classified healthy.
As for corporate earnings, the quarterly reporting season continues to
produce an unappetising diet of the good, the bad and the ugly.
For <ORGANIZATION>United Technologies</ORGANIZATION>, the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE> loss of Dollars 1.22bn was about
as ugly as it gets. In its defence, <ORGANIZATION>United Tech</ORGANIZATION>'s loss was the product of a
Dollars 1.275bn charge to cover the cost of a huge restructuring, which the
aerospace and building group hopes will go toward restoring its good looks.
There is a price for the economy to pay, however, in the loss of almost
14,000 jobs and the closure of a host of <ORGANIZATION>United Tech</ORGANIZATION> facilities.
<ORGANIZATION>Delta Air Lines</ORGANIZATION> was another to report an unattractive loss for the final
quarter of the year. The Dollars 237m shortfall was partly a hangover from
<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>'s purchase of the failed <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am</ORGANIZATION>'s east coast shuttle operations and
transatlantic routes. The figures were not warmly received by investors who
had been keen buyers of the stocks until recently. Having peaked at over
<LOCATION>Dollars 75</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> ran into heavy selling in the latter half of the week and
by yesterday lunchtime had settled at Dollars 71.
The best corporate news of the week came from a most unlikely source - a
computer manufacturer. <ORGANIZATION>Unisys</ORGANIZATION> recorded <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE> profits of Dollars
80.5m, and reported that orders booked during the <DATE>last three months of 1991</DATE>
were the heaviest for five years. The market loved it, and the shares
bounced from Dollars 5 1/2 at the start of the week to Dollars 7 1/2 at the
end, a handsome 36 per cent gain.
 --------------------------
<DATE>Monday</DATE>     3254.03 - <DATE>10.95
Tuesday</DATE>    3223.39 - 30.64
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>  3255.50 + 32.42
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>   3226.74 - 29.07
<DATE>Friday</DATE>     3232.78 +  6.04
 --------------------------
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
Weekend Page 2 Graph (Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900503-0213 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-03-90 0912EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-Dryer Adv04   05-03 0774</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Dryer, Adv 04,0795</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv04</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release PM Friday, May 4, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>NBC's `Hunter' an Ex-Reporter, Sort Of</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Stepfanie in 9th graf is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's not widely known, but <PERSON>Fred Dryer</PERSON> played a
hard-boiled sports reporter before he became the hard-eyed
constable of <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Hunter.'' The occasion: a Superbowl press
conference in <DATE>January 1975</DATE>.
   He and <PERSON>Lance Rentzel</PERSON> wore battered fedoras with hatbrim cards
that said PRESS. They technically were employed by the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles
Rams</ORGANIZATION> then. But they had press credentials secured by <PERSON>Dick Schaap</PERSON>,
then a magazine sports editor.
   In their non-Rams capacity as newshawks, Dryer recalls, they
asked such probing questions as: ``They say this is the Big Game
and there's no tomorrow. Will you in fact be disappointed when the
sun comes up tomorrow?''
   For some reason, this caused grumbling from scribes who took pro
football as almost seriously as TV does. Most, however, realized a
put-on was under way. Not so some <ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION>
functionaries.
   ``They went crazy,'' <PERSON>Dryer</PERSON> said with slight grin. In due course,
he said, then-NFL Commissioner <PERSON>Pete Rozelle</PERSON> made inquiries: ``He
said, `I understand you guys are reporters. What are you doing?'
   ``I said, `Well, we're here to cover the news and print the .. .
unmentioned. There's a lot of smut that needs to be punched up, and
we're just the two guys to do it.'''
   The light dawned. Rozelle realized it was a spoof. The
Superbowl, in which the Rams weren't playing, came and went.
   Six years later, so did Dryer, at least from pro ball after 13
seasons as a defensive tackle for the Rams and <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION>.
Although he knew that party had to end sometime, he hadn't
particularly thought what he'd do after football until <DATE>1978</DATE>, he
said.
   Then, after considering and rejecting life in real estate, he
began considering the acting business, then studied it for five
years with actress <PERSON>Nina Foch</PERSON>.
   ``I had to find out what it was, how interested I was in it, and
most important, could I make a living at it,'' he says.
   Small roles here and there followed, including four ``Cheers''
episodes as <PERSON>Ted Danson</PERSON>'s old pal from baseball days. Then he read
for ``Hunter,'' which some critics would later sneer at as a
small-screen edition of ``Dirty Harry.''
   Similar sneers greeted his first venture into feature films, a
modern Marine shoot-'em-up called ``Death Before Dishonor,'' two
years ago. It proved dead on arrival at the box office, for which
<ORGANIZATION>Dryer</ORGANIZATION> blames the producers.
   But ``Hunter'' has lasted six seasons with Dryer as its lean,
blue-jeaned star. <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> has found it a durable <DATE>Saturday</DATE> series.
   The network, which in mid-April shifted ``Hunter'' to <DATE>Mondays</DATE>,
says a seventh season is likely. If so, <PERSON>Dryer</PERSON>, who says it already
has been renewed, will start anew with a new female partner.
   <PERSON>Stepfanie Kramer</PERSON> is giving up her role as <PERSON>Hunter</PERSON>'s sidekick,
Sgt. <PERSON>Dee Dee McCall</PERSON>, for films and singing. Her swan song, so to
speak, will occur in <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s episode when she marries an old flame.
   Dryer, who at 6-foot-6 is the tallest of TV's cops, pondered a
visitor's theory. It had nothing to do with <PERSON>Kramer</PERSON>'s departure.
   The theory was that pro football players-turned-actors seem to
be more successful and tend to have longer runs in network series
if they've played on the defensive line.
   Two examples: <PERSON>Merlin Olsen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Alex Karras</PERSON>. The former piled up
more than seven years in <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Little House on the Prairie,''
``Father Murphy'' and the short-lived `Aaron's Way.'' Karras had
four <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> years in ``<PERSON>Webster</PERSON>.''
   True, former running back <PERSON>Ed Marinaro</PERSON> had five seasons as a
co-star of ``Hill Street Blues.'' But the much better-known
quarterback, <PERSON>Joe Namath</PERSON>, lasted only one month as the star of <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s
``The Waverly Wonders.''
   Dryer thought about all this. His eyes took on an evil glint.
``Well,'' he said, ``I think the true intelligence is in defense.''
   __
   Elsewhere in television:
   ANOTHER REASON TO CONTINUE LIVING: An <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> movie based on the
``Archie'' cartoon strip, will be shown <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. In it, <PERSON>Archie</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Veronica</PERSON>, Jughead and <PERSON>Betty</PERSON> now are thirtysomething and coping with
adult problems like divorce, careers and single parenthood.
   BERGENS EVERYWHERE: <PERSON>Frances Bergen</PERSON>, mother of the star of <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>'
``<PERSON>Murphy Brown</PERSON>,'' will be the guest star of the show's <DATE>May 21</DATE>
episode, in which Corky (Faith Ford) gets married. <PERSON>Mrs. Bergen</PERSON>, who
plays the groom's mother, probably will be watching the <DATE>May 19</DATE>
edition of <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s ``<DATE>Saturday</DATE> Night Live'' with great interest.
<PERSON>Candace Bergen</PERSON> will be the show's host.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance PM Fri May 4</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06184167 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06184167 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  Fifteen tons of sand doesn't make a beach. But the 18 groups that showed up
for the Sand Castles and Other Architectural Marvels Contest in Palo Alto knew
how to fake it. They pretended that the plaza in front of City Hall was
Malibu.;    Never mind that nature didn't cooperate. It drizzled on and off
Friday. Event organizers had contemplated cancellation earlier in the day.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ADULTS MAKE SAND CASTLES SERIOUS FUN  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Today on the Peninsula  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <ORGANIZATION>First Wimbledon</ORGANIZATION>, and now this. But the sky just pouted and never cried, so
the third-annual contest continued.;    The mondo speakers didn't blast the
Beach Boys or Jan and Dean. Instead, the <ORGANIZATION>Cowboy Junkies</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Elvis Costello</PERSON>
serenaded contestants. But they seemed oblivious to the music. Sand-castle
building is serious business. Many design firms and architectural companies
entered. Some even brought blue prints for their creations. It was not exactly
kid stuff here.;    The kids were restricted to a couple of "community
sandboxes," where they seemed to have a heap more fun than the adults.;    The
adults were too busy to notice such trivial things as fun. They built
pyramids, Mayan temples, castles and dragons. One of the winners, Scale Models
Unlimited, built an elaborate zoo with caverns. Another group built a giant
hand holding a pencil. Another built a giant sandwich -- it looked yummy,
too.;    The most eloquent piece, undoubtedly, was <PERSON>Sam Smidt</PERSON>'s Res Ipsa
Loquitur -- "The Thing Speaks for Itself." It depicted a football field, where
toy soldiers stood in a football formation. When designer <PERSON>Sam Smidt</PERSON> heard
about the sand castle contest, he thought, "Geez, this is really an
opportunity to make a social statement.";    He had heard from a friend that
more people watched the gulf war than the <LOCATION>Superbowl</LOCATION>. Thus, the inspiration for
the anti-war sand sculpture. Perhaps the piece, which won the greatest
architectural marvel award, will inspire more "statement" sand castles next
year.;    After the contest, the clean up was no fun. It took the city crew
most of the weekend to shovel the sand onto a tractor, said organizer <PERSON>Susan
Churcher</PERSON>. Then workers had to sweep the remaining grains off the plaza. The
drought prohibited the crew from using water to wash away the sand.;  MOVIE
MAGIC: The movies are one of the best ways to escape these hot days. One of
the best movie houses is the <ORGANIZATION>Stanford Theatre</ORGANIZATION>, where "Holiday" and "Bringing
Up Baby" are showing. <PERSON>Cary Grant</PERSON> and <PERSON>Katharine Hepburn</PERSON>. No need to say more.
The movies are shown at the <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION> movie palace through tomorrow.; GREEN NO
MORE: <PERSON>Naturalist Luis Tam</PERSON> has gone to the forests of <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, and he's
brought back a bunch of slides. He will show the beautiful landscapes of the
southeastern African island, its animals, and the fragile remains of its rain
forests noon to <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>July 17</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Peninsula Conservation Center</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>2448</DATE>
<ORGANIZATION>Watson Ct.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. For details, call (415) 494-9301.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  De Tran column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910702  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  484  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday July 2, 1991
00184167,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110290-0177 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 302021 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 2, 1990, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 29; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
761 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PENDRAGONS ESCAPE WITH 'BEST ILLUSIONISTS' AWARD; 
</P>
<P>
MAGIC: THE COUPLE ARE ELATED THAT JUDGES CHOSE THEM OVER DAVID COPPERFIELD. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARK CHALON SMITH, SPECIAL TO THE TIMES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Pendragons are more than familiar with <PERSON>David Copperfield</PERSON>. As magic's top 
gun, <PERSON>Copperfield</PERSON> is the guy who fills arenas, does TV specials and is known for 
splashy, sometimes schmaltzy and almost always amazing tricks. 
</P>
<P>
Other illusionists routinely face performing in his shadow, including the 
Pendragons. But <PERSON>Jonathan</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, the former UC <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> students turned 
husband-and-wife magic team, found more of the spotlight recently when they 
were named Best Illusionists in the <ORGANIZATION>International Magic Awards</ORGANIZATION> -- over 
<LOCATION>Copperfield</LOCATION> and several other performers. 
</P>
<P>
"We beat him!" <PERSON>Jonathan Pendragon</PERSON> said during a telephone interview from <LOCATION>Las 
Vegas</LOCATION>, where the couple were performing at the Aladdin hotel and casino. "I was 
excited, it's kind of amazing -- sort of like <PERSON>David</PERSON> and Goliath or <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> and the 
Giant Killer. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>David</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Copperfield</ORGANIZATION>) is visual and spectacular, but I think (the judges) were 
more interested in tradition. We like to keep it more straight, less 
sensational. The contest reflected, I think, more of a purist attitude." 
</P>
<P>
The two-hour-long competition, with categories including entertainers of the 
year (won by <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> regulars Siegfried and Roy), best close-up performer, 
comedy magician, escape artist and technical magician (<ORGANIZATION>Copperfield</ORGANIZATION> did win this 
one), is scheduled to air <DATE>Monday</DATE> at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> on <ORGANIZATION>KTTV Channel 11</ORGANIZATION>. Winning 
routines, including the <PERSON>Pendragons</PERSON>' "Interlude" and "Metamorphosis," will be 
shown. 
</P>
<P>
Although reluctant to describe the illusions specifically, <ORGANIZATION>Pendragon</ORGANIZATION> said that 
<LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> "appears to come through my chest" in "Interlude," while 
"Metamorphosis" involves "a rapid escape." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Pendragon</ORGANIZATION> pointed out that both feats are typical of their approach, which 
involves a physical style utilizing his gymnastic and diving training (he's 
competed on the college level) and <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>'s experience as a dancer, gymnast 
and body builder (she was runner-up in the <DATE>1982</DATE> Body Building Superbowl 
contest). 
</P>
<P>
They avoid the gaudy costumes ("We hate rhinestones," he said) and the more 
traditional tuxedo garb ("It's too restrictive for the way we perform") favored 
by most magicians. Instead, they rely on scant, monotone outfits that allow 
movement and emphasize their physiques. 
</P>
<P>
Agility and quickness are integral to the act, which features levitations, 
disappearances and escapes, a <ORGANIZATION>Pendragon</ORGANIZATION> trademark. He said they hold the record 
for an escape from a locked trunk popularized by <PERSON>Harry Houdini</PERSON>, who did it in 
seven seconds. <ORGANIZATION>Pendragon</ORGANIZATION> does it in three. 
</P>
<P>
"There's drama in that because everyone is usually amazed when we accomplish it 
so soon. We combine our physical presence with an acting presence to create a 
style that adds to the illusions. 
</P>
<P>
"Besides, the rapidity is not purely for the sake of speed . . . a real 
magician would not stall; he would simply wave his hand and the magic would 
happen. As an actor, I try to make my magic look as real as possible." 
</P>
<P>
The Pendragons met in the late '70s while attending <ORGANIZATION>UCI</ORGANIZATION>, where <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> was 
studying dance, among other things, and <PERSON>Jonathan</PERSON> pursued drama. He was also 
performing solo in local and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> clubs as a magician, when not 
moonlighting as a Hollywood stuntman (he's doubled for <PERSON>Burgess Meredith</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>John Belushi</PERSON>, among others). <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, too, was a double, having appeared on 
"Charlie's Angels" and "Quincy, <LOCATION>M.E.</LOCATION>" They started dating, and eventually he 
asked her to take part in his act. 
</P>
<P>
At first, they offered the basics, using "manipulation and other standard 
tricks" but soon turned to a more physical style to set them apart. He also 
wanted to make <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> more than a pretty assistant and began building a 
routine around their equal partnership. 
</P>
<P>
They progressed rapidly. Although they haven't achieved the household fame of 
<ORGANIZATION>Copperfield</ORGANIZATION> and, before him, <PERSON>Doug Henning</PERSON>, the Pendragons are reasonably 
well-known among magic fans. Their work in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>, the acknowledged mecca 
for working magicians, the past few years and various appearances on television 
underscores that. 
</P>
<P>
In talking about magic, <ORGANIZATION>Pendragon</ORGANIZATION> is apt to get a little philosophical, 
referring to its "preternatural" beauty and ability to be "intellectually 
puzzling." Artistry and sound technique add up to good magic, which comes down 
to "telling a story and tapping into the kid in us." 
</P>
<P>
After a pause, he added that the best illusion "when performed expertly and 
with imagination can instill those lost feelings of youth and wonder that are 
rare and thrilling." 
</P>
<P>
 "The International Magic Awards," featuring the Pendragons, is scheduled to 
air <DATE>Monday</DATE> at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> on <ORGANIZATION>KTTV Channel 11</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P><P></P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Award-winning illusionists Jonathan and Charlotte Pendragon. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PENDRAGON, JONATHAN; PENDRAGON, CHARLOTTE; MAGICIANS; AWARDS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-10398</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DEIATAEJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930508
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 MAY 93 / Sport: New York's hard-nosed heroes - Basketball
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PATRICK HARVERSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
RECENT <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Knicks' basketball games at <ORGANIZATION>Madison Square Garden</ORGANIZATION> have been
a bit like a night at the <LOCATION>Oscars</LOCATION>, so hungry has Hollywood-on-the-Hudson been
to associate itself with the best sports story in town.
In recent weeks, <PERSON>Jack</PERSON>, Dusty, <LOCATION>Woody</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Spike</PERSON> and <PERSON>Arnold</PERSON> have all been there,
tasting the special atmosphere that <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> generates every time it looks
as if one of the city's teams is on the verge of greatness. When the
baseball Mets won the World Series in <DATE>1986</DATE>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> went berserk, as it did
the last time the Knicks won a championship, in <DATE>1973</DATE>.
Yet since the mid-1980s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> sports fans have had little to cheer. The
football Giants won the SuperBowl in <DATE>1991</DATE>, but the title was earned against
the backdrop of the Gulf War, so celebrations were muted.
This year, however, the Knicks have captured the city's imagination. In the
regular season they won 60 of their 82 games, ending with the second best
record in the 27-team <ORGANIZATION>National Basketball Association</ORGANIZATION>.
To success-starved <LOCATION>New Yorkers</LOCATION>, the Knicks' performance has been especially
gratifying because it was only two years ago that the team seemed mired in
mediocrity.
In <DATE>1991</DATE> they scraped into the playoffs, only to go out at the first attempt
to the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bulls</ORGANIZATION> in three straight games. That poor effort disgusted the
fans and the local media. The season ended in complete disarray. The coach
lacked the support of his team and the <PERSON>Knicks</PERSON>' only star, <PERSON>Patrick Ewing</PERSON>,
wanted to escape <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
Yet, just <DATE>two years later</DATE>, the Knicks are fancied to reach the play-off
finals. They have beaten the <ORGANIZATION>Indiana Pacers</ORGANIZATION> in the first round and start
their second-round series against the <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> Hornets tomorrow.
Much of the credit for the Knicks' renaissance must go to <PERSON>Pat Riley</PERSON>, the
team's coach. In the <DATE>1980s</DATE> <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> coached the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Lakers</LOCATION> to five <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>
titles, but when he joined the Knicks at the start of the <DATE>1991-92</DATE> season
there were many who still believed he had not proved himself.
Critics argued that the Lakers were so good that it did not matter who
coached them. They said that a team led by legends like <PERSON>Kareem Abdul Jabbar</PERSON>
and Earvin 'Magic' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> would have won five championships if they had
been coached by <PERSON>Michael Jackson</PERSON>. In the Knicks, <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> saw an opportunity to
win the respect that was denied him in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
Today, <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> has triumphed, and with a team that could not be more different
to his title-winners of the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. The Lakers dominated through deft
ball-handling and passing, and swift counter-attacks. They were adored by
their fans in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, who liked to think that the team played the game
the way they lived - creative, fast and loose.
The Knicks' have won the hearts of their city because their approach meshes
closely with <ORGANIZATION>New Yorkers</ORGANIZATION>' image of themselves - hardworking, tough and
uncompromising.
Above all, the <ORGANIZATION>Knicks</ORGANIZATION>' game is built around big men, aggressive defending,
and an intimidating attitude that occasionally borders on thuggery.
Their bruising style has made the Knicks the most feared team in the league,
and hugely popular in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. It is not surprising that the fans'
favourites this year have been <PERSON>Anthony Mason</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Starks</PERSON>, two ferocious
competitors whose intensely physical play causes havoc when they defend, and
creates scoring opportunities when the ball moves up court.
The dark side of streetfighters like <PERSON>Mason</PERSON> and <PERSON>Starks</PERSON> sometimes surfaces.
The Knicks' have a poor disciplinary record. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <PERSON>Starks</PERSON> was thrown
out of a play-off game for head-butting <PERSON>Reggie Miller</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Pacers</ORGANIZATION>.
The other <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> weapons include the dominant presence under the basket
and the accurate shooting (especially under pressure) of <PERSON>Ewing</PERSON>, the canny
generalship of point guard <PERSON>Doc Rivers</PERSON> and the strongest substitutes' bench
in the <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION>. Add <PERSON>Riley</PERSON>'s long experience of post-season play, and the Knicks
look as if they have the ingredients for a championship.
Yet, over such a long haul - the playoffs do not end until <DATE>June</DATE> and the
final three rounds involve a best-of-seven series - it may come down to
which team is hungriest for the title.
After consecutive championships, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s appetite may be sated. The best
teams in the western division - <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> - have the talent, but
there are doubts over their willingness to mix it up with the toughest teams
from the east.
Furthermore, the Knicks are desperate to win. Ewing, who has won national
college championships and Olympic gold, has said he will not feel fulfilled
until he wins an <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> title. Veterans such as <PERSON>Rolando Blackman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rivers</PERSON>
know this may be their last shot at glory, and <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> wants to prove he can
win it all with a team other than the <ORGANIZATION>Lakers</ORGANIZATION>.
As for <PERSON>Mason</PERSON> and <PERSON>Starks</PERSON>, they have reached the top the hard way - via the
basketball wilderness of semi-professional leagues, obscure European
leagues, and no-hope 10-day contracts with losing NBA teams. As <PERSON>Starks</PERSON> said
recently: 'Remember, I wasn't supposed to be in the pros. But once I got a
taste, I knew it was just a matter of time.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7941 Sports Clubs, Managers, and Promoters.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page IX
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900129-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-29-90 1625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush-Grumpy     01-29 0207</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Grumpy,200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Is Grumpy; Ate Too Much Barbecue</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``I'm in a grumpy mood <DATE>today</DATE>,'' President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
groused <DATE>Monday</DATE>, complaining he had eaten too much <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> barbecue at
a Superbowl party.
   ``No answers today. I'm trying to think of answers and (I'm
getting) too many questions,'' he said as reporters asked him about
the <MONEY>$1.23 trillion</MONEY> budget plan he unveiled for the fiscal year
beginning <DATE>Oct. 1</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> talked about his bad mood during a picture-taking ceremony
in the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> with visiting British Foreign Secretary <PERSON>Douglas
Hurd</PERSON>.
   Brushing off the press as he normally does at photo
opportunities, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said, ``I ate too much yesterday and I just
don't feel like answering any questions. And besides that, it
violates the groundrules to answer any questions.''
   He allowed as how he sometimes does answer, but ``only when we
want to answer questions.''
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and his wife <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON> had about a dozen people in <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to
watch the <LOCATION>Superbowl</LOCATION>, and served barbecue from Ft. Worth.
   While saying he had overindulged, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> quickly added, ``I don't
want to get any rumors started about my physical condition.
   ``I'm just grumpy. I don't want to talk about it.
   ``It was good,'' he concluded, talking about the food.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891109-0262 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-89 0140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-AdAwards Bjt   11-09 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ad Awards, Bjt,0627</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ad Club Picks Federal Express ``Fast-Talker'' Ad As Best of '80s</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express Co.</ORGANIZATION> commercial that featured
an incredibly fast-talking businessman was the best advertisement
of the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, according to a survey of the board of the ad trade
group The One Club.
   The Orwellian ``<DATE>1984</DATE>'' commercial for <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and a
series of Rolling Stone magazine print ads noting the differences
between some perceptions about its readers and reality also were
ranked among the best ads of the decade, the group said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Ads for <PERSON>Levi Strauss</PERSON>' jeans, <ORGANIZATION>Nike</ORGANIZATION> shoes, the wine coolers
<ORGANIZATION>Bartles &amp; Jaymes</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Cooler and <PERSON>Miller Lite</PERSON> beer also
made the list.
   The One Club, an association of advertising copywriters and art
directors, developed its ranking based on responses to surveys in
which each of its 13 directors was asked to rank personal favorites
from the past decade.
   None of the directors' ad agencies placed an ad on the decade's
best list.
   Of the 12 best ads, 10 involved television commercials, one was
a print campaign and one used billboards.
   <PERSON>Mike Hughes</PERSON>, vice chairman and creative director of <ORGANIZATION>The Martin
Agency of Richmond</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, said the directors generally were trying
to identify ads that broke from convention and spawned imitators of
their own.
   But he said <DATE>1985</DATE> commercials for <PERSON>Levi</PERSON>'s 501 jeans, which showed
young people in urban settings cast in a blue-shaded hue, had a
style copied widely. ``A lot of commercials became blue,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> said the top-rated ``Fast Talker'' ad from <ORGANIZATION>Federal
Express</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1982</DATE> brought activity to a halt in many households each
time the commercial aired.
   A separate <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION> campaign from <DATE>1980</DATE> that showed top
executives anxious to get a package delivered picking up the phone
and saying ``Hello-o-o Federal'' broke the ad taboo of ``Never make
the customer look silly,'' <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> said.
   Apple's ``<DATE>1984</DATE>'' ad showed a dreary scene of prisoners filing in
for a televised address by a dogmatic leader. The gloom was
shattered when a woman tossed a club that broke the screen. The ad
ran only once _ during the telecast of the <DATE>1984</DATE> Superbowl football
game _ but <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> said no other ad has had more impact on one
airing.
   Authorship of a memorable ad in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> did not necessarily
mean an ad agency kept the assignment. Ally <ORGANIZATION>&amp; Gargano</ORGANIZATION>, which made
the two winning <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION> ads, is no longer the <ORGANIZATION>Federal
Express</ORGANIZATION> agency, and <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> has dropped Chiat-Day, which made
``<DATE>1984</DATE>,'' as its agency.
   But Chiat-Day offices, now known as Chiat-Day-Mojo, were
responsible for five of the 12 best ads, according to the <ORGANIZATION>One Club</ORGANIZATION>
survey.
   Here is the list of best ads of the decade, the year and the
agency responsible for them, according to The One Club:
   1. <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION>, ``Fast-Talker,'' <DATE>1982</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Ally &amp; Gargano</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>.
   2. Apple Computer, ``<DATE>1984</DATE>,'' <DATE>1984</DATE>, <LOCATION>Chiat-Day</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>
   3. Rolling Stone magazine, ``Perception-Reality Campaign,''
<DATE>1986</DATE>, <PERSON>Fallon McElligott</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>.
   4. <ORGANIZATION>Nynex</ORGANIZATION>, ``Dumbwaiters, Rock Drills, Furniture Stripping,''
<DATE>1988</DATE>, <LOCATION>Chiat-Day</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   5. <ORGANIZATION>Bartles &amp; Jaymes</ORGANIZATION>, introductory TV campaign, <DATE>1986</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Hal Riney &amp;
Partners</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   6. <PERSON>Levi Strauss</PERSON>, ``Gang, Blues Singer, Street Singer,'' <DATE>1985</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Foote Cone Belding</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   7. <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION>, ``Hello-o-o Federal,'' <DATE>1980</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Ally &amp; Gargano</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   8. <ORGANIZATION>Nike</ORGANIZATION>, billboard campaign, <DATE>1984</DATE>, <LOCATION>Chiat-Day</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   9. (tie) <ORGANIZATION>Nike</ORGANIZATION>, ``I Love <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION>,'' <DATE>1985</DATE>, <LOCATION>Chiat-Day</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Cooler, introductory TV campaign, <DATE>1987</DATE>, <LOCATION>Chiat-Day</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>; and <PERSON>Miller Lite</PERSON>, ``Butkus, <PERSON>Uecker</PERSON>, <PERSON>Powell</PERSON>,'' <DATE>1984</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Backer &amp; Spielvogel</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   10. Wendy's, ``Where's the Beef,'' <DATE>1984</DATE>,
Dancer-Fitzgerald-Sample, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881220-0215 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-88 0039EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-3-DAds Bjt   12-20 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-3-D Ads, Bjt,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>SuperBowl Halftime Show, Diet Coke Ad to Be Broadcast in 3-D</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola Co.</ORGANIZATION> has been stuck with 20 million
pairs of 3-D glasses ever since the last episode of ``Moonlighting''
was nixed last <DATE>spring</DATE> by the writers' strike. It says it just found
a super way to use them.
   The soft drink giant, the <ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>
announced <DATE>Monday</DATE> they would cooperate in a three-dimensional
broadcast of the 12-minute Super Bowl XXIII halftime show and a
45-second <ORGANIZATION>Diet Coke</ORGANIZATION> ad next month.
   The Atlanta-based company said its bottlers would distribute the
special glasses, which will enable fans to see the 3-D approach,
with purchases of <ORGANIZATION>Diet Coke</ORGANIZATION> in the two weeks before the <DATE>Jan. 22</DATE>
contest for the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> championship.
   Coca-Cola ordered the glasses earlier this year after agreeing
with the ``Moonlighting'' producers that a commercial and a portion
of the final show of the 1987-88 season would be shot with the new
3-D technology.
   But the episode was canceled after the writers went on strike and
the <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION> commercial never was made. Production of the glasses
was halted at 20 million and they were stored while <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION> looked
for other TV showcases.
   Network executives said the halftime program would be the first
live 3-D broadcast on network television, and would continue <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s
tradition of innovation in football coverage. <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> broadcast a
``silent minute'' to give viewers a break from the Super Bowl
pre-game show in <DATE>1986</DATE> and aired an entire regular season game with
no announcers a few years ago.
   Viewers will need the glasses to get the 3-D effect, but a new
technology called Nuoptix 3-D, developed by <PERSON>Terry Beard</PERSON>, founder and
head of the <ORGANIZATION>Los-Angeles-based Nuoptix Associates Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, leaves the
picture normal for others.
   The patented process avoids the distortion or double-imaging of
the picture that the 3-D processes of the <DATE>1950s</DATE> caused for those
without special glasses.
   Not content to let a volley sound in the cola wars without
responding, <ORGANIZATION>Pepsi-Cola Co.</ORGANIZATION> announced separately <DATE>Monday</DATE> that its Diet
<ORGANIZATION>Pepsi</ORGANIZATION> brand has agreed to be the official sponsor of <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>
player talent show to be broadcast before the big game. The talent
show will match <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> players in competition as singers, dancers and
comedians.
   Calling the announcement ``a surprise move,'' <ORGANIZATION>Pepsi</ORGANIZATION>'s executive
vice president of marketing and sales, <PERSON>Michael Lorelli</PERSON>, said ``Diet
<ORGANIZATION>Pepsi</ORGANIZATION>'s end-run on <ORGANIZATION>Diet Coke</ORGANIZATION> just signaled the start of an intense
off-the-field battle.''
   Asked about <ORGANIZATION>Pepsi</ORGANIZATION>'s announcement at the news conference where he
announced the deal with <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>NBC Sports</ORGANIZATION> executive producer
<PERSON>Michael Weisman</PERSON> said the network had not settled sponsorship of the
pre-game talent show.
   But a <ORGANIZATION>Pepsi</ORGANIZATION> spokesman, <PERSON>Tod MacKenize</PERSON>, insisted that <ORGANIZATION>Pepsi-Cola</ORGANIZATION>
had returned a signed contract to <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>last week</DATE> and that the deal
was done.
   Coca-Cola, based in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Pepsi-Cola</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Somers</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, dominate the <MONEY>$43.2 billion</MONEY> <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> soft drink business.
   Diet <ORGANIZATION>Coke</ORGANIZATION> is the best-selling diet soft drink and the third
biggest seller overall with about <PERCENT>8.2 percent</PERCENT> of the overall soft
drink market. Diet <ORGANIZATION>Pepsi</ORGANIZATION> ranks second in the category and fourth
overall at <PERCENT>5.2 percent</PERCENT>.
   The two soft drink giants are always on the lookout for splashy
new ways to boost anticipation of their commercials and get big
audiences for them.
   <PERSON>Michael Beindorff</PERSON>, vice president for advertising at <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION>,
said he had been aproached with dozens of opportunities to showcase
a 3-D commercial, but rejected them until the Super Bowl opportunity
came along.
   ``This is not just a few minutes or a couple of special
effects,'' <PERSON>Beindorff</PERSON> said. ``It's not just pre-game fluff or a
post-game throwaway.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900706-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-06-90 0942EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-TchaikovskyCompetition 1stLd-Writehru a0471 07-06 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tchaikovsky Competition, 1st Ld-Writehru, a0471,0360</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Vocalist Wins Tchaikovsky Gold Medal</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 3 grafs to CORRECT that not first time for cello
and vocals. Pickup 4th, `Alyssa Park...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American vocalists <PERSON>Deborah Voigt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hans Choi</PERSON>
today won top honors in the ninth international Tchaikovsky musical
competition.
   Akiko Suwanai of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> took first place in the violin section of
the contest, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Gustav Rivinius</PERSON> won the gold medal for
cello, and Soviet <PERSON>Boris Berezovski</PERSON> took first place for piano,
contest officials said.
   The Tchaikovsky competition has been held every four years since
<DATE>1958</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Alyssa Park</PERSON>, a 16-year-old violinist from <LOCATION>Lexington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>, came
in third and received three medals, for third place, for most
talented performer and for most artistic performer.
   ``I was very honored, but also very puzzled,'' she said later,
noting the international jury awarded her medals for most artistic
and most talented, but then only gave her third place.
   She admitted feeling some tension. ``But I just tried to treat
it as a concert and play,'' she said.
   Ten Americans were among the 48 finalists competing for gold
medals <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   ``This is the superbowl of musical competition,'' said <PERSON>Daniel
Pollack</PERSON>, a competitor in the piano competion in <DATE>1958</DATE> and now a jury
member.
   <PERSON>Ms. Voigt</PERSON>, 29, a former apprentice with the <ORGANIZATION>San Francisco Opera
Company</ORGANIZATION>, won the gold medal for best female vocalist. She lives in
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Before the contest, <PERSON>Ms. Voigt</PERSON> said she wanted to win because the
Tchaikovsky competition is the best known in the world and can give
a singing career an immediate boost.
   ``The amount of publicity a singer can get here is more than I
could pay.''
   Choi, a former student at the La Scala opera company of <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, got the gold medal for male vocalist. He has lived in the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> for two years and currently resides in <LOCATION>Flushing</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   During the competition, he said the biggest problem was
language. ``I must sing in six languages, and I must sing perfectly
in six languanges, because the judges come from so many countries.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06027116 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06027116 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; CHAMPIONSHIP; GAME; FORECAST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  BUFFALO, N.Y. It's a dateline. It's a football game. No, it's SuperBowl, and
that means I have to make a prediction.;    I hate making predictions. But I
like the Giants.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TAKE GIANTS OUTRIGHT  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     I like the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> to win Super Bowl XXV over the <LOCATION>Buffalo Bills</LOCATION>. Take the
points -- the Giants are getting seven -- but you won't need them, and neither
will the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>. They'll win outright.;    The perspective on this matchup has
been severely skewed by <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>'s 51-3 rout of the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Raiders</ORGANIZATION> last
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Oh, it was impressive. So was the Bills' 44-34 beating of <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> <DATE>a week
earlier</DATE>. In two playoff games, the Bills have 95 points and nearly 1,000 yards
in offense.;    But today, the Bills aren't playing in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>. They aren't
playing a warm-weather team in a cold, windy stadium. They are playing against
a defense the likes of which they have not seen, except for once. On <DATE>Dec. 15</DATE>,
the Bills played the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> and beat them 17-13.;    "THAT was our worst
game," Giants safety <PERSON>Dave Duerson</PERSON> said last week. It was a statement, not an
excuse.;    "We stunk," said Coach Bill Parcells.;    <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>
stunk in two areas, specifically: short-yardage offense, and tackling. Indeed,
videotape shows 11 missed tackles by the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>, resulting in 153 additional
yards for the Bills.;    It would be dangerous to put too much emphasis on
that <DATE>Dec. 15</DATE> game. A lot has changed in six weeks. Buffalo quarterback <PERSON>Jim
Kelly</PERSON>, injured in that game, has returned. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> quarterback <PERSON>Phil Simms</PERSON>,
also injured that day, has not. But <PERSON>Jeff Hostetler</PERSON> has shown heart and
ability, and whatever the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> lose by not having <PERSON>Simms</PERSON> -- if they lose
anything at all -- is offset by two more differences from the <DATE>Dec. 15</DATE>
meeting:;    First, this game will be played on grass, where the Bills are 2-5
the last two seasons.;    Second, this is the Super Bowl, where no Bills
player has ever been. Granted, the hype has been extraordinarily small. Cut in
half by the schedule and reduced further by events in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, this
might be the least-hyped Super Bowl in the <DATE>last 20 years.</DATE>;    But when the
players step on the field today, they'll know where they are and they'll feel
the height of the stakes. The Giants have been here before -- 25 of them,
including Parcells.;    To many of the "experts" at the Super Bowl, <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON>
is the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>' only chance. I don't know. Ever since that night at <LOCATION>Candlestick
Park</LOCATION>, when <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> went for broke on fourth-and-goal from the 9, I've
wondered about the genius tag he wears.;    But <PERSON>Marv Levy</PERSON> is in a panic, they
say. He's tight. As evidence, they cite his decision to change hotels in
<LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>. Heck, that wasn't panic; that was a great move. You don't come to the
Super Bowl to stay at a Holiday Inn.;    Levy has done a tremendous job. The
Bickering Bills are now the Super Bowl Bills. They've got the no-huddle
offense. They've got the league's most-balanced offense. They've got <PERSON>Thurman
Thomas</PERSON>, a great running back. They've got <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>, a fine quarterback.;    But,
in football, good hitting beats good pitching.;    <ORGANIZATION>The Giants</ORGANIZATION>' defense is No.
1 in fewest points allowed, No. 2 in yards allowed, No. 4 against the run and
No. 6 against the pass. Only one back has rushed for more than 100 yards
against the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>, and it wasn't Thurman Thomas. (<LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> rookie <PERSON>Johnny
Johnson</PERSON> ran for 108; <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> had 60 yards -- in 21 carries -- in the <DATE>Dec. 15</DATE>
game.);    The Giants are tough, and they're smart. They've got a plan to
counteract the no-huddle offense. They've also got <PERSON>Lawrence Taylor</PERSON>. He can
still dominate a game, and you might see that today. He sees this as possibly
his last Super Bowl. He is a man possessed.;    And, of course, the Bills
can't score if they don't have the ball. Against the 49ers <DATE>last Sunday</DATE>, the
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> offense controlled the ball for almost 40 minutes. It was a 40-20
split the week before against <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, too.;    There's no reason to think the
<ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> can't do that against the Bills. They already have, in fact; the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>
controlled the ball for 37 minutes, 59 seconds of that <DATE>Dec. 15</DATE> game. The Bills
rank 15th against the run.;    If this game comes down to a field goal, who do
you like: <PERSON>Matt Bahr</PERSON> or <PERSON>Scott Norwood</PERSON>? If it's a punting contest, you've got to
like the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>' <PERSON>Sean Landeta.</PERSON>;    See, you can find a dozen reasons to like
the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>. But you need only one, really, and it's the one I woke up with
<DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>: These guys stopped <LOCATION>Joe Montana</LOCATION> twice. That's enough for me.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Bud Geracie column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Tampa, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910127  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  796  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday January 27, 1991
00027116,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011689-0098 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 6273 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 16, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 10; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1206 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NOTES; 
</P>
<P>
CINCINNATI NOT GETTING CREDIT IT DESERVES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BOB OATES, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MIAMI 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
One of the chief differences so far between this and other recent Super Bowl 
weeks is the widespread lack of support for the <ORGANIZATION>American Football Conference</ORGANIZATION> 
entry here next <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Cincinnati Bengals</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Everybody I've read or run into is picking the (<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>) 49ers," <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> 
Cowboys President <PERSON>Tex Schramm</PERSON> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
"I've never seen such unanimity despite the fact that <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> has a better 
shot, in my opinion, than a lot of other (<DATE>1980s</DATE>) AFC teams." 
</P>
<P>
Unlike the last 4 winters, when quarterbacks such as <PERSON>John Elway</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dan Marino</PERSON> 
appeared to give AFC teams a solid chance, <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Boomer Esiason</PERSON> and the 
Bengals' 15th-ranked defense don't seem -- in the view of most observers -- to 
be a match for <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON> and the third-ranked 49er defense. 
</P>
<P>
"I'll give you one prediction," <PERSON>Schramm</PERSON> said. "If the 49ers agree (with the 
majority view), they'll lose. This is a game of the mind. Nobody's invincible 
if you think you are. 
</P>
<P>
The Bengals, first to arrive for the 23rd renewal of the series, began workouts 
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> afternoon at the <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> Dolphins practice facility, which will be their 
home away from a freezing home this week. 
</P>
<P>
Coach <PERSON>Sam Wyche</PERSON>, who closed the practice to the public, reported no new 
injuries or illness. 
</P>
<P>
Coach <PERSON>Bill Walsh</PERSON> acknowledged <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that he has thought about stepping down as 
49er coach next season, but said he will remain with the team no matter what he 
decides. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm going to remain with the 49ers, quite possibly in the same capacity," 
<PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> said, shortly after arriving with the team in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"When you coach 30 years, you have to look pretty seriously at your life and 
career. But there are other times when you say, 'I can't give it up. It's what 
I do.' " 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> said he would decide soon after the Super Bowl whether to stay as coach 
or move to an executive capacity. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Eddie DeBartolo</PERSON>, the 49er owner, surprised <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> and team by acting as the 
hotel doorman when they arrived in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I didn't realize it was him. I didn't have time to tip him," said <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON>, whose 
team will begin practice at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Miami</ORGANIZATION> today. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wayne Sevier</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Chargers</ORGANIZATION> assistant who coached in this game with the 
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Redskins in <DATE>1983</DATE>, is among the football people who reason that it 
was bad luck for <PERSON>Wyche</PERSON> and his no-huddle offense that they drew the 49ers and 
Coach <PERSON>Bill Walsh</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>'s first Super Bowl since <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> will have a (defensive) plan for the no-huddle, you can count on that," 
<PERSON>Sevier</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
For one thing, with 225-pound strong safety <PERSON>Jeff Fuller</PERSON> in the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 
lineup, the 49ers can make a conventional alignment look like the nickel 
defense, or vice versa, <PERSON>Sevier</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"Fuller is as solid against the run as he is active against the pass," the <LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION> coach added. "He's bigger than (49er linebacker) <PERSON>Keena Turner</PERSON>, who lists 
at 222." 
</P>
<P>
Fuller is listed at 216, though his opponents doubt that he was that small 10 
or 15 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
"(Against no-huddle formations) a big safety like Fuller is a tremendous asset 
to a team like the 49ers," <PERSON>Sevier</PERSON> said. "I mean, when big (<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> fullback) 
<PERSON>Ickey Woods</PERSON> is running against a little safety in the ordinary nickel, it's a 
mismatch. Fuller changes that dimension. 
</P>
<P>
"It's similar with (<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> linebacker) <PERSON>Charles Haley</PERSON>, who can be either 
a down lineman or a linebacker. The no-huddle offense loses a lot of its 
effectiveness against multiple-formation players like Fuller and <PERSON>Haley</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"The 49ers don't have to worry about bringing in defensive specialists. They're 
already on the field." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sid Gillman</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Famer</ORGANIZATION> who used to coach the Rams and other <ORGANIZATION>National 
Football League</ORGANIZATION> teams, is no fan of the no-huddle attack in any case. 
</P>
<P>
"That's a haphazard way to run an offense, with people running around out there 
shouting at other people," <PERSON>Gillman</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"Besides, if it's third and 5, I'm going to send in an extra cornerback, 
anyhow, no-huddle or not." 
</P>
<P>
Sevier, who is a candidate for at least one of the coaching vacancies that have 
materialized in the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>this winter</DATE>, expects a relatively penalty-free Super 
Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
Though the referees throw a lot of flags each fall in the regular season, they 
normally restrain themselves in the championship game. 
</P>
<P>
As Sevier sees it, there are three reasons for this: 
</P>
<P>
"First, you get a better quality team in the Super Bowl," he said. "Good teams 
make fewer fouls. 
</P>
<P>
"Second, these are the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s best officials of the year. Like Super Bowl 
players, they're at the very top of their game, or they wouldn't be here, and 
they don't want an official's call to be the difference. So they make sure that 
anything they call, they actually see. 
</P>
<P>
"Officials are like the rest of us, and in a hum-drum game in the regular 
season they're more subject to bad calls. 
</P>
<P>
"Third, Super Bowl officials, being the best at their profession, are less 
likely than other officials to call clipping on a kick return. 
</P>
<P>
"That's the penalty that is most often not a foul. And it comes when blocking 
angles are changed after the kick returner changes direction. 
</P>
<P>
"Returners run to a designated point of attack -- but if the kicking team shuts 
them down there, they're coached to run (elsewhere) to daylight. This sets up 
unforeseen blocking angles. 
</P>
<P>
"What would have been a good block becomes a push in the back -- and the 
official drops his handkerchief. In the regular season, I mean, they do. 
</P>
<P>
"You're less likely to see that in the Super Bowl." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Joe Browne</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> said TV surveys show that <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of those viewing Super Bowl 
XXIII on home television will be women. 
</P>
<P>
"That's more than double the number of women who usually watch a sports event," 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
Eleven <LOCATION>South Florida</LOCATION> taxi drivers, serving on something called the Super Bowl 
'89 Taxi Squad, are acting as role models in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> this week for other drivers. 
</P>
<P>
It's part of a <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> Nice campaign. 
</P>
<P>
The drivers were trained in courtesy and other welcome virtues at <ORGANIZATION>St. Thomas 
University</ORGANIZATION> nearby. Many <LOCATION>Dade County</LOCATION> taxi drivers are wearing welcome-to-Miami 
Super Bowl hats and shirts funded by a <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> grant from a <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> 
corporation. 
</P>
<P>
It remains to be seen if the improvements are cosmetic or otherwise, but fares 
in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> do seem more reasonable. 
</P>
<P>
Unless he changes his mind, <PERSON>Alvin Garrett</PERSON>'s ring from the <DATE>1983</DATE> Super Bowl is 
going to the highest bidder. In an auction of sorts, the former <ORGANIZATION>Washington 
Redskins</ORGANIZATION> wide receiver has taken out a classified ad in <ORGANIZATION>The Washington Post</ORGANIZATION> in 
hopes of selling the ring, according to a Post story. 
</P>
<P>
The going price is undetermined, although <PERSON>Garrett</PERSON> said <PERSON>Friday</PERSON> <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> is a 
nice, round figure. Early callers are stuck at about <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
"That wouldn't be enough," he said. "We're just starting it off. It'll climb." 
</P>
<P>
The ad began running in the Post this week under "Antiques and Collectibles" 
and reads, "COLLECTOR'S ITEM -- <DATE>1982</DATE> Redskins World Champ Superbowl ring. Very 
valuable &amp; rare oppty." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Garrett</PERSON> said he has been unemployed for a month or two and that he needs the 
money. "I thought about this since a long time ago," he said. "I guess you have 
to be me to understand. It's just a ring. When I got it, it was good to have, 
but there's more to life than a gold band and a diamond. . . . You need to have 
enough money to have shelter, a car to drive, food to eat." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Quarterback Boomer Esiason is back to work with the rest of the 
Cincinnati Bengals Sunday at Miami. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1502EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Gulf-Japan-Markets Bjt   08-19 0717</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Japan-Markets, Bjt,0742</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gulf Crisis Sends Tokyo Markets Reeling</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By S.L. BACHMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's invasion of <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION> sent the already bearish
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> stock market plummeting, and traders said the trend is likely
to continue.
   The dollar-yen exchange rate, meanwhile, settled into a range of
around 147 to <MONEY>148 yen</MONEY> to the dollar after major fluctuations early
in the crisis.
   Analysts predicted that the strength of the Japanese economy,
and the relative weakness of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> economy, would keep the
exchange rate hovering around the same level until the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION>
stalemate breaks.
   <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s stock traders were already seven months into a bear
market by <DATE>Aug. 2</DATE>, when Iraqi troops overtook <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION>. The market,
which had been near the 31,000-point level, immediately plunged
nearly 600 points.
   The next two weeks brought new shocks.
   The first was <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s decision a few days after the invasion to
impose unpredented strict sanctions on <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION>, followed by the <ORGANIZATION>United
Nations</ORGANIZATION>' decision to impose sanctions.
   The second was Prime Minister <PERSON>Toshiki Kaifu</PERSON>'s decision the
following <DATE>Monday</DATE> to cancel his long-planned tour of five <ORGANIZATION>Middle
Eastern</ORGANIZATION> countries, scheduled to begin <DATE>Aug. 15</DATE>.
   Also during the second full week of <DATE>August</DATE>, the traditional
``O-bon'' holiday, beautiful weather and the distraction of the
national high school baseball tournament, combined to weaken
interest in all markets, traders said.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the 225-issue <ORGANIZATION>Nikkei Stock Average</ORGANIZATION> closed at
26,786.72 points, down <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT> from its <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE> close.
   Traders said the market would continue to slide.
   ``The most likely scenario for the stock market right now is to
weaken further,'' said <PERSON>Pelham Smithers</PERSON>, an analyst for <ORGANIZATION>Shearson,
Lehman</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Hutton Asia, Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, citing weakness in the bond market along
with uncertainty about the Iraq-Kuwait situation as influences.
   Low yields on the stock market, he said, ``have made other
instruments, such as holding cash, more attractive.''
   Long-term interest rates on bonds, for instance, started going
up in <DATE>June</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> agreed to spend some <MONEY>$2.72 billion</MONEY> on public
works over the next 10 years, he said. The yield of the benchmark
10-year Japanese government bond closed <DATE>Friday</DATE> at <PERCENT>8.050 percent</PERCENT>, up
from <PERCENT>7.505 percent</PERCENT> on <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE>.
   The market has been on a long-term downswing since <DATE>Dec. 29</DATE>, when
the latest postwar ``Superbowl'' market peaked at 38,916 points,
said <PERSON>Darrel Whitten</PERSON>, director of research at the <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> office of
<ORGANIZATION>Prudential Bache Securities</ORGANIZATION>.
   Superbowl markets, when markets typically expanded by about <PERCENT>5.5
percent</PERCENT>, have been followed by corrections averaging 80 to 90
months, he said. ``The question is how long the adjustment will
last.''
   Another indicator, the five-year moving average, suggests the
market will bottom out at 25,000-21,000 points, he said.
   With higher oil prices killing any chance of bringing interest
rates down, and corporate profits unlikely to go up, ``The blow-off
comes in the market,'' he said.
   Early in the crisis, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s near total dependence on imported
oil buoyed the dollar.
   Brent Crude for <DATE>October</DATE> delivery closed <DATE>Friday</DATE> at about <MONEY>$26.10</MONEY>
to <MONEY>$26.20</MONEY> a barrel in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, compared with <MONEY>$19.90</MONEY> to <MONEY>$21.00</MONEY> a
barrel in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE>.
   But eventually the markets valued the yen higher because of
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s economic strength. Although the dollar normally gains
strength in times of crisis, the structural weaknesses of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
economy has overwhelmed its traditional strength in times of
crisis, many traders said.
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> has been working since the first oil shocks of the early
<DATE>1970s</DATE> to broaden its list of suppliers and lessen its dependence on
oil imports through efficiency and use of other energy sources,
notably nuclear, they said.
   ``The yen appears to have settled temporarily into a trading
range against the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar and the <LOCATION>Deutschemark</LOCATION>, and the earlier
pattern of dollar weakness is not expected to re-emerge until the
<LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> situation is clarified,'' said analysts at <ORGANIZATION>Salomon
Brothers Asia, Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, in a newsletter prepared for the week of <DATE>Aug.
13</DATE>.
   The dollar closed at <MONEY>147.35 yen</MONEY> to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar <DATE>Friday</DATE>. On
<DATE>Aug. 2</DATE>, the currency jumped <MONEY>2.25 yen</MONEY> to <MONEY>147.13 yen</MONEY>. Closing figures
bounced between <MONEY>149 yen</MONEY> and <MONEY>150 yen</MONEY> but no higher than <MONEY>150.65 yen</MONEY>
in subsequent days.
   With energy prices already high, oil and utility company profits
would cushion the Japanese economy, while the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> economy
is struggling under numerous burdens, added analyst <PERSON>Robert A
Feldman</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-1098</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFZARAD6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940625
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 JUN 94 / As They Say in Europe: Passion that eludes the US
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JAMES MORGAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Last <DATE>weekend</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>La Gazzetta Sportiva</ORGANIZATION> said: 'E non si puo neppure imprecare alla
sfortuna' (one cannot even blame misfortune). This observation on the defeat
at the hands, or feet, of <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> in the World Cup, could have been taken
from a barely-known opera by Puccini which I have unearthed - <PERSON>Il Fanciullo</PERSON>
del Ouest (The Boy of the Golden West).
The hero, <LOCATION>Chicherino</LOCATION>, sings this sad aria, E non si puo, having been forced
to emigrate and take up American football after scoring a last-minute own
goal in a European cup match against <ORGANIZATION>Lammermoor United</ORGANIZATION>. He was also rejected
by his beloved Calcia. She sings L'Italia sprofonda nel grigiore (<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>
plunged in gloom - quoted on page 3 of Sportiva) when he scores an historic
touchdown in the <LOCATION>Superbowl</LOCATION> <DATE>a year later</DATE>.
But not all <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> was plunged in gloom at the defeat. For the opponents of
<PERSON>Silvio Berlusconi</PERSON>, the country's new leader, there was covert rejoicing.
Berlusconi owns AC <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION> and their players constitute the largest element in
the Italian team. La Repubblica headlined the surprise defeat: '<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, in
the shape of <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION>, beaten.'
So, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, in the shape of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, won; nine of the team were born in
places such as <ORGANIZATION>Ealing</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> suburb.
There was one other country which enjoyed a startling victory <DATE>last weekend</DATE> -
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. That again was an odd case of foreigners, at least a sort of
foreigner, playing a crucial role. In the match against <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, which
brought tears of admiration, there was a wondrous goal by <PERSON>Gheorghe Hagi</PERSON>. The
commentators spent much of the rest of the game arguing as to whether he
could have meant it. (He did because he had done it before.)
Hagi turns out to be an Aromanian, a small group from <LOCATION>Macedonia</LOCATION> which speaks
an odd form of Romanian. He is a man of few words in that language, just
saying: 'Keep your fingers crossed,' to the mass circulation Evenimentul
Zilei in its attempt to extract an interview.
<LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s other goals were scored by <PERSON>Florin Raducioiu</PERSON>, who was positively
prolix by comparison, observing that the 3-1 victory was compensation for
having kept his compatriots up all night. The <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> fiesta began at
around four in the <TIME>morning local time</TIME>, the first occasion for national
rejoicing since <PERSON>Mr</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mrs Ceausescu</PERSON> were shot on <DATE>Christmas Day, 1989</DATE>.
Evenimentul carried an even more unusual World Cup story. In the middle of
the small knot of Romanian supporters at the <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> Rose Bowl was an
emotional Dutch woman waving their national flag. Asked what she was doing
there, she replied: 'I am Astrid, wife of <ORGANIZATION>Raducioiu</ORGANIZATION>,' which sounds
suspiciously like something stolen from a Dutch-Romanian phrase book. The
star striker had, it emerged, secretly married her three days before.
There has been Europe-wide speculation as to whether the host nation will
become interested in what the rest of the world calls football. The
consensus is that it will not - and that is no bad thing.
No one liked the opening ceremony. La Stampa was the most favourable, saying
it was 'simple, fast and cheap'. Another Italian paper, <LOCATION>Tuttosport</LOCATION>, said the
only good thing was that it was short, while Sport in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> said the contest
opened with a 'grey, grim and short celebration'.
A French paper, La Nouvelle Republique du Centre-Ouest, pondered how a
country that had exported its culture to the rest of the world, and was
largely made up of European immigrants, had remained closed to football.
'America loves violent sports and high scores. It hates drawn games. It
prefers by far the organised progression towards the opposing goal to a
subtle combination made up of fantasy and improvisation . . . Perhaps
passions are not as universal as one would like to think.'
Soccer could become a mass sport in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> if the game abandoned the offside
rule, doubled the size of the goal, stopped every five minutes for bogus
reasons and employed teams made up of genetic curiosities. It would not be
soccer but it would appeal to TV networks and advertisers. For they will
never accept the game of football as it is known to the rest of the world.
<PERSON>James Morgan</PERSON> is economics correspondent of the <ORGANIZATION>BBC World Service</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>XGZ  Europe.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2711 Newspapers.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page VIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900705-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-05-90 1205EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Soviet-Tchaikovsky     07-05 0366</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Soviet-Tchaikovsky,0377</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ninth International Tchaikovsky Musical Competition Ends</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN IAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The prestigious Tchaikovsky competition drew to a
close today with final performances by 48 musicians, including 10
Americans.
   Musicians were competing for the top prize in four categories:
piano, violin, and _ for the first time since the event was
initially held in <DATE>1958</DATE> _ voice and cello.
   Called the ``superbowl of musical competition,'' by one judge,
the Tchaikovsky competition is held every four years.
   The competition, which began <DATE>June 14</DATE>, drew 335 competitors from
51 countries, organizers said. Winners were to be announced <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   The top musicians in each category receive a <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> streo
system, a gold medal and 5,000 rubles _ a non-convertible currency
that cannot be taken from the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   ``This is the most important competition in the world,'' said
finalist <PERSON>Hans Choi</PERSON>, 31, a South Korean-born singer who lives in <LOCATION>New
York City</LOCATION>. ``I must sing perfctly in six languanges because the
judges come from so many countries.''
   This year, for the first time, not only are the contestants and
judges international, but the sponsorship as well. The hard-pressed
Soviet hosts turned to a Japanese company to donate the stereo
equipment offered as prizes.
   <PERSON>Deborah Voigt</PERSON>, 29, a singer who lives in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, said the
Soviet audiences had been very supportive.
   ``I am a bit overwhelmed. The audience response has been
unbelievable,'' she said. ``I used to think Italians were the best
audiences, but now I think Russians make the best audience by far.''
   The contest spokeswoman, <PERSON>Galina Tyurina</PERSON>, said the four halls
where the competition has been held were filled to capacity for
each performance.
   ``We have nothing but empty shelves in our shops,'' said
<PERSON>Tyurina</PERSON>, ``but we love our music. There is no shortage of music in
our country.''
   <PERSON>Lucia Lin</PERSON>, a 28-year-old violinist from <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, said she came to
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> because of the competition's reputation. Lin plays with the
<ORGANIZATION>Boston Symphony Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's a lot of work _ stressful and
grueling _ but I'm glad I came,'' she said.
   The Tchaikovsky competition is organized by the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of
Culture</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Union of Composers</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>All-Union Music Society</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880901-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-01-88 0621EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a PM-BRF--Drummer-Slaying     09-01 0153</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Drummer-Slaying,0159</SECOND>
<HEAD>Musician Charged In Ex-Wife's Death</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The drummer for singer <PERSON>Kenny Rogers</PERSON> has
been formally charged with first-degree murder in the shooting of
his ex-wife.
   <PERSON>Bobby Daniels</PERSON>, 41, was being held in Metro Jail without bond
pending a preliminary hearing scheduled for today.
   He is accused of shooting <PERSON>Sylvia K. Coakley</PERSON>, 35, a real estate
agent, through a storm door of her home before dawn <DATE>Aug. 16</DATE>.
   The couple had been divorced for about eight years, but problems
escalated between the two in the weeks before the shooting,
authorities said.
   Coakley had taken out a warrant for <PERSON>Daniels</PERSON>' arrest on charges
of assault and battery when he allegedly assaulted her in her home
<DATE>July 13</DATE>.
   Daniels has been <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON>' drummer for about a dozen years. He
also was co-producer of the <DATE>1986</DATE> music video, ``Superbowl
Shuffle,'' which was recorded by members of the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bears</ORGANIZATION>
football team.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06006158 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06006158 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; Dryer  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  TELEVISION; CELEBRITY; QA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  QUESTION: Could you please give me some information on the football and acting
careers of Fred Dryer of "Hunter"?;    ANSWER: Dryer was a standout defensive
end through most of his NFL career: three seasons with the New York Giants
(1968-72) and nine with the Los Angeles Rams (1972-81). Twice named All-Pro,
he's also a Super Bowl veteran (1980).  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  TV Magazine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DON'T MESS WITH 'HUNTER' STAR  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Celebrity Questions  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Those who followed Dryer's football career know that he had a reputation
for being opinionated, outspoken -- and, to some, obnoxious -- long before
gaining a reputation for throwing his 6-foot-6, 220-pound weight around
"Hunter." The anecdotes are plentiful: How Dryer cut short an on-camera
interview with <PERSON>Howard Cosell</PERSON> by answering unwelcome questions with expletives;
how he and ex-teammate <PERSON>Lance Rentzel</PERSON> pretended to be reporters and "crashed"
the press corps covering the <DATE>1975</DATE> Superbowl; how he criticized fellow players
and management.;    Dryer began to study acting in <DATE>1980</DATE>. After hanging up his
cleats in <DATE>1981</DATE>, he served briefly as a <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> color commentator, then went
full-force into acting, chalking up credits in TV movies such as "Starmaker"
with <PERSON>Rock Hudson</PERSON>, and several TV pilots. He came close to landing the role of
<PERSON>Sam Malone</PERSON> in "Cheers" -- and wound up playing a friend of <PERSON>Sam</PERSON> (<PERSON>Ted Danson</PERSON>) in
several episodes -- before "Hunter.";    Q: Was <PERSON>Tom Selleck</PERSON> once a regular on
"The Young and the Restless"?;    A: <PERSON>Selleck</PERSON> did appear on the soap in <DATE>1975</DATE> --
as publisher <PERSON>Jed Andrews</PERSON> -- but his run lasted a mere nine shows. Asked to
sign a contract to continue with the show, he declined.;    Q: Whatever
happened to <PERSON>Joyce DeWitt</PERSON> of "Three's Company"?;    A: Since the series died in
<DATE>1984</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>DeWitt</ORGANIZATION> has done some plays and has traveled around the world twice.
She's reading screenplays.;     Q: On "The Virginian," did <PERSON>James Drury</PERSON> ever
have a name or was he always referred to as The Virginian?;    A: The
mysterious Virginian never revealed his name -- not in the TV series, not in
the "Virginian" movies that preceded it (including <DATE>1929</DATE>'s "The Virginian"
starring <PERSON>Gary Cooper</PERSON> and <PERSON>Walter Huston</PERSON>), and not in the <DATE>1902</DATE> <PERSON>Owen Wister</PERSON>
novel. (box)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  STACY JENEL SMITH, Tribune Media Services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910106  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  74  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  357  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday January 6, 1991
00006158,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-14348</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EGODBABAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940715
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 JUL 94 / World Cup '94: More important than matters of life and death
 -Political unrest, civil war and economic hardship are simply minor
irritations
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By SIMON KUPER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The best way to get applauded on the streets of <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> is to wear a Brazilian
football shirt. Haiti's team are so bad they were kept out of the World Cup
by <LOCATION>Bermuda</LOCATION>, so the whole country supports <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
'You are asking which is more important - <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> or a <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> invasion?' one fan
asked an American reporter. 'We are hungry every day. We have problems every
day. The Americans talk about invading every day. But we only have the World
Cup every four years.'
During the World Cup, economic sanctions against <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> have failed to bite
and talks between government and opposition were out of the question. At
half-time during matches, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s black-and white TV sets show bloody videos
of the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> invasion of <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>, with texts like No to Intervention
superimposed.
'This country is demobilised by the World Cup,' complains Haitian Prime
Minister <PERSON>Robert Malval</PERSON>. 'I think when we wake up on <DATE>July 18</DATE> - that's the end
of the World Cup party. And that will be the beginning of the end of the
party here.'
This World Cup is having a bigger effect on countries' politics than any
previous World Cup. True, the Argentine junta used the <DATE>1978</DATE> World Cup much
as the Haitian junta is using this one, and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1954</DATE> triumph did
more to restore German self-respect than <PERSON>Konrad Adenauer</PERSON> ever could.
Other examples abound. But this World Cup is more serious. For a start,
there are more TV sets in the world today than there were even four years
ago. The tournament is attracting vast audiences. The average human - a
Chinese peasant, <ORGANIZATION>Essex Man</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Alexandr Solzhenitsyn</PERSON> - will probably have
watched six World Cup games by the end of <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s final.
Rwandans root for <LOCATION>Nigeria</LOCATION>, Bangladeshis for <PERSON>Maradona</PERSON> (they held protest
marches in <LOCATION>Dhaka</LOCATION> after he was banned for drug-taking), and no doubt the
Eskimos have their favourite team.
In <DATE>1950</DATE>, famously, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> learned by telegram that the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> had beaten
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, and even later things were not much better in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. But telegrams do not tend to demobilise nations.
Second, in this lone superpower world, the World Cup is the one key arena
which the Americans do not dominate. One Mexican soccer-lover living in
<LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> told me that he would prefer not to see football taking off in the
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.
The World Cup is the most direct way we have of ranking the nations of the
world - it is hard to compare GDPs in a way that is quite as visually
appealing - and the Americans' weakness at soccer leaves the field
relatively even.
Soccer can give a nation status. When we say '<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> beat <ORGANIZATION>Holland</ORGANIZATION>' we feel
we are talking not just about their soccer teams but about the countries
themselves.
'In the World Cup, all we lost is two games. We didn't lose our national
honour,' a Colombian state governor tried to argue a few days ago. He was
standing beside the coffin of <PERSON>Andres Escobar</PERSON>, the Colombian player (and
own-goal scorer) slain on his return home.
Whereas in the past most countries were dictatorships propped up by the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
or <ORGANIZATION>USSR</ORGANIZATION>, now dozens are (or are becoming) democracies. <PERSON>Nicolae Ceaucescu</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Todor Zhivkov</PERSON> did not worry about public opinion, and in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> nor did
African leaders.
Now the Cameroonian president, <PERSON>Paul Biya</PERSON>, is so worried that for two World
Cups in a row he has recalled the middle-aged <PERSON>Roger Milla</PERSON> to the team (what
will he do in <DATE>1998</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Milla</LOCATION> is 46?).
Ethnic tension rises, and rulers look to the World Cup to foster unity.
General <PERSON>Sani Abacha</PERSON> likes the Nigerian team to include players from each of
the country's three main tribes, and after <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> beat <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, President
<PERSON>Ion Iliescu</PERSON> said the ethnically diverse team had created a 'national
consensus.' (That was before the ethnic <PERSON>Serb Belodedici</PERSON> missed the decisive
penalty in the quarter-final).
The <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> squad, which contains Hispanics, blacks, Italian- and Greek-Americans
 -precious few Wasps - received a call from President <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> that was shown
on prime-time TV.
Democratic rulers everywhere are struggling, and they all turn to the World
Cup. In <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, where soccer is perhaps the least tarnished national
institution of the moment, <PERSON>Silvio Berlusconi</PERSON> got himself elected prime
minister with a party named after a football chant.
In <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, presidents have appeared on TV during the
World Cup to suggest changes to the national team's line-up. Even in <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>,
Prime Minister <PERSON>Gro Brundtland</PERSON> appeared on a TV panel commenting on the
country's opening game.
Countries that need the World Cup most were only admitted to it quite
recently. <ORGANIZATION>Fifa</ORGANIZATION>, soccer's governing body, first gave <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> a World Cup berth
in <DATE>1970</DATE>; only this year did the continent get three places. <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, with more
than half the world's population, for long had only one spot, and still has
only two.
And the poor are improving. African teams regularly reach the second round.
The Third World cares: when <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> drew with <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION> in <DATE>1990</DATE>, soldiers of all
factions in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> spent the night firing into the air. When <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> beat
<LOCATION>Cameroon</LOCATION> a couple of weeks later, a Bangladeshi man had a heart attack and a
Bangladeshi woman killed herself. 'The elimination of <LOCATION>Cameroon</LOCATION> also means
the end of my life,' read her suicide note.
Americans are trying hard to understand. 'When <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> lost in <DATE>1990</DATE> people
were jumping off buildings,' said <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> star striker <PERSON>Eric Wynalda</PERSON>. 'I don't
think anyone jumped off a building when <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> lost the Superbowl.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P794  Commercial Sports.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890111-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-89 1510EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     01-11 0989</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,1026</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Kitty Dukakis</PERSON> is off on a speaking tour, her
associates say. And that's about all they'll say.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Boston Globe</ORGANIZATION> reported that <PERSON>Mrs. Dukakis</PERSON> was to deliver a
speech <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to a group of admirers at a private home in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>. But neither her <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> agent, her <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lawyer nor
her <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> staff would disclose the location and nature of the event.
   Nor would they disclose the name of the group sponsoring the
speech, for which the wife of Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> reportedly will
net as much as <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY>.
   ``We are not hiding anything. It's just a private matter,''
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>Robert Barnett</PERSON> told the newspaper. ``We tend to
forget that people do have privacy. You shouldn't be shocked or
amazed.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Kitty Dukakis</PERSON> is off on a speaking tour, her
associates say. And that's about all they'll say.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Boston Globe</ORGANIZATION> reported that <PERSON>Mrs. Dukakis</PERSON> was to deliver a
speech <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to a group of admirers at a private home in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>. But neither her <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> agent, her <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lawyer nor
her <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> staff would disclose the location and nature of the event.
   Nor would they disclose the name of the group sponsoring the
speech, for which the wife of Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> reportedly will
net as much as <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY>.
   ``We are not hiding anything. It's just a private matter,''
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>Robert Barnett</PERSON> told the newspaper. ``We tend to
forget that people do have privacy. You shouldn't be shocked or
amazed.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Kitty Dukakis</PERSON> is off on a speaking tour, her
associates say. And that's about all they'll say.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Boston Globe</ORGANIZATION> reported that <PERSON>Mrs. Dukakis</PERSON> was to deliver a
speech <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to a group of admirers at a private home in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>. But neither her <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> agent, her <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lawyer nor
her <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> staff would disclose the location and nature of the event.
   Nor would they disclose the name of the group sponsoring the
speech, for which the wife of Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> reportedly will
net as much as <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY>.
   ``We are not hiding anything. It's just a private matter,''
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>Robert Barnett</PERSON> told the newspaper. ``We tend to
forget that people do have privacy. You shouldn't be shocked or
amazed.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BARTOW, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Kitty Dukakis</PERSON> is off on a speaking tour, her
associates say. And that's about all they'll say.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Boston Globe</ORGANIZATION> reported that <PERSON>Mrs. Dukakis</PERSON> was to deliver a
speech <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to a group of admirers at a private home in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>. But neither her <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> agent, her <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lawyer nor
her <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> staff would disclose the location and nature of the event.
   Nor would they disclose the name of the group sponsoring the
speech, for which the wife of Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> reportedly will
net as much as <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY>.
   ``We are not hiding anything. It's just a private matter,''
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>Robert Barnett</PERSON> told the newspaper. ``We tend to
forget that people do have privacy. You shouldn't be shocked or
amazed.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PRUDENVILLE, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Kitty Dukakis</PERSON> is off on a speaking tour, her
associates say. And that's about all they'll say.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Boston Globe</ORGANIZATION> reported that <PERSON>Mrs. Dukakis</PERSON> was to deliver a
speech <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to a group of admirers at a private home in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>. But neither her <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> agent, her <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lawyer nor
her <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> staff would disclose the location and nature of the event.
   Nor would they disclose the name of the group sponsoring the
speech, for which the wife of Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> reportedly will
net as much as <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY>.
   ``We are not hiding anything. It's just a private matter,''
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>Robert Barnett</PERSON> told the newspaper. ``We tend to
forget that people do have privacy. You shouldn't be shocked or
amazed.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Kitty Dukakis</PERSON> is off on a speaking tour, her
associates say. And that's about all they'll say.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Boston Globe</ORGANIZATION> reported that <PERSON>Mrs. Dukakis</PERSON> was to deliver a
speech <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to a group of admirers at a private home in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>. But neither her <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> agent, her <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lawyer nor
her <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> staff would disclose the location and nature of the event.
   Nor would they disclose the name of the group sponsoring the
speech, for which the wife of Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> reportedly will
net as much as <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY>.
   ``We are not hiding anything. It's just a private matter,''
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>Robert Barnett</PERSON> told the newspaper. ``We tend to
forget that people do have privacy. You shouldn't be shocked or
amazed.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Kitty Dukakis</PERSON> is off on a speaking tour, her
associates say. And that's about all they'll say.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Boston Globe</ORGANIZATION> reported that <PERSON>Mrs. Dukakis</PERSON> was to deliver a
speech <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to a group of admirers at a private home in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>. But neither her <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> agent, her <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lawyer nor
her <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> staff would disclose the location and nature of the event.
   Nor would they disclose the name of the group sponsoring the
speech, for which the wife of Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> reportedly will
net as much as <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY>.
   ``We are not hiding anything. It's just a private matter,''
