<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111489-0039 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 134373 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 14, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 2; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
254 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DODGERS, ANGELS PLAN TALKS WITH FREE AGENT LANGSTON 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ROSS NEWHAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Set to battle over free agents <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robin Yount</PERSON> in what may become 
a Freeway Series of a different nature, the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> and Angels begin the 
process today, when <PERSON>Fred Claire</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> executive vice president, meets 
with left-handed pitcher <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> and his agent, <LOCATION>Arn Tellem</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Angels, according to a source, have a <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> meeting with <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> and 
Tellem. 
</P>
<P>
Langston is believed to favor the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION>, Angels and <LOCATION>San Diego Padres</LOCATION> on the 
basis of location, but bidding is expected to stretch from coast to coast, and 
began <DATE>Monday</DATE> when the 90 players who filed for free agency were eligible to 
accept offers from clubs other than their own. 
</P>
<P>
Langston heard from only the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners</ORGANIZATION>, under new ownership since 
<PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, who spent five-plus seasons there, was traded to the <LOCATION>Montreal Expos</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Yount</PERSON>, as a center fielder who can bat leadoff, represents the solution to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION>' two most pressing needs. 
</P>
<P>
Yount is vacationing in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. The speculation is that, at 34, he is reluctant 
to leave the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> and may be interested in the <LOCATION>Angels</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, <PERSON>Tony DeMarco</PERSON>, the agent for free agent pitcher <PERSON>Fernando Valenzuela</PERSON>, 
said the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> have increased their offer from one year to one year and an 
option for <DATE>1991</DATE>, but the money in both years is still less than the <MONEY>$1.85 
million</MONEY> that <ORGANIZATION>Valenzuela</ORGANIZATION> received in <DATE>1989</DATE> and far less than the three-year, 
<MONEY>$6-million</MONEY> package that <PERSON>Valenzuela</PERSON> is believed to be seeking. 
</P>
<P>
Times staff writers <PERSON>Bill Plaschke</PERSON> and <PERSON>Helene Elliott</PERSON> contributed to this story. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
LANGSTON, MARK; FREE AGENTS (SPORTS); YOUNT, ROBIN; LOS ANGELES DODGERS 
(BASEBALL TEAM); CALIFORNIA ANGELS (BASEBALL TEAM); VALENZUELA, FERNANDO 
(BASEBALL PLAYER) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06073176 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06073176 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  ANAHEIM; CALIFORNIA; PROFESSIONAL; BASEBALL; MAN; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE morning-after found Mark Langston smiling, for a change.;    He was
happiest about having thrown strikes. He didn't do that last season. He didn't
do much of anything, except collect his paycheck, which was then among the
richest in baseball history.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THIS YEAR IS 'A DIFFERENT STORY' FOR ANGELS'
LANGSTON  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Baseball
Around the Cactus League  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     For <MONEY>$3.2 million</MONEY>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> gave the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Angels 10 wins, 17 losses
and a 4.40 ERA. In the bargain, he got a big case of self-doubt, the biggest,
he said, since his junior season at <ORGANIZATION>San Jose State</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981.</DATE>;    "I lacked
confidence last year," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>. "This year, it's a
different story.";    For <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, this year officially began <DATE>Monday</DATE>
<TIME>afternoon</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Packard Stadium</ORGANIZATION>, on the campus of <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State University</ORGANIZATION>.
There, against the <LOCATION>San Diego Padres</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> pitched three innings of
two-hit, shutout ball. He threw strikes. He threw hard. He won. He did all the
things he was expected to do last season.;    Explaining a season gone bad is
like explaining a marriage gone bad. You've got all kinds of reasons, and no
clue where to start. Which was the biggest? Which was first?;    <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>
insists on this much: The money had no part in it. None.;    When a guy signs
a big contract and then flops, the standard explanation is that he pressed, he
tried too hard to justify the salary he's making. It's tired, but very
possibly true. It's logical. It's in line with what we know about human
nature. But, where it concerns him, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> fights this notion with the
bulldog tenacity for which he is not known.;    "I never thought about (the
money)," he says. "I don't think any guy could live up to that kind of
contract; you wouldn't even try. You're basically paid on what you've done in
the past, anyway. . . . It wasn't the money.";    The <DATE>1990</DATE> season began so
promisingly for <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>. Signed to a free-agent contract for five years and
<MONEY>$16 million</MONEY>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> made a debut that was worth every penny: He pitched a
no-hitter at <LOCATION>Anaheim Stadium</LOCATION>. Against his old team, no less. The downer was
that <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> couldn't finish the game; he left after seven innings and even
that had been a gamble, given the short <DATE>spring</DATE> training.;    It was mid-August
before <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> won another game at <LOCATION>Anaheim Stadium</LOCATION>. He lost nine straight
decisions there. He didn't win anywhere between <DATE>June 5</DATE> and <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE>, his record
dropping from 4-5 to 4-13. At his worst, he was 5-15. He finished with his
lowest win total since <DATE>1985</DATE> and his most losses ever.;    "A lot of things
were involved," he said. "Probably, it was more mental than anything.";   
<PERSON>Langston</PERSON> got frustrated, understandably so. In early <DATE>June</DATE>, he lost 2-1 despite
12 strikeouts. Two weeks later, he lost again 2-1, despite striking out 10. In
<DATE>June</DATE>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> had a 2.36 ERA -- and a 1-3 record. And he let it get to him.; 
  "I kept looking at the next start as the one that would turn me around,"
<PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said, "and then, during the course of the game, I'd get defensive."; 
  He'd nibble at the corners. He'd fall behind. He'd walk the guy, or be
forced to come in with a hittable pitch. And the streak went on, including an
8-1 loss at home in which <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> allowed 10 hits in 2 2/3 innings and was
booed off the mound.;    <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>, 30, put in a winter of hard work, riding a
bike to build his legs and endurance. Not that either were a problem last
season.;    He also is ironing out a flaw in his delivery. Not that it
matters, either. Langston noticed the flaw while studying videotape; later, he
discovered he had pitched with the same flaw in <DATE>1988</DATE>, when he went 15-11 for
Seattle.;    So it wasn't mechanics. And it wasn't physical. And, dammit, it
wasn't the money. Whatever it was, it's gone. It's a new year, a fresh start,
and that might make all the difference for <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> in <DATE>1991</DATE>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Bud Geracie column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Mesa, Ariz.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910313  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  677  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday March 13, 1991
00073176,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA120289-0147 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 143542 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 2, 1989, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
507 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ANGELS SIGN LANGSTON TO BASEBALL'S RICHEST CONTRACT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By HELENE ELLIOTT, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ANAHEIM 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Angels boldly pursued and won baseball's premier free agent 
<DATE>Friday</DATE> when left-handed pitcher <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> agreed to a guaranteed, 
five-year, <MONEY>$16-million</MONEY> contract that made him -- at least for the moment -- the 
highest-paid player in baseball. 
</P>
<P>
The 29-year-old <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> native spurned "serious" proposals from the <ORGANIZATION>Los 
Angeles Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>New York Yankees</LOCATION> to enlist with the Angels, becoming the 
sixth starting pitcher on a staff that last season had the second-best 
earned-run average in the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Langston's contract, which will contain a no-trade clause, will be the longest 
given a professional baseball player since <PERSON>Eddie Murray</PERSON> signed a five-year pact 
with the <ORGANIZATION>Baltimore Orioles</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1987</DATE> (<PERSON>Murray</PERSON> subsequently was traded to the 
Dodgers) and is the most lucrative guaranteed contract ever, surpassing the 
<MONEY>$13.6 million</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Dave Winfield</ORGANIZATION> was guaranteed by the <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION> in a 10-year deal 
before the <DATE>1981</DATE> season. 
</P>
<P>
Langston also becomes baseball's third <MONEY>$3-million</MONEY> man, joining <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>'s 
<PERSON>Kirby Puckett</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Rickey Henderson</PERSON> in that elite group. He will get a 
<MONEY>$1.5-million</MONEY> signing bonus, a <DATE>1990</DATE> salary of <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> and a salary of <MONEY>$3.25 
million</MONEY> in each of the succeeding four years. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm not out to break ground in that regard," said <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, the Angels' 
biggest free-agent signing since <PERSON>Reggie Jackson</PERSON> joined the club in <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
While admitting that the dollar amounts discussed "without a doubt boggles the 
mind," security was paramount in <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>'s mind. 
</P>
<P>
"Some teams were close, like the Dodgers and Yankees, but I think from the 
start -- from the very first meeting with the Angels -- meeting with (owners) 
Mr. and <PERSON>Mrs.</PERSON> (Gene and <PERSON>Jackie) Autry</PERSON>, the Angels were first-class, and from 
that point on, they took the lead," said <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, who had a combined record of 
16-14 last season with the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Montreal Expos</ORGANIZATION> and has a career 
record of 86-76. 
</P>
<P>
"I was more comfortable with the situation they presented before me as far as 
the five-year deal and the no-trade provision. That's something that was very 
important to me. Every time we (he and agent Arn Tellem) said something, they 
responded. They were the front-runner as far as responding to everything we had 
to say. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"My main concern was playing for a pennant-contending team," he said. "Even 
when I played for <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, I thought the Angels were classy and I always liked 
playing in <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION>. I knew every year they would do what it took to put a 
winning team on the field." 
</P>
<P>
Angel General Manager <PERSON>Mike Port</PERSON>, who in the past has been criticized for not 
aggressively pursuing free agents, said signing <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> will give him more 
options in trade discussions. 
</P>
<P>
Reluctant in the past to sign players for longer than two years, Port made an 
exception because of Langston's ability and the knowledge that another starter 
might have averted the late-season collapse that took the Angels out of the AL 
West race last <DATE>summer</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
* DEALING AN ACE 
</P>
<P>
Langston is delighted but the Dodgers are disappointed by Angels' latest 
acquisition. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mark Langston, formerly a Expo, will get $16 million over 5 years. 
Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
LANGSTON, MARK; AUTRY, GENE; CALIFORNIA ANGELS (BASEBALL TEAM); BASEBALL 
PLAYERS -- WAGES AND SALARIES; CONTRACTS; SPORTS STATISTICS; SPORTS RECORDS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06348169 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06348169 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Oakland's Allen Temple Cantateers are in their 10th year of
producing 'Black Nativity'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BLACK; MINORITY; HOLIDAY; SHOW; REVIEW; OAKLAND  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  JAMES Mercer Langston Hughes, spearhead of the Harlem Renaissance, was truly a
renaissance man.;   Born in 1902, he foresaw and lived to contribute to the
civil rights movement of the '60s.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THIRTY YEARS AGO, LANGSTON HUGHES WROTE A BLACK
NATIVITY PAGEANT THAT REMAINS ONE OF A KIND
GOSPEL CHRISTMAS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     His early poem "The Negro Speaks of Rivers" (<DATE>1922</DATE>), written the <DATE>summer</DATE>
after he graduated from high school (<DATE>1922</DATE>), is still a landmark work,
anthologized in countless college texts and collections. Later works were
built on speech rhythms derived from the blues and jazz.;   He won poetry
prizes and a writing scholarship to <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> at a
time when blacks in the fine arts were almost as rare as unicorns. Though
circumspect about his sexual orientation, he also was honest about being gay
in a culture that has always viewed homosexuality with suspicion.;   In
addition to his own writings (poetry, novels, stories and an autobiography),
<PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> also translated the work of <PERSON>Federico Garcia Lorca</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gabriela Mistral</PERSON>
from the Spanish, wrote the lyrics to <PERSON>Kurt Weill</PERSON>'s naturalistic folk opera
"Street Scene" and collected black poetry and folklore for two standard
anthologies published in the '50s. He also created a popular comic-strip
character, <PERSON>Jess B. Semple</PERSON>, who lived on the funny pages of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Post
for many years.;   In <DATE>1967</DATE>, just before his death, he published "The Panther
and the Lash," a final burst of bitter poetry about the betrayal of
African-Americans by the compromises of civil rights.;   And in <DATE>1961</DATE>, he wrote
"Black Nativity," a Christmas pageant with gospel music.;   <PERSON>Betty Gadling</PERSON>,
minister of music at <ORGANIZATION>Allen Temple Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, saw a production
of "Black Nativity" on television in the '60s, featuring <PERSON>Alex Bradford</PERSON>. She
obtained a copy of its still-unpublished script and spent years tracking down
its music.;   Some of the music was gospel standards, such as "Go Tell It On
the Mountain," and familiar Christmas carols. But some of it, like "Rise Up,
Shepherds, and Follow," she had never heard, she said.;   She located what she
could, with the help of several friends' collections and the library of the
<ORGANIZATION>American Baptist Theological Seminary</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Pacific School of Religion.</ORGANIZATION>;   "The rest we wrote," she
said matter-of-factly. Who is "we"? "Well, me," she answered.;   The result is
an annual "Black Nativity" production, performed by 47 singers from the temple
choir and a dance group.;   In this, the pageant's 10th year, it has expanded
to two weekends of performances and has traveled to <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>.
Next year, the production has an invitation to perform at a church in <LOCATION>San
Mateo.</LOCATION>;   Gadling describes it as ideal for children and families. (It runs
about two hours and 15 minutes.) The first act tells the story of the Nativity
in song and dance. The second is a '40s revival meeting, led by a preacher
(<PERSON>Michael Johnson</PERSON>, who is a deacon at the temple).;   Why is it important?
"It's the only black thing of its kind," says Gadling. And <PERSON>Langston Hughes</PERSON>
wrote it.; Black Nativity; By <PERSON>Langston Hughes</PERSON>; Producer: <ORGANIZATION>Allen Temple Baptist
Church</ORGANIZATION>; When: <TIME>8 tonight</TIME>, 2:30 and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>; Where:
<PERSON>Calvin Simmons Theater</PERSON>, 10th and <PERSON>Fallon</PERSON> streets, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>; Tickets: <MONEY>$15</MONEY>, <MONEY>$8</MONEY>
seniors and students, <MONEY>$6</MONEY> children. (510) 444-8575 (<ORGANIZATION>Neal Thrams Ticket Agency</ORGANIZATION>),
(510) 638-8291 (Revelations Gospel Music Store), (510) 843-7282 (<PERSON>Reid</PERSON>'s
Records); Parking: Street or free adjacent lot  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JUDITH GREEN, Mercury News Theater Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911213  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  25  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  577  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, December 13, 1991
00348169,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111189-0027 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 133191 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 11, 1989, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 2; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
637 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PRIZE LEFT-HANDER LANGSTON GRANTS AUDIENCE TO PADRES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BOB NIGHTENGALE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON>, the free-agent left-handed starter who is being wooed by almost 
half of the teams in baseball, agreed <DATE>Friday</DATE> to a private meeting next week in 
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> with <LOCATION>Padre</LOCATION> Manager <PERSON>Jack McKeon</PERSON> when his agent opens negotiations 
with the team. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Fred Lane</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Padres</ORGANIZATION>' Chicago-based attorney, is scheduled to travel in <LOCATION>Los 
Angeles</LOCATION> early next week and begin contract negotiations with agent <LOCATION>Arn Tellem</LOCATION>. 
In a separate meeting, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> is scheduled to talk with <PERSON>McKeon</PERSON>, <PERSON>Tellem</PERSON> said, 
to discuss baseball philosophy. 
</P>
<P>
"Arn told me that Mark thinks very highly of <PERSON>Jack McKeon</PERSON>," <PERSON>Lane</PERSON> said, "and 
that's why he wants to meet him." 
</P>
<P>
Said <PERSON>McKeon</PERSON>: "I look forward to talking to him, and as you know, I'd sure love 
to have him on our club." 
</P>
<P>
There are at least 10 teams, <PERSON>Tellem</PERSON> said, that have expressed interest in 
<LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>. Tellem will meet with most of them next week, but said there is no 
timetable as to when <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> will make his decision. 
</P>
<P>
Langston, 29, who was born in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> and raised in the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>, is expected 
to become the highest-paid pitcher in baseball. Those considered to be involved 
in heavy bidding besides the Padres are the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Angels</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>St. Louis 
Cardinals</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York Yankees</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco Giants</LOCATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Montreal Expos</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Who his top choice is depends on who you listen to. 
</P>
<P>
Many will tell you it's the Dodgers, considering that his wife is pursing an 
acting career. Others will tell you the <LOCATION>Padres</LOCATION>, because of the city. And some 
will say the Cardinals, with their spacious ballpark. 
</P>
<P>
"All I can tell you is that he wants to play for a contender," <PERSON>Tellem</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Said <PERSON>McKeon</PERSON>: "I just hope it's us." 
</P>
<P>
Before the Padres begin negotiations with <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, however, they hope to have 
their own free-agent pitcher -- left-handed reliever <PERSON>Mark Davis</PERSON> -- under 
contract. 
</P>
<P>
The Padres made a new proposal to <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, offering him a guaranteed 
three-year contract, sources said, for about <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY>. It would give <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> 
the most lucrative contract on the club, exceeding the <MONEY>$5.25 million</MONEY> for three 
years obtained last <DATE>December</DATE> by free-agent starter <PERSON>Bruce Hurst</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
This was the third offer the Padres have made to <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> since the season's 
conclusion, the second since <DATE>Oct. 30</DATE>, when <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> filed for free agency. It was 
made after <PERSON>Alan Hendricks</PERSON>, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON>' agent, telephoned Lane on <DATE>Friday</DATE> and said 
that they were looking for an increase from the <ORGANIZATION>Padres</ORGANIZATION>' last proposal. 
</P>
<P>
"He called me, and he stated their position," <PERSON>Lane</PERSON> said, "and I stated our 
position. I then gave them a new proposal, and he said he will get back to me." 
</P>
<P>
Is Lane optimistic that <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> will accept the offer? 
</P>
<P>
"No," he said. 
</P>
<P>
"Frankly, I don't think they're going to do anything unless <PERSON>Mark</PERSON> decided 
they're going to do something. I don't think there's any reason for them not to 
take our proposal, but I still think they're inclined to wait." 
</P>
<P>
Teams can begin negotiations with free agents at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> (PST) <DATE>Monday</DATE>. Davis 
will be in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> that day to receive his trophy as the Rolaids relief 
pitcher of the year in the <ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Hendricks</PERSON> said he is sure there 
will be plenty of interest. 
</P>
<P>
But of the 84 players who have filed for free agency, no one figures to be paid 
as handsomely as <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>. Although his 86-76 career record hardly is dazzling, 
this is a pitcher who led the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> in strikeouts for three seasons 
while playing for the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners</ORGANIZATION>, who have never had a winning season. 
</P>
<P>
Langston was traded by the <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> on <DATE>May 25</DATE> after rejecting a 
three-year, <MONEY>$7.1-million</MONEY> contract. He was 12-9 with a 2.39 ERA in four months 
with the <LOCATION>Expos</LOCATION>, but when they attempted to sign him, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> reportedly turned 
down a three-year, <MONEY>$9 million</MONEY> contract. 
</P>
<P>
So just how much will it cost the Padres to sign <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> now? 
</P>
<P>
"I don't know," <PERSON>Lane</PERSON> said, "that's what we're about to find out." 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA052989-0062 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 63382 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 29, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 11; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
617 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NATIONAL LEAGUE ROUNDUP; 
</P>
<P>
LANGSTON SOLID IN DEBUT FOR EXPOS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAN HAFNER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> was one of the best pitchers in the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> when he 
worked for the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners</ORGANIZATION>, but he often expressed dissatisfaction with 
the way he was treated there, and had requested a trade. 
</P>
<P>
Langston, who was acquired by the <ORGANIZATION>Montreal Expos</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> for three pitching 
prospects, made his <ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> debut <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, and both he and 
the Expos were pleased. 
</P>
<P>
The hard-throwing left-hander, who led the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> in strikeouts three 
times, struck out 12 in eight innings and pitched the Expos to a 10-2 victory. 
</P>
<P>
Langston, who didn't get a chance to hit at <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> because of the designated 
hitter rule, also showed he knew how to handle a bat. He singled and drove in a 
run in the eighth. In his eight innings, he yielded only four hits and one 
earned run. 
</P>
<P>
"It felt like my major league debut," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said. "Having been around awhile 
helped block out things. I definitely feel a part of this team already. I was 
afraid I might go out there and get bombed." 
</P>
<P>
The Expos made <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> feel welcome with a fine display of hitting. <PERSON>Tim Raines</PERSON> 
hit a three-run homer in the fifth inning to give him a 6-0 lead. <PERSON>Tim Wallach</PERSON> 
had three doubles and drove in three runs. 
</P>
<P>
Maybe the offensive explosion will make it a little easier to sign <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, 
who is eligible to become a free agent at the end of the season. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Francisco 8</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 5 -- Even a long hitting slump doesn't prevent 
the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> from scoring runs when <PERSON>Rick Reuschel</PERSON> pitches. 
</P>
<P>
Reuschel, 40, became the first nine-game winner in the majors although he 
lasted only 5 1/3 innings and the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> managed just four hits at <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
One of the hits was a grand slam by <PERSON>Will Clark</PERSON> in the fourth inning, and from 
then on it was downhill for the right-hander. 
</P>
<P>
The Giants matched their hit total by committing four errors, making two of the 
four runs <PERSON>Reuschel</PERSON> (9-2) allowed unearned. 
</P>
<P>
Houston 9, <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 2 -- If <DATE>today</DATE> wasn't Memorial Day, the Pirates would 
probably have declared it a holiday, anyway, because <PERSON>Glenn Davis</PERSON> finally left 
town. 
</P>
<P>
The Astros' first baseman just about destroyed the Pirates' pitching staff over 
the weekend. 
</P>
<P>
Davis hit a home run in each game to lead <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> to a three-game sweep. His 
three-run homer in the fifth inning in this one gave <PERSON>Mike Scott</PERSON> a 6-2 lead and 
it was a romp. 
</P>
<P>
He hit a two-run homer in the third inning of <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s 4-2 victory. 
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, he hit a dramatic two-run home run with two out in the ninth to tie 
the game and the Astros won in the 12th, 5-4. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Davis</PERSON>, who has 12 home runs this season, has a lifetime average of .347 against 
the Pirates. 
</P>
<P>
Scott (7-3) went a strong six innings to beat the Pirates for the fourth time 
in a row. 
</P>
<P>
Chicago 6, <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 1 -- <PERSON>Mike Bielecki</PERSON> missed out on his shutout at <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, 
but he accomplished his primary goal -- beating the Reds. 
</P>
<P>
The Reds had a 5-0 record against the right-hander, but except for the 
hot-hitting <PERSON>Chris Sabo</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bielecki</PERSON> had everyone under control. 
</P>
<P>
Bielecki went the distance, giving up seven hits to improve his record to 4-2. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sabo</PERSON>, after a brilliant start in <DATE>1988</DATE> as a rookie, cooled off and didn't hit a 
homer from early <DATE>July</DATE> to the end of the season. 
</P>
<P>
He didn't show much power at the start of this season. But, when he spoiled 
<PERSON>Bielecki</PERSON>'s shutout with a homer in the eighth, it gave him four in the last 
five games. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>St. Louis 3</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 3 (tie) -- It rained so hard at <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> in the bottom of 
the 10th that the field was unplayable and the game was called. It will be 
replayed in its entirety, but all the statistics count. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Pedro Guerrero</PERSON>, hitting .360 with men in scoring position, hit a two-run homer 
and a run-scoring single to give the Cardinals a 3-0 lead. DAN <PERSON>HAFNER</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mark Langston delivers a pitch Sunday against Padres in San Diego. He 
won and also had 12 strikeouts. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051089-0152 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 55554 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 10, 1989, Wednesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part A; Page 8; Column 3; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
184 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LANGSTON GOES 8 WITHOUT A HIT, THEN LOSES 3-2 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
TORONTO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Blue Jays</ORGANIZATION>, held hitless for eight innings by <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON>, 
rallied for three runs in the ninth <DATE>today</DATE> and beat the <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> 3-2, with 
<PERSON>George Bell</PERSON> driving in the winning run with a bloop single off reliever <PERSON>Mike 
Schooler</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Langston had shackled the <ORGANIZATION>Blue Jays</ORGANIZATION> through the first eight innings, allowing 
only one baserunner, on shortstop <PERSON>Omar Vizquel</PERSON>'s error in the seventh. 
</P>
<P>
But in the ninth, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> unraveled quickly. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Tom Lawless</PERSON>, pinch-hitting for <PERSON>Lloyd Moseby</PERSON>, led off the inning with a solid 
single to center, ending <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>'s chance to become the first <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> pitcher 
to hurl a no-hitter. 
</P>
<P>
After <PERSON>Nelson Liriano</PERSON> sacrificed Lawless to second, <PERSON>Bob Brenly</PERSON>, batting for <PERSON>Rob 
Ducey</PERSON>, doubled down the left field line, scoring Lawless and ending <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>'s 
shutout. 
</P>
<P>
Junior Felix then tied the score 2-2 with an <ORGANIZATION>RBI</ORGANIZATION> single to center, driving in 
pinch-runner <PERSON>Alexis Infante</PERSON>. Felix went to second on the throw to the plate, 
and <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> was replaced by Schooler. 
</P>
<P>
Schooler retired <PERSON>Kelly Gruber</PERSON> on a grounder to third and intentionally walked 
<PERSON>Tony Fernandez</PERSON> to pitch to the slumping <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mark Langston 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA071289-0084 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 81142 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 12, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part 6; Page 2; Column 3; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
604 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PROTEST FROM POET'S ESTATE KEEPS FILM OUT OF GAY FESTIVAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DOUGLAS SADOWNICK 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Larry Horne</PERSON> could hardly contain his excitement at <DATE>last winter</DATE>'s <LOCATION>Berlin Gay</LOCATION> and 
Lesbian Film Festival when he saw "Looking for Langston," director <PERSON>Isaac 
Julien</PERSON>'s study of homosexuality during the <ORGANIZATION>Harlem Renaissance</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I considered it the first black gay feature film ever made," said <PERSON>Horne</PERSON>, the 
director and founder of the seventh <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> International Gay and Lesbian 
Film and <ORGANIZATION>Video Festival</ORGANIZATION>, which runs through <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Directors Guild of 
America Theater</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>West Hollywood</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Horne</PERSON>, who has shown all of the London-based <PERSON>Julien</PERSON>'s previous films, had 
decided to open the festival with "Looking for Langston," which deals with 
intimate bonds between gay blacks and whites. <PERSON>Langston Hughes</PERSON>' poetry is 
presented as a voice-over in parts of the movie. The black poet died in <DATE>1967</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"It would set the tone," <PERSON>Horne</PERSON> proclaimed, "of a festival that was shaped along 
the themes of multi-culturalism." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Horne</PERSON>'s dream recently fell apart when <PERSON>Ada Griffin</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>New 
York-based Third World Newsreel</ORGANIZATION>, the distributor of "Langston," called and 
demanded that he not show the film. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> estate sent a cease-and-desist letter to <PERSON>Julien</PERSON> in mid-June 
informing him that he would put <PERSON>Griffin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Horne</PERSON>'s festival and himself in legal 
jeopardy if the film were screened. 
</P>
<P>
The cause for the crisis? Julien had secured the rights to quote <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON>' poetry 
in the film, but only for use in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. ("Langston" already has been shown on 
"Out on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>," a gay series on <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Channel 4.) 
</P>
<P>
But according to <PERSON>Griffin</PERSON>, film maker <PERSON>Julien</PERSON> apparently wasn't aware of the 
resistance he would meet from the "black bourgeoisie" who, she feels, "see 
Hughes as a racial icon." 
</P>
<P>
"They (the estate) were appalled at any inference that <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> might have been a 
homosexual and they wanted all mentions of him out," said <PERSON>Griffin</PERSON> from her <LOCATION>New 
York</LOCATION> office. 
</P>
<P>
Hughes' sexuality has long been debated among academics. Lately, an acclaimed 
biography of <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON>' life by <PERSON>Arnold Rampersad</PERSON>, published by <ORGANIZATION>Oxford University 
Press</ORGANIZATION>, was unable to confirm that <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> was homosexual. 
</P>
<P>
However, the editors of "Gay and Lesbian Poetry of Our Time," published by <ORGANIZATION>St. 
Martin's Press</ORGANIZATION>, included four poems by <ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION> in their anthology. 
</P>
<P>
Why the fuss then about "Langston"? 
</P>
<P>
According to <PERSON>Horne</PERSON>, "the power of celluloid is formidable, even if we're 
talking independent art films -- which is why I wanted to program this festival 
along multicultural themes." 
</P>
<P>
For <PERSON>Horne</PERSON>'s part, "the absence of 'Langston' doesn't necessarily detract from 
the festival." Rather, he says that "the mess" points out how "much we still 
need gay and lesbian film festivals." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Julien</PERSON>, who was contacted at his <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> production company, SanKoFa, seemed to 
take the pulling of the film from the festival in stride. 
</P>
<P>
"The Hughes estate had four major points of contention: that we delete all of 
<PERSON>Hughes</PERSON>' poetry, all mention of the estate in the credits of the film and all 
excerpts of Hughes reading his poetry on <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> television, as well as pay for the 
estate's legal expenses in suing us. 
</P>
<P>
"We will delete the poetry," <PERSON>Julien</PERSON> said. "I want the film to get shown -- and 
the film isn't so much about <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> as it's about 'looking' for cultural pride. 
</P>
<P>
"But I will not comply with deleting the <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> footage because that is part of 
the public domain. And even though we are trying our best to act in good faith 
with the estate, we will not go so far as to pay for their expenses." 
</P>
<P>
Officials from <ORGANIZATION>Harold Ober Associates</ORGANIZATION>, an agency that represents the <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> 
estate, refused to comment on the legal or social implications of their 
cease-and-desist letter when questioned by <ORGANIZATION>The Times</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MOTION PICTURES; COMPLAINTS; PROPERTY RIGHTS; DOCUMENTARIES; HUGHES, LANGSTON; 
FESTIVALS; HOMOSEXUALS; HORNE, LARRY; JULIEN, ISAAC 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA120189-0154 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 142473 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 1, 1989, Friday, Orange County P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 1; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
216 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LOCAL; 
</P>
<P>
ANGELS SIGN PITCHER LANGSTON TO 5-YEAR, $16-MILLION CONTRACT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Service Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In a bold move sure to send the skyrocketing price of baseball free agents even 
higher, the Angels today signed <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> to a five-year contract worth <MONEY>$16 
million</MONEY>, making the 29-year-old left-hander the game's highest paid player. 
(Details, Page P10) 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, who had a combined 16-14 record with the <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> and Expos last 
season, got the longest contract awarded a player since the mid-1980s. Only 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Rickey Henderson</PERSON> broke the <MONEY>$3-million</MONEY> contract barrier when he 
re-signed with the World Champion Oakland A's for <MONEY>$12 million</MONEY> over four years. 
That was the first contract of that length since <DATE>October, 1985</DATE>, when <PERSON>Ken 
Oberkfell</PERSON> signed a four-year, <MONEY>$3-million</MONEY> agreement with the <LOCATION>Atlanta Braves</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
This off-season, which promises to be the busiest free-agent market ever, has 
seen <PERSON>Bryn Smith</PERSON> leave <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> to sign a <MONEY>$6-million</MONEY>, three-year deal with the 
<ORGANIZATION>St. Louis Cardinals</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Kirby Puckett</PERSON> re-sign with the <LOCATION>Minnesota Twins</LOCATION> for <MONEY>$9 
million</MONEY> over three years and <PERSON>Pascual Perez</PERSON> sign with the <ORGANIZATION>New York Yankees</ORGANIZATION> for 
<MONEY>$5.7 million</MONEY> for three years. 
</P>
<P>
Langston, a native of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, had held discussions with the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> and 
Yankees before signing with the already pitching-rich Angels. The staff last 
season had a collective earned-run average of 3.28, second-best in the <ORGANIZATION>American 
League</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mark Langston 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA052989-0026 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 63292 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 29, 1989, Monday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 1; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1002 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LANGSTON SHUTS DOWN PADRES IN HIS EXPO DEBUT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BOB WOLF 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Ever since <DATE>last winter</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Padres</LOCATION> had longed for the day when <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> 
would pitch at <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Jack Murphy Stadium</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
That day finally came <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, but <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> was wearing the wrong uniform. 
</P>
<P>
The Padres had done all they could to acquire the left-handed <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, 28, who 
had been placed on sale by the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners</ORGANIZATION> because his <MONEY>$1.3-million-a-year</MONEY> 
contract will run out at the end of the season. But he wound up with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Montreal Expos</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a deal for three young pitchers, and the Padres 
suffered the additional indignity of being the first <ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> team to 
face him. 
</P>
<P>
The 10-2 score by which the Expos humiliated the Padres only began to tell how 
dominant <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> was. He pitched one-hit ball for six innings, and didn't give 
up a run until his working margin had reached 8-0. He left after eight innings 
with a four-hitter and 12 strikeouts, and one of the two <LOCATION>Padre</LOCATION> runs was 
unearned. 
</P>
<P>
Granted, the <LOCATION>Padres</LOCATION> did a lot to embarrass themselves in front of a packed 
house of 48,023, lured in large measure by a postgame concert by the Beach 
Boys. 
</P>
<P>
The pitching of <PERSON>Eric Show</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dave Leiper</PERSON> was a perfect match for the <ORGANIZATION>Padres</ORGANIZATION>' 
anemic hitting, and <PERSON>Leiper</PERSON> made a terrible situation worse with a throw to 
third base following a rundown that ranked with the wildest on record. 
</P>
<P>
Even a member of the <LOCATION>Padre</LOCATION> coaching staff got into the act. <PERSON>Sandy Alomar Sr.</PERSON>, 
directing traffic at third base, put a fitting finish to the lamentable 
performance by sending <PERSON>Carmelo Martinez</PERSON> home from second base on <PERSON>Tim Flannery</PERSON>'s 
single with the Padres eight runs behind. Martinez was an easy game-ending out. 
</P>
<P>
Afterward, <PERSON>Martinez</PERSON> summed things up by saying, "I hope the Beach Boys put on a 
better show." 
</P>
<P>
As <PERSON>Martinez</PERSON> suspected, the <DATE>second half of the doubleheader</DATE> was far more 
entertaining than the baseball game. Still, anyone with a keen eye for pitching 
had to be impressed by <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>. And anyone with the <ORGANIZATION>Padres</ORGANIZATION>' interests at heart 
had to wonder how good they would be if they had landed him. 
</P>
<P>
From the time <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> reached an impasse in contract negotiations with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION>, he had been the object of a manhunt that spread over both major 
leagues. Since he could have become a free agent this <DATE>fall</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> 
couldn't wait to unload him. 
</P>
<P>
Of course, the <ORGANIZATION>Expos</ORGANIZATION> will lose <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> if they can't sign him, but as Manager 
<PERSON>Buck Rodgers</PERSON> put it, "We're going for it in <DATE>'89</DATE>. Anything after that will be a 
bonus." 
</P>
<P>
Since <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> is a native of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> -- he moved to <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> at the age 
of 4 -- and has expressed displeasure over going to <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, there is still 
hope among Padre diehards that he will come here eventually. However, <LOCATION>Padre</LOCATION> 
Manager <PERSON>Jack McKeon</PERSON> is not among the optimists. 
</P>
<P>
"I have to think that if they're trying to win a pennant, he'll be with them 
quite a while," <PERSON>McKeon</PERSON> said. "Maybe if they're out of the race by <DATE>September</DATE>, we 
might see another deal, but I doubt if that will happen." 
</P>
<P>
Of all people, the only <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> player to get a hit off Langston in the first 
six innings was Show. The <LOCATION>Padre</LOCATION> pitcher took advantage of one of <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>'s few 
mistakes by lining a double to right field in the third. 
</P>
<P>
Even on that count, though, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> had the last laugh. This was the first 
time he had ever batted in the majors because of the designated-hitter rule 
used in the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION>. And he got the first hit of his career -- also his 
first run batted in -- in his fourth and last time at bat. It was a single to 
center off <PERSON>Leiper</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"That hit definitely made my day," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said. "It was a pretty wild 
experience. It looked pretty ugly. I was just trying to put the ball in play. 
Now I can put it on my mantel." 
</P>
<P>
Langston is a switch-hitter, and his hit came on his first swing batting 
right-handed. 
</P>
<P>
As for his pitching, he said, "I was really excited to be with a new team and 
with a big crowd. The guys went right out and scored some runs, so I could take 
a deep breath. We got the crowd out of it real early. It was my job to keep 
them out." 
</P>
<P>
Langston probably could have finished without difficulty, but he said, "I was 
getting a little tired. I really didn't want to pitch the ninth, because I 
don't like to go over 130 pitches (He threw 138). If it had been a close game, 
it would have been different." 
</P>
<P>
Rodgers offered a second reason for calling in closer <PERSON>Tim Burke</PERSON>, who has nine 
saves, to finish the game." 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Burke</PERSON> hadn't worked in almost a week," <PERSON>Rodgers</PERSON> said. "I wanted to give him an 
inning to keep him sharp." 
</P>
<P>
Show (6-5) was gunning for a <LOCATION>Padre</LOCATION> record of 93 victories -- he is tied with 
<PERSON>Randy Jones</PERSON> -- but it became apparent in a hurry that he wasn't going to get 
it. He yielded one run in the second and two in the fourth, then served up a 
three-run homer to <PERSON>Tim Raines</PERSON> in the fifth. By that time, the frustrated fans 
were booing loudly and often. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Tim Wallach</PERSON> was the Expos' big bomber, tying a club record with three doubles. 
</P>
<P>
How good was Langston? Just ask some of the Padres. 
</P>
<P>
Flannery is a left-handed hitter who normally plays only against right-handed 
pitchers. But he was pressed into service because of <PERSON>Randy Ready</PERSON>'s leg injury, 
and looked back on it as quite an experience. 
</P>
<P>
"Any left-hander is tough for me," <PERSON>Flannery</PERSON> said. "Even <PERSON>Jimmy Allen</PERSON>, our 
batting-practice pitcher, gives me trouble. But <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> is one of the toughest 
I've ever seen. He's always ahead of you, so you're always hitting 
defensively." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jack Clark</PERSON> said, "He's like a left-handed <PERSON>Dwight Gooden</PERSON>. He's a great pitcher 
-- not a good one, a great one." 
</P>
<P>
Padre Notes 
</P>
<P>
The 10 runs scored by the Expos set a season record for <ORGANIZATION>Padre</ORGANIZATION> opponents. The 
previous high was nine. Said Padre Manager <PERSON>Jack McKeon</PERSON>: "This was our first 
blowout all year." It came on the first anniversary of <PERSON>McKeon</PERSON>'s debut as 
manager after the firing of <PERSON>Larry Bowa</PERSON>. . . . Expo Manager <PERSON>Buck Rodgers</PERSON> said 
the trade for <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> couldn't have been made but for a surplus of talent 
in the <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> farm system. "It's a tribute to our scouting and farm 
department that we've developed players other clubs want." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101389-0095 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 120031 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 13, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 2; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1151 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LANGSTON FINDS THE LOCAL AREA ATTRACTIVE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ROSS NEWHAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A whirlwind trip to <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> this week only seemed to confirm <PERSON>Mark 
Langston</PERSON>'s feelings that he would like to make <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> a more 
permanent stop when he leaves the <ORGANIZATION>Montreal Expos</ORGANIZATION> soon as a free-agent pitcher. 
</P>
<P>
An amateur musician who plays a number of instruments -- "and is master of 
none" -- Langston satisfied those interests <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by jamming with a good 
friend, pop star <PERSON>Bruce Hornsby</PERSON>, in the garage of <ORGANIZATION>Hornsby</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Encino</LOCATION> home. 
</P>
<P>
And that night, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> watched the Kings play the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Islanders at the 
Forum, then met <PERSON>Wayne Gretzky</PERSON>, who brightened the moment for Langston by 
telling the pitcher that he was one of the first players <PERSON>Gretzky</PERSON> picked for his 
rotisserie league team. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Gretzky</PERSON> didn't say how his team did, but he could soon be rooting for <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION> 
on a home-team basis. 
</P>
<P>
"I wouldn't mind that at all," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when asked about the 
possibility of pitching for <ORGANIZATION>Gretzky</ORGANIZATION>'s hometown <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION>. "He would be a great 
guy to pal around with." 
</P>
<P>
A budding friendship isn't the only attraction for Langston in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, but 
neither is he closing the door on other possibilities. 
</P>
<P>
Eligible to file for free agency on the day after the World Series and having 
already rejected a three-year, <MONEY>$9-million</MONEY> offer from the <LOCATION>Expos</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said 
he has eight teams in mind. 
</P>
<P>
They are the five <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> teams plus the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Cubs</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>St. Louis Cardinals</LOCATION> 
and <ORGANIZATION>New York Yankees</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said it is too early to rank the eight or pinpoint preferences, but he 
does favor <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>, meaning the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION>, Angels or <LOCATION>San Diego 
Padres</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Agent <PERSON>Arn Tellem</PERSON> said he expects <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> to emerge as baseball's highest-paid 
pitcher and player -- if only on the basis of competitive bidding and economic 
appreciation since <PERSON>Orel Hershiser</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> signed his three-year, 
<MONEY>$7.9-million</MONEY> contract last <DATE>winter</DATE>, and <PERSON>Frank Viola</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Minnesota Twins</LOCATION> 
matched it in <DATE>April</DATE> before his trade to the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mets. 
</P>
<P>
Asked, however, if the threat of a labor lockout or strike might not depress a 
market in which Langston looms as the most attractive commodity, <PERSON>Tellem</PERSON> shook 
his head and said: "For Mark and the other top free agents, I think it will be 
a very active market. I think the clubs will look on it as a window of 
opportunity, a chance to grab the top players before the labor problems develop 
next <DATE>spring</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
Langston, who made <MONEY>$1.3 million</MONEY> this season, said his decision will be based on 
baseball and financial considerations, the most important aspect being the 
competitiveness of the club. The <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION>, Angels and Padres satisfy that 
criterion, he said. 
</P>
<P>
"I want to be on a contending club, a club that has a chance to win," he said. 
"I really feel that if the Expos had won, it would have left a different taste 
with me. 
</P>
<P>
"That's not to say I've ruled out the possibility of re-signing with the Expos, 
but I would have definitely been more interested if we had won." 
</P>
<P>
Langston, a 29-year-old left-hander who led the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> in strikeouts 
in three of his five seasons with the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners</ORGANIZATION>, was traded to the Expos 
on <DATE>May 25</DATE> and compiled an overall record of 16-14, winning 10 of his first 13 
decisions with <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> before losing six of his last eight, thanks in large 
part to illness, injury and lack of support. 
</P>
<P>
His earned-run average of 2.39 was the <ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION>'s third best, and his 
overall strikeout total of 235 in 250 innings was second in the majors to <PERSON>Nolan 
Ryan</PERSON>'s 301. 
</P>
<P>
Langston has pitched 225 innings or more in each of his six seasons except 
<DATE>1985</DATE>, when he had an elbow injury. And while pitching for the hapless <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> 
in the confining <LOCATION>Kingdome</LOCATION>, he won 19 of his team's 78 games in <DATE>1987</DATE> and 15 of 
his team's 68 in <DATE>1988</DATE>. His 17 wins in <DATE>1984</DATE> were the most by a rookie 
left-hander since <PERSON>Gary Peters</PERSON> won 19 for the <DATE>1963</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Chicago White Sox</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Expos, pursuing a "win now" philosophy, traded three young pitchers for 
<LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>, knowing he might leave at the end of the season. <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said he was 
treated well by <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> fans and looked at his future in that city with an 
open mind -- at least until the final six weeks of a season in which he thought 
the Expos were rolling toward a division title. 
</P>
<P>
"It was as if someone pulled the plug," he said. "Everything crumbled and I 
don't know why. We lost seven in a row to the Cubs and Mets and I still had an 
open mind, but I wanted to see how we rebounded and we never did. The situation 
kept getting worse." 
</P>
<P>
The Expos could be devastated now by the departure of several free agents, 
including <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hubie Brooks</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Both are Californians who want to return, although <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, who grew up in 
<LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>, said he will maintain his winter home in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, no matter where 
he signs. 
</P>
<P>
"Being from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, there would be a nice sense of coming home," he said. 
"And I've always felt that when you step on the field in <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> or at <LOCATION>Dodger 
Stadium</LOCATION>, there's a feeling that this is what the big leagues are all about. 
Plus, you don't hear a lot of negative things from the stands like you do in 
other parks. The fans come to be entertained, and generally are. The quality of 
the organizations speaks for itself." 
</P>
<P>
Langston's wife, <PERSON>Michelle</PERSON>, has studied acting, and <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said he has 
relatives in the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> area with whom he gets together two or three times a 
winter to attend basketball and hockey games in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"We've always had fun here. We've always felt very comfortable here," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Does he have a preference to leagues? 
</P>
<P>
"I really enjoyed the <ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> because I like to participate," he said. 
"I like to bat and run the bases. It brought back some boyhood memories. I even 
broke up a double play against the <ORGANIZATION>Cardinals</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Jose Oquendo</PERSON> asked if I was all 
right, and I just laughed. It was fun again. 
</P>
<P>
"But I could also make an easy adjustment to the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION>. I spent five 
years there. I know the league very well. I really don't think the question of 
leagues will be a major issue." 
</P>
<P>
There is speculation that it will be, that aside from participating more in the 
<ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> likes the idea of pitching to a lineup devoid of a 
designated hitter in a league where pitchers work fewer innings because they 
are apt to give way to pinch hitters. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Fred Claire</PERSON>, executive vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION>, refused to discuss 
<PERSON>Langston</PERSON> because of tampering restrictions. Sources close to the club believe 
<PERSON>Claire</PERSON> will pursue <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> as he did <PERSON>Dave Righetti</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gary Gaetti</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Signing Langston would allow Claire to trade a young pitcher -- <PERSON>John Wetteland</PERSON>, 
perhaps -- for a center fielder. 
</P>
<P>
The Angels view <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> in a similar manner. "When you consider what we were 
prepared to pay <PERSON>Bruce Hurst</PERSON> and <PERSON>Nolan Ryan</PERSON> <DATE>last winter</DATE>, I'm confident we will 
be in the bidding for <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>," a club executive said. "We had a surprisingly 
good season but realize we have to build on it. We can't stand pat, 
particularly when you consider the quality of the opposition." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, LANGSTON VISITS Montreal Expo left-hander Mark Langston, soon to become 
a free agent, visited Los Angeles this week. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BASEBALL TEAMS; SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA; LANGSTON, MARK; BASEBALL PLAYERS; FREE 
AGENTS (SPORTS); MONTREAL EXPOS (BASEBALL TEAM); LOS ANGELES DODGERS (BASEBALL 
TEAM); CALIFORNIA ANGELS (BASEBALL TEAM) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA120389-0237 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 143832 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 3, 1989, Sunday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 6; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
761 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MIKE PENNER: LANGSTON MAKES THE MIND RACE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Mike Penner 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A million for your thoughts? 
</P>
<P>
When it comes to <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> and the Angels, we have 16 more . . . 
</P>
<P>
1. <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> combined, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> was 16-14 for <DATE>1989</DATE>. Ten years 
earlier, <PERSON>Nolan Ryan</PERSON> had the same record for the Angels -- and all that got him 
was a new uniform and <PERSON>Buzzie Bavasi</PERSON>'s immortal epithet: "We can replace him 
with a couple of 8-7 pitchers." 
</P>
<P>
2. <PERSON>Mike Witt</PERSON> was also a 16-14 free agent in <DATE>1987</DATE> before the Angels decided to 
keep their <PERSON>Witt</PERSON> about them for two more years. Total price tag: <MONEY>$2.8 million</MONEY> -- 
or about what <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> will have cleared by next <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
3. The inflation, of course, is insane, but would any of this have been 
necessary if <PERSON>Bavasi</PERSON> had deemed Ryan worth keeping in <DATE>1979</DATE>? As they used to say 
in the commercial, you can pay me now . . . or you can pay me later. 
</P>
<P>
4. In <DATE>1990</DATE>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> will bid to become the first Angel pitcher to lead the 
league in strikeouts since you-know-who in <DATE>1979</DATE>. Langston's main challenger? 
You know who. 
</P>
<P>
5. The Angels have just about cornered the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> market on 
left-handed starting pitchers. In <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Chuck Finley</PERSON>, they have the two 
best. And in a few years, <PERSON>Jim Abbott</PERSON> could make it a top-three sweep. 
</P>
<P>
6. Then again, we know about the Angels' luck with free-agent pitchers. <PERSON>Bruce 
Kison</PERSON>, the first attempt at replacing <PERSON>Ryan</PERSON>, was 3-6 in <DATE>1980</DATE>. <PERSON>John D'Acquisto</PERSON> 
was 0-0 with a 10.71 ERA in <DATE>1981</DATE>. Bill <ORGANIZATION>Travers</ORGANIZATION> was 0-3 with a 5.91 ERA in <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Frank LaCorte</PERSON> was 1-2 with a 7.06 ERA in <DATE>1984</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Five years later, the Angels finally worked up enough courage to try it again. 
And, they needed every minute. 
</P>
<P>
7. Did somebody mention rotator cuff? Not funny, not funny at all. 
</P>
<P>
8. That's the number of games the Angels finished behind <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> last season. 
In <DATE>1989</DATE>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> won seven more games than the man he might replace in the 
Angel rotation, <PERSON>Mike Witt</PERSON>. Still not enough. 
</P>
<P>
9. But the gap could continue to narrow this week in <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>, this year's 
site for baseball's winter swap meet. Does the name <PERSON>Joe Carter</PERSON> ring a bell? If 
the Angels are unable to pull a new-age <PERSON>Robin Hood</PERSON> on <PERSON>Robin Yount</PERSON> -- take from 
the rich and give to the rich -- look for the Angels to zero in on the 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> hammer, the <PERSON>Jose Canseco</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>. Minus the hotline. 
</P>
<P>
With <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> in tow, the Angels finally have some cards to play. But with 
<LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> reportedly offering <PERSON>Mike Greenwell</PERSON>, straight-up, for <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>, the Indians 
aren't likely to settle for any discards. A starting pitcher -- say, <PERSON>Witt</PERSON> or 
<PERSON>Kirk McCaskill</PERSON> -- and a regular player -- maybe even <PERSON>Devon White</PERSON> -- may have to 
go. 
</P>
<P>
Heavy-duty stuff, yes. But with <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>, the Angels are allowed the luxury of 
thinking big for the first time in a long time. 
</P>
<P>
10. First <PERSON>Bert Blyleven</PERSON> and now <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>. If the Angels can't beat 'em, the 
plan is to take 'em out of circulation. 
</P>
<P>
Before his mid-summer trade from <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> was 2-0 against 
the Angels last season -- including a 7-0 shutout in <LOCATION>Abbott</LOCATION>'s big league debut. 
That duplicated <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>'s record against <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in <DATE>1988</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
But now, the only time Angel hitters will have to face <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION> is during 
batting practice at spring training. For the next five years that much is 
guaranteed. Somewhere, <PERSON>Jack Howell</PERSON> is sleeping easier. 
</P>
<P>
11. OK, let's stack them up. The Athletics' top five starters vs. the Angels' 
top five. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Dave Stewart</PERSON> vs. Langston? Push. <PERSON>Mike Moore</PERSON> vs. <PERSON>Finley</PERSON>? Slight edge to A's. <PERSON>Bob 
Welch</PERSON> vs. <PERSON>Blyleven</PERSON>? Slight edge to Angels. Storm <PERSON>Davis vs. McCaskill</PERSON>? Solid 
edge to Angels. <PERSON>Todd Burns</PERSON> vs. Abbott? Edge to Angels again. 
</P>
<P>
This being a happy time for the Angels, we'll save the outfield and infield 
matchups for later. 
</P>
<P>
12. Langston's number with the <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> and the Expos. With the <LOCATION>Angels</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Doug 
Rader</PERSON> wears it. Wonder who's going to have to give it up? 
</P>
<P>
13. <PERSON>Lance Parrish</PERSON>'s number. Don't forget him, <PERSON>Mike Port</PERSON>. Langston's a nice new 
toy, but in this case, a battery is not necessarily included. 
</P>
<P>
14. Finally, the Angels got an arm up on the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION>. In the only Freeway 
Series that matters, the Angels swept aside their inferiority complex to the 
north and won the <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION> sweepstakes in a walk. Port 1, <PERSON>Fred Claire 0</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
15. Wonder what <PERSON>Wally Joyner</PERSON> thinks about those <MONEY>16 million dollars</MONEY>. Two more 
years and <PERSON>Wally</PERSON> gets to go for the free-agent gold. And he's in the lineup 
every day. 
</P>
<P>
16. Will the last pitcher out of <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> please take the flag? First <PERSON>Pascual 
Perez</PERSON>, then <PERSON>Bryn Smith</PERSON> and now Langston -- all in one week. Is there anyone 
left in the <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> rotation? <PERSON>John Candelaria</PERSON>? <PERSON>Kevin Gross</PERSON>? <PERSON>Steve Rogers</PERSON>? 
</P>
<P>
Now we know why they're called the Ex-pos. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mark Langston finds himself between two reporters Friday at Bellevue, 
Wash., home after agreeing to a five-year, $16-million contract. Associated 
Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
LANGSTON, MARK; BASEBALL PLAYERS -- WAGES AND SALARIES; CALIFORNIA ANGELS 
(BASEBALL TEAM) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06191220 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06191220 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mark Langston  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BASEBALL; PROFESSIONAL; SO-CALIF.; CHAMPIONSHIP; GAME; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mark Langston will not be the American League's starting pitcher tonight at
the SkyDome, which is just fine with him. After what he went through last
year, just being an All-Star is enough.;    The former San Jose State pitcher
1990 season. He went 10-17, and although the Angels scored only 18 runs in
those losses, he was seen as another free-agent flop.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  AFTER BEING LABELED A BUST, LANGSTON ENJOYS
BOOM YEAR  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  All-Star Game Preview  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     After this half-season, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> has begun to justify the expenditure. He
is 12-3, winning two more games than he ever had by an All-Star break. He has
pitched into the seventh inning or later in 15 of his past 17 starts and has
teamed with <PERSON>Chuck Finley</PERSON> to lead <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> into contention. Why the dramatic
change?;    "Just having a very good team to play for has helped," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>
said <DATE>Monday</DATE>. "We have a different team than last year. We have <PERSON>Dave Winfield</PERSON>
for a whole year, <PERSON>Wally Joyner</PERSON> is healthy and doing well, and we picked up
<PERSON>Gary Gaetti</PERSON> at third base.;    "Defensively, we're extremely sound. We have
the bats to keep us close, and the bullpen, with (All-Star teammate) <PERSON>Bryan
Harvey</PERSON>, has been outstanding. That's all helped.";    <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> spent most of
his career as a bright spot on a bad <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> team. He made the All-Star team
in <DATE>1987</DATE>, finishing that season with 262 strikeouts in 272 innings. He was
traded to <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> in <DATE>May 1989</DATE> for <PERSON>Randy Johnson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Brian Holman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gene
Harris</PERSON>, and he bolted for big money and a big market after that season.;   
<PERSON>Langston</PERSON> began his Angels career by teaming with <PERSON>Mike Witt</PERSON> to throw a
no-hitter, but it went all downhill from there. "I lost four games in a row,
2-1," he said. "Then I got beat around pretty badly and lost confidence. I had
made my living being an offensive, aggressive pitcher, and I lost that. I
tried to pick my spots, and I fell behind in counts.";    Through it all,
<PERSON>Langston</PERSON> never threw so much as a tantrum. He never kicked a water cooler. "To
me, he's an All-Star two years in a row," Angels Manager <PERSON>Doug Rader</PERSON> said. "Not
necessarily from a performance standpoint, but from a character standpoint."; 
  Longtime rival <PERSON>Kirby Puckett</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> said of Langston: "There's nothing
any different about him that I've seen. You just try to make him get the ball
down.";    <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> and <PERSON>Finley</PERSON> each have 12 victories, tying <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Scott
Erickson</PERSON> for the league lead. At this rate, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> could have his first
20-win season. He won 19 games in <DATE>'87</DATE>, a <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> record.;    "You can win 30
games, but if your team doesn't get into the playoffs, it doesn't really
matter," he said. "I felt I had a legitimate chance with <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>. We were in
first for 2 1/2 months before folding, and I still think we had the best team.
Now, even though it's a tough division, we're in a very good position.";   
<PERSON>Langston</PERSON> has come a long way in a season, and a long way since he left defunct
Buchser High School in <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>. He was offered plenty of soccer
scholarships, but there was not much interest in him as a baseball player. His
heart said baseball, and he said <DATE>Monday</DATE> with a rich man's grin, "It was the
right decision.";    "I had a good time at <LOCATION>San Jose State</LOCATION>," he said. "The main
thing there was just that the competition was up a little bit. It was a lot of
fun, and it sent me on my way."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MARK NEWMAN, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Toronto  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910709  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  615  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday July 9, 1991
00191220,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110189-0065 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 128513 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 1, 1989, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 5; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
703 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PADRES FIRE NEW PITCH TO DAVIS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BOB NIGHTENGALE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Padres, in hopes that reliever <PERSON>Mark Davis</PERSON> forgets all about this free-agent 
business, offered him a new contract proposal <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, one which they believe 
will convince him to remain in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
While awaiting their answer, the Padres went ahead <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and contacted <PERSON>Arn 
Tellem</PERSON>, the agent for free-agent pitcher <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON>, informing him that they 
will pursue the left-handed starter. 
</P>
<P>
"We're very interested in him," said <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>Fred Lane</PERSON>, who will 
conduct the negotiations for the Padres, "and I think they're very interested 
in us." 
</P>
<P>
Lane, who along with La Jolla attorney <PERSON>Beth Benes</PERSON> is conducting the <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> 
negotiations for the Padres, said however that the Padres' first priority in 
the free-agent market continues to be <PERSON>Davis</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Davis</PERSON>, a left-hander who saved a Padre-record 44 games in <DATE>1989</DATE> and was selected 
as <ORGANIZATION>The Sporting News' National League</ORGANIZATION> pitcher of the year, filed for free 
agency <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. But before <PERSON>Davis</PERSON>' agent, <PERSON>Alan Hendricks</PERSON>, even had a chance 
to test the marketplace, the Padres had a new contract proposal awaiting 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
"We had already made them a fabulous offer, but we made them even a more 
fabulous offer after we learned that they filed for free agency," <PERSON>Lane</PERSON> said. 
"We wanted to give Mark something to think about. 
</P>
<P>
"We want Mark to know that we're very sincere, and how much the Padres want 
him. He knows that from our words. And now he knows that from our numbers." 
</P>
<P>
Lane refused to reveal the Padres' offer, saying, "I don't want to educate my 
competition," but it is believed that it is a three-year guaranteed contract 
for at least <MONEY>$7 million</MONEY> with possibly an option for a fourth year. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Davis</PERSON> was unaware of the <ORGANIZATION>Padres</ORGANIZATION>' new offer <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. <PERSON>Hendricks</PERSON>, his agent, was 
undergoing foot surgery, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> said, but he's expected to speak with him today 
and discuss the proposal. 
</P>
<P>
"Coming back to <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> is still my first choice," <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> said. "Just because 
I filed for free agency doesn't mean that I'm not even thinking about <LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION>, that's far from my intention. I just want to protect myself." 
</P>
<P>
Davis would not disclose how much it will take for the Padres to keep him, but 
said that he's seeking a four-year contract. 
</P>
<P>
"A contract for more than three years is something I'd definitely like," <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> 
said. "I know they're not common, but it's something I think a team and a 
player could work out." 
</P>
<P>
Said Lane: "We can probably work out anything, but we don't want to do 
something nuts. I'm certain everything will work out. We're going to get him; 
we're going to get him. 
</P>
<P>
"This offer is something that'll be so attractive to him that he'll have to 
take it now." 
</P>
<P>
And if <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hendricks</PERSON> continue to explore the possibilities of the 
free-agent market? 
</P>
<P>
"Well, in that case," <PERSON>Lane</PERSON> said, "I'll just hope he's not interested in the 
teams that are interested in him." 
</P>
<P>
While in the marketing mood <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the Padres officially launched their claim 
in the <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION> sweepstakes. They are considered to be among <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>'s top 
three choices, along with the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Athletics</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
It's unknown just how much it will cost to lure <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> to the <LOCATION>Padres</LOCATION>, but 
it's almost certain that he will become the highest-paid pitcher in baseball, 
exceeding <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> a year. The Padres, and every other team with the 
exception of the <ORGANIZATION>Montreal Expos</ORGANIZATION>, are not allowed to negotiate with <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> or 
discuss monetary terms until after <DATE>Nov. 13</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
If the Padres are successful in acquiring <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>, 12-9, 2.39 ERA, they would 
enter the <DATE>1990</DATE> season with perhaps the strongest pitching rotation in the 
<ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Bruce Hurst</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ed Whitson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Eric Show</PERSON>, <PERSON>Andy Benes</PERSON> and <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>. 
It also would enable them to package one or two pitchers along with a catcher 
to obtain a starting center fielder. 
</P>
<P>
The Padres also could be in the market for other free agents, such as 
outfielder <PERSON>Hubie Brooks</PERSON> and first baseman <PERSON>Keith Hernandez</PERSON>, but have yet to 
decide if they'll pursue any others besides <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"We still have to sit down, get a list together, and discuss just who fits our 
needs," said <PERSON>Tony Siegle</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Padre</ORGANIZATION> vice president, player personnel. "It's quite 
obvious we can't sign everybody." 
</P>
<P>
In reality, they'd be ecstatic just to sign a certain pair of left-handers. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mark Davis 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072689-0015 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 86773 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 26, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 5; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
642 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NATIONAL LEAGUE ROUNDUP; 
</P>
<P>
LANGSTON TRADE AGAIN PAYS DIVIDENDS FOR EXPOS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAN HAFNER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When the <ORGANIZATION>Montreal Expos</ORGANIZATION> decided that <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> was the pitcher they needed 
to contend in the <ORGANIZATION>National League East</ORGANIZATION>, they were willing to pay the price. 
</P>
<P>
They sent three promising pitchers to the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners</ORGANIZATION> for the 
hard-throwing left-hander. There has not been a moment that the Expos have 
regretted the move. 
</P>
<P>
While <PERSON>Randy Johnson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Brian Holman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gene Harris</PERSON> have potential, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> has 
pitched the Expos into first place. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> struck out 10 and gave up only five hits in 
a 2-0 victory over the <LOCATION>Philadelphia Phillies</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Langston, who has three shutouts in his 12 starts for <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, improved to 8-3 
as an Expo. 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> made his <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> debut <DATE>May 28</DATE>, the Expos were in fourth place 
with a 23-24 record. They are 36-17 since he joined them and lead the division 
by 3 1/2 games. 
</P>
<P>
"He has given us even more than we hoped he would," Manager <PERSON>Buck Rodgers</PERSON> said. 
"He has given us a chance to win every game he's started. There are times when 
nobody pitches any better." 
</P>
<P>
Even in his three defeats, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> pitched at least six innings. In eight of 
his other nine, he has not given up more than one earned run. In the other, he 
gave up three runs in eight innings. 
</P>
<P>
"It's nice to get runs," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said, "but it's probably better for me if we 
don't score too many. In close games I tend to concentrate more and make more 
of my pitches count. When it's close, you have to have an idea of what you want 
every pitch to do before you throw it." 
</P>
<P>
Chicago 4, <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 2 -- The Cubs, who are becoming the Expos' chief 
challenger, ended <PERSON>Joe Magrane</PERSON>'s six-game winning streak, at <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Paul Kilgus</PERSON> (6-9), who had not won since <DATE>June 6</DATE>, worked six innings and singled 
in a run. The Cub bullpen finished up for Kilgus. <PERSON>Mitch Williams</PERSON> pitched the 
last two innings, gave up a run and took over the league lead with his 25th 
save. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jose Oquendo</PERSON> of the Cardinals had two hits to extend his hitting streak to 23 
games, longest in the major leagues. 
</P>
<P>
Magrane (11-7) gave up six hits and three runs in seven innings. He struck out 
five. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Francisco 5</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 4 -- <PERSON>Robby Thompson</PERSON> hit a home run and the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> won 
their second in a row at <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, handing the Braves their sixth consecutive 
defeat. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mike LaCoss</PERSON> (5-6) worked seven innings and <PERSON>Craig Lefferts</PERSON> earned his 18th save. 
Ed Whited hit a two-run home run in the ninth for <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Pittsburgh 4, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 2 -- <PERSON>Bobby Bonilla</PERSON> singled in the tie-breaking run in 
the eighth inning at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, ending the Mets' six-game winning streak. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jeff King</PERSON> led off the ninth against loser <PERSON>Rick Aguilera</PERSON> (6-4) with his first 
major league home run. <PERSON>Bill Landrum</PERSON> worked the bottom of the ninth for his 14th 
save. 
</P>
<P>
Said <PERSON>Doug Drabek</PERSON>, who fell to 8-7: "I don't think I've ever won on my birthday 
before, except once in the minors. It was exciting to beat this club." 
</P>
<P>
The defeat dropped the Mets into third place, behind the Cubs. 
</P>
<P>
Said Met Manager <PERSON>Davey Johnson</PERSON>: "We know we're not going to win them all. 
There's still a lot of baseball left. We've played well. That's all I'm 
concerned about." 
</P>
<P>
San Diego 6, <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 2 -- As the injuries continue to mount for the Reds, so 
do the the defeats. <PERSON>Eric Davis</PERSON> joined the long list of injured players and 
missed this game at <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Padres, who had lost four in a row at home to the <LOCATION>Cardinals</LOCATION> <DATE>last weekend</DATE>, 
handed the Reds their ninth consecutive defeat and 13th in their last 14 games. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Ed Whitson</PERSON>, enjoying his finest season, improved to 14-6. The victories match 
his career high in <DATE>1984</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Garry Templeton</PERSON> singled in two runs in the fourth and <PERSON>Shawn Abner</PERSON> hit a 
three-run home run in the seventh to back <PERSON>Whitson</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Before the game, the Reds put left-hander <PERSON>Danny Jackson</PERSON> on the disabled list 
because of a shoulder injury. <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, a 23-game winner last season, is 6-11 
and has an earned-run average of 5.60. DAN <PERSON>HAFNER</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06103027 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06103027 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; SAFE AT SECOND -- The Angels' Wally Joyner
beats the tag by Seattle's Harold Reynolds.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; BASEBALL; GAME; BRIEF  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The California Angels think Mark Langston, the left-hander they signed to a
five-year, $16 million contract last year, is going to bounce back strongly
from his 17-loss season in 1990.;    So does Langston.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LANGSTON HELPS ANGELS TO SERIES SWEEP
HE PITCHES SIX SHUTOUT INNINGS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  A.L. ROUNDUP  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Langston took a step in that direction <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when he pitched six strong
innings in a 5-0 victory over his old team, the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners.</ORGANIZATION>;    The
victory allowed the Angels, an 80-82 team last season, to sweep the <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION>
in the season-opening, three-game series. It also gave the Angels their best
start since going 5-0 in <DATE>1970.</DATE>;    "He didn't doubt himself last year," Angels
Manager <PERSON>Doug Rader</PERSON> said of <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>. "It's important for anybody to get off to
a good start just simply because it's something to be proud. If he were going
to self destruct, it certainly would have been last year. It wouldn't have
been for an unsuccessful debut in <DATE>1991</DATE>.";    A year ago, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> was one of
the biggest free-agent flops in baseball, going 10-17 with a 4.40 ERA. His
only highlight came in his debut, exactly a year ago, when he pitched seven
innings against <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> and combined with <PERSON>Mike Witt</PERSON> in the first of baseball's
record nine no-hitters.;    In <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s game, <PERSON>Dave Winfield</PERSON> drove in three
runs for the second straight game. He had a two-run double in the seventh.;   
"It takes a lot of pressure off of you when you've got the runs," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>
said. "<PERSON>Dave</PERSON> had a really big hit. It gave us a really big lift.";    <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>
gave up a two-out single to <PERSON>Ken Griffey Jr.</PERSON> in the first inning and then
retired 13 straight <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> before <PERSON>Dave Valle</PERSON> opened the sixth with a
single.;    <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> was lifted when the <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> loaded the bases on singles
by <PERSON>Edgar Martinez</PERSON> and <PERSON>Griffey</PERSON> and a walk to <PERSON>Alvin Davis</PERSON>. But <PERSON>Jeff Robinson</PERSON>
came in and got the next three outs.;    <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> got <PERSON>Jay Buhner</PERSON> to foul out
to first baseman <PERSON>Wally Joyner</PERSON>, <PERSON>Pete O'Brien</PERSON> to pop out to shortstop <PERSON>Dick
Schofield</PERSON> and struck out pinch hitter <PERSON>Greg Briley</PERSON>. He retired the <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> in
order in the eighth and ninth for a save.;    "You can't read too much this
early," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said. "But it's very encouraging. It's outstanding to be able
to come in here and take three from probably their three best pitchers.";
INDIANS 6, RED SOX 4: <PERSON>Brook Jacoby</PERSON> drove in three runs and <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> spoiled
<PERSON>Danny Darwin</PERSON>'s debut in <LOCATION>Boston.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Eric King</PERSON> blanked <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> on three hits
over six innings before tiring and needing relief help in a three-run seventh.
<PERSON>Doug Jones</PERSON> pitched the ninth for his second save.;    <ORGANIZATION>Darwin</ORGANIZATION>, signed for <MONEY>$11.8
million</MONEY> as a free agent after leading the <ORGANIZATION>National League</ORGANIZATION> in ERA last season
for <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, was unimpressive in his first start for the Red Sox.;    The
Indians rocked <PERSON>Darwin</PERSON> for three runs in the first inning and added three more
in the second, the last two coming on <PERSON>Jacoby</PERSON>'s wind-blown triple off reliever
<PERSON>Tom Bolton.</PERSON>; BLUE JAYS 7, BREWERS 3: Off-season acquisitions <PERSON>Devon White</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Joe Carter</PERSON> continued to spark the offense and <PERSON>David Wells</PERSON> pitched eight strong
innings as host <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> beat Milwaukee.;    <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>, acquired from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>,
drove in two runs, giving him five in four games while batting .400 for the
<ORGANIZATION>Blue Jays</ORGANIZATION>. White, traded by <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, went 3 for 5 and scored three runs,
giving him five for the season to go with a .389 average.;    <PERSON>Wells</PERSON> (1-0), who
has never pitched a complete game in 28 career starts, allowed three runs on
eight hits, struck out two and walked one.; TIGERS 11, YANKEES 5: <PERSON>Cecil
Fielder</PERSON> drove in three runs and scored four times as <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> beat visiting <LOCATION>New
York.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Travis Fryman</PERSON> also had three RBIs for <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Roberto Kelly</PERSON>
drove in a career-high five runs for the Yankees.;    Fielder, who led the
majors last season with 51 homers and 132 RBIs, singled home two runs in the
seventh and drove in another with a fielder's choice grounder in the eighth.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Wire Services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910412  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  700  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday April 12, 1991
00103027,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060190-0187 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 227593 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 1, 1990, Friday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part P; Page 11; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
874 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COMMENTARY; 
</P>
<P>
WITH 10 DRAFT PICKS, EXPOS HAVE CHANCE TO DOMINATE THE '90S 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TOM VERDUCCI, NEWSDAY 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Expos were dejected and depleted <DATE>last winter</DATE> when <PERSON>Hubie Brooks</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mark 
Langston</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bryn Smith</PERSON> and <PERSON>Pascual Perez</PERSON> left the organization as free agents. 
They lost one of their leading run-producers and three starting pitchers and 
had nothing to show for it. That changes <DATE>Monday</DATE>, when the draft offers <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 
the chance to reload. The Expos hold 10 of the first 53 picks. 
</P>
<P>
Montreal has two picks in the first round (including one from the Angels, who 
signed Langston), four picks in a supplemental round immediately after the 
first round (one each for losing <LOCATION>Langston</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Brooks</PERSON> and <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> and one because 
they failed to sign their first-round pick from last year), and four more in 
the second round (their own pick plus one each for losing <PERSON>Brooks</PERSON>, <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Smith</PERSON>). 
</P>
<P>
"We have the chance to really do well," said <PERSON>Gary Hughes</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>'s director 
of scouting. "Usually you only have two picks among the quality players in the 
first two rounds. Now we've got 10. There's a much better chance to be 
successful." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, which has already signed and developed all of its starting eight 
except for shortstop <PERSON>Spike Owen</PERSON>, has a chance to become a dominant team for the 
<DATE>1990s</DATE>. But then, we've heard such talk before. 
</P>
<P>
The Expos drafted <PERSON>Ellis Valentine</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gary Carter</PERSON> in <DATE>1972</DATE> and took <PERSON>Bill 
Gullickson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Scott Sanderson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tim Raines</PERSON> in <DATE>1977</DATE>. Then, in <DATE>1979</DATE>, they won 95 
games in what was the franchise's first winning season. They were expected to 
be the team of the <DATE>'80s</DATE> but won only one title in the decade, and that was in 
the fractured strike season, <DATE>1981</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Now the Expos are coming off two straight .500 seasons and are considered such 
an unattractive franchise that although it is up for sale, no one is bidding 
for it. If nothing else, 10 of the first 53 picks of the draft give <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 
reason for optimism. 
</P>
<P>
"We think we're going in the right direction," <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> said. "What good has free 
agency done <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, anyway? We haven't had much success in 
attracting or keeping free agents. But if we build a successful organization, 
people will want to stay and people will want to come." 
</P>
<P>
Oddly enough, the team that could be hurt most by <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>'s abundance of picks 
is the <LOCATION>New York Yankees</LOCATION>. <PERSON>George Bradley</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION>' vice president of player 
personnel and development, explained that the Expos are likely to take players 
the <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION> covet. 
</P>
<P>
"Montreal scouts in basically the same way we do," <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> said. "They're 
nearly identical to us. More so than any other club. That's why, after the 
first round at least, all of their picks are probably going to cost us some 
players. They're just like us in that they go for good athletes, younger 
players, they're not afraid to take chances and they may go for a kid who is 
regarded as tough to sign. We're very, very similar." 
</P>
<P>
A's may pick more winners -- Here is some bad news for all the teams who are 
trying to catch up with <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>: The world champion Athletics, who built the 
core of their team through the draft, have seven of the first 66 selections 
<DATE>Monday</DATE>. Oakland obtained five extra picks as compensation for losing free 
agents <PERSON>Dave Parker</PERSON>, Storm <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tony Phillips</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"We didn't want to lose those players, but this is the way the system works," 
said <PERSON>Dick Bogard</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>'s director of scouting. "I love it. We know we're 
going to get some good players. Throughout the system, our biggest need is 
pitching. We're looking to address that in the draft." 
</P>
<P>
Glory is fleeting -- On <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, the <LOCATION>Phillies</LOCATION> reached first place for the 
Daily News both played the story on Page One. 
</P>
<P>
"We just wanted to get to .500 and then build on that," said <PERSON>Von Hayes</PERSON>, the 
only player left from that <DATE>1984</DATE> team. "Now that we're in first, it's the same 
principle. Little by little, we want to pick up some games and build on our 
lead." 
</P>
<P>
The Phillies lost the <TIME>next night</TIME> and dropped out of first place. They lost 
their next two games after that, too, to fall 2 1/2 games out. 
</P>
<P>
But give <ORGANIZATION>General Manager Lee Thomas</ORGANIZATION> credit for unloading three established 
<LOCATION>Phillies</LOCATION> -- <PERSON>Steve Bedrosian</PERSON>, <PERSON>Juan Samuel</PERSON> and <PERSON>Chris James</PERSON> -- within a 15-day 
span last <DATE>June</DATE> in order to get <PERSON>Charlie Hayes</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dennis Cook</PERSON>, <PERSON>Terry Mulholland</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Roger McDowell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lenny Dykstra</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Kruk</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Randy Ready</ORGANIZATION>. All three of the 
deals look like steals. 
</P>
<P>
The Phillies' pitching is still too inexperienced and inconsistent for this 
team to win the <ORGANIZATION>National League East</ORGANIZATION>. But it appears <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> will be a 
factor in the race for the first time since <DATE>1986</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't think teams can afford to say anymore, 'Oh, we're playing the 
<ORGANIZATION>Phillies</ORGANIZATION>' and count on wins," reliever <PERSON>McDowell</PERSON> said. "I don't see <DATE>September</DATE> as 
a time when we'll be playing out the string." 
</P>
<P>
Call them F Troop -- <PERSON>McDowell</PERSON> said of the Phillies' turnover: "We're just a 
bunch of misfits. This team is a co-op. We're like the <LOCATION>Miami Marlins</LOCATION>. We're 
just a group of guys who like to play baseball but didn't have the chance to 
play every day. Look around here. We've got guys from <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, the Mets. . . . It's a situation where we feel we can 
play a little bit, no matter what anybody else says." 
</P>
<P>
Said Leyva: "Yeah, we've got some castoffs. I call them F Troop." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mark Langston, left, and Hubie Brooks are among the players lost by the 
Expos. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121089-0144 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 146542 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 10, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 4; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1050 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MIKE DOWNEY: MARK HIS WORD, ANGELS TO BE TOUGH 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MIKE DOWNEY 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
For a man who's worth more money than most <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> savings and loans, <PERSON>Mark 
Langston</PERSON> still seems a fairly down-to-earth chap. Oh, he looks spiffy enough in 
his wild wide-striped suit and purplish shoes that resemble something <PERSON>Jack 
Nicholson</PERSON>'s Joker might wear, and his glamorous wife keeps a diamond on her 
finger that is larger than <LOCATION>Anaheim Stadium</LOCATION>, but what the heck, when you got it, 
flaunt it. What should these people do -- wear blue jeans ripped at the knee? 
</P>
<P>
Langston looks sharp, feels sharp and talks a good game, too. He wants not to 
make waves, even this close to the ocean. Says he's glad to be an Angel, glad 
to be where it's warm, glad to be making what he's making no matter how much 
more <PERSON>Mark Davis</PERSON> or <PERSON>Robin Yount</PERSON> or anybody else in baseball's <ORGANIZATION>Billionaire Boys 
Club</ORGANIZATION> eventually commands, and says he's glad to be playing his home games on 
real grass for a change, even though "I'm a pitcher, so I'm always in the dirt 
anyway." 
</P>
<P>
Outspoken? Not particularly. 
</P>
<P>
The biggest limb <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> ventured onto, at his welcoming party <DATE>Friday</DATE> at the 
Big A, was his description of the Angels as "the team to beat" in the <ORGANIZATION>American 
League West</ORGANIZATION> next season, even with the <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Athletics</ORGANIZATION> having been to 
back-to-back World Series. That one raised a couple of eyebrows. 
</P>
<P>
Langston explains that he and his off-season next-door neighbor, A's outfielder 
<PERSON>Dave Henderson</PERSON>, have been chatting over the back fence about <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>'s need to 
fill voids left by Storm <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> on the mound and <PERSON>Dave Parker</PERSON> in the batter's box 
and clubhouse, which in turn has led Langston to this startling conclusion: 
"The Angels definitely figure to be the front-runners going into the season." 
</P>
<P>
Just wait'll <PERSON>Jose Canseco</PERSON> hears that. Be sure to dial 1-900-JOSE, or whatever 
his number is, any time next week, because Canseco probably will be picking the 
Angels to finish seventh. 
</P>
<P>
Keep in mind, though, this is neither controversy nor conceit on <ORGANIZATION>Langston</ORGANIZATION>'s 
part. It's enthusiasm. It's a mind-set taking hold. This is <PERSON>Mark Langston</PERSON> 
already getting into the proper mood for the season, getting himself into a 
suitable frame of mind after toiling for ballclubs that stayed away from 
pennant races as though they had incentive bonuses in their contracts not to 
win. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm a very poor loser," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> makes a point of saying and later repeating. 
</P>
<P>
He mentions how he gave a great deal of thought to signing a long-term deal 
with the <ORGANIZATION>Montreal Expos</ORGANIZATION> in the middle of last season, soon after they sent 
three pitchers to the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Mariners</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>May 25</DATE> just to be able to rent him. 
Then something happened to unsettle <PERSON>Langston</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
As he recalls: "We hit a skid where we lost seven games in a row, or something 
like that, and I was anxious to see how the team would bounce back. Well, we 
didn't bounce back." 
</P>
<P>
That indicated to him something about the club, about its hunger to win. 
</P>
<P>
Same thing at <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>. Langston ran into the new owner of the Mariners the 
other day, liked his upbeat attitude, told him it was "too bad he hadn't bought 
the team sooner, because things would be very different right now." 
</P>
<P>
Might he have signed to stay put, had <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> had more generous management? 
</P>
<P>
"I probably would have signed," <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> said. "I'm just very glad that I 
didn't. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Spike Owen</PERSON> and I used to talk about it almost nightly in <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, why we 
never could win when we were in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> together. All you have to do is look 
around the league to understand it. Look at the <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> A's -- half the team's 
ex-Mariners. You could fill an All-Star team with the players <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> has let 
go." 
</P>
<P>
Since <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> is eager to please, he answers affirmatively when someone from 
the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> asks him if the biggest factor in his free agency was playing 
for a team on the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>. As a native Californian, <PERSON>Langston</PERSON> hardly minded 
saying yes. Trouble is, it's untrue. It's a little white lie, no harm intended. 
</P>
<P>
Remember, this is a pitcher who just finished saying how he nearly signed with 
<LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, or would have stayed in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, given the money. He negotiated with 
the <ORGANIZATION>New York Yankees</ORGANIZATION>, with the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Cubs</ORGANIZATION>, with the <ORGANIZATION>St. Louis Cardinals</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
