<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890724-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-24-89 0531EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-FranceFashion     07-24 0719</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-France Fashion,0738</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lacroix Still Signs Clothes with Fun, Fantasy and Luxury</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Christian Lacroix</PERSON>, maintaining his reputation as a
young creator, brought out a collection of fun, fantasy, lace and
furs on the first day of haute couture showings for next winter.
   As <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> sweltered under a rare heatwave, top couturiers on
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> unveiled their luxurious, befurred and feathered models for
cooler weather.
   Lacroix's pouf skirt finally ran out of steam. But he's kept a
taste for beautiful, opulent fabrics and top-heavy outfits full of
quirky, funny ideas.
   He's a man who takes chances with these expensive fabrics and he
usually wins, though not always. The applause after the show was
tepid.
   <PERSON>Bernard Arnault</PERSON>, head of the Agache financial consortium backing
<PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON>, waffled when asked if the eccentric, creative designer is
still a hot money-maker. ``His clothes are beautiful. That's all
that counts,'' he said.
   Lacroix's clothes with the draped fichu shoulder, the big hoods
or head scarves and collars over tiny skirts are great on the
runway, but perhaps not at every party, no matter how splashy.
   He used a lot of browns, dolling up pinstriped jackets with
draped satin fronts and sable cuffs, sometimes teamed with a
mole-colored velvet skirt. Mixing up textures with abandon, he put
a tiny lame ``damasked'' bolero over a trapeze minidress in shades
of mustard and burgundy, with a quilted velvet panel on the skirt.
   Some of the luxury fantasy was hilarious, till one tried to tote
up the cost of the enormous sable parka topping chocolate shorts
with braided silk cornrows flipping over them like a reggae singer
gone wild _ a mini-fantasy well over <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY>.
   Lacroix's violet jersey dress was a soothing contrast to all the
show-off fabrics. His little shortie flared coats in faille and
satin were wearable. There were wonderful moments like the long,
slinky carmine velvet coat with huge sparkling buttons worn over
slimming pants embroidered with stars.
   The brown and khaki silks were always topped up with lively
shades of coral, saffron, turquoise or gold.
   For evening, <PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON>'s hand-painted pink and green tulle
ballerina fantasies and jeweled tunics looked like a <ORGANIZATION>Midsummer
Night</ORGANIZATION>'s Dream of luxury. Other ballerina numbers were in rich red
velvet and black, always sparkling with touches of gold.
   The dazzling jeweled boleros and jackets looked like a treasure
trove of <LOCATION>Ali Baba</LOCATION>'s Cave.
   And after Christian discovered his mom's lace-edged satin
slip-dress, his versions of lace for the runway simply took off in
a froth of glory.
   The heavy guipure effects, the lame-embroidered dresses in
khaki, cream and gold, the damasked and brocade dresses with
pheasant or ostrich-feather trim harked back to the best of the
negligee looks in the <LOCATION>Twenties</LOCATION> and Thirties. But things were always
a bit on the wild side _ a la Christian Lacroix.
   Japanese couturiere <PERSON>Hanae Mori</PERSON>, celebrating 35 years in the
fashion business and a new shop in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, showed beautifully
crafted clothes with more workmanship than fantasy.
   Her fit and cut are always impeccable, and the swirling
red-black-green harlequin coat over a pine green short sheath is
anything but stodgy. Her full-skirted grey flannel suits with black
velvet decor and the Mori trademark butterfly pins should please
her faithful regulars.
   Her true couture details _ like satin basketweaving basque
waists in suits _ testified to her craftsmanship. She was lavish
with fancy fabrics, but her lame-flecked or sequin-embroidered lace
numbers were demure rather than daring.
   The dresses that made one want to weep with joy were the chiffon
prints in <LOCATION>Mori</LOCATION>'s ``old'' style _ the feather-light chiffon print
landscapes with the most delicate Japanese prints of flowers, trees
and birds.
   Torrente's forte is showbiz, and she wisely showed plenty of
spangled numbers to look great onstage or at a gala dinner.
   Her three full, long cashmere wraparound coats in emerald,
cardinal and rust looked light, easy and warm. Her saffron fitted
spencer jacket over an aubergine long, slinky skirt is a good way
of easing into evening.
   And she went all out for late-day glitz: a few jet embroidered
dresses had discreet trains. Colorful patchwork jackets had fur or
ostrich-feather cuffs. The all-sequined slink would be fine for
midnight at <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>. Easier to wear would be the tuxedos with big
pearl pink satin lapels.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900121-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-21-90 1919EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-France-Fashion     01-21 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Fashion,0609</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hot and Sweet Clothes from Lacroix, Versace for Summer Couture</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR10</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Runways sizzled and burst into bloom at <DATE>summer</DATE>
couture shows that opened over the weekend.
   The extravagant dream clothes by <ORGANIZATION>Gianni Versace</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Christian
Lacroix</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hanae Mori</PERSON> and <PERSON>Torrente</PERSON> showed that flowers and feathers
will be hot this <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   Italian <ORGANIZATION>Gianni Versace</ORGANIZATION> got a jump on the French fashion houses
by showing his feathery decollete styles <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at the <ORGANIZATION>Ritz
Hotel</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> is mine'' crowed the 43-year-old designer, who is not an
official member of the French designers association and was staging
his first show of atelier clothes in the <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> of Lights.
   Versace turned out witty, minx-like and colorful styles with
enough elaborate beading to create a couture effect.
   ``Great for wives of the mafia,'' groused one resentful French
fashion commentator.
   But <PERSON>Julie Andrews</PERSON> loved them. ``Especially the little sheaths
with boa effects and jeweled necklines,'' said the star.
   Versace is designing the costumes for ``Ch'in Ch'in,'' a new
film starring <PERSON>Miss Andrews</PERSON> and <PERSON>Marcello Mastrioanni</PERSON> and directed by
<ORGANIZATION>Gene Saks</ORGANIZATION>.
   Versace won hearts with his sexy cuts that were too playful to
be vulgar. His use of elaborate beading, ostrich feathers and
rhinestones on asymmetrically draped long skirts and short skirts
were typical of the inventive Italian.
   His swirled breastplate effects on bustiers vied with
embroidered commedia dell'arte harlequin and abstract effects in
hot colors on lean pants or skirts. Also featured were
ostrich-feather tutu styles and a rhinestone-edged, flame-red
sheath split to the hip.
   Christian <PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON>'s show <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at the <ORGANIZATION>Intercontinental
Hotel</ORGANIZATION> ballroom was no less stunning and began with some wonderful
dressy silk and crepe suits with fitted asymmetrical jackets and
huge rhinestone buttons.
   Lacroix used opulent fabrics, often bringing out his signature
touches like trapeze-shaped coats, enormous puffy sleeves, draped
fichu or shawl effects and the occasional big organza bow-train
down the back. He also brought out some luscious organzas edged in
appliqued flowers.
   Lacroix used clouds of ostrich feathers to give a light touch to
some beautifully cut chiffons and georgette silks in delectable
colors like butter, peach and tea-rose pink.
   And looking at the bias cuts leaves no doubt: <PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON> may be an
artist above all, but he's definitely become a couturier.
   Japanese couturier <PERSON>Hanae Mori</PERSON> _ considered a <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> designer for
more than 15 years now _ showed the sexiest, youngest fashions
she's ever designed.
   Her skirts were often draped, clinging with hemlines way above
the knee, and jackets were fitted and sometimes featured plunging
necklines over sweetheart strapless dresses.
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> was a favorite color with <PERSON>Mrs. Mori</PERSON>, and she dolled it up
beautifully in white-striped fitted silk grosgrain suits, draped it
and paired it with lace in slinky evening gowns.
   She also went in for some siren-like vermilion draped silks, and
striking shades like cyclamen purple paired with gold lame.
   Besides her enchanting trademark sequined Japanese landscape and
wave-patterned embroidered dresses, <PERSON>Mrs. Mori</PERSON> also used some of her
favorite motifs _ butterflies and flowers.
   Torrente, whose real name is <PERSON>Rose Mett</PERSON>, also laid on a
lighthearted show that included pique suits with swooped hems on
the fitted jackets for day wear. She dressed up navy crepe suits to
advantage with gold lame rick-rack piping, and some of her great
flower-girl looks centered on enormous anemone print chemise
dresses that looked very easy to wear.
   Among her charming girlish looks were short lace ballerina
dresses and slinky strapless gowns with touches of raffia.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891124-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-24-89 1226EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-ToysRecalled     11-24 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Toys Recalled,0290</SECOND>
<HEAD>``Slinky'' Animal Pull Toys Recalled</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: also on general news wires.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 40,000 models of a classic American
toy have been recalled because paint used on them may contain too
much lead, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Consumer Product Safety Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
   The agency also says hundreds of thousands of clown dolls are
being recalled because they pose a choking hazard.
   The makers of ``Slinky'' animal pull toys, a variation on the
standard accordion-like wired toy, are voluntarily recalling them
because the red paint used on the eyes, tongue and cheeks may
contain a higher percentage of lead paint than the agency allows.
   <ORGANIZATION>CPSC</ORGANIZATION> standards limit to <PERCENT>.06 percent</PERCENT> the lead content of paint
used on children's items.
   The 43,000 Slinky toys sold since <DATE>1986</DATE>, have red and white pull
cords and come in the form of a train, worm, seal, frog,
caterpillar, dalmation and kitten. They are made by <ORGANIZATION>James
Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Hollidaysburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CPSC</ORGANIZATION> also said 234,000 dolls manufactured by the Omaha-based
<ORGANIZATION>Oriental Trading Co.</ORGANIZATION> and sold through mail order catalogues as the
``Dress Up Clown'' or ``Funny Clown'' were recalled because they
have small parts that present a choking risk to young children.
   The agency said the 13-inch dolls, used to teach children to
dress themselves, have zipper clasps, buttons and buckles that came
off during standard tests.
   ``These small parts make the dolls banned hazardous substances
because they present a choking, ingestion and aspiration hazard to
children,'' the agency said in a written statement.
   There have been no reported injuries associated with either toy.
   Consumers may return the toys to the place of purchase for a
full refund.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881009-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-09-88 2021EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d f PM-Slinky     10-09 0803</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Slinky,0833</SECOND>
<HEAD>Not All Fun and Games for Slinky's Developer</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: This is for Monday PMs.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CASSANDRA BURRELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOLLIDAYSBURG, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Children around the world have played
with springy Slinkies for 43 years, but the 70-year-old woman who
helped invent the wire toy says it hasn't been all fun and games.
   <PERSON>Betty James</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>James Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, says her late
husband, <PERSON>Richard James</PERSON>, a mechanical engineer and naval architect,
came up with the idea of the toy in <DATE>1943</DATE> while aboard a ship. He
saw a torsion <DATE>spring fall</DATE> from a table and bounce.
   <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> took control of the business in <DATE>1960</DATE>, when her
husband lost interest and left the family to join what she called a
religious cult in <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>. He died there in <DATE>1974</DATE>.
   ``To this day,'' she said, ``I don't know what a torsion <DATE>spring</DATE>
is.''
   <ORGANIZATION>James Industries</ORGANIZATION> is a spartan, no-nonsense firm that turns out
Slinkies by the millions in this small central <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> town.
It employs 120 people who manufacture, package, sell and ship
Slinkies from a single building.
   A grandmother of 10, <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> says she's basically a doting
mother devoted to her six adult children and their families.
According to her oldest son, she's also a demanding and assertive
boss.
   ``She expects a lot out of you. She expects you to produce. And,
so you do produce,'' said <PERSON>Richard James II</PERSON>, 46. He is Slinky sales
manager and the only one of three sons and three daughters to join
the family business.
   <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON>, who is known as ``Big Betty,'' is not too big to
take telephone messages for her staff and do many other tasks.
``When we first moved into this building, I used to clean the
toilets, too,'' she said.
   She's been involved in every aspect of production and promotion.
   Slinky was put on the market in <DATE>1945</DATE>, after the Jameses spent
two years experimenting with various types of steel.
   After receiving a patent, they demonstrated the toys at a
<ORGANIZATION>Gimbel</ORGANIZATION>'s department store in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>. ``They gave us the end
of a counter so we could show how it walked,'' <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> recalled.
   ``I was so scared that no one would buy them, I called a friend
and asked her to come along. I thought we would each buy one if
nobody else did,'' she said.
   She needn't have worried. After a quick demonstration, the first
400 Slinkies sold out in 90 minutes at a dollar each.
   ``I was so taken aback when I saw this crowd of people _ and
everyone was waving dollar bills.''
   Each night, <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> took the day's production home from the
manufacturer and wrapped the Slinkies by hand with yellow paper.
   <PERSON>Richard James</PERSON>, meanwhile, came up with other inventions, but
none were successful.
   ``He was a dreamer,'' she said. ``He developed a refrigerator
that would dispense soft drinks, but we took it out because we were
drinking so many soft drinks we were getting fat. He also wanted to
work on an amphibious car.''
   When her husband left, <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> struggled to keep the business
alive to feed herself and her children.
   ``To me, my family is the most precious thing in life. ... I
always wanted a family because I was an only child,'' she said.
``You do what you have to do for them. I did what I had to do.''
   The first Slinky plant was in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Germantown</LOCATION> section.
<PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> moved to <LOCATION>Hollidaysburg</LOCATION>, 180 miles away, 23 years ago
because she had family and friends in the area who could help care
for her children.
   The family moved a year and a half before the company's move was
complete, and <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> commuted to <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> each week. She
drove to <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> evenings, returning home on
<DATE>Thursdays</DATE>.
   ``It was hard to see her crying because she had to leave the six
of us,'' her son <PERSON>Richard</PERSON> said.
   Today, <ORGANIZATION>James Industries</ORGANIZATION> sells millions of Slinkies around the
world. <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON>, who with her children owns all company stock,
declined to release the number of units sold annually or annual
sales figures. Slinkies usually retail for less than <MONEY>$2</MONEY>.
   The company produces other toys, including building blocks,
plastic rings, games and pin wheels. ``But Slinky outsells them
all,'' <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> said.
   ``It's simple. It's a universal toy. It's a toy that doesn't
need any explanation. It has intrinsic play value,'' her son said.
``There are very few other toys like that.''
   <ORGANIZATION>James Industries</ORGANIZATION> began producing brightly colored plastic
Slinkies in <DATE>1979</DATE>, to appeal to younger children, especially infants.
   <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> and her son gasp at the thought of updating the
television commercial jingle that declares ``Slinky, Slinky ...
Everyone loves a Slinky.'' The song was written in <DATE>1963</DATE>.
   ``We'll just stick to something that's good,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881006-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-06-88 1209EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-AnotherLook:Slinky ADV10   10-06 0817</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Another Look: Slinky, ADV 10,0843</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv10</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday PMs, Oct. 10, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Not All Fun and Games for Slinky's Developer</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CASSANDRA BURRELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOLLIDAYSBURG, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Children around the world have played
with springy Slinkies for 43 years, but the 70-year-old woman who
helped invent the wire toy says it hasn't been all fun and games.
   <PERSON>Betty James</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>James Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, says her late
husband, <PERSON>Richard James</PERSON>, a mechanical engineer and naval architect,
came up with the idea of the toy in <DATE>1943</DATE> while aboard a ship. He
saw a torsion <DATE>spring fall</DATE> from a table and bounce.
   <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> took control of the business in <DATE>1960</DATE>, when her
husband lost interest and left the family to join what she called a
religious cult in <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>. He died there in <DATE>1974</DATE>.
   ``To this day,'' she said, ``I don't know what a torsion <DATE>spring</DATE>
is.''
   <ORGANIZATION>James Industries</ORGANIZATION> is a spartan, no-nonsense firm that turns out
Slinkies by the millions in this small central <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> town.
It employs 120 people who manufacture, package, sell and ship
Slinkies from a single building.
   A grandmother of 10, <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> says she's basically a doting
mother devoted to her six adult children and their families.
According to her oldest son, she's also a demanding and assertive
boss.
   ``She expects a lot out of you. She expects you to produce. And,
so you do produce,'' said <PERSON>Richard James II</PERSON>, 46. He is Slinky sales
manager and the only one of three sons and three daughters to join
the family business.
   <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON>, who is known as ``Big Betty,'' is not too big to
take telephone messages for her staff and do many other tasks.
``When we first moved into this building, I used to clean the
toilets, too,'' she said.
   She's been involved in every aspect of production and promotion.
   Slinky was put on the market in <DATE>1945</DATE>, after the Jameses spent
two years experimenting with various types of steel.
   After receiving a patent, they demonstrated the toys at a
<ORGANIZATION>Gimbel</ORGANIZATION>'s department store in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>. ``They gave us the end
of a counter so we could show how it walked,'' <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> recalled.
   ``I was so scared that no one would buy them, I called a friend
and asked her to come along. I thought we would each buy one if
nobody else did,'' she said.
   She needn't have worried. After a quick demonstration, the first
400 Slinkies sold out in 90 minutes at a dollar each.
   ``I was so taken aback when I saw this crowd of people _ and
everyone was waving dollar bills.''
   Each night, <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> took the day's production home from the
manufacturer and wrapped the Slinkies by hand with yellow paper.
   <PERSON>Richard James</PERSON>, meanwhile, came up with other inventions, but
none were successful.
   ``He was a dreamer,'' she said. ``He developed a refrigerator
that would dispense soft drinks, but we took it out because we were
drinking so many soft drinks we were getting fat. He also wanted to
work on an amphibious car.''
   When her husband left, <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> struggled to keep the business
alive to feed herself and her children.
   ``To me, my family is the most precious thing in life. ... I
always wanted a family because I was an only child,'' she said.
``You do what you have to do for them. I did what I had to do.''
   The first Slinky plant was in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Germantown</LOCATION> section.
<PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> moved to <LOCATION>Hollidaysburg</LOCATION>, 180 miles away, 23 years ago
because she had family and friends in the area who could help care
for her children.
   The family moved a year and a half before the company's move was
complete, and <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> commuted to <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> each week. She
drove to <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> evenings, returning home on
<DATE>Thursdays</DATE>.
   ``It was hard to see her crying because she had to leave the six
of us,'' her son <PERSON>Richard</PERSON> said.
   Today, <ORGANIZATION>James Industries</ORGANIZATION> sells millions of Slinkies around the
world. <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON>, who with her children owns all company stock,
declined to release the number of units sold annually or annual
sales figures. Slinkies usually retail for less than <MONEY>$2</MONEY>.
   The company produces other toys, including building blocks,
plastic rings, games and pin wheels. ``But Slinky outsells them
all,'' <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> said.
   ``It's simple. It's a universal toy. It's a toy that doesn't
need any explanation. It has intrinsic play value,'' her son said.
``There are very few other toys like that.''
   <ORGANIZATION>James Industries</ORGANIZATION> began producing brightly colored plastic
Slinkies in <DATE>1979</DATE>, to appeal to younger children, especially infants.
   <PERSON>Mrs. James</PERSON> and her son gasp at the thought of updating the
television commercial jingle that declares ``Slinky, Slinky ...
Everyone loves a Slinky.'' The song was written in <DATE>1963</DATE>.
   ``We'll just stick to something that's good,'' she said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Mon PMs, Oct. 10</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112589-0090 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 139702 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 25, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 28; Column 2; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
82 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LEAD IN PAINT FORCES RECALL OF SLINKY TOYS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
More than 40,000 Slinky animal pull toys have been recalled because paint used 
</P>
<P>
The agency also says 234,000 clown dolls are being recalled because they pose a 
choking hazard. The dolls, manufactured by Omaha-based <ORGANIZATION>Oriental Trading Co.</ORGANIZATION> and 
sold through mail order catalogues as the "Dress Up Clown" or "Funny Clown," 
were recalled because they have small parts that present a choking risk to 
young children. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PRODUCT SAFETY; PRODUCT RECALLS; TOYS; DOLLS; PAINT; LEAD; POISONS AND 
POISONINGS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900313-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-13-90 0048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Britain-Fashion     03-13 0659</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Britain-Fashion,0682</SECOND>
<HEAD>London Fashion: Short, Sporty by Day; Slinky by Night</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The fall fashion message from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> is short,
sporty by day and slinky by night, with flashes of British wit and
individuality.
   The mood among designers, however, is uncertain.
   Top designers <PERSON>Katherine Hamnett</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Galliano</PERSON> skipped <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
to show in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. Two other big names, <PERSON>Rifat Ozbek</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jaspar
Conran</PERSON>, opted for videos instead of catwalk shows, and fewer buyers
stopped off in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> en route from <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Nonetheless, there was still some of that old wacky madness that
put <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> on the fashion map.
   <PERSON>Vivienne Westwood</PERSON>, the mother of punk garb, captivated the
audience with a collection ranging from classic tailored tartan
suits to fake fur-trimmed bloomers worn with Old Master-print
corsets.
   A Lycra-clad dancing troupe dressed as haute couture pigs opened
the show based on barnyard characters of country life. Bodymap did
a vision of drag-queen club life in their sexy sportswear
collection.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s designers of the year, Workers For Freedom duo <PERSON>Richard
Nott</PERSON> and <PERSON>Graham Fraser</PERSON>, showed a collection <PERSON>Nott</PERSON> described as
``spare feminity,'' which featured bikinis over striped body suits,
one of the key fall looks from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>London Fashion Week</ORGANIZATION>, which ends <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, has spread out even
further with designers showing all over town and the trade show
featuring about 250 exhibitors at the Olympia 2 exhibition hall.
   At <LOCATION>Olympia</LOCATION>, accessories from hats to bracelets seemed hotter
than clothes.
   ``I think largely because of high interest rates and the high
cost of living, women can't afford to buy another outfit, so
they're buying accessories,'' said <PERSON>Beverley Mann</PERSON>, 28, one of the
design duo of the costume jewelry firm <ORGANIZATION>Flash Harry</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Melanie Lazlo</PERSON> of Obsession, another costume jewelry firm, said:
``<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> is kind of a melting pot for a wide range of accessories
ranging from the weird and wonderful to the Channel-type classic.''
   Many fashion designers said the number of buyers was down.
   ``It's much quieter than it was last year,'' said <PERSON>David Sassoon</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Belville</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sassoon-Lorcan Mullany</PERSON>, one of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s top eveningwear
designers.
   ``I think stores everywhere are having a hard time,'' he said.
``Where money's tight, they want selling clothes. They don't want
jokes. ... They don't want over the top things they might have
indulged in previously.''
   <PERSON>Benny Ong</PERSON>, another leading designer whose soft, sensual clothes
sell internationally, agreed that the economic situation was
keeping buyers away from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   ``That's why it's important at those times when the economic
situation is not so hot to go for color _ to pick yourself up,'' he
said. ``Power-dressing has also changed to something more feminine
and confident.''
   <PERSON>Edina Ronay</PERSON>, bucking the trend with her first catwalk show, said
her business was up and insisted <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> was ``not going to fall
flat on its face because two people show in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>,''
   Her collection of suits and parkas in orange, ochre and olive,
fur-trimmed and brocade hooded jackets and skin-tight gold lame and
black tops and body suits won high marks for wearability.
   There were plenty other wearable clothes as well.
   <PERSON>Bruce Oldfield</PERSON>, who designs many of Princess Diana's dresses,
incorporated the sporty spirit in his hooded, printed parkas,
luxurious velvet bodysuits, sequined sweatshirts and a
gold-sequined bomber jacket with pants.
   <PERSON>Caroline Charles</PERSON> did a ``Eurochic'' collection featuring
Romanian peasant embroideries and folksy tapestry and fringing
alongside her snappy city suits and slinky evening dresses.
   Ozbek abandoned his <DATE>summer</DATE> white for dazzling colors _ another
fall theme _ in hooded tops, tunics, cropped bomber jackets and
leggings and body suits in dazzling sequins, stretch velvet and
gold lame.
   Conran found his inspiration in ``the off-duty ballerina,'' with
body-hugging catsuits topped by cropped leather jackets and quilted
bronze bomber jackets.
   <PERSON>Helen Story</PERSON>, one of the up-and-coming young designers, had fun
with a soccer-for-women look, again featuring hooded bomber jackets
and soccer shorts with her signature fringing.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891018-0212 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-89 2043EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-France-Fashion     10-18 0776</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-France-Fashion,0799</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shows Open on Optimistic, Feminine Notes for Summer</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lots of youthful, feminine clothes were shown in
early openings <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> as ready-to-wear shows for <DATE>summer 1990</DATE> got
underway.
   Great fabrics, curvy silhouettes and soft color palettes were
about the only things designers had in common as everybody did his
or her own thing.
   Also on the opening day, <ORGANIZATION>Lanvin</ORGANIZATION> announced at a press conference
that <PERSON>Claude Montana</PERSON> _ known as one of the most creative
ready-to-wear talents in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> _ would be the new creator of
<ORGANIZATION>Lanvin</ORGANIZATION>'s couture. <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> is a maverick, whose strong fashions and
silhouettes have often rocked the fashion world.
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s first couture collection will be shown in <DATE>January</DATE>, for
next <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   In her tent show in a courtyard of the <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Lolita Lempicka</LOCATION>
showed clothes with just enough chic to keep the sweet fashions
from cloying. Her bicolored fitted linen suits, either short to the
knee or maxi-length, often had fitted jackets with scalloped
necklines.
   One of her main silhouettes was formed by gold-buttoned long
redingotes giving a funnel shape to the linens or textured
``beehive'' ivory silks.
   Other flowingly feminine shapes came out under billowy-topped
dusters with long wrapped skirts.
   Lempicka's garden-party clothes had fresh allure with appliqued
daisies or fitted jackets in daisy prints. Dressy looks for wedding
parties are Lempicka's forte, but she also brought out some fun
fringed, clinging outfits in raffia _ a big new ``fabric'' for next
<DATE>summer</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Doby Broda</PERSON>'s idea of the <DATE>1990s</DATE> harks to the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, with lots of
flowing pyjamas and long skirts. Some in the audience liked her
flower-sprigged ``farmer's daughter'' dresses in soft or murky
colors.
   More fun were her easy pants or skirts outfits based on
``dishcloth'' linens _ the little loose dishcloth-plaid boleros
paired with solid blue full pants, skirts or occasionally shorts.
   For evening, her gold lame bias-cut dresses and flared pants
looked slinky enough to steal applause at parties, though perhaps
not quite luxurious enough for <PERSON>Marlene Dietrich</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Emmanuelle Khanh</PERSON> brought out a lot of long and slinky suits for
cruise wear, as well as some modest one-piece maillot bathing suits
with little flounces at the hip.
   Her sailor looks ranged from pants to shorts to skirts _ in
crisp navy and white or more original rusty brown cottons and
linens. For late-day, her best lines were easily fitted outfits
with strong black and white arabesque embroideries around collars
and shoulders.
   The Japanese are out in force as usual. <PERSON>Hanae Mori</PERSON> will show
later in the week, but <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> was awarded the Legion of
Honor for her contribution to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> fashion in the couture and
ready-to-wear shows she has shown and sold here for over 20 years.
   <PERSON>Junko Shimada</PERSON>'s bouncy young styles were always figure-hugging,
featuring bright turquoise beach mini-dresses with pointed hems,
printed in seashell patterns, topped with fishnet stoles.
   There was lots of creativity here _ from scalloped pique fitted
suits with very short skirts to a whole range of clinging broadly
striped sailor suits teaming pullovers with bell-bottomed jerseys
or tight bermudas like turn-of-the-century bathing costumes.
   The neat linen suits with decollete, small-waisted jackets in
shades of sand, turquoise, pale pink and chocolate had details like
big bucket pockets, tab pockets or perky pointed peplums.
   And <PERSON>Shimada</PERSON>'s combinations of dark plaids and insets, sleeves
and double collars or tobacco-brown organza looked original, if not
for everyone.
   Party girls with good figures will probably love the khaki green
clinging jersey and gold lame outfits with their gold lattice-work
hemlines and mousseline stoles.
   <PERSON>Hiroko Koshino</PERSON>'s collection was based on a cruise down the <ORGANIZATION>Nile</ORGANIZATION>,
from safari suits to outfits with asymmetrical details, folding and
pleating that could have come right from an Egyptian fresco or the
wardrobe of Cleopatra herself.
   In patterned silks and textured linens, the inspiration may have
been ancient, but the lines were modern _ with lots of high-waisted
pants, some bare midriffs, original jackets with one side covered
in a pleated scarf effect over wraparound skirts.
   There were lots of long jackets over pleated skirts or vests
sewn onto the skirt in a dress. And whether worn with shorts,
pleated or draped long skirts, the effect of these combinations was
never heavy.
   The colors _ sandy beige or grey, Nile green, deep fresco blue,
terra-cotta and mustard or gold _ gave the silk and linen outfits
an original cachet for next <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   Transparency was rife in the shows, but nowhere was it more
obvious than at <LOCATION>Kimijima</LOCATION>. He concentrated on mousselines and
fishnets topped with enough sparkly sequins to cause a few
shipwrecks with sailors spotting his revealing mermaid minis.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891021-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-21-89 0002EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Fashion     10-21 0795</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fashion,0816</SECOND>
<HEAD>Classics at Givenchy, Slinky Styles at Tarlazzi</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Saturday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From classic elegance at <ORGANIZATION>Givenchy</ORGANIZATION> to skin-tight and
slinky jerseys at <LOCATION>Tarlazzi</LOCATION>, styles in <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s fashion shows for
next <DATE>summer</DATE> ran the gamut.
   Tailored, ruffled, draped, and bare-midriff looks took over the
runways as the fashion picture was unfocused.
   Givenchy had his act together, a sophisticated range of clothes
that looked worthy of the elder statesman of couture.
   But the clothes were far from elderly. Givenchy simply took some
of his favorite themes and brought them out in luxurious fabrics.
He firmly padded shoulders for shape, ignoring the softer shoulders
elsewhere. There were lots of short skirts and easy long pants, in
plaid or solid suits with fitted or bolero tops. The suits were
handsome in windowpane plaids, stripes or glen plaids in silks,
linens and cottons.
   Simple sheaths with big padded cap sleeves or off-the-shoulder
banded tops with huge puffy sleeves over narrow short skirts added
to the range of feminine silhouettes for <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   There were navy, gray and neutrals for daytime, with sizzling
colors for later on. They came out in gazar or organza outfits with
big flounces, flowered prints, shades of orange, pink, wisteria and
turquoise, sometimes decorated with lily-of-the valley appliques or
sparkly fish just for fun.
   Karl Lagerfeld's ideas oozed with originality, all the clothes
cut for action from striped knit pullovers, long pants and shorts
to the fluid, full-skirted minis.
   Borrowing some of his own ideas from <LOCATION>Chanel</LOCATION>, where he's also
head designer, Lagerfeld sometimes paired big tweed checked blazers
with dark chiffon culottes and long skirts.
   Jackets were the forte, and whether short or long, they were
always fitted to the waist, and often had deeply cut lapels,
hugging the hips over contrasting short and lean skirts with
matching tights or the new, full minis. The best jacket had
crescent-shaped lapels _ one large, one small _ and for evening it
came out with pearled embroidery.
   Lagerfeld's prettiest cocktail clothes paired up black and white
short looks in bustier outfits with revealing black lace loose
jackets.
   Folklore and graphic prints with sequins and big polka-dotted
satins and cottons looked great too. Lagerfeld mixed them up in
tiny minis with fitted jackets, or in long, high-waisted pyjamas
and short or cutaway jackets.
   ``Come play with me,'' declared <PERSON>Angelo Tarlazzi</PERSON> in his program.
The Italian designer, who now also plies his trade for Guy Laroche
couture, went all out for hot-colored and clingy knits, leaving
little to the imagination. With elastic shoulder wraps, many bare
midriffs, pleated ruffles at the bust or hem, some of the viscose
knits were convertible _ and could be pulled out from mini length
to make a long dress.
   The most amusing evening dresses were called ``totems,'' and
combined bubbles of African-inspired prints in hot colors and black
with raffia fringes and fishnet hems.
   To emphasize the waist, he gave a girdle effect in lame
waist-cinchers to many outfits, with fullness in blouses above and
long pants or shorts below.
   Tarlazzi raided the linen closet for his ideas in <DATE>summer</DATE> white:
hem-stitched jackets and flounced skirts with boleros were a great
exercise in what you can do with sheets, napkins and tablecloths.
   <PERSON>Anne-Marie Beretta</PERSON>'s daytime suits with mother of pearl buttons
or snaps on long jackets worn with pedal pushes or pleated skirts
looked a bit too strict for the pampered set that frequents the
<ORGANIZATION>Automobile Club</ORGANIZATION>, where the show was held.
   The outfits were better in light pastel linens, forest green and
petrol blue than in the rather sad shades of khaki, putty and muddy
brown that predominated.
   She draped lots of clothes rather awkwardly for daytime, giving
them a heavy look in front. But some of the taffeta and lace
evening drapes and big ruffles were opulent if not especially
feminine.
   <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION> was reborn for <PERSON>Bernard Perris</PERSON>, who went back to the
<DATE>1960s</DATE> and <DATE>'70s</DATE> for his inspiration. His girls trotted out in
flared, funnel-shaped trousers, lots of embroidered and jeweled
hipster pants and skirts, and fringes all over the place.
   He also harked back to the age of Aquarius in his mixed Indian
cotton and silk prints in wrapped and draped skirts and
cummerbunds. And his idea of the tuxedo got all dressed up with
acres of long tassels.
   Bellbottomed pants, jumpsuits and shorts came out at <LOCATION>Chloe</LOCATION>, the
collection designed by <PERSON>Martine Sitbon</PERSON>. Her black pants suits or
short skirts with cutaway jackets were stitched with white, giving
nice vertical lines all over.
   The many cut-outs, bareback and bare-midriff outfits gave
another nod to the <DATE>1960s</DATE> in this group of shows that seems to be
floundering as designers search for details and silhouettes for the
<DATE>1990s</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881007-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-07-88 1431EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Kenya-Poachers     10-07 0374</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kenya-Poachers,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wildlife Ministry Fires 10 Wardens</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Ministry</ORGANIZATION> has fired 10 game
wardens and rangers and suspended 33 others in a campaign to stop
elephant poaching, newspapers reported <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Wild game hunting is banned in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>, but poachers kill
elephants for their valuable ivory tusks and are decimating <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s
elephant herds.
   Ivory tusks sell for <MONEY>$82</MONEY> a pound. Much of the ivory smuggled
from <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> ends up in the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>, where it is carved into jewelry
and figurines.
   ``If they have broken the law, they will be prosecLeakey, assistant
minister for tourism and wildlife, told
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Leakey's comments were reportuted,'' Philip
ed by <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s
three English-language newspapers, The Standard, the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Nation</ORGANIZATION>
and the <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> Times.
   He said the 10 rangers and game wardens dismissed had been
working in <LOCATION>Tsavo</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Amboseli</ORGANIZATION> national parks.
Twenty-nine game wardens and four rangers also have been
interdicted pending further investigations, said <PERSON>Leakey</PERSON>.
   ``We have sacked them and investigations are ongoing,'' he said.
``Every effort will be made to bring these people to justice.''
   It was unclear whether the 43 rangers and game wardens affected
by the move included the 33 officers of different ranks the
ministry suspended in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Leakey</PERSON> said the ministry planned to intensify training programs
for wildlife officers in K come home, to bring his wife and two children
back to their own country, but his professional achievements and
aspirations had reached too high. So he set out to fulfill a new
dream: a world-class heart hospital in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Now it has become a
reality. ``It's a passion for me to come back and train others,''
he says.
   PM-India-Heart Hospital, by <PERSON>Earleen Fisher</PERSON>, moved <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> as
b0250 for <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> PMs, <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FEUDING FASHION FAMILY: `Of the Guccis, Only Ashes Remain'</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Ministry</ORGANIZATION> has fired 10 game
wardens and rangers and suspended 33 others in a campaign to stop
elephant poaching, newspapers reported <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Wild game hunting is banned in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>, but poachers kill
elephants for their valuable ivory tusks and are decimating <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s
elephant herds.
   Ivory tusks sell for <MONEY>$82</MONEY> a pound. Much of the ivory smuggled
from <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> ends up in the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>, where it is carved into jewelry
and figurines.
   ``If they have broken the law, they will be prosecLeakey, assistant
minister for tourism and wildlife, told
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Leakey's comments were reportuted,'' Philip
ed by <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s
three English-language newspapers, The Standard, the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Nation</ORGANIZATION>
and the <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> Times.
   He said the 10 rangers and game wardens dismissed had been
working in <LOCATION>Tsavo</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Amboseli</ORGANIZATION> national parks.
Twenty-nine game wardens and four rangers also have been
interdicted pending further investigations, said <PERSON>Leakey</PERSON>.
   ``We have sacked them and investigations are ongoing,'' he said.
``Every effort will be made to bring these people to justice.''
   It was unclear whether the 43 rangers and game wardens affected
by the move included the 33 officers of different ranks the
ministry suspended in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Leakey</PERSON> said the ministry planned to intensify training programs
for wildlife officers in K come home, to bring his wife and two children
back to their own country, but his professional achievements and
aspirations had reached too high. So he set out to fulfill a new
dream: a world-class heart hospital in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Now it has become a
reality. ``It's a passion for me to come back and train others,''
he says.
   PM-India-Heart Hospital, by <PERSON>Earleen Fisher</PERSON>, moved <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> as
b0250 for <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> PMs, <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>$3 MILLION `CHICKEN FEED': All's Relative In Era of Huge Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Ministry</ORGANIZATION> has fired 10 game
wardens and rangers and suspended 33 others in a campaign to stop
elephant poaching, newspapers reported <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Wild game hunting is banned in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>, but poachers kill
elephants for their valuable ivory tusks and are decimating <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s
elephant herds.
   Ivory tusks sell for <MONEY>$82</MONEY> a pound. Much of the ivory smuggled
from <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> ends up in the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>, where it is carved into jewelry
and figurines.
   ``If they have broken the law, they will be prosecLeakey, assistant
minister for tourism and wildlife, told
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Leakey's comments were reportuted,'' Philip
ed by <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s
three English-language newspapers, The Standard, the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Nation</ORGANIZATION>
and the <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> Times.
   He said the 10 rangers and game wardens dismissed had been
working in <LOCATION>Tsavo</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Amboseli</ORGANIZATION> national parks.
Twenty-nine game wardens and four rangers also have been
interdicted pending further investigations, said <PERSON>Leakey</PERSON>.
   ``We have sacked them and investigations are ongoing,'' he said.
``Every effort will be made to bring these people to justice.''
   It was unclear whether the 43 rangers and game wardens affected
by the move included the 33 officers of different ranks the
ministry suspended in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Leakey</PERSON> said the ministry planned to intensify training programs
for wildlife officers in K come home, to bring his wife and two children
back to their own country, but his professional achievements and
aspirations had reached too high. So he set out to fulfill a new
dream: a world-class heart hospital in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Now it has become a
reality. ``It's a passion for me to come back and train others,''
he says.
   PM-India-Heart Hospital, by <PERSON>Earleen Fisher</PERSON>, moved <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> as
b0250 for <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> PMs, <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ALSO:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Ministry</ORGANIZATION> has fired 10 game
wardens and rangers and suspended 33 others in a campaign to stop
elephant poaching, newspapers reported <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Wild game hunting is banned in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>, but poachers kill
elephants for their valuable ivory tusks and are decimating <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s
elephant herds.
   Ivory tusks sell for <MONEY>$82</MONEY> a pound. Much of the ivory smuggled
from <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> ends up in the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>, where it is carved into jewelry
and figurines.
   ``If they have broken the law, they will be prosecLeakey, assistant
minister for tourism and wildlife, told
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Leakey's comments were reportuted,'' Philip
ed by <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s
three English-language newspapers, The Standard, the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Nation</ORGANIZATION>
and the <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> Times.
   He said the 10 rangers and game wardens dismissed had been
working in <LOCATION>Tsavo</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Amboseli</ORGANIZATION> national parks.
Twenty-nine game wardens and four rangers also have been
interdicted pending further investigations, said <PERSON>Leakey</PERSON>.
   ``We have sacked them and investigations are ongoing,'' he said.
``Every effort will be made to bring these people to justice.''
   It was unclear whether the 43 rangers and game wardens affected
by the move included the 33 officers of different ranks the
ministry suspended in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Leakey</PERSON> said the ministry planned to intensify training programs
for wildlife officers in K come home, to bring his wife and two children
back to their own country, but his professional achievements and
aspirations had reached too high. So he set out to fulfill a new
dream: a world-class heart hospital in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Now it has become a
reality. ``It's a passion for me to come back and train others,''
he says.
   PM-India-Heart Hospital, by <PERSON>Earleen Fisher</PERSON>, moved <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> as
b0250 for <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> PMs, <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900729-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-29-90 1425EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Fashion     07-29 0648</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fashion,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter Haute Couture is Short, Scintillating</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This winter's tale of haute couture as seen last
week was a fabulous fantasy, with designers spinning out their
dreams in rich confections for the elite, or just for show.
   Short to shorter is the norm in daytime lengths, though houses
like <PERSON>Saint Laurent</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Givenchy</ORGANIZATION> generally kept skirts wearably just
above the knee.
   And was enough gold and jeweled embroidery around to boost many
prices into the stratosphere.
   But dream on ... and take note of silhouettes, fabrics and
color, often more modestly available in ready-to-wear. There is a
rainbow of possibilities, with each designer pushing his own
outlines and themes.
   The fashion world was pleased to see <PERSON>Claude Montana</PERSON> win the
coveted Golden Thimble award for his Lanvin collection, following
his disappointing debut there last <DATE>January</DATE>.
   His pyramid shortie coats and babydoll jackets, his lean pants
or skirt suits, his great use of luxury fabrics from cashmere to
faille taffeta showed <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s mastery of his art, so often
praised before in his own luxury ready-to-wear line.
   The pyramid shape or other shortie-coat looks cropped up all
over the place. Saint Laurent's more sober versions have deep, full
dolmen sleeves.
   Shoulders are mainly rounded, even sloped. The only hold-outs
for important padding are Saint Laurent and <ORGANIZATION>Givenchy</ORGANIZATION>.
   Suits are body-skimming but not so tight as a few seasons ago,
with great long jackets and some nice flyaway boleros.
   Generally the daytime fabrics were smooth, light and soft in
cashmeres or broadcloth or tweedy, with flecked or herringbones,
some bold black and red plaids _ great at <LOCATION>Valentino</LOCATION>, for example.
Python is a new favorite for trim at <ORGANIZATION>Givenchy</ORGANIZATION>, for a whole jacket
or more at <ORGANIZATION>Saint Laurent</ORGANIZATION>.
   Daytime colors included fall stand-bys _ siena, gray, burnt
orange, ochre, pine and brick, plus some white and all the browns
from caramel to chocolate. Dior's <PERSON>Gianfranco Ferre</PERSON> did
extraordinary things with mixes of blue shades from plum to
ultramarine or indigo.
   In both daytime and late-day wear, <PERSON>Karl Lagerfeld</PERSON> at Chanel
pleased those who would like to look young and kittenish with minis
over fancy thigh boots _ from hot satin to jeweled or embroidered
suede.
   Lagerfeld's boots were among the most flamboyant in a
newly-revived trend for long, lean and high or flat-heeled boots.
   He seems torn between the <DATE>1960s</DATE> ingenue look and the l8th
century of Marie-Antoinette, topping dressy, skimpy minis with big
satin and taffeta embroidered pannier skirts.
   Exotic lands and themes inspired many designers. <PERSON>Jean-Louis
Scherrer</PERSON> was praised for a collection based on the splendors of
<LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Near East</LOCATION> in Persian-rug weaves for his suits
and colorful hooded burnoose-style coats.
   Except for a wild jeweled bathing suit with tights, <PERSON>Christian
Lacroix</PERSON> kept his exuberance in check, though there was plenty of
glamor in evening dresses inspired by <ORGANIZATION>Goya</ORGANIZATION>, or contemporary gold
lame suits topped with enormous velvet artists' berets, as well as
some extravagant Moorish-style embroidery.
   Everything came up roses at <ORGANIZATION>Ungaro</ORGANIZATION>, who used magnificent flower
prints from dawn to dark. His bright piped tweed daytime suits in
grey, red or royal blue with their checked stoles were stunning too.
   It was in evening wear, however, that <PERSON>Ungaro</PERSON> and other
couturiers turned into real showmen. His extravagant, rosy silk
panniered dresses might not be to everybody's taste. But he offered
an alternative: glamorous black slinky crepe or chiffon gowns with
halter necklines, camisole or scooped-out tops draped in
rhinestones or pearls.
   For evening, anything goes as long as it looks rich. And
decolletes are more daring than ever, with bosoms pushed up under
empire curved bodices, visible in sparkly net or chiffon
see-throughs, or suggestive with necklines slashed to the waist.
   Feathers came out often _ ostriches, pheasant, cock and other
types were used. Scherrer's spicy asymmetrical draped and feathered
minis were especially titillating.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900123-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-23-90 1409EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Fashion     01-23 0816</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fashion,0841</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Bearable Lightness of Being in Fashion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Feathery-light fabrics and skin-baring styles
pepped up the runways <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as designers revealed their happy
holiday haute couture clothes for <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   The day was a triumph for <PERSON>Emanuel Ungaro</PERSON>, who has been totally
seduced by a light new look. He's simplified his feminine styles to
essentials, using gossamer fabrics and stunning colors to display
his talents.
   This is great news for his fans who found some of his recent
shows overloaded with show-off trimmings and superfluous details.
   ``C'est la vie,'' <PERSON>Ungaro</PERSON> smiled after the show when asked if his
recent marriage had been an influence on his fashion. The
Italian-born couturier, long a <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> fixture, married <PERSON>Laura Fanfani</PERSON>
in <DATE>November</DATE>. They are expecting a baby.
   Ungaro's new looks started off with neatly fitted raw silk suits
in shades of bordeaux and chrome yellow followed by bi- and
tricolored light gabardine suits with swirling details in shades
from violet, pink and orange to khaki and some peacock blues.
   ``I was aiming for the elegance of my old master, <LOCATION>Balenciaga</LOCATION>,''
said <PERSON>Ungaro</PERSON>.
   His remarkable daytime looks included satin-lined short cashmere
coats in sizzling colors topping some beautifully cut and draped
short crepe dresses.
   When it came to dressier clothes, <ORGANIZATION>Ungaro</ORGANIZATION> followed through
beautifully. His slinky short silk shifts in all colors topped by
floaty mousseline squares were perfect in their understatement.
   Of course, <ORGANIZATION>Ungaro</ORGANIZATION> had to have some fun with rich fabrics. He
used plenty of heavy guipure lace, draped lame floral fabrics, and
sequined, brocaded jackets or blouses to haute couture advantage.
   Karl Lagerfeld also had a light touch in his show for <ORGANIZATION>Chanel</ORGANIZATION>,
which won warm praise from the fashion crowd.
   The abbreviated styles were resolutely younger than ever. They
were so short and sweet they looked apt for the junior miss set.
   Lagerfeld continued some of his past Chanel ideas. For instance
the shortie jacket over legs alone became a sort of pretty
coat-dress this time and in fact was cut sexily like a tulip. It
could be worn with a half-skirt or a puff of chiffon.
   These Lolitas often paraded down the runway in long ``<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>''
or fitted riding jackets with deep decolletes. There were all kinds
of couture details: black velvet cuffs and lapels on the softest of
pinks, black and white raffia piping on many jackets and skirts,
graphic geometric patterns embroidered on a white mini-coat.
   To end it all in grand style, Lagerfeld brought out an array of
short-long evening gowns bathed in clouds of chiffon, sometimes
combined with elaborate guipure lace.
   Louis Feraud turned out a smashing collection of bright,
beautiful clothes showing the creator from the south of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in
top form. He led off with a garden party of emerald and violet
leaf-embroidered short suits with scoop necks, setting a sunny tone.
   Everything was bright and wearable, even the full, iridescent
taffeta garden-party gowns in shades of gold-red with tucks at
bustier and hemline.
   Feraud had lots to put anybody in a good mood. Sportive women
might like the emerald and black gros-grain blazer over a pleated
light satin emerald short skirt.
   A woman dressing for <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> would like the ivory white suits with
a black sunray yoke effect at the neck of a boxy jacket. The
broad-striped pastel linens would be winners for all kinds of
<DATE>summer</DATE> moments.
   An ebullient <ORGANIZATION>Feraud</ORGANIZATION> turned out a rainbow of pastels in crepe
dresses cut in arabesques or swirls topped by huge chiffon shawls.
   It was down to the sea for the end of the show with a gorgeous
line of sequined mermaid flapper dresses and prints in funny fish
motifs.
   All was light and lovely at <PERSON>Philippe Venet</PERSON>, who turned out his
usual superb couture looks _ this time sexier and more colorful
than ever.
   Not known to the masses, <PERSON>Venet</PERSON> is one of the rare couturiers who
owns his own business and makes a living by serving up custom-made
couture to a faithful clientele.
   He led off with lean raw silk outfits piped in satin, perhaps a
strapless dress and fitted jacket in bordeaux and coral setting the
tone for the clothes that followed. He featured some particularly
marvelous suits, scooping out many necklines to daring decolletes.
   The palette was lovely, and full of warm tones like tangerine,
peach, almond green, lilac and tender pink. But one shouldn't
forget the incomparably lovely iridescent satin and taffeta short
evening dresses with their huge bows and jeweled touches.
   <PERSON>Angelo Tarlazzi</PERSON>, the Italian-born couturier at <ORGANIZATION>Guy Laroche</ORGANIZATION> since
the designer died <DATE>last year</DATE>, went south of the border for his
inspiration. Some suggest he should have stayed there, since the
blouson toppers over narrow minis or ample peasant dresses with
stitched details looked more like ready-to-wear than couture.
   Not even the transparent chiffon-topped evening wear had enough
distinction to give the show cachet.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880314-0270 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-14-88 0625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Fashion:FrenchCouture     03-14 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Fashion: French Couture,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>BC-SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>FASHION: French Couture</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY700, NY702</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Suits are back in force for <DATE>spring</DATE> _ especially as
haute couture sees the picture. They look everything from wildly
extroverted to wearable for business and travel.
   And the crowning glory of all the couture pizazz is _ what else?
_ hats. The designers let their fantasy run mad, from the sublime
to the silly.
   For couture _ which is not for average shoppers, but serves
mainly as a strong prototype for what might be found on the racks _
here are ideas to look for:
   Suits are nearly always waist-hugging and short, with jackets
short or long to choose from, and shoulders still shaped, but more
played-down than in the past.
   Saint Laurent's suits hit both day and dressy notes. His
sharply-tailored long jackets with double-breasted or belted safari
effects are worn with knotted chiffon scarves at the neck for
softening the seriousness of the suit.
   Large boater-style hats give his suits a cachet of total chic.
   His dressier suit is plastered with a sequined cubistic design,
elegance and height added by a wrapped fez hat in a different
color, such as purple to contrast with a turquoise satin skirt.
   Dior suits are peppier than ever, but still in the daywear
category. They're charmingly bouncy with stiffened, full skirts,
very small waists and the crowning touch of tiny perched boater
hats.
   Lagerfeld at <ORGANIZATION>Chanel</ORGANIZATION> has brought back some great Chanel ideas in
suits that are just above the knee _ terrific white tweeds bordered
in bicolored ribbon piping. The topper? For this <DATE>spring</DATE>'s touch,
it's a large banded straw hat overturned like a salad bowl.
   His slinky long suits are harbingers of next winter; he says
they're definitely coming back. This is glorious news for those who
want to hide their knees. They look authoritative in checked and
solid ensembles with long tulip-wrapped jackets, and the salad-bowl
hat becomes bigger than ever.
   Budding out into springtime dressy looks, <PERSON>Nini Ricci</PERSON> showed
loads of suits with layers of ruffles on skirts, dressy jackets
fitted with a little padding on the shoulders, big stand-out peplum
effects on long jackets.
   Polka dots in these flirtatious clothes are often matched with a
big dotted sunhat.
   Jean-Louis <PERSON>Scherrer</PERSON>'s silk suits come right out of the hothouse
for <DATE>spring</DATE>, with flowers all over them _ maybe teaming black and
white with bright flower prints in skirts, lapels and cuffs in
ultra-fitted suits. And of course, the big-brimmed garden-party hat
nearly eclipses the shoulders with flowers.
   More about hats: Solidly sane or simply crazy, they add a fillip
to any outfit, and lots of fun to the fashion party. Sailor hats
are a favorite at <ORGANIZATION>Louis Feraud</ORGANIZATION>. Maryll Lanvin opts for little
flower baskets to top her fussily feminine short outfits in a
collection based on her ``secret garden.''
   With flowers in patterns, appliques and even sleeve shapes in
these collections, naturally flowered hats are de rigueur.
   <PERSON>Pierre Cardin</PERSON> practically made a whole outfit with his gigantic
yellow wildflower chapeau covering the model's face, if not her
body _ which was clad in a slinging black mini.
   Kal Lagerfeld added an original touch to his Chanel collection
with the dashing multi-layered straw hat fluted in waves like a
seashell, but shaped more like a flounced stand-out skirt.
   <PERSON>Marc Bohan</PERSON> at Dior branched out into tongue-in-cheek fantasy by
pairing a feathery fright wig with all the allure of a jungle
``Hottentot'' to go with a draped zebra-striped dress.
   And in the devil-may-care vein, wonder boy <PERSON>Christian Lacroix</PERSON>
matched zany hats to some of his fanciful outfits. For a circus
look, he topped a puffy-skirted short dress with a towering tube
slightly curved for laughs. In a sunny beach-inspired mood, he
shaped a straw hat like a whorled sea-snail.
   With these showy or relatively safe toppers, there are plenty of
choices to try on and take home from the hat bar.
   But make sure you get the quick lift you'd get at a cocktail bar
_ rather than a hangover.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890323-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-23-89 1317EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Fashion     03-23 0822</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fashion,0847</SECOND>
<HEAD>Choice of Styles Offered in Ready-to-Wear Fashion Circus</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Short or long skirts, fitted or trapeze coats _ the
fashion capital saw several silhouettes during the winter
ready-to-wear fashion circus.
   As fashion sails into the <DATE>1990s</DATE>, the passage may be a bit rough
for women looking for direction and designers who don't seem to know
where to turn.
   But the good news is that individuals are truly free to choose
their style, whether in pants and skirts or jackets and coats. And
there is no evidence of designers conspiring to put women into
stylishly ridiculous gear.
   Those fed up with the skirt-length dilemma may just abandon the
skirt altogether and wear a beautiful hacking jacket or dressier
model over opaque tights as Lagerfeld displayed at both his own and
at the Chanel collection, with an elegant bow to the <DATE>1960s</DATE>.
   Elsewhere, skirts were the familiar short lengths to just above
the knee, or nearly ankle-length in trumpet shapes, pleated or
handsome in a circle of leather at <ORGANIZATION>Ungaro</ORGANIZATION>.
   Christian <PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON> went his own eccentric way, showing softly
feminine silhouettes and his favorite flowing trapeze styles. Some
loved his loud patchwork looks for ready-to-wear; others were
dazzled by his more expensive ``Luxe'' collection, shimmering with
Byzantine splendor.
   Shoulders were softened or reduced to natural proportions in
feminine silhouettes that marked the waist without undue emphasis.
   The new long jacket was gently fitted, sometimes with a
martingale belting the back, while some were asymmetrical in front,
or outlined in bold piping. Yet others appeared in swallow-tail or
cutaway style.
   Snug spencers, battle jackets and boleros shared the honors for
diminutive jacket styles.
   From the men's wardrobe but looking handsomely feminine were
pinstriped bankers' suits at <PERSON>Hanae Mori</PERSON> and the straight tweed
trousers pleated at the waist by master tailors <PERSON>Yves Saint Laurent</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Jean-Louis Scherrer</PERSON>.
   Long redingotes and short hooded duffel jackets looked terrific,
but <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> also offers some handsome belted trenches, lounging coats
or car coats in luxury cashmere or wool blends _ sometimes collared
and lined with generous lashings of fur.
   Capes were a big item at <ORGANIZATION>Saint Laurent</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Patrick Kelly</PERSON>, whose
Little Red Riding Hood was a show-stealer. And Italians <PERSON>Angelo
Tarlazzi</PERSON> and <PERSON>Romeo Gigli</PERSON> placed their models in cocoon coats.
Gigli's fabulous Byzantine-embroidered cocoon made news over his
outfits in butterfly-light fabrics.
   The color spectrum zoomed from a range of darks _ especially
chocolate brown and charcoal _ to autumnal <ORGANIZATION>Beaujolais</ORGANIZATION>, cognac,
caramel, gold, mustard, olive, forest green, and misty shades of
lavender and pink.
   <PERSON>Claude Montana</PERSON>'s collection brought out hues of blue, from
glacier to deep petrol in his trouser suits.
   But there were hot colors, too, and those who love red will be
happy, as every shade pepped up the runways, from garnet,
fire-engine or poppy to orange-coral, fuchsia and magenta.
   The fabrics gave new softness to the clothes, with flecked
tweeds, big and bold glen or windowpane grid plaids, looking peppy
when placed on the diagonal.
   Butter-soft leather, calfskin or suede gave the appeal of luxury
to many outfits _ remarkable when appliqued with arabesque designs
on short Yves Saint Laurent jackets.
   A taste for exoticism ran to wild-animal prints, done in various
styles and fabrics at <PERSON>Hanae Mori</PERSON>, <PERSON>Scherrer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>. But
the only true furs seen were fox, vicuna, Mongolian lamb and mink.
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s mink was amazing, dyed in his favorite blues and ridged
to look like chenille or corduroy. Otherwise coats looked
appealingly warm in bright mohairs or <LOCATION>Shetland</LOCATION>.
   Wool and silk jerseys were used generously in softer styles _
especially in dresses, which made a modest comeback for day wear.
Knits often had ethnic overtones, black and white at <ORGANIZATION>Chanel</ORGANIZATION>,
startlingly bright at <LOCATION>Lacroix</LOCATION>.
   For late-day, the designers came up with some stunning cocktail
suits or dresses with jackets _ all fit to sup at the Ritz. Among
the most memorable: Chanel's lightly fitted gold corduroy-ridged
lame jacket over a satin-piped wrapped skirt topped with floppy
satin bows.
   Black velvet gave opulent allure to day or evening clothes, and
crimped panne or cut velvet added old-fashioned charm to much of the
evening wear.
   In fact, fabrics for after sunset were so luxurious that they
defined the lines of the outfit. Satin and slithery crepe de chine
were favorites for slinky dinner gowns or pajamas.
   Black silk ``grain de poudre'' was used in all versions of the
``smoking'' or tuxedo style _ still a wardrobe staple, whether with
pants or a skirt.
   Sheer chiffon revealed body lines, while iridescent taffeta
lightly puffed around it in other models. Lame fabrics and
embroidery made evening wear look bewitchingly shimmering, sometimes
sexy, but never glitzy.
   And the lame brocades at houses like <PERSON>Hanae Mori</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Saint Laurent</PERSON> shone with an extra dash of exoticism as the designers
went at least partly to the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>, Byzantium or <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION> for
inspiration.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900124-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-24-90 1315EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Fashion     01-24 0665</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fashion,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saint Laurent Triumphs, Montana Flops</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Yves Saint Laurent</PERSON> won a long, standing ovation
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> as he waltzed down the runway, kissing his models after a
show of <DATE>summer</DATE> haute couture featuring clean, colorful classics as
only he can make.
   The crowd's enthusiasm contrasted with <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s debut of
ready-to-wear wizard <PERSON>Claude Montana</PERSON> as haute couturier for the
celebrated house of <ORGANIZATION>Lanvin</ORGANIZATION>, a sad moment in which <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> seemed
out of his element.
   ``<PERSON>Yves Saint Laurent</PERSON> was more to the couture point,'' said
fashionable <PERSON>Paloma Picasso</PERSON>. ``I loved his evening wear, with so
many ideas and such fabulous color combinations, as usual.''
   Saint Laurent's day wear was both striking and wearable. It
centered on sharp white, ivory or navy ottoman or shantung suits _
including sleek pants or short skirts with tailored jackets.
   Disregarding fashion critics who tell him to discard shoulder
pads, <PERSON>Saint Laurent</PERSON> still shows his daytime clothes neatly padded
out to give shape. But the blouses underneath have softer shapes in
scoop-necked satin or organza models, with cap or raglan sleeves.
   He dedicated many models to past or present entertainment stars.
Some looked downright odd, like the frog-buttoned black gazar coat
over a pants suit dedicated to <PERSON>Rita Hayworth</PERSON>.
   But his homage to his home in <LOCATION>Morocco</LOCATION> was a simple white satin
sheath topped by a stunning jacket that made the dress. Engineered
by master embroiderer <PERSON>Francois Lesage</PERSON>, it was an extravaganza of
mirror sequins, beads and crystals.
   In easy-to-wear daytime lines, <PERSON>Saint Laurent</PERSON> turned out a soft
midnight blue silk chemise dress with big white buttons and several
silk shirt waists in jungle-panther prints.
   His faultless use of fabric and color went from slinky little
cream satin ``Mademoiselle de <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>'' short tea dresses to a fresh
blue plaid organdy dance dress with puffy sleeves and deep
decollete.
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, by contrast, lacked the elegant elaboration of haute
couture. ``It was pure <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>,'' tersely commented <PERSON>Ellin Saltzman</PERSON>,
corporate fashion director of <ORGANIZATION>R.H. Macy Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   Not that the clothes were bad; they had <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s original
touch, and the great ready-to-wear creator of blousons put on lots
of them in luxury fabrics such as pink-lined copper satin over lean
linen pants.
   But the poor reception would seem a setback for <ORGANIZATION>Midland Bank</ORGANIZATION>,
which took over <LOCATION>Lanvin</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> and chose <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> to lead the
couture creation. Some observers thought <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> had done better
collections under his own label.
   The billowy white short gazar ``trench coats'' had <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>
cachet. <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> and earthy colors like khaki, tobacco, chocolate and
clay were featured in luxury fabrics.
   Montana based his silhouette on lean pants and jodhpurs, with
most interest in the toppers like a striped sequined shortie duffel
coat over navy shorts.
   But the audience looked mainly perplexed, with some sniffing
that the combinations just did not make a couture look. Rich
clientele who usually love <PERSON>Lanvin</PERSON> are unlikely to go for the
austere evening wear, with spider web see-through effects on top.
   However, lovely late-day ideas in fabulous fabrics were paraded
at the young couture house of Lecoanet-Hemant.
   The clothes were form-fitting, with clever draping, insertion of
elaborate lace touches under waistlines, lashings of white organza
on collars or skirt flounces adding dashes of fun.
   A typical little sexy cocktail outfit paired an asymmetrical
fitted jacket over a tiny lean coral leather skirt.
   Designer <PERSON>Didier Lecoanet</PERSON> also worked with new raffia lace trim
and gold braid effects in the bright outfits. Other summery touches
were in the mother-of-pearl shell embroideries.
   With some cutouts revealing skin for <DATE>summer</DATE>, plenty of bouncy
evening wear with short skirts in front and train effects in back,
the festive outfits in light organza, brocade, taffeta faille and
gazar were truly worthy of the haute couture label.
   The clothes, costing many thousands of dollars per outfit, are
mainly for show. Only about 2,000 women regularly buy couture,
which is meant to power the fashion houses' other activities, from
accessories to perfumes.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890710-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-89 0114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Fashion:France     07-10 0820</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Fashion: France,0844</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Fashion: France</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY702, NY703</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The good news about styles for the <DATE>early 1990s</DATE> is
that they seem to be aimed at women with minds of their own, rather
than at sheepish fashionplates to be herded into ridiculous garb to
look trendy.
   There's a vast choice in the offerings to send the <DATE>1980s</DATE> out in
style. The clothes are hardly revolutionary, but the best are timely
and as freshly appealing as champagne.
   Designers are letting go of their recent visions of bouncy,
ruffly little girls in poufs, as well as slinky vamps.
   Finally, they're thinking of women who work, travel and like to
feel easy and pretty in whatever they choose. Whether the clothes
are based on masculine styles or are all dressed up for evening,
they are presented with an eye to both ease and elegance.
   Silhouettes and fabrics are softer in these new clothes, with a
light touch of body-consciousness in the structuring. Shoulders are
padded for shape but never dominate.
   Skirt lengths are barely relevant, though quite long and above
the knee are the younger-looking norms. Karl Lagerfeld at <ORGANIZATION>Chanel</ORGANIZATION>
dismisses any discussion of skirt lengths as being ``for old
crones.'' His answer to youth is to show some outfits without any
skirt at all _ simply tights under handsome jackets.
   Trousers are a welcome solution, though the wide A-line look has
been cut back to somewhat straighter lines _ on the dressy side in
suits _ with waist tucking, as at <ORGANIZATION>Saint Laurent</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Jean-Louis
Scherrer</PERSON>.
   Jackets are starred everywhere. They range from very long styles,
flattering as they cover the derriere, to snug spencers, battle
jackets and boleros. Details may be strong in piping, zigzag
fastening, little belts or vents at the back.
   And several designers give fantasy touches with swallowtail or
cutaway styles in dressier models.
   Coats are another big story. If you like trench or belted
``bathrobe'' styles, you'll find handsome ones for fall.
   Italians designers like <PERSON>Tarlazzi</PERSON> and <PERSON>Romeo Gigli</PERSON> ``cocoon'' their
models in sumptuous coats. Tarlazzi's camel-colored wrap with a
bright lining is remarkable. Gigli's opulent Byzantine cocoons are
so colorful they seem to have already matured into butterflies.
   Christian Lacroix plays with the cape theme in loud color
combinations with his short suits or in more subdued styles to evoke
the <ORGANIZATION>England of Vita Sackville-West</ORGANIZATION> and the literary Bloomsbury set.
   Capes are glamorous at <ORGANIZATION>Saint Laurent</ORGANIZATION> and hot numbers at <PERSON>Patrick
Kelly</PERSON>, where little caped riding hoods are as fun as they are
colorful.
   As classic suits have come back into focus in the fashion
picture, so have soft dresses, looking better than ever as buttoned
coat dresses, shirtdresses and little shifts.
   Fabrics are important for these stylishly soft clothes, making
them more fluid and sensual than ever _ even the flecked caviar
tweeds. Large plaids, stripes and houndstooth checks offer new
choices at <ORGANIZATION>Christian Lacroix</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Scherrer</PERSON> and elsewhere.
   Synthetics such as fake furs and wool or silk blends are looking
better than ever. And the new softer, lighter woolens are a boon to
travelers, who'd rather arrive not looking rumpled.
   Folk art is making a chic comeback with <PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON>'s favorite
Provencal motifs or kilim rug designs, as well as the handsome black
and white Chanel knits borrowed from Indian weaves.
   Scherrer and <PERSON>Hanae Mori</PERSON> are keen on exotic animal prints and
weaves, and <PERSON>Scherrer</PERSON>'s feather patterns add a light touch as well.
   Look for temptingly light jerseys, cashmeres, and knits in cables
and other textures this season, along with soft flannel and
broadcloth. The new tweed and serge don't scratch.
   The up-to-date gold, mustard, olive and forest green. Lavender
and deep purple or pink add a heathery touch to autumn wardrobes.
   But <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> isn't timid about color. The designers are prodigious
in their use of red _ everything from deep raspberry or garnet to
cardinal, orange-coral, fuchsia, fire engine or flame. These also
mix well with deep brown, purple or black.
   The evening scene means a transformation from workaday outfits to
splendidly feminine clothes for cocktails at the Ritz or dinner at
<ORGANIZATION>Maxim's</ORGANIZATION>. Black is still reliable for sexy little lace or velvet
numbers, and never before have silk ``grain de poudre'' tuxedo
outfits with pants or skirts looked so attractively varied or
feminine.
   But overall, we're seeing more late-day color, in decollete or
``bustier'' dresses with practical little jackets.
   Lame and brocade give dazzle to clothes for welcoming in <DATE>1990</DATE> _
especially the Japanese flower-print patterns at <PERSON>Hanae Mori</PERSON>, and the
Byzantine motifs at <LOCATION>Lacroix</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Gigli</PERSON> and elsewhere.
   Scene-stealing hats for these glamorous clothes are <PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON>'s
``mad hatter'' chapeau, his big buccaneer hat, and large-brimmed
skimmers at <ORGANIZATION>Chanel</ORGANIZATION>. Turbans, berets and fur toques are also good
head warmers as well as fashionable.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901019-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-19-90 2016EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Fashion     10-19 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Fashion,0667</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gilt-Edged Givenchy, Leggy Lagerfeld</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hubert de <ORGANIZATION>Givenchy</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>summer</DATE> ready-to-wear show
<DATE>Friday</DATE> burst out with lovely and wearable styles. This past master
of couture made the luxury clothes look very expensive, which they
are.
   It was a gilded collection, featuring gold threads in the first
knit items right through gilt nailheads all over, plus gold lame
shining through the colorful silk print dinner dresses at the end.
   On a new youth kick, the man who invented <PERSON>Audrey Hepburn</PERSON>'s best
``gamine'' styles for her films more than 30 years ago gives his
latest styles modern updates. Among the youngest: a strapless
cable-knit top with a shortie black tulip-wrap skirt rimmed in gold
button details.
   His ballooning silky harem pants looked refreshing this week.
Everybody else is showing pants that look as though they'd been
molded on the model.
   Givenchy showed many well-cut straight trousers with good
cardigan and cable-knit tops, or jackets cut long and straight or
rather full. The fine poplins, linens and plenty of gold buttons
should please the rich set of a certain age.
   Younger fans will like his airy organza dresses and
off-the-shoulder minis in harlequin or bold fruit and flower
prints.
   The serpent theme gliding through a few collections here looks
gaily-colored on bright leather belts, narrow skirts, sleeve
details.
   Karl Lagerfeld also aims for younger looks, continuing his leggy
themes with good jackets and loose tops he started last year.
   Some of the best of this slim-leg look topped by flowing jackets
or cape effects came out in silky jersey fabrics in colors ranging
from subtle linden green or beige to salmon.
   Lagerfeld's pants are cigarette-slim, or simply cotton tights.
The young, but not very flattering, favorite style is to cut off
the dark tights at various lengths along the leg, showing bootees
below.
   Lots of ideas popped up from little apron outfits with shirred
waists right through to plaid jackets of all lengths and cuts worn
over the tights with matching plaid small boots.
   Bright piping on asymmetrical little dresses or sleeveless white
jackets had a certain young charm, along with the buttoned plastron
effects over short linen dresses in bright red or sky blue.
   Lagerfeld also went in for some graphic and check effects, using
checked sheer wraps over maillot bathing suits, and sequined
checkerboard decor for the evening wear in trapeze topped minis or
slinky sheaths.
   <PERSON>Bernard Perris</PERSON> also went all-out for graphic prints and sequined
late-day wear, in minis, long pants, and easy toppers.
   This designer has a raft of <DATE>summer</DATE> ideas, ranging from lace-up
safari styles to neon-striped graphics and body-molding leather
outfits in hot shades of vermilion, bright blue and cyclamen.
   His luscious sheer white embroidered blouses with tight sequined
black pants and gold belts evoked a brassy pirate set to swing at
the disco.
   <PERSON>Thierry Mugler</PERSON> put on a show worthy of a striptease nightclub,
but not all went smoothly.
   <PERSON>Danielle Mitterrand</PERSON>, wife of the French president, and Culture
Minister <PERSON>Jack Lang</PERSON> were among those who waited nearly two hours in
sauna-type heat waiting for the show to begin.
   Before <PERSON>Mugler</PERSON> wound up with a nearly nude <PERSON>Diana Ross</PERSON> (with
chunky glass just decently covering the strategic points and a
fuchsia tulle cape), he'd brought out several other Imam and other
famous models, clothed in outrageous costumes.
   It was mainly lycra and skin, plus a few little bunnies in
bloomer-playsuits, and even a Chinese-lantern outfit in acid shades
of pink and green.
   The rare true dress or suit was applauded, in one case a
pleasantly draped white sheath as worn by famed model of the <DATE>1970s</DATE>,
<PERSON>Lauren Htton</PERSON>.
   Another audience came back later to see <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> swan down the
catwalk. But most observers agreed: <PERSON>Mugler</PERSON> should either make
clothes and show them as such or take up showbiz as his real
profession.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901015-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-15-90 1944EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Fashion 1stLd-Writethru a0710 10-15 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Fashion, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0710,0788</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Designers in Overtime with New '90s Swing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS five grafs of new material.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   British designers have reinvented the Sixties with
a sexy, snappy '90s swing for next <DATE>spring</DATE> and <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   Nostalgia for the '60s isn't surprising for the country that
invented the miniskirt. But the designers didn't wallow in it. They
pushed it forward into the very modern Nineties with some of the
best collections seen here in years.
   The British look for <DATE>1991</DATE> is short, simple and sexy.
   The sportswear influence is strong, with cropped jackets and
shorts the hot favorites. But the big news is that dresses are
back, especially skimpy shifts ala <PERSON>Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis</PERSON> and
<ORGANIZATION>Audrey Hepburn</ORGANIZATION>.
   It's definitely going to be a white <DATE>summer</DATE> in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, though
the color palette runs from black and navy to summer pastels,
occasionally vivid tropical hues, and a smattering of the bright
and bold prints featured in <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION>.
   ``It's a '90s version of simplicity dressing,'' said designer
<PERSON>Benny Ong</PERSON>. ``I think the '60s heralded the innocence of it, and the
'90s makes a full circle and says now we have arrived. I think the
difference is, it's a realized woman who is dressing now - and
there is a choice.''
   Designers who lived through the '60s - <PERSON>Caroline Charles</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Edina
Ronay</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Jean Muir</PERSON> - and those too young to remember - <PERSON>Arabella
Pollen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jasper Conran</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bruce Oldfield</PERSON> - showed very individual,
wearable collections with an accent on youth at shows over the
<DATE>weekend</DATE> and on <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Caroline Charles</PERSON> did trapeze-line coats and short little shifts,
some in black and white prints, set off by <PERSON>Jackie</PERSON> Kennedy-style
pillbox hats and big sunglasses.
   Arabella Pollen did her sexiest collection yet, featuring
houndstooth check jackets worn with hot pants or hipster miniskirts
and minishifts for evening decorated with pieces of cut mirror. ``A
sort of neon <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>,'' the designer said.
   <PERSON>Bruce Oldfield</PERSON> featured a pared-down look with fluid nautical
print silk shifts, trapeze dresses over slinky jersey bodysuits,
and glamorous asymmetrical sand-colored chiffons with gilt chains
setting off the bust or derriere.
   <PERSON>Paul Costello</PERSON> did his classic linen separates in sherbet colors
and a lovely white linen shift but his back-to-front jacket dresses
in shiny brocades were less successful.
   <PERSON>Betty Jackson</PERSON> mixed figure-hugging pants with loose jackets and,
with an eye to the not-so-young, did some knee-length shifts. <ORGANIZATION>Edina
Ronay</ORGANIZATION> featured mint and pink pastel sequins for evening with
chiffon and raw silk in the same colors. <PERSON>Jasper Conran</PERSON>'s lean and
fluid classically tailored jackets, shorts and short knife-pleated
skirts were back on the catwalk.
   <PERSON>Rifat Ozbek</PERSON>, who has the biggest international clout, opted for
a video presentation instead of a catwalk show. Titled
``Afrodizzia,'' it featured hot African colors, sequins and prints
as well as Rasta ragamuffins in African print leggings and rough
linen tops embroidered with compact discs.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> also kept its reputation for the wild and wacky.
   <PERSON>Vivienne Westwood</PERSON>, who originated punk fashion and won this
year's Designer of the Year, marched to her own tune in her ``Cut,
Slash and Pull'' collection. It featured very demure '40s-style
tailored suits with midi-skirts alongside slashed and ripped denim
shorts and dresses and shocking bikinis and shorts embellished with
bow-tied phallic symbols.
   Westwood, honored <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at an award ceremony at <PERSON>Royal
Albert Hall</PERSON>, developed the punk look and incorporated anarchy into
fashion. One of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s most unorthodox and influential
designers, she has designed for the Sex Pistols, Boy <PERSON>George</PERSON> and
<LOCATION>Bananarama</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Pam Hogg</PERSON>'s very sexy cotton bustiers, peek-a-boo catsuits, and
short-shorts in dark red, smoked green and mauve, were worn by
models with shaved heads and a wide grey stripe across their eyes.
   Workers For Freedom, the design duo of <PERSON>Graham Fraser</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard
Nott</PERSON> who won the <DATE>1989</DATE> Designer of the Year award, picked ``Delicate
Bondage'' for their theme. Some models were strapped into soft
knee-length dresses with leather harnesses. Others wore brightly
printed kimono styles and shirts with evil eyes.
   Body Map's body-hugging ``Square'' collection showed the
influence of Mondrian prints. Ghosts featured clinging minis in
lime and tangerine.
   Red or Dead showed a short red playsuit in synthetic rubber
diving suit material, shorts with red shield stamps that peel off,
and baby dolls embroidered with ``Kiss Me Quick'' and other
sayings.
   Several designers noted there were very few American buyers and
said it was due to the weak dollar and strong British pound. But
Red or Dead spokeswoman <PERSON>Catherine Morris</PERSON> said it had brought down
its prices on clothes and was ``doing outrageously well in
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900625-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-25-90 0100EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Fashion-Fraiberger     06-25 0625</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fashion-Fraiberger,0645</SECOND>
<HEAD>Candice Fraiberger's Divinely Dressy Styles for Americans</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Fashion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Candice Fraiberger</PERSON> is her own best model: tall,
slim and totally Parisienne, she is a beautiful blonde who
specializes in dressy clothes to make others look beautiful too.
   Following a modest start four years ago, Fraiberger (pronounced
``fray-bear-jay'') is gradually proving she has an authoritative
flair for creating boutique clothes.
   Her new winter line unveiled last week showed well-cut
sarong-draped skirts, neat boleros with baroque appliqued
embroidery over strapless dresses, draped chiffons, plenty of
sequins and sparkle combined with lace, satin, taffeta and velvet.
   The only criticism of these finished clothes is that some look a
bit too fussy for the French. But so far, that doesn't matter,
because Fraiberger is now better-known in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> than in
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   She regularly travels to posh American department stores, and is
well-known in emporia like <ORGANIZATION>Neiman-Marcus</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Saks</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Nordstrom</ORGANIZATION>'s.
   Her clothes lack the hard-edge chic of styles by someone like
<PERSON>Jacqueline de Ribes</PERSON>, another society beauty designing her own label
line _ whose stricter, slinky silhouettes often recall Yves Saint
Laurent.
   But the Fraiberger line has more than a touch of haute couture
and therefore class. It's made in workshops in the <LOCATION>Rue
Poissonniere</LOCATION>, the heart of the garment district east of central
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, and is lovingly finished by seamstresses in the couture
tradition appreciated by connoisseurs.
   The luxury fabrics and detailing put them into a category
superior to ready-to-wear. But in their price-range of <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> to
<MONEY>$6,000 dollars</MONEY> per outfit, the clothes are worth watching.
   For price and quality, they compare favorably with lines like
<PERSON>Christian Lacroix</PERSON>'s ``luxe,'' whose price tags can be double or
triple Fraiberger's.
   Indeed, with feminine touches like flared umbrella skirts over
crinolines and contrasts of pink and black velvet in embroidered
dresses with decorated matadors' boleros, one sees a definite
<PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON> influence at work here.
   ``Personally I never have time to think about what I wear,''
said <PERSON>Ms. Fraiberger</PERSON> after her small showroom parade of winter
cocktail and evening clothes. ``I'm totally absorbed by what I'm
making for others.''
   But she did look smashing in her black-and-white cotton <DATE>summer</DATE>
suit with beaded, embroidered lapels, fitted for elegance with just
a hint of sexiness.
   Paradoxically this ``fortysomething'' lady (who looks at least
15 years younger) has more fans in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> than in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   ``I had learned about clothes from working in retail in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,
but it was the Americans who first enjoyed and ordered my styles
when I started my own business,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Fraiberger</PERSON>.
   Married to an investment counselor and mother of two grown
children, <PERSON>Ms. Fraiberger</PERSON> says she is financing her own business,
not backed by any grand consortium as many style creators are today.
   ``Sadly enough, I don't even have a proper boutique yet in
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,'' she said, adding that her friends and those in the know
come to her showroom at <ORGANIZATION>Rue Aguesseau</ORGANIZATION>, just around the corner from
the fashionable <ORGANIZATION>Faubourg Saint-Honore</ORGANIZATION>.
   However, she's selling well in style-conscious countries like
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, and is at last attracting favorable comments
from the French fashion press as well.
   ``I think the clothes look very well-made,'' said <PERSON>Christine
Marais</PERSON>, of French <PERSON>Harper</PERSON>'s Bazaar.
   ``The feel of dressiness is quite American,'' observed <PERSON>Laurence
Beurdeley</PERSON>, of the glossy fashion magazine ``l'Officiel de la Mode.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Fraiberger</PERSON> says she believes in dressing up rather than
down, and is proud to look spiffy as a bandbox herself.
   ``I think the French are wrong to affect the casual styles seen
so much on the streets here,'' she says. ``It shows a sloppiness of
mind. I understand tourists wearing practical shoes for
sightseeing. But I think women should do their best to be feminine
and elegant.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901018-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-18-90 0006EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-France-Fashion     10-18 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-France-Fashion,0726</SECOND>
<HEAD>Latest Fashion Styles are Strictly for Spring Chickens</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Thursday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos sent Oct. 17</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Young, skin-baring and refreshing are the first
messages as ready-to-wear shows for next <DATE>spring</DATE> get under way.
   More than 80 designers will be showing for the next week in a
courtyard in the <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION> and elsewhere, spending up to <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> for
the larger runway shows.
   There appears to be as much hype and crowd interest as in the
past, despite of market downtrends and the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> crisis.
   Lolita Lempicka got applause <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for a lilting collection
that featured micro-models with bustiers and bras shaped like
underwear.
   This lingerie trend started out with several houses last season,
and <LOCATION>Lempicka</LOCATION> took it into a perky ingenue vein, adding lace to
little green or pink satin slip dresses, covering them decently
with peppy short trench coats.
   She, like several other designers showing this week, liked the
look of bare backs crossed by straps, and occasional bare midriffs.
As her forte is suits, she put plenty of pep back into grey flannel
by adding appliqued flower details.
   Some of her shortie prints had a certain <DATE>1940s</DATE> nostalgia with
their fit and head-wraps, though they were far too short for that
period.
   Those wanting to dress up Lolita-style might try some of the
little white dresses decked out in big pearl or silver baubles and
buttons. If they were not in light <DATE>summer</DATE> fabrics, they would look
just fine along with the skaters at <ORGANIZATION>Rockefeller Center</ORGANIZATION> at
<LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION>.
   Lempicka showed some safari suits and appealing sailor looks,
turning up already elsewhere as well.
   At <ORGANIZATION>Dorothee Bis</ORGANIZATION>, the clothes also had a youthful bent - with
shorts, shortie jackets, flaring tent dresses, corsair and longer
pants. They came in red-white-blue linens and kabig, a kind of
smooth broadcloth like that used in pea jackets.
   <PERSON>Paco Rabanne</PERSON>'s show in a small Left Bank shop was also a hit for
the younger set who can wear the stretch fabrics and micro-minis.
   The Spanish-born inventor of the chain-mail and metallic dresses
put a witty little flourish on some of his bare-midriff cotton
outfits: they were made of cotton patterned just like his original
metal-plate models of some 20 years ago. Some were even cut and
metal ringed, though the plates were cotton this time.
   Metallic lame stripes in green and warm yellow added late-day
dash to trouser outfits.
   <PERSON>Ishiro Kimijima</PERSON>'s collection was one of the most creative so
far. This 61-year-old Japanese brought out a smart group of
beachwear with fishnet inspiration, a good use of raffia, lots of
