<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011389-0001 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 4722 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 13, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 2; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
268 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MARTIN LUTHER KING DAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<DATE>Monday</DATE> marks the celebration of <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Day</ORGANIZATION>. The 60th anniversary of 
his birth is <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Closed: All government offices, courts, banks, schools, libraries and post 
offices. 
</P>
<P>
Open: Stock and commodity exchanges and many businesses. <ORGANIZATION>RTD</ORGANIZATION> buses will follow 
daily schedules. 
</P>
<P>
Among the celebrations are: 
</P>
<P>
The second annual celebration for the I Have a <ORGANIZATION>Dream Foundation</ORGANIZATION> takes place 
today at <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> in the auditorium at <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Junior High School</ORGANIZATION>, 4120 11th Ave. 
It will feature the one-act play, "Freedom Comes of Age." 
</P>
<P>
The Baha'i community presents "Martin Luther King: A Man of Peace," a program 
featuring speakers and entertainment <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 
Baha'i Center, 5755 Rodeo Road. 
</P>
<P>
The fourth annual Kingdom Day Parade on <DATE>Monday</DATE> begins at <TIME>11 a.m</TIME>. The route 
travels east along <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Boulevard, beginning at <ORGANIZATION>Crenshaw 
Boulevard</ORGANIZATION> and ending at <LOCATION>Exposition Park</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Student organizations of the <ORGANIZATION>Claremont Colleges</ORGANIZATION> will sponsor a commemorative 
ceremony <DATE>Monday</DATE> at noon in the <ORGANIZATION>McKenna Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> on the <ORGANIZATION>Claremont McKenna 
College</ORGANIZATION> campus in <LOCATION>Claremont</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The third annual King Day drive for food and clothing for the homeless will 
take place <DATE>Monday</DATE> when hundreds of volunteers will go door to door asking for 
donations that will be picked up later in the day. Sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Southern 
Christian Leadership Conference</ORGANIZATION>, SANE/FREEZE and the <ORGANIZATION>L.A. Homeless Healthcare 
Project</ORGANIZATION>, volunteers will gather at <TIME>11:30 a.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Holman Methodist Church</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>3320</DATE> 
<ORGANIZATION>W. Adams Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Bethel Lutheran Church</ORGANIZATION>, 700 E. 70th St., <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, and the 
Church in <LOCATION>Ocean Park</LOCATION>, 235 Hill <ORGANIZATION>St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Part of exhibit at newly opened Martin Luther King Jr. Legacy Assn. 
MICHAEL EDWARDS / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
List 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011589-0059 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 5593 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 15, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 6; Page 1; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
847 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
KING SITE HONORS HIS MEMORY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES HILLINGER, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ATLANTA 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Dennis Ulysees</PERSON>, 31, a stonemason from <LOCATION>Tacoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, stood in front of <ORGANIZATION>Martin 
Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION>'s resting place, his right arm wrapped around his daughter, 
<PERSON>Casandra</PERSON>, 10. Neither spoke for several minutes. Both just stood there gazing 
at the tomb. 
</P>
<P>
As they left, Ulysees explained he had brought his daughter to the <ORGANIZATION>Martin 
Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. National Historic Site so she could learn more about the slain 
civil rights leader. "I want her to know him, to know how important he was for 
black people like us," <PERSON>Ulysees</PERSON> said. "I want her to live her life with his life 
as a model." 
</P>
<P>
A few minutes later, <PERSON>Charlene Mitchell Rogers</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> television newscaster, 
appeared with her son, <PERSON>Jonathan</PERSON>, 8. "I came to <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> especially to visit the 
site," <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said. "I brought my son along because I believe it is essential 
he come here. 
</P>
<P>
"He has never known segregation," continued <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON>, 39. "He has grown up in a 
privileged environment. I want to make certain he knows who he is and where he 
came from, that this man was responsible for the freedoms he has. I don't want 
him ever to forget." 
</P>
<P>
Every day people gather here in the heart of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s Sweet Auburn district to 
pay homage to <PERSON>King</PERSON>, who died <DATE>April 4, 1968</DATE>, in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, the victim of an 
assassin's bullet. But on this day, which would have been <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s <DATE>60th birthday</DATE>, 
thousands are expected to gather at the site's reflecting pool where his tomb 
is mounted on a pedestal. Inscribed on his crypt are <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s words: "Free at 
last. Free at last. Thank God Almighty I'm free at last." 
</P>
<P>
The two-block-long national historic site was set aside by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE> and 
has been administered since by the <ORGANIZATION>National Park Service</ORGANIZATION>. Its purpose is to 
protect and interpret for the benefit, inspiration and education of present and 
future generations the place where <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> was born, lived, 
worked and worshiped. 
</P>
<P>
"Last year 840,000 visitors came here, half black, half white," explained 
<PERSON>Randolph Scott</PERSON>, 58, a former <LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, high school history teacher who has 
been the site's superintendent for the <DATE>last four years</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Among the site's points of interest: the home at 501 <LOCATION>Auburn Ave.</LOCATION> where <PERSON>King</PERSON> was 
born; his tomb a block away at the <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Center for 
<ORGANIZATION>Non-Violent Social Change</ORGANIZATION>, founded in <DATE>1968</DATE> and headed by his wife, <PERSON>Coretta 
Scott King</PERSON>; and <ORGANIZATION>Ebenezer Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION>, located two blocks from his 
birthplace. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Like Father, Grandfather 
</P>
<P>
His father, <PERSON>Martin Luther King Sr.</PERSON>, was pastor of the church from <DATE>1931</DATE> to <DATE>1975</DATE>; 
his grandfather, <PERSON>A. D. Williams</PERSON>, presided from <DATE>1894</DATE> to <DATE>1931</DATE>. <PERSON>Martin Luther King 
Jr.</PERSON> preached his first sermon at <ORGANIZATION>Ebenezer Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION> when he was 17 and 
served as co-pastor with his father from <DATE>1960</DATE> to <DATE>1968</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
It was there that his body lay in state and also where his mother, <PERSON>Alberta 
Williams King</PERSON>, was slain <DATE>six years later</DATE> as she played the organ during a 
religious service. 
</P>
<P>
At the two-story, 14-room Queen <PERSON>Anne</PERSON> clapboard home where King was born and 
lived until <DATE>1941</DATE>, visitors are taken on a tour by ranger <PERSON>Shelly Lewis</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"Many people say they can feel <PERSON>Dr. King</PERSON>'s spirit, feel his presence in this 
house," said <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON>, 30, of <LOCATION>Bolton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION> "Many visitors get quite emotional. 
They break down and cry." 
</P>
<P>
Also born there were his brother, <PERSON>A. D.</PERSON>, who drowned in a swimming pool 
accident in <DATE>1969</DATE>, and his sister, <PERSON>Christine King Farris</PERSON>, a professor at 
<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Spelman College</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Family Belongings 
</P>
<P>
The home contains the family's original furniture, including the piano King 
played as a boy, his baseball glove, Monopoly game, family icebox and washing 
machine. 
</P>
<P>
"Sweet <PERSON>Auburn</PERSON> was a mecca of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s leading black business and commercial 
enterprises and a middle-class black residential area when <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON> 
lived here," site superintendent <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> said. The <ORGANIZATION>Park Service</ORGANIZATION> now owns 13 
turn-of-the-century homes and buildings in 21.5-acre site and plans to acquire 
27 more, he said. Seven have already been restored to their original state. 
</P>
<P>
Among the area's buildings is <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s famed <ORGANIZATION>Royal Peacock Club</ORGANIZATION> where <PERSON>Duke 
Ellington</PERSON>, <PERSON>Billy Eckstein</PERSON>, <PERSON>Louis Armstrong</PERSON> and other well-known black 
entertainers performed. <PERSON>John Wesley Dobbs</PERSON>, grandfather of former <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> Mayor 
<PERSON>Maynard H. Jackson</PERSON>, is credited with giving the area its nickname, Sweet 
Auburn. 
</P>
<P>
Service</ORGANIZATION> operates a museum filled with memorabilia and photographs highlighting 
the life of the civil rights leader. 
</P>
<P>
On display are the Nobel Peace Prize he received as well as the Medal of 
Freedom, his clothing, clerical robes and favorite neckties. Behind glass is 
the key to Room 307 at the <LOCATION>Lorraine Hotel</LOCATION> where King was killed, the wallet he 
was carrying when shot, his handwritten sermons and well-worn Bible. 
</P>
<P>
"What is important to my mother, my brother and my two sisters is the 
ever-growing interest in my father and what he worked for in his lifetime," 
said <PERSON>Martin Luther King III</PERSON>, 31, a <LOCATION>Fulton County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, commissioner. "I hope 
and pray it will continue to grow with his memory helping to achieve justice 
and equality for all mankind." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Dennis Ulysees and daughter Casandra view tomb of Martin Luther King Jr. 
; Photo, Martin Luther King III, left, and Randolph Scott, superintendent of 
the King historic site, beneath portrait of the slain leader. CHARLES HILLINGER 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Series 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
KING, MARTIN LUTHER JR; ATLANTA (GA) -- LANDMARKS; BLACKS -- HISTORY; HISTORIC 
SITES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011589-0156 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 5834 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 15, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 5; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
309 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MARTIN LUTHER KING DAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<DATE>Monday</DATE> marks the celebration of <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Day</ORGANIZATION>. The 60th anniversary of 
his birth is today. 
</P>
<P>
Closed: All government offices, courts, banks, schools, libraries and post 
offices. 
</P>
<P>
Open: Stock and commodity exchanges and most businesses. <ORGANIZATION>RTD</ORGANIZATION> buses will follow 
daily schedules. 
</P>
<P>
Among the celebrations on <DATE>Monday</DATE> are: 
</P>
<P>
* The <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Memorial Golf Tournament</ORGANIZATION> to benefit the <ORGANIZATION>Southern 
Christian Leadership Conference</ORGANIZATION> begins at <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> Rio <ORGANIZATION>Hondo Golf Course</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Downey</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* Volunteers will go door to door asking for donations for the third annual 
King Day drive for food and clothing for the homeless. Volunteers will gather 
at <TIME>10:30 a.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Holman Methodist Church</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>3320</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>W. Adams Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Bethel Lutheran 
Church</ORGANIZATION>, 700 E. 70th St., <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, and the Church in <LOCATION>Ocean Park</LOCATION>, 235 Hill 
<ORGANIZATION>St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* The fourth annual Kingdom Day Parade begins at <TIME>11 a.m</TIME>. The route travels east 
along <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Boulevard, beginning at <ORGANIZATION>Crenshaw Boulevard</ORGANIZATION> and 
ending at <ORGANIZATION>Exposition Park</ORGANIZATION> with a <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> rally. 
</P>
<P>
* Anti-apartheid student march and rally. It starts at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> at the site of 
the former <ORGANIZATION>South African Consulate</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>9107</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Wilshire Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>, and ends at 
consulate's current site, 510 <ORGANIZATION>N. La Cienega Blvd</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* Mayor <PERSON>Tom Bradley</PERSON> will address an ecumenical tribute at noon. Greater 
<ORGANIZATION>Cornerstone Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>5946</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>S. Figueroa St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* Student organizations of the <ORGANIZATION>Claremont Colleges</ORGANIZATION> will sponsor a commemorative 
ceremony at noon in the <ORGANIZATION>McKenna Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> on the <ORGANIZATION>Claremont McKenna College</ORGANIZATION> 
campus in <LOCATION>Claremont</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* The <ORGANIZATION>New CalArts Twentieth Century Players</ORGANIZATION> will perform two original pieces at 
a musical tribute to King at 12:10 p.m. <ORGANIZATION>Transamerica Center Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1149</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>S. 
Hill St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* The <ORGANIZATION>San Fernando Valley Interfaith Commemoration of King</ORGANIZATION>'s birthday begins at 
<TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> Valley <PERSON>Beth Shalom Temple</PERSON>, 15739 <LOCATION>Ventura Blvd.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Encino</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011689-0047 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 6144 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 16, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 4; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
432 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MARTIN LUTHER KING DAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Today marks the celebration of <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Day</ORGANIZATION>. The 60th anniversary of 
his birth was <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Closed: All government offices, courts, banks, schools, libraries and post 
offices. 
</P>
<P>
Open: Stock and commodity exchanges and most businesses. <ORGANIZATION>RTD</ORGANIZATION> buses will follow 
daily schedules. 
</P>
<P>
Among the celebrations today are: 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Memorial Golf Tournament</ORGANIZATION> to benefit the <ORGANIZATION>Southern 
Christian Leadership Conference</ORGANIZATION> begins at <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> at the <ORGANIZATION>Rio Hondo Golf Course</ORGANIZATION> 
in <LOCATION>Downey</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Volunteers will go door to door asking for donations for the third annual King 
Day drive for food and clothing for the homeless. Volunteers will gather at 
<TIME>10:30 a.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Holman Methodist Church</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>3320</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>W. Adams Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Bethel Lutheran 
Church</ORGANIZATION>, 700 E. 70th St., <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, and the Church in <LOCATION>Ocean Park</LOCATION>, 235 Hill 
<ORGANIZATION>St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The fourth annual Kingdom Day Parade begins at <TIME>11 a.m</TIME>. The route travels east 
along <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Boulevard, beginning at <ORGANIZATION>Crenshaw Boulevard</ORGANIZATION> and 
ending at <ORGANIZATION>Exposition Park</ORGANIZATION> with a <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> rally. 
</P>
<P>
Anti-apartheid student march and rally. It starts at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> at the site of the 
former <ORGANIZATION>South African Consulate</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>9107</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Wilshire Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>, and ends at consulate's 
current site, 510 <ORGANIZATION>N. La Cienega Blvd</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Mayor <PERSON>Tom Bradley</PERSON> will address an ecumenical tribute at noon. Greater 
<ORGANIZATION>Cornerstone Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>5946</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>S. Figueroa St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Student organizations of the <ORGANIZATION>Claremont Colleges</ORGANIZATION> will sponsor a commemorative 
ceremony at noon in the <ORGANIZATION>McKenna Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> on the <ORGANIZATION>Claremont McKenna College</ORGANIZATION> 
campus in <LOCATION>Claremont</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>New CalArts Twentieth Century Players</ORGANIZATION> will perform two original pieces at a 
musical tribute to King at 12:10 p.m. <ORGANIZATION>Transamerica Center Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1149</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>S. 
Hill St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Crosstown Project</ORGANIZATION>, a program aimed at encouraging black students to attend 
college, will sponsor a performance at <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> of "The Ultimate Triumph of 
Brotherhood of Love," at <ORGANIZATION>Whittier College</ORGANIZATION>. Ettinger Faculty/Alumni Center, 
13406 <LOCATION>Philadelphia St.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Whittier</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
Lutherans from throughout the greater <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> area will meet for the eighth 
annual worship celebration and <ORGANIZATION>Holy Communion</ORGANIZATION> service commemorating the life of 
King at <TIME>3:30 p.m.</TIME>, <ORGANIZATION>Stouffer Concourse</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>5400</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>W. Century Blvd</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Rev. <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> will be the keynote speaker at the 12th annual King 
birthday celebration, presented by the <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Legacy Assn.</ORGANIZATION> and the 
Figueroa St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>San Fernando Valley Interfaith Commemoration of King</ORGANIZATION>'s birthday begins at 
<TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Valley Beth Shalom Temple</ORGANIZATION>, 15739 <LOCATION>Ventura Blvd.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Encino</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
List 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
HOLIDAYS; KING, MARTIN LUTHER JR 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011390-0014 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 161351 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 13, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
122 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
KINGDOM DAY PARADE ROUTE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <DATE>1990</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Kingdom Day Parade</ORGANIZATION> will be held <DATE>Monday</DATE> to commemorate the <DATE>Jan. 15 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Boulevard will be closed to traffic and parking. 
</P>
<P>
Parade will begin at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> 
</P>
<P>
Starting point is at <PERSON>Crenshaw</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION> boulevards. 
</P>
<P>
Reviewing stand for judges will be at <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Blvd. near <ORGANIZATION>McClung 
Drive</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Termination point will be at the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Coliseum</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Menlo</LOCATION> and 39th 
streets. 
</P>
<P>
Registration and parade assignments will be at <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Boulevard 
and <LOCATION>Marlton Avenue</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Grand marshal will be <PERSON>Ruth Washington</PERSON>, publisher of the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Sentinel</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
More than 4,000 people are expected to participate. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, KINGDOM DAY PARADE ROUTE; JOHN SNYDER / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PARADES; LOS ANGELES -- CELEBRATIONS; HOLIDAYS; KING, MARTIN LUTHER JR; 
TRANSPORTATION ROUTES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890810-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-10-89 1635EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DexterKing     08-10 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dexter King,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>King Center Confirms Resignation Of Slain Leader's Youngest Son</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Dexter King</PERSON>, the youngest son of slain civil
rights leader <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON>, has resigned as president of
the center named for his father, center officials confirmed
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The resignation had been rumored for several days because of
apparent rifts among the leadership of the <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>.
Center for <ORGANIZATION>Nonviolent Social Change</ORGANIZATION> over how it should be managed.
   ``We regret to announce that <PERSON>Dexter Scott King</PERSON> has resigned his
post as president,'' said a statement from <ORGANIZATION>King Center</ORGANIZATION> board
Chairman <PERSON>Jesse Hill Jr</PERSON>.
   ``It must be borne in mind that the changing circumstances,
staff and management changes and tragic assassinations have not
changed this eternal commitment to social change through creative
love and revolutionary non-violence,'' Hill added.
   Hill's statement did not elaborate on the reasons for <PERSON>Dexter
King</PERSON>'s departure, and neither he nor King immediately returned
telephone calls <DATE>Thursday</DATE> seeking comment.
   In <DATE>January</DATE>, the center's board of directors elected <PERSON>King</PERSON>, 28, to
take over the presidency from his mother, <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON>, who
remained as chief executive officer. He officially took over <DATE>April
4</DATE>, the 21st anniversary of his father's assassination.
   He was touted at the time as an ambitious young leader who
sought a vigorous role in the center, hoping to place it on a solid
financial footing and cut its dependency on donations.
   Civil rights leaders in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> said <DATE>this week</DATE> that there has
been conflict within the center's leadership over fiscal and
personnel concerns, and there were reports of a dispute between
<PERSON>King</PERSON> and his mother.
   Mayor <PERSON>Andrew Young</PERSON>, who was an aide to the Rev. <PERSON>Martin Luther
King Jr.</PERSON> in the '60s, was quoted by <ORGANIZATION>The Atlanta
Journal-Constitution</ORGANIZATION> as saying the resignation was part of a family
dispute fueled by a generation gap.
   City Councilman <PERSON>Hosea Williams</PERSON>, who also was a King aide, said
the center recently had begun to focus more on leading the civil
rights movement, placing itself in competition with the <ORGANIZATION>Southern
Christian Leadership Conference</ORGANIZATION> founded by the elder King.
   The King Center, located on <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s historic <LOCATION>Auburn Avenue</LOCATION>,
once the heart of the black community's business district, contains
a museum and <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION>'s tomb.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011689-0046 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 6143 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 16, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 4; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
538 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VIGIL, PRAYERS MARK KING BIRTHDAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From United Press International 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As Americans remembered <PERSON>Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> on his 60th birthday 
anniversary with a candlelight vigil and prayers, his widow, <PERSON>Coretta Scott 
King</PERSON>, gave her annual "State of the Dream" address <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, calling the civil 
rights gains her late husband inspired "fragile" and warning that "much remains 
to be done." 
</P>
<P>
At <ORGANIZATION>Boston University's School of Theology</ORGANIZATION>, where King received a doctorate 
degree in <DATE>1955</DATE>, students and teachers gathered for a <DATE>Sunday</DATE> night candlelight 
vigil. 
</P>
<P>
President-elect <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, returning to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from a three-day 
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> fishing vacation, scheduled an address to a prayer breakfast at a 
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> hotel today -- a federal holiday recognized by every state except 
<LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
King was killed by a sniper on <DATE>April 4, 1968</DATE>, while standing on a motel balcony 
in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn</LOCATION>. The assassin, <PERSON>James Earl Ray</PERSON>, was imprisoned for life. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Selma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, three blacks will be sworn in as members of the <ORGANIZATION>Dallas County 
Commission</ORGANIZATION> today. It was there that King began the historic <DATE>1965</DATE> 
Selma-to-Montgomery march that resulted in passage of the Voting Rights Act. 
</P>
<P>
The swearing-in of <PERSON>Erskine Minor</PERSON>, <PERSON>Perry Varner</PERSON> and <PERSON>D. L. Pope</PERSON> will end 112 
years of white county rule and 10 years of legal battles to keep the commission 
white in a place where <PERCENT>55%</PERCENT> of the residents are black. The three new 
commissioners were elected in special balloting last month. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON>, speaking at the packed <ORGANIZATION>Ebenezer Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, where 
<PERSON>King</PERSON> and his father shared the pulpit, said the ceremony was to honor "a 
courageous young dreamer who picked up the torch of freedom and carried it from 
<LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> with an unshakable faith in the promise of the American 
dream. Martin passed that torch to us to continue the pursuit of the dream. 
</P>
<P>
" . . . Although the 'white only' signs of the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and <DATE>1960s</DATE> are gone," she 
said, "segregated neighborhoods and schools remain a pervasive fact of American 
life." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Play by <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> Students 
</P>
<P>
The city of <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> was hosting a ceremony and a tribute to King, including a 
performance today of a play written by students titled "Dreams." The play's 
title was taken from <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s moving <DATE>1963</DATE> "I Have a Dream" speech in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
An interfaith service was held in the nation's capital at the <ORGANIZATION>Washington Hebrew 
Congregation</ORGANIZATION> to commemorate <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s birthday, and the civil rights leader was 
remembered in religious services throughout the country. 
</P>
<P>
In Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Mormon Church</ORGANIZATION> said it is closing its offices today to 
allow church employees to observe the holiday. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Boston University</ORGANIZATION> was holding religious services to commemorate <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s birthday 
and to mark today's holiday. 
</P>
<P>
The Rev. <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON>, in a sermon <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at a church in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s 
poverty-stricken <LOCATION>Harlem</LOCATION> section, lashed out at those who set back <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s 
efforts by "self-destruction" through drugs and violence. "<PERSON>Dr. King</PERSON> was our 
gift from God. <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON> did not fight and die for your right to use 
cocaine, crack and heroin," said <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, who marched for civil rights with 
King. 
</P>
<P>
Jackson will be in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> today to deliver a sermon and help lead a parade. 
Tonight in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, he will receive the <ORGANIZATION>SCLC Martin Luther King Award</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Martin Luther King III, left, son of the slain civil rights leader, 
takes baton from Rashiid Shareef at end of Selma-to-Atlanta relay race. The 
event was part of celebrations marking King's 60th birthday. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
UNITED STATES -- CELEBRATIONS; HOLIDAYS; KING, MARTIN LUTHER JR 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890414-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-14-89 1641EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DeathPenalty     04-14 0439</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Death Penalty,0450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Death Penalty Opponents Launch Campaign</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A daughter of <PERSON>Sen. Robert F. Kennedy</PERSON> and a son of
<ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION> helped launch a campaign against capital
punishment on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, saying the death penalty will not bring their
slain fathers back to life.
   Society should put some killers in jail ``and leave them there
forever. But while we're at it, dismantle the electric chair, the
gas chamber. They won't bring back my father, they'll only take
someone else's father,'' said <PERSON>M. Kerry Kennedy</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, who was 8
when her father was killed in <DATE>1968</DATE>.
   Other speakers during a meeting at the <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>.
Center for <ORGANIZATION>Nonviolent Social Change</ORGANIZATION> urged religious leaders to
become more active in mobilizing their congregations against the
death penalty.
   The campaign, called ``Lighting the Torch of Conscience,'' is
aimed at getting the religious community to confront the capital
punishment issue. It will culminate in <DATE>June 1990</DATE> with a 330-mile
pilgrimage from <LOCATION>Starke</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, where <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s electric chair is
located, to <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Camille Bell</PERSON>, an <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> woman whose son Yusef, 9, was murdered
in <DATE>1979</DATE>, also spoke against capital punishment. <PERSON>Yusef Bell</PERSON> was one
of more than 20 young black Atlantans whose deaths were attributed
by police to <PERSON>Wayne Williams</PERSON>, currently serving two life prison
terms for two of the killings.
   ``I know the pain I felt when <PERSON>Yusef</PERSON> died,'' <PERSON>Ms. Bell</PERSON> told the
gathering of about 100. ``No other mother should have to feel that
bring my father back.''
   ``If we believe in an eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth,
most of us would be without eyes and without teeth,'' he said.
   <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s session opened with <PERSON>Delbert Tibbs</PERSON>, a former <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>
death row inmate, carrying a lighted torch from <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s tomb into an
auditorium of the King center.
   Tibbs, convicted of murder and rape, spent two years on death
row before his conviction was overturned and he was freed in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   He urged people to ``listen to and be guided by that still,
small voice from within'' to work to solve crime problems without
the death penalty.
   Sister <PERSON>Helen Prejean</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>, a death row spiritual
adviser and director of the Pilgrimage for Life program in her
hometown, said she had accompanied three men to the electric chair
and watched them die.
   ``They are the fire in me that is not going to go away until
things change,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890811-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-11-89 0430EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-KingCenter     08-11 0555</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-King Center,0572</SECOND>
<HEAD>King Resignation Prompts Allegations of Unrest</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURAN NEERGAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The youngest son of slain civil rights leader
<ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION> has resigned as president of the center that
carries his father's name amid talk of a rift among the leadership
over the center's direction.
   <PERSON>Dexter King</PERSON>'s resignation was announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>Martin
was given.
   Civil rights leaders in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> said <PERSON>King</PERSON> stepped down because
of conflicts over fiscal and personnel concerns, and there were
reports of a rift between <PERSON>King</PERSON> and his mother, <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>Atlanta City</LOCATION> Councilman <PERSON>Hosea Williams</PERSON> said the center was
encroaching on the leadership position in the civil rights movement
King founded.
   ``The center's purpose was to perpetuate the legacy of <PERSON>Dr. King</PERSON>,
but not to carry on the whole movement,'' said <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>, a former
lieutenant of the elder King. ``When they started talking about
leading the movement, freeing black folk, they started competing,
and both got hurt.''
   Mayor <PERSON>Andrew Young</PERSON>, who was an aide to the elder King in the
'60s, was quoted by <ORGANIZATION>The Atlanta Journal-Constitution</ORGANIZATION> as saying the
resignation was part of a family dispute fueled by a generation gap.
said <PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON> might return to the presidency she relinquished to
her son.
   The <ORGANIZATION>King Center</ORGANIZATION> is a non-profit organization devoted to
education about <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s teachings and philosophy. It also urges
action on international racial issues, especially apartheid in
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, and is host to the annual <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION>
birthday week celebration.
   The <ORGANIZATION>SCLC</ORGANIZATION> has taken an activist approach to the problems of
poverty and racism since it was founded in <DATE>1957</DATE> by King and the
Revs. <PERSON>Joseph Lowery</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ralph Abernathy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Fred Shuttlesworth</PERSON>.
   ``We are the activist arm of the movement,'' <PERSON>Lowery</PERSON> has said.
``When you do that, you step on toes and you don't become the most
popular kid on the block.''
   The Rev. <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON>, a follower of King in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and a
in a telephone interview from <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> that the two groups are
   ``The fact that <PERSON>Dr. King</PERSON> remains a frame of reference for
justice is mainly that his work has been institutionalized,''
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> said, referring to the center.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>SCLC</ORGANIZATION>'s legacy (is) direct action, challenging the racism,
challenging anti-semitism,'' he added.
   <PERSON>Dexter King</PERSON>, 28, was elected in <DATE>January</DATE> to take over from his
mother, who remained as chief executive officer. He said he wanted
to cut the center's dependency on donations and put it on a solid
financial base so it could ``market and disseminate'' non-violent
teachings.
   King could not be reached at the office of his business,
<ORGANIZATION>Visionary Development Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   In a statement from the <ORGANIZATION>King Center</ORGANIZATION>, board Chairman <PERSON>Jesse Hill
Jr.</PERSON> did not address the reasons for <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s decision.
   ``It must be borne in mind that the changing circumstances,
staff and management changes and tragic assassinations have not
changed this eternal commitment to social change through creative
love and revolutionary non-violence,'' Hill wrote.
   The King Center, on <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s historic <LOCATION>Auburn Avenue</LOCATION>, contains a
museum and <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION>'s tomb.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890117-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-17-89 0531EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-KingRdp     01-17 0747</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-King Rdp,0769</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Remember King with Speeches, Prayer, Protest</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos AX12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Ringing bells and ringing speeches commemorated the legacy of the
Rev. <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> amid renewed calls to strive for the
goals of the slain civil rights leader.
   Marchers filled city streets in <LOCATION>San Franciso</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Liberty Bell</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> was symbolically tapped, and national leaders descended
on <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s hometown to join his family in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> on the federal day
marking his 60th birthday.
   ``He lived a hero's life. He dreamed a hero's dreams,''
President-elect <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told black leaders in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. ``He left a
hero's indelible mark on the mind and imagination of a great
nation.''
   A unity march across the <ORGANIZATION>University of Michigan</ORGANIZATION> campus in <PERSON>Ann
Arbor</PERSON> drew about 2,000 people, who paraded as the university's
carillon played ``We Shall Overcome,'' the anthem of the civil
rights movement.
   Later <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Andrew Young</PERSON> told a <ORGANIZATION>University of
Michigan</ORGANIZATION> audience that, ``The world King left is not a great deal
different.''
   ``But there seems to be an awareness that violence is not the
solution to the world's problems, as we learned in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, as the
Russians have learned in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, and as the <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> has learned.''
   Nowhere was <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s influence felt more strongly than in <LOCATION>Selma</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, where he began the <DATE>1965</DATE> Selma-to-Montgomery march that helped
establish voting rights for blacks throughout the South.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, three blacks were sworn in as members of the <ORGANIZATION>Dallas
County Commission</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Selma</LOCATION>. They became the first black <LOCATION>Dallas
County</LOCATION> commissioners since Reconstruction and gave the five-member
commission a black majority.
   ``We bring home to <LOCATION>Dallas County</LOCATION> the harvest of the <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther
King</ORGANIZATION> voting rights act,'' said <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge U. W. Clemon</PERSON>, the
first black federal judge in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, who administered the oath of
office.
   King's widow, <PERSON>Corretta Scott King</PERSON>, was joined by black and white
political leaders for the annual ecumenical service at the <ORGANIZATION>Ebenezer
Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION>, where <PERSON>King</PERSON> and his father preached.
   The Rev. <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON>, once one of <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s young lieutenants,
used the occasion to criticize the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration's civil
rights record and President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s suggestion that civil rights
leaders bolster their position by fostering an attitude of
oppression among blacks.
   Jackson called <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s statements ``petty comments from the same
man who implied that <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> was a communist.''
   In <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Ambassador <PERSON>Edward Perkins</PERSON>, who is
black, marked the holiday by unveiling a bronze bust of King that
will sit in a new <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> embassay compound. The ceremony included
blacks and whites who have been prominent critics of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s
system of racial separation.
   In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, parades were held in places like <LOCATION>New
Orleans</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, where 15,000 people
marching from four directions converged on <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>.
Plaza.
   ``I took part because <PERSON>Dr. King</PERSON>'s dream has not been fully
realized,'' said <PERSON>Elbert Winbush</PERSON>, 32, of <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, who joined
10,000 others in the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> parade with his three daughters.
   King would have been 60 on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. He was 39 years old when he
was shot to death by a sniper in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>April 4, 1968</DATE>.
   King's birthday was first celebrated as a national holiday in
<DATE>1986</DATE>, three years after <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> named the third <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <DATE>January</DATE>
as a holiday in his honor. All but six states have adopted the day
as a state holiday. The six states are <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, when black leaders symbolically struck the
Liberty Bell as a signal for bells to ring nationwide, Mayor <PERSON>W.
Wilson Goode</PERSON> cited the bell's famous crack.
   ``That crack is a symbol that there are some things
unfulfilled,'' <PERSON>Goode</PERSON> said.
   At the <ORGANIZATION>Michigan Capitol</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Lansing</LOCATION>, children struck the state's
replica of the <ORGANIZATION>Liberty Bell</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``He was a great man and he believed in what he was doing. He
tried to bring peace between all kinds of people,'' said <PERSON>Sharonda
Gardenhire</PERSON>, 10, of <LOCATION>Lansing</LOCATION>, shortly after she gave the rope a tug.
   A speech by one of <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s sons in <LOCATION>Eugene</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, was delayed for
about an hour after two telephoned bomb threats. The observance
resumed after the building was search and no bomb was found.
   <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King III</ORGANIZATION> said that in the 21 years since his father
was assassinated ``this nation has made great strides.'' But he
added that, ``I've got news for you. We've still got a long way to
do.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900115-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-15-90 1321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-KingHolidayRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0537 01-15 1027</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-King Holiday Rdp, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0537,1049</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nation Marks Birthday of Martin Luther King Jr.</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs the 11th graf, ``There were plans,'' with 5 grafs to
update with Liberty Bell, other observances, student protest; and
Subs the last graf to CORRECT that just four states have no holiday
but not all give workers a holiday.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AX2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBRA ELLIOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Worshipers at <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION>'s church
were urged today on the slain civil rights leader's birthday to
keep alive his memory and his philosophy of non-violence.
   ``This is a man who is a deep current in our memory,'' said the
Rev. <PERSON>Cecil Williams</PERSON>, pastor of <ORGANIZATION>Glide Memorial United Methodist
Church</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. ``Let us live then not only his dream, but
let us live the practice of non-violence and unconditional love.''
   Williams spoke at the annual ecumenical service at <ORGANIZATION>Ebenezer
Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION>.
   Church services, parades, and other celebrations were held
nationwide during the weekend before the federal holiday, which for
the first time falls on the slain civil-rights leader's actual
birthday.
   He would have been 61 today.
   Also planned today in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> was a ``March of Celebration''
parade, being televised nationally for the first time.
   A former King lieutenant, the Rev. <PERSON>Hosea Williams</PERSON>, stood in
front of an <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> housing project to criticize the day's
activities for making a travesty of <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s dream of equality and
justice.
   Williams, <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s field organizer in the civil rights movement,
complained that people were starving in the city while thousands of
dollars were being spent on the parade. ``I am really upset with
all this gaiety,'' he said.
   This year's holiday follows a series of bombings and threats,
apparently racially motivated, in the Southeast, and a flareup of
racial tensions in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> after an apparent hoax in which a white
man had claimed a black mugger fatally shot his pregnant wife.
   It also comes at a time of gains for blacks _ the election of
<PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON>, first black mayor of <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, and the nation's
first elected black governor, <PERSON>L. Douglas Wilder</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>.
   ``Today, the sound of libery is being heard all around the
world,'' said <PERSON>James Farmer</PERSON>, founder of the <ORGANIZATION>Congress for Racial
Equality</ORGANIZATION>, as he pounded three times with his fist on the <ORGANIZATION>Liberty
Bell</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>. ``Those who have been denied liberty love it
most. Dr. King loved liberty and he fought and died for it.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> held a moment of silence at noon.
   In <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, one of just four states without some form of
King holiday, about 200 <ORGANIZATION>Merrimack Valley High School</ORGANIZATION> pupils walked
out of morning classes today in <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION> to recognize <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther
King Day</ORGANIZATION>, which the school does not observe.
   ``This is our own personal way of remembering him,'' said senior
<PERSON>Mike Krumenacker</PERSON>, one of three pupils who organized the impromptu
gathering of about a third of the school's pupils.
   And in another of the four states, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, thousands marched in
<LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION> today to honor King. A racially mixed crowd
carried black balloons along a four-mile stretch of downtown
<LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> as they headed for a rally at the state Capitol.
   King, the son of an <LOCATION>Atlanta Baptist</LOCATION> minister, led non-violent
marches in the South in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and <DATE>1960s</DATE> in a quest to end
discrimination against blacks and other minorities. He was
assassinated on <DATE>April 4, 1968</DATE>, in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON> delivered her annual ``state of
the dream'' address at <ORGANIZATION>Ebenezer Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION>.
   King's widow applauded pro-democracy shifts worldwide and said
the civil rights movement would not be deterred by the recent wave
of bombings and threats against blacks. A federal judge and a black
<LOCATION>Savannah</LOCATION> lawyer were killed in two bombings.
   ``In the <DATE>last year</DATE>, we've seen hundreds of thousands of people
marching through the streets of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Warsaw</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Prague</LOCATION>, all singing `We Shall
Overcome' in a host of languages,'' she said.
   ``We're not going to be turned around by letter bombs or threats
or any kind of violence,'' she said. ``Instead, we're going
forward, with unity and courage and commitment.''
   Also in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, more than 500 students and teachers at <ORGANIZATION>Booker
T. Washington High School</ORGANIZATION> joined civil rights leader <PERSON>Rosa Parks</PERSON> to
paint a mural dedicated to King. The mural displayed, ``Let Freedom
Ring.''
   In <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, where blacks have complained about aggressive police
tactics in their search for the killer of a pregnant white woman in
<DATE>October</DATE>, about 25 activists planned to demonstrate at a King
memorial breakfast today to protest the presence of Mayor <PERSON>Raymond
Flynn</PERSON>.
   Tensions have been heightened after revelations that <PERSON>Charles
Stuart</PERSON> himself probably killed his wife. He committed suicide this
month.
   ``We don't feel Mayor <PERSON>Flynn</PERSON> should have a seat of honor at this
occasion,'' said <PERSON>Sadiki Kambon</PERSON>, director of a group called the
<ORGANIZATION>Community for Human Rights</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The mayor came on the scene that (<DATE>October</DATE>) <TIME>night</TIME> and was told
by police that an African male killed a white female,'' <PERSON>Kambon</PERSON>
said. ``The mandate was `Get me someone,' and the police proceeded
to roust black males in <LOCATION>Mission Hill</LOCATION> and the entire city.''
   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> told about 400 people at <ORGANIZATION>Judson Memorial
Church</ORGANIZATION> that ``<PERSON>Dr. King</PERSON> took us to the dawn of a new era. It is up
to us to push on into the bright light of day.''
   Wilder, sworn in <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, said on ABC-TV's ``This Week With
<PERSON>David Brinkley</PERSON>'' on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that a black could occupy the <ORGANIZATION>White
House</ORGANIZATION> ``in our time.''
   In <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, the Rev. <PERSON>Joseph Lowery</PERSON>, president and co-founder of
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   ``Don't let them make a pious dreamer out of him,'' <PERSON>Lowery</PERSON> said.
``He was a non-violent revolutionary. ... The spirit of <ORGANIZATION>Martin
Luther King</ORGANIZATION> demands that we be activists.''
   Federal offices were closed today, and most states gave the day
off to their workers as well. The four without any form of King
holiday are <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, but some
other states kept workers on the job but marked the day in some
other way.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880906-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-06-88 1018EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Kings'Deputy     09-06 0324</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Kings' Deputy,0333</SECOND>
<HEAD>Deputy Assigned to Provide Security for King Family</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A deputy has been assigned to provide security
for the family of <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION> for the past five months,
a measure defended by the county sheriff as a valid use of tax
money.
   ``I'd say it's public money going to protect a public family,''
<LOCATION>Fulton County</LOCATION> Sheriff <PERSON>Richard Lankford</PERSON> was quoted as saying in
today's editions of The <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> Constitution. ``Anything that
happened to the <PERSON>King</PERSON> family at this juncture would become
international.''
   King was assassinated <DATE>April 4, 1968</DATE>, in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn</LOCATION>. His
mother, <PERSON>Alberta King</PERSON>, was shot to death in <DATE>1975</DATE> while playing the
organ for a <DATE>Sunday</DATE> service in an <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> church.
   ``It would be an indictment, I think, against our community if
another tragedy would befall the family,'' the sheriff said in
acknowledging he assigned deputy <PERSON>Angelo Willoughby</PERSON> to the post.
   The newspaper said it learned of the deputy's hiring through
county records.
   County Manager <PERSON>Sam Brownlee</PERSON> said the county commission should
have been asked to approve the assignment because it amounts to
publicly financed protection for a private family.
   ``That is not something the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Commissioners</ORGANIZATION> has
authorized,'' he said. ``That's something the sheriff has done.''
   Willoughby reports daily to the <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Center
for Non-violent Social Change.
   ``I don't know if I would say he's a bodyguard, but he's there
for the protection of the family as well as for the security of the
center itself,'' <PERSON>Lankford</PERSON> said.
   The civil rights leader's son, <ORGANIZATION>Fulton County Commissioner Martin
Luther King III</ORGANIZATION>, said he appreciates the officer's presence.
   ``I carry the name <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON> and that draws
crackpots,'' he said.
   ``A guy came up and approached my mother (<ORGANIZATION>Coretta Scott King</ORGANIZATION>)
last week,'' <PERSON>King</PERSON> said. ``He was just crazy. If he (<PERSON>Willoughby</PERSON>) had
not been there, something might have happened. Once he saw a police
official there, he backed off.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900116-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-16-90 0802EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-KingDayRdp     01-16 0825</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-King Day Rdp,0847</SECOND>
<HEAD>Memorials But Also Violence on King Holiday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands marched and prayed and church bells rang on the
protesters demonstrated against states, schools and businesses not
observing the federal holiday.
   Three <PERSON>Ku Klux Klansmen</PERSON> handed out leaflets in <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>,
fights broke out between blacks and whites in <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South
Carolina</LOCATION> and racist graffiti was sprayed on signs on a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
highway named after King.
   King's survivors and others remembering him in services around
the nation said they harbored no illusions that his work was
finished.
   ``It's great that we celebrate his birthday but this day should
be a day where we recommit ourselves to finishing his dream,''
<PERSON>King</PERSON>'s son, <PERSON>Martin Luther King 3rd</PERSON>, who was 10 when his father died
in <DATE>1968</DATE>, told 500 people at a <ORGANIZATION>DePaul University</ORGANIZATION> church after
leading a candlelight march <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   King's widow, <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON>, spoke in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> at an annual
ecumenical service at <LOCATION>Ebenezer Baptist Church</LOCATION>, where her husband
delivered some of his most stirring orations.
   ``Now is the time to organize a global non-violent movement
based on <PERSON>Dr. King</PERSON>'s teachings, to put an end to the scourges of
poverty, hunger, racism and bigotry, war and militarism,'' she said.
   Security for the service was heavy following recent racially
motivated mail bombings in the Southeast. Bomb-sniffing dogs
inspected the church beforehand; visitors were required for the
first time to pass through metal detectors, and police took up
posts throughout the church during the service.
   Security also was heavy for a <DATE>March</DATE> of Celebration held later in
downtown <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>. Police estimated 400,000 people watched.
   A former top King lieutenant, the Rev. <PERSON>Hosea Williams</PERSON>,
complained that the parade trivialized the day and wasted money
better spent on the poor. ``This has been prostituted more than any
other holiday except Jesus Christ's birthday,'' he said outside an
<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> housing project.
   About 25,000 people lined <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>' streets for the fifth
annual King Birthday Celebration Parade down a boulevard named for
him, and 2,500 turned out for an annual breakfast in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>. In
<LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, about 300 people gathered at The <PERSON>Lorraine Motel</PERSON>,
where King was assassinated on <DATE>April 4, 1968</DATE>.
   ``We didn't want the children to think that <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON>'s
birthday was just another day for watching television,'' said
<PERSON>Mardest Van Hooks</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> teacher who helped bring a group of
youngsters to The <PERSON>Lorraine</PERSON>.
   The Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>Federal Holiday Commission</ORGANIZATION> said bells
chimed at <TIME>12:30 p.m.</TIME> EST in all 50 states and 144 countries. The
<ORGANIZATION>Liberty Bell</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> was tapped three times. The <ORGANIZATION>New York
Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> paused for a moment at noon.
   The holiday, first celebrated in <DATE>1986</DATE>, fell on <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s actual
birthday for the first time.
   In <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, one of four states without any form of King
holiday, students at high schools in <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Milford</LOCATION>, Merrimack
and <LOCATION>Wolfeboro</LOCATION> staged protest rallies.
   ``<PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON> wasn't just for black people. He changed
everything for everyone, not just black people,'' <ORGANIZATION>Merrimack Valley
High</ORGANIZATION> senior <PERSON>John Morin</PERSON>, who is white, told fellow students.
   In <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, where the King holiday has long been a bitter
controversy, a <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> crowd estimated at nearly 15,000 heard
lawmakers and community leaders at the Capitol urge them to vote in
a referendum this <DATE>fall</DATE> over whether to let a King Day observance
become law.
   A bill to make the day a holiday was introduced <DATE>Monday</DATE> in the
<ORGANIZATION>Idaho Senate</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> also has no form of King Holiday, while some
other states keep workers on the job but mark the day in other ways.
   About 200 people protested outside a bank in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, that
stayed open. <PERSON>Norman Eenith</PERSON>, 35, held an outstretched dollar bill
and said, ``This is what it's all about.''
   In <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>, following a parade in King's honor attended by
tens of thousands, two whites were arrested after a fight in which
a black man was hit with nail-studded boards, officials said.
   At <ORGANIZATION>Garrett High School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, one of several area
schools that canceled the day off to make up for days lost during
Hurricane Hugo, about five black students angry at having to attend
school on the holiday assaulted two white students, Principal <PERSON>Rex
Whitcomb</PERSON> said. Police helped restore order.
   In <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, two signs on 10-mile stretch of highway named for
King were painted with swastikas and the letters ``SWP,'' thought
to stand for ``Supreme White Power,'' police said.
   In <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, a county commissioner said he received numerous
telephone threats after he protested a newspaper advertisement
depicting <PERSON>King</PERSON>, a birthday cake and a garbage truck. The ad said
trash would be picked up as usual <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``All of a sudden I recognized that I felt a particular fear
that as a young white man, fairly protected growing up, I had never
felt before _ what so many people in this group must have felt,''
<PERSON>Yordon</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011190-0156 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 160611 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 11, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Westside; Part J; Page 2; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
126 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WESTSIDE DIGEST: CRENSHAW; 
</P>
<P>
EVENTS MARK KING BIRTHDAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Nearly 200 posters honoring the life of slain civil rights leader <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther 
King Jr.</ORGANIZATION> are on display from 6 to <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> at the <ORGANIZATION>Baldwin Hills Crenshaw Plaza</ORGANIZATION>, 
<PERSON>Crenshaw</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION> boulevards. 
</P>
<P>
The poster display, the work of school-age artists, begins a celebration that 
will include the creation of a living memorial to <PERSON>King</PERSON> with the planting of 390 
<LOCATION>Canary Island</LOCATION> pine trees on <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Boulevard on <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
In addition, the <ORGANIZATION>Afro-American Quilters of Los Angeles</ORGANIZATION> will present 
"Reflections of Our Heritage," an exhibition of more than 100 handmade quilts, 
at the <ORGANIZATION>Baldwin Hills Crenshaw Plaza</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Jan. 19</DATE> to 21. More than 60 photographs of 
the Dance Theatre of <LOCATION>Harlem</LOCATION> also will be on display at the plaza until <DATE>Feb. 4</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890116-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-16-89 1202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-KingRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0519 01-16 0820</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-King Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0519,0834</SECOND>
<HEAD>Martin Luther King: The Nation Remembers The Dream</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf with 3 grafs to UPDATE with Thornburgh, Bush comments;
SUBS 9th graf pvs to CORRECT number of demonstrators to 51 sted 72 and
charges to disorderly conduct sted trespassing; pickup 10th graf pvs, `Elsewhere
around ... Rights Act.' Deletes, to tighten, last 6 grafs, bgng ``When
will ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos AX2, AX6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Worshippers filling the Rev. <PERSON>Martin Luther King
Jr.</PERSON>'s church were admonished today to remember the slain civil
rights leader's birthday by rededicating themselves to his work.
   ``It is our hope and our desire ... that we will realize it is an
unending quest,'' said the Rev. <PERSON>Joseph Roberts</PERSON>, pastor of <ORGANIZATION>Ebenezer
Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION>, where <PERSON>King</PERSON> and his father preached.
   Roberts opened the annual ecumenical service that attracted
local, state and federal officials to mark the national holiday
honoring King. Among those gathered on the podium were members of
<PERSON>King</PERSON>'s family, the Rev. <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney General <PERSON>Dick
Thornburgh</PERSON>, actress <PERSON>Jane Fonda</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Joe Frank Harris</PERSON> and
the state's senators and congressmen.
   Thornburgh called King ``a martyr slain in his prime while trying
to make <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and the world a place where justice, freedom and
peace could flourish.''
   President-elect <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> sent a letter to be read at the
service, in which he pledged that his administration ``will work
tirelessly for the strict enforcement of civil rights as well as for
absolute equality for all Americans.''
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> commemorated the holiday with a glowing
tribute to King in a speech to about 300 prominent blacks.
   ``He lived a hero's life. He dreamed a hero's dreams. He left a
hero's indelible mark on the mind and imagination of a great
nation,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told members of the <ORGANIZATION>Inaugural Afro-American Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   Looking ahead to his inauguration on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said: ``What
becomes of <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON>'s dreams is up to us. We must not fail
him. We must not fail ourselves.''
   In <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Ambassador <PERSON>Edward Perkins</PERSON> marked the
holiday by unveiling a bronze bust of King on a bushy plot of land
in <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION> where the new <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> embassy is to stand.
   In <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> invoked <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s
memory when he announced an executive order that will bar the state
from buying goods and services from companies that have dealings
with the South African government.
   In <LOCATION>Groton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, 51 demonstrators were arrested on charges of
disorderly conduct at the <ORGANIZATION>Electric</ORGANIZATION> Boat shipyard as they protested
the construction of Trident nuclear submarines. The demonstrators,
many carrying pictures of King and citing his belief in non-violent
protest, said the demonstration was held in observance of his
birthday.
   Elsewhere around the nation, planned observances of the King
holiday included the swearing-in of the first blacks on the <LOCATION>Dallas
County</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>) Commission in more than a century. The ceremony was
scheduled for <LOCATION>Selma</LOCATION>, where King began the <DATE>1965</DATE> Selma-to-Montgomery
march that resulted in passage of the Voting Rights Act.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Liberty Bell</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> was to be symbolically tapped
today and church and school bells were being rung in <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>.
Golfers were to tee off in a suburban <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> tournament
   The observance at <ORGANIZATION>Ebenezer Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION> capped a week of
remembrance in <LOCATION>King</LOCATION>'s hometown. At the church <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s widow
urged <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to hold true to his call for ``a kinder, gentler nation''
and to impose strict sanctions against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   In addition, <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON> said in her annual ``State of the
Dream'' speech, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> must do more by ``providing
education and economic assistance directly to black <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION>
who bear the brunt of suffering in that troubled land.''
   ``I think we ought to take the president-elect at his word and
hold him to his call for a kinder, gentler nation where peace and
justice are in fact a reality,'' she said. ``But a kinder, gentler
nation will require kinder, gentler leaders.''
   <PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON> spoke before an estimated 1,200 people at the church
where <PERSON>King</PERSON> and his father were co-pastors. It may have been her
final ``State of the Dream'' address as president of <ORGANIZATION>The King
Center</ORGANIZATION>, a memorial and policy center in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, she announced that her 27-year-old son, <PERSON>Dexter Scott
King</PERSON>, would assume the presidency <DATE>April 4</DATE> _ the 21st anniversary of
<PERSON>King</PERSON>'s assassination at a <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, motel in <DATE>1968</DATE>.
   Today is the fourth year for the King national holiday. In <DATE>1983</DATE>,
after considerable debate, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> named the third <DATE>Monday</DATE> in
<DATE>January</DATE> as a national holiday honoring King, whose actual birthday
was <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Most states also observe <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Day as a state
holiday. Among the few that don't is <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, where rallies were
planned in <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION> and where prospects are uncertain for
a measure that lawmakers plan to introduce this year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06021193 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06021193 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; Coretta Scott King  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; BLACK; LEADER; HOLIDAY; MEMORIAL; SF-BAY-AREA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Remembering Martin Luther King Jr. and his commitment to peace was high on the
agenda of "Freedom Train" riders waiting at the Southern Pacific station in
San Jose this morning.;    "I'm coming to honor what Martin Luther King
represented," said Neil Cossman, 48, of San Jose, as he waited for the train
to leave for San Francisco and the annual celebration of King's life and
legacy. "I want to make a statement against the war, and I think this
represents that.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  RIDERS OF 'FREEDOM TRAIN' HONOR KING, DECRY
GULF WAR  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  (box) King preached peace, Coretta King writes, Page 7B.
Associated Press contributed to this report.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "Until you end war, you won't end poverty, and until you end poverty, you
won't end racism," <PERSON>Cossman</PERSON> said. "They are all tied together. The things he
represented are being set back by war in <LOCATION>Iraq</LOCATION>.";    He added, "Every time a
plane goes down, the money spent on that plane represents I don't know how
many other lives lost to poverty, in addition to the tragedy of the loss of
the pilot's life.";    <PERSON>Dr. Amos Brown</PERSON>, pastor of the <ORGANIZATION>Third Baptist Church</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and chairman for that city's program today, was in <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> to
ride the train.;    <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> saw definite parallels between <PERSON>King</PERSON> and the war in
the <LOCATION>Middle East.</LOCATION>;    "King was a non-violent prophet-philosopher who took a
stand calling for the end of the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War, even when it was unpopular to do
so," <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> recalled. "I often heard him say it would have been morally
inconsistent for him to talk about freedom and justice for blacks and not be
concerned about lives in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>.";    He believes the slain civil rights
leader "would have said we should have gone to the conference table to
negotiate a settlement. He would have raised some serious questions regarding
the fairness and justice of 25 to <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of the men and women in the
<LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> being black or other minorities. He would have seen this as a
fallout of racism and injustice in our nation.";    In <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE>,
several hundred people gathered in a poor neighborhood in a march to
commemorate <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s birthday.;    Participants carried placards that read
"There has got to be a way to connect the human race," and other slogans
reminiscent of the slain civil rights leader's non-violent philosophy.;    "We
have come to Bayview-Hunters Point to affirm peace in our society and to deal
with our domestic problems -- drugs and violence," said the Rev. <PERSON>Cecil
Williams</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Glide Memorial United Methodist Church.</ORGANIZATION>;    "This is an
affirmation of what <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON> preached -- pro-peace, not anti-war,"
he said. "We want to live peace. We want to stop the war.";    In <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s widow, <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON> and others observing the civil rights
leader's birthday remembered him as an advocate of non-violence and urged an
immediate halt to the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> war.;    "Our most urgent short-term
priority at the international level is a cease-fire in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>,"
<PERSON>Coretta King</PERSON> said in her annual State of the Dream speech <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Ebenezer
Baptist Church.</LOCATION>;    In <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, Girl Scouts in a <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> parade honoring King on
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> carried a 10-foot-long banner saying, "King's dream did not include
war.";    Today's holiday winds up 10 days of celebrations marking <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s
birthday. Assassinated in <DATE>1968</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>King</ORGANIZATION> would have turned 62 on <DATE>Jan. 15</DATE>. The
annual King ecumenical service <TIME>this morning</TIME> at <LOCATION>Ebenezer</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>King</PERSON> and his
father were co-pastors, <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Maynard Jackson</PERSON> said he was angered by
war-related polls showing that many white Americans believe blacks who oppose
the war are unpatriotic.;    "Let's set the record straight," he said. "The
ethnic group that has produced the fewest number of traitors in time of war is
Afro-Americans.";    <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> noted that a large percentage of blacks are
serving with the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf.</LOCATION>;    A rally honoring King
was scheduled today in <LOCATION>Helena</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mont</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> are
the only states where his birthday still isn't a paid state holiday.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JIM DICKEY, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910121  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  691  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday January 21, 1991
00021193,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890114-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-89 1551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Lee-Jackson-King     01-14 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lee-Jackson-King,0564</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lee-Jackson-King Day A Celebration Of Diversity In Virginia</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-King's Church, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILARY APPELMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>'s joint celebration <DATE>Monday</DATE> of the
birthdays of two Confederate generals and a black civil rights
leader on Lee-Jackson-King Day is ``the perfect combination of
diversity,'' says the man responsible for the merger.
   Lt. Gov. <PERSON>L. Douglas Wilder</PERSON>, who as a state senator five years ago
pushed through the bill making <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Day a <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>
holiday, says he doesn't find it ironic that King shares the holiday
with <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> natives <PERSON>Robert E. Lee</PERSON> and <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> ``Stonewall'' <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>.
   ``I find no irony in it at all,'' <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON>, a grandson of slaves
and the first black elected to statewide office in the South since
Reconstruction, said <DATE>Friday</DATE>. ``It shows we are prepared to recognize
good men. Men of principle have differed on principle and I think
all three were men of principle.''
   <PERSON>James Farmer</PERSON>, a civil rights leader who worked with <PERSON>King</PERSON>, said
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> that <PERSON>King</PERSON> deserves a day all his own because ``<PERSON>Martin
Luther King</PERSON> stood alone as a giant.''
   But he said <PERSON>King</PERSON> would have been amused at being linked with
heroes of the Confederacy.
   ``<PERSON>Dr. King</PERSON> was very tolerant of things like that,'' Farmer said.
``If he is looking down from heaven now I can hear him laughing.''
   The bill passed the state legislature in <DATE>1984</DATE> after seven years
of effort by <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON> and often acrimonious debate in public hearings.
   Opponents objected to honoring a non-Virginian with a holiday
when favorite sons such as <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Patrick Henry</PERSON> did
not have their own days. Celebrating <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s birthday on the third
<DATE>Monday</DATE> in <DATE>January</DATE>, already designated as Lee-Jackson Day, also drew
protest.
   King's birthday is <DATE>Jan. 15, 1929</DATE>. Lee was born <DATE>Jan. 19, 1807</DATE> and
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> was born <DATE>Jan. 21, 1824</DATE>.
   ``The memory of Lee and <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> is sacred to the hearts of all
true Virginians. To replace our heroes with <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON> or
any other non-Virginian is to betray the greatness of our heritage
as a commonwealth,'' Forest <PERSON>Tucker</PERSON>, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Sons of
Confederate Veterans</ORGANIZATION>, said in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   But <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON> persisted. ``I have never taken to the floor of the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> to say one word against <PERSON>Stonewall Jackson</PERSON>,'' he told his
fellow legislators five years ago. ``I have never failed to stand in
honor of <PERSON>Robert E. Lee</PERSON>. But that cause which is sacred to many
Virginians is not sacred to all Virginians.''
   <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON>, who is expected to announce his candidacy for governor
this month, now minimizes the controversy over the bill, pointing
instead to ceremonies around the state honoring King. In <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>,
for example, a week of activities is being devoted in memory of the
slain civil rights leader, including forums, worship services and a
touring stage show performing works by black writers.
   <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Day is a state holiday in all states
except <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. Mississippians honor both <PERSON>Lee</PERSON>'s and <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s birthdays on the
same day.
   <PERSON>Charles Sadler</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Federal
Holiday Commission</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, said his group doesn't mind
how <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s birthday is celebrated, as long as it is. A joint holiday
is ``better than nothing,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900328-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-28-90 2305EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Idaho-KingDay     03-28 0330</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Idaho-King Day,0340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bill Providing King Holiday Passes in Idaho</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOISE, Idaho (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Idaho House</ORGANIZATION> approved legislation
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to make <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> the 47th state with a holiday honoring
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> voted 53-27 for the bill previously passed by the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. Later, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> accepted a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> amendment that made the
holiday's complete name ``Martin Luther King Jr.-Idaho Human Rights
Day.''
   Final approval by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> was expected <DATE>Thursday</DATE> before the
bill goes to Gov. <PERSON>Cecil Andrus</PERSON>, who proposed the holiday.
   The bill was the subject of tortuous arguments in the
legislature last week. Opponents said their constituents didn't
care about <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We're told this isn't a black holiday, but yet we're also told
we can't change the name,'' said Rep. <PERSON>Stan Hawkins</PERSON>, a Republican.
``If you really have a guilt trip in mind by passing this, you're
making a mistake.''
   Rep. <PERSON>L. Ed Brown</PERSON>, also a Republican and one of the bill's
sponsors, said the decision on the bill would ``say more about
<LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> than .. about <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON>.''
   ``<LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> is not the state in the <LOCATION>Union</LOCATION> that's going to determine
<PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON>'s greatness,'' <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said. ``Forty-six states
and the federal government have already done that.''
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said adopting a King holiday would ``send a very special
message to future generations about how Idahoans feel about
minorities.''
   Besides <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, only <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> have not
adopted state holidays corresponding with the federal holiday
honoring King on the third <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Idaho Legislature</ORGANIZATION> created a state commemorative day in <DATE>1987</DATE>,
and a bill creating a state holiday died in a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> committee last
year despite arguments its failure would only reinforce the
perception some have of <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> as a haven for racists.
   Opponents said they objected to another day off for government
employees. Proponents said <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>'s economy would suffer through
lost tourism and convention business if it failed to establish the
holiday.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880719-0211 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-19-88 2037EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-CVN--Dukakis 2ndLd-Writethru a0764 07-19 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CVN--Dukakis, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0764,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dukakis Visits Martin Luther King Center</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts 1 graf with Dukakis attending night fundraiser after
9th graf pvs, ``He wanted ...''
^By DONALD M. ROTHBERG</NOTE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>, a day away from his party's
presidential nomination, invoked the memory of <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King
Jr</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and pledged to work to ``inspire and uplift this
country.''
   The <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> Democrat and his designated running mate,
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>, received a tour of the <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King
Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Center from the civil rights leader's widow, <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON>.
   Earlier, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>, his wife, <PERSON>Kitty</PERSON>, and adviser <PERSON>Paul Brountas</PERSON> had
breakfast in the candidate's hotel suite with <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION> president
<PERSON>Lane Kirkland</PERSON> and his wife, <PERSON>Irena</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' aides, sensitive to accusations that labor wields too
much influence in the Democratic Party, did not list the breakfast
session on his schedule.
   An <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION> spokesman called the breakfast ``routine.''
   ``I'm sure what they talked about was how to win in <DATE>November</DATE>,''
said federation spokesman <PERSON>Rex Hardesty</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> was spending most of the day in his suite working with
speechwriter <PERSON>Bill Woodward</PERSON> on the address he will deliver <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
when he accepts the presidential nomination.
   He met for nearly an hour with the Democrats' Hispanic members
of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, a meeting they said <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> asked for. Rep. <PERSON>Albert
Bustamante</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> said they talked about involving Hispanics in
the campaign and in the transition team, if <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> is elected.
   ``He wanted to establish a dialogue with the leadership of the
Hispanic community in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>,'' said <PERSON>Bustamante</PERSON>. ``We were real
pleased.''
   While the convention wound up its debate on the platform,
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> attended a closed fund-raiser in a downtown office
building. Accompanying the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> governor was his cousin,
Academy Award-winning actress <PERSON>Olympia Dukakis</PERSON>.
   The last threat to convention unity was resolved earlier in the
day with announcement that aides to <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> had
reached agreement on most platform differences.
   With <PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON> leading the way, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> and their
wives looked at exhibits at the <ORGANIZATION>King Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first one they stopped at contained mementos of the passage
of legislation establishing a national holiday commemorating <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s
birthday, <DATE>Jan. 15</DATE>.
   One of the exhibits was a photograph of President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> signing
the legislation. It included an inscription, ``To Coretta King.
With respect and high esteem on a very special day.'' It was
signed, ``<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>.''
   The Republican vice president is <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' certain opponent in
the fall election.
   Other exhibits included the key to Room 307 at the <PERSON>Lorraine
Motel</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn</LOCATION>. King was standing on the balcony outside
that room when he was shot and killed in <DATE>1968</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION>, awarded to King, as well as the
Presidential Medal of Freedom, awarded him posthumously, also were
displayed.
   The final stop on the tour was <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s tomb, inscribed, ``Rev.
<PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> <DATE>1929</DATE> - <DATE>1968</DATE>. Free at last, Free at last,
<ORGANIZATION>Thank God</ORGANIZATION> almighty I'm free at last.''
   In a brief speech that included several quotations from <LOCATION>King</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> described the slain civil rights leader as ``a man of
action, he was a man of inspiration.''
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> was nearby, and <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> said that if elected he and his
vice president ``are going to do our very best, with your support,
to inspire and uplift this country.''
   Dukakis praised the convention keynote speech by <ORGANIZATION>Texas State</ORGANIZATION>
Treasurer <PERSON>Ann Richards</PERSON> and noted that neither he nor <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> ``have
ever won any blue ribbons for great oratory.''
   Then he added, ``And after <PERSON>Jesse</PERSON> gets through tonight, none of
us will meet the standard <PERSON>Ann Richards</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> set for
this convention.''
   <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> was the featured convention speaker <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112189-0050 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 137841 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 21, 1989, Tuesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
474 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CALIFORNIA 94 RENAMED TO HONOR MARTIN LUTHER KING 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ARMANDO ACUNA, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A 10-mile stretch of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 94, from downtown <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to its interchange 
with <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 125 in <LOCATION>La Mesa</LOCATION>, was formally christened <DATE>Monday</DATE> as the <ORGANIZATION>Martin 
Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Freeway. 
</P>
<P>
Four green-and-white signs, each 14 feet long by 3 1/2 feet wide, along the 
state route were unveiled <DATE>Monday</DATE> at a press conference officially acknowledging 
the name change, <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>'s latest effort to find a permanent memorial for the 
slain civil-rights leader. 
</P>
<P>
For two years, the memorial issue has thrust the city in a racially and 
politically divisive debate. The renaming of the freeway has been one of the 
least favorite choices of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>'s black community. 
</P>
<P>
The Rev. <PERSON>George Stevens</PERSON>, a black community leader who has fought to have the 
<ORGANIZATION>San Diego Convention Center</ORGANIZATION> named for King, said at the unveiling that, 
although he supports renaming the freeway, he isn't satisfied, and that <LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION> must still deal with what he called racism and oppression. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>April, 1986</DATE>, the <LOCATION>San Diego City Council</LOCATION> decided against seeking a name 
change for <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 94 and instead voted to designate Market Street as <ORGANIZATION>Martin 
Luther King Way</ORGANIZATION>. But, a year later, <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> voters rescinded that decision by 
overwhelmingly approving a referendum that restored Market Street. 
</P>
<P>
In the aftermath, a private group, led by members of the <ORGANIZATION>Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, 
worked with black leaders to find another replacement, settling on a 
scholarship fund and King statue to be built in <LOCATION>Balboa Park</LOCATION>. Fund raising for 
the <MONEY>$750,000</MONEY> goal has stalled at about <MONEY>$150,000</MONEY>, civic leaders said recently. 
</P>
<P>
Also attempting to move ahead was the <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION>, which called on the <ORGANIZATION>Board 
of Port Commissioners</ORGANIZATION> to name the new convention center in <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s honor, a 
recommendation pushed by the <ORGANIZATION>King Tribute Advisory Board</ORGANIZATION>. The group held a 
series of eight poorly attended public hearings before voting on its 
recommendation. 
</P>
<P>
By <DATE>last July</DATE>, the port board decided by a 4-3 vote to keep <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s name off the 
center, which opens to the public <DATE>Friday</DATE> as the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Convention Center</ORGANIZATION>. A 
Stevens-led group has promised to protest and picket the opening ceremonies. 
</P>
<P>
It was after that vote that Assemblyman <PERSON>Pete Chacon</PERSON> (D-San Diego) and state 
<PERSON>Sen. Wadie P. Deddeh</PERSON> (D-Chula Vista) introduced a resolution asking the 
Legislature to rename <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 94. The Legislature approved the request in 
<DATE>September</DATE>, specifying, however, that private donations be used to pay for the 
new signs. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Freeway Committee</ORGANIZATION> was formed to raise the money. Its 
chairman is Bishop <PERSON>George McKinney</PERSON>, pastor of <ORGANIZATION>St. Stephen's Church of God</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Christ</LOCATION> on Imperial Avenue. Sharing the leadership of the group are <PERSON>Gordon C. 
Luce</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Great American Bank</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Kim Fletcher</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>HomeFed Bank</ORGANIZATION>, 
and <PERSON>Deddeh</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The group has raised <MONEY>$1,400</MONEY> of the <MONEY>$2,700</MONEY> needed for the signs, according to a 
committee spokeswoman. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, KING TRIBUTE: A 10-mile stretch of California 94 was christened Martin 
Luther King Jr. Highway. The naming of the highway comes after an often bitter 
two-year struggle to find a suitable tribute for the slain civil rights leader 
in San Diego. ; Photo, Newly installed sign on California 94 proclaims that it 
is now the Martin Luther King Jr. Freeway. DON BARTLETTI / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890819-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-89 1344EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DexterKing     08-19 0765</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dexter King,0792</SECOND>
<HEAD>Old Guard, Youth in Familiar Civil Rights Movement Conflict</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SONYA ROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The civil rights coalition <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr.</ORGANIZATION>
put together more than three decades ago was having a foot-stompin'
good time in <LOCATION>Ebenezer Baptist Church</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE>.
   Marchers from the movement's high time swayed and clapped to
gospel music. Movement royalty _ <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s widow, sister and three of
his children _ were on hand for festivities that lasted until
midnight.
   But one person was noticeably absent: <PERSON>Dexter Scott King</PERSON>.
   He called himself ``the son of a son of a movement'' when he
became president of his father's memorial center, but left the
center in a huff <DATE>four months later</DATE> amid a reported power struggle
with his mother, <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON>.
   King, 28, the youngest son, has kept a low profile since his
resignation <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE> from the <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Center for
<ORGANIZATION>Nonviolent Social Change</ORGANIZATION>. Neigher he nor his mother responded to
repeated requests for interviews.
   The <ORGANIZATION>King Center</ORGANIZATION>'s directors emerged from a six-hour meeting
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with a new job for King, but they have not announced what
it is. King has given no indication whether he will accept the job.
   The directors have said the center's presidency will remain
vacant and they consider the matter basically resolved.
last week, there were several who identified with <PERSON>Dexter King</PERSON>'s
position: that of a young leader who wants his ideas heard in a
movement where the old guard is reluctant to surrender control.
   Among them was <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>John Lewis</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ga.</LOCATION>, a leader in the
49, said such power struggles were a problem nearly 30 years ago.
   ``The sit-ins and the Freedom Rides in <ORGANIZATION>SNCC</ORGANIZATION> were also a revolt
against the old leadership,'' he said. ``What made it different in
that period was we had been provided a role, and a place at the
table.
   ``You cannot take the dream ... to participate, put it in a
bottle and put a cap on it. We should open the doors, make young
people feel welcome.''
   ``One thing about <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> _ he welcomed the
involvement of young people,'' <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> said. ``He praised the vigor
they could bring to a struggle.''
   Civil rights leaders, many of whom have acted as surrogate
fathers to <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s children, said they are concerned about <PERSON>Dexter
King</PERSON>'s welfare.
   ``I do plan to talk to him,'' said <ORGANIZATION>SCLC</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Joseph Lowery</PERSON>,
a member of the <ORGANIZATION>King Center</ORGANIZATION>'s board of directors and a longtime <PERSON>King</PERSON>
family friend. ``I think some mistakes were made on both sides.
   ``I think he's amenable to working it out. He loves the center
and I'm sure he wants to be involved in the vital work the center
does.''
   But another King aide, <PERSON>Hosea Williams</PERSON>, said, ``He ain't going
back in there.'' <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said <PERSON>King</PERSON> left because the center's
leaders, by giving him the role of ``president-in-training,'' showed
they were unwilling to give him power to change things.
   ``They killed the boy's spirit. He sees now how costly it is, how
tough it is to be a true leader,'' <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said.
   ``They talking about training. What kind of training does he
need?'' Williams asked. ``Old age is the inability to accept change.
And that is just the problem that <PERSON>Dexter</PERSON> ran into.''
   The Rev. <PERSON>Tony Minor</PERSON>, 30, could readily identify with what <PERSON>Dexter
King</PERSON> experienced.
   Minor, the <ORGANIZATION>SCLC</ORGANIZATION>'s youngest chapter president, pulled together a
conference chapter in <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, that, after eight months, has
150 members _ mostly people under 35.
   A graduate of <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON>'s alma mater, <ORGANIZATION>Morehouse College</ORGANIZATION>,
Minor spent five years as an aide for <PERSON>Lowery</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> Mayor
<PERSON>Andrew Young</PERSON>, learning how to move his ministry into the community
and listening to stories about the movement days.
   Minor said the <ORGANIZATION>SCLC</ORGANIZATION> has made room at the top for youth before,
and he doesn't mind waiting for his day in the sun.
   ``The challenge is for younger leaders to respect and support
veterans who have been around,'' he said. ``Those veterans should,
in turn, adopt the young leaders, teach them, support them.''
   But <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said, ``Young leaders must not back up or submit to
old leaders like me.''
   ``They've just got to come up and push old leaders on out of the
way,'' he said. ``Old leaders must realize ... we should voluntarily
allow the young leaders to take over and meet today's challenge.
   ``If we don't do that, then what we have suffered for will
perish.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072789-0037 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 87201 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 27, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 10; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
412 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MURALIST PAINTS FACE OF HOPE FOR YOUTH; 
</P>
<P>
MARTIN LUTHER KING JR. ELEMENTARY IS GETTING IMAGE OF ITS NAMESAKE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARICARMEN EROLES, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Amid drug deals and gang fights in <LOCATION>Southeast San Diego</LOCATION>, an artist is trying to 
keep the Rev. <PERSON>Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON>'s dream alive. 
</P>
<P>
At <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Elementary School, <PERSON>Eddie Edwards</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> is 
painting a two-story-high mural that he says will help show children that they 
can turn their own dreams into reality. 
</P>
<P>
King's face is the focal point of the mural, which is being painted on the east 
wall of the school's auditorium. Below him, children of different races play 
with building blocks with the words friendship, love, peace and we shall 
overcome inscribed on them. <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> says he hopes the mural will make a 
stronger impression on the children than do the drug deals that take place 
around the school. 
</P>
<P>
"If you touch hands with the youth, you touch hands with the future," he said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> sees art as an alternative to drugs and crime and explained that he 
decided to portray King in the mural in the hope that children will see they 
can follow the slain civil rights leader's dream to improve their lives. 
</P>
<P>
The mural, which <ORGANIZATION>Edwards</ORGANIZATION> started in <DATE>late June</DATE>, faces the school playground at 
31st Street, where he said drug dealers stand during school hours. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Dana Flowers</PERSON>, a teacher at the school, said she too hopes that <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s positive 
image will turn the children away from drugs. 
</P>
<P>
Several children have already shown interest in the mural and have helped 
<PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> with it, listening to him talk about King and what the painting 
