<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890401-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-89 1132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AlamoBattle Bjt   04-01 0847</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alamo Battle, Bjt,0866</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alamo Management Battle Pits Hispanics Against `Daughters of Texas
Republic'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID SEDENO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 150 years ago, legend has it, Alamo
commander <PERSON>William B. Travis</PERSON> drew a line across the grounds of the
old Spanish mission. He asked his men to step over it and defend
the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> against thousands of Mexican troops.
   Today, the Daughters of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, who have cared
for the Alamo for 84 years, are emulating <PERSON>Travis</PERSON>' legendary gesture
as they battle with legislators and Hispanic leaders who want to
wrestle control of the Alamo away from the 6,000-member group.
   Travis lost his battle to <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> in <DATE>March 1836</DATE>, but <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
troops rallied with the cry ``Remember the Alamo!'' and later
defeated Mexican troops to regain the Alamo and win <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>'
independence from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Now, critics of the Daughters of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> say the
mission would be better run by a state agency accountable to the
public, particularly in light of an audit that showed the
<ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION>' Alamo chapter with a budget surplus of nearly <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY>.
   ``We aren't hiding anything. Our books are open and we are
complying with the open records and open meetings laws,'' said
<PERSON>Marjorie Hardy</PERSON>, a chapter chairwoman. Tourism officials estimate
chapter members usher close to 10 million visitors a year through
the mission in the heart of downtown.
   Shifting control to the state, <PERSON>Ms. Hardy</PERSON> said, would cost
taxpayers because state workers would be paid for duties that
volunteers now perform. As for the surplus, <PERSON>Ms. Hardy</PERSON> said it was
being saved to build a larger theater in the complex.
   ``We are very proud of what we have done with the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, but we
are not bragging about ourselves. Maybe we should,'' <PERSON>Ms. Hardy</PERSON> said.
   Daughters of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> are descendants of people who
lived in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> between <DATE>1836</DATE> and <DATE>1845</DATE>, when it was an independent
republic before becoming part of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. The Daughters
received a state charter in <DATE>1905</DATE> to operate the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>.
   The complex includes a chapel with artifacts and flags, a
souvenir shop and research library, a small building where
documentaries are shown and enclosed grounds with several cannons
on display. Admission is free, and operating expenses are covered
by souvenir sales profits. No state money is used.
   Recently, the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION> asked Attorney General <PERSON>Jim Mattox</PERSON> to
clarify their legal status; he ruled that the group must comply
with the state open records law because it manages a state-owned
site.
   Meanwhile, state Rep. <PERSON>Ron Wilson</PERSON> filed a bill that would
transfer control of the Alamo from the Daughters to the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Parks
&amp; Wildlife Department</ORGANIZATION>, which operates numerous state parks and
museums.
   ``It's a historical structure, probably the most historical
structure in the state, and for the state not to have control or
management of it is a little absurd,'' he said. A <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> committee
is slated to have a hearing on the bill later this month.
   Adding fuel to the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> controversy is <PERSON>Jose Garcia de Lara</PERSON>,
president of the <ORGANIZATION>League of United Latin American Citizens</ORGANIZATION>.
   Garcia, who says he is a descendant of <PERSON>Bernardo Gutierrez de
Lara</PERSON>, author of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> declaration of independence,
maintains the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> is a symbol of oppression for Hispanics.
   He said the League and the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION> should work together to see
that Hispanic heroes of the Alamo _ Mexicans who fought alongside
the other <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> defenders _ are granted the same respect as <ORGANIZATION>Travis</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>James Bowie</PERSON> and <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON>.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>DRT</ORGANIZATION> has a perception that they own the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> and because
of that they have managed it and handled it in a way that has
excluded Hispanics from participating in historical activities,''
de <PERSON>Lara</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Adela Navarro</PERSON>, 85-year-old descendant of Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
statesman <PERSON>Jose Antonio Navarro</PERSON>, also favors state control of the
<LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, though she herself is a member of a Daughters chapter.
   ``These old girls play dirty politics. The Alamo doesn't belong
to them ...,'' <PERSON>Ms. Navarro</PERSON> said. ``They think they are superior and
they are not.''
   But supporters of the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION>, including Mayor <PERSON>Henry Cisneros</PERSON>
and state Rep. <PERSON>Orlando Garcia</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, say the group has
done an admirable job of restoring the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> and telling the
history of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> accurately.
   ``They are blood descendants of the heroes of the Alamo,''
<PERSON>Cisneros</PERSON> said. ``No one else will treat either the building or the
history of the period with the care and reverence they bring to the
task.''
   Garcia, who had asked the Daughters to open their records,
agrees they take care of the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> as no one else could and adds,
``the state is not in a position to be assuming new burdens.''
   <PERSON>Pauline Wilson</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION>' Alamo chapter, said
hard work went into making the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> the tourist attraction it is
today.
   ``The older members brought in their husbands, their kids, even
their maids to clean the place out,'' she said. ``Where were all
these people when we were having such a hard time with it?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042389-0090 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 47761 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 23, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 19; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
650 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DAUGHTERS DRAW LINE OVER ALAMO CONTROL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVID SEDENO, Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN ANTONIO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
More than 150 years ago, legend has it, <PERSON>William B. Travis</PERSON>, commander at the 
<LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, drew a line across the grounds of the old Spanish mission. He asked his 
men to step over it and defend <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> against thousands of Mexican troops. 
</P>
<P>
Today, the Daughters of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, keepers of the Alamo for 84 
years, are emulating <PERSON>Travis</PERSON>' legendary gesture as they battle with legislators 
and Latino leaders who want to wrest control of the historic battle site from 
the 6,000-member group. 
</P>
<P>
Travis lost the battle with Gen. <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> in <DATE>March, 1836</DATE>, but <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> troops 
rallied to the cry "Remember the Alamo!" as they continued to fight, later 
winning <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' independence from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Now, critics of the Daughters of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> say the mission would be 
better run by a state agency accountable to the public, particularly in light 
of an audit that showed the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION>' Alamo chapter with a budget surplus of 
nearly <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
"We aren't hiding anything. Our books are open, and we are complying with the 
open records and open meetings laws," said <PERSON>Marjorie Hardy</PERSON>, a chapter 
chairwoman. Tourism officials estimate that chapter members usher close to 10 
million visitors a year through the mission in the heart of downtown. 
</P>
<P>
Shifting control to the state, <PERSON>Hardy</PERSON> said, would cost taxpayers because state 
workers would have to be paid for duties that volunteers now perform. As for 
the surplus, she said it is being saved to build a larger theater in the 
complex. 
</P>
<P>
"We are very proud of what we have done with the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, but we are not bragging 
about ourselves. Maybe we should," she said. 
</P>
<P>
Members of the Daughters are descendants of people who lived in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> between 
<DATE>1836</DATE> and <DATE>1845</DATE>, when it was an independent republic not yet part of the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>. The Daughters received a state charter in <DATE>1905</DATE> to operate the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The complex includes a chapel with artifacts and flags, a souvenir shop and 
research library, a small building where documentary films are shown and 
enclosed grounds with several cannons on display. Admission is free and 
operating expenses are covered by souvenir sales profits. No state money is 
used. 
</P>
<P>
Recently, the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION> asked Atty. Gen. <PERSON>Jim Mattox</PERSON> to clarify their legal 
status, and he said the group must comply with the state open-records law 
because it manages a state-owned property. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, state Rep. <PERSON>Ron Wilson</PERSON> has introduced legislation to transfer control 
of the Alamo from the Daughters to the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Parks &amp; Wildlife Department</ORGANIZATION>, 
which operates state parks and museums. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a historical structure, probably the most historical structure in the 
state, and for the state not to have control or management of it is a little 
absurd," <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> said. A <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> committee is to consider the bill later this 
month. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, <PERSON>Jose Garcia de Lara</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>League of United Latin 
American Citizens</ORGANIZATION>, criticizes the way the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> has been run. Garcia, who says 
he is descended from <PERSON>Bernardo Gutierrez de Lara</PERSON>, author of the Republic of 
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> declaration of independence, says the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> is a symbol of oppression to 
Latinos. 
</P>
<P>
He said the League and the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION> should work together to see that Latino 
heroes of the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> -- Mexicans who fought alongside the other defenders -- are 
afforded the same respect as <ORGANIZATION>Travis</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>James Bowie</PERSON> and <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"The <ORGANIZATION>DRT</ORGANIZATION> has a perception that they own the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> because they have managed it 
and handled it in a way that has excluded Hispanics from participating in 
historical activities," de <PERSON>Lara</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Supporters of the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION>, including Mayor <PERSON>Henry Cisneros</PERSON> and state Rep. 
<PERSON>Orlando Garcia</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, say the group has done an admirable job of 
restoration and of telling the history of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> accurately. 
</P>
<P>
"They are blood descendants of the heroes of the Alamo," <PERSON>Cisneros</PERSON> said. "No one 
else will treat either the building or the history of the period with the care 
and reverence they bring to the task." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06203211 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06203211 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: John Wayne as the to-be-skewered Davy Crockett in 'The Alamo'
movie.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  TRAVEL; PAST; WAR; HISTORY; CITY; TEXAS  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A HUSHED group of tourists shuffles past the spot where Maj. Robert Evans
fell. Standing nearby, a white-haired man wearing a string tie holds aloft a
sign: "This Is a Shrine. Please Be Quiet. Thank You.";    Texans take their
heroes seriously. Death threats are not uncommon for those undertaking to sort
out what really happened at the Alamo 155 years ago.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE BATTLE OF THE ALAMO RAGES ON AMONG HISTORIANS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Destination: Texas  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "I definitely got hostile reactions," says <PERSON>Jeff Long</PERSON>, whose "Duel of
Eagles: The Mexican and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fight for the Alamo," was published last year.;  
 "For about two months I had crank calls at all hours, including a couple of
death threats," says Long. "Finally I had to hide behind the telephone
answering machine.";    Among Long's assertions:;    (check) Famed knife
fighter <PERSON>Jim Bowie</PERSON> wanted to surrender to <ORGANIZATION>Mexican General Santa Anna</ORGANIZATION> long
before the battle began.;    (check) Despite 26-year-old Col. <PERSON>William Barrett
Travis</PERSON>' "weird fanaticism" at times, the commander of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> troops actually
tried to surrender just before the assault.;    (check) Both <PERSON>Bowie</PERSON> and <PERSON>Travis</PERSON>
might have committed suicide when the Mexicans breached the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>'s defenses.;
   Such statements still stir bonfires of Lone Star pride. Many Texans are
touchiest of all over the question of how <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON> died.;    Long
dismisses the idea that the former bear-fighter-turned-congressman went down
clubbing Mexican foes over the head with his <PERSON>Brown Bess</PERSON> musket -- or on the
end of a lance, as <PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON> had it in the <DATE>1960</DATE> film, "The Alamo.";   
Instead, writes Long, "<PERSON>David Crockett</PERSON> made a choice. The Go Ahead man quit. He
did more than quit. He lied. He dodged. He denied his role in the fighting.
With his life in the balance, <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> proceeded to do what he did best:
talk.";    This story of <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> vainly pleading for his life has been told
before. A number of Mexican eyewitnesses wrote of <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> being brought
before <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>, who they said contemptuously turned away and ordered
<PERSON>Crockett</PERSON>'s execution on the spot.;    Many serious scholars of the Alamo
accept this account, which was widely reported at the time. But it never fails
to provoke an angry reaction, especially among those steeped in Hollywood
versions, beginning with the <DATE>1955</DATE> Walt Disney TV series, "<PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON>, King
of the Wild Frontier.";    "All these men who were at the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> have been
blown up over the years as such heroes of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> history that a lot of people
don't appreciate this type of book," says <PERSON>Betty Burr</PERSON>, president general of the
Daughters of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas.</LOCATION>;    The organization has operated the
<LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, which belongs to the state, since <DATE>1905</DATE>. Under the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION>'
stewardship, according to <ORGANIZATION>Southern Methodist University</ORGANIZATION> historian <PERSON>David J.
Weber</PERSON>, the Alamo "has become a religious shrine. It's really kind of
comparable to visiting <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>.";    Controversy over the defenders' final hours
is not new. In <DATE>1975</DATE> a new English translation of a Mexican official's diary
account of <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON>'s execution set off a media storm.;    The fury had not
abated by <DATE>1986</DATE>, when an article about <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> by <ORGANIZATION>University of New Mexico</ORGANIZATION>
historian <PERSON>Paul Andrew Hutton</PERSON> appeared in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> Monthly magazine.;    "I
thought the article was hopeless, slavish hero worship," <PERSON>Hutton</PERSON> tells <ORGANIZATION>National
Geographic</ORGANIZATION>. Nevertheless, he received "some wonderful hate mail" because of
his version of <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON>'s death by execution.;    Anonymous callers are not
the only people in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> who disagree with Long's acerbic treatment of the
<LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>'s defenders, however. Historian <ORGANIZATION>Archie P. McDonald of Stephen F. Austin
State University</ORGANIZATION> believes the book has a clear pro-Mexican bias throughout.;  
 "I have to be careful saying things like this, because I will be taken for
just another <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> chauvinist," says <ORGANIZATION>McDonald</ORGANIZATION>, author of a <DATE>1976</DATE> biography of
Travis. "But I don't think the sources substantiate, for example, the kind of
character assassination of Travis that comes through.";    There is no dispute
over how <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> met his death. It was witnessed by one of the women whom <LOCATION>Santa
Anna spared.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> was one of the odd collection of soldiers, speculators
and adventurers who found themselves at the old Spanish mission in the frigid
predawn hours of <DATE>March 6, 1836</DATE>. He died late in the 90-minute battle. A
Mexican bullet ended his desperate, unsuccessful attempt to blow up the powder
magazine and wipe out invaders and defenders alike.;    After executing a
small group of prisoners, probably including <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> had all the
Texans' bodies burned.;    Lingering questions about their final hours may lie
in some forgotten Mexican military archives. Or they may rest irretrievably
with the charred remains of the Texans, which have never been found.;  IF
YOU'RE INTERESTED; For information, contact the <ORGANIZATION>San Antonio Chamber of
Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 1628, <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 78296; (512) 229-2100.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DONALD SMITH, National Geographic  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Antonio, Texas  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910721  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  798  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday July 21, 1991
00203211,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881012-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-12-88 0456EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AlamoBattles     10-12 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Alamo Battles,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alamo Battle's Descendants Still Fight On</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Alamo may have been at peace since <DATE>1836</DATE>,
but descendants of those who fought there have a new battle brewing
over control of <MONEY>$1.7 million</MONEY> banked from souvenir sales at the
shrine.
   The Daughters of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> have always had charge of
the Alamo and its bank account. But the <ORGANIZATION>League of United Latin
American Citizens</ORGANIZATION>, angered over what it calls a misrepresentation
of history by the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION>, says they should turn any surplus over
to the state.
   ``In my opinion, all they want to do is get their hands on the
money,'' <PERSON>Ella Stumpf</PERSON>, 84, one of the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION>, said this week.
   The Alamo is a self-financing facility: No state tax money is
invested and the Daughters must generate funds from the souvenir
shop to pay for a staff of 65 and an annual budget in excess of <MONEY>$1
million</MONEY>.
   The mission, visited by 3 million people a year, occupies four
acres of state land in downtown <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>. The Daughters serve at
the pleasure of the <ORGANIZATION>Legislature</ORGANIZATION>, which alone has authority to end
their custodial role.
   ``I don't think too many people knew they had <MONEY>$1.7 million</MONEY> in
the bank off sales from their souvenir shop. I don't think anyone
had ever asked,'' said state Rep. <PERSON>Orlando Garcia</PERSON>, whose inquiry
into the Alamo ledgers started the current flap.
   <PERSON>Garcia</PERSON> said unless the Daughters ``have a great purpose for
these funds'' the money could become available to the state.
   When the attorney general ruled that the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> finances fell
under the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> Open Records Act, the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters</ORGANIZATION> sent a copy of
their latest audited budget to <LOCATION>Garcia</LOCATION>.
   ``We'd never had to face this before. ... We're happy to do
whatever the proper authorities want us to do. We don't have
anything to hide,'' said <PERSON>Peggy Dibrell</PERSON>, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Daughters'
Alamo Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   Attached to the audit was a note explaining the intended plans
for the surplus funds: a new film and activity center, two new
educational films and a permanent operating ``hedge'' against a
sudden drop-off in tourism.
   <PERSON>Jose Garcia de Lara</PERSON>, president of the Latin American citizens
league, was quick to call for a full accounting of the finances,
with any surplus funds be considered for other state programs.
   ``Quite frankly, we aren't very adamant about taking over the
<LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>. Our main issue is we want accountability by whomever is
running it to the peoples of the state and to the history of our
citizenry,'' he said.
   ``The Daughters have created their history by perpetuating myth
and by omission: These thousands of bad Mexicans killed our few
good Anglos and this has made the chapel a symbol of oppression.''
   About 180 Texans, including <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jim Bowie</PERSON>, died at
the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> fort-chapel when it was attacked by an army of thousands
of Mexicans during the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> Revolution in <DATE>1836</DATE>.
   But <PERSON>Garcia</PERSON>, the legislator, said there is no historical or
cultural component to his inquiry.
   ``I don't have time to get annoyed by what did or didn't happen
in <DATE>1836</DATE>,'' he said. ``What is at issue is access to records about
finances that should be public. My name could be <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON> the
Fifth and I'd be asking the same questions.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900710-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-90 1334EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Summit-Spouses 1stLd-Writethru a0515 07-10 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Summit-Spouses, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0515,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede HOUSTON</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Top 11 grafs new with tour of Mission San Jose, editing
changes; pickup pvs 10th graf bgng, On Monday; Joci in 6th graf is
CQ.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LAURA TOLLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As world leaders at the seven-nation
economic debated the world's future, their spouses toured this
historic city for a glimpse of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' past.
   First Lady <PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON> led the summit wives on a 20-minute tour
of <LOCATION>Mission San Jose</LOCATION>, one of five old Spanish missions still
standing in <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>. The fort-like stone mission was built in
<DATE>1720</DATE> by a Franciscan priest for teaching Christianity and European
culture to the Indians.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON>'s guests included <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Danielle Mitterrand</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Mila Mulroney</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Livia Andreotti</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Sachiyo
Kaifu</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Denis Thatcher</PERSON>, the only male summit spouse, skipped
the tour.
   <PERSON>Hannelore Kohl</PERSON>, wife of West German Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, and
did not accompany their husbands to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   After touring the mission, the women went to a private luncheon
at the home Joci and <PERSON>Joe Straus, Jr.</PERSON>, longtime friends of the
Bushes, followed by a tour of the Alamo and the renovated Majestic
Theater.
   At one time, <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> was a contender as the economic summit
site, but it lost out to <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s adopted hometown.
   The Alamo is the site of the historic <DATE>1836</DATE> battle between the
Mexican army and men led by Col. <PERSON>William Travis</PERSON> who were fighting
for <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' independence from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Mexican Gen. <PERSON>Santa Anna</PERSON>'s troops greatly outnumbered the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>'s
defenders, who were besieged for 14 days before the Mexicans
attacked. All 189 of <PERSON>Travis</PERSON>' men were killed.
   The incident gave birth to the battle cry, ``Remember the
Alamo!'' used by other Texans who fought for freedom.
   After visiting <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, the spouses were returning to
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, where they planned to tour the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> Medical Center on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the final day of the summit.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the spouses were guests of <LOCATION>Betty</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Hugh Liedtkes</PERSON>,
close friends of the Bushes, for a dinner in the upscale Memorial
neighborhood in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>.
   Liedtke is a wealthy oil man who knew <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> when the president
was in the oil business in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> before entering politics.
   The menu included quail, gazpacho soup, shrimp creole remoulade,
poached snapper and asparagus. Dessert was called <ORGANIZATION>Strawberries
Summit</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and <PERSON>Liedtke</PERSON> met years ago in <LOCATION>West Texas</LOCATION> while both were in
the oil business, and they helped form <ORGANIZATION>Zapata Petroleum</ORGANIZATION>.
Eventually, the company's investors spilt, although <PERSON>Liedtke</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> remained friends.
   Liedtke is the former chief of Houston-based <ORGANIZATION>Pennzoil Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the
oil company that won an <MONEY>$10.3 billion</MONEY> judgment in <DATE>1985</DATE> from <ORGANIZATION>Texaco
Inc.</ORGANIZATION> over <ORGANIZATION>Texaco</ORGANIZATION>'s takeover of <ORGANIZATION>Getty Oil Co</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Pennzoil</ORGANIZATION> later settled
for <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   Liedtke is still chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Pennzoil</ORGANIZATION>'s board.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900709-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-09-90 1650EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Summit-FirstLadies     07-09 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-First Ladies,0450</SECOND>
<HEAD>AM-Summit Rpd, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sightseeing, Socializing On Summit Spouses Schedule</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA TOLLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As the summit leaders focus on global issues,
their spouses have a full schedule of sightseeing and socializing,
starting with a private dinner at friends of President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s
<DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   The seven leaders of the industrialized world planned a working
dinner <DATE>Monday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Bayou Bend</ORGANIZATION>, a mansion-turned-museum, while they
spouses were guests of <LOCATION>Betty</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Hugh Liedtkes</PERSON>.
   The Liedtkes, close friends of both <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and his wife, <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON>,
invited the spouses to their home for dinner in the upscale
Memorial neighborhood. Liedtke is a wealthy oil man who knew <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
when the president was in the oil business in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> before entering
politics.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the spouses planned to fly to <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> to tour
the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Mission San Jose</LOCATION> and the renovated Majestic Theatre.
<LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> also was in the running to host the economic summit,
but the city lost out to <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s adopted hometown. .
   The Alamo is the site of the historic <DATE>1836</DATE> battle between the
Mexican army and a group of men led by Col. <PERSON>William Travis</PERSON> who were
fighting for <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' independence from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Mexican Gen. <PERSON>Santa Anna</PERSON>'s troops greatly outnumbered the Alamo
forces, although historical records do not provide an exact number.
The Mexican soldiers laid siege on the Alamo for 14 days before
attacking.
   All of <PERSON>Travis</PERSON>' men _ 189 _ were killed, and the tragic fight
gave birth to the battle cry, ``Remember the Alamo!'' for other
Texans fighting for freedom.
   After visiting <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, the spouses were to return to
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>. They also planned to tour the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> Medical Center on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the final day of the summit.
   Besides <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON>, the spouses include <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Danielle
Mitterrand</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Mila Mulroney</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Livia Andreotti</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Sachiyo Kaifu</PERSON> and <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Denis Thatcher</PERSON>, the only male
spouse.
   <PERSON>Hannelore Kohl</PERSON>, wife of West German Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, and
did not accompany their husbands to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   The wives of several other local leaders also planned to attend
<DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s dinner at the <PERSON>Liedtke</PERSON> home. The menu included quail,
gazpacho soup, shrimp creole remoulade, poached snapper and
asparagus. Dessert was called strawberries summit.
   After dinner, the group was to be entertained by a string trio
and a singing duo. The trio's members are all teen-agers.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and <PERSON>Liedtke</PERSON> met years ago in <LOCATION>West Texas</LOCATION> while both were in
the oil business, and they helped form <ORGANIZATION>Zapata Petroleum</ORGANIZATION>.
Eventually, the company's investors spilt, although <PERSON>Liedtke</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> remained friends.
   Liedtke is the former chief of Houston-based <ORGANIZATION>Pennzoil Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the
oil company that won an <MONEY>$10.3 billion</MONEY> judgment in <DATE>1985</DATE> from <ORGANIZATION>Texaco
Inc.</ORGANIZATION> over <ORGANIZATION>Texaco</ORGANIZATION>'s takeover of <ORGANIZATION>Getty Oil Co</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Pennzoil</ORGANIZATION> later settled
for <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   Liedtke is still chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Pennzoil</ORGANIZATION>'s board.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880224-0271 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-24-88 1334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-AlamoMovie Adv29   02-24 1065</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alamo Movie, Adv 29,1097</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv29</NOTE>
<HEAD>Advance for Mon AMs, Feb 29, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: `Kieth' is cq in 6th graf</NOTE>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIKE COCHRAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At age 65, native <PERSON>Texan George A.
McAlister</PERSON> is a big, friendly, drawling former coach, educator and
inventor turned businessman, rancher, historian, author and dreamer.
   His dream was to make a film based on the battle of the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>.
That dream is coming true.
   With blazing cannons and bloody sabres, the heroes of the Alamo
relive on a giant new screen this week the fateful 13-day siege
that inspired <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to win its independence from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in <DATE>1836</DATE>. A
black-tie premiere of the docudrama is set for <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Entitled ``Alamo ... The Price of Freedom,'' the 45-minute film
is an account of the battle based largely on the research and books
of <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON>, and it has stirred some controversy.
   Academy Award-winning filmmaker <PERSON>Kieth Merrill</PERSON> directed the
movie, part of a <MONEY>$7.2 million</MONEY> project that includes a new IMAX
theater with its 84{-foot wide, six-story high screen. The 426-seat
theater is housed in the new <ORGANIZATION>Rivercenter Mall</ORGANIZATION>, which overlooks the
Alamo grounds.
   The IMAX system is designed to give viewers visually stunning
images as well as a sense of participation in the on-screen
activity.
   ``The Price of Freedom'' was filmed <DATE>last summer</DATE> at <LOCATION>Alamo Village</LOCATION>
near <LOCATION>Brackettville</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON> built the set for his epic
<DATE>1960</DATE> film, ``The Alamo.''
   <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s premiere benefits the research library operated by
the Daughters of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and includes a reception and
dinner-dance and remarks by <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> billionaire <PERSON>Nelson Bunker Hunt</PERSON>.
   Gov. <PERSON>Bill Clements</PERSON> will be on hand the next day for formal
dedication ceremonies, which coincide with the 152nd anniversary of
the fall of the Alamo to Mexican Gen. <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>.
   ``There are two great symbols of freedom in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON>
said. ``First is the Statue of Liberty. But it is just that _ a
symbol of freedom. Then there is this old stone mission, the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>,
a shrine to the price of freedom.
   ``And there is a difference between a symbol of freedom and a
price of freedom.''
   A veteran of World War II and the Korean conflict, <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON>
pointed out gently that a lot of people are willing to live for a
cause but only a very few are willing to die for one.
   ``The defenders of the Alamo were willing to die for freedom,''
he said. ``And more than 3 million people from all over the world
came to the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> to pay homage to those 189 brave men
who gave their lives that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> might be free.''
   McAlister once stood outside the Alamo for days asking visitors
if they would pay to see an authentic movie of the historic battle
and if they were familiar with IMAX theaters.
   He liked the answers. And the premiere this <DATE>weekend</DATE> showcases
the results of that private poll.
   While stressing the importance of authenticity, <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON> points
out quickly that much of what occurred at the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> is subject to
speculation and individual interpretation.
   ``There are no chronicles of the Alamo and what happened
there,'' he said.
   Still, <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON> spent 12 years researching his books. His
travels took him to <LOCATION>Goliad</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Jacinto</LOCATION>, Washington-on-the-Brazos
and other battle sites and to <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> to visit the hometowns of the most famous defenders of
the Alamo: Col. <PERSON>William B. Travis</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jim Bowie</PERSON>, <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON> and
<PERSON>James Bonham</PERSON>.
   McAlister also describes the Alamo contribution of the Tejanos,
the nine Mexicans who supported the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> cause.
   He and his colleagues say they have made their movie as
historically accurate as possible without sacrificing dramatic and
entertainment value.
   ``If we were going to make a movie for several generations, I
did not want it to be fiction,'' <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON> said.
   The movie has no stars but uses 450 members of war-enactment
societies across the country who are dedicated to historical
accuracy, costume and customs.
   McAlister was surprised and dismayed when <LOCATION>San Antonio City</LOCATION>
Councilman <PERSON>Walter Martinez</PERSON> and a group of residents accused the
producers of distorting historical facts.
   <PERSON>Kathy Pena-Sosa</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>Texas Cavalcade</ORGANIZATION>, said some
objectionable scenes were deleted in the final editing from 73
minutes to 45 minutes, but professed to be puzzled by the criticism.
   ``In a community that's <PERCENT>54 percent</PERCENT> Hispanic,'' she said, ``we're
not going to make a movie that's offensive to Hispanics.''
   Born and raised in <LOCATION>East Texas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON> got his first exposure
to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> history in a two-room, two-teacher schoolhouse in a tiny
hamlet near <ORGANIZATION>Commerce</ORGANIZATION>.
   He interrupted his collegiate studies at <ORGANIZATION>East Texas State</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1942</DATE> to enlist in the Marines, but returned after the war to get a
master's degree in math. His minor was history.
   During an academic career that was interrupted when he was
recalled to active duty in <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> in <DATE>1950</DATE>, <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON> was a dean at
<ORGANIZATION>Howard County Junior College in Big Spring</ORGANIZATION>, as well as chairman of
the math department, coach of the track team and an amateur
inventor.
   In <DATE>1955</DATE>, with <MONEY>$150</MONEY>, he founded a company called <ORGANIZATION>GAMCO</ORGANIZATION> to create
and build teaching aids for math students, including a classroom
computer and an electronic teaching machine. The sale of <ORGANIZATION>GAMCO</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1966</DATE> made him a millionaire.
   It also freed him to pursue his ranching and writing interests
and to devote more time to historical research.
   His first novel, ``Nothing is Forever,'' was based on the early
life of Travis. That book evolved into a second novel, ``A Time to
Love ... A Time to Die.''
   This led in turn to ``Alamo ... The Price of Freedom,'' a
non-fiction book which <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON> describes as ``history as I view
it and my personal research reveals it.''
   For <PERSON>McAlister</PERSON>, ``The Price of Freedom'' is more than a movie or
a business venture.
   Said he: ``I would like to leave a legacy on the screen that
retells the story of this sacrifice for freedom ... that
demonstrates to a new generation that freedom isn't free ... that
liberty rests finally on those willing to die for it.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Mon AMs, Feb 29</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910626-0049
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910626-0049.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Letters to the Editor:
   Smile When You Say
   `Lost Cause,' Podner
</HL>
<DATE>
06/26/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A9
</SO>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
TEXAS (TX)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Your June 10 article calling Alamo, Texas, the "famous
namesake of a lost cause" must have raised the hair on the
nape of every Texan and student of Texas history. Of course,
you were referring to the Battle of the Alamo, which took
place in San Antonio in March 1836. But as to the "lost
cause," I haven't a clue as to what you were talking about.
The Texas Revolution, of which the siege of the Alamo was an
integral part, was far from a lost cause.
   The delay inflicted upon the Mexican army by the tenacious
defenders of the Alamo gave Sam Houston time to gather his
ragtag Texan irregulars and make a stand a month later at the
Battle of San Jacinto, near what is now Houston. There they
routed Santa Anna's army and won independence for the
Republic of Texas.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   If the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> had been part of a lost cause, there would
not only be no <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, but probably no <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, since these
states came into being as a direct result of the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
Revolution and the subsequent <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Mexican <DATE>War nine years
later</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Jerry W. Grisham
   Houston</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900711-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-11-90 1339EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Summit-Spouses 1stLd-Writethru a0427 07-11 0607</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Summit-Spouses, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0427,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Spouses Tour Medical Center</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES with Houston tours, edits to tighten, No Pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LAURA TOLLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   First lady <PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON> met with young cancer
patients today while the wives of the other summit leaders toured
different parts of the renowned <ORGANIZATION>Texas Medical Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   The women visited the medical center <TIME>this morning</TIME> before their
husbands issued their final communique on the three-day summit at
the <PERSON>George R. Brown</PERSON> Convention Center.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> went to the pediatric division of the <ORGANIZATION>M.D. Anderson
Cancer Center</ORGANIZATION> where she talked with children attending summer
classes at the hospital.
   One of the patients, 15-year-old <PERSON>Denis Lokter</PERSON>, came from the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> to get treatment.
   ``We had a wonderful visit from your president,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> told
the youth referring Soviet Leader <PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON>'s recent trip
to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The children gave her a book filled with drawings of dinosaurs
they had made on a computer. They also presented her with a package
of Christmas cards designed by children at the hospital.
   ``I think she was really good,'' said <PERSON>Patrick Chapman</PERSON>, who
turned 7 today.
   ``She called me a nickname _ Fang _ because I don't have a tooth
here,'' he said referring to his missing front tooth.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> was joined by <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Danielle Mitterrand</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s
<PERSON>Mila Mulroney</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Livia Andreotti</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Sachiyo Kaifu</PERSON>.
They went to different hospitals at the 600-acre medical center
complex that includes 14 hospitals and two medical schools and four
nursing schools.
   England's <PERSON>Denis Thatcher</PERSON>, the only male spouse, did not visit a
hospital.
   <PERSON>Hannelore Kohl</PERSON>, wife of West German Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, and
did not accompany their husbands to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> took the four women to <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> to
visit an 18th century mission and the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, while <PERSON>Thatcher</PERSON> visited
his son, <PERSON>Mark</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   ``Nobody can come to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> without seeing the Alamo,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON>
told the crowd of several hundred people who braved the heat and
lined up along police barricades to cheer the first ladies.
   ``I wanted to show off a different part of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. I wanted them
to see a side of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> that you might not see any place else, not
only in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> but in this country,'' she said.
   ``You've really turned out for us and given us a wonderful
day.'' she said.
   At the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Lila Cockrell</PERSON> gave the women
proclamations saying they were all ``alcaldes,'' or mayors, of the
original <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>.
   The Alamo is the site of the historic <DATE>1836</DATE> battle between the
Mexican army and a group of men led by Col. <PERSON>William Travis</PERSON> who were
fighting for <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' independence from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Mexican Gen. <PERSON>Santa Anna</PERSON>'s troops greatly outnumbered the Alamo
forces, although historical records do not provide an exact number.
The Mexican soldiers laid siege on the Alamo for 14 days before
attacking.
   All 189 of <PERSON>Travis</PERSON>' men were killed, and the tragic fight gave
birth to the battle cry, ``Remember the Alamo!''
   Earlier, the women were greeted by about 900 children at the
<ORGANIZATION>Majestic Theater</ORGANIZATION>, a palatial theater built in <DATE>1929</DATE> and restored and
reopened last <DATE>August</DATE>.
   The children, from the city's parks and recreation program, were
told about their prestigious visitors only at the last minute. They
cheered and waved miniature <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> flags as the women entered the
ornate theater.
   The spouses also visited the <LOCATION>Mission San Jose</LOCATION> where they heard
traditional mariachi music.
   The mission, established in <DATE>1720</DATE> by a Franciscan priest, is one
of five old Spanish missions still standing in <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901015-0247 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-15-90 0408EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Travel:SanAntoni     10-15 0547</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Travel: San Antonio,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Travel: San Antonio</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY706</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLEY SHANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A picturesque river winds through historic
downtown. Adventurous sorts explore ancient Spanish missions - and
spicy Mexican food. Margaritas and mariachi music abound.
   It's all part of the appeal of <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, a place of history
and romance, where diversions are many.
   From its quaint restaurants and pubs along the popular River
Walk to the museums of the nearby <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, this city of a million
people - the nation's ninth-largest - fascinates all ages. And the
friendly, relaxed mood is instantly pleasing.
   ``Charming, that's the word we hear a lot,'' says <PERSON>Frances
Schultschik</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Convention and Visitors Bureau</ORGANIZATION>. ``There are a
lot of things for people to do, with the history and the charm.''
   By far the most popular destination is the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, site of a <DATE>1836</DATE>
battle in which 189 <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> patriots died at the hands of the Mexican
army of <ORGANIZATION>General Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna</ORGANIZATION>.
   Established in <DATE>1718</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, or <LOCATION>Mission San Antonio</LOCATION> de
<ORGANIZATION>Valero</ORGANIZATION>, was one of a chain of Spanish missions built by Franciscan
friars trying to introduce Christianity to the Indians. The Texans
later used the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> as a fort in the war for independence from
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Missions <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Concepcion</PERSON>, <PERSON>San Juan Capistrano</PERSON> and <PERSON>Espada</PERSON>
also dot the city as part of the <ORGANIZATION>San Antonio Missions National
Historical Park</ORGANIZATION>. Each of the missions has an active parish church.
They are popular spots for traditional <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> weddings.
   La Villita is another must-see attraction for history-lovers.
This downtown village is nestled along the <LOCATION>San Antonio River</LOCATION> and
houses shops and art galleries in its old buildings.
   The Menger Hotel, built in the <DATE>19th century</DATE> next to the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>,
has gone through several restorations to preserve its historic
atmosphere. The hotel's bar, where <PERSON>Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON> recruited his
``Rough Riders,'' is filled with folklore.
   Across downtown, a literal taste of <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> awaits at <LOCATION>Market
Square</LOCATION>, patterned after a traditional Mexican market. The famous <ORGANIZATION>Mi
Tierra</ORGANIZATION> and La Margarita restaurants serve up sizzling fajitas,
savory enchiladas and other favorite Mexican foods and beverages.
Jovial mariachi musicians provide the entertainment.
   Just as popular are the market's assortment of gift shops and
its dozens of trinket-selling vendors in the huge <LOCATION>El Mercado</LOCATION>.
   The ultimate <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> event takes place each <DATE>spring</DATE> when the
entire city lets loose for ``Fiesta.'' Dozens of festivals, parades
and other special events take over the city during the wild
three-week party.
   Festivals also are part of <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>'s charm the rest of the
year.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Texas Folk Life Festival</ORGANIZATION> on the grounds of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute of
Texan Cultures</ORGANIZATION> in early <DATE>August</DATE> celebrates the diverse ethnic
heritage of the state with food, music and dancing.
   A festival of lights illuminates the River Walk at <LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION>. A
10-day <ORGANIZATION>St. Patrick</ORGANIZATION>'s Day celebration - featuring the river dyed
green - takes place in <DATE>March</DATE>. Various other art and music festivals
occur throughout the year.
   ``The city is known for its fiestas - just about any time of
year you can come down here and be a part of some event that's
going on,'' <PERSON>Ms. Schultschik</PERSON> says.
   For visitors who like amusement parks or animals, <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>
has at least two major attractions.
   At <ORGANIZATION>Sea World of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, killer whales, dolphins and sea lions
perform shows, and sharks, penguins and other sea creatures are
exhibited in natural settings.
   The internationally known <LOCATION>San Antonio Zoo</LOCATION> has 3,612 animals,
representing 674 species. Its African antelope collection is one of
the largest and most varied in the world. It's the only zoo
exhibiting an endangered whooping crane.
   In <DATE>1992</DATE>, the city will greet its newest attraction, a musical
theme park called ``Fiesta Texas.'' Park developers, who also
created Opryland in <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>, say <LOCATION>Fiesta Texas</LOCATION> will feature the
music and culture of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900703-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-03-90 1529EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DavyCrockettReunion Bjt   07-03 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Davy Crockett Reunion, Bjt,0612</SECOND>
<HEAD>Descendants Tip Coonskin Cap to Memory of Famed Frontiersman</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DN2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DARRYL EWING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GRANBURY, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON> probably wasn't born on a
mountaintop in <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>. And nobody really thinks he shot a bear
when he was only 3.
   But that doesn't take anything away from the legend, at least
for the 180 Crockett descendants gathering in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> this week.
   ``Those kinds of things are interesting to read about, but they
don't necessarily reflect the real <PERSON>David Crockett</PERSON>,'' said <PERSON>Leonard
Stasney</PERSON>, one of the <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> descendants holding their fifth
biennial reunion at this town, 30 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION>.
Davy's widow settled in <LOCATION>Granbury</LOCATION> after his death at the battle of
the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> in <DATE>1836</DATE>.
   ``The myth was bigger than the man,'' said descendant <PERSON>Sandra
Weaver</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Granbury</LOCATION>, who wore a cloth <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> doll with a real coon
tail on the cap, the whole thing pinned to her shoulder like a huge
corsage.
   <PERSON>Ms. Weaver</PERSON> and <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> kin traded tales about their famous
ancestor <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at the clan picnic, swapped gossip and argued over
the best place to get a genuine coonskin cap.
   They debated how often a fighter could fire the muskets of
<ORGANIZATION>Davy</ORGANIZATION>'s day and whether <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> was killed in action or, as some
historians say, executed by the Mexicans after surrendering the
<LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>.
   ``<PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON> went down swinging a rifle _ he wasn't no
coward,'' insisted <PERSON>Charles Edward Crockett Sr.</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Falls City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore</LOCATION>.
   ``It just doesn't matter,'' <PERSON>Ms. Weaver</PERSON> said. ``All the men who
died at the Alamo were heroes.''
   For the descendants gathered at <LOCATION>Granbury</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Plantation Inn</ORGANIZATION>, it's
the search for a ``real'' <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON> that matters most.
   And according to them, that's not the <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON> a generation
of Americans knew from the Disney TV series that made the
buckskin-clad actor <PERSON>Fess Parker</PERSON> an instant celebrity and prompted
millions of youngsters to buy coonskin caps.
   The show became one of the biggest overnight hits in television
history. Ninety million people watched the TV <PERSON>Davy</PERSON> swing his rifle
as <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>'s troops attacked the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, according to <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>
productions. ``The Ballad of <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON>,'' the theme song of the
series, sold 18 million copies in <DATE>1955</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Joy Bland, the new president of the descendants' group,
dismisses all that as Hollywood glamour.
   ``They don't stick to the real facts. I never could sit through
the whole program. It was awful,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Bland</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>
``The clothing was too modern; the story line was unrealistic.''
   Only one descendant donned a coonskin cap for the reunion, and
he was in period costume to demonstrate the rifles and muskets of
<ORGANIZATION>Crockett</ORGANIZATION>'s era.
   About 200 people belong to the non-profit corporation
Descendants of <PERSON>David Crockett</PERSON>, based in <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>. Members must be
blood relations to <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON>. Associate memberships are extended to
cousins, historians and others who revere the pioneer.
   ``It's kind of exciting to talk to all the people that you are
related to that you don't really know,'' <PERSON>Stasney</PERSON> said. ``It's just
exciting to know that we can share the little bits and pieces of
information and learn a little more about who we are.''
   Some said it's simply a relief to tell people they're <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON>
descendants and be believed.
   <PERSON>Toni Daigle</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Whitecastle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>La.</LOCATION>, said she takes pictures and
documents to her children's school to convince classmates they
really are related to the famous frontiersman.
   ``It's hard,'' <PERSON>Ms. Daigle</PERSON> said, ``because some other kids come
up and say, ``Oh yeah _ I'm kin to <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>, too.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880426-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-26-88 1855EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BowieControversy     04-26 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bowie Controversy,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Austin Urged to Rename Bowie High</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hispanic and black leaders are urging
Austin school officials to name a new high school after someone
other than <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> hero <PERSON>James Bowie</PERSON>, arguing that <PERSON>Bowie</PERSON> was a slave
trader.
   <PERSON>Gary Bledsoe</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>NAACP</ORGANIZATION>'s Austin chapter, said
<PERSON>Bowie</PERSON> isn't the kind of person whose name should be on a school.
   ``The plain and simple truth, according to some of the most
noted <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> historians ... is that <PERSON>Jim Bowie</PERSON> smuggled slaves into
<LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, sold them at vastly inflated prices, owned then,
sold fictitious land grants for <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> land, fraudulently sold land
owned by his in-laws and committed many other heinous and nefarious
acts,'' <PERSON>Bledsoe</PERSON> said.
   Black and Hispanic leaders have suggested naming the school
after a Hispanic. No Austin high school has a Hispanic namesake.
   The Daughters of the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and 420 other people
recommended that the school be named for <ORGANIZATION>Bowie</ORGANIZATION>. In a <DATE>March</DATE> vote,
the <ORGANIZATION>Austin Independent School District Board of Trustees</ORGANIZATION> approved
<PERSON>Bowie</PERSON>'s name for the school with two board members dissenting. For
the matter to be reheard, a board member who voted in favor of
<LOCATION>Bowie</LOCATION>'s name must move for reconsideration. No such motion was made
at the panel's latest meeting <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   A <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> native, <PERSON>Bowie</PERSON> was an adventurer who by age 18 had
earned a reputation for riding alligators and wrestling bears. In
<DATE>1828</DATE>, he moved to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and settled in <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>. After first
sharing command at the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> with <PERSON>William B. Travis</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Bowie</ORGANIZATION> fell ill
and died on <DATE>March 6, 1836</DATE>, when Mexican soldiers captured the
mission. A county and a city in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> are named for him.
and others sent a letter complaining of the name choice to the
school board <DATE>April 11</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890613-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-89 0928EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AlamoHero     06-13 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Alamo Hero,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>School District Rejects Alamo Hero</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRYAN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Educators here have drawn the line against
naming a school for the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> hero <PERSON>William Barret Travis</PERSON>. The
problem: skeletons in his closet.
   It turns out the man who drew the famous line in the dirt during
the defense of the chapel-fort in <DATE>1836</DATE> abandoned his wife and child
and owned slaves.
   Bryan school trustees voted <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> to name the school
instead after black educator <PERSON>Mary Branch</PERSON>, the first woman college
president in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Countless schools and streets in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> are named for Travis. In
fact, the school named for Branch will replace <PERSON>Bryan</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Travis
Elementary School</ORGANIZATION>, which will close next year. Bryan is a town of
59,000 about 60 miles from <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>.
   During the siege of the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Travis</PERSON> wrote an appeal for help.
Legend also has it that when the defenders were surrounded by
Mexican troops, he drew a line and asked those willing to die for
freedom to cross it with him.
   Trustee <PERSON>Wendy Costa</PERSON> pointed out that <PERSON>Travis</PERSON> had abandoned his
family. Noting also that <PERSON>Bryan</PERSON>'s population is <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT> black, she
asked, ``How can we even consider naming a school after someone who
was so strongly in favor of slavery?''
   <PERSON>Bob Calvert</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Texas State Historical Society</ORGANIZATION> described
<PERSON>Travis</PERSON> as a ``ne'er-do-well who in two weeks' time happened to do
something wonderful.''
   ``All of my life I've been told that <PERSON>William Barret Travis</PERSON> is the
greatest <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> hero,'' said Trustee <PERSON>Travis Bryan Jr.</PERSON> ``No power on
earth can convince me he's not, not even <PERSON>Wendy Costa</PERSON>.''
   ``The name of <PERSON>William Barret Travis</PERSON> must be sustained. I'm going
to vote for him, even if everybody votes against me,'' <PERSON>Bryan</PERSON> said.
   The vote was 4-3 in favor of <LOCATION>Ms. Branch</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA040390-0094 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 198852 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 3, 1990, Tuesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 1; Column 2; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1764 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MOVIES AND BULLFIGHTS ARE SPICE OF LIFE FOR S.D. BORDER STRADDLER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SYD LOVE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The idea was to kidnap <PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"We were in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> filming 'The Alamo.' One day at lunch I made the suggestion 
to a bunch of the Mexican extras working in the picture as <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>'s troops. 
I didn't tell them I was kidding. 
</P>
<P>
"I said, 'Look. Texas belonged to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. It was literally stolen from us. What 
I'm going to propose to you is dangerous, so if you want to forget it, OK. . . 
.' 
</P>
<P>
" 'I can get live ammunition. . . .' At this point, everyone became very tense. 
I told them: 'We get this tall guy -- what's his name? Win? Wino? We kidnap him 
and contact <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. We'll give him back if the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> will give us 
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> back.' 
</P>
<P>
"One colonel said he had a family to think of. Another said the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> was 
only two hours away and, 'They'll wipe us out.' I said, 'Yes. But we'll die as 
heroes.' The next day I had lunch alone." 
</P>
<P>
The speaker was <PERSON>Ruben Dario Padilla Colon y Magallanes</PERSON>, a longtime <LOCATION>San Diegan</LOCATION> 
reminiscing about a kaleidoscopic and sometimes fascinating life on both sides 
of the U.S.-Mexican border. 
</P>
<P>
An interview related to <LOCATION>Padilla</LOCATION>'s 80th birthday evoked memories of those deeds 
that have entertained him, from his career in the film industry to wearing 
pistol and badge as police chief of <LOCATION>Texcoco</LOCATION>, to working in tourism and politics 
and publicity in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Baja California Norte</LOCATION>, and more. 
</P>
<P>
In his milieu, "everyone," it seems, 
</P>
<P>
knows <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON>, and he knows "everyone." He is one of those binationals common 
along the border, but nothing is common about him. Padilla is a gregarious, 
knowledgeable, humorous character, quick with a joke, a fact or a connection, a 
man known to be able to get the job done or send you to someone who can. He can 
even get you out of jail with a phone call, two at the most (<LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> or 
<LOCATION>Mexicali</LOCATION> only). 
</P>
<P>
In "The Alamo," Padilla portrays Gen. <PERSON>Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna</PERSON>, leading his 
soldiers at <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> against defenders holed up in the old mission called 
The Alamo. It was filmed in <DATE>1959</DATE> near <LOCATION>Brackettville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I didn't have many lines," <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said, "but <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> is referred to all 
the way through, so he's a major character." 
</P>
<P>
And of course he had to ride a white horse, as was <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>'s custom. Former 
Texas Gov. Price <PERSON>Daniels</PERSON> provided his horse, White Cloud. <PERSON>Ruben Padilla</PERSON> had 
never ridden. 
</P>
<P>
At the moment <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> was to appear at the head of his troops, <PERSON>Michael 
Wayne</PERSON>, the actor's son, told <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON>, who was wearing an authentic 1836 Mexican 
army uniform: "You'd better mount." 
</P>
<P>
"Mount what?" Padilla asked. "I've never ridden before." 
</P>
<P>
"You'd better tell Dad." 
</P>
<P>
Padilla said, "You tell him." 
</P>
<P>
Eventually, <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> learned to manage on horseback, although once during a 
charge he fell. 
</P>
<P>
"All I heard was, 'Cut, cut, cut,' " <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said. "And I never heard so much 
cussing (from <PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON>) in my life." 
</P>
<P>
Padilla, originally a researcher for the film and assistant to the producer, 
was selected for the role in a compromise. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a cameo part, so they needed someone famous or an unknown. <PERSON>Marlon Brando</PERSON> 
turned it down. Then they got a young fellow locally." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Richard Widmark</PERSON> and <PERSON>Laurence Harvey</PERSON>, also in the film, objected because of 
the candidate's youth. Someone mentioned that <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> had acting experience. 
Padilla continued: 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON> said, 'He doesn't look like <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>.' I told him, 'You don't 
look like <PERSON>Jim Bowie</PERSON>, either.' " 
</P>
<P>
Another cameo role was filled by the famed bullfighter, <PERSON>Carlos Arruza</PERSON>, who 
portrays a Mexican lieutenant delivering a message to <LOCATION>Bowie</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Travis</PERSON>, <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> 
and the others. 
</P>
<P>
Singer <PERSON>Pedro Vargas</PERSON> refused the role. So Padilla, for many years one of 
Arruza's best friends, arranged for the matador to handle it. "Arruza got 
<MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> for the part." 
</P>
<P>
Much of <LOCATION>Padilla</LOCATION>'s life has centered around movie making and bullfighting. 
Friends in one field often led him to the other in a glamorous and pleasant 
ricochet. The pattern for this life may have been cut by <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON>'s father, 
<PERSON>Dario</PERSON>, a Mexican importer-exporter who was a friend of the first great Mexican 
bullfighter, <PERSON>Rodolfo Gaona</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
However, for <PERSON>Ruben Padilla</PERSON>, born in <LOCATION>Guadalajara</LOCATION> on <DATE>Feb. 16, 1910</DATE>, the first 
personal step was his fast friendship with another star matador, <PERSON>Silverio 
Perez</PERSON>, whom he met in the early <DATE>1940s</DATE> at <LOCATION>Mexicali</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Silverio</PERSON> -- 
immortalized in song and politics as well as in the taurine world -- was 
fighting. 
</P>
<P>
Padilla lived across the border in <LOCATION>Calexico</LOCATION>, where the family had moved in <DATE>1923</DATE> 
after spending four years in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to avoid the terrors and confusions 
of the Mexican Revolution. 
</P>
<P>
Later, at <ORGANIZATION>Hotel Caesar</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> after a bullfight in the early <DATE>1940s</DATE>, <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> 
introduced <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> and other matadors to producer-director <PERSON>Budd Boetticher</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Budd</PERSON> had a script, "Torero," which became "The Bullfighter and the Lady," 
<PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said. '<PERSON>Wayne</PERSON> had just finished '<ORGANIZATION>Sands of Iwo Jima</ORGANIZATION>' and had quite a bit 
of money. Budd contacted him about financing the movie, and <PERSON>Wayne</PERSON> was 
interested. He called me at <LOCATION>Calexico</LOCATION> (to arrange for bullfighters). He was very 
concerned about how much the matadors would have to be paid. 
</P>
<P>
"I said, 'Yes, <PERSON>Mr. Wayne</PERSON>?' " And in that slow resonant voice, <PERSON>Wayne</PERSON> told 
Padilla: "My friends call me Duke." And that started a friendship that ended 
only with <PERSON>Wayne</PERSON>'s death in <DATE>1979</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Padilla arranged for the matadors. And so <PERSON>Wayne</PERSON> financed "The Bullfighter and 
the Lady" with a <MONEY>$450,000</MONEY> budget ("A lot of money then," <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said). Padilla 
portrayed the impresario in a cast that included <PERSON>Robert Stack</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gilbert Roland</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Katy Jurado</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Virginia Grey</LOCATION>. It was filmed in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. Naturally, there 
was an occasional party. 
</P>
<P>
"Stack liked the sauce made from maguey worms until we told him what it was." 
</P>
<P>
Padilla portrayed Pedro in <PERSON>Boetticher</PERSON>'s film "Wings of the Hawk," starring <PERSON>Van 
Heflin</PERSON>; was adviser for the bullfight sequence in "Mexican Hayride" with <PERSON>Abbott</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Costello</PERSON>; was assistant to the producer in "The War Wagon," filmed in 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> with <PERSON>Kirk Douglas</PERSON>; was in <PERSON>Boetticher</PERSON>'s documentary, "Arruza," narrated 
by <PERSON>Anthony Quinn</PERSON>, whom <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> met at <ORGANIZATION>Hotel Caesar</ORGANIZATION>, naturally, "in the early 
<DATE>1940s</DATE>," and enjoyed his most important role as the detective in the 
Mexican-Italian movie "Bus Ride." 
</P>
<P>
Padilla enjoyed a brief taurine career as bullring judge at <LOCATION>Mexicali</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION>, twice having matadors arrested for allowing picadors to abuse bulls. 
And, in the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, at <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Balboa Stadium</LOCATION>, he staged what was probably 
the first bloodless bullfight in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Along the way he helped a young American woman obtain her start in the 
entertainment world. 
</P>
<P>
"It was in the early <DATE>1940s</DATE>," <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said. "The manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Hotel de Anza</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Calexico</LOCATION> called me. He said he had a problem with a guest, a young girl who 
hadn't paid her bill in three weeks. 'She says she has a contact.' 
</P>
<P>
"So I went to her room. Her name was <PERSON>Yolanda Warren</PERSON>. She was a beautiful girl, 
a brunette, about 16 or 17. I read the contract. It was for a nightclub that 
didn't exist. But she had to go to <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> to make a success of herself. I 
took her to eat. I advised her against going. . . . " 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Warren</PERSON>, from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state, was determined to make her mark in the 
Mexican capital. Padilla contacted <PERSON>Silverio Perez</PERSON>, who was fighting in <LOCATION>Mexicali</LOCATION> 
on the following <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. One of the matador's assistants could drive <LOCATION>Warren</LOCATION> to 
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> as he returned. 
</P>
<P>
"On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> she called me from <LOCATION>El Paso</LOCATION>. The assistant wanted to place her in a 
brothel. I gave her some phone numbers in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> and wired her some 
money." 
</P>
<P>
On her own, she obtained a job dancing at a cheap cabaret in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. Her 
style was Tahitian. One night an important politician, out slumming, was 
attracted to her. He tore some big bills in half and sent one set of the halves 
to her. 
</P>
<P>
"She spurned him. There was a big scene, big headlines in the papers. The 
cabaret became famous, and she did too." 
</P>
<P>
In fact, using a name that complemented her sensuous movements, she became the 
most famous dancer in <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>: Tongolele. (Now living in <LOCATION>Mexico 
City</LOCATION> as <PERSON>Yolanda Montes</PERSON>, Tongolele made a guest appearance last fall at a 
benefit for ailing bandleader <PERSON>Perez Prado</PERSON>. Her old movies are on Channel 12.) 
</P>
<P>
Although the matador <PERSON>Silverio</PERSON> was unable to help <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> in the Tongolele 
episode, he arranged for his friend's only experience in law enforcement. It 
was in the <DATE>winter of 1967-68</DATE>, during one of <PERSON>Silverio</PERSON>'s three terms as mayor of 
<LOCATION>Texcoco</LOCATION>, the small and historic town that had been home to <LOCATION>Netzahualcoyotl</LOCATION>, the 
cultured Chichimeca king and poet crowned there in <DATE>1428</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"Silverio appointed me police chief to bring tourism from <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> 
said. "Fortunately, I had a great assistant chief. One night there was a 
shooting at a dance. A couple of brothers killed a couple of other men. I 
suggested sending out a posse. The assistant chief suggested taking it easy. He 
said the killers weren't professionals, that they had family in <LOCATION>Texcoco</LOCATION>, that 
we should play it cool. 
</P>
<P>
"In a month they were spotted in a local market. I didn't go for them. I all of 
a sudden had a cold." 
</P>
<P>
The assistant chief arrested the pair without a fight. 
</P>
<P>
For a six-year term starting in <DATE>1953</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Baja California Norte</LOCATION> became a 
state, <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> was the first state tourism director. In that capacity, he often 
arranged front-row bullfight seats for <PERSON>Quinn</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Orson Welles</LOCATION> and other Hollywood 
personalities. Simultaneously, <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> was secretary general of the 
"middle-class" sector for <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s ruling political party. 
</P>
<P>
Now he lives in <LOCATION>Mission Hills</LOCATION>, an easy walk to the shops and restaurants in the 
vicinity of Goldfinch and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> streets, directs <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> publicity for the 
<LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> bullfights and keeps in touch with his family, including brother Oscar, 
well known in local politics and in the insurance business; son <PERSON>Ruben Jr.</PERSON>, also 
an insurance executive; son <PERSON>Marco Antonio</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Customs inspector; and two 
granddaughters and three grandsons, including <PERSON>Ruben</PERSON>, a magician. 
</P>
<P>
Padilla, who retained his Mexican citizenship, critically observes activities 
major and minor on both sides of the border. For instance, on the <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> 
traffic circles called gloriettas: 
</P>
<P>
"Approach them according to your machismo and the weight of your vehicle." 
</P>
<P>
On the future of <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION>: 
</P>
<P>
"There is really a new <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> now. Tourists should feel no qualms about 
visiting. . . . The main problem is lack of water." 
</P>
<P>
And he denigrates use of the words "Hispanic" and "Chicano" to describe 
Mexicans or Mexican-Americans -- Hispanic because it belongs rightly to 
Spaniards only, he says, the other because it is recently coined and of 
uncertain origin. He is a Mexican, he will tell you, descended from Spaniards 
and Indians. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Ruben Dario Padilla Colon y Magallanes reflects on his 80 years of life. 
; Photo, Old friends John Wayne and Padilla in 1970 at Calexico airport. ; 
Photo, Padilla with a 1959 picture showing him in full costume during the 
shooting of "The Alamo." DON BARTLETTI / Los Angeles Times; Photo, RUBEN 
PADILLA ; Photo, Dancer Tongolele with Ruben Dario Padilla Colon y Magallanes. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920214-0025
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920214-0025.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Letters to the Editor:
   Remember San Jacinto
</HL>
<DATE>
02/14/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A11
</SO>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
TEXAS (TX)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   In your Jan. 20 article "Mexico Guards Its Precious Oil
Business," there are serious discrepancies, i.e., "Yankee
interlopers, who, after all, took oil-rich Texas from Mexico
in 1848."
   Texas took itself from Mexico on April 21, 1836, defeating
Gen. Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna in the 20-minute Battle of
San Jacinto, as every third-grader in Texas could tell you --
or could have in 1927, anyway.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   And Texans are not Yankees.
   <ORGANIZATION>Allen T. Smith
   El Paso</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BowieKnife     08-26 0174</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bowie Knife,0178</SECOND>
<HEAD>Group Scraps Plans to Buy `Bowie' Knife</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <MONEY>$3.5 million</MONEY> offer for a knife believed to have
belonged to <PERSON>James Bowie</PERSON> during the battle of the Alamo was
withdrawn because the dagger's owner refused to have it tested for
authenticity.
   Spirit of the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>, a non-profit fund-raising group, dropped
the offer, president <PERSON>John Stokes</PERSON> said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Bartley Dean Moore</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Riverside</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, said family lore has it
that a young Mexican soldier found the knife after the mission fell
in <DATE>1836</DATE>. In <DATE>1890</DATE>, the soldier gave the knife to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s grandfather
in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to settle a <MONEY>$5</MONEY> debt, the story goes.
   Museum curators and other experts discounted the claim.
   The fund-raising group, formed last year, had agreed to pay <MONEY>$3.5
million</MONEY> if the knife proved genuine, but wanted tests to determine
its age and metal content.
   All 187 American defenders, including <PERSON>Bowie</PERSON> and <PERSON>Davy Crockett</PERSON>,
were killed in the 13-day siege of the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>. Legend credits <PERSON>Bowie</PERSON>
with inventing what is now known as the bowie knife.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042390-0141 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 279434 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 23, 1990, Monday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<P>
RUBEN PADILLA 
</P>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 5; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1138 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
REMINISCENCES OF LIFE ON BOTH SIDES; 
</P>
<P>
CULTURE: MOVIES AND BULLFIGHTS ARE THE SPICE OF LIFE FOR AN 80-YEAR-OLD SAN 
DIEGO BORDER STRADDLER. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SYD LOVE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The idea was to kidnap <PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"We were in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> filming 'The Alamo.' One day at lunch I made the suggestion 
to a bunch of the Mexican extras working in the picture as <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>'s troops. 
I didn't tell them I was kidding. 
</P>
<P>
"I said, 'Look. Texas belonged to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. It was literally stolen from us. What 
I'm going to propose to you is dangerous, so if you want to forget it, OK. . . 
.' 
</P>
<P>
" 'I can get live ammunition. . . .' At this point, everyone became very tense. 
I told them: 'We get this tall guy -- what's his name? Win? Wino? We kidnap him 
and contact <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. We'll give him back if the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> will give us 
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> back.' 
</P>
<P>
"One colonel said he had a family to think of. Another said the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> was 
only two hours away and, 'They'll wipe us out.' I said, 'Yes. But we'll die as 
heroes.' The next day I had lunch alone." 
</P>
<P>
The speaker was <PERSON>Ruben Dario Padilla Colon y Magallanes</PERSON>, a longtime <LOCATION>San Diegan</LOCATION> 
reminiscing about a kaleidoscopic and sometimes fascinating life on both sides 
of the U.S.-Mexican border. 
</P>
<P>
An interview related to <LOCATION>Padilla</LOCATION>'s 80th birthday evoked memories of those deeds 
that have entertained him, from his career in the film industry to wearing 
pistol and badge as police chief of <LOCATION>Texcoco</LOCATION>, to working in tourism and politics 
and publicity in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Baja California Norte</LOCATION>, and more. 
</P>
<P>
In his milieu, it seems that everyone knows <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> and he knows everyone. He 
is one of those binationals common along the border, but nothing is common 
about him. Padilla is a gregarious, knowledgeable, humorous character, quick 
with a joke, a fact or a connection, a man known to be able to get the job done 
or send you to someone who can. He can even get you out of jail with a phone 
call, two at the most (<LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Mexicali</LOCATION> only). 
</P>
<P>
In "The Alamo," Padilla portrays Gen. <PERSON>Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna</PERSON>, leading his 
soldiers at <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> against defenders holed up in the old mission called 
The Alamo. It was filmed in <DATE>1959</DATE> near <LOCATION>Brackettville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I didn't have many lines," <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said, "but <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> is referred to all 
the way through, so he's a major character." 
</P>
<P>
And of course he had to ride a white horse, as was <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>'s custom. Former 
Texas Gov. Price <PERSON>Daniels</PERSON> provided his horse, White Cloud. Padilla had never 
ridden. 
</P>
<P>
At the moment <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> was to appear at the head of his troops, <PERSON>Michael 
Wayne</PERSON>, the actor's son, told <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON>, who was wearing an authentic 1836 Mexican 
army uniform: "You'd better mount." 
</P>
<P>
"Mount what?" Padilla asked. "I've never ridden before." 
</P>
<P>
"You'd better tell Dad." 
</P>
<P>
Padilla said, "You tell him." 
</P>
<P>
Eventually, <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> learned to manage on horseback, although once during a 
charge he fell. 
</P>
<P>
"All I heard was, 'Cut, cut, cut,' " <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said. "And I never heard so much 
cussing (from <PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON>) in my life." 
</P>
<P>
Much of <LOCATION>Padilla</LOCATION>'s life has revolved around filmmaking and bullfighting. Friends 
in one field often led him to the other in a glamorous and pleasant ricochet. 
The pattern for this life may have been cut by <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON>'s father, <PERSON>Dario</PERSON>, a 
Mexican importer-exporter who was a friend of the first great Mexican 
bullfighter, <PERSON>Rodolfo Gaona</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
However, for <PERSON>Ruben Padilla</PERSON>, born in <LOCATION>Guadalajara</LOCATION> on <DATE>Feb. 16, 1910</DATE>, the first 
personal step was his fast friendship with another star matador, <PERSON>Silverio 
Perez</PERSON>, whom he met in the early <DATE>1940s</DATE> at <LOCATION>Mexicali</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Silverio</PERSON> -- 
immortalized in song and politics as well as in the taurine world -- was 
fighting. 
</P>
<P>
Padilla lived across the border in <LOCATION>Calexico</LOCATION>, where the family had moved in <DATE>1923</DATE> 
after spending four years in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to avoid the terrors and confusions 
of the Mexican Revolution. 
</P>
<P>
Later, at <ORGANIZATION>Hotel Caesar</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> after a bullfight in the early <DATE>1940s</DATE>, <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> 
introduced <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> and other matadors to producer-director <PERSON>Budd Boetticher</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Budd</PERSON> had a script, "Torero," which became "The Bullfighter and the Lady," 
<PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said. '<PERSON>Wayne</PERSON> had just finished '<ORGANIZATION>Sands of Iwo Jima</ORGANIZATION>' and had quite a bit 
of money. Budd contacted him about financing the movie, and <PERSON>Wayne</PERSON> was 
interested. He called me at <LOCATION>Calexico</LOCATION> (to arrange for bullfighters). He was very 
concerned about how much the matadors would have to be paid. 
</P>
<P>
"I said, 'Yes, <PERSON>Mr. Wayne</PERSON>?' " And in that slow resonant voice, <PERSON>Wayne</PERSON> told 
Padilla: "My friends call me Duke." And that started a friendship that ended 
only with <PERSON>Wayne</PERSON>'s death in <DATE>1979</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Padilla arranged for the matadors. And so <PERSON>Wayne</PERSON> financed "The Bullfighter and 
the Lady" with a <MONEY>$450,000</MONEY> budget ("A lot of money then," <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> said). Padilla 
portrayed the impresario in a cast that included <PERSON>Robert Stack</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gilbert Roland</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Katy Jurado</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Virginia Grey</LOCATION>. It was filmed in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. Naturally, there 
was an occasional party. 
</P>
<P>
"Stack liked the sauce made from maguey worms until we told him what it was." 
</P>
<P>
Padilla portrayed Pedro in <PERSON>Boetticher</PERSON>'s film "Wings of the Hawk," starring <PERSON>Van 
Heflin</PERSON>; was adviser for the bullfight sequence in "Mexican Hayride" with <PERSON>Abbott</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Costello</PERSON>; was assistant to the producer in "The War Wagon," filmed in 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> with <PERSON>Kirk Douglas</PERSON>; was in <PERSON>Boetticher</PERSON>'s documentary "Arruza," narrated by 
<PERSON>Anthony Quinn</PERSON>, whom <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> met at <ORGANIZATION>Hotel Caesar</ORGANIZATION>, naturally, "in the early 
<DATE>1940s</DATE>," and enjoyed his most important role as the detective in the 
Mexican-Italian movie "Bus Ride." 
</P>
<P>
Padilla enjoyed a brief taurine career as bullring judge at <LOCATION>Mexicali</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION>, twice having matadors arrested for allowing picadors to abuse bulls. 
And, in the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, at <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Balboa Stadium</LOCATION>, he staged what was probably 
the first bloodless bullfight in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For a six-year term starting in <DATE>1953</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Baja California Norte</LOCATION> became a 
state, <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> was the first state tourism director. In that capacity, he often 
arranged front-row bullfight seats for <PERSON>Quinn</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Orson Welles</LOCATION> and other Hollywood 
personalities. Simultaneously, <PERSON>Padilla</PERSON> was secretary general of the 
"middle-class" sector for <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s ruling political party. 
</P>
<P>
Now he lives in <LOCATION>Mission Hills</LOCATION>, directs <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> publicity for the <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> 
bullfights and keeps in touch with his family, including brother Oscar, well 
known in local politics and in the insurance business; son <PERSON>Ruben Jr.</PERSON>, also an 
insurance executive; son <PERSON>Marco Antonio</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Customs inspector; and two 
granddaughters and three grandsons, including <PERSON>Ruben</PERSON>, a magician. 
</P>
<P>
Padilla, who retained his Mexican citizenship, critically observes activities 
major and minor on both sides of the border. For instance, on the future of 
<LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION>: 
</P>
<P>
"There is really a new <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> now. Tourists should feel no qualms about 
visiting. . . . The main problem is lack of water." 
</P>
<P>
And he denigrates use of the words "Hispanic" and "Chicano" to describe 
Mexicans or Mexican-Americans -- Hispanic because it belongs rightly to 
Spaniards only, he says, the other because it is recently coined and of 
uncertain origin. He is a Mexican, he will tell you, descended from Spaniards 
and Indians. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Ruben Dario Padilla Colon y Magallanes recalls playing Gen. Antonio 
Lopez de Santa Anna in "The Alamo," starring John Wayne, in 1959. DON BARTLETTI 
/ Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
LIFESTYLESACTORS; UNITED STATES -- FOREIGN RELATIONS -- MEXICO; BULLFIGHTING 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890822-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-22-89 1442EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--AlamoGraffiti     08-22 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Alamo Graffiti,0174</SECOND>
<HEAD>Workers Find Graffiti Possibly Left By Alamo Defender</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Workers at the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> discovered graffiti that
may have been left by an Alamo defender in <DATE>1836</DATE> on a door of the
mission.
   ``We found original mission plaster,'' <PERSON>Alamo Curator Steve Beck</PERSON>
said. ``There is graffiti in which the dates <DATE>1894</DATE> and <DATE>1897</DATE> are
written in pencil, and the name <PERSON>Mills</PERSON> is inscribed into the surface.
The name is about 4 inches long and 1{ inches tall.''
   The name may have been carved by <PERSON>William Mills</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, who
was among the 189 men known to have died <DATE>March 6, 1836</DATE>, defending
the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION> in the struggle for <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> independence.
   ``We don't have any solid proof it was <PERSON>William Mills</PERSON>, but it's a
good possibility,'' <PERSON>Beck</PERSON> said.
   Beck and stone mason <PERSON>Baltazar Espinosa</PERSON> discovered the graffiti as
they worked on the north side of the <ORGANIZATION>Shrine of Texas Liberty</ORGANIZATION> as part
of an ongoing preservation project. The door dates to the early
<DATE>1700s</DATE>, <PERSON>Beck</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880502-0072 </DOCNO>
<HL> So Does This Mean That Texas Remains a Territory of Mexico? </HL>
<AUTHOR> Paul Duke Jr. (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   Oil prices slide. 
Real estate goes bust. 
Banks collapse. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Dallas Cowboys</ORGANIZATION> notch their first losing season in two decades. 

   Texans have seen plenty of woes in recent years. 
Now, to top it all off, even the value of their printed paper is plunging. 
And not just any paper, but <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>'s proudest heritage, including certain copies of its own <DATE>1836</DATE> Declaration of Independence from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, which sold for up to <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY>. 

   A number of them have turned out to be phonies. 
Someone -- no one knows who -- has been "diddling around with the stuff of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> history," says an angry <PERSON>Don Carleton</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Barker Texas History Center</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION>. 

   And they've been doing so for the past 15 years, according to Austin-based publisher and rare-book dealer <PERSON>W. Thomas Taylor</PERSON>, who alerted <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> booksellers to the problem earlier this month. 
<PERSON>Mr. Taylor</PERSON> himself unwittingly sold several of the phony documents. 

   The duped also include such patriotic <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> bigwigs as Gov. <PERSON>William Clements</PERSON>, as well as numerous libraries and universities, including the <ORGANIZATION>Barker Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
It owns a fake copy of a particularly sacred <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> text, Col. <PERSON>William Barrett Travis</PERSON>'s "Victory or Death" letter, penned just as the Mexican forces closed in on the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>. 

   All of the forgeries purport to be general-distribution circulars printed in the <DATE>1830s</DATE> and <DATE>'40s</DATE>, during the Republic of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> era. 
But the typefaces used, says <PERSON>Mr. Taylor</PERSON>, weren't invented until decades later. 
Aside from that big gaffe, the fastidious forgers dotted some i's that went undotted in the originals. 
<PERSON>Mr. Taylor</PERSON> figures a total of about 100 false documents are in circulation, and embarassed booksellers around the state are apologetically returning their customers' money. 

   But not all <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> tycoons were taken in. 
A while back, <PERSON>H. Ross Perot</PERSON> was offered a Travis circular. 
Experts at <ORGANIZATION>Yale University</ORGANIZATION>, which has a verified Travis letter, were skeptical, and <PERSON>Mr. Perot</PERSON> passed. 

   Still, that hasn't stopped others from offering him a supposed original <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Declaration of Independence and the sword General <PERSON>Cornwallis</PERSON> surrendered to <LOCATION>George Washington</LOCATION>. 
Says <PERSON>Mr. Perot</PERSON>: "There are days when I think people must believe I'm the biggest patsy around." 
