<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910306-0148
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910306-0148.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   It's Never Fun, but It's Not Often
   A Dog Bite Is Really a Royal Pain
   ----
   By Ken Wells
</HL>
<DATE>
03/06/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<CO>
   EUROP
</CO>
<LP>
   LONDON -- Scandalous questions are dogging Britain's Royal
Family: Why are the royal pooches biting the hand that feeds
them? Is there bad blood among the blue-blooded canines?
   Dog behaviorists all over this dog-crazy nation were
seeking answers yesterday after Buckingham Palace tersely
confirmed that Queen Elizabeth II had been bitten on the left
hand by one of her beloved pet corgis. Apparently, the queen,
trying to reassert royal authority, waded into a snarling
pack of 10 corgis who had dropped their palace manners and
were busy thrashing one another.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   It was the second royal free-for-all involving palace
corgis in the past two years. In <DATE>1989</DATE>, the queen's corgi
Chipper was killed by a corgi pack led by <ORGANIZATION>Ranger</ORGANIZATION>, a corgi
owned by Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>'s mother, known affectionately here
as the Queen Mum. In this case, as well, two of the pooches
apparently belonged to the Queen Mum.
   In the latest incident, which occurred at <ORGANIZATION>Windsor Castle</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Her Majesty</ORGANIZATION> suffered a nip on a finger and thumb; the wounds
required three stitches. A royal chauffeur was also bitten
while trying to help the queen separate the dogs.
   "The queen is very brave to have done this," says canine
behaviorist <PERSON>Anthony Burley</PERSON>, who shudders to think that the
attack could have been much worse. "To put your hand in
between fighting corgis is to put your hand into a food
mixer." Corgis are a handful -- low, long and strong, with
grown males averaging 20 to 24 pounds.
   Buckingham Palace might have been tempted to let sleeping
dogs lie and refuse to confirm the attack, except that the
queen's injuries were observed publicly for the first time
yesterday when she conducted a 75-minute investiture ceremony
at the palace. Palace observers who were present noted that
she sported plastic bandages on her left thumb and
forefinger.
   While lauding the queen's bravery, dog psychologists were
also gently suggesting to Her Majesty that she consider other
means of restoring order among her dogs. "Grab a tea tray and
bang it loudly over their heads, then drop it between the
dogs," <PERSON>Mr. Burley</PERSON> says. "You need something physical between
them, but it shouldn't be your hand."
   Unanswered is whether the dog that drew royal blood is in
the royal doghouse. But <PERSON>Roger Mugford</PERSON>, the queen's animal
behaviorist, says: "I suspect the dog will be forgiven."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890506-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-89 0408EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Britain-Dog     05-06 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Britain-Dog,0142</SECOND>
<HEAD>Queen's Dog Dead After Windsor Castle Fight</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A dog belonging to <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON> died after
being bitten in a fight with other royal dogs at <ORGANIZATION>Windsor Castle</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Chipper, a 12-year-old cross between a dachshund and a corgi,
was involved in a fight started by <ORGANIZATION>Ranger</ORGANIZATION>, a corgi belonging to
<PERSON>Queen Mother Elizabeth</PERSON>, the palace said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   The crossbreed, known as a dorgi, was stitched up after the
fight by a veterinarian but died, the palace said.
   The queen was given a corgi by her parents in the <DATE>1930s</DATE> when she
was a little princess. They became the royal family's most popular
house dogs because of their small size but palace staff and
visitors say the dogs tend to snap at ankles.
   Princess <PERSON>Margaret</PERSON>, the queen's sister, preferred dachshunds.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881106-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-06-88 1113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Queen'sCorgis     11-06 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Queen's Corgis,0186</SECOND>
<HEAD>Palace Silent On Report That Queen's Dogs Seeing Psychologist</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>'s corgi dogs are being treated
by an animal psychologist because of their bad record of nipping
members of the royal household, The Mail on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> reported.
   The paper said guardsmen, policemen, footmen and even the royal
clockwinder have fallen prey to the corgis' nips.
   <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> refused comment. ``I don't think we'd like to
comment on that kind of story,'' said a palace spokesman who by
custom was not identified.
   The dogs are being seen by animal behavior specialist <PERSON>Dr. Roger
Mugford</PERSON>, who firmly believes in counseling owners as well, The Mail
on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> said.
   Mugford, whose office was closed <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, was quoted by the paper
as saying of corgis: ``They are, of course, collie-type dogs,
originally bred for cattle herding. As such, they will chase
anything, particularly ankles.''
   The present generation of royal corgis, according to the paper,
are named: Spark, <LOCATION>Mist</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Sable</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Diamond</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Kelpie</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Piper</ORGANIZATION>,
Chipper and <PERSON>Harris</PERSON>. The article did not say how many of the dogs are
receiving treatment.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06066024 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06066024 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Elizabeth  </CAPTION>
<LEADPARA>  One of Queen Elizabeth II's pet Welsh corgi dogs bit her left hand Sunday,
inflicting a wound that required three stitches to close.;    A spokesman for
Buckingham Palace said it happened at Windsor Castle while the queen was
trying to break up a dogfight. He said a chauffeur also was bitten.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  A ROYAL DOG BITE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  People  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     At last count, the queen had six corgis. Her devotion to them dates from
her youth, when her parents gave her one. Her mother has two of the dogs,
which tend to be snappy and yappy.;    In <DATE>1988</DATE>, the queen consulted an animal
psychologist about the dogs' behavior, which included nipping ankles of the
household staff.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Information in this column if from Mercury News wire services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910306  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  111  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday March 6, 1991
00066024,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-8734</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CBOAPADEFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920215
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 FEB 92 / A dog's life at Buck House: As they say in Europe
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JAMES MORGAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
EVERY foreign correspondent in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> has seen the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> film that celebrated
the 40th anniversary of the Queen's accession to the throne, <ORGANIZATION>Elizabeth R</ORGANIZATION>, or
Isabel R as she is known in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
Isabel, <LOCATION>Felipe</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Carlos</PERSON> and Ana are familiar figures there: Spitting Image,
the coarse British satirical television programme, has a wide audience. Such
are the realities of the <LOCATION>New Europe</LOCATION>. So <PERSON>Enric Gonzalez</PERSON> in <LOCATION>El Pais</LOCATION> was
writing for a well-informed readership in his useful summary of the Queen's
decades.
'<PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON> has seen the disappearance of the Empire, the hard recovery of
the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, the cultural revolution of the '60s, the trade union torments of
the '70s and the petty bourgeois Thatcherite insurrection of the '80s
without altering her routine.' The heart of this routine is tea. The Queen
always takes tea with her corgis, 'for whom she personally mixes meat and
biscuits which the little animals eat on the red carpets of her private
homes.'
Corgis were fully researched for <ORGANIZATION>Bernhard Heimrich</ORGANIZATION>'s account in the
<LOCATION>Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</LOCATION>. 'Corgis are short-legged, bustling little
dogs from <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION>, which in the handbook are described as ideal for the
farmyard, vigilant guardians and good comrades. The queen has six corgis,
which she feeds with meat and biscuits every day at half past four.'
Heimrich finds the British almost as interesting as the corgis. He says that
a third of us dream about the Queen, and most of the dreams include drinking
tea with the monarch - sans corgis. So we enter the British subconscious,
and a dark place it proves to be:
'The second surprise (after the dreams) is that it is mainly night in the
<PERSON>Reich</PERSON> of Elizabeth II. This has been recognised for some time but has not
been fully accepted. On the Empire of her predecessor the sun never set. The
four decades of Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON> encompass the British generation which
has to abandon this dream, and the Queen as a dream figure behind the walls
of her palace in the middle of British reality, is there to help.'
Le <PERSON>Monde</PERSON>'s correspondent, <PERSON>Laurent Zecchini</PERSON>, emerges as a hitherto
unimaginable entity - a French <PERSON>Barbara Pym</PERSON>. He too reports the dream of
taking tea with the Queen. 'In the collective unconscious of her people, the
Queen keeps her place at the centre of a pile of useless little things,
dusty but essential, which make <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> in the eyes of so many people
the vestal priestess of the cult of memories . . .'
The elegiac theme then really takes hold: 'Forty years, and always that
certain smile - a little fixed, this great professionalism, this intangible
etiquette, these prime ministers who succeed one another for the invariable
tea and conversations of no importance.'
The Italians care little for psychological speculation, and less for tea, or
even corgis. They are interested in not paying income tax. So in Il Sole-24
Ore, <PERSON>Alessandro Merli</PERSON>, with his usual good taste, celebrated 40 glorious
years of getting away with it. He reverently asked: 'Is the Queen of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>
the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>'s biggest tax evader?'
Merli noted that earlier monarchs had indeed paid income tax. He then ran
through the figures on the Queen's wealth and income and concluded she could
well afford to pay. But he has fears about the succession: her non-payment
of tax 'does not mean that <PERSON>Prince Charles</PERSON>, who likes to appear in the
forefront of 'inner city' causes, will not start doing it again.'
That will not satisfy the royalist <PERSON>Zecchini</PERSON> in Le Monde: 'The Queen will
have to find a recipe for a sort of neo-monarchy for the next century, an
alchemy which will bring together modernity and tradition. In the <DATE>next
decade</DATE> the Queen will celebrate her golden jubilee and her 75 years. Until
then, without any doubt, 'God Save the Queen.''
<PERSON>James Morgan</PERSON> is economics correspondent of the <ORGANIZATION>BBC World Service</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XVI
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-3837</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFMDJAD6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940613
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 JUN 94 / Observer: Going begging
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Nice to see Lady <PERSON>Margaret Colville</PERSON> made Companion of the Royal Victorian
Order in the latest honours list. As 'Extra Woman of the Bedchamber to <PERSON>Queen
Elizabeth</PERSON> the Queen Mother', she no doubt deserves it.
And something for below stairs, too: Royal Victorian Medals (Silver) to  -
among others - <PERSON>Henry Charles Bynoth</PERSON> (roofing contractor), <PERSON>Christopher Arthur
Chiverton</PERSON> (trapper, <LOCATION>Great Park</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Crown Estate</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Windsor</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>Peter Horace
Matthews</PERSON> (senior sous chef, Buckingham palace).
Nothing for the corgis?
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P99   Nonclassifiable Establishments.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 23
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06349082 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06349082 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: 'Inside Buckingham Palace'; 'Inside Buckingham Palace'
includes casual photos, such as this one of Di with wet hair.; PHOTO: 'Inside
Buckingham Palace'; Princess Diana practiced her tap dancing in the palace's
Music Room. (Color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BOOK; REVIEW; CELEBRITY; UK; HOUSING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE sight of Queen Elizabeth II, Prince Philip and the rest of the British
royal family waving from the front upstairs balcony at Buckingham Palace is
familiar. What's totally unfamiliar are the rooms behind that balcony -- the
palace interior.;   There is the frieze-filled Centre Room, where the royal
family lines up before walking out on the balcony. There is the Music Room,
with its domed ceiling and hardwood floors, where Princess Diana practiced her
tap dancing. And there is guest bedroom number No. 236, with its canopied bed,
pink silk walls and a cozy-looking but never used fireplace.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Home  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BEAUTIFULLY ILLUSTRATED BOOKS MAKE LITERALLY
DELIGHTFUL GIFTS FOR FRIENDS OR EVEN YOURSELF
IT'S A ROYAL LIFE: BOOK LOOKS INSIDE BUCKINGHAM
PALACE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cover Story; See also related article on page 1D of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     These rooms and the lifestyles of those who live in and pass through them
are the focus of "Inside Buckingham Palace, The Private World of the Royal
Family" by <PERSON>Andrew Morton</PERSON> (Summit Books, <MONEY>$20</MONEY>). This coffee-table style book,
with its beautiful photographs, is hard to put down, even if you don't follow
all the gossip about the royal family.;   "People see <LOCATION>Buckingham Palace</LOCATION> as a
personification of mystery and majesty," says <PERSON>Morton</PERSON>, who has spent more than
a decade chronicling the comings and goings of <LOCATION>Charles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Diana</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Fergie</ORGANIZATION> and
all.;   "The palace is the center for national rejoicing and sorrow," he says.
"It was the place people ran to on the day the second World War ended. It's a
national rallying point and the royal family has come to symbolize universal
values of duty, obligation and family life.";   Life inside the palace,
according to <PERSON>Morton</PERSON>, is as different and extreme as any commoner might expect.
It takes three days to set the table for a major banquet, using place settings
valued at <MONEY>$5,400</MONEY> each, and another three days to wash up. A system of traffic
lights keeps the footmen, pages and butlers who serve and clear from
colliding. And there are two men who do nothing but tend to the winding and
servicing of the 300 clocks in the house.;   There are rooms set aside for
everything from television and radio broadcasts to a bedroom for the queen's
pet corgi dogs. One of the most fascinating is the Gift Room, so-called
because this is where the queen goes to choose gifts she wants to give
someone.;   "It's her own personal shop inside the palace," <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> says.
"Obviously she hasn't time to go shopping. There is lots of porcelain and the
gifts range from the simplest things like a waste basket to little silver
holders you put glasses of tea in.";   <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> divides the interior of the
palace into three areas. "The staff areas are like government offices or the
back rooms of a large hotel, without any glitter or glitz. There are the state
apartments which have polish -- red carpet, mirrors, Regency furniture and
gilt. And the private quarters, which are more comfortable and cozy." The
latter, he says, "contain the kinds of things they like -- pink carnations in
the queen's room and pictures she's chosen herself. Fergie's room has teddy
bears and a helicopter helmet and <ORGANIZATION>Fisher-Price</ORGANIZATION> toys all over the place.";   In
describing the private areas, <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> makes no attempt to hide his disdain for
the fact that <ORGANIZATION>Fergie</ORGANIZATION> has almost no closet space. "It's ridiculous -- you have
the premier duchess in the land with her clothes on hangers outside in the
red-carpeted corridor, but she likes <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> because it's
comfortable, near her friends, away from prying eyes, and she can enjoy
herself away from the public.";   Authoritative as he is on <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Morton</PERSON>'s visits have been confined to a narrow area that does not include even
the <ORGANIZATION>Centre Room</ORGANIZATION>, let alone the private quarters he describes in such vivid
detail.;   "After every book I write, the courtiers have a little inquiry on
how on earth I got such accurate information," he boasts. "It's because of
contacts. I've cultivated people in key positions like any specialist would.";
  Would <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> pay for information?;   He pauses slightly and says, "I'd
haggle.";   A testimony to his sleuthing is the detailed floor plan of the
principal and bedroom floors of the palace. "It's not well-known at all, but I
wanted to print the layout of the private quarters so people could get an idea
of it," he says.;   <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> has yet to hear what the queen or <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> Yard
thinks about it, but he is pleased to reveal that one of his previous books,
about the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Yacht Britannia</ORGANIZATION>, was such a hit that "the queen gave lots of
copies away as Christmas presents.";   While they live in lavish surroundings,
the royal family is anything but lavish in their personal spending habits.
"There is no conspicuous consumption in the way of <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON> or that
<PERSON>Helmsley</PERSON> woman (<LOCATION>Leona</LOCATION>)," <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> says. "It's not the kind of family where you
could accuse them of living extravagantly. Everything is of the finest
quality, but they keep whatever they have for a long time, longer than you and
I.";   Fan that he admits he is, <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> still believes the economy kick is
taken too far at times. "It's ridiculous," he says. "You have <PERSON>Diana</PERSON> and <PERSON>Fergie</PERSON>
and the children using a local hotel's swimming pool because the queen hasn't
spent the money on a pool at <LOCATION>Balmoral</LOCATION>. It's the same at <LOCATION>Sandringham</LOCATION>. You have
the richest woman in the world not having a swimming pool!";   The pampered
life led by the queen and her family, with someone always there to run the
bath water, lay out their clothes and help them dress, has made them, in
<PERSON>Morton</PERSON>'s words, "a bit helpless. They're institutionalized. I don't mean that
in a nasty or negative way. Quite frankly, I'd feel a bit daunted if my day's
schedule said at 10:30 you'll hold an investiture, at noon you'll meet an
ambassador, at 2 you meet the prime minister, at 3 you do a walkabout and that
evening you host a dinner. If you've never done it before in your life, it's
the same way if you've never run a bath or pressed your clothes. They're bred
to a certain kind of function.";   <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> started covering the royal family
while working as a Fleet Street reporter.;   Three years ago <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> gave up
his newspaper job to start <ORGANIZATION>Palace Press</ORGANIZATION>, which specializes in covering the
royal family. He readily agrees most people view the topic he has chosen as
"very trivial, but once you get into it, it's a very interesting subject
because it touches on many areas of society from an anthropological,
sociological and historical viewpoint.";   While <PERSON>Morton</PERSON>'s latest book is on
the palace itself and the lifestyle within the walls, you can't resist asking
his opinion of the constant rumors about Prince <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> and <PERSON>Princess Diana</PERSON>'s
marriage.;   "There's always going to be rumors because of the 13-year age
gap," he says. "They have separate interests, a separate circle of friends and
separate timetables. I saw them in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, but they didn't seem to be happy.
Only people within a marriage can say how it is from day to day and month to
month."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MARY GOTTSCHALK, Mercury News Style Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911214  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,220  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, December 14, 1991
00349082,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-17508</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EDCACAE7FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940402
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 APR 94 / Arts: Royals on the dole - Alastair Macaulay reviews The
Queen and I, on stage
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALASTAIR MACAULAY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Name? '<PERSON>Elizabeth Windsor</PERSON>.' (A Social Services officer is interviewing the
next woman in line for an emergency supplementary payment.) 'Address?'
'<ORGANIZATION>Number Nine Hellebore Close</ORGANIZATION>' 'Former address?' '<ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION>, The
Mall.' 'What were you doing there?' 'I was being the Queen.' 'You were in an
institution? We can't give you any money.'
Sue <ORGANIZATION>Townsend</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1992</DATE> bestseller The Queen and I is a dark joke, a barbed
dream of republicanism in which <PERSON>Mrs Elizabeth Windsor</PERSON> and family learn to
live in the modern hell of a council estate in the <LOCATION>Midlands</LOCATION>. Now it has
become a play, which has just had its premiere, neatly, in the <LOCATION>Midlands</LOCATION> (at
the <LOCATION>Leicester Haymarket</LOCATION>), and will tour <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION> before reaching
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Royal Court</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>June 7</DATE>. The play is different in many details from
the novel. Updated to suit recent Royal developments, and including a few
songs (too few - phew - to qualify it as a musical), it is funny, touching,
shrewd.
Part of the fun of The Queen and I (on page or stage) is to do with Royal
gossip. How would <PERSON>Margaret</PERSON> cope? Philip? The answer in either case is
wickedly amusing. In the stage version the adulterous <PERSON>Charles</PERSON>, who has been
allocated a single person flat, soon shacks up with <PERSON>Leanne</PERSON>, the most
promiscuous girl on the estate, and becomes a good dad to her illegitimate
baby. Diana starts a flirtation with <PERSON>Fitzroy</PERSON>, a local black, and works out
with him ('Once your muscle tone goes, you may as well be dead'). The stage
Queen and I is also mildly feminist: which leads to its funniest scene - a
women's group in which <PERSON>Liz</PERSON>, <PERSON>Diana</PERSON> and neighbours practise assertiveness -
and its best song, What Makes the Husbands Leave Home?' And the fact that
<PERSON>Liz Windsor</PERSON> herself turns out to be matey, outspoken, decent, hard-working,
will please royalists as well as republicans.
But the stage version of The Queen and I is more overtly socialist than the
novel. Some of its stylised versions of gangland chants are trite - a
simplistic effort to understand the gang mentality that sounds in fact
condescending. Elsewhere, however, the realities of council estate life are
caught with realism, as well as humour. It proves both gratifying and
credible (not to mention ironic) that, on her first Christmas Day in her new
home, <PERSON>Mrs Windsor</PERSON> of Hell(ebore) Close, rallies and makes a televised speech
to the nation - no, not the Queen's Speech, de haut en bas, but the reverse:
a pensioner's appeal on behalf of those who, like herself, are making do on
inadequate benefits.
<PERSON>Max Stafford-Clark</PERSON> directs. The fun of all the performances lies less in
their precision of Royal mimicry (though Doon Mackichan makes very witty use
of <LOCATION>Diana</LOCATION>'s tricks with her eyes) than in the impish vigour with which they
bring them to life. Thus <PERSON>Mrs Philomena Toussaint</PERSON> (<PERSON>David Howey</PERSON>) and <PERSON>Mrs Vi
Toby</PERSON> (<PERSON>Carole Hayman</PERSON>) become as vivid to us as their ex-Royal neighbours. The
songs, by <PERSON>Mickey Gallagher</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ian Dury</PERSON>, are the least surefire element of
the show. A certain glee comes from hearing the Windsors and their
neighbours do a rap number, but less than you might hope.
The fine cast is led by <PERSON>Pam Ferris</PERSON> as the <PERSON>Queen</PERSON> - an outstanding
performance. She brings out some surprisingly serious dimensions. Talking
nostalgically to a vision of her old nanny, she suddenly exclaims softly,
'Crawfie - we lived in <ORGANIZATION>Paradise</ORGANIZATION>'. The line - a gentle echo of Lear's 'I have
ta'en too little care of this' - brings a real pang. At the same time, she
is as good as everyone else in the play's element of naughty caricature. The
way she uses her corgi on that Social Services officer (you have to see
this) is the play's funniest moment.
The Queen and I continues at the <LOCATION>Haymarket</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Leicester</LOCATION>, until <DATE>April 16</DATE>. In a
double bill with <PERSON>Jim Cartwright</PERSON>'s Road, it tours to <LOCATION>Bath</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cardiff</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hull</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Woking</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Blackpool</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Norwich</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Court Theatre</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7922 Theatrical Producers and Services.
    P7929 Entertainers and Entertainment Groups.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XVI
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-10360</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DEIATAFLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930508
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 MAY 93 / Hawks &amp; Handsaws: Defence of the realm
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MICHAEL THOMPSON-NOEL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
TENNIS lessons. Chess lessons. My life at present is a whirlwind of
instruction. Yesterday it was a chess lesson, one of a series that I and two
friends are having to prepare ourselves for the <PERSON>Nigel Short-Gary Kasparov</PERSON>
world chess tussle in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in <DATE>September</DATE>. The two friends are: <PERSON>John Major</PERSON>,
prime minister of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>House of
Windsor</ORGANIZATION>. Our instructor is <PERSON>Nigel Short</PERSON> himself. We meet in utmost secrecy.
Unusually, the Queen was accompanied by the Seven Dwarfs, her seven Welsh
corgis, who are notorious, at <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION>, for savaging the flunkies.
But the Queen soon settled them. Before the lesson started she produced
seven silver bowls into which she spooned caviar. The dwarfs gobbled it
greedily and collapsed in a malevolent heap.
'That's put paid to them,' she said. '<PERSON>Nigel</PERSON> - let us start. One must get
away on time. There are more ructions brewing - more media allegations.
Where will it all end? Not that one isn't inured. No es para tanto.'
'Right-ho,' said <PERSON>Nigel</PERSON>, whose own mental and physical preparation for his
match against <PERSON>Kasparov</PERSON> the barbarian is proceeding smoothly. 'Today I
thought we'd study sacrificial play in the middle-game, especially
sacrificial play aimed at destroying our opponent's defensive structure.
Remember my golden rule: before launching any sort of attack, sacrificial or
otherwise, always count the number of pieces you will be attacking with and
try to ensure it exceeds the number of pieces your opponent will be
defending with.'
<PERSON>Nigel</PERSON> said he would show us a game he played against Agdestein in <DATE>1987</DATE>,
involving the Greek bishop sacrifice. With grandmasterly finesse he set up
the pieces and moved them at great speed, so that all we could see was a
blur of pawns and bishops and cleverly skulking knights.
'Right,' said <PERSON>Nigel</PERSON>. 'This brings us to move 14. From here, play went: 14,
Bxh7+, Kxh7; 15, Ng5+, Kg8; 16, Qd3, Rfe8. So how did play continue?'
John Major wriggled and frowned. 'I must say, <PERSON>Nigel</PERSON>,' he said, 'that
sacrificial play leaves me with feelings of considerable unease. It does not
seem logical to throw away a perfectly stalwart piece when you are doing
jolly well anyway and embark upon a course of action that is little short of
reckless. It reminds me of politics. I am being urged at the present time to
sacrifice <PERSON>Norman Lamont</PERSON>, my chancellor of the exchequer. But as <PERSON>Michael</PERSON> has
pointed out, alone among his colleagues, <PERSON>Norman</PERSON> is a hero, a man of
considerable stature. Why should I cast him out?'
The Queen trilled with merriment. 'In one's own line of business,' she said,
'one gets accustomed to stratagems, especially mid-game sacrifices. You work
to five-year terms. A monarch thinks in centuries. Qui non proficit deficit.
Anyway, the answer to <PERSON>Nigel</PERSON>'s little teaser is strikingly obvious. What
follows must be: 17, Qh7+, Kf8; 18, f5] . . . '
'Absolutely brill,' said <PERSON>Nigel</PERSON>. 'Exactly how it happened. Then I put the
boot in. It was completely open house.'
'<PERSON>Nigel</PERSON>]' exclaimed the Queen. 'One wishes you hadn't said that. Completely
open house. That is one's current strategem, one's sop to the
anti-monarchists, but one would rather you didn't remind one. Can you
imagine the mess and noise when <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> is thrown open to the
populace this <DATE>summer</DATE>? One is dreading it entirely. And what will they be
gawking at? Just a load of art works, mainly dusty pictures. One is sending
the dwarfs to <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>. They are liable to go berserk.'
I had been quiet until now, but I could not resist the opening. I said: 'I
agree with the character in <PERSON>Barry Unsworth</PERSON>'s novel, <PERSON>Stone Virgin</PERSON>, who says,
in all seriousness, that great works of art are more important than people -
that life can spawn more life, but that you can't spawn Gothic Madonnas.
'Look at the floods in <LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION> in <DATE>1966</DATE>, which triggered off countless
restoration projects and set the money flowing. 'If it hadn't been <LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION>,'
says this character, 'if there had only been people to worry about, what
would anyone have done? I'll tell you. They would have sent a few food
parcels and forgotten all about it'.'
The Queen smiled. She said: '<PERSON>Michael</PERSON> does go on.' She revived the dwarfs
with smelling salts and telephoned for her car and detective. The rest of us
did the same. So ended our second lesson.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9111 Executive Offices.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XXII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-532</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DI1CRADDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930928
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  28 SEP 93 / Arts: Smashing Pumpkins - Pop
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PETER BERLIN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Far below the <ORGANIZATION>Brixton Academy</ORGANIZATION>'s cavernous black ceiling, beneath the shadowy
Italianate mock-buildings that decorate its upper walls, 1,000, perhaps
2,000 young people crush together, often crash together, illuminated
occasionally by harsh white lights from the stage. Bodies rise, feet first,
from this churning sea and are passed from hand to hand before sinking
again. From time to time the mass raise their arms and point as one towards
the front of the stage on which stand three skinny individuals lit in lurid
greens, reds, blues holding guitars.
The noise is overpowering, a screaming, thudding, relentless assault not
just on the ears but on the body. This is the Smashing Pumpkins
emphatically affirming its status as one of the hottest alternative rock
bands. It is a highly enjoyable experience. (Although it helps to have been
put in the mood by security guards whose purpose in life is to stop
passholders seeing the concert.)
What lifts the band above most of its contemporaries is its ability to use
the limited and increasingly hackneyed vocabulary of loud thrash guitar rock
to express a distinctive musical personality.
On Siamese Dream, the latest album, the Pumpkins vary the pace with
moderately complex arrangements, acoustic guitar and even a dash of cello.
Live, such signposts of subletly are abandoned for simple churn and kerrang.
The effect is visceral. The fact that the speakers are so loud that every
bass note feels like a punch in the stomach has something to do with it, but
although other bands play as loud, few are as emotionally engaging.
The assault is not unrelenting. The lull in the storm is one of leader <PERSON>Billy
Corgan</PERSON>'s favourite tricks. The wall of guitar noise from <PERSON>Corgan</PERSON> and <PERSON>James
Iha</PERSON> abates, to expose the powerful skeleton of the Pumpkins' music: the
edgy, sinuous, crunching rhythm of D'Arcy, the bass player, and drummer
<PERSON>Jimmy Chamberlin</PERSON>. The effect can be disconcerting. When 'Today' begins in
relative calm, the audience chants the lyrics with <PERSON>Corgan</PERSON>, a sort of
singalong-a-max-volume, before it builds to a roar that drowns even singing
along in your head.
Each song is distinctly sculpted from the noise and the brief abatement of
noise. Each possesses its own crushing logic. But the ceaseless ebb and flow
in the tidal wave of noise prevents the set as a whole building momentum.
The effect is too controlled. It is a relief when the Pumpkins finish the
set by smashing through '<ORGANIZATION>Cherub Rock</ORGANIZATION>' in one unbroken surge.
The encore is also reassuring. It is a shambles. Corgan emerges in a clown
suit and after 'Spaceboy' - so laid back it even contains some bottleneck
guitar from <PERSON>Iha</PERSON> - the control evaporates halfway through the next song which
starts with a surge of adrenalin and dribbles to an end with <PERSON>Corgan</PERSON>
hectoring the audience in enjoyable ego-crazed rock-star style. After a
confusing final blast of parody power chords they are gone. The audience
seems unsure whether to laugh or cheer and stands as if stunned until
someone turns the house lights on.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7929 Entertainers and Entertainment Groups.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121989-0070 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 150742 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 19, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 2; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
72 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BRIEFLY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Acquire Corgi Toys</ORGANIZATION>: The Hawthorne company said it will acquire <ORGANIZATION>Corgi 
Toys Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a British concern that produces miniature cars and models, for an 
undisclosed price. The announcement comes two weeks after <ORGANIZATION>Mattel</ORGANIZATION>, which will 
sell more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> worth of toys this year, reported strong revenue for 
the <LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION> season with a continuation of <DATE>1989</DATE>'s <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> sales growth. Corgi has 
annual revenue of about <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief; Corporate Earnings 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
UNITED STATES -- FOREIGN INVESTMENTS -- ENGLAND; MATTEL INC; TOYS; CORGI TOYS 
LTD 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900612-0066
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900612-0066.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   An Unlikely Battle
   Pits Englishmen
   Against Mad Dogs
   ----
   Attacks by Vicious Canines
   Lead the Wardens to Don
   Riot Gear, Pack Pistols
   ----
   By Tony Horwitz
</HL>
<DATE>
06/12/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<LP>
   LONDON -- Chief Inspector Jan Eachus stares past thick
bars at the suspect he dragged in the previous night, after a
fierce street fight. The suspect, known only as Bella, glares
back through smoldering black eyes. Bella doesn't have a rap
sheet, but Mr. Eachus knows this isn't her first offense.
"Just look at those scars," he says, pointing at raw marks
across Bella's powerful shoulders. "No question this one's
been in a scrap before."
   Mr. Eachus will tell this to the judge as evidence that
Bella, an American pit bull terrier, shouldn't have been
allowed to roam uncontrolled. Bella's handler could be fined
more than $3,000 or imprisoned for up to six months. Bella,
who ripped open a dachshund's throat and bit its owner's
hand, will pay the ultimate price. "See ya in doggy heaven,"
says Mr. Eachus, watching Bella gnaw at the bars of her cage.
Asked if there's anything a pit bull such as Bella won't
bite, Mr. Eachus responds, "A 747 jetliner -- flight."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   England is renowned as a nation of dog lovers, a land
where corgis trail <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON> and where shoppers park
their poodles in a carpeted kennel at Harrods department
store. Queen Victoria even shared her deathbed with a
Pomeranian. But <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s long affair with dogs has soured.
Aggressive breeds such as pit bulls and Rottweilers are
suddenly in vogue, and as their numbers have risen, so have
reports of dog attacks. The result is public panic,
Parliamentary debate and press headlines suggestive of "The
Hound of the Baskervilles":
   "Devil Dog Scars Tot"
   "Girl, 8, Scalped in Dog Horror."
   England isn't the first country to do battle with
dangerous dogs, but it may be unique in the lethal force it
is deploying. Some animal wardens are arming themselves with
riot shields, chain mail, and ultrasonic stun guns. "Heroes
get bit," explains <PERSON>Mr. Eachus</PERSON>, an inspector with the <ORGANIZATION>Royal
which is often called to handle vicious dogs. In a country
where gun control is so strict that most police go unarmed,
<PERSON>Mr. Eachus</PERSON> is licensed to pack a .32 automatic pistol in his
van.
   "We need that kind of weaponry to control humans, not
dogs," <PERSON>Micky Niego</PERSON>, an official with the <ORGANIZATION>American Society</ORGANIZATION> for
the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, says of the varied
English arsenal. Some <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> wardens carry tranquilizing darts
and <ORGANIZATION>Mace</ORGANIZATION>, but most prefer nets and rods with loops.
   The English say their situation demands special tactics.
Unlike the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, where rabies has led to tight animal
control, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> is free of the disease and has no dog
licensing, no leash law and, in many areas, no dog wardens.
England's pet-obsessed public also can be feral in defending
animal rights. "The English worry more about the welfare of
poor little pooch than they do about the safety of <PERSON>Joe
Public</PERSON>," says <PERSON>Mr. Eachus</PERSON>, an American who has been living in
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> since <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   The English also resist the notion that some breeds may be
tough to tame. "People think a little loving care will turn
pit bulls into nice pets," says <PERSON>Roger Mugford</PERSON>, an animal
psychologist in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. "They're wrong." <PERSON>Mr. Mugford</PERSON> echoes
the view of many English experts in describing the dogs as
fearless, almost immune to pain, "and able to turn from
playful jokers into psychopathic killers without a moment's
warning."
   Some dog warriors are taking no chances. Standing beside
her van in the <LOCATION>north England</LOCATION> city of <LOCATION>Bradford</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pat Harwood</PERSON>
dons the latest in canine battle dress. Long blond curls
vanish beneath a visored helmet designed for riot control by
the <ORGANIZATION>North Atlantic Treaty Organization</ORGANIZATION>. Hands slip into
elbow-length gloves. She cradles a reinforced plastic
"Armadillo Tactical Riot Shield," used by police to repel
missiles. Her tall frame is enveloped by a zip-up jump suit,
lined with chain mesh and heavily padded.
   "I feel like I'm inside a Brillo Pad," says the warden,
her voice muffled by the helmet's visor. <PERSON>Ms. Harwood</PERSON> uses the
suit only for emergencies, but she never patrols without her
"Dazer," a pocket-sized weapon designed to startle dogs with
a high-frequency squeal. "It's important to intimidate," says
her boss, senior warden <PERSON>Terry Singh</PERSON>.
   Some say such gladiators are barking up the wrong tree.
"If you approach a pit bull looking like a creature from
Mars, he's more likely to go berserk and bite you," says
<PERSON>Kevin McNicholas</PERSON>, a veteran <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> dog warden.
   Answering a call on his van's radio phone, <PERSON>Mr. McNicholas</PERSON>
races to a suburban home whose residents are alarmed by a
gnashing sound from an adjoining yard. He finds a huge German
shepherd ripping apart the fence between the two yards with
its fangs. When the dog bounds toward him, <PERSON>Mr. McNicholas</PERSON>
kneels, clicks his tongue and slips a rope around the dog's
neck. "It doesn't need to be <LOCATION>Waterloo</LOCATION> every time you take a
dog in," he says, calmly guiding the animal into his van.
   On another call, an anxious woman points into her
neighbor's yard, where two dummies hang from trees, their
pants legs in shreds. The woman says her neighbors often
stand in the yard shouting "Kill]" as two pit bulls tear the
effigies apart. <PERSON>Mr. McNicholas</PERSON>'s advice: If the dogs come
close, stand perfectly still, avoid eye contact, and, if
possible, whimper like a puppy. "Dog biscuits also help," he
says. The most lethal weapon he has ever employed is a fire
extinguisher. In eight years of service, he hasn't been
bitten.
   Many other officials haven't been so lucky. There were
7,717 dog attacks on mailmen last year; dozens of police were
injured. <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> police also are receiving twice as many calls
about dangerous dogs as they did just six months ago. While
fatal attacks remain rare (one or two a year compared to an
average of 15 in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>), there now are an estimated
500,000 strays on English streets and crowded dog pounds with
cages marked "Mad] Take Care]"
   Despite strong lobbying by police, postmen, the <ORGANIZATION>RSPCA</ORGANIZATION> and
other groups, Parliament narrowly rejected a dog registration
law in <DATE>May</DATE>. But the government now is considering banning
some breeds, or requiring that such dogs be muzzled in
public. "It sounds like hysteria until a Rottweiler chews
your kid to pieces," says <PERSON>Bill Wadman-Taylor</PERSON>, a veterinarian
and head of the Battersea Dogs Home in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bill Edmond</PERSON>, head of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Kennel Club</ORGANIZATION>, says the <ORGANIZATION>RSPCA</ORGANIZATION>
and other groups are overreacting. "The problem is people,
not dogs," he says. "Irresponsible owners can make any dog
vicious." His organization opposes dog licensing and other
restrictions "because the people who are neglecting their
dogs, or training them to attack, are the very same people
who won't comply with the licensing law."
   The <ORGANIZATION>RSPCA</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Mr. Eachus</PERSON> doesn't hesitate to get tough with
both mad dogs and Englishmen. The chain-smoking inspector has
shot two dogs to death and donned riot gear to take in many
others. In his van, he carries a forensic kit containing a
magnifying glass, camera and tweezers to collect evidence
such as dried blood and dogs' hair for use in prosecuting
owners.
   "There's no room for amateurism here," says the veteran
enforcer. He can quote chapter and verse from English dog
law, such as the <DATE>1847</DATE> statute citing owners for "suffering to
be at large a ferocious unmuzzled dog," and more recent laws
regarding the fouling of sidewalks with what some
euphemistically call "dog-logs."
   <PERSON>Mr. Eachus</PERSON> predicts that the craze for pit bulls and other
macho dogs will peak in a few years, as it has in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> In
the meantime, though, "we need to get dangerous dogs off the
street and their owners behind bars," he says.
   Officials fear, however, that another creature may soon
terrorize <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>RSPCA</ORGANIZATION> recently received a panicked
phone call reporting that a wild boar was running amok in a
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> street. It turned out to be a Vietnamese pot-bellied
pig, a faddish pet in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> that is just now reaching
English shores.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900423-0005
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900423-0005.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   OK, What Rhymes
   With Vogue and Eats
   Raw Chicken Necks?
   ---
   Answer: Dogue de Bordeaux,
   A Breed New to Many
   And a True Power Dog
   ----
   By Pamela Sebastian
</HL>
<DATE>
04/23/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Douglas Quinn was so taken with the phlegmatic
dog star of the movie "Turner &amp; Hooch" that he took out a
classified ad seeking a "Hooch" pup. "I liked the dog, and I
want it. That's all," says Mr. Quinn, a man of few words and
the father of 3 1/2-year-old twin boys in Barry, Ontario. So
far, no response to the ad.
   Just wait till Mr. Quinn finds out that the gargoyle-faced
dogue de Bordeaux can cost as much as $1,800, weighs 125
pounds and craves 12 pounds of raw chicken necks each day,
plus kibble. "It isn't easy to get chicken necks," concedes
Peter Curley, the breeder who supplied four dogs for the
movie, which also stars Tom Hanks.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mr. Curley</PERSON> adds that though the dogue may have achieved a
certain vogue thanks to <LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION>, smart (as in fashionable)
doesn't necessarily mean smart (as in intelligent). "The only
thing you can train the <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION> to do is eat and sleep,"
says <PERSON>Mr. Curley</PERSON>, who now is branching out to an even rarer
breed: the presa de Canario, known as "the gripping dog" of
the <LOCATION>Canary Islands</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Curley</PERSON> expects that strong-jawed
beast to be popular at dog shows and to command maybe <MONEY>$2,500</MONEY>.
   The <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION> and the presa are power dogs -- not mere pets
but status symbols. "I'm sure it happens that there are
people who buy dogs like they buy cars," says <PERSON>Peter L.
Borchelt</PERSON>, an animal psychologist in <LOCATION>Forest Hills</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   <PERSON>Carol Lea Benjamin</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> author whose book
"Second-Hand Dog" is a paean to the mongrel, notes that
"breeds are often chosen because somebody famous has one" --
the president of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, say, or an admired movie star.
Appreciating that fact, the <ORGANIZATION>International Kennel Club</ORGANIZATION>, which
is really just a pet store in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, sometimes manages to
plant items in the gossip columns disclosing that an actor --
<PERSON>Bruce Willis</PERSON>, for instance -- is taking delivery of some
Akita pups or that singer <PERSON>Roberta Flack</PERSON> has a fox-faced shiba
inu. Gilt by association, in other words. It is supposed to
move dogs, and it undoubtedly does.
   People magazine recently predicted that the bichon frise,
a bit of fluff whose name means curly- haired lap-dog, will
be one of the top five dogs of the <DATE>1990s</DATE>, "style-wise." And
in no time at all, <PERSON>Tina Geores</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> breeder, was
advertising it as "the most stylish dog of the '90s."
   <PERSON>Ms. Geores</PERSON> claims the bichon is getting more and more
popular "with very trendy people, people in show business,"
people like <PERSON>Carly Simon</PERSON>, the singer and songwriter. "They are
such a pleasant little dog," <PERSON>Ms. Geores</PERSON> says. "They're easy
to travel with. They're easy to live with." They cost between
<MONEY>$650</MONEY> and <MONEY>$1,200</MONEY>.
   The authoritative <ORGANIZATION>American Kennel Club</ORGANIZATION>, which is not a pet
store in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, is a little slower on the uptake than
readers of People. It recognizes only 130 breeds, and the
<LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION> and shiba inu aren't two of them. The <ORGANIZATION>AKC</ORGANIZATION> each year
lists the top 10 breeds (in terms of registrations), and most
are not exotic power dogs. Cockers and Labs, poodles, golden
retrievers and German shepherds head the list, in that order,
although two currently fashionable breeds, Rottweiler and
chow chow (chow for short), do make the latest top 10.
   "The <PERSON>Rotty</PERSON> is the guard dog of the moment," says <PERSON>John
Mandeville</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>AKC</ORGANIZATION> judging official. He says the bear-faced
chow is probably the "pre-eminent fad dog." <PERSON>Mr. Mandeville</PERSON>
notes that both dogs tend to be hard to handle, particularly
if they aren't well trained and if the owner isn't assertive.
But, he says, many breed-conscious masters unfortunately
can't see past the pup. "If there's anything cuter than an
eight- or 10-week-old chow puppy, I'm not sure what it is,"
he says. But then one day, the dog owner wakes up to find a
giant, shedding beast (with a blue tongue in the case of the
chow) who wants to be boss. "Cute" can easily enough turn
into "trouble."
   That hasn't kept <ORGANIZATION>AKC</ORGANIZATION> registrations from reaching an
all-time high, as more Americans seek to spend their mad
money on the perfect dog. The dogue de <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION> may not be
it, for a variety of reasons, one of which is that it
originally was bred as a fighting dog. It is said to be good
with children. But it might just have the neighbor's shih tzu
for lunch.
   The border collie (like <PERSON>Mike</PERSON> the Dog in the film "Down and
Out in <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION>") is a current favorite. So are
bulldogs. <PERSON>Jack Russell</PERSON> terriers are popular with the horsy
set. The short-legged Welsh corgi is big (<ORGANIZATION>Queen Elizabeth II</ORGANIZATION>
has at least one). And so, of course, is the English bull
terrier (thanks to <ORGANIZATION>Anheuser-Busch</ORGANIZATION>, Bud Light and <ORGANIZATION>Spuds
MacKenzie</ORGANIZATION>).
   <PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON> and the president have been good for English
springer spaniels. Theirs -- <PERSON>Millie</PERSON> and her pups -- have been
good for the Bushes politically. (Yes, <PERSON>Messrs. Reagan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> had famous dogs, too.) <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> gave
this advice to a Republican running for <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>:
"One single word. Puppies. Worth 10 points."
   Like politicians, dog breeds have their moment. But the
popular ones get overbred, by puppy mills and others trying
to take advantage of demand. "With anything trendy, there's a
rush to breed for profit," says <PERSON>Mr. Borchelt</PERSON>, the animal
psychologist. "That's no good." Puppy mills turn out dogs
with physical and psychological problems, dogs that can't
handle their aggressive impulses, dogs that bite.
   And ultimately a breed will pass out of fashion, as the
shar-pei seems to be doing now. It is that wrinkly creature
which, as a pup, looks more like a pile of sweat shirts than
a dog.
   On a tour of the Animal Medical Center in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr.
Borchelt</PERSON> is interrupted twice by veterinarians seeking his
advice about their patients. An elderly woman has a "nervous
chow," says one. The other confides: "I've got a problem with
an aggressive shar-pei."
   The Chinese shar-pei, or "sand-skin," was nearly extinct
in the <DATE>1950s</DATE>. But, <DATE>two decades later</DATE>, it caught on with the
rare-dog breeders and, in <DATE>1983</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Neiman Marcus Christmas</ORGANIZATION>
catalog featured a pair of shar-pei pups -- at <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> each.
The rage began. Today there are more than 50,000 shar-peis.
The price has come down to as little as <MONEY>$100</MONEY>, a sign that the
fad is about played out. And that's only the half of it.
   "The shar-pei is a veterinarian's dream," says <PERSON>Michael
Marder</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> vet. "I'm seeing a lot of health and
behavioral problems, not life-threatening but chronic," he
says. Skin trouble is especially common.
   <PERSON>Ethel Petry</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>Central Point</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, is familiar from an
owner's standpoint with the shar-pei's potential for
ailments. She chose her shar-pei puppy largely because his
front paws were "broken down," and she was afraid the
flat-footed dog would be destroyed.
   Timothy, now three years old, cost her a hundred bucks.
But he was no bargain. His doctor bills have been at least
five times that. He contracted a bad case of mange, and he
tends to be sickly. "He can be playing with you one minute,"
<PERSON>Ms. Petry</PERSON> says, "and come down with a temperature of 104
degees the next."
   Efforts to fix the dog's feet failed, and the little pads
on his paws never toughened up. So, "<PERSON>Timothy</PERSON> is a grass-dog.
I never walk him on the street," says his owner. He travels
by car from his backyard to the park for outings. And at
least once, <PERSON>Ms. Petry</PERSON> has had to carry <PERSON>Timothy</PERSON> in her arms to
keep him off the pavement. Still, she says, "We get along."
   Fortunately, passe power dogs seldom seem to end up at the
pound, abandoned by owners who have traded up to a newer
model. <PERSON>Marjorie Stein</PERSON>, manager of adoption services for the
<ORGANIZATION>North Shore Animal League</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Port Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, says she
sees few of the exotic breeds: "A chichi dog has a much
better chance of getting a home by word of mouth. Generally,
somebody wants it."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-5532</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CIBBTAEBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920829
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  29 AUG 92 / Please leave me alone, Fergie: Dominic Lawson wishes the
royals would stop interfering with him
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DOMINIC LAWSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
'THIS 'royal tapes' business is the last straw,' said my taxi driver, and I
had to agree. The ever-encroaching invasion of privacy must cease. It is
time that the royal family stopped intruding on our private lives. We may be
only subjects but even under a monarchy we have some rights, above all the
right to be left alone to lead our private lives in peace and quiet, away
from the glare of royal publicity.
The monarch herself, of course, we cannot avoid. Every time we attach a
stamp to an envelope we are obliged to lick the back of the Queen's head, as
if we were a corgi seeking an approving royal pat. Falling asleep at the end
of the day's television on BBC1, one is obliged to wake up and stand to
attention as the national anthem is played at full blast by the <ORGANIZATION>BBC Symphony
Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>, whose members, I gather, call the tune 'royalties'.
Then there are the intrusive royal garden parties. We live near <LOCATION>Buckingham
Palace</LOCATION>, so perhaps I am unduly sensitive. But none of our other neighbours,
not even the inhabitants of <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION>'s numerous bail hostels, cause as much
local disturbance and disruption.
Of course one can leave <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> to avoid the din around the Palace. We favour
the south of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, around <ORGANIZATION>St Tropez</ORGANIZATION>. But this year the <ORGANIZATION>Duchess of York</ORGANIZATION> and
her financial adviser got there first, and the place now resembles
Bedlam-by-the-sea.
I cannot understand why, when members of the royal family can stay in
countless castles, all with walls high enough to hide behind and thick
enough to soundproof the most amorous affairs, some of their number should
still choose to cavort in a way which we cannot help but see, in gruesome
colour, all over our servants' newspapers.
Worse still was the return of the errant duchess. Again, perhaps I have been
unlucky, but did she and her exuberant friends have to make such a din at
Foxtrot Oscar while we were trying to enjoy a quiet dinner next door at
Tante Claire?
I suppose the rot started in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>, when the Queen - doubtless following
bad advice, rather than acting on her own sound instincts - agreed to make
the royal household into media stars with the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> film The Family. Suddenly
these remote and austere figures intruded for the first time into our homes,
like uninvited house guests.
In recent years this publicity-seeking has developed in a distinctly
down-market direction. We had the <ORGANIZATION>Duchess of York</ORGANIZATION>'s characteristically
bizarre television promotion, It's a Royal Knock-Out, not to mention the
interminably over-promoted Budgie the Helicopter books.
While the Prince of <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION>'s publications have been less intrusive, indeed
tastefully obscure, it came as a shock to turn on one's television to see
the heir to the throne cavorting about in the highlands and islands with the
popular TV personality <PERSON>Selina Scott</PERSON>. I would not question the prince's
choice of companion - I, too, consider <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> to be a woman of rare beauty
and intelligence - but could not the future king have left us in peace,
rather than forced us to watch the two of them at peak-time and grind our
teeth in envy at his good fortune? To encourage such resentment is to foment
revolution and the overthrow of the monarchy.
But, as the taxi driver said, the saga of the royal tapes is the final
straw. I have no idea whether the tape purporting to be of the Princess of
<LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION> talking to a male admirer is in fact a recording of the princess's
voice or not, and the official line from the palace is that they have no
idea either.
But let us suppose that the tape is genuine, as The Sun claims. Surely the
royal family with its enormous and untaxed wealth, can afford a private
telephone exchange. Surely they realise how easy it is to get a crossed line
on <ORGANIZATION>British Telecom</ORGANIZATION>'s outmoded system. How many innocent members of the
general public must over the years have suffered the irritation of suddenly
hearing snatches of conversation between members of the royal family who
ought to know better.
No wonder a retired bank manager, exasperated at having his calls
interrupted, finally lost his temper, recorded his latest crossed royal
line, and handed it to The Sun.
Perhaps this incident will finally teach the royal family their lesson. If
they will only go back to their castles, fill their moats, pull up their
drawbridges and leave us alone, then we will once again love, cherish and
admire them.
God Save The Queen.
<PERSON>Dominic Lawson</PERSON> is editor of The Spectator.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XVIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900804-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-04-90 1523EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People     08-04 0852</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0885</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY44, LON6</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Happy Birthday Grandmother England,'' read a
banner carried by one of thousands of admirers outside the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
home of the <PERSON>Queen Mother</PERSON>, who celebrated her <DATE>90th birthday Saturday</DATE>.
   Crowds of fans, some of whom had camped out overnight to get a
better viewing position, were rewarded when she stepped onto the
geranium-framed balcony about 11 a.m. to wave and smile. The Band
of the Coldstream Guards played ``Happy Birthday'' as she appeared.
   The mother of Queen Elizabeth II then emerged to greet the crowd
around <ORGANIZATION>Clarence House</ORGANIZATION>, the mansion that has been her <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> home
since she was widowed 38 years ago.
   Dozens of children gathered around her, offering balloons and
bouquets of daisies, zinnias, lilies and baby's breath. She gently
patted the shoulder of each.
   Looking cool and relaxed despite the hot weather, she spent
nearly a half-hour shaking hands and saying ``Thank you'' to the
crowd lined up along police barricades on the mansion's grounds.
   ``It's been marvelous. Everybody has been so kind,'' she said.
   She then walked beyond the house gates, despite the objections
of nervous security guards, to visit with the crowd.
   Nearly anything associated with her pleased the crowd, which
even cheered when her corgi dog appeared at the door to the house.
   ``For me, she is everything that belongs to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. She's the
figurehead ... the grandmother to us all. She's absolutely
wonderful,'' said <PERSON>Emily Coughlin</PERSON>, who had waited outside since
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   After the appearance, the Queen Mother was joined for lunch by
her daughters, <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON> and <PERSON>Princess Margaret</PERSON>, and her
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Happy Birthday Grandmother England,'' read a
banner carried by one of thousands of admirers outside the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
home of the <PERSON>Queen Mother</PERSON>, who celebrated her <DATE>90th birthday Saturday</DATE>.
   Crowds of fans, some of whom had camped out overnight to get a
better viewing position, were rewarded when she stepped onto the
geranium-framed balcony about 11 a.m. to wave and smile. The Band
of the Coldstream Guards played ``Happy Birthday'' as she appeared.
   The mother of Queen Elizabeth II then emerged to greet the crowd
around <ORGANIZATION>Clarence House</ORGANIZATION>, the mansion that has been her <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> home
since she was widowed 38 years ago.
   Dozens of children gathered around her, offering balloons and
bouquets of daisies, zinnias, lilies and baby's breath. She gently
patted the shoulder of each.
   Looking cool and relaxed despite the hot weather, she spent
nearly a half-hour shaking hands and saying ``Thank you'' to the
crowd lined up along police barricades on the mansion's grounds.
   ``It's been marvelous. Everybody has been so kind,'' she said.
   She then walked beyond the house gates, despite the objections
of nervous security guards, to visit with the crowd.
   Nearly anything associated with her pleased the crowd, which
even cheered when her corgi dog appeared at the door to the house.
   ``For me, she is everything that belongs to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. She's the
figurehead ... the grandmother to us all. She's absolutely
wonderful,'' said <PERSON>Emily Coughlin</PERSON>, who had waited outside since
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   After the appearance, the Queen Mother was joined for lunch by
her daughters, <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON> and <PERSON>Princess Margaret</PERSON>, and her
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Happy Birthday Grandmother England,'' read a
banner carried by one of thousands of admirers outside the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
home of the <PERSON>Queen Mother</PERSON>, who celebrated her <DATE>90th birthday Saturday</DATE>.
   Crowds of fans, some of whom had camped out overnight to get a
better viewing position, were rewarded when she stepped onto the
geranium-framed balcony about 11 a.m. to wave and smile. The Band
of the Coldstream Guards played ``Happy Birthday'' as she appeared.
   The mother of Queen Elizabeth II then emerged to greet the crowd
around <ORGANIZATION>Clarence House</ORGANIZATION>, the mansion that has been her <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> home
since she was widowed 38 years ago.
   Dozens of children gathered around her, offering balloons and
bouquets of daisies, zinnias, lilies and baby's breath. She gently
patted the shoulder of each.
   Looking cool and relaxed despite the hot weather, she spent
nearly a half-hour shaking hands and saying ``Thank you'' to the
crowd lined up along police barricades on the mansion's grounds.
   ``It's been marvelous. Everybody has been so kind,'' she said.
   She then walked beyond the house gates, despite the objections
of nervous security guards, to visit with the crowd.
   Nearly anything associated with her pleased the crowd, which
even cheered when her corgi dog appeared at the door to the house.
   ``For me, she is everything that belongs to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. She's the
figurehead ... the grandmother to us all. She's absolutely
wonderful,'' said <PERSON>Emily Coughlin</PERSON>, who had waited outside since
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   After the appearance, the Queen Mother was joined for lunch by
her daughters, <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON> and <PERSON>Princess Margaret</PERSON>, and her
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Longer version moving on some sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Happy Birthday Grandmother England,'' read a
banner carried by one of thousands of admirers outside the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
home of the <PERSON>Queen Mother</PERSON>, who celebrated her <DATE>90th birthday Saturday</DATE>.
   Crowds of fans, some of whom had camped out overnight to get a
better viewing position, were rewarded when she stepped onto the
geranium-framed balcony about 11 a.m. to wave and smile. The Band
of the Coldstream Guards played ``Happy Birthday'' as she appeared.
   The mother of Queen Elizabeth II then emerged to greet the crowd
around <ORGANIZATION>Clarence House</ORGANIZATION>, the mansion that has been her <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> home
since she was widowed 38 years ago.
   Dozens of children gathered around her, offering balloons and
bouquets of daisies, zinnias, lilies and baby's breath. She gently
patted the shoulder of each.
   Looking cool and relaxed despite the hot weather, she spent
nearly a half-hour shaking hands and saying ``Thank you'' to the
crowd lined up along police barricades on the mansion's grounds.
   ``It's been marvelous. Everybody has been so kind,'' she said.
   She then walked beyond the house gates, despite the objections
of nervous security guards, to visit with the crowd.
   Nearly anything associated with her pleased the crowd, which
even cheered when her corgi dog appeared at the door to the house.
   ``For me, she is everything that belongs to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. She's the
figurehead ... the grandmother to us all. She's absolutely
wonderful,'' said <PERSON>Emily Coughlin</PERSON>, who had waited outside since
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   After the appearance, the Queen Mother was joined for lunch by
her daughters, <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON> and <PERSON>Princess Margaret</PERSON>, and her
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880304-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-88 1038EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-WindsorCastle     03-04 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Windsor Castle,0353</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tower Of Windsor Castle Damaged By Shifting Foundations</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WINDSOR, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 800-year-old Round Tower at <ORGANIZATION>Windsor
Castle</ORGANIZATION>, one of Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>'s homes, has been damaged by
shifting foundations, the <ORGANIZATION>Department of the Environment</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   The castle overlooking the <LOCATION>River Thames</LOCATION> is reportedly the
queen's favorite home and is one of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s top tourist
attractions. The monarch's royal standard is flown from the tower
when she is in residence.
   ``There has been a slight movement to the Round Tower at <ORGANIZATION>Windsor
Castle</ORGANIZATION>. We are looking into it,'' the government department said in
a brief statement.
   The statement added that the cause was not known and gave no
details about the extent of the damage.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Daily Telegraph</ORGANIZATION>, which first broke the story, described the
damage to the five-story tower as serious following a shift in its
ancient foundations.
   The <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> newspaper said the tower moved two weeks ago,
bringing down plaster, causing cracks to appear in the stonework
and jamming a door and two windows.
   It said the queen had inspected the tower. <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION>
said in a statement: ``The queen is obviously concerned and is
   The queen and her husband, <PERSON>Prince Philip</PERSON>, live for much of the
year at <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> but they and their family spend
each Christmas at <ORGANIZATION>Windsor Castle</ORGANIZATION>. Windsor is 21 miles west of
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   The Round Tower is the most imposing feature of the castle. The
foundations of the tower and the rest of its lower part were built
by <ORGANIZATION>King Henry II</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1172</DATE>. The upper part was added 6{ centuries
later in the reign of <ORGANIZATION>King George IV</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Round Tower is built on a mound thrown up by the Saxons, the
Teutonic invaders who conquered <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> between the 5th and 7th
centuries. They ruled until their army under <PERSON>King Harold</PERSON> was beaten
at the <ORGANIZATION>Battle of Hastings</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1066</DATE> by <PERSON>Duke William</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Normandy</LOCATION>, who
then became King William I of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   The original castle was built by <ORGANIZATION>King William</ORGANIZATION> around 1070.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890601-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-01-89 1329EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bush-Queen     06-01 0578</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Queen,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Samples Splendor of Palace and Smiles At Queen's Command</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> had lunch with <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON>
on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, sampled the splendor of <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> and smiled
for the cameras at her majesty's command.
   The royal event began with a glitch over the delayed opening of
<PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON>'s car door, but by the time lunch ended 30 minutes
behind schedule there were smiles all around and the queen told the
president: ``I hope to see you again soon.''
   When the presidential limousine pulled up to the palace's
red-carpeted <ORGANIZATION>Grand Entrance</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> jumped out. But nobody opened
<PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON>'s door until the queen, frowning and shaking her head,
raised her voice and said: ``Open it.''
   A <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Secret Service</ORGANIZATION> agent complied immediately and <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON>,
wearing an emerald green dress, emerged smiling as though nothing
had happened.
   It was the Bushes' first taste of British royal hospitality and
the queen and her husband, <PERSON>Prince Philip</PERSON>, brought out one of
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s biggest tourist attractions _ the <ORGANIZATION>2nd Battalion Scots
Guards</ORGANIZATION> in their red tunics and bearskin hats.
   The president arrived at <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> from talks with Prime
Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> at her Downing Street residence.
Escorted by <LOCATION>Philip</LOCATION>, he inspected a 100-strong honor guard mounted
by the <ORGANIZATION>Scots Guards</ORGANIZATION> after their band played the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> national
anthem.
   ``That was so beautiful,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told his hosts. ``I have never
heard `The Star-Spangled Banner' being played better.''
   Then he added hastily: ``with all respect to the <ORGANIZATION>Marine</ORGANIZATION> band.''
   Both couples then went inside, chatting animatedly as they
walked through a few of the palace's 600 rooms on their way to
cocktails with the 30 other luncheon guests.
   Between cocktails and lunch, the Bushes and their royal hosts
slipped out for a quick look at the mainly 17th century Dutch
masterpieces in the palace picture gallery.
   ``It's just us. It's very quiet,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said in a joking
reference to the cocktail hubbub he left behind.
   As they approached photographers, the queen, wearing a blue and
white striped silk dress, told <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> with a grin: ``Smile.'' He
obeyed.
   Luncheon was served in the ivory and gold Music Room overlooking
the 45-acre palace garden. The magnificent domed room with 18 blue
and gilt columns has been used for many royal christenings
including those of Prince <PERSON>Charles</PERSON>, the heir to the throne, and
<PERSON>Charles</PERSON>' heir, <PERSON>Prince William</PERSON>.
   Flanked by the queen and Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
sat down to a meal of smoked salmon mousse, duck with honey and
brandy sauce, broad beans, asparagus and potatoes, artichoke salad
and mango ice cream.
   The three wines included two which the queen served Soviet
leader <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON> and his wife <PERSON>Raisa</PERSON> when they lunched
together at <ORGANIZATION>Windsor Castle</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>April</DATE>. They are an Alsatian white
Gewurztraminer Dopff <DATE>1983</DATE> and the queen's private port, Royal
Vintage <DATE>1955</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> said the queen's choice of wines was
``coincidence.''
   The guests included <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON>'s husband <PERSON>Denis</PERSON>, Secretary of
State <PERSON>James Baker III</PERSON>, his British counterpart Sir <PERSON>Geoffrey Howe</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Terry Hands</PERSON>, artistic director of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Shakespeare Theater</ORGANIZATION>,
and <PERSON>Charles Wilson</PERSON>, editor of The Times of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   When former President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> went to <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> just a
year ago for tea with the queen, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> television reporter shouted
questions to him, breeching accepted behavior at formal royal
occasions.
   To avoid a repetition, reporters at the entrance were made to
stand behind a sound-proof glass screen.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890407-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-07-89 1055EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Gorbachev-Pageantry 2ndLd-Writethru a0578 04-07 0547</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gorbachev-Pageantry, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0578,0561</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Invites Queen To Soviet Union</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with Gorbachev inviting queen to the Soviet
Union. TRIMS to tighten. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Gorbachev-Britain</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos upcoming</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WINDSOR, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON> today had lunch with
<PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON> at <LOCATION>Windsor Castle</LOCATION> and invited her to visit the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   Her office said the queen told <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> she would like to
accept, but her foreign travel is fixed years in advance.
   She would be the first British sovereign to visit the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION> since the Russian royal family, her cousins, were murdered
after the <DATE>1917</DATE> Bolshevik revolution.
   ``Thanking <PERSON>Mr. Gorbachev</PERSON>, Her Majesty explained that the program
for her visits were fixed a number of years in advance. She hoped
it would be possible to visit the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> in due course,'' a
<ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> statement said.
   The announcement came as the Soviet leader left <LOCATION>Windsor Castle</LOCATION>
for <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Heathrow Airport</LOCATION> to return home at the end of a
40-hour visit to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
   Earlier, <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> and his wife <PERSON>Raisa</PERSON> drove to the majestic
castle on the <LOCATION>Thames River</LOCATION> in drizzling rain.
   Maj. <PERSON>Nicholas Parsons</PERSON> invited the <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION> leader in fluent
Russian to inspect a guard of honor of bearskin-capped <ORGANIZATION>Coldstream
Guards</ORGANIZATION>.
   The queen, in bright pink skirt and cape, and her husband,
<PERSON>Prince Philip</PERSON>, greeted her guests on the castle doorstep.
   <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> was the first Soviet leader since <DATE>1967</DATE> to meet the
queen, and by putting the royal seal on his 40-hour visit to
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, he clearly hoped to enhance the benign image he is trying
to implant in <LOCATION>Western</LOCATION> minds.
   <ORGANIZATION>Windsor Castle</ORGANIZATION>, the palace 20 miles west of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, has been a
royal residence for more than 800 years, and the queen took the
Gorbachevs on a tour of some of its rooms and held a lunch in their
honor.
   The 34 guests, including Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> and
her husband <PERSON>Denis</PERSON>, ate smoked salmon cornets filled with crabmeat,
layers of fillet of beef, duck puree and sliced artichoke, all
baked in pastry.
   Earlier today, <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> delivered a major televised policy
speech in the oak-paneled, chandeliered splendor of <LOCATION>Guildhall</LOCATION>, for
800 years the seat of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> city government.
   Like many of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s archaic institutions, the <ORGANIZATION>Guildhall</ORGANIZATION>'s
power is more in its looks than in its powers. Like Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth
II</PERSON>, the Guildhall and its lord mayor are restricted largely to
ceremonial duties.
   The Gorbachevs arrived at the <ORGANIZATION>Guildhall</ORGANIZATION> in a 24-car motorcade
through the congested streets of the <LOCATION>City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s financial
district, where the lord mayor, <PERSON>Alderman</PERSON> Sir <PERSON>Christopher Collett</PERSON>,
waited, resplendent in black, gold-braided robes and three-corner
hat.
   <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> was escorted into the building in a procession led by
the mayor, the sergeant at arms and officials bearing a sword and a
gold mace, symbol of city authority.
   A trumpet fanfare announced the Gorbachevs' entry into the hall,
and they stood beside <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> and her husband <PERSON>Denis</PERSON> as the
Soviet and British anthems were played.
   An array of dignitaries packed the hall, ranging across the
political spectrum from <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> through Archbishop of
Canterbury <PERSON>Robert Runcie</PERSON> to <PERSON>Bruce Kent</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Campaign
for Nuclear Disarmament</ORGANIZATION>.
   Pikemen, musketeers, sheriffs and city elders in blue robes
stood by to complete the pageant.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880221-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-21-88 2146EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Palace     02-21 0280</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Palace,0288</SECOND>
<HEAD>Intruder Arrested In Buckingham Palace Mews</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A drunken youth penetrated security devices
designed to protect the royal family and was arrested about 200
yards from <LOCATION>Buckingham Palace</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> Yard said early <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The Yard, headquarters of the metropolitan police, said the
incident occurred <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>. It said no further action was
planned against the youth, who was released after being cautioned
for being drunk and disorderly.
   The Yard declined to give the youth's name, address or age. It
also would not detail how he got into the royal mews, which serves
as stable and garage for <ORGANIZATION>Queen Elizabeth II</ORGANIZATION>'s 30 carriage horses,
coaches and cars.
   He was arrested in the mews, about 200 yards from the palace.
   The mews is normally entered from <LOCATION>Buckingham Palace Road</LOCATION> through
a huge pair of doors set in a high wall topped with spikes, barbed
wire, alarms and remote control cameras.
   The palace said the queen was not at <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> at the
time of the intrusion.
   She was at <ORGANIZATION>Windsor Castle</ORGANIZATION>, 21 miles west of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, where the
royal family often prefers to spend weekends.
   Security at 650-room <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> and its 45 acres of
grounds was improved after an unemployed drifter, <PERSON>Michael Fagan</PERSON>,
climbed a drainpipe in <DATE>1982</DATE> to reach the queen's bedroom, sat on
her bed and spoke to her before he was nabbed.
   A jury found <PERSON>Fagan</PERSON> innocent of stealing a bottle of Californian
wine which he drank during a break-in at the palace earlier in
<DATE>1982</DATE>. He was never charged with breaking in to the palace because
it was regarded as trespassing, a civil offense, and the palace
wouldn't take him to court.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890407-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-07-89 1815EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gorbachev-Queen 1st-LdWritethru   04-07 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gorbachev-Queen, 1st-Ld Writethru,a0739,0824</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Pops Question &amp; Queen Accepts Invitation to Moscow</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERT 3 grafs after 8th pvs, `In November...' to ADD Soviet
comment on invitation to queen. Pickup 9th pvs, `Gorbachev was...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WINDSOR, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON> followed in the
footsteps of the czars and came to <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON>'s castle on
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, then asked the question Britons have been speculating about
for months.
   He asked the monarch if she would come to <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>. Prime Minister
<PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> said the queen gave ``a very definite yes.''
   Winding up his two-day visit, the Soviet leader sampled
old-fashioned British pageantry _ first in the oak-paneled splendor
of the <LOCATION>Guildhall</LOCATION>, for 800 years the seat of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> city government,
then in majestic <LOCATION>Windsor Castle</LOCATION> overlooking the <LOCATION>River Thames</LOCATION>.
   Elizabeth will be the first British monarch to visit the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION> since the revolution that ousted the czars and brought the
communists to power.
   The invitation has great implications because of the close
kinship of the Russian and British royal families. Czar <PERSON>Nicholas
II</PERSON>, a cousin of the queen's grandfather, was murdered with his
family in <DATE>1918</DATE>, ending the <LOCATION>Romanov</LOCATION> dynasty.
   The queen's reaction sounded somewhat guarded. A <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham
Palace</ORGANIZATION> statement said: ``Thanking <PERSON>Mr. Gorbachev</PERSON>, Her Majesty
explained that the program for her visits were fixed a number of
years in advance. She hoped it would be possible to visit the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> in due course.''
   But <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON>, whose government has the final word on
approving or rejecting a visit, said: ``It's a very definite yes.''
She added the queen was ``very positive, very glad, very happy''
about the invitation.
   In <DATE>November</DATE>, a month before <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> originally was scheduled
to visit <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, reports of a Soviet prospective invitation to the
queen started circulating and <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> let it be known she
thought it was too soon to give such a resounding stamp of approval
to the Soviet leader's reform plans.
   At a news conference in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, Soviet officials
were asked whether the palace or British government had insisted
the Soviets apologize for the treatment of the Russian royal family
before the queen accepted the invitation.
   Yevgeny Primakov of the <ORGANIZATION>Soviet Institute of World Economic and
International Politics</ORGANIZATION> said there were ``no preconditions on either
side.''
   He said Soviets are reasessing their history but added: ``This
is not the point. This is an invitation to a head of state of a
country with which we are trying to find points of convergence.''
   <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> was driven to <LOCATION>Windsor Castle</LOCATION>, 21 miles west of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
_ the first Soviet leader since <DATE>1967</DATE> to visit the queen.
   In drizzling rain, he took the Royal Salute from the Guard of
Honor mounted by the <ORGANIZATION>1st Battalion Coldstream Guards</ORGANIZATION>. The captain
then reported to <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> in Russian and the Soviet leader,
carrying his hat in his hand, reviewed the troops clad in gray
greatcoats and bearskin hats.
   The queen, wearing a pink cape and matching skirt, then took
<PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> and his wife, <PERSON>Raisa</PERSON>, on a quick tour of the palace _ past
relics from the <LOCATION>Crusades</LOCATION>, medieval knights on horseback, <PERSON>King Henry
VIII</PERSON>'s suit of armor, and a painting of the Russian Emperor
<PERSON>Alexander I. Gorbachev</PERSON> beamed in recognition.
   The party made a brief detour to enable <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> to look at a
malachite vase given to Queen Victoria by Czar <PERSON>Nicholas I.
   Nicholas</PERSON> I was the first of the czarist cousins to come to
<LOCATION>Windsor</LOCATION>, spending three days in <DATE>June 1844</DATE> as <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION>'s guest.
Alexander II, the future <PERSON>Alexander III</PERSON>, and the future <PERSON>Nicholas II</PERSON>,
were also entertained at <LOCATION>Windsor</LOCATION> by the British royals.
   <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> invited the queen to visit the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> over a lunch of smoked salmon, pastry filled with
layers of beef, duck puree and artichoke and avocado salad, and
three wines.
   The 34 guests included <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> and her husband, <PERSON>Denis</PERSON>, and
the queen's youngest son, <PERSON>Prince Edward</PERSON>, who will be visiting
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> next week with the <ORGANIZATION>National Youth Theater</ORGANIZATION>.
   Lord <ORGANIZATION>St. John of Fawsley</ORGANIZATION>, a constitutional expert, said the
invitation ``will cement the very warm relationship between
ourselves and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>. I think it will put an end to all
tensions that could have come from the memories of the
assassination of the czar and I think the queen will have a very
ecstatic reception.''
   <PERSON>Harold Brooks-Baker</PERSON>, publishing director of <PERSON>Burke</PERSON>'s peerage,
said the queen should insist that the Soviets disclose where Czar
<PERSON>Nicolas II</PERSON> and his family are buried, and that she be allowed to
pay her respects.
   ``The fact that the queen could see the graves of her relations,
and repair the damage done after the Russian Revolution in a
Christian and religious way, would perhaps bring these countries
closer together than anyone ever thought possible,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06147073 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06147073 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  UK; RULING; FAMILY; HISTORY; GUIDELINE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE ROYAL family has many members, but these are the ones most followed by the
press and the public:;    (check) Queen Elizabeth II: Monarch and head of the
royal family. She and her husband Prince Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh, live
in Buckingham Palace.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHO'S WHO, WHAT'S WHAT AMONG BRITISH ROYALTY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related story on this page.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     (check) Prince Charles: The Prince of <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION>, heir to the throne, lives in
<LOCATION>Kensington Palace</LOCATION> with his wife, <PERSON>Princess Diana</PERSON>, and two children, <LOCATION>Princes
William</LOCATION> and Henry.;    (check) Prince Andrew: <PERSON>Charles</PERSON>' brother, the <ORGANIZATION>Duke of
York</ORGANIZATION>, is a handsome Naval officer who had a reputation as a playboy before he
married the former <PERSON>Sarah Ferguson</PERSON> ("Fergie"), now the ebullient Duchess of
York.;    (check) Princess Anne: <PERSON>Charles</PERSON>' sister, the Princess Royal, makes
many charitable appearances.;    (check) Prince Edward: Still unmarried,
<ORGANIZATION>Edward</ORGANIZATION> is a bit of a royal maverick.;    (check) The Queen Mother: Now 91 but
still very active, the popular widow of <PERSON>George VI</PERSON> and mother of Queen
Elizabeth II lives in <LOCATION>Clarence House.</LOCATION>;    (check) Princess Margaret: Sister of
the queen, she lives in <LOCATION>Kensington Palace.</LOCATION>;    (check) The <ORGANIZATION>Duke</ORGANIZATION> and Duchess of
Kent: These first cousins to the queen are familiar to Americans as the
patrons of the <LOCATION>Wimbledon</LOCATION> tennis championships.;     Royal Palaces;    Of the
many current royal residences, only five palaces in the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> area are open
to the public. All have an admission charge. They are:;    (check) Kensington:
The state apartments and court dress collections can be seen. Built by
<PERSON>Christopher Wren</PERSON> for <ORGANIZATION>William III</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Mary II</PERSON>. Open all year <DATE>Monday-Saturday 9</DATE>
<TIME>a.m.-5 p.m.</TIME>, <DATE>Sunday 1</DATE> <TIME>p.m.-5 p.m.</TIME> Information: (071) 937-9561.;    (check)
<LOCATION>Kew</LOCATION>: This was the <DATE>summer</DATE> retreat for <PERSON>George III</PERSON>, Queen <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> and their 15
children. Open daily <DATE>April-September 11</DATE> <TIME>a.m.-5:30 p.m.</TIME> Information: (081)
940-3321.;    (check) <LOCATION>Hampton Court</LOCATION>: Built by <PERSON>Cardinal Wolsey</PERSON> and embellished
by <PERSON>Henry VIII</PERSON>. Open daily mid-March to mid-October <TIME>9:30 a.m.-6 p.m.</TIME>; closes at
<TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> other months. Information: (081) 977-8441.;    (check) Tower of
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>: Famed castle on the <LOCATION>Thames</LOCATION>, 900 years old. Where the Crown Jewels are
kept. Open daily <DATE>March-October, Monday-Saturday</DATE> <TIME>9:30 a.m.-5:45 p.m.</TIME>, <DATE>Sunday 2</DATE>
<TIME>p.m.-5:45 p.m.</TIME>; other months it closes at <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> Information (071)
709-0765.;    (check) <ORGANIZATION>Banqueting House</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Whitehall</ORGANIZATION>: Designed by <PERSON>Indigo Jones</PERSON>,
this is the only remaining building of James I's Palace of <ORGANIZATION>Whitehall</ORGANIZATION>. Open all
year Tuesday-Saturday.;     'Royal' events;  Certain events during the year
attract members of the royal family. Among them are these <DATE>summer</DATE> events in and
around <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>:;    (check) <LOCATION>Epsom Downs</LOCATION>: The Derby is held the first <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
in June.;    (check) Trooping of the Color: The Queen leads this parade in
honor of her "official" birthday, the second <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in June.;    (check)
Royal Ascot: For four days in <DATE>June</DATE>, the royals gather to enjoy the races,
arriving by carriage.;    (check) The Garter Ceremony: On <DATE>Monday</DATE> of <ORGANIZATION>Ascot
Week</ORGANIZATION>, the Queen invests new knights at <ORGANIZATION>Windsor Castle</ORGANIZATION> after a procession from
the castle to <LOCATION>St. George</LOCATION>'s Chapel.;    (check) <LOCATION>Wimbledon</LOCATION>: The annual tennis
championships this year run for two weeks starting <DATE>June 24.</DATE>;    (check) Queen
Mother's Birthday Celebration: All the royals gather on the <TIME>morning</TIME> of <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>
to wish the Queen Mother a happy birthday at her <ORGANIZATION>Clarence House</ORGANIZATION> residence.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JAY CLARKE, Knight-Ridder Newspapers  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910526  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  542  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday May 26, 1991
00147073,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881031-0148 </DOCNO>
<HL> Technology: AT&amp;T Computer Business Gets Big Boost --- Massive Air Force Contract Bolsters Firm in Battle Over Standards for Unix </HL>
<AUTHOR> Janet Guyon (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> T WANB DEC IBM HON LK ZE CDA TRW </CO>
<IN> EDP ARO </IN>
<G> DEF </G>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s computer business and its Unix operating system got a big boost <DATE>Friday</DATE> when the company won an estimated <MONEY>$929 million</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> contract. 

   The award provides <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> with much-needed credibility in the computer industry, analysts said, and is likely to be used by the telephone giant as a major marketing tool. 
<ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> executives said the contract with options runs for eight years and could be worth more than <MONEY>$4.5 billion</MONEY> if the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> and civilian agencies order their authorized limits for equipment, software and services. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> contract, one of the government's largest computer orders ever, had been closely watched by the computer industry. 
The size of the contract helped create a major industry fight over future computer standards, because the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> required bidders to offer systems compatible with Unix, an operating system developed and licensed by <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> that has become increasingly popular as the base level of software controlling operations on engineering workstations, many minicomputers and some personal computers. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wang Laboratories Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, for instance, didn't bid after protesting against the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>'s requirement of compatibility with <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION>'s latest version of Unix-Unix System <PERSON>V. 

   Robert Kavner</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Data Systems Group</ORGANIZATION>, said he hopes the contract will help <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> reach an agreement with the <ORGANIZATION>Open Software Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, a computer group challenging the company's control of Unix. 
The group has pledged to develop a system using <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s Unix version, <LOCATION>AIX</LOCATION>, which isn't fully compatible with <ORGANIZATION>Unix System V. AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION>, in turn, has formed a group to push Unix System V. 

   "This bid doesn't decide the entire marketplace," <PERSON>Mr. Kavner</PERSON> said. 
"But it is an incremental affirmation of our operating system. 
I hope those in <ORGANIZATION>OSF</ORGANIZATION> will continue to ship Unix System V and feel more and more comfortable it's the route to go." 

   How much business <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> actually will get from the contract isn't clear. 
Capt. <PERSON>Warren Sypher</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Communications Command</ORGANIZATION>, which announced the contract, said he understood its value to be <MONEY>$929 million</MONEY> over eight years. 
However, <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> executives said that the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> agencies covered by the contract are authorized to spend about <MONEY>$4.5 billion</MONEY>, and that the <MONEY>$929 million</MONEY> estimate covers only the first two years. 

   Whatever its final value, the win gives <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION>'s computer business a shot in the arm. 
<ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION>'s current computer revenue is about <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> annually, analysts estimate, and the unit, which has had losses totaling <MONEY>billions of dollars</MONEY>, isn't expected to become profitable until late next year at the earliest. 

   "They certainly need whatever they can get" in computer orders, said <PERSON>Richard Toole</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
"But I really think their problems in computers will have to be solved by acquisition." 
<PERSON>Mr. Kavner</PERSON> said the contract will help <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Data Systems Group</ORGANIZATION> turn profitable sooner than his budget now plans. 
