<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900326-0156 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-26-90 2213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ParallelTragedies     03-26 0557</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Parallel Tragedies,0570</SECOND>
<HEAD>City's Deadliest Fires Had More In Common Than Date</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Social Club Fire, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY NEUMEISTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 87 people who died in a social club fire
were martyrs to the quest for a better life, just like 146 people
killed exactly 79 years earlier in a fire in a city garment
factory, Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> told about 700 people at a memorial service for victims
of the <DATE>1911</DATE> fire at the <ORGANIZATION>Triangle Shirtwaist Co.</ORGANIZATION> that both tragedies
killed immigrants looking for improved living conditions in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
   ``With vicious irony yesterday, on the 79th anniversary of the
Triangle Shirtwaist fire, history repeated itself,'' the mayor said
at the site of the earlier blaze.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the bodies of trapped revelers were found packed into
the <ORGANIZATION>Happy Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>. A Cuban immigrant was
charged with setting fire to the club's only exit after he was
thrown out.
   Authorities said the club's patrons never had a chance to escape
the blaze because the building did not follow fire codes. It was
the same lack of concern for people that caused such devastation at
the Triangle factory in <LOCATION>Greenwich Village</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said.
   ``So the lessons of the Triangle Shirtwaist fire are not
something we commemorate today, they are lessons that have been
driven home for us all to learn, once again,'' <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said.
   ``Now, the martyrs of <DATE>March 25, 1911</DATE>, and the martyrs of <DATE>March
25, 1990</DATE>, are joined forever,'' he said. ``Like the victims at the
<ORGANIZATION>Happy Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION>, most of those who died on this killing
ground were immigrants to our shores.''
   ``They, too, came to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> to find a dream. Instead, they
found misery, exploitation and an agonizing death,'' he said.
``These 146 workers didn't have to die. Neither did the 87 people
in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>.''
   Later, a fire truck ladder was raised up to the 10-story
building's sixth floor, the highest a fire ladder would go in those
days, as a fire bell was rung to mark the deaths. A wreath of white
roses was placed above pictures of the fire.
   ``They died at this building because they were seen as surplus
labor. They died because they didn't speak English very well,
because they weren't organized, because no one spoke up for them or
represented their interests and because their employer didn't care
about them,'' <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said.
   ``In fact, that very day in <DATE>1911</DATE>, their boss went out late in
the <TIME>afternoon</TIME> and locked all the workers of the <ORGANIZATION>Triangle Shirtwaist
Co.</ORGANIZATION> inside, just to make sure none of them tried to leave early
while he did some shopping,'' he said.
   ``All 146 of them died painfully, horribly, just like the 87 who
died yesterday,'' the mayor added. ``And all of them died
unnecessarily, just like the 87 who died yesterday.''
   He recalled, though, that the workers' deaths inspired the labor
movement and brought about lasting changes in laws to protect
workers. Sweatshops have re-emerged in recent years and it is
necessary again to battle exploitation, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said.
   ``And again, there are those operating in the shadows, running
sweatshops and illegal social clubs and pursuing other schemes,
turning the lure and promise of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> into a nightmare for those
who seek to redeem the promise,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900326-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-26-90 1407EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SocialClubCrackdown 2ndLd-Writethru a0539 03-26 0857</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Social Club Crackdown, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0539,0875</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mayor Orders Crackdown on Illegal Clubs</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs to UPDATE with details of sweep, more
than 200 clubs visited, other detai. Picks up 15th graf pvs,
`Sunday's fire...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL GEITNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Inspectors this morning visited more than 200
social clubs in a crackdown ordered by Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON>
following the deadliest city fire in 79 years. Only a fraction of
them were found to be open, but 52 safety violations were cited,
authorities said.
   ``I will tell you it will not be an endless battle,'' <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON>
said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> after touring the charred Happy Land social club in the
<LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>. ``Anybody that had an opportunity to view those 87 bodies
knows that we're not going to tolerate this.''
   Previous mayors have waged a long and unsuccessful battle to
close clubs that are operating illegally. The dancing and drinking
nightspots are popular among immigrants because they are cheap.
   A task force put together by then-Mayor <PERSON>Edward Koch</PERSON> after a <DATE>1988</DATE>
Bronx social club fire that killed seven people will be beefed up,
<PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said. Before <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire, only one team remained from the
10-team task force.
   A sweep of social clubs was conducted between <TIME>midnight</TIME> and <TIME>7
a.m.</TIME>, police said.
   Officers and task force inspectors went to 241 suspected illegal
clubs citywide and posted vacate orders at 187 of them, said Sgt.
<PERSON>Dick Vreeland</PERSON>, a police spokesman. In most cases, the orders were
posted on closed doors, because just 23 of the clubs were found to
be open for business. Fifty-two safety violations and 30 summonses
were issued.
   During the sweep, five people were arrested for weapons
possession, 11 loaded firearms recovered, cars were towed and
parking tickets issued.
   <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, in raids unrelated to the fire, a police task
force raided several social clubs in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> and arrested five
people for weapons possession, said Sgt. <PERSON>Tina Mohrmann</PERSON>, a police
spokeswoman.
   <PERSON>Albert Scardino</PERSON>, the mayor's press secretary, said police list
about 1,220 clubs without liquor licenses, with about 1,000
considered inactive. The Happy Land was considered inactive.
   ``They range from a group of elderly men who get together to
play cards and watch a ballgame on a <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> to
full-fledged nightclub operations,'' said <PERSON>Richard Chernela</PERSON>, a state
<ORGANIZATION>Liquor Authority</ORGANIZATION> spokesman.
   The number of clubs citywide is hard to pin down since they can
<DATE>spring</DATE> up overnight, often in a dank basement or abandoned building.
   A review of city records <DATE>Sunday</DATE> turned up 173 social clubs that
had been ordered vacated. Inspectors were told to make sure the 173
are closed. There was no immediate explanation of how other clubs
visited today were selected.
   If the illegal clubs are not shut immediately, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> had said,
``we'll see to it that they certainly aren't open come the next
weekend.''
   <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire occurred 79 years to the day after a blaze at the
<ORGANIZATION>Triangle Shirtwaist Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> that claimed 145 lives,
many of them immigrant garment workers. That blaze led to reforms
around the nation in workplace safety.
   Just about anyone can go to a social club, despite the term's
implication of exclusivity. The Happy Land charged <MONEY>$5</MONEY> for admission.
   Despite periodic campaigns to close them, many of the clubs have
become centers of urban problems, from noise and double-parking to
gambling, prostitution and drug dealing.
   The clubs often are rife with building, health and fire code
violations that can lead to tragedy. Five people died in a <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>
club fire in <DATE>1985</DATE>, and 25 people were killed in a <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> fire in
<DATE>1976</DATE>.
   ``People are literally taking their lives in their hands at
these clubs,'' <ORGANIZATION>Bronx Borough</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Fernando Ferrer</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said a vacate order was issued in <DATE>November 1988</DATE> against
the Happy Land because the club did not have a proper sprinkler
system, exits, emergency lighting and signs.
   City records show an arrest was made there on <DATE>July 24</DATE> and the
club was closed again on <DATE>Nov. 1</DATE>, he said.
   City officials said the building was sold last year to <PERSON>Karl
Rubman</PERSON>, but <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said it was unclear who owns the property now.
Residents said the manager of the club was <ORGANIZATION>Elias Colon</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Daily
News</ORGANIZATION> reported that <ORGANIZATION>Colon</ORGANIZATION>'s wife, <PERSON>Elena</PERSON>, was one of the survivors of
the fire.
   Some said it may be impossible to close the social clubs
completely.
   ``Our experience in the city in the <DATE>last 20 years</DATE> demonstrates
that clearly,'' said <PERSON>William Kornblum</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Center for
Social Research</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>City University of New York Graduate School</ORGANIZATION>.
   Many people, especially those from poor neighborhoods where
affordable alternatives are scarce, go to the clubs looking for a
place to socialize where they feel welcome.
   Some clubs are closed under the city's <DATE>1984</DATE> padlock law, which
allows police to shutter a location for a year if two crimes are
committed on the site within a 12-month period.
   But the owners, if they can be located, are rarely convicted.
   Even when the clubs are shuttered, an owner may reopen around
the corner or down the street, attracting the same crowd.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900326-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-26-90 1416EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SocialClubFire 5thLd-Writethru a0587 03-26 1162</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Social Club Fire, 5th Ld - Writethru, a0587,1188</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire Allegedly Set By Spurned Lover Kills 87 at Unlicensed Social
Club</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 11-12th grafs, `Authorities early...', with 2 grafs to
UPDATE with number of clubs visited citywide, 52 safety violations
cited. Picks up 13th graf pvs, `It was...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY6,7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAUL REYES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man bounced from a <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> social club for
quarreling with an ex-girlfriend returned with a jug of gasoline
and set a fire that killed 87 people at the nightspot, which had
been ordered closed, police said.
   <PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON>, 36, was charged with multiple counts of murder
and arson in the pre-dawn blaze <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at the Happy Land social
club, police Sgt. <PERSON>Edward Burns</PERSON> said.
   He appeared early this morning in <ORGANIZATION>Bronx County Criminal Court</ORGANIZATION>
and was ordered held without bail and placed in an isolated cell
under a suicide watch in a <LOCATION>Rikers Island</LOCATION> jail, <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> said.
   Meanwhile, authorities launched a crackdown on social clubs,
drinking and dancing nightspots that proliferate in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s poor
neighborhoods and often operate without proper licenses and safety
features. Happy Land was operating despite a <DATE>1988</DATE> closure order
that cited safety violations including improper exits.
   Most of the dead suffocated in thick smoke in the pre-dawn blaze
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>, authorities said. Some people were trampled to death;
others broke a hole through a wall to an adjoining hall in a
desperate attempt to escape.
   Emergency workers described bodies felled by smoke so quickly
that they still had their legs wrapped around a bar stool, gripped
drinks or held hands. Only three people managed to reach safety by
way of the two doors on the front of the two-story Happy Land
social club.
   ``People literallywere stacked on top of each other,'' said
<PERSON>Anthony De Vita</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Fire Department</ORGANIZATION>'s command chief. ``It was a
firetrap.''
   Gonzalez, a Cuban immigrant and former boyfriend of a Happy
Land's ticket seller, was thrown out of the club after a quarrel in
which he tried to woo back the woman, police said.
   After warning, ``I'll be back,'' he returned with a jug of
gasoline, sprinkled the fuel on the floor and lit it, said Lt.
<PERSON>James Malvey</PERSON>.
   Gonzalez cried with remorse under questioning, said Lt. <PERSON>Raymond
O'Donnell</PERSON>, a police spokesman. ``Basically, he's saying he did
it,'' <PERSON>O'Donnell</PERSON> said.
   Authorities early today inspected more than 200 social clubs
across the city, finding most of them closed. Vacate orders were
posted at 187 of them, and 52 safety violation notices were issued,
said Sgt. <PERSON>Dick Vreeland</PERSON>, a police spokesman. In addition, five
people were arrested for weapons possessions.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, officials had said a review of city records showed at
least 173 social clubs had been ordered to shut down in the past,
and Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> ordered officials to make sure they were
closed.
   It was the deadliest fire in the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> since
the <DATE>1977</DATE> blaze at the <ORGANIZATION>Beverly Hills Supper Club</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Southgate</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>,
that killed 164 people. A New Year's Eve <DATE>1986</DATE> fire at a hotel in
<LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, killed 97.
   The fire occurred exactly 79 years after a blaze at the <ORGANIZATION>Triangle
Shirtwaist Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, a garment factory, that claimed
145 lives. That blaze led to reforms around the nation in workplace
safety.
   At a ceremony today marking the Triangle fire, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> referred
to <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s club fire, noting that in both cases most of the
victims were immigrants. As in <DATE>1911</DATE>, he said, ``there are those
operating in the shadows, running sweatshops and illegal social
clubs and pursuing other schemes, turning the lure and promise of
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> into a nightmare for those who seek to redeem the
promise.'' The ceremony had been scheduled long before <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s
fire.
   After <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire, the impoverished Latino neighborhood near
the <LOCATION>Bronx Zoo</LOCATION> was thick with mourners, who were asked to identify
relatives from snapshots of the bodies posted on the wall of a high
school.
   Killed were 61 men and 26 women, most of them Honduran and
Dominican immigrants.
   ``Most of the bodies were in dance clothes,'' <ORGANIZATION>Emergency Medical
Services</ORGANIZATION> specialist <PERSON>Christopher McCarthy</PERSON> said. ``They were out to
have fun.''
   <PERSON>Alva Romero</PERSON>, a Honduran immigrant, lost six relatives, including
a daughter, both brothers and a sister. <PERSON>Jerome Ford</PERSON> lost five
relatives. The local Honduran soccer club lost several players.
   The government in <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION> today expressed regret over the fire.
Foreign Ministry spokesman <PERSON>Eugenio Castro</PERSON> said officials were
``deeply moved by the deaths of many countrymen in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.''
   Happy Land was ordered shut in <DATE>November 1988</DATE> and again a year
later because of inadequate exits, sprinkler systems, emergency
lighting and signs, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said. It had no liquor or cabaret
license.
   City officials said the building was sold last year to <PERSON>Karl
Rubman</PERSON>, but <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said it was unclear who owns the property now.
Residents said the manager of the club was <ORGANIZATION>Elias Colon</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Daily
News</ORGANIZATION> reported that <ORGANIZATION>Colon</ORGANIZATION>'s wife, <PERSON>Elena</PERSON>, was one of the survivors of
the fire.
   Despite their name, the social clubs admit anyone. Happy Land
charged a <MONEY>$5</MONEY> admission price at the door; its illegally served
drinks cost about <MONEY>$3</MONEY> each.
   ``I will tell you it will not be an endless battle,'' the mayor
said in announcing the crackdown on illegal clubs. ``Anybody that
had an opportunity to view those 87 bodies knows that we're not
going to tolerate this.''
   Mayor <PERSON>Ed Koch</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON>' predecessor, made a similar promise
after a <DATE>1988</DATE> Bronx social club fire killed seven people. The clubs
are popular among poor immigrants.
   Two rickety staircases lead to the second-story dance floor
where most of the bodies were found. Disc jockey <PERSON>Ruben Valladares</PERSON>,
who spun reggae, salsa and calypso records, ran through the flames
and was hospitalized with severe burns.
   At least two other women escaped. Their condition was unknown.
   ``People were screaming; they were all burned,'' said <PERSON>Rosemary
Green</PERSON>, who found the club on fire when she arrived to meet her
sister-in-law and cousin. ``Once you got in the entrance there was
no way to get out.''
   Gonzalez, an unemployed warehouse worker, came to the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> on the Mariel boatlift in <DATE>1980</DATE>, <PERSON>O'Donnell</PERSON> said.
   Police said he went into the club about <TIME>3 a.m.</TIME> and began arguing
with the woman.
   ``He's trying to talk her into making up; she's saying `Leave me
alone,''' <PERSON>O'Donnell</PERSON> said. The man's ex-girlfriend left before the
fire, which was reported at <TIME>3:41 a.m.</TIME>, <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said. Police withheld
her identity.
   <PERSON>Denise Garcia</PERSON>, 20, a filing clerk who lives in the neighborhood,
said she and her friends avoided the club because they considered
it ``too sleazy.'' The building was rickety and the dance floor
sometimes trembled, she said.
   One firefighter broke a leg; 13 of his colleagues also were
injured.
   Gonzalez was charged with two counts of arson, 87 counts of
murder in the course of arson, 87 counts of murder by depraved
indifference to human life and one count of attempted murder.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2002EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FireClubs 1stLd-Writethru a0716 03-25 0780</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fire Clubs, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0716,0799</SECOND>
<HEAD>Illegal Clubs Proliferate Despite Efforts to Close Them</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with mayor promising to close
unlicensed clubs, figures on number of clubs, number of people
killed in city's worst fire. Pick up 10th graf pvs, `Just about...'
DELETES next-to-last graf to conform. </NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Social Club Fire, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL GEITNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of dangerous and illegal social clubs
thrive in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> despite efforts to close them, because people in
poor neighborhoods have few alternatives for entertainment,
officials say.
   ``People are literally taking their lives in their hands at
these clubs,'' <ORGANIZATION>Bronx Borough</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Fernando Ferrer</PERSON> said after a
fire <DATE>Sunday</DATE> killed 87 people at the Happy Land social club.
   It was the city's deadliest blaze since 145 people were killed
in a fire at a garment factory, the <ORGANIZATION>Triangle Shirtwaist Co.</ORGANIZATION> of
<LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, 79 years ago to the day.
   Authorities said most of the predawn revelers were trapped on a
second-story dance floor and died from smoke inhalation. The
building lacked proper exits and other safeguards.
   The 4-year-old club, which didn't have a liquor or cabaret
license, was shut down for the second time <DATE>Nov. 1, 1989</DATE>, by the
city <ORGANIZATION>Buildings Department</ORGANIZATION>, but reopened illegally, Mayor <PERSON>David
Dinkins</PERSON> said.
   Despite periodic campaigns to close them, social clubs have been
centers of urban problems ranging from noise and double-parking to
gambling, drug dealing and prostitution.
   Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> estimated there are at least 700 social
clubs in the city.
   They often are rife with building, health and fire code
violations that can lead to tragedy. Six people died in a <DATE>1988</DATE> fire
at a <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> club, five in a <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> club fire in <DATE>1985</DATE>, and 25
people were killed in another <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> fire in <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   ``I don't know what it's going to take _ an army _ to stop them
from going to places like this,'' said newly elected <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Jose
Serrano</PERSON> after visiting the scene <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   City records reviewed <DATE>Sunday</DATE> showed 173 social clubs had been
given orders to vacate, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said at an <TIME>afternoon</TIME> news
conference.
   ``Tonight, we will commence to check those places, see that
they're in fact closed,'' he said. ``We'll see to it that they
certainly aren't open come the next weekend.''
   Just about anyone can go to a social club, despite the term's
implication of exclusivity. An employee usually keeps an eye on the
door, but a club member is generally anyone who walks in on a given
night.
   ``They range from a group of elderly men who get together to
play cards and watch a ballgame on a <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> to
full-fledged nightclub operations,'' said <PERSON>Richard Chernela</PERSON>, a state
<ORGANIZATION>Liquor Authority</ORGANIZATION> spokesman.
   <ORGANIZATION>New York State</ORGANIZATION> liquor licenses cost up to <MONEY>$5,100</MONEY> and are good
for three years. But many club operators don't apply for one,
sometimes because they or potential employees may have criminal
records that would disqualify them.
   While the city's licensed bars are required to close by <TIME>4 a.m.</TIME>,
social clubs often stay open until dawn or later, usually to the
distress of nearby residents. Neighborhood residents said <ORGANIZATION>Happy
Land</ORGANIZATION> stayed open until <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME>
   Often there's a cover charge _ <MONEY>$5</MONEY> at Happy Land. Often the clubs
sell drinks.
   Many who go to the clubs are looking for a place to socialize
that they can afford and where they feel welcome. But they also
attract a criminal element.
   A state task force reported several years ago that alcohol
consumption is often of secondary importance.
   ``The primary function of these operations has developed into
prostitution, gambling, drugs and trafficking in stolen property,''
it said.
   Just <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, a police task force in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> raided
several social clubs and arrested five people for weapons
possession, said Sgt. <PERSON>Tina Mohrmann</PERSON>, a police spokeswoman.
   Some clubs are closed under the city's ``padlock law,'' which
allows police to shutter a location for a year if two crimes are
committed on the site within a 12-month period.
   But the owners _ if they can be found _ are rarely convicted.
Defendants arrested in police raids often end up pleading guilty to
a lesser charge, which then doesn't qualify as a criminal
conviction under the padlock law.
   Even when the clubs are shuttered, the owners often open up
again around the corner or down the street, attracting the same
crowd.
   Then-Mayor <PERSON>Edward Koch</PERSON> put together an interagency task force
after the <DATE>1988</DATE> fire sparked a public outcry about the dangers of
social clubs.
   ``The ironic thing is that all the legislation is on the
books,'' said <PERSON>Clint Roswell</PERSON>, a spokesman for <PERSON>Ferrer</PERSON>. ``It's just
(an) enforcement problem.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900326-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-26-90 2027EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SocialClubFire 1stLd-Writethru a0673 03-26 1124</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Social Club Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0673,1150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Spurned Boyfriend Charged in 87 Fire Deaths</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RECASTS lead to reflect that suspect was charged with two
murder counts in each death; SUBS 7th graf, `He was...,' to UPDATE
with Gonzalez transferred to psychiatric ward; SUBS 25th graf,
`Johnson said...,' to restore dropped word `no'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD PYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The man accused of setting fire to the Happy
Land social club was arraigned <DATE>Monday</DATE> on charges of murdering 87
people, and police said he told them ``the devil got into me.''
   Authorities began shutting other illegal clubs in response to
<LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s worst fire in 79 years.
   The families of the 87 victims, most of whom were Honduran or
Dominican immigrants, sought solace in their grief, and a
government task force was set up to counsel them and help make
funeral arrangements.
   <PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON>, 36, was accused of setting the fire early <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
with <MONEY>$1</MONEY> worth of gasoline after arguing with a former girlfriend
who worked at the illegal club. He is said to have threatened to
``shut this place down.''
   ``I got angry, the devil got into me, and I set the place on
fire,'' <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> told authorities, according to a police source who
spoke to <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> on condition of anonymity.
   During a hearing at <ORGANIZATION>Bronx County Criminal Court</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> was
charged with 87 counts of murder committed during the course of
arson; 87 counts of murder by depraved indifference to human life;
one count of attempted murder; and two counts of arson.
   The case was turned over to a grand jury, and <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> will not
be asked to enter a plea unless an indictment is issued. He was
held under a suicide watch at the <LOCATION>Rikers Island</LOCATION> jail and later
admitted to <ORGANIZATION>Kings County Hospital Psychiatric Ward</ORGANIZATION>, where he will
be held indefinitely, said <PERSON>Ruby Ryles</PERSON>, a city jails spokeswoman.
   The deaths were believed to be the most ever charged to a single
suspect in the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   ``He is a double animal,'' said <PERSON>Rene J. Mena</PERSON>, 63, whose son,
<PERSON>Rene Jr.</PERSON>, 30, died. ``Here, they're going to have good food for
him, a book, a movie. In <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>, we don't do it that way.''
   District Attorney <PERSON>Robert T. Johnson</PERSON> said he hoped that if
<PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> is convicted, he would get consecutive prison sentences
amounting to 2,000 years.
   An equally angry Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> ordered a sweep of other
suspected unlicensed social clubs. Police and a special task force
visited 241 clubs citywide from midnight to <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE> and
posted vacate orders on 187.
   Only 23 of the clubs were open _ most are closed on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
nights. There were 52 safety violations and 30 summonses issued,
said Sgt. <PERSON>Dick Vreeland</PERSON>, a police spokesman.
   In the <LOCATION>East Tremont</LOCATION> section of the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>, families drifted in
and out of Public School 67, across from the fire-blackened club. A
task force of state, city and private agencies there helped them
make funeral arrangements and offered counseling and financial
assistance.
   ``It's orderly, but it's not emotionally orderly,'' said <PERSON>Ken
Curtin</PERSON>, a local <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> disaster relief director. ``It's highly
charged. There are a lot of outbursts of grief.''
``is deeply moved by the deaths of many countrymen in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.''
The Honduran telephone company said it was swamped with calls from
people seeking word about loved ones.
   The fire broke out at <TIME>3:40 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, and those inside the
club suffocated, burned or were trampled to death in a matter of
minutes.
   They had to ``choose between a wall of fire or retreating and
dying of asphyxiation,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   Police believe five people escaped from the fire: three patrons;
<PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON>'s former girlfriend, <PERSON>Lydia Feliciano</PERSON>; and the club disc
jockey.
   The disc jockey, identified in published reports as <PERSON>Ruben
Valladares</PERSON>, was listed as stable at <ORGANIZATION>Jacobi Hospital</ORGANIZATION> with burns over
<PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of his body, said hospital spokeswoman <PERSON>Vicki Ciampa</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON> and the others, whose names were withheld, escaped
serious injury. <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON> is in protective custody.
   <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> had been ejected from the club after
arguing with <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON> and threatening to ``shut this place
down.''
   He allegedly bought <MONEY>$1</MONEY> worth of gasoline at a nearby service
station, then returned and faked making a telephone call when he
saw a possible witness. When that person left, he allegedly poured
gasoline between the street and an inside door of the club and
ignited it.
   After that, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said, he watched it burn for a while, making
statements to at least two witnesses about his role in the fire. He
then went home, where police found him a few hours later. He made a
videotaped admission to police, authorities said.
   <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> knew the two-story club lacked windows,
rear exits and adequate staircases. He also knew how crowded it
was, authorities said.
   Gonzalez, who came to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> on the <DATE>1980</DATE>
Mariel boatlift, had no arrest record here, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said he has the name of a possible club owner, but will
not release it until it's confirmed. A vacate order was issued in
<DATE>November 1988</DATE> and again a year later because Happy Land lacked a
proper sprinkler system, exits, emergency lighting and signs. It
also had no liquor or cabaret license, the mayor said.
   The fire struck on the 79th anniversary of the <ORGANIZATION>Triangle
Shirtwaist Co.</ORGANIZATION> fire. That <DATE>1911</DATE> tragedy claimed 146 lives, many of
them immigrant garment workers, leading to nationwide reforms in
workplace safety.
   Dinkins discussed night club tragedy while addressing 700
garment workers and other union members who gathered <DATE>Monday</DATE> in
<LOCATION>Lower Manhattan</LOCATION> to commemorate the Triangle fire.
   ``They came to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> in search of a better life. Early
yesterday morning their American dream became a fatal nightmare,''
said <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON>, who inspected the scene of <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire.
   ``The sight of those bodies, lined along the walls like so many
wax figures, and the realization of the panic and the pain they
must have suffered in their last moments, will remain with me for
the rest of my life,'' said <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON>. ``Most horrifying is that this
should never have happened.''
   Roman Catholic Cardinal <PERSON>John J. O'Connor</PERSON> officiated at an
hour-long, English and Spanish prayer service outside the club on
<DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. A thousand mourners began the service by walking
a few blocks from <PERSON>St. Thomas Aquinas</PERSON> church, the parish of many of
the victims.
   ``We pray for those who died,'' said <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON>. ``We pray in a
special way for those who survived. We need to pray for the dead
and for the survivors. ... Our best is never good enough in
circumstances of this sort.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900327-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-27-90 1123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SocialClubFire 4thLd-Writethru a0528 03-27 1070</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Social Club Fire, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0528,1094</SECOND>
<HEAD>Spurned Boyfriend Charged in 87 Fire Deaths, Prosecutors Probe
Ownership</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to focus lead on investigation of
ownership, confirm reports on Turner's husband; picks up 7th graf,
`Across from...' SUBS 21st graf, `Valladares was...' to UPDATE disc
jockey's condition.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD PYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prosecutors are investigating whether owners in
a corporate chain that includes the husband of actress <PERSON>Kathleen
Turner</PERSON> may share responsibility in the fire deaths of 87 people in
an illegal nightclub.
   The Cuban immigrant accused of torching the club to avenge a
romantic snub was under a suicide watch in a psychiatric ward today
after allegedly telling police he set the blaze because ``the devil
got into me.''
   <PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON>, 36, was charged with murdering 87 people by
setting fire <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to the jammed Happy Land social club in the
<LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>.
   Miss <ORGANIZATION>Turner</ORGANIZATION>'s husband, <PERSON>Jay Weiss</PERSON>, acknowledged through a
statement by his lawyer that he and a partner are principals of
<ORGANIZATION>Little Peach Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which leased the club site in <DATE>1985</DATE> from a
corporation controlled by real estate developer <PERSON>Alex DiLorenzo III</PERSON>.
Two years later Little Peach sublet the two-story building to <PERSON>Elias
Colon</PERSON>, who operated the Happy Land club.
   Colon died in the fire.
   The statement by the lawyer, <PERSON>Roger Boyle</PERSON>, said <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON>' company
``has been actively pressing eviction proceedings against <PERSON>Mr. Colon</PERSON>
and had hoped that a final eviction would have resulted from a
trial scheduled for <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of this week.''
   The statement said <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> and his partner, <PERSON>Morris Jaffe</PERSON>, ``are
horrified at the events of this <DATE>weekend</DATE> and lament the loss of life
which ensued.''
   Bronx District Attorney <PERSON>Robert Johnson</PERSON> has said he has 10
assistants working on prosecuting <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> and also ``working on
the investigation of whether or not there is any possible
responsibility, criminal liability, on the part of the club and-or
the owner of the building.''
   Across from the fire-blackened club in an impoverished
neighborhood near the <LOCATION>Bronx Zoo</LOCATION>, families on <DATE>Monday</DATE> drifted in and
out of Public School 67, where agencies helped arrange funerals and
offered counseling and financial aid.
   Anger was directed at <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON>' former girlfriend, <PERSON>Lydia
Feliciano</PERSON>, when she appeared at the school to inquire about aid for
friends.
   ``I can't believe she is here. How could she show her face?''
said <PERSON>Edgardo Rodriguez</PERSON>, 22, who lost four friends and was awaiting
information on financial aid to send their bodies home to <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>.
   When asked why she came to the school, <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON> responded,
``I lost people too. I lost friends.'' As a crowd gathered around
her, two police officers escorted <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON> out of a back
entrance of the school.
   A huge wooden cross stood in front of the nightclub's ruins as
neighbors prayed at an outdoor service conducted in English and
Spanish. The service <DATE>Monday</DATE> ended with the singing of ``De
Colores,'' a song about brotherly love.
   At the direction of Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON>, authorities visited 241
clubs citywide from midnight to <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE> and posted orders on
187 of them to vacate.
   Police issued 52 safety violations and 30 summonses, said Sgt.
<PERSON>Dick Vreeland</PERSON>.
   Police said <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> had vowed to ``shut this place down'' after
an argument with <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON>, a Happy Land employee who had split
with the unemployed <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> several months ago.
   ``I got angry, the devil got into me, and I set the place on
fire,'' <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> told authorities, according to a police source who
spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Gonzalez was arraigned on 87 counts of murder committed in the
course of arson; 87 counts of murder by depraved indifference to
human life; one count of attempted murder, and two counts of arson.
He entered no plea.
   Johnson, the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> district attorney, said he hoped <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON>
would get consecutive sentences amounting to 2,000 years in prison
if convicted.
   Gonzalez, who was jailed for army desertion in <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> in the
<DATE>1970s</DATE>, came to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> on the <DATE>1980</DATE> Mariel
boatlift. He told immigration officials he had portrayed himself as
a drug trafficker to get kicked out of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION>
reported.
   The victims of <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire, many of them Honduran immigrants,
suffocated, burned or were trampled to death. They had to ``choose
between a wall of fire or retreating and dying of asphyxiation,''
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   Police believe five people escaped: three patrons; <PERSON>Ms.
Feliciano</PERSON>, and the club disc jockey, <PERSON>Ruben Valladares</PERSON>.
   Valladares was listed in critical but stable condition today at
<ORGANIZATION>Jacobi Hospital</ORGANIZATION> with burns over <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of his body. <PERSON>Ms.
Feliciano</PERSON> and the others escaped serious injury. <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON> is
in protective custody.
   <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> had described the following sequence:
   After arguing with <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON>, with whom he sought to resume
a relationship, he was ejected from the club.
   He bought <MONEY>$1</MONEY> worth of gasoline at a nearby station, returned and
faked making a telephone call when he saw someone. When that person
left, he poured gasoline between the street and an inside door and
ignited it.
   Gonzalez watched it burn for awhile, making statements to at
least two witnesses about his role in the fire. Then he went home,
where police found him a few hours later, his shoes reeking of
gasoline. He made a videotaped admission to police.
   <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> knew the two-story club lacked windows,
rear exits and adequate staircases. He also knew how crowded it was.
   ``He is a double animal,'' said <PERSON>Rene J. Mena</PERSON>, whose son, <PERSON>Rene
Jr.</PERSON>, 30, died in the fire. ``Here, they're going to have good food
for him, a book, a movie. In <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>, we don't do it that
way.''
   A vacate order was issued in <DATE>1988</DATE> against the club and again a
year later because Happy Land lacked a proper sprinkler system,
exits, emergency lighting and signs. It also had no liquor or
cabaret license, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said.
   Dinkins discussed <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s tragedy while addressing garment
workers <DATE>Monday</DATE> commemorating <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Triangle Shirtwaist
Co.</ORGANIZATION> fire, which occurred exactly 79 years before the Happy Land
blaze. The <DATE>1911</DATE> tragedy claimed 146 lives and transformed workplace
safety laws around the country.
   ``The sight of those bodies, lined along the walls like so many
wax figures, and the realization of the panic and the pain they
must have suffered in their last moments, will remain with me for
the rest of my life,'' <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SocialClubFire 5thLd-Writethru a0753 03-25 0992</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Social Club Fire, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0753,1023</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire Kills 87 at Unlicensed Social Club; Man Charged</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 26th graf to CORRECT spelling to Ungar sted Unger.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY7,8,11,16,19,27; LaserColor NY6,15; LaserGraphic
NY25</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VERENA DOBNIK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire raced through an illegal social club early
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> and turned a packed dance floor into a deathtrap of smoke
and flame that killed 87. A man who allegedly had earlier fought
with a club worker was charged with arson and murder.
   The fire, the nation's worst in 13 years, tore through the Happy
Land club, which authorities said lacked proper exits and other
safeguards.
   The <TIME>3:40 a.m.</TIME> fire killed 61 men and 26 women, most of them
Honduran and Dominican immigrants. Most were found on the second
floor.
   ``People literally were stacked on top of each other,'' said
<PERSON>Anthony De Vita</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Fire Department</ORGANIZATION>'s command chief. ``It was a
firetrap,'' he said of the two-story building in an impoverished
neighborhood near the <LOCATION>Bronx Zoo</LOCATION>.
   Some of the victims broke a hole through a wall to an adjoining
hall in a desperate attempt to save their lives, said <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>
worker <PERSON>Margaret Glugover</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON>, 36, was charged with arson and murder in the
case, said Lt. <PERSON>Raymond O'Donnell</PERSON>, a police spokesman. The district
attorney's office later would determine how many counts Gonzalez
would be charged.
   ``We believe the motive in this case was the result of a dispute
he had with a female employee of the club,'' Police Commissioner
<PERSON>Lee Brown</PERSON> said at a <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> news conference <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>.
   Gonzalez emigrated in <DATE>1980</DATE> from <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> during the Mariel boatlift
that brought 125,000 Cubans to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   Police said <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> went into the club about <TIME>3 a.m.</TIME> and began
arguing with his former girlfriend, who sold tickets near the
entrance.
   ``He's trying to talk her into making up, she's saying `Leave me
alone,''' <PERSON>O'Donnell</PERSON> said.
   A club bouncer evicted the man half an hour later, and police
alleged he returned and started the fire near the entrance.
   The woman employee left before the fire, <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said.
   At least two women and one man, believed to be the club's disc
jockey, escaped. The man was seriously burned; the condition of the
women was unknown.
   Most of the dead were believed to have suffocated from the thick
smoke, which billowed hundreds of feet, but some were trampled,
said <PERSON>Lynn Schulman</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>Emergency Medical Service</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman.
   ``This is the worst thing I have seen in my career,'' said
<ORGANIZATION>Emergency Medical Services</ORGANIZATION> specialist <PERSON>Christopher McCarthy</PERSON>. ``It
hurt my stomach. It was sickening.''
   ``Most of the bodies were in dance clothes,'' <PERSON>McCarthy</PERSON> said.
``They were out to have fun. ... I saw wall-to-wall bodies _ an
indication of mass confusion and panic.''
   The fire was the deadliest in the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
since a <DATE>May 28, 1977</DATE>, blaze at the <ORGANIZATION>Beverly Hills Supper Club</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Southgate</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>, that killed 164 people. A <DATE>Dec. 31, 1986</DATE>, fire at a
hotel in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth, killed 96
people.
   The tragedy occurred in <LOCATION>East Tremont</LOCATION>, a section of the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>
borough. Deputy Mayor <PERSON>Bill Lynch</PERSON> described it as an ``economically
disadvantaged, working-class, Latino neighborhood.''
   The building housed a group that organized children's baseball
as well as adult social events, said <PERSON>Lillian Rivera</PERSON>, a neighbor.
   A makeshift morgue was set up at a hall next door. Authorities
took <ORGANIZATION>Polaroid</ORGANIZATION> pictures of the bodies and showed them to 200 friends
and relatives at a school across the street where the cries and
wails of relatives could be heard outside. Then, the bodies were
moved to a hospital morgue.
   After viewing the bodies, Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> called the scene
``graphic and sad.''
   <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said a vacate order was issued in <DATE>November 1988</DATE> because
the club lacked a proper sprinkler system, exits, emergency
lighting and signs.
   City records show the club was again ordered closed on <DATE>Nov. 1,
1989</DATE>, by the <ORGANIZATION>Buildings Department</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said.
   ``I don't know what subsequent visits were made there,'' the
mayor said.
   The club had no liquor or cabaret license.
   Two neighborhood residents said three gunshots were heard just
before the fire. <PERSON>Robert Ungar</PERSON>, deputy fire commissioner, said he
could not confirm another report that cans of accelerant were found.
   So-called ``social clubs'' proliferate in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s poor
neighborhoods, and despite their name many of them admit virtually
anyone who wants to enter, functioning essentially as unlicensed
taverns or dance clubs.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> police officials have estimated that alcohol is sold
without a license at more than 200 locations.
   Authorities said the victims tried to escape the windowless club
down a stairway just wide enough for one person. A second stairway
apparently wasn't used, perhaps because it couldn't be reached from
the club.
   Sixty-nine of the victims died upstairs, where the dance floor
was located.
   ``People were screaming; they were all burned,'' said <PERSON>Rosemary
Green</PERSON>, who found the club on fire when she arrived to meet her
sister-in-law and cousin. ``Once you got in the entrance there was
no way to get out.''
   <PERSON>Denise Garcia</PERSON>, 20, a filing clerk who lives in the neighborhood,
said she and her friends avoided the club because they considered
it ``too sleazy.'' The building was rickety and the dance floor
sometimes trembled, she said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Garcia</PERSON> said the club's patrons included many illegal
immigrants.
   The tragedy occurred on the 79th anniversary of the <ORGANIZATION>Triangle
Shirtwaist Co.</ORGANIZATION> fire in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, which killed 145 people, most of
them immigrant garment workers, and led to reforms governing
workplace safety.
   EMS Lt. <PERSON>Roy David</PERSON> said he got to the scene just as the male
survivor was staggering out.
   ``He walked toward me. He couldn't talk. He couldn't say
anything. All we could do was treat him,'' <PERSON>David</PERSON> said.
   Five firefighters, including a battalion chief who broke his
leg, were taken to <LOCATION>Jacobi</LOCATION> after inhaling smoke. Six other
firefighters were treated at the scene for smoke inhalation.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0926EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-SocialClubFire 7thLd-Writethru a0641 03-25 0781</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Social Club Fire, 7th Ld - Writethru, a0641,0802</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>New York City Social Club Fire Kills At Least 87</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with new quotes, injured man described as
'lone survivor,' adds background on previous fires, clarifies that
it was worst fire in continental U.S., since Puerto Rico, site of
1986 fire that killed 96, is U.S. territory. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VERENA DOBNIK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A suspicious fire swept through a jam-packed,
illegal social club for Latin immigrants in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> early <DATE>Sunday</DATE>,
killing at least 87 people, fire officials said.
   The fire, the worst in the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in 13
years, was reported at the <ORGANIZATION>Happy Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION> near the <LOCATION>Bronx
Zoo</LOCATION> at <TIME>3:41 a.m.</TIME> and quickly spread through the two-story brick
building. Authorities and witnesses said the panic-stricken victims
were trapped and only one man apparently managed to escape,
severely burned.
   ``This is the worst thing I have seen in my career. It hurt my
stomach. It was sickening,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Emergency Medical Services</ORGANIZATION>
specialist <PERSON>Christopher McCarthy</PERSON>.
   ``Most of the bodies were in dance clothes,'' he said. ``They
were out to have fun. ... I saw wall-to-wall bodies _ an indication
of mass confusion and panic.''
   The blaze was brought under control by <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME>, said a fire
department spokesman, <PERSON>Lee Rodriguez</PERSON>.
   Officials said the fire's rapid spread suggested an accelerant
was used. ``That heavy volume of fire immediately arouses
suspicion,'' said Assistant Fire Chief <PERSON>Robert Ungar</PERSON>.
   One witness heard what sounded like gunshots before the fire.
But <PERSON>Unger</PERSON> would not comment on reports that there was a fight
before the fire broke out or that gasoline cans were found at the
scene.
   EMS Lt. <PERSON>Roy David</PERSON> said he got to the scene just a man believed
to be the lone survivor, apparently the club's disc jockey, was
staggering out.
   ``He walked toward me,'' <PERSON>David</PERSON> said. ``He couldn't talk. He
couldn't say anything. All we could do was treat him.''
   Another witness, <PERSON>Victor Perry</PERSON>, said: ``There were no people
coming out. The <ORGANIZATION>DJ</ORGANIZATION>'s clothes were stuck to his burnt skin which was
coming off.''
   The building received an eviction notice in <DATE>January</DATE> because of
improper exits, and was in the process of being condemned, said
Building Commissioner <PERSON>Charles Smith</PERSON>.
   ``The sad part of it is that this did not have to happen,'' said
Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON>, who visited the scene a few hours after the
fire. Many of an estimateed 700 similar clubs operating in <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION> may be unsafe, and are being investigated, he said.
   A fire at another <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> social club killed 25 people on <DATE>Oct. 24,
1976</DATE>.
   Ungar put the death toll at 87 or 88 people. A makeshift morgue
was set up in the building next door, and relatives gathered at the
scene. Authorities said the victims were mostly Latin immigrants,
primarily Hondurans.
   <PERSON>Lynn Schulman</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>EMS</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman, said most of the victims died
from smoke inhalation, but added, ``Some people were trampled.''
   She said the survivor was a 25-year-old man who suffered
second-and third-degree burns on his arms and legs and was taken to
<ORGANIZATION>Jacobi Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in guarded condition.
   Five firefighters, including a battalion chief who broke his
leg, were taken to <ORGANIZATION>Jacobi Hospital</ORGANIZATION> after inhaling smoke and at
least six other firefighters were treated for minor smoke
inhalation at the scene, she said.
   <PERSON>Perry</PERSON> said three sounds like gunshots were heard just prior to
the fire in the building that housed the club, which was only 20
feet by 50 feet.
   <PERSON>Rosemary Green</PERSON>, whose sister-in-law and cousin were at the club,
said she and other people were coming from a neighborhood birthday
party and going to club when she encountered the scene.
   ``People were screaming. They were all burned. ... We're looking
for friends and relatives and nobody's telling us anything,'' she
said. ``Once you got in the entrance there was no way to get out.''
   The building housed a group that organized children's baseball
as well as adult socializing, said <PERSON>Lillian Rivera</PERSON>, a neighbor who
lives across the street from the club.
   At least 30 firefighters from six companies were called to the
scene, <PERSON>Rodriguez</PERSON> said.
   The fire was the deadliest in the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
since a <DATE>May 28, 1977</DATE>, blaze that consumed the <ORGANIZATION>Beverly Hills Supper
Club</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Southgate</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>, killing 164 people. A <DATE>Dec. 31, 1986</DATE>, fire
at a hotel in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth, killed 96
people.
   <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire occurred on the 79th anniversary of one of <LOCATION>New
York City</LOCATION>'s worst fires, the <ORGANIZATION>Triangle Shirtwaist Co.</ORGANIZATION> blaze that
killed 145 people, most of them immigrant workers. The fire led to
reforms governing safety of the workplace.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900329-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-29-90 2230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SocialClubFire 1stLd-Writethru a0680 03-29 0733</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Social Club Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0680,0752</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Lawsuit Filed in Fire That Killed 87</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS in 8 grafs with lawsuit filed; pick up 5th graf, `Julio
Gonzalez ...'. SUBS 11th graf pvs, `The building ...', with 4 grafs
to UPDATE with Dinkins aide's involvement with illegal
establishment; pick up 12th graf pvs, `The city has ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LARRY NEUMEISTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The mother of one of the 87 people killed in a
fire at an illegal social club filed a <MONEY>$510 million</MONEY> lawsuit
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the first stemming from the inferno, an attorney said.
   The lawsuit seeks that amount in damages from the owners,
lessees and proprietors of the <ORGANIZATION>Happy Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>.
It also names the man charged with setting the fire.
   Attorney <PERSON>Harry Lipsig</PERSON> said he filed the lawsuit in <ORGANIZATION>Bronx state
Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s trial-level court, on behalf of <PERSON>Jennie
Mae Danzler</PERSON>, mother of <PERSON>Natalie Danzler</PERSON>, 31.
   <PERSON>Lipsig</PERSON> said he also notified city officials he planned to sue
the city ``because of its reckless conduct in connection with the
club.''
   Earlier <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, angry <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> members pressed top city
officials about how Happy Land could have remained open despite
repeated warnings that such clubs were catastrophes waiting to
happen.
   ``If you don't learn from the past you're condemned to repeat
its mistakes,'' council member <PERSON>Sheldon S. Leffler</PERSON> said as he
questioned Police Commissioner <PERSON>Lee Brown</PERSON> at a meeting of the
council's <ORGANIZATION>Public Safety Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We all bear the blame,'' <ORGANIZATION>Bronx Borough</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Fernando
Ferrer</PERSON> said outside the meeting. ``We've got to keep the heat on
until we can resolve this problem.''
   The fire occurred early <DATE>Sunday</DATE> as the club's patrons, many of
them Honduran immigrants, danced and drank liquor in a building
that lacked a liquor license and violated much of the fire code.
   <PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON>, 36, was charged with 87 counts of felony murder,
87 counts of murder through depraved indifference and one count of
attempted murder and arson. Police said he had argued with his
former girlfriend, a worker at the club.
   The <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> itself has come under criticism since the fire
because a bill that would have increased penalties for operating
clubs illegally was allowed to die in committee.
   But on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, council members criticized fire and building
officials over enforcement of existing laws.
   Several council members said they were surprised to learn that
laws giving the city authority to ``seal'' premises were
interpreted as meaning only that a notice could be posted on the
door.
   During several hours of testimony, city officials insisted a
crackdown on unlicensed social clubs was more than a paper threat.
<PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said eight clubs were closed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and 15 on
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by a beefed-up task force of police, fire and buildings
inspectors.
   One establishment ordered closed last year and again <DATE>Monday</DATE> was
<ORGANIZATION>El Caney</ORGANIZATION>, whose board of directors included Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON>'
Hispanic affairs commissioner, <PERSON>William Nieves</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Daily News</ORGANIZATION>
disclosed <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> defended his aide at a news conference <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, saying
the <LOCATION>East Harlem</LOCATION> establishment was a non-profit cultural and
educational center, not a commercial social club.
   But he acknowledged that fire and building inspectors found the
building had faulty fire doors and should have been closed. He said
<PERSON>Nieves</PERSON> had resigned from the establishment's board of directors
before taking the city post.
   The building housing Happy Land was owned by real estate
developer <PERSON>Alex DiLorenzo</PERSON> and leased to a group called <ORGANIZATION>One Peach
Associates</ORGANIZATION>, which is partly owned by <PERSON>Jay Weiss</PERSON>, husband of actress
<PERSON>Kathleen Turner</PERSON>. One Peach sublet the building for <MONEY>$1,950</MONEY> a month
to club proprieter <PERSON>Elias Colon</PERSON>, who died in the fire.
   The city has been trying since <DATE>1988</DATE> to close another illegal
Bronx social club in a building owned by <ORGANIZATION>DiLorenzo</ORGANIZATION> and leased by
<PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> and his partner in <LOCATION>One Peach</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Morris Jaffe</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>New York Newsday</ORGANIZATION>
reported.
   Weiss's attorneys have said they never were formally notified of
the violations the city found at Happy Land.
   DiLorenzo is the landlord for two other illegal clubs ordered
closed <DATE>Nov. 20, 1988</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>The Daily News</ORGANIZATION> reported. Those clubs were
ordered shut again this week.
   Separately, <PERSON>DiLorenzo</PERSON> has been accused of 1,585 violations in
four <LOCATION>Harlem</LOCATION> apartment buildings he owned, 150 of them for
conditions considered imminently dangerous, the News said.
   DiLorenzo's attorney, <PERSON>Mark Friedlander</PERSON>, did not immediately
return a telephone call to his office <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900326-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-26-90 1833EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SocialClubs-Enforcement     03-26 0893</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Social Clubs-Enforcement,0916</SECOND>
<HEAD>Social Club Fire: Cruel Incarnation of a Familiar Nightmare</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Social Club Fire, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GARY LANGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire raced through a <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> social club, snuffing
out lives in a rush of flame and toxic smoke. The mayor, horrified
at the carnage, formed a task force to close down the city's
illegal nightspots.
   That was a year and a half ago.
   <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the nightmare returned in an even crueler incarnation.
Instead of six people, 87 were now dead in a crowded club. The
city's crackdown had failed. And given continued failure, experts
said <DATE>Monday</DATE>, many more may die.
   ``These places are fire traps. They're supermarkets of crime.
They're in violation of every code imaginable,'' said state <PERSON>Sen.
Jeremy Weinstein</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> Democrat who led an investigation of
illegal social clubs in <DATE>1981</DATE>.
   ``It's not just the city of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, it's true for every city
in the country,'' he said in an interview. ``It's something every
urban area has had to deal with in the last decade. And none has
been dealing with it.''
   Indeed, despite a renewed crackdown announced <DATE>Monday</DATE>. ``It
wouldn't shock me if this happened again,'' said <PERSON>Charles Ryan</PERSON>, an
ex-fire captain and now fire science department chairman at <ORGANIZATION>John
Jay College of Criminal Justice</ORGANIZATION>. ``These places reopen as fast as
they shut 'em down.''
   The problem is not a new one. In <DATE>1942</DATE>, 491 people lost their
lives at <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Cocoanut Grove</LOCATION> club in the nation's worst fire
ever. Like the <ORGANIZATION>Happy Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION>, site of <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire, the
<LOCATION>Cocoanut Grove</LOCATION> was overcrowded at the time of the blaze and lacked
adequate exits for patrons.
   That fire led to new national fire codes for emergency exits,
lighting and other factors that could contribute to a blaze.
   Ryan and others said the simple problem is in enforcing such
laws. But it also is more complex than that, they said _ a
combination of the city's enormous problems, shrinking budget and
paralyzing bureaucracy.
   And there is another, equally daunting factor: Tremendous demand
for the illegal but inexpensive clubs, particularly in poor
immigrant communities where life is difficult, diversions are
scarce and danger is a commonplace.
   ``People who are living in tough conditions of life are going to
look for opportunities to blow off some steam,'' said Prof. <PERSON>William
Kornblum</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Social Research Center</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>City
University of New York</ORGANIZATION>'s graduate school. ``They're going to pay
less attention to the dangers around them.''
   The hazards can be legion. At the Happy Land club, authorities
say there was no open fire exit, no first-floor sprinkler system,
no proper emergency lights, and bars on the sole window.
   The only way out was through the front door. It was blocked by
flames, allegedly ignited by an arsonist. Sixty-one men and 26
women died.
   The deaths are all the more tragic for the city's failed effort
to shut down the Happy Land. The task force formed by Mayor <PERSON>Edward
I. Koch</PERSON> in <DATE>1988</DATE> won an order that year that it be closed.
Apparently it was, for a time. And at some point, unknown to the
authorities, it reopened.
   ``Most horrifying is that this should never have happened,''
said Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON>. ``That club had been inspected. It had
been cited. And it had been ordered closed.'' He immediately
launched another crackdown, with police posting vacate orders on
187 social clubs <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   But those orders don't solve the problem. Said Ryan: ``Issuing a
piece of paper and saying, `You're closed' doesn't mean anything
unless you come around and whack the guy on the head.''
   With 2,031 inspections by the task force last year,
identification of illegal clubs has been adequate, <PERSON>Ryan</PERSON> said.
``It's the follow-up that's weak,'' he said. ``That's the nut of
the problem: inadequate enforcement.''
   Fuller enforcement would require substantial manpower. The
police estimate there are 1,220 social clubs in the city, with
about 1,000 listed as inactive. But Happy Land was one of those
``inactive'' clubs.
   Kornblum guessed the city in fact has 500 to 600 operating
social clubs _ some legal, many not _ with more in nearby suburbs.
   ``It is true that complete enforcement is futile. The clubs are
always moving to new locations, always trying to stay a step or two
ahead of the authorities,'' <PERSON>Kornblum</PERSON> said. But he said aggressive
followup could save lives, if the city provided the resources.
   There are other approaches as well. With a view of social clubs
as cultural centers, <PERSON>Kornblum</PERSON> suggested low-interest city loans for
legally operated clubs that could take the place of illegal dives.
   Ryan, for his part, suggested cracking down on the liquor
merchants who keep the clubs supplied, and possibly placing a legal
limit on retail liquor sales. <PERSON>Weinstein</PERSON> said he would investigate
the idea.
   Yet <PERSON>Weinstein</PERSON> noted that little of this is new. In <DATE>1981</DATE>, his
panel's report on illegal social clubs included this warning: ``The
potential fire hazard alone is of such proportion that numerous
lives could be lost at any time no matter how minor the fire was at
the outset.''
   ``How ironic that after so many years, we're still back where we
started,'' he said. ``Now a lot of people are going to be up in
arms over this. And then, eventually, it's going to fade _ until it
happens again.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900330-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-30-90 0756EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SocialClubFire     03-30 0557</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Social Club Fire,0569</SECOND>
<HEAD>$510 Million Lawsuit Filed In Wake Of Social Club Fire</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY NEUMEISTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An illegal social club served alcohol without a
license to an already-drunk man who is accused of killing 87 people
when he torched the place, a <MONEY>$510 million</MONEY> lawsuit says.
   The lawsuit was filed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> as relatives and friends of
victims held funerals and wakes, and as the accused, <PERSON>Julio
Gonzalez</PERSON>, appeared in <ORGANIZATION>Bronx Criminal Court</ORGANIZATION> for a hearing.
   About 1,000 mourners gathered <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> outside <PERSON>Ortiz</PERSON>
Funeral Home in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> for the wakes of six victims of the <ORGANIZATION>Happy
Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION> fire.
   ``We want justice,'' said <PERSON>Edith Melendez</PERSON>, the girlfriend of <PERSON>Luis
Drummond</PERSON>, who died in the fire <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. ``Give him (Gonzalez) to us.
We could take him to the park, pour some gasoline on him like he
did to our family and friends.''
   The suit was filed in <ORGANIZATION>Bronx state Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s
trial-level court, by attorney <PERSON>Harry Lipsig</PERSON> on behalf of <PERSON>Jennie Mae
Danzler</PERSON>, mother of another fire victim, 31-year-old <PERSON>Natalie Danzler</PERSON>.
   The suit names as defendants the social club itself; <ORGANIZATION>Clarendon
Place Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, owner of the premises; <ORGANIZATION>Little Peach Realty</ORGANIZATION>, lessee;
<PERSON>Alex DiLorenzo III</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jay Weiss</PERSON> and <PERSON>Morris Jaffe</PERSON>, officers of <LOCATION>Little
Peach</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Elena Colon</PERSON>, widow of club owner <PERSON>Elias Colon</PERSON>, who died in
the fire; and <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON>. <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> is the husband of actress <PERSON>Kathleen
Turner</PERSON>.
million</MONEY> in punitive damages. It claims, among other things, that
Happy Land served alcohol without a license and served it to
<PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> when he already was intoxicated.
   Authorities <DATE>Thursday</DATE> continued to crack down on illegal social
clubs, with more than 100 police officers transferred from the
<ORGANIZATION>Tactical Narcotics Teams</ORGANIZATION> to a reactivated <ORGANIZATION>Social Club Task Force</ORGANIZATION>.
The force has visited hundreds of social clubs citywide since
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire, closing about two dozen and issuing citations.
   Meanwhile, Criminal Court <PERSON>Judge Effrain Alvarado</PERSON> ruled <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
at hearing over legal representation of <PERSON>Gonzales</PERSON> that the Legal Aid
Society may continue as his counsel through the grand jury process.
But the judge appointed lawyer <PERSON>Richard Berne</PERSON> to take over the case
after that.
   Security was tight during the hearing. At one point, a man
yelled, ``Julio, I'm going to watch you.'' The man was a friend of
one of the fire victims.
   Gonzalez, a 36-year-old Cuban emigre, was arrested <DATE>Sunday</DATE> and
charged with 87 counts of murder through depraved indifference, 87
counts of felony murder, and one count of attempted murder and
arson. He allegedly set the fire after a fight with his
ex-girlfriend, who worked at the club.
   Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> contested a published report
that his director of <ORGANIZATION>Latino Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>William Nieves</PERSON>, had operated
an illegal social club.
   <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said the establishment, called <ORGANIZATION>El Caney</ORGANIZATION>, was really a
cultural center. He acknowledged the site had been cited for
building and fire code violations and should have been closed.
   Members of the <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> grilled top city officials about the
fire <DATE>Thursday</DATE> during a meeting of the council's <ORGANIZATION>Public Safety
Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   They demanded to know why Happy Land was not padlocked after the
city discovered it was operating illegally and unsafely. Fire and
buildings department officials said the law was unclear whether a
building could be padlocked without a hearing.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900327-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-27-90 1617EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Clubs-OtherCities     03-27 0362</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Clubs-Other Cities,0372</SECOND>
<HEAD>Other Cities Act to Prevent Social Club Tragedy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Social Club Fire, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and several <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> cities have begun cracking down
on illegal social clubs like <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s Happy Land, the firetrap
where 87 people died in a gasoline-fed blaze.
   Officials in many cities around the nation say they don't have
such clubs, which typically operate without licenses and stay open
after hours. But in those cities that do, <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire sent a
cautionary message.
   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> he was conferring
with the <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> speaker about legislation to regulate the
clubs, including stiffer penalties for violations.
   <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> acknowledged that social clubs are useful as ethnic
meeting places, but he had a message for patrons: ``I would tell
them to tell the management they're not going to frequent them
again until they make them safe again.''
   In <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, Building Commissioner <PERSON>Daniel Weil</PERSON> said city
officials are inspecting at least 100 registered non-profit social
clubs, and will be trying to locate any unlicensed clubs in hopes
of preventing a tragedy like the Happy Land fire.
   ``When a tragedy like this occurs, you don't want to ignore
it,'' <PERSON>Weil</PERSON> said.
   There was similar concern in several <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> cities.
   In <LOCATION>Elizabeth</LOCATION>, Mayor <PERSON>Thomas G. Dunn</PERSON> said city inspectors would
put at least seven illegal nightclubs out of business as a result
of the Happy Land fire. Two owners of one club were arrested <DATE>Monday</DATE>
and about 100 patrons chased from the place, he said.
   In <LOCATION>Paterson</LOCATION>, vice squad Sgt. <PERSON>Michael Recca</PERSON> said three or four
such establishments have been shut down in the last month.
   ``Generally the violations involve illegal alcoholic beverage
sales and with that we find a high incidence of drug sales between
patrons,'' he said.
   In <LOCATION>Camden</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Cyrus Saxon</PERSON>, the city's alcoholic beverage control
investigator, is seeking inspections of unlicensed social clubs in
the city. <PERSON>Saxon</PERSON> said most of the night-spots do not have liquor
licenses, but serve alcohol and cater to a dancing crowd.
   ``The problem is you don't really know,'' said <PERSON>Saxon</PERSON>. ``You
don't know if these places have enough exits or fire escapes.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900329-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-29-90 0557EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SocialClubFire     03-29 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Social Club Fire,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mourners Pay Respects to Happy Land Victims</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAUL REYES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sobs and cries from hundreds of mourners rang
out at a Roman Catholic church as the caskets of 17 victims from
the <ORGANIZATION>Happy Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION> fire were arrayed in the form of a large
crucifix.
   One pink coffin for a female victim and 16 blue coffins for
males were carried <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> from the <ORGANIZATION>Rivera Funeral Home</ORGANIZATION> in the
<LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> across the street from <LOCATION>St. Joseph</LOCATION>'s church.
   The dead were among 87 people, most of them Honduran immigrants,
who perished <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in the illegal social club that was allegedly
set afire by a spurned lover. It was the city's worst fire in 79
years.
   ``God never, never abandons us. Sudden death is also sudden
mercy,'' the Rev. <PERSON>Henry Hill</PERSON> told more than 1,000 mourners packed
inside the church.
   ``My heart goes out to each and every family,'' said Hill, a
Honduran native. ``The church understands your loss and extends its
sympathies and love.''
   Another 1,000 people unable to fit in the church huddled outside
on the street, about 10 blocks from the scene of the fire.
   The Honduran government declared three days of national mourning
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and said 78 victims had been identified as Honduran. Most
of the bodies will be buried in <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>.
   But relatives who are illegally in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> may not be
able to return if they travel to <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION> to attend burial services.
   Before the Mass, hundreds of mourners prayed in the funeral home
and then stood in the street. At least three women fainted and more
than 15 required medical attention.
   <PERSON>Jose Alvarez</PERSON>, who came for the wake of his brother <PERSON>Denny</PERSON>, 22,
left the funeral home sobbing and clinging to a cousin and friend.
   Across the street on the church steps, <PERSON>Denny</PERSON>'s father, <LOCATION>Pedro</LOCATION>,
railed against the man charged with setting the blaze, 36-year-old
Cuban emigrant <PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON>.
   ``They ought to take him and give him a public hanging. People
like that don't deserve to live,'' <PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON> said.
   Roses and daffodils in vases and coffee cans were placed in
front of the the smoke-blackened red brick social club. Burned
coats, some still on hangers, lay piled against the building. A
paper sign on a tree listed the victims' names and ages.
   Nearby, family members went to a school to collect their
relatives' personal effects.
   <PERSON>Carlos Pena</PERSON> clutched a manila envelope which held a watch, keys,
and some cash his brother <PERSON>Eli</PERSON>, 26, had when he died at the club.
   The watch arrived with <ORGANIZATION>Eli</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Carlos</PERSON> said the
timepiece would now be his. ``It means a lot, a reminder,'' he said.
   The wake at the funeral home began three hours after a <ORGANIZATION>Bronx
Civil Court</ORGANIZATION> refused to let the landlord of the social club reclaim
the establishment until it decides whether the late tenant's widow
should replace her husband in an eviction suit.
   The hearing, scheduled before the blaze <DATE>Sunday</DATE> whose victims
included club proprietor <PERSON>Elias Colon</PERSON>, did not delve into
responsibility for the tragedy. It only dealt with the demand of
the building's landlord, <ORGANIZATION>One Peach Associates</ORGANIZATION>, for <ORGANIZATION>Colon</ORGANIZATION>'s eviction
for failing to pay rent.
   Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> said legislation would be submitted today to
<ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> that would impose heavy penalties on landlords and
operators of illegal social clubs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2017EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SocialClubFire     04-01 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Social Club Fire,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: City Owns At Least 52 Buildings Housing Clubs</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Realty Reality, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 52 drinking and dancing clubs listed by
the city as ``nuisances'' are on city-owned properties, making
government the biggest landlord of the illegal establishments,
according to published reports.
   A crackdown began after 87 people died <DATE>March 25</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Happy
Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION>, an illegal social club in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>, in an arson
fire that was the deadliest blaze in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> since <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   The bodies of 48 of the victims were flown <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Kennedy
International Airport</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION> aboard a DC-8 chartered by the
<ORGANIZATION>American Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>. In all, 79 of the victims were believed to be
Hondurans.
   ``Most of them went to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> with high hopes, and
they came back dead. We are very sad,'' said Honduran President
<PERSON>Rafael Leonardo Callejas</PERSON>, who went to <LOCATION>San Pedro Sulla</LOCATION> to be with
dozens of grieving relatives.
   A grand jury on <DATE>Friday</DATE> indicted 36-year-old Cuban immigrant
<PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON> on charges of murder, arson, attempted murder and
assault. He is accused of starting the fire with gasoline after
being rejected by a former girlfriend who worked at the club.
   In the latest citywide social club sweep from <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> to
early <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Social Club Task Force</ORGANIZATION> members visited 356 clubs and
found 122 of them open, said police Sgt. <PERSON>Diane Kubler</PERSON>. They issued
54 vacate orders, 132 summonses and 193 notices of violation. One
person was arrested.
   Clubs such as the <ORGANIZATION>Wanda Social Club</ORGANIZATION>, which was slapped with a
vacate order <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, are a particular embarassment to the
city. The city is the landlord.
   The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION>, citing police records, reported <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that
52 of the 1,255 clubs listed as ``nuisance'' establishments were in
properties owned by the city, including two in Housing Authority
projects. The records portray the city as the largest landlord of
such clubs.
   Buildings, finance and <ORGANIZATION>Department of Housing Preservation and
Development</ORGANIZATION> records indicated there were 46 to 66 social clubs in
city-owned buildings, department Commissioner <PERSON>Felice Michetti</PERSON> told
the Times.
   Department inspectors were surveying them, she said.
   City-owned residential buildings house as many as 46 illegal
clubs, the <ORGANIZATION>Daily News</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, basing its report on a review
of <ORGANIZATION>Buildings Department</ORGANIZATION> and real estate records as well as reports
from inspections by city agencies.
   The News said the number could increase as city officials check
contradictory listings of illegal clubs.
   The city inherited the clubs along with vast numbers of tenants
and abandoned buildings, said <PERSON>Lee Jones</PERSON>, a spokesman for Mayor
<PERSON>David N. Dinkins</PERSON>.
   ``Is it embarrassing?'' Jones said. ``It's something we're going
to have to deal with.''
   In the event of death or injury in a fire or other calamity, the
city might be liable in lawsuits involving such establishments, the
<ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Michetti</PERSON> said there were two grounds for city action. If the
tenant doesn't have a bona fide lease, ``we can bring an eviction
action,'' she said. Otherwise, the city can move for a vacate order
and ultimately padlock the property for violating fire and building
codes or selling alcohol without a state license.
   The city has moved against two other city-owned social club
tenants besides the <LOCATION>Wanda</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said. Authorities last week
issued a vacate order for a club in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> and closed another in
the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900327-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-27-90 0134EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Clubs-Enforcement     03-27 0783</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Clubs-Enforcement,0802</SECOND>
<HEAD>Social Club Fire: a Nightmare Foretold</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Social Club Fire, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GARY LANGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The tragedy was foretold, its prevention
attempted. But law enforcement failed customers of the <ORGANIZATION>Happy Land
Social Club</ORGANIZATION>, as experts say it is failing to protect the patrons of
other illegal nightspots.
   ``These places are fire traps. They're in violation of every
code imaginable,'' state <PERSON>Sen. Jeremy Weinstein</PERSON>, who led an
investigation of social clubs in <DATE>1981</DATE>, said <DATE>Monday</DATE>. ``It's true for
every city in the country.''
   But it is in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> that the nightmare was realized:
Eighty-seven lives snuffed out in a rush of flame and toxic smoke
early <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. The Happy Land's habitues, mainly poor immigrants,
were trapped and felled in moments.
   It should not have happened. A year and a half ago, when seven
died in a similar fire, the mayor formed a task force to close down
unlicensed clubs. Soon after, the city ordered Happy Land closed
for fire safety violations.
   It apparently did close for a time _ and then opened again,
unnoticed by officialdom. ``These places reopen as fast as they
shut 'em down,'' said <PERSON>Charles Ryan</PERSON>, an ex-fire captain and now fire
science department chairman at <ORGANIZATION>John Jay College of Criminal Justice</ORGANIZATION>.
   As a result, despite a renewed crackdown announced <DATE>Monday</DATE>, he
said, ``It wouldn't shock me if this happened again.''
   The simple problem is inadequate law enforcement, <PERSON>Ryan</PERSON> and
others said. But they also called it more complex than that _ a
combination of the city's enormous problems, shrinking budget and
paralyzing bureaucracy.
   And there is another, equally daunting factor: Tremendous demand
for the illegal but inexpensive clubs, particularly in poor
immigrant communities where life is difficult, diversions are
scarce and danger is commonplace.
   ``People who are living in tough conditions of life are going to
look for opportunities to blow off some steam,'' said Professor
<PERSON>William Kornblum</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Social Research Center</ORGANIZATION> at the
<ORGANIZATION>City University of New York</ORGANIZATION>'s graduate school. ``They're going to
pay less attention to the dangers around them.''
   The hazards can be legion. At the <ORGANIZATION>Happy Land</ORGANIZATION>, authorities say
there was no open fire exit, no first-floor sprinkler system, no
proper emergency lights, and bars on the sole window. The only way
out was through the front door, and it was blocked by flames,
allegedly ignited by an arsonist.
   The deaths are all the more tragic for the city's failed effort
to shut the Happy Land down. ``This should never have happened,''
said Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON>. ``That club had been inspected. It had
been cited. And it had been ordered closed.''
   He immediately launched another crackdown, with police posting
vacate orders on 187 social clubs <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   But vacate orders alone cannot solve the problem. ``Issuing a
piece of paper and saying, `You're closed' doesn't mean anything
unless you come around and whack the guy on the head,'' said <PERSON>Ryan</PERSON>.
   Identification of illegal clubs has been adequate, he said, with
2,031 inspections last year by the task force formed in <DATE>1988</DATE> by
then-Mayor <PERSON>Edward I. Koch</PERSON>. ``It's the follow-up that's weak,'' <PERSON>Ryan</PERSON>
said. ``That's the nut of the problem: inadequate enforcement.''
   Better enforcement would require more manpower. The police
estimate there are 1,220 social clubs in the city, with about 1,000
listed as inactive. But Happy Land was one of those ``inactive''
clubs, and <PERSON>Kornblum</PERSON> guessed the city in fact has 500 to 600
operating social clubs _ some legal, many not.
   ``It is true that complete enforcement is futile. The clubs are
always moving to new locations, always trying to stay a step or two
ahead of the authorities,'' <PERSON>Kornblum</PERSON> said. But he said aggressive
followup could save lives, if the city provided the resources.
   There are other approaches, as well. With a view of social clubs
as cultural centers, <PERSON>Kornblum</PERSON> suggested low-interest city loans for
legally operated clubs that could take the place of illegal dives.
   Ryan, for his part, suggested cracking down on the liquor
merchants who keep the clubs supplied, and possibly placing a legal
limit on retail liquor sales. <PERSON>Weinstein</PERSON> said he would investigate
the idea.
   Yet <PERSON>Weinstein</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> Democrat, noted that little of this is
new. In <DATE>1981</DATE>, his panel's report on illegal social clubs included
this warning, ``The potential fire hazard alone is of such
proportion that numerous lives could be lost at any time no matter
how minor the fire was at the outset.''
   ``How ironic that after so many years, we're still back where we
started,'' he said. ``Now a lot of people are going to be up in
arms over this. And then, eventually, it's going to fade _ until it
happens again.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900327-0156 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-27-90 1846EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SocialClubFire 1stLd-Writethru a0699 03-27 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Social Club Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0699,0739</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prosecutors Probe Ownership of Club Where 87 Died</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RECASTS lead; SUBS 4th graf, `Gonzalez allegedly ...,' to
DELETE incorrect reference to `no fire sprinklers.' SUBS last graf
to CORRECT number of other survivors to four, sted three.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY20,21</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAYNER PIKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prosecutors on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> investigated the tangled
ownership of the <ORGANIZATION>Happy Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION> to determine whether the
landlords, including actress <PERSON>Kathleen Turner</PERSON>'s husband, share
responsibility in the fiery deaths of 87 people.
   The district attorney's office also said a grand jury had begun
hearing evidence against <PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON>, a 36-year-old Cuban emigre
who reportedly confessed to setting the fire at the illegal
discotheque early <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   ``We'll have a made case even if he backs out of the
confession,'' said <PERSON>Edward McCarthy</PERSON>, spokesman for the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>
prosecutor's office.
   Gonzalez allegedly bought <MONEY>$1</MONEY> worth of gasoline and ignited it in
the doorway to the two-story unlicensed club after a fight with his
ex-girlfriend, who worked there. The club had no emergency exits
and no second-story windows; the victims had neither the time nor
the means to escape.
   The building that housed the club was leased to Happy Land's
operator by <PERSON>Miss Turner</PERSON>'s husband, <PERSON>Jay Weiss</PERSON>, who in turn had
leased it from one of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s major real estate operators, <PERSON>Alex
DiLorenzo III</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>McCarthy</PERSON> said the issue of landlord responsibility wasn't clear.
Prosecutors still had to determine whether anyone beyond the club
operator, <PERSON>Elias Colon</PERSON>, who died in the fire, knew the building had
been served with notices of building code violations.
   <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON>, through a statement by his lawyer, <PERSON>Roger Boyle</PERSON>,
acknowledged that <ORGANIZATION>Little Peach Realty</ORGANIZATION>, a company he owns with
<PERSON>Morris Jaffe</PERSON>, leased the building in <DATE>1985</DATE> from a DiLorenzo company,
<ORGANIZATION>Clarendon Place Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   Two years later, Little Peach leased the club to <LOCATION>Colon</LOCATION>, but
<PERSON>Boyle</PERSON> said that since last <DATE>spring</DATE> the company had been trying to
evict Colon for not paying rent. The case was to have been heard in
court <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Boyle</PERSON> said <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> would have no further statement.
   Miss <PERSON>Turner</PERSON> said through her publicist, <PERSON>Susan Geller</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>: ``This is an act of a violent madman. It's a tragedy. It
doesn't reflect on me or my husband.''
   Miss <ORGANIZATION>Turner</ORGANIZATION> is in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> starring in a Broadway revival of
``Cat on a Hot Tin Roof.''
   According to Assistant Fire Chief <PERSON>William Feehan</PERSON>, inspectors are
supposed to serve notices of code violations on the responsible
person at the scene and not necessarily to building owners.
   The Happy Land tragedy spurred Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> to reactivate
a police, fire and buildings department task force formed in the
wake of another fatal club fire.
   Fire <ORGANIZATION>Department</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>John Mulligan</PERSON> said the agency received
nearly 1,000 calls <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the first day of operating a special
number for reports of illegal social clubs.
   <PERSON>Mulligan</PERSON> said the names and addresses of some 500 clubs were
divulged.
   ``The department is elated,'' <PERSON>Mulligan</PERSON> said. ``It shows the
public is aware of the problem now and there's not much you can do
about it unless the public gets involved.''
   The man charged with 87 counts of murder, <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON>, remained in
the prison ward of <ORGANIZATION>Kings County Hospital</ORGANIZATION>, awaiting his next court
appearance.
   According to District Attorney <PERSON>Robert Johnson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> made
admissions to people he had spoken to after early <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fire.
The district attorney said <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> gave police a videotaped
confession later in the day in which he admitted he torched the
Happy Land with gasoline in a fit of pique against his former
girlfriend, <PERSON>Lydia Feliciano</PERSON>, who worked at the club.
   ``We're going to put on (the witness stand) the girlfriend, the
guy that sold him the gasoline, the two guys he talked to _ the
neighbors _ at his house,'' <PERSON>McCarthy</PERSON> said.
   ``And then we have the container that held the gasoline, his
sneakers, which were soaked with gasoline. We even cut up a hunk of
the floor and brought it in to prove the burn pattern was caused by
gasoline.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON> escaped the fire without serious injury. One of
the four other survivors, club disc jockey <PERSON>Ruben Valladarez</PERSON>, was in
critical but stable condition at <ORGANIZATION>Jacobi Hospital</ORGANIZATION> with burns over <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT> of this body. Hospital spokeswoman <PERSON>Vicki Ciampa</PERSON> said he had
about a 50-50 chance of survival.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900328-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-28-90 1022EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SocialClubFire 3rdLd-Writethru a0507 03-28 0796</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Social Club Fire, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0507,0815</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prosecutors Build Case Against Suspect, Investigate Building
Ownership</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 9-10, `It's unfortunate...', with three grafs to
ADD attribution on quote and Turner's comment through publicist.
Picks up 11th graf, `Among those...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAYNER PIKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prosecutors intend to use a pair of
gasoline-soaked sneakers and a hunk of dance floor to help make
their case against a man charged with setting the fire that killed
87 people in a social club.
   A grand jury <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> began hearing evidence against 36-year-old
<PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON>, charged with 87 murders in the blaze at the <ORGANIZATION>Happy
Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>. Police said he set the fire early
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> after being snubbed by an ex-girlfriend who worked there.
   ``We'll have a made case even if he backs out of the
confession,'' said <PERSON>Edward McCarthy</PERSON>, spokesman for the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>
prosecutor's office.
   Gonzalez was transferred <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to a prison unit within the
psychiatric ward at <ORGANIZATION>Bellevue Hospital</ORGANIZATION>, where a fellow inmate said
he raged for hours against his ex-girlfriend.
   ``He is so emotionally distraught that tears keep coming down,''
the inmate, <PERSON>Louis Cuascut</PERSON>, said in today's <LOCATION>New York Post</LOCATION>. ``He
seems very, very depressed.''
   The Happy Land club had been ordered closed for fire and safety
code violations and the landlord was trying to evict the owner for
non-payment of rent.
   The building that housed the illegal club was subleased to the
club's operator by a company co-owned by actress <PERSON>Kathleen Turner</PERSON>'s
husband, <PERSON>Jay Weiss</PERSON>. He leased it from one of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s biggest
landlords, <PERSON>Alex DiLorenzo III</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Turner</PERSON> said she was shocked by the fire but that her husband
wasn't to blame.
   ``It's unfortunate that it was that building but the fact is
that you can even throw a firebomb into <ORGANIZATION>McDonald's</ORGANIZATION> and it would
have had the same result,'' <PERSON>Turner</PERSON> said outside her <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>
apartment, the <ORGANIZATION>Post</ORGANIZATION> reported today.
   The actress, starring in a Broadway revival of ``Cat on a Hot
Tin Roof,'' said she was afraid that people would come to her home
seeking vengeance.
   Turner also said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> through her publicist, ``This is an act
of a violent madman. It's a tragedy. It doesn't reflect on me or my
husband.''
   Among those scheduled to testify against <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> are his
ex-girlfriend, <PERSON>Lydia Feliciano</PERSON>, a worker at the club; and the man
who sold <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> the <MONEY>$1</MONEY> worth of gasoline he allegedly used to
start the blaze.
   ``And then we have the container that held the gasoline, his
sneakers, which were soaked with gasoline,'' <PERSON>McCarthy</PERSON> said. ``We
even cut up a hunk of the floor and brought it in to prove the burn
pattern was caused by gasoline.''
   District Attorney <PERSON>Robert Johnson</PERSON> said <PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON> gave police a
videotaped statement in which he admitted that he torched the Happy
Land in a pique against <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON>.
   Besides <PERSON>Ms. Feliciano</PERSON>, four other people escaped the inferno.
   Authorities had warned <PERSON>DiLorenzo</PERSON> that Happy Land was riddled
with violations, including an illegally added second floor, no
sprinklers on the first floor, no second exit and no fire alarms,
Building Commissioner <PERSON>Charles Smith Jr.</PERSON> said in today's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
Times.
   Normally the violations report would have been forwarded by the
owner to the leaseholder, but <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON>' attorneys said they never
received a formal notice of the violations. They would not comment
on whether they knew of them.
   <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON>, through his lawyer <PERSON>Roger Boyle</PERSON>, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>One
Peach Associates</ORGANIZATION>, a company he owns with <PERSON>Morris Jaffe</PERSON>, leased the
building in <DATE>1985</DATE> from <PERSON>DiLorenzo</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Clarendon Place Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   One Peach two years later leased the club to its operator, <LOCATION>Elias
Colon</LOCATION>, for up to <MONEY>$1,950</MONEY> a month. <PERSON>Boyle</PERSON> said that since last <DATE>spring</DATE>
the company had been trying to evict Colon for not paying rent. The
case was to have been heard in court today. Colon died in the fire.
   One Peach also leased space to a second after-hours club, called
La Salsa, around the corner from Happy Land, for <MONEY>$2,500</MONEY> a month,
the <ORGANIZATION>Daily News</ORGANIZATION> reported today.
   Neighborhood residents said La Salsa, too, was packed with
revelers <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. The club has one door and no windows.
Because of fire code violations, it had been ordered to close in
<DATE>August 1988</DATE>.
   Because many of the fire victims were poor Honduran immigrants,
10 airlines have offered to ship the remains free from <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Larry Mackler</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>American Red
Cross</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> plans to fly next-of-kin back as well to make
funeral arrangements.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Prosecutors intend to use a pair of
gasoline-soaked sneakers and a hunk of dance floor to help make
their case against a man charged with setting the fire that killed
87 people in a social club.
   A grand jury <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> began hearing evidence against 36-year-old
<PERSON>Julio Gonzalez</PERSON>, charged with 87 murders in the blaze at the <ORGANIZATION>Happy
Land Social Club</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>. Police said he set the fire early
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> after being snubbed by an ex-girlfriend who worked there.
   ``We'll have a made case even if he backs out of the
confession,'' said <PERSON>Edward McCarthy</PERSON>, spokesman for the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>
prosecutor's office.
   Gonzalez was transferred <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to a prison unit within the
psychiatric ward at <ORGANIZATION>Bellevue Hospital</ORGANIZATION>, where a fellow inmate said
he raged for hours against his ex-girlfriend.
   ``He is so emotionally distraught that tears keep coming down,''
