<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880809-0237 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-09-88 1629EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-SouthernPacificMerger Bjt   08-09 0814</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Southern Pacific Merger, Bjt,0838</SECOND>
<HEAD>ICC OKs Rio Grande Purchase of Southern Pacific</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> received government
approval <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> for its <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> purchase of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern
Pacific Railroad</ORGANIZATION>, one of the nation's oldest rail lines with track
stretching from <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>.
   Southern <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>, which has 15,000 miles of track, will retain
its name and incorporate into its operations the smaller <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp;
Rio Grande Western Railroad</ORGANIZATION> once the purchase is completed, company
officials said.
   By a 4-0 vote, the <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION> gave approval
for the railroad's sale by its parent <ORGANIZATION>Sante Fe Southern Pacific
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, to <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries</ORGANIZATION>, a subsidiary of the Denver-based
<ORGANIZATION>Anschutz Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Philip Anschutz</PERSON>, owner of the privately held company, told
reporters he intends to concentrate on reducing <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s
debts, partly through the sale of some of its real estate holdings,
and modernize the railroad's equipment and facilities.
   ``We will be in the railroad business, first and foremost,''
said <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON>, whose background is in energy.
   <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON>, who has a reputation of being reclusive, acknowledged
that he had never before held a news conference, but he said he
wanted to meet with reporters to set to rest unfounded ``rumors,''
including one that sought the <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION> to break it up and
make a quick profit.
   ``It's very important that this company be kept together,'' he
said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Anschutz Corp.</ORGANIZATION> purchased <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries</ORGANIZATION> four years
ago.
   <PERSON>William Holtman</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries</ORGANIZATION>, expressed
confidence in <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON>'s devotion to railroading. ``He's a
long-term player,'' <PERSON>Holtman</PERSON> said of <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> said the merger of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp;
Rio Grande Western</ORGANIZATION> railroads would have the best competitive
benefits and be in the public interest. The merger was recommended
by both the <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Transportation Department</ORGANIZATION>.
   The commission last year ordered the Chicago-based <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe
Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to divest itself of either the <ORGANIZATION>Southern
Pacific</ORGANIZATION> or the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> railroads after it rejected a proposal to
merge the two rail lines. The company chose to sell the <ORGANIZATION>Southern
Pacific</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s stock has been held in a trust for nearly
five years pending the outcome of the battle over who should own
the railroad.
   ``We look forward to completing the sale, getting out of
trusteeship and moving forward again with a clear idea of <ORGANIZATION>Southern
Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s future course and direction,'' said <PERSON>Denman McNear</PERSON>,
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Transportation Co</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s management team would be
chosen from among the senior managers of both the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>
and the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern</ORGANIZATION> reached agreement with <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries</ORGANIZATION>
on the sale last <DATE>February</DATE>, but when permission for the transaction
was sought from the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>, another railroad company, <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City
Southern Industries</ORGANIZATION>, objected and asked that it be allowed to buy
the railroad.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> in a series of votes <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> turned its back on the
<LOCATION>Kansas City Southern</LOCATION> proposal. One concern of the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> was <ORGANIZATION>Kansas
City Southern</ORGANIZATION>'s financial outlook in light of a <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> court
judgment that is under appeal.
   The judgment stems from antitrust and contract violations
involving a coal-slurry pipeline project in <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Kansas
City Southern</ORGANIZATION> had argued that the judgment would not affect its
ability to finance the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> purchase.
   <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> could challenge the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> ruling in court,
Rowland</PERSON>, said no decision has been made on what the next step, if
any, would be.
   ``We're not ruling out anything,'' <PERSON>Rowland</PERSON> told reporters after
the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> vote.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, which is rich in history, operates up and
down the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> and along the southern tier of the country with
tracks stretching from <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, through central <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
and across the <LOCATION>Southwest</LOCATION> as far east as <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>. It also
operates lines from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Ogden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, where it links up
with the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western</ORGANIZATION>, and from <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> to the
<ORGANIZATION>Gulf Coast</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> runs along a central corridor from <LOCATION>Ogden</LOCATION>
to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>.
   Both railroads have been closely intertwined with the history of
the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>, helping to bring in settlers, miners and industry.
   Southern Pacific's founders helped drive the golden spike in
<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> in <DATE>1869</DATE>, linking the country's first transcontinental rail
line. Two years later, the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> ran its first train
from <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON> said the new railroad ``will operate under the banner
of <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>,'' although within the company the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio
Grande Western</ORGANIZATION> will continue to maintain its own identity.
   He said he decided to retain the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> name because
it is by far the larger of the two railroads and probably better
known. ``Last of all, I like the name,'' he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880809-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-09-88 1130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SouthernPacificMerger     08-09 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Southern Pacific Merger,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>ICC OKs Railroad's Sale</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION> today
unanimously approved the sale of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Railroad to
Rio Grande Industries</ORGANIZATION>, creating a 15,000-mile rail system that
covers 15 states from <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries</ORGANIZATION> has agreed to buy the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>
from <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> in a 4-0 vote said the merger of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>
and the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western</ORGANIZATION> railroads would have the best
competitive results and be in the public interest.
   The commission last year ordered the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to divest itself of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> after the rejection
of that railroad's merger with the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern</ORGANIZATION> reached agreement with <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries</ORGANIZATION>,
but when permission for the sale was sought from the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>, another
railroad company, <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern Industries</ORGANIZATION>, objected and
sought to buy <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> as well.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> in a series of votes today turned its back on the
<LOCATION>Kansas City Southern</LOCATION> proposal and approved the sale to <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande
Industries</ORGANIZATION> instead.
   At a news conference, <PERSON>Philip Anschutz</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande
Industries</ORGANIZATION>, applauded the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> decision and said the combined
railroads ``will operate under the banner of Southern Pacific.''
   He said that senior officers of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> will be
announced before the purchase is completed and that managers will
be drawn from the ranks of both railroads.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> also has extensive real estate holdings in
the West, but <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON> said, ``We will be in the railroad business,
first and foremost.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> operates up and down the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> and
along the southern tier of the country with tracks stretching from
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, through central <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> through <LOCATION>El Paso</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>,
and as far east as <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>. It also operates from <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> to
the <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Coast</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> runs along a central corridor from
<LOCATION>Ogden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> could challenge the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> ruling in court but
Rowland</PERSON>, said no decision has been made on what the next step, if
any, would be.
   ``We're not ruling out anything. ... I don't know what our
options are,'' <PERSON>Rowland</PERSON> told reporters after the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> vote.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870701-0088 </DOCNO>
<HL> 
 </HL>
<SO>  </SO>
<IN> BNI KSU LABOR SFX
TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION (ICC) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION>, ending one of the longest-running sagas in modern railroad history, refused to reconsider its <DATE>1986</DATE> rejection of the proposed merger of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Atchison, Topeka &amp; Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> railroads. 

   The 4-1 vote underscored the commission's continued strong concerns about the potentially anti-competitive nature of the merger, which would have produced the nation's third-largest railroad, with more than 25,000 miles of track in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The action will force <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, the Chicago-based parent company of both railroads, to sell at least one of the railroads. 
The corporation was created in <DATE>1983</DATE> when <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> merged with <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Co.</ORGANIZATION>, and it has operated the two railroads separately while awaiting <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> approval. 
Last <DATE>July</DATE>, the commission rejected the merger. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>, in refusing to review that decision yesterday, gave <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> 90 days to submit a divestiture plan. 
It is the first time in recent years that the commission ordered such a divestiture. 
The company will have up to two years to sell one of the railroads, according to commission staff members. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s stock rose sharply yesterday, closing at <MONEY>$50</MONEY>, up <MONEY>$3.75</MONEY> in <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading. 
It was the most actively traded issue on the exchange, with 4.9 million shares changing hands. 
In addition, <ORGANIZATION>Standard &amp; Poor's Corp.</ORGANIZATION> put the company's debt ratings under review and <ORGANIZATION>Moody's Investors Service Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said it will continue an existing review. 

   Railroad industry analysts say the collapse of the merger is likely to touch off a buying spree for portions of one or both of the railroads and could lead to creation of the nation's first coast-to-coast rail system if an <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> railroad emerges as the buyer. 

   At a news conference immediately after the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> vote, <PERSON>Landon Rowland</PERSON>, chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, said his company would make an offer within the next 60 days to buy <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 
Hours later, <ORGANIZATION>Burlington Northern Railroad</ORGANIZATION> said it was "interested in acquiring segments of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> or the <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> Fe or both." 
In addition, some <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> managers and a rail union official separately raised the possibility of buyouts. 

   <PERSON>John Reed</PERSON>, chairman and chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, at the news conference expressed disappointment about the commission decision, but said the company wouldn't appeal it in court. 

   "Our employees have been held in suspense long enough," he said. 
"We just have to get on with our business." 
The company, he added, plans a major realignment involving a renewed focus on its "core businesses" of natural resources, petroleum and transportation, and the sale of a number of other subsidiaries. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Reed</PERSON>, in response to a question, denied that the company already has decided to sell <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, which remains weaker than <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> despite recent signs of improvement. 
"We haven't made any decision as to which railroad will be disposed of," he said. 
He added that it was "conceivable" both railroads would be sold, particularly if management failed to win more concessions from labor. 

   However, industry sources doubted that <PERSON>Mr. Reed</PERSON>, who headed the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> for 16 years, would agree easily to sell that railroad. 
And <PERSON>Richard Kilroy</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Railway Labor Executives Association</ORGANIZATION>, a group representing rail labor unions, dismissed his statement on labor concessions as "posturing." 

   Analysts estimate the value of the two railroads is as much as <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>. 

   The commission, in upholding its earlier rejection of the merger, overruled a staff recommendation to reopen the case. 
The staff argued that a review of the case was needed because of the numerous agreements over track rights that <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> made with other railroads to ameliorate competitive problems. 

   But the majority of the commissioners dismissed that argument. 
"I'm not convinced that the anti-competitive effects we identified in the initial decision have been adequately remedied," said Commissioner <PERSON>Malcolm Sterrett</PERSON>. 
Vice Chairman <PERSON>Paul Lamboley</PERSON> agreed: "I don't think there is really a change at all." 

   Some analysts believe that railroad mergers are a necessity for the railroad industry to survive, and that closing or substantially narrowing that option could cripple the industry's chances. 

   By contrast, the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>'s denial was greeted with enthusiasm at <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 
Many of the high-ranking executives there had given up support for the merger long ago. 
At a staff meeting to draft a news release on the commission's decision, one top manager jokingly crossed out the word "disappointed" and scribbled in "tickled" to describe <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s reaction. 

   After several lean years, the <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION> is showing some signs of rebirth, due in large part to a stabilized customer base and lower costs for fuel and labor. 
The company showed a profit in the <DATE>first quarter</DATE>, usually the quarter with the lowest railroad traffic of the year. 

   The railroad also recently completed a <MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY> track improvement program and opened a container transfer facility outside <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to handle the growing number of merchandise containers coming off ships. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Mr. Reed</PERSON>, in describing the company's plans for realignment, said the following subsidiaries would be offered for sale: <PERSON>Robert E. McKee</PERSON>, a general contractor; <ORGANIZATION>Bankers Leasing &amp; Financial Corp.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Pacific Timber Co.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Central Pipeline Co.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Chaparral Pipeline</ORGANIZATION>; and <ORGANIZATION>Black Mesa Pipeline</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The company, whose most valuable holdings are its <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> of real estate assets, also signaled that it is willing to sell some of its fully developed properties. 
These include the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Design Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>McDonnell Douglas Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. 

   On the possible sale of either the <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> Fe or <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> railroads, the most intriguing possibility is that of the creation of a transcontinental rail carrier by an <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> railroad bidder. 
The benefits of such a combination appear to be growing, reflecting the boom in coast-to-coast shipments of containerized imports from the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>. 

   The big <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> railroads, <ORGANIZATION>Norfolk Southern Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Rail Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>CSX Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, declined comment. 
But <DATE>last May</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Norfolk Southern</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Arnold McKinnon</PERSON> told analysts that "we'll look" if one of the Western railroads became available. 

   Creating a transcontinental rail system faces some problems. 
Some rail executives long have dismissed as minimal the potential cost savings and traffic gains from such combinations. 
In addition, the formation of a coast-to-coast railroad likely would spur competitors to make similar combinations, and those proposed combinations would face regulatory hurdles, including <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> review. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880727-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-27-88 2228EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SouthernPacific-ICC     07-27 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Southern Pacific-ICC,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Railroads Vye For Southern Pacific</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION> heard from
two railroads <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that are vying for the purchase of the
<ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Railroad</ORGANIZATION>, which is on the auction block because of
a failed merger attempt last year.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, had agreed to sell its <ORGANIZATION>Southern
Pacific</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary to <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the parent
company of the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western Railroad</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$1.02
billion</MONEY>.
   But the deal, which requires <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> approval, has run into strong
opposition from <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern Industries</ORGANIZATION>, operator of the
<ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern Railroad</ORGANIZATION>, which has offered <MONEY>$1.25 billion</MONEY> for
the 13,000-mile rail system that stretches from <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> to the
<LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> heard from both railroads <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> as it tries to
determine which buyer to choose, or whether it might approve both
applications and allow <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> to choose.
   A decision is expected next month.
   <PERSON>Samuel Freeman</PERSON>, an attorney for <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries</ORGANIZATION>, told the
<ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> in formal arguments that the company is in better financial
position to buy the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> than is <LOCATION>Kansas City Southern</LOCATION>.
   ``The request (by <LOCATION>Kansas City Southern</LOCATION> that it be allowed to buy
the railroad) is unprecedented and unwarranted,'' he said.
   Rio Grande officials noted that <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> faces a
possible <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> settlement from a legal entanglement that
grew out of its role in the a failure of a coal slurry pipeline
project.
   <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION>, however, maintained before the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> that it
would be the most fit buyer of the <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>, arguing that
it is offering more money and plans to invest <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> more funds
in the railroad than the <LOCATION>Rio Grande</LOCATION>.
   ``We are committed to the acquisition and rehabilitation of the
<ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>,'' said <PERSON>Landon Rowland</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City
Southern Industries</ORGANIZATION>. He said the company would invest more than <MONEY>$4
billion</MONEY> in the railroad over a five-year period.
   <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> has accused the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, of
favoring the lower <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> bid because the merger would benefit
the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Railroad</ORGANIZATION>, the other rail line owned by <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe
Pacific Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Jerome Donohoe</PERSON>, representing <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, said the company
has a binding contract with <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> and could not complete the
sale this year if the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> were to choose <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> was put up for sale under an <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>
divestiture order after the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> rejected a planned merger
of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> with the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880809-0082 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sale of Southern Pacific to Rio Grande Is Expected to Get U.S. Approval Today </HL>
<AUTHOR> Judith Valente (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> KSU SFX </CO>
<IN> TNM TRA </IN>
<G> ICC </G>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION> is expected today to approve the sale of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Transportation Co.</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, closing a five-year controversy over the fate of one of the nation's oldest railroads. 

   The commission, meeting in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, is expected to approve the sale despite strenuous objections from <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which has offered <MONEY>$1.25 billion</MONEY> in cash and notes for <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 
A commission official said the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> is concerned about how a court judgment of as much as <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> against <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> in the state of <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> will affect that company's financial outlook. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> is appealing that judgment, which stems from antitrust and contract violations involving a coal-slurry pipeline project in <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>. 
A <LOCATION>Sioux Falls</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>, federal judge last <DATE>Friday</DATE> said he planned to issue an order barring <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> from completing any purchase of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> until the <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> case is resolved. 

   In <DATE>December</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s parent, <ORGANIZATION>Chicago-based Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, agreed to sell the rail unit to <LOCATION>Rio Grande</LOCATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Denver-based Anschutz Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, for <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY>. 
But the sale couldn't be finalized without the approval of the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>, which rules on whether such mergers are "in the public interest" and must insure they don't pose anti-competitive problems. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> has tried since then to prevent the sale, arguing that it's willing to invest more money in <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION> than <LOCATION>Rio Grande</LOCATION>, and would therefore make <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> a more viable competitor among railroads in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> maintains the <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> judgment it has been ordered to pay in <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> would have no effect on its plans for <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Landon Rowland</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION>'s president and chief executive officer, said a decision in favor of <LOCATION>Rio Grande</LOCATION> at today's <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> hearing would be "very disappointing." 
He left open the possibility that his company still may try to block the sale in the courts if it fails before the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The fate of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, which traces its beginnings to the first transcontinental railroad, has been in abeyance since <DATE>December 1983</DATE>, when it was acquired by <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> had hoped to merge <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>, which is based in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, with its other rail unit, the <ORGANIZATION>Atchison Topeka &amp; Santa Fe Railway</ORGANIZATION>. 
But after four years of hearings and rehearings, the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> rejected that proposal and ordered <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> to sell off one of its rail units. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870309-0029 </DOCNO>
<HL> Santa Fe Southern Still Faces Opposition
To Revised Plan for Merging Railroads
---
By Scott Kilman
<DD> 03/09/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SFX BNI UNP
TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS)
INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION (ICC) </IN>
<DATELINE> CHICAGO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s revised plan to create the nation's second-longest railroad still faces opposition from some competitors and regulators. 

   The plan, which was filed last week with the <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION>, details the concessions the transportation and natural resources giant is willing to grant to four Western railroads. 
The railroads had objected to its plans to merge its two railway units: the <LOCATION>Atchison</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Topeka &amp; Santa Fe Railway Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Transportation Co</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> is attempting to use the concessions to convince the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> to reopen hearings on its three-year struggle to merge the two railroads. 
The <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> blocked the merger last <DATE>July</DATE> on grounds that the combined railroads would have monopolized traffic on the <LOCATION>Pacific Coast</LOCATION> as well as between <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Coast</ORGANIZATION>. 

   According to the filing, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> is agreeing to let the four railroads use hundreds of miles of its track in return for similar rights. 
The arrangements strengthen the four railroads, which may in turn spur their competitors to try to derail the complicated merger plan. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Burlington Northern Railroad Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the nation's largest railroad, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> it opposes the revised merger proposal because, among other things, it would grant its biggest Western competitor, <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, access to the southwestern <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
"At the least, the anti-competitive problems don't go away, and it gives <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> the upper hand in the Southern corridor," said <ORGANIZATION>Burlington Northern</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Mike Wenninger</PERSON>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> has reached agreements with the <ORGANIZATION>Missouri-Kansas-Texas Railroad Co.</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Mexican Railway Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
The company said a final agreement with the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western Railroad Co.</ORGANIZATION> is snagged over "narrow, discrete issues" that it suggests could be settled by the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> or arbitration. 
The agreement would allow the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western</ORGANIZATION> to lease track in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> said it is looking at the concessions to determine whether they solve the anti-competitive problems raised by the original combination. 
"We are skeptical," said <PERSON>James R. Weiss</PERSON>, chief of the antitrust division's transportation, energy and agriculture section. 
"Trying to resolve (anti-competitive problems) through these fixes is difficult to do," he said. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Transportation Department</ORGANIZATION> has supported the merger of the railway units, which would encompass more than 25,000 miles of track from the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION> across the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern Railway Co.</ORGANIZATION> has opposed the revised merger plan because it wants to buy the Southern Pacific system. 
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> will have to divest itself of one of the railroad units if the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> rejection stands. 

   This complicated railroad battle was touched off in <DATE>1983</DATE> when <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> merged with <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Co.</ORGANIZATION> in a <MONEY>$6.4 billion</MONEY> transaction. 
The energy and natural resources operations of the two companies were immediately combined but the railroad units were kept separate pending <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> approval. 
<ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> is managed independently through a trust. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> said it has drummed up support to reopen the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> hearings from, among others, the governors of 12 states and from 1,700 companies that ship goods over the affected railroad lines. 
Interested parties have three weeks from <DATE>last Thursday</DATE> to file comments on <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s merger petition. 


   The concessions are an about-face for <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman, <PERSON>John J. Schmidt</PERSON>. 
Prior to the rejection of the merger proposal by the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>, he had maintained that any concessions could severely damage the viability of the merger. 
Now the company is saying the concessions improve the merger. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> wasn't available to comment. 
A company spokesman said the trackage-rights swaps and lease agreements with the four railroads would allow the merged units to take shortcuts and trim maintenance costs, among other things. 
The petition estimates that <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> would save itself about <MONEY>$295 million</MONEY> annually by merging the units this way. 
Under the old plan, the company thought it would save about <MONEY>$288 million</MONEY> annually. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880810-0106 </DOCNO>
<HL> Rio Grande Bid For Southern Pacific Cleared --- ICC Endorses Offer for Unit Of Santa Fe Southern Valued at $1.02 Billion </HL>
<AUTHOR> Laurie McGinley (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> KSU SFX </CO>
<IN> TRA TNM </IN>
<G> ICC </G>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION> approved the <MONEY>$1.02 billion</MONEY> sale of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Railroad to Denver-based Rio Grande Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, spurning a competing bid from <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern Industries Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Philip Anschutz</PERSON> said that company's railroad unit, <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western Railroad</ORGANIZATION>, will be combined with <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> and run under the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> name. 

   The new rail system, with 15,000 miles of track, will be the fifth largest in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, covering 15 states west of the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION>. 
It will be based in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, as <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> is now, and will have a major regional office in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. 

   In a 20-minute session, the commission voted 4-0 to approve <LOCATION>Rio Grande</LOCATION>'s application to buy <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> from Chicago-based <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and 4-0 to reject <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern's</ORGANIZATION>. 
<PERSON>Heather Gradison</PERSON>, chairman of the commission, said the transaction would "produce substantial public benefits" without "discernible harms to competition or to essential railroad service." 

   <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> member <PERSON>Paul Lamboley</PERSON> appeared to speak for his colleagues in articulating a major argument against the <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> bid: a pending court judgment against that <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, railroad company of as much as <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY>. 
He said the prospect of the judgment clouds the company's financial outlook and would delay completion of any <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> purchase of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The judgment against <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> stems from antitrust and contract violations involving a coal-slurry pipeline project in <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>. 
The railroad is appealing the judgment, but a federal judge last week said he would bar <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> from completing a purchase of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> until the case is resolved. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION>'s bid for <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> totaled <MONEY>$1.25 billion</MONEY> in cash and debentures. 
<ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION>'s bid was all cash. 

   Meanwhile, <PERSON>David Berger</PERSON>, an attorney in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, is seeking certification from a state court in <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Del.</LOCATION>, to press a class-action suit on behalf of <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern</ORGANIZATION> shareholders. 
The suit would charge that the company's management breached its fiduciary duties in accepting the lower bid and would seek damages of at least <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> yesterday criticized the commission's decision to approve its rival's bid, saying, "The biggest loser was the public interest." 
The railroad contended that it planned to spend <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY> more on <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> over the next five years than <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> plans to spend. 
<ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> said its bid for <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> remains "on the table." 

   The commission vote apparently ends one of the longest-running sagas in the railroad business, over the future of <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>. 
In late <DATE>1983</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Industries</ORGANIZATION>, which owns <ORGANIZATION>Atchison Topeka &amp; Santa Fe Railway</ORGANIZATION>, bought <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Co.</ORGANIZATION>, owner of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Railroad</ORGANIZATION>. 
The parent companies merged their non-rail assets but operated their railroads separately pending <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> approval. 

   Last year, the commission, citing threats to competition, vetoed the rail merger and ordered <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> to sell one of its railroads. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890728-0154 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890728 </DD>
<AN> 890728-0154. </AN>
<HL> Industry Focus:
@  Trains Double Up to Get Truck Business
@  ---
@  New Car Setup Starts
@  Rate War, Aiding Shippers
@  ----
@  By Daniel Machalaba
<DD> 07/28/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<IN> TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The proliferation of double-stack container trains is igniting a rate war between truckers and railroads, benefiting shippers with lower freight rates. 

   More than 100 double-stack trains, which carry one container loaded above another, now ply the nation's long-haul east-west freight routes each week, compared with a handful five years ago. 
Double-stack rates between <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> dropped <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> in the past 12 months, as freight-hauling capacity continued to grow amid a slowdown in demand. 
Some analysts expect rates to fall further when additional trains are launched. 

   The transcontinental freight routes have become "extremely competitive," says <PERSON>John Koons</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Country Wide Transport Services Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a truck company. 
Double-stack trains are "taking a lot of freight that used to be routed via trucks." 

   More broadly, the double-stack trains are "increasing the efficiency of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> freight transportation and the competitiveness of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> manufacturers," says <PERSON>Gerard McCullough</PERSON>, deputy director of transportation studies at <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The rate cutting affects long-distance east-west freight flows of more than <MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY> a year. 
Some analysts estimate that the industrywide rate drops spurred by double-stack competition are saving <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> consumers between <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> and <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> a year. 

   Among the biggest rate cuts are ones on the busy <LOCATION>Chicago-Los Angeles</LOCATION> corridor, where rates for some carriers plunged from about <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY> for some of the bigger containers two years ago to <MONEY>$1,200</MONEY> to <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> now. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Proctor &amp; Gamble Co.</ORGANIZATION> recently shifted some of its business away from trucks to double-stack trains because of the rate cuts and improvements in double-stack service. 
The company now ships 20 container loads a week of potato chips, peanut butter and liquid detergent from its <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> plants to the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> by rail. 
In response to shipper defections, some truckers are slashing rates. 
Others are courting shippers further away from the major double-stack terminals. 
A few are fleeing transcontinental routes, focusing instead on shorter regional deliveries. 

   Country Wide is moving its headquarters from <LOCATION>Pomona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, where double-stack competition is keen, to <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn</LOCATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>MNX Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>St. Joseph</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, trucker, is redeploying trucks to less competitive routes in the Southeast. 
Recently, <ORGANIZATION>MNX</ORGANIZATION> bought a shipping broker to gain access to the fast-growing double-stack market. 
Another trucker, <ORGANIZATION>CRST Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Cedar Rapids</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, shelved plans to buy 50 more trucks, blaming rate declines. 

   "We're barely making money," says <PERSON>John Smith</PERSON>, president of CRST. 
"We're doing everything we can to keep costs down." 

   For decades the nation's railroads seemed helpless against trucking companies that siphoned off their most lucrative freight, leaving the rails with low-rated bulk traffic. 
They fought back with piggyback -- transporting highway trailers on flatcars -- but managed to win freight mainly from their own boxcars. 

   Double-stacks represent the "first concrete example of a new rail intermodal technology taking traffic off the highway," says <PERSON>Lee Lane</PERSON>, intermodal executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Association of American Railroads</ORGANIZATION>. 
By some estimates, double-stacks are capturing <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> freight shipments of more than <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> a year from trucks. 

   By stacking two containers on special rail cars, railroads nearly double train capacity and cut rail costs <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT>. 
The double-stack trains carry containers in low-slung, bathtub-shaped wells that provide a smoother ride than piggyback trains. 

   <ORGANIZATION>American President Cos.</ORGANIZATION>, an <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, Calif.-based ocean ship line, launched the first coast-to-coast double-stack train in <DATE>1984</DATE>. 
It was originally designed to speed international cargo off the company's ships on the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> to inland destinations. 
But to balance the heavy flow of Asian imports on its eastbound trains, the company solicited domestic freight to fill containers that would have returned empty to the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>. 
Later, <ORGANIZATION>American President</ORGANIZATION> expanded its trains to carry domestic freight in both directions. 

   "Our international freight volumes gave us the base to create a domestic freight system," says <PERSON>Donald Orris</PERSON>, president of the company's domestic freight unit. 

   Other ship lines, and the rail units of <ORGANIZATION>CSX Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Burlington Northern Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, have launched their own double-stack trains. 
Now they are trying to lure <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> domestic shippers to use the the trains by ordering thousands of large-capacity containers, expanding terminals, speeding up train schedules and reducing rates. 
Currently, domestic freight accounts for about <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of the cargo on double-stack trains and the business is growing rapidly. 

   <ORGANIZATION>CSX</ORGANIZATION> and American President have begun to dispatch their own company trucks and drivers, rather than relying on independent drivers, to move containers between shippers' loading docks and their railheads. 
That will eliminate some shipment delays, they say. 
And American President is refunding freight charges when it fails to deliver on time. 

   Double-stack operators are also making organizational changes, hiring executives from the trucking industry, for example. 
"The rails have finally realized after trial and error that to be competitive with truckers you have to think and act like a trucker," says <PERSON>M. McNeil Porter</PERSON>, a former trucking company executive who is president of <ORGANIZATION>CSX</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>CSL Intermodal</ORGANIZATION> unit. 

   Some shippers aren't likely to shift freight to double-stack trains any time soon. 
"Motor carriers cover more routes, give better service and their transit time is less," says <PERSON>Peter Brock</PERSON>, transportation manager of <ORGANIZATION>J.C. Penney Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
The trains are restricted, particularly in the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>, by bridge and tunnel clearances. 
And shipper surveys rate trucks higher than rail intermodal service in reliability, speed, door-to-door delivery and customer responsiveness. 

   But <ORGANIZATION>3M Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Campbell Soup Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>General Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s appliance division have recently switched some shipments to double-stack trains from trucks. 
One reason <ORGANIZATION>Procter &amp; Gamble</ORGANIZATION> switched some of its freight to trains from trucks is that "they use less fuel and create less pollution and that's good for the country," says <PERSON>Fred Morris</PERSON>, the company's transportation director. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Nabisco Foods Co.</ORGANIZATION> also plans to divert certain shipments to double-stacks because the company is concerned about the growing shortage of long-haul truck drivers. 
"We're trying to protect ourselves by putting as much freight on rail as we can," says <PERSON>William Ditoro</PERSON>, transportation director of the <ORGANIZATION>RJR Nabisco Inc.</ORGANIZATION> unit. 
"We're trying to wean ourselves off trucks." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870817-0108 </DOCNO>
<HL> Santa Fe Southern Believed to Be Trying
To Keep a Vital Southern Pacific Line
---
By Judith Valente
<DD> 08/17/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SFX
TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION (ICC) </IN>
<DATELINE> CHICAGO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, under orders from the <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION> to sell one of its two railroad units, is trying to persuade the regulatory agency to allow it to sell only a portion of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Transportation Co.</ORGANIZATION>, commission staff members and industry officials said. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> wants to retain Chicago-based <ORGANIZATION>Atchison Topeka &amp; Santa Fe Railway</ORGANIZATION>, its more profitable railroad property, these sources said. 
It also wants to keep a portion of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, known as the Cotton Belt line. 
The Cotton Belt, which runs from <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and from <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Tennesee</LOCATION>, would provide the <ORGANIZATION>Atchison Topeka &amp; Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> with two new gateways to the East: <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. 

   But such a plan would in turn rob Southern Pacific of these two cities and <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, the three most important gateways on its route system. 
"It would be a dagger in the heart of the <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>," a source close to the San Francisco-based railroad said. 

   <PERSON>Robert D. Krebs</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s chief executive officer, said through a spokesman that the company is continuing work on a divestiture plan and that reports of the possible sale of the Cotton Belt are "premature." 

   <PERSON>Denman K. McNear</PERSON>, chairman and chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, declined to comment. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> was formed in <DATE>1983</DATE> through the merger of the two railroads' parent companies, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
In <DATE>June</DATE>, it lost a four-year battle to merge the two railroad units, which had long competed for the transport of a wide range of commodities across the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> and which it continued to operate separately pending <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> approval. 
But the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>, which denied the merger on anti-competitive grounds, ordered the railroad, energy and real estate concern to submit a divestiture plan by <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE>. 

   Since then, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> officials have had several meetings with <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> commissioners and staff to discuss the possible sale of parts of <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>, the industry and commission sources said. 
Although it is unclear if the commission will allow the sale of only a portion of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, at least one commissioner, <PERSON>Paul Lamboley</PERSON>, has criticized the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> plan as "just another attempt at a merger," a commission official said. 

   Only one company, <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, has so far publicly expressed an interest in <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>. 
But <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> has yet to make a specific offer. 

   The Cotton Belt has been one of the more profitable routes in the <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION> system. 
In the <DATE>first five months of 1987</DATE>, the line had revenue of <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY>, compared with <MONEY>$140 million</MONEY> in the same period of <DATE>1986</DATE>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> unit had <DATE>1986</DATE> revenue of <MONEY>$2.27 billion</MONEY>. 

   Through the Cotton Belt line and its gateways at <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> trains transfer a wide range of cargo, including autos, lumber and petrochemicals, to other rail carriers for delivery to eastern cities. 
If the <ORGANIZATION>Atchison Topeka &amp; Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> is allowed to take control of those gateways, "it would spell disaster for the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>," an industry official said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861211-0173 </DOCNO>
<HL> Santa Fe Southern
Asks ICC to Restudy
Ruling on Merger Bid</HL>
<DD> 12/11/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SFX
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA) </IN>
<DATELINE> CHICAGO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it petitioned the <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION> late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to reconsider the rejection of a plan to merge its two railway units -- <LOCATION>Atchison</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Topeka &amp; Santa Fe Railway and Southern Pacific Transportation Co</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The appeal was expected. 
The regulatory commission blocked the proposed merger of the two railway units in <DATE>July</DATE> because of worries that it would hurt competition in the <LOCATION>Southwest</LOCATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> had until <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to ask that the merger talks be reopened. 

   The railroad combination, which was the first to be rejected by the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> in two decades, would have formed the nation's third-largest rail system. 
The two railway units have operated separately since their parents, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, combined in <DATE>1983</DATE> to form <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 
The companies' operations were combined except for the railroads, which need <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> approval to merge. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> also has interests in natural resources and forest products. 

   Since the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>'s rejection, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> has been trying to win support for the merger of its units from its railroad competitors. 
Earlier this month, it agreed to give <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION> the right to operate on some of the units' lines, among other things. 
The agreement is similar to a <DATE>September</DATE> accord that gave <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western Railroad</ORGANIZATION> access to markets west of <LOCATION>Ogden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870629-0141 </DOCNO>
<HL> Derailed Merger:
Plan to Join Santa Fe,
Southern Pacific Faces
A Possible Final Blow
---
How Errors by Management,
Red Tape Blocked Deal;
ICC May Act Tomorrow
---
The 'Pricing Freedom' Memo
---
By Judith Valente and Daniel Machalaba
<DD> 06/29/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SFX
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA)
INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION (ICC) </IN>
<TEXT>
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, executives of the <ORGANIZATION>Atchison, Topeka &amp; Santa Fe Railway</ORGANIZATION> devised a plan that seemed as solid as the carrier's granite track beds: create a giant new railroad by acquiring the rival <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 

   But <DATE>four years later</DATE>, one of the biggest mergers in rail history is falling apart. 
Although the parent companies have combined their assets, management errors and regulatory red tape have repeatedly delayed the blending of the two railroads, which are still held in separate units. 
Employee morale at both railroads has plunged, and contracts have been lost. 
In <DATE>April</DATE>, frustration over the ill-fated merger led to the ouster of Chairman <PERSON>John J. Schmidt</PERSON>. 
In <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>San Joaquin Valley</LOCATION>, stretches of track that were built to join the two railways end abruptly in the dirt. 

   But even as the two railroads and their parent, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, struggle with these problems, a much bigger one may be about to hit. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION>, which rejected the merger of the two lines in a decision last year, may vote at its scheduled meeting tomorrow to reject an appeal to reconsider the case. 
Although the agency could still change its mind, such a decision would be a consistent end to one of the most disaster-prone acquisitions in business history. 

   "It's a corporate and political mess that's positively stupefying," says <PERSON>William L. Withuhn</PERSON>, a railroad historian at the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian</ORGANIZATION> Institution in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. 
He adds that he can't remember a more "complex, tragic and confused railroad merger proposal." 

   If the commission does the unexpected and reopens the case, the review could last for years. 
That would probably be worse for the company than to bring the matter to a close now. 

   The failure of the merger could significantly alter the railroad map in the <LOCATION>Westand</LOCATION> possibly beyond. 
In addition to their colorful histories, both lines are major rail links. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION>'s greatest strength is its high-speed route between <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, which <PERSON>Judy Garland</PERSON> helped immortalize in the <PERSON>Johnny Mercer/Harry Warren</PERSON> song "On the <LOCATION>Atchison</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Topeka</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Santa Fe</LOCATION>." 
The <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, meanwhile, carries major quantities of the nation's lumber, produce, chemicals and merchandise containers. 
It also played a major role in developing <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and was once the state's biggest private landowner. 

   An <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> decision would probably include an order for the parent company to immediately divest itself of at least one of the railroads. 
Although the two carriers might be able to operate independently for some time, it is more probable that one or both would be sold to other railroads either as single entities or in pieces. 
In fact, one of the lines could end up in the hands of an <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION> railroad, forming the nation's first transcontinental carrier at a time when coast-to-coast rail traffic is surging because of heavy container traffic from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>. 

   The two railroads may have been the victims of bad timing. 
A few years before their proposed combination, the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> had easily approved the big mergers that created the <LOCATION>Norfolk Southern</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>CSX</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 
In arguing their case, the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> maintained, among other things, that the earlier decisions entitled them to similar treatment. 
And many in the industry believed that the proposal would fly through all government hearings with little problem. 

   But when the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> brought their case, the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> was under increasing pressure from <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to re-regulate the railroad industry. 
In addition, the carriers may have been overconfident. 
In any case, they presented a case that was filled with contradictions and errors. 
"It was an ecstasy of fumbling," says an <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> official. 
Commissioner <PERSON>Malcolm M.B. Sterrett</PERSON> adds that the hearing record was "replete with self-contradictory testimony, omissions and fuzziness." 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> started discussing a merger in the <DATE>summer of 1980</DATE>. 
But talks broke off after the two sides failed to agree on a price or a plan. 
One problem was a personality clash between the two railroads' leaders. 
<PERSON>John Shedd Reed</PERSON>, the Yale-educated chairman of the <LOCATION>Santa Fe</LOCATION>, was known for his genteel style. 
<PERSON>Benjamin Biaggini</PERSON>, the strong-willed Louisianian who headed the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, liked to play tough. 
Once, in the middle of a bumpy rail trip, he stopped the train and ordered the manager responsible for track maintenance to get off and stay out of the office until the tracks had been repaired. 

   In <DATE>1983</DATE> <PERSON>Mr. Reed</PERSON> retired, and his successor, <PERSON>John Schmidt</PERSON>, almost immediately resurrected the idea of a merger. 
Deregulation had led to a wave of big railroad combinations, and <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON>, a lawyer with a deep concern for the bottom line, was worried about the consequences of being left out. 
This time, <PERSON>Mr. Biaggini</PERSON> agreed. 

   The two companies were so confident of success that they merged their parent companies - including their real-estate, pipeline, mineral and timber interests -- without waiting for the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> to complete its review. 
Because federal law forbids merging railroads without <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> approval, they left the two carriers in separate subsidiaries. 
But they began repainting the locomotives with the red and yellow color scheme of the merged railroad. 

   From an antitrust standpoint, railroad merger cases tend to be complicated because they involve a wide range of interested parties from many locations. 
Until <DATE>1976</DATE>, when <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> imposed a 31-month time limit on <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> merger proceedings, some rail cases dragged on interminably. 
Many in the industry blamed the collapse of the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Rock Island &amp; Pacific Railroad</ORGANIZATION> on a decade-long <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> review. 

   But the process is still costly and exhaustive. 
Before the commission made its initial ruling in the <LOCATION>Santa Fe/Southern Pacific</LOCATION> case, it heard testimony from 130 witnesses, reviewed 600 exhibits and read more than 18,000 pages of transcripts. 

   Despite uncountable hours of preparation, the two railroads turned out to be their own worst enemies. 
A <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> witness testified that the merger wouldn't reduce competition because the two railroads -- both of which operate primarily in the West -- don't overlap much in the types of cargo that they carry. 
But the same witness later tried to make the point that other railroads that carted even one ton of any type of cargo would constitute a competitive threat to the combined <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe/ Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 

   At another point, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION>'s lawyers argued that competition from trucks would mitigate the effects of the merger. 
But the company's chief witness on the subject testified that trucks can't carry many bulk commodities as cheaply and efficiently as railroads. 

   The most apparent inconsistencies had to do with <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION>'s estimates of the financial strength of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 
First, the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> filed affidavits saying that it would be viable for years to come. 
Later, <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> said that the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> was close to bankruptcy. 
Investment bankers for the railroads variously estimated the worth of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> at <MONEY>$800 million</MONEY> and at a negative <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY>. 

   At one point, a flood of mail began to pour into the commission from rail customers who said they supported the merger. 
But <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> staff members noticed that each letter misspelled the name of the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>'s executive secretary, <PERSON>Noreta R. McGee</PERSON>. 
Instead of impressing the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>, the campaign helped lead to an inquiry into whether the railroads were unduly pressuring customers to support the merger. 

   The smoking gun, however, turned out to be a confidential report from <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> to the board about the pricing advantages of the merger. 
The memo said that the combination would help the railroads achieve "pricing freedom" and that one of the goals was a rail monopoly in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Southwest</LOCATION>. 
Although <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> succeeded in persuading the commission to keep the report under seal, the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> later referred to the memo as a "candid appraisal . . . unlike expert testimony and legal argument" of the true view of the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> railroad's management. 

   Last <DATE>July</DATE>, following a mere 17-minute discussion, the commission voted 4-1 to reject the merger as anti-competitive. 
The decision was unexpected, and it stunned the industry. 
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> had to cancel a luncheon with securities analysts scheduled for that day on the benefits of a favorable <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> ruling. 

   Few, however, were more surprised than <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON>. 
Calling the decision a "horrible mistake," he vowed a grassroots campaign to overturn it and ordered the company's lawyers to petition the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> to reopen the case. 

   Privately, though, some <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> board members were already blaming <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> for the commission's decision. 
In addition to the memo, some faulted him for being undiplomatic throughout the process. 
Indeed, afraid that the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> might yield to demands for changes, <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> had taken a tough, take-it-or-leave-it stance throughout the process. 

   The strategy seemed particularly ill-chosen later when, in an effort to get the merger reconsidered, <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> himself began offering concessions. 
One that particularly upset <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> employees was a proposal to lease what some believed was the soul of the railroad: the line between <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Ogden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, which dates back to <DATE>1869</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON>'s concessions, which eventually covered thousands of miles of track, "gave away more than we would have liked," says <PERSON>Robert West</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> director. 
After all the changes, it "wasn't the same merger it was and didn't have the same benefits," says <PERSON>Lester Kloss</PERSON>, a senior vice president of <ORGANIZATION>A.T. Kearney Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a consultant for both railroads. 

   The concessions brought other problems as well. 
While they helped <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> persuade the <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> to support the merger, they angered the <LOCATION>Burlington Northern</LOCATION>, which switched from a neutral position to opposing the merger. 
<PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> declined repeated requests from this newspaper for an interview on his role. 

   Opposition from competitors also contributed to the initial rejection of the merger, and that has angered <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> executives. 
"What irritates me," says <PERSON>Mr. Reed</PERSON>, "is that we didn't oppose the <LOCATION>Burlington Northern</LOCATION> mergers. 
We were gentlemen about it. 
But now that they've got theirs, they don't want anyone else to have similar capabilities." 

   The deterioration of the railroads -- particularly the <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION> - during this limbo period has led to a decline in employee morale. 
Engines have even been allowed to run out of fuel in mid-trip. 
"To a person, our employees are sick to death of the process. 
Sick of decisions not being made or being made in a convoluted fashion. 
Sick to death of this merger," says a mid-level manager at the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Competitors have been able to lure away business by exploiting the low morale and <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON>'s talk of a <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> bankruptcy -- "an unfortunate choice of words on his part," says <PERSON>Edward Ahern</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s vice president of administration. 
Overall, <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> has benefited the most, scoring a major coup when it won a big contract to haul finished automobiles for a joint venture of <ORGANIZATION>Toyota</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. 

   As the case has worn on, the distractions at both railroads have become overpowering. 
The merger "drove us nuts," says <PERSON>Lawrence Cena</PERSON>, who retired as the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> railroad's president about a year ago. 
Among other things, it contributed to the <LOCATION>Santa Fe</LOCATION>'s tardy entry into doublestack container trains, which carry ocean containers one above the other. 

   On the <DATE>Friday</DATE> before <DATE>Easter</DATE>, according to current and former managers of the two railroads, a group of outside <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> directors, led by <PERSON>Mr. Biaggini</PERSON>, the former <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> chairman, began plotting the ouster of <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON>. 
Although the two men had once been allies, <PERSON>Mr. Biaggini</PERSON> was angered shortly after his retirement when <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> took away his use of the company jet and forced him to vacate a large office with a panoramic view of <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION> for an office one-quarter the size with a view of a courtyard. 

   At a hastily called meeting, the board sided with <PERSON>Mr. Biaggini</PERSON>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON> was given a consultant's contract, reportedly worth <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY>, and an out-of-the-way office. 
His predecessor, <PERSON>Mr. Reed</PERSON>, agreed to come out of retirement to temporarily lead the company. 
<PERSON>Mr. Biaggini</PERSON> declines to discuss his role in the board's affairs. 

   Now, <PERSON>Mr. Reed</PERSON> finds himself confronting the company's biggest challenge ever. 
If the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> rules against the merger, he will have to decide whether the parent company should remain in the railroad business at all. 
"The most frustrating part is that the two companies have been in suspense for so many years," he says. 

   At the company's recent annual meeting, <PERSON>Mr. Reed</PERSON>, 70, told the audience that he had never dreamed he would return to the corporation. 
"I'm just an old lantern swinger," he said at one point. 
But later, when asked whether he thought the merger would ever succeed, he paused and looked perplexed. 
"With the way things have gone so far," he said, "I guess you couldn't be surprised by anything that might happen." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900608-0033
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900608-0033.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Southern Pacific Traveling Tough Track
   ---
   Real Estate Sales Keep
   Steam in Troubled Railroad
   ----
   By Daniel Machalaba
</HL>
<DATE>
06/08/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A5E
</SO>
<CO>
   MS
</CO>
<IN>
RAILROADS (RAI)
CORPORATE PROFILE (PRO)
REAL ESTATE INVESTMENTS (REA)
</IN>
<LP>
   SAN FRANCISCO -- Soon after Philip Anschutz bought
Southern Pacific Transportation Co. in 1988, dozens of
employees gathered in the Utah desert to re-create railroad
history.
   As cameras clicked, the celebrants posed on facing diesel
locomotives from the Southern Pacific and from Mr. Anschutz's
smaller Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western. Recalling the 1869
"golden spike" ceremony on completion of the first
transcontinental railroad, the scene was meant to symbolize
Mr. Anschutz's plan to revive Southern Pacific as part of a
new railroad across the West.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   But <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> is hitting rough
track.
   Faced with deepening losses at the railroad and high debt
obligations, <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> is keeping the <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>
afloat with accelerated real estate sales. Shippers complain
of management confusion, erratic pricing tactics and delays
caused by worn-out locomotives.
   "A lot of people thought <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON> coming aboard was like
<LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> coming down the chimney," says <PERSON>Rollin Bredenberg</PERSON>,
a <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> general manager. But combining the
railroad with <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON>'s smaller <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande
Western</ORGANIZATION> "hasn't solved any of the fundamental problems of the
<LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>," he concedes.
   Others worry that <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> owner of oil and
gas, real estate and Western art, doesn't know how to run a
railroad. <PERSON>Robert Starzel</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> vice chairman
and <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON> confidant, says that railroading has proven
"difficult for us" but insists his boss will make the
railroad prosper.
   Although the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> is the weakest of the
nation's seven major railroads and isn't publicly owned, its
health is of keen interest to shippers, consumers and
travelers. The railroad is the largest hauler of
international goods to the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>
ports and its scenic routes are traversed by <ORGANIZATION>Amtrak</ORGANIZATION> passenger
trains.
   <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> and minority partner, <ORGANIZATION>Morgan Stanley &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>,
acquired the company in a <MONEY>$1.02 billion</MONEY> leveraged buy-out
plus assumption of <MONEY>$780 million</MONEY> debt. The purchase was widely
hailed by <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> employees after a plan to merge
the railroad with <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION> was rejected by the
<ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   But hopes for fast rejuvenation of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> have
faded. The company's rail operations had a loss of <MONEY>$66
million</MONEY> last year, reflecting a downturn in automobile and
lumber traffic, rate wars, a major accident and the cost of
adding new trains. Proceeds from property sales, however,
resulted in net income of <MONEY>$98 million</MONEY>.
   However, when real estate sales failed to cover the
company's burden of debt and capital spending, <ORGANIZATION>Southern
Pacific</ORGANIZATION> renegotiated terms of its loan with <ORGANIZATION>Bank of America</ORGANIZATION>
last <DATE>December</DATE> to avoid default. In <DATE>April</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Moody's Investors
Service</ORGANIZATION> downgraded <MONEY>$695 million</MONEY> of the company's long-term
debt, concluding that proceeds from real estate sales will
only partially offset the gap in cash from lower rail
operating earnings.
   The company's disappointing railroad performance has
shaken the confidence of some shippers. "I'm concerned that
they will become financially insolvent and the railroad will
be sold piecemeal," says <PERSON>Homer Bollard</PERSON>, general traffic
manager of <ORGANIZATION>Louisiana-Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a big lumber shipper.
   Southern Pacific officials dismiss such concerns. "This
isn't a question of bankruptcy. There are <MONEY>billions of dollars</MONEY>
of assets here," says Vice Chairman <PERSON>Starzel</PERSON>. Even if company
forecasts for profitable rail operations next year don't pan
out, <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> could support its railroad with
proceeds from real estate sales for years, <PERSON>Mr. Starzel</PERSON> says.
   <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> declines to give interviews. But he has told
shippers that his 15,000-mile rail franchise is among the
strongest, because it includes two major east-west routes and
track to most <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Gulf</LOCATION> coast ports. To strengthen the
system, <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> bought a regional rail line last year,
giving <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> trains direct access to <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> for
the first time. Now he is trying to overcome the objections
of competing railroads to buy a second route to <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
Slight, restless and 50 years old, <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> likes to take
freight trains to meet crew members and entertain shippers
aboard the <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON> family yacht.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> is struggling to regain ground lost
to competitors when it was held in trust for five years
pending its aborted merger with <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION>. While Southern
Pacific languished, larger rivals <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Burlington Northern Inc.</ORGANIZATION> moved aggressively to shed surplus
lines and employees and invest in modern technology.
   Without the heavy coal and grain traffic of <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION>
and <LOCATION>Burlington Northern</LOCATION>, the railroad is also highly
dependent upon cyclical and rate competitive shipments of
lumber, automobiles, chemicals and containerized freight.
   <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> also inherited the results of years of
lagging capital spending. Although <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s main
lines have been upgraded, some of its yards are old and
poorly maintained. As he walks through <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s
freight yard in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, trainmaster <PERSON>Robert Melbo</PERSON> is
summoned by radio to a two-car derailment caused by rotted
ties under the rails.
   Much of the company's locomotive fleet is old and
outmoded. And its freight cars for carrying lumber are
deplorable, says <PERSON>Dennis Williams</PERSON>, director of traffic and
distribution at <ORGANIZATION>Bohemia Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Eugene</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> "They have some
good cars but too few. The rest are old and inefficient."
   But some problems are of <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON>'s own making. He
built the railroad's management team with a president from
the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> and a vice chairman from <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio
Grande</ORGANIZATION>, even though the two railroads have conflicting
philosophies. While President <PERSON>D. Michael Mohan</PERSON> was steeped in
the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s costcutting ways, Vice Chairman
<PERSON>William Holtman</PERSON> learned at <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> to put a
premium on service. Southern Pacific executives say the
confusion is heightened because <PERSON>Mr. Holtman</PERSON> sometimes differs
with <PERSON>Mr. Mohan</PERSON> on important decisions.
   Last year <PERSON>Mr. Mohan</PERSON> tried to cut crew costs by ordering
that freight trains be combined. But after freight began to
back up in yards and customers complained of delayed
shipments, <PERSON>Mr. Holtman</PERSON> shortened train sizes. "We adopt a
strategy, and before it can produce results, we drop it and
try something else," says <PERSON>Mr. Melbo</PERSON>, the trainmaster, adding
that the company has changed its train-size requirements four
times in the past 18 months.
   <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> has won some freight lost to competitors
but often at such low rates that the railroad lost money
hauling the traffic. "In our zeal to sign up customers we
lost sight of the fact that you sign them up to make money,
not just to lure them away from someone else," says a former
<ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> vice president.
   Now, the railroad's efforts to boost rates are straining
relationships with customers. "They had tremendous reductions
in rates to gain market share and then raised rates beyond
what the market will bear," says <PERSON>Philip Yeager</PERSON>, chairman of
<ORGANIZATION>Hub Group</ORGANIZATION>, a Chicago-based shippers' agent. "They have
bewildered the shipping public."
   Company officials say <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> sought to clear up
management confusion last fall by declaring <PERSON>Mr. Holtman</PERSON> head
of the railroad's day-to-day operations while putting <PERSON>Mr.
Mohan</PERSON> in charge of marketing and long-range strategy. Last
month <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> hired <PERSON>Don Orris</PERSON>, a former <ORGANIZATION>American
President Cos.</ORGANIZATION> executive who is highly regarded by shippers,
to give new direction to <LOCATION>Southern Pacific</LOCATION>'s troubled
marketing and sales department.
   Some shippers see signs of improvements. American
President, a big container shipper, recently dropped threats
to abandon the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> after the railroad boosted
on-time delivery of its shipments to <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> has won praise from rail labor. <PERSON>Glynn
Gallagher</PERSON>, a general chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>United Transportation
Union</ORGANIZATION>, says <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> improved relations between
management and labor by retiring a vice president who was
unpopular because of his harsh disciplinary tactics. "We're a
lot better off with <PERSON>Anschutz</PERSON> than we would have been any
other way," says <PERSON>Mr. Gallagher</PERSON>, who is supporting a plan to
sharply reduce crew sizes aboard <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> freight
trains in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Mr. Anschutz</PERSON> tries to accelerate sales of real
estate that company officials value at close to <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>.
The company stunned long-time employees last month by
announcing that the company's <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> headquarters
building may be offered for sale. <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> is also
trying to peddle surplus lines in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION> to the state for rail transit corridors. When state
officials had trouble meeting the company's price for the
lines, <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> contributed <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> to an
environmental group that campaigned for new sources of
transit funding. Californians voted on and passed measures
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, which will provide <MONEY>$1.9 billion</MONEY> for state rail
projects.
   "Voters have said not only that they want these rail
corridors but that they are willing to pay for them and that
can mean a lot of money for us," <PERSON>Mr. Starzel</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861202-0095 </DOCNO>
<HL> Santa Fe Southern Clears One Hurdle
In 3-Year Bid to Merge Railroad Units
---
By Charles F. McCoy
<DD> 12/02/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SFX UNP
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s three-year struggle to merge the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe and Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> railroads cleared one hurdle, but another may have surfaced. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> said it and <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, another railroad concern, agreed on a plan to clear up regulatory concerns that doomed the merger of the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> lines last <DATE>summer</DATE>. 
But at the same time, <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> voiced new objections to a similar agreement between <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> and another competitor. 
Those concerns could further tangle the merger effort. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> was formed in <DATE>1983</DATE> by the combination of <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 
The two companies' energy and other operations were immediately merged, but their railroad units have been kept apart pending <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION> approval. 

   As previously reported, the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> unexpectedly quashed the merger in <DATE>July</DATE> because of worries that the combination would stifle competition across the <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>. 
The rejection, the first time the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> had killed a railroad merger in 20 years, stunned the industry and led many industry officials to fear that the era of consolidation that began two decades ago -- the only thing that has kept many railroad concerns alive -- has ended. 

   Union Pacific originally argued against the merger, which would have created the nation's third-largest rail system. 
The new agreement, which will be submitted to the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> as part of a petition to reopen merger hearings, would give <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> the right to run its trains over some <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> lines in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> and other areas. 
It would also give <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> certain pricing authority and other rights. 

   However, a <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> official said that <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> has "serious problems" with a similar agreement forged between <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific and Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western Railroad Co.</ORGANIZATION>, another competitor that originally opposed the merger. 
In <DATE>September</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> agreed to give <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> access to markets west of <LOCATION>Ogden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>. 
In return, <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> said it would drop its opposition to the combination. 

   But the agreement allows <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> to operate in <LOCATION>central California</LOCATION> for the first time. 
<ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, which has operations in that area, has "problems with that, and that's something we'll have to have addressed" if the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> takes up the merger again, the <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> official said. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said he "wouldn't want to characterize" <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s stance. 
He said <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> intends to go through with its agreement with <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION>. 
"We recognize that not everybody will always be satisfied with these things," he said. 
"That's often the case where the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> is concerned." 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> has been expected to formally ask the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> to reconsider the merger for months. 
The spokesman said the company will submit its appeal to have the merger talks reopened within the next few days. 
It has until <DATE>Dec. 9</DATE> to file the petition, he said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871229-0037 </DOCNO>
<HL> Santa Fe to Sell Southern Pacific to Unit
Of Anschutz; Move Likely to Be Opposed
---
By Francine Schwadel and David J. Jefferson
<DD> 12/29/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SFX HENG LABOR
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION> agreed to sell its <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> railroad unit to <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$1.02 billion</MONEY>, but the proposal is likely to be vigorously contested in regulatory proceedings that could last a year or longer. 

   Two unsuccessful bidders -- <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Railway Labor Executives' Association</ORGANIZATION>, which represents <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> employees -- said they oppose the proposed sale and will continue to pursue their bids. 
"The process has just begun," said <PERSON>Richard I. Kilroy</PERSON>, chairman of the railway association. 

   The proposed sale also drew criticism from <ORGANIZATION>Henley Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a La Jolla, Calif.-based company that holds a <PERCENT>14.7%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Sante Fe</ORGANIZATION>. 
Henley, which has hinted that it is considering a proxy battle or tender offer for <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION>, called the proposal "unwise," saying it "amounts to a bankruptcy auction." 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> decided to sell <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> after the <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION>, citing anti-competitive concerns, ordered the Chicago-based company to shed one of the two railroad units that it has operated since <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
But <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> approval also will be needed for the sale to <LOCATION>Rio Grande</LOCATION>, a railroad unit of <ORGANIZATION>Denver-based Anschutz Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Malcolm Sterrett</PERSON>, one of five <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> commissioners, said the agency hopes to make a decision about the proposed sale "as soon as possible." 
He added, however, that the process could take a year or longer. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> said proceeds from the proposed sale would be used in connection with a plan to pay <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> shareholders at least <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY> in a previously announced restructuring of the railroad and energy concern. 
That plan, which involves additional borrowings, is seen partly as an effort to leverage <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> to make it less attractive to unwanted suitors. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> agreed to pay <MONEY>$1.02 billion</MONEY> in cash for <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> and to assume about <MONEY>$780 million</MONEY> in outstanding debt. 
<PERSON>Robert D. Krebs</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION>'s chief executive officer, said in a prepared statement that the proposed sale "is consistent with the public interest and is in the best interest of our shareholders." 

   However, <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Southern</ORGANIZATION> said its offer, which wasn't disclosed, was "hundreds of <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> higher in value" and faced "fewer regulatory problems." 
A spokeswoman for the <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, Mo.-based railroad pointed out that, when the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> ordered <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> to divest one of its railroad units, the agency commented that merging the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> with the <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> would result in "a loss of railroad competition in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>." 
An <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> official said that didn't necessarily mean the commission would reject the proposed sale. 

   Meanwhile, the railway employees association, which had offered to match any bid, maintained that its proposal was "the most viable in satisfying the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>'s divestiture order and the concerns of employees covered by existing agreements." 

   In <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Denman K. McNear</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, which has operated under a trust for the <DATE>last four years</DATE>, said that management is "disappointed" that its efforts with the railway employees association to buy the railroad "were not favorably considered." 

   Henley, which has interests in manufacturing, engineering and real estate, reiterated its contention that a sale or spinoff of <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION>'s "healthy" <PERSON>Atchison</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Topeka &amp; Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> railroad "would create significant value for shareholders and give the ailing <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> a chance to recover." 

   <PERSON>Michael D. Dingman</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Henley</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman and chief executive officer, declined to say what action his company might take in response to the proposed sale of the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 
The executive called the transaction "a travesty" and said that the proposed sale price is "way under its substantial value." 
However, <PERSON>Mr. Dingman</PERSON> added that "with a company as big as <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> there's still a lot of value there" even without <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Dingman</PERSON> also said that he expects the transaction "to create a turmoil at the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>." 

   A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Olympia &amp; York Developments Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, which holds an <PERCENT>8.2%</PERCENT> stake in <LOCATION>Santa Fe</LOCATION>, said the Toronto-based real estate company didn't plan any immediate comment on the proposed sale. 

   Southern <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>, formally known as the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Transportation Co.</ORGANIZATION>, operates a 13,000-mile system stretching from <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> with a route going from <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western Railroad</ORGANIZATION> unit of <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande Industries</ORGANIZATION> is a 2,500-mile system between <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo</LOCATION>. 

   The combination would create one of the five largest rail systems in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, a 15,500-mile system serving 14 states. 
<PERSON>Samuel R. Freeman</PERSON>, vice president and general counsel for <ORGANIZATION>Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION>, maintained that it would be "an end-to-end merger" that would "restore the competitive balance" in the central <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870129-0177 </DOCNO>
<HL> Santa Fe Southern Sets
Another Pact Aimed
At Aiding Merger Plan</HL>
<DD> 01/29/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SFX
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA) </IN>
<DATELINE> CHICAGO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it reached another agreement aimed at smoothing the way for the proposed merger of its two railway units, the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern</ORGANIZATION> said it reached a binding agreement with the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande Western Railroad Co.</ORGANIZATION>, allowing the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION> to retain access to markets west of <LOCATION>Ogden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>. 
As previously reported, the rail lines reached a tentative accord on rail access last <DATE>September</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>John J. Schmidt</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>, said, "This agreement and those previously announced with <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> and the Missouri-Kansas-Texas railroad have been designed to address adverse competitive impacts identified by the (<ORGANIZATION>Interstate Commerce Commission</ORGANIZATION>) relating to our proposed merger." 

   Last <DATE>July</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION> rejected the proposed merger, which would have formed the nation's third-largest rail system. 
The agency said the merger would be anti-competitive and cited opposition from several railroads, including the <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION> have operated separately since their parents, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, combined in <DATE>1983</DATE> to form <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific</ORGANIZATION>. 

   A petition to reopen the merger case is pending before the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>. 
