<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880707-0169 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-07-88 1344EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-Bergmanat70 Adv14   07-07 0834</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bergman at 70, Adv 14,0857</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv14</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thu AMs, July 14, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Ingmar Bergman Turns 70, Facing Career's Active Twilight</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Bergman's birthday is July 14.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CECILIA LONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Director <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON> is turning 70,
having reached what he calls the twilight of his career but basking
in a run of theater successes.
   Recuperating from a hip operation, <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> is quietly
celebrating his <DATE>July 14 birthday</DATE> at his retreat at <ORGANIZATION>Faro</ORGANIZATION>, a rugged
island of beaches and pine trees in the <LOCATION>Baltic Sea</LOCATION>, with some of
his eight children and his fifth wife, <PERSON>Ingrid</PERSON>.
   Bergman, whose films probed emotions and relationships rarely
touched by others, says he has made his last movie. That was his
<DATE>1982</DATE> triumph ``Fanny and <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON>,'' which won four <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>.
   But he is hardly slowing down, and has theater productions
scheduled in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> until <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   In <DATE>April</DATE> he scored a critical and box office sensation with his
stage production of <PERSON>Eugene O'Neill</PERSON>'s ``Long Day's Journey Into
Night.'' His autobiography, ``Lanterna Magica,'' was a Swedish
bestseller when it was published last year.
   His Swedish-language production of ``Hamlet,'' put in a modern
setting, was panned by some critics here, but was a sensation in
<LOCATION>Florence</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, and won a critics prize last year in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. It
played in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in <DATE>May</DATE>.
   ``Hamlet is on the top 10 list of really good performances,''
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> said in a radio interview. ``It is the best I can do, which
means that I have reached quite far with it,''
   His next directing project will be <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s ``A <DATE>Winter</DATE>'s
Tale,'' at <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>'s 200-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dramatic Theater</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> was not always the cultural hero in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> that he is
today. His volcanic temper didn't help.
   ``He used to refer to anyone who didn't throw furniture around
as `inhibited,'' says <PERSON>Gunnel Lindblom</PERSON>, one of his leading ladies.
   In <DATE>1969</DATE> he was fined heavily for hitting a theater critic known
for his sharp reviews.
   ``And it was worth it,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> said.
   Today he says the critics don't bother him as much.
   ``I don't even get angry,'' he said in the radio interview. ``Of
course when you were young you took it very hard and were very
hurt. But not after 45 years.''
   Now, he says, ``everybody is very kind to me. ... I suppose it
is because I have become old and harmless.''
   His many love affairs, often with women starring in his films,
drew more attention in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> than his art. But his latest marriage
_ his fifth _ has lasted since the early <DATE>1970</DATE>'s.
   In his memoirs he regrets what he describes as his earlier
fickleness and attributes it to sexual obsession.
   ``There were very many years of my life when I was so occupied
with what I was doing that I forgot wives and children. Now since I
am older it has been very nice and rewarding to get to know my
children,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> was <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s youngest theater director at 26 when he was
put in charge of the provincial <ORGANIZATION>Helsingborg City Theater</ORGANIZATION> in
southern <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>. The theatrical tradition, he says, has always been
the real influence on his art.
   He is best known for directing more than 50 films, most of which
he wrote himself. He won three Oscars for best foreign films: ``The
Virgin Spring'' in <DATE>1960</DATE>, ``Through a Glass Darkly'' in <DATE>1962</DATE> and
``Fanny and Alexander.''
   To mark the birthday, the <ORGANIZATION>Swedish Film Institute</ORGANIZATION> published a
special English-language edition of its magazine, <PERSON>Chaplin</PERSON>, paying
homage to the director who made his first film in <DATE>1944</DATE> and who
launched the careers of such international stars as <PERSON>Liv Ulmann</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Bibi Andersson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Max von Sydow</PERSON>.
   ``<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> is probably the greatest film artist, all things
considered, since the invention of the motion-picture camera,''
wrote <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON>, one of a dozen international directors
contributing to the 90-page tribute.
   Sir <PERSON>Richard Attenborough</PERSON>, the British director, said <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>
``extended the medium (of film) in a manner unequalled by any of
his contemporaries.''
   For some four decades <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> divided his time between theater
and film, likening the two forums to ``my wife and my mistress.''
After ``Fanny and Alexander'' he said he was giving up his
``mistress'' and devoting himself to the stage. Since then he
produced only one Swedish television film in <DATE>1984</DATE>, ``After the
Repetition.''
   ``Fanny and Alexander'' was a multi-levelled story of a
well-to-do family at the <DATE>turn of the century</DATE>, which appeared to
have traces of <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s own childhood with his clergyman father.
   The film marked <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s return to <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> after six years in
self-imposed exile in <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1976</DATE> he was hauled away by
police during a rehearsal and accused of tax violations. He was
cleared, but left the country in disgust.
   He is now back at the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dramatic Theater</ORGANIZATION>, where he saw his
first play at the age of 12 and where he was the director from <DATE>1963</DATE>
to <DATE>1966</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Thurs AMs July 14</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880713-0243 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-13-88 0440EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-Bergmanat70 Adv14-1stLd-Writethru b0368 07-13 0907</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bergman at 70, Adv 14-1st Ld-Writethru, b0368,0930</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv14</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thu AMs, July 14, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Ingmar Bergman Turns 70, Facing Career's Active Twilight</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: DELETES reference in 2nd graf to Bergman recuperating from
hip operation. INSERTS new third graf saying hip operation
postponed. Picks up 3rd graf pvs ``Bergman, whose ...'' Bergman's
birthday is July 14.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CECILIA LONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Director <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON> is turning 70,
having reached what he calls the twilight of his career but basking
in a run of theater successes.
   Bergman is quietly celebrating his <DATE>July 14 birthday</DATE> at his
retreat at <ORGANIZATION>Faro</ORGANIZATION>, a rugged island of beaches and pine trees in the
<LOCATION>Baltic Sea</LOCATION>, with some of his eight children and his fifth wife,
<PERSON>Ingrid</PERSON>.
   Associates describe his health as good, although he suffers from
a painful hip. But <PERSON>Gote Eriksson</PERSON>, planning director of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal
Dramatic Theater</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> was ``in good form'' at the premier
of his latest play in <DATE>April</DATE>, and postponed a hip operation which
had been scheuled for <DATE>May</DATE>.
   Bergman, whose films probed emotions and relationships rarely
touched by others, says he has made his last movie. That was his
<DATE>1982</DATE> triumph ``Fanny and <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON>,'' which won four <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>.
   But he is hardly slowing down, and has theater productions
scheduled in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> until <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   In <DATE>April</DATE> he scored a critical and box office sensation with his
stage production of <PERSON>Eugene O'Neill</PERSON>'s ``Long Day's Journey Into
Night.'' His autobiography, ``Lanterna Magica,'' was a Swedish
bestseller when it was published last year.
   His Swedish-language production of ``Hamlet,'' put in a modern
setting, was panned by some critics here, but was a sensation in
<LOCATION>Florence</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, and won a critics prize last year in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. It
played in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in <DATE>May</DATE>.
   ``Hamlet is on the top 10 list of really good performances,''
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> said in a radio interview. ``It is the best I can do, which
means that I have reached quite far with it,''
   His next directing project will be <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s ``A <DATE>Winter</DATE>'s
Tale,'' at <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>'s 200-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dramatic Theater</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> was not always the cultural hero in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> that he is
today. His volcanic temper didn't help.
   ``He used to refer to anyone who didn't throw furniture around
as `inhibited,'' says <PERSON>Gunnel Lindblom</PERSON>, one of his leading ladies.
   In <DATE>1969</DATE> he was fined heavily for hitting a theater critic known
for his sharp reviews.
   ``And it was worth it,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> said.
   Today he says the critics don't bother him as much.
   ``I don't even get angry,'' he said in the radio interview. ``Of
course when you were young you took it very hard and were very
hurt. But not after 45 years.''
   Now, he says, ``everybody is very kind to me. ... I suppose it
is because I have become old and harmless.''
   His many love affairs, often with women starring in his films,
drew more attention in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> than his art. But his latest marriage
_ his fifth _ has lasted since the early <DATE>1970</DATE>'s.
   In his memoirs he regrets what he describes as his earlier
fickleness and attributes it to sexual obsession.
   ``There were very many years of my life when I was so occupied
with what I was doing that I forgot wives and children. Now since I
am older it has been very nice and rewarding to get to know my
children,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> was <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s youngest theater director at 26 when he was
put in charge of the provincial <ORGANIZATION>Helsingborg City Theater</ORGANIZATION> in
southern <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>. The theatrical tradition, he says, has always been
the real influence on his art.
   He is best known for directing more than 50 films, most of which
he wrote himself. He won three Oscars for best foreign films: ``The
Virgin Spring'' in <DATE>1960</DATE>, ``Through a Glass Darkly'' in <DATE>1962</DATE> and
``Fanny and Alexander.''
   To mark the birthday, the <ORGANIZATION>Swedish Film Institute</ORGANIZATION> published a
special English-language edition of its magazine, <PERSON>Chaplin</PERSON>, paying
homage to the director who made his first film in <DATE>1944</DATE> and who
launched the careers of such international stars as <PERSON>Liv Ulmann</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Bibi Andersson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Max von Sydow</PERSON>.
   ``<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> is probably the greatest film artist, all things
considered, since the invention of the motion-picture camera,''
wrote <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON>, one of a dozen international directors
contributing to the 90-page tribute.
   Sir <PERSON>Richard Attenborough</PERSON>, the British director, said <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>
``extended the medium (of film) in a manner unequalled by any of
his contemporaries.''
   For some four decades <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> divided his time between theater
and film, likening the two forums to ``my wife and my mistress.''
After ``Fanny and Alexander'' he said he was giving up his
``mistress'' and devoting himself to the stage. Since then he
produced only one Swedish television film in <DATE>1984</DATE>, ``After the
Repetition.''
   ``Fanny and Alexander'' was a multi-levelled story of a
well-to-do family at the <DATE>turn of the century</DATE>, which appeared to
have traces of <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s own childhood with his clergyman father.
   The film marked <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s return to <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> after six years in
self-imposed exile in <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1976</DATE> he was hauled away by
police during a rehearsal and accused of tax violations. He was
cleared, but left the country in disgust.
   He is now back at the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dramatic Theater</ORGANIZATION>, where he saw his
first play at the age of 12 and where he was the director from <DATE>1963</DATE>
to <DATE>1966</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Thurs AMs July 14</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880408-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-88 1151EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:TheatricalSons Adv12   04-08 0902</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Theatrical Sons, Adv 12,0928</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv 12</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Tues PMs, April 12 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Max von Sydow and Ingmar Bergman Return Home</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After quarrels with the tax collector,
<LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s favorite theatrical sons have come home.
   <PERSON>Max von Sydow</PERSON> is back on the Swedish stage after a 14-year
absence. Director <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>, who lived in self-imposed exile
for several years, also is rehearsing a new play.
   Both <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>, whose brooding, introspective films in the <DATE>1950s</DATE>
and '60s gave Swedish film an international reputation, and von
<PERSON>Sydow</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s most durable actor, left the country because of tax
problems.
   Von <PERSON>Sydow</PERSON>, who lives in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> but comes back every year for
<DATE>summer</DATE> vacation, never thought of himself as an expatriate and has
returned twice to make films.
   ``I'm still totally Swedish,'' he said. ``I still have my roots
here.''
   Swedish taxes, among the highest in the world, are driving young
artists away, he said in an interview. The average Swede pays half
his salary in taxes, and marginal tax on top incomes can run as
high as <PERCENT>78 percent</PERCENT>.
   ``A lot of talent is not used in this country because of this.
If you don't get anything financially out of it, why work here?''
said von <PERSON>Sydow</PERSON>, 58.
   Among his 40 foreign film roles are the Jesuit priest in ``The
Exorcist,'' the assassin in ``Three Days of the Condor,'' and the
artist@husband in <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON>'s ``Hannah and Her Sisters.'' He
launched his career abroad in <DATE>1965</DATE> as Jesus in ``The Greatest Story
Ever Told.''
   Von <PERSON>Sydow</PERSON> left <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> in a huff in <DATE>1973</DATE> after paying what he
said was an unfairly large tax bill. He was assessed <MONEY>$20,050</MONEY> for
allegedly underpaying his taxes. His lawyers took the case to the
<ORGANIZATION>European Human Rights Commission</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>, claiming that the lack of
an appeal mechanism against the tax authorities was an infringement
of his rights. Last year, the Swedish government settled out of
court, repaying him <MONEY>$33,333</MONEY> compensation and <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> for costs.
   Von <PERSON>Sydow</PERSON> said he is trying to put the tax affair behind him
without bitterness.
   ``I'm trying not to be poisoned by paranoia,'' he said. ``Today
I feel freer than when I left, because this problem is solved and
because I know that if I want to I could work abroad all the time.''
   His ties to his country are stronger than others have shown.
Once Hollywood made stars of <PERSON>Greta Garbo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ingrid Bergman</PERSON>, they
were gone from <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> for good.
   Von <PERSON>Sydow</PERSON> is playing at the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dramatic Theater</ORGANIZATION>, where he
began his acting career 40 years ago and where he met <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>, with
whom he did 11 films.
   He said one reason for returning to the stage was fascination
with the character he was offered in ``Master Olof,'' an <DATE>1871</DATE> drama
by <PERSON>August Strindberg</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s greatest literary figure.
   He plays a roguish revolutionary during the 16th-century Swedish
Reformation. It's a supporting role, but von <PERSON>Sydow</PERSON> said he doesn't
care. ``It's the best part in the play,'' he said.
   He said he also was drawn by the double anniversary of the royal
theater's 200th year and the 80th year since it moved to its gilded
waterfront building, now a city landmark.
   Working in the Swedish language again ``is wonderful, it's
exciting,'' he said. ``It's still very difficult for me to act in
English, and it always will be. ... It takes a longer time to
really make the lines your own.''
   Last year von <PERSON>Sydow</PERSON>, who does three projects a year, finished
``Pelle the Conqueror,'' his first Swedish-language film in five
years.
   The title role of <LOCATION>Pelle</LOCATION>, a peasant farmhand, could have been
tailored for the tall, blond Swede with a farmer's weatherbeaten
look and huge hands. The role won him the prestigious Swedish
Golden Bug Award as best actor in <DATE>1987</DATE> and two Danish acting
prizes, one by critics and one by the film academy. The film will
be entered in the <LOCATION>Cannes</LOCATION> Film Festival.
   ``It's such a rich character,'' he said. ``He is so vulnerable
and so miserable; he is full of expectations, he is terribly
disappointed, he is very happy, he is furious. ... It's probably
the best part I've ever had.''
   Von <PERSON>Sydow</PERSON> also is directing his first movie, a Danish-language
film called ``Along the Roadside.''
   <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>, 69, is directing his fifth play since returning from
<LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, where he lived for about five years until he came
back in <DATE>1982</DATE> to film the acclaimed ``Fanny and Alexander.''
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, tax inspectors barged into a rehearsal and took the
famed director away for questioning on suspicion of tax evasion. He
was cleared of all charges, but he wrote in his <DATE>1987</DATE> autobiography
that the incident drove him into a depression that turned to rage
against his country.
   At the same time, he was uncomfortable away from <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>.
   ``I felt like an invalid who had lost an arm and a leg,'' he
wrote in his autobiography, ``Magic Lantern.''
   ``I longed for the old language, the friends and the
companionship.''
   <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s staging of <PERSON>Eugene O'Neill</PERSON>'s ``Long Day's Journey Into
Night'' reunites him with <PERSON>Bibi Andersson</PERSON> whom he discovered in a
soap advertisement in <DATE>1952</DATE> and launched as an international actress.
   Andersson, 53, left acting for several years to work in peace
causes, but came back to the stage in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PM Tues April 12</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880429-0142 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-29-88 1301EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Bergman Bjt   04-29 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bergman, Bjt,0627</SECOND>
<HEAD>Critics Rave As Bergman Stages A Classic</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto STO1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CECILIA LONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>'s staging of ``Long
Day's Journey Into Night'' is a smash with audiences and critics
more than three decades after the play premiered on the same
<LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION> stage.
   The revival of <PERSON>Eugene O'Neill</PERSON>'s classic at the <ORGANIZATION>National Dramatic
Theater</ORGANIZATION> earned what one critic called the best review he ever
wrote. The play opened <DATE>April 17</DATE> and is sold out through <DATE>August</DATE>.
   This triumph for <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>, who turns 70 on <DATE>July 14</DATE>, comes at a
time the director describes as the twilight of his career. He has
said he has made his last film.
   But his schedule is unusual for a man claiming to approach
retirement. His modernized Swedish-language version of Hamlet won
plaudits in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. The play goes to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in <DATE>June</DATE>.
   He also is preparing <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s ``A <DATE>Winter</DATE>'s Tale,'' and an
opera to open here in <DATE>1991</DATE>. In <DATE>November</DATE>, he published a
best-selling autobiography, ``Magic Lantern.''
   But seldom in his 50-year career has the applause of his home
critics been louder than for the <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> play.
   ``This is sensational. World theater, if anything,'' wrote
<PERSON>Ingmar Bjorksten</PERSON>, drama critic of the <ORGANIZATION>Svenska Dagbladet</ORGANIZATION>, in what he
called his most enthusiastic review ever.
   <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s handling of the play was ``full of human knowledge''
and marked by a ``sympathy and warmth unusual for him.''
   ``Brilliant,'' headlined Aftonbladet, which published three
glowing reviews. It called <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> ``a brilliant editor'' for
cutting an hour from the original script ``with nothing of
<PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON>'s essentials removed.''
   The play stars <PERSON>Bibi Andersson</PERSON>, whom <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> launched on an
international career in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and with whom he had a two-year
affair 30 years ago.
   ``I have never experienced such box office pressure for a play
like this. People are writing and calling from all over the
country, even <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>,'' theater director <PERSON>Lars Lofgren</PERSON>
told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Dramatic Theater, which celebrates its centennial this year,
was given the rights to stage the world premiere of <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON>'s
unpublished plays after his death in <DATE>1953</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Tom Olsson</PERSON>, the theater's librarian and an <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> scholar, said
that according to the playwright's widow <ORGANIZATION>Carlotta</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> was
pleased with the theater's handling of his early plays and their
success on the Swedish stage.
   ``Long Day's Journey'' premiered on <DATE>Feb. 10, 1956</DATE>, and the play
was such a hit that it entered theatrical legend here. It won the
<DATE>1957</DATE> Pulitzer Prize for drama.
   <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> was absent from the revival's opening night 32 years
later. He said later he was looking after his flu-stricken wife,
<PERSON>Ingrid</PERSON>, and did not want to draw attention from the actors.
   His associates said <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> also was suffering from a painful
hip which plagued him through the rehearsals and was scheduled for
an operation shortly after the premiere.
   But he received a special ovation when the ensemble bowed to an
empty seat in the first row after their ninth curtain call.
   Bergman's movies, which he began making in the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, won world
acclaim for their brooding explorations of troubled relationships.
   Outraged by an charge of tax evasion which was later dropped,
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> lived in self-imposed exile in <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> for seven
years, before returning home in <DATE>1982</DATE> to direct the film ``Fanny and
Alexander.''
   <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s 70th birthday is likely to be the subject of national
celebrations. Chaplin magazine, published by the Swedish Film
Institute, published a 90-page English-language special edition in
<DATE>April</DATE> with tributes from leading movie directors.
   ``Probably the greatest film artist, all things considered,
since the invention of the motion picture camera,'' said <PERSON>Woody
Allen</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890927-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-27-89 0138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e PM-APArts:Bergman     09-27 0742</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Bergman,0762</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ingmar Bergman Writes Revealing Play About his Parents</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As a child, <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>'s parents
locked him in a dark closet when he disobeyed. To amuse himself, he
beamed a flashlight with a colored light onto the wall and
pretended he was at the movies.
   Now 71, the famed director has written a screenplay about his
father, <PERSON>Erik Bergman</PERSON>, an insecure and depression-prone pastor, and
his mother, <PERSON>Karin</PERSON>, a woman of iron self-discipline who cringed at
any show of love.
   In ``Good Intentions,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> casts back his memory and his
imagination to the first 10 years of his parent's turbulent
relationship and marriage.
   The play is a six-hour chronicle in four acts, to be shown as a
four-part television series and a two-part movie. Production begins
late next year, and the scheduled premiere will be on Swedish
television Channel One in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   ``I feel a great need to tell the story of these two people who
are in my blood, my nerves and my genes,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> said.
   Bergman gave up film direction after his <DATE>1982</DATE> ``Fanny and
<PERSON>Alexander</PERSON>,'' which won four <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>. Since then, he has been
busy producing stage plays at the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dramatic Theater</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>, which once rejected him for a job when he was an
aspiring 21-year-old production assistant.
   For ``Good Intentions,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> vacated the director's chair to
Danish filmmaker <PERSON>Bille August</PERSON>, whose ``Pelle the Conqueror'' won
the <DATE>1989</DATE> Academy Award for best foreign film. <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> said that
after he saw ``Pelle'' six times, the choice of the 40-year-old
<PERSON>Dane</PERSON> was obvious.
   August called the screenplay ``one of the best love stories I
have ever read. It is a great drama and an honor to take part in
delivering.''
   As evidenced in his confession-like autobiography, ``The Magic
Lantern,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> has been grappling with confusion for many years
over his feelings for his parents.
   They have appeared on screen before, in some of the best of
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s 50 films. In ``Fanny and <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON>,'' a soft-spoken
clergymen slowly exposes himself as consumed with fanaticism and
hatred.
   The <DATE>1973</DATE> film ``Cries and Whispers'' is about three sisters and
a servant girl. <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> has said they represent four aspects of his
mother, whom he was seeking to understand through his characters.
   He nurtured the idea for ``Good Intentions'' ever since
completing ``Fanny and Alexander.'' In his memoirs, he wrote about
his parents from his childhood perspective, which was often brutal
and angry.
   It left him unsatisfied. ``I started writing about all the
dreams and memories of my parents. Finally, I had a script,'' he
said. It took him five months <DATE>last year</DATE> to write it.
   The new film promises a sympathetic look at a young couple, a
theology student and a somewhat spoiled young woman from an
affluent home. The characters have fictional names, which allows
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> to play with facts.
   The movie covers the time of the couple's meeting in <DATE>1909</DATE> to the
year of <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s birth in <DATE>1918</DATE>.
   In his memoirs, <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> wrote about his failure to reach his
parents and his own attempts to hide despair by burying any display
of feeling. His emotions, he said, ``inhabited a closed room and
were produced on command, but never rashly.''
   He was raised according to ``the concepts of sin, confession,
punishment, forgiveness and grace _ concrete factors in
relationships between children, parents and God.''
   He described his father, a Lutheran minister, as ``nervous,
irritable and depressive. ... He was always fretting and given to
violent outbursts of temper.''
   His mother ``was always tense, slept badly and used strong
remedies which had side effects causing restlessness and anxiety.
Like Father, she was haunted by a sense of inadequacy.''
   The book barely touches on his parent's feelings for each other,
but a stormy picture emerges when it does.
   As a child, he recalled seeing them in a fierce argument and
scuffle. ``We didn't know that Mother had gone through a passionate
love affair or that Father suffered from severe depression. Mother
was preparing to break out of her marriage, Father threatening to
take his own life.''
   Divorce in those days was almost unthinkable, especially for a
respected pastor, and the church stepped in to reconcile the couple.
   Yet the reconciliation was mostly for show. ``What was outwardly
an irreproachable picture of good family unity was inwardly misery
and exhausting conflicts,'' he wrote.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890922-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-22-89 1400EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e AM-APArts:Bergman Adv27   09-22 0756</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AP Arts: Bergman, Adv 27,0775</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday AMs, Sept. 27, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ingmar Bergman Writes Revealing Play About His Parents</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As a child, <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>'s parents
locked him in a dark closet when he disobeyed. To amuse himself, he
beamed a flashlight with a colored light onto the wall and pretended
he was at the movies.
   Now 71, the famed director has written a screenplay about his
father, <PERSON>Erik Bergman</PERSON>, an insecure and depression-prone pastor, and
his mother, <PERSON>Karin</PERSON>, a woman of iron self-discipline who cringed at
any show of love.
   In ``Good Intentions,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> casts back his memory and his
imagination to the first 10 years of his parent's turbulent
relationship and marriage.
   The play is a six-hour chronicle in four acts, to be shown as a
four-part television series and a two-part movie. Production begins
late next year, and the scheduled premiere will be on Swedish
television Channel One in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   ``I feel a great need to tell the story of these two people who
are in my blood, my nerves and my genes,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> said.
   Bergman gave up film direction after his <DATE>1982</DATE> ``Fanny and
<PERSON>Alexander</PERSON>,'' which won four <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>. Since then, he has been
busy producing stage plays at the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dramatic Theater</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>, which once rejected him for a job when he was an aspiring
21-year-old production assistant.
   For ``Good Intentions,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> vacated the director's chair to
Danish filmmaker <PERSON>Bille August</PERSON>, whose ``Pelle the Conqueror'' won the
<DATE>1989</DATE> Academy Award for best foreign film. <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> said that after he
saw ``Pelle'' six times, the choice of the 40-year-old <PERSON>Dane</PERSON> was
obvious.
   August called the screenplay ``one of the best love stories I
have ever read. It is a great drama and an honor to take part in
delivering.''
   As evidenced in his confession-like autobiography, ``The Magic
Lantern,'' <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> has been grappling with confusion for many years
over his feelings for his parents.
   They have appeared on screen before, in some of the best of
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s 50 films. In ``Fanny and <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON>,'' a soft-spoken
clergymen slowly exposes himself as consumed with fanaticism and
hatred.
   The <DATE>1973</DATE> film ``Cries and Whispers'' is about three sisters and a
servant girl. <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> has said they represent four aspects of his
mother, whom he was seeking to understand through his characters.
   He nurtured the idea for ``Good Intentions'' ever since
completing ``Fanny and Alexander.'' In his memoirs, he wrote about
his parents from his childhood perspective, which was often brutal
and angry.
   It left him unsatisfied. ``I started writing about all the dreams
and memories of my parents. Finally, I had a script,'' he said. It
took him five months <DATE>last year</DATE> to write it.
   The new film promises a sympathetic look at a young couple, a
theology student and a somewhat spoiled young woman from an affluent
home. The characters have fictional names, which allows <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> to
play with facts.
   The movie covers the time of the couple's meeting in <DATE>1909</DATE> to the
year of <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s birth in <DATE>1918</DATE>.
   In his memoirs, <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> wrote about his failure to reach his
parents and his own attempts to hide despair by burying any display
of feeling. His emotions, he said, ``inhabited a closed room and
were produced on command, but never rashly.''
   He was raised according to ``the concepts of sin, confession,
punishment, forgiveness and grace _ concrete factors in
relationships between children, parents and God.''
   He described his father, a Lutheran minister, as ``nervous,
irritable and depressive. ... He was always fretting and given to
violent outbursts of temper.''
   His mother ``was always tense, slept badly and used strong
remedies which had side effects causing restlessness and anxiety.
Like Father, she was haunted by a sense of inadequacy.''
   The book barely touches on his parent's feelings for each other,
but a stormy picture emerges when it does.
   As a child, he recalled seeing them in a fierce argument and
scuffle. ``We didn't know that Mother had gone through a passionate
love affair or that Father suffered from severe depression. Mother
was preparing to break out of her marriage, Father threatening to
take his own life.''
   Divorce in those days was almost unthinkable, especially for a
respected pastor, and the church stepped in to reconcile the couple.
   Yet the reconciliation was mostly for show. ``What was outwardly
an irreproachable picture of good family unity was inwardly misery
and exhausting conflicts,'' he wrote.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed AMs, Sept. 27</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880902-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-88 1223EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Sweden-Arts Bjt   09-02 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sweden-Arts, Bjt,0587</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sounds of Silince: Sweden Goes Three Minutes Without Culture</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pavarotti stayed off the stage, movies
stopped in midreel, concert halls were hushed and radio programs
fell silent.
   Cultural life in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> came to a halt for three minutes at <TIME>8:15
p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when actors, musicians, dancers, and even librarians
protested what they called the low level of government support.
   Artists in most countries might be envious of the Swedes.
Stockholm, capital of a country of 8.4 million people, has as many
theaters as <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. Artists can get state grants, but they say it
isn't enough to live on.
   State-supported theaters have launched the careers of director
<PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON> and actors such as <PERSON>Ingrid Bergman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Max von Sydow</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Ingrid Tulin</PERSON>.
   The nation which awards the Nobel prize for literature sells 2.5
million theater tickets a year, nearly one for every third person.
   In an article published <DATE>Friday</DATE>, actress <PERSON>Bibi Andersson</PERSON> protested
that the cultural assistance were too low, projects were too
vulnerable to cuts, and grants were too snagged in bureaucratic
tangles.
   ``Why do actors have to get swallowed up in bureaucracy? Why do
fiery spirits grow tired?'' she wrote in the Aftonbladet daily.
   ``What we wanted was to make culture an election issue,'' she
said, referring to the <DATE>Sept. 18</DATE> national elections. ``It's a
question of priorities.''
   ``The strike was a success for the artists. They got a lot of
attention and managed to get their message across,'' said <PERSON>Martin
Lindbloom</PERSON>, spokesman of the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Education and Culture</ORGANIZATION>.
   In the west coast city of <LOCATION>Goteborg</LOCATION>, touring opera tenor <PERSON>Luciano
Pavarotti</PERSON> delayed the start of his performance by three minutes in
support of the strike. His audience stood in silence during that
time.
   One channel of the state-run television broke into its regular
program for live reports showing movie theaters with darkened
screens, silent stages and a candlelight vigil in <LOCATION>Goteborg</LOCATION> by 400
people. Two radio channels were quiet, while the third played <PERSON>Simon</PERSON>
and <ORGANIZATION>Garfunkel</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Sounds of Silence.''
   At <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Dramatic Theater</ORGANIZATION>, the staging of <PERSON>Eugene
O'Neill</PERSON>'s ``Long Day's Journey Into Night'' gave the protest a
unique twist.
   At precisely <TIME>8:15 p.m.</TIME>, the young artist <PERSON>Edmund</PERSON> delivered his
line, ``I'm broke.'' Action froze on stage for three minutes, then
<PERSON>Edmund</PERSON>'s father resumed the play with the reply: ``You're always
broke, and you always will be.''
   Official figures cited by Lindbloom say national support for the
arts is nearly as high in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> as in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, and more than
anywhere else in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
   Direct yearly support amounts to <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY>, and municipal
subsidies to local cutural establishment is about <MONEY>$937 million</MONEY>,
<PERSON>Lindbloom</PERSON> said.
   Together with indirect help, such as building new museums or
libraries, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> spends about <PERCENT>1.5 percent</PERCENT> of its gross national
product on the arts, he told the <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>.
   Although nothing has been trimmed from the national budget,
local authorities slash cultural projects first whenever they run
into trouble, complained <PERSON>Ingmar Bjorksten</PERSON>, the cultural affairs
correspondent for <ORGANIZATION>Svenska Dagbladet</ORGANIZATION>.
   Unemployment among artists is five times the national average of
just under <PERCENT>2 percent</PERCENT>, <PERSON>Bjorksten</PERSON> wrote.
   ``The only way for culture to get more money is to make a
fuss,'' said <PERSON>Svante Weyner</PERSON>, head of <LOCATION>Radio Sweden</LOCATION>'s cultural
division. Last year the radio cut the budget for a popular program
of radio plays. The budget was restored only after <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>
intervened.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881003-0215 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf: Director Peers at Self Through Glass Darkly </HL>
<AUTHOR> Cynthia Grenier </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   Seventy seems to be the age these days when famous directors at last feel free enough in spirit to present themselves naked to the world, showing all their warts in tight close-up. 

   Earlier this <DATE>summer</DATE> we had <PERSON>Elia Kazan</PERSON> baring his soul in some 700 pages; now it is the turn of <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>, who in "The Magic Lantern" (Viking, <MONEY>$19.95</MONEY>) manages in a scant 308 pages to document abundantly just how monstrous a monstre sacre he is. 
Like <PERSON>Mr. Kazan</PERSON>, the little <PERSON>Ingmar</PERSON> was an unhappy child who grew into a veritable adolescent nerd. 
He adored his mother, but she often sent him away with "cool ironic words," leaving him weeping with rage and disappointment. 
He discovered that illness immediately attracted her attention, and embarked on a lifetime of stomach disorders and nearly unremitting nervous maladies. 
The onset of the production of every new film or play always sent him off to a clinic for a few weeks. 

   Life with mother proved singularly trying for Ingmar. 
When he was 55, his mother phoned him at his theater to tell him that his father was in the hospital, about to be operated on for a malignant tumor. 
"She wanted me to go see him." 
Ingmar explained that he had neither the time nor the desire to do so, that his father was a person to whom he was indifferent, and that his presence could only frighten and embarrass his father on what was sure to be his deathbed. 
"Mother was angry." 
She persisted. 
"I was upset and refused to be emotionally blackmailed. 
This eternal blackmail." 
His mother began crying; Ingmar hung up on her. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Bergman</PERSON>'s relations with his many wives, many more children, siblings and women friends are described briefly and chillingly. 
He does record that his then-19-year-old son, <PERSON>Ingmar Jr.</PERSON>, after the death of his mother in an automobile accident, looked at him "with a cold contempt that silenced me." 
<PERSON>Harriet Anderson</PERSON>, star of so many <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> films, (and the cause of the breakup with <PERSON>Ingmar Jr.</PERSON>'s mother during the making of "Summer With Monika") is about the only person to receive kind or generous words in the book. 
For a really icy chill, consider <PERSON>Mr. Bergman</PERSON>'s description of <PERSON>Greta Garbo</PERSON> past her prime: "Her mouth was ugly, a pale slit surrounded by transverse wrinkles. 
It was strange and disturbing. 
All that beauty and in the middle of the beauty a shrill discord. 
No plastic surgeon or makeup man could conjure away that mouth and what it told me." 

   The man is cruel. 

   Reading this autobiography may prove an unnerving experience to those for whom "Wild Strawberries," "Smiles of a Summer Night" and "The Seventh Seal" affectionately are seminal film memories of youth. 
<PERSON>Mr. Bergman</PERSON> shows us their creator as a man eaten alive by his demons: cold, selfish, petty, mean. 
<PERSON>Mr. Bergman</PERSON> does tell us he knew he had persuasive powers, "that I could make people do what I wanted them to do, that I had some kind of surface charm which I could switch on and off at will." 

   Indeed, in reading these memoirs I had to remind myself constantly that when I spent many hours in his company about 20 years ago, I found him one of the most charming individuals I had ever met. 
At the time, <PERSON>Mr. Bergman</PERSON> said that he could not bear dealing with his own male peers. 
Only men much younger or much older were acceptable to him. 
If he discovered they were disadvantaged in some way, say, by being homosexual or Jewish, this discovery seemed to relax him socially. 
So too with women he appeared to enjoy this edge of advantage. 
Women also fascinated him almost as a species. 
He would become utterly absorbed getting to know a woman. 
His interest and curiosity had no bounds. 
Perhaps at 70, however, <PERSON>Mr. Bergman</PERSON> feels the need to charm is over. 
There is certainly no charm at all in this book. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Bergman</PERSON> seems to be saying: Here I am, a thoroughly hateful individual. 
Take me as I am -- if you can. 
He lays out evidence in abundance, even to telling how at age 15 in <LOCATION>Weimar</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, he took part in a Nazi rally. 
"I shouted like everyone else, held out my arm like everyone else, howled like everyone else and loved it like everyone else." 
The speaker at the rally was <PERSON>Adolf Hitler</PERSON>. 
"I loved {<PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>}," says <PERSON>Mr. Bergman</PERSON>. 
"For many years, I was on Hitler's side, delighted by his successes and saddened by his defeats." 
His brother was one of the founders and organizers of the <ORGANIZATION>Swedish National-Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION>, and several times his father voted for the party's candidates. 
It was only well after the war that the now-adult <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> finally accepted that the concentration camps were not "prearranged propaganda lies." 

   Still, at 70, <PERSON>Mr. Bergman</PERSON> faces into the dark night, "neither able nor willing to imagine another life, some kind of life beyond the frontier -- the perspective is appalling." 
He ends his autobiography with an entry purportedly from his mother's diary, a few days after his birth. 
"I pray to God with no confidence. 
One will probably have to manage alone as best one can." 

   ---
   <PERSON>Ms. Grenier</PERSON>, formerly a vice president at <ORGANIZATION>United Artists</ORGANIZATION>, is a senior editor at The World and I magazine. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111690-0048 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 308714 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 16, 1990, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 26; Column 5; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
517 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MOVIE REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
1957 BERGMAN CLASSIC RELATES INNER JOURNEY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARK CHALON SMITH, SPECIAL TO THE TIMES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Dreaming is emblematic of <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>'s "Wild Strawberries." This masterful 
Swedish director at first submerges us in his old hero's nightmare, and later, 
the film finds its own dimension where reality is often enveloped by fantasy. 
</P>
<P>
The first scenes set the tone and course for this <DATE>1957</DATE> movie, screening tonight 
at <ORGANIZATION>UC Irvine</ORGANIZATION>. Hallucinatory is one way to describe the beginning, as we're 
introduced to <PERSON>Isak Borg</PERSON> (<PERSON>Victor Sjostrom</PERSON>), a 78-year-old doctor known for his 
toughness. He's lying in bed, having a dream that eventually becomes a 
nightmare. 
</P>
<P>
In it, <PERSON>Isak</PERSON> is wandering down a street. Everything seems calm, but then <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> 
lays out a series of metaphors -- timepieces without hands; a rushing, 
out-of-control hearse drawn by black horses; a pervading isolation that comes 
from the deserted town square. 
</P>
<P>
When the hearse crashes, a coffin falls out. The corpse, suddenly alive, 
reaches out to <PERSON>Isak</PERSON>, who sees that it's he who is dead. He wakes up with 
thoughts of his mortality and decides to drive instead of fly to a distant 
university where he will be given an honorary degree. 
</P>
<P>
Isak takes along his lovely daughter-in-law (<ORGANIZATION>Ingrid Thulin</ORGANIZATION>) and picks up three 
young hitchhikers (<PERSON>Bibi Andersson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bjorn Bjelvenstam</PERSON> and <PERSON>Folke Sundquist</PERSON>) after 
they stop at his boyhood home. All three, especially the girl among them, are 
spirited, and their presence revitalizes Isak. 
</P>
<P>
Isak and his companions are now traveling in the real world, but Isak can't 
escape the earlier dream. The foreshadowing becomes overshadowing as <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> 
thrusts Isak into several dreamlike reveries, juxtaposing the present with his 
uneasy past. The trip becomes an odyssey of self-revelation, regret and 
grudging acceptance. 
</P>
<P>
Like "The Seventh Seal," which was released a year before, "Wild Strawberries" 
initially baffled many critics, who found the symbolism too personal and 
arcane. It did poorly in limited release in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> but soon became a favorite 
of the art houses. <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s early films, like those of Fellini, were the first 
international cult movies. 
</P>
<P>
The critics' complaints seem odd now. <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s vision is unique, but there's a 
universal sweep to <PERSON>Isak</PERSON>'s self-absorption and the way the director describes it 
that speaks to everyone who has considered the path of their lives. 
</P>
<P>
This is, to be sure, a film of great melancholy and introspection without a 
happy or heroic resolution. At times, all the pondering freezes the action, 
requiring our patience and attention. "Wild Strawberries," a true classic, is 
as far away from an easy Hollywood movie as you can get. 
</P>
<P>
It has much to offer, from <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s exploration of the narrative form to the 
script's reliance on the subconscious for inspiration. On a scholarly level, 
the film displays <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s career-long preoccupations with death, spiritual 
truth and rejuvenation. They've become his signatures. 
</P>
<P>
 <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>'s "Wild Strawberries" will be screened tonight at 7 and 9 at <ORGANIZATION>UC 
Irvine's Student Center Crystal Cove Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> as part of the <ORGANIZATION>UCI</ORGANIZATION> Film Society 
Directors' Personal Portraits series. Tickets: <MONEY>$2</MONEY> to <MONEY>$4</MONEY>. (714) 856-6379. 
</P><P></P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Motion Picture Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-15472</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CGBA7ABFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920702
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 JUL 92 / Arts: Family emotions pared to the bone - Cinema
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIGEL ANDREWS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE BEST INTENTIONS (12) <LOCATION>Lumiere</LOCATION>, Gate Notting Hill
THE RAPTURE (18) MGMs West End
THE INNER CIRCLE (15) Odeon Haymarket
CASABLANCA (U) Empire
It is <LOCATION>Cannes</LOCATION> Film festival delivery fortnight. A week after the film that by
wide consent should have won the <DATE>1992</DATE> Golden Palm, <PERSON>Robert Altman</PERSON>'s The
Player, we welcome to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> the film that did win the <ORGANIZATION>Golden Palm</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Bille</LOCATION>
<DATE>August</DATE>'s The Best Intentions.
In the auteurist shorthand used and abused today, we say '<PERSON>Altman</PERSON>'s' and
'<DATE>August</DATE>'s' films. But The Player owed much of its crackle to <PERSON>Michael
Tolkin</PERSON>'s script from his own novel. (For more about <PERSON>Mr</PERSON> T read on in this
column.) And The Best Intentions boasts a script by <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON> based on
the lives of his own parents. Who is to call it an <DATE>August</DATE> film rather than a
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> film?
It is certainly a long film. Three hours, and even that a digest of the
six-hour serial version simultaneously prepared for TV. If pressed against a
wall by a man with a gun, I would say that in some respects The Best
Intentions is not a film at all: more a roman fleuve in pictures about the
love between a rich girl with a possessive family, played by <PERSON>Pernilla August</PERSON>
 -the director's wife, who won the <LOCATION>Cannes</LOCATION> best actress prize - and a young
pastor with a blond moustache and a live-in guilt complex (<PERSON>Samuel Frohler</PERSON>).
Yet 20 minutes into this story, we scarcely care what aesthetic category we
put it into. Film or mini-series, family album or novel-with-pictures, it
surges majestically through the century's early years as <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> recreates
the bitter-sweet romance of his mother <PERSON>Anna</PERSON> and father <PERSON>Henrik</PERSON>. Henrik is a
cold-eyed Lutheran priest, <PERSON>Anna</PERSON> a walking nervous breakdown. Between them,
in snowscapes and lakelands that dazzle the eye, they create the conditions
of elegiac dementia in which young Ingmar could be born.
This is a prequel to <ORGANIZATION>Fanny And Alexander</ORGANIZATION>. Some of the same gusty relatives
tack and billow across the screen, as turbulent variations are played on the
theme of family life. Anna's folk are wealth-encrusted Swedish bourgeoisie,
from raspy old Papa (<PERSON>Max Von Sydow</PERSON>) who watches the distant trains from his
mound of rugs by the window, to melting-eyed Mama, a pudgy former beauty who
hides reserves of malice in the folds of her outward kindness. Meanwhile
<PERSON>Henrik</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Mama</LOCATION> is a dotty old peasant woman living in the wilds and his
departed father has been replaced by an invisible, implacable,
incomprehensible God.
The defects of the parents are visited on the children and children's
children. As <PERSON>Henrik</PERSON> and <PERSON>Anna</PERSON> quarrel in their snowbound parish, which looks
as if it is a sermon's throw from the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION>, their little son (<ORGANIZATION>Ingmar</ORGANIZATION>'s
older brother) is nearly murdered by the surly ragamuffin they adopt out of
Christian kindness. He is a cousin to all those haunted, stark-eyed urchins
who have prowled through <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s films from The Seventh Seal to The
Silence.
Wonderfully elliptical even at its sprawling length, the film never
'explains' unhappiness or inhumanity. It merely exposes it vividly,
impassively, surgically on the snow-white sheet of the story's scenic
operating table.
Bergman the writer has lost none of his skill at paring emotion to the bone
and then beyond to the marrow. Quarrel scenes have a lacerating force;
reconciliations a melting poignancy; silences a terrifying ambiguity. If The
Best Intentions is less than the best of <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> as a film - less than Hour
Of <ORGANIZATION>The Wolf</ORGANIZATION> or Persona or Fanny And <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON> - it is because <DATE>August</DATE> is more
skilled at shaping performances than shaping screen pictures. Bergman would
have let the madness of human hope and despair spill out into the lighting
and camerawork. August merely records that madness in the performances, but
the performances at best, especially from <PERSON>Mrs August</PERSON>, are richness enough.
If God is a supporting villain in The Best Intentions, he is the
arch-villain in <PERSON>Michael Tolkin</PERSON>'s The Rapture. The writer of <ORGANIZATION>The Player</ORGANIZATION> wrote
and directed this electrifying fable about the evils of Christian
fundamentalism. Made on a mini-budget, it is part satire, part melodrama,
part visionary B-movie. One can imagine the moguls licking their lips. 'She
was only a switchboard operator,' the advertising copyline might run, 'but
she found a hot line to Heaven.'
The film's crazed primitivism is its strength. <PERSON>Mimi Rogers</PERSON>, who is fast
turning into today's <PERSON>Barbara Stanwyck</PERSON>, plays the telephone employee who
gives up her life as a daytime drudge and night-time debauchee - attending
swinger orgies with her suavely greying boyfriend <PERSON>Patrick Bauchau</PERSON> - when God
calls her 'collect'.
Will she pay for the call? Yes indeed. A bright light, a vision, a death;
then the poignant pleadings of her little daughter. Soon Miss R is out in
the desert waiting for God to snatch up her and the little one in a
pre-Judgment Day 'rapture.' But God moves in mysterious ways, especially
when He is the God of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s born-again fundamentalists. Even when
<PERSON>Gabriel</PERSON>'s horn sounds in the film's astonishing finale, mystical
triumphalism is nowhere in sight. And the horsemen of the apocalypse pound
unfeeling through the mires of human grief and disenchantment.
If I spell out more of the plot, your own astonishment will be ruined. The
Rapture has a few first-time film-maker's faults: the over-urgent piling on
of saleable ingredients (sex, drugs, sudden death), too many
plonk-the-camera-down dialogue scenes. But it also has a first-time
film-maker's miraculous innocence. Scenes that a veteran would claim you
'could not do' are carried off here with a sublime insouciance.
The message of the film is that miracles do not happen: or not the useful,
daily miracles we pray for as distinct from the global magic act we all
await on Judgment Day. But this film is a miracle of its kind: a story that
pierces the veil between here and the beyond with a rough magic far more
powerful than the whimsical mysticism we have grown used to with Ghost and
company.
The Inner Circle is set in a city where everyone speaks English with a
strenuous Russian accent. It is <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1940s</DATE>, where according to
writer-director <PERSON>Andrei Konchalovsky</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Maria</ORGANIZATION>'s Lovers, <ORGANIZATION>Runaway Train</ORGANIZATION>) a young
man in the likeness of <PERSON>Tom Hulce</PERSON> served as film projectionist to a man with
a walrus moustache and Oriental eye make-up called <PERSON>Joseph Stalin</PERSON> (<PERSON>Alexandre
Zbruev</PERSON>).
While our hero falls under the tyrant's evil spell, his wife (<ORGANIZATION>Lolita
Davidovich</ORGANIZATION>) busies herself swinging between liberal goodheartedness - she
pays forbidden visits to a sickly-sentimental Jewish orphan (<PERSON>Bess Meyer</PERSON>) -
and cynical despair. In the latter mode, she lends her body to <PERSON>Bob Hoskins</PERSON>,
alias <ORGANIZATION>KGB</ORGANIZATION> chief <PERSON>Beria</PERSON>. They make love in his private train compartment as
the rolling-stock of history rattles towards <ORGANIZATION>Stalin</ORGANIZATION>'s final days.
The first film ever shot in the corridors of the <ORGANIZATION>KGB</ORGANIZATION>, let alone <PERSON>Beria</PERSON>'s
train compartment, The Inner Circle is also the umpteenth film to turn
truth-based political tragedy into dial-a-cliche melodrama. Overacted by
almost everyone in sight and scripted for stark risibility - 'F---off' says
<PERSON>Stalin</PERSON> to a VIP petitioner early on and the dialogue does not improve - it
comes to life only when raiding history direct. The climactic scenes of
people literally trampled to death in the crowds jostling towards <ORGANIZATION>Uncle
Joe</ORGANIZATION>'s coffin shows the grim punishment that awaits a nation that misjudges
its leader during his life and turns misjudgment into deification after his
death.
Casablanca is 50 years old and has also undergone deification. But no
misjudgment here: the film is still a classic. Re-opening in a new 35-mm
print, it reanimates <LOCATION>Bogart</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> and company and sets them dancing
through <PERSON>Rick</PERSON>'s Cafe Americain as the dialogue crackles, the romance revs and
<PERSON>Dooley Wilson</PERSON> at the piano keeps telling us we must remember this. Who on
earth could forget?
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880516-0255 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-88 1445EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-APN--TheaterWeek Adv29   05-16 0878</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Theater Week, Adv 29,0899</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv29</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, May 29</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w
photo.)</NOTE>

<BYLINE>By MICHAEL KUCHWARA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Drama Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>

<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, May 29</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900416-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-16-90 0619EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Sweden-Garbo     04-16 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sweden-Garbo,0303</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swedes Remember Greta Garbo With Pride</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Obit-Garbo, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In her native country, <PERSON>Greta Garbo</PERSON> was
remembered with pride today as an actress whose charisma made her
``the world's best known Swedish emigrant.''
   ``I do not know what it was that made everybody turn around and
keep looking at her when we entered a restaurant,'' <PERSON>Garbo</PERSON>'s
longtime friend <PERSON>Mimi Pollack</PERSON> said on Swedish national radio.
   <PERSON>Ms. Pollack</PERSON> and <PERSON>Garbo</PERSON> were fellow students at <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Royal
Theater School</ORGANIZATION> in the early <DATE>1920s</DATE>. <PERSON>Ms. Pollack</PERSON> said they had not
been in touch since <PERSON>Garbo</PERSON> fell ill this <DATE>winter</DATE>.
   Swedish film professor <PERSON>Leif Furhammar</PERSON> said he remembered her as
a someone ``who walks down the stairs in such a way that you cannot
take your eyes off her.''
   <PERSON>Torsten Jungstedt</PERSON>, a Swedish film critic, told the Swedish
national news agency TT that <PERSON>Garbo</PERSON>'s ``face was perfect for film.
It was a close shot face with an enormous amount of life in it.''
   ``Photographers said it had a light of its own,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Garbo</PERSON> died <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> hospital. She was 84.
   She grew up in <LOCATION>Soder</LOCATION>, a workers' district in southern <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>.
Director <PERSON>Mauritz Stiller</PERSON> discovered her at the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Theater
School</ORGANIZATION>. Stiller and <PERSON>Pollack</PERSON> persuaded her to change her name from
<PERSON>Greta Gustafsson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Greta Garbo</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Garbo</PERSON> was the first of several Swedes who made international
film careers, including director <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>, and actors <PERSON>Ingrid
Bergman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Max von Sydow</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bibi Andersson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Anita Ekberg</PERSON>, and most
recently <PERSON>Lena Olin</PERSON>.
   Stiller had gone with <PERSON>Garbo</PERSON> to <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1925</DATE> and tried to
bring her back to <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> when he returned two years later. But she
stayed on and later became an American citizen, returning to <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>
to visit only occasionally.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880318-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-18-88 0850EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Obit-Kohner     03-18 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Kohner,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>Talent Agent Paul Kohner Dead at 85</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hollywood agent <PERSON>Paul Kohner</PERSON>, who represented
such diverse talents as <PERSON>Charles Bronson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON> and <PERSON>John
Huston</PERSON>, has died of heart failure. He was 85.
   <PERSON>Kohner</PERSON> died <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>,
Medical Center, said <PERSON>John Strauss</PERSON>, a longtime associate. His wife,
former Mexican film star <PERSON>Lupita Tovar</PERSON>, and family members were at
his bedside.
   Until a recent illness, <PERSON>Kohner</PERSON> headed the <PERSON>Paul Kohner</PERSON> agency,
which celebrates its 50th anniversary in <DATE>May</DATE>.
   Throughout his career, <PERSON>Kohner</PERSON> represented hundreds of stars,
espcecially Europeans, including <PERSON>Greta Garbo</PERSON>, <PERSON>Marlene Dietrich</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Maurice Chevalier</PERSON>, <PERSON>Liv Ullman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Max von Sydow</PERSON> and <PERSON>Klaus Maria
Brandauer</PERSON>.
   In addition to his native Czechoslovakian, <PERSON>Kohner</PERSON> spoke Italian,
German, Spanish, French and English. He frequently traveled abroad.
   Over the past 20 years, <PERSON>Kohner</PERSON> was instrumental in bringing all
of Swedish director <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>'s films to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Strauss</PERSON> said.
   During World War II <PERSON>Kohner</PERSON> helped organize the European Film
Fund, later the European Relief Fund, which provided emigre artists
with financial assistance and help in obtaining visas to come to
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Kohner</PERSON> was born in <PERSON>Teplitz Schoenau</PERSON>, in what is now
<LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION>.
   While working as a reporter for his father's film industry trade
newspapers in <DATE>1920</DATE>, <PERSON>Kohner</PERSON> interviewed then-head of Universal
Pictures <PERSON>Carl Laemmle</PERSON> and came away with the promise of a job in
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   He came to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> the same year and worked in various
departments at <ORGANIZATION>Universal</ORGANIZATION>, including publicity, promotion,
distribution and production. Eventually he produced
foreign-language films for the studio, both in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
and in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
   Among the more important English films he produced were ``The
Hunchback of <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>,'' starring <LOCATION>Lon Chaney</LOCATION>; ``A House
Divided,'' directed by <PERSON>William Wyler</PERSON>; ``The Chinese Parrot,''
starring <PERSON>Conrad Veidt</PERSON>; and ``Love Me and the World is Mine,''
starring <PERSON>Mary Philbin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Norman Kerry</PERSON>.
   He is survived by his wife; daughter <PERSON>Susan Kohner Weitz</PERSON>; son
<PERSON>Paul J.</PERSON> ``Pancho'' <PERSON>Kohner</PERSON>; four grandchildren and a brother, <PERSON>Walter</PERSON>.
   Funeral services will be <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Hillside Memorial Park</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890926-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-26-89 1412EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--VonSydow Adv06-08   09-26 1057</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Von Sydow, Adv 06-08,1078</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv06</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv08</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Oct. 6-8, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Star Watch: From the Profound to the Frivolous</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB THOMAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MONTREAL (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The blond giant stood tentatively on the stage
of the Place des Artes theater, seemingly amazed at the standing
ovation accorded him by the packed audience.
   <PERSON>Max Von Sydow</PERSON> had come to the <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> World Film Festival for a
tribute to his 30-year career that has brought distinction to
movies on both sides of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>. The program included clips
from two widely divergent films: <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>'s ``The Virgin
Spring'' (<DATE>1959</DATE>) and ``Hannah and Her Sisters'' (<DATE>1986</DATE>).
   A dialogue with the actor was followed by a screening of the
Danish-made ``Pelle the Conqueror,'' which drew the <ORGANIZATION>Motion Picture
Academy</ORGANIZATION>'s best foreign-language film Oscar of <DATE>1988</DATE> as well as a
nomination as best actor for <ORGANIZATION>Von Sydow</ORGANIZATION>. He received a second
standing ovation when he left the stage.
   ``It's very strange,'' he admitted afterward. ``I don't know how
you feel, but I feel like I'm 25 inside. I don't feel that I have
any kind of `lifetime achievement.'''
   Film critics would argue with that. If he had appeared only in
the <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> films, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> would have earned a place in movie
history. But he also has contributed a series of noteworthy
performances in a wide variety of films, from the profound (<ORGANIZATION>Jesus
Christ</ORGANIZATION> in ``The Greatest Story Ever Told'') to the eerie (``The
Exorcist'') to the frivolous (Ming the Merciless in ``Flash
Gordon'').
   Like most successful actors, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>'s career was the result
of a series of happy accidents. He was born 60 years ago in <LOCATION>Lund</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, the son of a university professor and his wife. Max
happened to see some plays in nearby <LOCATION>Malmo</LOCATION>, prompting him to enroll
in dramatic classes at high school. After his two-year military
service, he enrolled in the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Academy</ORGANIZATION>, training ground for such
famous Swedes as <PERSON>Greta Garbo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ingrid Bergman</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> played repertory at the <ORGANIZATION>Malmo Municipal Theater</ORGANIZATION>, where
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> had been hired as chief director. When <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON> filmed ``The
Seventh Seal,'' he chose the young actor as a returning Crusader.
The pair collaborated on 11 films.
   <PERSON>George Stevens</PERSON> was impressed with <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>'s strong, mystical
persona and cast him in the mammoth, unrealized ``The Greatest
Story Ever Told.'' ``<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'' with <PERSON>Julie Andrews</PERSON> was also a
disappointment, but the two films established <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> as an
international star. He has been working all over the world ever
since.
   Before leaving <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> for a new film in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>
paused for an interview with <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>:
   Q. You have now directed your first film, ``Katinka.'' How did
you like being on the other side of the camera?
   A. ``It was a great experience, very exciting. I had never had
any plans to become a director, but this was something very
special. It dealt with a novel I had found a long time ago; I fell
in love with it immediately and saw it as a film with me playing a
part in it.
   ``I tried to convince my director friends, but nobody caught on
to it. Then someone approached me to direct the film, and I
couldn't turn it down. I was too old to play one of the parts,
unfortunately. Time does these things to you. It was a great
experience, exhausting, but I learned a lot.''
   Q. At the tribute you mentioned that the first 20 years as an
actor were a kind of therapy for you. What did you mean?
   A. ``I have a feeling that many actors choose acting because
there's something they long for but cannot reach, that there's
something they cannot express in their private lives, that there's
a threshold they cannot pass.
   ``I was a very shy boy when I was a kid. I had difficulty to
communicate with people I didn't know. When I started acting in an
amateur group in high school, although I wasn't aware of it at the
time, I suddenly got a tool in my hand that was wonderful. I was
allowed to express all kinds of strange things that I never dared
to express before. Now I could do it with the character as a
shield, as a defense, and as an excuse.
   ``I think that for many years I used my profession as some kind
of a mental therapy. I worked all the time, and I needed it. I was
restless, and I was very crazy if I was not allowed to work.
Through the years I have backed off. Life has helped me, and my
friends and my wife and my family. Today I don't need that therapy
anymore.''
   Q. The acting life has sent you all over the world. Did you
expect that when you started out?
   A. ``No, that happened later. It has its advantages and its
drawbacks. But that can be very exciting. I'm grateful because I've
seen so much of the world that I wouldn't have seen otherwise. But
sometimes you get a little too much of hotel rooms and suitcases
and packing and unpacking. I think I'll try to take it a little
easier in the future.
   ``I'm planning to do more theater, at least one production a
year, limited engagement.''
   Q. Where is home nowadays?
   A. ``My home is in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. Funny thing is that I haven't spent
much time there because I've been working elsewhere. We have an
apartment which I like very much. It's a wonderful old palace in
the old quarter of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. It's where Beaumarchais wrote `The
Marriage of Figaro.' It has been remodeled, and we have the attic
of the house.
   ``We also have a <DATE>summer</DATE> place in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, and <DATE>summer</DATE> in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> is
very important. I guess I am more of a country boy than a city boy,
even though I grew up in a small town.''
   Q. Your world travels have caused separations from your family,
right?
   A. ``Not always, but for long periods. My wife comes along when
I go to places she thinks she will enjoy. It's not easy. But I have
a good wife, and we like each other very much. We have managed to
stay together.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Oct. 6-8</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880609-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-09-88 2305EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-Theater     06-09 0626</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Theater,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ingmar Bergman's Production of `Hamlet' Travels to Brooklyn</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs planned.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL KUCHWARA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Drama Critic</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nothing is quite what it should be in the world
created by director <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON> for his startling, violent and
often mesmerizing production of ``Hamlet'' which arrived this week
at the <ORGANIZATION>Brooklyn Academy of Music</ORGANIZATION> for an eight-performance run.
   In <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s unnerving creation for the Royal Dramatic Theater
of <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> becomes an environment of decay, sexual excess,
psychotic behavior and ultimately needless slaughter carried out to
ear-bursting pop music and the whir of minicams and tape recorders.
   Elsinore has been transformed into a castle of lost souls where
a drunken king and queen have sex in public while the court titters
and applauds, Polonius preaches like a stuffy British barrister,
<ORGANIZATION>Ophelia</ORGANIZATION> becomes a disheveled flower child gone mad, the Gravedigger
turns into an existential comic waiting for Godot and Fortinbras
storms the stage as a black-bereted guerrilla leader.
   At the center of <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s chaos stands a tall, dark, brooding
Hamlet who would not look out of place in one of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s tonier
rock clubs. Dressed entirely in black and wearing sunglasses, the
actor slouches on stage. As played by a fascinating and forceful
actor named <PERSON>Peter Stormare</PERSON>, this Hamlet arrives with a <PERSON>Marlon
Brando</PERSON> swagger and a <PERSON>Norman Bates</PERSON> psychosis.
   Stormare, an intense, hawk-like presence, brings a wild energy
to the 3{-hour production. The actor is not an introspective Hamlet
calmly reasoning out what should be done. This prince rails against
the world and what has happened to the kingdom since his uncle
murdered his father and married his mother.
   When this Hamlet acts, he gets carried away. When he kills
Polonius, he stabs him in the eye and then scrawls the word `blood'
on the wall. When he tells <ORGANIZATION>Ophelia</ORGANIZATION> to ``get thee to a nunnery,'' he
nearly rapes her in the process.
   There is one radical change in the text, involving the transfer
of one famous speech from one scene to another. When Hamlet is
talking quietly to the player king about how to act out his
father's death, the young prince, overcome with grief, suddenly
breaks down and delivers ``To be or not to be?'' It's an
interesting concept, particularly since the actor portraying the
player king, <ORGANIZATION>Per Myrberg</ORGANIZATION>, also plays the ghost of Hamlet's father.
   Bergman's production contains some startling imagery, much of it
designed by <PERSON>Goran Wassberg</PERSON>. His setting is simple _ a bare, black
stage, an arc of lights hanging above it and a circle, outlined in
red, placed on the floor at center stage.
   Wassberg's costumes are equally eye-catching, many of them in
shades of red and from different periods of fashion. The contrast
between the old and new underlines the uncertainty that plagues
this royal court.
   <PERSON>Pernilla Ostergren</PERSON> is a touching <ORGANIZATION>Ophelia</ORGANIZATION>, a child-woman who
remains on stage for much of evening, a forlorn witness to most of
the debauchery. <PERSON>Borje Ahlstedt</PERSON> is a randy, boozy Claudius while
<PERSON>Gunnel Lindblom</PERSON> as <PERSON>Gertrude</PERSON> matches him in every debauchery. Rarely
have these two royal misfits been so ably put on stage.
   The production is performed in Swedish, and the language
difference eventually poses a problem. For audiences familiar with
the English text, <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s interpretation of the story should be
readily accessible. But others with no knowledge of the play will
be lost. What's also missing from the production, at least for an
English-speaking audience, is the readily recognizable poetry.
   Still, there are <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s startling images of a world gone out
of control. The foreign language may cloud the text, but the
director's particular point of view shines through with a clarity
that makes this ``Hamlet'' a compelling and often haunting evening
of theater.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-6847</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CKSC7ACYFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921119
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 NOV 92 / Arts: Ibsen and Bergman - a marriage made in heaven / The
first European theatre festival in Dusseldorf is proving a heady experience
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JACKIE WULLSCHLAGER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
President <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> paid for it, <PERSON>Giorgio Strehler</PERSON> opened it, and <PERSON>Ingmar
Bergman</PERSON> was the catch of week one. At the first European Theatre Festival
launched last week in <LOCATION>Dusseldorf</LOCATION>, radical chic has never been more
sparkling. Bergman and <ORGANIZATION>Ibsen</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Strehler</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Goldoni</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Brecht</PERSON> directed by his
son in law; a revolutionary Catalan Figaro; from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> the <ORGANIZATION>RNT</ORGANIZATION>'s Angels in
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>: stars stud the stage, tickets are gold dust, visitors fill smoky
bars for midnight post-mortems. The mood recalls <LOCATION>Edinburgh</LOCATION>, the variety
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION> and the quality <LOCATION>Salzburg</LOCATION>: on the first few days' tasting this new
festival, whose venue will change each year, looks set to become <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s
most heady and prestigious theatre binge.
Bergman doing <ORGANIZATION>Ibsen</ORGANIZATION> is a marriage made in heaven, and the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Theatre
Stockholm's Peer Gynt</ORGANIZATION> offers a rare chance to see film-maker as stage
director. <ORGANIZATION>Peer Gynt</ORGANIZATION>, its series of frozen scenes in Peer's life unravelled
like magic boxes, is a natural vehicle for cinematic theatricality; in to it
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>, always an autobiographical artist, injects a personal vision which
transforms this often wooden piece into an emotional coup de force. A
century on, <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s art is rooted in scenes close to Ibsen: moral
integrity; a sense of sin powerfully visualised; individual expression
within claustrophobic relationships; the meeting of dream and reality.
<PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s set is a sinister red room, centre stage, enclosed within the
larger frame of Peer's home. High, thick wooden walls carved with flowers,
dim gaslights, a grandfather clock, a sturdy crib, hem it in on three sides.
Actions, memories, are compressed into this chamber of the imagination; like
dreams, each seen has its own visual logic. The wedding guests, in flame-red
folk-dress buttoned up to neck and wrists, weighed down with gold brocade
and buckles, hijack the room for a hellish, anti-erotic tap dance full of
jerkily suppressed lunges for freedom. The trolls, green tarts in flounces,
frills and dreadlocks, drag Peer on a rhino to an orgy in a madhouse. They
hang over the roof of the room swinging erect green tails and snorting
lewdly. Sex screams out, Peer hurtles about trying to conceal a huge rubber
penis emerging between his legs.
Later, laser beams focus on top-hatted men in black encircling Peer; their
accusations echo as distortions from loudspeakers across a vast auditorium
and against a chorus of church bells: a choking vision of guilt.
Loneliness, repression and sin are the motifs. Solveig's family, Amish-style
puritans, march in line like geese, fall to their knees chant prayers, a
young child spies on <ORGANIZATION>Peer</ORGANIZATION> from a doorway. Based on <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>'s own upbringing,
they are as chilling an emblem of cruel rectitude as the father in his film
Fanny and <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON>. <PERSON>Lena Andre</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Solveig</PERSON>, symbol of love, unwinds with
conviction and subtlety from torment into a mix of nervousness/grace,
fear/determination.
As Peer, <PERSON>Borje Andersson</PERSON> is Everyman: chubby, dazed, endlessly flexible
face; round, hapless body; a dreamer whose desires are now pathetic, now
comic, now horrifying. He sticks out his tongue at us, drops his trousers at
the whiff of a woman; he is also the desperate loner; seeking warmth,
meaning, justification. A magnificent, inexhaustible performance.
The European Theatre Festival to <DATE>November 27</DATE> at the <LOCATION>Dusseldorf</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Schauspielhaus</ORGANIZATION>. Festival information 0211 36 87 136.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880527-0272 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-27-88 1118EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:VonSydow Adv03   05-27 0619</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Von Sydow, Adv 03,0636</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv 03</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Fri PMs, June 3 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Esteemed Swedish Actor Turns To London Stage</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT WOLF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Swedish screen star <PERSON>Max Von Sydow</PERSON>, whose new film
``Pelle the Conqueror'' won the grand prize at the <ORGANIZATION>Cannes Film
Festival</ORGANIZATION>, is turning to the English stage in a career move he
described as ``a great surprise.''
   ``It's very exciting,'' the tall, lanky <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> said of his
upcoming role as Prospero in <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s ``The Tempest.'' The
play opens <DATE>Oct. 6</DATE> at <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s Old Vic theater for a limited run
through <DATE>Nov. 26</DATE>.
   The production, directed by <PERSON>Jonathan Miller</PERSON>, will mark <PERSON>Von
Sydow</PERSON>'s first English-language appearance on the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> stage. He
previously appeared in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1974</DATE> in a Swedish staging of
<PERSON>Henrik Ibsen</PERSON>'s ``The Wild Duck.''
   That production was directed by <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>, with whom <PERSON>Von
Sydow</PERSON> has had a long and illustrious career on stage and in such
films as ``The Seventh Seal,'' ``Wild Strawberries,'' ``Through a
Glass Darkly'' and ``The Passion of <PERSON>Anna</PERSON>.''
   On Broadway, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> has starred in two flops: ``The Night of
the Tribades,'' with <PERSON>Eileen Atkins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bibi Andersson</PERSON>, and ``Duet
for One,'' with <PERSON>Anne Bancroft</PERSON>.
   ``It's a very interesting idea,'' <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>, 58, said of
director <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>'s choice that he play <PERSON>Prospero</PERSON>, a part more often
associated with English actors in their twilight years.
   <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>, in a separate interview, explained his casting.
   ``I wanted to break out of the noble aria approach English
performers often take to the part,'' said <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>, who is in his
first year as the artistic director of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s venerable Old Vic.
   ``I've never seen Max on stage, but I know he is a great,
accomplished actor. I've seen all his films.''
   Prospero furthers what has been an unusually busy year for <ORGANIZATION>Von
Sydow</ORGANIZATION>. He is presently appearing at the <ORGANIZATION>National Theater of
Stockholm</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>August Strindberg</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1872</DATE> ``Master Olof.''
   In Bille <DATE>August</DATE>'s prize-winning Danish film, ``Pelle the
Conqueror,'' <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> heads up a family of immigrant farmworkers
at the turn of the century, giving a performance for which he's won
critical praise. The film won La Palme D'Or, the top prize, at the
41st annual Cannes Film Festival which ended on <DATE>May 23</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> was also represented at <LOCATION>Cannes</LOCATION> with his directorial
debut, ``<PERSON>Katinka</PERSON>,'' adapted from a novel by the Danish author
<PERSON>Herman Bang</PERSON> about a three-way love affair.
   He said he had originally hoped to act in a movie version of the
book when he first read the novel 25 years ago.
   Now, since he was too old for the male leads, he decided to
direct the movie instead: ``Coincidence put the possibility in my
hands.''
   Of his English-language films, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> said he looked back
fondly on ``Hannah and Her Sisters,'' <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON>'s <DATE>1986</DATE> movie in
which he played <PERSON>Barbara Hershey</PERSON>'s tortured, irascible companion.
   ``Most of the scripts one gets are so bad it was wonderful to
receive one with intelligent dialogue,'' said the actor, who felt
challenged by <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>'s requirements.
   ``He (<PERSON>Allen</PERSON>) demands <PERCENT>200 percent</PERCENT> of a naturalistic style. He
does not allow any literary phrasings or pronunciation,'' <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>
said.
   This version of ``The Tempest'' will mark the fourth major
production of the play to be seen in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> this year; both the
star and his director said they would not be seeing the others.
   ``It's very disturbing to be influenced,'' said <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>, who
last played <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s conjurer-poet in a Swedish production 35
years ago when, he said, he was ``much too young.''
   <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said, ``I don't go very much to the theater. It's too
much of a busman's holiday.''
   End Adv PM Fri <DATE>June 3</DATE>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA080590-0248 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 258801 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 5, 1990, Sunday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
TV Times; Page 76; Television Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
799 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VON SYDOW'S SCENES OF DESTRUCTION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By NANCY MILLS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
"This movie is not entertainment," <PERSON>Max Von Sydow</PERSON> says, casting his eye over the 
bloody costumes of dozens of Japanese people lying in a church courtyard. "It's 
much more of a political statement." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>, who received a best actor Oscar nomination last year for "Pelle the 
Conqueror," is talking about <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s "<LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION>: Out of the Ashes," about the 
aftermath of the <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION> bombing. It airs at <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the 45th 
anniversary of the day the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> dropped the first atomic bomb, on 
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"The pacifist in me made me interested in this project," he says, explaining 
his decision to portray a German Catholic priest working in <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug</DATE>. 
6, <DATE>1945</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"I think it's good that we're sometimes reminded of important events in 
history. When Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> visited <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION> recently, he says, 'We have 
to look to the past to learn for the future."' 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>, who first came to worldwide notice 35 years ago through the films of 
fellow <PERSON>Swede Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>, explains he's not just talking about bombs. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION> has become a metaphor not just for nuclear war but for war and 
destruction and violence toward civilians," he says. "It's not just the idea we 
should not use nuclear arms. We should not start another war because it's 
madness." 
</P>
<P>
The scene <DATE>today</DATE> in <LOCATION>Valencia</LOCATION>, which is standing in for <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION>, occurs the day 
after the bomb fell. With two wind machines at work blowing smoke and dust in 
the actors' faces, the scene is eerily reminiscent of photographs taken of the 
destruction. 
</P>
<P>
Wearing a black cassock, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> busily attends the wounded. 
</P>
<P>
The bomb on <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION>, which flattened <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of the city, resulted in nearly 
130,000 casualties. A second bomb dropped on <LOCATION>Nagasaki</LOCATION> <DATE>three days later</DATE> prompted 
the Japanese to accept unconditional surrender, bringing an end to World War 
II. 
</P>
<P>
Unlike other movies that have examined <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s decision to bomb <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, the 
focus of "<LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION>: Out of the Ashes" follows the survivors. In the ensemble 
film, <ORGANIZATION>Von Sydow</ORGANIZATION> shares billing with <PERSON>Judd Nelson</PERSON> (an <ORGANIZATION>American POW</ORGANIZATION> interned in a 
<LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION> jail), <PERSON>Pat Morita</PERSON> (a <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION> postman), <PERSON>Tamlyn Tomito</PERSON> (a 
Japanese-American whose husband is in the Japanese Army) and <PERSON>Kim Miyori</PERSON> (a 
mother of a missing child). 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> is reluctant to address the moral issues surrounding <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION>. "We 
don't know what would have happened if <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> hadn't dropped the bombs," he 
said. "It's easy to say that no bombs should have been dropped. But this was a 
war situation, and dropping them was an attempt to end the war." 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>, 61, was too young to have fought in World War II, he did 
see its effects first-hand. In <DATE>1945</DATE> he was a high school student in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, a 
country that remained neutral during the war. "That <DATE>spring</DATE>," he recalls, "the 
concentration camps were opened, and members of the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> went in and 
brought a large number of prisoners to southern <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I belonged to a folk dance group that visited these poor, miserable people and 
performed for them. We were asked to learn a number of national anthems, and we 
sang them. It was an extremely emotional experience. Many of these people were 
in terrible shape. They looked like walking skeletons, but they were beaming 
with joy as we entertained them." 
</P>
<P>
Encouraged by such a reception, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> ignored his parents' plan for him to 
enter college and instead pursued an acting career. "I was in such a hurry to 
be an actor," he remembers. "Now I'm sometimes mad at myself that I didn't stop 
and study for a couple of years." 
</P>
<P>
Instead, he attended <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>'s Royal Academy of Dramatic Arts, began a stage 
career and then had the good fortune to meet <PERSON>Bergman</PERSON>. His work in the 
director's "The Seventh Seal," "The Magician" and "The Virgin Spring" brought 
him to the attention of Hollywood. In <DATE>1965</DATE>, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> came to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> to play 
Christ in "The Greatest Story Ever Told," and he has come back periodically 
ever since. 
</P>
<P>
Apart from the title role in "The Exorcist" and a small part in "Hannah and Her 
Sisters," as <PERSON>Barbara Hershey</PERSON>'s intellectual lover, most of <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>'s work in 
<LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION> films has been villainous. "It's because I'm foreign," he explains in 
his ever-so-lightly accented English, Rand foreigners are very often villains." 
Since the success of "Pelle the Conqueror," an Oscar-winner in <DATE>1989</DATE> for best 
foreign film, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON> thinks he has a new image in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. "Now 
I'm getting less villain offers and more normal people offers," he says. 
</P>
<P>
Even as his Hollywood career prospers, <PERSON>Von Sydow</PERSON>, who has lived in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> for more than a decade, intends to move back to <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> to pursue stage 
work. "If they want me, I'll do one limited theater engagement there every year 
and films the rest of the time," he says. "It's a daydream, but I hope it will 
work." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, "The pacifist in me made me interested in this project," says 
actor Max Von Sydow about his role as a German Catholic priest working in 
Hiroshima on Aug. 6, 1945. On Sunday, 45 years after the atom bomb, NBC airs 
"Hiroshima: Out of the Ashes." 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-15933</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DDHB2AC9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930408
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 APR 93 / Arts: Small-town tales - Cinema
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIGEL ANDREWS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
ONE FALSE MOVE (18)
<PERSON>Carl Franklin</PERSON>
LEAP OF FAITH (PG)
<PERSON>Richard Pearce</PERSON>
THE OX (12)
<PERSON>Sven Nykvist</PERSON>
BEST OF THE BEST 2 (18)
<PERSON>Robert Radler</PERSON>
<LOCATION>PARIS</LOCATION> IS BURNING
<PERSON>Jennie Livingston
Star</PERSON> <LOCATION>City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Rustwater</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, are both small towns near the
middle of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. But look closely - is there a big difference? Exactly.
One is in <PERSON>Jim Thompson</PERSON> country, the other is in <PERSON>Sinclair Lewis</PERSON> country.
Star City is the small town as rural spittoon. In the irresistibly grimy,
downbeat thriller One False Move - scripted by <PERSON>Billy Bob Thornton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tom
Epperson</PERSON> but surely ghost-dictated by that master of elevated pulp <PERSON>J.
Thompson</PERSON> - the town plays host to fugitive gangsters, dimwitted lawmen and a
climactic carnage that Aeschylus would be proud of.
Up the road a little - go north and bend left - is Rust-water in wheatbelt
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>. For displaced urban crime read agriculture under stress. There is a
drought here and the farms are dying; and if one pastoral crisis is not
enough, here comes another. Revivalist preacher <PERSON>Jonas Nightengale</PERSON> (<PERSON>Steve
Martin</PERSON>), comedy-cloned by screenwriter <PERSON>Janus Cercone</PERSON> from <PERSON>Sinclair Lewis</PERSON>'s
<PERSON>Elmer Gantry</PERSON>, passes through town with his all-singing, all-praying tent
show. He gives the rain-starved farmers hope; he raiseth the lame and sick
(the language is catching); he thumps his <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION>; and he is a frightful,
pearly-teethed fraud made winning by the charismatic <PERSON>Mr Martin</PERSON>.
When films venture outside <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> they usually end up in <LOCATION>Cutesville</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION>. See ET, Back To The Future and <ORGANIZATION>Co</ORGANIZATION>. To Hollywood any place without smog,
faxes and power breakfasts must seem strange and innocent. But One False
Move, by a mile the better of the week's rural twosome, makes a rich dark
joke of this (faux)-navete. At the centre: a young Southern sheriff (Bill
Paxton) intent on proving his mettle to two visiting lawmen (one white, one
black) from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. All the Angelenos want to do is to round up a pair
of cocaine-dealing killers (also one black, one white) who massacred a
roomful of people back in LA and then fled with their guns, their drugs and
their girl (<ORGANIZATION>Cynthia Williams</ORGANIZATION>). Will they come to ground in the girl's home
town of <LOCATION>Star City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>?
Not yet. First the movie, directed with sizzling grace by ex-actor <PERSON>Carl
Franklin</PERSON>, travels all over the south-western states as the getaway trio make
for <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> (to sell their drugs) before being harried by police pursuit
into doubling back north for <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>. Back here the film's other character
grouping has been in mocking parallel action. For two black/white crooks
with a brown-skinned girl read two black/white city cops with a redneck
sheriff.
The racial patch-quilting, though teasingly displayed, is never deployed for
facile tension. Indeed Southern values are almost respected for their loony
matter-of-factness. Paxton's pinbrained lawman is a creation so ridiculous
it is sublime. He boasts, he bumbles, he preens. And he obliviously throws
out the word 'nigger' while his black colleague pretends polite deafness.
Even the sheriff's wife shakes her head at his intellect, while
simultaneously advertising her own. ('He watches TV, I read non-fiction'.)
And when her man goes off to do what a man's gotta do, the film moves into a
High Noon climax re-staged - brilliantly - as nihilist farce.
One False Move is a rural tragicomedy with the deadly grace of a sidewinder.
Leap Of Faith is more like a stoned python. It folds itself round its
subject's neck, makes some promising hissing noises - and then falls asleep
on the job. We love the sight of <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> dancing into town with his big-band
show of dubious miracles: orchestrated by <ORGANIZATION>Debra Winger</ORGANIZATION> at the backstage
computer, feeding audience information into <ORGANIZATION>Martin</ORGANIZATION>'s on-stage earpiece. 'Man
in white shirt, hard of hearing', 'Woman in pink with arthritis'. Then the
slapping-on of hands, the customer's fainting fall, the lordy-lordy
paroxysms of ersatz joy.
Unfortunately, something else in the movie soon reveals itself as ersatz. It
is the subplot. Make that two subplots: for while Winger romances the
improbably saintly town sheriff <PERSON>Liam Neeson</PERSON> - so handsome, so gentle, so
liberal (no redneckery in this burg) - <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> makes a play for diner
waitress <ORGANIZATION>Lolita Davidovitch</ORGANIZATION>. She has a crippled, chess-playing little
brother (<PERSON>Lukas Haas</PERSON> of Witness) who will surely, if <PERSON>Cliff Eidelman</PERSON>'s music
has not done the job by then, end by melting his and our hearts.
Can a real miracle happen? Yes indeed. For lo, the cinema exit doors finally
open before we have all passed out with terminal queasiness. Director
<PERSON>Richard Pearce</PERSON> (Heartland, No Mercy) delivers the razzle-dazzle in the
revivalist set pieces, with <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> exploding all over stage. But no
star-director team can keep their anti-twaddle guns firing in the face of
both the appointed target - high-sleaze evangelism - and a whole lot of
late, unscheduled fire from Hollywood inspirationalism.
* You cannot escape small-town life even, or especially, in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Sven
Nykvist</PERSON>'s The Ox is about pastoral bigotry and brutalism. A terrible fate
befalls <PERSON>Helge Roos</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Stellan Skarsgard</ORGANIZATION>) when he kills a neighbour's ox to
feed himself and his family during <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s 1860s famine. Flogged and
life-sentenced to hard labour, he is then betrayed by his starving wife for
the sake of their starving child. Nor, gentle reader, does the horror stop
there . . .
This truth-based tragedy of errors makes <PERSON>Thomas Hardy</PERSON> seem like <PERSON>Louisa May
Alcott</PERSON>. It also makes for spellbinding cinema. Writer-director <PERSON>Nykvist</PERSON> is
best-known as a cameraman to the great and famous, having lensed 22 <PERSON>Ingmar
