<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881013-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-13-88 0234EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BurningAmazon     10-13 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Burning Amazon,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazilian Leader Pledges to Stop Amazon Destruction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JORGE MEDEROS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Brazilian officials, vowing not to be
pressured by economic interests, have promised to stem the
widespread burning of <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle that already has destroyed an
area larger than <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON> has unveiled a plan aimed mainly at
stopping uncontrolled forest burning by farmers and ranchers.
   ``We must create nationwide consciousness that we are all
passengers in the adventure of Man on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Sarney</PERSON> said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in a ceremony announcing the program. ``The era of
unlimited natural resources is over.''
   The program, called ``Our Nature,'' calls for a temporary end to
government tax and financing benefits for large-scale cattle
ranching in the northern <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> and a ban on exports of unprocessed
tropical timber.
   Environmentalists have charged that the clearing of vast <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>
tracts by the primitive slash-and-burn method has released hundreds
of tons of noxious gases into the atmosphere.
   They say this is contributing to the greenhouse effect, the
gradual warming of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere by a concentration of
pollutants that act like a blanket, trapping the sun's warmth.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s government-run <ORGANIZATION>Space Research Institute</ORGANIZATION> said about
77,000 square miles of land were cleared by the slash-and-burn
method in <DATE>1987</DATE> and forecast a similar amount for this year.
   The program also includes a recommendation to <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
to cut mercury imports. Free-lance gold prospectors throughout the
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> use the highly toxic element to separate gold from river
silt and then throw the waste into the water.
   ``This program is going to shake up powerful economic
interests,'' said <PERSON>Antonio Jose Guimaraes</PERSON>, president of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s
federal <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION>. ``But the government is resolved to carry
it out.''
   Earlier laws designed to colonize and develop the impoverished
<LOCATION>Amazon Basin</LOCATION>, which covers an area equal to roughly two-thirds of
the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, permitted land developers to burn
off <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of their properties _ the fastest and cheapest way
to clear land _ and then gave them tax deductions for doing so.
   The <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> has estimated that since <DATE>1978</DATE> this type of
land-clearing in the <LOCATION>Brazilan Amazon</LOCATION> has destroyed 240,000 square
miles of natural tropical rainforest cover, an area larger than
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   Interior Minister <PERSON>Joao Alves</PERSON> said the tax break suspensions were
temporary, because the government is working out a plan to
determine which parts of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> can be used for farming and
ranching and which must be left alone.
   Private developers complained about the plan even before it was
announced.
   <PERSON>Orlando Mariutti</PERSON>, who has three projects on a total of 136,000
acres in the western state of <ORGANIZATION>Mato Grosso</ORGANIZATION>, told the newspaper Folha
de <PERSON>S. Paulo</PERSON> that ``Cutting tax incentives will hold back
development of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.''
   Large developers in the region, he said, ``generally preserve
more than the <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the land required by law.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881012-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-12-88 2115EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Brazil-Amazon     10-12 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Amazon,0479</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazilian Leader Pledges to Stop Amazon Destruction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JORGE MEDEROS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
unveiled a plan aimed mainly at stopping massive, uncontrolled
burning in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle by farmers and ranchers which has
aggravated the worldwide ``greenhouse effect.''
   The program, called ``Our Nature,'' calls for a temporary end to
government tax and financing benefits for large-scale cattle
ranching in the northern <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> and a ban on exports of unprocessed
tropical timber.
   Environmentalists have charged that the clearing of vast <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>
tracts by the primitive slash-and-burn method has released hundreds
of tons of noxious gases into the atmosphere.
   They say this causes the greenhouse effect, the gradual warming
of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere by a concentration of pollutants that act
like a blanket, trapping the sun's warmth.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s government-run <ORGANIZATION>Space Research Institute</ORGANIZATION> said about
77,000 square miles of land were cleared by the slash-and-burn
method in <DATE>1987</DATE> and forecast a similar amount for this year.
   ``We must create nationwide consciousness that we are all
passengers in the adventure of Man on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Sarney</PERSON> said in a
ceremony announcing the program. ``The era of unlimited natural
resources is over.''
   The ``Our Nature'' program also contains a recommendation to
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to cut mercury imports. Free-lance gold
prospectors throughout the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> use the highly toxic element to
separate gold from river silt and then throw the waste into the
water.
   ``This program is going to shake up powerful economic
interests,'' said <PERSON>Antonio Jose Guimaraes</PERSON>, president of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s
federal <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION>. ``But the government is resolved to carry
it out.''
   Earlier laws designed to colonize and develop the poor <LOCATION>Amazon
Basin</LOCATION>, which covers an area equal to roughly two-thirds of the 48
continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, permitted land developers to burn off <PERCENT>50
percent</PERCENT> of their properties _ the fastest and cheapest way to open
up clear areas _ and then gave them tax deductions for doing so.
   The <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> has estimated that since <DATE>1978</DATE> this type of
land-clearing in the <LOCATION>Brazilan Amazon</LOCATION> has destroyed 240,000 square
miles of natural tropical rainforest cover _ an area larger than
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   Interior Minister <PERSON>Joao Alves</PERSON> said the tax break suspensions were
temporary, because the government is working out a plan to
determine which parts of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> can be used for farming and
ranching and which must be left alone.
   Even before ``Our Nature'' was announced, private <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>
developers complained about the plan.
   <PERSON>Orlando Mariutti</PERSON>, who has three projects on a total of 136,000
acres in the western state of <ORGANIZATION>Mato Grosso</ORGANIZATION>, told the newspaper Folha
de <PERSON>S. Paulo</PERSON> that ``Cutting tax incentives will hold back
development of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.''
   Large developers in the region, he said, ``generally preserve
more than the <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the land required by law.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881017-0227 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-17-88 1346EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-APN--BurningAmazon ADV30-2Takes   10-17 0853</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Burning Amazon, ADV 30-2 Takes,0874</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv30</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Oct. 30</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 2 b&amp;w
photos, 1 drawing. Colorfoto subscribers get 1 35mm slide.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ The government of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> this month announced an
environmental plan aimed primarily at slowing the uncontrolled
burning of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle by farmers and ranchers, a practice
which among other things has aggravated the worldwide ``greenhouse
effect.'' Here is a report on the slash-and-burn land clearing that
has destroyed 240,000 square miles of rain forest in the past 10
years.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By STAN LEHMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTO VELHO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ The government of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> this month announced an
environmental plan aimed primarily at slowing the uncontrolled
burning of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle by farmers and ranchers, a practice
which among other things has aggravated the worldwide ``greenhouse
effect.'' Here is a report on the slash-and-burn land clearing that
has destroyed 240,000 square miles of rain forest in the past 10
years.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042389-0057 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 47674 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 23, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Opinion; Part 5; Page 2; Column 1; Opinion Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
842 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BRAZIL TRIES TO STOP SLASH-AND-BURN DESTRUCTION OF RICH AMAZON FORESTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By William R. Long, William R. Long is The Times' correspondent in Rio de 
Janeiro. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
PORTO VELHO, BRAZIL 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here in the state of <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION> on the southern flank of the great <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain 
forest, a new frontier opened up in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE>. Encouraged for a decade by 
the Brazilian government, hundreds of thousands of settlers came to help push 
back the wilderness and share the bounty. <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION> was the land of opportunity, 
the Golden West of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Now the heady frontier spirit has faded and a new realism seems to be setting 
in. 
</P>
<P>
Slash-and-burn farming and ranching has stripped away as much as one-third of 
the forest that once protected <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION>'s soil from the baking sun and leaching 
rains. The state's jungle Indian population has dwindled from 40,000 to 5,000, 
according to a study by Brazilian anthropologist <PERSON>Cecilia Meireles</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Small farmers who thought <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION> promised an escape from poverty have failed 
to improve their lot. Malaria is a frequent visitor at makeshift rural homes. 
Porto Velho, the state capital, is crowded with slum dwellers who gave up on 
the land. Although the government spent <MONEY>hundreds of millions of dollars</MONEY> on a 
frontier development program called Polonoroeste, farmers have received little 
technical or financial aid. More than half the land they have cleared is 
uncultivated and has given way to a matted growth of secondary brush called 
capoeira. 
</P>
<P>
Like other areas on the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> frontier, <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION> obviously hasn't turned out 
the way it was supposed to. Officials here don't need foreign conservationists 
to tell them that, but in the past year, European and American worries about 
destruction of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> forest have poured down on <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> like tropical rain. 
Perhaps because of the international pressure, perhaps because it makes sense, 
Brazilian authorities are adopting new policies aimed at slowing the 
destruction. Some conservationists are skeptical about the effectiveness of the 
policies, but at least on paper, preservation is becoming the new official 
watchword in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> region of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON> has announced a series of protective measures in a 
program called "Our Nature." One new decree suspends official credits and tax 
breaks that had encouraged cattle ranchers to turn forest into pasture. The 
program also includes a zoning study that would put huge forest areas 
off-limits to ranchers, farmers, loggers and miners. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION> state government already has its own zoning plan. Approved last 
<DATE>June</DATE>, it limits agricultural activities largely to central and southern areas 
of the state where most deforestation has taken place and where soils are 
richest. 
</P>
<P>
Vice Gov. <PERSON>Orestes Muniz</PERSON>, also <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION>'s planning secretary, says that by 
recovering millions of acres gone to capoeira, the state can save vast areas of 
virgin forest from the wasteful slash-and-burn cycle. Technicians are also 
experimenting with the use of capoeira as cover for crops that require shade, 
such as coffee and fruit trees. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Muniz</PERSON> said the zoning plan sets aside about <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of the state's territory as 
natural preserves. To enforce protective measures, the state police force has 
created a forest patrol unit that now employs 350 officers and eventually will 
have 1,000. A freeze on all deforestation is in effect, pending implementation 
of the plan. Thirty percent of the state is designated as extractive reserves 
and managed forests, where rubber, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> nuts, medicinal plants and selected 
hardwoods and other products can be harvested without deforestation. Officials 
say the potential for economic returns is great. Rondonia woodlands contain an 
estimated 40,000 plant species, only about a tenth of which have been 
classified and studied. Another <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of preserved forest area includes natural 
parks and Indian lands. 
</P>
<P>
To implement the plan, the state is starting a program called Planafloro, with 
projects for education, technical aid and financing to help people to preserve 
the forest while exploiting its riches. 
</P>
<P>
"To the extent that the small producer gets income from the standing forest, he 
will not cut more down," said <PERSON>Teodorico Rocha</PERSON>, a federal official helping on 
the Planafloro. 
</P>
<P>
Planafloro will cost an estimated <MONEY>$213 million</MONEY>, and the national government is 
negotiating for a loan from the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> to cover part of the cost. <PERSON>Rocha</PERSON> 
said it is "absurd" for <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> to increase the heavy burden of its <MONEY>$115 billion</MONEY> 
foreign debt, but the country cannot afford to pay for the conservation program 
by itself. 
</P>
<P>
"There is consciousness for preserving the environment in <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION>," he said. 
"What is lacking are the means, financing." 
</P>
<P>
In an emotional speech this month, President <PERSON>Sarney</PERSON> appealed to foreigners who 
accuse <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> of destroying the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> to help provide the means for preserving 
it. 
</P>
<P>
"Transfer technology to us without costs," <PERSON>Sarney</PERSON> said. "Help us to combat the 
burning with airplanes, with equipment, with products. Help us to reforest with 
material, scientific and human resources." 
</P>
<P>
Foreign aid alone cannot prevent further destruction in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> by economic 
interests and ignorance, but Brazilians who want to save the forest need all 
the help they can get. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Drawing, BARBARA D. CUMMINGS / for The Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Opinion 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890614-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-14-89 2141EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Amazon 2ndLd-Writethru a0749 06-14 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Amazon, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0749,0470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire Destroyed Nearly 50,000 Square Miles of Rain Forest in 1988</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 6 grafs for last graf ``The institute ...'' to UPDATE with
scientist saying satellite findings misleading. No Pickup</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAO PAULO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire destroyed nearly 50,000 square
miles of <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest last year, wiping out a section of land
roughly the size of <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, according to Brazilian satellite
studies released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   However, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Space Studies Institute</ORGANIZATION> said the amount of
forest cleared by farmers and ranchers was not as great as in <DATE>1987</DATE>,
when 80,000 square miles were destroyed.
   Preliminary results of satellite studies showed that 48,400
square miles were set on fire in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>, physicist
<PERSON>Marcos</PERSON> da <ORGANIZATION>Costa Pereira</ORGANIZATION> said by phone from the institute in <LOCATION>Sao Jose</LOCATION>
dos <PERSON>Campos</PERSON>, 60 miles northeast of <LOCATION>Sao Paulo</LOCATION>.
   The burned area comprises about <PERCENT>2.42 percent</PERCENT> of the 2 million
square miles that is considered the legal <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>, which is made up
of the Brazilian states of <LOCATION>Amapa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Para</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Roraima</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maranhao</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Goias</LOCATION>,
Acre, <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mato Grosso</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Pereira</PERSON> said about <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the 48,400 square
miles was either virgin rain forest or savannahs. The remaining area
was land that was burned for the second or third time by cattle
ranchers and farmers getting rid of secondary vegetation that had
grown back.
   In both cases, he added, the centuries-old slash-and-burn
technique was used to clear the land to plant crops and create
pastureland.
   He said it was difficult to say how much of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain
forest has been devastated in all, ``but I think it's safe to say
that about <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of the entire area has been destroyed over the
past century.''
   Pereira attributed the decline in burned forest to ``political
and economic factors,'' referring to the international pressure on
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> to preserve its rain forest.
   Another scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>National Institute of Research</ORGANIZATION> on the
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Manaus</LOCATION> said the satellite findings can be misleading even
though he agrees a large portion of the rain forest has been
destroyed by fire.
   ``They overestimate the total amount of legal <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> area
burned,'' said <PERSON>Philip Fearnside</PERSON>, who estimated <PERCENT>8.4 percent</PERCENT> of the
legal <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest has been destroyed this century.
   <PERSON>Fearnside</PERSON> said among other things, the satellite used to collect
the data is built to study clouds and oceans.
   He said satellite sensors often are ``saturated'' by heat from
fires, causing the satellite to register a large area being burned
even if the fire is confined to a small area.
   ``But the important thing is that a tremendous area of the rain
forest is being burned,'' <PERSON>Fearnside</PERSON> stressed.
   The <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> accounts for <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of the world's tropical rain
forests.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900205-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-05-90 1440EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--OurLand Adv18-1stAdd   02-05 0839</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Our Land, Adv 18-1st Add,0863</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv18</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sun., Feb. 18</NOTE>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: the family.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The migratory birds and the wetland fit the conservancy's
charter. With <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> from its revolving fund, the
conservationists bought the ranch and leased it back to the
McQuerry family with certain conditions.
   The family would have to change certain farming operations. For
instance, they would not be permitted to graze the wetland area
from fall to the following <DATE>summer</DATE> when the birds use the estuary.
   When the family was able, they would buy the ranch back, but
those covenants would remain.
   ``If we hadn't stepped in, certainly the family was going into
bankruptcy,'' says <PERSON>Ralph Grossi</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>American Farmland
Trust</ORGANIZATION>. ``They would have lost the farm.''
   The farmland trust felt there was a real danger of development
to the land and the natural ecosystem around the lake.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> covers some 3,600,000 square miles or 2.3
trillion acres. Of those, 78,000 square miles or almost 50 million
acres are inland waterways. There are also more than 88,000 miles
of tidal shoreline.
   Conservationist groups can't protect it all, nor, they say,
should they. Often they seek to cooperate with developers, allowing
residential uses, but sequestering other areas. In some cases,
developers pay mitigation fees for the damage their developments
might cause. Those funds are used to enhance the protected land.
   Says the <ORGANIZATION>Nature Conservancy</ORGANIZATION>'s Dennis: ``When you're talking
about an ecosystem, you could be talking about anything from 5,000
acres to 500 square miles.''
   So he outlines a compromise, a core that the conservationists
want to own and manage. Around that they would establish a larger
area where timbering and mining are banned. ``Then you may want an
additional buffer where development is OK, but it's got to be
limited. You may allow a cluster of homes here on 2-to 5-acre
tracts and preserve farmland over there.''
   Even individuals are taking a page from their book and designing
small local operations to save such properties as a farm in
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> or 400 acres of rolling countryside in <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>. The
farm remained a farm, and the <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> tract is now home to an
organically safe golf course.
   In the array of people in the conservation army, there is also
an array of purposes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Nature Conservancy</ORGANIZATION>'s 542,000 members, dedicated to
preserving habitats, have financed a <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> organization that
has saved almost 4 million sensitive acres since it was founded in
<DATE>1953</DATE>. It has 1,000 employees and probably 10,000 volunteers and
covers every state
   Considerably younger (10 years old) and smaller (a staff of 30
nationwide) is the American Farmland Trust, dedicated to saving the
nation's farms and improving farming techniques. Yet, it churns
accounts of more than <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> to get more acres for the buck.
   ``We are concerned about the debt burden in agriculture,'' says
the trust's president, <PERSON>Ralph Grossi</PERSON>. ``Many farmers are going out
of business and their land isn't being cared for adequately.''
   Organizations from the <ORGANIZATION>National Wildlife Federation</ORGANIZATION> to the
<ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Ducks
Unlimited</ORGANIZATION>, a hunter's group, often find themselves working in
   They all have one thing in common. They can move more quickly
than local or state governments can, and, using charitable tax
benefits, they can bring in a deal cheaper than developers can.
   By stripping a piece of land of development rights, it is not
only protected regardless of who owns it, but income tax benefits
can either bring the owner a sizable tax deduction or provide
instant cash for a farmer.
   It also reduces the value of the land and hence its tax
assessment, which deprives the county or state of some tax revenue.
But counties and states usually are willing to forgo taxes on some
property to enhance the value of land around it.
   Witness <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON>, who has asked for <MONEY>$1.9
billion</MONEY> to set aside areas of the <ORGANIZATION>Empire State</ORGANIZATION> for scenic and
recreation purposes. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> has provided more than <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY>
for similar purposes, and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> has an active land acquisition
program.
   But the smallest of communities can be stirred to action.
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s west coast is a beautiful blend of dunes, orchards and
sandy beaches on <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION>. It is a magnet for those wanting
second homes, and unlike the coast of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, which it mimics
in miniature, it has no coastal commission to protect it.
   Local land trusts, with the help of the <ORGANIZATION>Farmland Trust</ORGANIZATION>, moved in
to buy a 507-acre farm on the <LOCATION>Old Mission Peninsula</LOCATION>, blocking any
further residential development. It will remain an orchard in an
area that prides itself as being the ``Cherry Capital of the
World.''
   ``It's unlikely that some crops will be grown in any quantity in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> 30 to 40 years from now,'' says <PERSON>Grossi</PERSON> of the
Farmland Trust. ``The growing areas that are required, the climate,
the soil, the weather, those unique values are essentially the same
as those that attract people.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901130-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-30-90 1315EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i BC-FightfortheAmazon Adv09   11-30 1111</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Fight for the Amazon, Adv09,1381</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv09</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday Dec 9 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Ranchers and Rubber Tappers Fight Over Rain Forest</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhotos</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PETER MUELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILEIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The death threat was nothing new to the
rubber tappers' union in this <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> town.
   ``I've been hired to kill you,'' read a scrawled note slipped
under the office door in <DATE>November</DATE>. It said three union leaders and
the local's truck driver ``can't make it to <DATE>1991</DATE>.''
   The note was unsigned, but there was little doubt at union
headquarters who was behind it: cattle ranchers, the tappers'
enemies in a bloody dispute for land rights in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s tropical
rain forest.
   Since the union was founded in <DATE>1975</DATE>, such threats have been
common and deadly serious. The local says ``pistoleiros,'' gunmen
hired by landowners, have killed more than 150 tappers and Indians.
   One victim was <PERSON>CHico Mendes</PERSON>, a rubber tapper and union leader
who had become an internationally consulted expert on the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.
Shotgun fire from ambush cut him down in <DATE>December 1988</DATE> at his home
in <LOCATION>Xapuri</LOCATION>, near the Bolivian border 2,650 miles northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de
Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>.
   A local rancher, <PERSON>Darli Alves da Silva</PERSON>, and his son <PERSON>Darci</PERSON> were
arrested. Their trial is scheduled to begin <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Xapuri</LOCATION>.
   ``This is the land where they threaten and do it,'' said
<PERSON>Osmarino AMancio Rodrigues</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>Brasileia</LOCATION> union local
And one of those on the note's list. ``No one has ever escaped.''
   He added, with a laugh: ``Two of my bodyguards were threatened.
Now I'll have to get bodyguards for my bodyguards.''
   Rodrigues, 34, is widely regarded as the successor to <PERSON>Chico
Mendes</PERSON> as the leader of a grass-roots movement against destruction
of the rain forest.
   Jose da <PERSON>SIlva Pereira</PERSON>, another tapper on the death list, said:
``When ranchers want to get rid of a tapper, they come in shooting,
kill his livestock and burn his house. If he doesn't leave, he
dies.''
   A new alliance of rubber tappers and <ORGANIZATION>Amazon Indians</ORGANIZATION> is
challenging the notion that ``developing'' the forest means cutting
it down for timber or burning it to make pasture.
   Uncontrolled slash-and-burn clearing already has destroyed more
than 250,000 square miles of rain forest, an area the equal to
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. A patch of jungle the size of a football field disappears
every eight seconds, adding to the greenhouse effect that is
warming the planet.
   Those whose livelihoods come from the forest favor an
alternative called ``extractivist reserves,'' a new system of
landholding in which the government expropriates rain forest to
allow commercial harvesting of fruits, nuts and other renewable
products.
   Such reserves give tappers legal rights to the jungle, where for
years they were squatters on the huge feudal estates of cattle
barons and big landowners. The government now has 7{ million acres
of reserves in <LOCATION>AMazonia</LOCATION> and plans to set aside 55 million more by
<DATE>1993</DATE>.
   ONe region of nearly 2{ million acres is named for <PERSON>Chico Mendes</PERSON>.
   ``There won't be peace in the forest without land reform,'' said
<PERSON>Rodrigues</PERSON>, a short, swarthy man with a black beard. ``In <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION>,
that means Indian reservations and extractivist reserves.''
   The main argument for protecting the forest is simply that it's
More profitable alive.
   Aminded consumers in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Amazon fruits,
nuts, oils and essences are heading north to make everything from
ice cream and nut candy to cosmetics.
   ``We have to prove the economic value of the rain forest and
generate income to save it,'' anthropologist <PERSON>Jason Clay</PERSON> said in an
interview. Clay is research director of <ORGANIZATION>Cultural Survival</ORGANIZATION>, a
non-profit group based in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, and visits <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>
frequently.
   Cultural SUrvival buys jungle products and resells them to
companies abroad, charging a <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT> ``environmental premium''
used to help forest peoples.
   Clay said he showed samples of 350 rain forest products and
businessmen were interested in 38 of them. He reported orders worth
<MONEY>$4 million</MONEY>, and said several companies pledged part of their
profits to rain forest projects.
   Extractivist reserves are ``one of the few environmentally
viable alternatives for the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>,'' he said.
   ``We have to make the reserves more economically rewarding. Then
we can use them to recover degraded areas and as buffer zones for
the genetic hotspots, the really fragile parts of <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION> that
shouldn't be used.''
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has tried for decades to tap the riches of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>, a
wilderness of two million square miles that is larger than <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
without the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION> contains <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of the world's rain forest;
one-fifth of its fresh water; 5 million species of plants, animals
and insects, and rich deposits of gold, diamonds, iron, tin and
other minerals. Despite those riches, most of its inhabitants live
in grinding poverty.
   Attempts by the military regime of 1964-1985 to ``open up the
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>'' were an ecological nightmare.
   Huge development projects like the Trans-Amazon highway, farm
settlements and the <LOCATION>Balbina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tucurui</LOCATION> hydroelectric dams wiped
out huge tracts of forest and nearly destroyed some native tribes.
   Government incentives attracted cattle ranchers, who kept
burning the jungle off the sandy soil to replace pasture that
lasted only two or three years. Experts say their productivity is Secretary
<PERSON>Jose Lutzenberger</PERSON>, an internationally
respected ecologist, says <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> is trying to change its image as a
destroyer of the environment.
   ``Extractivist reserves are extremely important,'' he said in an
interview. ``We must create many more of them.''
   <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> has pledged <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> to the <ORGANIZATION>National Rubber Tappers
Council</ORGANIZATION>, starting next year, to develop extractivist reserves.
   THe newest and largest of the special areas is the <PERSON>Chico Mendes</PERSON>
REserve, which covers 2.4 million acres in the western <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> state
of Acre, where the most violence has occurred.
   On the reserves, tappers' associations sign long-term contracts
with the government for the ``use and benefit'' of the land. They
must obey rules for protecting the environment or forfeit the area.
   ``This was our great victory,'' said <PERSON>Nelson Custodio da Silva</PERSON>, a
rubber tapper. ``We fought four years for this reserve.''
   Problems remain. Most reserves have not yet been expropriated
and the government foresees a long legal battle with landowners.
The <PERSON>Chico Mendes</PERSON> Reserve was created by former President <PERSON>Jose
Sarney</PERSON> three days before he left office in <DATE>March</DATE>.
   ``It was a great party, but the bill wasn't paid,'' <PERSON>Marco
Antonio Mendes</PERSON>, the Acre state environment secretary, said in an
interview.
   Tappers also have not escaped exploitation by ``marreteiros'' -
middlemen who trade commercial goods like salt and cloth for rubber
and nuts, and routinely charge three or four times the regular
price.
   Nearly all the profit from jungle produce is made elsewhere.
Tappers earn only 3 to <MONEY>4 cents</MONEY> a pound for <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> nuts, about <PERCENT>2
percent</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> wholesale price.
   Acre state's <ORGANIZATION>Technology Foundation</ORGANIZATION> is running a unique
experiment in forest management on the remote border with Amazonas
state.
   At the 166,000-acre Antimari reserve, technicians are studying
how to ``densify'' the forest by planting without upsetting the
natural balance. They are concentrating on bamboo, timber and more
than 800 types of medicinal plants, as well as rubber and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>
nuts.
   ``This is a first for <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Gilberto Siqueira</PERSON>, the
foundation president. ``It will show us the limits of exploitation
without disturbing the whole.''
   Another experimental project is a cooperative in <LOCATION>Xapuri</LOCATION> that
shells, packs and exports <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> nuts. It is the first
nut-processing plant owned by the tappers.
paid a fair price,'' said <PERSON>Rolando Polanco</PERSON>, a worker at the
cooperative. ``We're trying to give the tappers a better deal.''
   The plant, built with a <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> gift from Cultural Survival,
employs 78 people and processes 1,100 pounds of nuts a day, barely
one-tenth of the production in <LOCATION>Xapuri</LOCATION> alone. Polanco said expansion
depends on donations from environmental groups and businessmen.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday Dec 9</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The death threat was nothing new to the
rubber tappers' union in this <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> town.
   ``I've been hired to kill you,'' read a scrawled note slipped
under the office door in <DATE>November</DATE>. It said three union leaders and
the local's truck driver ``can't make it to <DATE>1991</DATE>.''
   The note was unsigned, but there was little doubt at union
headquarters who was behind it: cattle ranchers, the tappers'
enemies in a bloody dispute for land rights in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s tropical
rain forest.
   Since the union was founded in <DATE>1975</DATE>, such threats have been
common and deadly serious. The local says ``pistoleiros,'' gunmen
hired by landowners, have killed more than 150 tappers and Indians.
   One victim was <PERSON>CHico Mendes</PERSON>, a rubber tapper and union leader
who had become an internationally consulted expert on the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.
Shotgun fire from ambush cut him down in <DATE>December 1988</DATE> at his home
in <LOCATION>Xapuri</LOCATION>, near the Bolivian border 2,650 miles northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de
Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>.
   A local rancher, <PERSON>Darli Alves da Silva</PERSON>, and his son <PERSON>Darci</PERSON> were
arrested. Their trial is scheduled to begin <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Xapuri</LOCATION>.
   ``This is the land where they threaten and do it,'' said
<PERSON>Osmarino AMancio Rodrigues</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>Brasileia</LOCATION> union local
And one of those on the note's list. ``No one has ever escaped.''
   He added, with a laugh: ``Two of my bodyguards were threatened.
Now I'll have to get bodyguards for my bodyguards.''
   Rodrigues, 34, is widely regarded as the successor to <PERSON>Chico
Mendes</PERSON> as the leader of a grass-roots movement against destruction
of the rain forest.
   Jose da <PERSON>SIlva Pereira</PERSON>, another tapper on the death list, said:
``When ranchers want to get rid of a tapper, they come in shooting,
kill his livestock and burn his house. If he doesn't leave, he
dies.''
   A new alliance of rubber tappers and <ORGANIZATION>Amazon Indians</ORGANIZATION> is
challenging the notion that ``developing'' the forest means cutting
it down for timber or burning it to make pasture.
   Uncontrolled slash-and-burn clearing already has destroyed more
than 250,000 square miles of rain forest, an area the equal to
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. A patch of jungle the size of a football field disappears
every eight seconds, adding to the greenhouse effect that is
warming the planet.
   Those whose livelihoods come from the forest favor an
alternative called ``extractivist reserves,'' a new system of
landholding in which the government expropriates rain forest to
allow commercial harvesting of fruits, nuts and other renewable
products.
   Such reserves give tappers legal rights to the jungle, where for
years they were squatters on the huge feudal estates of cattle
barons and big landowners. The government now has 7{ million acres
of reserves in <LOCATION>AMazonia</LOCATION> and plans to set aside 55 million more by
<DATE>1993</DATE>.
   ONe region of nearly 2{ million acres is named for <PERSON>Chico Mendes</PERSON>.
   ``There won't be peace in the forest without land reform,'' said
<PERSON>Rodrigues</PERSON>, a short, swarthy man with a black beard. ``In <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION>,
that means Indian reservations and extractivist reserves.''
   The main argument for protecting the forest is simply that it's
More profitable alive.
   Aminded consumers in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Amazon fruits,
nuts, oils and essences are heading north to make everything from
ice cream and nut candy to cosmetics.
   ``We have to prove the economic value of the rain forest and
generate income to save it,'' anthropologist <PERSON>Jason Clay</PERSON> said in an
interview. Clay is research director of <ORGANIZATION>Cultural Survival</ORGANIZATION>, a
non-profit group based in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, and visits <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>
frequently.
   Cultural SUrvival buys jungle products and resells them to
companies abroad, charging a <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT> ``environmental premium''
used to help forest peoples.
   Clay said he showed samples of 350 rain forest products and
businessmen were interested in 38 of them. He reported orders worth
<MONEY>$4 million</MONEY>, and said several companies pledged part of their
profits to rain forest projects.
   Extractivist reserves are ``one of the few environmentally
viable alternatives for the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>,'' he said.
   ``We have to make the reserves more economically rewarding. Then
we can use them to recover degraded areas and as buffer zones for
the genetic hotspots, the really fragile parts of <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION> that
shouldn't be used.''
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has tried for decades to tap the riches of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>, a
wilderness of two million square miles that is larger than <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
without the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION> contains <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of the world's rain forest;
one-fifth of its fresh water; 5 million species of plants, animals
and insects, and rich deposits of gold, diamonds, iron, tin and
other minerals. Despite those riches, most of its inhabitants live
in grinding poverty.
   Attempts by the military regime of 1964-1985 to ``open up the
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>'' were an ecological nightmare.
   Huge development projects like the Trans-Amazon highway, farm
settlements and the <LOCATION>Balbina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tucurui</LOCATION> hydroelectric dams wiped
out huge tracts of forest and nearly destroyed some native tribes.
   Government incentives attracted cattle ranchers, who kept
burning the jungle off the sandy soil to replace pasture that
lasted only two or three years. Experts say their productivity is Secretary
<PERSON>Jose Lutzenberger</PERSON>, an internationally
respected ecologist, says <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> is trying to change its image as a
destroyer of the environment.
   ``Extractivist reserves are extremely important,'' he said in an
interview. ``We must create many more of them.''
   <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> has pledged <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> to the <ORGANIZATION>National Rubber Tappers
Council</ORGANIZATION>, starting next year, to develop extractivist reserves.
   THe newest and largest of the special areas is the <PERSON>Chico Mendes</PERSON>
REserve, which covers 2.4 million acres in the western <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> state
of Acre, where the most violence has occurred.
   On the reserves, tappers' associations sign long-term contracts
with the government for the ``use and benefit'' of the land. They
must obey rules for protecting the environment or forfeit the area.
   ``This was our great victory,'' said <PERSON>Nelson Custodio da Silva</PERSON>, a
rubber tapper. ``We fought four years for this reserve.''
   Problems remain. Most reserves have not yet been expropriated
and the government foresees a long legal battle with landowners.
The <PERSON>Chico Mendes</PERSON> Reserve was created by former President <PERSON>Jose
Sarney</PERSON> three days before he left office in <DATE>March</DATE>.
   ``It was a great party, but the bill wasn't paid,'' <PERSON>Marco
Antonio Mendes</PERSON>, the Acre state environment secretary, said in an
interview.
   Tappers also have not escaped exploitation by ``marreteiros'' -
middlemen who trade commercial goods like salt and cloth for rubber
and nuts, and routinely charge three or four times the regular
price.
   Nearly all the profit from jungle produce is made elsewhere.
Tappers earn only 3 to <MONEY>4 cents</MONEY> a pound for <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> nuts, about <PERCENT>2
percent</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> wholesale price.
   Acre state's <ORGANIZATION>Technology Foundation</ORGANIZATION> is running a unique
experiment in forest management on the remote border with Amazonas
state.
   At the 166,000-acre Antimari reserve, technicians are studying
how to ``densify'' the forest by planting without upsetting the
natural balance. They are concentrating on bamboo, timber and more
than 800 types of medicinal plants, as well as rubber and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>
nuts.
   ``This is a first for <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Gilberto Siqueira</PERSON>, the
foundation president. ``It will show us the limits of exploitation
without disturbing the whole.''
   Another experimental project is a cooperative in <LOCATION>Xapuri</LOCATION> that
shells, packs and exports <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> nuts. It is the first
nut-processing plant owned by the tappers.
paid a fair price,'' said <PERSON>Rolando Polanco</PERSON>, a worker at the
cooperative. ``We're trying to give the tappers a better deal.''
   The plant, built with a <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> gift from Cultural Survival,
employs 78 people and processes 1,100 pounds of nuts a day, barely
one-tenth of the production in <LOCATION>Xapuri</LOCATION> alone. Polanco said expansion
depends on donations from environmental groups and businessmen.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900508-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-08-90 2155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Brazil-Amazon     05-08 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Amazon,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazil's Environment Chief Vows to Develop the Amazon `Humanely'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JORGE MEDEROS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s environment czar vowed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
to curb the destruction of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest and to develop
the biologically sensitive area in a ``rational, humane and
ecological'' manner.
   ``We can't stop development and growth, but yes, we can make
human occupation compatible with the survival of the planet,'' said
<ORGANIZATION>National Environment</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Jose Lutzenberger</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON>, 64, outlined a plan for encouraging development
and farming while preserving the unique ecological balance of the
2-million square mile rain forest.
   A world-renown ecologist, he said the government will introduce
a program to revitalize the forest's soil through organic
agricultural methods and to reduce the traditional style of
slash-and-burn farming that has destroyed 200,000 square miles of
the region.
   He said the <ORGANIZATION>Collor de Mello</ORGANIZATION> administration, which first took
office in <DATE>March</DATE>, will also quadruple its fire-fighting efforts.
   ``In this way we will stop small farmers, impoverished by soil
that only gives two or three harvests, from burning other tracts of
the jungle,'' said <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON>. He said the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> and the
<ORGANIZATION>Inter-American Development Bank</ORGANIZATION> had expressed interest in financing
the program but gave no details.
   Slash-and-burn farmers clear large tracts of unused land by
setting fires and then plant crops until the soil is exhausted.
They then move on to fresh land.
   <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> said the burnings are now monitored by satellites
that can detect even small brush fires. He said forest rangers in
helicopters are used to catch and fine violators.
   He said <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> will also explore alternative energy sources such
as solar, wind and biomass energy instead of building the huge
hydroelectric dams that were popular in recent decades.
   Environmentalists have opposed the dams saying they flood huge
tracts of <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> land, killing trees and animals while providing
few benefits for the thousands of Indians and Brazilian farmers
living in the area.
   He specifically singled out the <ORGANIZATION>Itaipu</ORGANIZATION> dam, built by <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Paraguay</LOCATION> on the <LOCATION>Parana River</LOCATION> dividing the countries and the <LOCATION>Tucurui</LOCATION>
project in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>Itaipu</ORGANIZATION> only produces at <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of its capacity and we
don't even know what to do with so much energy,'' <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON>
said. ``<LOCATION>Tucurui</LOCATION> generates electricity for large aluminum factories
that export minerals at low cost and the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> natives don't see
any benefit.''
   <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> should scrap plans for large dams in
the rain forest and concentrate instead on promoting small
generators and floating river turbines financed and run by local
municipalities and private businessmen.
   The appointment of <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON>, an agronomist educated in the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, was seen as a victory for conservationists, who
claim <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has traditionally done little to preserve the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.
   ``There are many people who would like to see the jungle
disappear to raise cattle, but they won't do it with my approval,''
he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060890-0004 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 230494 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 8, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1150 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
RAIN FORESTS DISAPPEARING 50% QUICKER THAN FEARED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LARRY B. STAMMER, TIMES ENVIRONMENTAL WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Destruction of the world's tropical forests is occurring nearly <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> faster than 
the best previous scientific estimates showed, with enough trees being lost 
each year to cover the state of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>World Resources Institute</ORGANIZATION> said 
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Between 40 million and 50 million acres are lost annually, according to new 
satellite measurements of vanishing timberland, with the biggest losses 
occurring in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION> (formerly <LOCATION>Burma</LOCATION>) and <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Earlier estimates by the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> and other organizations placed annual 
losses at 28 million acres. But these estimates were based on data gathered 
before <DATE>1980</DATE>, compared to the latest findings, which are based on <DATE>1987</DATE> data. The 
earlier figures also were obtained largely through less accurate ground 
observations. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s published report marked the first comprehensive picture of worldwide 
deforestation trends based on a compilation of recent studies. 
</P>
<P>
"We were startled, frankly," institute President <PERSON>James Gustave Speth</PERSON> said in a 
telephone interview from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. "We're looking at an environmental tragedy 
unfolding. It's much worse than had been previously suspected." 
</P>
<P>
The report, published in collaboration with the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, has disturbing 
implications both for global warming and the extinction of plant and animal 
species, he said. 
</P>
<P>
Tropical forests are believed to not only shelter half of the world's plant and 
animal species -- most of them as yet undiscovered -- but serve as a major 
brake on the buildup of carbon dioxide, a principal contributor to global 
warming. 
</P>
<P>
Forests, most prominently in the Third World, are cut down at a rapid pace to 
provide wood for export and fuel, and to clear land for development and 
agriculture. When forests are cleared and burned, huge amounts of the carbon is 
returned to the atmosphere in the form of carbon dioxide gas. Tree burning 
accounts for an estimated <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of worldwide total carbon dioxide emissions. 
Burning fossil fuels like coal, oil and gasoline accounts for most of the rest. 
</P>
<P>
"If you combine increasing deforestation with the increasing use of fossil 
fuels in the industrial countries . . . it's easy to understand why the 
emissions of greenhouse gases have tripled over a 30-year period," <PERSON>Speth</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
But he also cited reason for optimism, noting that in the last several years 
some nations, notably <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, have promised to curb the clearing of 
forests. 
</P>
<P>
too early to comment on the new estimates but that the institute's 
deforestation figures were based on "fairly reputable" studies. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Ellen Tillier</PERSON>, public affairs officer with the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 
agreed. She said the higher deforestation rate was "along the lines" of recent 
estimates by the bank, which finances international development projects. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Allen L. Hammond</PERSON>, editor of the volume, "World Resources, 1990-91," called the 
updated estimate released <DATE>Thursday</DATE> conservative. "In countries where we have 
reliable new data, its far worse than <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT>. Fifty percent is a world average," 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hammond</PERSON> said most of the estimates were based on data collected by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
satellites and analyzed by scientists in the countries studied and by outside 
scientists. 
</P>
<P>
The data covers only half of the world's nations that have tropical forests. 
Additional studies are under way, including an update due in <DATE>1992</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. 
Food and Agriculture Organization</ORGANIZATION>, whose study released in <DATE>1980</DATE> was the basis 
for the lower estimates called into question <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hammond</PERSON> said that when that information is made public, it will, "in fact, show 
even higher rates of deforestation than we're reporting." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, which has the world's largest remaining tropical forests, also has the 
largest area of annual deforestation. The new studies indicate that <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s 
million acres outside the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1987</DATE>, a peak year of deforestation in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, the rate of loss was as much 
as <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> higher than earlier estimates for that country. During that year, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> 
caused 1.2 million tons of carbon to be released into the atmosphere, virtually 
the same amount pumped into the air by the much more industrialized <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> from the burning of fossil fuels like coal, oil and gasoline. 
</P>
<P>
Since <DATE>1987</DATE>, however, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has taken steps to dramatically reduce the 
destruction, including stepped-up enforcement and the elimination of tax 
incentives that led to large-scale land clearing. 
</P>
<P>
Two days ago, President <PERSON>Fernando Collor</PERSON> de Mello announced that <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s armed 
forces were ready to help stop the burning and deforestation of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain 
forest. 
</P>
<P>
But progress in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> is not expected to change the overall picture because 
deforestation in most other Third World countries appears to be increasing, the 
institute said. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>World Resources Institute</ORGANIZATION>'s report <DATE>Thursday</DATE> noted dramatic upswings in 
other countries' deforestation rates. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION>, for example, 1.7 million acres are lost each year, "an astounding" 
<PERCENT>545%</PERCENT> increase over <DATE>1980</DATE> estimates. The <DATE>1980</DATE> estimate relied on information 
collected in the mid-1970's and a <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Food and Agriculture Organization</ORGANIZATION> 
computer model of rural population trends. 
</P>
<P>
The new estimate is based on recent field work, a continuing analysis of aerial 
photographs and satellite data and extrapolations from the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> data. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, satellite sensing studies point to a 10-fold increase over previous 
estimates to 3.7 million acres a year. 
</P>
<P>
The Indonesian deforestation estimate of 2.2 million aces a year is <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> more 
than the <DATE>1980</DATE> estimate, and <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION>'s figure rose <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> to 300,000 acres lost 
annually. Only in <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> are the old and new estimates comparable. 
</P>
<P>
"The <DATE>1980s</DATE> were a decade of devastation for the global environment. In the 
<DATE>1990s</DATE> things could either get much, much worse or we could begin to start a 
healing. It all depends on what our governments are willing to do, more than 
anything else," <PERSON>Speth</PERSON> said. He called developments in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> encouraging. 
</P>
<P>
The report, published in collaboration with the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Environment Program</ORGANIZATION> and 
the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Development Program</ORGANIZATION>, also for the first time ranked greenhouse gas 
emissions from 146 countries. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> ranked No. 1 and No. 2, respectively. 
Combined, they accounted for nearly <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of all greenhouse gas emissions 
worldwide in <DATE>1987</DATE>, followed by <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>. If the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> is considered as a single entity, it 
would rank second behind the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> instead of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Worldwide, the equivalent of <MONEY>6.5 billion tons</MONEY> of carbon in the form of carbon 
dioxide, methane and chlorofluorocarbons were added to the atmosphere in <DATE>1987</DATE>, 
the report said. 
</P>
<P>
LAST STAND IN <LOCATION>PALAWAN</LOCATION> -- Loggers and squatter farmers strip Philippine forests. 
A5 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Chart, VANISHING TIMBERLAND: Tropical forests are being lost 50% faster than 
earlier studies had estimated, the World Resources Institute reports. The chart 
compares the estimated new rate of annual deforestation with the old estimates 
for the nine countries studied. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
RAIN FORESTS; DEFORESTATION; ENVIRONMENT; ECOLOGY; GREENHOUSE EFFECT; THIRD 
WORLD -- DEVELOPMENT AND REDEVELOPMENT 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890829-0169 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-89 2151EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Amazon     08-29 0489</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Amazon,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Begins Emergency Plan to Control Fires in Amazon</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By Jorge Mederos</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A government official said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> police
are fighting indiscriminate burning and tree-cutting in parts of the
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest under emergency measures that already have
brought <MONEY>$9 million</MONEY> in fines.
   <PERSON>Jose Roberto Lima</PERSON>, a spokesman for the state's <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian
Environmental Institute</ORGANIZATION>, said institute agents and federal police
began patrolling part of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle in five helicopters in
early <DATE>August</DATE>.
   In that month, ranchers and farmers traditionally begin to burn
off forest growth for pasture and planting.
   ``The area is wild and the settlers extremely dangerous. If you
don't police the jungle with a machine gun on your side, you're as
good as dead,'' <LOCATION>Lima</LOCATION> said in an interview.
   He said agents had handed out fines of about <MONEY>$9 million</MONEY> in the
<DATE>first 15 days</DATE> of the exercise.
   Among those fined were farmers, ranchers, steel mills that use
wood to fuel blast furnaces and 15 sawmills.
   <LOCATION>Lima</LOCATION> said fines will be used to support an emergency
environmental package called ``Our Nature'' announced earlier this
year.
   Amid mounting world concern that the destruction of the forest
could disastrously change global weather, the Brazilian government
also this year suspended incentives for large-scale agricultural and
cattle ranching projects and created a special police force to
control fires.
   Satellite photographs show that in the past 10 years the 2
million-square-mile rain forest, the world's largest, has lost an
area half the size of <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> to slashing, burning and mining.
   Ecologists charge the government has done little to discourage
the uncontrolled destruction.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> initially refused offers of help from international
organizations and foreign governments, saying that would amount to
meddling in its internal affairs but has softened that position in
recent months.
   The government earlier this year turned down offers from the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> to discuss swapping part
of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s <MONEY>$115 million</MONEY> debt for preserving <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> land, which
covers two-thirds of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and is home to 15 million people.
   But <LOCATION>Lima</LOCATION> said the institute hopes to receive help from foreign
governments to strengthen its efforts.
   <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> already have promised five tanker planes to help
put out forest fires, he said.
   In just 25 hours of flights over the so-called <ORGANIZATION>Parrot</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Beak</LOCATION>
region in southern Para _ the site of bloody clashes between peasant
farmers and large landowners _ agents found 150 areas where the
forest was being illegally destroyed, <LOCATION>Lima</LOCATION> said.
   He said the patrols have rescued 150 animals and 120 birds, some
threatened with extinction.
   The patrols will continue for three months over the jungle states
of <LOCATION>Para</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mato Grosso</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Rondonia</LOCATION> and Acre, <LOCATION>Lima</LOCATION> said. The so-called
Legal <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> also includes the states of <LOCATION>Amapa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Roraima</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maranhao</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Tocantins</LOCATION> and Amazonas.
   Uncontrolled colonization has destroyed more than <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT> of
the rain forest, satellite photos show. Some researchers put the
figure at nearer <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890315-0268 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-15-89 1244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-EXP--RainForests Adv19-2Takes   03-15 1113</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Rain Forests, Adv 19 - 2 Takes,1140</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday, March 19, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Campaign to Preserve Rain Forest Progresses Slowly</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhotos, LaserGraphics</HEAD>
<HEAD>An Explorations Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM COHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A campaign to preserve the remaining half of the
world's tropical rain forests has finally taken root, but the task
is enormous and the last gasp for the ``lungs of the Earth'' could
be less than a century away.
   Environmentalists are pleased with their initial success three
years after they began challenging governments, industries and
banks. But an area the size of a soccer field is destroyed each
minute, and the young preservation movement seeks fundamental
changes in political, economic and social structures to save the
teeming jungles of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>.
   An aggressive campaign of publicity, education and confrontation
began in <DATE>1985</DATE> and appeared to capture the world's attention last
year. Almost overnight, it seemed, world leaders began calling for
greater efforts to halt the chopping and burning of rain forests.
Conferences discussed such technical conservation issues as
``sustainable management.'' Rock stars Sting and The Grateful Dead
played benefit concerts for the cause. Media coverage increased.
   Some recent fruits of that effort:
   _<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in <DATE>October</DATE> announced suspension of tax benefits for
landowners who destroy the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest, the largest and
fastest-disappearing on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   _<ORGANIZATION>The International Tropical Timber Organization</ORGANIZATION> approved a <MONEY>$4
million</MONEY> project in northern <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> that calls for loggers to consult
with environmental groups, government agencies, native Indians and
local workers to plan long-term forest development and preservation.
   _Some 500 Brazilian Indians from 20 tribes gathered last month to
oppose planned hydroelectric dams in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> that could flood
rain forest areas, including their homes. The meeting was the first
by the tribes, which traditionally have battled over territory and
remained isolated.
   _<LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> imposed a nationwide logging ban after
environmentalists blamed uncontrolled timber harvesting for floods
that killed more than 350 people in <DATE>November</DATE>. Last <DATE>April</DATE>, officials
suspended plans for a hydroelectric dam that environmentalists said
would have ruined <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>'s last virgin rain forest.
   _<LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> earmarked about <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY> for saving tropical
forests.
   ``Without a coherent strategy for protecting the tropical forests
in which everyone concerned participates, we cannot master the vast
problems threatening the future of all mankind,'' said West German
Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>.
   ``We have to be ambitious. We're in trouble,'' said <PERSON>Randall
Hayes</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-based Rainforest Action Network</ORGANIZATION>. ``If we
don't get the changes we need in the next five years, then we've
lost the rain forests.''
   The results could be catastrophic.
   Rain forests cover some 2.4 billion acres of the planet, about
half the original amount, ecologists say.
   Sometimes called the ``lungs of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' they act as a
carbon dioxide isn't removed from the atmosphere, it can trap heat,
which some scientists say causes a global warming trend called the
greenhouse effect. Burning the rain forests, a common way to create
arable land, also adds carbon to the atmosphere.
   Rain forests are storehouses of plant, insect and animal species,
some of which could prove useful for drugs and other scientific
endeavors. Scientists say only a small percentage of the 5 million
species in the forests, many of them unique to the tropical
environment, have been studied.
   In addition, 200 million people live in and around rain forests,
including indigenous tribes who depend on them for sustenance and
shelter.
   Nonetheless, preservation presents complexities that cut across
social and political boundaries. Many rain forests are in developing
countries that need to capitalize on their natural resources and
must borrow money for costly modernization projects, such as
highways and power plants.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, for example, has the developing world's largest foreign
debt at <MONEY>$115 billion</MONEY>. Two of its limited number of export products
are beef and timber _industries that cause major forest destruction.
Cattle ranchers burn forests to create grazing land; loggers clear
jungle in search of exotic hardwoods.
   Meanwhile, poor farmers burn small tracts to grow crops. The
soil, so fertile under the rain forest canopy, is then leached of
nutrients in seasonal heavy rains, forcing farmers to move on and
burn another patch every few years.
   Last fall, Brazilian President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON> suspended tax benefits
for land developers and banned exports of unprocessed tropical
timber. ``We must create nationwide consciousness that we are all
passengers in the adventure of man on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. The era of unlimited
natural resources is over,'' he said.
   But environmentalists contend the harmful practices continue.
Now, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> is balking at proposals to swap some of its foreign debt
for saving parcels of rain forest. Such plans would entail creation
of an international commission to watch over the preserved jungle.
   ``We can't turn the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> into a sort of national park for
humanity,'' <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s foreign minister, <PERSON>Roberto de Abreu Sodre</PERSON>, said.
``Our priority is economic development. We're open to international
suggestions, but not those that interfere in Brazilian sovereignty.''
   Industrial giants such as the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and European
countries, which have little or no rain forest, have been the most
vocal about the developing nations' efforts to halt the destruction.
That causes particular resentment.
   A conference of eight nations in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> region, including
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, earlier this month issued a declaration rejecting foreign
interference while saying development must preserve the environment
and wild resources.
   ``Part of the problem is that it's coming down to the developed
countries versus the developing countries,'' said a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> activist
who monitors the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>, the largest source of aid to developing
nations.
   ``They (developing countries) say, `You raped your countries to
get developed, and now you're stopping us from doing it,''' said the
activist, who spoke on condition his name not be used.
   But <PERSON>N.F. Potter</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s executive director at the <ORGANIZATION>151-nation
World Bank</ORGANIZATION>, said: ``There are ways of doing things without making
the same mistakes.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> has been criticized by environmentalists, who say
it ignores ecological issues when funding projects. At issue are
billions of dollars; in the <DATE>fiscal year ending June 30</DATE>, the bank
expects to loan a record <MONEY>$21 billion</MONEY>.
   ``These bankers are unbelievably ignorant. They are absolutely
reckless,'' said <PERSON>Brent Blackwelder</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-based Environmental
Policy Institute</ORGANIZATION>.
   Under increasing pressure from member nations and environmental
groups not to fund ecologically harmful projects, the bank set up a
department in <DATE>1987</DATE> to assess the potential damage of development
projects.
   ``You can see a lot more environmental consciousness than there
was two years ago,'' said an official with a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> agency that
monitors aid. ``There has been movement. I'm not saying there has
been all the movement necessary.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880701-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-88 2345EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Timber     07-01 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Timber,0527</SECOND>
<HEAD>Timber Industry Approves Environment Plan for Amazon</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER MUELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Conservation groups applauded a
decision <DATE>Friday</DATE> by the international timber industry to promote
environment-conscious logging in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle, the world's
largest tropical rainforest.
   The U.S.-based World Wildlife Fund said the decision _ the first
of its kind by the timber industry _ could slow destruction of the
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rainforest, a key regulator of the world's weather.
   The <ORGANIZATION>International Tropical Timber Organization</ORGANIZATION>, an association
of 42 producing and consuming countries, approved a <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY>
logging and conservation project in the remote jungle state of
Acre, on <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s border with <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>, 2,800 miles northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Rio
de Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>.
   The project calls for ``integrated'' development of jungle
products, such as <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> nuts and rubber, as well as timber. It
also calls for loggers to consult with environmental groups,
government agencies, native Indians and local workers to plan
long-term development to preserve the rainforest.
   ``This was the big one. We hope the Acre project can serve as a
model not just for the rest of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> but for all tropical
forests,'' <PERSON>Adam Markham</PERSON>, press spokesman for the World Wildlife
Fund, told the AP at the end of a 10-day meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>Timber
Organization</ORGANIZATION>.
   The organization's members control <PERCENT>95 percent</PERCENT> of the world's
<MONEY>$5.6 billion</MONEY> tropical timber trade.
   As timber trade shifts away from the shrinking forests of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>
and southeast <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, the mahogany-rich <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> is seen as the next
great source of hardwood.
   But conservationists are worried about the effect on the climate
of uncontrolled logging in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> basin, a <MONEY>2 million</MONEY>
square-mile region as large as <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> that covers parts of seven
South American countries and contains a third of the world's
rainforest.
   Already the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> forest is disappearing at the rate of some 27
million acres a year, mostly at the hands of small farmers and
ranchers who cut and burn the trees, <PERSON>Markham</PERSON> said.
   ``The rainforest is a gaseous sink for carbon dioxide. The trees
soak it up. If we cut them down, there's no way to get rid of the
gas. And that contributes to the greenhouse effect,'' he said.
   The greenhouse effect is a gradual warming of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s
surface because of excessive carbon dioxide and pollutants in the
atmosphere that trap the sun's heat, like a greenhouse. It is
thought to be a possible cause of the current drought in the <LOCATION>U.S.
Midwest</LOCATION>.
   The Acre project, which will get about <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> from the
Brazilan government and the rest from the <ORGANIZATION>Timber Organization</ORGANIZATION>, is
the largest approved since the organization was founded in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   Smaller conservation programs, similar to the Acre project, were
approved for <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>.
   Other proposals approved at the Rio meeting were:
   _Development of a ``news market service,'' to help producing
countries market better.
   _Standardization of timber specifications among member
countries, to cut waste caused by conflicting measurements.
   _Improvement of harvesting and processing equipment.
   The next meeting of the organization is scheduled for <DATE>November</DATE>
in <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Brazil-Amazon     10-07 0649</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Brazil-Amazon,0768</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazilian Elections Bad News for Ecologists</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KEN SILVERSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The sweeping victories by
conservatives in last week's congressional and gubernatorial races
will mean bad news for the rain forest and its defenders,
environmentalists say.
   Conservatives won a large majority in last week's voting, and
showed special strength in the nine states of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> region.
   ``Almost all . . . are totally opposed to ecological concerns
and rational development,'' <PERSON>Fernando Gabeira</PERSON>, a leader of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s
small <ORGANIZATION>Green Party</ORGANIZATION>, said over the weekend.
   The federal government sets most environmental policy, but
political scientist <PERSON>David Fleischer</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Brasilia</ORGANIZATION>
noted: ``Almost all policy enforcement is carried out by local
authorities. If they show no interest in protecting the
environment, decisions at the federal level lose much of their
impact.''
   Right-wing candidates for governor won outright victories in
three of the nine states and were headed for <DATE>Nov. 25</DATE> runoffs in the
other six.
   Only in two small states, Acre and <LOCATION>Amapa</LOCATION>, did pro-ecology
candidates even get to the runoffs.
   Candidates had to win an absolute majority to take a first-round
victory.
   In congressional races, conservatives won at least 11 of the 13
senate chairs at stake in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> region and all but a few of
the house seats.
   Rightist populists have long dominated the impoverished region.
Much of their success comes from support by major landowners, who
traditionally control the votes of the rural poor.
   Many voters also view environmentalism as an attempt to block
economic growth and lock the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> into perennial backwardness.
   Slash-and-burn techniques used by ranchers and farmers have
already destroyed about <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT> of the 2-million-square-mile
wilderness, according to government figures.
   In Amazonas, the area's largest state, incoming governor
<PERSON>Gilberto Mestrinho</PERSON> favors widescale destruction of the rain forest
to promote large mining and agricultural projects.
   The state's new senator, <PERSON>Amazonino Mendes</PERSON>, proposed handing out
chain saws to settlers to speed the felling of the forest.
   In neighboring <LOCATION>Roraima</LOCATION> state, both gubernatorial finalists
openly opposed federal plans to remove thousands of gold miners
from the territory of the <ORGANIZATION>Yanomami Indians</ORGANIZATION>, the world's largest
remaining primitive tribe.
   The miners illegally search for gold, diamonds and other
minerals on Indian land. Armed clashes and imported diseases killed
about 1,500 of the tribe's remaining 9,000 members in the past
three years.
   The favorite in <LOCATION>Roraima</LOCATION>'s gubernatorial race is <PERSON>Romero Juca</PERSON>, now
on trial for illegally authorizing logging on Indian land when he
was chief of the <ORGANIZATION>National Indian Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   ``The elections in <LOCATION>Roraima</LOCATION> could spell the end for the
<ORGANIZATION>Yanomami</ORGANIZATION>,'' <PERSON>Fleischer</PERSON> remarked,
   In Para state, the runoff pits anti-ecology candidates <PERSON>Jaber
Barbalho</PERSON> and Sahid Xerfan.
   Para has been the site of repeated clashes between Indians and
miners. Miners have dumped about 600 tons of mercury from gold
prospecting into the <LOCATION>Tapajos River</LOCATION>.
   ``We have no preference in <LOCATION>Para</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Gabeira</PERSON> said. ``Neither
possible winner will defend the Indians or the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.''
   Big farmers are blamed for most of the violence plaguing the
region. More than 1,000 peasant activists were killed in land
conflicts in the past decade.
   The Rev. <PERSON>Ricardo Resende</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Pastoral Land Commission</ORGANIZATION> said in
a phone interview from Para state, ``The new governors are well
known and most have never demonstrated any interest in protecting
the region's poor. Small farmers will continue to be expelled from
their land.''
   His commission is linked with the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Gabeira</PERSON> said the only bright spot was in Acre, home to thousands
of rubber tappers, where <PERSON>Jorge Viana</PERSON> of the pro-environmentalist
<ORGANIZATION>Workers Party</ORGANIZATION> won a spot in the second round.
   His strength is largely attributed to the legacy of
world-renowned unionist and ecologist <PERSON>Chico Mendes</PERSON>, a Workers Party
activist murdered in <DATE>1988</DATE>. Mendes' alleged killers are going on
trial <DATE>Oct. 25</DATE>, and the publicity could boost <ORGANIZATION>Viana</ORGANIZATION>'s campaign.
   There was another note of encouragement to the rain forest's
advocates <DATE>Sunday</DATE> contained in an article in the newspaper Jornal do
Brasil.
   It reported that the area of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest destroyed by
fires in <DATE>1990</DATE> was down considerably from last year. Data compiled
by <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Institute of Space Research</ORGANIZATION> showed overall
destruction may be down by as much as <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT>, the newspaper
said.
   Institute President <PERSON>Marcio Barbosa</PERSON> was quoted as saying that the
space satellite that monitors the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> has been crucial to
efforts to prevent further damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022590-0027 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 181023 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 25, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 6; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1611 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NATURE CONSERVANCY BUYS UP LAND TO WARD OFF DEVELOPMENT; 
</P>
<P>
PRESERVATION: CONSERVATIONISTS WITH SUCCESS IN LAW AND BUSINESS BRING MONEY TO 
THE CAUSE AND FUEL AMBITIOUS ACQUISITIONS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN BARBOUR, ASSOCIATED PRESS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When the <ORGANIZATION>Nature Conservancy</ORGANIZATION> bought 502 square miles of <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> -- <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of a 
mountain range and a more diverse population of mammals than any national park 
in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> -- it was hailed as a milestone. 
</P>
<P>
It certainly was. But the purchase in late <DATE>January</DATE> was also the culmination of 
an explosion of conservation efforts in the <DATE>last 10 years</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
A new breed of conservationists is buying up big chunks of the American 
landscape, stamping the land inviolate to the bulldozer's blade. 
</P>
<P>
How much money the conservancy paid for the Gray Ranch in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, astride 
the <ORGANIZATION>Continental Divide</ORGANIZATION>, wasn't made public. But it was probably in the 
neighborhood of <MONEY>$18 million</MONEY>, a sum that would have sounded improbable to a 
conservationist's ears a decade ago. 
</P>
<P>
What it brought under the conservancy's protection was almost all the <LOCATION>Animas 
Mountain</LOCATION> range; some 100 plant and animal species listed as endangered, 
threatened or rare; 13 pre-Columbian archeological digs and hundreds of others 
as yet unexplored; herds of Chihuahuan pronghorn antelope; seven different 
habitat types from desert grassland to chaparral and coniferous forest; and 
endangered bits of nature from the white-eared hummingbird to the night 
blooming cereus. 
</P>
<P>
The conservancy acted when it discovered the ranch owners wanted to sell and 
there was the threat the land might be broken up and developed. 
</P>
<P>
Conservancy President <PERSON>John C. Sawhill</PERSON>, announcing the buy, said: "Few intact 
natural systems of this caliber exist in the world today. The . . . effort also 
represents the future trend for the <ORGANIZATION>Nature Conservancy</ORGANIZATION> and its partners. To 
truly ensure our natural world for future generations, we are developing 
creative ways to safeguard much larger landscapes." 
</P>
<P>
A few years ago, such an effort would have been only a dream, but 
conservationists are becoming sophisticated advocates -- scientists, business 
graduates, experts in law and real estate. 
</P>
<P>
Inch by precious inch they are preserving farmland, wilderness and open spaces 
against development, more effectively than ever before. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Nature Conservancy</ORGANIZATION> is a sort of symbol for individuals and other land 
trusts. Before the <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> deal, it was taking an average of 1,000 acres a 
day out of commercial play. 
</P>
<P>
Says <PERSON>Mike Dennis</PERSON>, general counsel of the conservancy: "For every scientist we 
have around here, we probably have an MBA, a tax lawyer and a real estate 
attorney." 
</P>
<P>
Environmentalists have sharpened their skills in the private sector, recycling 
many of the same dollars each time to buy new land. They have discovered 
revolving funds, a war fund that doesn't have to stay invested. They can plunk 
down <MONEY>several million dollars</MONEY> until, by prior arrangement, a government agency 
can repay them, assuming custodial care of the property. 
</P>
<P>
Or they can buy a piece of property, deprive it of the potential for commercial 
development, and resell the land for a somewhat lesser cost to what they think 
is an appropriate buyer. 
</P>
<P>
Who is that buyer? A farmer who will farm without being tempted by high 
developer prices, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>, which wants to protect 
the land, or a trust that is able to preserve the land as open space, a vista, 
a place apart. 
</P>
<P>
In any case, the conservationists send the resale dollars back into their 
revolving funds to be used again. 
</P>
<P>
None of these organizations or individuals could succeed without local support. 
When a developer wanted to take a 147-acre scenic hay meadow in <LOCATION>Jackson Hole</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, to put in 70 to 80 houses, the local land trust negotiated an option on 
the land priced at <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The county came up with one-third and the land trust raised the rest from 
private donations. 
</P>
<P>
Says <PERSON>Jean Hocker</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Land Trust Alliance</ORGANIZATION>, an umbrella organization 
in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> for hundreds of local land trusts: "The community heard about it 
and came to the rescue." The deal took three months. Speed is important. 
</P>
<P>
There are more than 800 local land trusts established in states, counties and 
communities -- almost half of them formed in the past 10 years. They protect 
about 2 million acres and they own 300,000. Some of them have million-dollar 
budgets. 
</P>
<P>
Sometimes conservationists act in concert. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>McQuerry Ranch</ORGANIZATION>, 3,500 acres at the foot of the 11,000-foot peaks of 
<LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Ruby Mountains</LOCATION>, was in financial trouble, the family in danger of 
losing the land they had farmed for generations. 
</P>
<P>
A third of the ranch is a unique desert wetland area around <PERSON>Franklin Lake</PERSON>, the 
kind of terrain that attracts resort development. It is also a nesting area for 
migratory birds. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>American Farmland Trust</ORGANIZATION> suggested to the Nature Conservancy that the best 
way to preserve the land was to enhance the way in which the farm was operated 
by the family. 
</P>
<P>
The migratory birds and the wetland fit the conservancy's charter. With 
<MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> from its revolving fund, the conservationists bought the ranch and 
leased it back to the McQuerry family with certain conditions. 
</P>
<P>
The family would have to change certain farming operations. For instance, they 
would not be permitted to graze the wetland area from fall to the following 
<DATE>summer</DATE> when the birds use the estuary. 
</P>
<P>
When the family was able, they would buy the ranch back, but those covenants 
would remain. 
</P>
<P>
"If we hadn't stepped in, certainly the family was going into bankruptcy," says 
<PERSON>Ralph Grossi</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>American Farmland Trust</ORGANIZATION>. "They would have lost 
the farm." 
</P>
<P>
The farmland trust felt there was a real danger of development to the land and 
to the natural ecosystem around the lake. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> covers some 3.6 million square miles, or 2.3 trillion acres. 
Of those, 78,000 square miles, or almost 50 million acres, are inland 
waterways. There are also more than 88,000 miles of tidal shoreline. 
</P>
<P>
Conservationist groups can't protect it all, nor, they say, should they. Often 
they seek to cooperate with developers, allowing residential uses, but 
sequestering other areas. In some cases, developers pay mitigation fees for the 
damage their developments might cause. Those funds are used to enhance the 
protected land. 
</P>
<P>
Says the <ORGANIZATION>Nature Conservancy</ORGANIZATION>'s Dennis: "When you're talking about an ecosystem, 
you could be talking about anything from 5,000 acres to 500 square miles." 
</P>
<P>
So he outlines a compromise, a core that the conservationists want to own and 
manage. Around that they would establish a larger area where timbering and 
mining are banned. "Then you may want an additional buffer where development is 
OK, but it's got to be limited. You may allow a cluster of homes here on 2- to 
5-acre tracts and preserve farmland over there." 
</P>
<P>
Even individuals are taking a page from their book and designing small local 
operations to save such properties as a farm in <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> or 400 acres of 
rolling countryside in <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>. The farm remained a farm, and the 
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> tract is now home to an organically safe golf course. 
</P>
<P>
In the array of people in the conservation army, there is also an array of 
purposes. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Nature Conservancy</ORGANIZATION>'s 542,000 members, dedicated to preserving habitats, 
have financed a <MONEY>$600-million</MONEY> organization that has saved almost 4 million 
sensitive acres since it was founded in <DATE>1953</DATE>. It has 1,000 employees and 
probably 10,000 volunteers and covers every state. 
</P>
<P>
Considerably younger (10 years old) and smaller (a staff of 30 nationwide) is 
the American Farmland Trust, dedicated to saving the nation's farms and 
improving farming techniques. Yet, it churns accounts of more than <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> 
to get more acres for the buck. 
</P>
<P>
"We are concerned about the debt burden in agriculture," says the trust's 
president, <PERSON>Ralph Grossi</PERSON>. "Many farmers are going out of business and their land 
isn't being cared for adequately." 
</P>
<P>
Organizations from the <ORGANIZATION>National Wildlife Federation</ORGANIZATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, 
from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Ducks Unlimited</ORGANIZATION>, a hunter's group, 
often find themselves working in concert. 
</P>
<P>
They all have one thing in common. They can move more quickly than local or 
state governments can and, using charitable tax benefits, they can bring in a 
deal cheaper than developers can. 
</P>
<P>
By stripping a piece of land of development rights, it is not only protected 
regardless of who owns it, but income tax benefits can either bring the owner a 
sizable tax deduction or provide instant cash for a farmer. 
</P>
<P>
It also reduces the value of the land and hence its tax assessment, which 
deprives the county or state of some tax revenue. But counties and states 
usually are willing to forgo taxes on some property to enhance the value of 
land around it. 
</P>
<P>
Witness <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s Gov. <PERSON>Mario M. Cuomo</PERSON>, who has asked for <MONEY>$1.9 billion</MONEY> to set 
aside areas of the <ORGANIZATION>Empire State</ORGANIZATION> for scenic and recreation purposes. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 
has provided more than <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY> for similar purposes, and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> has an 
active land acquisition program. 
</P>
<P>
But the smallest of communities can be stirred to action. <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s west coast 
is a beautiful blend of dunes, orchards and sandy beaches on <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION>. It 
is a magnet for those wanting second homes, and unlike the coast of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, 
which it mimics in miniature, it has no coastal commission to protect it. 
</P>
<P>
Local land trusts, with the help of the <ORGANIZATION>Farmland Trust</ORGANIZATION>, moved in to buy a 
507-acre farm on the <LOCATION>Old Mission Peninsula</LOCATION>, blocking any further residential 
development. It will remain an orchard in an area that prides itself as being 
the "Cherry Capital of the World." 
</P>
<P>
"It's unlikely that some crops will be grown in any quantity in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> 30 to 40 years from now," says <PERSON>Grossi</PERSON> of the Farmland Trust. "The 
growing areas that are required, the climate, the soil, the weather, those 
unique values are essentially the same as those that attract people." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, The Nature Conservancy helped save the huge McQuerry Ranch, near 
Nevada's Ruby Mountains, and New York's Mashomack Preserve, right. ; Photo, The 
Maine Coast Heritage Trust bought and saved Western Head, a peninsula near the 
Canadian border. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890315-0271 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-15-89 1248EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-EXP--RainForests-Brazil Adv19   03-15 0782</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Rain Forests-Brazil, Adv 19,0805</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday, March 19, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Brazil Wants to Keep Control Over Amazon</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-EXP--Rain Forests</HEAD>
<HEAD>An Explorations Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA GENASCI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   International pressure is mounting
on <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> to preserve its fast-disappearing <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest, but
the debt-ridden South American nation continues to resist what it
considers to be foreign meddling.
   There is growing concern worldwide that destruction of the 2
million-square-mile rain forest, the world's largest and
fastest-disappearing, could change global weather with potentially
disastrous consequences.
   Satellite photos of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> show that in the past 10 years, an
area the size of <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> has been slashed, burned and mined away.
About <PERCENT>9 percent</PERCENT> of the region is irreparably damaged, said
researcher <PERSON>Philip M. Fearnside</PERSON>.
   But ecologists charge that the government has done little to
discourage uncontrolled destruction.
   In <DATE>January</DATE>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> congressional delegation led by <PERSON>Sen. Timothy
Wirth</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Colo.</LOCATION>, met with President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON> to discuss swapping
part of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s <MONEY>$115 billion</MONEY> debt for preserving <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> land.
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> have made similar proposals, involving
creating an international commission to oversee the forest that
covers two-thirds of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and is home to 15 million people.
   All received the same answer _ <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> won't be told what to do.
   ``We can't turn the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> into a sort of national park for
humanity. Our priority is economic development. We're open to
international suggestions but not those that interfere in Brazilian
sovereignty,'' Foreign Minister <PERSON>Roberto de Abreu Sodre</PERSON> said recently.
   ``We can't be condemned to having a large part of our territory
prevented from being developed, particularly when the developed
world is responsible for the world's greatest ecological
disasters,'' said Deputy Foreign Minister <PERSON>Paulo Tarso Flecha</PERSON> de <LOCATION>Lima</LOCATION>.
   Over the past two decades, the government has given cattle
ranchers tax breaks and other indirect subsidies totaling about <MONEY>$2
billion</MONEY>, even though studies show most of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> is unsuited to
ranching or farming.
   The tropical soil is extremely fragile. When the protective
forest canopy is burned, nutrients wash away in the heavy rains.
   ``A typical field won't stand more than two crops, and a cattle
pasture lasts not more than a decade,'' said <PERSON>Fearnside</PERSON>, a professor
at the <ORGANIZATION>Amazonia Research Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Manaus</LOCATION>, the principal <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>
city. ``Only about <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> soil is suitable for
conventional farming.''
   In addition, much of the land has been cleared and burned by
farmers and by land speculators hoping for a better price for
homesteaded property, he said.
   Satellite photos of thousands of fires set by farmers and
developers drew world attention last year, as did the <DATE>December</DATE>
slaying of internationally known ecologist Francisco ``Chico''
<PERSON>Mendes</PERSON>.
   The leader of a local rubber tappers union, <PERSON>Mendes</PERSON> fought to keep
ranchers from cutting down the jungle for pasture. He had called for
more harvesting of <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> resources such as nuts, latex and plants,
while preserving the trees.
   Four people, including the son of a rancher, have been arrested.
   In a nation where <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the people survive on less than
<MONEY>$90</MONEY> a month, ecologists and politicians argue that the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> has
not created enough jobs to justify the destruction and its future
consequences.
   ``The idea that you tear down the rain forest to create jobs is
not sound,'' <PERSON>Wirth</PERSON> said. ``To send a lot of people out there to
settle the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> just doesn't work.''
   In the <DATE>1920s</DATE>, auto magnate <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION> failed in a scheme to
cultivate rubber trees in a vast area now known as ``Fordlandia.''
Decades later, in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and <DATE>'70s</DATE>, shipping magnate <PERSON>Daniel Ludwig</PERSON>
lost a reported <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> in an ambitious plan to produce wood pulp
and rice on the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Jari River</LOCATION>.
   ``Vast areas of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> have been devastated and the poverty
is no less,'' said <PERSON>Artur Virgilio</PERSON>, mayor of <LOCATION>Manaus</LOCATION>. ``Only the
wealthy have so far benefited from the destruction.''
   Foreign groups have said they would pressure international
financial institutions not to release new funding for Amazon-related
projects. The <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>, which has loaned <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> $<MONEY>15 billion</MONEY> since
<DATE>1949</DATE> for energy-related and development projects, is a principal
target.
   For example, environmental groups have urged the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> to
reject a <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> loan that would help <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> refinance some
debt from construction of dams and power plants. They say <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>
