<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900924-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-24-90 1806EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Diets-Teens     09-24 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Diets-Teens,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congress Hears Appeals For Restrictions On Diet Pills</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIANE DUSTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A couple whose daughter died after years of
diet pill abuse asked a congressional panel <DATE>Monday</DATE> to push for
restrictions on non-prescription weight loss drugs.
   ``She might have had a chance had these products been denied her
as a child,'' said <PERSON>Anthony</PERSON> and <PERSON>Diana Smith</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>State Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Noelle Smith</PERSON>, 20, died a year ago of cardiac arrest after
struggling since she was 14 with the eating disorder anorexia
nervosa, which is an avoidance of food, and bulimia, which involves
binging and purging.
   ``She was constantly sneaking diet products into the house,''
said <PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON>. ``Every time we found and took from <LOCATION>Noelle</LOCATION> a box of
diet pills, laxatives or diuretics, she would go to the corner
store and buy a new supply.''
   <PERSON>Jessica McDonald</PERSON>, 20, of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, said she suffered
from the same eating disorders as a teen-ager and regularly
consumed whole boxes of non-prescription diet pills at a time.
   ``Even though I went to the drug store practically every day to
buy pills or some other product to help me lose weight, no one ever
tried to stop me or asked what I wanted the pills for,'' said
<ORGANIZATION>McDonald</ORGANIZATION>.
   She said that ``at the very least there should be an age
restriction to prevent young people from buying these drugs.''
Anorexia Nervosa and Associated Disorders</ORGANIZATION>, said at least one of 10
adolescents engage in dangerous eating disorders as they try to
diet.
   ``The adolescent whoreduces food amounts to starvation levels
is playing havoc with his or her body's viability,'' said <PERSON>Meehan</PERSON>.
``Children who begin dieting at an early age may delay or prevent
menstruation because females need 18 to <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT> of body fat for
this purpose.''
   Meehan also decried the availability of diet pills.
   ``Diet pills containing the drug phenylpropanolamine, or <ORGANIZATION>PPA</ORGANIZATION>,
pose an additional and very serious health risk to adolescents,''
she said.
   The drug is in most of the numerous, popular non-prescription
diet products used by about 10 million consumers a year. Many
medical authorities say it can cause high blood pressure, kidney
disease, heart muscle damage, heart rhythm abnormalities and
seizures.
   The Smiths, <ORGANIZATION>McDonald</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Meehan</PERSON> were among witnesses testifying
before the <ORGANIZATION>House Small Business</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee, which has been
investigating the weight loss industry.
   A report from the subcommittee staff noted a <ORGANIZATION>University of San
Francisco</ORGANIZATION> study of 500 girls which showed almost half the
9-year-olds and <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of those age 10 and 11 were dieting,
even though just <PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT> of the group was overweight.
   ``Our investigation found that juveniles are dieting more
obsessively than ever, and that many are suffering adverse health
effects and even death,'' said the staff report.
   Chairman <PERSON>Ron Wyden</PERSON>, D-Oregon, has been after the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Trade
Commission</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Food and Drug Administration</ORGANIZATION> to crack down on
shady diet practices.
   He said the <ORGANIZATION>FTC</ORGANIZATION> has 14 investigations under way of diet
companies and diet programs.
   But he criticized the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION> for being lax on enforcement.
   ``For almost a decade, the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION> has dawdled over regulations that
would make it illegal to sell diet products containing about 100
ineffective ingredients,'' said <PERSON>Wyden</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900920-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-20-90 1133EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--FoodObsessed-Dis Adv24   09-20 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Food Obsessed-Disorders, Adv24,0706</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Monday, Sept. 24, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Anorexia, Bulimia Are Growing Problem for Men</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-EXP--Food Obsessed, b0954-b0955</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY MacVEAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Despite a new focus on being healthy rather than
merely thin, anorexia and bulimia continue to haunt young women,
and the number of men who suffer from eating disorders appears to
be growing.
   The last decade was full of images of the dangers of eating
disorders, on television and in movies and women's magazines.
   An anorexic teen-ager was a character in the movie ``Down and
Out in <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION>.'' <PERSON>Jane Fonda</PERSON> told the world she had suffered
from bulimia. <PERSON>Karen Carpenter</PERSON> lost her life to an eating disorder.
Even a ``<DATE>Saturday</DATE> Night Live'' skit included an anorexic cookbook.
   The diseases have not gone away, though experts say estimates at
the time that <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of college women suffered from them were
exaggerated. And new pressures have come to bear on those who are
susceptible.
   ``It's not good enough just to be thin, but one has to have
muscles in the right places, for a man or a woman. You get into the
fat content of your body, how much muscle tone,'' said <PERSON>Leonard S.
Levitz</PERSON>, clincal director of the <ORGANIZATION>Renfrew Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>,
which in <DATE>1985</DATE> became the first residential facility for treatment
of eating disorders.
   So now there is ``exercise bulimia,'' in which sufferers turn to
extraordinary amounts of exercise rather than, or in addition to,
laxatives or vomiting.
   Anorexia is estimated to be two to four times as common <DATE>today</DATE> as
30 years ago. Bulimia also appears to be more common. The best
estimates seem to be that <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT> of college women
are afflicted, <PERSON>Levitz</PERSON> said.
   Anorexia nervosa is characterized by self-starvation, an intense
fear of becoming fat and a feeling that one is fat, despite being
emaciated. Bulimia involves a pattern of binge eating followed by
purging by vomiting or with diruetics.
   Although anorexia was identified in <DATE>1873</DATE> by a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> physician,
there is a centuries-long history of women controlling their
appetites, <PERSON>Joan Jacobs Brumberg</PERSON> wrote in her book ``Fasting
Girls.''
   In the <DATE>1300s</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>St. Catherine of Siena</ORGANIZATION> was said to eat only a
handful of herbs a day. In the midieval period, fasting was central
to female holiness.
   Bulimia, however, is newer, becoming epidemic only in <DATE>1973</DATE> or
<DATE>1974</DATE>, when ``a lot of trends came together in terms of broad
societal issues, concern over body weight, role of women, people
being under tremendous pressure to be perfect, the breakdown of
family life,'' <PERSON>Levitz</PERSON> said.
   A victim ``feels powerless in the world, no sense of control of
her life, and a real fear that if her eating, like her emotions,
got out of control, who knows what would happen,'' <PERSON>Levitz</PERSON> said.
   Treatment generally is an intensive combination of therapy,
education and behavior modification.
   These generally are diseases of intelligent women, found in the
middle and upper classes of developed countries. The incidence
appears to be increasing in <LOCATION>Scandinavia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
   New research is showing that many of those who suffer from
eating disorders dieted as preteen-agers, were sexually abused, or
abuse drugs or alcohol, <PERSON>Levitz</PERSON> said. Also linked to the disease are
such issues as fear of growth into womanhood.
   At adolescence, girls come to think of the normal changes
occurring in their bodies as fatness and enter a war of wills to
control them. Boys, however, take pride in their growth.
   The overwhelming majority of people with eating disorders are
women, but experts say more and more men are afflicted,
particularly those involved in weight-conscious pursuits like
wrestling, dancing or modeling.
   Is there a way out?
   Said Levitz: ``Yes, I think there's a way. And I used to be more
hopeful about it happening. The main thing we have to do is change
people's perceptions of how you deal with different body weights.
How you look is a part of how you are as a person. And there are
many, many other things that are equally or more important.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday, Sept. 24</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Despite a new focus on being healthy rather than
merely thin, anorexia and bulimia continue to haunt young women,
and the number of men who suffer from eating disorders appears to
be growing.
   The last decade was full of images of the dangers of eating
disorders, on television and in movies and women's magazines.
   An anorexic teen-ager was a character in the movie ``Down and
Out in <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION>.'' <PERSON>Jane Fonda</PERSON> told the world she had suffered
from bulimia. <PERSON>Karen Carpenter</PERSON> lost her life to an eating disorder.
Even a ``<DATE>Saturday</DATE> Night Live'' skit included an anorexic cookbook.
   The diseases have not gone away, though experts say estimates at
the time that <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of college women suffered from them were
exaggerated. And new pressures have come to bear on those who are
susceptible.
   ``It's not good enough just to be thin, but one has to have
muscles in the right places, for a man or a woman. You get into the
fat content of your body, how much muscle tone,'' said <PERSON>Leonard S.
Levitz</PERSON>, clincal director of the <ORGANIZATION>Renfrew Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>,
which in <DATE>1985</DATE> became the first residential facility for treatment
of eating disorders.
   So now there is ``exercise bulimia,'' in which sufferers turn to
extraordinary amounts of exercise rather than, or in addition to,
laxatives or vomiting.
   Anorexia is estimated to be two to four times as common <DATE>today</DATE> as
30 years ago. Bulimia also appears to be more common. The best
estimates seem to be that <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT> of college women
are afflicted, <PERSON>Levitz</PERSON> said.
   Anorexia nervosa is characterized by self-starvation, an intense
fear of becoming fat and a feeling that one is fat, despite being
emaciated. Bulimia involves a pattern of binge eating followed by
purging by vomiting or with diruetics.
   Although anorexia was identified in <DATE>1873</DATE> by a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> physician,
there is a centuries-long history of women controlling their
appetites, <PERSON>Joan Jacobs Brumberg</PERSON> wrote in her book ``Fasting
Girls.''
   In the <DATE>1300s</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>St. Catherine of Siena</ORGANIZATION> was said to eat only a
handful of herbs a day. In the midieval period, fasting was central
to female holiness.
   Bulimia, however, is newer, becoming epidemic only in <DATE>1973</DATE> or
<DATE>1974</DATE>, when ``a lot of trends came together in terms of broad
societal issues, concern over body weight, role of women, people
being under tremendous pressure to be perfect, the breakdown of
family life,'' <PERSON>Levitz</PERSON> said.
   A victim ``feels powerless in the world, no sense of control of
her life, and a real fear that if her eating, like her emotions,
got out of control, who knows what would happen,'' <PERSON>Levitz</PERSON> said.
   Treatment generally is an intensive combination of therapy,
education and behavior modification.
   These generally are diseases of intelligent women, found in the
middle and upper classes of developed countries. The incidence
appears to be increasing in <LOCATION>Scandinavia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
   New research is showing that many of those who suffer from
eating disorders dieted as preteen-agers, were sexually abused, or
abuse drugs or alcohol, <PERSON>Levitz</PERSON> said. Also linked to the disease are
such issues as fear of growth into womanhood.
   At adolescence, girls come to think of the normal changes
occurring in their bodies as fatness and enter a war of wills to
control them. Boys, however, take pride in their growth.
   The overwhelming majority of people with eating disorders are
women, but experts say more and more men are afflicted,
particularly those involved in weight-conscious pursuits like
wrestling, dancing or modeling.
   Is there a way out?
   Said Levitz: ``Yes, I think there's a way. And I used to be more
hopeful about it happening. The main thing we have to do is change
people's perceptions of how you deal with different body weights.
How you look is a part of how you are as a person. And there are
many, many other things that are equally or more important.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890102-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-02-89 1908EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AnorexiaCalls     01-02 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Anorexia Calls,0381</SECOND>
<HEAD>TV Movie Sparks More Than 500 Calls For Help</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE RULE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 500 people nationwide called a
toll-free number for information about anorexia nervosa after
watching a television movie about singer <PERSON>Karen Carpenter</PERSON>, who died
as a result of the eating disorder.
   When ``The <PERSON>Karen Carpenter</PERSON> Story'' was broadcast by <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME>, many affiliate stations displayed the toll-free telephone
number of a <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> center devoted to treating eating disorders.
   Since the number, 800-334-8415, appeared, the <ORGANIZATION>Renfrew Center</ORGANIZATION> has
received more than 500 calls asking for information, <PERSON>Judy Goldstein</PERSON>,
the center's director of admissions, said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``We expected the explosion of interest,'' <PERSON>Ms. Goldstein</PERSON> said.
``We put in extra telephone lines to handle the calls.''
   The center is sending callers a brochure with basic information
about the disorder and a list of self-help centers throughout the
country, said <PERSON>Sam Menaged</PERSON>, a co-founder.
   ``We were at the phones until <TIME>3 a.m.</TIME>'' <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <PERSON>Menaged</PERSON> said.
``The calls started trickling in from the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>, then as the
night went on, I noticed we were talking to (people in) <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Carpenter</PERSON> and her brother, <PERSON>Richard</PERSON>, recorded 20 top 10 hit
songs during the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, singing such tunes as ``Close to You,''
``Top of the World,'' ``We've Only Just Begun,'' and their No. 1
remake of ``Please <PERSON>Mr. Postman</PERSON>.''
   She died in <DATE>1983</DATE> of heart failure due to anorexia nervosa, an
eating disorder characterized by an obsession with weight loss and
an aversion to food.
   Although the disorder primarily affects women _ especially young
women _ no pattern to the calls existed, <PERSON>Ms. Goldstein</PERSON> said.
   A number of callers also asked about bulimia, an eating disorder
characterized by binging then purging the body of food.
   ``In the movie, <PERSON>Karen Carpenter</PERSON> had recovered but died several
months later,'' <PERSON>Ms. Goldstein</PERSON> said. ``She had done so much damage to
her body. ... She wasn't able to make it.''
   Recovered anorexics should continue to receive therapy or
support, <PERSON>Ms. Goldstein</PERSON> said, so they will be aware of their
continued needs.
   She said the center normally gets about 100 calls per week from
people seeking information about the disorder.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901018-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-18-90 0039EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--Anorexia     10-18 0148</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Anorexia,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Increase Seen In Anorexia Nervosa Among Young</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A children's hospital says anorexia nervosa is up
among diet-crazed girls as young as 8 years old who are worried
about their weight because of social pressure.
   ``It's part of the general culture that we live in where
fitness, slimness, health is very much promoted and some of that
rubs off on young children,'' said <PERSON>Rachel Waugh</PERSON>, a specialist in
childhood eating disorders at the <ORGANIZATION>Great Ormond Street Hospital</ORGANIZATION> for
Sick Children.
   <PERSON>Ms. Waugh</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that most people with anorexia nervosa
are in their teens or early twenties, but that the hospital has
seen an increase in referrals of younger girls. She gave no figures
or percentages.
   Parents should be alert to large weight losses in their children
or extremely selective eating habits, she said in a radio interview
with the <ORGANIZATION>British Broadcasting Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061290-0021 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 232231 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 12, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 11; Column 4; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
142 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DR. NEIL SOLOMON: ANOREXIA IN TEENS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By NEIL SOLOMON 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Question: I never realized how really dangerous an eating disorder could be 
until I read about anorexia in your column. Do these dangers apply to women of 
all ages? For example, if a teen-ager has an eating problem, isn't there a 
chance that she'll outgrow it? I would imagine that anorexia in a teen-ager 
would not be as serious a condition as it would be in an older woman. 
</P>
<P>
Rochester</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>) Medical Center tend to support your view. They report that 
most adolescent girls who develop anorexia nervosa respond to treatment with a 
return to their normal weight; fewer than <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of those studied had a 
continuing problem related to their eating disorder. Moreover, neither their 
educational nor employment accomplishments were affected by the disorder. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ901226-0055
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
901226-0055.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Pill Warning:
   Diet Drugs Teens Use,
   Often in Huge Doses,
   Bring Calls for Controls
   ---
   Kids Can Buy All They Want
   Of Nonprescription Items
   Despite Danger in Overuse
   ---
   Case of the Late Noelle Smith
   ----
   By Kathleen Deveny
</HL>
<DATE>
12/26/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE 1
</SO>
<CO>
   Z.CIG SGP Z.SAN
</CO>
<IN>
DRUG MANUFACTURERS (DRG)
HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS, MEDICINE, DENTISTRY (HEA)
ADVERTISING, MARKETING, PUBLIC RELATIONS (ADV)
</IN>
<GV>
CONGRESS (CNG)
FOOD AND DRUG ADMINISTRATION (FDA)
</GV>
<LP>
   A cheerleader for the Little Cyclones, a swimmer and
gymnast, Noelle Smith was popular at Ames High School in
Ames, Iowa. And she seemed well-adjusted. But she thought she
was fat.
   To get ready for a Christmas dance during her junior year,
Noelle lost five pounds. After a mediocre report card a few
weeks later, the youngster, weighing 120 pounds and standing
5-foot-3, told her parents she was going on a diet.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   At first, she refused to eat anything but half a piece of
toast a day. Later, she began devouring over-the-counter diet
pills, as well as laxatives and diuretics. Eventually, she
was taking as many as 10 boxes of appetite suppressants a
week. Although <PERSON>Noelle</PERSON> tried to hide her habit, her parents
occasionally would find empty boxes of diet pills such as
Dexatrim and Acutrim in her pockets.
   In <DATE>July 1989</DATE>, <PERSON>Noelle</PERSON> died of heart failure. She was 20
years old.
   For the eight million Americans said to suffer from eating
disorders, the lure of readily available, over-the-counter
diet drugs often seems irresistible. The pills hold the
promise of quick, low-cost, painless weight loss, without the
need of a prescription. Doctors say that the majority of
patients they treat for anorexia or bulimia, mainly young
women, routinely misuse diet pills, diuretics, laxatives and
drugs such as ipecac that induce vomiting.
   The problem isn't confined to those with textbook eating
disorders. Many outwardly healthy teen-agers think of these
drugs as a standard way to diet. An astonishing <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> of
teen-age girls responding to a recent survey by Sassy
magazine reported using diet pills, while <PERCENT>13%</PERCENT> of the
magazine's young readers have tried laxatives or diuretics
for weight loss.
   In the grip of compulsive dieting, many youngsters come to
depend on large doses of drugs, often with serious
consequences to their health. Taken in excess, common diet
pills can cause anxiety, high blood pressure and even
cerebral hemorrhages. Big doses of laxatives and diuretics
can deplete body levels of electrolytes such as potassium and
sodium. This can lead to cardiac failure.
   Young people have no trouble buying diet pills, which are
available throughout the country without any age
restrictions. If they choose, drugstores can exert some
control over their sale, such as keeping the products behind
the counter. But most don't. "There was nothing we could do
to shut off the supply," says <PERSON>Noelle</PERSON>'s father, <PERSON>Anthony Smith</PERSON>.
"No one ever asked why a 16-year-old-girl was constantly
buying diet pills, laxatives and diuretics."
   A congressional inquiry earlier this year focused
attention on the problem. "The role {diet pills} play in
eating disorders has been documented," says Rep. <PERSON>Ron Wyden</PERSON>
(D., <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>), whose subcommittee of the <ORGANIZATION>Small Business
Committee</ORGANIZATION> conducted the inquiry. "These products should be
kept out of the hands of kids."
   But after nearly a decade of reviewing the pills, the <ORGANIZATION>Food
and Drug Administration</ORGANIZATION> has done little but mull the problem.
Although it recently proposed banning 111 ingredients used
historically in nonprescription diet drugs (110 to be banned
as ineffective, and one, guar gum, as dangerous), most of
these aren't used anymore.
   The <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION> has indicated it will continue to approve
phenylpropanolamine (PPA). This is the active ingredient in
the most common nonprescription diet pills, including
Dexatrim (made by <ORGANIZATION>Thompson Medical Co.</ORGANIZATION>) and Acutrim
(<ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy Corp.</ORGANIZATION>), which together dominate the <MONEY>$220 million</MONEY>
market. <ORGANIZATION>PPA</ORGANIZATION> is also the ingredient critics say causes the
trouble. A mild stimulant chemically similar to adrenalin,
<ORGANIZATION>PPA</ORGANIZATION> is also found in such cold remedies as Contac and
Alka-Seltzer Plus -- products that aren't abused by dieters
and in which <ORGANIZATION>PPA</ORGANIZATION> isn't considered a problem.
   Marketers of the over-the-counter diet medications insist
their products are safe and effective. Industry-sponsored
studies recently submitted to the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION> prove it, says <PERSON>Bill
Soller</PERSON>, director of science and technology for the
<ORGANIZATION>Nonprescription Drug Manufacturers Association</ORGANIZATION>.
   The industry also points to a <DATE>1988</DATE> study by the <ORGANIZATION>National
Institute of Drug Abuse</ORGANIZATION> that says abuse of over-the-counter
diet pills has in fact declined over the past few years
because fewer kids use them. Twenty-two percent of
high-school seniors, boys and girls, currently use them,
according to the study.
   Critics of PPA-based diet pills contend such drugs
teenagers. At the same time, they say, there is no proof the
pills promote significant or permanent weight loss -- while
for some allergic or hypersensitive individuals and people
with certain health problems, the drugs are dangerous even
when taken according to directions.
   Labels warn of risk to diabetics and people with high
blood pressure and other conditions. But critics' indictment
of the drugs is much more sweeping: "They are neither
effective nor safe," asserts <PERSON>Thaddeus Prout</PERSON>, a physician who
chaired an <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION> committee in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> that reviewed
prescription diet drugs.
   Aggressive marketing by pharmaceutical companies has also
come under attack. Between them, <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Thompson
Medical</ORGANIZATION> spend <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> a year advertising the products,
often holding out the promise of effortless weight loss.
Though the industry itself claims the drugs will help dieters
lose less than a pound a week, Dexatrim's packaging invites
buyers to "lose weight fast."
   Just about any drug can be dangerous when used improperly,
but some researchers say <ORGANIZATION>PPA</ORGANIZATION> is riskier than other commonly
available medications, in part simply because it is abused by
desperate people. In a recent report, <PERSON>Paul Raford</PERSON>, a
physician specializing in public health who advises Rep.
<PERSON>Wyden</PERSON>'s subcommittee, concluded that <ORGANIZATION>PPA</ORGANIZATION> is far more
dangerous than ingredients in the sort of over-the-counter
drugs that people aren't tempted to take in huge quantities.
   Some marketers deny there is any abuse of the drugs. "I
don't have any data that show people under the age of 18 are
using our products," asserts <PERSON>Alison Mann</PERSON>, brand manager for
<ORGANIZATION>Thompson Medical</ORGANIZATION>'s Dexatrim.
   Amphetamines, drugs once prescribed for dieters and
frequently abused, lost favor among doctors in the mid-1970s.
Now most doctors shun the potentially addictive drugs in
favor of behavior modification and nutrition training
programs.
   However, doctors estimate that <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of patients with eating
disorders take laxatives, as purgatives. And many routinely
consume diuretics to achieve a temporary loss of fluids.
Anything for a quick weight loss. "They don't think about the
consequences; kids feel as if they are immortal," says <PERSON>Vivian
Nervosa and Associated Disorders</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>Highland Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION> "The
drugs help kids to eat chaotically."
   Consider <PERSON>Kelli Kirkpatrick</PERSON>, now 26. At 16, she would drink
mouthwash after meals to help make herself vomit, then take a
handful of laxative pills. "I'd be in a lot of pain after I
took them, but it didn't matter much to me," she says. "I
would feel my hip bone, and if the bone stuck out from my
stomach, I'd feel successful."
   <PERSON>Meredith Lee</PERSON>, a 16-year-old junior in suburban <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>,
says diets and drugs often go together in her school. She
began dieting with a friend when she was in the eighth grade,
at first eating only carrots and rice cakes for lunch. Soon,
the two stopped eating altogether. Then <PERSON>Ms. Lee</PERSON> began using
nonprescription diuretics "to flush the extra water out of
me." She began taking two pills in the <TIME>morning</TIME> and two at
night. But once, after downing more than 20 pills, she awoke
to feel her room spinning. She was violently ill for days and
had to take medication to stop vomiting.
   Despite the quantities of drugs some young women consume,
many are initially successful at concealing their behavior.
<PERSON>Ms. Lee</PERSON> convinced her mother that her diuretics overdose was
a bout of flu. Doctors note that people with eating disorders
are often ashamed and very secretive.
   Even though <PERSON>Noelle Smith</PERSON>'s parents were aware of her
illness and had her hospitalized several times, they couldn't
stop her drug use. Every time they confiscated a box of diet
pills or laxatives, she would buy more. She told friends she
would resort to shoplifting when she couldn't borrow the
money for them.
   Access was never a problem for <PERSON>Jessica McDonald</PERSON>, now a
20-year-old college junior in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C</LOCATION>. She started
buying diet pills at 12, taking a cue from a friend at ballet
school. Two years later, she added diuretics and laxatives as
drugs of abuse. Though she shopped at the same drugstore
nearly every day, "No one ever said anything to me," she
says.
   Because these drugs are available without a prescription,
they are widely thought to be innocuous. Their very
availability bestows an aura of safety.
   Neither Ex-Lax nor Correctol brands of chemical laxatives,
which doctors say are popular with obsessive dieters because
they quickly produce temporary weight loss, have label
warnings about misuse by dieters, though they do caution
against prolonged use. "We are aware the abuse of these
products exists, but we haven't done anything to encourage
it," says a spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Schering-Plough Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, maker of
Correctol. A <ORGANIZATION>Sandoz Pharmaceuticals Corp.</ORGANIZATION> spokesman says he
is unaware of any abuse of the company's Ex-Lax.
   The label on a box of Acutrim warns only that the pills
aren't for children under 12. It doesn't warn against taking
too much. Boxes of Dexatrim urge somewhat more caution. They
warn users not to exceed the recommended dosage and they tell
youngsters between 12 and 18 to consult a doctor before
taking the pills.
   A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> says that he doesn't believe
Acutrim is heavily abused, but that the company plans to
alter labeling in the next few months anyway. Boxes will say
Acutrim isn't intended for those under 18. "There's been a
lot of publicity about this issue," he says, "and we feel a
responsibility to do something."
   Rep. <PERSON>Wyden</PERSON> advocates making directions on diet pills more
specific or including warnings about misuse. The <ORGANIZATION>National
Association of Anorexia Nervosa and Associated Disorders</ORGANIZATION> has
proposed some limitations on selling diet pills, laxatives
and diuretics to customers under 18, like keeping the
products behind the counter where they have to be asked for.
   But retailers and manufacturers point out that the drugs
have been approved by the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION>, and say the agency is
virtually certain to bless the continued use of <ORGANIZATION>PPA</ORGANIZATION> in
nonprescription diet drugs even if it recommends new
labeling. "Limiting the access of minors would be very
difficult," says <PERSON>Mr. Soller</PERSON> of the manufacturers'
association. "Teen-agers found a way to buy alcohol.
Restricting access simply camouflages the problem."
   For now, that problem remains right there in the open on
drugstore shelves. <PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON>, <PERSON>Noelle</PERSON>'s father, spreads on his
dining-room table snapshots he took of a display of diet
pills and diuretics at a local drugstore. "We weren't perfect
parents," he says. "We made mistakes, but they were loving
mistakes. We just didn't know over-the-counter drugs could
cause such a problem."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA082189-0039 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 97323 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 21, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 4; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
166 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IN BRIEF: SCIENCE / MEDICINE; 
</P>
<P>
DIETING MAY SPARK ANOREXIA 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Compiled from staff and wire reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
An addiction to opiates produced by the brain while dieting may be the cause of 
anorexia nervosa, an eating disorder in which patients starve themselves, 
sometimes to death, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> researchers said last week. The scientists say 
their research, presented at the 40th annual meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>American Society</ORGANIZATION> 
"abnormal biological responses" to diet-triggered opiates. 
</P>
<P>
Typically these opiates, called endorphins, produce a "high" and an increased 
appetite. But in anorexia patients, those effects may be out of balance, so 
hunger is overridden by the euphoria, said <ORGANIZATION>Wayne State University</ORGANIZATION> 
pharmacologist <PERSON>Mary Ann Marrazzi</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
In their study, the researchers discovered that some mice demonstrated 
decreased appetite and increased activity when given morphine, an opiate. If a 
person responded similarly to their own opiates, released during dieting, it 
would mimic the behavior of anorexia nervosa patients, she said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ENDORPHINS; WEIGHT REDUCTION; EATING DISORDERS; DRUG ADDICTION; MEDICAL 
RESEARCH 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891106-0242 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-06-89 0639EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Holidays:Eating     11-06 0249</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Holidays: Eating,0258</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Holidays: Eating</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Fat doesn't have to be part of the fun during the holidays, says
Weight Watchers magazine.
   There are ways to resist temptations to over-indulge, the
magazine says, and offers this advice:
   _ Plan ahead. Have a snack before going to a get-together so you
won't be ``starving'' when you get there.
   _ Practice moderation. Make room in your day's menu for a
reasonable helping of your favorite foods, but don't abandon your
diet guidelines completely.
   _ Just say no, thanks. Think about ways to turn down food
without sounding hostile, sanctimonious or rude.
   _ Avoid high-risk situations. Stay away from the all-you-can eat
buffet. Let your guests take home the leftovers.
   _ Don't drink too much. Alcohol has a high-calorie content _ and
can destroy your resolve to resist other temptations.
   The holidays are often most difficult for people with eating
disorders and their families, says <PERSON>Dr. Charles A. Murkofsy</PERSON>,
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Eating Disorders Program</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Gracie Square Hospital</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   ``A person with an eating disorder will often bully the family
into having turkey without all the trimmings, or refuse to
participate in the holiday meal at all,'' he says.
   Families, he suggests, should give recognition to the eating
disorder instead of denying its existence, and make mutually
agreeable compromises on food choices.
   He says the most common eating disorders are anorexia nervosa, a
self-induced starvation, and bulimia, a cycle of binging and
purging.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06062058 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06062058 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  BEVERAGE; RELATION; FOOD; DISEASE; LIFESTYLE; MEDICAL; RESEARCH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Consuming too much caffeine may worsen binge eating, vomiting or other
behaviors associated with eating disorders, researchers say.;    A study at
the University of Michigan has found that people who suffer from eating
disorders and consumed more than 750 milligrams of caffeine a day binged,
vomited and exercised more than people whose caffeine intake was moderate or
light.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TOO MUCH COFFEE MAY WORSEN BINGES
CAFFEINE LINKED TO EATING DISORDERS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Fasting and use of laxatives, diet pills, diuretics or enemas were also
higher among heavy caffeine users, said <PERSON>Dr. Dean D. Krahn</PERSON>, author of the
study.;    The study is published in the <DATE>March</DATE> issue of the journal Hospital
and <ORGANIZATION>Community Psychiatry.</ORGANIZATION>;    High caffeine intake was defined as the
equivalent of about eight cups of coffee, 15 cups of tea or 16 12-oz. cans of
soda a day, <PERSON>Krahn</PERSON> said.;    Moderate caffeine intake consisted of between
three and eight cups of coffee, five to 15 cups of tea or five to 16 12-oz.
cans of soda a day, he said.;    People who drank less than three cups of
coffee, five cups of tea or five 12-oz. cans of soda a day were considered low
caffeine users, he said.;    Eating disorders, such as anorexia nervosa and
bulimia, are psychological problems characterized by a preoccupation with
being thin.;    More than 5 million women suffer from eating disorders,
who suffer from such disorders may fast, vomit or take medications to lose
weight.;    <PERSON>Kahn</PERSON> studied 171 women with eating disorders.;    Moderate or
heavy caffeine users binged more than those whose intake was low, <PERSON>Krahn</PERSON> said.;
   They also experienced more severe anxiety and depression than low caffeine
users.;    Heavy caffeine users were more likely than moderate and light users
to smoke cigarettes and drink alcohol, which may indicate a greater tendency
to abuse other chemicals, <PERSON>Krahn</PERSON> said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Medical Tribune News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910302  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  304  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday March 2, 1991
00062058,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881121-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-21-88 1530EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AnorexicThanksgiving 1stLd-Writethru a060 11-21 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Anorexic Thanksgiving, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0641,0761</SECOND>
<HEAD>Victims of Eating Disorders Hold Thanksgiving Dinner Together</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 5th, ``It's kind ...,' with dinner's
menu.</NOTE>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LORI DODGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For Thanksgiving dinner, <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON> used to fix
herself a small salad while the rest of her family sat down to
turkey and dressing.
   Lisa skipped dinner altogether one year and instead took an
overdose of pills.
   What should have been a holiday was a nightmare for the two women
because they suffered from anorexia. The thought of a bountiful
feast spread out before them repulsed them.
   But this year, both <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lisa</PERSON> will sit down to a
traditional Thanksgiving meal with several hundred others who suffer
from eating disorders. The dinner is a part of the annual <ORGANIZATION>National
Eating Disorders Week</ORGANIZATION> originated by their doctor, <PERSON>Felix Larocca</PERSON>, a
child psychiatrist who specializes in treating disorders like
anorexia and bulimia.
   ``It's kind of like a homecoming,'' said <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON>, who asked that
her last name be withheld. ``You feel a little more comfortable
sitting with people who you know have the same problem. It's a
little easier to eat.''
   The dinner will be a traditional one, with all the trimmings:
roast turkey, dressing, wild rice, broccoli, glazed carrots, mixed
fruit, dinner rolls, cranberry sauce, pumpkin pie and carrot cake.
   Victims of anorexia refuse to eat because they believe themselves
fat even when they're dangerously underweight, while bulimia
sufferers binge and purge, eating sometimes enormous amounts of food
and then throwing up.
   Most of those who suffer from these eating disorders are young,
white women, bt more and more cases are being diagnosed among men,
blacks, Asians and children.
   Larocca is the founder of <ORGANIZATION>BASH Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which stands for Bulimia
Anorexia Self-Help. Based in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, it is an internationally
known program for people with eating disorders.
   The annual dinner began five years ago to help <PERSON>Larocca</PERSON>'s patients
shift the focus of the Thanksgiving holiday away from food. ``The
idea is to socialize, to get reacquainted,'' he said. ``The dinner
is played down.''
   The first dinner was held after <PERSON>Lisa</PERSON> tried to commit suicide with
the overdose she took while home from college for Thanksgiving.
   ``She said she couldn't handle it, she hated the holiday,''
<PERSON>Larocca</PERSON> said. ``People talked about food and insisted everybody take
seconds.''
   ``It was a miracle she survived, but she made it and lived.''
   Last year, about 300 past and present patients of <PERSON>Larocca</PERSON>'s,
their families and friends attended the meal. In conjunction with
the meal, seminars and workshops on eating and mood disorders are
offered.
   BASH is the outpatient program for the <ORGANIZATION>BASH Treatment and
Research Center</ORGANIZATION>, based at <ORGANIZATION>Deaconess Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. The
program, which <PERSON>Larocca</PERSON> founded in <DATE>1981</DATE>, seeks to restore proper
eating habits to patients through behavior modification, individual
and group therapy and nutritional guidance.
   Both anorexia and bulimia can be fatal. Besides malnutrition,
victims of eating disorders can suffer electrolyte imbalances, which
can cause abnormal heart rhythms, and amenorrhea, the loss of
menstruation. Frequent vomiting by bulimics can lead to tooth decay.
One victim was pop singer <PERSON>Karen Carpenter</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>1983</DATE> at the
age of 33 of complications of anorexia.
   Sufferers also can become addicted to diet pills and laxatives,
which can lower the body's potassium content, making heart failure a
risk.
   <PERSON>Larocca</PERSON> said compulsive exercising is now being recognized as yet
another tool for people who suffer eating disorders. ``Exercise
addicts start quite innocently,'' he said. ``But once they get
caught in the treadmill of exercise, they suffer anxiety when they
can't get their fix.''
   Larocca's self-help program began with a suggestion from several
of his anorexic and bulimic patients, who met in a group with him
once a month, that a meeting that included relatives of people with
eating disorders would be beneficial.
   BASH now reaches some 6,000 people in the <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> area, and
with the distribution of its newsletter, more than 15,000 people
around the world, <PERSON>Larocca</PERSON> said. It also operates a 24-hour toll-free
crisis hotline.
   Both <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lisa</PERSON> have recovered, although they still find
the meetings helpful for dealing with self-image problems.
   ``Now I don't feel I have to go so much for myself, but to help
other people,'' said <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON>, who spent one Thanksgiving in the
hospital being fed through tubes. ``It's just amazing that knowing
that other people have been through the same things helps a lot.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881226-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-88 1405EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-26 0875</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0910</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY44, TOK1, TOK4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Michael Jackson</PERSON> whirled and twirled his way <DATE>Monday</DATE>
through a show billed in the Japanese press as a ``farewell
concert'' but made no mention of retiring.
   Jackson spoke to the audience only briefly during the two-hour
show, the ninth and final concert of his current stand in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>,
saying: ``Domo arigato (thank you) to everyone in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'' and ``I
love you, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.''
   In <DATE>August</DATE>, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s manager, <PERSON>Frank Dileo</PERSON>, said the tour probably
would be <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s last. He said <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, 30, would go on to ``do
movies and other things.''
   <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> was supposed to be the final stop on the 14-month,
four-continent tour. But three shows in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> that were
canceled last month because <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> had throat problems have been
rescheduled for next month.
   After <PERSON>Dileo</PERSON>'s comments, newspapers dubbed the <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> appearances
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s ``farewell concerts'' and promoters sold T-shirts and hats
emblazoned with that slogan.
   The nine concerts _ 450,000 tickets in all in the 50,000-seat
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> Dome _ were quick sellouts.
   ``It's going to be lonely without <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>. It's as though his
life is over,'' said <PERSON>Yuriko Wada</PERSON>, an office worker from Kyoto who
attended the concert.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: For Release 6 p.m. EST</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Michael Jackson</PERSON> whirled and twirled his way <DATE>Monday</DATE>
through a show billed in the Japanese press as a ``farewell
concert'' but made no mention of retiring.
   Jackson spoke to the audience only briefly during the two-hour
show, the ninth and final concert of his current stand in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>,
saying: ``Domo arigato (thank you) to everyone in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'' and ``I
love you, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.''
   In <DATE>August</DATE>, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s manager, <PERSON>Frank Dileo</PERSON>, said the tour probably
would be <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s last. He said <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, 30, would go on to ``do
movies and other things.''
   <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> was supposed to be the final stop on the 14-month,
four-continent tour. But three shows in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> that were
canceled last month because <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> had throat problems have been
rescheduled for next month.
   After <PERSON>Dileo</PERSON>'s comments, newspapers dubbed the <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> appearances
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s ``farewell concerts'' and promoters sold T-shirts and hats
emblazoned with that slogan.
   The nine concerts _ 450,000 tickets in all in the 50,000-seat
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> Dome _ were quick sellouts.
   ``It's going to be lonely without <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>. It's as though his
life is over,'' said <PERSON>Yuriko Wada</PERSON>, an office worker from Kyoto who
attended the concert.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: For release at 6:30 p.m. EST</NOTE>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Michael Jackson</PERSON> whirled and twirled his way <DATE>Monday</DATE>
through a show billed in the Japanese press as a ``farewell
concert'' but made no mention of retiring.
   Jackson spoke to the audience only briefly during the two-hour
show, the ninth and final concert of his current stand in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>,
saying: ``Domo arigato (thank you) to everyone in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'' and ``I
love you, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.''
   In <DATE>August</DATE>, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s manager, <PERSON>Frank Dileo</PERSON>, said the tour probably
would be <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s last. He said <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, 30, would go on to ``do
movies and other things.''
   <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> was supposed to be the final stop on the 14-month,
four-continent tour. But three shows in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> that were
canceled last month because <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> had throat problems have been
rescheduled for next month.
   After <PERSON>Dileo</PERSON>'s comments, newspapers dubbed the <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> appearances
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s ``farewell concerts'' and promoters sold T-shirts and hats
emblazoned with that slogan.
   The nine concerts _ 450,000 tickets in all in the 50,000-seat
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> Dome _ were quick sellouts.
   ``It's going to be lonely without <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>. It's as though his
life is over,'' said <PERSON>Yuriko Wada</PERSON>, an office worker from Kyoto who
attended the concert.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Michael Jackson</PERSON> whirled and twirled his way <DATE>Monday</DATE>
through a show billed in the Japanese press as a ``farewell
concert'' but made no mention of retiring.
   Jackson spoke to the audience only briefly during the two-hour
show, the ninth and final concert of his current stand in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>,
saying: ``Domo arigato (thank you) to everyone in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'' and ``I
love you, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.''
   In <DATE>August</DATE>, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s manager, <PERSON>Frank Dileo</PERSON>, said the tour probably
would be <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s last. He said <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, 30, would go on to ``do
movies and other things.''
   <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> was supposed to be the final stop on the 14-month,
four-continent tour. But three shows in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> that were
canceled last month because <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> had throat problems have been
rescheduled for next month.
   After <PERSON>Dileo</PERSON>'s comments, newspapers dubbed the <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> appearances
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s ``farewell concerts'' and promoters sold T-shirts and hats
emblazoned with that slogan.
   The nine concerts _ 450,000 tickets in all in the 50,000-seat
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> Dome _ were quick sellouts.
   ``It's going to be lonely without <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>. It's as though his
life is over,'' said <PERSON>Yuriko Wada</PERSON>, an office worker from Kyoto who
attended the concert.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Michael Jackson</PERSON> whirled and twirled his way <DATE>Monday</DATE>
through a show billed in the Japanese press as a ``farewell
concert'' but made no mention of retiring.
   Jackson spoke to the audience only briefly during the two-hour
show, the ninth and final concert of his current stand in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>,
saying: ``Domo arigato (thank you) to everyone in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'' and ``I
love you, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.''
   In <DATE>August</DATE>, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s manager, <PERSON>Frank Dileo</PERSON>, said the tour probably
would be <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s last. He said <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, 30, would go on to ``do
movies and other things.''
   <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> was supposed to be the final stop on the 14-month,
four-continent tour. But three shows in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> that were
canceled last month because <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> had throat problems have been
rescheduled for next month.
   After <PERSON>Dileo</PERSON>'s comments, newspapers dubbed the <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> appearances
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s ``farewell concerts'' and promoters sold T-shirts and hats
emblazoned with that slogan.
   The nine concerts _ 450,000 tickets in all in the 50,000-seat
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> Dome _ were quick sellouts.
   ``It's going to be lonely without <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>. It's as though his
life is over,'' said <PERSON>Yuriko Wada</PERSON>, an office worker from Kyoto who
attended the concert.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891025-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-25-89 0127EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-EatingDisorders     10-25 0222</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Eating Disorders,0228</SECOND>
<HEAD>Disorders Affect Nutritional Needs, Study Shows</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A study suggests the nutritional needs of
women with eating disorders differ from those of normal women.
   A study by <ORGANIZATION>Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic</ORGANIZATION> found that
women recovering from bulimia needed only <PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT> of the normal
intake of calories. Conversely, women recovering from anorexia
needed two-thirds more calories than normal.
   Bulimia is the disorder of gorging and purging. Anorexia is an
avoidance of food.
   The study of 23 recovering bulimic women who were trying to
maintain normal weight found that the women required only 10
calories per pound of body weight, or <PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT> of the 13.8 daily
calories per pound that healthy women need.
   Separate studies involving 31 recovering anorexic women found
they needed 22.3 calories per pound of body weight to maintain
their normal weight.
   ``These findings have led to new treatment methods in our
program ... and they help us to understand the physiological
factors that complicate the psychological issues of eating
disorders,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Walter Kaye</PERSON>, director of the institute's
Center for <ORGANIZATION>Overcoming Problem Eating</ORGANIZATION>.
   The findings were published in a recent issue of the <ORGANIZATION>American
Journal of Nutrition</ORGANIZATION> and released to the public <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in
conjunction with <ORGANIZATION>Easting Disorders Awareness Week</ORGANIZATION>.
   The studies were conducted during the last three years, <PERSON>Kaye</PERSON>
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890502-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-02-89 0032EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Children-Dieting     05-02 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Children-Dieting,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study: Elementary School Pupils Watch Their Waistlines</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Children, like adults, may be keenly conscious
of their waistlines and many have tried dieting, a hospital survey
suggests.
   Nearly half of 318 elementary school children surveyed worried
they were overweight, and more than a third said they had attempted
diets, according to a study released <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``This study tells us that it's not just the 15-, 20- or
40-year-olds who feel they're overweight _ 9- and 10-year-olds feel
the same way,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Michael J. Maloney</PERSON>, director of psychiatry
and psychology at <ORGANIZATION>Children's Hospital Medical Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>.
   The study, ``A Survey of Dieting Behavior and Eating Attitudes
in Children,'' will be published in <DATE>September</DATE>'s issue of
Pediatrics, a monthly professional journal.
   Researchers at the hospital surveyed girls and boys in the third
through sixth grades at two randomly hosen schools in middle-income
Cincinnati-area neighborhoods.
   Of those surveyed, the researchers said <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> indicated
they were uncomfortable with their bodies and wanted to be thinner.
Thirty-seven percent said they had already tried to lose weight,
<PERSON>Maloney</PERSON> said.
   ``Girls in grades five and six reported significantly more
discomfort about their bodies than girls in grades three and four
or boys in all grades,'' he said.
   A total of <PERCENT>6.9 percent</PERCENT> gave responses similar to those obtained
in studies of teen-agers and young adult females who suffer from
anorexia nervosa, a condition characterized by severe and prolonged
inability or refusal to eat, he said.
   ``Previous research has determined that <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of
17-year-old girls think they're overweight, but only 20 to <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT> really are,'' he said.
   The researchers plan a six-year followup study in hopes of
learning more about the possible causes of eating disorders and
ways to treat them.
   Maloney planned to present his findings <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>American
Society for Pediatric Research</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880915-0078 </DOCNO>
<HL> Researchers Link Some Binge Eating To Hormone Levels </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> PHA </IN>
<DATELINE> BOSTON (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some binge eaters produce unusually small amounts of a hormone that ordinarily signals people that they are full, according to a study. 

   The report suggests that a defect in production of this natural chemical may be an underlying cause of bulimia nervosa, an eating disorder in which people stuff themselves with food and then make themselves vomit. 

   Other studies have shown that anti-depression medicine is an effective way to curb binge eating, and the latest research shows that the drugs also seem to increase levels of the appetite hormone after a meal. 

   However, the researchers say further study will be necessary to see if correcting the apparent hormonal abnormality is important in controlling bulimia. 

   The study was conducted by Drs. 
It was published in <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s New England Journal of Medicine. 

   The study compared 14 women with bulimia with 10 healthy volunteers. 
It found that after a meal, the binge eaters produced unusually low levels of cholecystokinin, a hormone released from the intestines that produces satiety. 

   In an accompanying editorial, Drs. 
<PERSON>David B. Herzog</PERSON> and <PERSON>Paul M. Copeland</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts General Hospital</ORGANIZATION> cautioned that "it is premature to conclude" that low hormone levels make people susceptible to binge eating. 

   But they added, "Investigating bulimia nervosa from the perspective of defective satiety offers a promising avenue of research." 

   They noted that <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> of young adult American women and a much smaller number of men are believed to have the disorder. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911227-0014
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911227-0014.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Letters to the Editor:
   Attitudes on Eating
   Can Make You Retch
</HL>
<DATE>
12/27/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A11
</SO>
<LP>
   Your story about Carol Lopacich's disinheritance from the
Baxter International Inc. fortune ("She Might Have Inherited
Millions, But for Her Mother," page one, Nov. 25) because of
her parent's disapproval of her size is a shocking and
dramatic example of the high price women often pay because of
how they look.
   I suffered from bulimia from ages 15 to 22, partly because
my swim coaches never missed an opportunity to comment on how
important it was to be "lean and mean." Now as the president
of a foundation that assists others with the same problem, I
get thousands of letters from women who say it took just one
disparaging comment from a parent, coach or other authority
figure for them to start binging, starving, vomiting,
compulsively exercising and abusing laxatives. Some say their
parents even have scales set up next to the refrigerator to
determine whether they "deserve" to eat or not.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The most common precursor to developing an eating disorder
is "going on a little diet," and bulimia and anorexia
together have the highest mortality rate of any psychiatric
illness. So that ought to be food for thought for anyone who
is tempted to comment on another person's weight.
   <ORGANIZATION>Caroline Adams Miller
   President
   Foundation for Education About Eating Disorders</ORGANIZATION>
   <LOCATION>Middletown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA080389-0137 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 90331 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 3, 1989, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 5; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
338 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FIRM TO HALT FALSE CLAIMS FOR DIET PILLS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARIA L. La GANGA, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A <LOCATION>Tustin</LOCATION> company that advertised its weight-loss pill as "the diet miracle of 
the '90s" has agreed to stop making false claims about the product, which was 
the subject of an eight-month investigation by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Postal Inspection 
Service</ORGANIZATION>, federal authorities said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
officers, <LOCATION>John</LOCATION>. J. and <PERSON>Clare W. Kogler</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>, said Postal Inspector 
<PERSON>Donald Obritsch</PERSON>. Such charges could be filed if the Koglers break their consent 
agreement with the postal service. 
</P>
<P>
According to the agreement, which was signed on <DATE>July 24</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Koglers</ORGANIZATION> also must 
refund all money spent on Anorex <DATE>2000</DATE> to customers who request it, <PERSON>Obritsch</PERSON> 
said. The Koglers could not be reached for comment. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Fat-Burning Machine' 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Obritsch</PERSON> said that the <PERSON>Koglers</PERSON> have agreed to stop "falsely representing that 
Anorex <DATE>2000</DATE> will aid in weight loss or fat reduction." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jordon Whitney</PERSON> advertised Anorex <DATE>2000</DATE> in about 100 newspapers nationwide 
between <DATE>January</DATE> and <DATE>April</DATE>. The ads bragged that the product would turn the body 
into a "fat-burning machine," <PERSON>Obritsch</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Anorex <DATE>2000</DATE> was touted as "an all-natural, bioactive diet pill," <PERSON>Obritsch</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"The advertisement said, 'Researchers warn that Anorex <DATE>2000</DATE> is an extremely 
powerful anorectic agent and should not be taken lightly,' " he recounted. " 
'If weight drops too fast, Anorex <DATE>2000</DATE> should not be taken for several days.' " 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Vitamins and Fiber 
</P>
<P>
But during the postal service investigation, the pills were examined by a 
professor of medicine at <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>, who concluded that the product "is useless, 
fraudulent, and intended to deceive a gullible buyer," according to an 
affidavit. 
</P>
<P>
While the pills are not harmful, <PERSON>Dr. E.J. Drenick</PERSON> surmised that they contain 
only vitamins and fiber. A 30-day supply cost dieters <MONEY>$36.95</MONEY>, plus <MONEY>$3</MONEY> for 
delivery. 
</P>
<P>
Although postal inspectors have no idea how many diet pills were sold or how 
much the company took in with its fraudulent ads, <PERSON>Obritsch</PERSON> said, the firm 
received about 200 letters a day. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FALSE ADVERTISING; MAIL FRAUD; INVESTIGATIONS; POSTAL INSPECTION SERVICE; 
JORDON WHITNEY INC 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06023069 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06023069 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  UNION CITY and the New Haven Unified School District will hold a semi-annual
Project DARE (Drug Abuse Resistance Education) graduation from 7 to 8 p.m.
today at The Pavilion, James Logan High School, 1800 H St., Union City. Some
480 fifth-grade students have completed the 17-week DARE program. The
graduating students have prepared an anti-drug message to present to the
audience of James Logan High School students and their parents.;    Outfielder
Darren Lewis, recently signed by the San Francisco Giants after his stint with
the Oakland A's, has accepted DARE's invitation to make a special guest
appearance.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PROJECT DARE GRADS TO HEAR DARREN LEWIS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Alameda County Log  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The DARE program, taught by a specially trained, uniformed police officer,
emphasizes life skills and methods to employ in resisting pressure to use
drugs.;    For more information about graduation exercises and the DARE
program, call Officer <PERSON>Ray Gedney</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Union City Police Department</ORGANIZATION> at (415)
471-1365.; TODAY; A forum presented as a community service to help families
and individuals cope with the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> crisis will be held at <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>
at the <ORGANIZATION>CPC Fremont</ORGANIZATION> hospital, 39001 <ORGANIZATION>Sundale Drive</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>. For more
information, call (415) 796-1100.; (hbox); <ORGANIZATION>The Union City Library</ORGANIZATION> holds its
final program of the <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> "preschool story time" series with
librarian <PERSON>Pat Ryan</PERSON> at <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> at 34007 Alvarado/Niles Road. For more
information, call (415) 745-1464.; COMING; <ORGANIZATION>Eden Hospital Medical Center</ORGANIZATION> offers
a free monthly eating disorders support group on the <DATE>fourth Thursday</DATE> of each
month for those suffering from anorexia nervosa or bulimia. The next meeting
is scheduled from 6:30 to <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the third floor conference
room at the hospital. For more information, call <ORGANIZATION>Eden</ORGANIZATION>'s Mental Health services
24-hour hot line at (415) 889-5016.; (hbox); <LOCATION>Irvington</LOCATION> High School drama
students present "Oliver Twist" at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and at noon <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at
41800 Blacow Road, <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>. The cost is <MONEY>$5</MONEY> per person and <MONEY>$3</MONEY> for seniors and
students under 12 years of age. For details, call (415) 656-5711.; (hbox);   
A new chapter of <LOCATION>Pax Christi</LOCATION> (Latin for "Peace of Christ") meets at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> in the Dominican Convent auditorium, 43326 <LOCATION>Mission Blvd.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>.
The international Catholic peace group is open to everyone. For more
information, call <PERSON>Louise Lynch</PERSON> at (415) 657-3798 or <PERSON>Faye Butler</PERSON> at (415)
490-7737.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Alameda County/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910123  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  389  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday January 23, 1991
00023069,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880915-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-15-88 0230EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BingeEaters     09-15 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Binge Eaters,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Binge Eaters May Have Defect in Hormone Controlling Appetite</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Abnormally low amounts of a hormone that controls
appetite may play a role in bulimia, the cycles of binge eating and
purging suffered by some young women, a study published today
concludes.
   The preliminary report found that some people with the disorder
make unusually small amounts of cholecystokinin, a hormone produced
by the intestines that makes people feel full, or sated, after a
meal.
   ``We conclude that patients with bulimia do not have normal
satiety and have impaired secretion of cholecystokinin in response
to a meal,'' the researchers wrote in the <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> Journal of
Medicine.
   Between <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT> of young adult American women
and a much smaller number of men are believed to have the disorder.
Victims tend to eat large quantities of food, then purposely purge
themselves with vomiting or laxatives.
   Other studies have shown that anti-depression medicine is an
effective way to curb binge eating, and the latest research found
that the drugs also seem to increase levels of the appetite hormone
after a meal.
   However, the researchers cautioned that further study will be
necessary to see if correcting the apparent hormonal abnormality is
important in controlling bulimia.
   The study by Drs. <PERSON>Thomas D. Geracioti Jr.</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Institute of Mental Health</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Rodger A. Liddle</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University
of California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, compared the hormone levels after
eating in 14 women with bulimia to 10 healthy volunteers.
   In an accompanying editorial, Drs. <PERSON>David B. Herzog</PERSON> and <PERSON>Paul M.
Copeland</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts General Hospital</ORGANIZATION> cautioned that it is
premature to conclude that low hormone levels make people
susceptible to binge eating.
   But they added, ``Investigating bulimia nervosa from the
perspective of defective satiety offers a promising avenue of
research.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880216-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-16-88 0717EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-NobleHouse Adv17   02-16 0855</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Noble House, Adv 17,0870</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv17</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Wed PMs, Feb. 17, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Clavell's `Noble House' Miniseries on NBC</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHRYN BAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With any joss _ that means ``luck'' in Chinese _
there'll be something to do next week rather than spend eight hours
on <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s mind-numbing miniseries, the ignoble ``<ORGANIZATION>Noble House</ORGANIZATION>,''
based on <PERSON>James Clavell</PERSON>'s best-selling novel of the same title.
   The plot is preposterous, the acting spotty, the music overdone,
the love scenes embarrassing, the special effects fakey. And after
investing <TIME>eight hours _ two hours a night</TIME>, <DATE>Sunday</DATE> through
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, on <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> _ everything is tied up neatly at the end, not
through any clever plot twist, but because of an act of God. Thanks
a lot.
   <PERSON>Pierce Brosnan</PERSON>, late of ``<PERSON>Remington Steele</PERSON>,'' is a fine actor,
but he's too pretty for <PERSON>Ian Dunross</PERSON>, a tough, middle-aged corporate
kingpin descended from Scottish pirates. Then this suave, exotic
fellow is given as a love interest gawky <PERSON>Deborah Raffin</PERSON> as
gosh-darn American <PERSON>Casey Tcholok</PERSON>, a perky corporate raider.
   Casey is a tip-o'-the-hat to feminism. The rest of the women in
the cast are the typical array of hookers, mistresses, or, at best,
secretaries.
   <ORGANIZATION>Ben Masters</ORGANIZATION> manages a believable performance as deceptively
affable <PERSON>Linc Barlett</PERSON>, <PERSON>Casey</PERSON>'s boss and honcho of a huge <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
conglomerate. But it's the villains who get the best of the
miniseries _ <PERSON>John Rhys-Davies</PERSON> as jealous <PERSON>Quillan Gornt</PERSON>, longtime
<ORGANIZATION>Noble House</ORGANIZATION> rival, and <PERSON>Khigh Diegh</PERSON>, the most fun of all as Four
Finger Wu, a wily bandit who operates from a junk in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>
harbor, cuffing his honest son into helping toss hapless henchman
overboard.
   The miniseries was shot in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and on location in exotic <LOCATION>Hong
Kong</LOCATION>.
   As the miniseries opens, Dunross is becoming the new tai-pan, or
boss, of <ORGANIZATION>Noble House</ORGANIZATION>, a huge Hong Kong-based trading company. He
has inherited a financial mess from his predecessor (<ORGANIZATION>Denholm
Elliott</ORGANIZATION>) and must struggle to keep the company from going under.
   To that end, he entertains a merger offer by a Linc's company,
<ORGANIZATION>Par-Con Industries</ORGANIZATION>.
   Enter Linc, accompanied by <PERSON>Casey</PERSON>, come to <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> to cut a
deal. Talk about your ugly Americans _ during their brief stay,
banks fail, stock markets plunge, fires rage, buildings collapse,
and murders are most foul. Anybody with a lick of sense would
skedaddle back to the States and chalk it up to poor junket
planning. And a people who place so much emphasis on joss _ as the
Chinese must, since the word turns up several times a night _ would
surely notice that these two haven't exactly brought a ray of
sunshine to their happy port city.
   Shortly after Linc and <PERSON>Casey</PERSON> arrive, Linc secretly meets with
<PERSON>Gornt</PERSON>, who entices Linc with a possible joint raid on the <ORGANIZATION>Noble
House</ORGANIZATION>. Casey, in the meantime, is linking up with <PERSON>Ian</PERSON>. Everyone
remains irritatingly pleasant in between natural disasters.
   Also in the meantime, bandits play keep-away with a stolen,
broken half-coin that figures in an inscrutable ancient tradition
entitling the bearer to a lucrative ``favor'' from the <ORGANIZATION>Noble House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Though the plot is supposed to take place over a few days, it
seems like years. Time passage is such a problem that at one point,
the characters have to explain in dialogue what has happened when
and remark how it all seems so long ago.
   For viewers, it will all seem so long ago, too. ``Noble House''
isn't good enough to be good, or even bad enough to be good. As a
four-hour junk-TV snack, maybe. But for anyone willing to invest
eight hours _ good joss.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   With any joss _ that means ``luck'' in Chinese _
there'll be something to do next week rather than spend eight hours
on <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s mind-numbing miniseries, the ignoble ``<ORGANIZATION>Noble House</ORGANIZATION>,''
based on <PERSON>James Clavell</PERSON>'s best-selling novel of the same title.
   The plot is preposterous, the acting spotty, the music overdone,
the love scenes embarrassing, the special effects fakey. And after
investing <TIME>eight hours _ two hours a night</TIME>, <DATE>Sunday</DATE> through
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, on <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> _ everything is tied up neatly at the end, not
through any clever plot twist, but because of an act of God. Thanks
a lot.
   <PERSON>Pierce Brosnan</PERSON>, late of ``<PERSON>Remington Steele</PERSON>,'' is a fine actor,
but he's too pretty for <PERSON>Ian Dunross</PERSON>, a tough, middle-aged corporate
kingpin descended from Scottish pirates. Then this suave, exotic
fellow is given as a love interest gawky <PERSON>Deborah Raffin</PERSON> as
gosh-darn American <PERSON>Casey Tcholok</PERSON>, a perky corporate raider.
   Casey is a tip-o'-the-hat to feminism. The rest of the women in
the cast are the typical array of hookers, mistresses, or, at best,
secretaries.
   <ORGANIZATION>Ben Masters</ORGANIZATION> manages a believable performance as deceptively
affable <PERSON>Linc Barlett</PERSON>, <PERSON>Casey</PERSON>'s boss and honcho of a huge <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
conglomerate. But it's the villains who get the best of the
miniseries _ <PERSON>John Rhys-Davies</PERSON> as jealous <PERSON>Quillan Gornt</PERSON>, longtime
<ORGANIZATION>Noble House</ORGANIZATION> rival, and <PERSON>Khigh Diegh</PERSON>, the most fun of all as Four
Finger Wu, a wily bandit who operates from a junk in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>
harbor, cuffing his honest son into helping toss hapless henchman
overboard.
   The miniseries was shot in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and on location in exotic <LOCATION>Hong
Kong</LOCATION>.
   As the miniseries opens, Dunross is becoming the new tai-pan, or
boss, of <ORGANIZATION>Noble House</ORGANIZATION>, a huge Hong Kong-based trading company. He
has inherited a financial mess from his predecessor (<ORGANIZATION>Denholm
Elliott</ORGANIZATION>) and must struggle to keep the company from going under.
   To that end, he entertains a merger offer by a Linc's company,
<ORGANIZATION>Par-Con Industries</ORGANIZATION>.
   Enter Linc, accompanied by <PERSON>Casey</PERSON>, come to <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> to cut a
deal. Talk about your ugly Americans _ during their brief stay,
banks fail, stock markets plunge, fires rage, buildings collapse,
and murders are most foul. Anybody with a lick of sense would
skedaddle back to the States and chalk it up to poor junket
planning. And a people who place so much emphasis on joss _ as the
Chinese must, since the word turns up several times a night _ would
surely notice that these two haven't exactly brought a ray of
sunshine to their happy port city.
   Shortly after Linc and <PERSON>Casey</PERSON> arrive, Linc secretly meets with
<PERSON>Gornt</PERSON>, who entices Linc with a possible joint raid on the <ORGANIZATION>Noble
House</ORGANIZATION>. Casey, in the meantime, is linking up with <PERSON>Ian</PERSON>. Everyone
remains irritatingly pleasant in between natural disasters.
   Also in the meantime, bandits play keep-away with a stolen,
broken half-coin that figures in an inscrutable ancient tradition
entitling the bearer to a lucrative ``favor'' from the <ORGANIZATION>Noble House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Though the plot is supposed to take place over a few days, it
seems like years. Time passage is such a problem that at one point,
the characters have to explain in dialogue what has happened when
and remark how it all seems so long ago.
   For viewers, it will all seem so long ago, too. ``Noble House''
isn't good enough to be good, or even bad enough to be good. As a
four-hour junk-TV snack, maybe. But for anyone willing to invest
eight hours _ good joss.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Wed PMs, Feb. 17</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-15636</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CGABQAD2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920701
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 JUL 92 / World News in Brief: Anorexic girl can be treated
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
The Court of Appeal ruled that a 16-year-old anorexic girl can be treated
for her illness against her wishes. The girl, who weighs 5st 7lb, is in the
care of a local authority which wants to send her to a unit specialising in
eating disorders.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 1
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA012289-0118 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 8692 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 22, 1989, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 2; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
938 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COMMENTARY; 
</P>
<P>
SCHOOL CLINIC ISSUE DESERVES RECHECKING 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MAUREEN BROWN, Maureen Brown is a former teacher who lives in La Jolla. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
From what I have observed thus far, the <ORGANIZATION>Nintendo</ORGANIZATION> computer game system comes 
with a more comprehensive set of instructions and programs than parents and 
educators acquire with children. In <ORGANIZATION>Nintendo</ORGANIZATION>, guidelines are tidy and clearly 
mapped out, and the player needs only to comply with the instructions to 
perform skillfully. 
</P>
<P>
Oh, were it only so with parenting and education. With innumerable variables 
such as personality, behavior, intelligent quotient and economic factors, 
decisions affecting children become so much more onerous. Every decree must be 
weighed carefully and eventually re-evaluated when the timing is suitable. When 
the issues immersed in the judgment are emotional and controversial, time bears 
an important role in determining when best to approach the topic again. 
</P>
<P>
"Time crumbles things; everything grows under the power of time and is 
forgotten through the lapse of time," Aristotle wrote. 
</P>
<P>
Almost three years have elapsed since the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Unified School District</ORGANIZATION> 
considered establishing health-care clinics at some high schools. Funded by a 
private foundation, the centers would have been staffed by professionals who, 
depending on the program adopted by the district, would provide physical 
examinations, immunizations, counseling and birth control information. 
</P>
<P>
The district appointed a committee of 30 people from business, educational, 
health and religious sectors to listen to the public's opinion, examine the 
needs of the community, study similar programs in other school districts and 
make a recommendation to the school board. The committee made a favorable 
recommendation to the school district. 
</P>
<P>
The board considered the recommendation of the committee, listened to more 
community debate and assessed that the public was unwilling to accept the role 
of the school district in this form of health care. 
</P>
<P>
But after three years, and two new board members, it's time to reconsider 
issue. 
</P>
<P>
It is fitting to bury the anger and emotional drama that accompanied the idea 
of school-based health clinics and approach the topic again in a caring milieu. 
Sufficient time may have passed to allow the various interest groups to 
approach the issue with facts, and without the distraction of emotion. 
</P>
<P>
The school district will now have more data to present to the community. 
Educators can interpret the effectiveness of similar programs in parallel 
communities. Does there still appear to be a need for the clinics in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>? 
</P>
<P>
Three years will have allowed religious factions to show how the alternative 
programs they suggested have been implemented and whether they have met the 
needs of adolescents. 
</P>
<P>
Three years will have given the medical community and affiliated groups an 
opportunity to relate how their programs have dealt with the issue of 
adolescent medicine. 
</P>
<P>
And, in three years, the legions of adolescents and parents will have grown, 
affording another group an opportunity to study and discuss the issue. 
</P>
<P>
Now is the time for the parents who supported the clinic to determine if their 
reasoning was accurate. Do they have specific examples where health care on 
campus might have helped a teen-ager? Moreover, it is an occasion for the 
parents who opposed the program to render their opinions. May we hear again 
from the mother of the ninth-grader who saw no need for such support. How have 
the subsequent years influenced her conviction? 
</P>
<P>
And this mother of four, who now has two high school students? How have the 
three years affected my views? <PERSON>Bobby McFerrin</PERSON>, the Grammy nominee, sings to me, 
"Don't worry, be happy," my dear friend tells me to pray more, but I am not 
calmed by what I read, hear or see. 
</P>
<P>
Am I alone in my belief that, although we counsel our children, preach to them, 
monitor their activities and love them, we still need and benefit from the 
assistance of other professionals? 
</P>
<P>
Three years later, like other parents, I am chanting "say 'no' " to drugs and 
alcohol, capitalizing on the merits of abstinence with regard to teen-age sex, 
stressing good nutrition and asking that wet towels not be left on the bedroom 
floors. Yet, I am still finding wet towels on the bedroom floors. 
</P>
<P>
I have sat with the anxious friend whose daughter had anorexia nervosa and 
wondered about other young people. I have heard of the football player who 
works at gaining weight or the wrestler who attempts to lose weight to wrestle 
in a different weight class. While discussing vitamins, nutritional supplements 
and diuretics, I observe adolescents consuming mass quantities of nachos and 
diet soda. 
</P>
<P>
I have heard the whispered talk of the young girl who needed an abortion and 
questioned how this might have been prevented. 
</P>
<P>
I have delivered the liturgical reading at the funeral of the friend who died 
from AIDS and prayed that I would not have to see another mother's anguish. 
</P>
<P>
I have applauded the PE teacher who introduced the topic of scoliosis and 
discovered the young girl's advanced case. I have been told of the curious 
teen-ager, who, after studying the circulatory system in a science class, had 
his blood pressure checked at a local shopping center. <DATE>Three days later</DATE>, 
cardiac surgery saved his life. How many others? 
</P>
<P>
And I have winced in the midst of a discussion about the child admitted to a 
drug and alcohol treatment program as another parent quipped, "Well, I know 
that none of my teen-agers would ever use drugs or drink alcohol." 
</P>
<P>
I have seen teen-agers weep over the suicide of a friend and watched parents 
and teachers question how they might have helped. 
</P>
<P>
The re-evaluation of school-based, health clinics in the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Unified 
School District</ORGANIZATION>. It's time. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Drawing, Steven Lopez 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Opinion 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110789-0040 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 131183 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 7, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1256 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
KAREN CARPENTER: SHE HAD ONLY JUST BEGUN; 
</P>
<P>
POP: NEW CARPENTERS' ALBUM FEATURES FOUR SONGS FROM KAREN'S ILL-FATED SOLO 
COLLECTION. THE ALBUM SUGGESTS SHE MIGHT HAVE HAD A CAREER AS A SOLOIST. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PAUL GREIN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
KarenandRichard. 
</P>
<P>
Those names were linked so often in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, when the Carpenters were the 
hottest duo in pop music, that many pop fans came to think of the pair as one. 
</P>
<P>
That was fine early in the decade when the <PERSON>Downey</PERSON> brother-and-sister team was 
turning out instant standards such as "We've Only Just Begun" and "Close to 
You," but it started to bother <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE> when the duo's fortunes 
declined sharply. 
</P>
<P>
In an effort to establish an independent identity at last, <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> moved to <LOCATION>New 
York</LOCATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE> to record a solo album with Grammy-winning producer <PERSON>Phil Ramone</PERSON>, 
whose credits include hits by <PERSON>Billy Joel</PERSON>, <PERSON>Paul Simon</PERSON> and Barbra Streisand. 
</P>
<P>
But the album was never released. Instead, <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard</PERSON> reteamed to record 
a traditional Carpenters album, which failed to reverse their downward career 
momentum. And in <DATE>1983</DATE> -- after a brief, failed marriage -- <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> died at 32 of 
complications from anorexia nervosa, an eating disorder which had plagued her 
since the mid '70s. 
</P>
<P>
With her death, the "lost <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> tapes" became even more of a source of mystery 
among fans. But they remained unavailable -- until now. 
</P>
<P>
Four songs from that shelved <DATE>1979</DATE> album are featured -- along with eight 
previously unreleased Carpenters recordings -- on a just-released Carpenters 
album, "Love-lines." 
</P>
<P>
The recordings -- released to coincide with the 20th anniversary of the 
Carpenters' signing with <ORGANIZATION>A&amp;M Records</ORGANIZATION> -- suggest that <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> could work 
effectively outside the Carpenters' mellow pop sound and could have gone on to 
a thriving solo career. 
</P>
<P>
The big question: Why was the solo album put in limbo? 
</P>
<P>
The bigger question: If the album had been released and been successful, would 
things have turned out differently for <PERSON>Karen</PERSON>? 
</P>
<P>
The suspicion in some music industry quarters has been that <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> shelved the 
solo album out of loyalty to <PERSON>Richard</PERSON>, who was anxious to get back to work in 
<DATE>1979</DATE> after recovering from a Quaalude dependency. (<ORGANIZATION>Richard</ORGANIZATION>'s dependency was 
revealed in CBS-TV's "The <PERSON>Karen Carpenter Story</PERSON>," the highest-rated TV movie of 
the 1988-89 season.) 
</P>
<P>
In an interview tied to the release of the new album, <PERSON>Richard Carpenter</PERSON>, 43, 
was candid about the conflicts within the Carpenters in the late '70s. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Karen</PERSON> would mention every now and again that it would be nice to receive some 
accolades as a solo singer," he said in an A&amp;M office in <LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION>. "Of 
course, that made me feel badly, because we were a duo. Lord knows, she was the 
star of the duo, but that's not quite the same." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Richard</PERSON> said that he had a less-than-supportive reaction to <PERSON>Karen</PERSON>'s 
announcement -- just after he had begun a six-week drug rehabilitation program 
-- that she was planning to record an album without him. 
</P>
<P>
"I probably said something like, 'You're just abandoning ship, just taking off 
and doing what you want to do.' I was feeling sorry for myself," he said. "It 
was a combination of feeling I was being abandoned -- which was anything but 
the case looking back on it -- and thinking this was a perfect time for her to 
get some treatment for her disorder. So I was not happy, and I told her as 
much." 
</P>
<P>
Richard, who produced and arranged the <ORGANIZATION>Carpenters</ORGANIZATION>' long string of hits, also 
acknowledged that he felt threatened by <PERSON>Karen</PERSON>'s teaming up with another 
producer. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm human and it did cross my mind that something could come out of this and 
just explode at which time I would be going through a number of emotions. I'd 
be happy for <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> because I always felt that she should have been in the Top 
5. On the other hand, being sensitive and feeling I'd done a good job for the 
Carpenters I would have been a little bit upset." 
</P>
<P>
In a separate interview from his <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> office, producer <PERSON>Phil Ramone</PERSON> 
discussed his and <PERSON>Karen</PERSON>'s objective on the album. "We were thinking two things: 
How do we make a record that doesn't sound like the Carpenters, and what could 
we say lyrically in these songs that has a more mature attitude?" 
</P>
<P>
The solo album included a spare, intimate reading of the sexually direct "Make 
Believe It's Your First Time" and a bluesy version of <PERSON>Paul Simon</PERSON>'s "Still Crazy 
After All These Years" -- though <PERSON>Karen</PERSON>, mindful of her prim image -- had <PERSON>Simon</PERSON> 
change the line, "4 in the morning / crapped out / yawning" to the more demure 
"crashed out." 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Karen</PERSON> was frustrated by the Goody Two-Shoes image, but she was torn," <PERSON>Ramone</PERSON> 
said. "She wanted to do try new things, but then she'd turn around and say, 
'We're going to do another Carpenters Christmas special.' I kept saying, 'The 
(Andy) <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> family even got past that one.' " 
</P>
<P>
Ramone still remembers the day in early <DATE>1980</DATE> when he and <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> played the album 
for <PERSON>Richard</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>A&amp;M</ORGANIZATION> founders <PERSON>Herb Alpert</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jerry Moss</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"The silence was deafening," he said. "<PERSON>Richard</PERSON> didn't say much and still 
hasn't. He's accepted these songs kind of like stepchildren. <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> was always 
the sweetheart of A&amp;M, and <PERSON>Herb</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jerry</PERSON> reacted almost like it was their 
teen-age daughter I was messing with." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Alpert</PERSON>, who wrote the liner notes to the Carpenters' debut album and found the 
team's breakthrough hit, "Close to You," declined to be interviewed for this 
story. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Richard Carpenter</PERSON> remembers giving <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> a mixed, but essentially lukewarm, 
review of the solo project. 
</P>
<P>
"I probably said it was very nice," he said. "It certainly is well-produced and 
well-assembled. But some of it was disco, and I'm not a disco fan, and I 
thought she was singing a little bit too high on some of the songs." 
</P>
<P>
And <PERSON>Carpenter</PERSON> applied some not-so-subtle pressure on <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> by telling her how 
eager he was to begin work on the next Carpenters album. "I was much better by 
then and was kicking myself for what I had done to my life," he said. "So I 
mentioned that whenever she was ready, I was ready. I had all the tunes set to 
go." 
</P>
<P>
The deciding factor came when A&amp;M executives asked <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ramone</PERSON> to go 
back into the studio to record a few more songs for the solo project. 
</P>
<P>
"It was up to <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> to decide if she wanted to spend more time on it or not," 
<PERSON>Richard</PERSON> said. "She didn't and that was that. I've gotten a lot of letters 
through the years since <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> passed on kind of accusing me of not releasing 
the solo album. It's not my doing at all. It's <PERSON>Karen</PERSON>'s wishes I'm honoring." 
</P>
<P>
In a <DATE>1981</DATE> interview, <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> said that <PERSON>Richard</PERSON>'s desire to get back to work took 
precedence over completing the solo project. But <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> added that she valued 
the solo experience. "It was fun cutting it and seeing that I could do all that 
-- sing a different type of tune and work with different people. I was scared 
to death beforehand. I basically knew one producer, one arranger, one studio, 
one record company and that was it. . . . I'm used to being part of a duo. 
Richard's like a third arm to me." 
</P>
<P>
Stung by the cool reception at the playback session, <PERSON>Ramone</PERSON> and <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> went to 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> for a vacation. "I watched this girl disintegrate in front of me," 
<PERSON>Ramone</PERSON> said. "It was hard for her to express anger, but sometimes she'd be 
sitting there and she'd say, 'Why is this happening? What did I do wrong? 
Should we listen to the tape? Is it the mix?' " 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Ramone</PERSON> said that <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> was ultimately proud of the album: "It was the first 
step to her standing on her own and also the last chance. 
</P>
<P>
"I truly believe that if she had made it through this she could have gone on to 
have a long career," <PERSON>Ramone</PERSON> said. "A lot of the pop songs and movie songs and 
duets of the '80s would have been hers. 
</P>
<P>
"A voice like <PERSON>Karen</PERSON>'s -- rich, womanly -- comes along once every 20 years. 
Voices like that should have a chance to do a variety of things." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Jacket covers for new "Lovelines" album, left, and Karen's proposed solo 
album. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
AUDIO RECORDINGS; CARPENTER, RICHARD; CARPENTER, KAREN 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06133172 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06133172 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: A dermatologist performs a dermabrasion operation  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BOOK; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE BEAUTY MYTH: How Images of Beauty; Are Used Against Women  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Arts &amp; Books  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE PRICE OF BEAUTY
FIXATION ON LOOKS MEANS LOSS OF POWER  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Books
Faludi, a Wall Street Journal reporter based in San Francisco, recently won
the Pulitzer Prize for explanatory journalism. She is the author of "Backlash:
The Undeclared War Against American Women," which will be published in October.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  By <PERSON>Naomi Wolf; Morrow</PERSON>, 291 pp., <MONEY>$21.95</MONEY>;  WHY, in an era when women are
supposedly freer than ever before, do so many middle-class women chain
themselves to private beauty torture chambers, starving and purging their
bellies, scalding their faces with Retin-A "treatments" and acid peels, or
slicing their body parts with plastic surgery (now the fastest growing medical
specialty in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>)?;    Pop psychologists, so-called women's
health experts and, of course, women's magazine writers have tackled this
question in recent years, most with less-than-; illuminating insights.
Typically, these authorities wind up pointing an accusing finger at women's
liberation itself. Women have applied the feminist tenets of control and
mastery to their own bodies, they charge, and with devastating results. An
anorexic, they say, is an autonomous woman gone haywire.;    The more
psychoanalytically inclined look to the family for answers. They blame that
whipping girl of long-standing: Mom. It must be the pressures to please a
never-satisfied maternal figure that have turned the overachieving daughter
against her own flesh.;    Still others charge that the baby boom ethic is
behind the epidemic in eating disorders and the mania for liposuction and
breast implants. The Me Generation woman wants it all, they sniff, thin hips
and big breasts. She is greedy and so she binges and purges, literally having
her cake and eating it, too.;     In "The Beauty Myth," <PERSON>Naomi Wolf</PERSON> rejects
these explanations, and their tendency to assign responsibility to the
individual woman in isolation, and opts for a refreshingly political and
social analysis. Women are increasingly obsessed with perfecting their bodies,
she argues, not because they are overly feminist or self-indulgent but because
they have been subjected to a feminist-fearing and anything-but-indulgent
culture that has raised the stakes in the beauty market to an unbearable high.
American culture demands that women attain an aesthetic standard that is
virtually inhuman, and it offers, as a means of reaching its impossible goal,
tools that are increasingly painful, destructive and even deadly.;     The new
ideal, or "beauty myth," <PERSON>Wolf</PERSON> says, has arisen as a way of keeping the newly
independent woman down. "For every feminist action there is an equal and
opposite beauty myth reaction," <PERSON>Wolf</PERSON> writes. "The fixation on 'beauty' of the
<DATE>1980s</DATE> was a direct consequence of, and a one-to-one check and balance upon,
the entry of women into powerful positions." It advises women, as she aptly
recasts the old saw: "You are now too rich. Therefore, you cannot be too
thin.";    <PERSON>Wolf</PERSON> puts forward a set of disturbing, some by now
all-too-familiar, statistics on the ravages of this modern beauty fixation:
the reports that as many as one in five college women are anorexic or bulimic;
the studies that show breast implants have blocked the detection of cancer and
so facilitated its spread; the findings that liquid fast diets have led to 60
deaths and that liposuction operations have caused at least 14. As <PERSON>Wolf</PERSON>
rightly points out, even more appalling than the toll of the beauty myth is
society's -- and journalism's -- willingness to turn a blind eye to it, to
trivialize its origins as "vanity" and to promote its ends as "liberation."
The press, in particular, so often seems more interested in pimping for the
beauty industry than exposing its unattractive effects.;     The analysis that
Wolf offers, presented properly, might have provided much-needed fodder in
women's battle for equal status and self-respect. But <PERSON>Wolf</PERSON>, in her zeal to
