<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901029-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-29-90 0821EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-India 1stLd-Writethru a0480 10-29 0696</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0480,0850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eye of the Storm: Calm at Shrine Claimed By Hindus and Moslems</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 6 grafs to UPDATE with death reported in Lucknow,
Hindu fundamentalists say thousands of followers are hiding near
disputed site. Pickup 5th graf pvs, ```Communal tension..'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bored policemen shoo monkeys and glance
sleepily at closed-circuit television cameras as they enforce a
curfew in this town whose name has become a battle cry in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
latest political and religious crisis.
   About 100 people have been killed throughout <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in the past
week in riots caused by Hindu plans to build a temple on a dusty
hilltop where a Moslem mosque now stands.
   The latest death was reported today in <LOCATION>Lucknow</LOCATION>, capital of <LOCATION>Uttar
Pradesh</LOCATION> state 75 miles west of <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>. Police officials said Hindu
crowds surged through a Moslem neighborhood throwing bricks.
   The religious feud has precipitated a political crisis that has
brought Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>'s government to the brink of
collapse.
   But the firestorm raging elsewhere in the country is masked by
inactivity and tight security in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, where Hindu
fundamentalists vow they will get through roadblocks and start
building their temple to the god <ORGANIZATION>Rama</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The fundamentalists said <DATE>today</DATE> in a handwritten communique that
thousands of followers were hiding near <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> and were ready to
start building.
   ``Communal tension will flare up all over the country, but an
<LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> resident will not let a drop of blood be spilled because
then <ORGANIZATION>Rama</ORGANIZATION>'s name will be sullied,'' said <PERSON>Mudit Sharma</PERSON>, who works
for a Hindu charity near the disputed site.
   ``Moslems of the area are not any diferent from Hindus,''
<PERSON>Sharma</PERSON> said. ``They participate in our festivals. We go to their
house during Islamic festivals. All these fights are because of
political loafers.''
   The fundamentalist cause has been espoused by the Hindu
right-wing <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata Party</ORGANIZATION>. Its top leaders are among the
more about 80,000 people arrested in the <DATE>last week</DATE> while trying to
march to <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, 300 miles east of <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>.
   The arrests prompted the party to withdraw its support for
<ORGANIZATION>Singh</ORGANIZATION>'s coalition government, leaving him without the parliamentary
majority needed to stay in office.
   Singh, who plans to face <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> for a vote of confidence on
<DATE>Nov. 7</DATE>, wants the temple-mosque dispute settled in court.
   The fundamentalists claim the mosque stands atop the very spot
where <PERSON>Lord Rama</PERSON> was born and therefore is a religious matter, not a
legal one. Moslems, a minority in officially secular but
predominantly <LOCATION>Hindu India</LOCATION>, fear the displacement of one mosque
could jeopardize hundreds of other Islamic sites across the
country.
   The mosque, called the <PERSON>Babri Masjid</PERSON>, was constructed in the <DATE>16th
century</DATE> when Mogul armies conquered northern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Hindu
fundamentalists claimed the Moslem conquerors destroyed a Rama
temple on the spot where the mosque now stands.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Hindu World Council</ORGANIZATION>, backed by the <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata Party</ORGANIZATION>,
has organized the campaign to build the temple by either moving or
demolishing the little mosque.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the government of Uttar Pradesh state imposed an
around-the-clock curfew in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> to keep temple advocates from
reaching the disputed hilltop. Trains to the area were halted and
roads blocked by police and paramilitary troops.
   ``They have made <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> into a cantonment for political gains.
Let them arrest us, but thousands of devotees will come to <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>
tomorrow,'' said <PERSON>Tara Kant Jha</PERSON>, secretary of the <ORGANIZATION>World Hindu
Council</ORGANIZATION>'s local office in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>.
   The council and the <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata Party</ORGANIZATION> claim the
government's tough stand on <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> is only a bid to win Moslem
votes.
   Moslems make up <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people, of
whom <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> are Hindu. In <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh state</LOCATION>, where the
government is allied with <PERSON>Singh</PERSON>, Moslems account for about <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT> of the 120 million people.
   Hindu-Moslem clashes occur periodically in other parts of <LOCATION>Uttar
Pradesh</LOCATION>, but no one can remember trouble around <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> or its twin
town of <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION>, three miles down the road. About a quarter of the
area's population is Moslem.
   ``There never has been any communal tension in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION> or
<LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>. And I don't think there will be after <DATE>Oct. 30</DATE>,'' the date
deemed auspicious by Hindu astrologers to start building the Rama
temple, said District Commissioner <PERSON>Madhukar Gupta</PERSON>, the top civil
administrator of the area.
   Most residents agree. They seem unconcerned about the curfew,
but business is suffering.
   Ayodhya is a major Hindu pilgrimage site. There are about 6,000
temples in the town of 45,000 people on the banks of the <LOCATION>River
Saryu</LOCATION>.
   Most people live on the business generated by tens of thousands
of Hindu pilgrims who arrive every year in <DATE>October</DATE> for a Hindu
festival.
   About 20,000 security troops deployed around <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> have
prevented pilgrims from entering <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> <DATE>this week</DATE>, fearing Hindu
activists may infiltrate the town.
   Elaborate security arrangements include closed-circuit
television cameras and iron gates every 20 yards on the lane
leading to the disputed hilltop.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901023-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-23-90 0417EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-India     10-23 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India,0747</SECOND>
<HEAD>Defection Of Hindu Fundamentalist Party Threatens Singh Government</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EARLEEN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A right-wing Hindu party withdrew its
support for Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>'s government today,
threatening to bring down the fragile coalition that has governed
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> for the past 10 months.
   Singh refused to resign and said he would take the battle to
floor of <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION>, where his centrist <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> government
had relied on the votes of the Hindu fundamentalist <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya
Janata Party</ORGANIZATION> to survive.
   The crisis was precipitated by the arrest earlier <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> of
<ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata</ORGANIZATION>'s president, <PERSON>Lal Krishna Advani</PERSON>, as he led a
cross-country march to muster support for building a new Hindu
temple on the site of a <DATE>16th century</DATE> Moslem mosque.
   About six hours later, party leaders submitted a letter to
Indian President <PERSON>Ramaswamy Venkataraman</PERSON> withdrawing support for
<ORGANIZATION>Singh's National Front</ORGANIZATION> government.
   The prime minister told reporters at the presidential palace
that the loss of Bharatiya Janata support ``doesn't mean that all
support is gone.'' However, it was unclear how he could avoid
calling new elections.
   With the defection of the <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata Party</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Singh</PERSON>'s
centrist government loses the fragile majority it cobbled together
from across the political spectrum after <DATE>November</DATE> general
elections.
   No single party had won enough seats to take power unilaterally.
   The next steps are up to <PERSON>Singh</PERSON> and the president.
   Under the constitution, the options include <PERSON>Singh</PERSON>'s resignation
as prime minister and elections for a new Parliament.
   President <PERSON>Venkataraman</PERSON> could also ask Singh to try to muster a
new majority in <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION>, which appears mathematically and
politically improbable.
   Or, the president can turn to the opposition leader, former
Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON>, and ask if <ORGANIZATION>Gandhi</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION>
could form a coalition government.
   That also appears unlikely.
   The crisis was precipitated by <PERSON>Advani</PERSON>'s determination to go
ahead with his march to bolster support for the campaign to replace
a Moslem mosque with a temple to the Hindu god <ORGANIZATION>Lord Rama</ORGANIZATION>.
   Singh had urged Hindu fundamentalists to postpone the temple
plan. At least 80 people died this month in Hindu-Moslem clashes
spurred by the dispute.
   In a nationally televised address <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, <PERSON>Singh</PERSON> renewed
his appeal and said he was prepared to face the fact that his stand
could bring down the government.
   ``Religious fanaticism is the first step towards the foundation
for a theocratic state,'' <PERSON>Singh</PERSON> said in his 20-minute TV speech.
``It will be the death of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as a secular state.''
   The prime minister added: ``Hundreds of governments can come and
go, but the nation should remain one.''
   Advani was arrested about sunrise in a remote part of <LOCATION>Bihar</LOCATION>
state near the village of Samastipur, about 450 miles southeast of
<LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>.
   He had been leading a caravan of supporters across the Hindu
heartland to demonstrate and bolster support for plans to build a
temple on a site now occupied by a 16th century mosque in the holy
Hindu town of <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>. Ayodhya is in <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh state</LOCATION>, which
lies between <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bihar</LOCATION> state.
   Advani's planned path through <LOCATION>Bihar</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Uttar Pradesh</PERSON> en route
to <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> would have taken him through poor villages populated by
both Moslems and Hindus. In <LOCATION>Bihar</LOCATION> especially, these villages have
been recurring flashpoints for Hindu-Moslem violence.
   Hindu fundamentalists have vowed to start building the temple in
one week on the spot where they say the Hindu god <ORGANIZATION>Lord Rama</ORGANIZATION> was
born. Moslem activists and religious leaders have vowed to prevent
any encroachment on the mosque.
   The outcry has torn at the social and political fabric of
officially secular <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, where <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of the 880 million
people are Hindus. Moslems form <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of the population.
   Singh took office in <DATE>December</DATE> after ousting <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> and his
<ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>November</DATE> general election. Although the
<ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> and its allies hold 210 of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>'s 522 seats,
it lacked the majority to govern.
   Singh's <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> coalition holds just 141 seats, but it
won the tacit support of the two extremes of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s political
spectrum: <PERSON>Advani</PERSON>'s right-wing Hindu party and the Left Front
alliance of several communist parties.
   With that support, <PERSON>Singh</PERSON> could draw on enough votes to give him
the majority needed to pass legislation and stay in power.
   Bharatiya Janata has 88 members of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, the Left Front
51.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900209-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-09-90 1643EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ReligiousDispute     02-09 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Religious Dispute,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fundamentalist Hindus Defer Plan to Build Disputed Temple</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAJU GOPALAKRISHNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fundamentalist Hindus decided <DATE>Friday</DATE> to
postpone building a temple at a disputed religious site claimed by
both Moslems and Hindus.
   Avaidyanath, a Hindu priest who uses one name, told reporters
the <ORGANIZATION>World Hindu Conference</ORGANIZATION> decided to postpone construction of the
temple for at least four months so the government can find a
solution to the long-running dispute.
   Construction was to have started <DATE>Feb. 14</DATE> on land that also
contains a 16th century mosque.
   Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON> said building the shrine would inflame
religious passions and lead to widespread violence, and he urged
Hindus to call off construction.
   ``We have decided to accept the prime minister's appeal,'' said
<PERSON>Avaidyanath</PERSON>, who wore the saffron robes of a Hindu ascetic. ``We'll
give him four months to solve the issue.''
   Last year, at least 300 people died in violence sparked by the
Hindu group's decision to build the temple and raze the mosque. The
foundation stone for the shrine was laid <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>, but construction
was postponed because of the dispute.
   Hindus claim the site is the birthplace of the <ORGANIZATION>Rama</ORGANIZATION>, an
incarnation of <LOCATION>Vishnu</LOCATION>, one of the most important Hindu gods. They
say the Babri Masjid, or the mosque named after <PERSON>Moghal</PERSON> emperor
<PERSON>Babar</PERSON>, was built over <LOCATION>Rama</LOCATION>'s birthplace.
   Moslems say it is difficult to say where Rama was born and they
will not accept destruction of their mosque.
   The issue has become a flashpoint for tensions between <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
majority Hindus, who make up <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of its 880 million people,
and its Moslems, who form the country's largest minority but still
comprise only <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of the population.
   The dispute became a major issue in last <DATE>November</DATE>'s general
elections, and analysts say it was one of the causes of the
downfall of the previous prime minister, <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON>.
   Singh, his successor, has not come up with any specfic plan to
solve the problem but has promised to set up a government committee
to meet Hindu and Moslem representatves and try to come up with a
solution.
   ``The problem has been hanging for 450 years,'' said <PERSON>Ashok
Singhal</PERSON>, general secretary of the <ORGANIZATION>World Hindu Conference</ORGANIZATION>. ``Four
months more will not matter.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901030-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-30-90 0034EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India 1stLd-Writethru a0622 10-30 0590</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0622,0729</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hindus Break through Police Lines, Storm toward Disputed Shrine</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 15 grafs to UPDATE with Hindu fundamentalists
breaking through police barricades and battling police. Picks up
19th pvs, `In New ...'
^LaserPhoto AYO3</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of Hindu holy men and their
followers broke through police barricades <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and stormed
toward the Moslem mosque they want to replace with a Hindu temple.
   Many were beaten back by police who fired tear gas and lashed
out with iron-tipped bamboo canes. Dozens were injured. Hindu holy
men screamed obscenities from rooftops and pelted the police with
stones.
   About 200 people overran police lines in the narrow lanes and
were halted at the foot of the hill just 600 feet from the mosque.
   The religious dispute has made the name of this Hindu holy town
a battle cry in Moslem-Hindu riots that have left more than 100
dead across <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in the past week.
   The dispute threatens to topple the government of Prime Minister
<PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>. A right-wing Hindu party withdrew its support for Singh
last week when his government tried to deter plans to build new
Hindu temple where the mosque now stands.
   Ayodhya had been under around-the-clock curfew since <DATE>Friday</DATE> in
an effort to keep Hindu fundamentalists from carrying out their vow
to begin construction of the temple <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Roads leading to the <DATE>16th century</DATE> mosque were blocked, but about
5,000 people emerged from hiding places in fields around <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>
before sunrise and stormed a bridge leading into the town.
   Police arrested between 100 and 200 people and rained blows with
their bamboo canes on fallen members of the crowd. The 600
policemen on the mile-long bridge eventually turned back the crowd.
   Inside <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, a town of about 40,000 people, reporters saw
some members of the state police force lift barricades and let
Hindu holy men run into the lanes leading to the mosque. The
infiltrators were halted short of the mosque by federal
paramilitary police.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, a group of about 80 Hindu holy men in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> threw
stones at police and set a bus on fire when authorities attempted
to arrest a local Hindu priest, a police inspector said.
   The inspector, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said it was
an isolated incident and did not cause any lasting tension.
   But within an hour of the skirmish, authorities banned entry
into <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> and canceled passes issued to reporters.
   Despite the efforts to deter them and the presence of 20,000
police and paramilitary troops in town, the Hindu fundamentalists
vowed to start the temple construction program as scheduled.
   In <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>World Hindu Council</ORGANIZATION> had claimed
10,000 supporters had slipped through police cordons and roadblocks
around <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>.
   The exact time for the start of construction has not been
announced.
   In <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, Prime Minister Singh offered to resign if the
Hindu fundamentalist <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata Party</ORGANIZATION>, which supports the
temple construction program, would accept a legal verdict on the
dispute.
   Singh's <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> coalition was relegated to a minority in
<LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE> after Bharatiya Janata withdrew its support to
the government. Singh has maintained he still holds a parliamentary
majority and is scheduled to seek a vote of confidence on <DATE>Nov. 7</DATE>.
   The government has vowed to block the temple construction and
said a court of law should decide who the site belongs to.
   The fundamentalists claim the mosque stands atop the very spot
where Rama, one of the most worshipped Hindu gods, was born and
therefore is a religious matter, not a legal one.
   Moslems, a minority in officially secular but predominantly
<LOCATION>Hindu India</LOCATION>, fear the displacement of one mosque could jeopardize
hundreds of other Islamic sites across the country.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE> the government of Uttar Pradesh state imposed an
around-the-clock curfew in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> in an effort to keep temple
advocates from reaching the disputed hilltop. Trains to the area
were halted and roads blocked by police and paramilitary troops.
   Moslems make up <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people, of
whom <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> are Hindu. In <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh state</LOCATION>, where the
government is allied with <PERSON>Singh</PERSON>, Moslems account for about <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT> of the 120 million people.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901030-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-30-90 0950EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-India 3rdLd-Writethru a0502 10-30 0626</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0502,0772</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Fire on Crowd in Religious Dispute, Five Killed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 9 grafs to UPDATE death toll, ADD Singh offer to
resign, details. Pick up 9th graf pvs, `Hindu holy...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Troops opened fire today on Hindu
fundamentalists who broke through police lines and surged toward a
holy site claimed by both Hindus and Moslems. At least five people
were killed and 20 wounded.
   Thirteen more people died in Hindu-Moslem clashes in several
cities hundreds of miles away, police said. At least 125 people
have been killed in riots across <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> this past week, most in
clashes between Hindus and Moslems.
   The dispute threatens to topple the government of Prime Minister
<PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>, who opposes the Hindu campaign to replace a
16th-century Moslem mosque.
   Militant members of the country's Hindu majority had said they
would begin tearing down the mosque today and replacing it with a
temple.
   Singh today repeated his offer to resign if members of his party
in Parliament ``feel that change of leadership will serve larger
goals.'' He made a similar offer <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   About 200 Hindus eventually reached the site <DATE>today</DATE> in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>.
Those who got through planted Hindu religious flags on the mosque
in victory before police drove them away.
   About 10,000 people who had surged past police barricades
surrounded the perimeter of the disputed site when three Hindu holy
men urged them to halt the violence, saying they had negotiated a
peaceful sttlement with local officials. But part of the crowd
apparently did not hear the appeal and pushed toward the mosque,
setting fire to six police jeeps along the way.
   Police then opened fire. The federal government later announced
that five people were killed. About 20 others were injured by the
gunfire, witnesses said.
   Hindu holy men screamed obscenities from rooftops and pelted the
police with stones. At least four officers were injured.
   Many of the militant Hindus were beaten back by police, who
fired tear gas and lashed out with iron-tipped bamboo canes. Dozens
were injured.
   The crowd initially halted about 100 yards from the mosque,
where police and paramilitary troops stood with rifles ready. But
later about 200 Hindus broke through police lines and reached the
small, one-story mosque.
   Young men wearing orange headbands, the color of the Hindu
faith, climbed atop the mosque and chipped concrete from each of
its three domes, claiming this was a ``symbolic destruction'' of
the Islamic shrine.
   They planted a saffron flag atop each dome before police drove
them away. Jubilant crowds poured through the streets, shouting
``Victory to mother <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>!''
   In <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, the government's chief spokesman, <PERSON>Ramamohan Rao</PERSON>,
said there was no damage to the mosque.
   The <ORGANIZATION>World Hindu Council</ORGANIZATION>, which is leading the temple program,
said it would go ahead with its construction effort.
   ``We will only rest when the temple in complete,'' <PERSON>Girilal
Kishore</PERSON>, a Hindu holy man and senior official of the council told
reporters in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>.
   Ayodha, a city of 40,000 people, had been under a
round-the-clock curfew since <DATE>Friday</DATE> and roads leading to the mosque
were blocked as authorities tried to halt any attempt to tear down
the mosque.
   But people emerged from hiding places in fields around <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>
before sunrise and stormed a bridge leading into the town.
   About 20,000 police and paramilitary troops were deployed in and
around <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, 300 miles southeast of <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>. They were among
200,000 security troops on alert throughout <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh</LOCATION> state.
   About 80,000 people have been arrested in the <DATE>last week</DATE> in the
rural state. Most were made under preventive detention laws that
allow authorities to hold people without charge when they believe
public safety is threatened.
   The detainees included top leaders of the right-wing <ORGANIZATION>Hindu
Bharatiya Janata Party</ORGANIZATION>. It has withdrawn its support for Prime
Minister Singh in <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION>, plunging <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> into political crisis.
   Singh now does not have a reliable vote bank in <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> to
preserve his minority government, which took office last <DATE>December</DATE>.
   The mosque at issue was built on the place that many Hindu
leaders claim is the very spot where the god Rama was born.
   Moslems, who make up <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people,
fear that if one mosque is moved or destroyed, hundreds of other
Islamic shrines across <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> would be in peril.
   Athough <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is constitutionally a secular nation, Hindus
comprise <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of the population and have always held the
prime minister's post.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890201-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-01-89 0446EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-TheHindus     02-01 0777</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-The Hindus,0801</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0410 to fix numbering.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Hinduism, With 330 Million Gods and Goddesses, Confuses Even Hindus</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALLAHABAD, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One holy man walked naked among his
disciples, offering sacred ash, blessings and cardamoms as
consecrated host. Not far away, another holy man delivered a sermon
while dressed in a saffron robe.
   ``Why move naked?'' the second said. ``You can reach God
dressed.''
   A third, who pitched his tent nearby, told his group: ``Dress
does not matter. Ways do not matter. ... Be pure, be good and you
will reach heaven. You need no guru.''
   They were Hindu holy men at the <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION>'s biggest congregation,
the ``<PERSON>Kumbh Mela</PERSON>,'' which began here recently in <LOCATION>Allahabad</LOCATION>.
   The three holy men, each with different views, were examples of
the diversity of a religion believed to have been practiced since
the third millennium B.C.
   They also showed that <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION>, with 330 million gods and
goddesses, can be confusing even to Hindus.
   The religion claims a following of 730 million people in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION> and parts of <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Southeast
Asia</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Mauritius</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Fiji</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION>. For
comparison, the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> claims a following of 850
million.
   An estimated 500,000 holy men and their followers started camping
at <LOCATION>Allahabad</LOCATION> on <DATE>Jan. 14</DATE>, for a seven-week congregation, or fair,
during which 30 million to 40 million pilgrims were expected to take
dips at the ``Sangam,'' the confluence of the three rivers most
sacred to Hindus _ the <LOCATION>Ganges</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Jamuna</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Saraswathi</ORGANIZATION>.
   The ``Sangam,'' which takes it's name from a mythical fight
between gods and demons over a pot of nectar, is held every 12 years
when <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> enters Taurus and the Sun and the <PERSON>Moon</PERSON> are in Capricorn.
   ``You can't explain <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>M.P. Asthana</PERSON>, who has
attended four earlier fairs. ``It is a way of life, where karmas
(the results of deeds) are most important. Even to an average <PERSON>Hindu</PERSON>,
the faith is so confusing.''
   He added: ``No one can explain how we got to acquire and where
are our 330 million gods and goddesses.''
   Believers worship images and statues of gods and goddesses as
well as live animals, including rats. In <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION> every god has his
steed, or vehicle, and the rat is the vehicle of Ganesha on whom the
elephant-headed, master-of-ceremony god rides.
   Hinduism postulates that everyone goes through a series of
rebirths, or reincarnations, that eventually lead to <LOCATION>Moksha</LOCATION>, the
spiritual salvation that frees one from the cycle of rebirths.
   ``With each rebirth you can move closer to or further from
eventual moksha,'' said <PERSON>Asthana</PERSON>, who is the spokesman for the state
government of <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh</LOCATION>, in which <ORGANIZATION>Allahabad</ORGANIZATION> is a major city.
   ``The deciding factor is one's karma. Bad actions result in bad
karma, which leads one to lower incarnation and a step further from
salvation.
   ``But if one's actions have been good he or she will reincarnate
on a higher level and be a step closer to eventual freedom from
rebirth.''
   Coming to <LOCATION>Allahabad</LOCATION> has special significance for Hindus and tens
of thousands come daily to take holy dips at the <LOCATION>Sangam</LOCATION>, believing
doing this during the auspicious planetary conjugation will wash
away all the sins of a lifetime and release them from the cycle of
births and rebirths.
   ``It is like appearing directly before God for confessions,''
said <PERSON>Jagannath Dwevedi</PERSON>, the chief adminstrator of the fair.
   ``No one knows how bathing will wash off sins, but the belief is
so great that no logic stands.''
   Before taking the dip, pilgrims offer milk and marigolds to the
rivers in a purification ritual and later throw water with their
hands toward the sky, believing that some drops will reach their
ancestors in the heaven.
   ``Now, this sounds like a total nonsense, but people do it,''
said the 56-year-old Dwevedi. ``It is the age-old belief. It is
above logic.''
   Nagas are the naked recluses of <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION> and they have their own
logic.
   ``Nakedness ends all dichotomy in human life,'' said one,
refusing to give his name. ``We were born naked and therefore should
remain naked and die naked.''
   Fifty-two different religious groups put up sprawling tent homes
at the fair. Each has its own way to reach God. Most of them
constantly smoke marijuana. They say it helps them meditate and
become closer to God.
   ``This makes <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION> unique,'' said <PERSON>Asthana</PERSON>. ``There is no
restriction on how you reach your goal _ salvation.''
   Only vegetables appear on the fair's menus because devout Hindus
are vegetarians and eating beef is taboo. Hindus worship the cow.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890123-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-23-89 2117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-TheHindus Adv01   01-23 0786</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-The Hindus, Adv 01,0810</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wed AMs, Feb. 1, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Hinduism, with 330 Million Gods and Goddesses, Confuses Even Hindus</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALLAHABAD, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One holy man walked naked among his
disciples, offering sacred ash, blessings and cardamoms as
consecrated host. Not far away, another holy man delivered a sermon
while dressed in a saffron robe.
   ``Why move naked?'' the second said. ``You can reach God
dressed.''
   A third, who pitched his tent nearby, told his group: ``Dress
does not matter. Ways do not matter. ... Be pure, be good and you
will reach heaven. You need no guru.''
   They were Hindu holy men at the <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION>'s biggest congregation,
the ``<PERSON>Kumbh Mela</PERSON>,'' which began here recently in <LOCATION>Allahabad</LOCATION>.
   The three holy men, each with different views, were examples of
the diversity of a religion believed to have been practiced since
the third millennium B.C.
   They also showed that <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION>, with 330 million gods and
goddesses, can be confusing even to Hindus.
   The religion claims a following of 730 million people in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION> and parts of <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Southeast
Asia</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Mauritius</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Fiji</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION>. For
comparison, the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> claims a following of 850
million.
   An estimated 500,000 holy men and their followers started camping
at <LOCATION>Allahabad</LOCATION> on <DATE>Jan. 14</DATE>, for a seven-week congregation, or fair,
during which 30 million to 40 million pilgrims were expected to take
dips at the ``Sangam,'' the confluence of the three rivers most
sacred to Hindus _ the <LOCATION>Ganges</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Jamuna</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Saraswathi</ORGANIZATION>.
   The ``Sangam,'' which takes it's name from a mythical fight
between gods and demons over a pot of nectar, is held every 12 years
when <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> enters Taurus and the Sun and the <PERSON>Moon</PERSON> are in Capricorn.
   ``You can't explain <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>M.P. Asthana</PERSON>, who has
attended four earlier fairs. ``It is a way of life, where karmas
(the results of deeds) are most important. Even to an average <PERSON>Hindu</PERSON>,
the faith is so confusing.''
   He added: ``No one can explain how we got to acquire and where
are our 330 million gods and goddesses.''
   Believers worship images and statues of gods and goddesses as
well as live animals, including rats. In <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION> every god has his
steed, or vehicle, and the rat is the vehicle of Ganesha on whom the
elephant-headed, master-of-ceremony god rides.
   Hinduism postulates that everyone goes through a series of
rebirths, or reincarnations, that eventually lead to <LOCATION>Moksha</LOCATION>, the
spiritual salvation that frees one from the cycle of rebirths.
   ``With each rebirth you can move closer to or further from
eventual moksha,'' said <PERSON>Asthana</PERSON>, who is the spokesman for the state
government of <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh</LOCATION>, in which <ORGANIZATION>Allahabad</ORGANIZATION> is a major city.
   ``The deciding factor is one's karma. Bad actions result in bad
karma, which leads one to lower incarnation and a step further from
salvation.
   ``But if one's actions have been good he or she will reincarnate
on a higher level and be a step closer to eventual freedom from
rebirth.''
   Coming to <LOCATION>Allahabad</LOCATION> has special significance for Hindus and tens
of thousands come daily to take holy dips at the <LOCATION>Sangam</LOCATION>, believing
doing this during the auspicious planetary conjugation will wash
away all the sins of a lifetime and release them from the cycle of
births and rebirths.
   ``It is like appearing directly before God for confessions,''
said <PERSON>Jagannath Dwevedi</PERSON>, the chief adminstrator of the fair.
   ``No one knows how bathing will wash off sins, but the belief is
so great that no logic stands.''
   Before taking the dip, pilgrims offer milk and marigolds to the
rivers in a purification ritual and later throw water with their
hands toward the sky, believing that some drops will reach their
ancestors in the heaven.
   ``Now, this sounds like a total nonsense, but people do it,''
said the 56-year-old Dwevedi. ``It is the age-old belief. It is
above logic.''
   Nagas are the naked recluses of <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION> and they have their own
logic.
   ``Nakedness ends all dichotomy in human life,'' said one,
refusing to give his name. ``We were born naked and therefore should
remain naked and die naked.''
   Fifty-two different religious groups put up sprawling tent homes
at the fair. Each has its own way to reach God. Most of them
constantly smoke marijuana. They say it helps them meditate and
become closer to God.
   ``This makes <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION> unique,'' said <PERSON>Asthana</PERSON>. ``There is no
restriction on how you reach your goal _ salvation.''
   Only vegetables appear on the fair's menus because devout Hindus
are vegetarians and eating beef is taboo. Hindus worship the cow.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed AMs, Feb. 1</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891112-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-12-89 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-TempleProtest     11-12 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Temple Protest,0559</SECOND>
<UNK>Magistrate Blocks Hindu Construction at Site Claimed by Moslems</UNK>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A district magistrate on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> blocked
construction of a Hindu temple that has ignited violent protests by
Moslems who claim the project infringes on their holy land, a news
agency said.
   Press Trust of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> said the fundamentalist Hindu group trying
to build the temple at <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, 325 miles southeast of <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>,
had agred to delay construction pending discussions at a religious
convocation in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   At least 300 people have been killed in Hindu-Moslem riots in
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> since mid-August, when the World Conference of Hindus vowed
to build the temple on a site occupied by a 16th century mosque.
   The foundation of the new temple was placed <DATE>Friday</DATE> about 120
feet in front of the Babri Masjid mosque, whose name honors <PERSON>Babar</PERSON>,
one of the Mogul conquerors who introduced Islam to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   The ceremony touched off attacks on Hindu temples and shops
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> in two neighboring Moslem nations: <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, which were part of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> before <DATE>1947</DATE> when the former
British-ruled subcontinent was partitioned along religious lines
into independent nations.
   More protests erupted <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. In <LOCATION>Lahore</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, hundreds of
Pakistanis lined a major street, chanting slogans and rattling
placards in opposition to the temple.
   Moslems and Hindus both claim the temple site is sacred to their
religion. Hindus say the mosque was built atop an ancient Hindu
temple marking the birthplace of <ORGANIZATION>Lord Ram</ORGANIZATION>, one of the most popular
gods in the Hindu pantheon.
   The area's district magistrate, <PERSON>R.S. Srivastava</PERSON>, was quoted
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> by Press Trust of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as saying he could not give the
Hindus permission to continue digging at the site as long as the
matter was pending in court.
   Press Trust said the Hindu group building the temple, <ORGANIZATION>Vishwa
Hindu Parishad</ORGANIZATION>, had agreed to halt work temporarily.
   It quoted the group's general secretary, <PERSON>Ashok Singhal</PERSON>, as
saying a decision on the next course of action would be made during
a Hindu conference in <LOCATION>Allahabad</LOCATION> on <DATE>Jan. 27</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Singhal</PERSON> said last week his group would not try to demolish the
mosque but wanted to remove it ``intact and honorably'' from the
site.
   Moslems say this would set a bad precedent, since they say there
are at least 316 other mosques in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> that Hindus claim are built
on Hindu holy places.
the planned temple as ``a willful desecration of an Islamic holy
place.'' An Indian foreign ministry spokesman promptly accused her
of ``malicious meddling'' in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s internal affairs.
   <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> also have criticized the Indian government.
   The dispute has become a chief issue in Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv
Gandhi</PERSON>'s re-election campaign. On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s most
influential Islamic clergyman, <PERSON>Syed Abdullah Bukhari</PERSON>, urged Moslems
to vote <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> and his <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> out of office.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has more Moslems than any other country in the world
except <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, even though Indian Moslems form only <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT>
of the population of 880 million. They traditionally have voted for
the <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION>, so their alienation could prove crucial in the
elections on <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE>, 24 and 26.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has had a secular government but it has always been headed
by Hindus who make up <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of the population.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891109-0148 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-89 1829EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Shrine     11-09 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Shrine,0577</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hindus Begin Building Temple at Disputed Site</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EARLEEN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With a superficial scratching of earth and
placement of four bricks, Hindu fundamentalists <DATE>Thursday</DATE> reaffirmed
their intention to build a temple that has stirred a religious and
political storm.
   Outnumbered by police and paramilitary troops surrounding the
site, about 2,000 Hindu holy men, politicians, worshipers and
youthful, unarmed guards mobbed a patch of earth considered sacred
by Hindus and Moslems.
   Tens of thousands of other Hindu faithfuls streamed by behind
the ceremony site outside a police barricade. Hindus planned a
formal start to dig the foundation on <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   At least 290 people have died in Hindu-Moslem clashes since
<DATE>August</DATE> when Hindu fundamentalists announced they would build a new
temple to the god Ram on the site of an existing 17th century
mosque.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Vishwa Hindu Parishad</ORGANIZATION>, which is behind the temple program,
maintains the mosque was built atop an ancient Hindu temple marking
the spot where the group says Ram was born 900,000 years ago.
   Most of the deaths occurred late last month in <LOCATION>Bihar</LOCATION> state, next
to <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>'s Uttar Pradesh state, as bricks for the temple were
borne by Hindu processions to this dusty town on the <LOCATION>Saryu River</LOCATION>.
   There have been no reports of deaths in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, and there was
no sign of violence in the town of 35,000 on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>
case has become a major campaign issue for Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv
Gandhi</PERSON> as he seeks to return his <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> to power in
elections that will be conducted <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE>, 24 and 26.
   But neither he nor the man trying to replace him, <PERSON>Vishwanath
Pratap Singh</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> coalition, has offered a
solution. They are fearful of alienating the vote of Hindus, who
make up <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 milliion people, although Hindus
traditionally have voted for secular parties. The candidates also
want the Moslem vote, which usually has gone heavily to the
<ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION>.
   Singh had planned to visit <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to cool religious
tensions, but changed his plans and made a short stop in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION>,
about four miles away.
   In <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Singh</PERSON> said the Hindu-Moslem dispute over the
<LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> site ``cannot be decided by the courts.'' He declined to
say how it should be decided.
   The question of proprietorship at <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> has been dragging
through the courts for four decades.
   So far the only thing legally clear is that the initial
foundation for the new temple is slated for a 25-foot-by-23-foot
plot owned by a Hindu. This tiny plot could hold little more than
the front steps of the proposed temple.
   The rest of the envisoned two-story, three-domed structure would
engulf land whose ownership is under dispute, including the <DATE>17th
century</DATE> mosque.
   ``We will not break down this structure,'' said <PERSON>Ashok Singhal</PERSON>,
referring to the the building Moslems call the Babri Masjid, or
<ORGANIZATION>Mosque of Babar</ORGANIZATION>. Hindus call it the <LOCATION>Ram Janambhoomi</LOCATION>, or <ORGANIZATION>Ram</ORGANIZATION>'s
birthplace.
   ``It can be lifted _ honorably lifted _ and moved, so this
mosque, if it is a mosque, is not destroyed,'' said <PERSON>Singhal</PERSON>, a
senior trustee of the committee to build the new Hindu temple.
   <PERSON>Singhal</PERSON> said he hoped to make such an attempt and begin
contruction within a month, leaving the impression that it would be
deferred until after a new government is chosen.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901101-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-01-90 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India Bjt   11-01 0622</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India, Bjt,0766</SECOND>
<HEAD>Death Toll in Nine Days of Religious Riots Tops 200</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaaserPhoto AYO1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Religious riots sparked by Hindu
fundamentalists' attempt to seize a Moslem mosque intensified
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>, and the death toll in nine days of clashes rose to more
than 200.
   News agencies and officials reported at least 31 people died
across the country on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. They were killed in battles between
Hindus and Moslems or when police fired on mobs or when victims
died in hospitals of injuries suffered in earlier riots.
   At least 210 people have died since <DATE>Oct. 24</DATE>, when the fighting
began.
   Most of the deaths were in <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh</LOCATION>, the state where the
disputed shrine is located, and in <LOCATION>Gujarat</LOCATION> state. Both states have
a history of sectarian clashes and simmering tensions between
Hindus and Moslems.
   Uttar Pradesh is <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s most populous state. At least <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT> of its 120 million people are Moslems. Violence has erupted
in 22 of its 63 districts, according to police officials in
<LOCATION>Lucknow</LOCATION>, the state capital.
   The disput has also caused riots in neighboring <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>, an
Islamic nation, where Moslem mobs attacked temples and Hindu shops
and homes after hearing of the violence in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   At least one person was killed in <LOCATION>Dhaka</LOCATION>, which is under curfew
along with the port city of <LOCATION>Chittagong</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, site of the disputed mosque, the bodies of three
Hindus were found <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in the <LOCATION>Saryu River</LOCATION>.
   The victims were apparently killed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> when police opened
fire to throw back Hindus who stormed the mosque, residents said.
At least seven people are previously known to have died in the
police action.
   The discovery of the bodies led to the deployment of extra
government troops around the dusty temple town and forced Hindu
groups to postpone a fresh attempt to storm the mosque.
   But members of the fundamentalist <ORGANIZATION>World Hindu Council</ORGANIZATION> vowed to
continue their efforts to take over the disputed site. <PERSON>Ashok
Singhal</PERSON>, the council's general secretary, told a public meeting
outside <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> his group would not give up its campaign to replace
the mosque with a temple.
   Singhal is wanted by the police. His appearance at a
well-publicized meeting attended by thousands of people lent
credence to reports that many police officers are sympathetic to
the Hindu movement.
   ``There is no power on earth which can stop us from building the
temple,'' <PERSON>Singhal</PERSON> told the crowd. ``There is no place for Islam in
our nation.''
   Singhal, who wore a bandage around his head, sustained injuries
during <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s attack on the temple. He later slipped away from
the hospital where he was treated.
   The <ORGANIZATION>World Hindu Council</ORGANIZATION> says the 460-year-old Babri mosque is
built over the birthplace of <ORGANIZATION>Lord Rama</ORGANIZATION>, one of the most revered
Hindu gods.
   At least 900 people were killed in Hindu-Moslem violence last
year when the group first announced its intention to take over the
site by force.
   The dispute has threatened to bring down Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P.
Singh</PERSON>'s 11-month-old government. A pro-Hindu party, which had
supported the government coalition, withdrew its backing two weeks
ago when its president was arrested while leading a march to drum
up support for the temple construction.
   In another political development <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> of
former Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON> supported the government of
<PERSON>Chimanbhai Patel</PERSON>, a member of <ORGANIZATION>Singh's National Front</ORGANIZATION> coalition, in
a vote of confidence in the <LOCATION>Gujarat</LOCATION> state assembly.
   Patel's government had been reduced to a minority after the
Hindu right-wing <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata Party</ORGANIZATION> withdrew support in line
with its decision to jettison the <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> coalition in the
federal Parliament.
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> leaders in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> defended the decision by
saying they were willing to support the <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> - but not
Singh. They have said the party will oppose Singh in the <DATE>Nov. 7</DATE>
confidence vote - but could support a <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> government if
Singh were replaced as prime minister.
   Political commentators and newspapers have attacked <PERSON>Singh</PERSON> for
what they call his vacillation on the temple-mosque dispute, saying
it is the greatest threat to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s political system since the
country became independent in <DATE>1947</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is predominantly Hindu and all its prime ministers have
belonged to the majority community, but tolerance of all religions
and secularism is a part of its constitution.
   Hindus make up <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people and
Moslems comprise <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of the population. The others include
Sikhs, Christians and Buddhists.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901207-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-07-90 1619EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India     12-07 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India,0431</SECOND>
<HEAD>Violence Between Hindus and Moslems in Southern India</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Violence between Hindus and Moslems broke
out in southern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE> and at least 16 people were killed in
stabbings, news reports said. Four others were killed elsewhere in
the nation.
   Authorities clamped an indefinite curfew on the southern town,
<LOCATION>Hyderabad</LOCATION>, confining people to their homes. Press Trust of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>
said the violence started in the <TIME>morning</TIME> and continued throughout
the day despite the curfew.
   Fighting between followers of the two faiths also erupted in
<LOCATION>northern Aligarh</LOCATION>, where at least three people were killed and 12
injured, Press Trust reported. A curfew was also imposed in
<LOCATION>Aligarh</LOCATION>, it said.
   And in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, the flashpoint of a lingering dispute between
the religious groups, a Moslem man was burned to death after Hindu
fundamentalists accused him of trying to disrupt their campaign to
replace a mosque with a temple.
   The identities of victims were not given. Indian news media do
not identify the victims or perpetrators of sectarian violence for
fear it might exacerbate tensions.
   At least 380 people have died in Hindu-Moslem violence in the
last two months since Hindu fundamentalists announced plans to pull
down a disputed mosque in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> and replace it with a temple.
   At least 22 people were killed when police opened fire on Hindu
militants attempting to storm the mosque on <DATE>Oct. 30</DATE> and again on
<DATE>Nov. 2</DATE>.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the militants resumed their campaign to storm the
temple. But they did not resist when police blocked them from
reaching the disputed shrine, apparently because of an
understanding the event would be more symbolic than real.
   The religious crisis ignited by the Hindu campaign brought down
the government of former Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON> last month.
fundamentalist party withdrew support over the prime minister's
<LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> policy.
   Singh was replaced <DATE>Nov. 10</DATE> by <PERSON>Chandra Shekhar</PERSON>, who has said he
will attempt to defuse the issue by holding talks with Moslem and
Hindu leaders. The talks began in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> earlier this week but
have made no real progress.
   The dispute over the mosque has lingered for more than 100
years. Hindus say Moslem invaders built the small mosque atop a
temple marking the birthplace of <ORGANIZATION>Rama</ORGANIZATION>, a Hindu god. Moslems say it
is impossible to say where Rama was born.
   Hindus comprise <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people.
Moslems make up <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901208-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-08-90 1414EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Violence     12-08 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Violence,0406</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hindu, Moslems Clash in Two Towns</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hindus and Moslems clashed in a central
city <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, and news reports said at least seven people died,
including four passengers dragged from a train by a mob.
   The clashes in <LOCATION>Aligarh</LOCATION>, 80 miles southeast of <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, forced
the city adminstration to call for army reinforcements and impose
an indefinite curfew, <ORGANIZATION>United News of India</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Fighting also broke out in the southern city of <LOCATION>Hyderabad</LOCATION>, and
<ORGANIZATION>UNI</ORGANIZATION> said one person was slain.
   At least 380 people have been killed in Hindu-Moslem violence in
the last two months after Hindu fundamentalists announced plans to
take over a mosque and replace it with a temple.
   The deaths in <LOCATION>Aligarh</LOCATION> brought the total number of people killed
in sectarian violence in the city since <DATE>Friday</DATE> to at least 16,
Press Trust of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>UNI</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The news agencies did not name the victims. Indian media
prohibit identification of victims or the perpetrators of sectarian
violence for fear that it will exacerbate further tensions.
   UNI said the city adminstration called the army to help the
police and imposed an indefinite curfew restricting people to their
homes. It was not immediately known what caused the clashes.
   Among the victims were four passengers of a train who were
dragged out and killed by a mob, <ORGANIZATION>UNI</ORGANIZATION> said.
   In the Hindu temple town of <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, the flashpoint of a
lingering dispute between <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s Hindu majority and Moslem
minority, at least 1,200 Hindu fundamentalists allowed themselves
to be arrested on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> as part of a campaign to replace the
disputed mosque with a temple.
   ``Courting'' arrest is a traditional form of protest in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
Hundreds, sometimes thousands, of people are detained for few hours
and then released without charges.
   The religious crisis ignited by the Hindu campaign also
triggered the downfall of previous Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>'s
government.
   Singh was replaced <DATE>Nov. 10</DATE> by <PERSON>Chandra Shekhar</PERSON>, who has said he
will attempt to defuse the issue by holding talks with religious
leaders. The talks have made no real progress.
   Hindus say Moslem invaders built the small mosque atop a temple
marking the birthplace of the Hindu god <ORGANIZATION>Rama</ORGANIZATION>. Moslems say it is
impossible to pinpoint where Rama was born.
   Hindus make up <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people. Moslems
comprise <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1628EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Hindus     10-14 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Hindus,0535</SECOND>
<HEAD>Procession to Support Building of Temple Reaches Delhi</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A procession of Hindu conservatives
arrived in the capital <DATE>Sunday</DATE> on a 6,000-mile pilgrimage to promote
the building of a temple on a site claimed by Moslems and now
occupied by a mosque.
   Tens of thousands of supporters cheered the two-mile-long
procession as it reached the capital 20 days after setting out from
the western city of <LOCATION>Somnath</LOCATION>.
   The procession was led by <PERSON>Lal Krishna Advani</PERSON>, leader of the
<ORGANIZATION>Indian People's Party</ORGANIZATION>, who rode in a <ORGANIZATION>Toyota</ORGANIZATION> pick-up converted to
look like a chariot used in festivals to carry Hindu idols.
   The pilgrimage was on a roundabout route to the holy town of
<LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, 300 miles southeast of <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> and home to the disputed
site. Hindus revere <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> as the birthplace of <ORGANIZATION>Lord Rama</ORGANIZATION>, an
important Hindu god.
   Hindu fundamentalists want to tear down the mosque they claim
replaced a temple destroyed in the <DATE>16th century</DATE> by Moghul
conquerers. Moslem leaders dispute the claim and refuse to vacate
the site. Neither side will compromise.
   ``Never in the 40 years of my political life have I seen such
vast popular support for an issue,'' <PERSON>Advani</PERSON> told Press Trust of
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   News agencies said police put dozens of <PERSON>Advani</PERSON>'s supporters
under preventative detention in towns along the route, apparently
fearing Moslem-Hindu clashes.
   Earlier, police used truncheons to clear a path for the
procession through a crowd of 200 people protesting a new
government policy that would reserve half of federal jobs for
lower-caste Hindus, suppressed for centuries.
   There are 17 million unemployed educated youths, many of them
from the upper castes. The new policy, over which more than 60
students have committed suicide, has overshadowed the deeper
problem between the two religious communities.
   While <PERSON>Advani</PERSON> prepared for a rally, expected to draw more than
100,000 supporters, <ORGANIZATION>People's Party</ORGANIZATION> activists drove through the city
on trucks garlanded with marigolds, blaring a message that ``the
temple will be built.''
   The dispute is also laced with politics, piting not only Hindus
against Moslems, but Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON> against <ORGANIZATION>Advani's
People's Party</ORGANIZATION>, which provides crucial support to keep the minority
government in power.
   The fundamentalists say they will tear down the mosque and begin
building the new Ram temple on <DATE>Oct. 30</DATE>, with or without permission.
The Uttar Pradesh local government has said it will not allow
<PERSON>Advani</PERSON>'s procession into the state.
   Singh has urged restraint until a court rules on petitions
submitted by both sides. Advani has said, however, it was not a
matter for the courts to settle.
   Advani has said the <ORGANIZATION>People's Party</ORGANIZATION> will decide in <DATE>November</DATE>
whether it will continue to support <PERSON>Singh</PERSON>'s coalition, implying the
temple issue may determine its stand. A withdrawal of support could
lead to an election next year.
   Hindus comprise <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people.
   Critics say mounting tensions fueled by the procession through
eight Indian states were responsible for two outbursts of violence
between Hindus and Moslems over the <DATE>last two weeks</DATE> in which at
least 80 people died.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891110-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-10-89 0943EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-India-ReligiousDispute     11-10 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India-Religious Dispute,0561</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslems Protest, Hindus Rejoice over Disputed Shrine Site</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EARLEEN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FAIZABAD, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities arrested about 1,000 Moslems
today when they tried to march to the nearby town of <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, where
triumphal Hindus celebrated the building of a new temple on a site
claimed by both religions.
   The Moslem protest was peaceful, but one of its leaders who was
arrested, <PERSON>Zafaryab Jilani</PERSON>, warned: ``When all these methods fail,
arms are taken up. The next generation may not listen to peaceful
protest.''
   At least 290 people have been killed in Hindu-Moslem violence in
three Indian states since <DATE>August</DATE>, when plans for the new temple
were announced. So far the violence has not spread to <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION>, 330 miles southeast of the capital <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>.
   The demonstrators in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION> accused Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv
Gandhi</PERSON> and his <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> of caving in to Hindu fundamentalists
in a bid for votes from the Hindu majority in national elections
less than two weeks away.
   ``If this ruling <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> is ousted from power, perhaps
secular government can be saved,'' said <PERSON>Jilani</PERSON>, a senior leader of
the <ORGANIZATION>All India Babri Masjid Action Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   Babri Masjid, or the <ORGANIZATION>Mosque of Babar</ORGANIZATION>, was built in the <DATE>17th
century</DATE> in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> on the spot where Hindu fundamentalists claim
one of their most popular gods, <LOCATION>Lord Ram</LOCATION>, was born.
   About 90 minutes after the Moslems were arrested in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION>, a
frenzied mob of Hindu worshipers celebrated the placing of the
foundation stone of a new temple to <ORGANIZATION>Ram</ORGANIZATION> about 120 feet from the
Babri Masjid. They flung marigold petals into a 6-foot hole where
their leaders reverently placed a pile of bricks and a cornerstone.
   Police wearing helmets and chest protectors struggled to keep
from falling into the pit as at least 5,000 pilgrims pushed into
the small hilltop enclave in less than an hour.
   The Hindu-Moslem dispute over the <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> hilltop is centuries
old, but the the current furor centers on who owns the land where
the foundation is being laid for a new Hindu temple. Hindus and
Moslems had agreed that one tiny plot that was to hold the
foundation stone was owned by a Hindu.
   The rest of the land needed to complete the new Ram temple is
disputed.
   While the Moslems opposed the construction of the new temple,
they agreed they could not prevent its foundation stone from being
placed on the little plot owned by a Hindu.
   So far the courts in <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh state</LOCATION>, where the government
is headed by <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION>, have declined to rule who
actually owns the property.
   The demonstrators in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION> vowed today to turn the Moslem
votes away from <LOCATION>Gandhi</LOCATION> in national elections scheduled <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE>, 24
and 26.
   ``After today, Moslems will not vote for <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>,'' said
<PERSON>Mohammad Azam Khan</PERSON>, an Uttar Pradesh state legislator from the
opposition <ORGANIZATION>Janata Party</ORGANIZATION>, or <ORGANIZATION>People's Party</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hindus make up about <PERCENT>83 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people.
While Moslems make up <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> of the population, they have voted
heavily for the <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> since <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> became independent from
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE>.
   With <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> facing a tough challenge this month from <PERSON>Vishwanath
Pratap Singh</PERSON>, leader of the <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> coalition, the Moslem
vote could be pivotal.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1627EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India     10-28 0521</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India,0630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Security Forces Seal Moslem Shrine, Arrest Thousands</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AYO2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police arrested thousands more Hindu
pilgrims <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, including a member of a Hindu royal family, in an
attempt to avoid more bloodshed in a dispute over a Moslem shrine
in this town.
   The Hindu-Moslem conflict over the shrine claimed at least 96
lives in rioting last week and has jeopardized Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P.
Singh</PERSON>'s government.
   More than 60,000 people were arrested by <DATE>Saturday</DATE> as troops
sealed off <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> and the borders of Uttar Pradesh state from a
swarm of Hindu pilgrims.
   Police gave no figure for the number of arrests <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, but
Press Trust of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>United News of India</ORGANIZATION> said 15,000 were
detained at one southern border crossing.
   Among them was <PERSON>Vijaya Raje Scindia</PERSON>, vice president of the
right-wing Hindu party Bharatiya Janata. She was the maharani, or
princess, of <LOCATION>Gwalior</LOCATION> before <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> abolished princely states 20
years ago.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Scindia</PERSON> was arrested on charges of ``violating a
prohibitory order,'' <ORGANIZATION>United News</ORGANIZATION> reported. The state government had
banned the leaders of several Hindu fundamentalist groups from the
state.
   The news agencies said 300 truckloads of Hindu pilgrims
accompanying <PERSON>Mrs. Scindia</PERSON> were driven to temporary jails in schools
and public areas around the state. Twelve members of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>
also were detained by police forming a security net around the
shrine.
   ``It's like a war zone. Not even an ant can get past us,'' said
one police officer protecting the shrine.
   The controversy is centered on a 16th century mosque, the Babri
Masjid, in this town of 40,000 people about 300 miles southeast of
<LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>.
   Hindu fundamentalists say the mosque stands on the birthplace of
the god Rama. They say they will replace the structure with a
temple and have set <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for beginning construction.
   The government, saying it is obliged to defend minority
interests, has pledged not to allow the mosque to be displaced
until the courts decide the issue.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata Party</ORGANIZATION> withdrew support from <ORGANIZATION>Singh's
National Front</ORGANIZATION> coalition <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Singh's minority government
depended on the Hindu party and the Communist-led Left Front for
its survival.
   A <ORGANIZATION>United News</ORGANIZATION> report quoted <PERSON>Singh</PERSON> as saying <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that the
Hindu party was trying to ``usurp power, even at the cost of
communal conflagration and the country's unity.''
   Singh must face a vote of confidence in <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> on <DATE>Nov. 7</DATE>.
The Bharatiya Janata and the opposition <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> party have said
they will vote against <ORGANIZATION>Singh</ORGANIZATION>, which virtually assures his defeat.
   Elections are likely early next year.
   ``The (political) matter is closed. It is with the security
forces now, and they will do their duty,'' said the police official
at a barricade on the road to Aydohya. Heavily armed policemen
manned the barrier.
   All entry points to <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> in a 60-mile radius are blocked by
barricades, he said. The national railway suspended service through
the state.
   About 200,000 policemen and paramilitary forces have fanned
across the state. In Ayodya, an indefinite curfew imposed <DATE>Friday</DATE>
was lifted for just two hours <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>.
   Officials refuse to say how many policemen are deployed around
the shrine, but some officers said the figure was about 20,000.
Policemen lounged in the shade of narrow lanes leading to the
shrine, playing with monkeys who inhabit the area.
   Moslems comprise <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of the 120 million people in <LOCATION>Uttar
Pradesh</LOCATION>.
   Though Moslems are only <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million
people, they live in almost every Indian state. Hindus are <PERCENT>82
percent</PERCENT> of the population.
   Religious tensions between Hindus and Moslems erupt
periodically, and dozens of people are killed in clashes every
year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891110-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-10-89 1259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Shrine     11-10 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Shrine,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslems Protest, Hindus Celebrate Over Shrine Site</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EARLEEN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FAIZABAD, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police arrested 1,000 Moslem protesters
<DATE>Friday</DATE> who tried to march to nearby <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, where celebrating
Hindus laid the foundation stone of a new temple at a site claimed
by both religions.
   The Moslem demonstration was peaceful, but <PERSON>Zafaryab Jilani</PERSON>, one
of its leaders, declared: ``When all these methods fail, arms are
taken up. The next generation may not listen to peaceful protest.''
   At least 290 people have been killed in Hindu-Moslem violence in
three Indian states since plans for the temple were announced in
<DATE>August</DATE>. No violence has been reported in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>.
   Protest leaders in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION> accused Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON>
and his <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> of giving in to Hindu fundamentalists in a
quest for Hindu votes in national elections set for <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE>, 24 an
26.
   ``If this ruling <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> is ousted from power, perhaps
secular government can be saved,'' said <PERSON>Jilani</PERSON>, a senior leader of
the <ORGANIZATION>All-India Babri Masjid Action Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   Babri Masjid, the <ORGANIZATION>Mosque of Babar</ORGANIZATION>, was built in the <DATE>17th century</DATE>
on the spot in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> where Hindu fundamentalists claim one of
their most popular gods, <LOCATION>Lord Ram</LOCATION>, was born.
   About 90 minutes after the arrests in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION>, Hindus
celebrated the laying of the foundation stone of a new Ram temple
130 feet from the <ORGANIZATION>Babar Mosque</ORGANIZATION>. They flung marigold petals into a
6-foot-deep hole in which their leaders reverently placed bricks
and the stone.
   Police wearing helmets and chest protectors struggled to keep
from falling into the pit as at least 5,000 pilgrims pushed into
the small, hilltop enclave in less than an hour.
   The dispute over the <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> hilltop in <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh</LOCATION> state is
centuries old and the current chapter began on a night in <DATE>1949</DATE>,
when a Ram idol was spirited into the mosque. A court ordered the
mosque closed to people of both faiths in an effort to prevent
religious strife.
   In <DATE>1986</DATE>, another court order opened the <ORGANIZATION>Babar Mosque</ORGANIZATION>, but only
to Hindus. That decision prompted riots across <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in which at
least 200 people died.
   Currently, the argument centers on who owns the land where the
foundation is being laid. Hindus and Moslems agree the small plot
intended for the stone is owned by a Hindu, but the rest of the
landed needed for the temple remains in dispute.
   Although Moslems opposed construction of the temple, they agreed
they could not prevent the stone from being laid in the plot owned
by a Hindu.
   Late <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, however, Moslem activists contended the
foundation site was spilling over to property they claim is Moslem.
   Courts in <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh state</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION>
controls the government, have declined to rule who owns the
property.
   ``After today, Moslems will not vote for <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>,'' <PERSON>Mohammad
Azam Khan</PERSON>, an Uttar Pradesh state legislator from the opposition
<ORGANIZATION>Janata Party</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Azam, like <PERSON>Jilani</PERSON>, is a convenor _ a sort of senior organizer _
of the <ORGANIZATION>Babri Masjid Action Committee</ORGANIZATION>. Both were among those
arrested in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION>.
   The arrests were part of a uniquely Indian form of peaceful
protest in which people do something they know police will not
allow, such as marching to <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, thus inviting arrest. The
police oblige by rounding them up, generally with little or no
force.
   In <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION>, the Moslems and at least 40 Hindu sympathizers
climbed willingly into freight-hauling trucks and waved as they
were driven to a police compound on the outskirts.
   At the compound, they sat on the ground listening to leaders
exhort them to preserve <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as a secular state and vote <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>
and his party out of office.
   Moslems, who make up <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people,
have given the <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> strong support since <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
independence from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE>. Gandhi faces a tough challenge
from <PERSON>Vishwanath Pratap Singh</PERSON>, leader of the <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION>
coalition, and the Moslem vote could be pivotal.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901031-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-31-90 0715EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-India 1stLd-Writethru   10-31 0554</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0484,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven More Dead, Troops Guard Holy Site, Unrest Spreads To
Bangladesh</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with seven dead today, week's
death toll at 158. ADDS details of Bangladesh violence. Picks up
9th graf. `Police imposed...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DEL2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hindus and Moslems fought with knives and
guns in scattered violence today, leaving at least seven more
people dead, and more troops were sent to guard a disputed holy
site in this northeastern city.
   The dispute over the site has pushed the government to the brink
of collapse and violence stemming from it has left at least 158
people dead in the past week. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, the violence spread
to neighboring <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>.
   Troops killed five people and wounded at least 20 in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> when thousands of Hindu militants broke through police
barricades and forced their way to a 460-year-old mosque they want
to replace with a Hindu temple.
   Hindu fundamentalists had vowed to start construction <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> on
a temple to the <ORGANIZATION>Hindu god Rama</ORGANIZATION> on the site, which they revere as
the god's birthplace.
   The fundamentalists say the mosque should be razed to make way
for a Hindu temple in this holy town 300 miles southeast of <LOCATION>New
Delhi</LOCATION>. Hindus make up <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s population. Moslems
comprise <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
   At least 45 people died in street battles <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and today in
six states, mostly in cities with large Moslem minorities, as the
decades-old Hindu-Moslem dispute over the ownership of the site
came to a head.
   One Hindu man committed suicide <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in protest.
   Today's deaths, from stabbings and shootings, occurred in what
Indian news agencies described as mob violence in four widely
separated cities in western and southern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Indian news reports
do not identify victims or give many details, in the belief that
doing so would aggravate tensions.
   In <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>, gangs of Moslems armed with knives or clubs
attacked at least 11 Hindu temples and smashed idols in the
southern port of <LOCATION>Chittagong</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night to protest the <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>
episode. Hundreds of Hindu homes and shops were burned, but no
injuries were reported.
   Police imposed a curfew on the city at dawn today. No injuries
or arrests were reported.
   The <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> dispute has has brought Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>'s
government to the verge of collapse.
   Authorities deployed additional troops around the disputed
shrine today and blocked the bridge across the sacred <LOCATION>Saryu River</LOCATION>,
where 6,000 Hindus had gathered..
   The devotees sat in the fields opposite the town and sang hymns,
and the anger of the previous day seemed to have eased.
   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s widespread violence prompted Singh to renew an offer
to resign. Singh's 11-month-old coalition lost its majority in
<LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> last week when an allied right-wing Hindu party withdrew
support over the temple issue.
   Singh has been under mounting pressure from dissidents in his
party to quit. He faces a parliamentary vote of no-confidence on
<DATE>Nov. 7</DATE>, and his letter offering to step down seemed to presuppose
that the government will lose.
   ``All energies should be directed to diffuse the situation and
maintain communal harmony. It is in the pursuit of these goals that
we have sacrificed a whole government,'' he wrote to the president
of his <ORGANIZATION>Janata Dal</ORGANIZATION> party.
   ``My conscience is clear that I have sacrificed the highest
office for the cause of unity of the country and the oppressed,''
he wrote.
   The letter was dismissed by the <ORGANIZATION>Janata Dal</ORGANIZATION> dissidents as an
attempt by Singh to rally his supporters. The party is to meet
early next week to decide the leadership question.
   Most political analysts predict elections within a few months
and a possible return to government by former Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv
Gandhi</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION>, which governed <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> for all but four of
its 43 years of independence.
   At least 900 people were killed in Hindu-Moslem violence last
year after the Hindu group announced its plans to replace the
mosque with a temple.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901019-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-19-90 2055EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Temple     10-19 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Temple,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Proposes Plan to Freeze Hindu-Moslem Dispute</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government, trying to defuse a
Hindu-Moslem dispute that has claimed scores of lives, proposed
<DATE>Friday</DATE> to allow Hindus to build a temple at a sacred site without
destroying a mosque already there.
   But Hindu traditionalists rejected the plan, which was unveiled
at the end of a frantic day of meetings and two sessions of Prime
Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>'s Cabinet.
   Singh's government is under threat of collapse if no solution to
the conflict is found by the end of the month.
   The dispute concerns a 16th century mosque in the holy town of
<LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>. Hindus say it was built on the foundations of a temple
over the traditional birthplace of the Hindu god <ORGANIZATION>Rama</ORGANIZATION>.
   A fundamentalist group, the <ORGANIZATION>Hindu World Council</ORGANIZATION>, has vowed to
begin rebuilding the temple on <DATE>Oct. 30</DATE>. Moslems have said they
won't let that happen.
   Officials fear a bloodbath unless a settlement is found. Riots
between the two religious communities have claimed thousands of
lives over the decades, and violence over <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> left more than 80
people dead earlier in the month.
   The secretary of the Hindu group, <PERSON>Ashok Singhal</PERSON>, said the
government plan was unacceptable because it left the mosque in
place.
   The government has said it will not allow the mosque to be
displaced, and has urged all sides to await the decision of the
courts on dozens of petitions.
   Police and paramilitary forces have sealed off <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, 300
miles east of <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, and about 5,000 Hindu politicians and
activists have been detained.
   Information Minister <PERSON>Parvatheneni Upendra</PERSON> said the prime
minister's plan calls for the government to acquire properties
around the disputed site. Land would be made available for the
construction of a temple, while cases pending before a local court
could be transfered to the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> for quick handling.
Meanwhile, the mosque would stay.
   <PERSON>Upendra</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata</ORGANIZATION>, a right-wing Hindu party that
is a key government ally, had indicated it might support the prime
minister's plan. But a Bharatiya Janata leader denied that.
   ``It seems the government is more keen to assuage the sentiments
and protect the interests of the Moslem community with disregard to
the sentiments of tens of millions of the overwhelming majority,''
said party secretary <PERSON>J.P. Mathur</PERSON>.
   Lal <PERSON>Krishna Advani</PERSON>, head of Bharatiya Janata, has been leading a
6,000-mile pilgrimage to rally public opinion for the temple. Army
troops were deployed along the route of his caravan.
   Hindus comprise <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million people, while
Moslems make up <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of the population.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891104-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-04-89 1123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SacredCause     11-04 0772</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sacred Cause,0792</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hindu-Moslem Conflict: A Road Paved with Death, Bricks, Politics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EARLEEN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Swearing devotion to the Hindu god Ram
and a willingness to die for their beliefs, hundreds of young men
set out <DATE>Saturday</DATE> with sanctified bricks on a mission that has
spurred Hindu-Moslem riots and caused at least 280 deaths.
   Their destination is <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, 325 miles to the southeast, where
plans for a new Hindu temple have propelled religious strife to the
forefront of Prime Minister <PERSON>Rajiv Gandhi</PERSON>'s battle for re-election.
   From the width and depth of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, convoys of trucks and buses
are heading to <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> in the heart of <LOCATION>Uttar Pradesh</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s most
populous state and a bellwether in elections. In their wake,
Moslems and Hindus have shot, stabbed and burned each other to
death.
   ``To put up the bricks for the Hindus, this is important,'' said
<PERSON>Rajesh Kumar</PERSON>, a 19-year-old English student who joined the
procession of seven buses and at least four trucks that left <LOCATION>New
Delhi</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   ``The name of the god Ram is enough to defend ourselves,'' he
said, then patted a holster containing a brass trident with sharp
spears. ``The blade is less than 4 inches, so it's legally
permitted,'' he said with a grin. ``This is just a symbol, not a
weapon.''
   Some of the young men carried sabers and hockey sticks, which
older organizers hastened to describe as religious symbols or
evidence of youthful sportsmanship.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, ardent Hindus plan to lay the foundation for a new
temple to <ORGANIZATION>Lord Ram</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> next to a disputed shrine claimed by
both Moslems and Hindus.
   Vishwa Hindu Parishad, the fundamentalist group behind the
temple drive, says it has gathered bricks from more than 375,000
cities and towns throughout <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and from Hindus in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Western Europe</LOCATION>. After being blessed by Hindu holy
men, the bricks are borne by believers and festooned with bright
red and orange satin and chiffon, tied up with tinsel and garlanded
with marigolds.
   This joyous celebration of religious right has left a trail of
death in villages where Hindus and Moslems have lived side by side
for centuries.
   Hindu-Moslem clashes are particularly worrisome now.
   With national elections barely three weeks away, both <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON> and
opposition leader <PERSON>Vishwanath Pratap Singh</PERSON> have been urging
religious harmony while at the same time trying not to alienate the
Hindu fundamentalist vote or the potentially pivotal vote of
Moslems, who make up <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> of the population. Hindus account
for <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT>.
   Gandhi officially launched his campaign <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Faizabad</LOCATION>, four
miles down the road from <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, with an accusation that unnamed
opposition parties were ``fanning communal feelings for their
vested political interests.''
   ``Communalism'' is the catchword Indian politicians and news
media use for religious strife in an effort to avoid singling out
specific faiths or being perceived as taking sides.
   Back in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, Singh of the opposition <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION>
coalition was accusing <PERSON>Gandhi</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Congress Party</ORGANIZATION> of trying to turn
<LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> into ``a flashpoint'' of communal violence.
   Many participants in <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s send-off of the convoy said they
would vote for the <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata Party</ORGANIZATION>. This right-wing Hindu
party is not a member of the <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> but has been making
deals with the front for a share of the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> seats to be
determined in the elections being conducted <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE>, 24 and 26.
   The young men making the trip, as well as older ones encouraging
them, vowed that the journey would be peaceful unless ``the
Mohammedans'' started something or the government failed to
maintain order.
   In late <DATE>October</DATE>, similar ``Ram shila,'' or Ram brick,
processions precipitated several days of Hindu-Moslem clashes in
<LOCATION>Bihar</LOCATION> state. At least 201 people died by official count, which does
not specify the victims' religions.
   Indian newspapers have given indications that many, perhaps
most, of the victims were Moslems. When the dead and wounded have
been identified, the names have usually been Islamic.
   In addition to the <DATE>October</DATE> deaths, about 80 other people have
been killed in <LOCATION>Bihar</LOCATION> and four other states since <DATE>August</DATE> when plans
were announced to build the temple at <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, revered by Hindus as
<ORGANIZATION>Ram</ORGANIZATION>'s birthplace.
   The <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> convoy of trucks and buses, with their load of
5,045 bricks and about 300 men, is to pass through towns with
sizeable Moslem populations.
   ``What can we say about trouble?'' asked <PERSON>R.K. Mathur</PERSON>, a
40-year-old music teacher attired in blue denim jeans and jacket.
``We are going on our mission.''
   <PERSON>Manesh Gupta</PERSON>, a 19-year-old photographer, added: ``If we die, it
is no problem _ <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT>, no problem.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880222-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-22-88 0024EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Byways-TempleTown     02-22 0665</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Byways-Temple Town,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>WORLD BYWAYS: Temple Town _ An Indian Oasis of Tranquility</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP Extra
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ This is one of a series of occasional reports by
Associated Press correspondents on life and customs in the byways
of the world.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SEEMA SIROHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PUSHKAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This town of cobblestone streets and
sparkling white houses is a long way from anywhere in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, but
millions cross a desert every year to get to it and wash away their
sins in its holy lake.
who seek out its tranquility.
   Its beginnings lie with <PERSON>Lord Brahma</PERSON>, the creator of the universe
in Hindu mythology. Hindu texts have it that when <PERSON>Brahma</PERSON> was
seeking a place for a holy ceremony, he chose Pushkar.
   He dropped a lotus from his hand and water spouted from the
desert to form a lake, according to the texts that date from the
8th century B.C.
   In these modern times, as the sun rises, Hindu pilgrims chant
mantras and take a dip in <LOCATION>Pushkar Lake</LOCATION>, believing all their sins
will be washed away by the holy waters.
   Europeans and Americans often are seen by the lake, sharing the
religious experience. They feed grain to pigeons and sweets to
long-tailed monkeys who scramble across the pinnacles of the town's
400 temples where ascetics, Hindu monks and other holy men gather.
   Pushkar, a town of 9,000 people, is an oasis of tranquility, far
removed from the bustling cities and teeming slums of <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New
Delhi</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Calcutta</LOCATION>.
   The blazing sun soaks into everything.
   It was the sacred month of <PERSON>Kartik</PERSON>, signifying the onset of
winter, when <PERSON>Lord Brahma</PERSON> is said to have dropped his lotus blossom.
   Brahma, foremost in the Hindu trinity of supreme gods, had been
looking for a suitable site to perform a major religious ceremony.
   But his wife, <PERSON>Savitri</PERSON>, could not attend the ritual. Angered, she
decreed that henceforth Brahma would be worshiped at only one place.
   Pushkar became the sole earthly home of the peaceful god of
creation, while millions of shrines were erected across <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to
<ORGANIZATION>Lord Shiva</ORGANIZATION> the destroyer and to ferocious goddesses like Kali and
Durga who are often depicted as fire-spitting images carrying heads
of evil men they had slain in battle.
   But this oasis in the desert emerged as a major holy town for
the Hindus, almost equal in importance to <ORGANIZATION>Benaras</ORGANIZATION>, the ``eternal
city.'' Hindus believe that one goes to heaven if one dies in
<ORGANIZATION>Benaras</ORGANIZATION>.
   Pilgrims come by the thousands to <ORGANIZATION>Pushkar</ORGANIZATION>, 250 miles southwest
of <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, to bathe in the lake and revive the memory of
<LOCATION>Brahma</LOCATION>'s majestic rite every year on <PERSON>Kartik Poornima</PERSON>, the full moon
night in the month of <DATE>November</DATE>.
   Shielded by <ORGANIZATION>Nag Pahar</ORGANIZATION>, or <ORGANIZATION>Serpent Mountain</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Pushkar</ORGANIZATION> has <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
_ and perhaps the world's _ only temple to <LOCATION>Brahma</LOCATION>.
   The town centers on the lake, where there are several steps for
bathing. Signs warn foreigners ``not to wear shorts and other
revealing clothes, not to smoke, drink near the lake or take
photographs, not to kiss, embrace or indulge in other irreverent
acts.''
   The steps, called ghats, are controlled by vigilant and
aggressive brahmin priests, who preside over religious ceremonies,
armed with horoscopes. They watch every pilgrim approaching the
lake and pounce on potential clients.
   Each visit is recorded in their bulky, cloth-covered books. A
priest can easily tell a devotee when his grandfather visited
Pushkar by referring to the dog-eared notebooks.
   Displeasing a priest can be unpleasant. He will pronounce curses
on one's entire family, naming all _ the grandfather, father and
sons.
   From the lake, the steps lead up to the main street, a favorite
shopping center with the tourists. The shops are stacked with
exotic handicrafts, peasant skirts and other clothes native to this
part of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Velvet shirts and pajamas, musts for low-budget
travelers, hang in vibrant displays.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901030-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-30-90 1455EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India 1stLd-Writethru a0600 10-30 0729</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0600,0900</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Forces Fire on Hindus, Killing 5, Wounding 20</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 19 grafs to UPDATE with three more dead outside
Ayodhya; Pickup 20th, `The army...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AYO1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government forces fired on thousands of
Hindu fundamentalists who broke through police barricades <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
and forced their way into a heavily guarded mosque. Five Hindus
were killed and 20 wounded.
   At least 26 people were killed in other parts of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as the
decades-old dispute between Hindus and Moslems over ownership of
the site came to a head.
   The controversy has left at least 138 people dead in the past
week, brought Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>'s government close to
collapse and further strained already tense relations between
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s Hindu majority and Moslem minority.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Singh, who opposes the Hindu campaign to replace the 16th-century</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Government forces fired on thousands of
Hindu fundamentalists who broke through police barricades <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
and forced their way into a heavily guarded mosque. Five Hindus
were killed and 20 wounded.
   At least 26 people were killed in other parts of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as the
decades-old dispute between Hindus and Moslems over ownership of
the site came to a head.
   The controversy has left at least 138 people dead in the past
week, brought Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>'s government close to
collapse and further strained already tense relations between
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s Hindu majority and Moslem minority.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-10013</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EBKCTADLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940211
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 FEB 94 / Arts: A living picture of Hinduism - Patricia Morison finds
much more than sacred cows at the British Museum
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PATRICIA MORISON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION> is not well understood in the west, even though many of its
individual features are familiar. One thinks of sacred cows, many-armed
dancing gods, <PERSON>Hari Krishna</PERSON>, titillating stories of tantric excesses, TV
epics and yogis who stand for years on one leg. The difficulty most people
have is fitting these colourful elements into a coherent picture of the
everyday religion of modern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
For Deities and Devotion at the <ORGANIZATION>British Museum</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Richard Blurton</PERSON>, its curator
of oriental antiquities, has trawled the <ORGANIZATION>Museum</ORGANIZATION>'s magnificent resources of
Hindu art, and borrowed some others - in particular from the scandalously
inaccessible hoard in the Victorian and <ORGANIZATION>Albert Museum</ORGANIZATION>. His aim is simple and
admirably achieved: to explain and 'demystify' <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION>.
By the <DATE>end of this century</DATE>, <PERSON>Blurton</PERSON> points out, the Indian population will
outstrip <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s. Since the majority of Indians are Hindus, it behoves us
all to form a picture of <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION> as a living, evolving faith - although the
resurgence of intolerant, militant Hindu fundamentalism is rather
overlooked.
It is a beautiful show; but, more importantly, it sets out examples of Hindu
devotional art, ancient and modern, to teach the essentials of the religion.
The gallery looks stunning in red and saffron yellow, a remarkable
improvement on the BM's customary boring world of grey and white. I
particularly liked the calligraphy by <ORGANIZATION>Sehmi Satwinder of Alphabet Soups</ORGANIZATION>.
An exceptionally large quantity of Indian paintings is on view, lit dimly to
protect them but brilliantly colourful. In the first section introducing the
principal gods, there is a series of miniatures from <LOCATION>Rajasthan</LOCATION> of around
<DATE>1800</DATE> depicting Vishnu in his ten orthodox incarnations. Here we find
battling Rama of the <ORGANIZATION>Ramayana</ORGANIZATION> epic, playful <PERSON>Krishna</PERSON>, and <ORGANIZATION>Buddha</ORGANIZATION>, an example
of a historical individual subsumed into the pantheon. Few of us would
identify the splendid white parade-horse with a parasol attached to his
saddle as the last incarnation of Vishnu as horse-headed Kalki, as he is yet
to show himself.
Cruder images of gods abound from all over <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>; on comics, palm-leaf
books, on the scrolls used by professional story-tellers, and on cheap and
