<DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890926-0058 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890926 </DD>
<AN> 890926-0058. </AN>
<HL> Who's News:
@  Three Top Officials at American Suzuki
@  Quit Suddenly; President Is Reassigned
@  ----
@  By Bradley A. Stertz
<DD> 09/26/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> J.SUZ WNEWS </CO>
<IN> AUTOMOBILES (AUT) </IN>
<TEXT>

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891013-0160 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891013 </DD>
<AN> 891013-0160. </AN>
<HL> Suzuki Motor Co.'s
@  Anderson Is Named
@  Top U.S. Sales Official </HL>
<DD> 10/13/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> J.SUZ WNEWS </CO>
<DATELINE> BREA, Calif.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales arm has named <PERSON>Gary Anderson</PERSON> its top <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> official in the wake of a series of resignations last month. 

   Three senior executives, all Americans, quit in <DATE>September</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Doug Mazza</PERSON>, former vice president and general manager and at the time the top American, said in a prepared statement that his and the other resignations were prompted by "changes in the company's operating goals and philosophies." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Anderson</PERSON>, who joined <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>June 1987</DATE>, gets the title of marketing director for the company's automotive division. 
He inherits "bits of several positions," said a Suzuki spokeswoman, who added that a reorganization last month has eliminated some previous posts. 

   In his new job, <PERSON>Mr. Anderson</PERSON> will oversee all sales, advertising and dealer development activities in addition to formulating marketing strategies. 
Some of these duties had been handled by <PERSON>Mr. Mazza</PERSON> and others by <PERSON>John Dorsey</PERSON>, former director of sales, and <PERSON>Larry Messelt</PERSON>, former national sales manager. 
Messrs. 
<PERSON>Dorsey</PERSON> and Messelt were the other two executives who resigned in <DATE>September</DATE>. 

   Suzuki sales so far this year, at 24,405 cars and sport utility vehicles, are less than half the level of a year ago, despite the introduction of two additional vehicles, including <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON>'s first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> car. 

   "Suzuki recognizes its responsibility to boost dealer confidence and improve direct communication with its dealers and field personnel on its plans and strategies," said <PERSON>Mr. Anderson</PERSON> in a prepared statement. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Anderson</PERSON> was most recently <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> regional sales manager. 
He also served as manager of dealer development. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA092689-0131 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 112664 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 26, 1989, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 1; Column 4; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
650 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PEOPLE: SAMURAI SALES PLUNGE SPARKS SHUFFLE AT AMERICAN SUZUKI 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN O'DELL, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, staggered by a catastrophic decline in Samurai 
sales and weakness in its other automotive lines, said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that its 
president has been reassigned to corporate headquarters in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, and the three 
top officials of the auto division have resigned. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kenji Shimizu</PERSON>, chairman of Brea-based <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>July</DATE> and a longtime 
executive and managing director of the <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> conglomerate in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, 
will replace <PERSON>Toshiyuki Arai</PERSON> as president of <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Yoshi Fujii</PERSON>, another longtime <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> executive from corporate headquarters in 
<LOCATION>Hamamatsu</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, has been named to the new position of executive vice 
president of the <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> automotive division, which markets cars and 
sports vehicles. Other American Suzuki divisions market motorcycles and such 
miscellaneous products as outboard motors and snowmobiles. 
</P>
<P>
A company spokeswoman said no replacements have been named for the three <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
automotive division executives who resigned <DATE>Monday</DATE>: <PERSON>Doug Mazza</PERSON>, vice president; 
<PERSON>John Dorsey</PERSON>, sales director, and <PERSON>Larry Messelt</PERSON>, national sales manager. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dorsey</PERSON> were hired in <DATE>1985</DATE> to create <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s auto division, 
the same year Suzuki introduced the Samurai. 
</P>
<P>
The Samurai quickly caught on with younger drivers interested in low-cost 
sports vehicles, and sales soared to 81,349 cars in <DATE>1987</DATE>. But in <DATE>June, 1988</DATE>, 
Consumer Reports magazine criticized the Samurai as being susceptible to 
rolling over, and sales began to plummet. 
</P>
<P>
Even though a federal study has since concluded that the Samurai is no more 
prone to rolling over than are similar vehicles, sales slumped to about 50,000 
in the <DATE>first eight months of 1988</DATE>, and in the first eight months of this year, 
just 3,399 Samurais have been sold. 
</P>
<P>
Sales of <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s other vehicles -- a line of subcompacts and another sports 
vehicle introduced within the last year -- have also been hurt by the 
publicity. As of <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>, Suzuki had sold just 21,389 cars and sports utility 
vehicles in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In <ORGANIZATION>American Samurai</ORGANIZATION>'s only statement about the management changes, spokeswoman 
year." 
</P>
<P>
"When <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> and <PERSON>Arai</PERSON> started in <DATE>1985</DATE>, they had only one automobile product, the 
Samurai, and the goal was to establish a following for and generate sales of 
the Samurai, which they did," she said. 
</P>
<P>
"But now Suzuki is in a situation where we have a full line, including the 
Sidekick and the Swift passenger cars. The complexion of the company has 
changed, and there are different goals and philosophies on how best to run what 
essentially is a new company." 
</P>
<P>
Also <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> announced its <DATE>1990</DATE> automobile lineup. The Samurai 
is being de-emphasized, with fewer models and options being offered. Meanwhile, 
the Sidekick -- a squat version of the Samurai with a lower center of gravity, 
is being offered in several new configurations. As <DATE>last year</DATE>, there will be 
three models of the Swift. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
SHAKE-UP AT <ORGANIZATION>AMERICAN SUZUKI 
</P>
<P>
American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Brea</LOCATION>, reorganized its executive suite 
<DATE>Monday</DATE> amid a continuing sales slump. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kenji Shimizu</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Chairman since <DATE>July</DATE>, will assume the additional title of president. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Toshiyuki Arai</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Former president, reassigned to corporate headquarters in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Doug Mazza</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Former vice president, one of three automotive division executives who 
resigned. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
SUZUKI'S SAGGING SALES 
</P>
<P>
Suzuki Sales 
</P>
<TABLEÊCWL="2.22IN:1.78IN:1.78IN:2.33IN:2.33IN"ÊWDM="ABS"ÊNCOLS="5">
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊSPN="4"ÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
NUMBER OF VEHICLES SOLD 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
<DATE>August 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
August</DATE> 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
First 8 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
First 8 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
 * <DATE>1988 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
1989 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
Months 1988 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="C"ÊCVJ="C">
Months 1989</DATE> 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="L"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELL>
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELL>
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELL>
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELL>
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="L"ÊCVJ="C">
All models 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
12,208 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
3,300 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
49,756 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
21,389 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="L"ÊCVJ="C">
Samurai 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
12,208 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
193 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
49,756 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
3,399 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="L"ÊCVJ="C">
Sidekick 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
2,376 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
13,827 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="L"ÊCVJ="C">
Swift GT 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
601 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
3,001 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="L"ÊCVJ="C">
Swift GLX 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
103 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
838 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
<TABLEROW>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="L"ÊCVJ="C">
Swift GA 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
57 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
161 
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
<TABLECELLÊCHJ="R"ÊCVJ="C">
</TABLECELL>
<CELLRULE>  </CELLRULE>
</TABLEROW>
<ROWRULE>  </ROWRULE>
</TABLE>
<P>
</P>
<P>
*Suzuki sold only the Samurai Jan.-August <DATE>1988</DATE>. Other vehicles were introduced 
later in the year and in <DATE>1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Source: <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Table, SUZUKI'S SAGGING SALES ; Photo, Sales of Suzuki's Samurai fell 
dramatically after a consumer group raised concerns about the vehicle's 
stability in turns. ; Photo, Kenji Shimizu ; Photo, Toshiyuki Arai ; Photo, 
Doug Mazza 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Full Run 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
AMERICAN SUZUKI MOTOR CORP; EXECUTIVES; MANAGEMENT; AUTOMOBILE INDUSTRY -- 
LABOR RELATIONS; CORPORATE RESTRUCTURING; SAMURAI (AUTOMOBILE); AUTOMOBILE 
SALES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100189-0034 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 114541 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 1, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 1; Column 4; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1783 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SUZUKI FALLS VICTIM TO ITS OWN SAMURAI 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN CHARLES TIGHE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It was just <DATE>two years ago</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, basking in the 
popularity of its Samurai sport vehicle, predicted that it would soon be 
selling a full line of automobiles in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. By <DATE>1990</DATE>, the company -- best 
known for its motorcycles -- expected to sell 300,000 cars and sport utility 
vehicles in this country. 
</P>
<P>
Much has changed for Suzuki since then and most of it for the worse. 
</P>
<P>
Sales of the Samurai have plummeted to 3,399 in the <DATE>first eight months of this 
year</DATE> from a high of 81,349 in <DATE>1987</DATE>. And sales of four new models introduced in 
the past year have been dismal: As of <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> had sold only 21,389 cars 
and sport utility vehicles. 
</P>
<P>
As the crucial 1990-model season gets into full swing, <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> appears 
unprepared. 
</P>
<P>
Last <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s president was reassigned to corporate 
headquarters in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, and three core members of the company's American 
management team abruptly resigned. 
</P>
<P>
The shake-up shocked Suzuki dealers, whose first shipments of <DATE>1990</DATE> vehicles 
were arriving that day. The company is not saying whether it plans to name 
replacements for the executives who resigned. The three were widely credited 
for the Samurai's early success. 
</P>
<P>
There have been other changes at <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Brea</LOCATION> headquarters. More than 
<PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> headquarters staff -- or about 25 workers -- were laid 
off earlier this year, a high-ranking executive of <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s parent company in 
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> took over as chairman of the operation in <DATE>July</DATE>, and the company is 
seeking a new advertising agency as the selling season begins. 
</P>
<P>
As Vice President <PERSON>Doug Mazza</PERSON>, Sales Director <PERSON>John Dorsey</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>National Sales</ORGANIZATION> 
Manager <PERSON>Larry Messelt</PERSON> were resigning last week, marketing strategies for the 
1990-model season were still being developed and the company's only advertising 
was on billboards. The resignations left other plans undecided and raised 
speculation from analysts about more resignations or layoffs. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Safety Issue 
</P>
<P>
"The best anyone can do is guess at where this company is headed," said <PERSON>Jeremy 
Anwyl</PERSON>, an auto industry consultant in <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The decline of Brea-based American Suzuki can be traced to <DATE>June, 1988</DATE>, when the 
publisher of Consumer Reports magazine sharply criticized the safety of the 
Samurai, claiming that it was more prone to rolling over than other sport 
utility vehicles. 
</P>
<P>
Suzuki spent <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> on rebates and lobbying in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> to 
defend itself against the accusation. Early this year, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> won vindication 
when a federal study concluded that the vehicle was no more susceptible to 
rolling over than other similar sport trucks. By <DATE>March</DATE>, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> officials said 
the problem had been put to rest. 
</P>
<P>
However, not only has the Samurai failed to recover, but a <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman 
now acknowledges that the attacks on the Samurai have also tainted the image of 
<ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s four other vehicles. 
</P>
<P>
The Sidekick -- a utility vehicle similar to the Samurai -- and three models of 
the spunky Swift subcompact car have earned praise from reviewers, but sales 
have been disappointing. One Swift model, the GLX, has sold fewer than 1,000 
units and is being dropped from the <DATE>1990</DATE> line. 
</P>
<P>
"Beyond the Samurai, people don't have another image of <LOCATION>Suzuki</LOCATION>, except maybe as 
a motorcycle maker," said <PERSON>Anwyl</PERSON>, president of the ad agency <ORGANIZATION>USP Automotive 
Advertising</ORGANIZATION>. "When people criticized the Samurai, they might as well have been 
criticizing the whole Suzuki name." 
</P>
<P>
Company officials declined to discuss their marketing or sales plans, which for 
several years were developed largely by <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON>. Industry analysts describe the 
next several months as a crucial period for <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> to rebuild identity 
with consumers and with <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dealers. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Dealers Disenchanted 
</P>
<P>
"Following these resignations, if they don't come back very strong with a lot 
of money, some new products and some major personnel announcements, (<ORGANIZATION>American 
Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>) might as well just go away," said <PERSON>Lee Sattley</PERSON>, vice president of 
operations for <ORGANIZATION>Astro Management</ORGANIZATION>, which closed its <ORGANIZATION>Lakewood Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> dealership in 
<DATE>August</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Sattley said his company, which still operates large <ORGANIZATION>Nissan</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> 
dealerships, decided to shut down its Suzuki operations "to stop the bleeding." 
He said he expects that other dealers will likely consider doing the same in 
the wake of <DATE>last week</DATE>'s resignations. 
</P>
<P>
"When you aren't getting a return on investment, and I don't imagine many 
dealers are, you look at your level of confidence in management," <PERSON>Sattley</PERSON> said. 
"Now, with basically all the familiar leadership decimated, it's pretty hard to 
have confidence." 
</P>
<P>
Many dealers made fast and hefty profits in <DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE> on the Samurai, which 
was introduced in <DATE>1985</DATE>. Now they get few requests for either the Samurai or the 
Swift, which holds the honor as the most fuel-efficient import for <DATE>1990</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The struggles of Suzuki are similar to those faced by the West German auto 
maker <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION>. In <DATE>1986</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>' "60 Minutes" aired a story that said the <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION> 5000 
had a tendency to suddenly and dangerously accelerate. It wasn't until <DATE>July</DATE> of 
this year that the federal government cleared <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION> in a major report, and 
concluded that the problem resulted from driver error. 
</P>
<P>
But <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION>'s sales -- across the board, not just for the <DATE>5000</DATE> -- have fallen 
precipitously over the past three years. After peaking at 73,000 cars in <DATE>1985</DATE>, 
sales fell to 23,000 last year, and analysts say <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION> may never regain its <DATE>1985</DATE> 
sales level. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Identity Crisis' 
</P>
<P>
"With <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION> and Suzuki, once these companies were damaged, they can be 
vindicated and bring out the best product anywhere, but it doesn't make much 
consulting firm in <LOCATION>Newport Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Suzuki's "identity crisis," as one analyst described it, first took its toll at 
the dealer level. 
</P>
<P>
When Suzuki officials decided that clearing the Samurai name was the company's 
top priority, most of the company's resources were directed to that effort for 
several months. As a result, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON>'s long-time strategy of maintaining close 
relationships with dealers started to weaken, said <PERSON>Jesse Snyder</PERSON>, <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> 
editor of Automotive News. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Snyder</PERSON> said that when <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> introduced the Samurai in <DATE>1985</DATE>, the company spent 
a great deal of time calling on dealers and listening to their ideas and 
complaints. This was important in helping Suzuki build dealer loyalty. 
</P>
<P>
Because <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> did not have a broad line of cars, the company couldn't insist 
that dealers sell only Suzukis. Instead, they signed up dealers whose lots were 
crowded with Nissans, <LOCATION>Toyotas</LOCATION>, Plymouths or Fords. 
</P>
<P>
After the Samurai controversy erupted, dealers continued to hang the Suzuki 
sign on their lots, but few customers were asking about Suzukis and few 
salesmen were having much luck selling the cars. 
</P>
<P>
"Suzuki went to the back of the dealer's mind, and it hasn't come back," <PERSON>Snyder</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Trying to Respond 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bart Thomson</PERSON>, who was sales manager of <PERSON>Cormier Suzuki</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Lake Forest</LOCATION>, described 
Suzuki as slow to respond to dealers' needs. Some dealers felt that they 
weren't getting the answers that they needed to questions about the <ORGANIZATION>Samurai</ORGANIZATION>'s 
safety and its future. Cormier, which operates dealerships for several car 
makers, closed its Suzuki dealership in <DATE>August</DATE> when it sold its franchise to 
Superior Suzuki in <LOCATION>Garden Grove</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Some dealers said <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> is now trying to be responsive again. 
</P>
<P>
"They're asking us what we think," said <PERSON>John Mason</PERSON>, sales manager of <ORGANIZATION>Duarte 
Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>. Duarte sold 78 Suzukis in <DATE>August</DATE> and was American Suzuki's top dealer 
for the month. Suzuki's 285 dealers sold fewer than 12 cars each on average in 
<DATE>August</DATE>, a volume considered to be anemic. 
</P>
<P>
As an incentive to its dealers, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> in <DATE>August</DATE> agreed to pay half the cost of 
its dealers' advertising, at least through the end of <DATE>October</DATE>. Right now, that 
advertising makes up most of <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s advertising effort. 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Kenji Shimizu</PERSON> relocated from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> to take the newly 
created position of chairman of all of <LOCATION>Suzuki</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> businesses, including a 
struggling motorcycle operation, he said he planned to restore auto sales by 
increasing the company's ad budget. 
</P>
<P>
However, when the <DATE>1990</DATE> Sidekick and the three-door Swift GA were introduced 
<DATE>Sept. 25</DATE>, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> had no major ad campaign to accompany the new models. While 
other auto makers are spending millions of dollars for sophisticated television 
and magazine ad campaigns, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON>'s only ads will be on billboards. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Agency Hunt 
</P>
<P>
Suzuki put its advertising account up for review early in the <DATE>summer</DATE>, and had 
planned to name a new agency in <DATE>mid-September</DATE>. However, presentations from 
prospective agencies were abruptly canceled when <PERSON>Shimizu</PERSON> and then-president 
<PERSON>Toshiyuki Arai</PERSON> were called to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> for meetings. It was <PERSON>Arai</PERSON> who was later 
reassigned to the home office. 
</P>
<P>
Presentations by the ad agencies have been rescheduled for the middle of 
<DATE>October</DATE>, but some analysts said <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> may not have an ad campaign for the rest 
of its fiscal year, which ends <DATE>March 31</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Suzuki spokeswoman <PERSON>Laura Segall</PERSON> said <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> may have a new campaign before 
<DATE>April</DATE> but no decision has been made and she declined to discuss the size of 
this year's ad budget. At the height of the <ORGANIZATION>Samurai</ORGANIZATION>'s popularity, annual ad 
spending was estimated at <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY>. For <DATE>fiscal 1989</DATE>, the figure fell to <MONEY>$30 
million</MONEY>, and this year's total might be less than <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>, industry 
observers said. 
</P>
<P>
"You can have the finest cars. But if nobody knows about you, you won't sell 
them," <PERSON>Anwyl</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Analysts said that for <DATE>1990</DATE>, Suzuki appears to be de-emphasizing the Samurai, 
which for the first time is only available with a soft-top. Instead, the 
Sidekick and Swift are available with more options. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Heavy Competition 
</P>
<P>
A new Swift three-door hatchback with a retail price of <MONEY>$6,400</MONEY> will make Suzuki 
more competitive in <DATE>1990</DATE>, analyst <PERSON>Peterson</PERSON> said. An early version of the car 
was introduced in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in <DATE>July</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Snyder of Automotive News</ORGANIZATION> said there is still a glut of inexpensive vehicles 
similar to most Swift models. And the Swifts are not the cheapest or sportiest 
of the cars that they compete against, he said. 
</P>
<P>
American Suzuki also increasingly is competing against its own parent company, 
<ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co., Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. In addition to selling cars through <ORGANIZATION>American 
Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>, the parent company sells its Sidekick and a version of the Swift to 
<ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION>, which includes them in its Geo line, an increasingly popular 
line of import cars from several manufacturers. 
</P>
<P>
The Sidekick is sold as the Geo Tracker and the Geo Metro is a Swift, described 
by <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> as a "stripped-down model." 
</P>
<P>
"What is the reason for the Swift to be marketed as the Swift?" Anwyl asked 
rhetorically. "There doesn't seem to be one." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Rows of Suzuki cars languish on the lot of Worthington Suzuki in 
Huntington Beach. ROD BOREN / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MARKETING; AUTOMOBILE SALES; AUTOMOBILES; PRODUCT SAFETY; AUTOMOBILE SAFETY; 
AMERICAN SUZUKI MOTOR CORP; CORPORATE RESTRUCTURING; ADVERTISING 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880610-0130 </DOCNO>
<HL> Suzuki Lashes Out at Samurai's Critics, Calling Testing of Vehicles 'Distorted' </HL>
<AUTHOR> Joseph B. White (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> AUT </IN>
<TEXT>
   With sales of its Samurai sport utility vehicle slumping, <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> blasted Consumer Reports magazine for using "distorted" testing to reach the "inaccurate" and "defamatory" conclusion that Samurai is unsafe because it tends to roll over in sharp turns. 

   At a 90-minute news conference beamed by satellite from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to reporters in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, the company escalated its war on <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union of U.S. Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the magazine's publisher, accusing it of "biased" and "seriously flawed" testing. 
<PERSON>Doug Mazza</PERSON>, vice president and general manager of <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s automotive division, said <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON>, a "small Japanese company" is being unfairly singled out for criticism. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Mazza</PERSON> conceded that <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> hadn't asked the consumer group for more detailed information about exactly how it had conducted its road tests. 
But he insisted: "We do not have a rollover problem." 

   R. <PERSON>David Pittle</PERSON>, technical director for <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>, asserted yesterday that the group's testing was fair. 
He added that <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> hasn't heard from Suzuki since he sent the company a copy of the Consumer Reports article, a videotape of a road test, and a copy of the test protocol. 
That was one day before the <DATE>June 2</DATE> news conference at which <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> pronounced the Samurai "unacceptable" and urged that all 150,000 Samurai vehicles sold in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> be recalled, he said. 
The group's findings came two months after similar charges by the Washington-based Center for Auto Safety. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Pittle</PERSON> called <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON>'s suggestion that it is the victim of a conspiracy "bizarre." 
He added: "Let's keep our eye on the ball. 
The car rolls over when it shouldn't." 

   As part of its effort to counter the safety critics, Suzuki spent an extra <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> just for television advertising during the past week, <PERSON>Mr. Mazza</PERSON> said. 
The company also has supplied its dealers with a videotape detailing the company's case that the Samurai is stable. 

   Suzuki's immediate, combative stance -- complete with broad hints of possible legal action -- is a sharp contrast to the silent treatment some other auto makers have used in the face of similar attacks. 

   Samurai sales were slumping even before the safety questions came to the fore in <DATE>March</DATE>. 
But they fell <PERCENT>22.5%</PERCENT> that month, and <PERCENT>26%</PERCENT> in <DATE>April</DATE>, from the year-earlier periods. 
They appeared to rebound in <DATE>May</DATE>, but Suzuki dealers contacted since the <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> made its report say showroom traffic is off again. 

   Suzuki's troubles have been a source of glee for <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s Jeep-Eagle dealers. 
The Samurai had cut heavily into sales of Jeep's Wrangler models, but one Jeep dealer in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> said questions about Samurai safety appear to be changing that. 

   "We had 30 Wranglers in, and in two weeks time they're gone," said <PERSON>Bill Gill</PERSON>, manager of the sales department for <ORGANIZATION>Royal Jeep-Eagle</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Fern Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
Nationwide, Wrangler sales through <DATE>May 31</DATE> were up <PERCENT>43%</PERCENT> from a year earlier. 
Samurai and Wrangler appeal to the same young audience, but now "their parents are bringing them here instead of there," <PERSON>Mr. Gill</PERSON> said. 

   A few miles away, <PERSON>Jeff Nanton</PERSON>, an owner of <PERSON>Seminole Suzuki</PERSON>, said his sales are soft, but he blamed that on a "depressed" regional market. 
"What we're fighting is an allegation rather than a fact," he said. 
"We've had many customers call in total support of the vehicle." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870902-0167 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sport-Utility
Vehicles Tap
Market Niches
---
By Stephen Buckley
<DD> 09/02/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> C GM F
AUTOS, AUTO PARTS (AUT) </IN>
<TEXT>
   When <PERSON>Melvin Adams</PERSON> bought his first sport-utility vehicle, a Chevrolet Blazer, back in <DATE>1975</DATE>, he mainly wanted the four-wheel-drive function to help battle treacherous winter roads. 

   Last year, <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON> bought a new compact S10 Blazer for outdoor recreation and hunting -- and for his wife's daily use around town. 
Nowadays, "you can drive them to something like a wedding and no one will care," says <PERSON>Mr. Adams</PERSON>, a vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Coleman Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a camping-equipment concern based in <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan</LOCATION>. 
"They're more socially acceptable." 

   Indeed, sport-utility vehicles have surged in popularity in recent years. 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales are expected to reach 820,000 this year, more than six times the 132,000 sold in <DATE>1982</DATE> when the boom began. 

   The big reason for the increase has been the rapid proliferation in models and the expanding array of buyers they have drawn, from teen-agers in search of cheap wheels to image-conscious young adults drawn by the vehicles' new high-status looks. 
In <DATE>1981</DATE>, Americans had only 10 essentially similar models to choose from. 
Now there are twice as many, from the spartan, subcompact Suzuki Samurai that sells for <MONEY>$7,725</MONEY>, to the <ORGANIZATION>Range Rover</ORGANIZATION>, a new luxury British import that costs <MONEY>$31,900</MONEY> and has attracted such buyers as actor <PERSON>Jack Nicholson</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Queen Elizabeth II</ORGANIZATION>. 

   "You can get them as nice as a Cadillac," says <PERSON>Lance Kirk</PERSON>, general manager of <PERSON>Dick Hatfield Chevrolet</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Augusta</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan</LOCATION>. 

   Until the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, the sport-utilities were strictly plain vanilla -- unadorned work vehicles or fun-mobiles mainly for off-road use. 
On many models, the only options available were four-wheel-drive, power steering and air conditioning. 
Jeep, now owned by <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, long dominated the market, with a <PERCENT>36%</PERCENT> share in <DATE>1977</DATE>. 

   Today, manufacturers are scrambling to fill a variety of niches. 
A year ago, Jeep discontinued its CJ, a basic model directly descended from the World War II jeep, and introduced the Wrangler. 
"On the CJ, even the top and the doors were optional," says <PERSON>Martin Levine</PERSON>, general marketing manager for <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION>'s new Jeep/Eagle division. 
"On the Wrangler, things like leather interior, automatic transmission, stereo-cassette radio, rear-window defroster, not to mention the top and the doors, are all standard features." 
The company will introduce another upscale sport-utility entry, called the ZJ, probably within the next two years, he adds. 

   Nonetheless, Jeep envies the success of <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> at the other end of the market. 
The Japanese company has sold a hefty 91,000 Samurais since introducing the vehicle in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> <DATE>less than two years ago</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Levine</PERSON> says Jeep/Eagle is "studying the lower end of the market" for a possible new entry. 
So is <LOCATION>Yugo America</LOCATION>, which wants to challenge the Samurai with its own vehicle priced under <MONEY>$9,000</MONEY>. 

   Suzuki, meanwhile, plans to counterattack with an upscale model targeted at an older audience than Samurai buyers, says <PERSON>N. Douglas Mazza</PERSON>, vice president and general manager of the company's <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> unit. 

   <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> division -- which now leads the 10 sport-utility makers with <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> of the market -- will soon introduce a sleeker version of the S10 Blazer, called the <LOCATION>Serengeti</LOCATION>, with all-leather interior and paint-trim wheels. 

   Will all these new models find enough buyers? 
The <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> increase expected in sport-utility sales this year is certainly healthy in a year when car sales are down. 
But the sort of double-digit annual sales gains that occurred between <DATE>1982</DATE> and <DATE>1985</DATE> probably won't return, if only because the overall sales volume is now so large. 

   Some dealers and market analysts fear the boom may wane because current owners are starting to have families, and thus are looking for bigger vehicles. 
Both <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which makes the Bronco line, will address that problem by introducing four-door compacts by <DATE>1991</DATE>. 

   "Our sales (of <ORGANIZATION>Toyota Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s two-door 4Runner model) are down, and I think people wanting a four-door vehicle is part of it," says <PERSON>Robert Bowling</PERSON>, general manager of <ORGANIZATION>Seeger Toyota</ORGANIZATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Creve Coeur</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Mo</LOCATION>. 
"A four-door is better for car pooling, better for kids, better for cargo." 
Toyota at this time has no plans for a four-door model, a spokesman says. 

   Manufacturers may hit on other new marketing strategies as well. 
Suzuki, for instance, may begin to stress the Samurai's commercial uses. 
"It's a growing incremental part of our business that we think is important," says <PERSON>Mr. Mazza</PERSON>. 
Suzuki recently gave a Samurai to the city of <LOCATION>Brea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, home of the company's <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> headquarters, "and now they've assigned it to their water company." 

   (See: "Corrections &amp; Amplifications: Leather Interior" -- WSJ <DATE>Sept. 4, 1987</DATE>) 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880912-0099 </DOCNO>
<HL> Different Data Lies Behind Samurai Dispute </HL>
<AUTHOR> Bradley A. Stertz (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> AUT </IN>
<G> TRN </G>
<TEXT>
   Consumers might be forgiven for being confused. 
In <DATE>June</DATE>, Consumer Reports magazine said the Suzuki Samurai "is so likely to roll over . . . that it is unfit for its intended use." 
But just this month a federal safety agency refused to order a recall and said the Samurai is no more unsafe than any Jeep-like vehicle. 

   Were they talking about the same car? 
Yes -- but they were basing their judgments on different statistics and road tests. 

   "Under circumstances like these, you have to wonder where consumers can go to get unbiased information," says <PERSON>George Hoffer</PERSON>, professor of automotive economics at <ORGANIZATION>Virginia Commonwealth University</ORGANIZATION>. 
"The weakness with the system is that people can design their tests to come up with whatever data they want." 

   That was certainly the case with <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s Samurai. 
In its analysis of the <ORGANIZATION>Samurai</ORGANIZATION>'s safety, the <ORGANIZATION>National Highway Traffic Safety Administration</ORGANIZATION> focused on fatality rates; those numbers showed fatalities from rollovers involving <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s Bronco II occur three times as often as Samurai rollover deaths. 

   Based on those figures, <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> officials say they saw no reason to open an extensive safety investigation into the Samurai, despite the Consumer Reports article. 
"We looked at other statistics," says <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Tim Hurd</PERSON>. 
"But the fatality rates seemed to overwhelmingly suggest there wasn't anything uniquely wrong with the Samurai." 

   But <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union of U.S. Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the publisher of Consumer Reports, chose to use different numbers when it condemned the vehicle, citing <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> crash-avoidance surveys taken in four states in <DATE>1986</DATE>. 
The statistics showed Samurais rolling over in <PERCENT>64%</PERCENT> of all single-vehicle accidents (those where only a Samurai was involved). 
That compared with a <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> rate for the now-discontinued Jeep CJ-5, which has been a target of rollover charges for years. 

   "We thought our numbers . . . showed reason for some serious concern," says <PERSON>Robert Knoll</PERSON>, the chief of <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>'s auto-testing division. 

   The two sides were also at odds on the road tests. 
Consumers Union ran the Samurai through the same course it uses to test all vehicles. 
On a maneuver to suddenly avoid an object in the road, the Samurai began tipping over. 

   Suzuki and <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> argue that <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>'s tests aren't reliable. 
"We used tests that have been approved by engineers and in use by the auto industry for a long time," says <PERSON>Douglas Mazza</PERSON>, vice president and general manager of <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales arm. 
"The tests used by <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> were not instrumented, were not recorded and were not scientific." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Knoll</PERSON> disputes such contentions. 
"Our tests replicate what will happen to drivers in the real world," he says. 
"In one of theirs, they drive around and around in a circle at faster speeds. 
I have to wonder how often that happens on roadways?" 

   <PERSON>Mr. Knoll</PERSON> notes -- and <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Mr. Hurd</PERSON> confirms -- that <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> didn't do its own testing of the Samurai. 

   Although <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> declined to investigate the Samurai, it did agree to start developing tests to evaluate rollover risks for all vehicles. 
While the safety of sport-utility vehicles has been an issue for more than a decade, there's still no standard driving test to determine whether individual models are prone to roll over. 

   This isn't the first time <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> has gotten into a fight over safety statistics. 

   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> Administrator <PERSON>Diane Steed</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> that deaths from automatic-shift <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> vehicles slipping from "park" to "reverse" were declining substantially after a settlement that made <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> install warning stickers in the cars. 
Using its own fatality data, <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> said deaths dropped by <PERCENT>300%</PERCENT> following the <DATE>1980</DATE> settlement. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>General Accounting Office</ORGANIZATION> study <DATE>a year later</DATE>, though, said there had been a delay in reporting many deaths. 
As a result, the <ORGANIZATION>GAO</ORGANIZATION> study stated, deaths in <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> park-to-reverse cases had actually increased after the <DATE>1980</DATE> settlement. 

   At that point, <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> decided to switch to the number of reported park-to-reverse incidents instead of the fatality figures. 
The new data showed park-to-reverse accidents declining. 
That data wasn't generated independently; instead it was provided by <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>. 

   NHTSA at the time said they changed to different numbers because the total fatalities were not high enough to generate accurate statistics. 
<ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> won't comment further on the <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> case. 

   But <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION>'s critics see parallels with the Samurai. 
"With <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> and with Suzuki," says <PERSON>Clarence Ditlow</PERSON>, director of the Washington-based Center for <ORGANIZATION>Auto Safety</ORGANIZATION>, "it was a matter of <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> having a pre-ordained position, and demonstrating its ability to develop numbers to support that position." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880610-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-88 0205EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SamuraiDefense     06-10 0616</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Samurai Defense,0632</SECOND>
<HEAD>Automaker Denies Vehicle Prone To Rollovers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GARTIES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The maker of the <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Samurai</ORGANIZATION> took the
offense in a battle over the vehicle's safety, disputing the
validity of tests by Consumer Reports magazine that found the
Samurai dangerously prone to roll over.
   The tests by <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>, the magazine's publisher,
apparently were intended to persuade the government to adopt new
stability standards for sport-utility vehicles like the Samurai,
<ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION> executive <PERSON>Doug Mazza</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``The Suzuki Samurai has been falsely accused, and it does not
have a design error,'' <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said. ``We have absolute confidence in
its safety record and road-worthiness in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.''
   Calling the test results ``inaccurate and defamatory,'' <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON>,
vice president of Brea-based <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said the
company was considering a lawsuit against <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>.
   Consumers Union stands by its tests, said <PERSON>David Berliner</PERSON>,
assistant director of the non-profit organization based in <LOCATION>Mount
Vernon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y</LOCATION>. He denied the tests were intended to influence federal
regulations.
   <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>last week</DATE> the Samurai rolled over in abrupt
maneuvers because it is too tall for its small wheelbase. Similar
vehicles passed the test. The group called for the immediate recall
of all 160,000 Samurais on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> roads and reimbursement of their
owners.
   But <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said government accident statistics, along with tests
conducted by an automotive engineering consultant for Suzuki, show
the four-wheel-drive vehicle is safe under typical driving
conditions, safer than some other vehicles of its type.
   At simultaneous news conferences in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> showed films of Samurais passing a number of what
were described as rigorous tests of the car's ability to stay
upright.
   ``For years the <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> has been pressing the government
for an unrealistic rollover standard,'' <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said. ``What better
way than pressing the smallest Japanese automaker with the No. 1
selling sport-utility vehicle?''
   Publicity about the <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> tests is expected to cut
Samurai sales, <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said, adding that the company has boosted its
advertising budget by <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> a week to counter consumer fears
raised by the tests. The <MONEY>$8,500</MONEY> vehicle is promoted as a fun car
for the youth market.
   Suzuki's auto engineering consultant, <PERSON>Jon McKibben</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>,
said it appeared the <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> test driver deliberately
turned the Samurai more sharply than other sport-utility vehicles
in the obstacle-avoidance test. Sport-utility vehicles are
Jeep-like light trucks.
   McKibben acknowledged that he knew of the test only by watching
a videotape of it.
   Berliner of the <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> responded: ``We never suggested
that the Samurai will turn over every time a driver swerves to
avoid an obstacle in the road. We said that its design creates
enough chance of that happening to the typical driver that it poses
an unacceptable risk.''
   The Samurais in the Consumers Union tests may have been made
unstable by 300-pound ``outriggers'' bolted to the cars to keep
them from rolling over completely, <PERSON>McKibben</PERSON> said.
   However, <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> contends the outriggers actually should
have been 44 reported incidents of Samurais rolling over, involving
53 injuries and 16 deaths.
   Consumers Union filed a petition with the <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> seeking rules
requiring that sport-utility vehicles be put through road tests for
safety, rather than just requiring them to meet design standards.
   Suzuki said its study of federal statistics on fatal accidents
found that in the <DATE>last two years</DATE>, there were three fatal accidents
in which a Samurai may have rolled over on a relatively flat
surface. In two of those cases, the drivers had been drinking and
none of the victims wore seat belts, <PERSON>McKibben</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890323-0284 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-23-89 1747EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-SamuraiSettlement     03-23 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Samurai Settlement,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>Attorneys General: Suzuki Agrees to Include Warning in Samurai Ads</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION> has agreed to pay
<MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> to seven states and to include in future advertisements a
warning that its Samurai sport vehicle may roll over if turned too
sharply.
   The agreement announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> settles lawsuits filed by <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> accusing the car manufacturer _ the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> arm of Japanese
automaker Suzuki _ of false and deceptive advertising. It was
effective <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   American Suzuki, based in <LOCATION>Brea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, entered the agreement
without admitting any guilt or safety problems. The <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> is to
cover the states' costs in preparing the cases.
   The states began investigating the Samurai's safety <DATE>last June</DATE>
after Consumer Reports magazine gave the popular, four-wheel-drive
sport utility vehicle its first ``not acceptable'' rating in 10
years.
   Consumers Union, publisher of Consumer Reports, said the <MONEY>$8,500</MONEY>
Samurai is too short, too narrow, too light and its center of
gravity is too high to be safe. It was the first car of 349 tested
in the <DATE>last decade</DATE> to roll over during a routine accident-avoidance
test, in which cars are made to swerve to avoid an obstacle in the
road, the group reported.
   ``This agreement strongly affirms that the Samurai is a safe
vehicle and strongly supports the federal government decision that
there is no reason to investigate the safety of the Samurai,'' <PERSON>N.
Douglas Mazza</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s vice president, said in a statement.
   Consumers Union, of <LOCATION>Mount Vernon</LOCATION>, had asked the <ORGANIZATION>National Highway
Traffic Safety Administration</ORGANIZATION> to recall the more than 150,000
Japanese-built Samurais sold in this country since its introduction
in <DATE>November 1985</DATE>.
   The agency denied the recall petition in <DATE>September</DATE>, saying the
Samurai had a rollover rate ``within the range of most other light
utility vehicles.'' It also said most rollovers were influenced by
``drinking, low ambient light and lack or driver familiarity (with)
either the vehicle or the road.''
   New York Attorney general <PERSON>Robert Abrams</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that the
states took action because ``the federal government has, once again,
failed to act to protect the consumers of this country.''
   Samurai print ads now must include the following statement:
``This vehicle handles differently from ordinary passenger cars.
Federal law cautions to avoid sharp turns and abrupt maneuvers which
can cause vehicles of this type to roll over. Always wear your
seatbelt. For specific details, please read your owner's manual.''
   A shorter version of the statement is required for television and
radio ads, <PERSON>Abrams</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Abrams</PERSON> said his investigation indicated previous <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> ads
``deceived the public by promoting the Samurai as a safe, fun
passenger vehicle while knowing it...can present considerable
dangers to young, inexperienced, first-time purchasers who were
<ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s target buyers.''
   Suzuki contended its advertising did not violate state laws but
decided to agree to a settlement to avoid possible legal action by
the states.
   ``For <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> and Samurai owners, this agreement with the
attorneys general is the final chapter in a long story of false
allegations about the Samurai,'' <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880602-0326 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-02-88 1958EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-SuzukiSamurai     06-02 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Suzuki Samurai,0769</SECOND>
<HEAD>Consumer Group Calls For Ban on Suzuki Utility Vehicle</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: also on general news wires.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY45</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Samurai</ORGANIZATION>, a popular sport utility
vehicle, tends to roll over in sudden turns and should be banned,
the publishers of Consumer Reports magazine said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``That car literally trips over its own feet, and I wouldn't
want to be in it,'' said <PERSON>R. David Pittle</PERSON>, technical director of the
non-profit <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>, which publishes the monthly magazine.
   In an article scheduled to appear in its <DATE>July</DATE> issue, Consumer
Reports labels the Japanese-made Samurai ``not acceptable'' _ the
first time it has given such a rating to a car in 10 years.
   <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Brea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, defended its
vehicle.
   ``The Samurai was thoroughly tested for safety, including
stability and handling, prior to its introduction into the <LOCATION>United
<ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We have absolute confidence that we are selling a safe and
stable vehicle,'' he said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Consumers Union filed a petition with the <ORGANIZATION>National Highway
Traffic Safety Administration</ORGANIZATION> asking that the agency change its
regulations to ban the Samurai, which the petition called ``wholly
unsuitable for consumer use.''
   A similar petition alleging the Samurai's rollover problem was
filed in <DATE>February</DATE> by the Center for <ORGANIZATION>Auto Safety</ORGANIZATION>, a non-profit,
Washington-based consumer group. The government has yet to act on
that petition.
   Both petitions demand that a stability standard for vehicles
that would let the government ban any car that has an undue
propensity to roll over.
   <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> said the Samurai is the first car out of 349
tested in the <DATE>last decade</DATE> to roll over during a routine
accident-avoidance test, in which cars are made to swerve to avoid
an obstacle in the road.
   At a news conference, <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> officials showed a
videotape in which the Samurai lurched onto two wheels and began to
roll over when it suddenly changed lanes at just under 40 mph.
   The car did not roll onto its side because it had been equipped
with arm-like extensions to avoid a rollover. <PERSON>Pittle</PERSON> said the
extensions actually improved the car's stability by lowering its
center of gravity.
   The Samurai's major competitors, the Jeep Wrangler, the Jeep
Cherokee and the <ORGANIZATION>Isuzu Trooper</ORGANIZATION>, were shown making the same maneuver
without losing stability at speeds over 40 mph.
   ``We are not surprised that professional drivers can cause the
Samurai or other motor vehicles to roll over,'' <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said. ``But
the real results of the Samurai safety is proven on American roads
everyday.''
   Between <DATE>November 1985</DATE>, when the Samurai was introduced, and the
end of <DATE>April 1988</DATE> there have been 154,675 Samurais sold in the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. The cars have a suggested retail price of about
<MONEY>$8,500</MONEY>.
there have been 44 reported Samurai rollovers involving 53 injuries
and 16 deaths.
   <ORGANIZATION>NHTSA</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Ron DeFore</PERSON> said he could not comment on whether
the <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> has a higher rollover rate than its competitors, but
said utility vehicles generally have a fatality rate three times
that of light-duty vehicles, such as small pickups, and that
rollovers account for two-thirds of the fatalities in utility
vehicles.
   <PERSON>DeFore</PERSON> said drivers of utility vehicles such as the Samurai tend
to be younger and more adventurous than the average driver of a
passenger car, and therefore are more prone to accidents.
   In its statement, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> said that in all of the accidental
deaths involving the car, police found that serious driver errors
led to the accidents.
   The company also said it believes the attacks on the Samurai may
have been triggered in part by trial lawyers seeking to foster
public opinion against <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> and perhaps the entire sport vehicle
industry.
   Suzuki also said it believes it has been targeted because the
Samurai is the leading imported sport utility vehicle from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>
and has gained tremendous media attention because of its uniqueness
and affordability.
   The company said it would continue trying to determine the
original source of allegations against the vehicle and why the
company is being singled out. It will then consider legal action,
it said.
   The most famous vehicle rollovers involved the Jeep CJ5 and CJ7,
which the Wrangler superseded in <DATE>1986</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which bought
<ORGANIZATION>American Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August</DATE>, inherited liability for lawsuits
seeking nearly <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY> in damages caused by Jeep rollovers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880922-0072 </DOCNO>
<HL> Suzuki, Ending Its Dependence On Samurai, Plans 2 New Vehicles </HL>
<AUTHOR> Bradley A. Stertz (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> GM </CO>
<IN> AUT MON </IN>
<DATELINE> DETROIT  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Struggling <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> is trying to rebound by introducing two new vehicles this <DATE>fall</DATE>, including a new Jeep-like model aimed at keeping the young buyers the company is in danger of losing. 

   The new Suzuki Swift subcompact car and <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Sidekick</ORGANIZATION> sport utility vehicle will leave the Japanese manufacturer far less dependent on the four-wheel-drive Samurai model. 
That sport utility vehicle has been <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON>'s sole model since entering the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>, and its sales plunged in <DATE>June</DATE> following charges that the Samurai is unsafe and tends to roll over in sharp turns. 

   Suzuki's <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales and marketing arm will continue to sell the Samurai in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> during the <DATE>1989</DATE> model year. 
But company officials say Samurai supplies will be far lower, with just 2,000 Samurais a month coming from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> at least through <DATE>April</DATE>. 
Suzuki used to sell 6,000 to 7,000 Samurais a month last year, and sold a record 12,208 in <DATE>August</DATE>. 
That was after <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> instituted deep discounts and aggressive advertising to counter critics and bring buyers back to showrooms. 

   But now the company's marketing attention is shifting completely away from the Samurai in favor of the two new vehicles. 
Suzuki officials say they will spend <MONEY>$11 million</MONEY> in advertising by year end to launch the Swift and the Sidekick. 
By <DATE>April</DATE>, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> expects to ship 20,000 of the cars and 30,000 of the sport-utility vehicles to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   Versions of both vehicles will be imported by <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> for its new Geo line. 
But <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> limited <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s version of the Swift to a three-cylinder engine while giving its own models a more-powerful four-cylinder engine. 
Also, availability of <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s version of the <ORGANIZATION>Sidekick</ORGANIZATION> will be limited to a few states. 

   The looks of the Sidekick and Samurai are similar, although Suzuki increased the wheelbase of the Sidekick by nearly seven inches -- a move that's expected to add stability. 
The pricing of the two vehicles also will be close. 
The Sidekick's base price is <MONEY>$8,995</MONEY>, compared with the Samurai's <MONEY>$8,495</MONEY> base price. 

   Suzuki officials insist the two will attract different buyers. 
"There are still people out there that want a Samurai and not a Sidekick," said <PERSON>Jim Weber</PERSON>, communications director for <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION> "I've got to think a lot of that is utilitarian, or for uniqueness." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880609-0297 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-09-88 1713EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f BC-SuzukiSamurai     06-09 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Suzuki Samurai,0332</SECOND>
<HEAD>Suzuki Lashes Back At Criticism Of Samurai's Safety</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: AMs version expected by 6 p.m. EDT.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GARTIES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A consumer group's accusation that the sporty
<ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Samurai</ORGANIZATION> is prone to roll over was denounced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by the
Japanese automaker as ``inaccurate and defamatory.''
   Test results announced last week by <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> publisher of Consumer Reports Magazine, unfairly suggest the
popular four-wheel drive vehicle is unsafe under normal driving
<ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``If the magazine had acted responsibly and reviewed the
available information it would have been aware that the Samurai has
one of the best records on file,'' <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said.
   Last week the influential consumer organization condemned the
Samurai as being so prone to roll over that it cannot be modified
to be safe. <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> recommended a omplete recall of the
120,000 or more Samurais sold in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and a complete refund to
owners.
   Responding to the accusations made by Suzuki in news conferences
in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> spokesman
<PERSON>David Berliner</PERSON> defended the organization's tests as valid. He said
similar vehicles made by competitors passed the same tests that
caused the Samurai to tip over.
   Government accident statistics and tests conducted by an
independent automotive safety consultant showed the Samurai was as
safe or safer than other sport-utility vehicles, <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said. That
industry term refers to four-wheel drive cars and light pick-up
trucks.
   Samurai is considering legal action against <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said. He suggested the consumer group made its accusations as
part of a calculated campaign to persuade the government to adopt
stricter rollover standards.
   ``For years the <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> has been pressing the government
for an unrealistic rollover standard,'' <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said. ``What better
way than pressing the smallest Japanese automaker with the No. 1
selling sport-utility vehicle?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880903-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-03-88 0520EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SamuraiSales     09-03 0487</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Samurai Sales,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Samurai Sales Hit Record In August Despite Rollover Concerns</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boosted by rebates that could cut the sticker
price by almost <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales of the Suzuki Samurai set a
record in <DATE>August</DATE> despite concerns about the four-wheel-drive
vehicle's safety.
   Official sales figures will not be reported until <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, but
<PERSON>Douglas Mazza</PERSON>, general manager of <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s automotive division,
said <DATE>Friday</DATE> he hoped the total would exceed 10,000 for the month.
   The surprising turnaround appears to be the result of the
generous dealer incentive program by the Japanese carmaker and
fading public concern about the rollover issue raised by <ORGANIZATION>Consumers
Union</ORGANIZATION>, publisher of Consumer Reports magazine.
   ``It will clearly be a record for our company, which is
impressive for 80 to 90 days from when our accuser first came at
us,'' <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said.
   Sales plummeted <PERCENT>70.6 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>June</DATE> to 2,199 after the <DATE>June 2</DATE>
report by <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>. The group said the <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Samurai</ORGANIZATION>'s
center of gravity was too high, making it too likely to tip over
when the driver swerved sharply.
   American Suzuki produced its own tests and statistical evidence
to back its claim the Samurai was safe, and on <DATE>July 13</DATE> announced
<MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> incentives to dealers that made it possible for them to cut
a quarter of the <ORGANIZATION>Samurai</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$7,995</MONEY> base price.
   Samurai sales rose to 6,327 in <DATE>July</DATE>, about average.
   Sales from <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE> through <DATE>Friday</DATE>, which is the end of the latest
reporting period, will smash the record of 8,365 set in <DATE>July 1987</DATE>,
said <PERSON>Laura Segall</PERSON>, of the public relations firm <ORGANIZATION>Rogers &amp;
Associates</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>'s public relations agency.
   The dealer incentive program ended <DATE>Friday</DATE>, and the company and
its competitors will be watching closely to see whether the sales
momentum continues.
   Suzuki had been counting on a rebound in Samurai sales to create
a good atmosphere for the introduction this <DATE>fall</DATE> of two new
vehicles: a bigger, more powerful, more expensive sport-utility
vehicle named the Sidekick, and a passenger car named the Swift.
   The Sidekick is scheduled to be introduced this month. The Swift
will be introduced in <DATE>October</DATE> in a two-door hatchback version and
in <DATE>November</DATE> in a four-door hatchback model.
   The Samurai received a boost <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when the <ORGANIZATION>National Highway
Traffic Safety Administration</ORGANIZATION> turned down petitions to investigate
and recall the vehicle. The agency said the Samurai is no more
dangerous than similar vehicles made by other companies.
   The agency did grant a <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> request to start a
rule-making procedure to establish a minimum standard for vehicles
to protect against rollovers.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Transportation Department</ORGANIZATION> agency said it had found 113
reported rollovers involving the Samurai and related vehicles made
by <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>, which resulted in 25 deaths and 120 injuries. But the
agency attributed many of the rollovers to unsafe driving, drinking
and unfamiliarity with the vehicles.
   American Suzuki, based in <LOCATION>Brea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, is the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> arm of
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900613-0120
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900613-0120.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Chrysler to End
   Joint Venture
   With Renault
   ---
   Mini-Sport Vehicle Project
   Is No Longer Attractive,
   U.S., French Firms Say
   ----
   By Jacqueline Mitchell
</HL>
<DATE>
06/13/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A6
</SO>
<CO>
   C F.RNA
</CO>
<IN>
AUTOMOBILES (AUT)
</IN>
<LP>
   HIGHLAND PARK, Mich. -- Chrysler Corp. and Renault S.A.
said they agreed to terminate their joint venture to produce
a new mini-sport utility vehicle because the venture "is no
longer economically attractive."
   The U.S. and French auto makers didn't provide much detail
about why they are scrapping the venture, but persons
familiar with the deal say it was plagued with problems and
unanswered questions.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   One of the biggest problems was just how well the little
Jeeps, codenamed "JJ," would sell. When the venture was
established in <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> said <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales might reach
100,000 a year. "Clearly, the way that market is performing,
there is no way it could support that many units," said
<PERSON>Christopher Cedergren</PERSON>, director of competitive assessments at
<ORGANIZATION>J.D. Power &amp; Associates</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> market research firm.
   This is partly because of increasing competition from
products such as <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet Geo
Tracker</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Daihatsu Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s Rocky, and <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s
Samurai and <ORGANIZATION>Sidekick</ORGANIZATION>.
   In addition, consumers seem to prefer larger sport utility
models including <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION>'s Jeep Cherokee and <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor
Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s Explorer. As a result, <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> isn't the only <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
auto maker to rethink plans for little sport utility
vehicles. <PERSON>Mr. Cedergren</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> scrapped about a year ago a
mini-Jeep-like vehicle codenamed "UW52."
   It isn't clear whether <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> will abandon JJ
completely. In a statement, the No. 3 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> auto maker said it
"intends to continue" with the project and is "reviewing
various implementation alternatives." But a spokesman said <PERSON>JJ</PERSON>
is "still iffy. . . . We aren't going to build any vehicle we
can't make money on."
   One <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> executive said the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> auto maker had
recently taken a "fresh business look" at the venture in the
wake of the mid-May resignation of international operations
vice president <PERSON>Michael N. Hammes</PERSON> to take a top job at <ORGANIZATION>Black &amp;
Decker Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   Chrysler officials were said to be concerned about several
issues. One involved <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION>'s ceding four key markets to
<ORGANIZATION>Renault</ORGANIZATION>, including <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>. In addition, <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION>
wanted to build the four-door version first; <ORGANIZATION>Renault</ORGANIZATION> favored
the two-door.
   The manufacturers budgeted <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> for the venture
but neither would say how much they've actually spent. The
<ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> will reimburse <ORGANIZATION>Renault</ORGANIZATION> for
expenses incurred during the feasibility study but he
wouldn't be more specific.
   The initial agreement called for JJ to be built in <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and sold world-wide, with European
deliveries estimated at 50,000 a year. European production
was to begin in <DATE>July 1992</DATE>, with North American output
following about <DATE>six months later</DATE>.
   In <DATE>February</DATE>, the companies said they had chosen a <ORGANIZATION>Renault</ORGANIZATION>
factory in <LOCATION>Valladolid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, as the European source.
<ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> hadn't confirmed the <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> location, but
<ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Toledo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, Jeep plant was expected to get the
job.
   A <ORGANIZATION>United Auto Workers</ORGANIZATION> union spokesman said union members
at the plant ratified a tentative contract <DATE>Monday</DATE> that would
keep the plant open until <DATE>1997</DATE>. The contract includes a
commitment from <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> that if JJ is built in <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION>, it will be built in <LOCATION>Toledo</LOCATION>. But the tentative
contract is contingent on "a lot of ifs," the <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION> spokesman
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880603-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-03-88 0342EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SuzukiSamurai Bjt   06-03 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Suzuki Samurai, Bjt,0752</SECOND>
<HEAD>Consumer Group Calls For Ban On Suzuki Utility Vehicle</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Samurai</ORGANIZATION> is so unstable it ``literally
trips over its own feet'' and rolls over, says the publisher of
Consumer Reports, which gave the popular sport vehicle its first
``not acceptable'' rating in 10 years.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>American Suzuki Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION> defended the Japanese-built
Samurai as safe and said there was no justification for the
magazine publisher's claim that it should be banned because it
tends to turn over in sudden turns.
   Consumers Union, publisher of Consumer Reports, said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
the Samurai is too short, too narrow, too light and has too high a
center of gravity to be safe. It asked federal regulators to recall
the more than 150,000 Samurais sold in this country and provide
refunds to owners.
   Consumers Union called the four-wheel-drive sport utility
vehicle ``wholly unsuitable for consumer use'' in a petition filed
   ``That car literally trips over its own feet, and I wouldn't
want to be in it,'' said <PERSON>R. David Pittle</PERSON>, technical director of
<ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION>, at a news conference. ``They're promoted as safe,
fun vehicles, when the fact of the matter is, they're not.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> said the <MONEY>$8,500</MONEY> Samurai was the first car out of
349 tested in the <DATE>last decade</DATE> to roll over during a routine
accident-avoidance test, in which cars are made to swerve to avoid
an obstacle in the road.
   Consumers Union officials showed a videotape in which the
Samurai lurched onto two wheels and began to roll over when it
suddenly changed lanes at just under 40 mph. Arm-like extensions
installed to protect the test drivers prevented the car from
rolling onto its side.
   The Samurai's major competitors, the Jeep Wrangler, the Jeep
Cherokee and the <ORGANIZATION>Isuzu Trooper</ORGANIZATION>, were shown making the same maneuver
without losing stability at speeds higher than 40 mph.
   It was 10 years ago that Consumer Reports labeled the <ORGANIZATION>Dodge
Omni-Plymouth Horizon</ORGANIZATION> models ``not acceptable,'' saying they had a
dangerous steering problem. The problem was corrected the next
model year, the magazine said.
   ``We were thinking of turning it over to our older son. Now we
won't do that,'' said <PERSON>Edward Taylor</PERSON>, 41, of <LOCATION>Cleveland Heights</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, who owns a convertible Samurai.
   ``You're driving down the road at 65 mph and a cat or dog jumps
out in front of you, you have to find out how good a driver you
are. It's something I'm not looking forward to,'' he said.
Suzuki</ORGANIZATION>, said, ``We have absolute confidence that we are selling a
safe and stable vehicle.''
   The company said the Samurai was thoroughly tested for safety,
stability and handling before it was introduced in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> in <DATE>November 1985</DATE>. Suzuki sold 154,675 of them through <DATE>April</DATE>.
   ``We are not surprised that professional drivers can cause the
Samurai or other motor vehicles to roll over,'' <PERSON>Mazza</PERSON> said. ``But
the real results of the Samurai safety is proven on American roads
every day.''
   The petition from <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> asked that the government
require similar vehicles to pass driving tests rather than just
meet design standards.
   The Center for Auto Safety filed a similar petition in <DATE>February</DATE>,
citing the Samurai's rollover problem. The center said the Samurai
had been involved in at least 32 rollover accidents, resulting in
have been 44 reported incidents of Samurais rolling over, involving
53 injuries and 16 deaths. A spokesman for the agency, <PERSON>Ron DeFore</PERSON>,
would not comment on the <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> petition. The agency has
120 days to respond.
   The company says police found serious driver error in all of the
fatal accidents.
   <PERSON>DeFore</PERSON> said he could not comment on whether the <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> has a
higher rollover rate than its competitors. He said utility vehicles
in general have a fatality rate that is three times that of
light-duty vehicles, such as small pickups, and that rollovers
account for two-thirds of the fatalities in utility vehicles.
   <PERSON>DeFore</PERSON> said drivers of utility vehicles tend to be younger and
more adventurous than the average driver, and are more prone to
accidents.
   Details of the tests are in a report to be published in the <DATE>July</DATE>
issue of Consumer Reports.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870504-0062 </DOCNO>
<HL> Suzuki Lifts Samurai Price
7%, Citing Dollar's Decline</HL>
<DD> 05/04/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> AUTOS, AUTO PARTS (AUT) </IN>
<DATELINE> BREA, Calif.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki of America Automotive Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it increased by <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> the price of its <DATE>1987</DATE> Samurai sport utility vehicles, the company's only automotive product in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   The unit of <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> said the new suggested retail price for hardtop and convertible Samurai models is <MONEY>$7,495</MONEY>, up from <MONEY>$6,995</MONEY>, effective immediately. 
"We have worked very hard to hold down the cost of the Samurai during the severe period of dollar devaluation," said <PERSON>N. Douglas Mazza</PERSON>, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON>'s vice president and general manager. 
"We find now we have reached a point where a price increase is unavoidable." 

   Despite the increase, <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> said it still had the lowest-price offering in the increasingly competitive sport-utility vehicle market. 

   Several other Japanese auto makers -- including <ORGANIZATION>Honda Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mazda Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Motor Corp.</ORGANIZATION> -- have announced price increases this year because the of sharp rise in the yen's value. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880328-0126 </DOCNO>
<HL> Japanese Sport Utility Vehicles Remain In Truck Category, Bypassing Car Quota </HL>
<AUTHOR> Melinda Grenier Guiles (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> JAPAN </CO>
<IN> AUT MON </IN>
<G> CNG TRE </G>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Customs Service</ORGANIZATION> will continue to allow Japanese-made sport utility vehicles without back seats and passenger "amenities" to enter this country as trucks. 

   The decision resolves, for the time being, a controversy that began last <DATE>fall</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> customs officials proposed reclassifying as cars the popular Jeep-like models, which include <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Samurai</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Montero</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Isuzu Trooper</ORGANIZATION>. 
This would have restricted their importation because a Japanese government quota limits <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> car shipments to about 2.3 million a year. 

   The move represents at least a temporary setback for Rep. <PERSON>John D. Dingell</PERSON> (D. 
<LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>), chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House Energy and Commerce Committee</ORGANIZATION>, who initiated the debate. 
Concerned because manufacturers and dealers often installed back seats and other passenger-related equipment after the vehicles cleared customs as trucks, <PERSON>Mr. Dingell</PERSON> asked the <ORGANIZATION>Customs Service</ORGANIZATION> to determine whether the Japanese companies were intentionally circumventing the quota. 
Truck shipments aren't restricted, but face a <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> U.S. duty compared with the <PERCENT>2.5%</PERCENT> duty on cars. 

   Customs Commissioner <PERSON>William von Raab</PERSON> acknowledged that the decision "seems illogical . . . when people see how these vehicles are being used." 
Their versatility and the availability of such carlike features as stereo radio, air conditioning, plush seats and carpeting boosted sales to nearly 200,000 last year. 

   But <PERSON>Mr. von Raab</PERSON> said in a statement that current law "provides very little room for discretion. . . . 
Customs must classify vehicles in their condition as imported." 

   He said in order to "clear up the confusion over classification criteria, the <ORGANIZATION>Customs Service</ORGANIZATION> will be asking for public comment in the near future" on how to "simplify" the classification process. 
Possible solutions could include a new category for sport utility vehicles, or changes in the existing criteria to emphasize the way the vehicles are used rather than their condition as imported. 
Such changes could take months as the <ORGANIZATION>Customs Service</ORGANIZATION> collects and considers the comments. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Dingell</PERSON>'s response was sharp and immediate. 
"We don't like illogical decisions any more than Commissioner von Raab . . . but the <ORGANIZATION>Customs Service</ORGANIZATION> announcement makes it look like they are bowing to the Japanese firms who are trying to circumvent the Voluntary Restraint Agreement's requirements." 

   Not surprisingly, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales arms of <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Isuzu Motors Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> disagreed. 
All had asked the <ORGANIZATION>Customs Service</ORGANIZATION> to reconsider the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> district office's proposal to reclassify the vehicles. 

   "We're very happy with the way this came out," said <PERSON>Munford Page Hall II</PERSON>, an attorney with <ORGANIZATION>Dorsey &amp; Whitney</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, representing <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki of America Automotive Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 
"We know we did not incorporate any substantial changes into the (current) vehicles" that would have made them different from the models customs officials originally agreed were trucks. 

   As for the prospect that the classification might change in the future, the companies all said they will have to wait and see what the <ORGANIZATION>Customs Service</ORGANIZATION> decides. 
In the meantime, "our position is that we're just going to continue as is," said <PERSON>E.F. Kern</PERSON>, vice president of marketing for <ORGANIZATION>American Isuzu Motors Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880707-0162 </DOCNO>
<HL> Suzuki Samurai's Sales Have Plunged Since Consumers Union Called It Unsafe </HL>
<AUTHOR> Bradley A. Stertz (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> AUT </IN>
<TEXT>
   Sales of <ORGANIZATION>Suzuki Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s Samurai plunged <PERCENT>70.5%</PERCENT> in <DATE>June</DATE>, following charges by <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> that the four-wheel-drive sport-utility vehicle is unsafe. 

   The whopping monthly sales decline was the worst that <PERSON>Suzuki</PERSON> has posted since it first introduced the Samurai to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> in <DATE>November 1985</DATE>. 
The poor sales also left many Suzuki dealers uncertain about the vehicle's future, even though several said sales improved somewhat in recent days. 

   Suzuki, which sells only the Samurai in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, reported <DATE>June</DATE> sales dropped to 2,199 vehicles from the 7,479 it sold a year earlier. 
Suzuki sold 6,074 Samurai vehicles in <DATE>May</DATE>, before <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> published in its Consumer Reports magazine an article saying the Samurai has a "dangerous propensity" to roll over when its driver attempts to make a sharp turn. 

   Suzuki's <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials offered little comment yesterday on the steep sales decline, in an apparent attempt to play down the bad news. 
In a news release, the company said it "was not surprised by the drop in sales . . . because of the widespread negative publicity on the Samurai." 

   Suzuki dealers said they hope the company moves quickly to attract buyers back into showrooms. 
"This whole situation is frustrating because I have no control over it," said <PERSON>Tom Lilly</PERSON>, general manager of <PERSON>George Ballas Suzuki</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Toledo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>. 
"Whatever Suzuki comes out with couldn't hurt at this point." 

   Some dealers may take matters into their own hands. 
<PERSON>Mr. Lilly</PERSON>'s dealership, for example, is weighing giving Samurai buyers free life-insurance policies. 
Others are flooding their local television broadcasts with press releases and advertising that stresses the quality and safety of the vehicles. 

   Dealers also are trying to talk upbeat. 
Although <PERSON>Dick Smith Suzuki</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, sold only 17 Samurais in <DATE>June</DATE>, general manager <PERSON>Phil Smith</PERSON> expects to sell about 30 in <DATE>July</DATE> and 40 in <DATE>August</DATE>. 
"As time progresses, the furor tends to get out of people's minds," <PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON> said. 
"People may be more inquisitive now, but at least they're coming in the doors again." 

   Since the appearance of the Consumer Reports article, Suzuki officials have hinted that the company may sue its critics. 
But company officials and dealers said they needed to wait and assess the damage to sales. 

   Such damage was evident yesterday, but a Suzuki spokesman said the company still hasn't made any decision about legal action or any other moves, such as increased advertising or buyer incentives. 
Suzuki did increase its advertising immediately after Consumer Reports published its article in its <DATE>July</DATE> issue and changed its theme to safety from fun. 
Attorneys general from several states have begun investigations to determine whether that advertising is deceptive. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-3801 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi079_b_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-079 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  23 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> United States &amp; Canada </F>
<H3> <TI>   Former U.S. President Nixon Dies 22 Apr </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Former U.S. President Nixon Dies 22 Apr </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW2304101194 Beijing XINHUA Domestice Service in Chinese 
0749 GMT 23 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> OW2304101194 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA Domestice Service </F>
<F P=105>  Chinese </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 22 Apr (XINHUA) -- Former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
President <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON> died of a major stroke at <DATE>2108</DATE> (EST) 
today at <ORGANIZATION>New York Hospital Cornell Medical Center</ORGANIZATION> at the age of 
81, reports reaching here said. 
  Nixon suffered a major stroke at his <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> home at 
around supper time on <DATE>April 18</DATE>, and he was soon rushed to the 
hospital. 
  Beginning <DATE>Thursday</DATE> [21 <DATE>April</DATE>] afternoon, <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> lapsed into a 
very deep coma. 
  The life-long Republican was born in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> on 9 <DATE>January 
in <DATE>1946</DATE> and to the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1950</DATE>. He was elected vice 
president as running-mate to <PERSON>Dwight Eisenhower</PERSON> in <DATE>1952</DATE> and 
re-elected vice president in <DATE>1956</DATE>. 
over Democrat <PERSON>Hubert Humphrey</PERSON> and independent <PERSON>George Wallace</PERSON> and 
on 20 <DATE>January 1969</DATE>, he was sworn in as the 37th president of the 
country. 
  In <DATE>November 1972</DATE> he was re-elected <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> president until 9 
<DATE>August 1974</DATE>, when he was forced to resign in culmination of the 
Watergate scandal, thus becoming the only president in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
history to resign to avoid impeachment. 
  The former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> leader visited <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in <DATE>February 1972</DATE> and at 
the end of his visit, the Chinese and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Governments issued 
the famous "<LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION> Communique," opening the door to Sino-U.S. 
exchanges. He later visited <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> five more times as an old 
friend of the Chinese people. 
  Beginning <TIME>this evening</TIME>, flags in the capital <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and 
the rest of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> will fly at half-mast for 30 days 
to mourn <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON>'s death. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881107-0076 </DOCNO>
<HL> Who's News: Dior-New York President Colombe Nicholas Resigns </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> WNEWS </CO>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christian <PERSON>Dior-New York</PERSON> said its president, <PERSON>Colombe Nicholas</PERSON>, resigned "for personal reasons." 

   No successor was named. 
<PERSON>Ms. Nicholas</PERSON> couldn't be reached for comment. 

   <PERSON>Ms. Nicholas</PERSON>, an attorney who has 10 years of retail experience and speaks fluent French, made headlines in <DATE>1980</DATE> when she beat out other male candidates to become the head of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> operations for the French design company. 
Under her reign, <ORGANIZATION>Christian Dior</ORGANIZATION> expanded its <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> licenses to 48 from 32 and tripled annual revenue to about <MONEY>$420 million</MONEY>. 

   The 43-year-old <PERSON>Ms. Nicholas</PERSON> was credited with helping to jazz up Dior's staid image, notably with the help of the racy "three Diors" -- a woman and two men -- print ads in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>. 
She was currently involved in getting Dior's first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> boutique launched on <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s Upper East Side by the end of the year. 

   In leaving Dior, <PERSON>Ms. Nicholas</PERSON> also resigned from her management responsibilities for French designer <PERSON>Christian Lacroix</PERSON> in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
Both Dior and <PERSON>Lacroix</PERSON> are controlled by a French-based conglomerate, <ORGANIZATION>Financiere Agache</ORGANIZATION>. 
