<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890911-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-11-89 0223EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-PrisonPopulation     09-11 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Prison Population,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prison Population Rises Over 670,000</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The number of inmates in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> prisons jumped by
a record <PERCENT>7.3 percent</PERCENT> during the <DATE>first half of 1989</DATE> to a total of
673,565 inmates, the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Justice Statistics</ORGANIZATION> says.
   The six-month increase of 46,004 inmates was higher than any
full-year increase recorded during the 64 years that the government
has counted prisoners, the bureau said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The largest annual increase ever recorded was in <DATE>1981-82</DATE>, when
the national prison population grew by 41,060 inmates, from 344,283
to 385,343, said <PERSON>Tom Hester</PERSON> of the bureau.
   The surge in prison population during the <DATE>first half of 1989</DATE> was
brought about by increases of <PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT> in the number of men
imprisoned and <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT> in the number of women, the bureau said.
   Attorney General <PERSON>Dick Thornburgh</PERSON> said the increase was ``an
indication that more criminals, many convicted of drug-related
offenses, are being caught and punished.''
   ``The criminal justice system is working,'' <PERSON>Thornburgh</PERSON> said in a
statement. ``People who break the law do pay the price.''
   The figures dramatize the need for almost 1,800 new prison beds a
week, the bureau said. ``<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> needs to act swiftly on President
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s violent crime legislation, which provides for the
construction of more than 24,000 new federal prison beds,''
<PERSON>Thornburgh</PERSON> said.
   The national drug control strategy, announced by <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> last
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, echoed the crime legislation <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> called for in <DATE>May</DATE> in
seeking <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE> budget authorization for additional
federal prison space.
   Most of the increase from <DATE>Dec. 31, 1988</DATE>, to <DATE>June 30, 1989</DATE>,
occurred in the state prison systems, where the population grew by
41,214 or <PERCENT>7.1 percent</PERCENT>, from 577,633 at the end of <DATE>1988</DATE> to 618,847 at
the end of <DATE>June</DATE>. During the same period, the federal prison
population expanded by 4,790, a <PERCENT>9.7 percent</PERCENT> increase from 49,928 to
54,718.
   During the six-month period, nine jurisdictions reported
double-digit growth in their inmate populations: <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>20.3
percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>19.9 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>18.4 percent</PERCENT>;
<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>13.2 percent</PERCENT>; the <LOCATION>District of Columbia</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>12.1 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>,
<PERCENT>11.3 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>10.6 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>10.4 percent</PERCENT>; and
<LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>10.2 percent</PERCENT>.
   Two states experienced declines in prison populations _
<LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>2.3 percent</PERCENT>, and <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>2.1 percent</PERCENT>. And
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> had such a small increase, only 2 prisoners more, that the
change was listed as <PERCENT>0 percent</PERCENT>.
   Since <DATE>1980</DATE>, the number of state and federal prisoners serving
sentences of more than one year _ known as sentenced prisoners _
more than doubled, from 315,974, while four states recorded a
tripling of such inmates _ <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New
Jersey</LOCATION>.
   An additional 25 states and the <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> doubled
their prison populations.
   Overall, the number of sentenced prisoners as of <DATE>June 30</DATE> was 260
per 100,000 population, with 18 of them in federal prisons and 242
in state institutions. On <DATE>Dec. 31, 1980</DATE>, there were 139 sentenced
prisoners per 100,000 population, the bureau said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870818-0048 </DOCNO>
<HL> REGIONS:
Multistate Lottery's Prospects
Grow, Even Absent Big States
---
By Eugene Carlson
<DD> 08/18/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   RULE ONE in the lottery business: The bigger the jackpot, the more tickets you sell. 
So if you're running a state lottery that offers relatively small cash awards, and you know that hundreds -- perhaps thousands -- of your potential customers are playing the multimillion-dollar lottery in the big state next door, your strategy is pretty clear: Double, triple or quadruple your own grand prize, and keep those ticket sales at home. 

   That's exactly what <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, whose citizens are regular players in the wealthy lottery in neighboring <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, hope to do. 
Starting early next year, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> plan to join forces with several other states in a coast-to-coast, multistate lottery. 

   The idea is to promote the same lottery"<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s Game" is one of the names being considered -- in states from <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>. 
The states would be linked by satellite every <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> for the weekly drawing. 

   The new game is likely to hurt ticket sales in participating states' existing lotteries. 
But organizers of the multistate game are betting that the public's usual response to lotteries will prevail. 
That is, a large population base will produce lots of ticket sales, which will build big jackpots, which will inspire even more sales, far outweighing any revenue loss in single-state games. 
As usual in the lottery business, the odds of winning will be infinitesimal. 

   THE BIG QUESTION is membership. 
Six states, with a combined population of 16 million, already are committed to the plan: <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> says it's in, too. 
If past experience is any guide, that should make the multistate lottery one of the nation's richest games of chance. 

   It would be richer still if <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, both early supporters of the multistate idea, weren't sitting on the sidelines. 
Illinois Gov. <PERSON>James Thompson</PERSON> is stringing out a decision whether to participate. 
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s lottery director, <PERSON>John Quinn</PERSON>, says his state won't play unless <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> does. (<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s legislature needs to approve the state's multistate membership; a bill to that effect apparently died last month when the assembly recessed.) 

   Signing up the two big states would triple the multistate lottery's projected population base to 45 million. 
The small states think this is wonderful, because residents of <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> would have a shot -- albeit tiny -- at a huge grand prize in a homestate lottery. 
Ticket sales in those states would presumably soar. 

   THE RATIONALE BEHIND LOTTERIES, after all, is to raise money for state government programs and thus ease the bite on taxpayers. 
Oregon's lottery, just two years old, has already earned <MONEY>$70 million</MONEY> for state economic development programs ranging from new university buildings to commercial fishing piers. 
In <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>42%</PERCENT> of lottery income goes to elementary and secondary schools. 
Last year, that came to <MONEY>$553 million</MONEY>. 

   Indeed, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, with its own popular lottery, has less incentive than the smaller states to join the multistate lottery. 
It was <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, after all, that produced the richest prize won by a single ticketholder in a North American lottery: <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> in <DATE>September 1984</DATE>. 
The huge pot came after the lottery went four weeks without a winner, the grand prize rolling over and growing each week. 

   "During those four weeks, we had tremendous ticket sales," recalls <PERSON>Michael Jones</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>'s lottery superintendent at the time and now a Chicago-based lottery consultant. 

   It's what lottery directors dream about: a game designed in such a way that every so often, no one wins the grand prize for two or three weeks in a row. 
The prize money builds, newspapers and television give the game big coverage, and people line up everywhere to buy tickets in a sort of gambler's feeding frenzy. 

   But <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION>'s grand prize hasn't come close to that level since , leading the state's lottery strategists to wonder how to boost business. 
One way is to join the multistate game. 
<PERSON>Rebecca Paul</PERSON>, who resigned as <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION>'s lottery director last week to head <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s new lottery, thinks that's the wave of the future. 
In <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, multistate or multiprovince lotteries are the most widely played. 
"I think that's where we're headed three to five years from now," <PERSON>Ms. Paul</PERSON> says. 

   MR. JONES FORESEES a different format. 
"I see the large states getting together in a super lotto." 
He suggests a "triangle game" with <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, or a Great Lakes regional lottery, with <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>. 
There is a precedent: <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> already run a lottery called <ORGANIZATION>Tristate Megabucks</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Ms. Paul</PERSON>, whose <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> game will begin <DATE>Jan. 15</DATE>, doesn't like the idea of such fragmented lotteries. 
"I think it's bad for the industry to have competing multistate games," she says. 

   Multistate games aren't the only way to draw more players; states can also change the odds on an existing game. 
Illinois did that in <DATE>April</DATE>, introducing a new <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> lotto drawing that makes it easier to win a cheap prize (last week it was one chance in 89 to win <MONEY>$12</MONEY> on a <MONEY>$1</MONEY> ticket), but tougher to win the grand prize (one chance in 15.4 million). 
The idea paid off late last month, when the jackpot reached <MONEY>$22 million</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION>'s highest in three years. 

   As for the multistate plan, <ORGANIZATION>Sharon Sharp</ORGANIZATION>, who took over yesterday as <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION> lottery director, says she hasn't made up her mind about <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION> membership. 
If the answer is yes, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> will be the site of the weekly multistate lottery drawing. 
If <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION> says no, the winning numbers will be picked in <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910909-0175
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910909-0175.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   PEOPLE PATTERNS
   ----
   By Alan L. Otten
</HL>
<DATE>
09/09/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
FINANCIAL (FIN)
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
MEDICAL AND BIOTECHNOLOGY, GENETIC RESEARCH, PROSTHETICS (MTC)
REAL ESTATE INVESTMENTS (REA)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<GV>
COMMERCE DEPARTMENT (COM)
HEALTH AND HUMAN SERVICES (HHS)
</GV>
<RE>
FLORIDA (FL)
MASSACHUSETTS (MA)
MARYLAND (MD)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PENNSYLVANIA (PA)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Racial Groups Diverge
   In Timing of First Births
                                                                                                       

</LP>
<TEXT>
   RACIAL differences in the timing of first births are
widening, two <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION> demographers find.
   Drawing on birth and other records published since <DATE>1979</DATE>,
<PERSON>Renbao Chen</PERSON> and <PERSON>S. Philip Morgan</PERSON> determine that from <DATE>1980</DATE> to
<DATE>1987</DATE> white women under 30 years old continued an earlier
trend toward postponing their first birth, while white women
over 30 began showing slightly higher rates of first births
than over-30 women of earlier decades, clearly seeking to
catch up on postponed fertility. Nonwhite women -- blacks,
Asians and others -- also tended to have their first children
at somewhat later ages than nonwhite women in earlier years.
   But at every age from the teens on, blacks and other
nonwhites were far more likely to be having their first birth
than were white women of the same age. For example, in <DATE>1987</DATE> a
20-year-old nonwhite woman was almost twice as likely to have
her first child in the following year as was a 20-year-old
white woman, while a 25-year-old nonwhite woman was about 1
1/2 times more likely to be having her first child than her
white counterpart.
   The research also showed that nonwhite women now have far
lower rates of childlessness than white women. Historically,
blacks had far higher rates, due largely to health and other
involuntary factors. This situation started reversing in the
<DATE>1950s</DATE>, and the difference has grown greater as more white
women have forgone having children altogether. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, for
instance, a white woman born in <DATE>1954</DATE> was better than three
times more likely to be childless than a 33-year-old
nonwhite.
                                                                                                       

   Farm Belt Holds Onto
   Its Oldest Americans
                                                                                                       

   THE OLDEST old, those 85 or more, bulk largest in the Farm
Belt, <DATE>1990</DATE> census figures show.
   Not surprisingly, the largest numbers of 85-plus men and
women are found in the most populous states: <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>. In each of these, people 85 and over total well
into six figures.
   Looked at as a percentage of a state's population,
however, a much different picture emerges. In 14 states, the
85-and-older group accounts for <PERCENT>1.5%</PERCENT> or more of the total
population. Iowa leads with <PERCENT>2.0%</PERCENT>, closely followed by <LOCATION>South
Dakota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>1.9%</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>1.8%</PERCENT> and
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>1.7%</PERCENT>.
   In nine other states, including <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, the oldest old account for
<PERCENT>1.6%</PERCENT> or <PERCENT>1.5%</PERCENT> of the total. The other states in this category
are <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>: <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, by contrast, is at the bottom of the ranking,
with only <PERCENT>0.2%</PERCENT> of its population 85 or older.
   Much the same states rank at or near the top in the
percentage of total state population living in nursing homes.
The <LOCATION>Dakotas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> are the only states with
at least <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> of their populations living in nursing homes.
Census Bureau specialist <PERSON>Cynthia Taeuber</PERSON> says most nursing
home residents are 85 or older.
   So why do the oldest old figure so heavily in these
states? <PERSON>Ms. Taeuber</PERSON> hypothesizes that in most of these states
younger adults move out to seek better job opportunities,
while the older natives stay and age in place, inevitably
constituting a larger share of the total. And with their
children moved away, many end up in nursing homes.
   Another census report says that the number of
centenarians, men and women 100 or older, more than doubled
between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1990</DATE>, increasing to 35,808 from an estimated
14,000 to 16,000. (There was no precise count in <DATE>1980</DATE>.) More
than 28,000 of the 35,808 were women, and well over 29,000 of
the total were white.
                                                                                                       

   Golf Has More Players,
   Who Play More Often
                                                                                                       

   MORE PEOPLE are playing golf, and most are playing more
often, a recreation specialist reports.
   <PERSON>Rod Warnick</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Massachusetts</ORGANIZATION> professor who
tracks leisure trends, calculates that the number of adult
golfers increased about <PERCENT>6%</PERCENT> a year in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> to 22.2
million, while the number of days played grew about <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT>
annually to 393.7 million. Moreover, he notes, the number of
"heavy" golfers, those playing 20 or more times a year, grew
even faster, more than doubling to 6.8 million, while the
number of days these avid golfers played increased about <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT>
annually to almost 300 million days.
   <PERSON>Mr. Warnick</PERSON> says the growth of leisure time, the
increasing numbers of retirees and the aging of the baby
boomers all contributed. He also finds that more women and
minorities have taken up the game -- a trend he sees as apt
to lead to further anti-discrimination suits against golf
clubs and courses that aren't fully integrated or given to
equal treatment.
                                                                                                       

   Odds and Ends
                                                                                                       

   MOBILE HOMES make up <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> of the nation's housing inventory,
the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports. This is the fastest-growing type
of housing, up <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> since <DATE>1980</DATE>. . . . Athletes who play hard
to win are more apt to get hurt than those who just play for
fun, <ORGANIZATION>University of Florida</ORGANIZATION> researchers find. They say those
who take a game too much to heart are more likely to put
themselves in a risky situation in an effort to come out
ahead. . . . Diseases and other causes of disability in women
65 and older will be the subject of a seven-year study by the
<ORGANIZATION>Johns Hopkins School of Medicine</ORGANIZATION> under a contract with the
government's <ORGANIZATION>National Institute on Aging</ORGANIZATION>. About two-thirds of
all disabled older people are female.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870122-0092 </DOCNO>
<HL> Justices Decide States Can Deny Benefits
To Women Leaving Jobs for Pregnancy
---
By Stephen Wermiel
<DD> 01/22/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> LABOR JCP IP
ENVIRONMENT (ENV)
SUPREME COURT (SUP)
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS) </IN>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> ruled unanimously that federal law permits states to deny unemployment compensation to women who give up their jobs because of pregnancy. 

   The high court upheld a <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> law that denies unemployment benefits to all employees who leave work for reasons that aren't caused by the job itself. 
Under <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> law, for example, layoffs or illness caused by a job would be considered work-related; pregnancy isn't viewed as a job-related reason for leaving. 

   By an 8-0 vote, the high court ruled that a federal law passed in <DATE>1976</DATE> says pregnant women can't be singled out for less-favorable treatment than other workers who seek jobless benefits. 
The law doesn't say pregnant women must be treated better, the court said in an opinion written by Justice <PERSON>Sandra O'Connor</PERSON>. 

   Estimates of the number of states with laws similar to <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>'s vary. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> mentioned <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>, while the lawyer for the woman challenging the <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> law listed <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The ruling involves different federal and state laws from <DATE>last week</DATE>'s 6-3 decision that states may require employers to give disability leave and to guarantee job reinstatement to pregnant women. 

   Last week's ruling said that federal civil rights law didn't bar the states from requiring that pregnant women be given disability leave, while the decision yesterday involves the federal unemployment law and whether it requires states to provide jobless benefits to pregnant women who leave work. 
The court yesterday made no mention at all of the decision last week. 

   Last week, the justices went out of their way to say that the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> law didn't really require preferential treatment for women; the law simply made women equal in the work place. 
In yesterday's ruling, however, the court said that interpreting federal law to require unemployment benefits for pregnant women would discriminate against other unemployed persons for whom benefits aren't required. 

   The lawsuit was filed by <PERSON>Linda Wimberly</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>J.C. Penney Co.</ORGANIZATION> cashier who took a leave of absence to have a baby in <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
<LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> law doesn't require reinstatement, and when she wanted to return to work one month after her baby was born, the company said there was no job available. 
Her unemployment claim was rejected by the state, and the <ORGANIZATION>Missouri Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> upheld the denial of benefits. 

   The high court's ruling upheld the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration's interpretation of the federal law. 

   Justice <PERSON>Harry Blackmun</PERSON> didn't participate in the case and gave no explanation. 

   Water-Pollution Suits
   The justices ruled 9-0 that a company that is located in one state and pollutes interstate waters can be sued in the courts of another state affected by the pollution. 
But the lawsuit must be decided based on the laws of the state from which the pollution came, rather than based on the affected state's law, the court said in a 5-4 vote. 

   The opinion written by Justice <PERSON>Lewis Powell</PERSON> said that applying one state's pollution laws to a polluting company in another state would interfere with federal water-pollution standards and enforcement. 

   The ruling came in a lawsuit filed by <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> and some of its residents in state court in <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>. 
The suit alleged that an <ORGANIZATION>International Paper Co.</ORGANIZATION> mill on the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> side of <LOCATION>Lake Champlain</LOCATION> was discharging waste into the lake, polluting interstate waters. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> rejected the company's argument that only federal law should apply to the case, and rejected the state's claim that <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> law should apply. 
As a result of the ruling, <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> may continue the lawsuit, but <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> law will govern the case. 

   Justices <PERSON>William Brennan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Thurgood Marshall</PERSON>, <PERSON>Harry Blackmun</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Stevens</PERSON> agreed that some state lawsuits are allowed under the federal law, but disagreed that <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> law must be applied. 

   Annexing Voting Areas
   The justices ruled 6-3 that a city's refusal to annex a largely black neighborhood when it does annex a white neighborhood may violate the federal voting rights law. 
The court upheld a federal court's refusal to approve a proposed annexation by the city of <LOCATION>Pleasant Grove</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala</LOCATION>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> had also refused to approve the city's plan. 

   The voting rights law requires some cities and states to obtain the department's approval before making any changes that affect voting rights. 
The city argued that proposed annexations during the <DATE>1970s</DATE> of a white area and an unoccupied area that the city intended for white housing didn't change voting rights of minorities because the city had an all-white population at the time. 

   But the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>, giving broad meaning to the law, said the annexations of white areas could be seen as an effort to minimize the likely impact of future black voters, which is "as impermissible a purpose as the dilution of present black voting strength." 

   Justices <PERSON>Powell</PERSON>, <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> and Chief Justice <PERSON>William Rehnquist</PERSON> dissented. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890804-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-04-89 0742EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Census-Metros     08-04 1004</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census-Metros,0691</SECOND>
<HEAD>Half of All Americans Live in 37 Metro Areas</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: also on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two centuries after the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was
founded as a largely agricultural nation, nearly nine-tenths of the
population growth is occurring in metropolitan areas, the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports.
   Almost half of all Americans reside in just 37 major urban
areas, the bureau said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a new analysis of the patterns
of growth. And the metropolitan share of the population is growing
faster than that in rural areas.
   The ``rural renaissance'' reported in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> when small towns
and rural areas were growing seems to have ended, with increases in
cities and suburbs now well in the lead.
   The census study found that about <PERCENT>86 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's
population growth since <DATE>1980</DATE> has occurred in the 282 officially
designated metropolitan areas across the country. That pattern
represents a return to the metropolitan area dominance that has
been common since the era of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Depression</ORGANIZATION>, the bureau
reported.
   The analysis of <DATE>1987</DATE> figures found that nearly half of all
Americans, <PERCENT>48.9 percent</PERCENT>, reside in the 37 metro areas with
populations of a million or more.
   Led by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, these metro areas had 119
million residents in <DATE>1987</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> leads the way as the only state entirely included
within metropolitan areas, the bureau noted. The northern portion
of the state is included in the greater <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> metro area while
the southern portion is part of the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> region.
   Seven other states have more than <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of their
populations in metropolitan areas _ <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Idaho is the least metropolitan state with only about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>
of its residents in urban areas, the report added.
   Reflecting the nation's overall population trend, metropolitan
area growth has tended to flow to the South and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in recent
years, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> observed in its study of growth patterns
between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The population loss experienced in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> during the
<DATE>1970s</DATE> has halted in this decade, the agency found, while the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> has continued to have net losses in recent years.
   ``A slowdown in population growth has taken place since <DATE>1980</DATE> in
much of the interior of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, especially in
nonmetropolitan areas,'' noted the report prepared by <PERSON>Donald E.
Starsinic</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard L. Forstall</PERSON>.
   During this decade the nonmetropolitan population declined in 10
contiguous states _ <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
bureau pointed out.
   The nation's metro areas with 1 million or more residents, as of
<DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>, were <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 18.0 million; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, 13.5
million; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, 8.1 million; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, 5.9 million;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, 5.9 million; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, 4.6 million; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, 4.1
million; <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, 3.7 million;
   Also <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, 2.9
million; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, 2.7 million; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, 2.6 million; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>,
2.4 million; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
<LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
   And <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, 1.9 million; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, 1.9
million; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, 1.8 million; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, 1.7 million; <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>,
1.5 million; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, 1.5 million; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 1.4 million;
<LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
   Plus <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>,
1.1 million and Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION>, 1.1 million.
   Here is a state-by-state rundown of the percentage of the
population living in metropolitan areas as of <DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Two centuries after the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was
founded as a largely agricultural nation, nearly nine-tenths of the
population growth is occurring in metropolitan areas, the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports.
   Almost half of all Americans reside in just 37 major urban
areas, the bureau said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a new analysis of the patterns
of growth. And the metropolitan share of the population is growing
faster than that in rural areas.
   The ``rural renaissance'' reported in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> when small towns
and rural areas were growing seems to have ended, with increases in
cities and suburbs now well in the lead.
   The census study found that about <PERCENT>86 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's
population growth since <DATE>1980</DATE> has occurred in the 282 officially
designated metropolitan areas across the country. That pattern
represents a return to the metropolitan area dominance that has
been common since the era of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Depression</ORGANIZATION>, the bureau
reported.
   The analysis of <DATE>1987</DATE> figures found that nearly half of all
Americans, <PERCENT>48.9 percent</PERCENT>, reside in the 37 metro areas with
populations of a million or more.
   Led by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, these metro areas had 119
million residents in <DATE>1987</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> leads the way as the only state entirely included
within metropolitan areas, the bureau noted. The northern portion
of the state is included in the greater <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> metro area while
the southern portion is part of the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> region.
   Seven other states have more than <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of their
populations in metropolitan areas _ <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Idaho is the least metropolitan state with only about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>
of its residents in urban areas, the report added.
   Reflecting the nation's overall population trend, metropolitan
area growth has tended to flow to the South and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in recent
years, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> observed in its study of growth patterns
between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The population loss experienced in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> during the
<DATE>1970s</DATE> has halted in this decade, the agency found, while the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> has continued to have net losses in recent years.
   ``A slowdown in population growth has taken place since <DATE>1980</DATE> in
much of the interior of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, especially in
nonmetropolitan areas,'' noted the report prepared by <PERSON>Donald E.
Starsinic</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard L. Forstall</PERSON>.
   During this decade the nonmetropolitan population declined in 10
contiguous states _ <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
bureau pointed out.
   The nation's metro areas with 1 million or more residents, as of
<DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>, were <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 18.0 million; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, 13.5
million; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, 8.1 million; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, 5.9 million;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, 5.9 million; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, 4.6 million; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, 4.1
million; <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, 3.7 million;
   Also <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, 2.9
million; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, 2.7 million; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, 2.6 million; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>,
2.4 million; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
<LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
   And <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, 1.9 million; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, 1.9
million; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, 1.8 million; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, 1.7 million; <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>,
1.5 million; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, 1.5 million; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 1.4 million;
<LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
   Plus <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>,
1.1 million and Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION>, 1.1 million.
   Here is a state-by-state rundown of the percentage of the
population living in metropolitan areas as of <DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890819-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-89 0209EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WhiteSquirrels     08-19 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-White Squirrels,0782</SECOND>
<HEAD>Missouri Town Nuts About Albino Squirrels</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Saturday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY NACHTIGAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MARIONVILLE, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They're nuts about white squirrels in
<LOCATION>Marionville</LOCATION>. Just ask the folks at the <ORGANIZATION>White Squirrel Furniture
Store</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>White Squirrel Car Wash</ORGANIZATION> or the <ORGANIZATION>White Squirrel Hollow Bed
&amp; Breakfast</ORGANIZATION>.
   And watch where you're driving: A 21-year-old city ordinance
imposes a <MONEY>$500</MONEY> fine for deliberately injuring or killing one of the
rare albino squirrels. Motorists must yield right of way to them.
   No one has ever been arrested for violating the law, but that
doesn't mean it's taken lightly.
   ``If I catch somebody killing a white squirrel, I will issue a
citation,'' said Police Chief <PERSON>Jesse Merritt</PERSON>, who wears a
squirrel-emblazoned shoulder patch on his uniform. ``It's no joke.''
   Some people even go so far as to trap the albinos' gray cousins
and banish them from the small southwest <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> town to give the
white squirrels first crack at the nuts.
   <LOCATION>Marionville</LOCATION>, home to 2,000 people and nearly half that many white
squirrels, has a billboard welcoming visitors to the ``Home of the
White Squirrel.''
   Only one other community in the nation _ <LOCATION>Olney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION> _ is known
to have a sizable concentration of the snow-white squirrels, but
<LOCATION>Marionville</LOCATION>'s colony is much larger, says <PERSON>James Smart</PERSON>, a local
authority and booster of the animal.
   ``We've blown <PERSON>Olney</PERSON> off the map,'' he boasts. Olney has a measly
few dozen squirrels, he figures.
   Wildlife experts say finding any albino animal colony the size of
<LOCATION>Marionville</LOCATION>'s is rare.
   ``Normally you see an albino show up occasionally in a population
such as squirrels or birds or deer, but entire populations are not
something you come across all that frequently,'' said <PERSON>Eric
Kurzejeski</PERSON>, a state wildlife research biologist.
   Signs of <LOCATION>Marionville</LOCATION>'s affection for the white squirrel, which
mates and otherwise interacts normally with its gray cousin, are
everywhere.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Lions Club</ORGANIZATION> sells white squirrel T-shirts and pins to raise
money to buy redwood boxes that are placed in trees as homes for the
squirrels. More than 500 dens have been put up, and volunteers have
planted hundreds of nut trees.
   ``We've had orders for T-shirts from <LOCATION>Kalamazoo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>,'' says <PERSON>Smart</PERSON>, a Lions
member. ``<LOCATION>Marionville</LOCATION> is a small town, but people who grew up here
and moved away still remember their roots and want to help the white
squirrel.''
   White squirrels first appeared in <LOCATION>Marionville</LOCATION> around <DATE>1860</DATE>, Smart
says. According to local legend, a couple of the critters escaped
from a traveling circus and began multiplying, or were the product
of a weird experiment by a local scientist.
   Smart became fascinated by white squirrels when one showed up on
the deck of his home about 12 years ago. He set out to increase the
population by trapping the more numerous gray squirrels in the woods
around his home and releasing them several miles away to provide
more room for the whites.
   ``We trapped 110 gray squirrels in a year and a half,'' he said.
``It was just amazing what the whites did then.''
   Smart estimates that about three dozen albino squirrels live in
30 den boxes and in trees on his heavily wooded property.
   ``I have one picture at home with 17 white squirrels in it,'' he
said.
   Retirees <PERSON>Johnie</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ann Clark</PERSON> spend hours on their back porch
watching the white squirrels munch corn and walnuts placed at their
feeders. The couple had no white squirrels until Smart transplanted
some there a few years ago.
   ``They'll play just like a little kitten,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Clark</PERSON> said.
``There will be five or six in the yard looking for something to eat
and I'll say, `Don't leave, <PERSON>Johnie</PERSON>'s bringing you something.' I
swear they can understand me.''
   <PERSON>Diana Wise</PERSON>, who runs the <ORGANIZATION>White Squirrel Hollow Bed &amp; Breakfast</ORGANIZATION>
with her husband, <PERSON>Clint</PERSON>, says people come for miles to see the
animals.
   ``A lot of people don't really believe we have white squirrels
because they stop at noon and don't see them,'' she said. ``The best
time to see them is 6:30 or 7 in the morning and around 7, <TIME>7:30 at
night</TIME> when they're feeding. They don't like the heat and I think the
light hurts their pink eyes.''
   Smart used to hunt gray squirrels (``Young squirrel, fried, with
biscuits and gravy _ you can't beat it''), but not anymore.
   ``The squirrels are a hobby, a challenge for me now,'' he says.
``I guess I'm paying back for all the hunting I used to do.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880914-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-14-88 0105EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-Reagan     09-14 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Reagan,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Stumping for GOP Ticket in Missouri, Where He Won Big in
1984</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: Top expected about 10 a.m. EDT with remarks embargoed for
1:30 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> follows Vice President
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> into <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, he is taking his campaign for the
Republican ticket to a state he carried narrowly in <DATE>1980</DATE> and
resoundingly four years ago.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> was flying today to <LOCATION>Cape Girardeau</LOCATION>, a shipping center on
the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION>, for a rally at <ORGANIZATION>Southeast Missouri State
University</ORGANIZATION>, and then on to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> to address 1,000 guests at a
<MONEY>$250-a-plate</MONEY> fund-raising dinner.
   ``The general thrust of both of these speeches is support for
the Republican ticket, acknowledgement of the economic successes of
this administration, discussion of the differences between liberals
and conservatives,'' <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Marlin Fitzwater</PERSON> said
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``The first rally speech may focus a little more on the economy
and the second one a little more on military strength,'' the
spokesman said. ``But they will both be traditional political
speeches, covering the themes that the president has discussed in
the past.''
   The president plans one or two speaking forays each week until
the <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE> election.
   GOP candidates who will benefit from the <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> events include
Gov. <PERSON>John Ashcroft</PERSON>, seeking a second term against <ORGANIZATION>Democratic State</ORGANIZATION>
Rep. <PERSON>Betty Hearnes</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, the wife of former Gov. <PERSON>Warren
Hearnes</PERSON>; and <PERSON>Sen. John Danforth</PERSON>, opposed by State <PERSON>Sen. Jay Nixon</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Hillsboro</LOCATION> as he seeks his third term.
   Both <PERSON>Ashcroft</PERSON> and <PERSON>Danforth</PERSON> enjoy comfortable leads in state
public opinion polls.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, speaking <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Jefferson City</LOCATION>, the state capital,
pledged, ``We will never go back to the grain-embargo days of those
Democrats, <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>, and who knows who else.''
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> took <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>'s 11 electoral votes with <PERCENT>51 percent</PERCENT> of the
popular vote against then-President <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> in <DATE>1980</DATE> and swept the
state with <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the popular vote against <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON> in
<DATE>1984</DATE>.
   Records showed that the only incumbent president to visit <LOCATION>Cape
Girardeau</LOCATION> previously was <PERSON>William Howard Taft</PERSON> on <DATE>Oct. 26, 1902</DATE>.
<PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> will speak at the year-old Show Me Center.
   In <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, the state's most populous city with a metropolitan
area population of more than 2 million, the president will speak at
the <ORGANIZATION>Omni Hotel St. Louis</ORGANIZATION> at an event for the <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> GOP Victory
'88 fund.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881023-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-23-88 0133EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p BC-APElectionService 70takes   10-23 1314</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-AP Election Service, 70 takes,1379</SECOND>
<HEAD>1988 Candidates For President, Governor, U.S. Senate, U.S. House</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL C. CRAFT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>President and Vice President</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Governor</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>U.S. Senate</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>U.S. House</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Electoral College</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Americans elect a new president and vice president this year
along with a dozen state governors, 33 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators and all 435
members of the next <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   Election Day is <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated the nation's
voting-age population _ people aged 18 or over _ will be 182.6
million, about 8.1 million more than in <DATE>1984</DATE> when 92,654,861
actually voted for president.
   This year's election is for the four-year presidential and vice
presidential terms starting next <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, when Republican <PERSON>Ronald W.
Reagan</PERSON> will retire after eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here's the <DATE>1988</DATE> election situation for top federal and state
offices:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890424-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-24-89 1104EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-PrisonPopulation 1stLd-Writethru a0443 04-24 0804</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Prison Population, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0443,770</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prison Population Outpacing Capacity</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts 3 grafs on FBI crime report after 3rd graf, ``The 1988''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An increase in drug-related arrests and
stricter sentencing requirements have brought about a <PERCENT>7.4 percent</PERCENT>
hike in the number of inmates in federal and state prisons, but
prison capacity hasn't kept up, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION>.
   At the end of <DATE>1988</DATE>, a record 627,402 men and women were
incarcerated nationwide, but the most optimistic estimate of prison
capacity said there was room for 566,898. While the prison
population was increasing by <PERCENT>7.4 percent</PERCENT>, the prison capacity was
increasing by just <PERCENT>5.5 percent</PERCENT>.
   ``The <DATE>1988</DATE> increase translates into a nationwide need for more
than 800 new prison bed spaces per week,'' said the report written
by <PERSON>Lawrence A. Greenfeld</PERSON>, corrections unit chief for the
department's <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Justice Statistics</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION>, meanwhile, announced that serious crimes nationwide
rose <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT> between <DATE>1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE>. The total number of violent
crimes reported to law enforcement agencies increased <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT>,
paced by a <PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT> jump in aggravated assaults in the last year,
according to preliminary results of the <DATE>1988</DATE> Uniform Crime Report.
   The report said motor vehicle thefts increased <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> from
last year.
   The <DATE>1988</DATE> crime index increased <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT> in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> and
South but registered no change in the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>. The index _ the
total number of crimes reported to state and local authorities _
increased <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT> in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   The report released <DATE>Sunday</DATE> said the 42,967 additional prisoners
in <DATE>1988</DATE> were about 3,500 more than the number added during <DATE>1987</DATE>.
There had been a <PERCENT>7.2 percent</PERCENT> hike in <DATE>1987</DATE> over the previous year.
   The report attributed the increases both to the heightened
likelihood that a serious offender will receive a prison sentence
and a <PERCENT>113 percent</PERCENT> increase in the number of adults arrested for
drug trafficking or manufacturing.
   And the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Prisons</ORGANIZATION> expects the increases to continue.
   ``Obviously, the increased efforts of law enforcement to combat
drug problems (will hike the population), as well as the new
sentencing guidelines under which inmates will be serving longer
sentences,'' said <PERSON>Greg Bogdan</PERSON>.
   The federal prison population, which stood at 49,928 at the end
of <DATE>1988</DATE>, a <PERCENT>3.4 percent</PERCENT> increase over the 48,300 at the <DATE>end of 1987</DATE>,
is expected to reach some 83,500 by <DATE>1995</DATE>, <PERSON>Bogdan</PERSON> said.
   The report said that nationwide, state prisons were operating at
<PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>23 percent</PERCENT> over capacity, while federal prisons were
estimated to be between <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>72 percent</PERCENT> over capacity.
<PERSON>Bogdan</PERSON> said the federal prisons were operating at an average of <PERCENT>55
percent</PERCENT> over capacity.
   During <DATE>1988</DATE>, total state and federal prison capacities increased
by 28,000 to 31,000 beds, depending on how the various
jurisdictions rated capacities, the report found.
   The report, which calculated prison population based both on all
prisoners and on those sentenced to more than one year, called
``sentenced prisoners,'' found that since <DATE>1980</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>District of
Columbia</ORGANIZATION> and the federal prison system have more than doubled the
number of sentenced prisoners.
   <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> have
experienced a threefold increase since <DATE>1980</DATE>, when total prison
populations in those states were 29,725, to <DATE>1988</DATE> totals of 93,597.
   The states that have more than doubled the number of such
prisoners since <DATE>1980</DATE> were <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   The incarceration rate, based on the number of people sentenced
to more than one year in prison, reached 244 per 100,000 residents
nationwide. In <DATE>1980</DATE>, the rate was 139 per 100,000.
   The Western states had the highest increase in total prisoners,
<PERCENT>11.5 percent</PERCENT>, while the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION> had a <PERCENT>9.2 percent</PERCENT> increase, the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> <PERCENT>8.6 percent</PERCENT>, and the <LOCATION>South</LOCATION> <PERCENT>4.7 percent</PERCENT>.
   The 10 states with the biggest percentage increase in total
prison population from <DATE>1987</DATE> to <DATE>1988</DATE> were <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>33.5
percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>24.7 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>17.5 percent</PERCENT>,
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>16.1 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>13.7 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>11.1
percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>10.8 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>10.6 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>,
<PERCENT>10.1 percent</PERCENT>, and <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>9.9 percent</PERCENT>.
   But the prison population actually declined in seven states, the
report found. The states with declines were <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, down by
<PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>5.1 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>2.3 percent</PERCENT>;
<LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>1.7 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>0.9
percent</PERCENT>, and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>0.2 percent</PERCENT>.
   Although men in prison still vastly outnumber the women
incarcerated, the number of women inmates increased at a faster
rate during <DATE>1988</DATE>, <PERCENT>12.5 percent</PERCENT>, than the men, <PERCENT>7.1 percent</PERCENT>. The
number of women in state and federal prisons grew from 29,064 at
the <DATE>end of 1987</DATE> to 32,691 at the end of <DATE>1988</DATE>, while the number of
men in prison increased from 555,371 to 594,711.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870915-0101 </DOCNO>
<HL> 
 </HL>
<SO>  </SO>
<IN> REGIONS -- </IN>
<TEXT>
Plan for a County's Survival:
First, Eliminate Some Towns
---
By <PERSON>Eugene Carlson</PERSON>
09/15/87
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)
   IMAGINE A LOCAL ELECTION where you are given the choice of dissolving your hometown. 
Wiping it clean off the map. 
A lot of voters in <LOCATION>St. Louis County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, may face that decision next <DATE>spring</DATE> as part of an unusual experiment in government reorganization. 

   The audacious plan is being championed by <ORGANIZATION>St. Louis County Executive Gene McNary</ORGANIZATION>. 
For starters, he suggests completely redrawing the boundaries within <LOCATION>St. Louis County</LOCATION>, creating 21 municipalities where 90 exist now. 
<PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON> says streamlining the county's crazy-quilt geography, along with rejiggering the tax system, would bring efficiency to local government and improve the area's business climate. 

   It would also put a stop to a phenomenon that is making life miserable for <PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON> and a lot of other officials of counties in fast-growing metropolitan areas of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
This is the push by communities to gobble up valuable, tax-producing land through annexation or outright incorporation. 

   WHEN A CITY or a town reaches beyond its boundaries and snaps up a shopping center or an affluent housing development on county land, it improves its own tax base. 
The county, meanwhile, loses a chunk of real estate that was generating revenue for its own treasury. 

   The trend is strictly one-way. 
<PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON> and other metropolitan county executives seem powerless to stem the land grabs. 
They foresee a situation not many years hence when communities will have skimmed off all the valuable real estate, leaving counties in possession of a handful of isolated, unattractive parcels. 

   What to do? 
<PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON>'s plan at first glance looks like surrender. 
He proposes incorporating all of <LOCATION>St. Louis County</LOCATION>, wrapping every last chunk of county land into one or another community's boundaries. 
The county budget would be cut in half; it would turn over police and fire duties to the communities and worry only about regional matters, such as roads and economic development. 

   <LOCATION>St. Louis County</LOCATION>, 524 square miles and one million population, nestles between the <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> rivers and the western limits of the city of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. 
It is largely developed, with a mix of wealthy and low-income neighborhoods, factories and parkland. 
About <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of the county's land is inside some municipality's boundaries. 
The rest of the area, most of it on the county's periphery at the farthest distance from downtown <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, is unincorporated. 

   IT'S THE PROLIFERATION of cities and towns in the county that grates <PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON>'s sense of government efficiency. 
The 90 municipalities range from a robust community of over 50,000 population to glorified neighborhoods with fewer than 100 residents. 
That's the second-highest number of cities and towns of any county in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, the county says; only <LOCATION>Allegheny County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, which includes <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> and environs, has more. 

   <PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON> totes up the numbers. 
"There are 530 elected officials, 43 fire departments and 70 police departments. 
There's something like 700 different taxing rates. 
It's ludicrous for people to be paying for that kind of inefficiency." 

   Continued piecemeal zoning and incorporation will leave the county in dire straits, the executive says. 
"We'll have 130 or 150 municipalities, and any time a company wants to come in, there'll be a neighborhood zoning board to make them dance through the hoops. 
That's not conducive to economic vitality. 

   <PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON> and his planning staff have produced a blueprint that radically alters this patchwork pattern. 
It shows 21 communities, nearly all with populations in the 25,000 to 75,000 range. 
That's large enough to provide a broad range of city services but not so big that citizens can't be heard. 

   The new cities would absorb smaller units and get some county land on the side. 
For example, the revamped city of <LOCATION>Normandy</LOCATION> would digest all or part of 26 municipalities. 

   THE VOTING PROCEDURE is complex. 
A signature-gathering campaign has assured county reorganization a place on the ballot. 
The actual plan will be drafted by a 15-member <ORGANIZATION>Board of Freeholders</ORGANIZATION>, a peculiar institution created by <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>'s constitution to arbitrate conflict between the city and county of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. 
It could be <PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON>'s blueprint, or one substantially different. 

   Oddly, the freeholder procedure for county reorganization also requires approval by city of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> voters. 
<PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON> says city officials have pledged not to sabotage reorganization, despite a nasty disagreement over the location of a new professional football stadium that is taking on the character of a blood feud. 

   Selling reorganization, particularly to county residents and elected officials of towns destined to disappear, won't be easy. 
"The strategy is to preserve the large municipalities and give them some of the unincorporated land they've been trying to annex anyway," says <PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON>. 
And the small communities? 
"They're proud of their independence, but with the loss of (federal) revenue sharing, they're about to go under anyway." 

   The county executive is reconciled to howls of pain. 
"The very small municipalities will get <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of the ink and make <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of the noise on radio and television," he says. 
But their numbers at the ballot box aren't large. 
The 25 smallest communities make up only <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> of the county electorate. 
"We hope they'll be reasonable about finding a solution," <PERSON>Mr. McNary</PERSON> says, without much conviction. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891208-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-08-89 0350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-NuclearCargo     12-08 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nuclear Cargo,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>DOT Defends Nuke Shipment Routes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF BARKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Department of Transportation</ORGANIZATION> says the
government chose a ``reasonable'' route to transport damaged fuel
from the <LOCATION>Three Mile Island</LOCATION> nuclear plant to <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, despite concerns
that the cargo crosses too many urban areas.
   The <ORGANIZATION>DOT</ORGANIZATION> said in a 47-page report this week that the <ORGANIZATION>Energy
Department</ORGANIZATION> made ``a reasonable choice when evaluated against the
multiple objective route selection criteria.''
   However, the report also said, ``During the course of planning
the shipping campaign, the <ORGANIZATION>Energy Department</ORGANIZATION> did not have
well-developed operational guidelines for route selection.''
   Population exposure was not a significant factor in picking the
route, the report said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Energy Department</ORGANIZATION> is 3{ years into a program to haul 300,000
pounds of damaged, radioactive fuel by train from the crippled <ORGANIZATION>TMI</ORGANIZATION>
Unit 2 reactor in <LOCATION>Middletown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, to an <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> laboratory 2,400
miles away.
   Along the way, the fuel passes through <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. At the lab, the
material is analyzed by <ORGANIZATION>EG&amp;G Idaho</ORGANIZATION>, an <ORGANIZATION>Energy Department</ORGANIZATION> contractor
hoping to learn more about the <DATE>1979</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>TMI</ORGANIZATION> incident, the nation's
worst commercial nuclear accident.
   Twenty trips, each taking about five days, have been completed
by the <ORGANIZATION>Conrail</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Union Pacific</ORGANIZATION> railroads. There are expected to
be two more, <ORGANIZATION>TMI</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Mary Wells</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The report noted that the <ORGANIZATION>Energy Department</ORGANIZATION> ``encountered
opposition to the route, which passes through several large cities
(<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>). Most
concerns were from the <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> area, and to a lesser extent,
<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> areas and by the states of <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>.''
   The fuel, along with metal debris, is contained in canisters
secured inside layered stainless steel and lead casks designed to
withstand accidents.
   Because of its confidence in the casks, the <ORGANIZATION>Energy Department</ORGANIZATION>
did not use population exposure as a major determining factor in
choosing the route, <ORGANIZATION>DOT</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``Since the best quality track is usually found on lines
connecting and traversing large population centers, the <ORGANIZATION>Energy
Department</ORGANIZATION> is generally forced to choose between using higher
quality track and avoiding high population areas,'' the report said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>DOT</ORGANIZATION> study was prompted by a request from <PERSON>Sen. John Danforth</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Mo.</LOCATION>, for an independent assessment of the route.
   While it found the safety risks acceptable, <ORGANIZATION>DOT</ORGANIZATION> said the public,
``influenced by the nature of the material, apparently perceives a
risk higher than that based on technical considerations.''
   However, <ORGANIZATION>DOT</ORGANIZATION> also said that <ORGANIZATION>Energy Department</ORGANIZATION> poorly documented
its route selection decisions and lacked proper guidelines.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Energy Department</ORGANIZATION> said in a news release that ``this lack of
documentation does not indicate non-compliance with regulations or
breach of public safety.''
   The shipments are part of the overall <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> cleanup of the
<ORGANIZATION>TMI</ORGANIZATION> reactor.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871013-0105 </DOCNO>
<HL> REGIONS:
Alaska Learns What It's Like
To Register a Population Loss
---
By Eugene Carlson
<DD> 10/13/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> LABOR
ECONOMIC NEWS (ECO) </IN>
<TEXT>
   ADD <LOCATION>ALASKA</LOCATION> to the short list of states losing population. 
The reason: a sharp increase in the number of residents moving out. 
In the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, a healthy influx of newcomers, plus the highest natural population increase of any state (about six babies are born in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> for every person that dies), kept population moving up briskly. 
Between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1986</DATE>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s population rose <PERCENT>32%</PERCENT>, by far the fastest rate of increase of any state. 

   But as the state's oil-based economy softened, the traditional migration pattern reversed. 
<PERSON>Gregory Williams</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s state demographer, estimates that in the 12 months ended in <DATE>July 1987</DATE>, up to 15,000 more people left <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> than moved into the state. 
That was more than enough to offset the natural population increase of about 10,000 for the same period. 

   With <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s unemployment rate close to <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>, a lot of out-migrants have headed for <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>, where the job market is healthier. 
There is a plus side to this outflow: Sluicing out excess workers should bring the local labor supply into better balance and help stanch the state's population loss. 
"We're seeing signs that this (population drain) has begun to bottom out," says <PERSON>Mr. Williams</PERSON>. 

   Ten states either lost population or had no population gain in the 12 months ended in <DATE>July 1986</DATE>, the most recent estimates published by the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>. 
They are: <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. 

   ---
   <LOCATION>PHILLY</LOCATION> MEETS THE JOB SQUEEZE: <ORGANIZATION>First Pennsylvania Bank</ORGANIZATION>'s quarterly survey of executives in Philadelphia-area companies picks up some of the same labor shortage complaints that <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> executives have been making the past couple of years. 

   Nearly <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of the metro <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> companies questioned said they planned to add employees next year, from managers to production workers, and all but a few said finding these workers would be tough. 
Higher pay doesn't seem to help much. 
The companies are already paying an average <MONEY>$6.58</MONEY> an hour for entry-level workers. 
Only <PERCENT>11%</PERCENT> said they had anyone on the payroll making the <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour minimum wage. 

   Despite the labor crunch, only <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> of the companies said they'd consider moving operations to an area with more abundant labor. 

   ---
   LITTLE PHNOM PENH: <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, is now reputed to have the largest concentration of ethnic Cambodians outside <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>. 
No one has yet done a full-fledged head count, but <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s education department says there are 3,325 "English impaired" students in <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> schools whose first language is Khmer (the Cambodian national language), double the number of the next-highest school district. 

   Add to this figure Cambodian students fluent in English, factor in parents, toddlers and in-laws at home, plus other adults, and the Cambodian population in <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> could fall in the 25,000 to 40,000 range. 

   ---
   NORTH DAKOTANS TRADITIONALLY VOTE in large numbers, but in the <DATE>November 1986</DATE> congressional elections, they beat every state in both registration (an amazing <PERCENT>95%</PERCENT> of the voting age population) and turnout at the polls (<PERCENT>73%</PERCENT>). 
A fiercely contested <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> race, in which Democrat Kent Conrad nosed out Republican incumbent <PERSON>Mark Andrews</PERSON>, helped fire the voters enthusiasm. 

   <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> all had turnouts of more than <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of the voting-age populace in <DATE>1986</DATE>, according to a new voting behavior analysis from the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>. 
The worst performer: <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, where only one-third of potentially eligible voters cast ballots. 

   ---
   <LOCATION>ARIZONA</LOCATION> PURCHASING MANAGERS see signs of prosperity mixed with looming inflation. 
Average delivery time on incoming shipments is now the longest since mid-1984. 
Inventory levels continue to grow, and new orders in <DATE>August</DATE> and <DATE>September</DATE> were unusually strong. 
Meanwhile, price increases in the last two months were at the fastest rate in more than three years. 

   ---
   EMPLOYEE TRANSFERS to high-cost areas aren't going down well, says relocation consultant <ORGANIZATION>Runzheimer International</ORGANIZATION>, of <LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wis</LOCATION>. 
Three-fourths of 143 corporate relocation administrators questioned said employees reassigned to the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> metropolitan area either resisted the move or refused to go. 
Other areas where <ORGANIZATION>Runzheimer</ORGANIZATION> says above-average cost-of-living is a significant barrier to relocation: <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 

   ---
   BRIEFS: Ornamental plants and flowers passed citrus products last year as <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s No. 1 cash crop, says the <ORGANIZATION>University of Florida</ORGANIZATION>. . . . 
<LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>'s legislature makes the fiddle the official state musical instrument. . . . 
For upscale vacationers, <ORGANIZATION>Countryman Press</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>, publishes "<LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> on <MONEY>$500</MONEY> a Day." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870120-0089 </DOCNO>
<HL> REGIONS:
States Hoping to Hit Jackpot
With Big Combined Lottery
---
By Eugene Carlson
<DD> 01/20/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CANDA
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO) </IN>
<TEXT>
   THE BIGGEST get-rich-quick scheme in the history of the <LOCATION>Republic</LOCATION>, a multistate lottery, is in the works. 
Just imagine. 
Citizens of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Oregon</ORGANIZATION> and other states competing with each other every week for a single jackpot running as high as <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY>. 
Millions of citizens will buy tickets in this, the closest thing yet to a national lottery, and participating states will reap <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> for worthy causes. 
All of this, lottery promoters say, is the next best thing to a sure bet. 

   Names for the gambling extravaganza are already being tossed around: <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s Game and The All-American Game are favorites. 
There is an organizing body, the <ORGANIZATION>Multistate Lotto Board</ORGANIZATION>, headed by <PERSON>Peter O'Connell</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>'s lottery director. 
<PERSON>Mr. O'Connell</PERSON> says the game will be running by fall. 

   Two hurdles remain. 
Many states need approval of their legislatures to participate. 
And enough states must sign on to make the enterprise worthwhile. 
Odds that each will occur appear good. 

   The idea for a nationwide multistate lottery germinated in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION>. 
Small states there have been restless under the existing lottery system, which operates on two basic principles. 
One: The size of a lottery jackpot is determined by the number of people buying tickets. 
Two: As jackpots get bigger, more and more people shell out money to play. 

   THIS PUTS STATES with small populations at a disadvantage. 
<LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>'s biggest-ever jackpot, <MONEY>$2.2 million</MONEY>, looks puny next to the grand prizes offered twice weekly in neighboring <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> that routinely run <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY> or so. 

   <PERSON>Mr. O'Connell</PERSON> says <ORGANIZATION>Rhode Islanders</ORGANIZATION> regularly play the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> lotteries, siphoning off sales that would otherwise stay home. 
"People will chase a large jackpot," he says. 
When <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s lottery was nearing its record <MONEY>$41 million</MONEY> jackpot in <DATE>August 1985</DATE>, he adds, "people would get one person and fly him to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to buy tickets. 
They were abandoning the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> lotteries and sending money to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
That tells you something." 

   What it tells small states, <PERSON>Mr. O'Connell</PERSON> thinks, is that they should band together to keep the money at home. 
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> fought the attraction of the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> lottery by joining forces. 
<ORGANIZATION>Tristate Megabucks</ORGANIZATION>, the nation's only regional lottery, has delivered. 
The three states, with fewer than three million people, ran up a jackpot of <MONEY>$9.6 million</MONEY> last <DATE>June</DATE>. 

   <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> is Exhibit B. 
The 10 Canadian provinces conduct a combined lottery draw every <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. 
The four-year-old nationwide lotto game, run by the provinces themselves, is offered in addition to each province's own lottery. 

   FEWER PEOPLE now play the lotteries in their own provinces, but this is more than offset by huge sales for the nationwide game. 
"If the provincial games in <DATE>1982</DATE> were at 100, then they're at 80 now, but the total lottery volume is 220," says <PERSON>Guy Simonis</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>British Columbia Lottery Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 
Since the provinces run both games, they are money ahead. 

   Revenue this year in the Canadian interprovincial lottery should approach <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> (Canadian). 
"This in a country with the population of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Mr. Simonis</PERSON> notes. 

   Small states aren't the only multistate boosters. 
<PERSON>John Quinn</PERSON>, director of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> lottery, says it's smart tactics for his state to join. 
If surrounding states that traditionally offer smaller lottery prizes than <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> suddenly start offering a piece of the big-buck multistate jackpot, <LOCATION>New Yorkers</LOCATION> might start crossing state lines to play the multistate game. 
"I think we'd be losing some sales," <PERSON>Mr. Quinn</PERSON> says. 
But if <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s legislature gives the multistate concept a thumbs up, "there's no doubt in my mind our bottom line will improve." 

   HERE'S HOW the game will work: States will sell weekly multistate tickets in addition to their existing lottery games. 
The game will be a lotto format, players selecting six numbers from a predetermined field. 
Each state will administer its own multistate ticket sales. 
If no one has the exact numbers, the prize rolls over and continues to build. 
Organizers say they'll cap the jackpot at <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY>, with any extra being used to build the next grand prize. 

   The winning numbers will be drawn in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, probably on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. 
States will contribute to the jackpot fund in proportion to the number of tickets they sell. 
If <ORGANIZATION>Oregon</ORGANIZATION> sells <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> of a week's multistate lottery tickets, it kicks in <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> of the jackpot total. 

   <PERSON>Michael Jones</PERSON>, a Chicago-based lottery consultant, says the key sections are mostly technical, such as how to ensure uniform payout rules and audit standards. 
Putting computer software and drawing equipment in place can be done quickly, he says. 

   The list of interested states has shifted in recent weeks. 

   <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, which claims to offer more lottery games than any state, is on the sidelines. 
"We might be adding one too many products," says lottery director <PERSON>Blair Gettig</PERSON>. 
"Right now, we don't see the advantage." 

   <PERSON>Mr. O'Connell</PERSON> of the lottery board doesn't mind the dissent. 
"I'd start with three states -- <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> -- but we expect more," he says. 
"Once we're up and running, it's only a matter of time before they'll all be trying to join." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901231-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-31-90 1354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-APN--EagleProgram ADV13   12-31 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Eagle Program, ADV 13,0764</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv13</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Jan. 13</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w
photo.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Here's an eagle whose picture could be on a
postage stamp as a proud symbol of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. But this one went bad.
Born in captivity and then released in the wild, he started doing
things eagles are not supposed to do, raiding barnyards. But in the
land of the free he'll get a second chance.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Here's an eagle whose picture could be on a
postage stamp as a proud symbol of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. But this one went bad.
Born in captivity and then released in the wild, he started doing
things eagles are not supposed to do, raiding barnyards. But in the
land of the free he'll get a second chance.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By JERRY NACHTIGAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Here's an eagle whose picture could be on a
postage stamp as a proud symbol of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. But this one went bad.
Born in captivity and then released in the wild, he started doing
things eagles are not supposed to do, raiding barnyards. But in the
land of the free he'll get a second chance.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV Sunday Jan. 13</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Here's an eagle whose picture could be on a
postage stamp as a proud symbol of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. But this one went bad.
Born in captivity and then released in the wild, he started doing
things eagles are not supposed to do, raiding barnyards. But in the
land of the free he'll get a second chance.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ901227-0001
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
901227-0001.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Census Bureau Adds 3.8 Million to Count
   But Critics Say Millions Remain Missing
   ----
   By David Wessel
</HL>
<DATE>
12/27/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A3
</SO>
<GV>
COMMERCE DEPARTMENT (COM)
CONGRESS (CNG)
</GV>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- The Census Bureau added 3.8 million more
people to its 1990 headcount, but critics continue to
complain that the bureau is missing millions more.
   The bureau said yesterday that its almost-final tally from
the 1990 census is 249,632,692 people, 10.2% more than the
1980 census found.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The addition of 3.8 million people to the preliminary
total released this <DATE>summer</DATE> reflects 2.9 million residents the
bureau missed the first time as well as the anticipated
922,819 military and other federal employees and dependents
overseas.
   Under the Constitution, the new headcount will result in a
shift of 19 seats in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> is the big winner, adding seven seats to give
it 52 representatives, or nearly <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> of all the seats in the
435-member <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is the big loser. It will lose
three seats and end up with 31 seats after the <DATE>1992</DATE> election.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> tally includes military and other federal workers
and dependents living overseas. The <DATE>1980</DATE> tally didn't.
Excluding those people, the resident population of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
grew by <PERCENT>9.8%</PERCENT> during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>Barbara
Bryant</PERSON> said.
   The bureau may yet make additional adjustments to the
tally. Under terms of an out-of-court settlement of a lawsuit
brought by <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> and others who argued that the
census disproportionately misses minorities, the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce
Department</ORGANIZATION> must decide by <DATE>July 15</DATE> whether to adjust the
tallies statistically to compensate for the undercount.
Commerce Undersecretary <PERSON>Michael Darby</PERSON> yesterday called the
<DATE>1990</DATE> census "full, fair and efficient."
   But congressional skepticism persists. "It's not a
question of whether we have counted everyone. The census
never does," said Rep. <PERSON>Thomas Sawyer</PERSON> (D., <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>), chairman of
the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> census subcommittee. "The question is how close
they've come to the truth."
   <ORGANIZATION>New York State Attorney</ORGANIZATION> General <PERSON>Robert Abrams</PERSON>, among those
suing the bureau, was quick to complain that the <DATE>1990</DATE> census
still undercounted his state. "When large segments of our
residents are left out of the political process, democracy is
devalued for all of us," he said.
   Additions to the preliminary tally reflect, among other
things, recanvassing of a substantial number of housing units
by census enumerators. With aid from state and local
governments, the bureau also identified about 125,000 housing
units it had missed. It also turned up an extra 400,000
people from parole records, <PERSON>Mrs. Bryant</PERSON> said recently.
   <PERSON>Mr. Darby</PERSON> noted that the new tally is "surprisingly close"
to earlier projections that the census would find a
population of 250 million. But Rep. <PERSON>Sawyer</PERSON> noted that the
249.6 million total is still substantially shy of the
bureau's recent projections, based on demographic data, of
253.4 million.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> census confirms trends identified in earlier
reports, such as the rapid growth of the western states. "The
West is the big population gainer," <PERSON>Mrs. Bryant</PERSON> said. In the
past decade, the population of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> has grown by <PERCENT>22%</PERCENT>,
while the South grew by <PERCENT>13.5%</PERCENT>, the Northeast by <PERCENT>3.4%</PERCENT>, and the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> by <PERCENT>1.3%</PERCENT>.
   The reassignment of seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> reflects these
trends, with the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and Sunbelt states gaining at the
expense of the big industrial states of the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>. In addition to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, states adding seats
include <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, which gains four seats; <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which gains
three seats; and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, which each gain one seat.
   Besides <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, states losing seats include <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, which each lose two seats;
and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, which each lose one
seat.
   None of these shifts comes as a surprise, however. Earlier
bureau reports on the <DATE>1990</DATE> count pointed to all of them.
   The figures may provide new ammunition for the <ORGANIZATION>District of
Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s perennially unsuccessful campaign for statehood.
Although the census found that the district lost population
during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, it still is larger than either <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. Yet the district hasn't any seats in the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, and its one representative in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> can't vote.
   The bureau also noted yesterday that four states lost
population in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. They are <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>.
   ---
                       Population Power
                                                                                                       

   State-by-state tally of population and seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House
of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> based on <DATE>1990</DATE> census
                                                                                                       

                               <DATE>1990</DATE>        TOTAL    CHANGE
                            POPULATION     HOUSE     FROM
                          (In millions)    SEATS    PRESENT
                                                                                                       

   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>                 29.84         52          7
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>                   18.04         31         -3
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>                      17.06         30          3
