<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901214-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-14-90 0055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Galileo-Earth     12-14 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galileo-Earth,0599</SECOND>
<HEAD>Galileo Photographs Moon's Far Side for First Time Since Apollo</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The far side of the moon, last
photographed by Apollo astronauts two decades ago, was captured on
film again by the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft when it zoomed past the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
on its long voyage to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It's staggering to realize we've been neglecting our own
satellite,'' said <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist at
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   Astronauts with the 1969-1972 Apollo lunar missions photographed
the back side of the moon, but <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the last good
pictures before <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> were made by unmanned lunar orbiters during
the <DATE>1960s</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> passed the moon after it swooped 597 miles above the
southwest <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. It used <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s gravity as a
slingshot to help expand the spacecraft's orbit around the sun so
it can reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1995</DATE>. It used <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> for the same purpose
last <DATE>February</DATE> and will fly past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> again in <DATE>December 1992</DATE>.
   The planetary encounters are meant solely to help propel <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>
on its <MONEY>$1.4 billion</MONEY> mission to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. But scientists took the
opportunity to use the spacecraft to study <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in dress
rehearsals for exploring <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Three of <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s new photographs of the moon and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> were
released <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION> as <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> zoomed away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, snapping more
pictures of its home planet from a distance of 2.33 million miles.
   One photo shows the crescent moon, while another shows <PERSON>Mare
Orientale</PERSON>, a 550-mile-wide meteorite impact crater on the far side
of the moon, which is always pointed away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Because of
the way the moon orbits <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, only five-eighths of its surface can
be seen from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s third picture shows half of <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, including the
<ORGANIZATION>Ross Ice Shelf</ORGANIZATION> and mountains poking through ice near <LOCATION>McMurdo</LOCATION> Sound.
   ``This is the first time we've had a chance to use a spacecraft
designed to explore another planet to come back and look at our own
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and moon as if we were alien observers,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   ``In the process, we're learning some new scientific things
about our own world and its companion, but perhaps more
importantly, it's providing us a different perspective on our own
home planet as a fragile world,'' he said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> is the first craft equipped with modern instruments to
study the far side of the moon and photographed some regions for
the first time, said <PERSON>Clark Chapman</PERSON>, a researcher from the <ORGANIZATION>Planetary
Science Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>.
   ``We're going to learn a lot about the geology of the back side
of the moon,'' <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said. ``It's been a fantastic lunar mission
already.''
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> plans to release more pictures <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and hopes to
display a movie made of 1,400 still images showing clouds moving
above the spinning <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Some unreleased pictures were displayed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> during a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
closed-circuit television broadcast. They showed closeup views of
clouds drifting above <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and more distant peeks at <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Andes</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was launched from space shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>Oct. 18,
1989</DATE>.
   It was to have been sent on a direct, two-year flight to
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. But after the <DATE>1986</DATE> explosion that destroyed the shuttle
Challenger, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> decided it was too risky to launch <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> from
the shuttle using a powerful liquid-fueled rocket. A weaker booster
was used, requiring <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> to use the gravity of Venus and Earth
to make a looping 2.4-billion-mile, six-year voyage.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901208-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-08-90 1958EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Galileo 1stLd-Writethru a0577 12-08 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galileo, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0577,0695</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jupiter-Bound Spacecraft Visits Earth on 6-Year Journey</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 4th graf, `Everything is ...' to ADD
comment on instrument performance and value of flyby as rehearsal
for Jupiter; SUBS 7-8th grafs pvs, `The trajectory ...' to ADD that
far side of moon will be viewed over next few days and describe
pictures of moon and Earth. Picks up 9th graf pvs, `Its path ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Space Shuttle, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN ANTCZAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The spacecraft <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> grabbed <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s
gravity coattails <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and arced around the planet on a
fleeting visit home 13{ months into a six-year voyage to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Taking pictures and exploring with instruments, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> used
Earth as a gravity slingshot, hurtling 597 miles above the western
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, the point of closest approach.
   The encounter, at <TIME>12:35 p.m. PST</TIME>, increased the craft's speed by
11,600 mph, giving it a speed of 79,000 mph relative to the sun.
Relative to the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, which is also moving, the maximum speed was
30,721 mph.
   ``Everything is working exactly as it should,'' said mission
director <PERSON>Neal E. Ausman Jr.</PERSON> at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory as
the craft flew through <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s shadow. ``We've had no glitches, no
problems.''
   Project officials said the flyby was a valuable dress rehearsal
for the <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> encounter.
   ``Every time we turn an instrument on, we have problems
understanding what we've done to it, and what we probably can do to
the software,'' said <PERSON>Clayne M. Yeates</PERSON>, science and mission design
manager. ``So we're really learning how to operate these
instruments. It's been invaluable for us to collect this data.''
   Project manager <PERSON>William J. O'Neil</PERSON> added, ``Once we do figure out
what they're doing we find that they're operating up to expectation
or beyond.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s looping 2.4 billion-mile route to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> made it the
first planetary spacecraft to approach Earth from space and
provided scientists the first opportunity to look at the world in
the same way as they have other planets.
   Controllers ordered <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s instruments to measure gases that
cause ``greenhouse effect'' warming of the atmosphere and study
high-altitude water vapor involved in creating and destroying the
ozone layer.
   The trajectory also allowed scientists to explore the far side
of the moon, always facing away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, with modern instruments
for the first time. The far side observations will occur over
several days.
   Galileo approached from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s dark side, measuring its
magnetic field and solar plasma flows, and taking pictures of the
crescent moon.
   Two pictures released soon after the flyby showed a portion of
the near-side of the moon and a cloud-streaked view of central
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. Data and pictures will continue to come in as <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>
speeds away.
   Its path also took it 2,162 miles above the orbiting space
shuttle <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>.
   Exploration of the blue planet and its moon was an added bonus
to <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$1.4 billion</MONEY> mission.
   The spacecraft was originally designed to make a 2{-year direct
flight to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> for long-term observation of the solar system's
biggest planet.
review after the explosion of the space shuttle Challenger in <DATE>1986</DATE>
led to changes in <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s own booster system that made a direct
flight impossible because its new rocket was less powerful.
   Shuttle Atlantis carried <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> into orbit <DATE>Oct. 18, 1989</DATE>, and
launched it on a roundabout trajectory using three gravity assists
from <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The spacecraft flew past <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Feb. 10</DATE>. It will get another
boost from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on <DATE>Dec. 8, 1992</DATE>. That encounter will be closer, at
an altitude of about 200 miles. The pass will also greatly widen
its orbit around the sun in order to intercept <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will go into orbit around <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Dec. 7, 1995</DATE>.
   A probe launched from <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> five months earlier will plunge
into the atmosphere at 100,000 mph, deploy a parachute and make
measurements for 75 minutes until it is crushed by intense
pressure.
   The orbiter will continue to explore <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and 10 of its 16
known moons for two years.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901129-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-29-90 1818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Galileo-Earth     11-29 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galileo-Earth,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>Galileo Spacecraft Speeds Toward Earth for Gravity Slingshot to
Jupiter</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft, racing toward a
close encounter with <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> next week so it can reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1995</DATE>, will explore its home planet like an alien world, scientists
said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The camera-bearing planetary spacecraft will be the first to
approach Earth from space, so the <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> flyby will be ``our first
chance to look at <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as we have at other planets in the solar
system,'' <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist, said during
a news conference.
   ``It gives humankind a vantage point to look at their world as
they've never seen it before,'' <PERSON>Bill O'Neil</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> project
   Galileo is the most sophisticated planetary spacecraft ever
built. It was launched from space shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>Oct. 18,
1989</DATE>, starting its <MONEY>$1.4 billion</MONEY>, 2.4 billion-mile journey to
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the solar system's largest planet.
   Starting in <DATE>December 1995</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> orbiter will spend two
years exploring <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and 10 of its moons after deploying a probe
that will make measurements in <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere until it is
crushed by intense pressure there.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s route was designed so the unmanned spacecraft could
use Venus and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as ``gravity slingshots'' to expand its orbit
around the sun and reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. It will use Earth for that
purpose <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> and again in <DATE>December 1992</DATE>. It used <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> as a
gravity slingshot last <DATE>February</DATE>.
   Scientists decided to take advantage of the close encounters to
make pictures and measurements of Venus and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Data collected
at <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> was stored on <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s tape recorder and sent to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
<DATE>last week</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s optical camera made detailed pictures of the uppermost
layer of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' sulfuric acid clouds, as did spacecraft that
visited Venus previously. But <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s infrared camera made the
first still pictures and a movie showing clouds moving in 150 mph
winds in <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' middle and lower cloud decks.
   Severe turbulence that may be caused by thunderstorms was
detected in the middle cloud layer, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientist <PERSON>Robert Carlson</PERSON>
said.
   Studying <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' acid clouds and its carbon dioxide atmosphere
may help scientists understand how increasing carbon dioxide levels
in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere will warm the planet like glass traps heat in
a greenhouse, said <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> astronomer <PERSON>Michael Belton</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> also discovered remarkably fast high-energy particles
flowing away from <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, a surprise because space around the planet
was thought to be placid, said <ORGANIZATION>University of Iowa</ORGANIZATION> physicist <ORGANIZATION>Louis
Frank</ORGANIZATION>.
   The spacecraft also recorded scratchy and screechy sounds
created by waves in electrically charged solar wind particles that
sweep around <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>. Scientists played the tape <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will swoop about 593 miles above the southwest <LOCATION>Atlantic
Ocean</LOCATION> at <TIME>3:35 p.m. EST</TIME> <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was 4.46 million miles from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The spacecraft will measure gases that cause ``greenhouse
effect'' warming of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere, and study high-altitude
water vapor that helps create and destroy <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s protective ozone
layer, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> also will be the first spacecraft with modern
instruments to study the far side of the moon, which is always
pointed away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901211-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-11-90 0205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Galileo     12-11 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galileo,0345</SECOND>
<HEAD>With Space Shuttle, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Flyby Allows Photos of Moon's Far Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists say pictures of the far side
of the moon taken by the spacecraft <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will help fill a blank
spot on the map of the planet.
   The pictures, taken as <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> sped past the moon and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on
its six-year voyage to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, also should reveal more about the
mineral content of the moon's crust, scientists said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``We're actually doing some new observation,'' said <PERSON>James Head</PERSON>,
a member of <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s imaging team at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion
black and white photos of the full moon that provided a sharp image
of the <LOCATION>Orientale Basin</LOCATION> as well as portions of both the near and far
sides of the moon.
   The spacecraft swung into the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s gravitational field
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, hurtling 597 miles above the western <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> at the
point of its closest approach.
   By sweeping near <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was able to use gravitational
pull like a slingshot to increase its speed by 11,600 mph, boosting
its velocity to 79,000 mph in relation to the sun.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s approach allowed scientists to focus the craft's
cameras on the far side of the moon for the first exploration of
the region since <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Apollo missions in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   The cameras photographed a wedge of moonscape near the south
pole on the far side that somehow was missed by previous <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and
Soviet mapping missions, said project scientist <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>.
   ``That's interesting, it's got craters just like the rest of the
moon, but there's no great scientific surprise in that,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>
said.
   A subsequent journey through the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s magnetic field gave
scientists their first measurements of a solar storm in which
magnetically charged ions take on higher energy levels.
   The data could reveal whether the majority of these ions, which
trigger colorful auroras near <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s magnetic poles, come from the
sun or <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Lou Frank</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s magnetic field
working group.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901219-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-19-90 1802EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Galileo-Earth     12-19 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galileo-Earth,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>Galileo Flyby Spurs NASA `Aliens' to Conclude There's Life on
Earth</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos LA6, LA7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientists pretending to be
explorers from another world said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> they had concluded life
exists on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, and it may be intelligent.
   The scientists based their conclusinon on data from the
Jupiter-bound <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft.
   ``The accumulated evidence we have ... would give your
hypothetical explorer a very strong indication you had biological
activity on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s chief
scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s study of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> illustrates how researchers use data
collected by spacecraft to reach conclusions about other planets.
   Galileo boomeranged past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and the moon <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE>, using the
planet's gravity as a slingshot to speed it up and expand its orbit
around the sun so it can reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1995</DATE>.
   Scientists used the opportunity to treat Earth as an alien
planet, ordering <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> to snap a few thousand pictures and make
numerous measurements. They outlined their findings during a
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> news conference.
   Measurements made by <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s infrared light-detecting
instrument showed <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere is rich in nitrous oxide,
methane and oxygen, indicating ``there's a lot of life'' on the
planet, said laboratory scientist <PERSON>Robert W. Carlson</PERSON>.
   Another of <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s instruments picked up non-natural radio
signals that got stronger closer to the planet, which would make
alien scientists strongly suspect <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> has intelligent life that
makes radio broadcasts, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   The spaceship also detected lightning bolts, made measurements
to help explain creation of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern and Southern Lights</ORGANIZATION>,
determined the planet is warmed by a mild ``greenhouse effect'' and
detected a high-altitude ice cloud that helps cause the annual hole
in the protective ozone layer over <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>.
   On the moon, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> found evidence of a huge volcanic eruption
4 billion years ago. That shows such volcanic activity occurred
about 200 million years earlier than previously believed, said
<ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION> geologist <PERSON>Jim Head</PERSON>.
   The spacecraft's pictures also confirmed the existence of a
1,200-mile-wide meteorite impact basin on the southern hemisphere
of the moon's far side, the largest such crater ever identified,
more of <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s photos of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and moon <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   One was a mosaic, assembled from 11 separate pictures, showing
all of icy <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>. Others showed huge lunar craters, a color
map of minerals on the moon's surface, clouds swirling over <LOCATION>South
America</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s larger lakes and Great Barrier Reef.
   The pictures didn't display evidence of life on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> because
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s closest approach to the planet, at a distance of 597
miles, was over the southwest <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>. The detail in the
pictures was inadequate to reveal buildings, scientists said.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> also displayed two short movies, made by assembling
hundreds of <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s still photos, showing the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and moon
spinning.
   ``Top that, <PERSON>Ted Turner</PERSON>!'' Head declared after the colorized
lunar movie was played. He was referring to media mogul <PERSON>Turner</PERSON>'s
controversial practice of colorizing classic films.
   Also <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> fired its thrusters repeatedly to aim
itself properly for its close encounter with the asteroid Gaspra
next <DATE>Oct. 29</DATE>, said project manager <PERSON>Bill O'Neil</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will swing past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> again <DATE>Dec. 8, 1992</DATE>, for a final
``gravity slingshot'' maneuver to help it reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. In <DATE>July
1995</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will separate into an orbiter and a probe. Both will
reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>December 1995</DATE>.
   The probe will descend into <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere, returning data
to the orbiter until the probe is crushed by intense atmospheric
pressure. The orbiter will circle <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> for at least two years,
studying the planet and making closeup pictures of its 10 largest
moons.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901207-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-07-90 2107EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Galileo     12-07 0250</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galileo,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>Galileo Spacecraft Making Earth Rendezvous on `Slingslot' Path to
Jupiter</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft makes a
rendezvous with Earth on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, using the planet's gravity like
a slingshot to hurl it along on its six-year journey to the solar
system's largest planet, <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Launched in <DATE>October 1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will swoop about 593 miles
above the southwest <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> at <TIME>12:35 p.m. PST</TIME>.
   The pass will be monitored by mission controllers at the
Laboratory.
   During the flyby, the spacecraft will measure gases that cause
the ``greenhouse effect'' warming of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere and will
study high-altitude water vapor that helps create and destroy
Earth's ozone layer, scientists said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will also be the first spacecraft with modern
instruments to study the far side of the moon, which always faces
away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Oct. 18, 1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was released from the cargo bay of
space shuttle Atlantis. Then its own rocket booster launched the
spacecraft on its long voyage, with arrival at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> scheduled in
<DATE>1995</DATE>.
   In <DATE>February</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> neared <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> for its first ``gravity
assist'' maneuver, using the planet's gravity as a slingshot to
help it reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Next <DATE>Oct. 29</DATE>, the spacecraft swoops within 600 miles of asteroid
Gaspra, taking pictures and measurements. Then, on <DATE>Dec. 8, 1992</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> zooms about 185 miles above <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s surface in the third
and final ``gravity assist'' maneuver needed to hurl it toward
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will arrive at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Dec. 7, 1995</DATE>. The spacecraft
will orbit the planet and launch a probe to plung into its
atmosphere.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881111-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-11-88 1807EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Voyager-Neptune     11-11 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Neptune,0504</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Adjusts Voyager 2's Trajectory To Neptune</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Voyager 2 spacecraft, flying through
space 2.6 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, fired its thrusters <DATE>Friday</DATE> to
change course for its <DATE>August 1989</DATE> picture-taking encounter with the
planet <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``Responding to radio signals radioed from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 fired
its hydrazine thrusters for three minutes and 29 seconds beginning
at <TIME>6:55 a.m. PST</TIME>,'' said a statement issued by the space agency's
Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   Flight engineering manager <PERSON>Lanny Miller</PERSON> said radio signals sent
to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> by the space probe indicated the maneuver succeeded.
   The pre-planned course correction will bring Voyager 2 some 6,200
miles closer to the solar system's eighth planet, but another major
maneuver next <DATE>April</DATE> and several subsequent but minor trajectory
changes will be required before the <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> flyby, said laboratory
spokeswoman <PERSON>Mary Beth Murrill</PERSON>.
   The spacecraft _ which passed by <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE>
and Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE> _ is scheduled to sweep within 3,000 miles of
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s cloud tops at <TIME>9 p.m. PDT</TIME> next <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, taking pictures
with its television camera.
   Five hours later, it will fly within 24,000 miles of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s
moon <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, which scientists believe may have lakes of liquid
nitrogen.
   <PERSON>Murrill</PERSON> said Voyager 2 is 414.7 million miles from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, one
of the solar system's giant, gaseous outer planets.
   Radio commands to the probe and its response signals are
transmitted through large, dish-shaped radio antennae that make up
the Deep Space Network operated by the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and
Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Goldstone</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   Voyager 2 is so far away that the signals take four hours to
reach it, even traveling at the speed of light.
   The <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> encounter will be the last of the so-called ``grand
tour'' of the outer planets by the Voyager probes. Voyagers 1 and 2
were launched from <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1977</DATE>. Voyager 1, which
visited <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE>, now is headed out of the
solar system.
   Scientists have called the Voyager mission humanity's most
productive space exploration effort because the two picture-taking
probes learned hundreds of times more about the outer planets than
all previous studies combined.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientists have said that by <DATE>1995</DATE>, when both probes are
searching for the edge of the solar system, the total cost of the
mission will be about <MONEY>$920 million</MONEY>, which is less than half what the
<ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> spends during one workday.
   Among key Voyager discoveries were active volcanos spewing sulfur
on <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s moon Io, an icy volcanism that produced glacier-like
flows on some of the Saturnian and Uranian moons, and the discovery
of at least 17 previously unknown moons: three at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, at least
four at <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and 10 orbiting Uranus.
   The probes also discovered new rings encircling <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>
and Uranus; orange smog and ethane-methane rain on <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s moon
<ORGANIZATION>Titan</ORGANIZATION>, and dozens of giant hurricanes on <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA113090-0157 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 315734 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 30, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 36; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
799 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GALILEO SPACECRAFT RIGHT ON TARGET FOR EARTH FLYBY DEC. 8 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEE DYE, TIMES SCIENCE WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
After taking a brief look at <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft is speeding toward a 
close encounter with Earth <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> on its long journey to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and it is 
expected to hit its desired course almost on the button, scientists reported 
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Environmentalists had tried to block the launch of <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> last year because 
its instruments draw their energy from nuclear power, and some feared that a 
launch failure or a subsequent collision with <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION> could release deadly 
radioisotopes into the atmosphere. But there is no chance of that, scientists 
said, because <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will be within about 16 miles of its desired course, 
passing 590 miles over the surface of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will make an even closer Earth flyby in two years, passing less than 
200 miles from the planet on its way to its ultimate destination, <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. But 
nothing about the spacecraft has given officials with the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics 
and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> anything to worry about. 
</P>
<P>
"The spacecraft's health is excellent," said <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> project manager <PERSON>William J. 
O'Neil</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory. 
</P>
<P>
Galileo is functioning so well that "we don't have to do anything on the ground 
or anything on the spacecraft" to successfully zip by the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and use gravity 
to boost its speed by about 15,000 m.p.h. That is one of several maneuvers that 
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will go through in order to reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, where it will conduct a 
two-year study of the Jovian system. 
</P>
<P>
Originally, plans did not call for <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> to fly past either Venus or Earth, 
but a new course had to be developed after changes in the space program 
resulting from the Challenger disaster precluded the use of a rocket powerful 
enough to send it on a direct course to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. So both <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> are 
bonuses along the way, and scientists expect to make full use of both 
opportunities to study planets that are very similar in some ways, but quite 
different in others. 
</P>
<P>
The Earth flyby will be unique in that, for the first time, a spacecraft will 
reveal the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as it would appear to an alien spacecraft flying through the 
solar system. The flyby is expected to produce some first-ever pictures of the 
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and the moon. 
</P>
<P>
"We will see portions of the far side of the moon that have never been looked 
at with modern sensors," said <PERSON>Torrence V. Johnson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>JPL</LOCATION>, the project 
scientist. 
</P>
<P>
The images that <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will send back as it speeds toward <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, as well as 
the thousands of photographs it will take of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and that planet's moons, 
could be exceptionally rewarding because the camera aboard <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> is capable 
of creating extremely sharp images in very low light, scientists said. 
</P>
<P>
According to <PERSON>Michael Belton</PERSON>, leader of the imaging team, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s camera is 
about 100 times as sensitive to light as the cameras that sent back spectacular 
images from the two Voyagers as they explored the outer reaches of the solar 
system. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s visit to <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> has been upstaged by <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft, which 
uses a radar camera to pierce through the sulfur dioxide clouds that hide the 
planet's surface, but at least it gave scientists a chance to check out their 
instruments and pick up a little precious data on the brilliant white planet. 
</P>
<P>
The data, collected in <DATE>February</DATE>, was stored aboard the spacecraft until <DATE>last 
week</DATE>, when <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was close enough to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> to transmit it back. Scientists 
have spent the last few days devouring the information. 
</P>
<P>
"Christmas came early this year," <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
And there were a few surprises. 
</P>
<P>
For instance, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s instruments detected a concentration of electrons 
traveling at far higher speeds than would have been expected. 
</P>
<P>
The electrons apparently were accelerated to the extraordinary speeds because 
of some "interaction" of Venus with the million-mile-an-hour wind blowing off 
the sun. Asked the significance of the discovery, <PERSON>Louis Frank</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University 
of Iowa</ORGANIZATION>, head of the plasma science team, said: 
</P>
<P>
"It shows our ignorance of how to push particles around the solar system." 
</P>
<P>
The photos of Venus taken by <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> do not rival the sharp radar images that 
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> has been sending back for the last few weeks, but scientists embraced 
them anyway because they reveal additional details about the clouds that cover 
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>. That, in turn, is important because it gives scientists a chance to 
study the atmosphere of a planet that evolved quite differently from the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"We are living in an atmosphere that we are changing," <LOCATION>Belton</LOCATION> said, referring 
to the global warming effect that many scientists believe is taking place on 
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. "If you don't want the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> to change into something like that (Venus), 
then you better learn about atmospheres." 
</P>
<P>
Venus has an atmosphere that is rich in carbon dioxide, so it has already 
experienced the greenhouse effect. It is also devoid of life. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SPACE PROGRAMS -- UNITED STATES; SPACECRAFT; GALILEO (SPACECRAFT); SPACE 
EXPLORATION 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890820-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-20-89 1751EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Galileo-Jupiter     08-20 0624</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galileo-Jupiter,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Set For October Launch Of Spacecraft To Jupiter</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Voyager-Neptune, Bjt; AM-Space Shuttle</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientists said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> they plan to
launch ``the <ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION> of spacecraft'' from a space shuttle <DATE>Oct.
12</DATE>, catapulting the ship <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> so it can parachute a
probe into the giant planet's atmosphere.
   During its looping voyage toward a <DATE>December 1995</DATE> rendezvous with
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the spacecraft will fly by <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, pass <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> twice, see
parts of the moon not seen since the early <DATE>1960s</DATE> and make the first
close approach to an asteroid, the researchers said.
   The swings past <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> will catapult the spacecraft to
higher speeds so that it can reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> with the least
expenditure of fuel, the researchers said.
   When it passes <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will observe gases that cause
``greenhouse effect'' warming of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere, study depletion
of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s protective ozone layer, and make detailed observations of
parts of the moon for which only relatively primitive maps from the
early <DATE>1960s</DATE> are available, said <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>, the project
scientist.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft is a marvel,'' <PERSON>Neal Ausman Jr.</PERSON>, the
mission director, said during a news conference at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet
Propulsion Laboraory. ``It is the most complex spacecraft we've ever
flown at <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION> _ probably the most complex spacecraft ever.''
   <PERSON>Clayne Yeates</PERSON>, acting science and mission design manager, called
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> the ``the <ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION> of spacecraft,'' with an array of
scientific instruments that will allow far more detailed images and
scientific data on <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and its moons than could be obtained by
the twin Voyager spacecraft.
   Among the innovations is a new imaging device that will allow
researchers to take a picture every two-and-one-third seconds. The
television cameras on Voyager 2 can take a picture only once every
50 or 60 seconds, said <PERSON>Yeates</PERSON>.
   Voyager 2 is flying past the planet <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> <DATE>this week</DATE>, the climax
of its 12-year, 4.4-billion trek past four planets. It explored
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will drop a probe by parachute into the Jovian atmosphere
to make detailed observations. <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere is covered with
ammonia clouds and may contain ice clouds and water droplets
underneath.
   Researchers expect to get data on lightning bolts 10,000 to
100,000 times as strong as those seen on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will pass
600 miles from the Jovian moon Io, which has the most active
volcanoes in the solar system.
   The shuttle Atlantis is scheduled to carry <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> into <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
orbit <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>, then launch the spacecraft. <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will be boosted
into a trajectory that will take it looping around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, where it
will study the planet's atmosphere and make an attempt to confirm
the existence of lightning there.
   Galileo then will swing back past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in <DATE>December 1990</DATE>, using
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s gravity as a slingshot to pick up speed.
   Its next stop will be the asteroid belt between <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and Mars,
where in <DATE>October 1991</DATE> it will pass 600 miles from the asteroid
Gaspra, a typical asteroid about 10 miles long.
   ``We don't have any pictures of asteroids,'' said <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>.
``Nobody's been by one.''
   The spacecraft then will swing past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> again before being sent
on its way to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. It may have a second opportunity to pass by
an asteroid in <DATE>August 1993</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will make about 10 orbits around <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, passing closest
to Io but also near <LOCATION>Europa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ganymede</LOCATION>, two other Jovian moons.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> mission has been repeatedly delayed since work began
in <DATE>1977</DATE>, at which time launch was set for <DATE>1982</DATE>. Budget cuts during
the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration, design changes and the explosion of the
Challenger space shuttle all contributed to the delay, said <PERSON>John
Casani</PERSON>, former project manager and now in charge of all flight
projects at <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891005-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-05-89 1556EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-SpacecrafttoEarth Adv08   10-05 1038</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Spacecraft to Earth, Adv 08,1066</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv08</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Oct. 8, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Interplanetary Spacecraft To `Visit' Earth</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In <DATE>1990</DATE> and again in <DATE>1992</DATE>, the most
sophisticated space probe ever built will visit a planet with vast
oceans, a churning, molten interior and a rocky surface scarred by
earthquakes and active volcanoes.
   That planet is <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft, scheduled for launch aboard the space
shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, is ultimately bound for <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. But
its long, looping trajectory will sling it twice around its home
planet before dispatching it to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   That makes <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> the first spacecraft to approach Earth from
interplanetary space.
   ``It's showing people what the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> would look like to an
extraterrestrial,'' said <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>, project scientist on the
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> mission. ``We've never conducted a mission to planet Earth
like this before. We're going to go in and see what this place
looks like.''
   In addition to making observations concerning the greenhouse
effect and the Antarctic ozone hole, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will film what
scientists are calling the Earth movie, proposed by astronomer and
writer <PERSON>Carl Sagan</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Cornell University</ORGANIZATION>.
   In the movie, the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> will appear as a thin, distant crescent,
then gradually fill the frame and expand until surface objects 10
feet across are visible.
   As the spacecraft pulls away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s sunlit side, it will
take a backward-looking shot showing five days of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s
rotation, with the moon silently sweeping past as the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> recedes.
   ``A continuous zoom movie like that would be, it seems to me,
spectacular in reminding us of our position in space, of the tiny
planet that we're on,'' <PERSON>Sagan</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will also, at <LOCATION>Sagan</LOCATION>'s suggestion, use its
state-of-the-art instruments to map the atmosphere for methane,
carbon dioxide and other gases responsible for global warming. And
on its first pass, it will peer directly down into the ozone hole
over <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> has such capable and novel instruments, it seemed to
me important to do something about understanding the dangers to the
global environment,'' <PERSON>Sagan</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> is returning to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> only to pick up a boost in speed
from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s gravity as it begins its six-year journey. After its
launch, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will get a gravity kick by passing around <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>,
pick up more speed with the two passes by <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and then begin its
primary mission to orbit <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, explore its moons and dispatch a
probe into <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere.
   ``We wouldn't do anything on the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> encounters if we thought
it would jeopardize the primary mission,'' said <PERSON>Fraser P. Fanale</PERSON> of
the <ORGANIZATION>University of Hawaii</ORGANIZATION>, who is in charge of <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
science objectives.
   Scientists say the <MONEY>$1.4 billion</MONEY> probe's investigation of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>
and its moons will be the most scientifically rich that
interplanetary exploration has witnessed. The <DATE>1979</DATE> Voyager views of
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and its satellites were fascinating, but <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s images
will be 1,000 times clearer, they say.
   In <DATE>1995</DATE>, a smaller probe is to be fired by <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> into
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s cloud layers and make the first direct sampling of the
Jovian atmosphere. The probe will transmit data until it is crushed
and vaporized by extreme heat and pressure.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will orbit the planet gathering information on
temperatures, magnetic fields, radiation, cloud characteristics,
gravity fields and the dynamics of a weather system that produces
such phenomena as the mysterious Great Red Spot, a centuries-old
storm larger than <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The spacecraft was initially scheduled for launch in <DATE>1982</DATE> on a
direct course to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, but it has been delayed repeatedly as
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> wrangled over <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> financing and as
the space shuttle program fell far behind schedule.
   On <DATE>Sept. 28</DATE>, activists filed a suit seeking to prevent the
launch of the spacecraft because it is powered by plutonium. They
said a shuttle accident could spread toxic plutonium in populated
areas, but <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said its evaluations indicated the risk of
contamination was very low.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will do more than observe the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as it makes its way
to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. It will be the first spacecraft with modern instruments
to observe the dark side of the moon. ``There are a lot of things
we don't know about the far side of the moon,'' said <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>.
``It's been very difficult and frustrating to try to put together a
picture of the whole moon from the data we have.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will also search for ice in the shaded craters near the
moon's north pole and study the soil for clues to the evolution of
the moon's crust and its interior.
   The spacecraft will be active as it passes by <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, searching
for cloud patterns and possibly lightning. And it will visit at
least one and maybe two asteroids in the asteroid belt between Mars
and <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Its observations of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and moon may help resolve a debate
about the ``space snowballs'' hypothesis of <PERSON>Louis A. Frank</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Iowa</ORGANIZATION>.
   The theory holds that the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s lakes and oceans come from
precipitation caused by the melting of small comets bombarding the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere at the rate of 10 million a year.
   If that's true, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> should be able to spot hydrogen clouds
around the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and the moon, the result of the comets' water
molecules disintegrating. It should also detect water vapor rising
from the moon as comets collide with its surface.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will make the most accurate measurements yet of the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s mass, and it will study the sparkling ultraviolet
``airglow'' caused by the interaction of solar radiation with the
atmosphere.
   It may also show whether the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> is shadowed by a ring of
interplanetary dust around the sun, as some scientists have
proposed.
   All of these observations have another purpose, too. ``We may
learn things about using the spacecraft that would be valuable at
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>,'' said <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>.
   Finally, the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> observations have what <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> calls ``the
surprise component.'' The two Voyager flights to the outer planets
consistently revealed features of the planets that hadn't even been
imagined. Could a fresh look at <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> do the same?
   ``I would not want to bet against finding some things people
hadn't thought about,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said. ``Who knows?''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Oct. 8</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900210-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-10-90 0107EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Galileo-Venus 2ndLd-Writethru a0787 02-10 0998</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galileo-Venus, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0787,1020</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Jupiter-Bound Galileo Spacecraft Swings Past Venus</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with spacecraft making closest
approach to Venus; picks up 4th graf, `That started ...' Stands for
AMs.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY86</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spaceship swooped past Venus
early <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, and the cloud-shrouded planet acted as a gravity
slingshot to help hurl the craft toward its <DATE>1995</DATE> rendezvous with
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Engineers at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory received a radio
signal confirming that the 2.8-ton spacecraft made its closest
approach to Venus at <TIME>12:59 a.m. EST</TIME>, cruising 10,028 miles above
the planet's hellishly hot surface.
   ``We have just flown through our closest approach point to
Venus,'' said <PERSON>Bill O'Neil</PERSON>, science and mission design manager.
``The greatest challenge of getting <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> has been
met.''
   Four hours before the close encounter, radio signals received on
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> confirmed the spacecraft computer ordered <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s infrared
light sensor to start observing <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>. The instrument was looking
for the glow of the hot lower atmosphere backlighting cooler clouds
overhead, <PERSON>O'Neil</PERSON> said.
   That started an eight-hour period of intensive photography and
measurements, including a photographic search for lightning.
Earlier <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> studied dust particles and magnetic fields
in space, and measured Venusian atmospheric temperatures.
   ``The Venus encounter is our first major milestone in the
mission,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> project scientist <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>. ``After
the encounter, we have gained enough energy out of this celestial
billiard shot to get the energy we need to make it all the way to
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.''
   The power the spacecraft gains in the flyby is triple the energy
of its propellant supply, said mission director <PERSON>Neal Ausman</PERSON>.
   The <MONEY>$1.35 billion</MONEY> mission will let <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> examine <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, its
moon and one or two asteroids before the spacecraft separates into
an orbiter and a small probe in <DATE>July 1995</DATE>. In <DATE>December 1995</DATE>, they
arrive at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the solar system's largest planet, after a
2.4-billion-mile trip, including 182 million miles to reach <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was deployed from the space shuttle Atlantis last <DATE>Oct.
18</DATE>.
   Venus circles the sun between the orbits of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION>,
the closest planet to the sun. Acid-laden clouds extend 40 miles
above the surface, trapping heat in a runaway ``greenhouse effect''
that raised surface temperatures to 900 degrees Fahrenheit.
Atmospheric pressure is 90 times that on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Venus is about <PERCENT>95
percent</PERCENT> as wide as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Scientists suspect it may have active
volcanoes and shifting plates on its crust.
   The Venus flyby was designed purely to give <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> a boost for
its trip to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> by increasing its speed from 83,750 mph to
88,740 mph. In two other ``gravity assist'' maneuvers, the
spacecraft will use the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as a slingshot next <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> and again
on <DATE>Dec. 8, 1992</DATE>, so it will be properly aimed toward <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said.
   Scientists decided to take advantage of the Venus encounter by
having <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s camera and instruments make photographs and
measurements of Venus starting <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and continuing for a
week.
   But almost all the pictures and data _ stored on three tracks of
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s four-track tape recorder _ won't be sent back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
until <DATE>October</DATE>, when the spacecraft is close enough to transmit the
material with its low-gain antenna. That antenna now can be used
only for communications to keep <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> operating.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s main umbrella-shaped antenna must remain furled to
protect it from sunlight until after the craft makes its first
flight past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was programmed to photograph <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and study the planet
with its ultraviolet, infrared and visible light sensors to look
for lightning, study the makeup of the carbon dioxide atmosphere,
examine cloud and wind patterns, map cloudtop temperatures and peer
at the lower atmosphere.
   Sensors that detect particles and magnetic fields were
programmed to study how solar wind interacts with <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>'
atmosphere. At the same time, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> arranged for the <ORGANIZATION>Pioneer Venus
Orbiter</ORGANIZATION>, circling <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> since <DATE>1978</DATE>, to make similar measurements
closer to the planet, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   While nearly 20 other <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Soviet spacecraft have visited
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, ``we think we're going to get some real good stuff,'' he
said.
   But scientists won't know for months unless engineers meet
success next week when they try to have <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> send back a small
amount of data, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> added.
   Studies from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and previous spacecraft indicate <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> has
continent-sized highlands with peaks dwarfing <LOCATION>Mount Everest</LOCATION> and
hundreds of thousands of volcanoes stretching across lowland plains.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft, launched from <LOCATION>Atlantis</LOCATION> <DATE>last May 4</DATE>,
will go into orbit around Venus in <DATE>August</DATE>. It will use radar to
peer through the clouds and map at least <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>'
surface during a <MONEY>$550 million</MONEY> mission.
   When the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> probe and orbiter reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the probe will
parachute into the atmosphere and make measurements until intense
heat and pressure vaporize it. The orbiter will photograph and
study <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and its major moons until late <DATE>1997</DATE>, circling the
planet instead of flying past it like the Pioneer and Voyager
planned to send <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> on a two-year trip to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> by launching
it with a <ORGANIZATION>Centaur</ORGANIZATION> rocket after it was released from a shuttle.
   But the <DATE>1986</DATE> explosion that destroyed Challenger and killed
seven crew members raised safety concerns. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> decided against
using the volatile, liquid-fueled Centaur.
   So <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was launched with a much weaker <ORGANIZATION>Inertial Upper Stage</ORGANIZATION>
booster after it was deployed by Atlantis' crew. The weaker rocket
required <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> to redesign <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s route so the craft could
utilize gravity from <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and Earth for a much longer, looping
trip to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Environmentalists failed in court to stop <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> from having a
shuttle carry <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> into space. They feared a Challenger-like
explosion could contaminate <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> with plutonium in <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s
nuclear batteries, which are not reactors but generate electricity
using heat from the radioactive decay of plutonium. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said the
risk was minimal.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> is named for the Italian Renaissance astronomer who
discovered <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s major moons.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891019-0126 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891019 </DD>
<AN> 891019-0126. </AN>
<HL> Technology &amp; Health:
@  Space Shuttle Lifts Off, Carrying
@  A Jupiter-Bound Galileo Probe
@  ---
@  Atlantis Launching Is Hailed
@  In NASA Bid to Counter
@  Project's Troubled Past
@  ----
@  By Bob Davis
<DD> 10/19/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<IN> AEROSPACE (ARO) </IN>
<GV> FEDERAL GOVERNMENT (FDL) </GV>
<DATELINE> CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The space shuttle Atlantis boosted the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft on its way to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, giving a big lift as well to an ambitious <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> program of space exploration. 


   "<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> did it right; that's the message," said <PERSON>J.R. Thompson</PERSON>, the agency's deputy administrator. 

   The <MONEY>$1.4 billion</MONEY> robot spacecraft faces a six-year journey to explore <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and its 16 known moons. 
If all goes well, it will parachute a probe into the dense Jovian atmosphere in <DATE>July 1995</DATE> to pick up detailed data about gases that may be similar to the material from which the solar system was formed 4.6 billion years ago. 

   Investigating <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in detail may provide clues to what astronomer <PERSON>Tobias Owen</PERSON> calls the "cosmic paradox" of life: <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and other bodies in the outer solar system are rich in elements such as hydrogen that are essential for life on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, but these planets are lifeless; Earth, on the other hand, has a diminished store of such material but is rich in life. 
Some scientists have suggested that comets and asteroids may have brought enough of this kind of material from the outer solar system to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> to spawn life. 

   Beginning in <DATE>December 1995</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will begin a two-year tour of the Jovian moons. 
The photos showed active geysers on Io spewing sulfurous material 190 miles into its atmosphere and indicated that Europa may have an ocean hidden under a thick sheet of ice. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s photos of Europa will be more than 1,000 times as sharp as <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION>'s, according to <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s project scientist, and may show whether it actually has the only known ocean other than those on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 

"I'm happy and sad," he said. 

   Anti-nuclear activists took a less positive view. 
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will skim past Earth in <DATE>1990</DATE> and <DATE>1992</DATE>, collecting energy from the planet's gravitational field to gain momentum for its trip to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. 
The protesters point out that <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> also could crash to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> then. 

An unmanned spacecraft, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, already is heading to <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and is due to begin mapping the planet next <DATE>August</DATE>. 
Voyager 2 sent back spectacular photos of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and its moon, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, this <DATE>summer</DATE>. 

Next <DATE>March</DATE>, the shuttle Discovery will launch the Hubble space telescope, a <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> instrument designed to see the faintest galaxies in the universe. 

<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> won't attempt a rescue; instead, it will try to predict whether any of the rubble will smash to the ground and where. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890605-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-05-89 2316EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Voyager-Neptune     06-05 0441</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Neptune,0454</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voyager 2 Begins Picture-Taking Encounter With Neptune</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 2 began taking pictures <DATE>Monday</DATE>
of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, the last planet the space probe will encounter since it
was launched nearly 12 years ago on a spectacular tour of the solar
system, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> officials said.
   The spacecraft still is about 73 million miles from the planet,
about the distance from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> to the planet <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Ellis
Miner</PERSON>, Voyager deputy project scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion
Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>.
   But even at such distances, <PERSON>Miner</PERSON> said the electronic
picture-taking equipment aboard Voyager 2 can provide more detail
and clarity than anything available on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ``Each new picture gives us new information,'' <PERSON>Miner</PERSON> said. The
probe is taking about six images every three hours as it approaches
the planet at roughly 37,200 miles per hour.
   ``We're seeing a lot of detail on the atmosphere that we really
hadn't anticipated,'' <PERSON>Miner</PERSON> said.
   Enthusiastic members of <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION>'s imaging team already are
speculating that the findings will be more exciting than the images
of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, where Voyager cameras discovered extraterrestrial
volcanoes on Io, a moon.
   On <DATE>Aug. 6th</DATE>, Voyager 2 begins its close-encounter phase and the
probe's closest approach is scheduled for <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, when it will
pass within 3,000 miles of the planet.
   The first images were being recorded by the spacecraft's tape
recorders, and will be played back <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION> laboratory,
operated under contract by the <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>
   The probe now is so far away, more than 2.6 billion miles, that
data radioed at the speed of light take nearly four hours to reach
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION> officials said.
   Voyager 2 and its sister space probe, Voyager 1, were launched
within weeks of each other in the <DATE>summer of 1977</DATE> in what has proved
to be one of the most successful data gathering efforts from deep
space.
   ``They are the two most complex spacecraft missions that we have
launched to date,'' <PERSON>Miner</PERSON> said. ``It's been a truly amazing journey
that the two have had.''
   Voyager 1 was directed to make an extraordinary fly-by of
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>, which threw the space probe above the plane of the planets
and made it impossible to visit any more of the solar system's
outer planets.
   Voyager 2, however, sailed on to Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>, where it
observed 10 new moons, measured the planet's rotation and took
pictures of major portions of the planet and its moons.
   In addition to taking images of the planet, Voyager 2 also will
be measuring ultraviolet radiation and searching for escaping gases
and activity similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s aurora borealis and australis.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901130-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-30-90 0102EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Galileo-Earth     11-30 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galileo-Earth,0479</SECOND>
<HEAD>Galileo to Use Earth as Gravity Slingshot Dec. 8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jupiter-bound <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft
will zoom past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> next week, taking pictures and making
measurements as if its home planet were an alien world.
   ``It will be the first time the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> has been viewed from this
perspective. I expect it will give us a greater appreciation of
this place,'' said <PERSON>Bill O'Neil</PERSON>, project manager at the <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet
Propulsion Laboratory.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s close encounter with <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION> will take place on <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE>
and is aimed at using the planet's gravity like a slingshot to send
the craft on the right path.
   The craft will swoop about 593 miles above the southwest
<LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> at <TIME>12:35 p.m. PST</TIME> <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was 3.97 million
miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> today.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will be the first planetary craft to approach Earth from
space. So the flyby will be ``our first chance to look at <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as
we have at other planets,'' <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s chief
scientist, said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   During its flyby, the spacecraft will measure gases that cause
the ``greenhouse effect'' warming of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere and will
study high-altitude water vapor that helps create and destroy
Earth's ozone layer, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> also will be the first spacecraft with modern
instruments to study the far side of the moon, which is always
pointed away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, he added.
   Galileo is powered by two nuclear batteries - not reactors -
that use the decay of radioactive plutonium to produce electricity.
   Environmentalists unsuccessfully sued to halt <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s launch
for fear the plutonium could contaminate <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere. <PERSON>O'Neil</PERSON>
said the chance that <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will somehow plunge into <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s
atmosphere and release its plutonium is less than one in <MONEY>2 million</MONEY>.
   Even if it did happen, the plutonium would cause no more than 10
cancer deaths during the next 70 years, according to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>.
   Galileo is the most sophisticated unmanned spacecraft ever
built. It was launched from a space shuttle in <DATE>October 1989</DATE> and is
scheduled to rendezvous with <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1995</DATE> after a looping
2.4-billion-mile journey.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s route was designed so the spacecraft could use Venus
and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as ``gravity slingshots.'' It will use Earth for that
purpose <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> and again in <DATE>December 1992</DATE>.
   It used <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> as a gravity slingshot last <DATE>February</DATE>. Scientists
discussed their Venus findings on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s infrared camera made the first pictures of Venus'
middle and lower cloud decks. Pictures also were used to make a
movie showing clouds moving in 150 mph winds.
   Studying <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' acid clouds and its carbon dioxide atmosphere
may help scientists understand how increasing carbon dioxide levels
in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere will warm the planet like glass trapping heat
in a greenhouse, said <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> astronomer <PERSON>Michael Belton</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900210-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-10-90 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Galileo-Venus 3rdLd-Writethru a0498-502 02-10 0860</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galileo-Venus, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0498-502,0879</SECOND>
<HEAD>Galileo Spacecraft Swings Around Venus, Develops Camera Trouble</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 11 grafs to UPDATE with news conference;
scientists predicting no permanent problems from glitch; picks up
12th graf a0498: `Galileo's main ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft developed
camera trouble today after zooming around cloud-covered Venus in a
``celestial billiard shot'' that speeded the robot explorer toward
its <DATE>1995</DATE> encounter with <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Although the glitch threatened to prevent <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> from snapping
five dozen more pictures of Venus tonight and next week, project
scientist <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory said
it should cause no permanent problems for the mission.
   Mission director <PERSON>Neal Ausman</PERSON> said the TV camera shutter, after
taking 16 planned pictures of Venus early today, clicked open and
closed 452 times, twice per minute, apparently because of faulty
commands from the probe's main computer.
   Ausman, speaking at a news conference, said the unwanted
computer commands then stopped for reasons not immediately
understood, and a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> was working to fix the problem.
   The extra exposures weren't recorded, the malfunction won't harm
the 16 pictures that were taken, the camera was undamaged, and
engineers shut off the camera until it can be repaired, project
manager <PERSON>Dick Spehalski</PERSON> said.
   The 2.8-ton spacecraft made its closest approach to Venus at
<TIME>9:59 p.m. PST</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>. It was supposed to pass 10,028 miles above
the furnace-like surface of the second planet from the sun, but
actually came three or four miles closer, said mission science and
design manager <PERSON>Bill O'Neil</PERSON>.
   ``We have clearly achieved the sole objective of going to Venus:
a trajectory that will help us ultimately reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>,'' he said.
   As a result, scientists won't be very disappointed if the
malfunction prevents <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> from snapping an additional five dozen
planned pictures of <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, which has been photographed by numerous
other spacecraft, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   The 16 pictures taken will be used to study wind and cloud
patterns and search for lightning that might indicate the presence
of volcanoes erupting beneath the clouds.
   The spacecraft's ultraviolet, visible and infrared light sensors
studied the makeup of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' carbon dioxide atmosphere, mapped
cloud-top temperatures and looked for the glow of the hot lower
atmosphere backlighting cooler clouds overhead, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   The pictures and data were stored on <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s tape recorder,
and won't be sent back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> until <DATE>October</DATE> when the spacecraft
is close enough to transmit the material with its low-gain antenna.
That antenna now can be used only for communications to keep
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> operating.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s main umbrella-shaped antenna must remain furled to
protect it from sunlight until after the craft cruises past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE>.
   The <MONEY>$1.35 billion</MONEY> mission also will let <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> examine <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,
its moon and one or two asteroids before the spacecraft separates
into an orbiter and a small probe in <DATE>July 1995</DATE>. In <DATE>December 1995</DATE>,
they arrive at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the solar system's largest planet, after a
2.4-billion-mile trip, including 182 million miles to reach <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was deployed from space shuttle Atlantis last <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE>.
   Acid-laden clouds extend 40 miles above <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface, trapping
heat in a runaway ``greenhouse effect'' that raises surface
temperatures to 900 degrees Fahrenheit. Atmospheric pressure is 90
times that on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said the photos and measurements of Venus were secondary
to the main purpose of the flyby: using the planet as a ``gravity
slingshot'' to expand the spacecraft's orbit and boost its speed to
88,740 mph from 83,750 mph.
   ``We have gained enough energy out of this celestial billiard
shot to get the energy we need to make it all the say to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>,''
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will use the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as a gravity slingshot next <DATE>December</DATE>
and again <DATE>Dec. 8, 1992</DATE>, so it will be properly aimed toward
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft, launched from <LOCATION>Atlantis</LOCATION> <DATE>last May 4</DATE>,
will go into orbit around Venus in <DATE>August</DATE>. It will use radar map at
least <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface during a <MONEY>$550 million</MONEY> mission.
   When the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> probe and orbiter reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the probe will
parachute into the atmosphere and make measurements until intense
heat and pressure vaporizes it. The orbiter will photograph and
study <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and its major moons until late <DATE>1997</DATE>, circling the
planet instead of flying past it like the Pioneer and Voyager
spacecraft.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s roundabout route to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> is an indirect result of
seven crew members. After the tragedy, the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and
Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> decided against using powerful, volatile,
liquid-fueled Centaur rockets to launch spacecraft after they were
deployed from shuttles.
   Instead, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was launched by a weaker booster after it was
released from Atlantis' cargo bay. That made it necessary to use
the gravity of Venus and Earth to help speed and aim <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> toward
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. A <ORGANIZATION>Centaur</ORGANIZATION> would have propelled <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> to Venus in only
two years.
   Environmentalists failed in court to block <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s mission.
They feared a Challenger-like explosion could contaminate <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>
with plutonium in <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s nuclear batteries, which generate
electricity using heat from the radioactive decay of plutonium.
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said the risk was minimal.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900416-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-16-90 2130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GalileoManeuver     04-16 0244</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galileo Maneuver,0250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Galileo Fires Thrusters as Part of Earth, Jupiter Missions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft successfully
fired its thrusters almost 1,600 times during a four-day maneuver
designed to help it reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1995</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The sequence of thruster pulses, completed late last <DATE>Thursday</DATE>,
slowed the spacecraft by about 55 mph, said <PERSON>Jim Wilson</PERSON>, a spokesman
Propulsion Laboratory.
   The next set of maneuvers is scheduled for this <DATE>summer</DATE>, said <PERSON>Bob
MacMillin</PERSON> another spokesman.
   The 2.8-ton <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was launched on its <MONEY>$1.35 billion</MONEY> mission by
the space shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>Oct. 18</DATE>.
   It flew past Venus on <DATE>Feb. 9</DATE> so that planet could act as a
``gravity slingshot'' to help propel the spacecraft on its looping
2.4-billion-mile, six-year journey to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the solar system's
largest planet.
   The spacecraft will fly past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> of this year and
again on <DATE>Dec. 8, 1990</DATE>, in two more ``gravity slingshot'' maneuvers.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will examine Earth, <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s moon and one or two
asteroids before the spacecraft separates into an orbiter and a
small probe in <DATE>July 1995</DATE>. In <DATE>December 1995</DATE>, they arrive at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   There, the probe will parachute into the atmosphere and make
measurements until the planet's intense heat and pressure vaporize
it. The orbiter will photograph and study <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and its major
moons until late <DATE>1997</DATE>, circling the planet instead of flying past
it like the Pioneer and Voyager spacecraft.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891005-0217 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-05-89 1606EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Spacecraft-Mission Adv08   10-05 1224</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Spacecraft-Mission, Adv 08,1256</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv08</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Oct. 8, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Anti-Nuclear Activists Vow To Disrupt Shuttle Launch Because of Plutonium</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Spacecraft to Earth, b0739</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> starts the countdown <DATE>Monday</DATE>,
but <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s launch of the space shuttle Atlantis depends on
whether a federal judge permits its five astronauts to dispatch the
nuclear-powered <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> probe to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Anti-nuclear activists have sued to halt the flight, arguing
that a launch accident could spread radioactive plutonium over
densely populated parts of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. The space agency maintains the
danger is almost non-existent.
   Both sides will argue their cases in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District Court in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. <PERSON>Judge Oliver Gasch</PERSON> then will
decide whether to grant a temporary restraining order to stop the
launch, or to let the countdown proceed. This is the first time
anyone has gone to court to stop a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> launch.
   The plutonium argument overshadows the fact that the mission
involves the most expensive, most sophisticated unmanned space
probe ever built, a vehicle one mission official calls ``the
<ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION> of spacecraft.''
   After a six-year outward journey, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>, priced at <MONEY>$1.4
billion</MONEY>, is to shoot a probe into <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere and then
orbit the planet for two years.
   Mission planners say its investigation of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and its moons
will be the most scientifically rich that interplanetary
exploration has witnessed. The <DATE>1979</DATE> Voyager views of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and
its satellites were fascinating, but <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s images will be 1,000
times clearer, they say.
   The countdown is to start at <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>. If <PERSON>Gasch</PERSON> does not
rule quickly, the count will pause at the 11-hour mark, for several
days if necessary, awaiting a decision. Several critical steps,
including fueling the shuttle, occur after that point.
   If <PERSON>Gasch</PERSON> gives the green light, and no other problems arise,
Atlantis is scheduled to blast off at <TIME>1:29 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The activists vow that if they lose in court, they will
physically try to stop the liftoff.
   ``We are going to attempt to enter the launch area and sit on
the launch pad,'' said <PERSON>Bruce Gagnon</PERSON>, coordinator for the <ORGANIZATION>Florida
Coalition of Peace and Justice</ORGANIZATION>, one of three groups that filed the
suit.
   Extra security measures have been in force several days,
including closing to the public several roads approaching <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy
Space Center</ORGANIZATION>. These roads are normally closed only on launch days.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> officials are concerned that <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s brief, 10-minute
launch window would vanish if protesters penetrate the launch zone
with a boat or plane in the count's final minutes.
   At issue are <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s two generators and their fuel: 48 pounds
of radioactive plutonium-238 dioxide.
   The activists say that if the space shuttle crashed or exploded,
as the Challenger did in <DATE>1986</DATE>, the poisonous plutonium would be
released into the air.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has said the ``highest probability of launch-area release
of plutonium due to a shuttle accident is less than 1 in 2,500 and
such a release would have no appreciable adverse effects on the
population.''
   The agency quotes health physicists who say this type of
plutonium is relatively harmless unless a particle is inhaled or
lodges in an open wound, where it could cause cancer. Generally the
particles do not travel far in air and can be stopped by a piece of
paper or unbroken human skin.
   In tests, empty graphite plutonium containers have been blown
up, shot at and burned to determine how they survive all types of
accidents. They have withstood pressures far greater than those
generated by the Challenger explosion, say <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Energy
Department</ORGANIZATION>, which took part in the testing.
   The space agency notes that similar generators have flown on 22
space vehicles, including five manned Apollo moon missions, and
that in three instances the well-protected devices survived severe
accidents: two unmanned rockets that blew up in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and the
explosion aboard Apollo 13 in <DATE>1970</DATE>, which forced abandonment of a
moon landing.
   Plutonium 238's normal decay gives off intense heat, which
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will convert to electricity. No other power source is
practical for space missions too far from the sun to use solar
energy.
   The five astronauts who will fly the mission say they are not
concerned about flying with plutonium.
   ``I have no absolutely no qualms about the devices,'' said
commander <PERSON>Donald Williams</PERSON>.
   Pilot <PERSON>Mike McCulley</PERSON> was more blunt: ``I don't see how it can
hurt anyone unless it hits him on the head, and that's pretty
remote. I think it is a complete non-issue except as a
philosophical issue to some people.''
   ``My family is going to be down there watching the launch, as
well as other people that I love, and so I'm not concerned about
it; I feel it's safe,'' said mission specialist <PERSON>Ellen Baker</PERSON>.
   The other crew members, mission specialists <PERSON>Shannon Lucid</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Franklin Chang-Diaz</PERSON>, expressed similar feelings.
   Six hours after liftoff, the astronauts are to release <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>
from the cargo bay. An hour later, an attached motor will start the
6,700-pound craft on a six-year trip that will cover 2.4 billion
miles on the path to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the largest planet in our solar
system.
   Along the way, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will obtain fly-by data about the moon,
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and at least one asteroid, <LOCATION>Gaspra</LOCATION>. It will make two return
swings to within 600 miles of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>December 1995</DATE> a 737-pound probe released from the spacecraft
is to plunge into <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s cloud layers at 115,000 mph and make
the first direct sampling of the Jovian atmosphere. Slowed quickly
by the thickening atmosphere, the probe will pop a parachute and
transmit data to the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> mother ship for about an hour as it
descends about 360 miles before it is crushed and vaporized by
extreme heat and pressure.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will fire into orbit about the planet, and its 10
scientific instruments will gather information on temperatures,
magnetic fields, radiation, cloud characteristics and gravity
fields.
   Of particular interest will be the dynamics of a weather system
that produce the ever-changing bands, whirls and plumes seen from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and from the two Voyager spacecraft.
   The weather includes storms up to 25,000 miles across that have
raged for centuries. Among them is the mysterious Great Red Spot,
which the Voyagers determined is a tremendous atmospheric storm
similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s hurricanes.
   The Voyagers also found that <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, 318 times more massive
than <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, is a whirling ball of mostly liquid hydrogen, topped by
an atmosphere that is mostly hydrogen and helium. They discovered a
narrow ring of debris around the planet and found three new moons,
raising the toal to 16.
   The four largest moons bear the same relationship to their
planet as planets in our solar system do to the sun _ the nearest
being solid rock, like <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION>, and the farthest being a slush ball
with a rock in the center, like gaseous <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   Thus, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will examine data and transmit pictures of a
miniature solar system as it orbits <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Edward C. Stone</PERSON>,
is one of the mission scientists.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will give us more than just snapshots in passing, as
the Voyagers did,'' Stone said. ``Being there and observing over a
period of nearly two years will allow us to sort out the dynamics
of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and its moons.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Oct. 8</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890823-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-23-89 1328EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Voyager-Neptune 2ndLd-Writethru a0534 08-23 0924</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Voyager-Neptune, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0534,0945</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Probe Searches for More Neptunian Moons, Rings and Arcs</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with possible impact crater on
Triton; picks up 3rd graf, `The latest, ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 2, only a day away from its close
encounter with <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, was ready for new computer commands today as
it searched for more moons and rings after discovering a first
complete ring around the storm-wracked planet.
   A new picture taken by Voyager shows what appears to be a large
meteorite crater on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s major moon, deputy project
scientist <PERSON>Ellis Miner</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   Howewver, he said, there also are uncratered regions on the moon,
and scientists haven't yet definitely concluded the spot on the
still-fuzzy <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> picture is an impact crater.
   Engineers prepared to send Voyager the computer program this
afternoon to control how the spacecraft aims itself, its cameras and
other sensors during its flight past <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Doug
   The latest navigation information shows that after a 12-year,
4.4-billion-mile flight, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will be within one second and 22
miles of where it is supposed to be for the <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> flyby, he said.
   ``The spacecraft is working marvelously, with no problems at
all,'' <PERSON>Griffith</PERSON> said.
   He said the new computer program, smaller than that contained in
many popular computer games, is crucial to experiments in which
<ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will study the makeup of the atmospheres of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> by sending radio waves through their atmospheres to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Griffith</PERSON> said the new navigation data shows Voyager will make its
closest approach by flying 3,000 miles above <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s cloudtops at
<TIME>18 seconds before 8:56 p.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Until today's search for more moons, ``suspects have been seen
here and there,'' said <PERSON>Bradford Smith</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Arizona</ORGANIZATION>
planetary scientist who heads <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION>'s photographic imaging team.
``I would expect several more satellites.''
   So far, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> has found four small moons besides Nereid and
backward-orbiting <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, which were first seen years ago from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   After Voyager makes its closest approach to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, the probe
may find a sheet of ring material encircling the planet _ similar to
the broad band of dust it discovered around Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>,
laboratory astronomer <PERSON>Rich Terrile</PERSON> said.
   Smith announced <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the spacecraft found at least one
complete ring of diffuse debris orbiting <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>. He said a partial
ring discovered by the spacecraft almost two weeks ago also may
prove to be a second complete ring. It has parts that are thicker
than other parts.
   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s find, the latest in a string of discoveries by the
probe during passes by <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus,
elated scientists.
   ``I like the idea Voyager is going out with a bang. It's going to
blow our minds,'' said <PERSON>Carolyn Porco</PERSON>, a planetary scientist with the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Arizona</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>.
   Pictures taken by Voyager on <DATE>Aug. 11</DATE> revealed two partial rings _
or ring arcs _ extending around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>. One of them couldn't be
found in later images and was dubbed the ``lost arc,'' until Voyager
relocated it <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and found it goes all the way around the planet.
   Finding a complete ring was surprising. Voyager project scientist
<ORGANIZATION>Edward Stone</ORGANIZATION> said two months ago the planet might be orbited by 50
to 100 ring arcs, but he backed away from that <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   About 9 o'clock PDT tonight, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will cross within 1 million
miles of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, speeding toward the giant gaseous planet at 38,047
mph. It will be about 2.75 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, having traveled
a curving path of 4.4 billion miles since it was launched in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   At <TIME>2:10 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will zip within 24,000 miles of the
moon <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>.
   Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> is scheduled to visit the <ORGANIZATION>Jet
Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> several hours later to congratulate Voyager
scientists and engineers.
   Voyager was programmed to search today for more rings and arcs _
including any that might be in or near <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s orbit _ and to look
for ``shepherd moons.'' Rings get their shape from the pull of
gravity between a planet and its moons, so moons that corral rings
are called shepherd moons.
   Today's picture-snapping schedule also included 30 images of
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, four photos of one of the moons Voyager discovered, and 22
pictures of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and its surprisingly turbulent weather, with
racing clouds and an Earth-sized cyclone.
   Because of its bluish color and bright clouds, ``<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> looks
