<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-10516</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKEC2AAOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931105
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  05 NOV 93 / Belgium urges early active role for EMI
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PETER NORMAN, Economics Editor
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
MR <PERSON>Philippe Maystadt</PERSON>, the Belgian finance minister, yesterday suggested that
the planned <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> could start actively co-ordinating
the monetary policies of <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> member states with low inflation after it starts
operations in <DATE>January</DATE>.
At a seminar on economic and monetary union organised by the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Trust
for Education and Research</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Salomon Brothers International</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON>
floated the idea of low-inflation <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> countries agreeing a common monetary
growth target. The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> could then use this to organise monetary
co-ordination and monitor progress towards the achievement of durable price
stability in the <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION>.
The minister, who is current president of the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> council of
economics and finance ministers, also suggested that the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> might take over
announcing policy decisions such as interest rate changes of member central
banks agreeing to a common monetary target during the second stage of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>
which begins in <DATE>January</DATE>.
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>, which will be based in <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> and is seen as a forerunner of a
European central bank, has so far been given only vague guidance on the
scope of its operations and <PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON>'s remarks yesterday represented an
attempt to set an agenda for the institute.
In view of the 'rather long' second stage envisaged for <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>, it was
important to launch a qualitative step towards further European integration
and to ensure that the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> is not perceived as an empty shell, he said. <PERSON>Mr
Maystadt</PERSON> said that national central banks would continue to make independent
monetary policy decisions.
But he admitted that his idea of an <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> monetary target would push the
bankers and the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> towards the 'ultimate goal of conducting a single
monetary policy at <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION> level'.
Not surprisingly, his approach found no UK support. <PERSON>Mr Christopher Taylor</PERSON>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>'s chief European adviser, said the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>'s role should be
advisory and consultative, and it should have only a small staff.
<PERSON>Mr Taylor</PERSON> said the UK was wary of monetary aggregates and stressed that the
<ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> 'must not interfere with, or cut across, the monetary and exchange rate
policies of member states.'
<PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON> warned the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> against trying to operate the European exchange
rate mechanism with widened 15 per cent fluctuation margins until full
monetary union. The approach of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> could trigger competitive currency
depreciation and threaten the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> single market, he said.
He admitted that <DATE>January 1 1999</DATE> was now a more realistic target for
transition to a fully fledged monetary union than the original objective in
the Maastricht Treaty of <DATE>1997</DATE> for stage three.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BEZ  Belgium, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-10304</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKKCTAHHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931105
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  05 NOV 93 / Early policy role urged for monetary institute: Belgium
proposes agenda for new body
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PETER NORMAN, Economics Editor
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The planned <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> could start actively co-ordinating
the monetary policies of <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION> member states with low inflation after it
begins operations in <DATE>January</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr Philippe Maystadt</PERSON>, the Belgian finance
minister, suggested yesterday.
At a seminar on economic and monetary union organised by the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Trust
for Education and Research</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Salomon Brothers International</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON>
floated the idea of low-inflation <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> countries agreeing a common monetary
growth target. The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> could then use this to organise monetary
co-ordination and monitor progress towards the achievement of durable price
stability in the <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION>.
The minister, who is current president of the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> council of
economics and finance ministers, also suggested the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> might take over
announcing policy decisions such as interest rate changes of member central
banks agreeing to a common monetary target during the second stage of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>
which begins in <DATE>January</DATE>.
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>, which will be based in <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> and is seen as a forerunner of a
European central bank, has so far been given only vague guidance on the
scope of its operations and <PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON>'s remarks yesterday represented an
attempt to set an agenda for the institute.
In view of the 'rather long' second stage for <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>, it was important to
launch a qualitative step towards further European integration and to ensure
that the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> is not perceived as an empty shell, he said. <PERSON>Mr May-stadt</PERSON> said
that national central banks would continue to make independent monetary
policy decisions. But he admitted his idea of an <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> monetary target would
push the bankers and the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> towards the 'ultimate goal of conducting a
single monetary policy at <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION> level'.
Not surprisingly, his approach gained no UK support. <PERSON>Mr Christopher Taylor</PERSON>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>'s chief European adviser, said the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>'s role should be
advisory and consultative.
<PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON> warned the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> against trying to operate the European exchange
rate mechanism with widened 15 per cent fluctuation margins until full
monetary union. The approach of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> could trigger competitive currency
depreciation and threaten the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> single market, he said.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6011 Federal Reserve Banks.
    P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 18
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-15011</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJNDKAAPFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931014
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 OCT 93 / Bundesbank outlines monetary test for EC
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID WALLER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   FRANKFURT
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
EUROPE is entering a 'test phase' for monetary union, when individual
central banks have it within their power to create a solid basis for it, the
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> said yesterday.
Countries now had to prove the credibility of their national monetary
policy, rather than engage in disputes over the framework of European
monetary union (<ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>) as set down in the Maastricht treaty, <PERSON>Mr Hans Tietmeyer</PERSON>
told the <ORGANIZATION>VWD</ORGANIZATION> news agency.
This would be the only way that monetary union had a chance of being
successfully implemented in practice, <PERSON>Mr Tietmeyer</PERSON> cautioned. Countries
would have to show a firm commitment to monetary stability in the years
ahead and implement the institutional changes necessary to give national
central banks the necessary independence.
It was also important for public opinion to develop a 'stability culture',
he said. <PERSON>Mr Tietmeyer</PERSON> was giving his reaction to the <ORGANIZATION>German Constitutional
Court</ORGANIZATION>'s ruling on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s ratification of the Maastricht
treaty was valid.
The second stage of monetary union is due to to start on <DATE>January 1</DATE> next year
when the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> (EMI) will start operations. <PERSON>Mr
Tietmeyer</PERSON> said its role would be to strengthen co-operation between <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>
central banks and to co-ordinate the monetary policy of member nations with
a view to price stability.
But responsibility for monetary policy will remain with national central
banks during the second stage of monetary union, and all important decisions
on the <ORGANIZATION>EMS</ORGANIZATION> will continue to be taken unanimously, he said. <PERSON>Mr Tietmeyer</PERSON>
reiterated his call for the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> to be located in <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>DEZ  Germany, EC.
    QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-12449</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJ0CNAAJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931027
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 OCT 93 / Defenders of Emu deploy their forces
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW HILL
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE Belgian presidency of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr Jacques Delors</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> president,
and <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> employers, yesterday threw their weight behind
existing plans for economic and monetary union.
<PERSON>Mr Philippe Maystadt</PERSON>, Belgian finance minister, said the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary
Institute</ORGANIZATION> - forerunner of a European central bank - should play a forceful
role in preparing for a single currency by <DATE>1999</DATE>.
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> will begin its work on <DATE>January 1, 1994</DATE>, provided <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> leaders can
decide on a site for the institution at their summit in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mr Delors</PERSON> also stressed the importance of the <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> objectives, and the role
of the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>. In an interview for Belgian television, he said the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> would
'round up the lost sheep (among <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> economies), give new stability to a
relatively fixed exchange rate system, and lead to economic convergence'.
The currency turmoil of the last year has left the European monetary system
in disarray and recession has raised doubts about the original plans for
economic union. <PERSON>Mr John Major</PERSON>, the British prime minister, recently
dismissed the timetable for a single currency as 'folly'.
But <PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON>, one of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>'s longest-serving finance ministers, said
yesterday that the Maastricht deadline of <DATE>1999</DATE> for monetary union was still
feasible, even if the more ambitious target of <DATE>1997</DATE> would be difficult to
achieve because of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>'s economic problems.
In an interview with the <ORGANIZATION>Financial Times</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON> also defended the
nomination of <PERSON>Mr Alexandre Lamfalussy</PERSON> as the first president of the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>. The
choice should be confirmed by <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> leaders on <DATE>Friday</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON> said <PERSON>Mr
Lamfalussy</PERSON>, Belgian general manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Bank for International
Settlements</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Basle</LOCATION>, would give a new impetus to the Maastricht aims. 'We
know that <PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> is really convinced of the need for <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> to go to
a single currency: he's a true believer in the single currency and that's
not the case with all the bank governors.'
He said the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> would be 'a more permanent and more objective supervisory
body for the European monetary system' than existing inter-governmental
bodies like the secretive <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> monetary committee. <ORGANIZATION>Unice</ORGANIZATION>, which represents <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>
employers' federations, also called for <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> leaders to refocus on the <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>
objectives. 'We think that the single market without a stable monetary
relationship will be very difficult to sustain,' said <PERSON>Mr Carlos Ferrer</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Unice</ORGANIZATION>'s president.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BEZ  Belgium, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-9974</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKHDHADLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931108
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 NOV 93 / Economics Notebook: Reality plays tricks with Emu theory
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PETER NORMAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
It is, according to one old saw, better to travel hopefully than to arrive.
But as in so many things in life, the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> is turning
conventional wisdom on its head. Increasingly, the transitional second stage
of economic and monetary union, which starts on <DATE>January 1</DATE>, is shaping up to
be an especially difficult venture with many incalculable problems.
By contrast, the third and final stage of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>, with its planned single
currency and central bank, has been subject to so much analysis and
discussion over the past five years that its hazards, although real enough,
appear familiar and less daunting.
The second stage of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> is supposed to pave the way for fully fledged
monetary union towards the end of the decade. In it, <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> member states are to
strive for ever greater convergence of economic performance, particularly in
terms of price stability and sound public finance, and to step up policy
co-ordination.
Such far reaching changes are best attempted on a sound institutional basis
and against a favourable economic background. The past year's crises in the
European exchange rate mechanism and the continuing recession on the
continent mean neither condition applies at present. Compounding the
difficulties are policy inconsistencies, notably in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, and widely
divergent ideas among member states as to how far the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> should move down
the path of institutional integration in stage two.
With the community heading for yet another year of sub-optimal growth, the
economic background is especially bleak. Although <PERSON>Mr Henning Christophersen</PERSON>,
the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>'s economic affairs commissioner, has suggested that <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> growth could
be as high as <MONEY>2 per cent</MONEY> next year, others are far less hopeful.
The commission's own forecasters have suggested that growth next year will
be about 0.9 per cent, largely because they believe <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> is heading for
another year of declining economic activity. <PERSON>Mr Philippe Maystadt</PERSON>, the
Belgian finance minister and current president of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> economic and
finance ministers' council, noted last week that the commission was likely
to revise its growth forecasts upwards. But he added that many countries,
including <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, would not be following suit.
Low growth will make it more difficult for member states to control their
budget deficits and so will hamper progress towards meeting the <ORGANIZATION>Maastricht
Treaty</ORGANIZATION>'s convergence criteria, which include a 60 per cent limit for the
ratio of government debt to gross domestic product.
In the absence of draconian public spending cuts, which would be politically
risky, public debt is bound to keep rising as a percentage of GDP in those
<ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> countries where economic growth rates are lower than real interest rates.
This condition applies in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>. In <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>'s case, where the
ratio of debt to GDP is around 130 per cent, the outlook is one of further
deterioration unless and until growth exceeds real interest rates. In spite
of <DATE>last month</DATE>'s easing of <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> monetary policy, that date is probably
some way off.
Doubts about convergence will make <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> economies vulnerable to financial
market pressures in stage two. <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>'s debt problem has exposed its
currency the Belgian franc to selling pressure in recent weeks.
International investors have also been looking askance at other signs of
economic divergence that are not singled out in the <ORGANIZATION>Maastricht Treaty</ORGANIZATION>.
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s sharply rising unemployment rate was a key factor behind the loss
of confidence in the French franc ahead of the <DATE>July</DATE> and <DATE>August</DATE> currency
crisis that culminated in the widening of the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> fluctuation bands to 15
per cent. Looking ahead, there is no early sign that French unemployment
will decline from its current 11.8 per cent level, while youth unemployment
at about twice that rate is especially disturbing.
The joint Franco-German convergence programme, unveiled on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, has
caused surprise among some European officials for its optimistic view that
French growth could be as much as 3.5 per cent after <DATE>1995</DATE>. One non-official
view, expressed last week by Professor Christian de Boissieu of the <ORGANIZATION>Sorbonne
University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, was that growth would be nearer 2.5 per cent.
As worrying to European monetary officials is an apparent lack of coherence
in French monetary policy. At a recent monetary conference in <LOCATION>Amsterdam</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr
Andre Icard</PERSON>, director general of research at the French central bank,
insisted that currency stability was the main plank of monetary policy, in
spite of the franc's decline against the D-Mark since <DATE>August</DATE>. But he also
said <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> would pay more attention to the M3 money supply measure than in
the past.
Those who took his remarks at face value were left wondering how the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of
France</ORGANIZATION> would react to conflicting signals from its chosen indicators. Others
concluded that <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s current monetary policy was to shadow German
interest rates.
According to <PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON>, the planned <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>, which is
due to begin operating in <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> in <DATE>January</DATE>, is the ideal institution to
iron out such wrinkles and demonstrate consistency of decisions among
national central banks in the run up to stage three.
But that presupposes that <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> member states will have achieved a consensus on
what the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> should do and on the technicalities and instruments of an
eventual Europe-wide monetary policy.
Although discussion on the role and functions of the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> is just beginning,
it is already clear that there are wide divergences between authorities such
as the Belgian finance ministry that see it as an instrument to force
integration and the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> which think its role
should be mainly advisory.
It is too early to predict that the problems of stage two will prove so
great as to jeopardise the goal of monetary union. But they are much greater
than when the <ORGANIZATION>Maastricht Treaty</ORGANIZATION> was signed in <DATE>February 1992</DATE> and throw an
unflattering light on the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>'s habit of setting deadlines for policy change
without regard to economic developments.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>ECON  Gross domestic product.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    ECON  Economic Indicators.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-9232</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DHKB7AC4FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930811
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 AUG 93 / French call to keep monetary union timetable
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN RIDDING and REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PARIS, BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> should respect the timetable for achieving monetary
union, <PERSON>Mr Alain Lamassoure</PERSON>, French minister for European affairs, said
yesterday. He played down remarks by Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON> that the target
dates for creating a European currency might need extending.
'Let us keep to the calendar that we have together settled and on which we
are all agreed,' <PERSON>Mr Lamassoure</PERSON> said in a radio interview.
The German chancellor had warned on <DATE>Monday</DATE> that strict insistence on
economic convergence between <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> member states could delay creation of a
single European currency 'by a year or two.' Under the Maastricht treaty on
European union, <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> members are to introduce a single currency in <DATE>1997</DATE> or at
the latest by <DATE>1999</DATE>.
But some French officials indicated a flexible stance on the timing of
monetary union. They said <PERSON>Mr Lamassoure</PERSON>'s comments were mainly concerned
with the second stage of monetary union, which involves establishment of a
<ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>, precursor to a European central bank, and does
not involve strict convergence targets on inflation and budget deficits.
This stage is due to take effect from <DATE>January 1</DATE> next year.
As to the third and more demanding phase of monetary union, French officials
said that, if <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> member countries had difficulty in achieving the economic
convergence criteria, it might be better to extend the timetable than to
relax the required criteria.
One French official said that the question of the timetable for monetary
union would be discussed by the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> heads of government at their special
summit planned for <DATE>October</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mr Lamassoure</PERSON> denied any discord between <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and expressed
optimism about continued progress towards European integration.
Belgian Finance Minister <PERSON>Philipe Maystadt</PERSON> said that creating a single <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>
currency by <DATE>1999</DATE> remained realistic, <ORGANIZATION>Reuter</ORGANIZATION> reports from <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>.
He said Chancellor <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON>'s remarks merely indicated 'in a realistic manner
that the timetable for a single currency is more likely to be <DATE>January 1,
1999</DATE>, than <DATE>January 1, 1997</DATE>,' he said.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>FRZ  France, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-13755</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DDVCCACDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930422
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 APR 93 / Monetary union 'may be delayed'
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By EMMA TUCKER, Economics Staff
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
ECONOMIC SLOWDOWN in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> has cast doubt on the ability of <ORGANIZATION>European
Community</ORGANIZATION> member states to meet the timetable for monetary union contained
in the Maastricht treaty, according to a Commons committee report published
yesterday.
The <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Civil Service</ORGANIZATION> committee's report says it is not confident
that seven of the 12 member states, including <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, will be able to
fulfil the convergence criteria in time for monetary union in <DATE>January 1997</DATE>.
It will not be achieved before <DATE>1999</DATE> if <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> does not meet the criteria
within the next four years, says the committee, but in view of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s
present difficulties this may not happen.
In spite of doubts about the timetable, the report points to a widespread
belief among politicians in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, and probably elsewhere in the
community, that monetary union should, and will, take place in <DATE>1997</DATE>. The
view among most member states is that there should be considerable
flexibility in interpreting the convergence criteria, a view not shared by
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
Failure to ratify the Maastricht treaty by all member states does not mean
that prospects for monetary union would disappear, says the report.
'It is important not to underestimate the strength and depth of commitment
to monetary union amongst politicians elsewhere in the community,' it says,
adding that a number of member states would probably seek to create an
alternative institutional framework to pave the way for monetary union
should the Treaty be rejected.
The committee believes political pressure on the UK from other member
countries to rejoin the European exchange rate mechanism will grow.
Non-membership following UK ratification of the Maastricht treaty would
'cause difficulties' it says.
The report says that only limited progress has been made in practical
preparations for the establishment of the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> and
the <ORGANIZATION>European Central Bank</ORGANIZATION>, 'a fact that may reflect the wider uncertainties
surrounding the prospects for monetary union'.
<ORGANIZATION>Treasury and Civil Service Committee</ORGANIZATION> - Prospects for <ORGANIZATION>Monetary Union</ORGANIZATION>. HMSO.
Pounds 14.40
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-8502</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DESCQABCFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930519
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 MAY 93 / The Danish Referendum: Belgium to press for Maastricht goals
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW HILL
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>BELGIUM</LOCATION>, which takes over the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> presidency in <DATE>July</DATE>, will press ahead with
implementing <ORGANIZATION>Maastricht</ORGANIZATION>'s goals during the second half of the year, even if
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> fails to ratify the treaty. But <PERSON>Mr Willy Claes</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>'s foreign
minister, said <TIME>last night</TIME> the Danish referendum result made him confident
all 12 member states would soon be ready to move towards greater European
union.
Priorities for the six-month Belgian presidency would include preparing the
next phase of economic and monetary union, and a common foreign policy.
The second stage of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> - including establishing a <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary
Institute</ORGANIZATION>, forerunner of the central bank - begins next <DATE>January 1</DATE> and should
end with a single European currency in <DATE>1999</DATE> at the latest.
<PERSON>Mr Claes</PERSON> said <TIME>last night</TIME> that the demanding timetable was essential. But he
added that Maastricht's tough economic criteria for joining a monetary union
might have to be renegotiated if recession continued. <PERSON>Mr Philippe Maystadt</PERSON>,
Belgian finance minister, came out in favour of amending the criteria at the
<DATE>weekend</DATE>.
Earlier in the day, in a speech entitled 'Against Euro-pessimism', <PERSON>Mr Claes</PERSON>
said the original Treaty of <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> and the Single European Act, which laid the
foundation for the barrier-free internal market, were not enough to respond
to the economic and political challenges of the <DATE>1990s</DATE>. 'It's time to take a
further step and the Maastricht treaty gives us the means to do so,' he
said.
Pressed on the possibility that certain member states might not ratify the
treaty, <PERSON>Mr Claes</PERSON> told an invited audience in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> that the Belgian
presidency would still continue the task of deepening the <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION> with 10
or 11 member states, 'because there is no alternative'.
He said <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> intended to 'exploit all the new possibilities offered by
the Maastricht treaty for following a true common foreign and security
policy'. That would include preparing the administrative framework for such
a policy, and asking member states to define the areas in which common
action could be developed.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BEZ  Belgium, EC.
    QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-13750</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DDVCCACIFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930422
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 APR 93 / Monetary union 'may be delayed'
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By EMMA TUCKER, Economics Staff
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
ECONOMIC SLOWDOWN in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> has cast doubt on the ability of <ORGANIZATION>European
Community</ORGANIZATION> member states to meet the timetable for monetary union contained
in the Maastricht treaty, according to a Commons committee report published
yesterday.
The <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Civil Service</ORGANIZATION> committee's report says it is not confident
that seven of the 12 member states, including <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, will be able to
fulfil the convergence criteria in time for monetary union in <DATE>January 1997</DATE>.
It will not be achieved before <DATE>1999</DATE> if <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> does not meet the criteria
within the next four years, says the committee and in view of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s
difficulties this may not happen.
In spite of doubts about the timetable, the report points to a widespread
belief among politicians in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, and probably elsewhere in the
community, that monetary union should, and will, take place in <DATE>1997</DATE>.
Failure to ratify the Maastricht treaty by all member states does not mean
that prospects for monetary union would disappear, it says.
The report says that only limited progress has been made in preparations for
the establishment of the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>European
Central Bank</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Treasury and Civil Service Committee</ORGANIZATION> - Prospects for <ORGANIZATION>Monetary Union</ORGANIZATION>. HMSO.
Pounds 14.40
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-5196</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFHCQAHJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930604
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 JUN 93 / Special EC summit idea takes shape
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID MARSH, European Editor, QUENTIN PEEL and LIONEL BARBER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   LONDON, BONN, BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE IDEA of a special autumn <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> summit to discuss implementing the
Maastricht treaty received the backing yesterday of <PERSON>Mr Hans</PERSON> van den Broek,
European commissioner for external political relations.
Speaking in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, he said such a meeting would provide 'new and credible
impulses for carrying out and bringing forward the integration process'.
The proposal was made on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by six Christian Democrat leaders, headed
by Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>. The idea of calling a special summit to mark the
ratification of the Maastricht treaty fits in with the German chancellor's
desire to revive popular enthusiasm for the <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION> and give it 'a special
push ahead'.
One idea which could be explored is the possibility of bringing <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Finland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> into the <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION> before the end of <DATE>1995</DATE>, as
currently planned.
A second theme would be to offer a better deal to eastern <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> countries
whose full <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> membership is a much more distant prospect.
Yesterday, <PERSON>Mr van den Broek</PERSON> said he was optimistic that the regular
six-monthly <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> summit to be held in <LOCATION>Copenhagen</LOCATION> later this month would
endorse Commission proposals for further liberalisation of trade with
central and eastern <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
The measures are due to be discussed by <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers in <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
As for the suggested special summit, there is some doubt in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> whether it
should try to settle the thorny problem of siting new <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> institutions, in
particular the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>. It would require tough
negotiations, particularly between <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, which wants the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, which would prefer any other site.
Such haggling would be out of keeping with an optimistic, smiling summit,
which is clearly what <PERSON>Mr Kohl</PERSON> wants.
Just when a summit could be called depends not only on the British
parliament, but also on the German constitutional court, which is
considering a series of legal challenges to ratification of the Maastricht
treaty.
The court is expected to hold its oral hearing into the complaints by the
end of <DATE>June</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr Kohl</PERSON> hopes that a final decision will come before the <DATE>summer</DATE>
recess, but other officials are more cautious, suggesting that it may not be
ready until mid-September, or even early <DATE>October</DATE>.
That would still allow the special summit to be held by the end of <DATE>October</DATE>.
The incoming Belgian presidency of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> yesterday declared its
determination to set up the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> on schedule by
<DATE>January 1, 1994</DATE> - the start of the second stage of European monetary union,
<PERSON>Lionel Barber</PERSON> adds from <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>.
In a speech in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr Philippe Maystadt</PERSON>, Belgian finance minister,
called upon <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> member states to make the process toward <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> irreversible.
Failure to do so would encourage currency speculators, he said.
Federalist-minded <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> takes over the presidency from <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-5527</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DLACFAAKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931130
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 NOV 93 / Belgium talks up role of the EMI
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LIONEL BARBER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The Belgian presidency of the <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION> yesterday called for a stronger
role for the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> in the co-ordination of monetary
policies and the management of the exchange rate mechanism.
<PERSON>Mr Philippe Maystadt</PERSON>, Belgian finance minister, said the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> crisis and
introduction of wider fluctuation bands last <DATE>summer</DATE> made closer co-operation
imperative.
Without 'a significant qualitative improvement' in this area, the goal of
monetary union by the end of the decade could be at risk.
In a speech to the <ORGANIZATION>European Finance Convention</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr Maystadt</PERSON> also
admitted that the <DATE>January 1, 1999</DATE>, deadline was more realistic than the
original <DATE>1997</DATE>.
He offered several proposals for filling the political vacuum in the wake of
the <DATE>August</DATE> crisis which led to the introduction of 15 per cent fluctuation
bands for <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> currencies.
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> should be given 'an explicit role' in decisions leading to the entry
or realignment of an <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> currency.
States with low inflation might consider aligning their monetary policies to
a 'common intermediate target', in which case the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> might be allowed to
issue joint statements on national policy decisions taken by central banks
in this low-inflation zone.
The <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> should be strengthened, possibly through a more equitable sharing of
potential exchange rate losses arising from open-ended interventions. This
is a response to <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> criticism that its obligations to defend other
currencies was undermining its domestic monetary policies.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BEZ  Belgium, EC.
    QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>ECON  Economic Indicators.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-15889</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EAMCUAAXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940113
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 JAN 94 / Portugal talks up the role of EMI
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID MARSH and PETER WISE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   LISBON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Mr Anbal Cavaco Silva</PERSON>, the Portuguese prime minister, yesterday said he
hoped the newly-formed European monetary institute would help persuade
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> to cut interest rates more quickly to boost European economic
growth.
His comments are likely to increase German fears that the Frankfurt-based
<ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> could interfere with the statutory independence of the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION>.
In remarks plainly directed above all at <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr Cavaco Silva</PERSON> criticised
'national egoism' in economic policy. He said the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> would require 'a
commitment for everyone to pursue a community monetary policy'.
He added: 'I have some expectations for the work of the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>. Before, it was
quite clear that monetary policy co-ordination was not strong. I hope from
now on it will not just be a question of adapting to the decisions of the
<ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION>. The 12 members of the <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION> - all of them - will have a
say in monetary policy.'
Decision-making power will remain formally in the hands of national central
banks during stage two of the move to economic and monetary union, which
began on <DATE>January 1</DATE>. However, <PERSON>Mr Cavaco Silva</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>, which had its
first meeting on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, would have to play more than just an advisory
role.
'<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> is more than just the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION>,' he said.
His remarks yesterday put <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> firmly on the side of countries such as
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> which want the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> to play a more active
role.
<PERSON>Mr Cavaco Silva</PERSON> also said <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> needed a single currency to accompany the
internal market. However, he admitted it was now unlikely that monetary
union could take place before <DATE>1999</DATE>, compared with the earliest date
prescribed in the Maastricht treaty of <DATE>1997</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>PTZ  Portugal, EC.
    DEZ  Germany, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 3
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-13646</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJUC7AAJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931021
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  21 OCT 93 / Belgian set to head European bank
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW HILL and LIONEL BARBER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
EUROPEAN Community leaders are likely to back <PERSON>Mr Alexandre Lamfalussy</PERSON> next
week as a compromise candidate to head the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>,
forerunner of a European central bank.
<PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> was nominated for the post by <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> central bank governors
yesterday in a move which increases the likelihood of a deal at next week's
<LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> summit on the sensitive question of where to site the European
central bank. <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> is the leading contender.
But his selection, if confirmed, may disappoint enthusiasts for European
monetary union who were looking for a political heavyweight to give added
impetus to the process of economic and monetary integration.
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> will prepare for full European economic and monetary union by <DATE>1999</DATE>,
strengthening the co-ordination of <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> members' monetary policies and
supervising all aspects of the development of a single currency.
<PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON>, a Belgian, is currently general manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Bank for
International Settlements</ORGANIZATION>, which is owned by 33 central banks. He would hold
the office of <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> president for three years initially, beginning on <DATE>January
1, 1994</DATE>, when the next stage of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> is due to start. He would not
necessarily become president of a European central bank.
The governors' recommendation was announced in a letter from <PERSON>Mr Wim
Duisenberg</PERSON>, head of the Dutch central bank and chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> central
bank governors' committee, to <PERSON>Mr Jean-Luc Dehaene</PERSON>, the Belgian prime
minister, who will chair next week's summit.
EC leaders will consider the <PERSON>Lamfalussy</PERSON> nomination along with bids for the
location of the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> and the central bank, as well as lesser institutions.
EC finance ministers and the European parliament will be consulted on the
nomination before the summit, as required by the Maastricht treaty.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BEZ  Belgium, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6011 Federal Reserve Banks.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-15728</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CGABQABHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920701
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 JUL 92 / Europe, the state of the union: Hurdles en route to Emu
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MARTIN WOLF
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
With the <PERSON>Danes</PERSON>' rejection of the Maastricht treaty, the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>'s future has been
thrown into uncertainty. Today <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> takes over as president of the
<ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION>. Can <PERSON>John Major</PERSON> give it new direction? In a special four page
pull-out FT writers assess the prospects
IF THE Maastricht treaty were ratified, which now seems to depend mainly on
French voters, economic and monetary union would appear to be certain. Not
later than <DATE>January 1999</DATE> - just six and <DATE>a half years</DATE> from now - the <LOCATION>Ecu</LOCATION> is to
become the single currency of an economic and monetary union (<ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>) covering
some members of the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION>.
Things are not quite that simple. Even before the Danish 'no' vote,
financial markets did not believe that an <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> embracing all members of the
<ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> would be established; or, if they did, believed that
substantial realignments of some currencies were likely to occur beforehand.
The Danish vote, however, has significantly changed the markets' views of
the odds only in the cases of <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> itself, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.
If <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, which are improbable initial participants, are left
aside, and <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION> is left aside as well, as a virtually certain one, the
financial markets currently divide <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> members into three groups vis a vis
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, the country without whose presence <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> is deemed pointless:
The <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, which has a long-term bond yield differential in relation
to German Bunds of three-tenths of a percentage point and thus an expected
depreciation against the D-Mark of a mere 2 per cent by <DATE>1999</DATE>.
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, where long bond yield
differentials range from three-quarters of a percentage point in the case of
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, to <PERCENT>1.1 percentage points</PERCENT> in that of the UK. These imply overall
depreciations of between 5 and 7 per cent by <DATE>1999</DATE>.
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, where yield differentials are 4.1 percentage points and 5.1
percentage points, respectively. These imply expected depreciations of 23
and 28 per cent.
Once markets digested the Danish 'no', Dutch yield differentials have
declined. Those in the second group have increased rather little, by most in
the case of <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION>, which experienced a jump of about three-tenths of a
percentage point. But <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>'s differential has risen by almost four-tenths
of a point and <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s by almost half a point.
Markets expect a high degree of exchange rate stability within the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION>.
Their view is consistent with an <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> covering, in descending order of
probability: <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>
and the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>. Denmark would be able to join if it wished. But <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>
are deemed outside chances, like <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>.
How do these market expectations compare with the performance of countries
against the convergence criteria agreed at Maastricht? At present, only
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION> meet all the criteria precisely. Meanwhile, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>
seems to be much too far away on the fiscal criteria.
But remember the escape clauses:
The government fiscal deficit can exceed 3 per cent of gross domestic
product, provided at the time of evaluation it has declined substantially
and continuously, reaching a level close to 3 per cent.
The ratio of government debt to GDP can exceed 60 per cent, provided it 'is
sufficiently diminishing' and approaching that level at a satisfactory pace.
If the criteria are not applied too strictly, the eight countries now most
favourably judged by the markets should be able to join. <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> might be able
to join too.
It appears then that the convergence criteria, judged against current and
expected performance, would allow a move to <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>, even in <DATE>1997</DATE>. What could
still go wrong?
The Maastricht treaty could fail to be ratified.
Countries could refuse to do what they are committed to do, with the already
known exception of the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, One reason might be high unemployment, low growth
and a desire for large currency realignments. Another might be the German
desire to retain the D-Mark.
Such recantations, even just realignments, could create a serious crisis.
If, as now seems possible, the recantation would be by <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, the crisis
could be terminal.
Yet even the end of the project for an <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> need not end hopes of greater
monetary integration within <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Moves towards irrevocably fixed exchange
rates without divergence bands would be possible. The financial markets are,
in fact, convinced that a high degree of stability is likely. It is up to
the governments to prove them right.
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
<ORGANIZATION>Timetable for Monetary Union</ORGANIZATION>
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
<DATE>JANUARY 1 1994</DATE>. Beginning of the second stage of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>.
  All controls on exchange and payments are to have been eliminated.
  'At the start of the second stage a <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> shall
be established.'
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
<DATE>DECEMBER 31 1996</DATE>. Last date for the first evaluation of entry into the
third stage.
The Council shall decide:
  whether 'a majority of the Member States fulfil the necessary
conditions for adoption of a single currency'; and
  'whether it is appropriate for the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> to enter the third stage;'
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
<DATE>JANUARY 1 1999</DATE>. Last date for the start of the third stage:
  Before <DATE>July 1 1998</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Council</ORGANIZATION> shall 'confirm which member states
fulfil the necessary conditions for the adoption of a single currency.'
  Either after the date for the beginning of the third stage has been
set, or after <DATE>July 1 1998</DATE>, the European System of Central Banks and the
<ORGANIZATION>European Central Bank</ORGANIZATION> shall be established. 'The full exercise of their
powers shall start from the first day of the third stage.'
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-16009</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJHCKAD1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931008
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 OCT 93 / A caravan lost in the sands: Hard thinking on prospects for
European monetary union has begun
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LIONEL BARBER and DAVID MARSH
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
In a secluded hotel outside <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> finance ministers
gather today for a strategy meeting that could also represent a session of
revelatory group therapy. For the first time since the <DATE>summer</DATE> monetary
crisis which led to the virtual collapse of the European exchange rate
mechanism, the ministers will discuss what went wrong, and what happens
next.
Although French and Belgian politicians have made intermittent statements
blaming 'Anglo-Saxon speculators' for the currency unrest, the public debate
on the lessons of the July-August debacle has barely begun.
But in private, there has been plenty of hard thinking about the future of
European monetary co-operation and the goal of economic and monetary union.
The question is whether the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> has the political will to chart a new course
to restore confidence in the project for economic and monetary union - or
whether European currencies will continue to drift apart.
The emergency agreement on <DATE>August 2</DATE> on wider <MONEY>15 per cent</MONEY> fluctuation bands
in the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> brought the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> a breathing space after the successive currency
upsets since <DATE>autumn 1992</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mr Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, the German chancellor, has forecast a slippage of 'a year or
two' in the Maastricht timetable. The <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> government and the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION>,
however, maintain that the band widening leaves the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> fundamentally on
track for the Maastricht aim of achieving <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> by <DATE>1997</DATE> at the earliest and
<DATE>1999</DATE> at the latest. In spite of discomfort in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> over the weakening of
the French franc's link with the D-Mark, this view is backed by the French
government.
<PERSON>Mr John Major</PERSON>, the UK prime minister, has struck a jarring note by saying
the <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> plan has 'all the quaintness of a rain dance and about the same
potency' - a statement which has caused irritation in the <ORGANIZATION>EC Commission</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>.
In some German business and financial circles, there is agreement with <PERSON>Mr
Major</PERSON>'s view that the Maastricht timetable is unrealistic - but this is a
long way from the official line in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>.
One point seems to be undisputed: there will be no return to the old <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION>, in
which most currencies fluctuated around a 2 1/4 per cent band, until the
recession on the Continent has clearly come to an end. Earlier hopes of a
progressive narrowing of the 15 per cent fluctuation bands by the end of the
year have been quietly dropped.
Yet the common European interest in monetary stability should not be
under-estimated. Most member states want to avoid competitive currency
devaluations - shown by the way that <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> members have not used their
new-found flexibility during the last two months to lower their currencies
significantly against the D-Mark.
Far less common ground exists on what might replace the old narrow-band <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION>
which was supposed to represent the route to <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Jacques Delors</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>EC Commission</ORGANIZATION> president, has toyed with the idea of
curbing currency speculation by placing exchange controls on speculative
borrowing. His sentiments are fairly widely shared on the continent, but his
suggestion has drawn criticism from the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, and even the French government
regards it as a non-runner.
Sir <PERSON>Leon Brittan</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>EC Commissioner</ORGANIZATION> for external affairs, has meanwhile urged
states to stick to the Maastricht objectives but to make use of their
greater exchange rate flexibility. He has called on countries such as <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> to take advantage of the looser <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> arrangements to cut interest
rates and promote economic recovery.
In <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> is pinning its hopes on the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary
Institute</ORGANIZATION>. It is to be set on <DATE>January 1, 1994</DATE> - at the beginning of
so-called 'stage two' of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> - as the forerunner of a future <ORGANIZATION>European
Central Bank</ORGANIZATION>.
One idea circulating in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> is that individual central banks should
pool resources so the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> can intervene to defend embattled currencies. This
idea is, however, rejected by the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION>, which wants to retain complete
autonomy before the planned establishment of a fully-fledged <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> central
bank.
A broader goal of most <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> governments is to use the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> to help persuade the
<ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> take other countries' economies into account when taking interest
rate decisions. <PERSON>Mr Felipe Gonzalez</PERSON>, the Spanish prime minister, said this
week he hopes the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> will ease the 'frustrations' of having to wait 'week
by week' for the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> to lower interest rates.
So far, member states have failed to agree on the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>'s location or its
president. EC leaders will try to break the deadlock at a special summit on
<DATE>October 29</DATE>, when the <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION> is expected to place the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
However sensitive the question of where to site the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>, the real issue is
the drive by other <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> members to draw the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> into a more formal
system of monetary co-operation.
Much will depend on the state of the Franco-German alliance, which was badly
bruised during the <DATE>summer</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr Horst Teltschik</PERSON>, former foreign policy adviser
to Chancellor <PERSON>Kohl</PERSON>, and now a board member with the Munich-based <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> motor
group, describes French requests for unlimited support for the franc during
the monetary upset as irritating: 'They sometimes confuse our interests with
theirs,' he says.
One senior member of the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> council singles out for criticism <PERSON>Mr
Edmond Alphandery</PERSON>, the French economics minister, over his much-publicised
call in <DATE>June</DATE> for the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> to lower interest rates: 'He is a beginner,
and he made a beginner's mistakes.'
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> wanted to take advantage of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s perceived economic weakness
caused by reunification to push for greater monetary co-ordination. The
signs are that <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> has not abandoned this strategy.
In <DATE>August</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr Edouard Balladur</PERSON>, the French prime minister, persuaded <PERSON>Mr Kohl</PERSON>
to agree to a 'convergence' programme which <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> officials
believe could pave the way for more institutionalised co-operation.
The immediate outlook, however, for progress along the path towards <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>
appears gloomy. Three obstacles are apparent.
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s own post-unity problems. Large fiscal transfers from west to east
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> - currently more than DM150bn a year - will be needed for at least
another decade to maintain east German living standards. During this period
of strain for the 'anchor' economy in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> is unlikely to be
politically or economically ready to subsume its D-Mark into a single
European currency.
The diminishing chances that member states can meet the Maastricht
convergence targets, set down as conditions for <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>. This year, general
government deficits across the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> will average about 6 per cent of GDP -
double the 3 per cent target set at Maastricht.
The increasing temptation for European countries to see exchange rate
flexibility as a means of solving economic problems. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>
have shown that devaluation can be the clue to lowering interest rates and
restoring modest economic growth.
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s position is crucial. It remains torn between its desire to maintain
a tight link with the D-Mark and its need to engineer an economic recovery.
The <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> government's cautious monetary policy since <DATE>August</DATE> has allowed
French long-term interest rates to fall again to German levels. <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> is
hoping for a faster lowering of German interest rates next year, and a
corresponding weakening of the D-Mark. But this is a gamble for the Balladur
government as <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> heads towards the <DATE>1995</DATE> presidential elections.
The French strategy underlines how the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> remains the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>'s supreme
monetary arbiter. Mr <PERSON>Hans Tietmeyer</PERSON>, its new president, last week signalled
that the central bank's policies would remain geared to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s economic
priorities, not the rest of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
Thus for all the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION>'s new-found flexibility, the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION>'s
anti-inflation stubbornness could still cause difficulties. Some <ORGANIZATION>EC
Commission</ORGANIZATION> officials worry that members of the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> 'hard-core' such as
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> will be unable to maintain their recent currency
stability unless they soon act to restore economic growth through more
aggressive cuts in interest rates. If these cuts do not materialise, these
<LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> officials believe, another currency upheaval could be in store - an
event which would postpone <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> until the next century.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-11486</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJ4AOAAJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931030
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 OCT 93 / EC leaders use summit for display of unity
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LIONEL BARBER and DAVID GARDNER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
EC LEADERS yesterday restored a semblance of unity to the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION>
with a decision to base the future <ORGANIZATION>European Central Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> as
part of a wide-ranging agreement on the location of <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> institutions.
But the deal struck at a special European summit in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> followed an
acrimonious battle over the division of 'Euro-spoils', including veto
threats by the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> unless they got the European Agency for the
<ORGANIZATION>Evaluation of Medicinal Products</ORGANIZATION>.
After several hours of haggling, the prize went to the UK which immediately
praised the deal as creating several hundred jobs and confirming <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> as
a world leader in the pharmaceutical industry. <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> was given two sites as
a consolation prize - the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> trade-mark office and a new institution
responsible for monitoring health and safety.
The summit, chaired by the Belgian presidency of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>, was called to
revive <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s faltering progress toward greater political and monetary
integration after the near failure to ratify the Maastricht treaty.
The choice of <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> as the location for the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>
 -the forerunner of the <ORGANIZATION>European Central Bank</ORGANIZATION> - was seen as a minimum step
towards rebuilding credibility in <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Union</ORGANIZATION> after the <DATE>August 2</DATE>
currency crisis.
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, which stands to surrender the D-Mark under the Maastricht treaty at
the end of the century, fought tenaciously for the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>.
Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>'s argument that the choice of <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> was necessary
to reassure Germans about the loss of their symbol of post-war stability
carried the day over reservations from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> said <TIME>last night</TIME> the decision was 'a pity, not for the
City but for the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>'.
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>, whose president will be <PERSON>Mr Alexandre Lamfalussy</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, is the
institutional anchor for the second stage of <ORGANIZATION>EMU</ORGANIZATION> due to begin on <DATE>January 1,
1994</DATE> under the Maastricht treaty.
With the treaty set to enter force on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> leaders used the one-day
summit to pledge closer co-operation in foreign policy and the fight against
organised crime, as well as a broad endorsement of the goal of a European
monetary union by the end of the decade.
They steered clear of any new initiatives to tackle mass unemployment in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, preferring to wait for the <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION>'s White Paper on
competitiveness, employment and growth which will be presented at the next
summit in <DATE>December</DATE>.
They also avoided a damaging row over the <LOCATION>Uruguay Round</LOCATION> world trade talks in
which <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> is holding out for more concessions on farm trade. But the
final communique warned of the of the community 'turning in on itself.'
Despite relief that the log-jam over the location of more than 10 new
institutions had been broken, there was also an air of contrition among <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>
leaders and a general admission that mistakes had been made before and after
the Maastricht agreement.
EC summit, Page 3
Man in the News, Page 6
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>DEZ  Germany, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6011 Federal Reserve Banks.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 1
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-9798</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKIC6ADLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931109
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  09 NOV 93 / Euro-bank chief vowsto attack policies which threaten Emu
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW HILL
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
MR <PERSON>ALEXANDRE Lamfalussy</PERSON>, president-elect of the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>,
has promised to be a strong critic of 'unbalanced' economic policies which
threaten the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION>'s objective of monetary union.
In the first public indication of how he sees his role - contained in
written answers to members of the <ORGANIZATION>European Parliament</ORGANIZATION> - <PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> also
cast doubt on a return to the old European exchange rate mechanism, saying
he was not sure it was 'a realistic objective'.
<PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> is due to appear tomorrow before the parliament's committee on
opinion on his candidacy before he can be formally confirmed as president of
the Frankfurt-based forerunner of a European central bank. He is currently
written replies to the committee's questions were obtained yesterday by the
<ORGANIZATION>Financial Times</ORGANIZATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> will supervise the second stage of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>, beginning on <DATE>January 1 1994</DATE>,
and advise <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> members on monetary and exchange rate policy leading up to
full currency union by <DATE>1999</DATE>.
In his reply to the parliament's questionnaire, <PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>
would be more than just a passive observer of <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> economic and monetary
policy.
In particular, he said he would be prepared to highlight any imbalances
between monetary and fiscal and other economic policies which could
jeopardise the <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> aims. 'I shall make it my duty to draw attention to the
risks arising from an unbalanced policy mix,' he said.
He indicated he would be ready to act decisively if monetary and economic
policies appeared to be contradictory, and make full use of the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>'s power
to encourage dialogue between central banks and governments.
'At a certain point . . . if and when divergencies persist, public opinion
should be made aware of potential conflicts and of their possible
consequences,' he said.
Referring to <DATE>August</DATE>'s decision to allow <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION> currencies to fluctuate more
widely, <PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> said the currency crises of the past 18 months had
removed the 'disciplinary framework' which had helped promote convergence of
monetary policies.
He said co-ordinating monetary policies effectively in such a situation
would be one of the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>'s main challenges.
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> 'should spare no effort' to prevent exchange rate fluctuations
undermining the single market, he said. But he added: 'I am sure that it
would not be advisable to set any precise timetable for re-establishing a
more constraining exchange rate mechanism.' Member states should wait until
the business cycle had improved and renewed progress could be made towards
'broadly based convergence'.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>DEZ  Germany, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
    P6011 Federal Reserve Banks.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-8504</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DESCQABAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930519
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 MAY 93 / The Danish Referendum: Now real debate on European union
begins - Vote is unlikely to end crisis of legitimacy surrounding the treaty
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LIONEL BARBER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>DENMARK</LOCATION>'S decisive Yes to Maastricht will cause the political establishments
across <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> to breathe a sigh of relief. In the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, the result should tip
the scales decisively in favour of <PERSON>Mr John Major</PERSON> as he pushes the Maastricht
bill through its final stages in the UK parliament. Barring an upset in the
British or German courts, ratification seems secure.
Yet the Danish Yes is unlikely to end the crisis of legitimacy surrounding
the treaty. When <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> leaders agreed Maastricht in <DATE>December 1991</DATE>, they hailed
it as point of departure for European political and monetary union; but even
the latest Commission polls show public support for European integration is
tumbling.
The Danish endorsement does not amount to a true test of public support for
European union. The version of Maastricht which <ORGANIZATION>Danes</ORGANIZATION> approved yesterday
contains legally binding opt-outs on core elements of the treaty, including
the single European currency, European citizenship and defence policy.
A senior <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION> official declares the treaty will have no
obvious impact on the fundamental problems facing the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> such as rising
unemployment, low investment, public spending crises in almost all the
member states and monetary instability.
The Danish Yes should free the <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> and member-states to focus on the
<ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION>'s pressing challenges: enlargement negotiations with <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Finland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>; the political and economic integration of the
former Communist countries of eastern <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>; and the issue of European
competitiveness in relation to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, itself the subject of an
in-depth study ordered by <PERSON>Mr Jacques Delors</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> president.
A senior <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> official listed several 'tests' for the <ORGANIZATION>Community</ORGANIZATION> in the coming
months: making the single market work, including the removal of lingering
restrictions on the free movement of <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> citizens; concluding the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>
Round in the <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> trade talks; and ensuring stability inside the European
exchange rate mechanism so as to maintain the credibility of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> to
monetary union by <DATE>1999</DATE> at the latest.
Paradoxically, the Danish Yes may reignite the debate on European union. The
run-up to European parliament elections next year is an obvious launch-pad;
so, too, the sense among the European federalists that they no longer need
worry about frightening the minimalist <PERSON>Danes</PERSON> or the British as they edge
toward ratification. <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, which takes over the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> presidency from
<LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 1</DATE>, is in the lead.
<PERSON>Mr Alain Juppe</PERSON>, French foreign minister, is coming from a different
direction. In a speech to the French parliament yesterday, he spoke of a new
division of labour within the Community so that countries such as <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> could take the lead on security matters. He also hinted
that the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> needed to make institutional changes to cope with 16 or more
members. The first clues on <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> thinking will probably come next
month when it offers an opinion on <LOCATION>Malta</LOCATION>'s request for membership.
Last <DATE>weekend</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr Philippe Maystadt</PERSON>, Belgian foreign minister, came out in
favour of watering down the strict Maastricht 'convergence' criteria for
monetary union - a move which would allow an inner core of <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> member states
to move forward to fixed exchange rates, but which would alarm the
<ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION>, which has insisted that Maastricht must be respected to the
letter.
All this may simply be letting off steam; but it may also suggest that the
debate on the future course of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> may be about to begin. For if
Euro-sceptics and Euro-enthusiasts agree on anything, it is that Maastricht
settled nothing.
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
LANDMARKS IN EUROPEAN CO-OPERATION
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
<DATE>1957</DATE>        Treaty of <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> establishes <ORGANIZATION>European Economic Community</ORGANIZATION>;
            <LOCATION>Belguim</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West
            Germany</LOCATION>
1962        <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION> proposes European monetary union without
            success
<DATE>1970</DATE>        Heads of government adopt 'Werner plan' for European
            monetary union but have to abandon it
<DATE>1972</DATE>        'Snake' exchange rate mechanism set up as <PERSON>Bretton Woods</PERSON>
            system begins to break up
1973        <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION> join Community
<DATE>1979</DATE>        European Monetary System (EMS) starts operation, but goal of
            European monetary fund unfulfilled
<DATE>1981</DATE>        Greece joins Community
<DATE>1986</DATE>        Single European Act signed. Single market to come into force
            in <DATE>January 1993</DATE>. <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> join Community
<DATE>1990</DATE>        Rome summit: start of intergovernmental talks on European
            monetary and political union. German unification
<DATE>1991</DATE>        Maastricht treaty agreed by member states, sets out
            timetable for economic and monetary union
<DATE>1992</DATE>        Maastricht treaty rejected in Danish referendum by 51 per
            cent to 49 per cent, but approved in <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>
            Exchange Rate Mechanism turmoil: <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION>
            suspended membership, raising doubts of ERM/EMS future
Yesterday   <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> vote on Maastricht treaty, with opt-out
            clauses as agreed as last year's <LOCATION>Edinburgh</LOCATION> summitt
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
WHAT'S AT STAKE IN THE MAASTRICHT TREATY
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
Political Union
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 -Inter-governmental foreign and security policy 'which might in time
  lead to a common defence'
 -European citizenship
 -More extensive social policies (not applied to UK)
 -Central role for principle of subsidarity (decision-making close to
  the people)
 -Inter-governmental framework for justice and home affairs
 -Modest increase in powers for European parliament
 -Upgrading of court of auditors
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
Economic and monetary union
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 -Commitment to economic and monetary union by <DATE>1999</DATE> for countries which
  fulfil economic criteria
 -Increased pressure for countries to keep exchange rates stable in the
  European Monetary System
 -Cohesion fund to help poorer countries
 -European monetary institute to be set up in <DATE>1994</DATE> as forerunner to
  European central bank
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
    DKZ  Denmark, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-8586</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EKTAWAAMFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941119
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 NOV 94 / Tietmeyer warning on Emu
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW FISHER and JOHN RIDDING
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   FRANKFURT, PARIS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Mr Hans Tietmeyer</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION>, warned strongly yesterday
against rushing towards European monetary union before a joint monetary
policy had been worked out and full central banking independence achieved.
He was speaking the day after <PERSON>Mr Giovanni Ravasio</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION>'s
director-general for economic and monetary affairs, had held out the
possibility of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> as early as <DATE>1997</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr Tietmeyer</PERSON> said: 'I am convinced that
monetary policy integration in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> can only be the outcome of a lengthy
process.'
The struggle to devise the best monetary policy strategy and the right
instruments to implement this 'could prove to be even more difficult and
time-consuming than the preparations for issuing banknotes and coins,' he
warned in a speech to a <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> banking congress.
He said satisfactory monetary results could not be obtained without proper
independence for the future European central bank - it was indispensable to
have 'not only theoretical but also a far-reaching degree of actual
independence'.
The Maastricht treaty does not call for central banking independence until
stage three of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>. However, <PERSON>Mr Tietmeyer</PERSON> said it was 'crucial to enhance
the independence of national central banks at an early stage.'
The <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> and the central banks of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> are independent,
while the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> is subject to government control. Others are under
varying degrees of government influence.
The European central bank's independence could not be achieved at short
notice, he said.
On monetary policy, he criticised suggestions that an all-European, or
transnational, monetary target should be set now, in stage two of <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>. The
technical and institutional pre-conditions did not yet exist for an early
switch to a common monetary policy. Opinions on future policy also differed
widely.
<PERSON>Mr Tietmeyer</PERSON> was speaking in the week of the first council meeting of the
<ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> (EMI) at its new <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> headquarters. One of
its tasks is to recommend by the end of <DATE>1996</DATE> what type of inflation or money
supply targets should be pursued by the future central bank to achieve price
stability.
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>'s goal is to produce a 'turnkey' European central bank that could
begin operating as soon as <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> receives the political go-ahead.
<PERSON>Mr Kenneth Clarke</PERSON>, the UK chancellor of the exchequer, yesterday supported
the objective of European economic and monetary union, but said the
timetable laid down by the Maastricht treaty for a single currency was
invalid, while <PERSON>Mr John Major</PERSON>, the UK prime minister, claimed the question of
a single currency did not arise at the moment.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>DEZ  Germany, EC.
    FRZ  France, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-4783</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EIGDVAD2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940907
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  07 SEP 94 / EU monetary head sees hope on single currency
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LIONEL BARBER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> member states have turned a corner and could realistically consider the
prospect of a single European currency, <PERSON>Mr Alexandre Lamfalussy</PERSON>, president
of the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>, forerunner of the <ORGANIZATION>European Central Bank</ORGANIZATION>,
declared yesterday.
Falling interest rates, low inflation and close monetary co-ordination among
<ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> central banks had substantially reduced currency instability, <PERSON>Mr
Lamfalussy</PERSON> said. In one or two years, there could be some 'pleasant
surprises' among countries aspiring to join the planned economic and
monetary union.
<PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON>'s upbeat remarks to the European economic and social committee
in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> came ahead of weekend talks among <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> finance ministers in
<LOCATION>Lindau</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Lake Constance</LOCATION>. They will discuss the procedures for dealing
with big national budget deficits, one of the most important tests for <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>
membership.
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, which holds the rotating <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> presidency, has signalled it is unhappy
with the <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION> recommendation to exclude <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> from the
'excessive deficits' rules. <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION>, the only country which meets
<ORGANIZATION>Maastricht</ORGANIZATION>'s deficit criteria, is also excluded.
The <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> supports a generous interpretation of the debt rules because
<LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> has in recent years held its annual budget deficit within the
Maastricht target of 3 per cent of gross domestic product. But <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> does
not want to create a precedent that will make it easier for countries with
bigger debt problems, such as <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, to become full <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> members.
The <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>'s secretive monetary committee, meeting in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> yesterday, was
said to have approved <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> proposals for deficit reduction procedures
by <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> states other than <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> steered clear of the controversy over proposals to create a
'hard core' of five nations committed to faster integration in the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>.
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s ruling Christian Democrat party and its <ORGANIZATION>CSU</ORGANIZATION> coalition partner
proposed last week that the hard core should consist of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> stressed it was too soon to predict which <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> members would be
ready to form a monetary union by <DATE>1997</DATE> or <DATE>1999</DATE>, the two dates named in the
Maastricht treaty.
Without mentioning <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> or the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> president paid tribute to
countries which seemed to have escaped 'the infernal cycle of inflation',
even while allowing their currencies to depreciate during the monetary
upheaval of 1992-93.
Tietmeyer warns on <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> integration, Page 2
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BEZ  Belgium, EC.
    QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-3046</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DIPCOAALFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930916
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 SEP 93 / Plan to create 'dual anchor' for ERM: European Monetary
Institute to be urged to move more quickly
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID GARDNER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   STRASBOURG
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
MR <PERSON>Phillipe Maystadt</PERSON>, finance minister of <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> which presides over the
<ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>, yesterday hinted at a plan to create a 'dual anchor' for the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION>, with
the D-Mark locked to a new form of 'hard' Ecu, or European currency unit.
The plan is due to be unveiled next month by the <ORGANIZATION>European Parliament</ORGANIZATION>'s
monetary affairs committee.
Its essence is that the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION> (EMI), due to be set up
by <DATE>January</DATE> in <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION>'s second stage, should assume more quickly the functions
of the European central bank it is meant to prefigure, by issuing and
managing the Ecu as a joint anchor to the system alongside the D-Mark.
The Ecu would be fixed against the D-Mark, with other <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> currencies having
their weighting in the Ecu 'basket' adjusted according to whether they
appreciated or devalued, but with much tighter monetary co-ordination, and
more joint intervention capability.
<PERSON>Mr Joao Cravinho</PERSON>, the Portuguese socialist and economist who has devised the
plan, has already discussed it with <PERSON>Mr Jacques Delors</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION>
president, the Belgian presidency, the <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION>, and the Spanish prime
minister, <PERSON>Mr Felipe Gonzalez</PERSON>. <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> is the country most worried that if hard
currency member states try to establish a mini-Emu to salvage something from
the wreckage, both the <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> project and the single market will come apart.
The plan will include proposals that:
Member states turn over 20 per cent of their gold and foreign exchange
reserves to the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> to manage;
The member states issue all new debt in <LOCATION>Ecus</LOCATION>;
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Bundesbank</ORGANIZATION> assume joint responsibility for holding the
Ecu/D-Mark parity;
The Twelve set a joint 'interest rate indicator';
The Twelve evolve a joint incomes policy linking wage rises to productivity.
'If you're going to keep <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> on track the problem of the anchor (to the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION>)
has to be tackled,' <PERSON>Mr Cravinho</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>DEZ  Germany, EC.
    QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-4790</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EIGDVADVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940907
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  07 SEP 94 / Eurocurrency 'a realistic option': Lamfalussy offers
optimistic assessment of EU economies
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LIONEL BARBER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Mr Alexandre Lamfalussy</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>,
declared yesterday that <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> member states had turned a corner and could
realistically consider the prospect of a single European currency.
Falling interest rates, low inflation, and close monetary co-ordination
among <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> central banks had substantially reduced currency instability, <PERSON>Mr
Lamfalussy</PERSON> said. In one or two years, there could be some 'pleasant
surprises' among countries aspiring to join the planned economic and
monetary union.
<PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON>'s upbeat remarks to the European economic and social committee
in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> came ahead of weekend talks among <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> finance ministers. Their
meeting in <LOCATION>Lindau</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Lake Constance</LOCATION>, will discuss politically sensitive
procedures for dealing with big national budget deficits, one of the most
important tests for <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> membership.
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, which holds the rotating <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> presidency, has signalled it is unhappy
with the <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION> recommendation to exclude <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> from the
'excessive deficits' rules. <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION>, the only country which meets
<ORGANIZATION>Maastricht</ORGANIZATION>'s deficit criteria, is also excluded.
The <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> supports a generous interpretation of the debt rules because
<LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> has in recent years held its annual budget deficit within the
Maastricht target of 3 per cent of gross domestic product. But <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> does
not want to create a precedent that will make it easier for countries with
bigger debt problems, such as <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, to become full <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> members.
The <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>'s secretive monetary committee, meeting in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> yesterday, was
said to have approved <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> proposals for deficit reduction procedures
by <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> states other than <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> steered clear of the controversy over proposals to create a
'hard core' of five nations committed to faster integration in the <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>. The
ruling Christian Democrat party and its <ORGANIZATION>CSU</ORGANIZATION> coalition partner proposed last
week that the hard core should consist of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, the
<LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and the Benelux are often viewed as the most likely nucleus
of the planned monetary union. But <PERSON>Mr Lamfalussy</PERSON> stressed it was too soon to
predict which <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> members would be ready to form a union by <DATE>1997</DATE> or <DATE>1999</DATE>, the
two dates named in the treaty.
Without mentioning <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> or the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> president paid tribute to
countries which seemed to have escaped 'the infernal cycle of inflation',
even while allowing their currencies to depreciate during the monetary
upheaval of 1992-93.
This turbulence, which led to the widening of fluctuation bands in the
<ORGANIZATION>European Monetary System</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August 1992</DATE>, appeared to be over, said <PERSON>Mr
Lamfalussy</PERSON>. However, he insisted that the wider <ORGANIZATION>EMS</ORGANIZATION> bands should be
preserved in order to defend currencies against speculative pressures.
Tietmeyer warns on <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> integration, Page 2
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BEZ  Belgium, EC.
    QRZ  European Economic Community (EC).
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-11684</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJ4AOAABFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931030
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 OCT 93 / EC revives spirit of unity: Site chosen for central bank as
summit settles wrangle over institutions
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LIONEL BARBER and DAVID GARDNER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
EC LEADERS yesterday restored a semblance of unity to the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION>
with a decision to base the future <ORGANIZATION>European Central Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Frankurt</LOCATION> as part
of a wide-ranging agreement on the location of <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> institutions.
But the deal struck at a special European summit in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> followed an
acriminious battle over the division of Euro-spoils which included veto
threats by the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
The summit chaired by the Belgian presidency of the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> was called to revive
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s faltering progress toward greater political and monetary
integration after the near failure to ratify the Maastricht treaty.
The choice of <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> as the location for the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>
 -the forerunner of the <ORGANIZATION>European Central Bank</ORGANIZATION> - was seen as a minimum step
towards rebuilding credibility in <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary Union</ORGANIZATION> after the <DATE>August 2</DATE>
currency crisis which led to the suspension of the <ORGANIZATION>ERM</ORGANIZATION>.
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, which stands to surrender the D-Mark under the Maastricht treaty at
the end of the century, fought tenaciously for the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>. Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut
Kohl</PERSON>'s argument that the choice of <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> was necessary to reassure
Germans about the loss of their symbol of post-war stability carried the day
over reservations from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> said <TIME>last night</TIME> the decision was 'a pity, not for the
<LOCATION>City</LOCATION> but for the <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>.'
The <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION>, whose president will be <PERSON>Mr Alexandre Lamfalussy</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, is the
institutional anchor for the second stage of <ORGANIZATION>EMU</ORGANIZATION> due to begin on <DATE>January 1,
1994</DATE> under the Maastricht treaty.
With the treaty set to enter force on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> leaders used the one-day
summit to pledge closer co-operation in foreign policy and the fight against
organised crime, as well as a broad endorsement of the goal of a European
monetary union by the end of the decade.
EC leaders steered clear of any new initiatives to tackle mass unemployment
in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, preferring to wait for the <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION>'s White Paper on
competitiveness, employment and growth which will presented at the next
summit in <DATE>December</DATE>.
They also avoided a damaging row over the <LOCATION>Uruguay Round</LOCATION> world trade talks in
which <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> is holding out for more concessions on farm trade.
Despite relief that the log-jam over the location of more than 10 new
institutions had been broken, there was also an air of contrition among <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>
leaders and a general admission that mistakes had been made before and after
the agreement on the Maastricht.
