<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47304 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust012___94058" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-012 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   8 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Simulation of High-Energy Physical Processes With Aid of </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Simulation of High-Energy Physical Processes With Aid of </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Multitarget   Laser Sets 

<FÊP=102> 947J0029C St.Peterburg OPTICHESKIY ZHURNAL in Russian No. 1, 
Jan 94 (manuscript received 17 Sep 93) pp 84-94 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947J0029C </F>
<FÊP=104>  St.Peterburg OPTICHESKIY <ORGANIZATION>ZHURNAL </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by Yu.A. Rezunkov, candidate of technical sciences, </F>
department head, <PERSON>V.S. Sirazetdinov</PERSON>, candidate of technical 
sciences, manager of test stand for adaptive laser systems, <PERSON>A.V. 
Charukhchev</PERSON>, candidate of technical sciences, chief of power 
lasers laboratory, <PERSON>D.L. Starikov</PERSON>, doctor of physical and 
mathematical sciences, director, <ORGANIZATION>Scientific Research Institute 
of Comprehensive Optoelectronic Devices and Systems Testing</ORGANIZATION>, 
<ORGANIZATION>All-Russian Science Center at State Institute of Optics</ORGANIZATION> imeni 
<LOCATION>S.I. Vavilov</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 621.373.826.038] 
  [Abstract] Power lasers with widely variable 
characteristics have been built to serve as high-energy 
hyperdirectional radiation sources, as sources of luminous 
energy to be transmitted over long distances with minimum loss 
and to be received with subdiffractional precision. One of the 
largest research stands built at the <ORGANIZATION>Institute of Optics</ORGANIZATION> during 
the past 15 years is the 6-channel ``Progress,'' intended for 
the study of intense radiation and spherical target interaction 
relating to laser-induced thermonuclear fusion. It includes a 
Nd-glass master laser emitting pulses of up to 1.5 kJ energy and 
about 1 ns duration or a power of 3.5 <ORGANIZATION>TW</ORGANIZATION> in pulses of 0.1 ns 
duration. It also includes a chirp-pulse generator with a 
regenerative amplifier and a shaping-pulse generator, both 
feeding a common preamplifier with two inputs and three outputs. 
Pulses from one output pass through a compressor to the target 
inside a spherical chamber. Pulses from the other two outputs 
pass through a separator to a module which contains: a series of 
bar and disk amplifiers with successively larger (30 mm to 110 
mm) apertures with vacuum-type spatial filters separating the 
amplifiers and preventing self-action, electrooptical 
deflectors, electrooptical (Pockels) shutters and magnetooptical 
(<LOCATION>Faraday</LOCATION>) shutters decoupling the laser from targets, and 
harmonic filters. From here pulses proceed along six channels to 
six targets. Some pulses are deflected through an amplifier with 
a 140 mm aperture to two detectors with 150 mm and 250 mm 
apertures respectively. Some pulses are diverted to another 
compressor. This stand was used in experiments with pulse 
compression during stimulated Mandelshtam-Brillouin scattering. 
For generating and amplifying ultrashort chirp pulses of only 1 
mJ energy and 0.2-1.0 ns within a 2-4 nm spectral, a very 
inefficient Nd-glass laser is replaced with a mode-locked 
YAG:Nd[.sup]+3[/] laser emitting continuous sequences of 
pulses of 50 ps duration at a repetition rate of 100 MHz within 
a 0.2 nm wide spectral band. Chirp pulses of 0.15-0.6 ns 
duration are formed in single-mode fiber optics, where phase 
modulation and group velocity dispersion broaden the spectrum 
and elongate a pulse. Additional elongation of a pulse takes 
place in a lattice-type stretcher. Extraction of a pulse is 
effected by the electrooptical shutters, which are controlled by 
photoelectric switches. The regenerative amplifier then puts out 
a pulse of about 1 mJ energy, sufficient for transmission to the 
main amplifier channel with a 110 mm exit aperture. A second 
large research stand is the ``LAS'', which includes an Nd-glass 
laser with phase conjugation and a 110 mm output aperture. It 
emits pulses of up to 500 J and 25 ns duration in a beam with a 
divergence angle of 5 ?rad so that the axial radiation 
intensity reaches 80 aW/cm[.sup]2[/]. A third large research 
stand is the ``Chibis'', which includes a CO[.sub]2[/]-laser 
operation in the pulse-repetition mode. Experiments with this 
apparatus have demonstrated the feasibility of a 
focusing-deflecting system which uses large compound mirrors and 
of compensating its aberrations by means of phase conjugation. 
Figures 6; references 30. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-23057 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust009___94021" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-009 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   18 April 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Problem of Radiation Pulsations in Solid State Lasers </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Problem of Radiation Pulsations in Solid State Lasers </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   947J0018 St. Petersburg ZHURNAL TEKHNICHESKOY FIZIKI in 
Russian Vol. 63 No. 8, Aug 93 (manuscript received 23 Jun 92) pp </F>



<TEXT>
89-98 
<FÊP=103> 947J0018 </F>
<FÊP=104>  <ORGANIZATION>St. Petersburg ZHURNAL TEKHNICHESKOY FIZIKI </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>V. V. Antsiferov</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Vekua Physicotechnical </F>
Institute</ORGANIZATION>] 
  [Abstract] Experimental results are presented from studies 
of spectral and temporal characteristics of chromium and 
neodymium ion laser radiation in various media. The author 
obtained the results in a number of experiments using one 
experimental setup and identical conditions. This was done to 
eliminate the effect of technical perturbations of the 
resonator. The qualitative difference in the behavior of the 
free generation of chromium and neodymium ions suggests a 
physical mechanism which causes nonattenuating radiation 
pulsations in lasers using ions with an external working shell 
linked with the spallation of the working levels of the ions in 
their own radiation field. It is unambiguously found that 
chromium ion lasers, in contrast to neodymium ion lasers, have a 
distinct physical mechanism which causes nonattenuating 
pulsation of radiation intensity. Any mechanism associated with 
spatial interaction of modes in the active medium is ruled out. 
The difference in the lasers is ascribed to the great difference 
in the structure of the ions' working levels. The electric field 
of the laser radiation which arises in the active medium will 
affect only chromium ions, leading to further spallation of the 
working levels due to the dynamic Stark effect. When the field 
in the active medium is spatially inhomogeneous, a standing wave 
is formed whose spatial structure is altered during generation. 
The Stark effect leads to modulation of intensity over time and 
nonattenuating pulsations in intensity. When the spatial 
inhomogeneity of the field in the active medium is smoothed, 
this intensity modulation disappears. This conclusion was 
verified experimentally using titanium lasers. It may also be 
concluded that free generation of all rare earth ions in various 
media should occur in quasi-stationary mode without the need to 
smooth the spatial inhomogeneity of the field in the active 
medium. Figures 6; references 44, 33 Russian, 11 Western. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890121-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-21-89 0607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-Lasers Adv21-22 1stLd-Writethru 01-21 1050</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Lasers, Adv 21-22, 1st Ld-Writethru,1080</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv 21</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv 22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release weekend editions Jan. 21-22.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Laser, Superman of Light, Poised For Quantum Leap</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 22-23, Spectra Diode ... urinary-tract stones., to
lower wattage of laser, 55 sted 76, based on revision by company; CORRECT
name of company; change optical to ophthalmic; picks up 24th graf, Lasers
are ....</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserGraphic NY16 of Jan. 19.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER COY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They find things in the dark. They check
groceries, play concertos and perform eye surgery. They are faster
than a speeding bullet and could do serious damage to a locomotive.
   Lasers have been the Superman of the electromagnetic spectrum
ever since <DATE>1960</DATE>, when 33-year-old <PERSON>Theodore H. Maiman</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Hughes
Aircraft Co.</ORGANIZATION> built the first one from a pink ruby.
   As they near their 30th anniversary, though, lasers have switched
from comic-book novelties to necessities that preoccupy the
technology giants of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   Lasers are not only in compact disc players and bar-code scanners
at checkout counters, they are in the phone system, carrying
long-distance calls over hair-thin glass fibers.
   Now, lasers are poised to take a quantum leap. Tiny devices
called quantum lasers herald an era in which lasers will be more
central to the technology underlying daily life.
   Experts say quantum lasers and their cousins, quantum
transistors, could make possible supercomputers the size of
baseballs, and television screens of unparalleled clarity that hang
on the wall like a painting.
   ``Quantum devices are the wave of the future. Almost all of the
research that goes on involves quantum effects in some way or
another,'' said <PERSON>David V. Lang</PERSON>, director of the solid state
electronics research lab at <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T Bell Labs</ORGANIZATION>.
   Lasers are what some scientists call a ``killer'' technology:
Compact discs are killing vinyl records, for example, and nobody
uses copper anymore for long-distance phone lines.
   To repeat a familiar story, the Japanese are putting the
American-invented killer to use more effectively than Americans
themselves are.
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s dominance of mass-market electronics gives its companies
unmatched expertise in making things small, cheap and reliable. For
example, Japanese companies dominate the market for CD players,
which use more lasers than any other product.
   ``It's a byproduct of the Japanese decision to invest in consumer
electronics. They'll find an application and find the technology to
solve it. I wish we did it here,'' said <PERSON>Henry Kressel</PERSON>, a venture
capitalist at <ORGANIZATION>E.M. Warburg Pincus &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>. Inc. in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s twin towers of strength in lasers and semiconductors
could allow it to build the first computers in which chips are
connected by quantum laser beams instead of electricity. That
is intensively studying quantum well lasers and quantum well
transistors.
   At <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>, one of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s foremost laser
research centers, <PERSON>Alan Huang</PERSON> is hoping to leapfrog the Japanese. But
he admits the competition is tough: For an early model of his
``optical computer'' he had to use a diode laser he took from a
Japanese-made CD player.
   A laser is a directed needle of light purified to one particular
color, or wavelength. In contrast, ordinary light is a jumble of
many wavelengths flying in all directions.
of radiation. In a cascading effect, photons of light strike an
energized material and stimulate the release of more photons in a
synchronized pattern.
   The most powerful lasers, big enough for someone to walk inside,
are being used to attempt to fuse the nuclei of atoms in flashes of
energy a million times more intense than a nuclear blast. Sustained
nuclear fusion could be a source of clean, plentiful and cheap
electricity.
   At the other end of the scale are semiconductor diode lasers, no
bigger than a grain of salt _ the kind used in compact disc players
and the phone system. One exotic subspecies is the quantum laser.
   Scientists build quantum lasers by ``spray-painting'' atoms in a
layer cake of incredibly thin layers, some of which have impurities
added.
   The impure layers act like walls to trap electrons. Confining so
many electrons and their receptors (``holes'') to a tiny space makes
it easier to get a cascade of photons going, creating laser light.
   If a laser the size of a salt crystal were blown up to the size
of the World Trade Center in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, a quantum well would be about
the thickness of a rug in an office, said <PERSON>Michael Ettenberg</PERSON>,
director of the optoelectronics research lab at the <ORGANIZATION>David Sarnoff
Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   Quantum lasers are more precise and require less current, and
their efficiency in converting electricity to light is unmatched.
   Spectra Diode Laboratories of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, recently produced
55 watts of continuous wave power from a quantum laser, a record
power output and power conversion efficiency for a semiconductor
laser, president and chief executive <PERSON>Donald Scifres</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>The
Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> this past week.
   Ophthalmic surgeons have used lasers since <DATE>1970</DATE> to weld detached
retinas. Later came other medical uses like excising tumors and
eliminating cataracts. Today, lasers snaked into the body on optical
fibers clean arteries and destroy urinary-tract stones.
   Lasers are used to make pinholes in the nipples of baby bottles,
study components of car exhaust and form the three-dimensional
holograms used on credit cards _ and maybe someday dollar bills.
   The military has ``Star Wars'' designs for free-electron lasers
and powerful X-ray lasers, which physicist <ORGANIZATION>Edward Teller</ORGANIZATION> has
suggested could be triggered by a nuclear blast.
   Laser weapons would most likely be mounted in space: ``People
tried to shoot laser beams through the sky and what they discovered
was fog and rain,'' said <ORGANIZATION>William Bridges of California Institute of
Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   Quantum well lasers fill only one niche, but an important one.
Their speed and efficiency makes them ideal for rapid-fire
communication, initially for long-distance calls, later for links
between neighboring computers and eventually for the links between
chips in computers, said <PERSON>Robert Melcher</PERSON>, a laser expert for <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
   ``I've been in the laser game for 25 years now,'' said one
researcher, <PERSON>Ross A. McFarlane</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>Hughes Research Laboratories</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Malibu</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> ``That (quantum lasers) is where the future lies.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for weekend editions Jan. 21-22.</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890821-0062 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890817 </DD>
<AN> 890821-0062. </AN>
<HL> Centennial Journal: 100 Years in Business
@  ---
@  An Idea That Wasn't Off the Beam, 1958 </HL>
<DD> 08/17/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<TEXT>

   BUCK ROGERS, THE HERO of the 1929-1967 adventure strip, had less trouble with his ray gun than did <DATE>1958</DATE> inventors of an idea for a beam device later called a laser. 

   <PERSON>Arthur L. Schawlow</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Bell Laboratories</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Charles H. Townes</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION> consultant from <ORGANIZATION>Columbia University</ORGANIZATION>, on <DATE>Dec. 15, 1958</DATE>, published their "optical maser" paper and also filed the patent, assigned to <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION>. 

   But <PERSON>Gordon Gould</PERSON>, also of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, in an over-two-decade battle claimed he recorded his similar "laser" idea in <DATE>November 1957</DATE> with a candy store notary. 

   Both "masers" and "lasers" are devices containing crystal, gas or other substances that get atoms so excited as they bounce back and forth in step between two mirrors that they finally burst out in one coherent beam. 
Other light rays are merely incoherent waves. 

   <PERSON>Gould</PERSON> argued that his work was classified so he couldn't make his patent filing before <PERSON>Bell</PERSON>'s. 
After the long dispute, he won his patent on <DATE>Oct. 11, 1977</DATE>, by which time the <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION> patent had expired. 
On <DATE>March 1, 1982</DATE>, a court upheld his victory, and he became rich. 
In <DATE>December 1988</DATE> he won still another laser patent. 

   Neither <PERSON>Gould</PERSON> nor the Schawlow-Townes team ever made a working laser. 
The first one, using a ruby crystal, was built by <PERSON>Theodore H. Maiman</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Hughes Aircraft</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1960</DATE>. 

   Today there are millions of lasers, ranging in size from a grain of salt to a living room. 
They are used in everything from eye operations to automated supermarket checkouts to compact disc players to phone systems and three-dimensional photos. 
Future lasers could knock out enemy spacecraft. 
Welcome back, <ORGANIZATION>Buck Rogers</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-22836 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust008___94038" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-008 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   31 March 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Scientific Conference on 30 December 1992 by Department of </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Scientific Conference on 30 December 1992 by Department of </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
General   Physics and <ORGANIZATION>Astronomy of Russian Academy of Sciences 

<FÊP=102> 947J0011B Moscow USPEKHI FIZICHESKIKH NAUK</ORGANIZATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Russian Vol</ORGANIZATION>. 
163 No. 6, Nov-Dec 93 pp 85-88 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947J0011B </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> USPEKHI FIZICHESKIKH <ORGANIZATION>NAUK </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by member of editorial staff] </F>
  [Abstract] A scientific conference was held on 30 <DATE>December 
1992</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>Department of General Physics</ORGANIZATION> and Astronomy of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Russian Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION> at its <ORGANIZATION>Institute of Problems in 
Physics</ORGANIZATION> imeni <PERSON>P.L. Kapitsa</PERSON>. Three lectures on the topic of 
femtosecond pulses and their usefulness in physics were given: 
  1. ``Current Trends in Research on Femtosecond Pulses and 
Possibilities of Their Use in Experimental Studies Pertaining to 
Nonlinear Quantum Electrodynamics'' by <ORGANIZATION>P.G. Kryukov</ORGANIZATION>; 
  2. ``Nonlinear Propagation of Femtosecond Pulses Through 
Fiber-Optic Waveguides'' by Ye.M. Dianov, <ORGANIZATION>A.M. Prokhorov</ORGANIZATION>, and 
<PERSON>V.N. Serkin</PERSON>; 
  3. ``Generation of Ultrahigh-Intensity Optical Fields by 
<ORGANIZATION>Powerful Femtosecond Laser Systems Including Excimer-Laser 
Amplifiers</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Experiments Relating</ORGANIZATION> to Emission of Ultrashort 
X-Ray Pulses'' by <PERSON>V.M. Gordiyenko</PERSON>, <PERSON>N.I. Koroteyev</PERSON>, and <ORGANIZATION>V.T. 
Platonenko</ORGANIZATION>. 
  In this report is summarized the content of the third 
lecture, which relates to development of ``desktop'' terawatt 
lasers emitting femtosecond radiation pulses of only 0.01-1 J 
energy. The mechanism of the process includes ``inertial 
conservation'' of the laser-induced plasma during its expansion, 
heat transfer deeper into the target mainly by diffusion being 
the main factor which limits the plasma temperature. When the 
radiation intensity exceeds the 
10[.sup]18-[/]-10[.sup]19[/] W/cm[.sup]2[/], then light 
pressure exceeds thermodynamic pressure while the plasma 
temperature climbs to thousands of electron-volts and the 
electron concentration reaches 10[.sup]23[/]-10[.sup]24[/] 
cm[.sup]-3[/] under pressures of 10-100 Mbar. Under these 
conditions the motion of free electrons shifts into the 
relativistic mode, which imparts unique properties to a 
femtosecond surface plasma so that it becomes a new object of 
basic research. This applies particularly to the electrodynamics 
of interaction of high-intensity radiation and a rapidly 
expanding steep high-temperature plasma front, also to the 
emission of x-rays by such a plasma. The laser facility built at 
the <ORGANIZATION>Moscow State University</ORGANIZATION> under the late <ORGANIZATION>S.A. Akhmanov</ORGANIZATION> 
includes solid-state visible lasers with a 1-10 <ORGANIZATION>GW</ORGANIZATION> power rating 
and an molecular XeCl excimer laser with a 10-100 <ORGANIZATION>GW</ORGANIZATION> power 
rating which emit 570-630 nm radiation and 308 nm radiation 
respectively, in pulses of about 40 fs duration. Proper focusing 
makes attainable a radiation intensity even higher than 
10[.sup]16[/] W/cm[.sup]2[/] at the target surface. Owing 
to the low optical density of a surface plasma, most of its 
x-ray emission energy lines within the resonance lines of its 
ions. With the aid of multilayer resonance mirrors it therefore 
becomes possible to extract strong narrow-band x-ray pulses and 
especially so from plasmas with hydrogen-like or helium-like 
ions. Theoretical analysis of the x-ray emission mechanism 
indicates that thin-film targets of about 100 nm thickness form 
laser-induced plasmas which make effective sources of hard 
x-rays. In this the heat is retained at the target, because the 
dissipation mechanism is inactive here, so that a less than 
usual intensity of the ``heating'' laser beam will be adequate. 
References 7. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47476 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust013___94029" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-013 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   23 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   NH-CO 9-13 æm Lidar </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    NH-CO 9-13 æm Lidar </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
for   Sounding the Atmosphere 
[.sub]3[/][.sub]2[/] 
<FÊP=102> 947J0030F <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> IZVESTIYA AKADEMII NAUK: SERIYA 
FIZICHESKAYA in <ORGANIZATION>Russian Vol</ORGANIZATION>. 58 No. 2, <DATE>Feb. 94</DATE> pp. 202-206 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947J0030F </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> IZVESTIYA AKADEMII NAUK: SERIYA 
<ORGANIZATION>FIZICHESKAYA </F>

<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <ORGANIZATION>B.I. Vasilyev, Institute of Physics</ORGANIZATION> imeni <PERSON>P.N. </F>
Lebedev</PERSON> at <ORGANIZATION>Russian Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>A.B. Yastrebov</PERSON>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Ryazan Institute of Radio Engineering</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 
551.501.7:621.373.826.038.823] 
  [Abstract] The principle of differential infrared 
absorption with scattering is considered for sounding the 
atmosphere and its contaminants, especially CFCl[.sub]3[/] 
(Freon-11) CF[.sub]2[/]Cl[.sub]2[/] (Freon-12), and 
CCl[.sub]4[/]. Inasmuch as <ORGANIZATION>TEA CO</ORGANIZATION>[.sub]2[/]-lasers are 
inadequate for this purpose owing to the presence of transverse 
modes and the decorrelating effect of the atmosphere along with 
instability of the radiation intensity and poor reproducibility, 
an ammonia-nitrogen 9-13 ?m laser with resonant pumping by a 
pulsed CO[.sub]2[/]-laser is proposed instead. The optics 
include three diffraction gratings: G[.sub]1[/] (100 
lines/mm, 30? glancing angle) on the exit side of the pump 
laser cavity, G[.sub]2[/] (75 lines/mm, 23? glancing 
angle) behind the first, G[.sub]3[/] (100 lines/mm, 30? 
glancing angle) on the exit side of the NH[.sub]3[/]-laser. 
Pump radiation from the <ORGANIZATION>CO</ORGANIZATION>[.sub]2[/] laser impinges on the 
first grating, whereupon radiation leaving its zeroth order 
impinges almost normally on the second grating and then through 
its first order enters the cell with NH[.sub]3[/]. The 
optical cavity for this active medium is formed by a spherical 
opaque mirror with a 10 m radius off the optical axis in front 
and the third grating on the optical axis behind. The opaque 
mirror is positioned so that it reflects radiation emitted by 
the NH[.sub]3[/] laser onto the second grating, which then 
rereflects this radiation back into the cavity along with the 
pump radiation. Addition of nitrogen not only boosts the 
emission efficiency (to <PERCENT>20 %</PERCENT>) and the energy of emitted 
pulses 
(to 1.5 J) but also appreciably widens the emission spectrum (up 
to 13.5 ?m). Absence of optically weak elements inside the 
cavity makes possible periodically-pulsed operation of the 
NH[.sub]3[/]-N[.sub]2[/] laser. The laser is tuned by 
rotation of that third grating. Emission of 10-1000 ns long 
radiation pulses is achieved by passive locking of longitudinal 
modes. For measurement duty the system is modified and includes 
only two gratings. The first one (64 lines/mm, 31? glancing 
angle) tunes the pump radiation from the CO[.sub]2[/]-laser 
to one of the two absorption lines of the sR(5,k) transition in 
ammonia and thus, with the aid of a compound cavity formed by 
that grating and two mirrors, splits that radiation into two 
beams of unequal intensities. The cavity of the 
NH[.sub]3[/]-N[.sub]2[/] laser is now formed by this 
grating, another mirror, and the second grating (100 lines/mm, 
37? glancing angle). This grating tunes the radiation from 
that laser to the absorption line of whichever contaminating 
impurity in air is being targeted, for use as the probing 
radiation. The system now also includes a transceiver into which 
the first grating sends both tuned pump radiation and tuned 
probing radiation, not together but in separate differently 
directed beams brought together into the transceiver upon their 
reflection by another mirror each. Figures 2; tables 1; 
references 11. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47477 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust013___94030" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-013 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   23 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Efficient Operating Mode of Frequency-Tunable Liquid Laser </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Efficient Operating Mode of Frequency-Tunable Liquid Laser </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   947J0037 St. Peterburg ZHURNAL TEKHNICHESKOY FIZIKI in 
Russian Vol. 64 No. 1 (manuscript received 23 Jul 92) pp. 201-205 </F>

<F P=103> 947J0037 </F>
<F P=104>  St. Peterburg ZHURNAL TEKHNICHESKOY FIZIKI </F>
<F P=105>  Russian </F>


<TEXT>
CSO 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <ORGANIZATION>G.A. Vesnicheva</ORGANIZATION> and A.Yu. Ivanov, <ORGANIZATION>St. Peterburg </F>
Institute of Aviation Instrument Engineering</ORGANIZATION>; 07;02] 
  [Abstract] Considering that stable radiation emission by a 
liquid laser requires a sufficiently large number of molecules 
in the active medium, a uniform distribution of the liquid over 
the emission zone, and a precisely aligned high-Q dispersive 
optical cavity, these conditions are applied to dye lasers 
featuring the best performance characteristics of all: not only 
wavelength-tunability over the 0.26-1.3 ?m range and up to 10 
kW power emission pulse but also compactness and cost 
effectiveness. When dye and solvent are being thoroughly mixed 
while being pumped by pulse trains of optical radiation, 
however, both hydrodynamic and photothermodynamic turbulence 
with attendant heat-induced convection of the solution will 
inevitably develop as the dye flow rate and the pump radiation 
intensity exceed the respective critical ones. The result will 
be randomization of the emission process with attendant lowering 
of both pump and laser efficiency. In search of a way to avoid 
this drawback, the dye excitation and lasing dynamics are 
analyzed for limitations on stable and efficient performance. As 
the main limiting factors are regarded not only both turbulence 
modes and thermal convection but also photodecay of dye 
molecules upon incidence of a pumping radiation pulse, their 
subsequent restoration, and the stroboscopic effect. As the 
optimum construction of the active element is selected a 
cylindrical cell with dye solution and a cylindrical mixing 
device inside. Thus are established the conditions under which a 
``window'' will exist in the dependence of emission irregularity 
on the dye flow characteristics and the pump radiation 
characteristics within which the emission process is least 
disordered, allowing a dye flow rate sufficiently high for 
stable replacement of dye molecules during the interval between 
pump radiation pulses. The relations established in this 
analysis indicate the feasibility of a laser with dye molecules 
in different instantaneous states and thus of wavelength tuning 
without a resonator. A rhodamine-6G laser pumped by a neodymium 
laser with second-harmonic 10 kW radiation pulses of 10 ns 
duration was designed and built. Tests revealed no turbulence 
throughout the 1.2x10[.sup]-7[/]-1333 l/s range of dye flow 
through the emission zone. References 8. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-23060 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust009___94024" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-009 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   18 April 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> ELECTRONICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Main Results of Scientific Research Done by Institute of </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Main Results of Scientific Research Done by Institute of </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Radio   Engineering and Electronics at Russian Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION> 
in <DATE>1984-92</DATE> Period: Lasers and <ORGANIZATION>Optical Systems</ORGANIZATION> (Including Fiber 
Optics, Methods and Devices, also Generation of Electromagnetic 
Signals) 

<FÊP=102> 974K0066A <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> RADIOTEKHNIKA I ELEKTRONIKA in <ORGANIZATION>Russian Vol</ORGANIZATION>. 
38 No. 10, Oct 93 </F>

<FÊP=103> 974K0066A </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> RADIOTEKHNIKA I <ORGANIZATION>ELEKTRONIKA </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by Ye.N. Bazarov and <PERSON>K.I. Palatov</PERSON>] </F>
  [Abstract] During the 1984-92 period the <ORGANIZATION>Institute of Radio 
Engineering and Electronics</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Russian Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION> 
intensified research in the field of quantum electronics, the 
three main areas being: 
1) fiber- optics technology, 
2) laser materials and devices, 
3) spectroscopy based on nuclear-magnetic resonance or on 
luminescence. 
  In the first area have been for the first time developed: 
a) a method of extruding single-mode fibers with sheaths made of 
fluorine-doped quartz glass for 1.3-1.55 ?m infrared light 
b) a new technology for producing anisotropic single-mode fibers 
which maintain the polarization and the intensity of light with 
minimal losses 
c) a laboratory technology for producing single-mode fibers 
which transmit 1.3 ?m light with an only 0.7 dB/km maximum 
loss 
d) a method of welding together different fibers with an only 
0.5 dB loss per joint. In addition to improvement of the 
extruding apparatus, there have been developed a plasmochemical 
variant of vertical lateral deposition for glass-forming oxides 
with use of organometallic compounds as initial reactants, a 
method of producing large-aperture fibers, a method of producing 
low-loss multimode fibers. A new method of forming anisotropic 
``bow tie'' fibers, with the aid of thermal shields, has been 
proposed and demonstrated. A high magnetic susceptibility of 
single-mode fibers has been attained by use of using rare-earth 
elements as dopants. For the first time has been developed a 
tubeless method of lateral deposition of thin fluorosilicate 
sheaths on quartz rods in a microwave plasma. Jointly with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Institute of Optical Physics</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Scientific Research 
Institute of Electrical Systems</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Electrical 
Industry</ORGANIZATION> have been produced radiation-resistant power fibers, 
radiation-resistant and mechanically strong single-mode and 
multimode fibers, thick fiber strands for optical cables, and 
large-aperture low-loss fibers doped with various rare-earth 
elements as well as large-aperture quartz-quartz fibers for 
transmitting up to 500 W of laser radiation power with <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> 
efficiency. Other developments include deposition of polymer 
sheaths, new silicon elastomers for fiber coatings which will 
ensure at least <PERCENT>99%</PERCENT> transmission, and a cryogenic 
microcable 
for temperatures from 80?C down to -60?C. Theoretical 
studies have yielded a theory of microflexure and a new model of 
hydrolytic fracture of quartz fibers. New apparatus with 
fiber-optic components for measuring physical quantities and 
methods of doing it have also been developed, the components 
including fiber thermooptic channel switches, <PERSON>Fourier</PERSON> analyzers, 
a random-access memory, polarizers, light modulators, two-mode 
reflectometers, directional couplers, temperature and magnetic 
field transducers. Work has furthermore been done on several 
practical applications of fiber-optic technology. In the area of 
laser materials and devices there have been developed a method 
of hardening phosphate glass, a new Cr-Y-Er glass for 
heat-resistant minilasers and high-efficiency low- threshold 
quatrons, a 1.5 ?m Er-minilaser suitable for a record high 7 
Hz pulse repetition rate, borate glass activated with Yb and Er. 
There also have for the first time been achieved parametric 
resonance emission of ultraviolet picosecond pulses and 
continuous high-efficiency emission by Nd ions. Other new 
developments include powder lasers (Nd-ion implanted in powders 
of La oxide or oxysulfide, binary Na, La, <ORGANIZATION>Ba</ORGANIZATION>, or Gd chromate- 
molybdate, La-Sr niobate, and Ga-Yb sulfide with Nd impurity), a 
new kind of mirrors using resonant metal screens for optically 
pumped lasers, a highly long-time stable 
CO[.sub]2[/]-OsO[.sub]4[/], and diffusely reflecting 
coatings (aluminum, fused quartz, phosphate glass) for laser 
reflectors, also a new method of hardening phosphate glass for 
active media and a new method of welding together glasses 
containing chromium. The feasibility of producing fibers for 
high-efficiency transmission of infrared light has been proposed 
on the basis of theoretical analysis and then demonstrated 
experimentally on fibers transmitting 1.5 ?m at an average 
power of 2 W with an up to <PERCENT>30 %</PERCENT> efficiency. With 
low-energy 
ultraviolet lasers, efficient frequency conversion by stimulated 
Raman scattering has been achieved in a multipass vessel 
containing methane under a pressure of 30 atm. Research was done 
on both electron-magnetic resonance and nuclear- magnetic 
resonance spectroscopy, studies of the latter having revealed a 
``cascade'' narrowing of the <ORGANIZATION>NMR</ORGANIZATION> spectra owing to concurrent 
action of a strong radio-frequency field and slow molecular 
movements in solids. As to generators of electromagnetic 
signals, there have been developed microminiature microwave 
vacuum devices including solid-state oscillators such as 
transistors, avalanche diodes, and Gunn-effect diodes. More than 
80 scientific articles have been published during that period. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47481 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust013___94034" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-013 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   23 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Free-Electron X-Ray Laser Operating in Quantum Mode </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Free-Electron X-Ray Laser Operating in Quantum Mode </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   947J0041A Moscow ZHURNAL EKSPERIMENTALNOY I TEORETICHESKOY 
FIZIKI in Russian Vol. 105 No. 4, Apr. 94 (manuscript received </F>



<TEXT>
24 Aug 93) pp. 808-817 
<FÊP=103> 947J0041A </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> ZHURNAL EKSPERIMENTALNOY I TEORETICHESKOY 
FIZIKI </F>

<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>E.M. Belenov</PERSON>, <PERSON>S.V. Grigoryev</PERSON>, <PERSON>A.V. Nazarkin</PERSON>, and </F>
<ORGANIZATION>I.V. Smetanin, Institute of Physics</ORGANIZATION> imeni <PERSON>P.N. Lebedev</PERSON> at 
<ORGANIZATION>Russian Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>] 
  [Abstract] A novel emission mode of a free-electron x-ray 
laser with counterpropagating electron beam and optical pump 
laser (``optical wiggler'') beam, namely its quantum emission 
mode where emission of an x-ray quantum changes the electronic 
state appreciably, is analyzed by comparing it with its 
classical mode of operation. Interaction of relativistic 
electrons with both electromagnetic pump and signal fields, for 
simplicity assuming a collinear geometry. Such a laser with an 
optical pump differs from one with a conventional magnetostatic 
one in that its emission and absorption lines are completely 
separated so that the ratio = h/_D_|e of the distance h_o_ 
(h- Planck constant, _o_- frequency) between them to their 
effective width _D__e_ is _ee_ &gt; &gt;  1, while with a 
magnetic pump 
this ratio is _ee_ &lt;&lt; 1. Analysis of three-wave 
interaction 
confirms the validity of treating the laser as one with a 
completely inverted two-level active medium and describing its 
electron dynamics with the Klein-Gordon equation. By virtue of 
the conservation laws, the problem of transitions in a continuum 
reduces to the problem of resonance excitation of discrete 
levels in an anharmonic oscillator. This leads to a 
self-consistent closed nonlinear system of four partial 
differential equations completely describing the emission 
dynamics of such a laser: two equations the evolution of slowly 
varying amplitudes a[.sub]0[/](z,t) and a[.sub]-1[/](z,t), 
one equation the propagation of emission pulses, and one 
equation the evolution of the high-frequency signal. This system 
is analogous to the system of Maxwell-Bloch equations describing 
the interaction of a two-level atomic medium with a resonance 
field. The performance characteristics of this laser are 
calculated for the case of quasi-steady amplification with the 
durations of not only the high-frequency pump and signal pulses 
but also of the electron cluster much longer than the 
characteristic dimension of the interaction space divided by the 
speed of light. The laser is shown to be more efficient in the 
quantum mode than in the classical mode of operation, transition 
from the latter to the former being achievable by widening the 
energy range within the electron beam. References 24. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910828-0071
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910828-0071.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology:
   Blue-Green Laser Chip Developed by 3M
   Increases the Storage Capacity of Discs
   ----
   By James P. Miller
</HL>
<DATE>
08/28/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B5
</SO>
<CO>
   IBM MMM
</CO>
<MS>
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
DIVERSIFIED TECHNOLOGY (DTC)
SEMICONDUCTORS, INTEGRATED CHIPS (SEM)
</IN>
<RE>
MINNESOTA (MN)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing Co. said its researchers
have developed the first blue-green laser diode, calling it a
"major breakthrough in laser technology."
   The prototype device has the potential to triple or
quadruple the amount of data that can be stored on optical
and compact discs, the St. Paul, Minn., company said. It also
"opens new opportunities" for laser applications in fields
such as imaging, printing and communications.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   But 3M cautioned that "we're targeting two years" to
resolve technical hurdles before the so-called semiconductor
diode could become commercially viable.
   Semiconductor diodes, the size of a grain of sand or
smaller, convert electrical signals into tiny laser beams.
While best known for their use in recording and playing
compact discs, the inexpensive laser-producing chips are also
used in a host of other communication devices. But the chips
currently produce light only at the infrared -- or sometimes
visible red -- end of the spectrum.
   The laser diode developed by 3M produces "the shortest
wavelength ever generated by a semiconductor laser diode,"
the scientists said. The smaller the laser beam's wavelength,
the more densely it can pack optical data into an
informationstorage device.
   The 3M scientists' work is to be published shortly in the
science journal Applied Physics Letters.
   The 3M researchers used a new combination of materials to
construct the laser diode. While the chip's surface still
rests on a conventional base of gallium arsenide, the company
said its scientists were the first to successfully make use
of zinc selenide.
   For decades, the scientists wrote, zinc selenide has been
"promising" for development of a diode laser that could
produce visible light, but difficulties in "doping" the
compounds -- chemically treating them to make them effective
as semiconductors -- had previously blocked use of the
unconventional combination. Recent technological developments
both in doping and alternative treatments have lowered the
barriers, the scientists said.
   Other companies, both in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, are hard at
work on diodes that produce visible light. Scientists at
<ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Almaden Research
Center</ORGANIZATION> last year created a "potentially practical source of
blue laser light," by passing an infrared laser beam from a
conventional diode through a special crystal. The crystal
effectively halves the resulting beam's wavelength, bringing
it into the visible spectrum.
   <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s experimental blue-laser device currently converts
electricity into light at about <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> efficiency; 3M said its
prototype is about <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> efficient.
   <PERSON>Charles Walker</PERSON>, head of 3M's <ORGANIZATION>Photonics Research Lab</ORGANIZATION>, said
the researchers are "absolutely thrilled" with the device.
But he said "We have to . . . take it from something that
operates in a pulsed mode at low power at room temperature,
to something that operates in the continuous mode at room
temperature." The device currently operates continuously only
at extremely low temperatures.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47471 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust013___94024" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-013 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   23 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Power Laser with Compound Beam Aperture, Phase Conjugation </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Power Laser with Compound Beam Aperture, Phase Conjugation </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Mirrors,   and Pulse Compressors 

<FÊP=102> 947J0030A <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> IZVESTIYA AKADEMII NAUK: SERIYA 
FIZICHESKAYA in <ORGANIZATION>Russian Vol</ORGANIZATION>. 58 No. 2, <DATE>Feb. 94</DATE> pp. 9-12 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947J0030A </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> IZVESTIYA AKADEMII NAUK: SERIYA 
<ORGANIZATION>FIZICHESKAYA </F>

<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>V.N. Belousov</PERSON>, <PERSON>A.M. Mamin</PERSON>, Yu.K. Niziyenko, and </F>
<PERSON>A.R. Sidorov</PERSON>, ``Kurchatov Institute'' branch of <ORGANIZATION>Russian Science 
Center</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 535.375] 
  [Abstract] A Nd-glass laser set for thermonuclear fusion 
consisting was built and tested, a set consisting of a master 
oscillator and two successive amplifier stages with phase 
conjugation and pulse compression. The oscillator operates in 
the single longitudinal mode and single transverse mode. The two 
amplifiers operate in the four-pass mode. The beam emitted by 
the oscillator in pulses of 3 mJ energy and 25 ns duration 
passes through a x10 magnifying telescope, a 12x12 
mm[.sup]2[/] large aperture stop, and then two Faraday 
isolators before entering the first amplifier stage. The active 
medium here is a cylinder of neodymium glass 20 mm in diameter 
and 300 mm long. This preamplifier stage includes a cell filled 
with Ar + SF[.sub]6[/] mixture, where an SBMS (Stimulated 
Brillouin-Mandelshtam Scattering) mirror for phase conjugation 
is formed by a focusing lens with a 50 cm focal length. After 
four passes in this stage and with the energy of radiation thus 
having been boosted to 3-4 J, the beam proceeds through a x3.3 
magnifying telescope, a Faraday isolator with a 60x60 
mm[.sup]2[/] large aperture, and then a x2.5 magnifying 
telescope before entering with a 100x100 mm[.sup]2[/] 
aperture the second amplifier stage. The active medium here is 
an array of six slabs of neodymium glass 340 mm long with a 
20x120 mm[.sup]2[/] large cross-section each. They are 
optically pumped by seven rows of four IFP-5000 flash lamps 
between each two slabs, distilled water thermally insulating the 
slabs from these lamps. Each slab is followed sends radiation to 
a cell filled with Ar + SF[.sub]6[/] mixture, an SBMS mirror 
for phase conjugation in the pulse compression mode being formed 
in each by a 17 mm[.sup]2[/] large square lens with a 5 m 
focal length. Upon entering this second amplifier stage, the 
beam is thus split into six separate partial beams with a 17x100 
mm[.sup]2[/] large aperture each. It then leaves this stage 
with an about 100x100 mm[.sup]2[/] large compound aperture, 
the duration of radiation pulses having in this stage been 
shortened 20 ns to 2 ns duration. The energy reflectivity of the 
mirrors here is estimated at <PERCENT>50 %</PERCENT>. Two tests were 
performed: 1) 
with direct passage of the beam passage through the second 
stage, 2) with reflection of the beam first by only one lateral 
face of each slab and then by their both faces. Direct passage 
was found to cause breakdown of the active medium near the 
lateral faces of the slabs, but radiation pulses of <DATE>20-25</DATE> J 
energy were nevertheless coming from each slab. Reflection by 
one lateral face resulted in a more uniform distribution of 
radiation intensity over the beam cross- section and reflection 
by both lateral faces resulted its most nearly uniform 
distribution. In the latter case the divergence of the total 
radiation beam was smaller than 0.1 mrad, while the energy of 
radiation pulses from each slab still reached the 25 J level. 
Such a laser set can be modified for simultaneous radiation 
emission at two different frequencies. This can be achieved by 
splitting the beam into two in the preamplifier stage, using a 
device such as a Fresnel biprism, and directing each half- beam 
to a different SBMS mirror cell: one containing a compressed gas 
and one containing a solid substance. Then while the beam is 
being focused, a traveling interference pattern will form in the 
focal plane owing to different radiation wavelengths in the two 
half-apertures. Figures 3; references 3. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-21559 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jptac003___94062" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TAC-94-003 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Arms Control 

<DATE1>  7 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL </F>
<F P=101></F>
<H3> <TI>     Laser Weapon Ban Urged by Red Cross Could Affect Russia </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PM2302122794 Moscow IZVESTIYA in Russian 22 Feb 94 p 3 </F>
<F P=103> PM2302122794 </F>
<F P=104>  Moscow IZVESTIYA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Russian </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Leonid Mlechin report: "New Generation of Lasers Could </F>
Soon Enter Various Armies' Arsenals"] 
  [Text] The <ORGANIZATION>International Red Cross Committee</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> has 
appealed to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, urging that the 
development of laser weapons, which can blind a person, be 
stopped. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> is hoping to obtain a formal UN ban on the 
development and production of laser weapons. They are silent 
and invisible weapons. A person does not know that a laser is 
being aimed at him and has no time to prepare himself and 
somehow protect himself. 
  Laser weapons are an object of desire for all armies' 
generals. Several attempts to provide themselves with the combat 
lasers featured in science fiction novels have been dashed 
against the immutable laws of physics. In order to make a laser 
beam capable of burning through something it must be focused: 
This is impossible at long distances because of the law of 
diffraction. But it is also impossible to kill enemy soldiers or 
destroy his armored vehicles at short distances using modern 
lasers. So far lasers have found a use in high-precision 
weapons guidance systems. 
  According to information available to the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>, a new 
generation of lasers could soon enter Western armies' arsenals. 
At a 1km radius such a weapon, <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> specialists claim, 
could permanently blind a person. One of the aims is to blind 
aircrew. The <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> committee also fears that portable and 
easy-to-use combat lasers could fall into the hands of 
terrorists. 
  The demand to stop the development of laser weapons will 
make 
life difficult not only for the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> but also for 
<LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>, which has overtaken the West in the development of 
lasers for terrestrial and space use. Millions of what were 
then noninflationary rubles went on attempts to develop lasers 
to destroy satellites and ballistic missiles in space. 
  Tracked laser guns were developed by the "Luch" central 
design bureau and then the "Astrofizika" science and production 
association, which was led by <PERSON>Nikolay Ustinov</PERSON>, son of <PERSON>Dmitriy 
Ustinov</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Central Committee</ORGANIZATION> secretary for the military industry 
and later defense minister. In 20 years <MONEY>200 million rubles</MONEY> were 
spent and a dozen vulnerable tracked monsters which had no 
chance on the battlefield were constructed. 
  Under <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> work to improve the monster was halted. 
According to <ORGANIZATION>IZVESTIYA</ORGANIZATION> reports work was recently resumed. 
Possibly the generals are unable to abandon their long-standing 
dream. Maybe physics research is not standing still and there 
will be new opportunities to decrease the dimensions of combat 
lasers and make them cheaper. Their task is to disable the 
enemy's optical guidance instruments and blind operators. When 
enemy positions are illuminated by a laser beam the electronic 
optical guidance systems (of an aircraft, missile launcher, 
tank, artillery piece, or firearm) will themselves focus this 
beam and be disabled. If at this moment the operator is looking 
through the guidance instrument's eyepiece he will lose his 
sight. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-20531 </DOCNO>
<HT>      "jpest008___94027" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-EST-94-008 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Europe/International Economic Competitiveness </ABS>
<DATE1>   19 January 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> WEST EUROPE </F>
<F P=101> CORPORATE ALLIANCES </F>
<H3> <TI>   Germany: Bonn Leads Research in High-Efficiency Diode </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Germany: Bonn Leads Research in High-Efficiency Diode </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Lasers 

<FÊP=102>   94WS0213B Frankfurt/Main FRANKFURTER ZEITUNG/BLICK DURCH DIE 
WIRTSCHAFT in German <DATE>19 Jan 94</DATE> p 8 </F>

<FÊP=103> 94WS0213B </F>
<FÊP=104>  Frankfurt/Main FRANKFURTER ZEITUNG/BLICK DURCH DIE 
WIRTSCHAFT </F>

<FÊP=105>  German </F>
CSO 

  [TEXT] Hopes for a major advance in technology and 
development--<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s lead to be overtaken. 
  Thirty-four years after the discovery of the first laser, 
another generational shift in high-efficiency lasers is again 
approaching with the transition from tube technology to 
semi-conductor technology, or from gas laser to diode laser. In 
the areas of entertainment electronics and communications and 
information technology, the replacement of tube technology with 
semiconductor technology has already made possible and produced 
revolutionary developments. 
  It is expected that a similar major advance in technology 
and 
development in [the area of] high-efficiency lasers will 
fundamentally shape future laser equipment technology and open 
up new fields of application. The German government intends to 
support this development with the joint Laser <DATE>2000</DATE> program, 
which <ORGANIZATION>Federal Minister of Research</ORGANIZATION> and Technology <PERSON>Paul Krueger</PERSON> 
has now introduced in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. 
  Preparing the generational shift in technology with 
high-efficiency lasers is the object and goal of the pilot 
project, already started at the beginning of the year, on 
high-efficiency diode lasers and diode-pumped solid-state 
lasers. It has to do with developing a small, compact, 
high-efficiency, low- maintenance laser. It is expected that 
such an generation of lasers will open up broad markets. 
Materials processing in particular is being considered in this 
context, as well as using laser technology for television. 
  Substantial work was already done on the high-efficiency 
diode laser in the <DATE>second half of the 1980</DATE>'s in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> under 
the strictest secrecy in the <ORGANIZATION>Lawrence Livermore National 
Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> within the framework of the former SDI program. One 
important field of application which stands in the forefront is 
automobile manufacturing. The German government is hoping that 
with the current Laser 2000 program the present lead by the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> will be overtaken. So the project will be oriented 
toward the needs of industry. A project advisory council was 
formed representing <ORGANIZATION>Siemens</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Janoptik</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Rofin-Sinar</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Haas Laser</PERSON>, 
Adlas and <PERSON>Baasel</PERSON> [as written] Lasertechnik. The pilot project is 
currently made up of three joint projects in industry and four 
joint research [projects]. 
  Parallel to this, the four joint research projects will deal 
with basic research themes such as the preliminary research in 
securing technical scientific alternatives--for example, new 
technologies for high-efficiency diode lasers and new 
ytterbium-base solid-state lasers. 
  The work of the four joint research projects is being 
financed with about <MONEY>30 million German marks</MONEY> through the <ORGANIZATION>Federal 
Ministry of Research and Technology</ORGANIZATION>. For the three joint 
industry projects, financing in the amount of <MONEY>35 million German 
marks</MONEY> is being projected, to which the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Ministry of 
Research</ORGANIZATION> will contribute around <MONEY>19 million German marks</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47474 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust013___94027" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-013 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   23 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Remote Measurement of Thickness of Petroleum-Product Film on </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Remote Measurement of Thickness of Petroleum-Product Film on </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Water   With Excimer Laser 

<FÊP=102> 947J0030D <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> IZVESTIYA AKADEMII NAUK: SERIYA 
FIZICHESKAYA in <ORGANIZATION>Russian Vol</ORGANIZATION>. 58 No. 2, <DATE>Feb. 94</DATE> pp. 175-179 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947J0030D </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> IZVESTIYA AKADEMII NAUK: SERIYA 
<ORGANIZATION>FIZICHESKAYA </F>

<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by A.P. Zhevlakov, <LOCATION>D.O. Leshchenko</LOCATION>, <PERSON>S.A. Pakkonen</PERSON>, </F>
and <PERSON>V.M. Sidorenko</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>State Institute of Optics</ORGANIZATION> imeni <LOCATION>S.I. 
Vavilov</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 551.501.816+551.508.856] 
  [Abstract] Use of a fluorescent lidar with an excimer laser 
for measuring from a distance the thickness of films of 
petroleum products on water is considered, determination of the 
film thickness involving as usually two measurements of the 
fluorescence intensity of water twice: with and without the 
film. The principle of this method is based on the dependence of 
the hydrooptical properties, reflectivity and absorptivity, on 
the film thickness. These relations were studied experimentally 
with an XeCl-laser exciting the films with 308 nm radiation. 
Both absorption and emission spectra of various petroleum 
products, lubricants and fuels in cyclohexane solution, were 
measured in a spectrophotometer. The fluorescence intensity of 
such films on water was measured with a laboratory apparatus 
which included this XeCl laser and an aligning it He-Ne laser, 
two photomultipliers, a pyroelectric radiation receiver, an 
MDR-4 monochromator with a spectrally 2 nm wide slit, and four 
objectives consisting each of a mating biconvex and 
concavo-plane lens pair. A rotating wedge diverted a part of the 
excitation beam through either the first objective into the 
first photomultiplier or through the second objective into the 
pyroelectric radiation receiver. A right-angle prism reflected 
the remaining part of the excitation radiation through the third 
objective into the test cell with a specimen. A rotating plane 
mirror reflected the radiation from the fluorescing specimen 
through the fourth objective and then the monochromator into the 
second photomultiplier. Tests were performed on successively 
3-9-15-30 ?m thick films, with an XeCl-laser emitting 
radiation in pulses of 30 mJ energy and 30 ns duration at an 
either 0.1 Hz or 0.25 Hz repetition rate. Fluorescence was 
recorded within the 320-410 nm band, the maximum fluorescence 
signal shifting farter into the long-wave region as a light 
petroleum product was being replaced with successively heavier 
ones. With increasing film thickness, the fluorescence signal 
normalized to the Raman scattering signal was found to increase 
up to the fluorescence saturation level. Therefore, use of an 
excimer laser is recommended only for thin (d &lt; 15 ?m) 
films 
of petroleum products on water. Figures 3; references 9. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47299 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust012___94053" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-012 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   8 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Doppler Radar for Monitoring Motor Vehicle Moving Through </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Doppler Radar for Monitoring Motor Vehicle Moving Through </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Dust   Cloud 

<FÊP=102> 947J0028B St.Peterburg OPTICHESKIY ZHURNAL in 
Russian No. 2, Feb 94 (manuscript received 7 <DATE>May 93</DATE>) pp 33-36 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947J0028B </F>
<FÊP=104>  St.Peterburg OPTICHESKIY <ORGANIZATION>ZHURNAL </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <ORGANIZATION>A.P. Narysov</ORGANIZATION>, candidate of technical sciences, </F>
and <ORGANIZATION>V.V. Sadchikov</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Scientific-Industrial Association ``State 
Institute of Applied Optics</ORGANIZATION>'', <PERSON>Kazan</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 621.396.962] 
  [Abstract] Following a review of basic Doppler radar 
principles applied to detection of moving objects and 
determination of their velocities by measurement of Doppler 
reflection spectra, a Doppler radar with an optical rangefinder 
is described which has been developed and built for monitoring 
motor vehicles which move through dust clouds. The light source 
is an LGN-901 CO[.sub]2[/]-laser with operating at a power 
level of about 3 W. Its radiation is stabilized by means of a 
piezoceramic corrector and a diffraction grating, whereupon a 
primary plane <ORGANIZATION>Cu</ORGANIZATION> mirror reflects it at a 90? angle onto a <ORGANIZATION>Ge</ORGANIZATION> 
plate for splitting into an object beam and a reference beam. 
The object beam is twice reflected upon 45? incidence on two 
successive plane mirrors, for passage along a parallel path 
through a diaphragm into a collimating lens which reduces its 
divergence to one eighth of the original. The collimated beam, 
40 mm in diameter with a 0.6 mrad divergence angle, is then 
reflected by a plane scanning mirror onto the road under 
observation, whereupon a part of the returning beam is reflected 
by the same scanning mirror into a receiving objective coaxial 
with the collimator and operating in the Cassagrain mode. The 
objective lens has a 1000 mm focal length and a 200 mm outside 
diameter, its 110 mm inside diameter being larger than that of 
the collimating lens. The objective focuses the incoming 
radiation on the diffraction spot on the 0.2x0.2 mm[.sup]2[/] 
large light-sensitive surface of a HgCdTe photodetector, a 
high-speed photodiode with a 30 MHz wide passband. The reference 
beam meanwhile passes through two successive acoustooptic 
modulators operating at close to one another frequencies (40 MHz 
and 39.6 MHz) and then, after reflection by another plane 
mirror, through the receiving objective to the photodiode. For 
automatic frequency control another photodetector, a 
photoresistor with 1x1 mm[.sup]2[/] large light-sensitive 
surface and a 1 MHz wide passband, is placed at the entrance to 
the laser. Such a configuration of the optical system enables 
the radar set to operate in the energy mode and in the 
heterodyne mode without additional tuning. Use of two modulators 
significantly weakens the effect of direct illumination at the 
carrier frequency in the reference channel. The radar is 
calibrated against a foam plastic panel set into 50 Hz vibration 
by a 10GD-30 loudspeaker head. Figures 2; references 2. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47480 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust013___94033" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-013 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   23 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Coherent Doppler Wind Lidar With TEA CO-Laser </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Coherent Doppler Wind Lidar With TEA CO-Laser </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
[.sub]2[/] 
<FÊP=102>   947J0038C <ORGANIZATION>Moscow KVANTOVAYA ELEKTRONIKA</ORGANIZATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Russian Vol</ORGANIZATION>. 23 
No. 3, <DATE>Mar. 94</DATE> (manuscript received 22 Jul 93) pp. 284-290 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947J0038C </F>
<FÊP=104>  <ORGANIZATION>Moscow KVANTOVAYA ELEKTRONIKA </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>V.M. Gordiyenko</PERSON> and Yu.Ya. Putivskiy, </F>
<ORGANIZATION>International Laser Center</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Moscow State University</ORGANIZATION> imeni <LOCATION>M.V. 
Lomonosov</LOCATION>; PACS 42.79Qx; 42.68.Wt] 
  [Abstract] Construction of a Doppler wind lidar using a TEA 
(transverse excitation atmospheric pressure) pulsed 
single-frequency CO[.sub]2[/] injection laser for coherent 
reception and processing of data on winds in the lower 
atmospheric layers at altitudes up to 15 km. The design of such 
a lidar is based on the fundamental equation relating the 
signal-to-noise ratio to parameters of the sounding radiation 
pulses and of the atmospheric medium, the solution to this 
equation indicating the amount of energy needed for a sounding 
radiation pulse to reach the desired altitude. A laser set of 
this type with automatic ultraviolet preionization features both 
simplicity and reliability. Its one drawback is the sweeping of 
the emission frequency caused by presence of discharge electrons 
in the active medium, resonance polarization of <ORGANIZATION>CO</ORGANIZATION>[.sub]2[/] 
molecules, and acoustic expansion of heated gas. This sweep is 
best measured by optical heterodyning with radiation of a 
continuous-wave single-frequency reference CO[.sub]2[/]-laser 
and subsequent mixing the two signals in a HgCdTe photodetector 
for processing with the aid of an analog-to-digital converter. 
The results of these measurements were used for optimizing the 
composition of the active medium so as to ensure both minimum 
width of the emission band and maximum emission energy. The 
active medium, a CO[.sub]2[/]:N[.sub]2[/]:He = 1.5:2.5:6 
mixture is confined inside a typically 5 m long linear resonator 
cavity, this cavity being formed by a spherical mirror with a 
typically 18 m radius and a germanium wedge. The cavity contains 
also a NaCl wedge through which an external signal is injected 
into the active medium and through which some laser radiation is 
extracted for mode locking. Mode locking is achieved by noting 
the instant of time at which the frequency of the injected 
signal coincides with the frequency of the natural cavity mode 
and at that instant initiating a discharge in the TEA 
compartment. This instant can be recorded by a signal peak 
detector as corresponding to the maximum intensity on the 
interference pattern, with the cavity mirror oscillating 
harmonically at a frequency of typically 180 Hz. Such a <ORGANIZATION>TEA 
CO</ORGANIZATION>[.sub]2[/]-laser and a telescope were included in the 
prototype of a Doppler wind lidar, also a continuous-wave 
reference CO[.sub]2[/]-laser and a HgCdTe photodetector with 
an output amplifier, a DVK-2 computer, and a CAMAC crate. A 
model needed for determination of the signal scattering in the 
atmosphere is based on the following premises: 1. scattering is 
done by a large number of arbitrarily located identical aerosol 
particles moving at the wind velocity, 2. atmospheric turbulence 
influences only the wavefront of backscattered radiation, 3. 
signal attenuation in the atmosphere obeys Bouger's law. With 
this lidar were measured wind velocities along horizontal and 
vertical paths, whereupon he data were used for calculating wind 
velocity profiles and their dispersions. The authors thank 
Professor <PERSON>S.A. Akhmanov</PERSON> for initiating this study and then 
providing an comprehensive support, also <PERSON>G.A. Pogosov</PERSON> and <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> 
Kosovskiy for support and helpful discussion. Figures 7; 
references 34. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-22928 </DOCNO>
<HT>      "jpust008___94131" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-008 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   31 March 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> LIFE SCIENCES </F>
<F P=101> LASER AND NONIONIZING RADIATION </F>
<H3> <TI>   Possibilities of Using Fiber Optic Luminescent Light Sources </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Possibilities of Using Fiber Optic Luminescent Light Sources </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
in   Medical and <ORGANIZATION>Biological Research 

<FÊP=102> 947C0051A Moscow MEDITSINSKAYA TEKHNIKA</ORGANIZATION> in Russian No. 2, 
Mar-Apr 93 pp 13-14 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947C0051A </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> MEDITSINSKAYA TEKHNIKA </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>V.A. Monich</PERSON>, <LOCATION>I.V. Krivosheina</LOCATION>, <PERSON>S.L. </F>
Malinovskaya</PERSON>, <PERSON>K.N. Kontorshchikova</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Nizhniy Novgorod Medical 
Institute</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 615.849.19.03] 
  [Abstract] The emergence of low-power medical lasers and 
the resulting uses of such lasers on biological tissues as well 
reports that the use of noncoherent light sources and lasers in 
clinical practices leads to virtually indistinguishable results 
prompted renewed interest in developing light treatment devices 
using polymer optical fibers, especially since in most cases, 
the clinics do not have the facilities for retuning the laser 
radiation wavelength to match its spectrum with the resonant 
absorption lines of biologically significant molecules. The 
optical fiber will be able not only to transmit radiation 
bounded by the fiber end aperture but also the light generated 
by photoluminescence of the impurities. The structure of a 
two-layer optical fiber containing luminescing impurities and a 
block diagram of the fiber optic luminescent device are cited, 
and the design and operating principles of this low-intensity 
fiber optic luminescent device designed on the basis of the 
above characteristics are described in detail. The operating 
principle makes it possible to combine the function of injecting 
light into thin fibers and isolating spectral radiation bands 
which are most effective in given procedures. The device's 
ability to generate pulse radiation greatly increases the 
strength of the postoperative sutures; a 40 Hz frequency is 
optimal, and red light (600-680 nm) is the most efficient. 
Experiments with animals and donor blood demonstrates that 
monochromated light has a favorable effect on skin tissue 
regeneration. Figures 3; references 9. 


</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-24491 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust006___94022" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-006 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   09 March 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> ELECTRONICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Passive Synchronization of the Modes of Neodymium Lasers 
Using CuInSSe-Doped Glasses </TI></H3>


<TEXT>
[.sup]2x[/][.sub]2(1-x)[/] 
<FÊP=102>  947K0035D <ORGANIZATION>Moscow KVANTOVAYA ELEKTRONIKA</ORGANIZATION> in Russian Vol 20, 
No 9, Sep 93 pp 890-892 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947K0035D </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> KVANTOVAYA ELEKTRONIKA </F>
 Language: <FÊP=105>Russian </F>
Article Type:<ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>K. V. Yumashev</PERSON>, <PERSON>V. P. Mikhaylov</PERSON>, <PERSON>I. V. Bodnar</PERSON>, </F>
<PERSON>M. I. Demchuk</PERSON>, <PERSON>P. V. Prokoshin</PERSON>, <PERSON>R. S. Dashyan</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 
621.373.826.038.825.2] 
  [Abstract] Passive synchronization of the modes of YAG:Nd 
and YAlO[.sup]3[/] lasers using 
CuInS[.sup]2x[/]Se[.sub]2(1- x)[/]-doped glasses is 
discussed. The optical block diagram of the laser is provided 
and its functioning is described. The laser resonator is formed 
by a spherical mirror and a planar output mirror. A passive 
synchronization of modes was obtained when glasses with 
CuInS[.sup]1.2[/]Se[.sub]0.8[/] monocrystal were used as 
passive gates in pulsed solid state neodymium lasers. The pulse 
width was 36 and 16 ns for the YAG:Nd-and YAlO[.sup]3[/]:Nd 
lasers, respectively. The passive gates operate as saturating 
absorbers at low intensities and perform negative feed-back at 
high radiation intensities. The glasses with 
CuInS[.sup]2x[/]Se[.sub]2(1-x)[/] are a promising material 
for semiconductor cavity saturating absorbers for solid state 
lasers operating in a self-starting mode. The saturating 
absorbers exhibit a rapid relaxation, and have low losses and 
high saturation intensities. They can operate in a nonlinear 
mode within resonators of solid state lasers, interacting with 
pulse intensities in a pico range. The required operating wave 
length can be selected within the 0.9-1.3 ?m range by 
changing 
the stoichiometry coefficient and composition of the glass. 
Figures 4, references 11: 4 Russian, 7 Western. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47478 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust013___94031" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-013 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   23 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Feasibility of Electric-Discharge Excimer Laser With </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Feasibility of Electric-Discharge Excimer Laser With </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Condensed   Noble Gas as Active Medium 

<FÊP=102> 947J0038A <ORGANIZATION>Moscow KVANTOVAYA ELEKTRONIKA</ORGANIZATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Russian Vol</ORGANIZATION>. 23 
No. 3, <DATE>Mar. 94</DATE> (manuscript received 10 <DATE>May 93</DATE>) pp. 227-233 </F>

<FÊP=103> 947J0038A </F>
<FÊP=104>  <ORGANIZATION>Moscow KVANTOVAYA ELEKTRONIKA </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by Ye.<PERSON>B. Gordon</PERSON>, <PERSON>O.S. Rzhevskiy</PERSON>, and <PERSON>V.V. </F>
Khmelenko</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Institute of Energy Problems in Chemical Physics</ORGANIZATION> at 
<ORGANIZATION>Russian Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Chernogolovka</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Moscow Oblast</LOCATION>) 
branch; PACS 42.55.Gp;42.60.By] 
  [Abstract] The feasibility of achieving an excimer laser 
with a condensed active medium is examined for theoretical and 
experimental purposes. Inasmuch as most advantageous is 
transition of noble gases to a condensed phase and among all 
excimer lasers these lasers emit shortest- wave radiation, 
lasers, the most easily achievable Xe[.sub]2[/]-laser is 
considered for specificity. The first problem is avoiding 
absorption of emission-wavelength radiation under conditions of 
high gas densities. The solution of this problem is based on 
analysis of the known structure of lower energy levels and 
origin of molecular luminescence bands, also helpful being the 
known luminescence spectrum of crystalline solid xenon at 5 K 
temperature. The most difficult next problem is adequate pumping 
of the entire solid or liquid active medium, electric-discharge 
pumping being preferable to inefficient pumping by another laser 
and difficult to arrange pumping by a lamp. The necessary 
conditions for attaining a homogeneous electric discharge with 
sufficiently high energy for excitation of Xe atoms by electron 
impact are established by analyzing the drift of fast excess 
electrons through gaseous and liquid or solid xenon with 
attendant elastic scattering by its atoms. As the intensity of 
the electric field is increased above E* ? _e_/b= 2 kV/cm 
for 
xenon (_e_- electron energy, b- mean displacement of electron 
prior to its thermalization), the energy lost by ``hot'' 
electrons during their collisions with Xe atoms is increasingly 
compensated by the energy imparted to the field so that the net 
loss becomes negligible in an electric field of intensity E 
&gt; &gt; 
E* (3 kV/cm for xenon). A solid Xe-laser constructed according 
to these guidelines has an H-form cell with already liquid xenon 
between two plane mirrors parallel to its two wide walls. Two 
electrodes,anode and cathode, are lining the cell wall on 
opposite sides along the narrow middle segment so as to produce 
a transverse electric discharge through xenon within this 
segment. No electron multiplication takes place in this system 
and use of an external electron source is inconvenient. Instead, 
for sustaining the discharge, the metal cathode is covered with 
a layer of a radioactive target material and a photoemissive 
coating of a high-yield (low work function) material on top. 
This ensures an electron avalanche by chain multiplication and 
thus makes it very likely feasible to build 30 kW lasers 
emitting ultraviolet radiation in pulses of up to 1 ms duration 
with an up to <PERCENT>30 %</PERCENT> efficiency, not only Xe- lasers (172 
nm) but 
also Kr-lasers (145 nm) and Ar-lasers (128 nm). Figures 6; 
tables 1; references 26. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06158047 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06158047 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  OBITUARY; RESEARCH; TECHNOLOGY; CELEBRITY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Earl Bell knew there was more to lasers than the first one T.H. Maiman built
radiation" by using ruby, a solid material.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EARL BELL, LASER TECHNOLOGY GENIUS, CO-FOUNDER
OF SPECTRA-PHYSICS FIRM  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     When <PERSON>Mr. Bell</PERSON> co-founded <ORGANIZATION>Spectra-Physics</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, finding other ways to
"lase" wasn't a top priority, but he was searching, and so were others.;    In
<DATE>1961</DATE>, a team of scientists at <ORGANIZATION>Bell Laboratories</ORGANIZATION> operated a helium-neon gas
laser. <PERSON>Mr. Bell</PERSON> found a way to use it.;    "<PERSON>Earl Bell</PERSON> made the first
commercial helium-neon laser at <ORGANIZATION>Spectra-Physics</ORGANIZATION>," said <PERSON>Gene Watson</PERSON>, a former
colleague and now president of Chromex, a scientific instrument firm in
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M</LOCATION>. It produced the red laser lines shoppers now see every time
they buy groceries at a supermarket checkout scanner.;    But the red line
wasn't enough for the researchers at <ORGANIZATION>Spectra-Physics</ORGANIZATION>. They wanted more
powerful laser lines, in shades of blue and green, and they sought to do it
not just with the gas itself but with the ions created when gas atoms are
excited, <PERSON>Watson</PERSON> said.;    "Earl was conducting an experiment to get mercury
vapor to 'lase,' " <PERSON>Watson</PERSON> said.;    "He came bursting out of the lab and said,
'We got it. We got the green line.' ";    <PERSON>Watson</PERSON> said he asked, "Is it the one
you're looking for?";    "Well, what difference does it make?" <PERSON>Mr. Bell</PERSON>
answered. "It's green.";    With that answer, <PERSON>Watson</PERSON> said he learned an
inventor's lesson: " 'It's not what you're looking for that's important,' <PERSON>Earl</PERSON>
would say. 'It's what you get that's important.' ";    What was important was
a breakthrough in laser technology. While <PERSON>Mr. Bell</PERSON> was using mercury vapor
ions to "lase," Bill Bridges of <ORGANIZATION>Hughes Aircraft</ORGANIZATION> was using argon ions. They
both got a green line, and it opened up a new world in surgery and optics.;   
<DATE>Today</DATE>, the gas ion laser represents a <MONEY>$100 million-plus</MONEY> industry, said <PERSON>Herbert
M. Dwight Jr.</PERSON>, who along with <PERSON>Mr. Bell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Arnold Bloom</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bob Rempel</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ken
Ruddock</PERSON> founded <ORGANIZATION>Spectra-Physics</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1961.</DATE>;    "Its principal applications are
in medical uses, in microsurgery, but also in the graphics industry for
precise color separations," said <PERSON>Dwight</PERSON>, now chief executive officer of
<ORGANIZATION>Superconductor Technologies Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Santa Barbara.</LOCATION>;    The other lesson <PERSON>Mr.
Bell</PERSON> taught his co-workers was about the implementation of ideas. They saw him
as the most prolific inventor they have ever known.;    When <PERSON>Mr. Bell</PERSON> died of
cancer at age 70 recently, he had detected more than 30 laser intensities.;   
"He discovered more laser lines than any other single researcher," said
<PERSON>Watson</PERSON>. "This guy stood so far apart from the others. He not only had a good
idea every day, he acted on them, reduced them to practice.";    If <PERSON>Mr. Bell</PERSON>
had good ideas in lasers, he also had ideas that helped the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
explore outer space. One of his discoveries at <PERSON>Varian</PERSON> led to the development
of the compact atomic clock used on the Apollo moon mission. The research is
on permanent display in the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution's Museum of Science &amp;
Technology.</ORGANIZATION>;    Earlier, he participated in a definitive measurement of the
lifetime of the subatomic particle mu-meson while with the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian Atomic
Energy Project.</ORGANIZATION>;    <PERSON>Mr. Bell</PERSON> left <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in <DATE>1971</DATE> to realize a dream. He
managed the restoration and operation of the old <ORGANIZATION>Denver &amp; Rio Grande</ORGANIZATION>
narrow-gauge steam railroad between <LOCATION>Chama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Antonito</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>, now
known as the <ORGANIZATION>Cumbres &amp; Toltec Scenic Railroad.</ORGANIZATION>;    Before he began slowing
down, <PERSON>Mr. Bell</PERSON> returned to <LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION> to co-found one more high-tech firm,
<ORGANIZATION>Quanta-Ray Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Mountain View</LOCATION>; started another laser firm, <ORGANIZATION>Lasertechnics
Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>; and started still another laser research and development
firm in <LOCATION>Hyde Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah.</LOCATION>;    For much of his career, colleagues assumed he was
"<PERSON>Dr. Bell</PERSON>," but he never formally went beyond the 10th grade, <PERSON>Watson</PERSON> said. In
the <DATE>late 1980s</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Utah State University</ORGANIZATION> conferred a honorary doctor of science
degree on him.;     <PERSON>W. Earl Bell</PERSON>; (box)Born: <DATE>April 2, 1921</DATE>, <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION>,
Ontario.; (box)Died: <DATE>May 24, 1991</DATE>, <LOCATION>Hyde Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah.</LOCATION>; (box)Survived by: Wife,
<PERSON>Diane</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Hyde Park</LOCATION>; former wife, <PERSON>Betty</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Jerome</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>; sons, <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ross</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Jerome</LOCATION>; four grandchildren; two brothers and two sisters, all in <LOCATION>Canada.</LOCATION>;
(box)Services: Private memorial held at <LOCATION>Hyde Park</LOCATION>. Cremation. Ashes
distributed along the <ORGANIZATION>Cumbres &amp; Toltec Scenic Railroad</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910606  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  728  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday June 6, 1991
00158047,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-20606 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpjst012__l94039" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-JST-94-012-L </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Japan </ABS>
<DATE1>   5 January 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> Lasers, Sensors, Optics </F>
<H3> <TI>   NEC Semiconductor Laser Sets Record With Lowest Oscillation </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    NEC Semiconductor Laser Sets Record With Lowest Oscillation </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Current 

<FÊP=102>   94P60104A <ORGANIZATION>Tokyo NIKKEI SANGYO SHIMBUN</ORGANIZATION> in Japanese 5 Jan 94 p 
5 -- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<FÊP=103> 94P60104A </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> NIKKEI SANGYO SHIMBUN </F>
<FÊP=105>  Japanese </F>
CSO 

  [Text] <ORGANIZATION>NEC</ORGANIZATION> has developed a new type of laser element whose 
current required for laser oscillation is the smallest in the 
world. Pulsed radiation at room temperature with a current 
[threshold] value of 190 microamperes was achieved and this 
broke the previous world record. By way of comparison, this is 
less than one-tenth of the current used by conventional elements 
and it means a large reduction in electrical power for 
semiconductor lasers. The new element is also structured to 
accommodate high density integration and it can be useful for 
the realization of such things as super high speed optical 
computers, which use optical signals to process information, and 
optical circuitry devices. 
  The developed element is a type of surface-emission laser 
which emits radiation in a direction perpendicular to the 
substrate of the semiconductor. It emits infrared laser 
radiation at a wavelength of about 1 micron. The structure is 
unique in that the active radiation layer is sandwiched on both 
sides by multilayered semiconductor films. One side of the 
multilayered film is finely cut into a cylindrical shape. The 
diameter of the cylindrical part is 5 microns and the height is 
4 microns. 
  The multilayered film plays the role of a reflecting mirror 
for laser oscillation and by designing the thickness of one 
layer so that it is equal to the size of the wavelength, 
radiation loss is considerably limited. The conventional film 
layer has a margin of error of around <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> but <ORGANIZATION>NEC</ORGANIZATION>, by 
successfully establishing conditions for molecular beam crystal 
growth technology [molecular beam epitaxy], held it down to less 
than <PERCENT>0.3 percent</PERCENT>. Moreover, by using a cylindrical structure, 
the radiation is efficiently confined inside it, and a reduction 
of the current value necessary for laser oscillation was 
achieved. 
  It was experimentally confirmed that the new element began 
oscillation at 190 microamperes and, at 2 milliamperes, there 
was an optical output of 50 microwatts. The world's smallest 
previous semiconductor oscillation current value was 250 
microamperes. However, the element holding the world record was 
a conventional type that oscillates in a direction horizontal to 
the substrate and integration was difficult. Basically, since 
the newly developed element is a surface emission-type, it can 
be integrated and manufactured just like an ordinary transistor. 
  Currently, the resistance of the element is large and the 
efficiency is low, making continuous oscillation impossible. The 
next step will be to make progress toward continuous oscillation 
and improvement in the efficiency. 
  The semiconductor laser element is mostly used by itself as 
an optical source for compact disks and optical communications. 
However, if multiple integration can be accomplished, its uses 
will be expanded. For example, there is a possibility for using 
it for such things as optical computers, which process imagery 
data without conversion into electrical signals, or as an 
optical source for high-speed optical circuitry which switches 
multiple signals. 
  When the operating current per semiconductor laser is high, 
large electric power is necessary and integration is difficult. 
In order to make integration practical, the problem has been 
that of how to reduce the value of the oscillation current. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47483 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust013___94036" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-013 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   23 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Resonator for Technological YAG:Nd Laser </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Resonator for Technological YAG:Nd Laser </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   947J0042B St.Petersburg OPTIKA I SPEKTROSKOPIYA in Russian 
Vol. 76 No. 4, Apr. 94 (manuscript received 21 Oct. 93) pp. </F>



<TEXT>
667-670 
<FÊP=103> 947J0042B </F>
<FÊP=104>  <ORGANIZATION>St.Petersburg OPTIKA</ORGANIZATION> I <ORGANIZATION>SPEKTROSKOPIYA </F>
<FÊP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>A.V. Gorlanov</PERSON>, <LOCATION>S.A. Dimakov</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.I. Klimentyev</LOCATION>, </F>
<PERSON>I.B. Orlova</PERSON>, and <ORGANIZATION>N.A. Sventsitskaya, State Institute of Optics</ORGANIZATION> 
imeni <LOCATION>S.I. Vavilov</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>St.Petersburg</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 621.373:535] 
  [Abstract] An unstable resonator is proposed for the 
LIT-100 commercial YAG:Nd laser. The active medium of this laser 
consists of two cylindrical YAG:Nd rods 100 mm long and 6.3 mm 
in diameter, a thermal lens being induced in each. They are now 
placed each inside a single-lamp ellipsoidal reflector-luminaire 
and each pumped with a 24 A - 150 Hz current supplying a power 
of 5.5 kW. These luminaires are very energy-efficient but, owing 
to multimode radiation emission by the active medium, they form 
a widely divergent radiation beam. Stable resonators in the form 
of long planar cavities minimize the beam divergence, but with 
an attendant loss of power caused by distortions of higher 
orders than those due to formation of the thermal lenses in the 
active medium. Unstable resonators operating on the negative 
branch of the stability curve are known to minimize the beam 
divergence with minimum energy loss. Two variants of such a 
resonator have been designed and tested. The telescopic 
resonator providing an M= -1.7 magnification has a cavity formed 
by two concave mirrors with respectively 0.67 m and 0.4 m radii 
of curvature, the latter having a 3.6 mm diameter. The focus of 
each mirror coincides with the focus of the nearest to it 
thermal lens, the two thermal lenses having the same focal 
length and the distance between them being equal to twice that 
focal length. This resonator forms a radiation beam similar to 
that formed by a ``cat's eye'' reflector and not much better 
than that of the LIT-100 laser. The other resonator has a cavity 
formed by two plane total-reflection back mirrors and an exit 
mirror with a hole smaller than 6.3 mm in diameter. The image of 
this hole, formed by the two thermal intracavity lenses, 
coincides with it and the radiation beam thus exits through it 
with hardly any loss of power. Such a resonator with 
self-imaging of the exit hole rendered the best performance when 
its critical dimensions were: 1. diameter of exit hole d= 5.2 
mm, 2. focal length of thermal lenses f= 1 m, 3. distance from 
focus of the thermal lens before the exit mirror to the nearest 
back mirror L= 0.74 m. With this resonator the laser delivered a 
power of 160 W (80 W per rod) in a beam with a 1.6 mrad 
divergence angle (at <PERCENT>86%</PERCENT> maximum intensity level). 
Figures 3; 
tables 1; references 6. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-66322 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpcst008___94028" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-CST-94-008 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  China </ABS>
<DATE1>   24 May 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> Science &amp; Technology </F>
<F P=101> Lasers, Sensors, Optics </F>
<H3> <TI>   Nonlinear Processes From Interaction of 1.053 </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Nonlinear Processes From Interaction of 1.053 </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
?m   Laser With Hohlraum Targets 

<FÊP=102> 40100059A <LOCATION>Chengdu</LOCATION> QIANG JIGUANG YU LIZI SHU [HIGH-POWER 
LASER AND PARTICLE BEAMS] in Chinese Vol 6 No 1, Feb 94 pp 5-15 </F>

<FÊP=103> 40100059A </F>
<FÊP=104>  <LOCATION>Chengdu</LOCATION> QIANG JIGUANG YU LIZI SHU [HIGH-POWER 
LASER AND PARTICLE BEAMS] </F>

<FÊP=105>  Chinese </F>
CSO 

<FÊP=106> [English abstract of article by <LOCATION>Mei Qiyong</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Zhao Xuewei</PERSON>, et </F>
al. of <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Institute of Nuclear Physics</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Chemistry</ORGANIZATION>, No 
77, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 525, <LOCATION>Chengdu</LOCATION>, 610003; MS received 20 <DATE>Oct 92</DATE>, 
revised 20 Aug 93] 
  [Text] Abundant nonlinear processes may be produced in 
submillimeter-size hohlraum targets by 1.053 ?m laser light 
with duration of 1 ns and energy of 300-600 J. In experiments, 
Stimulated Brillouin Scattering (SBS) and Stimulated Raman 
Scattering (SRS) were directly measured, and Resonance 
Absorption (RA), Two-Plasmon Decay (TPD), and Ion Acoustic Decay 
(IAD) were observed indirectly. The experimental results show 
that <ORGANIZATION>SBS</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>SRS</ORGANIZATION> are the dominant nonlinear processes in cavity; 
they can scatter about <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the incident laser energy. 
Electron plasma waves stimulated by nonlinear processes such as 
<ORGANIZATION>SRS</ORGANIZATION>, TPD, RA, and <ORGANIZATION>IAD</ORGANIZATION> are the sources of suprathermal electron 
generation. Our research indicates that <ORGANIZATION>SRS</ORGANIZATION> is the chief process 
for electron plasma-wave generation in hohlraum targets, and it 
can produce suprathermal electrons with a total energy about <PERCENT>10 
percent</PERCENT> of incident laser energy. Because spectra of nonlinear 
process scattering light are closely related to the plasma 
state, we can obtain information about the plasma state through 
intensive measurement and analysis of these spectra of the 
scattering light. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-24493 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust006___94024" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-006 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   09 March 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> ELECTRONICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Multiplexed Fiber-Optic Sensors with Autodyne Detection </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  947K0035F Moscow KVANTOVAYA ELEKTRONIKA in Russian Vol 20, 
No 9, Sep 93 pp 903-913 </F>

<F P=103> 947K0035F </F>
<F P=104>  Moscow KVANTOVAYA ELEKTRONIKA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Russian </F>
Article Type:<ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>V. T. Potapov</PERSON>, <PERSON>A. M. Mamedov</PERSON>, <PERSON>S. V. Shatalin</PERSON>, <PERSON>R. </F>
V. Yushkaytis</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 681.586:681.7.068] 
  [Abstract] A method is proposed for construction of 
multiplex systems of fiber-optical interferometric sensors 
entirely without optical directional couplers. In these systems, 
the signal waves are formed by reflecting a portion of the 
radiation, propagating in the fiber lightguide, from semi- 
transparent mirrors, built within it, or from the internal 
nonhomogenieties of the lightguide itself. When they arrive back 
into the laser cavity, the lasing amplitude changes. Small 
changes in the length of the optical path in the lightguide, 
caused by the physical effects, which are being examined, can be 
detected by controlling the laser output. Theoretical 
relationships are developed for a frequency-modulated laser with 
optical feedback and the carrier frequency modulation method for 
multiplex sensors is discussed. Modulation characteristics of a 
He-Ne laser, the bistability of the longitudinal modes are 
examined and the effect of cross-talk is estimated. Autodyne 
multiplex sensors including underwater acoustics antenna and 
temperature sensors are also briefly discussed. The experimental 
study of frequency-scanned He-Ne-laser operating with different 
lightguide systems demonstrated that an autodyne detection is 
suitable for application with distributed sensors employing a 
Rayleigh scattering signal. Figures 9,references 12: 4 Russian, 
8 Western 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06313234 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06313234 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COMPUTER; RESEARCH; FIRST; TELEPHONE; COMPANY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Scientists at AT&amp;T's Bell Laboratories announced Thursday that they had
produced the world's smallest lasers, an advance that one day may simplify the
manufacture of a new generation of ultrafast computers controlled by beams of
light.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TINY LASERS MAY SPEED UP COMPUTERS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The same technology may also have other promising applications, including
building sensitive artificial-vision systems that could operate in a manner
similar to the human retina, researchers said.;   The <ORGANIZATION>Bell Labs</ORGANIZATION> research team
presented its work <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> at the annual meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>Optical
Society of America.</ORGANIZATION>;   Part of the report's significance is that the new
lasers -- which look like microscopic thumbtacks whose round tops emit
piercing beams of light -- can be made in arrays by the same process that is
used to make modern semiconductors.;   Thus the researchers said they believed
that optical computers, which exist today only in theory, might some day be
able to follow the same falling cost curves that have been emblematic of the
microelectronics industry.;   "We're hoping that when you get to computing
speeds above a billion cycles per second that optics will play a major part,"
said <PERSON>Richart Slusher</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Bell Labs Optical Physics Research
Department</ORGANIZATION>. "The key is whether these technologies will be cost effective.";  
The new lasers are made by alternating one or more layers of indium gallium
arsenide with layers of indium gallium arsenide phosphide. The thin layers
that constitute the laser head are only 400 atoms thick. The researchers then
etch away some material to leave the tiny thumbtack-shaped structures that can
emit laser light in several directions.;   So far, prototypes of tiny lasers
that are 2, 5 and 10 microns in diameter have been manufactured using the new
process. By comparison, a human hair is approximately 75 microns in diameter
and a conventional laser beam used to play a compact disk player is 250
microns in diameter.;   The new semiconductor laser was designed by <PERSON>Sam
McCall</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Bell Labs</ORGANIZATION> physicist.;   The researchers said that they would now
attempt a second key technological step: designing photon "wires" to guide the
beams emitted by the lasers.;   By building circuits of optical lasers and
other components, the researchers said they hoped to be able to fabricate
systems that would permit computer designers to create reliable connections
between computer chips in high-speed systems.;   The new lasers operate at
extremely low power levels and therefore would be well-suited as light sources
for future optical switches, the researchers said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911108  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  409  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, November 8, 1991
00313234,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-40421 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpest006__l94039" </HT>

