<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900502-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-02-90 1940EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-FarnsworthStatue     05-02 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Farnsworth Statue,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>``Father of Television'' Honored With U.S. Capitol Statue</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY ARNOLD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American inventor <PERSON>Philo T. Farnsworth</PERSON>, a
pioneer of television, was accorded what many believe was long
overdue glory <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> when a 7-foot bronze likeness of the
electronics genius was dedicated in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Capitol.
   With his 81-year-old widow, <PERSON>Elma Farnsworth</PERSON>, looking on, the
inventor was extolled as the father of television and his statue
was placed in the pantheon of famous Americans of the <ORGANIZATION>Capitol</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>National Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I think it's an honor long overdue,'' said <PERSON>Bruce Barnson</PERSON>, who
headed a commission that raised <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> to place <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> near
the likeness of a better-known <ORGANIZATION>Utahn</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I want to thank you all from the bottom of my heart ... for
this great honor,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Farnsworth</PERSON> told an audience at the Capitol
dedication.
   The ceremony included songs from the school choir from
<ORGANIZATION>Ridgecrest Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Butler</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>. Students from
<LOCATION>Ridgecrest</LOCATION> started the drive for the statue after they surveyed
<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> residents and recommended to the state legislature that
<PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> be the second <DATE>Utahn</DATE> honored in <LOCATION>Statuary Hall</LOCATION>.
   The statue by <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> sculptor <PERSON>James Avanti</PERSON> depicts <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>
holding an image dissector tube that was the heart of the
electronic television system that he first conceived as a
15-year-old high school student in <DATE>1922</DATE>.
   Farnsworth is called in an inscription at on the base of the
statue the ``Father of Television.''
   Farnsworth gained the first patent on his system, the precursor
of today's television, in <DATE>1934</DATE> after winning a patent battle with
the powerful <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> corporation, which later paid him <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> to
use his many patents. Most history books list <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> only as
one of many early pioneers of television.
   He died in <DATE>1971</DATE> while working on fusion research. He had
contributed more than 160 inventions, including radar and the
electron microscope. He was named to the <ORGANIZATION>National Inventors Hall of
Fame</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   Each state is allowed to honor two of its famous citizens with
statues in <ORGANIZATION>Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION>. But <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> had placed only Young in the
hall.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890605-0142 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-05-89 1147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--PhiloFarnsworth Adv08   06-05 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Philo Farnsworth, Adv 08,0763</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv08</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, June 8, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Decades Later, TV's Inventor is Focus of New Attention</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK WARBIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIGBY, Idaho (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fifty years after commercial television made
its flickering debut at the <LOCATION>New York World</LOCATION>'s Fair, the passion of a
gangly teen-ager who made it possible is finally being requited.
   ``It's high time,'' said <PERSON>Elma</PERSON> ``Pem'' <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>, who for 44
years was sounding board, sweetheart, lab assistant and wife to
<PERSON>Philo Taylor Farnsworth</PERSON>.
   But she wasn't his first love. Television was.
   <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>1971</DATE>, was 15 years old in <DATE>1922</DATE> when he
diagrammed his idea for an electronic TV system on a high school
blackboard in this eastern <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> farming town.
   Chemistry teacher <PERSON>Justin Tolman</PERSON>'s memory of that drawing,
including the first description of an electronic ``image
dissector'' TV camera tube, helped <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> win the first in a
series of patent battles with <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> over early TV technology in the
<DATE>1930s</DATE>.
   But if <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> won the battles, <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> won the war. Outside
<LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> and his native <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, most history and reference books place
him on the sidelines among ``other pioneers'' who contributed to
television's development.
   Most of the glory went to <PERSON>Vladimir Zworykin</PERSON>, the
Russian-American inventor who developed the iconoscope and
kinescope during a career primarily with <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>, who
received some 160 patents, finally was inducted into the <ORGANIZATION>National
Inventors Hall</ORGANIZATION> of Fame in <DATE>1984</DATE> _ seven years after <PERSON>Zworykin</PERSON>.
   ``We're going to set the record straight across the country,''
said <PERSON>Kent Farnsworth</PERSON>, the inventor's son.
   Utah Gov. <PERSON>Norm Bangerter</PERSON> proclaimed <DATE>May 2</DATE> ``<PERSON>Philo T. Farnsworth
Day</PERSON>,'' kicking off a fund-raising effort for a bronze statue of
<ORGANIZATION>Farnsworth in National Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION>. It is scheduled for placement
<DATE>May 2, 1990</DATE> in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Capitol.
   <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>, who was born in the southwestern <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> town of
<LOCATION>Beaver</LOCATION>, was picked for the honor by the <ORGANIZATION>Utah Legislature</ORGANIZATION> at the
urging of a <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> elementary school class that researched
a number of famous Utahns.
   ``People kind of like a guy who's an underdog,'' said <PERSON>Bruce
Barnson</PERSON>, principal at <ORGANIZATION>Ridgecrest Elementary</ORGANIZATION>. ``Here's a guy who was
brilliant, came up with television and really got nothing out of
it.''
   In <PERSON>Rigby</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Farnsworth Television Group</ORGANIZATION> is raising money for a
TV museum to highlight his achievements. There already are signs on
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 20 leading into the town of 2,600 proclaiming <PERSON>Rigby</PERSON> the
``Birthplace of Television.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Community Center</ORGANIZATION>, in a former bank building, has a
collection of <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> memorabilia in what used to be a vault.
Last year it featured the Emmy he won posthumously in <DATE>1978</DATE> for his
contributions to TV technology.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Farnsworth</PERSON>, now 81, recently wrote an essay about her
husband for People magazine, criticizing RCA chief <PERSON>David Sarnoff</PERSON>'s
effort to ``control the television industry just like he'd
controlled radio.''
   That theme is explored further in a book <PERSON>Mrs. Farnsworth</PERSON> hopes
to publish titled, ``Distant Vision: Romance and Discovery on an
Invisible Frontier.''
   She recounts how the financial strain of legal disputes with <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION>
forced the <ORGANIZATION>Farnsworth Television &amp; Radio Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to the verge of
bankruptcy, and finally to sell out to <ORGANIZATION>International Telephone &amp;
Telegraph</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1949</DATE>.
   But <PERSON>Edward W. Herold</PERSON>, a former RCA researcher and retired
director of the electronics research laboratory at the <ORGANIZATION>David
Sarnoff Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, said jabs at <LOCATION>Sarnoff</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Zworykin</PERSON> or <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> are misplaced.
   ``I think <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> got plenty of credit from the historians,
more than he deserves. He was really a genius; a really bright
guy,'' <PERSON>Herold</PERSON> said.
   ``<PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> was a competitor, and a good competitor... But I
would say he was eventually overwhelmed by the number of brilliant
people we had at RCA.''
   <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>, who continued research in physics after selling the
business, developed an early electron microscope to study the
uniformity of the phosphor coating on tubes in the image dissector.
His work also helped in development of night-vision scopes, radar
and an incubator for premature babies.
   He was at <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young University</ORGANIZATION> at the time of his death,
working on an area of physics that science has yet to conquer _
nuclear fusion.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Farnsworth</PERSON> said new attention to his life should be an
example to a new generation of discoverers. ``<PERSON>Phil</PERSON> was told
television was impossible by everyone he talked to about it. I'm
hoping this will encourage young people to stick by their guns and
not be dissuaded by anyone.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for June 8</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900425-0021
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900425-0021.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   And Let's Not Forget the Genius
   Who Invented Remote Control
   ----
   By Carrie Dolan
</HL>
<DATE>
04/25/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<LP>
   If Utahans have their way, Philo T. Farnsworth will become
a household name.
   Each state can place statues of two local heroes in the
U.S. Capitol. When a class of Utah fifth-graders learned
their state had only one -- of Mormon leader Brigham Young --
they sought a candidate for the other place of honor. Locals
overwhelmingly chose Mr. Farnsworth, an inventor who died in
1971 (one of Brigham Young's wives was runner-up).
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Utahans consider <PERSON>Mr. Farnsworth</PERSON> the "father of
television," the governor's spokeswoman says. "He's finally
getting his just recognition. In his lifetime, he wasn't
really recognized." A statue of <PERSON>Mr. Farnsworth</PERSON>, holding the
image-dissector tube he invented, will be unveiled <DATE>May 2</DATE> in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Utahans claim <ORGANIZATION>RCA Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which helped make TV a success,
stole much of the glory for inventing it. <PERSON>Vladimir Zworykin</PERSON>,
an <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> employee, "was working on the concept at the same
time," says <PERSON>Bruce Barnson</PERSON>, chairman of the <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> statue
committee. "He went to <PERSON>Philo</PERSON>'s lab, and <PERSON>Philo</PERSON> told him the
whole thing."
   Legal battles ensued until the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, when RCA (now a unit
of <ORGANIZATION>General Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION>) paid to cross license <PERSON>Mr.
Farnsworth</PERSON>'s patents, the first time the company had ever
licensed a patent. "The chief patent lawyer supposedly cried
when <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> had to purchase the license," says <PERSON>Elliot Sivowitch</PERSON>,
of the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution</ORGANIZATION>'s division of electricity and
physics.
   Unfortunately, <PERSON>Mr. Farnsworth</PERSON>'s patents "were too early,"
says his 82-year-old widow, <PERSON>Elma</PERSON> (her husband's first
TV-picture transmission was of her in <DATE>1929</DATE>). World War II
sidelined the infant industry, and "his patents started to
expire a few years after commercial television took off."
Worse, she claims, "historians went to <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> and got history
from their PR people. Phil was largely ignored."
   "<PERSON>Philo T. Farnsworth</PERSON> is a rather controversial issue,"
concedes <PERSON>William Boss</PERSON>, a retired <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> executive and consultant
to the <ORGANIZATION>Electronic Industries Association</ORGANIZATION>. "A lot of people
were working a long time" creating television.
   Though "<PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> did crucial experimental work," it's
tough to name one inventor of a complex technology, says <PERSON>Mr.
Sivowitch</PERSON>. "Generally speaking, when someone says they're
first, if you look hard enough, you'll find someone who's
more first." The British, for instance, cite <PERSON>John Logie Baird</PERSON>
as TV's inventor.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900503-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-03-90 0520EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-WashingtoninBrief     05-03 0668</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Washington in Brief,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Authorizes Five-Year Plan For Supercollider</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> has voted to authorize the
superconducting supercollider but refused to guarantee <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>'
investment in the <MONEY>$7.4 billion</MONEY> project.
   The bill, approved 309-109 <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, allows the <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Energy</ORGANIZATION> to build the particle accelerator near <LOCATION>Waxahachie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Costs above <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> would be left to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which has pledged
<MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>, and other sources, including foreign investors.
   House members by a 256-163 vote approved an amendment calling
for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government to return <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' investment if the <ORGANIZATION>Energy
Department</ORGANIZATION> cancels the project before <DATE>October 1995</DATE>.
   Rep. <PERSON>Dennis Eckart</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ohio</LOCATION>, said the vote did not assure
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> would fully fund the project. Spending will have to be
approved later during <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>' annual appropriations process.
   The bill was sent to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, but the supercollider will not
likely be authorized by the full chamber. An aide to <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd
Bentsen</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Texas</LOCATION>, said senators probably will act on the collider
during appropriations.
   The supercollider is a 54-mile underground ring in which streams
of protons guided by electromagnets would be hurled at almost the
speed of light until they smash together and break into even
smaller particles.
   Scientists say the supercollider would recreate the physical
state in the moment after the Big Bang, which some believe was the
beginning of the universe.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Administration Wants to Link Pay to Performance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> has voted to authorize the
superconducting supercollider but refused to guarantee <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>'
investment in the <MONEY>$7.4 billion</MONEY> project.
   The bill, approved 309-109 <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, allows the <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Energy</ORGANIZATION> to build the particle accelerator near <LOCATION>Waxahachie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Costs above <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> would be left to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which has pledged
<MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>, and other sources, including foreign investors.
   House members by a 256-163 vote approved an amendment calling
for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government to return <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' investment if the <ORGANIZATION>Energy
Department</ORGANIZATION> cancels the project before <DATE>October 1995</DATE>.
   Rep. <PERSON>Dennis Eckart</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ohio</LOCATION>, said the vote did not assure
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> would fully fund the project. Spending will have to be
approved later during <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>' annual appropriations process.
   The bill was sent to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, but the supercollider will not
likely be authorized by the full chamber. An aide to <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd
Bentsen</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Texas</LOCATION>, said senators probably will act on the collider
during appropriations.
   The supercollider is a 54-mile underground ring in which streams
of protons guided by electromagnets would be hurled at almost the
speed of light until they smash together and break into even
smaller particles.
   Scientists say the supercollider would recreate the physical
state in the moment after the Big Bang, which some believe was the
beginning of the universe.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>`Father of Television' Honored With US Capitol Statue</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> has voted to authorize the
superconducting supercollider but refused to guarantee <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>'
investment in the <MONEY>$7.4 billion</MONEY> project.
   The bill, approved 309-109 <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, allows the <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Energy</ORGANIZATION> to build the particle accelerator near <LOCATION>Waxahachie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Costs above <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> would be left to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which has pledged
<MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>, and other sources, including foreign investors.
   House members by a 256-163 vote approved an amendment calling
for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government to return <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' investment if the <ORGANIZATION>Energy
Department</ORGANIZATION> cancels the project before <DATE>October 1995</DATE>.
   Rep. <PERSON>Dennis Eckart</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ohio</LOCATION>, said the vote did not assure
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> would fully fund the project. Spending will have to be
approved later during <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>' annual appropriations process.
   The bill was sent to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, but the supercollider will not
likely be authorized by the full chamber. An aide to <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd
Bentsen</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Texas</LOCATION>, said senators probably will act on the collider
during appropriations.
   The supercollider is a 54-mile underground ring in which streams
of protons guided by electromagnets would be hurled at almost the
speed of light until they smash together and break into even
smaller particles.
   Scientists say the supercollider would recreate the physical
state in the moment after the Big Bang, which some believe was the
beginning of the universe.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880319-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-19-88 0015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Inventors     03-19 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Inventors,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Being Names To Inventors Hall Of Fame</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Inventors whose developments have affected
nearly every American in one way or another, and led to major
changes in society, will be added to the <ORGANIZATION>National Inventors Hall of
Fame</ORGANIZATION>.
   Special ceremonies have been scheduled for <DATE>March 27</DATE> to honor the
developers of oral contraceptives, computer memory, television
receivers and elevators, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Patent Office</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   The four new members will be inducted in ceremonies at the
<ORGANIZATION>Patent Office</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Arlington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va</LOCATION>. They bring to 72 the membership in
the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION>, which was opened in <DATE>1973</DATE> with a plaque honoring
<PERSON>Thomas A. Edison</PERSON>.
   New members of the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame are:
   _<PERSON>Elisha Graves Otis</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Halifax</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>, who patented the elevator
in <DATE>1861</DATE>.
memory operates.
   Graves becomes the latest inductee selected for development of
products that have become nearly universal.
   Others whose work is similarly well known include <PERSON>Edison</PERSON> for his
electric light, the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers for airplanes, <PERSON>Charles Goodyear</PERSON>
for vulcanized rubber and <ORGANIZATION>Rudolf Diesel</ORGANIZATION> for the internal combustion
engine.
   Colton joins <PERSON>Carl Djerassi</PERSON>, an Austrian-born chemist who was
inducted into the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame in <DATE>1978</DATE> for his pioneering work on
oral contraceptives.
   Parker's television receiver glows in nearly every American home
today, and in the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame he joins <PERSON>William D. Coolidge</PERSON>, who
invented the vacuum tube; <PERSON>Vladimir Zworykin</PERSON>, who developed the
cathode ray tube used for television pictures and <PERSON>Philo T.
Farnsworth</PERSON>, who developed the scanning, contrast and focusing
systems for television.
   In the development of computers, An Wang joins several other
pioneers already in the Hall of Fame. They include calculating
machine pioneer <PERSON>William Seward Burroughs</PERSON>; <PERSON>George R. Stibitz</PERSON> who
developed modern complex computer systems; <PERSON>Robert N. Noyce</PERSON>, a
pioneer in developing semiconductor devices; <PERSON>Jack S. Kilby</PERSON> who
developed miniaturized circuits and <PERSON>Jay W. Forrester</PERSON>, a leader in
early digital information storage.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061090-0213 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 231872 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 10, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 10; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1086 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AMERICA'S HEROES: MARBLE AND BRONZE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES HILLINGER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Each year, 1.5 million visitors view the bronze and marble statues that stand 
throughout the Capitol waiting to be recognized. 
</P>
<P>
Some are well-known. Many are not. 
</P>
<P>
Since <DATE>1864</DATE>, each state has been entitled to donate statues of two of its most 
distinguished deceased citizens for permanent exhibit in the <LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Once a state legislature decides who is to be honored, a statue is created and 
accepted by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for a place in the <ORGANIZATION>National Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION> -- <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s 
hall of fame. 
</P>
<P>
"People are always anxious to see the statues from their state. But often 
they're surprised and disappointed because they have no idea who (the people) 
depicted in the statues are," said <PERSON>Barbara Wolanin</PERSON>, 46, curator of <ORGANIZATION>Statuary 
Hall</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>1978</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s statues, both dedicated on <DATE>March 1, 1930</DATE>, are of a minister and a 
priest. It is the only state with two statues of clergy. 
</P>
<P>
Most visitors recognize Father <PERSON>Junipero Serra</PERSON>, the Franciscan priest who 
established nine <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> missions before he died in <DATE>1784</DATE>. Father <PERSON>Serra</PERSON>'s 
bronze likeness holds a little mission in his left hand, and in the right, a 
cross, held high above his head. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Thomas Starr King</PERSON> is not so familiar. "What did he do?" Californians typically 
ask when they see the statue. 
</P>
<P>
King, a Unitarian minister, came to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in <DATE>1860</DATE> from <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> to serve as 
pastor of the <ORGANIZATION>First Unitarian Church of San Francisco</ORGANIZATION>. It was during the Civil 
War and many Californians favored the Confederacy. Of the more than 100 
newspapers in the state, only 24 supported <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"King traveled throughout <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> championing the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> cause. He is 
remembered as the man whose matchless oratory kept <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in the union," 
curator <PERSON>Wolanin</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
King lived in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> only four years before dying at age 40 in <DATE>1864</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Of the 95 statues from 50 states, 14 are of religious leaders, including Father 
<PERSON>Damien</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>), who devoted his life to lepers on <LOCATION>Molokai</LOCATION>; Father <ORGANIZATION>Kino</ORGANIZATION> 
(<LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>), a Jesuit missionary, and <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>), the <ORGANIZATION>Mormon Church</ORGANIZATION> 
leader. 
</P>
<P>
Five states -- <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> -- have 
contributed only one statue each. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>May 2</DATE>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> became the latest state to present its second statue, a 7-foot-7 
bronze likeness of lanky <PERSON>Philo T. Farnsworth</PERSON> (1906-1971), known as the "Father 
of Television." The statue shows <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> holding one of his first 
cathode-ray tubes. He transmitted his first electronic TV picture in <DATE>1927</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Students at <ORGANIZATION>Ridgecrest Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Butler</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, under the guidance of 
Principal <PERSON>Bruce Barnson</PERSON>, led the effort to put the <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> statue in the 
<LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In a statewide poll conducted by students, residents favored <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> over 20 
other Utahans, including <PERSON>Eliza Snow</PERSON>, a poet and wife of <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young; Mormon 
Church</ORGANIZATION> leader <PERSON>Ezra Taft Benson</PERSON>; hotelier <PERSON>J. Willard Marriott</PERSON>, and heavyweight 
boxing champion <PERSON>Jack Dempsey</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Among those present for <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Norman Bangerter</PERSON>'s unveiling of the statue 
was the inventor's 81-year-old widow, <PERSON>Elma</PERSON> (Pem) <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Three statues are of Presidents: <PERSON>George Washington</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Andrew Jackson</PERSON> 
(<LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>James A. Garfield</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>). Four are of vice presidents, 36 of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
senators, 23 of <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> members, 30 of governors and 32 of military heroes. (Some 
held more than one of these titles.) Six statues honor women: <PERSON>Dr. Florence 
Sabin</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>), author of the "Sabin Health Laws" that modernized <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>'s 
public health system; <PERSON>Frances Willard</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>), founder of the Women's <ORGANIZATION>Christian 
Temperance Union</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Marie Sanford</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>), educator and champion of women's 
rights; <PERSON>Jeannette Rankin</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>), the nation's first congresswoman; Mother 
<PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>), a Catholic nun who contributed to the fields of health care, 
education and social work, and <PERSON>Esther Hobart Morris</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>), the first woman to 
hold judicial office in the nation. 
</P>
<P>
six physicians. A king is here -- Kamehameha (<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>), and a famed cowboy 
artist -- <PERSON>Charley Russell</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>). Oklahoma honors two American Indians: 
Sequoya, inventor of the Cherokee alphabet, and <PERSON>Will Rogers</PERSON>, humorist, 
newspaper columnist and movie star. 
</P>
<P>
In keeping with <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON>' famous advice to "Always keep an eye on <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to see 
what they're up to," his statue is the only one facing the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> chamber. 
</P>
<P>
The feet of many of the statues gleam from constant rubbing, "for good luck," 
by visitors. Will <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> has the shiniest feet of all. 
</P>
<P>
There are statues of the president and vice president of the <LOCATION>Confederacy</LOCATION>, 
<PERSON>Jefferson Davis</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>Alexander Hamilton Stephens</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>), respectively, as 
well as of "Father of Refrigeration" <PERSON>John Gorrie</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>), and steamboat inventor 
<PERSON>Robert Fulton</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>). 
</P>
<P>
America's best-known historic figures are here as well: Henry Clay (<LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Huey 
Long</PERSON> (<LOCATION>La.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>William Jennings Bryan</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Daniel Webster</PERSON> (<LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Robert E. Lee</PERSON> 
(<LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Samuel Adams</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Roger Williams</PERSON> (<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>John C. Calhoun</PERSON> (<LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>), <LOCATION>Sam 
Houston</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Stephen Austin</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>), and <PERSON>Ethan Allen</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>). 
</P>
<P>
Some of the lesser known include <PERSON>Jabez Curry</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Uriah Rose</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Edmund 
K. Smith</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>George Shoup</PERSON> (Ida.), <PERSON>Samuel Kirkwood</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>), <PERSON>George Glick</PERSON> 
(<LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Zachariah Chandler</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Zebulon Vance</PERSON> (<LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>Jason Lee</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>). 
Most visitors to <PERSON>Statuary Hall</PERSON> have no idea who they were, the curator said. 
</P>
<P>
"Other people pass away who are much more famous than many in Statuary Hall, 
but the states are stuck with those selected at an earlier time," longtime 
Capitol guide <PERSON>Madeline Allen</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Statuary Hall is in a part of the Capitol completed in <DATE>1807</DATE>, a domed 
semicircular room with sandstone walls and breccia marble columns, a room that 
housed the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> until <DATE>1857</DATE>, when the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> moved to its 
present, larger chamber. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed a bill in <DATE>1864</DATE> to create the <ORGANIZATION>National Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION> to house 
two marble or bronze statues from each state "of deceased persons illustrious 
for their historic renown or for distinguished civic or military services." 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1870</DATE>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> contributed the first statue, Revolutionary War hero 
<PERSON>Nathaniel Greene</PERSON>. By the <DATE>turn of the century</DATE>, 23 were on exhibit. 
</P>
<P>
By <DATE>1933</DATE>, there were 65 statues crowded into <PERSON>Statuary Hall</PERSON>, and it became clear 
that the floor would not support any more. 
</P>
<P>
It was then decided to keep most of the collection in the hall and place the 
others in prominent sites throughout the <LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Although the statues no longer stand in the same room, this gathering of heroes 
-- famous or not -- continues to be called <ORGANIZATION>National Statuary Hall</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Visitors pass statue of John Peter Gabriel Muhlenberg, above, a 
Revolutionary War hero, in the National Statuary Hall. The statue of humorist 
and movie star Will Rogers, left, faces the House of Representatives. ; Photo, 
COLOR, States have been donating up to two statues of their most distinguished 
citizens, from George Washington to Sequoya to Zebulon Vance, to the Capitol's 
National Statuary Hall since 1870. California's statues of Thomas Starr King, 
above, and Father Junipero Serra were dedicated in 1930. CHARLES HILLINGER / 
Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Series 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
STATUES; MUSEUMS -- WASHINGTON DC; NATIONAL STATUARY HALL 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042990-0037 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 211152 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 29, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 33; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1111 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
YOUNGSTERS PICK UP ON POWER POLITICS IN UTAH; 
</P>
<P>
EDUCATION: A CREATIVE ELEMENTARY SCHOOL PRINCIPAL URGES HIS CHARGES TO COME UP 
WITH BENEFICIAL IDEAS AND TURN THEM INTO LAW. THEY SUCCEED ON A NUMBER OF 
FRONTS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By RICK ATKINSON, THE WASHINGTON POST 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SANDY CITY, Utah 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Bruce R. Barnson</PERSON> is an ample, suspender-wearing educator with unfashionably 
long sideburns and a beguiling belief that politics is too important to be left 
to adults. 
</P>
<P>
For nearly a decade, the elementary school principal has urged his 11- and 
12-year-old charges to get down and dirty in state politics. Come up with an 
idea to benefit the commonweal, Barnson tells them, then lobby relentlessly to 
ram it through the Legislature. 
</P>
<P>
Through cunning, manipulation of the media, moral righteousness and 
old-fashioned political muscle, the students have assembled a record that would 
be the envy of any Capitol Hill power broker: Among other triumphs, they have 
pushed through a mandatory seat-belt law and a resolution opposing nuclear 
waste dumping in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
This year, the children's crusade is going national by asking <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to 
extend <ORGANIZATION>Daylight Saving Time</ORGANIZATION> another week to give trick-or-treaters an extra 
hour of light on <LOCATION>Halloween</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Empowerment of the young comes easily in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, which is the most youthful state 
in the <LOCATION>Union</LOCATION> thanks to a Mormon zeal for big families. One-third of the state's 
1.7 million people are under 15; the median age in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> is 26, compared to 32 
nationwide. 
</P>
<P>
As the state's <DATE>1990</DATE> "Statistical Abstract" notes, "<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>'s young population has 
placed unprecedented demands on the state's public education system during the 
last decade." <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> has the nation's most crowded classrooms, with a 
student-teacher ratio of 25.4 to 1; teachers earn less than their counterparts 
in 43 other states, and <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> ranks 50th in average annual expenditure per 
student. 
</P>
<P>
For <PERSON>Barnson</PERSON>, who was named <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>'s most distinguished elementary principal two 
years ago, all those youngsters are not so much a problem as an opportunity. 
After growing up on a farm in southern <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, Barnson dropped out of college, 
did a stint in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>, then labored in an open-pit copper mine in <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>. 
Working the graveyard shift one night, he had a revelation -- that "only 
coyotes and prostitutes work these kinds of hours" -- and returned to school to 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1983</DATE>, three years after <PERSON>Barnson</PERSON> became principal at <ORGANIZATION>Ridgecrest Elementary 
School</ORGANIZATION>, his fifth-graders launched their first, modest "legislative project." 
<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, they realized, had a state motto, "Industry"; a state bird, the sea gull; 
a state song, "<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, We Love Thee"; even a state fish, the rainbow trout. One 
thing it didn't have was a state bug. In the <ORGANIZATION>Beehive State</ORGANIZATION>, the leading 
candidate was somewhat self-evident. 
</P>
<P>
Armed with statistics about the honey industry and the bee's value to 
agriculture, a dozen pint-sized lobbyists worked over the state <ORGANIZATION>Senate's Energy 
and Natural Resources Committee</ORGANIZATION>. As a school scrapbook later put it, "They also 
learned to deal with opposition and some ridicule." But when then-Gov. <PERSON>Scott 
Matheson</PERSON> signed SB216 into law, he called it "the bright spot of the session." 
</P>
<P>
A year later, the students returned to the <LOCATION>Statehouse</LOCATION> with a weightier issue; 
in a meeting with <PERSON>Matheson</PERSON>, they noted that <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> was one of only nine states 
with no "child safety restraint" law. The governor, having twice failed to pass 
seat-belt legislation, urged the children to "march right upstairs to the 
Legislature" and press the issue. 
</P>
<P>
They did that and more -- manning observation posts near the school to count 
how many auto occupants were wearing seat belts, raising <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> for a "buckle 
up" billboard campaign, and sending educational packets to other schools. Over 
bitter opposition from state senators, who warned darkly about trampling 
"parents' rights," a bill requiring mandatory belting for children under age 5 
passed the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> 21 to 5 and eventually became law. 
</P>
<P>
Nuclear waste came next. Noting that geologists had identified a subterranean 
salt dome in one of <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>'s national parks potentially suitable for a temporary 
storage site for radioactive matter, <ORGANIZATION>Barnson</ORGANIZATION>'s students conducted a public 
opinion poll on the issue in <LOCATION>Salt Lake County</LOCATION>. Not surprisingly -- nuclear 
waste is about as popular here as a contagious skin disease -- <PERCENT>85%</PERCENT> of the 
respondents opposed the idea. The Legislature passed, and the governor signed, 
a resolution reflecting that sentiment. 
</P>
<P>
Such exercises, the school scrapbook declares, "foster patriotism, free 
enterprise and involved citizenship," while suggesting "the value of individual 
influence." 
</P>
<P>
Students also learn a little bare-knuckled politics, as demonstrated in their 
most recent enterprise: placing the statue of a famous <DATE>Utahn</DATE> in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
Capitol. 
</P>
<P>
More than a century ago, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> authorized each state to erect statues of two 
native sons -- or daughters -- in the hallowed halls. In <DATE>1950</DATE>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Brigham 
Young</ORGANIZATION> joined the pantheon; <DATE>four years ago</DATE>, students at <LOCATION>Ridgecrest</LOCATION> concluded 
that the time had come to fill the second niche. They drafted a list of 21 
significant figures in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>'s history and asked 27 elementary schools around 
the state to list their favorites; a slightly smaller list was sent to 501 
homes here in <LOCATION>Sandy</LOCATION>, and the students conducted an informal survey at a 
downtown mall. 
</P>
<P>
The clear favorite was one <PERSON>Philo T. Farnsworth</PERSON>, an inventor who is considered 
the father of television. A bill supporting <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON>'s immortalization passed 
the <ORGANIZATION>Utah House</ORGANIZATION> and cleared a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> committee, but trouble appeared from an 
unexpected quarter: Advocates of hotel magnate <PERSON>J. Willard Marriott</PERSON>, a native 
son from northern <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, outmaneuvered the children by tabling and eventually 
killing the <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> bill. 
</P>
<P>
In the <DATE>'87</DATE>-'88 school year, Barnson's students tried again, only to see history 
begin to repeat itself. A <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> bill cleared committees in both chambers, 
but the <ORGANIZATION>Marriott</ORGANIZATION> forces, who wanted their own man in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, bottled up 
<PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Rules Committee</ORGANIZATION>. It was time for hardball. As the 
school scrapbook recounted, "The committee finally let it out when, at our 
request, the TV stations asked why our bill was being held." After some more 
skin-of-the-teeth maneuvering, the bill finally became law, and a statue of 
<PERSON>Philo T. Farnsworth</PERSON> will soon appear in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Capitol. 
</P>
<P>
Barnson, who moved to <ORGANIZATION>Silver Mesa Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> this year, is slightly 
pessimistic about congressional willingness to extend daylight saving time, 
although the <ORGANIZATION>Utah Legislature</ORGANIZATION> supports the idea. The junior lobbyists are 
trying to compile statistics on the number of children killed by automobiles at 
dusk on <LOCATION>Halloween</LOCATION>, but that has been a difficult task. Persuading the lawmakers 
on Capitol Hill to tinker with the national clock also seems a bit daunting. 
"Our only ally is reason," <PERSON>Barnson</PERSON> sighed, "and I'm not sure reason works in 
smoke-filled rooms." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900125-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-25-90 0932EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Inventors 1stLd-Writethru a0445 01-25 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Inventors, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0445,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>10 Inventors Announced for Hall of Fame</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Corrects spelling of Tuskegee in 5th graf, Carver, once; subs
11th graf, Hollerith invented, to give full name of IBM</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pioneering scientists <PERSON>George Washington Carver</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Percy F. Julian</PERSON> are the first blacks named to the <ORGANIZATION>National
Inventors Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION>.
   They were among 10 people, including the founders of two of the
nation's largest computer companies and the developers of a leading
ulcer medicine, chosen for the honor.
   They ``are the real heroes of our age,'' <PERSON>Jeffrey M. Samuel</PERSON>,
acting commissioner of Patents and Trademarks, said about those
chosen <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``They are the thinkers and the problem-solvers. They have
opened new doors and pioneered new frontiers in science and
technology.''
   Carver, once director of agriculture at <ORGANIZATION>Tuskegee Institute</ORGANIZATION>, was
selected for his work developing countless products from peanuts
and sweet potatoes. Julian, a <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> chemist, was the first to
synthesize cortisone and other human hormones.
   ``He was one of the most persistent men I have known,'' <PERSON>Samuel
B. Massie</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Naval Academy</ORGANIZATION> said about <PERSON>Julian</PERSON>, a former
colleague.
   Tenacity was cited as a necessary ingredient by another man
being honored.
   <PERSON>Robert S. Ledley</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Georgetown University</ORGANIZATION> said the prerequisite
skills for success include a pragmatic attitude, boldness,
fortitude ``and `stick-to-itiveness' almost to the extent of
obsession.''
   <PERSON>Ledley</PERSON> was named to the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame for his development of the
CT scanner, a special X-ray device that allows doctors to see the
inner workings of the body in great detail.
   Honoree <PERSON>Herman Hollerith</PERSON> was described as having left behind a
motto for the generations: ``Do not fold, spindle or mutilate.''
   Hollerith invented the punch-card system that helped pave the
way to modern computers. A <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> employee, he halved the
time it took to tabulate the <DATE>1890</DATE> national head count and later
went on to help found the giant <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines
Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   The second computer pioneer honored was <PERSON>Kenneth S. Olsen</PERSON>,
developer of the magnetic memory core for computers and founder of
<ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Graham C. Durant</PERSON>, <PERSON>John C. Emmett</PERSON> and <PERSON>C. Robin Gannellin</PERSON> were
selected jointly for their work in medical chemistry. The three
developed the drug cimetidine, which has greatly reduced the need
for surgery for ulcer victims. It is known by the trade name
Tagamet.
   <PERSON>Charles P. Ginsberg</PERSON> was named for his work leading the
engineering team that developed the first practical videotape.
<PERSON>Eugene J. Houdry</PERSON>, a French-born engineer, was honored for
developing the procedure that allows crude oil to be processed into
high-grade gasoline and aviation fuel.
   The selection of 10 new members is the most since six were
chosen in <DATE>1985</DATE>, and brings total membership to 85. The <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame
was Founded at the <ORGANIZATION>Patent Office</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Arlington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va</LOCATION>. A new <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of
Fame building is scheduled to be built in <LOCATION>Akron</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Thomas A. Edison</PERSON> was the first member. The <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> also includes
many of the nation's best-known inventors, including <PERSON>Alexander
Graham Bell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Orville</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wilbur Wright</PERSON>, <PERSON>Charles Goodyear</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rudolf
Diesel</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Philo T. Farnsworth</PERSON>.
   The newest members will be inducted in <DATE>April</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06039194 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06039194 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Robert T. McKenzie; . . . Expert in vacuum tubes  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  OBITUARY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Rites were conducted this week for Robert T. McKenzie, 82, a pioneer in the
development of the television camera tube. He died Saturday of a heart attack
suffered at Stanford University Hospital.;    In the early 1930s, Mr. McKenzie
joined vacuum tube specialist Philo T. Farnsworth in Philadelphia, and with a
small group of young engineers and technicians they developed the first
practical television camera tube.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ROBERT MCKENZIE, TV CAMERA PIONEER  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Obituaries  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> tubes were used in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> for broadcasts of the <DATE>1936</DATE>
Olympics in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> and of the coronation of <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>King George VI</PERSON> in
<DATE>1937.</DATE>;    Some of the early work of <PERSON>Mr. McKenzie</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Farnsworth</ORGANIZATION> group is
on display in the <ORGANIZATION>Electronic History Museum</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Foothill College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Altos
Hills.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Mr. McKenzie</PERSON> was one of nine children born to a farmer in
<LOCATION>Limestone</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. At the age of 15 he was locally acclaimed for having
invented a mule-drawn harvesting device that enhanced productivity on cotton
farms. At 16, he went to <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and began his education as an electronics
engineer. He completed his education after returning to <LOCATION>Texas.</LOCATION>;    After his
work with the <PERSON>Farnsworth</PERSON> group, <PERSON>Mr. McKenzie</PERSON> was involved in introducing
television to the American public at the <DATE>1939</DATE> World's Fair in <LOCATION>New York.</LOCATION>;   
During World War II, he was employed by <ORGANIZATION>General Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION>, where he was
involved in the development of radar tubes and infrared image tubes. He worked
on the first infrared "sniperscope" and on a television-guided glide bomb,
which was used to destroy heavy-water plants in Germany.;    <PERSON>Mr. McKenzie</PERSON>
lived in <LOCATION>Schenectady</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> from <DATE>1940</DATE> to <DATE>1958</DATE>, when he moved
to <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION> to work for Sylvania in <LOCATION>Mountain View.</LOCATION>;    After his retirement
in <DATE>1971</DATE>, he worked in his garage on vacuum technology associated with laser
tube processing. But failing eyesight forced him to stop two years ago. At the
age of 75, he was employed briefly as a consultant for <ORGANIZATION>Coherent Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Palo
Alto</LOCATION> laser manufacturer.;    "His creative mind and intense interest in
advanced technology developments . . . was a principal aspect of his character
up to the time of his death," said a son, <PERSON>Robert L. McKenzie</PERSON> of Sunnyvale.;   
<PERSON>Mr. McKenzie</PERSON> also is survived by his wife, <PERSON>Genevieve M. McKenzie</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>;
another son, <PERSON>John P. McKenzie</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Walnut Creek</LOCATION>; sisters <PERSON>Jean Williams</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Rita York</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>; and six grandchildren.;   
Burial was in <LOCATION>Gate of Heaven Cemetery</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Altos</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910208  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  422  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday February 8, 1991
00039194,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900530-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-30-90 1632EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Three-DimensionTV     05-30 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Three-Dimension TV,0266</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inventor Says He Has Developed 3-D TV</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An inventor said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> he has developed
three-dimensional television, beating the world's electronics
giants.
   ``We think that just as black and white was converted into
color, so will color be converted into 3-D,'' said the 33-year-old
British inventor, <PERSON>James Ashbey</PERSON>.
   The technology does not require special glasses or screens. It
can convert all new and existing black and white and color films
into 3-D, along with live broadcasts, animation and computer
graphics, said his company, <ORGANIZATION>Delta Group</ORGANIZATION>.
   Ashbey displayed his invention at a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> studio, showing color
films in what he calls ``full natural perspective.''
   The effect appears three dimensional, but it loses some
resolution compared with a standard TV image, and is very blurry.
Ashbey did not display the 3-D and normal television versions of
the same film side-by-side for comparison.
   Ashbey said he has applied for an international patent for his
invention, which he calls ``Deep Vision.''
   He said he developed the technology with financial support from
<ORGANIZATION>RCA-Columbia Pictures International</ORGANIZATION>, which he said provided
<MONEY>$245,000</MONEY>, and the British entertainment group <ORGANIZATION>Brent Walker Holdings
PLC</ORGANIZATION>, which he said provided <MONEY>$642,200</MONEY>.
   Deep Vision electronically stimulates the brain into creating an
illusion, he said.
   The technology takes a normal film, makes a digital version and
inserts what Ashbey calls stereo cues. A digital decoder added to
an ordinary television set then uses these cues to send slightly
different images to each eye, and that creates the experience of
depth, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06070151 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06070151 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  FIRST; FEMALE; WOMAN; AWARD; RESEARCH; DRUG; BEGIN; PRODUCT; DISEASE; MEDICAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The National Inventors Hall of Fame last week chose to honor Gertrude Belle
Elion for her pioneering research at Burroughs Wellcome Co. that led to the
development of drugs to combat leukemia, septic shock and tissue rejection in
patients undergoing kidney transplants.;    The recognition makes Elion, 73,
the first woman to take her place alongside innovators like Alexander Graham
Bell and Thomas A. Edison in the Hall of Fame since the organization was begun
in 1973.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  'MAVERICK' WOMAN JOINS RANKS OF MEN IN INVENTORS
HALL OF FAME  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Two years ago, <PERSON>Elion</PERSON> (pronounced ELL-ee-on) shared the Nobel Prize for
medicine with her longtime colleague, <PERSON>George H. Hitchings.;    Elion</PERSON>, who was
born in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, has been a pioneer in more ways than one. Although
women have produced a number of major technological advances, women remain
rare among inventors and receive only about <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT> of all patents.;    "I
was a maverick," <PERSON>Elion</PERSON> said <DATE>last week.</DATE>;    At a time when most women did not
go to college, she graduated from <PERSON>Hunter</PERSON> with top honors at 19 and went on to
obtain a master's degree in chemistry.;    In the <DATE>1940s</DATE>, she and <PERSON>Hitchings</PERSON>
developed variations on components of the genetic material DNA that could be
used to fool cells and foil the reproductive machinery of viruses and
bacteria.;    But what made the work remarkable was that no one had yet
identified the double-helix structure of DNA or knew much about the way it
worked. But the two scientists did know that DNA was built from four chemical
components, known as bases. Their approach, therefore, was to develop fake
versions of these bases that would fool particular kinds of cells and lead to
useless DNA.;    <PERSON>Elion</PERSON> first used the approach to synthesize compounds that
block lymphocytes that cause leukemia, but the approach led her and other
researchers to develop a host of other drugs as well.;    <PERSON>Elion</PERSON> now holds
about 40 patents, and the approach has since been applied by other
scientists.;    The <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame is a non-profit organization based in <LOCATION>Akron</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>. Inductees are selected by a panel of scientists, patent attorneys and
other experts. Thus far, 94 inventors have been named to the hall.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910310  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  357  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday March 10, 1991
00070151,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900124-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-24-90 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Inventors     01-24 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Inventors,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ten Named to Hall of Fame</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A record 10 new members, including the first
two blacks, were named to the <ORGANIZATION>National Inventors Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``The 10 individuals we honor here today are the real heroes of
our age. ... They are the thinkers and the problem solvers. They
have opened new doors and pioneered new frontiers in science and
technology,'' said <PERSON>Jeffrey M. Samuels</PERSON>, acting commissioner of
patents and trademarks.
   <PERSON>George Washington Carver</PERSON> and <PERSON>Percy F. Julian</PERSON> were among the
inventors selected for inclusion this year, marking the first
blacks to be selected since the hall was begun in <DATE>1973</DATE>.
   Carver was selected for his work developing more than 500 uses
for peanuts, including cooking oil and printer's ink, and for sweet
potatoes, including synthetic rubber. He died in <DATE>1943</DATE>.
   Julian, a <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> chemist, was the first to synthesize cortisone
and other human hormones. Before the synthetic cortisone came onto
the market, the only cortisone available to treat rheumatoid
arthritis was produced from oxen bile, at a cost of <MONEY>hundreds of
dollars</MONEY> a drop.
   ``He was one of the most persistent men I have known,''
reflected <PERSON>Samuel B. Massie</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Naval Academy</ORGANIZATION>, once a
colleague of <PERSON>Julian</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   Tenacity was also cited as a necessary ingredient by another man
being honored.
   <PERSON>Robert S. Ledley</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Georgetown University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> said the
prerequisite skills for success as an inventor include a pragmatic
attitude, boldness, fortitude ``and stick-to-itiveness almost to
the extent of obsession.''
   <PERSON>Ledley</PERSON> was named to the hall of fame for his development of the
computerized tomographic, or CT, scanner, a device similar to an
x-ray machine that allows doctors to see the inner workings of the
body in great detail.
   Another man honored was <PERSON>Herman Hollerith</PERSON>, described as having
left behind a motto for the generations: ``do not fold, spindle or
mutilate.''
   Hollerith invented the punch-card system that helped pave the
way to modern computers. A <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> employee, he halved the
time it took to tabulate the <DATE>1890</DATE> national head count and later
went on to help found the giant <ORGANIZATION>IBM Co</ORGANIZATION>.
   In addition to <ORGANIZATION>Carver</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Julian</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ledley</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Hollerith</LOCATION>, inventors
selected for the hall of fame for <DATE>1990</DATE> are:
   _<PERSON>Graham C. Durant</PERSON>, <PERSON>John C. Emmett</PERSON> and <PERSON>C. Robin Gannellin</PERSON>,
medical chemists who developed the drug cimetidine, which has
greatly reduced the need for surgery for ulcer victims. It is known
by the trade name Tagamet.
   _<PERSON>Charles P. Ginsberg</PERSON>, who led the engineering team that
developed the first practical videotape.
   _<PERSON>Kenneth S. Olsen</PERSON>, developer of the magnetic memory core for
computers and founder of <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corporation</ORGANIZATION>.
   _<PERSON>Eugene J. Houdry</PERSON>, a French-born engineer who developed the
procedure that allowed crude oil to be processed into high grade
gasoline and aviation fuel.
   The selection of 10 new members is the most since six were
picked in <DATE>1985</DATE>, and brings total membership in the Hall of Fame to
85.
   Founded at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Patent Office</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Arlington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, the hall of
fame will eventually move to <LOCATION>Akron</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, where construction on a
new facility is to begin later this year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881229-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-88 0616EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f PM-BusinessMirror Adv29   12-29 0797</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Mirror, Adv 29,0829</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv 29</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Thursday Dec. 29</NOTE>
<HEAD>Is America Losing Ground To The Japanese?</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Business Analyst John Cunniff is on vacation.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE ZGANJAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Pres Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SCHENECTADY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From the days when inventor <PERSON>Thomas
Edison</PERSON>'s light bulb first lit the nights of <DATE>1879</DATE>, Americans have
been regarded as naturally inventive and creative.
   Much of that innovation derives from the work of scientists and
engineers at <ORGANIZATION>General Electric's Research and Development Center</ORGANIZATION>,
which traces its roots to the <ORGANIZATION>Edison Electrical Light Company</ORGANIZATION> formed
in <DATE>1878</DATE> to support the experiments of <PERSON>Thomas Edison</PERSON>.
   GE scientists brainstormed the magnetic resonance imager, which
uses magnetic fields and radio waves to create pictures of internal
organs without X-rays.
   Real diamonds were concocted in one of their laboratories, not
pulled from the depths of the earth.
   In <DATE>1979</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION> was the first company to pass the 50,000th patent
mark.
   But <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION>'s _ and <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s _ technological lead is being threatened
by the Japanese who, up until now, have had a reputation as clever
copycats.
   Since the end of World War II, the Japanese have borrowed
American inventions, improved them and turned them into inexpensive
household staples. Color television sets, transistor radios and
videocassettee recorders were all original American ideas the
Japanese have capitalized on.
   All that is changing.
   The Japanese are no longer content to pick the brains of American
scientists and engineers for new technology, says <PERSON>Roland W. Schmitt</PERSON>,
president of <ORGANIZATION>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy</ORGANIZATION> and former
vice president of corporate research and development at <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Japanese are trying to be innovators, <PERSON>Schmitt</PERSON> says.
   Their aggressive patenting efforts prove that. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> now acquires
more patents worldwide than any other country.
   <PERSON>Schmitt</PERSON> says the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> still leads the way in developing
new technology. ``But <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is now in a stage where they're starting
to do this,'' he said.
   Japanese business executives say it's only natural for their
companies to develop their own technology.
   ``Any company that hopes to continue making progress will require
innovation, be it through its own or transferred technology,'' said
<PERSON>Kazuya Hosaka</PERSON>, manager of <ORGANIZATION>Hitachi Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>'s patent office in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>.
   Many in this country question whether the Japanese can be
pioneering.
   The Japanese acquire hundreds of patents each year, they're quick
at turning inventions into products and their students study science
and technology in an education system considered superior in those
areas.
   But they're strangled by a culture that frowns upon risk-taking
and prizes collective action over individual effort. Their
scientists and engineers aren't trained to be pioneering.
   Americans, meanwhile, are encouraged to be creative.
   ``We educate our scientists to be pioneers,'' <PERSON>Schmitt</PERSON> said.
   A recent study for the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> showed that in
<DATE>1987</DATE>, three Japanese companies garnered the most <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> patents:
<ORGANIZATION>Hitachi</ORGANIZATION> with 873, <ORGANIZATION>Canon</ORGANIZATION> with 850 and <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION> with 830.
   <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION>, which until <DATE>1986</DATE> had held the No. 1 spot for 25 years, was
fourth with 782 patents.
   <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION> executives at the company's R&amp;D center, located in a sprawling
complex of buildings overlooking the <LOCATION>Mohawk River</LOCATION>, dispute the
results of the patent study done by <ORGANIZATION>Computer Horizons</ORGANIZATION>, a consulting
company. They argue <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION> would still rank as patent leader if the
study had included patents granted to RCA, which <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION> acquired in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   ``Whoever did the study obviously didn't know <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> was a
subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION>,'' said <PERSON>James C. Davis Jr.</PERSON>, manager of patent and
legal operations at <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION>.
   Top <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION> officials, though, see the study as a warning.
   ``It doesn't mean we shouldn't be concerned,'' said <PERSON>Walter Robb</PERSON>,
vice president of corporate research and development at <ORGANIZATION>GE</ORGANIZATION>. ``There
are still three Japanese companies in the top four.''
   Moreover, the Japanese are beating the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is their
ability to rapidly commercialize inventions, such as the VCR.
   ``We get out of the starting block fast,'' <PERSON>Schmitt</PERSON> said. ``But we
lose it on the long stretch. We've lost the ability to do the long
haul.''
   America's best hope in its competition with <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> may be its
education system. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is far ahead of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in an area
vital to technological and scientific development: the encouragement
of creative thought.
   Yet serious problems exist in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s education system.
   ``We have fewer and fewer students with an interest in science
and technology,'' said <PERSON>Schmitt</PERSON>, a former chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Science Board</ORGANIZATION>.
   He believes that for the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to remain No. 1 in science
and technology it must, in some ways, imitate the Japanese.
   ``The Japanese understand that manufacturability and customer
preferences are integral parts of the innovation process, not
afterthoughts,'' <PERSON>Schmitt</PERSON> said. ``I see no reason why we Americans
can't renew our skills at the application of science and technology
while maintaining our strength as pioneers.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PMs Thursday Dec. 29</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1536EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Obit-Bruch     05-06 0092</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Obit-Bruch,0098</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inventor of PAL Color Television System is Dead</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HANOVER, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Walter Bruch</PERSON>, a German television
pioneer who invented the <ORGANIZATION>PAL</ORGANIZATION> color system, has died, the Telefunken
company said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. He was 82.
   Bruch invented the Phase Alternation Line (PAL) color television
system 20 years ago. Telefunken, a West German maker of television
sets, said the system was now being used in 60 countries.
   Bruch had been <ORGANIZATION>Telefunken</ORGANIZATION>'s head of research for many years.
   Telefunken said <PERSON>Bruch</PERSON> died after a long illness but gave no
other details.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881114-0124 </DOCNO>
<HL> Technology (A Special Report): The Problem --- Showing Off: World's Fairs Celebrate Inventiveness And Point to Tomorrow's Pacesetters </HL>
<AUTHOR> Bernard Wysocki Jr. </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   ENGLAND REIGNED supreme in <DATE>1851</DATE>. 
Her colonies were vast, her navy invincible, her industrial and technological might unquestioned. 
But in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, at the <ORGANIZATION>Crystal Palace Exhibition</ORGANIZATION> of <DATE>1851</DATE>, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> stole the show. 

   <PERSON>Cyrus McCormick</PERSON>'s reaper drew thousands to a nearby farm. 
<ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> rubber products won a big prize. 
The biggest shocker, though, was the American system of manufacturing -- precision tools, interchangeable parts -- that made possible an unbelievable flow of pistols, clocks and other items at cheap prices. 

   The great fairs and expositions of the <DATE>19th</DATE> and <DATE>20th century</DATE> have always been a showcase of new technologies and inventions, but the fairs have been something more. 
They are a wonderful place to watch the gradual passing of technological supremacy from one part of the world to another. 

   In the decades following the <ORGANIZATION>Crystal Palace</ORGANIZATION> extravaganza, it was clear that <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> was seizing that supremacy. 
The nation's inventors developed the telephone, the incandescent lamp, the typewriter, the phonograph. 
Near the end of the century, Americans began building skyscrapers. 

   The British admired what they called the "American system of manufactures," but much of the technology the Americans used was actually borrowed from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and other European nations. 
<PERSON>Andrew Carnegie</PERSON>, for example, built a steel empire -- but it was initially based on the work of Sir <PERSON>Henry Bessemer</PERSON>, an Englishman. 

   History would repeat itself in later decades, but by then the scientific innovator would be <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. 
The great technological borrower and commercial exploiter would be <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 

   The <LOCATION>Chicago World</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Columbian Exposition</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>1893
   America</LOCATION> was showing off. 
If the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> fair of <DATE>1889</DATE> had been graced by the spectacular new iron tower designed by <ORGANIZATION>Eiffel</ORGANIZATION>, then the 1893 <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> fair would have its own symbol, equally impressive, totally American. 
A man named <PERSON>Gale Ferris</PERSON> constructed a giant wheel, 250 feet in diameter, capable of carrying 1400 people at a time. 

   The message of the <DATE>1893</DATE> fair was this: <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> is now the equal of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
The great capitalists of the day -- the steel, sugar, oil, beef and coal barons -- hired the finest architects, who produced a pseudoclassical with statuary, fountains and columns. 

   On <DATE>May 1</DATE>, president <PERSON>Grover Cleveland</PERSON> opened the fair by pressing a golden telegraph key and 10,000 electric lights flashed on. 
At night the effect was ethereal, sensational. 
All the buildings had been painted white, and the place soon became known all over the world as the "White City." 

   The same year, the <LOCATION>Duryea</LOCATION> brothers put the first American auto on the road. 
They were 10 years behind <PERSON>Gottlieb Daimler</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 
But, it was American manufacturing genius -- in the person of <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION> -- that brought the product within the grasp of the ordinary person. 
Ford introduced the moving assembly line in <DATE>1913</DATE>, cutting costs, cutting prices, and expanding output. 

   By the end of World War I, half the cars in the world had been made by <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor Co</ORGANIZATION>. 

   At the time of the <DATE>1893</DATE> fair, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> was still a long way from making cars. 
But it was on the way. 
Twenty five years before, under the young emperor <ORGANIZATION>Meiji</ORGANIZATION>, it had set itself a seemingly impossible goal: to catch up with the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in technology. 
It wasn't making cars, no -- but it had already begun to build ships and manufacture guns, locomotives, machinery and textile mills. 

   The <LOCATION>New York World</LOCATION>'s Fair, <DATE>1939</DATE>
   At this fair, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> showed it wasn't just the equal of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> but its superior. 
With the Depression still lingering, the <DATE>1939</DATE> fair offered hope -- the hope of a brighter future through technology. 
American technology. 

   RCA unveiled its television developments on opening day, with <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> becoming the first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> president to appear on the tube. 
<PERSON>David Sarnoff</PERSON> of RCA, writing shortly before the opening of the fair, predicted a future of mobile car phones, facsimile transmission and overseas TV broadcasts. 

   The runaway hit of the <DATE>1939</DATE> fair was the <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Futurama</ORGANIZATION> pavilion. 
People stood in line for hours to see a vision of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> in <DATE>1960</DATE> -- some 36,000 square feet of model American landscape, transformed by a vast web of superhighways. 

   Sitting in a soft chair, you glided 20 years into the future. 
Before you spread a giant landscape of the future. 
Over here was a thriving and prosperous city of heavy industry. 
Over there was an even more futuristic city, with shiny glass skyscrapers, outlying districts for business and for housing, and an outlying airport, all connected by a network of highways. 
It looked a lot like <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> today. 

   The Japanese exhibit at the fair focused only on traditional housing, gardens, and culture. There was no hint that <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> had already succeeded in building giant industrial combines and a war machine that was already in action against <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. -
   The <LOCATION>New York World</LOCATION>'s Fair, <DATE>1964</DATE>
   Japanese electronics companies introduced some early products at this fair, including the first calculator with an electronic readout. 
But they were put in the shade by <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor</ORGANIZATION>. 
It unveiled the Mustang, marking perhaps the zenith of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> auto industry. 
RCA introduced color television. 

   While this was going on, however, the first Japanese cars, made by <ORGANIZATION>Toyota</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Nissan</ORGANIZATION>, were beginning to arrive on American shores. 
No one could have foretold the tremendous impact they would eventually have on <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>'s supremacy. 
And no one could have foretold that <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> would dominate the world's manufacture of color televisions. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Tsukuba Exposition</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>1985
   Japan</LOCATION>'s real debut as a world-class technological power didn't come until <DATE>1985</DATE>, when 20 million people descended on <ORGANIZATION>Tsukuba Science City</ORGANIZATION>, north of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, for an <MONEY>$840 million</MONEY> extravaganza. 

   Tsukuba was new and unpopular, a thoroughly planned city with all the warmth of most thoroughly planned new cities. 
When the Japanese government relocated dozens of government laboratories to <LOCATION>Tsukuba</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, scientists howled. 
Tsukuba offered rice paddies, look-alike laboratory buildings, a dearth of shops and an overabundance of ennui -- but the fair itself was a celebration of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s awesome gains in technology. 

   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> was there, too, but its exhibits were overshadowed by those of the Japanese. 
By this time, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> also was losing to Japanese rivals in semiconductor memory chips, piling up huge trade deficits with <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, and was on the verge of becoming a debtor nation. 

   Tsukuba was very much a Japanese celebration, and a playful one. 
Few of the exhibits even tried to explain the intricacies of chemistry, biology or computers; much of the fair was aimed at young people, especially children. 

   They were entertained by huge television screens, cute little robots, enormous crowds. 
The biggest hit of the fair was the <ORGANIZATION>Fujitsu</ORGANIZATION> pavilion, which featured <ORGANIZATION>Fanuc Man</ORGANIZATION>, a 16-foot robot weighing 25 tons, a gigantic symbol of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s power in robotics. 
Fanuc Man could lift 400-pound barbells and could also assemble a small replica of himself. 

   The fair never explored the darker aspects of technological progress, even though the Japanese themselves were beginning to worry about invasion of privacy, computer crime, system failure, robot error, displaced workers, mental stress, video-terminal eye strain, and alienation of humans from each other. 
Tsukuba, however, gave only one message: Love technology. 

   <PERSON>Atsushi Shimokobe</PERSON>, one of the fair's senior planners, says he remembers seeing children who embraced computers and wouldn't let go. 
"There were some adults who saw that and were happy about it, but it made other adults anxious and uneasy," he recalls. 

   Even some of the children made it clear they wanted a future with something more than just technology, technology, technology. 
<PERSON>Peter Eggleton</PERSON>, science attache at the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, remembers taking his nine-year-old daughter's class to Expo <DATE>'85</DATE>. 
On the bus ride home, everybody talked about seeing a horse in one of the Japanese pavilions and a baby elephant from <LOCATION>Sri Lanka</LOCATION>. 
Says <PERSON>Mr. Eggleton</PERSON>, "This was a strong message for me." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880216-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-16-88 0552EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF-China-Convict     02-16 0146</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF-China-Convict,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Convict Invents Satellite Receiver in Prison Workshop</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 25-year-old convict helped bring television to
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s remote northwest by developing a satellite receiver in his
prison workshop, the official <ORGANIZATION>Xinhua News Agency</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Ren Huimin</PERSON>, serving a five-year sentence for fraud in a
penitentiary in the <ORGANIZATION>Ningxia Hui Autonomous Region</ORGANIZATION>'s capital of
<LOCATION>Yinchuan</LOCATION>, also has patented two other inventions, the report said.
   It said the satellite receiver designed and produced by <PERSON>Ren</PERSON> has
made it possible for <LOCATION>Yinchuan</LOCATION> residents to receive programs
transmitted from <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> by <ORGANIZATION>China Central Television</ORGANIZATION>.
   He also invented an ultra-high frequency analogue switch which
turns lights on and off when people enter or leave a room, and an
infra-red automatic alarm used in the prison.
   The report said <PERSON>Ren</PERSON> taught himself physics, chemistry, optics,
electronics and electromagnetics and dropped out of school to do
independent research.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910403-0074
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910403-0074.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology:
   U.S. Takes Up Inquiry
   Into Microchip's Invention
</HL>
<DATE>
04/03/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B8
</SO>
<CO>
   SCE TXN
</CO>
<MS>
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
UTILITIES (UTI)
</MS>
<IN>
DIVERSIFIED TECHNOLOGY (DTC)
ELECTRIC UTILITIES (ELC)
SEMICONDUCTORS, INTEGRATED CHIPS (SEM)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
TEXAS (TX)
</RE>
<LP>
   DALLAS -- Texas Instruments Inc. said the U.S. Patent and
Trademark Office has begun an investigation to determine if a
patent awarded to Gilbert P. Hyatt for the invention of the
single-chip microcomputer was first sought by Gary W. Boone
while working at Texas Instruments.
   The investigation is the first step in finding who
actually invented the device, which over the years has become
crucial to the manufacturing of televisions, computers and
other electronic products. The winner of the patent battle is
likely to claim millions of dollars in royalties from U.S.
and Japanese semiconductor companies now producing huge
volumes of more advanced versions of the device.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The electronics and defense company asked the patent
office on <DATE>Jan. 15</DATE> to investigate <PERSON>Mr. Hyatt</PERSON>'s patent, which
was awarded with great fanfare last year. A spokesman said
<ORGANIZATION>Texas Instruments</ORGANIZATION> is convinced <PERSON>Mr. Boone</PERSON> patented the device
on <DATE>July 19, 1971</DATE>. The company said <PERSON>Mr. Hyatt</PERSON>'s patent wasn't
filed until <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   Calling the challenge "frivolous," <PERSON>Mr. Hyatt</PERSON> said he filed
his patent in <DATE>1968</DATE>.
   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Texas Instruments</ORGANIZATION> said it agreed to develop a
new solar technology with <ORGANIZATION>Southern California Edison Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a
unit of <ORGANIZATION>SCEcorp</ORGANIZATION>. It said the two companies plan to develop a
new solar cell using low-purity silicon to convert sunlight
to electricity.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090189-0145 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 102161 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 1, 1989, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 7; Column 4; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
914 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
RISING TIDE OF FOREIGN PATENTS STIRS DEBATE ABOUT U.S. COMPETITIVENESS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CARL S. KAPLAN, Newsday 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Mikhail Tsinberg</PERSON>'s workroom at <ORGANIZATION>Philips Laboratories</ORGANIZATION> near <LOCATION>Ossining</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, brims 
with the gear of the modern inventor: Television monitors tuned to test 
patterns stand on shelves, stacks of electronic equipment blink silently in 
corners, and bench drawers display labels for mysterious gizmos such as "logic 
analyzer probes parts." 
</P>
<P>
It's a playground for the Soviet-born engineer, who in the past six years has 
won four <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> patents in high-definition television under the aegis of 
<ORGANIZATION>Dutch-owned North American Philips Corp</ORGANIZATION>. But it's also a vantage point from 
which he surveys <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> technology. And these days, Tsinberg is starting to worry 
that the invention prowess of his adopted country is weakening. 
</P>
<P>
He sees signs everywhere -- from what he terms the "lousy" science and math 
education in this country to the closing of major research laboratories owing 
to corporate restructurings. He notes, too, that European- and Asian-born 
scientists are the majority at research labs where he has worked in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> and that increasing numbers of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> patents are granted to Japanese 
companies. 
</P>
<P>
"When Sputnik was launched, it captured headlines" and prompted a rapid <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
response, the inventor said. "But with this slow decay process, there's nothing 
to put in headlines. It's hard to notice and very dangerous." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Just One <ORGANIZATION>Voice 
</P>
<P>
Tsinberg</ORGANIZATION>'s is just one voice in a growing debate about <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s technological 
competitiveness. Some analysts say <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s technology engine is sputtering 
while the engines of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Western Europe</LOCATION> are at full tilt. If 
current trends continue, analysts say, the nation will experience a technology 
deficit that could lead to more anemic manufacturing in certain industries and, 
ultimately, a decreased standard of living. America's loss of dominance in 
consumer electronics and automobiles is the point of the wedge, the experts 
maintain. 
</P>
<P>
Others say <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> is not lagging, that the country is pre-eminent in several 
cutting-edge fields such as biotechnology and computers. Rather, the world is 
simply catching up -- a positive development. 
</P>
<P>
At the center of the debate are statistics compiled by the federal Patent and 
<ORGANIZATION>Trademark Office</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Arlington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va</LOCATION>. An increasing number of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> patents are 
being awarded to foreign residents and corporations. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1988</DATE>, of the 77,925 patents issued (excluding grants for plants and 
designs), <PERCENT>48%</PERCENT> were awarded to nonresidents. Japan received the most (16,158, or 
<PERCENT>21%</PERCENT>), followed by <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> (<PERCENT>9%</PERCENT>), the <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> (<PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> each). 
</P>
<P>
This invention snapshot contrasts sharply with the picture 25 years before, 
when <PERCENT>18.6%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> patents were awarded to foreigners. Patent grants to 
foreigners will reach the <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> mark "within the next few years," predicts 
<PERSON>Herbert Wamsley</PERSON>, executive director of <ORGANIZATION>Intellectual Property Owners</ORGANIZATION>, a 
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> trade group. 
</P>
<P>
Not only is the percentage of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> patents to foreigners rising, but the number 
of patents granted to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> businesses and individuals is generally declining -- 
though there's been an uptick since <DATE>1982</DATE>. Last year for example, 40,497 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
patents for mechanical, chemical or electrical applications were granted to 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> residents. Fifteen years ago there were 51,504. 
</P>
<P>
For their part, Japanese companies have been particularly active in targeting 
-- and winning -- patents in such areas as consumer electronics, automotive and 
photo optics. In the category of internal combustion engines, for example, 
Japanese companies won <PERCENT>44%</PERCENT> of all <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> patents issued in <DATE>1987</DATE>, while <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
companies received <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT>. Ten years earlier, the shares were the exact reverse. 
</P>
<P>
A company routinely seeks patents in countries where it sells its products to 
keep others from making, using or selling the invention. 
</P>
<P>
Although the patent stats are in black and white, opposing sides of the 
"Is-American-inventiveness-slipping?" debate draw conclusions of different 
shades. 
</P>
<P>
Among those who see little cause for alarm is <PERSON>Richard Nelson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Henry Luce</PERSON> 
professor of <ORGANIZATION>International Political Economy</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Columbia University</ORGANIZATION>. For one 
thing, he notes, Japanese companies traditionally apply for more patents per 
innovation -- and receive them -- than do <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> companies. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Historical Anomaly 
</P>
<P>
Nelson also believes that the figures show the correction of a historical 
anomaly -- the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> pre-eminence in technology and manufacturing after World 
War II. 
</P>
<P>
Shattered by the war, it took <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> more than 15 years to catch up 
to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in trading and industrial output. What we are witnessing, 
<PERSON>Nelson</PERSON> said, is the rapid industrialization of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> relative to 
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, coupled with the globalization of the world's economy. 
</P>
<P>
Japanese companies, he said, are applying for more and more patents in the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> because they sell more and more products here. The amount of 
inventing in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is also going up, relative to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I suppose (these developments) bother our sensitivities quite a bit. But the 
sense of lost leadership . . . doesn't bother me," <PERSON>Nelson</PERSON> said. "Why should it? 
It makes for a more complex and balanced world for us to live in, not one 
that's necessarily detrimental." 
</P>
<P>
Echoing <PERSON>Nelson</PERSON>'s view is <PERSON>Edwin Mansfield</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Center for Economics 
and Technology</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION>. "I think it's true that the 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is not as dominant as it was before . . . but there are advantages to 
having a strong competitive <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and a strong <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. So I think it isn't as 
worrisome as some make out." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PATENTS; TECHNOLOGY; UNITED STATES -- INDUSTRY; BUSINESS -- UNITED STATES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901009-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-09-90 0405EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-TelevisionSurvey-List     10-09 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Television Survey-List,0755</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Television Survey</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUDONVILLE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Single Most Memorable TV Program</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Best Miniseries</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Best Drama Series</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Best Comedy Series</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Best Western Series</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Best Variety Series</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Best News Show or Documentary</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Best Late-Night Show</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Best Early-Morning Show</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Best Children's Program</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Memorable On-Camera Figure</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Memorable Comedy Figure</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Memorable Western Figure</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Memorable Variety-Music Figure</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Memorable News Figure</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Significant Business Figure</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Significant Producer</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Significant Director</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Significant Technical Innovation</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Most Significant Figure Overall</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top finishers in the
survey ``The Best of the <ORGANIZATION>First 50 Years of Television</ORGANIZATION>,'' which was
released <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The survey, conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Siena Research
Institute of Siena College</ORGANIZATION>, polled several hundred college
professors, broadcast education experts and critics from
major-market newspapers and television stations:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890210-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-10-89 0953EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Inventors     02-10 0211</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Inventors,200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inventors Hall of Fame to Add Four Members</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Inventors whose innovations range from the
moldboard plow to the magnetic resonance imager will be added to the
<ORGANIZATION>National Inventors Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>this weekend</DATE>.
   Induction ceremonies are scheduled for <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Patent
Office</ORGANIZATION>, home of the hall of fame.
   The four new members bring to 76 the number of inventors
memoralized at the <ORGANIZATION>Patent Office</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Arlington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va</LOCATION>.
