<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900929-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-29-90 1758EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FutureFighter     09-29 0430</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Future Fighter,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Second Competitor for Advanced Tactical Fighter Contract Gets
Airborne</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EDWARDS AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s prototype
of a 21st century fighter jet made its first flight <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in a
winner-take-all competition for the <ORGANIZATION>multibillion-dollar Advanced
Tactical Fighter</ORGANIZATION> contract.
   The YF-22 was airborne just 18 minutes, taking off from <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> Plant 42 in <LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION> and ending 25 mile away at this desert
flight test center.
   The flight was a milestone in a high-stakes contest between an
aerospace team headed by <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> and a team led by <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
for 1,250 <ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION> jets, to be built at a projected cost of <MONEY>$51 million</MONEY>
per plane.
   The winner must produce a jet that is highly maneuverable, uses
radar-evading stealth technology and can fly twice the speed of
sound for long periods of time. The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> wants 750 of the new
planes and the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> needs 500.
   Pilot <PERSON>Dave Ferguson</PERSON> said the YF-22 flew as expected although the
flight was shortened by 42 minutes because of problems at ground
telemetry stations.
   The jet burned so much fuel while sitting on the runway waiting
for takeoff that there wasn't enough left for the scheduled
one-hour flight.
   ``It was a very easy airplane to fly,'' said <PERSON>Ferguson</PERSON>, adding,
``I would be happy to put fuel in it and fly it this afternoon.''
   The jet reached an altitude of 12,500 feet and a speed of about
280 mph. The two-tone gray jet with stubby wings and a V-shaped
tail touched down smoothly in a light rain.
   The YF-22 was built by <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>General Dynamics Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Boeing Co</ORGANIZATION>. It was unveiled in <LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION> <DATE>Aug. 29</DATE>, two days after the
YF-23, built by <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>McDonnell Douglas Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, made
its first flight.
   Lockheed Vice President <PERSON>Sherman Mullin</PERSON>, head of the YF-22
project, said he could not compare the two planes because he didn't
have enough information about the YF-23.
   Each team has spent about <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> producing two prototype
jets each.
   ``It's obviously an extremely important program to us,'' said
<PERSON>Mullin</PERSON>. ``(But) it's not a program that's going to make or break
the <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Corp.</ORGANIZATION>''
   Both planes are built of advanced composite materials. The
<ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> aircraft has stubby wings. The <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> fighter has a
longer, cigarlike fuselage and a wingspread that looks like a kite.
   ``This is a great day from a technological perspective,'' said
<PERSON>Gary L. Denman</PERSON>, who heads an <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> research division. ``I can
assure you, what's out there in the airplane is the best in the
world.''
   Survival of the advanced fighter program was threatened by
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> until <LOCATION>Iraq</LOCATION>'s <DATE>Aug. 2</DATE> invasion of <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION>. The crisis has
enhanced prospects for approval of major defense contracts.
   If <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>McDonnell Douglas</ORGANIZATION> win the contract, the YF-23
would be built in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. The Lockheed-General Dynamics-Boeing
team plans to build YF-22s in <LOCATION>Marietta</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, if it wins. The
selection is due in <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   The <MONEY>$51 million</MONEY> cost of each jet is about twice that of the <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION>'s present top fighter, the F-15 Eagle.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890530-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-30-89 1252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--Whitehead'sFlight Adv11   05-30 1119</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Whitehead's Flight, Adv 11,1151</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv11</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, June 11</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo,
1 graphic.)</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ Two engineers, convinced that a <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>
inventor beat the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers into the air by more than two
years, have drawn up blueprints for an engine they believe is
almost identical to the ones that powered that first flight. The
next step, they hope, is to build working replicas of the engines
in an attempt to prove that <PERSON>Gustave Whitehead</PERSON> may have been cheated
out of his proper place in history.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ Two engineers, convinced that a <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>
inventor beat the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers into the air by more than two
years, have drawn up blueprints for an engine they believe is
almost identical to the ones that powered that first flight. The
next step, they hope, is to build working replicas of the engines
in an attempt to prove that <PERSON>Gustave Whitehead</PERSON> may have been cheated
out of his proper place in history.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>By DEAN GOLEMBESKI</NOTE>
<NOTE>Associated Press Writer</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CROMWELL, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ Two engineers, convinced that a <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>
inventor beat the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers into the air by more than two
years, have drawn up blueprints for an engine they believe is
almost identical to the ones that powered that first flight. The
next step, they hope, is to build working replicas of the engines
in an attempt to prove that <PERSON>Gustave Whitehead</PERSON> may have been cheated
out of his proper place in history.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, June 11</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890310-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-10-89 1638EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-StealthBomber 620   03-10 0616</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stealth Bomber, 620</SECOND>
<HEAD>B-2 Flight Delayed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NORMAN BLACK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The B-2 stealth bomber, unveiled last fall
after more than a decade of secret work, will not fly for the first
time before late <DATE>spring</DATE> or <DATE>summer</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Acknowledging recent reports that the schedule for the first
flight was in jeopardy, the service said that because of ``an
aggregation of minor system checkout problems, the B-2's first
flight is now expected to be in the late <DATE>spring</DATE> or early <DATE>summer</DATE> time
frame.''
   ``Routine systems checkout of the first B-2 Advanced Technology
Bomber is continuing ...,'' the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> added. ``After first
flight, the B-2 will undergo extensive testing at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force
Base</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>''
   When the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> made its first announcement last <DATE>summer</DATE> about
an unveiling for the unusual ``flying wing'' plane, it confidently
predicted the aircraft would be ready for its first flight in the
<DATE>fall of 1988</DATE>.
   The plane was ultimately shown to the public for the first time
<DATE>Nov. 22</DATE> at an <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> plant in <LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> officials said at the time they were not
going to rush the initial checkouts of the sophisticated flight
systems, but that they still expected the plane to fly before the
end of the year.
   Maj. <PERSON>Pat Mullaney</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> spokesman, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> the
problems encountered by technicians all had been relatively minor,
but that it took time to prepare a plane for its first flight.
   ``We have said all along that we're going to fly this airplane
when it's ready, and not according to some calendar schedule,'' said
<PERSON>Mullaney</PERSON>.
   The spokesman added the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> decided to release <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s
statement after encountering a problem with the bomber's
``environmental control,'' or air conditioning, system, within the
past week or so.
   A component of that system failed during a high-pressure test,
<PERSON>Mullaney</PERSON> said. Even though the system was purposely overloaded <PERCENT>50
percent</PERCENT> beyond its design limit at the time, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> decided
to fix the component to ensure an extra margin of safety.
   ``The fix for that is straightforward and corrective action is
underway,'' he said.
   The disclosure of checkout problems comes three months after the
<ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> announced the B-2 would carry a price tag _ including
research and development costs _ of <MONEY>$516 million</MONEY> per plane. That
will make it the most expensive airplane ever.
   According to the latest <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> estimate, the design,
development and construction of 132 planes will cost <MONEY>$68.1 billion</MONEY>
by the time production ends in mid-1995. Even if research and
development expenses are excluded, each plane still will cost <MONEY>$305
million</MONEY> to produce on the assembly line.
   The B-2, built primarily by <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, resembles a huge,
tailless manta ray, with wide sweeping wings blending smoothly into
rounded cockpit and engine housings on the top side.
   The stealth gets its name from the claim that it will be almost
invisible to enemy radar, due to the extensive use of exotic
composite materials, some of which absorb rather than reflect radar
waves; its lack of sharp surface angles; and a cross-section that
offers a very small profile to radar.
   The plane is a ``flying wing,'' a design resurrected from the
<DATE>1940s</DATE> that steers with flaps on the rear of the wings rather than
with a tail. The B-2 is described as an all-altitude penetration
bomber, as opposed to the B-1 bomber, which is designed to penetrate
enemy air defenses at low altitudes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> says the plane is 69 feet long, about the length of
an F-16 fighter plane. Its wingspan, at 172 feet, is almost as wide
as the aging B-52.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891006-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-06-89 1618EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WrightBrothers     10-06 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wright Brothers,0351</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wright Brothers Sites to Get Federal Preservation Study</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES HANNAH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DAYTON, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The federal government will study sites
where the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers lived and worked in a move that could
lead to a national park in the birthplace of aviation, officials
said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Rep. <PERSON>Tony Hall</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ohio</LOCATION>, said the <ORGANIZATION>National Park Service</ORGANIZATION> study,
expected to take 12 to 15 months, will help <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> decide whether
to confer national park status on the sites.
   A committee headed by <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>Judge Walter Rice</PERSON> was
formed to preserve the heritage of <PERSON>Orville</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wilbur Wright</PERSON>, who
developed the first heavier-than-air flying machine.
   ``Over the years ... we have lost many of the buildings, many of
the historic sites involved in the birth of aviation either to the
wrecking ball or to just plain indifference,'' <PERSON>Rice</PERSON> said. ``That
time is over.''
   The sites to be studied include <PERSON>Huffman Prairie</PERSON>, scene of the
<PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers' first flying experiments, and buildings that
housed the Wrights' airplane company, bicycle shop and printing
business.
   Also on the list are <PERSON>Hawthorne Hill</PERSON>, home of <PERSON>Orville Wright</PERSON>;
<ORGANIZATION>Carillon Park</ORGANIZATION>, home of the <ORGANIZATION>Wright Flyer III</ORGANIZATION>, known as the world's
first practical airplane; and <ORGANIZATION>Dunbar House</ORGANIZATION>, home of <PERSON>Paul Lawrence
Dunbar</PERSON>, poet and friend of the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers.
   <PERSON>William Gibson</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>National Park Service</ORGANIZATION> official based in
<LOCATION>Chillicothe</LOCATION>, said the agency will study options for managing the
sites, including oversight by the state or local government, the
private sector, or the federal government in the form of a national
park.
   ``We are impressed,'' said <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON>. ``The historic resources
associated with the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers that remain in <LOCATION>Dayton</LOCATION> are truly
impressive.''
   The city of <LOCATION>Dayton</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montgomery County</LOCATION> plan to contribute
<MONEY>$35,000</MONEY> apiece toward the study. Private contributions will also be
sought, officials said.
   While the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers constructed their early aircraft at
their bicycle shop in <LOCATION>Dayton</LOCATION>, they also are connected historically
with <PERSON>Kitty Hawk</PERSON>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, where on <DATE>Dec. 17, 1903</DATE>, they made the first
controlled, sustained flights in a power-driven airplane.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010389-0007 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 633 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 3, 1989, Tuesday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 9; Column 3 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
663 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
REFLECTIONS: THE P-38 WAS THE HIGHEST SPOT OF MY WHOLE MILITARY CAREER. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PERRY C. RIDDLE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Thomas G. McGuire</PERSON>, retired <ORGANIZATION>Valley College English</ORGANIZATION> teacher and competitive 
marksman, fell in love nearly 50 years ago. The object of his affection was a 
sleek new airplane built in <LOCATION>Burbank</LOCATION>. McGuire, 70, writes for "Lightning 
Strikes," the P-38 <ORGANIZATION>National Assn.</ORGANIZATION> newsletter. He lives in <LOCATION>Van Nuys</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The first time I ever saw a P-38, some nut in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> looped the Golden 
Gate Bridge. I thought, "Oh my God!" It was <DATE>1940</DATE>. I just dreamed of that damned 
airplane all those years that I was flying other stuff. 
</P>
<P>
I graduated as a pilot in <DATE>December of 1943</DATE>. I went down to <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> on the old 
daylight train, 220 young guys. When the war was over, I think about 69 of them 
were still alive, out of 220. I was lucky, I guess. 
</P>
<P>
I wanted to fly P-38s, but I was sent to instructor school. I taught advanced 
flying for all of <DATE>1944</DATE> and a little bit of <DATE>'45</DATE>. I never lost one student. I 
like to think it was because I was very careful with them that I never lost 
one. 
</P>
<P>
I first went to <LOCATION>Pecos</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex</LOCATION>. At <LOCATION>Pecos</LOCATION>, there was a cadet killed every week or 
so. We killed 13 in one night. We killed more men in training in the States 
than we lost overseas. A new pilot would ask, "How many pine boxes are going 
out of here a week?" Those statistics have never been made available to the 
public. 
</P>
<P>
We killed eight in one day at <LOCATION>Chico</LOCATION>. We killed nine in one day in <LOCATION>Santa Rosa</LOCATION>. 
My mother would phone the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> because the paper would 
just say, "Midair collision in <LOCATION>Santa Rosa</LOCATION>, both pilots killed." I didn't know 
how hard it was on her. 
</P>
<P>
I wanted to get out of the training command and into P-38s. Finally, I got my 
choice. 
</P>
<P>
The P-38 is a wonderful airplane, a twin-fuselage, single-seat fighter. The 
cockpit is between the two engines. It's got a lot of weight. It's got a lot of 
power. It had a nice, soft, sweet hum about it. It was the most incredible 
thing there was. The P-38 fought in every theater in World War II. It was the 
first American airplane of any type to fly over <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
No airplane ever had that many switches, lights and gadgets for one man to 
handle. It was harder to fly, more complicated. And it had the highest death 
rate in training and operation. 
</P>
<P>
In fighters, a solo flight is a very hairy thing, but especially in a P-38. I 
was really scared, too. You've got two engines pulling like hell. You have to 
lock your wheels, your legs jammed against the brake pedals, and you run it up 
to 3,000 r.p.m.s. I just let go of the brakes, poured the coal to it and got a 
shock from that slam back against the seat. I never felt that before. I had 
never been in anything that powerful. I came around and made a good landing, 
too. I got this funny feeling about that afterward, like, "Did I really do 
that?" 
</P>
<P>
I never went overseas. I flew P-38s out of <LOCATION>Santa Rosa</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Santa Rosa</LOCATION> was a real 
fighting airport, with loaded guns in the planes, in defense of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 
They were afraid the Jap submarines were going to come up and make a run over 
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
When the war was over, I had the weird experience of ferrying beautiful 
brand-new P-38s from <LOCATION>Lockheed</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Kingman</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, where they were just left to 
rot or to be chopped up. 
</P>
<P>
When I got out of the service, they offered to sell me a P-38 for <MONEY>$1,300</MONEY>. I 
didn't have the money then. I was going back to school, so I passed on that. 
Now one of those is worth <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
They made 10,000 of them, but only 13 are left. The P-38 Assn. is having this 
big blowup in <DATE>January</DATE> in <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>. They'll have some P-38s flying, and you 
can walk up and look at them or climb up the ladder in back. 
</P>
<P>
The P-38 was the highest spot of my whole military career. It was the greatest 
thing that ever happened to me. No words can really tell what it was like to 
fly those things at maximum performance. It was a most amazing kind of thing. 
I've never used narcotics, but one of the guys who has, told me that going 450 
miles an hour at low altitude in a P-38 gives you a higher boost than any kind 
of drug. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Thomas G. McGuire PERRY L. RIDDLE 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Interview 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880514-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-14-88 1556EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-KiteFlight     05-14 0380</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kite Flight,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Flying Child' Returns To Launch New Kite Rules</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOUNTAIN VIEW, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 70-pound girl whose kite took her
on an unscheduled flight returned <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to her liftoff site and
managed to stay on the ground as she launched a new set of kite
safety rules.
   DeAndra <ORGANIZATION>Anrig</ORGANIZATION>'s appearance ended a ban on kite flying at
<LOCATION>Shoreline Park</LOCATION> after the 8-year-old's kite string snagged on a
passing airplane <DATE>March 20</DATE> and carried her 10 feet off the ground
for at least 100 feet.
   The third-grader from <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> still has deep bruises on her back
but was so excited about <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s event that she couldn't sleep
<DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, according to her mother, <PERSON>Debbie</PERSON>. She flew a stunt
kite for about a minute before it fell to the grass.
   ``It feels fun,'' <PERSON>DeAndra</PERSON> said shyly to a crowd of reporters,
who outnumbered other spectators. ``It was fun just to get the kite
up in the air and flying it.''
   She warned other children not to fly kites next to nearby <LOCATION>Palo
Alto Airport</LOCATION>, from which planes were taking off and landing over
the park.
   But, she added: ``I want to fly again even though I was hurt.''
   <PERSON>Glenn Lyles</PERSON>, the city's Shoreline manager, had said it was
appropriate to have DeAndra be the first to officially fly a kite
after the regulations were revised.
   Greeting her today with a pat on the head, he said with a laugh,
``You've caused me a lot of work the last month.''
   The story of DeAndra's flight was relayed around the world by
the news media, which dubbed her <PERSON>Mary Poppins</PERSON>, Winnie the Pooh and
the Flying Nun.
   The plane sustained minor damage in the runin with the kite, but
landed safely.
   The city's new guidelines for kite flying at the park, which is
located near both the airport and <ORGANIZATION>Moffett Field Naval Air Station</ORGANIZATION>,
include a ban on flying kites higher than 150 feet.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Federal Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION> made no ruling as to who was
at fault in <DATE>March</DATE> when DeAndra was snagged by the airplane,
according to <PERSON>Lyles</PERSON>. The city's report indicates that the kite was
between 200 and 250 feet in the air, but the pilot who struck the
kite claimed to be at 700 feet, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090290-0133 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 270521 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 2, 1990, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
687 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
REFLECTIONS: 'FLYING FEELS SO FREE, SO LIBERATING. YOU'RE TOTALLY 
SELF-SUFFICIENT' 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Terry Rather, Times staff writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
San <ORGANIZATION>Diego State University</ORGANIZATION> journalism professor <PERSON>January Riddle</PERSON> received her 
license to fly in <DATE>1983</DATE>. Riddle, 46, mainly a recreational flier, had previously 
competed in only two small-scale races. But when the opportunity to fly in the 
<ORGANIZATION>Air Race Classic</ORGANIZATION>, the Super Bowl of women's aviation races, arose this <DATE>summer</DATE>, 
she teamed with experienced pilot <PERSON>Sally Bocinski</PERSON>. They borrowed a <ORGANIZATION>Cessna</ORGANIZATION> 172 
for the 2,600-mile, four-day journey that took the racers to obscure airports 
in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> before ending in 
<LOCATION>York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa</LOCATION>. Riddle, a member of the 99's, an international organization for women 
pilots founded by <PERSON>Amelia Earhart</PERSON>, is now preparing for a 500-mile, one-day race 
later this month. Riddle spoke with <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> staff writer <PERSON>Terry Rather</PERSON> and was 
photographed by <PERSON>Bob Grieser</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
It was wonderful being with all those accomplished women pilots. The race was 
never scary but was very intense, more so than I thought it would be. 
</P>
<P>
It's not like getting in a plane and leisurely going somewhere. Every minute 
you're concentrating on not getting off course, making sure the plane is flying 
at full capacity every single second, and watching the weather. It takes all of 
the skills that you ever learned and tests them every single moment. 
</P>
<P>
The start of the race was a thrill. It was a staggered start with airplanes 
taking off every 10 seconds. At the beginning of the race, no one talks to you. 
But, after you've flown, people say, "You're still here, you didn't flake out, 
you're still with us." Then you become part of the group. It's a special group, 
and it becomes an important part of your life. 
</P>
<P>
The airplane we had was one of the slowest allowed in the race, so we were 
actually in the air seven to eight hours a day. It took us three days to finish 
the race. So it was three days of getting up at <TIME>4:30 in the morning</TIME>. That was 
the killer. We had to be able to take off at the first possible minute because 
our airplane was so slow, and we had to land by sunset. 
</P>
<P>
I had never flown east of <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> or north of <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>, so I had a very small 
scope of what flying is like. There were 48 other planes, and no one had to fly 
at a certain altitude. You just watched what you're doing because it's up to 
you. It always is. The ultimate responsibility is with the pilot in all 
situations. But these races are surprisingly safe. The record for women's air 
races is very good. There were no crashes or injuries in this race, even though 
the possibility and potential was there. 
</P>
<P>
Finishing the race was an incredible experience. It was very challenging and 
very rewarding. The only thing I can compare winning that race to would be like 
getting an Oscar. It is the absolute, the ultimate, to say you won that race in 
that kind of competition. We finished 33rd, which is reputable. We were happy 
we did that well. 
</P>
<P>
Flying feels so free, so liberating. You're totally self-sufficient, really 
relying on you and your machine. I feel so fortunate to be able to do this. 
</P>
<P>
When I first started flying, I took a lot of kidding from the guys. There 
weren't a lot of women at that time taking lessons at that club. A lot of women 
who learn to fly do it because their boyfriends or husbands fly, not because 
they want to. There's a difference. That made me a little unique, because I 
wanted to fly. 
</P>
<P>
I always wanted to fly, but there was always something, like college or the job 
or husband and kids. Women tend to do that, put off their own dreams in favor 
of others. I found myself looking at my 40th birthday, so I decided now it's my 
turn, now I'm going to do it. 
</P>
<P>
Flying is really great. When I get a little crabby, my friends ask me how long 
it's been since I've flown. "You haven't flown in a while, have you?" My 
friends can tell when I haven't flown. 
</P>
<P>
It's an addiction. Anything that makes you feel so good makes you want to keep 
doing it. I'm amazed that people can learn to fly and not keep doing it. I 
can't even imagine that. It would be so painful to not be able to do that 
anymore. Flying adds an entire new dimension to your life. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, January Riddle Bob Grieser 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Interview 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890127-0256 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-27-89 0845EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Obit-Sopwith     01-27 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Sopwith,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Creator Of Sopwith Camel Dead At 101</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAGGIE JACKSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Aviation pioneer Sir <PERSON>Thomas Sopwith</PERSON>, the
adventure-loving creator of the famed World War I Sopwith Camel and
Pup airplanes, died <DATE>today</DATE>, his son said. He was 101.
   Sopwith, who taught himself to fly in <DATE>1910</DATE> and began designing
airplanes at age 26, died before dawn at his <DATE>19th century</DATE> manor home
near Winchester in southern <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, his son <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> said.
   ``Really he died of old age, but he'd had a marvelous (life),''
said <PERSON>Thomas Sopwith</PERSON>, 56, from his office in <LOCATION>Brighton</LOCATION>.
   The elder Sopwith, an accomplished race car driver and yachtsman
before he discovered his passion for airplanes, set several early
flying records.
   ``We had a lot of crashes in those days, but, bless you, it was
fun,'' he recalled on his 100th birthday last year. ``This new
experience of flying was one of the most exhilarating things that
had ever happened to me.''
   Sir <PERSON>John Lidbury</PERSON>, a former director of <ORGANIZATION>Sopwith</ORGANIZATION>'s Hawker Siddeley
aircraft company, said: ``He was a wonderful engineer, with great
technical ability and flair ... Everything he put his hand to he did
thoroughly and well.''
   More than 16,000 Sopwith airplanes were built for action in World
War I, including 6,000 Camels, which shot down more enemy aircraft
than any other allied plane. A <ORGANIZATION>Camel</ORGANIZATION> flown by <PERSON>Roy Brown</PERSON> shot down
the German <PERSON>Baron Von Richthofen</PERSON>, the infamous ``Red Baron.''
   <PERSON>Thomas Octave Murdoch Sopwith</PERSON>, born in <DATE>1888</DATE> into a wealthy
engineering family, was 16 when the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers flew under power
for the first time in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   Sopwith loved all racing, and became involved with motorcycles,
motorboats, ballooning and sailing before taking up flying in <DATE>1910</DATE>.
   He bought his first airplane for 630 pounds (then worth <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY>),
and after two flights as a passenger, he taught himself to fly. His
first solo flight ended in a crash, but he wasn't injured.
   Sopwith founded <ORGANIZATION>Sopwith Aviation Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1912</DATE> and gave up piloting
for design two years later. His company created the Snipe, the Pup
and the <ORGANIZATION>Camel</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Jack Bruce</PERSON>, an aviation historian, said some pilots grew to love
the <ORGANIZATION>Camel</ORGANIZATION>, which he called a ``neurotically responsive machine,''
but only after they had spent time with it.
   ``(It was) difficult to learn how to handle but once pilots had
got the hang of it, (it was) quite exceptionally maneuverable,'' he
told the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Telegraph</ORGANIZATION> last year. ``But a lot of pilots were
petrified at the thought of it.''
   Sopwith's second company, founded between the wars, took the name
of his test pilot <PERSON>Harry Hawker</PERSON> who died in <DATE>1921</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1936</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Sopwith</ORGANIZATION> gambled by building 1,000 of his Hurricane
airplanes without an advance order from the government, but the
plane later became the backbone of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Air Force</ORGANIZATION> when World
War II broke out.
   He retired as chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Hawker Siddeley Group</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1963</DATE>.
   Sopwith was married twice, and both his wives are deceased.
   He is survived by his son.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900828-0054
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900828-0054.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Jet Makes Maiden Flight
   In Air Force Job Rivalry
</HL>
<DATE>
08/28/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<CO>
   NOC MD UTX LK BA GD
</CO>
<IN>
AEROSPACE (ARO)
</IN>
<GV>
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF)
</GV>
<LP>
   EDWARDS AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. -- A version of the Air
Force's next-generation fighter jet, built by Northrop Corp.
and McDonnell Douglas Corp., took to the skies for the first
time yesterday, setting the stage for a showdown with another
version of the aircraft built by a rival team of aerospace
companies.
   The twin-engine YF-23, with a Northrop test pilot, Paul
Metz, at the controls, climbed to 25,000 feet, and functional
checks of basic subsystems were performed during the
early-morning, 50-minute flight. United Technologies Corp.'s
Pratt &amp; Whitney division made the engines on the YF-23.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "The airplane flies very clean, much cleaner than we
expected," <PERSON>Mr. Metz</PERSON> said. "During the climb-out, I was using
considerably less power than I expected, and the chase
airplanes were on afterburners just to stay with me -- with
my landing gear down."
   The other team, composed of <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Co.</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>General Dynamics Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, is scheduled to roll out its Advanced
Tactical Fighter, the YF-22, tomorrow at a <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> site in
<LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. The first flight of that plane is expected
to be next month.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>, which wants 750 of the jets to replace the
aging F-15 fighter, is scheduled to choose the winning team
in <DATE>April</DATE> and award the full-scale development contract three
months later. A second YF-23, which was delivered to a test
facility here in <DATE>June</DATE>, will fly with <ORGANIZATION>General Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION>
engines.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880818-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-18-88 0732EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     08-18 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>On The Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLARKSVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Folks around <LOCATION>Fairgrounds Park</LOCATION> who
thought they saw a lawn mower flying overhead weren't hallucinating.
   Not only did <LOCATION>Clarksville</LOCATION> inventor <PERSON>Freddie Roberts</PERSON> fly the remote
control lawn mower for several minutes in the park, he even made it
fly loops, turns and upside-down.
   ``I made it for fun and to silence a few critics who think I'm
crazy, including my wife,'' <PERSON>Roberts</PERSON>, 44, said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``Who says a lawn mower can't fly? This one can fly but it can't
cut grass ... unless we have a crash landing.''
   The flying mower, made of balsa wood and Styrofoam, weighs less
than 5 pounds and is equipped with a model airplane engine. It is
guided by a model-airplane radio remote control.
   Roberts, a model airplane enthusiast for 30 years, also flies
gyrocopters, ultra-lights and is getting his pilot's license.
   ``I plan to build a (remote control) flying <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> and
sleigh with reindeer for Christmas,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DURANGO, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Folks around <LOCATION>Fairgrounds Park</LOCATION> who
thought they saw a lawn mower flying overhead weren't hallucinating.
   Not only did <LOCATION>Clarksville</LOCATION> inventor <PERSON>Freddie Roberts</PERSON> fly the remote
control lawn mower for several minutes in the park, he even made it
fly loops, turns and upside-down.
   ``I made it for fun and to silence a few critics who think I'm
crazy, including my wife,'' <PERSON>Roberts</PERSON>, 44, said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``Who says a lawn mower can't fly? This one can fly but it can't
cut grass ... unless we have a crash landing.''
   The flying mower, made of balsa wood and Styrofoam, weighs less
than 5 pounds and is equipped with a model airplane engine. It is
guided by a model-airplane radio remote control.
   Roberts, a model airplane enthusiast for 30 years, also flies
gyrocopters, ultra-lights and is getting his pilot's license.
   ``I plan to build a (remote control) flying <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> and
sleigh with reindeer for Christmas,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>OSHKOSH, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Folks around <LOCATION>Fairgrounds Park</LOCATION> who
thought they saw a lawn mower flying overhead weren't hallucinating.
   Not only did <LOCATION>Clarksville</LOCATION> inventor <PERSON>Freddie Roberts</PERSON> fly the remote
control lawn mower for several minutes in the park, he even made it
fly loops, turns and upside-down.
   ``I made it for fun and to silence a few critics who think I'm
crazy, including my wife,'' <PERSON>Roberts</PERSON>, 44, said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``Who says a lawn mower can't fly? This one can fly but it can't
cut grass ... unless we have a crash landing.''
   The flying mower, made of balsa wood and Styrofoam, weighs less
than 5 pounds and is equipped with a model airplane engine. It is
guided by a model-airplane radio remote control.
   Roberts, a model airplane enthusiast for 30 years, also flies
gyrocopters, ultra-lights and is getting his pilot's license.
   ``I plan to build a (remote control) flying <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> and
sleigh with reindeer for Christmas,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06344169 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06344169 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SIERRA; COUNTY; UNUSUAL; NEWSPAPER  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Back in 1949, it remained to be seen if a little 16-page tabloid newspaper
could survive using no headlines, printing only "good" news and featuring
photographs of scenery.;   Could it survive in Sierra County, California's
second-smallest, in a tiny sawmill town that is not even the county seat? How
about if the publisher had no experience in journalism? And what if the paper
only came out every other week?  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SIERRA PAPER THRIVES ON 'GOOD NEWS' ONLY
TABLOID WITHOUT HEADLINES IS DELIVERED BY
AIRPLANE, SKIS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Now, 42 years later, the experiment appears to be a success. <PERSON>Hal Wright</PERSON> is
still in business with his unique <ORGANIZATION>Sierra Booster.</ORGANIZATION>;   "It's hard work, but I
guess we've proved it can be done," said <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> one recent afternoon in his
office a half block off <LOCATION>Loyalton</LOCATION>'s main drag.;   "We just figured we'd do it
our own way and see if it wouldn't work," said <PERSON>Wright</PERSON>, who left a factory job
in the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> to try journalism."It looked like a good way to get out of the
city, earn a living for ourselves in the mountains.";   For the paper's first
30 years or so, all the type was set by <PERSON>Wright</PERSON>'s wife, <PERSON>Allene</PERSON>, on an electric
typewriter. Each line had to be typed twice to determine the spacing between
letters and words to make all the lines the same length.;   In recent times, a
desk-top computer has eased that chore. Otherwise, the paper is largely
unchanged and it has never missed its two-week publishing cycle.;   "I
remember one time, though, in that heavy winter of <DATE>1952</DATE>, when I had to ski
over <LOCATION>Yuba Pass</LOCATION> to get the paper to the printers. I'd never been on skis
before. Took me 2 1/2 days to make it," <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> recalled.;   It was the next
year, he said, when he decided the Booster should own an airplane. He bought a
<DATE>1948</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Aeronca Sedan</ORGANIZATION>, took flying lessons, and began delivering the paper by
airplane on occasion.;   ". . . When I have time I like to take off and fly
around the valley here, see how many papers I can get on porches, throwing
them from the plane," he said.;   Flying in the remote area is fun, he said,
especially when the snow is heavy enough to use skis. "Then you can land and
take off anywhere.";   It is adventurous, too. Once his engine failed and he
made it to the airport with only enough altitude to clear the fence at the end
of the runway by barely a foot.;   <PERSON>Wright</PERSON>, a youthful 87, continues to fly and
belongs to the UFOs -- <ORGANIZATION>United Flying Octogenarians</ORGANIZATION>, a 97-member international
organization of licensed pilots in their 80s.;   He said he has slowed down in
recent years. For the past 10 years, daughter Jan Buck has taken over more and
more of the paper's chores from her parents. And three heart operations this
year caused <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> to lose <MONEY>15 pounds</MONEY>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  McClatchy News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Loyalton  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911209  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  477  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, December 9, 1991
00344169,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890824-0200 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-24-89 1704EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w AM-StealthHistory Adv28-29   08-24 0856</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stealth History, Adv 28-29,0869</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv28-29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Mon-Tues AMs, Aug. 28-29</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Stealth Bomber I and II</HEAD>
<HEAD>Stealth: Old Idea With New Popularity</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first ``stealth'' test of <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION>'s
flying-wing jet bomber was a remarkable success. Trouble was, four
decades ago, nobody much cared.
   Shortly before the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> canceled its order for the strange
YB-49, the late <DATE>1940s</DATE> forerunner to the B-2, <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> test pilot <PERSON>Max
Skelton</PERSON> flew a grand tour of air defense stations in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   ``Nobody found him _ until he was directly overhead,'' says
flying-wing historian <PERSON>Tim Wooldridge</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Air and Space
Museum</ORGANIZATION>. ``So even then, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> knew that that kind of
airplane was difficult to detect. The sad part is that they didn't
continue the testing.''
   Eventually, the lesson began to take hold, though the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
still wouldn't bring itself to embrace the flying-wing design for
decades. Speed and manueverability remained paramount objectives
through the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and <DATE>'60s</DATE>, though stealthiness gradually moved
higher on the priority list.
   Despite representations of the B-2 and its fighter counterpart,
the F-117A, as the only stealth aircraft in the world, the
anti-radar technology has been honed and shared by many other planes
in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> arsenal, some of which remain even more secret than the
B-2 itself. The aging U-2 spy plane and its successor, the SR-71
Blackbird, featured composite coatings. The B-1 and the F-117A
represent advances in wing and body blending as well as the
radar-absorbent materials on their skins.
   Contrary to popular belief, the marriage of stealth technology
with the flying wing, with its slender and hence naturally stealthy
profile, also goes back decades, dating almost to the birth of radar.
   Sir <PERSON>Robert Watson-Watt</PERSON>, the British radar pioneer, said as early
as <DATE>1935</DATE> that the aerial defense applications of his new technology
could be stymied by future bombers designed to reduce their radar
reflectivity. He and other engineers recognized that stealth would
have not so much to do with the size of the airplane, but with its
shape and the materials used to cover it.
   In World War II, as the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>
aggressively improved radar technology, German scientists led the
way in exploring methods to counter it _ including coatings designed
to absorb, rather than reflect, radar energy. These radar-absorbent
materials, or <ORGANIZATION>RAM</ORGANIZATION> for short, were first used to shield the snorkels
of German submarines from detection by radar-equipped aircraft. Too
late, really, the engineers turned their attention to their own
aircraft.
   Almost by happenstance, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> had already delivered a painful
lesson to the Third <PERSON>Reich</PERSON> about bombers and stealth technology.
Early in the war, the tiny de <ORGANIZATION>Havilland Company</ORGANIZATION> had answered the
panic call for virtually anything that would fly by building a
cheap, two-engine machine out of plywood, spruce and balsa. It was
initially scoffed at, but the Mosquito, which carried nary a
defensive gun, had the lowest loss rate of any World War II bomber
thanks to its speed, flying altitude and the nearly invisible
flicker it produced on radar screens.
   That lesson in mind, the brothers <PERSON>Walter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Reimar Horten</PERSON>,
working with a super-secret <ORGANIZATION>Luftwaffe</ORGANIZATION> group known as Sonderkommando
9, set out to build a super-Mosquito, one even stranger in design.
They came up with a flying wing, powered by two jet engines buried
behind the cockpit. But too late: The HoIX, the only prototype to
fly, in early <DATE>1945</DATE>, was destroyed when one of the engines failed; a
never-flown copy rests at the <ORGANIZATION>National Air and Space Museum</ORGANIZATION>'s
storage complex at Silver Hill, <LOCATION>Md</LOCATION>.
   ``It is a remarkably clean-looking airplane,'' says <PERSON>Wooldridge</PERSON>, a
museum official and the author of ``Winged Wonders: The Story of
Flying Wings.''
   The test models were covered with plywood, but production
versions were to have a skin mixing plywood, sawdust, charcoal and
glue _ a compound expressly intended to absorb radar waves. The
<PERSON>Hortens</PERSON> had built a high-load-bearing plane combining jet power, the
low-profile shape of the flying wing and integral <ORGANIZATION>RAM</ORGANIZATION>. It was the
B-2 of its day.
   More frightening to contemplate is how the war might have turned
if <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> had managed to deploy a larger model that the <PERSON>Hortens</PERSON> had
actually started to assemble in <DATE>April 1945</DATE>, the HoXVIII. It was an
enormous, six-jet flying-wing bomber, designed to fly at least 7,400
miles with an 8,000-pound bombload. Were it not for <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>'s
imminent defeat, that aircraft, rivaling the size of the B-2, might
have flown to bomb <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Unlike <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s rocket scientists, the <LOCATION>Horten</LOCATION> brothers were
rebuffed in their bid to pursue their breakthroughs for the Allies
after the war. Most <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> warplane manufacturers focused on the
obvious alternatives to stealth for making their craft less
vulnerable _ more speed, higher altitudes, heavier armor and
on-board defenses.
   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Jack Northrop</PERSON>, the founder and longtime design leader
of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> company that bears his name, waged a lonely
campaign for something entirely different _ though the <PERSON>Horten</PERSON>
brothers, headed for virtual exile in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, would not have
thought it so.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for AMs Aug. 28-29</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890828-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-28-89 0047EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-StealthHistory     08-28 0844</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stealth History,0858</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stealth: Old Idea With New Popularity</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Stealth Bomber I</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first ``stealth'' test of <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION>'s
flying-wing jet bomber was a remarkable success. Trouble was, four
decades ago, nobody much cared.
   Shortly before the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> canceled its order for the strange
YB-49, the late <DATE>1940s</DATE> forerunner to the B-2, <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> test pilot <PERSON>Max
Skelton</PERSON> flew a grand tour of air defense stations in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   ``Nobody found him _ until he was directly overhead,'' says
flying-wing historian <PERSON>Tim Wooldridge</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Air and Space
Museum</ORGANIZATION>. ``So even then, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> knew that that kind of
airplane was difficult to detect. The sad part is that they didn't
continue the testing.''
   Eventually, the lesson began to take hold, though the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
still wouldn't bring itself to embrace the flying-wing design for
decades. Speed and manueverability remained paramount objectives
through the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and <DATE>'60s</DATE>, though stealthiness gradually moved
higher on the priority list.
   Despite representations of the B-2 and its fighter counterpart,
the F-117A, as the only stealth aircraft in the world, the
anti-radar technology has been honed and shared by many other planes
in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> arsenal, some of which remain even more secret than the
B-2 itself. The aging U-2 spy plane and its successor, the SR-71
Blackbird, featured composite coatings. The B-1 and the F-117A
represent advances in wing and body blending as well as the
radar-absorbent materials on their skins.
   Contrary to popular belief, the marriage of stealth technology
with the flying wing, with its slender and hence naturally stealthy
profile, also goes back decades, dating almost to the birth of radar.
   Sir <PERSON>Robert Watson-Watt</PERSON>, the British radar pioneer, said as early
as <DATE>1935</DATE> that the aerial defense applications of his new technology
could be stymied by future bombers designed to reduce their radar
reflectivity. He and other engineers recognized that stealth would
have not so much to do with the size of the airplane, but with its
shape and the materials used to cover it.
   In World War II, as the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>
aggressively improved radar technology, German scientists led the
way in exploring methods to counter it _ including coatings designed
to absorb, rather than reflect, radar energy. These radar-absorbent
materials, or <ORGANIZATION>RAM</ORGANIZATION> for short, were first used to shield the snorkels
of German submarines from detection by radar-equipped aircraft. Too
late, really, the engineers turned their attention to their own
aircraft.
   Almost by happenstance, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> had already delivered a painful
lesson to the Third <PERSON>Reich</PERSON> about bombers and stealth technology.
Early in the war, the tiny de <ORGANIZATION>Havilland Company</ORGANIZATION> had answered the
panic call for virtually anything that would fly by building a
cheap, two-engine machine out of plywood, spruce and balsa. It was
initially scoffed at, but the Mosquito, which carried nary a
defensive gun, had the lowest loss rate of any World War II bomber
thanks to its speed, flying altitude and the nearly invisible
flicker it produced on radar screens.
   That lesson in mind, the brothers <PERSON>Walter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Reimar Horten</PERSON>,
working with a super-secret <ORGANIZATION>Luftwaffe</ORGANIZATION> group known as Sonderkommando
9, set out to build a super-Mosquito, one even stranger in design.
They came up with a flying wing, powered by two jet enginesburied
behind the cockpit. But too late: The HoIX, the only prototype to
fly, in early <DATE>1945</DATE>, was destroyed when one of the engines failed; a
never-flown copy rests at the <ORGANIZATION>National Air and Space Museum</ORGANIZATION>'s
storage complex at Silver Hill, <LOCATION>Md</LOCATION>.
   ``It is a remarkably clean-looking airplane,'' says <PERSON>Wooldridge</PERSON>, a
museum official and the author of ``Winged Wonders: The Story of
Flying Wings.''
   The test models were covered with plywood, but production
versions were to have a skin mixing plywood, sawdust, charcoal and
glue _ a compound expressly intended to absorb radar waves. The
<PERSON>Hortens</PERSON> had built a high-load-bearing plane combining jet power, the
low-profile shape of the flying wing and integral <ORGANIZATION>RAM</ORGANIZATION>. It was the
B-2 of its day.
   More frightening to contemplate is how the war might have turned
if <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> had managed to deploy a larger model that the <PERSON>Hortens</PERSON> had
actually started to assemble in <DATE>April 1945</DATE>, the HoXVIII. It was an
enormous, six-jet flying-wing bomber, designed to fly at least 7,400
miles with an 8,000-pound bombload. Were it not for <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>'s
imminent defeat, that aircraft, rivaling the size of the B-2, might
have flown to bomb <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Unlike <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s rocket scientists, the <LOCATION>Horten</LOCATION> brothers were
rebuffed in their bid to pursue their breakthroughs for the Allies
after the war. Most <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> warplane manufacturers focused on the
obvious alternatives to stealth for making their craft less
vulnerable _ more speed, higher altitudes, heavier armor and
on-board defenses.
   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Jack Northrop</PERSON>, the founder and longtime design leader
of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> company that bears his name, waged a lonely
campaign for something entirely different _ though the <PERSON>Horten</PERSON>
brothers, headed for virtual exile in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, would not have
thought it so.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881122-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-22-88 1858EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StealthBomber 1stLd-Writethru a0705 11-22 0937</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stealth Bomber, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0705,0959</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mystery-Shrouded B-2 Bomber Unveiled</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 9th graf, `The General' to reflect that $500 million is
a
rounded estimate. INSERTS 4 grafs after 17th graf, ``For years' to
UPDATE with senators' comments, uncertain timing of first flight.
Picks up 18th graf pvs, As the....'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos PALX1, PALX3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PALMDALE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> unveiled its
sinister-looking B-2 stealth bomber <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, giving the world its
first look at the gray-and-black flying wing designed to evade enemy
radar and deliver nuclear weapons.
   The bomber, which has never been flown, was towed slowly out of a
hangar at <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Plant 42 in the <LOCATION>Mojave Desert</LOCATION> to cheers from an
invitation-only crowd of 2,000 workers, military brass, media and
industry representatives.
   The B-2, built primarily by <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, resembles a huge,
tailless manta ray, with wide sweeping wings blending smoothly into
rounded cockpit and engine housings on the top side.
   The rollout ceremony, conducted before a giant American flag, was
in part a celebration of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> industrial ingenuity and in part, a
bit of high-tech saber rattling.
   Gen. <PERSON>Larry D. Welch</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>'s chief of staff, said the
plane's declared ability to slip through radar at all altitudes to
deliver its payload of nuclear bombs represents a potent deterrent
to those who would attack the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   ``Its stealth capability will permit it to penetrate the most
sophisticated air defenses and survive well into the <DATE>21st century</DATE>,''
<PERSON>Welch</PERSON> said. ``The B-2 is a superb example of the inherent
technological advantage of free society.''
   The rollout followed by three weeks the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>'s release of a
photo of another closely guarded project, <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s stealth
fighter, the F-117A. That plane has been flying since <DATE>1981</DATE> and was
declared ready for wartime missions in <DATE>1983</DATE>; its existence was
acknowledged because the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> was preparing to start its first
daylight flights.
   Nearly everything surrounding the stealth bomber is secret,
including the cost.
   The <ORGANIZATION>General Accounting Office</ORGANIZATION> estimates the fleet of 132 stealth
bombers the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> wants to assemble over the next several years
could cost taxpayers <MONEY>$68 billion</MONEY>. That would put them at more than
<MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> a copy.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> puts the total cost of the program at <MONEY>$30 billion</MONEY>
to <MONEY>$40 billion</MONEY>.
   The stealth gets its name from the claim that it will be
extremely difficult to detect by enemy radar, due to the extensive
use of exotic composite materials, some of which absorb rather than
reflect radar waves; its lack of sharp surface angles; and a
cross-section that offers a very small profile to radar.
   The plane is a ``flying wing,'' a design resurrected from the
<DATE>1940s</DATE> that steers with flaps on the rear of the wings rather than
with a tail. The B-2 displayed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was gray on top and black
beneath.
   Nobody was allowed to see the B-2 from the rear, presumably
because revealing the design of its engine exhaust system might help
enemy detection efforts.
   <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Edward C.</PERSON> ``Pete'' <PERSON>Aldridge Jr.</PERSON> told the
gathering the program's expense represents an investment in safety.
   ``Let all of us remember <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s enduring hope and prayer that
the B-2 will strengthen the cause of peace and that this magnificent
aircraft will never be flown in anger,'' <PERSON>Aldridge</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Thomas V. Jones</PERSON> saluted employees of his
company and of subcontractors who have worked on the project for a
decade, unable to describe their work.
   ``For years, they've been working in a kind of honorable exile,''
<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> said. ``They persevered, and now you can see what it's all
been about.''
   The first flight on most airplanes is six to 12 weeks after
rollout, but <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> officials refuse to commit to a date for the
first flight of the B-2.
   One of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senators at the ceremony, <PERSON>Pete Wilson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Calif.</LOCATION>,
said budget contraints could force a ``stretch out' of stealth
bomber production, although he noted that influential Democrats like
<PERSON>Sen. Sam Nunn</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ga.</LOCATION>, give the program bipartisan backing.
   Sen. <PERSON>James Exon</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Neb.</LOCATION>, said: ``Here, today, with the unveiling
of the stealth bomber, I have never felt better about the deterrence
of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. I think we've got a great airplane.''
   ``It has the potential to render obsolescent a very great
investment in Soviet air defenses,'' <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> said.
   As the bomber was towed out of a massive hanger, an <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
band broke into the stirring ``Stealth Fanfare,'' composed for the
occasion by <ORGANIZATION>Tech</ORGANIZATION>. Sgt. <PERSON>Allen Yankee</PERSON>, 35, of <LOCATION>McMinnville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, a
saxophonist in the band.
   The B-2 project was launched by former President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>.
Critics, including the private Union of Concerned Scientists, say
the B-2 deployment, planned for the early <DATE>1990s</DATE>, would hamper arms
control efforts by posing a greater threat than current planes to
enemy command posts and mobile missiles.
   The B-2 is described as an all-altitude penetration bomber, as
opposed to the B-1 bomber, which is designed to penetrate enemy air
defenses at low altitudes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> says the plane is 69 feet long, about the length of
an F-16 fighter plane. Its wingspan, at 172 feet, is almost as wide
as the aging B-52 it is designed to replace.
   Flight tests will begin _ probably early next year _ at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards
Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>, about 70 miles north of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Mojave
Desert</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> said the maiden flight will be the short hop
from the plant at <LOCATION>Palmdale</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON>.
   The bomber, which has inspired intense curiosity among aviation
buffs, has already inspired models, and a mockup appears in a
current automobile commercial.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880707-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-07-88 2044EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-BoeingOrder     07-07 0220</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boeing Order,0229</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quantas Orders Three Boeing Planes for About $380 Million</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Australian airline <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> has ordered two
<ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 747-400s and one 767-300 with extended range capability,
<ORGANIZATION>Boeing Commercial Airplanes</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The planes will be delivered between <DATE>September</DATE> and <DATE>December 1989</DATE>
and will cost about <MONEY>$380 million</MONEY>, including spare parts and
support, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> said in a news release.
   Qantas Chairman <PERSON>J.B. Leslie</PERSON> said the new planes, which will give
<ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> a 43-plane fleet, will serve the growing tourist market to
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. The airplanes will be financed by <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION>' foreign
exchange earnings and by overseas borrowings, he said.
   The order gives <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> six of the advanced-technology 747-400s,
the world's largest commercial jetliner, and five extended-range
767-300s.
   The four-engine 747-400, which made its first flight this
<DATE>spring</DATE>, can carry up to 660 passengers. With a more typical
configuration for 412 in two classes, the plane can fly more than
7,300 nautical miles, or from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>.
   The twin-engine 767-300 is capable of hauling up to 375
passengers, but can fly more than 7,000 miles with 210 aboard.
   So far this year, <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> has had orders for 401 jetliners worth
<MONEY>$18.2 billion</MONEY>, compared with 366 jets worth a record <MONEY>$19.9 billion</MONEY>
in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> now has 148 orders for 747-400s and 103 orders for
767-300s.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900830-0063
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900830-0063.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Lockheed Unveils a Prototype YF-22,
   Its Competitor to Replace F-15 Fighter
   ----
</HL>
<DATE>
08/30/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A2
</SO>
<CO>
   LK GD BA NOC MD GE UTX
</CO>
<IN>
AEROSPACE (ARO)
</IN>
<GV>
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF)
</GV>
<LP>
   PALMDALE, Calif. -- Lockheed Corp. and two other defense
contractors displayed a prototype of their candidate in the
competition to build the Air Force's next-generation fighter
jet.
   The winner of the contest between two proposed versions of
the so-called Advanced Tactical Fighter, or ATF, eventually
would replace the aging F-15s that have been pressed into
service in the Middle East.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The first YF-22, as the new Lockheed plane is known,
wouldn't be available for use by the military until the
beginning of the next decade. By that time, both company and
<ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> officials stress, the F-15 will be nearly 30 years
old, and many Third World nations are expected to have added
to their arsenals today's top-of-the-line Soviet fighters,
the MiG-29 Fulcrum and Su-27 Flanker. Already, 11 countries
possess the former.
   The YF-22, which <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> is manufacturing with <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Co.</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>General Dynamics Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, is competing with a YF-23 built
by <ORGANIZATION>Northrop Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>McDonnell Douglas Corp</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION>
plane made a 50-minute maiden flight earlier this week,
climbing to 25,000 feet and flying at 333 miles an hour.
   "As current events demonstrate, there are those in the
world willing to test American resolve and readiness," said
Gen. <PERSON>Ronald Yates</PERSON>, who runs the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Systems Command</ORGANIZATION>.
"That, in a broad sense, is why we need the <ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION>."
   In an interview, YF-22 program chief <PERSON>Sherman Mullin</PERSON> said
the fighter is tentatively set to make its first flight on
<DATE>Sept. 14</DATE>, but <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> officials insisted yesterday that
they didn't want to be pinned down on an exact date. Lockheed
Chairman <PERSON>Daniel Tellep</PERSON> reiterated the company's strongly held
view that the victor on the <ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION> won't be "he who flies first,
but he who flies best."
   The <ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION>, through a unique combination of speed, agility,
range and stealthiness, is designed to take and maintain
control over enemy airspace, providing ground troops and
ships with safe room to maneuver in battle. "It will preserve
our security well into the next century," Gen. <PERSON>Yates</PERSON>
asserted.
   But, in the eyes of many lawmakers, the federal budget
deficit remains as much of a threat as potential Third World
aggressors. And at a projected <MONEY>$51 million</MONEY> per aircraft -- a
<PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> higher price tag than that carried by the most advanced
model of the F-15 -- it's doubtful to many that the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>
will ever be authorized to buy all of the 750 ATFs that it
now says it needs. The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> also wants its own variant of the
<ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION>, and currently has plans to procure 546 of them to
replace the F-14.
   The YF-22, which was presented while <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON>'s "Ride of the
Valkyries" blared over a speaker system, in some respects
resembles <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION>'s F-117 Stealth fighter, with its angular
airframe. In fact, <PERSON>Mr. Mullin</PERSON> called it "loosely speaking,
the son of the F-117." With four tails and stubby wings, the
aircraft also has a far different appearance from the rival
YF-23. It is shorter than the <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION> plane, which features
a more cigar-shaped fuselage: 64 feet, 2 inches, vs. 67 feet,
four inches.
   The stakes are high for all the companies involved,
including engine makers <ORGANIZATION>General Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>United
Technologies Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Pratt &amp; Whitney</ORGANIZATION> unit, with this being
seen as the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION>'s last major airplane project
of the century that is still up for grabs. "You don't have to
be a <ORGANIZATION>Rhodes Scholar</ORGANIZATION> to see that the military-aircraft
business is compressing," <PERSON>Mr. Mullin</PERSON> said. "The loser is
going to be hit very hard."
   Still, <PERSON>Mr. Mullin</PERSON> said that even with expected cuts and
stretch-outs in the defense budget, <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> can foresee the
<ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION> generating as much as <MONEY>$100 billion</MONEY> in revenue for its
team over the years between the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>
requirements. "Admittedly, there is no guarantee that is
going to happen," <PERSON>Mr. Mullin</PERSON> said. "But we just can't
envision the production of 1970-era airplanes in the year
<DATE>2000</DATE>."
   Collectively, the industry has sunk more than <MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY>
into the 54-month demonstration-and-validation phase of the
<ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION> program, meaning that even if <PERSON>Mr. Mullin</PERSON>'s rosy
assessment is correct, it would take about 10 years for the
winners just to recover their investment. Major
subcontractors on the project have contributed another <MONEY>$800
million</MONEY> or so.
   The <ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION> "would be a nice piece of business for us," said
<PERSON>William Anders</PERSON>, vice chairman at <ORGANIZATION>General Dynamics</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>B. Daniel
Pinick</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION>'s defense and space group, said
that for his company, the YF-22 "meets one of our long-term
objectives: to be a maker of tactical aircraft."
   "The reason for that is simple," he added. "If you look at
where defense dollars around the world are going, it is into
these types of planes."
   But the success of the YF-22 is clearly most important for
<ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION>. Although <PERSON>Mr. Tellep</PERSON> asserted that winning the <ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION>
is "not make it or break it for <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> aircraft
activities," the company's historic role as a major supplier
of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> warplanes would almost surely be threatened by a loss
of this business. Although the YF-22 roll-out ceremony at
<ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION>'s factory here was at times drowned out by riveting
on P-3 aircraft, most of the company's major lines have wound
down or are slated to do so soon. In addition, the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>
recently terminated the company's contract to build the
successor to the P-3, the P-7.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090590-0046 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 271524 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 5, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
828 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JOURNEY OVER, SOLAR PLANE TAKES ITS PLACE IN THE SUN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JENIFER WARREN and EDITH STANLEY, TIMES STAFF WRITERS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SPOT, N.C. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A <LOCATION>Riverside County</LOCATION> man concluded history's first coast-to-coast flight in a 
solar-powered airplane here <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, abandoning plans to fly nine more miles to 
his original destination because of high winds. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Eric Raymond</PERSON>, 33, said winds gusting up to 35 m.p.h. persuaded him to scrub the 
last leg of his journey and instead take his plane by trailer to historic <PERSON>Kill 
Devil Hills</PERSON>, the sand dunes near <LOCATION>Kitty Hawk</LOCATION> where <PERSON>Orville</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wilbur Wright</PERSON> 
pioneered engine-powered aviation 87 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
"I landed basically at the beach yesterday," <PERSON>Raymond</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, one month 
and two days after his transcontinental trek began in the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> desert. 
"With the forecast for winds and storms, it doesn't look like it is worth 
flying the last nine miles." 
</P>
<P>
Including <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s 32-mile flight to Spot, where a storm forced him to land on 
a farmer's turf field, <PERSON>Raymond</PERSON> logged 2,467 miles during 119 hours and 23 
minutes in the air. 
</P>
<P>
Those unofficial figures easily make Raymond -- a national hang-gliding 
champion from <LOCATION>Lake Elsinore</LOCATION> -- a world record holder in solar-powered aviation. 
The longest previous flight -- in a craft designed by <PERSON>Paul MacCready</PERSON> of 
<LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> -- was across the English Channel in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Raymond, a lithe, bespectacled fellow, said he is not interested in records or 
recognition. He said his mission was to enlighten people about the potential of 
traveling with the help of the sun. 
</P>
<P>
"Solar is already quite practical for sporting aircraft," said <PERSON>Raymond</PERSON>, who 
built his 195-pound plane called Sun-Seeker, which resembles a giant dragonfly, 
in his garage. "Eventually, if the technology keeps improving . . . you will 
start seeing bigger and bigger and faster airplanes that are solar-powered." 
</P>
<P>
Crowds of tourists, reporters and local aviators gathered at historic Kill 
<ORGANIZATION>Devil Hills</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> and <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, anticipating the pilot's arrival. Some were 
disappointed when they learned Sun-Seeker would not be landing amid the 
rippling sea oats surrounding First Flight Airport, but most seemed impressed 
by <ORGANIZATION>Raymond</ORGANIZATION>'s feat. 
</P>
<P>
"What <PERSON>Eric</PERSON> has done is an example of creative engineering," said <PERSON>Gene 
O'Bleness</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>First Flight Society</ORGANIZATION>, a group of pilots 
and aviation history buffs. His group, along with the <PERSON>Kitty Hawk Kites</PERSON>, held a 
cake-and-champagne reception for <ORGANIZATION>Raymond</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and presented him 
with a leather bomber jacket with "Sun-Seeker" embroidered on the back. 
</P>
<P>
Raymond's journey began in the desert east of <LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 16</DATE>. <DATE>Two days 
later</DATE>, Sun-Seeker -- which uses solar cells to power an electric motor used 
during takeoffs and landings -- was damaged in <LOCATION>Lordsburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>, forcing the 
crew to return to <LOCATION>Lake Elsinore</LOCATION> for repairs. 
</P>
<P>
The flight recommenced <DATE>Aug. 2</DATE>, and <PERSON>Raymond</PERSON> hoped to reach <PERSON>Kitty Hawk</PERSON> in 10 
days. Poor flying conditions -- ranging from thunderstorms to head winds that 
at times blew the feather-light craft backward -- slowed the pilot's progress. 
The plane was grounded by foul weather on 10 days. 
</P>
<P>
Still, the thrill of the journey, with its potpourri of sights and encounters, 
overshadowed frustrations caused by the sluggish pace. 
</P>
<P>
"It's nice to fly across the country," <PERSON>Raymond</PERSON> said, recalling how the panorama 
changed gradually from desert to woods to farmland and mountains. 
</P>
<P>
Seeking to avoid big cities with crowded skies, <PERSON>Raymond</PERSON> plotted a southerly 
course that took him through some of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s most lonely reaches. Among the 
crew's nighttime stopovers were such places as <LOCATION>Cornudas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chanute</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Sedalia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>West Liberty</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The townsfolk and airport operators, <PERSON>Raymond</PERSON> said, were wonderfully hospitable. 
In <LOCATION>Littlefield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, the ground crew following Raymond accidentally wrecked 
the trailer needed to haul Sun-Seeker back to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. The local <ORGANIZATION>Chamber of 
Commerce</ORGANIZATION> president sent a team of mechanics to help out. 
</P>
<P>
"We were thinking, 'Oh boy, what is this going to cost?' " recalled <PERSON>Raymond</PERSON>'s 
wife, <LOCATION>Aida</LOCATION>, who followed her husband across the country in a chase plane. The 
local official, a glider pilot, refused to accept any money for the work. 
</P>
<P>
After resuming the trip, stiff winds and weak thermals -- the updrafts of warm 
air that lift Sun-Seeker to soaring altitude -- forced back-to-back landings in 
grassy fields in <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>. The plane, made mostly of carbon fiber, suffered 
only minor damage to one wing that struck a bush. 
</P>
<P>
Raymond spent the long hours in his tiny cockpit -- which measures only 21 
inches wide -- reading maps, lunching on the fruit and cookies his wife packed 
each day and maneuvering his craft in the wind. The only discomfort was the 
heat. 
</P>
<P>
"I have an air vent, but I close it when I'm trying to make the most distance," 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
A sportsman at heart, <PERSON>Raymond</PERSON> took advantage of the fierce winds <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and 
went sail boarding. After returning home, he plans to start on his next 
project: a solar-powered dirigible capable of flying around the world. 
</P>
<P>
Warren reported from <LOCATION>Riverside</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Stanley</ORGANIZATION> reported from <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Solar-powered Sun-Seeker, pictured in July test flight, logged 2,467 
miles during more than 119 hours in the air. MIKE SERGIEFF / For The Times; 
Photo, Sun-Seeker pilot Eric Raymond says his mission was not to set records 
but to enlighten people about the potential of solar power. ROBERT GABRIEL / 
Los Angeles Times; Map, FLIGHT OF THE SUN-SEEKER, AP / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FEATS; CROSS COUNTRY TRIPS; AIRPLANES; SOLAR ENERGY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880523-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-23-88 2050EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Tilt-Rotor     05-23 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tilt-Rotor,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Production Tilt-Rotor Aircraft Unveiled</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DN2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY JORDEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ARLINGTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first non-experimental aircraft that
flies both like a helicopter and an airplane rolled into the
spotlight <DATE>Monday</DATE>, hailed as an aviation milestone by legislators
and top military brass.
   The V-22 Osprey, a tilt-rotor craft that takes off and hovers
like a helicopter and flies like an airplane, received a standing
ovation from a crowd of 1,600. The crowd watched as the camouflaged
craft was towed onto the tarmac at <ORGANIZATION>Bell Helicopter Textron Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Flight Research Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first flight of the V-22, which has been in development for
30 years, is scheduled for <DATE>Aug. 15</DATE>. An advanced experimental model,
the XV-15, has been flying since <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   Fort Worth-based <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Helicopter Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>
are jointly developing the V-22 for the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Marines</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION>. The three services plan to buy 682 of the twin-engine
aircraft at an estimated cost of <MONEY>$16.6 million</MONEY> each.
   ``It's kind of awesome,'' Marine Corps Commandant <PERSON>Alfred M. Gray
Jr.</PERSON> told the crowd.
   ``It works, it's ahead of schedule and will be a sound
investment for taxpayers' money,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>William L.
Ball III</PERSON>, comparing the tilt-rotor's production to the jet engine's
development as aviation milestones.
   ``You are proving every day that a great country can still
outthink, out-design and out-produce all comers,'' <PERSON>Ball</PERSON> said.
   The three military services plan to use the V-22 for combat
assault, search and rescue, medical evacuation and special-forces
missions. Other uses, including anti-submarine warfare, also are
being studied. The cabin can carry 24 combat-equipped troops in
addition to a crew of three.
   ``On our abortive rescue attempt made in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> a few years ago,
think what could have happened if they'd had an Osprey,'' said
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> Speaker <PERSON>Jim Wright</PERSON>, referring to the failed <DATE>1980</DATE> rescue of 44
American hostages from <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>.
   The Osprey, about the size of a medium transport aircraft, has a
stocky 57.3-foot-long fuselage and twin engines mounted on thick,
stubby wings. Its engines point upward during takeoff and landing,
with 38-foot diameter rotor blades that parallel the ground.
   The engines rotate, or ``tilt,'' forward once the V-22 is
airborne. Rotors lock into place and act like oversized propellers,
pulling the Osprey through the air like a conventional aircraft.
   The tilt-rotor can fly with the speed and range of a turboprop
plane _ more than 360 mph _ but doesn't require an airport or
runway. It also can hover like a helicopter.
   ``I'm convinced that in the <DATE>next 20 years</DATE> there will be
thousands of these in use,'' said Bell President L.M. ``Jack''
<PERSON>Horner</PERSON>.
   Bell has talked with <ORGANIZATION>American Airlines</ORGANIZATION> and several commuter
companies about civilian uses for the craft, a spokesman said.
   ``The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> (and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>) Port Authority is a strong
supporter of this concept,'' said <PERSON>Horner</PERSON>. ``We could build a lot of
V-22s for the cost of one airport.
   The British-designed Harrier jump-jet also takes off and lands
vertically, but using jet-propulsion rather than a rotor system.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030690-0162 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 185651 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 6, 1990, Tuesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 1; Column 6; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
508 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
L.A. TO D.C. IN 68 MINUTES; 
</P>
<P>
RECORD 2,200 M.P.H. FLIGHT IS LAST FOR U.S. SPY PLANE; 
</P>
<P>
JET WILL BE HOUSED AT SMITHSONIAN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From United Press International 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CHANTILLY, Va. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>'s SR-71 Blackbird spy plane smashed a transcontinental speed 
record today as it flew into retirement and the history books. 
</P>
<P>
The nation's fastest operational airplane took off from <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> 
in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> at <TIME>4:30 a.m.</TIME>, refueled offshore, flew back over <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> and then 
shot off eastward at supersonic speeds that triggered a <TIME>6:01 a.m.</TIME> sonic boom. 
</P>
<P>
The Los Angeles-to-Washington flight was 1 hour, 8 minutes and 17 seconds, said 
the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution</ORGANIZATION>, which will keep the plane in the <ORGANIZATION>National Air and 
Space Museum</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
On the way to its retirement home at the museum, the airplane broke four flight 
time records, including the world record of 4 hours, 12 minutes and 10 seconds 
for a flight from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"We figured it would make it in about an hour," said <PERSON>Barbara Kornylo</PERSON> of 
<ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION>, the builder of the airplane. 
</P>
<P>
The SR-71, designed in the early <DATE>1960s</DATE>, is able to cruise faster than three 
times the speed of sound. The planes were built with a titanium alloy and can 
withstand temperatures exceeding 800 degrees Fahrenheit. The first flight of 
the SR-71 was on <DATE>Dec. 22, 1964</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
The Blackbird flies at an average speed of 2,200 m.p.h., about 400 m.p.h. to 
500 m.p.h. faster than the Concorde, which is the fastest airplane in 
commercial operation, <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Jim Ragsdale</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The SR-71 was never designed for commercial passenger use. It has seats only 
for a pilot and a reconnaissance systems officer and was designed to fly high, 
fast and unarmed on photographic reconnaissance missions. Because of the high 
altitudes the aircraft can reach, crew members on missions had to wear pressure 
suits and be connected to life support systems. 
</P>
<P>
The SR-71s were officially retired on <DATE>Feb. 26</DATE>, but <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed</ORGANIZATION> requested one of 
them to break some records publicly on its last flight, something that the 
plane has been doing -- but on a classified basis -- for years, <PERSON>Kornylo</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
In addition to breaking the world Los Angeles-to-Washington record set several 
years ago by pilot <PERSON>Brooke Knapp</PERSON> in her Lear jet 35A, the Blackbird also set 
speed records for the following: <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 2,153.24 m.p.h.; 
<LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, 2,242.48 m.p.h., and <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 
2,200.94 m.p.h. 
</P>
<P>
The Blackbird, after fueling over the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION> from an <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> KC-135, a 
type of flying gas station, passed through a radar screen and quickly 
accelerated past the speed of sound. 
</P>
<P>
Southland residents, hearing the sonic boom, called police to report the sound 
of an explosion or earthquake, Sgt. <PERSON>James McClard</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
While the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> has never publicly revealed how many SR-71s it commissioned 
to be built, 12 of them were stationed at <ORGANIZATION>Beale Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Northern 
California</LOCATION> in <DATE>January</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Besides the SR-71 that flew <DATE>today</DATE>, one is going to a museum at <ORGANIZATION>Warner-Robbins 
Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, another to <ORGANIZATION>March Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Southern 
use in high-altitude research. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Spectators view Blackbird spy plane at Dulles International Airport near 
Washington after its last flight. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880627-0142 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS: Watching the Warbirds Fly </HL>
<AUTHOR> Joe Morgenstern </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> Chino, Calif.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As in a dream, a P-51 Mustang fighter from World War II materialized out of the bright blue sky, thundered past the crowds at the edge of the airport runway, swept up into a steep, banking turn and disappeared into dazzlements of sunlight. 
Then, as if a Mustang weren't enough, a Japanese Zero -- a real Zero, for <PERSON>Pete</PERSON>'s sake! -- swooped down from nowhere into a slow roll, displaying the vivid red suns on its khaki wings. 

   Whose dream, you ask? 
Why, my dream, for one, the martial fantasy of a child of the <DATE>1940s</DATE>. 
But I'm hardly alone in my delight with such fly-by-day entertainments as the one staged here recently at a hot, dusty airport that started life as a training field in World War II. 
At airports across the country, crowds of all ages are turning out to ogle airplanes old and new. 
Another air-show season is upon us. 

   No one knows how many people go to air shows, though attendance must be up there in the millions. 
It's tricky enough to keep track of the events. 
One source, an aviation monthly in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> called the <LOCATION>Pacific Flyer</LOCATION>, lists 61 shows, fairs, expos and "warbird extravaganzas" in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> before the end of <DATE>September</DATE>. 
Some of the big ones star the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>'s Thunderbirds or the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s Blue Angels, stunt teams that propagandize heart-stoppingly, if indirectly, on behalf of military aviation. 
Many shows feature fly-bys of World War II aircraft that have been restored by private owners, or by outfits such as <ORGANIZATION>Chino</ORGANIZATION>'s Planes of Fame Museum. 
A few shows end in tragedy or near-tragedy. 
Last month at <LOCATION>El Toro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>Marine Corps</ORGANIZATION> pilot was severely injured when his Hornet fighter crashed during a demonstration loop. 

   The closest call at Chino, less than an hour's drive east of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, came when a gust of wind blew a big red umbrella off a Superpretzel stand, and the umbrella dealt a glancing blow to a spectator's camcorder. 
There was no lack of thrills for me, though. 
This was my first warbird extravaganza, and I was a pushover from the start. 

   Like other little boys during World War II, I'd drawn furtive pictures of fighters and bombers at my grammar school desk. 
In <DATE>1944</DATE>, at the age of 12, I had even written a poem -- a love poem, I'm afraid you'd have to call it -- in praise of the P-51 Mustang. 
"This ship has the lines of a powerful steed," it began, "and she's got the speed of a shot." 
I remember sending it to the Mustang's builders, <ORGANIZATION>North American Aircraft</ORGANIZATION>, and receiving an 8x10 glossy of my inamorata in flight. 

   Now I was watching a Mustang, as well as the last flyable Zero in the world, or so they said, and also startling myself, at every turn, with nuggets of knowledge I hadn't known I still possessed. 

   What, for example, was that twin-engine relic parked next to a hangar over there? 
A <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Lodestar</ORGANIZATION>, of course, its silhouette straight out of my old aircraft spotter's guide. 
The little low-winged trainer? 
A <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> SJN-5; I studied my reflection in the gorgeously re-chromed spinner of its <ORGANIZATION>Hamilton Standard</ORGANIZATION> propeller. 
The lumbering bomber with four engines and twin tails? 
I knew it for a B-24 Liberator before the announcer uttered a word. 
And when he asked the audience, "What did the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> version of the B-24 look like?" 
I could have hollered, as someone else did: "Single tail!" 

   It's easy to see why air shows are so popular. 
First off, they cross the carnival with the shopping mall. 
At one booth inside a hangar at Chino you could buy video highlights of the <DATE>1986</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Reno Air Races</ORGANIZATION>, a videocassette called "Flying the P-47 Thunderbolt," or one called "The <PERSON>Memphis Belle</PERSON>," which happens to be a fine World War II documentary, directed by <PERSON>William Wyler</PERSON>, about a B-17 Flying Fortress. 
Another booth sold toy gliders made of styrofoam -- no more balsa, alas for the ozone layer -- that looped the loop. 

   For sheer action, air shows even beat movies in 70 mm color and six-track Dolby. 
Until <DATE>last weekend</DATE> I'd never seen anything like the stunts flown by a pilot named <PERSON>Frank Sanders</PERSON> in a British-built Hawker Sea Fury, which seems to be mostly engine and burns 300 gallons of gasoline an hour. 
As he dove, inverted, toward the unflinching ground, he announced, over a radio patched into the <LOCATION>P.A.</LOCATION> system: "You'll hear me groan a little bit as we pull a few G's here." 
We groaned on cue as he rolled over, stood the airplane on its tail and hurtled straight up to a stall at 6,000 feet, white smoke trailing from smoke generators at his wingtips. 

   Then there's the obvious lure for war buffs and war lovers. 
During a momentary lull in the dive-bomber fly-by, the announcer interviewed a World War II ace named <PERSON>Mike Russo</PERSON>. 
"One day," <PERSON>Mr. Russo</PERSON> recalled, "I caught a regiment marching down the street, strafed them and killed 376 Germans . . ." I lost the rest of his sentence in engine noise. 

   But you don't have to love war to love warplanes. 
These killing machines from World War II are also objects of grace, distinctive design and raw power. 
They fly through the air the old way -- they churn it, with huge propellers. 
One favorite at <LOCATION>Chino</LOCATION> was a <ORGANIZATION>Boeing Flying Fortress</ORGANIZATION> called "Sentimental Journey," which had been flown in for the show from <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> by members of the <ORGANIZATION>Confederate Air Force</ORGANIZATION>, the private group that restores and flies old combat planes. 
Metal fatigue may be blighting newer Boeings these days, but it's not a threat that leaped to mind as one admired this B-17G, gleaming as brightly as if it had just been built. 

   "This is an airplane for pure flying," said the smiling pilot, <PERSON>Carl Schmieder</PERSON>, who is much too young to have fought in World War II, and who owns a small chain of jewelry stores in <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>. 
He told me that the four-engined bomber was built by <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON>, actually, under license from <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION>, at the very end of the war. 
Although it never saw combat, the <ORGANIZATION>Fortress</ORGANIZATION> flew photo mapping missions in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 

   As we talked in the shade of the bomber's wing, people lined up to look inside for <MONEY>$3</MONEY> a pop. 
One of them was a retired pharmacist from <LOCATION>South Laguna</LOCATION> named <PERSON>Frank Keneley</PERSON>. 
He said he'd been a navigator on B-17s during the war, until he was shot down by a Messerschmitt over <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and interned in a prison camp in <LOCATION>Upper Silesia</LOCATION>. 
When I expressed my wonderment at how this airplane had been restored, <PERSON>Mr. Keneley</PERSON> agreed, up to a point. 
"It's still not the same for me," he said. 
"All our planes were brand new, and all the wiring was brand new, with that nice new smell you can never get back." 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Morgenstern</PERSON> is a free-lance writer in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
