<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-16559</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DDFCIAHQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930405
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  05 APR 93 / Venezuela approves oil project
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOSEPH MANN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   CARACAS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE Venezuelan cabinet approved at the weekend a Dollars 1.7bn heavy oil
project to be carried out by <ORGANIZATION>Conoco</ORGANIZATION>, a subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>EI du Pont</ORGANIZATION>, and
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s national oil company, writes <PERSON>Joseph Mann</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>.
The project calls for producing and upgrading very heavy crude oil from
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s Orinoco oil belt, the world's largest known accumulation of
heavy oil and bitumen.
This is the first time a foreign company will be allowed to participate as a
direct investor in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil production sector since the republic
nationalised its petroleum industry in <DATE>1976</DATE>. It is also the first step
towards opening up large-scale production in the belt.
<ORGANIZATION>Conoco</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Maraven</ORGANIZATION>, a subsidiary of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s national oil company, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>,
will be equal partners in the project, according to <PERSON>Mr Frank Alcock</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
vice-president.
The plan, which must be approved by the Venezuelan congress, involves
producing 120,000 barrels a day of extra-heavy crude oil from the <LOCATION>Orinoco</LOCATION>
belt and converting it into 102,000 barrels a day of lighter gravity oil,
plus 3,000 tonnes of petroleum coke.
The belt, north of the Orinoco river, contains an estimated 1,200bn barrels
of extra-heavy crude oil and bitumen.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Conoco.
    Petoleos de Venezuela.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>VEZ  Venezuela, South America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P1311 Crude Petroleum and Natural Gas.
    P2911 Petroleum Refining.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Natural resources.
    COMP  Company News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 3
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-359</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EI2D5AFJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940929
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  29 SEP 94 / International Company News: Arco joins Venezuela in oil
development scheme
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOSEPH MANN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   CARACAS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Arco International Oil</ORGANIZATION> and Gas has signed a letter of intent with <ORGANIZATION>Corpoven</ORGANIZATION>,
a subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s national oil company, covering the
development of a heavy oil project requiring total investments of Dollars
3.5bn.
The plan is to produce and upgrade heavy crude oil from <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s Orinoco
Belt for export, reaching shipments of 200,000 barrels a day by <DATE>2004</DATE>.
The Orinoco Belt, located north of the <LOCATION>Orinoco River</LOCATION>, holds the world's
largest known reserves of heavy oils and bitumen. <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, which estimates
reserves in the belt at 1,200bn barrels, has assigned strategic importance
to developing this heavy oil potential.
<ORGANIZATION>Arco</ORGANIZATION>, a subsidiary of <LOCATION>Atlantic Richfield</LOCATION> of the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Corpoven</ORGANIZATION> plan to
upgrade heavy crude oil through a new industrial process to a lighter, more
valuable oil, and later blend the product with other Venezuelan crudes.
Exports are to be aimed mainly at <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> markets.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Arco International Oil and Gas.
    Corpoven.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    VEZ  Venezuela, South America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P1311 Crude Petroleum and Natural Gas.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Natural resources.
    MKTS  Production.
    RES  Capital expenditures.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-4011</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CLDBUACJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921204
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 DEC 92 / Survey of Venezuela (5): Treacly rival to coal and oil - The
potential and pitfalls of a new fuel from the Orinoco
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOSEPH MANN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
IN the mid-1980s, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>BP</ORGANIZATION> developed a new fuel called
Orimulsion.
Orimulsion, now registered by <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> as a trade name, is an emulsion made up
of approximately 70 per cent natural bitumen by volume, and 30 per cent
water, plus a surfactant, or additive to keep the mixture stable.
It is being marketed as a fuel for electric power generation plants and
other industrial facilities that generate power.
The motivation for developing this fuel came from the huge reserves of
bitumen and extra-heavy crude oil that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> possesses in the <LOCATION>Orinoco
Belt</LOCATION>, the world's largest deposits of their type.
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> has estimated that the Orinoco Belt holds 1.2 trillion barrels of
bitumen and heavy oil in place, and that around 270bn barrels can be
recovered for commercial use.
Orimulsion has been tested commercially in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, and
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> has signed long-term contracts to supply the product to power plants
in these countries and <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>PowerGen</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Ince</PERSON> B plant is one of the plants
in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> where Orimulsion is used.
In <DATE>1991</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> produced 1.1m tonnes of <LOCATION>Orimulsion</LOCATION>, four times its output the
previous year. Sales to international clients reached 885,000 tonnes in
<DATE>1991</DATE>, up 700,000 tonnes from <DATE>1990</DATE>.
Through its subsidiary <ORGANIZATION>Bitor</ORGANIZATION>, as well as joint ventures between <ORGANIZATION>Bitor</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>BP</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> is aggressively marketing Orimulsion internationally.
The company's goal is to be producing - and selling - around 41m tonnes per
annum by <DATE>1996</DATE>.
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> is pushing Orimulsion as an economical, long-term alternative to coal
and fuel oil. It can be transported and stored like fuel oil, and, unlike
coal, does not raise dust during transportation.
The company says that relatively small investments are required to adapt
plants that burn fuel oil to <LOCATION>Orimulsion</LOCATION>. However, some serious questions
have been raised in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and the UK about pollution problems that might be
associated with this new fuel, including emissions of sulphur dioxide and
nitrogen oxide (the two main acid rain gases), particles and others.
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> asserts that Orimulsion compares favourably with other fossil fuels in
terms of environmental impact.
Citing the results of independent tests and commercial applications, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
says that <ORGANIZATION>Orimulsion</ORGANIZATION> produces levels of sulphur dioxide emissions that are
lower than those produced by 2.5 per cent sulphur coal and slightly higher
than 3.5 per cent sulphur fuel oil.
It also asserts that <ORGANIZATION>Orimulsion</ORGANIZATION>'s high caloric value means that lower
volumes will be burned (and thus less sulphur dioxide released) than by
fuels with less caloric value, to generate the same amount of energy.
As for nitrogen oxide emissions, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> states that Orimulsion produces less
than coal and the same or less than fuel oil. The company says that
Orimulsion burned in conventional power stations produces about 20 per cent
less carbon dioxide than equivalent coal-fired stations, and levels similar
to plants burning fuel oil.
Particle emissions, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> states, are 'well within the strictest limits set
by developed industrialised countries", and acid smuts are unlikely in power
stations burning Orimulsion.
In test spills, a high percentage of <ORGANIZATION>Orimulsion</ORGANIZATION> disperses of its own accord,
the company says.
At the same time, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s R&amp;D unit, <ORGANIZATION>Intevep</ORGANIZATION>, has produced a 'second
generation' of Orimulsion that is supposed to be cleaner than the first.
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'S PERFORMANCE IN <DATE>1991</DATE>
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
Production (crude oil)                                  2.34m b/d
Exports of crude oil and refined products               2.12m b/d
Proved reserves of crude oil at year end           62.7bn barrels
Employees (not counting contracted workers)                54,850
Sales of refined products on Venezuelan market        340,000 b/d
Gross international revenues                       dollars 22.3bn
Average per barrel export price                     dollars 15.92
Pre-tax earnings                                    dollars 9.1bn
Taxes paid to Venezuelan treasury                   dollars 8.7bn
Operating costs in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>                        dollars 4.1bn
Net earnings                                         dollars 441m
Capital investments                                 dollars 3.7bn
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
Source: <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 14
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870501-0147 </DOCNO>
<HL> U.S. Begins to Take Notice as Venezuela
Lifts Its Estimates of Proven Oil Reserves
---
By James Tanner
<DD> 05/01/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> LATAM MDEST
PETROLEUM (PET)
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON) </IN>
<DATELINE> HOUSTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> is finally getting some attention from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> in its long-running campaign to sell more oil in the <LOCATION>U.S. 

   U.S.</LOCATION> energy officials have begun mentioning that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> is one of the biggest suppliers of oil to this country, although none are yet suggesting than Venezuelan oil imports be increased. 
And <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> geological teams were recently in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> to confirm the South American country's sharp upward revisions in its estimates of proven oil reserves. 

   Venezuelan oil officials still worry, nonetheless, that the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> might enact an oil-import tax. 
And they question whether <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s petroleum-producing potential is recognized in this country. 
They are puzzled by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> focus on the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> as the key, but possibly unstable, source for future oil needs while <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s big petroleum reserves are much closer and offer secure supplies. 

   In <DATE>January</DATE>, the most recent period for which figures are available, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> ranked No. 2 as an oil exporter to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> with an average of about 850,000 barrels daily, behind <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>, with almost 900,000. 
In recent years, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> have been the three largest exporters of oil to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   "There's no question we have more oil than <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Juan Chacin Guzman</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Petroleos de Venezuela S.A.</ORGANIZATION>, said in an interview. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Chacin</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> to participate in the <ORGANIZATION>World Petroleum Congress</ORGANIZATION>, and other officials of Petroleos de <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, the country's national oil company, may be stretching a point in comparing their oil reserves to <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>'s. 
At the beginning of this year, annual industry calculations generally put <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>'s proven oil reserves at <MONEY>167 billion barrels</MONEY> -- still the largest in the world and several times higher than the official 25-billion-barrel estimate for <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s proven reserves. 

   But <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s recent upgrading, which isn't yet reflected in official figures, doubled its own estimates of proven reserves to 55 billion barrels, about twice those of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
In addition, Petroleos de <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> counts 267 billion barrels of proven reserves of lower-quality extraheavy crude in its <LOCATION>Orinoco Oil Belt</LOCATION>. 

   Proven reserves are generally defined as those that can be produced with current technology at today's prices. 
According to geological experts from outside <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, Petroleos de <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> has followed generally accepted reserves-accounting practices in the recent revisions. 
The revisions include changing semi-proven reserves, a category that isn't any longer used by the industry, to proven reserves. 

Saudi crudes are lighter and thus more desired for refiners' fuel mix. 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, however, is much closer to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, only five days away by oil tanker. 
It has been a steady <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> supplier for decades, even during the Arab oil embargo. 
Most of its oil exports go to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   But Venezuelan conventional petroleum tends toward the less-desired heavier grades. 
The Orinoco crude is so dense that it is generally typed as nonconventional oil. 
Once pumped it must be kept heated or blended with light fuels to be transported, and many refineries aren't equipped to handle it. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Chacin</PERSON> said facilities are in place in the Orinoco Belt for output of 150,000 barrels a day of the heavy oil. 
Only about a third of that is currently being produced. 
In all, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> is producing around 1.5 million barrels a day of crude oil, about in line with its <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> quota. 
It also produces 160,000 barrels a day of condensate, a very light oil, and 110,000 barrels a day of gas liquids, neither of which is included in the <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> quota. 

   This leaves <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> with 900,000 barrels a day of unused production capacity, <PERSON>Mr. Chacin</PERSON> said. 
"We could go to four million barrels a day (production)," he said, noting that current capacity is 2.6 million barrels a day. 

   Exploration is mainly for lighter crudes. 
Petroleos de <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s operating subsidiaries recently have made some major finds of the higher-quality lighter oil. 
Those finds aren't yet included in the revised estimates. 

   In its push to open new markets for its oil, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> has been more aggressive than most <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> members in buying interests in petroleum refineries, particularly in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
Among recent investments, as previously reported, were <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> interests in refineries at <LOCATION>Lake Charles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>La.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Corpus Christi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex</LOCATION>. 
In the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, such arrangements currently provide outlets for 500,000 barrels a day of Venezuelan oil, <PERSON>Mr. Chacin</PERSON> said. 
Through additional joint ventures in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, he said, Petroleos de <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> expects to expand such sales to 700,000 barrels a day. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-4010</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CLDBUACKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921204
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 DEC 92 / Survey of Venezuela (4): Squeezed between rising taxes and
depressed prices - Oil industry tackles opposing pressures
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOSEPH MANN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>VENEZUELA</LOCATION>'S national oil company, <ORGANIZATION>Petroleos de Venezuela SA</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>), faces
some serious difficulties which are not of its own making.
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, with <DATE>1991</DATE> gross international sales of Dollars 22.3bn, is squeezed
between weak oil prices and steep taxes and investment requirements. While
the company remains well-managed, efficient and profitable, the current
situation has produced serious cash flow problems and has forced <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> to
acquire nearly Dollars 5bn in debt, having been debt-free only a few years
ago.
It also has been obliged to stretch out its capital investment programme and
seek international equity partners for projects in petroleum sectors that
previously had been off limits to private investment.
Like other major international oil companies, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> is suffering from the
effects of low oil prices on world markets. This year, the average export
price for <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> crude and refined products through mid-November fell below
last year's price of Dollars 15.92 per barrel. The export price was Dollars
20.33 per barrel in <DATE>1990</DATE> and Dollars 17.85 per barrel in <DATE>1989</DATE>.
And, like other big suppliers of refined petroleum products to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
market, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> - the world's third largest oil refiner - must spend large
sums on upgrading its refining complexes in order to meet tougher
environmental standards for key export products such as gasoline.
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> expects to invest at least Dollars 3.6bn in refinery improvements over
the next several years to meet or exceed provisions of the US Clean Air Act,
where it sells refined products, especially <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
These investments are also aimed at permitting <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s home refineries to
process increased volumes of heavy crude, which is abundant in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>.
(Apart from four refining complexes in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> wholly or partially
owns large oil refining and petrochemical plants in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.)
In addition, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> must constantly invest huge sums in crude oil production.
The country's oil fields suffer a potential decline in output of 22-23 per
cent per annum, which means that <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> must invest over Dollars 2bn a year
simply to maintain crude output at the present capacity level.
The company is also building new production potential, which requires even
greater investments. Its target is to raise crude oil production capacity
from the current level of 2.8m b/d to 4m b/d by <DATE>2002</DATE>. '<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> must grow,'
said <PERSON>Mr Alirio Parra</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Minister of Energy and Mines</ORGANIZATION>.
At the same time, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> is being slowly strangled by a heavy tax burden at
home. The company currently pays at least 82 per cent of its operating
profits to the <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Treasury</ORGANIZATION> in taxes and royalties. (The maximum
corporate tax rate for companies outside the oil sector is 30 per cent.) And
since the Venezuelan government relies on oil to provide most if its
revenues (despite years of talking about diversification), a dramatic
reduction in <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s tax burden cannot be made overnight.
Working together, Energy Minister <PERSON>Parra</PERSON> and the president of <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr
Gustavo Roosen</PERSON>, have been able to develop some solutions to the company's
problems, although relief will not be immediate.
The <ORGANIZATION>Energy Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, which draws up policy guidelines for <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, has eased
the company's tax burden slightly this year by adjusting the export value
system.
Export values of crude and refined products are used as a base to calculate
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> income taxes. The minister also has introduced legislation that would
phase out the export value system on a staggered basis by <DATE>1996</DATE>, and has
changed some accounting rules applied to <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s books and tax declarations.
These initiatives will provide substantial tax savings for the national oil
company in coming years, but will not pull the fiscal carpet out from under
the the government.
Other changes are also being studied to ease <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s tax burden. Taken as a
whole, these measures should ensure that <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> will be able to push ahead
comfortably with future investments and continue to generate net profits.
The government itself has proposed new taxes, including a version of VAT,
that will make it less dependent on the vicissitudes of its main commodity,
petroleum.
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> is moving ahead with direct investments in production and refining,
which are necessary if the company is to maintain its international market
share. But it has stretched out some projects contained in its medium term
investment plan, delayed others and is looking to international capital to
develop a variety of joint-venture projects in heavy oil, refining, natural
gas and other areas that were formerly the exclusive domain of <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> and its
subsidiaries.
'The most limited resource that the the petroleum industry has today is
money,' said <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> president <PERSON>Roosen</PERSON>. 'I don't want things to be left undone
simply because we don't have the cash.' The company's current investment
plan through <DATE>2002</DATE> totals Dollars 40bn, at <DATE>1992</DATE> prices.
Of this total, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> will carry out direct capital spending of Dollars 28bn,
while it hopes that international investors - either acting alone or in
joint ventures with the company - will invest another Dollars 12bn. Apart
from newly targeted areas for foreign investment such as oil production and
refining, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> has established - or is negotiating - joint ventures with
Venezuelan and international partners in natural gas, petrochemicals, coal
and <ORGANIZATION>Orimulsion</ORGANIZATION>, a new fuel that is an emulsion of bitumen and water. <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
is marketing Orimulsion as an alternative to coal in electric power plants.
To save money, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> also has cut its operating and capital budgets this
year, and will continue controlling costs in <DATE>1993</DATE>. Capital spending for <DATE>1992</DATE>
is expected to reach Dollars 3.7bn, about the same as last year.
PDVSA this year opened the door to limited-scale private investment in oil
production. It asked oil companies from <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and abroad to bid on crude
oil production contracts covering a series of old oil fields that <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
itself did not want to reactivate.
As a result, two groups made up of <ORGANIZATION>Benton Oil</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>US</LOCATION>)/Vinccler (<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>) and
<ORGANIZATION>Teikoku Oil of Japan</ORGANIZATION> signed operating contracts under which they pledged to
invest Dollars 280m over the next 10 years to develop new production from
marginal oil fields in eastern <LOCATION>Guarico</LOCATION> state and southeastern <LOCATION>Monagas</LOCATION> state.
The two groups will not own the oil and natural gas they produce, but will
turn it over to <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> subsidiaries and receive compensation according to the
volumes of oil they can pump.
Last month, Energy Minister <PERSON>Parra</PERSON> announced that the government and <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
were seeking bids for production contracts on 73 other marginal fields with
total proven oil reserves of more than 1.2bn barrels.
Heavy oil is an important resource for <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> has the world's
largest known deposits of bitumen and extra-heavy crude in the <LOCATION>Orinoco Belt</LOCATION>,
an area that lies north of the <LOCATION>Orinoco River</LOCATION>. Heavy and extra-heavy crude
oils contain high levels of carbon, sulphur and metals that must be removed
at high cost before the crude can be processed in normal oil refineries.
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> has two main approaches to developing its reserves of bitumen and
extra-heavy crudes. The first is an international marketing programme for
<ORGANIZATION>Orimulsion</ORGANIZATION>, a fuel composed of bitumen and water that is made by <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
subsidiaries. The second involves seeking a foreign partner who can provide
technology and capital for developing new production of extra-heavy crudes
and converting them into lighter, higher quality oils (called syncrudes)
that can be processed in normal refineries.
An upgrading plant using <ORGANIZATION>Veba Oel</ORGANIZATION> technology to produce 131,000 b/d of
synthetic crude oil, for example, would cost over Dollars 4bn. <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> has
signed letters of intent with more than a dozen international oil companies
with the idea of developing strategic business associations in heavy oil.
Due to the long start-up period for heavy oil projects of this type, the
government and <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> plan to offer investors access to light/medium crude
oils during the first stage of project development. This would give
investors a positive cash flow until the heavy oil processing plant could go
on stream. <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> is currently considering offers on heavy oil projects from
<ORGANIZATION>Conoco</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Veba Oel</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Elf Aquitaine</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mobil</ORGANIZATION> and Total.
 ------------------------------------------------------------
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>: DIRECT INVESTMENT 1993-98 (DOLLARS BN)
 ------------------------------------------------------------
Sector investments per cent of total
Total maintaining production capacity            13/65
Upgrading refineries in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>               3.6/18
Increasing crude oil production potential        1.4/7
Exploration                                      1.5/8
Venezuelan market                              0.252/1
Support activities and others                  0.182/1
 ------------------------------------------------------------
 ------------------------------------------------------------
PROVED RESERVES OF CRUDE OIL
 ------------------------------------------------------------
(billions of barrels at year end)
  <DATE>1976     1987     1988     1989     1990</DATE>     1991
18,228   58,084   58,504   59,041   60,055   62,650
 ------------------------------------------------------------
Source: <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
 ------------------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 14
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-12100 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat061_t_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-061 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  30 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Roundup of Economic Developments </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA3003015294 </F>
<F P=103> PA3003015294 </F>
<F P=104></F>



<TEXT>
Article   Type:BFN 

  [Editorial Report] The following is a compilation of 
reports on Venezuelan economic developments monitored through 29 
<DATE>March</DATE>. 
  The possibility that the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Federal Reserve</ORGANIZATION> may tighten 
its 
monetary policies and increase interest rates in the short term 
once again made the prices of Venezuelan foreign debt bonds 
decrease to the same level reached on 27 <DATE>November 1992</DATE>, a coup 
day. <ORGANIZATION>Chemical Bank</ORGANIZATION> reports indicate that the price of foreign 
debt bonds fell by four points and closed at 53.50 points. There 
is also a possibility that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> T-bills, whose profitability 
registered <PERCENT>6.97 percent</PERCENT>, will continue to decrease. On 21 <DATE>March</DATE>, 
all these scenarios combined made the <ORGANIZATION>Caracas Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> 
index lose <PERCENT>3.6 percent</PERCENT> and close at 24,654.82 points, which is a 
level similar to that reached on 16 <DATE>August 1992</DATE>. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas EL 
NACIONAL</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish 22 Mar 94 p E-1) 
  The Central Bank of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, BCV, is offering a record 
amount of 50 billion bolivares worth of zero-coupon bonds. About 
40 billion bolivares will mature in 90 days, and the remaining 
10 billion bolivares will mature in 182 days. The 
90-day-zero-coupon bonds registered a <PERCENT>52.13 percent</PERCENT> 
return-on-equity, ROE, rate, which in turn will make fluctuating 
interest rates increase. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas EL REPORTE DE LA ECONOMIA</ORGANIZATION> in 
Spanish 23 Mar 94 p 9) 
  <PERSON>Ferrominera Orinoco</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Edelca</ORGANIZATION>, subsidiaries of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Guayana Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>CVG</ORGANIZATION>, will not be included in the 
privatization process that the Executive Branch is promoting. 
CVG President <PERSON>Francisco Layrisse</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Caroni Aluminum Inc.</ORGANIZATION> is 
the only subsidiary that in six months, at the latest, will sell 
<PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT> of its stock to private companies. As for <ORGANIZATION>Ferrominera 
Orinoco</ORGANIZATION>, the private sector will only have access to invest in 
the iron transformation process. Ferrominera Orinoco President 
<PERSON>Andres Caleca</PERSON> said the law stipulates that only the state has 
the right to tap iron. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas Venezolana de Television Network</ORGANIZATION> 
in Spanish 1550 GMT 23 Mar 94) 
  The BCV's <ORGANIZATION>Board of Directors</ORGANIZATION> has decided to modify the 
mechanisms that control interest rates on loans. For instance, 
it decreased the ceiling rate that banks can charge with 
fluctuating interest rates from 20 to 15 points above the ROE 
rate on zero-coupon bonds. It is worth mentioning that the six 
largest banks currently charge an average fluctuating interest 
rate of <PERCENT>63.8 percent</PERCENT>. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas EL UNIVERSAL</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish 24 <DATE>Mar 
94</DATE> p 1-1) 
  The <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Nomenclature Committee</ORGANIZATION> recently decided 
to categorize Orimulsion as a bituminous substance. This 
decision opens new opportunities to sell larger amounts of this 
type of fuel to world markets. <PERSON>Frank Alcock</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Venezuela 
Petroleum</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Petroven</PERSON>, acting president, appeared before the 
<ORGANIZATION>Senate's Energy and Mines Commission</ORGANIZATION> and said that this new 
category for <ORGANIZATION>Orimulsion</ORGANIZATION> will prevent a reduction of its 
competitive edge in the Old Continent. The <ORGANIZATION>Council on Customs 
Affairs</ORGANIZATION> will issue its final ruling on Orimulsion on 4 <DATE>April</DATE>. 
Orimulsion exports amounted to 721,000 tons in <DATE>1992</DATE> and 2.79 
million tons in <DATE>1993</DATE>. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas EL NACIONAL</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish 24 <DATE>Mar 94</DATE> 
p E-6) 
  On 23 <DATE>March</DATE>, Petroven Acting President <PERSON>Fred Alcock</PERSON> said 
<PERSON>Petroven</PERSON> will reduce expenses in <DATE>1994</DATE> by an additional <MONEY>6 billion 
bolivares</MONEY>. He added that this reduction will bring to the 
treasury additional revenues amounting to <MONEY>26 billion bolivares</MONEY>. 
Alcock appeared before the <ORGANIZATION>Senate's Energy and Mines Commission</ORGANIZATION> 
to explain <ORGANIZATION>Petroven</ORGANIZATION>'s business plan. He also said that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> 
will continue to sell gasoline to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas EL 
DIARIO</ORGANIZATION> DE <LOCATION>CARACAS</LOCATION> in Spanish 24 <DATE>Mar 94 p 16</DATE>) 
  The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Federal Reserve</ORGANIZATION>'s decision to increase interest 
rates has landed a heavy blow on the already vulnerable 
Venezuelan economy because the price of its foreign debt bonds 
will drop. This means, however, that the risk to investment 
could fall, which in turn could attract more capital to the 
country. In short, the loss generated by lower prices on foreign 
debt bonds could be compensated by reinvesting said bonds on 
securities with higher interest rates as long as the bonds 
mature in the short term. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas EL REPORTE DE LA ECONOMIA</ORGANIZATION> in 
Spanish 24 <DATE>Mar 94</DATE> p 8) 
  <PERSON>Carlos Pulido Salvatierra</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Association of Venezuelan 
Exporters</ORGANIZATION> president, said nontraditional Venezuelan exports to 
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> amounted to <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> during the <DATE>first quarter of 
1994</DATE>. He added that it is expected that said exports will amount 
to almost <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1994</DATE>, which is <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> higher than in 
<DATE>1993</DATE>. (<ORGANIZATION>Hamburg DPA</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish 2038 GMT 25 <DATE>Mar 94</DATE>) 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Finance Ministry</ORGANIZATION> estimates that the <DATE>1995</DATE> budget will 
amount to 1.7 trillion bolivares and that gasoline prices will 
increase in <DATE>1995</DATE>. Finance Minister <PERSON>Julio Sosa Rodriguez</PERSON> said the 
mass transit system may receive additional subsidies in <DATE>1995</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Jorge Serrano</PERSON>, vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Federation of 
Associations and Chambers of Commerce and Industry</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Fedecamaras</LOCATION>, 
underscored that gasoline prices must drastically change because 
gasoline receives 40 billion bolivares worth of subsidies 
annually. The Fedecamaras believes that the price of high-octane 
gasoline must increase. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas Venezolana de Television 
Network</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish 2350 GMT 25 Mar 94) 
  New Petroven Director <PERSON>Luis Giusti</PERSON> has said Petroven reduced 
its investment costs by <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY> due to drops in hydrocarbon 
prices. He added that Petroven reduced other expenses by <MONEY>$3 
billion</MONEY>. Giusti pointed out that there is an international 
consensus on the opening of the national oil industry to private 
capital and that oil prices will not recover soon. (<LOCATION>Mexico City 
NOTIMEX</LOCATION> in Spanish <DATE>0118 GMT 29 Mar 94</DATE>) 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911223-0086
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911223-0086.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   National Oil Concerns Dominate Market;
   Exxon Slips Below Venezuela in Ranking
   ----
   By James Tanner
</HL>
<DATE>
12/23/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A5B
</SO>
<CO>
   C.KPT C.PDV C.PEM C.SAR MOB RD SC XON
</CO>
<MS>
ENERGY (ENE)
</MS>
<IN>
OIL-INTEGRATED MAJORS (OIL)
OIL-SECONDARY (OIS)
PETROLEUM (PET)
INTERNATIONAL TRADE NEWS (TRD)
</IN>
<NS>
JOINT VENTURES (JVN)
PETROLEUM MARKET (PET)
TRADE ISSUES (TRD)
</NS>
<RE>
ARABIAN PENINSULA (ARA)
EUROPE (EU)
KUWAIT (KU)
MIDDLE EAST (ML)
MEXICO (MX)
NETHERLANDS (NL)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
SAUDI ARABIA (SA)
SOUTH AMERICA (SM)
TEXAS (TX)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
UNITED STATES (US)
VIRGINIA (VA)
VENEZUELA (VE)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   National oil companies dominate new rankings of the
world's top oil companies with Petroleos de Venezuela moving
ahead of Exxon Corp. on at least one list.
   In its annual ranking of the 50 largest oil companies,
Petroleum Intelligence Weekly, or PIW, will report in its
issue out today that Petroleos de Venezuela, or PDVSA, is
third from the top.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In this position, up from fifth place last year,
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s aggressive government-owned company has jumped
ahead of both the U.S.-based <ORGANIZATION>Exxon</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s state-owned
Petroleos Mexicanos, or <ORGANIZATION>Pemex</ORGANIZATION>. But <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>'s
government-owned company, or <LOCATION>Saudi Aramco</LOCATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Royal
Dutch/Shell Group</ORGANIZATION> maintained their rankings by the oil
industry publication as the largest and the No. 2 companies.
   "Exxon's fall from the No. 1 to No. 4 slot over a few
years is indicative of the difficulties encountered by
privately-owned companies in obtaining secure sources of
crude oil following the nationalizations of oil and gas
reserves" by producer governments more than a decade ago, <ORGANIZATION>PIW</ORGANIZATION>
reported.
   <ORGANIZATION>PIW</ORGANIZATION> bases its ranking of the top 50 on the basis of
operational data from nearly 100 firms. Its focus on
operations differs from most financially-oriented corporate
rankings but allows "meaningful comparisons" of all types of
companies, the publication maintains.
   The rankings are based on the most recent operating data
available, <ORGANIZATION>PIW</ORGANIZATION> said. Given the lag in publishing information,
its latest rankings are for <DATE>1990</DATE>, it added. Government-owned
<ORGANIZATION>Kuwait Petroleum Co.</ORGANIZATION> dropped completely from the top 10 firms
in the <ORGANIZATION>PIW</ORGANIZATION> rankings and is now No. 14, reflecting the <ORGANIZATION>United
Nations</ORGANIZATION> embargo imposed after the Iraqi invasion of the
country in <DATE>August 1990</DATE>.
   The criteria used by <ORGANIZATION>PIW</ORGANIZATION> in its rankings are oil and gas
reserves, oil and gas production, refining capacity and
petroleum product sales. "Financial data are not used because
of the difficulties imposed in comparing state-owned firms
with private sector firms," <ORGANIZATION>PIW</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The oil industry newsletter said several of the
state-owned firms in the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of Petroleum Exporting
Countries</ORGANIZATION> are making significant headway in refining and
marketing endeavors even as they grow "upstream" in crude oil
production. <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> is setting the pace, the
publication added.
   According to <ORGANIZATION>PIW</ORGANIZATION>, the Venezuelan company added 400,000
barrels a day of refining capacity in <DATE>1990</DATE> while increasing
crude production by <PERCENT>7.5%</PERCENT> to more than 2.1 million barrels a
day. In contrast to <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s success, the reserves and
production performance of the major international oil
companies declined, <ORGANIZATION>PIW</ORGANIZATION> noted.
   As previously reported, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> has an ambitious <MONEY>$48 billion</MONEY>
energy expansion plan that includes an increase in its oil
production capacity to 3.5 million barrels a day by <DATE>1995</DATE>. It
is seeking foreign partners among the international oil
companies for their financial and technological assistance.
Several major oil companies already have signed preliminary
agreements with <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> that could lead to joint ventures in
the development of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil, including the heavy
Orinoco crudes.
   <ORGANIZATION>Mobil Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is the latest to link up with <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Mobil</ORGANIZATION>
announced <DATE>Friday</DATE> that it and <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> had signed a letter of
intent to study development and upgrading of heavy oil from
the <LOCATION>Orinoco</LOCATION> belt and other exploration and production
opportunities in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-9419</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKJC4AGTFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931110
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 NOV 93 / Commodities and Agriculture: A little help from their
friends - Venezuela is using foreign investment to develop the nation's
petroleum industry
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOSEPH MANN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> has announced a Dollars 45.8bn investment programme for its
petroleum industry over the next 10 years that stresses a substantial
increase in crude oil production capacity and the upgrading of oil
refineries to produce higher-quality products.
The plan, which was announced by <PERSON>Mr Gustavo Roosen</PERSON>, president of national
oil company <ORGANIZATION>Petroleos de Venezuela SA</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>), assigns a key role to foreign
investment in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil and gas sectors for the first time since the
country nationalised all private oil companies in <DATE>1976</DATE>.
Of the Dollars 48.5bn in projected capital spending, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> plans to invest
Dollars 29.1bn or 60 per cent of the total directly, while private companies
 -mainly foreign investors - are expected to supply the remainder of about
Dollars 19.4bn. Groups such as <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dutch/Shell</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Exxon</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Conoco</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi</ORGANIZATION>
and Total are already planning large joint-venture projects with <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> in
natural gas and heavy oil. And the Venezuelan oil company is actively
seeking new partners for a variety of other projects in oil exploration and
production, refining, petrochemicals and coal.
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> ranks as one of the world's biggest oil companies; at the <DATE>1992</DATE>
year-end it had 63.3bn barrels of crude oil reserves, the largest outside
the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION>.
One of the main thrusts of the company's investment programme is to develop
crude oil production potential of 4m barrels per day (b/d) by <DATE>2002</DATE>, up 1.1m
b/d from the current capacity of approximately 2.9m b/d.
New exploration work will be carried out in traditional oil production zones
and other areas, and <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s goal is to raise proved reserves of crude oil
to 65bn barrels over the next decade, up 3 per cent from the current level.
International investors are becoming involved in <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s plans through
operating agreements, production sharing and strategic associations.
Under operating agreements, private companies invest to develop production
of crude oil and natural gas in so-called 'marginal fields', or areas with
relatively small volumes of production that <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> does not wish to operate
directly. Investors do not own the oil and gas they produce but are
compensated according to production volume.
The first operating agreements were signed in <DATE>1992</DATE>, and earlier this year
<ORGANIZATION>British Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> agreed to invest around Dollars 60m over the next three
years in a marginal oil field under a 20-year operating agreement.
Using a <ORGANIZATION>BP</ORGANIZATION> study, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> has also identified sectors in eastern <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>
with strong prospects for large discoveries of light and medium-weight
crudes, which <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> needs to balance out its existing reserves, now
dominated by heavy crudes.
Next year, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> plans to look for international partners who will assume
all the risks to develop these zones. If commercial quantities of oil are
discovered, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> will share future production with the foreign partner.
Last <DATE>August</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> received congressional approval to move ahead with two
multi-billion dollar projects to produce and upgrade heavy oil. <ORGANIZATION>Conoco</ORGANIZATION>,
Total, <ORGANIZATION>Itochu</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Marubeni</ORGANIZATION> are the international partners. The investors
plan to produce heavy and extra-heavy crude from <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s Orinoco Belt (a
large reserve of heavy oil), and use delayed coking to convert it into
lighter-weight, higher-value crude for export. In addition, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Exxon</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi</ORGANIZATION> are developing a Dollars 5.6bn project to produce
liquefied natural gas (LNG) for export.
In refining, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> will complete upgrading projects at three of its home
refineries and raise crude processing capacity at these plants and <LOCATION>Curacao</LOCATION> -
where it leases a former <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> refinery from the government - from the
current level of 1.1m b/d to 1.2m b/d by <DATE>2002</DATE>. That increase will be quite
small in volume terms but the company is investing heavily to upgrade and
modernise the refineries so that they can turn out high-quality,
increased-value, refined products, meeting tougher environmental standards
in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and other markets.
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, which already owns, either wholly or jointly, large oil refining
operations in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, plans to expand its overseas network
through the acquisition of new refining capacity. The company would not
comment on its acquisition plans, but executives said future marketing
efforts would focus on <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, as well as on expanding
market share in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
In developing their 10-year programme, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> planners are assuming 2 per
cent annual growth in world energy demand during 1992-2002, with projected
demand for hydrocarbons reaching 76m b/d by <DATE>2002</DATE>, up from consumption of 66m
b/d in <DATE>1990</DATE>.
They also assume that potential demand for Venezuelan crude oil on
international markets will rise to about 3.6m b/d in <DATE>2002</DATE>, and to 4.5m b/d
in <DATE>2010</DATE>. Home demand for refined oil products is expected to grow at <MONEY>2 per
cent</MONEY> a year.
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s crude oil production last year averaged 2.33m b/d, while exports
of crude and refined products averaged 2.1m b/d, with crude accounting for
1.43m b/d of the total.
A large share of the country's crude oil exports is processed at <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
refineries in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Petroleos de Venezuela.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>VEZ  Venezuela, South America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
    P1311 Crude Petroleum and Natural Gas.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Capital expenditures.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 34
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-8469</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DHPB3AAYFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930816
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 AUG 93 / Caracas approves two oil projects
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOSEPH MANN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   CARACAS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Congress</ORGANIZATION> has approved two oil projects worth a total of
Dollars 4.8bn (Pounds 3.2bn), in which international investors will play an
important role.
The two joint ventures involve the production, upgrading and international
placement of heavy crude oil from <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s Orinoco Belt, the world's
largest accumulation of heavy oil and bitumen.
In both projects, the Venezuelan partner will be <ORGANIZATION>Maraven</ORGANIZATION>, a subsidiary of
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s national oil company, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Conoco</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>EI du Pont de Nemours</ORGANIZATION>, will hold 49.9 per cent equity in
one project that calls for total expenditures of Dollars 1.7bn. The
promoters plan to produce 120,000 barrels per day of heavy crude oil and use
a delayed coking process to make lighter crude that can be processed by a
<ORGANIZATION>Conoco</ORGANIZATION> refinery in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Maraven</ORGANIZATION> will also have 49.9 per cent equity.
In the other project, which has a projected cost of Dollars 3.1bn, the
international partners will be <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s Total and two Japanese companies,
<ORGANIZATION>Itochu</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Marubeni</ORGANIZATION>.
At present, Total is expected to have 40 per cent of equity, <ORGANIZATION>Maraven</ORGANIZATION> 35 per
cent and two Japanese partners 25 per cent. <ORGANIZATION>Maraven</ORGANIZATION> said the equity
composition of the projects could change if new international partners were
added.
On <DATE>August 10</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> opened the door to foreign investment in
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil and gas industries for the first time since the <DATE>1976</DATE>
nationalisation.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Maraven.
    Petroleos de Venezuela.
    Conoco Inc.
    Total.
    Itochu.
    Marubeni Corp.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>VEZ  Venezuela, South America.
    USZ  United States of America.
    FRZ  France, EC.
    JPZ  Japan, Asia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P1311 Crude Petroleum and Natural Gas.
    P2911 Petroleum Refining.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Strategic links &amp; Joint venture.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 3
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900810-0222 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-10-90 1843EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Venezuela-Oil     08-10 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Venezuela-Oil,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Venezuelan Energy Ministry Denies Ordering Oil Production Increase</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARIA TEJERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARACAS, Venezuela (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Energy and Ministry</ORGANIZATION> on
<DATE>Friday</DATE> denied reports that it had ordered the state oil industry to
raise output to cover <LOCATION>Iraq</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> quotas.
   ``Until this moment, the minister has not ordered any increase
and our production is still limited to our <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> quota of <MONEY>1.945
million barrels</MONEY> per day of crude,'' a ministry spokesman told <ORGANIZATION>The
Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``However, a new order could be given later on, depending on
<ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> agreements,'' he added.
   <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> will not make any unilateral hikes, and in any case,
from Arab leaders on the success of their peace efforts before
changing the level of output, the spokesman said.
   Energy Minister <PERSON>Celestino Armas</PERSON> is in ``constant touch'' with
other <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> ministers. The cartel has yet to make any decision about
making up for <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION>'s 3.1 million barrels per day and <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION>'s 1.5
million, the spokesman said.
   ``But depending on what happens in the Arab world, minister
Armas may make an announcement within a day or two,'' he said.
   Reports from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and elsewhere had indicated that the state
oil monopoly Petroleos de <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>S.A.</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>) had already
ordered its subsidiaries to raise output by around 500,000 bpd.
   However, by law, the ministry imparts instructions to <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>,
which cannot raise production on its own.
   According to a recent nationwide test, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> has the
capacity to produce between 2.6 and 2.7 million barrels of oil per
day, excluding heavy crudes. Its reserves are sixth in the world,
not counting oil in the <LOCATION>Orinoco</LOCATION> bitumen belt.
   <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> limitations have led to friction between the
ministry and <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, which has advocated overproduction to finance a
<MONEY>$20 billion</MONEY> program to expand the oil and petrochemical industries
over the next 10 years.
   A main goal is to raise production capacity to 3.5 million
barrels per day by <DATE>1995</DATE> and to 4 million by <DATE>2000</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911002-0107
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911002-0107.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Change of Heart:
   Venezuela Now Woos
   Oil Firms It Booted
   In '70s Nationalization
   ---
   That Is Good News for U.S.;
   Many Countries Now Vie
   For Expertise and Capital
   ---
   President Perez's Turnaround
   ----
   By James Tanner
</HL>
<DATE>
10/02/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<CO>
   AN BP BTN C.PDV ELF G.VEB I.ENI J.MIB P RD SC XON
</CO>
<MS>
ENERGY (ENE)
INDUSTRIAL (IDU)
</MS>
<IN>
OIL-DRILLING AND EXPLORATION (DRL)
DIVERSIFIED INDUSTRIAL (IDD)
HEAVY MACHINERY, FARM EQUIPMENT (MAC)
OIL-EQUIPMENT AND SERVICES (OIE)
OIL-INTEGRATED MAJORS (OIL)
PETROLEUM (PET)
</IN>
<NS>
JOINT VENTURES (JVN)
PETROLEUM MARKET (PET)
</NS>
<RE>
AFRICA (AF)
CALIFORNIA (CA)
EUROPE (EU)
FAR EAST (FE)
FRANCE (FR)
GERMANY (GE)
ILLINOIS (IL)
ITALY (ITA)
JAPAN (JA)
NIGERIA (NI)
NETHERLANDS (NL)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
OKLAHOMA (OK)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
SOUTH AMERICA (SM)
TEXAS (TX)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
UNITED STATES (US)
VENEZUELA (VE)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   CARACAS -- When he was president of Venezuela in the
mid-1970s, Carlos Andres Perez booted out foreign oil
companies. Now, president again, he is trying to get them
back.
   Mr. Perez makes no apology for the turnaround. Times and
nations have changed, he tells some visiting foreign
journalists over breakfast at the Miraflores Palace here.
"Remember that in the past, warships even came to Venezuela
to claim debts," he says.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Now, <PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON> envisions a major new role for foreign
companies -- especially multinationals such as <ORGANIZATION>Exxon Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Royal Dutch/Shell Group</ORGANIZATION>, with their technology and deep
pockets -- in a <MONEY>$40 billion-plus</MONEY> plan to speed development of
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s vast energy base.
   The heart of the expansion plan is a <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> leap in
oil-producing capacity, a net gain of a million barrels a
day, in just five years. "Our goal, and we stand firm on it,
is to produce 3.5 million barrels per day for the year <DATE>1995</DATE>,"
says <PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON>'s change of heart is part of a world-wide
pattern. From the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>, governments that once
shunned Western oil expertise and capital now are vying to
attract them. The turnaround is especially remarkable in
countries such as <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, where oil is so closely tied to
nationalism. Even now, <PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON> may have some persuading to
do at home, where <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s congress still must approve any
direct private roles in oil and gas projects.
   <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s new direction holds particular significance
for the <LOCATION>U.S. Venezuela</LOCATION> helped found the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of
Petroleum Exporting Countries</ORGANIZATION>, but it long has been a leading
and reliable supplier of oil to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, even during the
Arab oil embargo. <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> provides nearly one million
barrels a day, or nearly <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT>, of the oil used by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> That
ranks it third as a source of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> oil imports, behind only
<LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   Among the handful of countries that still have spare
producing capacity -- basically the five founders of <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> --
only <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> is outside the volatile <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> region.
The others are <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iraq</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil reserves are respectable even by <LOCATION>Middle
East</LOCATION> standards. Its proven conventional crude reserves are
estimated at 60 billion barrels. That is <PERCENT>6%</PERCENT> of the world's
total. Counting the Orinoco Belt's huge deposits of
extra-heavy oil, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s recoverable reserves reach an
astonishing 330 billion barrels. Orinoco's oil is not highly
prized because it is hard to pump, hard to refine and dirty
to burn, but all of those are problems that can best be fixed
with the technology of big oil companies.
   <PERSON>Michael Skol</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ambassador here, calls <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>
"the <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION> of the <LOCATION>Western Hemisphere</LOCATION>."
   To get the international oil companies back, however,
President <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> must convince them that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> not only
offers fewer political risks but bigger economic rewards than
other oil lands. It is suddenly a buyers' market for these
oil companies, largely because of the producing nations'
urgent need for more revenue.
   It is generally assumed that oil prices will remain flat,
after adjustments for inflation, over the next several years.
With the oil exporters no longer able to bank on escalating
prices, they must produce more barrels to produce more
income. But their older oil fields are running dry. That
means new technology and substantially more capital are
needed to rejuvenate these fields and develop new ones.
   Even most members of the 13-nation <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> are reaching for
capital and technical assistance from the oil companies. E.
<PERSON>John P. Browne</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>British Petroleum Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s chief executive for
exploration, estimates that <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> needs investments of <MONEY>$150
billion</MONEY> to meet the demand for its oil over the next decade.
   BP already is going back into some <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> countries where
former "concessions" had been expropriated or nationalized.
Only a few weeks ago, it resumed its search for oil in
<LOCATION>Nigeria</LOCATION>, where operations had been taken over in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> in
a spillover of a political dispute between the Nigerian and
British governments over policies toward <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. "Our
breath has been taken away by the speed" in which producing
nations are putting out the welcome mat, <PERSON>Mr. Browne</PERSON> says.
   <ORGANIZATION>BP</ORGANIZATION> has begun technical studies in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>. It also is
participating in a venture that developed and is marketing a
new boiler fuel -- Orimulsion -- in which water is mixed with
extra-heavy oil from <LOCATION>Orinoco</LOCATION> in a process that uses an
emulsifier. In addition to <ORGANIZATION>BP</ORGANIZATION>, four other oil companies have
signed "strategic association" agreements with Petroleos de
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, or <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, the state-owned oil company, so far this
year. The agreements are designed to lead to possible
joint-venture megaprojects in which the foreign companies
will help build multibillion-dollar refineries in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>
or abroad that can process Orinocotype oil.
   <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>, according to its president, <PERSON>Andres Sosa Pietri</PERSON>,
would own less than <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of each of these associations, in
order to keep them attractive to foreign investors. Also, the
foreign firms may get a crack at exploring for the more
valuable conventional crudes. "The heavy oil is less and less
attractive in today's green-type environment, but if they
give us the linkage of exploring lighter crude areas, it will
change the picture considerably," says an official of one oil
company holding talks with <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>.
   Other companies already signed up for the "association"
agreements are <ORGANIZATION>Veba</ORGANIZATION> A.G. of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Elf Aquitaine</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Ente Nazionale Idrocarburi</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Amoco Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of the
<LOCATION>U.S</LOCATION>. Other multinationals and smaller oil companies are
sending technical teams to investigate.
   In addition, a subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> and units of <ORGANIZATION>Exxon</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Royal Dutch/Shell</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Corp.</ORGANIZATION> recently signed a
preliminary development agreement for the huge Cristobal
Colon project. This is a proposed <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> liquefied
natural gas project on <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Paria Peninsula</LOCATION>, where
<PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON> first landed in <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>.
   The project is still in its early stages -- economic
studies must be done and the congress must approve it before
anything happens -- but Venezuelan oil officials see it as a
test case for the first direct hydrocarbon activity by
foreign firms since the nationalizations.
   President <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> cites <PERSON>Cristobal Colon</PERSON> as the best evidence
of what he calls the "new reality" in relations between
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and the foreign oil companies. "If need arises to
have objective proof," he says, "we can look at <ORGANIZATION>Shell</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Exxon</ORGANIZATION>, two nationalized oil companies in our country that
have renegotiated with us."
   In fact, international oil companies, most of them based
in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, were the chief developers of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil
industry, which began when oil was discovered in <DATE>1922</DATE>, and so
much flooded out that world oil prices crashed. But <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>
was a world leader in wringing better terms from the oil
companies and, by the <DATE>1960s</DATE>, oil nationalism was beginning to
surge. In <DATE>1971</DATE>, the Venezuelan congress decided that as oil
concessions ended, they wouldn't be renewed, but instead
would revert to the government.
   Although the first concession wasn't due to expire until
<DATE>1983</DATE>, the oil companies promptly began to slow their
investments. <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil production plunged. That led to
anger toward the companies and set the stage for the <DATE>1976</DATE>
nationalization. Meanwhile, the architect of the
nationalization, <PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON> -- then considered <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>'s
leading economic interventionist -- won a landslide
presidential victory.
   During his first term, from <DATE>1974</DATE> to <DATE>1979</DATE>, the oil bounty
was plentiful. Oil prices were surging, thanks in part to the
1973-74 Arab oil embargo, when <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> pumped flat out. Oil
prices were expected to escalate forever. Waste was rampant.
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> spent billions on superhighways and luxury imports.
But then, less than <DATE>a decade later</DATE>, the heady days were over.
Oil prices were plunging. <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s market share began
drying up. By the time <PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON> became president again, in
<DATE>1989</DATE>, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> was nearly bankrupt.
   To provide the harsh medicine <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> needed to recover,
<PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON> came into office the second time as a free marketer
rather than a free spender, ready to undo what he had wrought
earlier. He reduced tariffs, removed price controls, raised
interest rates and began a painful task of restructuring
through privatization and deregulation. Some banks already
have been privatized. Up for sale are the airline and
telephone companies.
   When <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION> invaded <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION> <DATE>last August</DATE>, once again pointing
up the instability of <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> oil, <PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON> and others
in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> saw an opportunity to attract oil investment
anew.
   Fortunately, President <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> had not burned his bridges to
the oil companies. He had used a pragmatic approach to the
nationalization, which was handled in a businesslike way.
Generally, the oil companies' compensation was considered
fair, although many of the companies grumbled about the
terms.
   Now, a few major oil firms such as <ORGANIZATION>Phillips Petroleum Co.</ORGANIZATION>
are snubbing <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s overtures. "We have priorities in
other parts of the world," says <PERSON>C. J. Silas</PERSON>, chairman of
<LOCATION>Phillips</LOCATION>. But one firm indication of the attractions
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> holds for foreign oil companies came this <DATE>summer</DATE>
after <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> called for "expressions of interest" on a new
program to resurrect washed-out oil fields. That brought more
than 200 inquiries.
   Some of those fields were discovered as long ago as the
<DATE>1920s</DATE> and <DATE>1930s</DATE>, and most have been closed for 30 years after
cumulative oil production of 1.4 billion barrels. One <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>
official calls them "squeezed oranges." Still, with their
reactivation by foreign firms, "we expect to increase
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s production by 150,000 to 200,000 barrels a day,"
says <PERSON>Celestino Armas</PERSON>, minister of energy and mines.
   One company interested in the fields is <ORGANIZATION>Benton Oil &amp; Gas
Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, a small oil and gas producer. "That is our
niche: old fields that the majors leave behind which still
have enough oil and gas that a company like ours can make a
profit," says <PERSON>Clancy Cottman</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Benton</ORGANIZATION> vice president. Also,
he says, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> is a stable country with good relations
with the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and very large oil and gas reserves. "If you
want to be a player there," he says, "it might do you well to
participate" in the marginal fields program.
   In addition, many oil people point out that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> has
the infrastructure that oil companies need -- the roads to
get their rigs in and the pipelines to get the oil out. It
also has a large number of refineries, both at home and in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> And, in <LOCATION>Petroleos de Venezuela</LOCATION>, it has
perhaps the world's most highly regarded and efficient
state-owned oil company.
   Before nationalization, the oil companies were largely
staffed by Venezuelans, and by the time of the
nationalization some <PERCENT>95%</PERCENT> of all the employees in the oil
industry -- including many in top management -- were
Venezuelan. As a result, the successor companies were run
essentially as they had been before the nationalization, with
the same people but with a new owner, the Venezuelan
government.
   Since nationalization, <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> has tripled <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s
reserves with new finds. Its oil sales now total more than
<MONEY>$14 billion</MONEY> a year. A recent <ORGANIZATION>Salomon Brothers</ORGANIZATION> report called
<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> "the fourth-largest oil conglomerate in the world."
   Oil companies still have some concerns about <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s
internal politics. Bringing in foreign companies remains a
highly charged issue, and the policy reversals of <PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON>
aren't being welcomed wholeheartedly in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>. There were
riots when gasoline prices were raised soon after he took
office. Subsidized gasoline prices, still dirt cheap by the
standards of most other countries, continue to increase, but
gradually.
   In addition, there is a hot debate over whether oil policy
should be set by the oil industry or the government. <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s
president, <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON>, says the government is just a
shareholder in the industry and should limit its role to
supervision of the budget at the annual meeting. <PERSON>Mr. Armas</PERSON>,
the oil minister, sees it differently. "The ministry is not
the manager of the {oil} industry, but the controller who
sets the policy," he says.
   Foreign companies are watching. "The politics casts a
little fresh doubt on the Venezuelan deals," says an official
of one major oil company, "but everything wouldn't crater if
<PERSON>Sosa Pietri</PERSON> lost his job tomorrow."
   <PERSON>Mr. Perez</PERSON> will likely have the last word. He appointed
both men. "There is no dispute," he says.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870420-0106 </DOCNO>
<HL> Venezuela Varies Its Energy Spending
To Weather the Slump in Oil Industry
---
By Amy Myers Jaffe
<DD> 04/20/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> LATAM
PETROLEUM (PET)
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
CHEMICALS, PLASTICS (CHM)
NATURAL GAS, PIPELINES (LNG)
MINING, METALS (NON-PRECIOUS) (MIN) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The current combination of stagnant world demand for oil and excess production capacity is forcing <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> to look beyond its oil sector for growth. 

   The state oil company, Petroleos de <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, has allocated more than <MONEY>$4.6 billion</MONEY> for 1986-90 to developing other energy resources such as petrochemicals, natural gas, coal and bitumen. 
For the same period, the company budgeted <MONEY>$4.7 billion</MONEY> for domestic oil exploration and development and <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> for upgrading oil refineries. 

   "We don't see a big increase coming in oil demand by the <DATE>end of this decade</DATE>," <PERSON>Pablo Reimpell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Petroleos</PERSON>' vice president, said in a telephone interview. 
"But we can look to areas like petrochemicals as a place to improve profitability." 

   <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil income fell <PERCENT>44%</PERCENT> last year to <MONEY>$7.2 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$12.86 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1985</DATE>, according to government figures. 
Its oil exports averaged 1,534,000 barrels a day last year at an average price of <MONEY>$13.90</MONEY> a barrel. 
In <DATE>1985</DATE>, output was smaller, averaging 1,371,000 barrels a day, but the average price was almost twice as high, at <MONEY>$25.89</MONEY> a barrel. 

   Oil prices are expected to remain stable this year at higher levels than in <DATE>1986</DATE>. 
But <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil production is restricted by an <ORGANIZATION>Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries</ORGANIZATION> quota agreement to 1,495,000 barrels a day. 
At that production rate, the country's oil income couldn't recover to its <DATE>1985</DATE> level unless prices averaged more than <MONEY>$23</MONEY> a barrel, and there is no sign of that happening. 

   Among the non-oil sectors, <ORGANIZATION>Petroleos</ORGANIZATION> has earmarked the largest amount of capital for expansion of its petrochemical industry. 
In contrast to its declining oil revenue, the company's petrochemical sales rose <PERCENT>24%</PERCENT> last year to about <MONEY>$559 million</MONEY>. 
Petrochemical export volume jumped <PERCENT>45%</PERCENT> last year from <DATE>1985</DATE>, while domestic sales rose <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT>. 

   A <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> investment program for the petrochemicals sector has been approved by the government through <DATE>1992</DATE>, according to Petroleos. 
Combined with private capital infusions, the sector is likely to see investment of more than <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>, <PERSON>Jack Tarbes</PERSON>, a Petroleos vice president, said recently. 

   Meanwhile, the state also plans to invest <MONEY>$1.4 billion</MONEY> to expand its natural gas network. 

   <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> has 55 trillion cubic feet of proven natural gas reserves, about <PERCENT>11%</PERCENT> of the total in the <LOCATION>Western Hemisphere</LOCATION>. 
Petroleos estimates current demand for natural gas in the country at 1.8 billion cubic feet a day and projects that this could rise to 3.2 billion by the end of the century. 

   To meet demand, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> will expand its gas-pipeline system from the eastern part of the country to <LOCATION>Lake Maracaibo</LOCATION>, a major oil and gas reserve area in western <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>. 

   The pipeline project, scheduled for completion around <DATE>1990</DATE>, would be the first to link the gas reserves in the west with two major power plants in central <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and the industrial facilities in the eastern part of the country. 

   Petroleos also hopes the project will eventually boost exports of liquefied petroleum gas, according to <PERSON>Emma Brossard</PERSON>, a consultant to the company and a director of the <ORGANIZATION>Center for Energy Studies</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Louisiana State University</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Over the next five years, <ORGANIZATION>Petroleos</ORGANIZATION> also will look for growth opportunities through new energy industries, officials say. 
One example is orimulsion, a low-cost industrial fuel being tested by the company's research affiliate, <ORGANIZATION>Intevep</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Orimulsion is made by mixing bitumen -- the heavy oil tar sands found in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil-rich Orinoco belt -- with water and additives to make it more easily transportable. 

   Petroleos and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> utility officials say that once fully tested, orimulsion could become a competing fuel to coal and residual fuel oil. 
Petroleos has earmarked <MONEY>$180 million</MONEY> for development of the experimental fuel between now and <DATE>1992</DATE>. 

   And while it is working on this potential competitor to coal, <ORGANIZATION>Petroleos</ORGANIZATION> also plans to invest more than <MONEY>$870 million</MONEY> in domestic coal production by the end of the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. 

   Its coal company, <LOCATION>Carbozulia</LOCATION>, recently signed a preliminary development agreement with <ORGANIZATION>ACC Venezuela Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, an affiliate of <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles-based Atlantic Richfield Co.</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Agip Carbone</ORGANIZATION>, an affiliate of the Italian energy holding company <ORGANIZATION>Ente Nazionale Idrocarburi</ORGANIZATION>, to develop an open-pit bituminous coal mine in <LOCATION>Guasare</LOCATION>, 330 miles west of <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s capital. 
The Guasare area is believed to hold bituminous coal deposits of 470 million tons. 

   Carbozulia President <PERSON>Luis Urdenata</PERSON> said the initial cost of building the mine and related facilities would be around <MONEY>$455 million</MONEY>. 
He said the foreign joint-venture partners would contribute about <PERCENT>48%</PERCENT>. 

   Initial production at the mine is projected to begin in the <DATE>last quarter</DATE> of this year, with full production by <DATE>1995</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Tarbes</PERSON> of Petroleos says the move into the coal business could assist, rather than conflict with, the fledgling orimulsion program. 

   "By getting into the coal business," he says, "we will be more expert in a market where orimulsion will need to compete." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-14608</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CAOBBAC2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920115
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 JAN 92 / Commodities and Agriculture: Venezuela's output record
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOE MANN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   CARACAS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>VENEZUELA</LOCATION>'S production of crude oil in <DATE>1991</DATE> averaged 2.488m barrels a day,
the highest level on record since the country's petroleum industry was
nationalised in <DATE>1976</DATE>, official sources said in <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>.
The <DATE>1991</DATE> production figure, which includes crude oil and small proportions
of condensates and natural gas liquids, represents an increase of nearly 11
per cent over <DATE>1990</DATE> production of 2.249m b/d. Exports of crude oil and
refined products in <DATE>1991</DATE> averaged 2.08m b/d, up more than 10 per cent from
the previous year's average of 1.88m b/d.
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s proven reserves of crude oil totalled 62.8bn barrels at the end
of <DATE>1991</DATE>, up 5 per cent from a year earlier. This means that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>
continues to hold the largest proved reserves of crude oil in the <LOCATION>Western
Hemisphere</LOCATION>, even without including the country's very large deposits of
extra heavy oil located in the <LOCATION>Orinoco Belt</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 30
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-57009 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat091_t_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-091 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Finance Minister Sosa Discusses Auctions, Economy </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Finance Minister Sosa Discusses Auctions, Economy </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1005035594 Caracas ECONOMIA HOY in Spanish 6 May 94 p 4 </F>
<F P=103> PA1005035594 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas ECONOMIA HOY </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Gregorio Salazar</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] Finance Minister <PERSON>Julio Sosa Rodriguez</PERSON> admitted 
yesterday, upon returning from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, that a 
significant portion of the funds obtained as a result of 
currency devaluation will be used to pay the foreign debt. As 
Minister <PERSON>Sosa</PERSON> was about to get into his car, which by the way 
has a private license plate, he was approached by a reporter who 
asked: 
  [Unidentified Reporter] What will the government do with the 
additional income obtained from the sale of dollars? 
  [<PERSON>Sosa</PERSON>] Well, there are various aspects. First of all, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Central Bank of Venezuela</ORGANIZATION> [BCV] is trying to reduce liquidity 
through the zero coupon bond mechanism and is trying to 
establish a more permanent method. On the other hand, you must 
remember that our budgets include foreign debt servicing which 
must be paid in dollars, which means that it will cost us more 
bolivares. So we already know where those bolivares will go. 
  [Reporter] Can those bolivares be used to pay the debt? 
  [Sosa] Obviously ... 
  Previously, <PERSON>Sosa</PERSON> had answered several questions from 
reporters who inquired about the differences between the 
auctioning of dollars and foreign exchange controls. "The 
auctioning of dollars and foreign exchange controls are two 
completely different things. The word auction itself implies 
that there are no controls, because I understand it means that 
you can offer `two,' I can offer `three,' and another person can 
offer `two and a half.' Controls would mean that if I say `two' 
that is it." 
  <PERSON>Sosa</PERSON> said there will be no alternate to the BCV as a source 
of dollars. 
  [Reporter] Is the BCV also trying to control the large 
number 
of dollars being sold? 
  [<PERSON>Sosa</PERSON>] Evidently, it is trying to handle this -- price and 
volume -- step by step. I believe, however, that it is being 
handled beyond the normal needs. 
  He had previously been asked whether the mechanism to 
auction 
foreign exchange would be permanent or temporary. "I think it 
will last for some time. BCV is always trying to establish the 
measures that best fit the circumstances. For instance, the 
system the bank used a little more than a year ago, the 
"crawling peg standard" -- I do not know how to translate that, 
it sounds like a spider climbing a wall -- was different from 
the one used previously. The new mechanism fits reality more 
closely, and I think it will work just fine. 
  Sosa turned philosophical when he was asked what he had 
meant 
when he said the auctioning of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars would be permanent. 
"God is the only permanent concept in life. All of the material 
things and man do not last forever, and whoever says the 
opposite is wrong. I meant that the system would last one year, 
maybe longer." 
  Someone told him that, according to <ORGANIZATION>National Convergence</ORGANIZATION> 
Deputy <PERSON>Jose Miguel Uzcategui</PERSON>, auctioning is the best exchange 
control. "Well, I will ask him to explain that to me when I see 
him." 
  Sosa expressed confidence in the auction mechanism 
established by BCV. He regards the system as convenient because 
financial markets are gradually returning to tranquillity. 
According to the finance minister, the Economic Cabinet 
discussed his trip to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and divided the cabinet into 
four sectors: political, social, infrastructure, and economic. 
  He said that in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, he met people willing to 
enter joint ventures with <ORGANIZATION>CVG</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Guayana Corporation</ORGANIZATION>] 
in aluminum and steel manufacturing. He also thinks that another 
plant for manufacturing methanol for export could be built in 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Sosa</PERSON>, who is always optimistic, confidently expects 
inflation to decline and interest rates to fall by the end of 
the year. 
  Later, he said flatly that <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Petroleum, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 
[<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>] 
will not be privatized. "There are very good possibilities for 
foreign capital, with technology, resources, and market 
potential, to join <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> subsidiaries in certain projects." A 
very large investment is required in the <LOCATION>Orinoco Strip</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Orinoco 
Delta</ORGANIZATION>, eastern <LOCATION>Monagas</LOCATION>, and the southern <LOCATION>Sucre</LOCATION> projects, which 
are open for investment. "This does not mean that <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> 
subsidiaries or <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION> itself will be privatized," he said. 
  Asked how international reserves will be affected, he 
answered: "Let us hope that trust will make them increase. I do 
not think this system will affect the reserves. If they are 
affected in any way, it will be for the better." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900416-0098
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900416-0098.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Venezuela to Ease Foreign Investment
   In Energy Sector, Petroleos Chief Says
   ----
   By Julia Lichtblau
</HL>
<DATE>
04/16/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B6C
</SO>
<CO>
   LATAM
</CO>
<IN>
PETROLEUM (PET)
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC NEWS AND STATISTICS (IEN)
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
</IN>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Venezuela expects within the next few months
to have completed steps to facilitate foreign investment in
its oil and petrochemical industries, said Petroleos de
Venezuela S.A. president, Andres Sosa Pietri.
   At a luncheon of the Venezuelan American Association in
New York last week, Mr. Sosa Pietri said the state oil
company is seeking to encourage foreign investment in an
effort to triple capacity in the next five years.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The government is sponsoring a bill in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to permit
foreign involvement in a proposed <MONEY>$3.5 billion</MONEY> liquefied
natural gas project, <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON> said. That project,
which is expected to require the development of offshore gas
reserves, would be an important new outlet for <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s
106 trillion cubic feet of natural gas.
   <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON> said that five or six foreign companies
have made firm offers to join a Petroleos affiliate in the
the end of <DATE>May</DATE>.
   Foreign participation in the Venezuelan oil industry has
been strictly limited since its nationalization during
administration. But after his re-election in late <DATE>1988</DATE>,
President <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> embarked on an economic overhaul package
intended to reduce the country's heavy foreign debt and
stimulate the local economy. That program has included
encouraging private sector participation in key industries,
allowing the market to set the exchange rate for the bolivar,
and lifting price controls on many goods.
   The encouragement of foreign investment in the energy
sector is still controversial in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, and some analysts
have expressed doubts that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> would move proposals
through as fast as <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON> thinks they will.
   High tax rates are one obstacle to foreign investment that
the government is hoping to alleviate. Corporations are
generally taxed at a rate of <PERCENT>48%</PERCENT>, while Petroleos struggles
under a composite tax burden of <PERCENT>82%</PERCENT>. He said <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is
considering legislation that would lower the corporate tax
rate to <PERCENT>35%</PERCENT>.
   To help with plans to increase crude oil production
capacity, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> also is considering revising rules that
prevent foreign participation in the upstream sector of
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s oil industry, <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON> said. New rules
could come by mid-May, he said.
   He didn't specify how the rules would be revised other
than to say that they wouldn't include concessions, which
aren't allowed by the constitution. However, he said
<PERSON>Petroleos</PERSON> hopes for "joint ventures from exploration all the
way through downstream."
   <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> also plans to expand its production of
orimulsion, a bitumen and water blend that competes with coal
at a price of about <MONEY>$5</MONEY> a barrel, <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON> said. "A
series of agreements" will put exports at 100,000 barrels a
day by <DATE>1992</DATE>, he said. That blend, developed by Petroleos and
the <ORGANIZATION>British Petroleum Co.</ORGANIZATION>, will enable <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> to take
advantage of its 230 billion barrels of bitumen reserves in
<LOCATION>Orinoco</LOCATION>.
   Regarding Petroleos itself, he said that there is a
reorganization under way to "enhance the role of Petroleos as
a holding company, not an operating company," and to
strengthen the role of the affiliates.
   The Petroleos chief took pains to emphasize that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>
sees its economic future tied to the health of the economies
of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, its main markets. Price
shocks aren't in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s interest, he stressed. "We
believe in price increases . . . that go along with world
inflation levels."
   <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON> said he didn't think that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s
membership in the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of Petroleum Exporting
Countries</ORGANIZATION> would hamstring its plans to increase crude-oil
production capacity beyond its present <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> quota. As demand
outstrips <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> production capacity, the need for quotas will
disappear, <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University Law School</ORGANIZATION> graduate
who spent his career as a self-described "entrepreneur in
medium-sized companies" dealing with international markets,
also addressed the outcry accompanying his appointment.
President <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> was criticized for appointing an outsider to
the company, but <PERSON>Mr. Sosa Pietri</PERSON> said it reflected the
president's commitment to encouraging the private sector and
maintaining Petroleos as a commercial entity.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-34628 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat120_t_94009" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-120 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Roundup of Economic Developments </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Roundup of Economic Developments </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2106180594 </F>
<F P=103> PA2106180594 </F>
<F P=104></F>



<TEXT>
BFN 

    [Editorial Report] The following is a compilation of 
reports on economic developments monitored through 21 <DATE>June</DATE>. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Banco de Maracaibo</ORGANIZATION> intervention board believes it is 
still possible to rescue this failing financial institution. The 
intervention board has completed a <ORGANIZATION>Banco de Maracaibo</ORGANIZATION> rescue 
plan that will be presented before the Banking 
Superintendency--the agency responsible for making a final 
decision on the issue. If the intervention board's plan is 
accepted, <ORGANIZATION>Banco de Maracaibo</ORGANIZATION> could begin operating again some 
time before <DATE>29 June</DATE>--the date when <ORGANIZATION>Fogade</ORGANIZATION> [Deposit Guarantee and 
Banking Protection Fund] is scheduled to reinstate additional 
losses of 7.2 billion bolivares. According to the intervention 
board, <ORGANIZATION>Banco de Maracaibo</ORGANIZATION> is in a position to reimburse <ORGANIZATION>Fogade</ORGANIZATION> 
all of the <MONEY>120 billion bolivares</MONEY> it has received in financial 
assistance so far. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas Union Radio Network</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish 2200 
GMT 20 Jun 94) 
  The banking liquidity coefficient has fallen to <PERCENT>30.6 
percent</PERCENT>. 
The coefficient, which measures cash availability in terms of 
total funds deposited in banks, was <PERCENT>30.6 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>May</DATE>. This 
means that for every 100 bolivares deposited by the public, the 
banking system is in a position to immediately provide slightly 
more than 30 bolivares. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas Union Radio</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish <DATE>1245 GMT 
20 Jun 94</DATE>) 
  According to <PERSON>Charles Roccia</PERSON>, vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Banco 
Provincial de Venezuela</ORGANIZATION>, a financing agreement was signed on 15 
<DATE>June</DATE> with a syndicate of Portuguese banks headed by <ORGANIZATION>Banco de 
Fomento de Portugal</ORGANIZATION>. The terms of the agreement include a <MONEY>$20 
million</MONEY> line of credit to be used to finance clients of 
Venezuelan banks who wish to import products from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. 
Roccia</PERSON> pointed out that the agreement is very significant, 
particularly at this time, because it shows <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s 
confidence in the Venezuelan banking system. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas EL GLOBO</ORGANIZATION> 
in <DATE>Spanish 16 Jun 94</DATE> p 12) 
  In <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, state-owned <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>) has 
announced that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> will begin selling orimulsion, boiler 
fuel made from heavy oil comprising <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> bitumen and <PERCENT>30 
percent</PERCENT> water, in the Chinese market as result of a recent 
agreement signed between the <ORGANIZATION>North Industries Shenzhen 
Corporation</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>PDVSA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Bitumenes del Orinoco</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary. The 
agreement includes the supply of orimulsion for an electrical 
plant scheduled to begin operations in <DATE>1995</DATE>. The Venezuelan 
company will be responsible to market, sale, and supply the 
orimulsion, as well as providing technical assistance to the 
client. (<ORGANIZATION>Paris AFP</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish 2018 GMT 20 Jun 94) 
  Recently released figures from the <ORGANIZATION>Central Statistics and 
Data Processing Office</ORGANIZATION> show that imports totaled <MONEY>$2.649 billion</MONEY> 
in the <DATE>first quarter</DATE> of the year, reflecting a <PERCENT>31.9 percent</PERCENT> drop 
from the same period in <DATE>1993</DATE>. The report also shows that <PERCENT>46.1 
percent</PERCENT> of all imports originated in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>; <PERCENT>7.1 
percent</PERCENT> from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>; <PERCENT>7.0 percent</PERCENT> from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>; <PERCENT>4.6 percent</PERCENT> from 
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>; <PERCENT>4.2 percent</PERCENT> from <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>; <PERCENT>3.2 percent</PERCENT> from <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>; and 
<PERCENT>3.0 percent</PERCENT> from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. (<ORGANIZATION>Caracas EL UNIVERSAL</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish 16 Jun 
94 p 2-1) 

</TEXT>
