<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900417-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-17-90 0524EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     04-17 0433</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0444</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Falls From South to Northeast, Snow in Upper Michigan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain fell in a broad swath today from <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, and
thunderstorms rattled <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>.
   While much of the nation enjoyed fair weather, rain fell early
today from <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and storms enveloped
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and parts of <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Texas Panhandle</LOCATION>.
   Snow fell in <LOCATION>northern Michigan</LOCATION>, where four inches were dumped
<DATE>Monday</DATE> on <ORGANIZATION>Sault Ste. Marie</ORGANIZATION>. Temperatures dipped early today to 30
degrees in <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON>, 29 in Minneapolis-St. Paul and 21 in
<LOCATION>Rapid City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>
   A cold front drifted southward, bringing gusty winds and colder
temperatures.
   Today's forecast called for showers running in a band from
<LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> to southern <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>, from <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> and across
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state. Thunderstorms were predicted from <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION>.
   A record temperature for <DATE>April 16</DATE> was broken at <LOCATION>Pocatello</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, where the mercury touched 80, up from the previous high of
79 in <DATE>1936</DATE>.
   The high temperature in the Lower 48 states <DATE>Monday</DATE> was 94 at
<LOCATION>Midland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EST</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 46 cloudy; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 60 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 45 fair;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 49 rain; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 62 fair; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 54 fair;
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 56 cloudy; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 52 rain; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 38 windy; Hatteras
61 fair; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 59 foggy; Key West 64 fair; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 59
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 74 fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 48 fair;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 50 fair; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 55 cloudy; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 35
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 50 fair; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 66 fair; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 54
cloudy.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 53 fair; Bismarck 26 fair; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 39 fair;
<LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 35 cloudy; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 33 fair; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 71 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 43 showers; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 40 windy; Little Rock 68
cloudy; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 60 cloudy; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 70 cloudy; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 61
cloudy; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 62 foggy; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 35 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION>
50 thunderstorm; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 33 partly cloudy; Rapid City 21 fair; <LOCATION>St.
Louis</LOCATION> 43 rain; Minneapolis-St. Paul 29 fair; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 30
snow; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 71 cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 57 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 36 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION>
67 fair; Casper 33 cloudy; Fairbanks 38 cloudy; Great Falls 34
fair; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 73 fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 60 windy; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 60 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 54 cloudy; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 72 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 59 cloudy; Reno 50 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 63
windy; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 61 fair; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 57 cloudy; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 55 fair;
<LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 49 fair.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 34 fair; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 39 cloudy; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 37
cloudy; Regina 23 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 45 showers; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 19 fair; <LOCATION>San
Juan</LOCATION> 74 fair.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900508-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-08-90 0541EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     05-08 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Blasts North Plains; Mild Over Much of Nation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A blast of cold descended over the <LOCATION>northern Plains</LOCATION> <DATE>early today</DATE>,
while much of the rest of the nation enjoyed mild weather.
   A thunderstorn rumbled through <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>, and
temperatures dropped into the 30s and 40s in the <LOCATION>Dakotas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>.
   Rain fell in <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, and
winds buffeted <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Key
West</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   Today's forecast called for snow flurries in <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>
and showers over <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> and southern <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Frost warnings were posted over <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>, and a hard
freeze was possible in <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, unseasonably high temperatures extended across the
<LOCATION>northern Plains</LOCATION>. The high of 92 in <LOCATION>St. Cloud</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, broke the
record of 87 for the date, set in <DATE>1963</DATE>.
   Flooding continued along the rain-swollen <LOCATION>Trinity River</LOCATION> south of
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   The high temperature in the nation <DATE>Monday</DATE> was 104 degrees at
<LOCATION>Bullhead City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 45 rain; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 49 fair;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 49 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 57 foggy; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 49
fair; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 58 fair; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 61 fair;
<LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 63 fair; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 51 fair; Key West 78 windy;
<LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 49 fair; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 52 fair; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 75 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
52 fair; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 58 fair; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 57 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>
39 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 57 fair; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 68 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 56 fair.
   _Central: Bismarck 41 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 50
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 68 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 65 windy; Little Rock 63 fair;
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 61 fair; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 53 fair; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 65 cloudy; <LOCATION>North
Platte</LOCATION> 50 thunderstorm; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 66 windy; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 66 fair;
Rapid City 40 fair; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 67 fair; Minneapolis-St. Paul 64
cloudy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 44 showers; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 66 cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 45 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 40 partly
cloudy; Casper 40 cloudy; Fairbanks 53 cloudy; Great Falls 29 fair;
<LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 74 fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 79 windy; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 62 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 48 fair; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 42 fair; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 83 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>
46 fair; Reno 53 fair; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 47 fair; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 59 cloudy;
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 51 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 45 fair; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 34 fair.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 30 snow; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 41 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 43 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Regina</LOCATION> 39 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 43 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 43 cloudy; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 78 partly cloudy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900613-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-90 0622EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     06-13 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Falls in Midwest, Northwest; Fair Weather Prevails</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain was scattered over <LOCATION>Upper Michigan</LOCATION>, northern <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and
the <ORGANIZATION>Northwest</ORGANIZATION> today, while fair weather prevailed much of the rest
of the nation.
   Today's forecast called for showers over parts of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, and thunderstorms in bands
from <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> through <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> through <LOCATION>Arksansas</LOCATION> and along
the southeastern coast of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Rain fell early today in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, and
<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>.
   Tornado warnings were posted over parts of <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South
Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>.
   A tornado touched down <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> near <LOCATION>Massena</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, but no
injuries or major property damage was reported. Heavy snow fell in
<LOCATION>Yellowstone Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, and snow and fog blanketed uplands in <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>.
   The high temperature for the nation was 105 degrees at <LOCATION>Bullhead
City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Presidio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 54 fair; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 69 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 55 fair;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 63 showers; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 66 fair;
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 64 cloudy; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 65 fair; Hatteras
66 fair; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 66 fair; Key West 81 cloudy; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 66
fair; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 70 fair; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 77 fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>
57 fair; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 62 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 45 fair;
<LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 72 fair; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 62 fair.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 72 fair; Bismarck 54 cloudy; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 55
fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 79 windy; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 82 fair; <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 66
fair; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 78 windy; Little Rock 71 fair; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 68
fair; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 73 fair; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 68 fair; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 78 fair;
<LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 64 cloudy; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 79 windy; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 70 windy;
Rapid City 59 fair; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 76 fair; Minneapolis-St. Paul 69
cloudy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 56 showers; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 78 partly cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 67 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 58 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 47 fair;
Casper 38 partly cloudy; Fairbanks 63 cloudy; Great Falls 43 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 77 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 78 windy; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>
63 fair; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 53 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 51 windy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 89
fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 52 cloudy; Reno 55 fair; Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION> 55
cloudy; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 63 cloudy; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 54 windy; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 50
drizzle; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 49 cloudy.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 43 showers; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 63 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 63 partly cloudy; Regina 45 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 61 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 59 showers; <LOCATION>Merida</LOCATION> 81 fair; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 79 fair.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900904-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-04-90 0600EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     09-04 0455</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Scattered in West; Scorcher Forecast in Southern Plains</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain was scattered in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> <DATE>early today</DATE>, and a heat wave
moved deeper into the nation's mid-section.
   Elsewhere today, rain fell at <LOCATION>Key West</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, and in <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> at
<LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON>.
   In the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>, there was rain in <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>, and
thunderstorms were over <LOCATION>Casper</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo</LOCATION>.
   The heat wave that baked the southern <LOCATION>Plains</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE> was
slowly moving eastward into <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> from southern
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and eastern <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>.
   Temperatures were expected to climb into the 100s in the region.
A high-pressure front was keeping temperatures about 15 degrees
above normal.
   Later today, thunderstorms were expected along a cold front
extending across <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>.
Damaging wind with large hail and flooding was possible.
   Rain also was likely in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>. Muggy weather was expected in the region.
   The forecast also called for rain in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and the southern
Rockies.
   Thunderstorms were likely in the desert <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>, threatening
flooding in the region because of frequent thunderstorms this
<DATE>summer</DATE>.
   The nation's high for <DATE>Monday</DATE> was 110 degrees at <LOCATION>Borrego Springs</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   Other reports <TIME>5 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 50 fair; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 76 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 58 fair;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 53 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, 74 cloudy; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION>
74 hazy; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 56 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 60
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 76 windy; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 74 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Key West 80</LOCATION> showers; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 66 foggy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 75 fair; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 79
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 62 fair; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>
57 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, 50 fair; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>
73 fair; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, 69 partly cloudy.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 80 fair; <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> 68 cloudy; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 63
fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 73 hazy; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 76 fair; <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 64 fair;
<LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 78 fair; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 67 fair; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 79 hazy; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>
75 fair; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 75 foggy; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 72 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION>
76 fair; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 72 fair; Rapid City 71 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 78
fair; Minneapolis-St. Paul 72 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 61
showers; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 73 partly cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 69 cloudy; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 52 rain; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 70 fair;
Casper 61 partly cloudy; Fairbanks 53 cloudy; Great Falls 60 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 80 fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 71 windy; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 66 fair;
<LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 62 fair; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 76 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 63 fair; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> 54 fair; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 72 showers;
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 68 fair; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 61 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 62 fair;
<LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 62 fair.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 45 fair; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 50 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 48 fair; Regina 48 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 48 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION>
57 fair; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 77 partly cloudy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900421-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-21-90 0551EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     04-21 0470</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0481</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Falls in Northwest, Midwest and West</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain drenched much of the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> and parts of
the southwest today, and freezing cold lingered in <LOCATION>Upper Michigan</LOCATION>.
   Storms raced across <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION> <DATE>early today</DATE> and fog hovered over
parts of the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>, including <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>, and
Little Rock, <LOCATION>Ark</LOCATION>.
   Rain fell in <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, and from the <LOCATION>Ohio Valley</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. Temperatures dropped to freezing at <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich</LOCATION>.
   Today's forecast predicted rain and thunderstorms in a band from
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. Rain also is expected to fall in parts
of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, thunderstorms were scattered across the southern
<LOCATION>Plains</LOCATION>, bringing hail to <LOCATION>Cochran County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Strong winds at
<LOCATION>Mountain Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>, destroyed a mobile home, damaged a trailer
and downed power lines.
   Storms over northern <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> produced thick hail at <LOCATION>San Angelo</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Atise</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Eastland</LOCATION> and near <LOCATION>Ranger</LOCATION>.
   Storms were scattered from <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> to eastern <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>
and eastern <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>, and from the <LOCATION>Great Basin</LOCATION> to
the northern Rockies. A thunderstorm over <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> spawned a tornado
west of the town of <LOCATION>Kimberly</LOCATION>.
   The high temperature for the nation <DATE>Friday</DATE> was 96 degrees at
<LOCATION>Lake Havasu City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EST</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 52 rain; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 61 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 53 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 49 rain; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 57 fair; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 61 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 62 rain; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 57 rain; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 54 drizzle;
<LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 60 fair; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 58 fair; Key West 74 fair; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION>
64 cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 58 fair; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 73 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 50
showers; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 56 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 55 showers;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 45 rain; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 63 fair;
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 59 partly cloudy.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 65 partly cloudy; Bismarck 60 fair; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>
52 foggy; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 50 fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 54 fair; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 67 fair;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 59 rain; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 52 foggy; Little Rock 62 foggy;
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 63 rain; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 65 thunderstorm; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 62 cloudy;
<LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 70 cloudy; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 47 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 60 fair;
<LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 51 fair; Rapid City 54 fair; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 60 partly cloudy;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 56 fair; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie 32</PERSON> fair; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>
72 cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 58 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 42 fair; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 51 fair;
Casper 60 fair; Fairbanks 39 partly cloudy; Great Falls 52 fair;
<LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 74 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 60 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 59 fair;
<LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 53 fair; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 56 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 78 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 46 fair; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> 49 showers; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 57
cloudy; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 62 cloudy; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 54 cloudy; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 50
cloudy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 48 cloudy.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 55 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 48 rain;
<LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 48 rain; Regina 48 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 50 foggy; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 59
windy; <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> 61 fair; <LOCATION>Acapulco</LOCATION> 81 partly cloudy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900724-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-24-90 0651EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     07-24 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0394</SECOND>
<HEAD>Skies Dry After a Night of Rain</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   There was rain in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> early today, but skies were dry
elsewhere after a night of showers throughout the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   Showers and thunderstorms <DATE>Monday</DATE> produced high winds that
knocked down trees in southern <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> and produced a tornado
in southern <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Okeechobee</LOCATION>.
   Rain extended from eastern <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> and
fell in parts of <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Showers and thunderstorms also extended from the southern half
of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>.
   Rain fell early today in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>.
   It was a tie for the nation's high temperature <DATE>Monday</DATE>; <LOCATION>Borrego
Springs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Lake Havasu City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, each peaked at 111
degrees.
   Other reports at <TIME>5 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 68 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 71 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>
75 cloudy; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 65 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, 79 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 71 fair; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 61 fair;
<LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 78 fair; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 77 fair; Key West 80 fair; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION>
70 cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 72 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 76 fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 72
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 73 cloudy; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 60 fair;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, 69 foggy; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 72 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 80
fair; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, 70 fair.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 70 foggy; Bismarck 62 fair; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 64
fair; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 60 fair; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 72 fair;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 60 fair; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 64 fair; Little Rock 72 foggy;
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 69 fair; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 71 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 68 fair;
<LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 73 fair; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 71 fair;
<LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 62 fair; Rapid City 58 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 68 fair;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 62 fair; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 54 foggy; <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> 77 partly cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 66 windy; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 57 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION>
70 partly cloudy; Casper 61 fair; Fairbanks 72 smoke; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 78
fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 91 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 64 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 65
fair; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 65 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 90 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>,
61 fair; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> 67 fair; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 74 fair; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 68 cloudy;
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 57 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 59 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 62 fair.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 59 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 64 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 63 cloudy; Regina 57 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION>
61 cloudy; <LOCATION>Merida</LOCATION> 75 fair; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 78 partly cloudy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900530-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-30-90 0625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     05-30 0432</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0444</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Across Northeast; Tornadoes Threatened in Texas</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain fell in the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION>, parts of the <LOCATION>northern Plains</LOCATION> and in
the inland mountains of the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION> <DATE>early today</DATE>.
   A tornado watch was in effect for portions of central and
north-central <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, with storms and flood-producing rain predicted
around the south-central Plains.
   Temperatures dropped close to or below freezing overnight in
parts of northern <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> and mountainous areas of
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>.
   Rain was expected to move into the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> <DATE>later today</DATE>, leaving
partially sunny skies in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION>.
   Scattered but heavy thunderstorms were expected in much of the
coastal <ORGANIZATION>Northwest</ORGANIZATION>, especially <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>.
   Three tornadoes touched down in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, one in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> and one
near <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said. They
caused no serious damage or injuries.
   Winds gusted to 90 mph at <LOCATION>Hobart</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>, damaging the roof of a
medical center.
   Heavy rainfall <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> included more than 2 inches in the
<TIME>afternoon</TIME> at <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   The nation's high for <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was 104 degrees at <LOCATION>Presidio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>5 a.m.</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 51 rain; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 55 rain;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 43 fair; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, 62 fair; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 55 fair;
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 53 fair; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 47 fair; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 42 fair; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 64
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 60 fair; Key West 79 cloudy; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION>
52 fair; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 55 fair; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 78 fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 54 rain;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 56 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 45 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>
53 rain; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 57 cloudy; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 72 fair; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, 55
windy.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 54 fair; <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> 60 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>
47 fair; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 48 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 58 fair; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 72
foggy; <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 50 fair; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 62 cloudy; Little Rock 64
hazy; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 58 fair; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 63 fair; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>New
Orleans</LOCATION> 66 fair; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 55 rain; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 67 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 64 cloudy; Rapid City 52 rain; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 59 partly
cloudy; Minneapolis-St. Paul 51 fair; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie 35</PERSON> fair; <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> 79 partly cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 51 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 54 fair; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 54 showers;
Casper 46 partly cloudy; Fairbanks 61 cloudy; Great Falls 53 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 74 cloudy; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 68 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>
57 fair; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 52 showers; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 55 cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 71 fair;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 54 partly cloudy; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> 47 fair; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 54
showers; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 62 cloudy; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 58 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 53 fair; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 48 fair.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 55 foggy; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 46 windy; Regina 63
windy; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 43 fair; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 52 fair; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 77 fair.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900425-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-25-90 0651EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     04-25 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Falls in Northwest, Fair Weather Over Much of Nation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain fell over parts of the <ORGANIZATION>Northwest</ORGANIZATION> today, while fair weather
prevailed across much of the rest of the nation.
   Today's forecast calls for rain over the <ORGANIZATION>Upper and Lower
Rockies</ORGANIZATION>, from <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> into <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, and scattered
storms in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, storms rumbled through <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Upper
Michigan</LOCATION>, parts of the <LOCATION>Upper Mississippi Valley</LOCATION>, eastern <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>.
   Showers and storms developed along a cold front extending from
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>. Rain also fell over the <LOCATION>northern Plains</LOCATION> and
the southern Rockies.
   Storms over the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Panhandle</ORGANIZATION> spawned a tornado and produced
golf ball- size hail south of the town of <ORGANIZATION>McLean</ORGANIZATION>.
   Forecasters said more severe weather was likely today in
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> after a tornado caused extensive property damage in
<LOCATION>Shattuck</LOCATION>.
   Fair skies prevailed from the <LOCATION>Southeastern</LOCATION> states into the <LOCATION>Ohio
Valley</LOCATION> and the mid-Atlantic coast.
   The high temperature for the nation <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was 94 at <LOCATION>Presidio</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   In other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 51 windy; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 45 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 71 fair; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 60 fair; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 57 fair;
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 64 fair; Hatteras 65
cloudy; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 55 fair; Key West 73 cloudy; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 66
fair; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 62 fair; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 73 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 48 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 46 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 63 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 42 cloudy; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 57 foggy; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 64 fair;
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 54 foggy.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 67 fair; Bismarck 55 cloudy; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 72
fair; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 45 fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 67 cloudy; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 67 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 68 fair; Little Rock 70 fair;
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 67 fair; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 69 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 65 fair;
<LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 70 cloudy; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 66 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION>
64 fair; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 67 partly cloudy; Rapid City 51 cloudy; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 74
partly cloudy; Minneapolis-St. Paul 69 fair; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 48
foggy; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 71 showers.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 42 showers; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 40 fair; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 45 fair;
Casper 44 drizzle; Fairbanks 40 fair; Great Falls 41 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 75 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 63 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 59 fair;
<LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 52 cloudy; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 47 fair; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 59 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 49 rain; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> 50 fair; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 51 windy; <LOCATION>San
Diego</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 52 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 46 rain; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 41
fair.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 39 fair; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 52 cloudy; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 54
cloudy; Regina 52 cloudy; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 54 fair; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 46 rain; <LOCATION>Mexico
City</LOCATION> 55 fair; <LOCATION>Acapulco</LOCATION> 81 fair; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 73 rain.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900104-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-04-90 0559EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     01-04 0484</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Rain Falls Across Midwest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Much of the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>, where temperatures warmed to above
freezing, was drenched in a cold rain early today, while the
northern Plains registered temperatures in the teens.
   Rain fell in <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> had snow.
   Western sections of the nation were seasonably cold early today.
Reno, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> had temperatures below freezing, and
temperatures were in the 30s and 40s along the <LOCATION>Pacific Coast</LOCATION> from
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>.
   Late <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, snow fell in parts of eastern <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> and
western <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, and rain fell in parts of <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>.
   Snowfall totals in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> <DATE>late Wednesday</DATE> included 5 inches at
Rye and <LOCATION>Beulah</LOCATION>.
   Thunderstorms produced large hail in north-central <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. Quarter-size hail was reported in <LOCATION>Nash</LOCATION>, and
dime-size hail fell south of <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION>.
   Also <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, rain extended across much of <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>,
the lower <LOCATION>Mississippi Valley</LOCATION>, eastern <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>northwest
Florida</LOCATION> and western <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state. Snow fell over some of the
higher elevations in eastern <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Temperatures warmed into the 30s and lower 40s in the <LOCATION>Great
Lakes</LOCATION> region. The afternoon high of 39 degrees at <LOCATION>Marquette</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>,
broke their previous record high for the date of 37 degrees
established in <DATE>1964</DATE> and tied in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   The nation's high on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> was 84 degrees at <LOCATION>Kingsville</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>4 a.m. EST</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>:
   _EAST: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 33 fair; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 52 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 33 fair;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 42; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, 52 foggy; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 50 rain;
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 45 rain; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 44 cloudy; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 38 rain; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION>
47 cloudy; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 49 foggy; Key West 73 drizzle; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 41
cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 48 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 74 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 31
fair; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 29 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 43 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, 31 fair; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 37 fair; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 61 fair;
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, 30 fair.
   _CENTRAL: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 57 cloudy; <ORGANIZATION>Bismarck</ORGANIZATION> 20 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 42 rain; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 18 fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 26 snow; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 54;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 43 rain; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 32 rain; Little Rock 56 foggy;
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 50 showery; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 51 cloudy; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 53 rain; <LOCATION>New
Orleans</LOCATION> 64 foggy; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 21 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 38 windy;
<LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 30 windy; Rapid City 19 fair; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 52 partly cloudy;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 18 cloudy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 34 foggy; <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> 61 partly cloudy.
   _WEST: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 25 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 18 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 25
cloudy; Casper 15 fair; Fairbanks -7 cloudy; Great Falls 29 windy;
<LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 74 fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 29 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 50 fair; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION>
30; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 43 cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 42 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 48
cloudy; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> 17 fair; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 12 fair; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 50 fair;
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 40 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 44 rain; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 31 fair.
   _INTERNATIONAL: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 14 foggy; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 37 cloudy; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 37
cloudy; Regina -3 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 39 cloudy; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> -5; <LOCATION>Acapulco</LOCATION> 75
fair; <LOCATION>San Juan 75</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-WeatherpageWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0 12-24 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0460,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>Icy West Stays Cold, Balmy East Cools</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `Other reports...', to end to CORRECT that
numbers are for 4 a.m. sted 5 a.m. EST; CORRECT readings for Boise,
Pendleton, Reno, Salt Lake City, and Minneapolis, where minus sign
was dropped.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Bone-chilling cold in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> collided with a rare winter warm
front over the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE>, generating heavy snow, sleet and rain
that caused serious flooding in parts of the <LOCATION>South</LOCATION>.
   A slew of winter weather warnings and advisories were posted
from coast to coast as the Arctic front that froze most of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>
<DATE>last week</DATE> edged toward the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   Snow fell today in the <LOCATION>Ohio Valley</LOCATION>, and was forecast for the
northern <LOCATION>Cascades</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>northern Plains</LOCATION> and Great
Lakes region.
   Heavy rain was expected in the East, Southeast and Appalachian
states.
   Subfreezing temperatures were common throughout the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>.
   After record highs throughout the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, including 71
degrees as far north as <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, and highs in the 60s into
southern <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, temperatures cooled considerably today.
   By <DATE>Christmas Day</DATE>, <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION> highs were likely to peak around 30
degrees. A cold snap continued in the West, but frigid temperatures
were expected to moderate somewhat.
   Other reports at <TIME>4 a.m. EST</TIME>:
   -East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 39 rain; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 33 windy; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 48 rain;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 26; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, 68 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 26
snow; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 13 snow; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 22 snow; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 15 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 71 foggy; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 71 partly cloudy; Key West
71 fair; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 28 cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 45 cloudy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 70 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 54 rain; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 61 rain; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 31 snow;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, 44 rain; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 65 rain; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 70 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, 64 cloudy.
   -Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 24 cloudy; <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> 13 snow; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 2
fair; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 12 fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 2 fair; <LOCATION>Fort Worth 17</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 2 fair; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 6 fair; Little Rock 14 fair;
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 13 snow; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 15 fair; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 16 snow; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>
33 windy; North Platte 2 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 14 fair; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 6 fair;
Rapid City 4 fair; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 4 fair; Minneapolis-St. Paul -12 fair;
<LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> zero fair; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 24 cloudy.
   -West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 3 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 21 foggy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> -20 foggy;
Casper 7 windy; Fairbanks 17 snow; Great Falls 18 windy; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>
72 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 19 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 43 fair; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION>
13 fair; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> -4 fair; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 35 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 16
fair; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> -5 fair; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> -6 fair; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 46 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 31 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 24 cloudy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 10
cloudy.
   -International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 25 windy; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 25 snow; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 19
snow; <PERSON>Regina</PERSON> zero fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 23 snow; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 08 fair; <LOCATION>Mexico
City</LOCATION> 48 fair; <LOCATION>Acapulco</LOCATION> 73 fair; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 70.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891116-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-16-89 0616EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     11-16 0536</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blast of Frigid Air Moves into Nation's Midsection</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A blast of frigid air continued to move through the nation's
midsection today, as thunderstorms were pushing out the warm
weather that the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> has had since the <DATE>weekend</DATE>.
   Tornadoes in <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> caused hundreds of injuries and many deaths <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Wintery weather swept into <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, bringing snow that put a
chill on the opening day of deer season and was a factor in an auto
accident in which four teen-agers were killed.
   Temperatures early <TIME>this morning</TIME> fell to freezing in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Peoria</LOCATION>, 30 in <LOCATION>Rockford</LOCATION> and 33 in <LOCATION>Decatur</LOCATION> as a light snow dusted
central <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, temperatures dipped into the teens and single
digits from eastern <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> through the <LOCATION>Dakotas</LOCATION> to northwestern
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> by <TIME>early evening</TIME>. Winds gusting to 40 mph produced wind
chill readings colder than 25 degrees below zero.
   There were dozens of reports of large hail and damaging winds in
<LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, while thunderstorms
produced heavy rain across parts of the <LOCATION>Ohio Valley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION> and
the central <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Coast</ORGANIZATION> states.
   In <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, thunderstorms produced an inch of rain in half an hour
in <LOCATION>Fairfield</LOCATION>, 1.75 inches of rain in 20 minutes at <LOCATION>Wayne</LOCATION>, and 1.7
inches of rain in 20 minutes at <LOCATION>Trenton</LOCATION>.
   Snow fell across the upper <LOCATION>Mississippi Valley</LOCATION> and western
sections of the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION> region <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, with heavy snow
today along the southern shore of Lake Superior and <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION>.
   Up to a foot of snow was expected to fall today in upper
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and storm warnings and watches were in effect for lower
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and northern <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>. Gale warnings were in effect for
Lake Superior and <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION>.
   The nation's high <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> was 92 degrees at <LOCATION>McAllen</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at a.m. EST:
   _East: <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 48 windy; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 64 showery; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 57;
<LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 71 thunderstorms; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 43 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 37 rain; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 41 rain; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 33 snow; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 73
windy; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 73 cloudy; Key West 78 fair; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 43
showery; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 63 cloudy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 75 fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 61 windy;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 64 cloudy; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 54 showery; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 56
foggy; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 68 windy; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 76 cloudy; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 65
cloudy.
   _Central: Bismarck 2 fair; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 33 cloudy; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 15 fair;
<LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 19 snow; <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 34 snow; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 23 windy;
Little Rock 45 fair; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 39 rain; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 43 fair; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>
42 cloudy; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 55 windy; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 10 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma
City</LOCATION> 33 fair; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 16 windy; Rapid City 5 fair; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 35 snow;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 15 windy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 25 snow; <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> 44 partly cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 16 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 31 cloudy; Casper 22 partly
cloudy; Fairbanks 2 cloudy; Great Falls 32 fair; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 69 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 52 cloudy; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 65 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION>
37 fair; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 37 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 58 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 42 fair; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> 30 fair; Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION> 29 cloudy; <LOCATION>San
Diego</LOCATION> 58 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 51 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 44 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 30 cloudy.
   _International: <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 61 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 45 foggy;
Regina 7 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 54 foggy; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 5 fair.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901214-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-14-90 0604EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-14 0369</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Across South; Snow in Northern Tier</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain fell across the <LOCATION>South</LOCATION> <DATE>early today</DATE>, and a cold winterlike
blast with some snow hit the northern <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   Much of the nation was under cloudy skies. Temperatures early
today along the lower <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> seaboard and <LOCATION>Gulf</LOCATION> coast were in the
60s.
   Rain fell along the mid-Mississippi valley, central <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and
the <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> coast.
   Temperatures dipped into the high teens and low 20s from
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, across the <LOCATION>Great Plains</LOCATION> and into <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> state.
   Snow fell in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>,
as well as in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. Up to a foot of snow was likely in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s northern <LOCATION>Sierra Nevada</LOCATION>.
   Light snow mixed with ice was expected in parts of the <LOCATION>northern
Plains</LOCATION>. Snow was likely in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>.
   Rain fell in <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> early today, and a cold front moving in from
the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> was expected to bring heavy snow later in the day to
the mountains of <ORGANIZATION>Oregon</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>.
   The nation's high on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> was 84 degrees at <LOCATION>Alice</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kingsville</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>McAllen</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>5 a.m. EST</TIME>:
   -<LOCATION>East</LOCATION>: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 19 fair; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 56 foggy; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 28 windy;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 20 fair; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, 58 cloudy; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 44 rain;
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 28 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 31 cloudy; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 22 fair;
Hatteras 52 rain; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 48 foggy; Key West 68 fair;
<LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 43 rain; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 59 cloudy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 61 fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 34
fair; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 34 fair; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 27 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, 23
fair; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 51 fair; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, 38 partly cloudy.
   -Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 49 foggy; <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> 16 fair; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 31
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 26 foggy; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 26 cloudy; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 45
cloudy; <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 26 fair; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 33 cloudy; Little Rock 42
cloudy; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 32 fair; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 43 cloudy; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 41 cloudy;
<LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 60 foggy; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 29 cloudy; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 37
foggy; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 30 cloudy; Rapid City 27 cloudy; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 31 fair;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 19 cloudy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie 08</PERSON> fair; <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> 58 cloudy.
   -West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 44 cloudy; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 14 fair; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 08 fair;
Casper 26 cloudy; Fairbanks 06 snow; Great Falls 18 fair; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>
71 showers; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 42 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 51 hazy; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 28
foggy; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 33 cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 58 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 39 rain; Reno 21 fair; Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION> 28 cloudy; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 53
fair; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 47 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 38 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 26
cloudy.
   -International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 27 fair; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 10 fair; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 09
fair; Regina 01 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 12 fair; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 19 fair; <LOCATION>Merida</LOCATION> 66
fair; <LOCATION>Havana</LOCATION> 64; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 74 partly cloudy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901106-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-06-90 0520EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     11-06 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0419</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow, Rain in Midwest and Northeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A storm that dumped up to 10 inches of snow on <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Lower
Peninsula</LOCATION> headed out of the state today, leaving cloudy skies and
low temperatures.
   The tail of the storm produced flurries in the <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> area and
rain elsewhere in <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>.
   More snow - up to five inches - was forecast today across the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> into <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>.
   The Northeast looked for early rain, followed by mostly, sunny
windy weather. Mostly sunny skies were forecast for the far West,
<ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and Southeast.
   Winds of 60 mph and stronger were forecast through tonight in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Sierra Nevada</LOCATION>.
   Stormy weather is forecast through <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in the northwest
gulf of <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, with winds of 115 mph expected through the <LOCATION>Barren
Islands</LOCATION>.
   The high temperature for the nation <DATE>Monday</DATE> was 86 degrees at
<LOCATION>Fort Myers</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Naval Air Station</ORGANIZATION> near
<LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   Other reports:
   -<LOCATION>East</LOCATION>: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 49 rain; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 43 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 50 rain;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 46 showers; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 62 fair; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 46
cloudy; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 40 cloudy; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 39 cloudy; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 36
windy; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 64 foggy; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 65 fair; Key West 70 fair;
<LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 46 cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 45 fair; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 68 fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 63
foggy; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 40 drizzle; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 47 rain; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 57
fair; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 73 cloudy; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 58 fair.
   -Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 45 cloudy; <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> 18 fair; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 35
fair; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 32 snow; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 36 cloudy; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 48 fair;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 38 cloudy; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 39 partly cloudy; Little Rock
37 fair; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 43 cloudy; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 38 fair; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 45
cloudy; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 47 fair; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 32 snow; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 44
fair; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 39 cloudy; Rapid City 27 snow; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 36 fair;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 28 fair; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie 29</PERSON> snow; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>
42 fair.
   -West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 42 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 25 snow; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 32 fair;
Casper 20 snow; Fairbanks 22 cloudy; Great Falls 13 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 77 fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 58 foggy; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION>
36 fair; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 38 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 58 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 40 cloudy; Reno 37 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 33 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 61 cloudy; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 44
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 30 fair.
   -International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 18 fair; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 43 rain; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 39
rain; Regina 05 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 43 rain; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 14 fair; <LOCATION>Nassau 79</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 76 partly cloudy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900428-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-28-90 0607EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     04-28 0605</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0624</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Floodwaters in north-central <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> were receding early today,
while the northwestern tier got snow and rain dampened parts of the
<LOCATION>South</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>.
   Tornadoes spawned by thunderstorms touched down <DATE>Friday</DATE> near
<LOCATION>Magee</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>, and near the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> towns of <LOCATION>Waco</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Coolidge</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Groesbeck</LOCATION>
and <PERSON>Hearne</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said.
   At least 200 homes in the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> community of Horseshoe Bend,
which is ringed by the rain-swollen <LOCATION>Brazos River</LOCATION>, remained under
water <DATE>Friday</DATE>, authorities said.
   Water stood 4 feet deep in the streets of <LOCATION>Brownwood</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>,
receding slowly. Lake <LOCATION>Brownwood</LOCATION> couldn't handle 16 inches of rain
since <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, authorities said.
   ``It's going to be a long-term thing, two or three weeks minimum
before businesses are back in operation,'' <LOCATION>Brownwood</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Bert
Massey</PERSON> said.
   ``It's the worst disaster to ever hit <LOCATION>Brownwood</LOCATION>. We're talking
about millions upon <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in damages in the business
district alone,'' he said.
   Hail also battered <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, including hailstones nearly an inch in
diameter southeast of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> and north of <LOCATION>Kerens</LOCATION>. Hail the size of
golf balls fell on <LOCATION>Hillsboro</LOCATION> and several other <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> cities.
   Rain early today fell in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, Little
Rock, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash</LOCATION>.
   Rapid City got snow.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> posted a winter storm warning for
<DATE>today</DATE> over the western mountains of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>. Snow advisories were
posted today elsewhere in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and parts of <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
state, <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>.
   Unseasonably cold temperatures, with snow in higher elevations,
were predicted today for the northern <ORGANIZATION>Sierra Nevada</ORGANIZATION> region and the
northern mountains of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   Utah could receive a foot of snow in higher mountains by <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME>.
   High temperatures <DATE>Friday</DATE> from the northern <LOCATION>Atlantic Coast</LOCATION> to the
upper Great Lakes were milder than usual. The weather service said
more than 36 high temperature records for the date were broken or
tied.
   The new temperature records include a high of 86 degrees in
<LOCATION>Bridgeport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, 89 degrees in <LOCATION>Cape Hatteras</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, and 92
degrees in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>.
   The high <DATE>Friday</DATE> in the Lower 48 states was 105 degrees in
<LOCATION>Borrego Springs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 67 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 76 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 69 fair; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 70
cloudy; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 67 cloudy; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 70 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>
64 fair; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 66 fair; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 69 partly cloudy; Key West
77 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 69 cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 67 cloudy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 74
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 61 fair; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 64 hazy; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>
68 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 57 fair; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 69 hazy; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 72
cloudy; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 71 fair.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 64 showers; <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> 22 fair; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 46
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 43 rain; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 52 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 66 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 46 cloudy; Little Rock
58 rain; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 71 cloudy; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 62 cloudy; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 69
rain; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 66 fair; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 33 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Oklahoma
City</LOCATION> 53 fair; Rapid City 31 snow; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 61 rain;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 50 cloudy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie 58</PERSON> fair; <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> 62 fair.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 55 fair; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 50 rain; Casper 39 cloudy;
Fairbanks 39 fair; Great Falls 40 showers; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 74 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 81 windy; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 60 foggy; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 55 rain;
<LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 42 windy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 79 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 44 partly
cloudy; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> 63 cloudy; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 57 cloudy; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 62
cloudy; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 41 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 37
rain.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 30 snow; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 61 fair; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 64
fair; Regina 23 cloudy; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 63 fair; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 28 snow; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>
75 fair.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900402-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-02-90 0521EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     04-02 0430</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0441</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thunderstorms Produce Hail in South, Skies Dry in West</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Thunderstorms produced hail and high winds in the South, and
skies were dry most everywhere west of the Rockies.
   Storms were severe <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in portions of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Hail the size of golf balls fell in <LOCATION>Andrews</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Highland
Home</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>; Wheeling, <LOCATION>W.Va.</LOCATION>, and De <PERSON>Kalb</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Miss</LOCATION>. High winds downed
trees and power lines in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>.
   Winds gusted to 58 mph in <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION> and a trailer home was
overturned near <LOCATION>Ansley</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, was whipped by
gusts of 78 mph.
   The weather service said thunderstorms spawned a tornado near
<LOCATION>Winters</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> also received thunderstorms.
   Light rain and drizzle fell over <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> state and <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>.
Light rain ahead of a cold front extended from <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> to upper
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>.
   Showers were scattered over <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Aouthern California</LOCATION>. Dry
weather prevailed elsewhere in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>, with fair skies over much
of the <LOCATION>Central Plains</LOCATION>.
   The high <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in the Lower 48 states was 89 degrees in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 43 drizzle; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 38
cloudy; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 64 foggy; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 54 fair; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>
54 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 43 fair; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 45 foggy; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 53
drizzle; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 67 cloudy; Key West 70 fair; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 55
fair; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 59 foggy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 72 fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 43 rain; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>
44 cloudy; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 45 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 39 drizzle; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>
52 foggy; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 67 fair; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 50 drizzle.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 49 foggy; <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> 27 fair; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 41
cloudy; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 42 fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 35 windy; <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 47 windy;
<LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 41 fair; Little Rock 62 foggy; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 51 fair;
<LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 55 fair; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 67 foggy; <LOCATION>North
Platte</LOCATION> 34 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 55 windy; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 35 fair; Rapid City
35 fair; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 47 fair; Minneapolis-St. Paul 33 windy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION>
Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 38 cloudy; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 63 foggy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 45 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 30 fair; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 53 fair;
Casper 36 fair; Fairbanks 31 fair; Great Falls 51 cloudy; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>
72 fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 60 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 55 fair; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 56 fair;
<LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 58 fair; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 63 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 52 cloudy; Reno
55 fair; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 51 fair; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 58 cloudy; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>
50 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 49 cloudy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 48 fair.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 46 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 41 rain;
<LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 37 cloudy; Regina 32 fair; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 39 showery; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 23
fair; <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> 66 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Acapulco</LOCATION> 81 fair.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900529-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-29-90 0624EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     05-29 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Falls in East, Plains</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain fell in the eastern half of the nation and in the <LOCATION>Upper
Plains</LOCATION> <DATE>early today</DATE>, flooding portions of <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
   Rain and showers extended from <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, and from <LOCATION>Casper</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash</LOCATION>. Thunderstorms looped
down from <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> coast and up to <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, wet, stormy weather advanced across the southeastern
quarter of the nation, spinning off at least four tornados.
Lightning killed one person in <LOCATION>Galveston Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Heavy rain overnight flooded parts of eastern and south-central
<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, leaving many roads impassable.
   Floodwaters up to 6 feet deep swamped <LOCATION>Murray City</LOCATION>, forcing the
evacuation of at least 50 residents, authorities said. The flooding
shoved one building off its foundations, caved in a hillside and
swept equipment out of a firehouse.
   ``The streets are a mess. In <DATE>1968</DATE> we had a flood, but it was
nothing like this,'' said firefighter <PERSON>Bob Koon</PERSON>. ``We got the trucks
out, but a lot of the other stuff is gone.''
   Tornadoes touched down near <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, southeast of <LOCATION>Houma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>La.</LOCATION>,
and west of <LOCATION>Huntington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>W.Va</LOCATION>.
   At <LOCATION>Morehead</LOCATION> in eastern <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, a twister overturned several
light aircraft and a small hangar at <LOCATION>Morehead-Rowan County Airport</LOCATION>
and apparently carried off two other planes, state police said. It
also downed power lines, destroyed a small office and damaged two
houses. No injuries were reported.
   Hail fell at Maiden, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Midway</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>W.Va.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Baldwin</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, and
<LOCATION>North Knoxville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn</LOCATION>.
   Today's forecast called for rain in <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>
and across the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION>. Storms were expected in <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>,
northern <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, northern <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and along the coasts of <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>.
   A high of 73 in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, broke the town's Memorial Day record
of 70 degrees that had stood for 27 years.
   The nation's high was 99 at <LOCATION>Beeville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 60 cloudy; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 63 fair; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 53 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 61 rain; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 73 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 62 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 59 rain; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 55
rain; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 59 cloudy; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 71 showers; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 74 fair;
Key West 80 windy; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 60 cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 66 foggy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 77
fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 58 cloudy; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 58 rain; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 54
foggy; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 49 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 55 rain; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 77
fair; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 53 rain.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 59 fair; Bismarck 56 fair; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 53 fair;
<LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 60 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 55 fair; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 68 fair;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 56 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 60 fair; Little Rock 63
foggy; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 61 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 58
fair; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 72 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 58 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 66 fair; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 55 fair; Rapid City 58 cloudy; <LOCATION>St.
Louis</LOCATION> 58 fair; Minneapolis-St. Paul 57 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste.
<PERSON>Marie 44</PERSON> fair; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 76 partly cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 67 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 55 windy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 57
showers; Casper 54 rain; Fairbanks 72 partly cloudy; Great Falls 57
cloudy; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 76 fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 57 fair;
<LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 54 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 55 cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 62 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 57 cloudy; Reno 53 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 52
showers; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 60 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 55 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 53 windy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 57 rain.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 54 cloudy; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 50 cloudy; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 46
cloudy; Regina 59 windy; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 59 rain; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 50 fair.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900521-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-21-90 0533EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     05-21 0499</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storms From Texas to North Carolina, Rain in Northeast and West</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain drenched much of the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION> today, and thunderstorms cut
a swath through the South.
   Today's forecast called for showers in the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>. A
band of thunderstorms was expected to stretch from central <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
through <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>.
   Rain fell early today from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>,
and west to <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>. Forecasters said parts of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> also could expect rain.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> issued severe thunderstorm warnings
overnight for parts of <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, thunderstorms rattled through parts of <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>,
   In <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, trees downed by high winds damaged homes in <LOCATION>Lamar</LOCATION>
and <PERSON>Walker</PERSON> counties, and near <LOCATION>Tuscumbia</LOCATION>. Storm winds also downed
power lines and damaged cars around <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION>. Winds gusted to 58
mph at Argo.
   In <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, storms felled trees and power lines near <LOCATION>Alpharetta</LOCATION>,
Cumming and <LOCATION>Gainesville</LOCATION>. Winds also downed trees at <LOCATION>Westminster</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>
   In <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, hail pounded <LOCATION>Clarksdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Grenada Lake</LOCATION> and
<PERSON>Greenwood</PERSON>, and winds gusted to 65 mph in <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION> and downed trees
and power lines in <LOCATION>Warren County</LOCATION>. Storms in central <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>
produced dime-size hail at <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, a tornado tore through two trailer parks on the
edge of <LOCATION>Rogersville</LOCATION>, 12 miles east of <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION>, injuring up to
10 people. In southeastern <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, storms spawned a tornado at
<LOCATION>Cheyenne</LOCATION>.
   The high temperature for the nation was 109 degrees at <LOCATION>Laredo</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 46 rain; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 66 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 45 rain;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 46 rain; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 76 fair; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 65 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 62 cloudy; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 48 drizzle; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 49 cloudy;
Hatteras 73 fair; Key West 80 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 65 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 66 rain; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 78 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 49 showers;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 53 rain; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 63 cloudy; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 45
rain; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 71 foggy; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 66 rain.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 64 cloudy; Bismarck 49 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 52 cloudy; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 52 fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 50 drizzle; <LOCATION>Fort
Worth</LOCATION> 78 fair; <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 54 cloudy; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 53 partly
cloudy; Little Rock 70 cloudy; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 66 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>
70 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 65 cloudy; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 78 cloudy; <LOCATION>North
Platte</LOCATION> 45 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 70 windy; <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 52 cloudy; Rapid City
49 fair; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 59 partly cloudy; Minneapolis-St. Paul 48 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie 44</PERSON> fair; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> 74 fair.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 48 showers; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 55
cloudy; Casper 44 fair; Fairbanks 56 partly cloudy; Great Falls 41
fair; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 74 fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 72 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 59 fair;
<LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 51 cloudy; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 51 cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 77 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 50 showers; Reno 52 fair; Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION> 52 fair; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 62
fair; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 57 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 48 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 47 cloudy.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 46 rain; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 45 rain; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 45
windy; Regina 50 cloudy; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 46 cloudy; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 55 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> 64 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 77 fair.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901010-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-10-90 0556EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     10-10 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drizzle in the Northeast; Showers in Florida</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The Northeast received drizzle and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> had showers early
today. Tenperatures dipped below freezing in the <LOCATION>central Plains</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>.
   Unseasonably warm weather was again predicted for the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>, with
highs in the 70s and 80s. Several Eastern cities set records for
the date <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, including <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, and
<LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>
   Rain was expected from <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION> region and
up into <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>. A tropical disturbance from the <LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION>
was expected to bring showers to the Southeast.
   Sunshine was forecast for the <LOCATION>Middle Atlantic</LOCATION> states and clear
skies were expcted from the <LOCATION>Plains</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> with only
<LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> looking for showers.
   Flurries were possible in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, where temperatures were
expected to reach only the 40s. The <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> was expecting highs in
the 50s and 60s, and most of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> was looking for temperatures
in the 80s and 90s.
   The high temperature for the nation <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was 99 degrees at
<LOCATION>Monrovia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>5 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   -<LOCATION>East</LOCATION>: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 47 cloudy; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 67 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>
67 fair; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 47 rain; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, 78 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 67 fair; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 55 foggy;
<LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 47 rain; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 76 fair; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 73 showers; Key
West 81 windy; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 67 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 68 partly cloudy;
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 80 windy; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 66 fair; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>
63 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, 55 drizzle; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 75
rain; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, 70 fair.
   -Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 69 cloudy; <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> 42 fair; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 47
showers; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 39 fair; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 40 cloudy; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 44 fair;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 52 rain; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 35 fair; Little Rock 48 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 59 drizzle; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 49 cloudy; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 55 cloudy; <LOCATION>New
Orleans</LOCATION> 59 showers; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 34 fair; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 38 fair;
<LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 28 foggy; Rapid City 35 fair; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 44 rain;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 31 fair; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie</PERSON> 39 cloudy; <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> 47 fair.
   -West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 44 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 36 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 54 partly
cloudy; Casper 43 fair; Fairbanks 30 fair; Great Falls 55 windy;
<LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 77 fair; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 71 fair; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION>
47 fair; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 55 cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 72 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 53
partly cloudy; <PERSON>Reno</PERSON> 41 fair; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 40 fair; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 64
fair; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 60 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 49 cloudy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 49 cloudy.
   -International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 37 windy; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 41 rain; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 41
rain; Regina 50 cloudy; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 43 rain; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION> 39 windy; <LOCATION>Merida</LOCATION>
73 fair; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 77 fair.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900602-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-02-90 0630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     06-02 0417</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wind and Rain Prevail in West, Plains</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Wind and rain prevailed early today in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Plains</LOCATION>.
Fair weather blessed parts of the Southeast and <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state received rain
early today. Thunderstorms were predicted for <DATE>later today</DATE> in a band
from <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> through the central <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and south to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Summer-like sun and mild temperatures were expected to continue
today in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>, followed by rain later in the week.
   Severe thunderstorms spawned about 10 tornadoes from <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Late <DATE>spring</DATE> snow fell in the <LOCATION>Rockies</LOCATION> and hail
battered <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Dallas-Fort Worth</LOCATION> area was whipped by winds of up to 60 mph
and drenched by 2 inches of rain in about 20 minutes, the <ORGANIZATION>National
Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Caribou, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, tied a high temperature record for the date
<DATE>Friday</DATE> with a reading of 82 degrees.
   Other reports at <TIME>3 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 68 showers; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 62 fair;
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 74 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 68
cloudy; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 70 hazy; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 67 cloudy; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 69 hazy;
Hatteras 68 fair; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 68 foggy; Key West 81 fair; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION>
62 foggy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 71 cloudy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 80 fair; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 63 fair;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 63 fair; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 64 fair; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> 59 partly
cloudy; <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> 67 hazy; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> 75 fair; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 66 fair.
   _Central: <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> 72 cloudy; Bismarck 54 rain; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 76
fair; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 49 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION> 69 fair; <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> 80
cloudy; <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> 72 hazy; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 71 windy; Little Rock 76
fair; <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> 71 hazy; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> 74 fair; <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> 71 cloudy; <LOCATION>New
Orleans</LOCATION> 79 fair; <LOCATION>North Platte</LOCATION> 53 windy; <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> 72 windy;
<LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> 71 windy; Rapid City 52 windy; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> 73 partly cloudy;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 75 cloudy; <LOCATION>Sault</LOCATION> Ste. <PERSON>Marie 54</PERSON> fair; <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION> 82 partly cloudy.
   _West: <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> 59 fair; <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> 54 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> 49 partly
cloudy; Casper 38 partly cloudy; Fairbanks 66 showers; Great Falls
46 windy; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> 76 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> 65 fair; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>
61 fair; <LOCATION>Medford</LOCATION> 51 cloudy; <LOCATION>Pendleton</LOCATION> 53 cloudy; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> 80 fair;
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 56 rain; Reno 56 cloudy; <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> 48 fair; <LOCATION>San
Diego</LOCATION> 62 fair; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 56 fair; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 51 cloudy; <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> 47
rain.
   _International: <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION> 46 showers; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> 55 fair; <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> 57
partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Regina</LOCATION> 59 showers; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> 61 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION>
59 rain; <LOCATION>Merida</LOCATION> 79 fair; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> 79 showers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900409-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-09-90 0627EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     04-09 0413</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold in East, Rockies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Northwest winds continued to bring partly cloudy skies and
colder temperatures to much of the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE>. Cold also prevailed
in the <LOCATION>Rockies</LOCATION>, and snow fell in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
   Freezing temperatures were reported this morning in northern <LOCATION>New
England</LOCATION> and northern <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> state. Temperatures in the 30s were
reported as far south as the <LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>. Rain fell in
parts of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Elsewhere, showers dampened <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, as much as a foot of snow fell in the mountains of
<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   Thunderstorms produced golf ball-size hail and wind gusts to
near 60 mph in southern <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. Several parked planes turned over
at <LOCATION>Tamiami Airport</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.
   Thunderstorms also dropped small hail at <LOCATION>Rock Springs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo</LOCATION>. Rain
and thundershowers, with snow in the mountains, also fell in parts
of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>.
   The high temperature for the Lower 48 states <DATE>Sunday</DATE> was 90
degrees at <LOCATION>Lajitas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Other reports at <TIME>5 a.m. EDT</TIME>:
   _East: <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 26 fair; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> 49 cloudy; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> 37 fair;
<LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION> 47 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION> 44 cloudy;
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 39 fair; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 41 fair; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> 46 fair; <LOCATION>Hatteras</LOCATION> 38
fair; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION> 60 partly cloudy; Key West 74 fair; <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION> 37
cloudy; <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION> 48 partly cloudy; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 71 rain; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 37 fair;
