<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891023-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-23-89 2216EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--RecordReviews Adv00   10-23 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Record Reviews, Adv 00,0474</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Anytime</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>In the Groove: Record Reviews</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   The Uptown String Quartet (<ORGANIZATION>Philips</ORGANIZATION>) _ <PERSON>Diane Monroe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lesa
Terry</PERSON>, violins; <PERSON>Maxine Roach</PERSON>, viola; <PERSON>Eileen M. Folson</PERSON>, Cello.
   
   A listener needs a change now and again, and this disc from the
Uptown String Quartet is spring cleaning for jaded ears.
   The name gives a clue _ a marriage of the string quartet with
the sounds from far uptown, beyond 110th Street in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. A big
shot of jazz, a little rag, a little blues, a lot of Polish.
   Listen to ``Midnight Child'' and it's evident why the mix is so
convincing. The virtuoso note-bending of the blues and gospel
singers was born for the violin. So, too, were the strutting
rhythms of ``Calvary,'' and doggone if <PERSON>Scott Joplin</PERSON> didn't have
strings in mind when he wrote ``Easy Winners.''
   It helps, too, that the four players are demon fiddlers, whose
various experiences include the <LOCATION>Philadelphia Orchestra</LOCATION>,
``Dreamgirls,'' the <LOCATION>New York Philharmonic</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Frank Sinatra</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sammy
Davis Jr.</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Wynton Marsalis</LOCATION> and producer <PERSON>Max Roach</PERSON>'s Double Quartet.
   Yes, it may seem a little strange, but this is no <ORGANIZATION>Beethoven</ORGANIZATION>'s
Ninth for massed accordion band kind of stunt. Each of a dozen cuts
is perfectly idiomatic, fresh, piquant, just right.
   The Uptown String Quartet threatens to give crossover recordings
a good name.
   _ By <PERSON>Robert Barr</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press Writer</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   The Uptown String Quartet (<ORGANIZATION>Philips</ORGANIZATION>) _ <PERSON>Diane Monroe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lesa
Terry</PERSON>, violins; <PERSON>Maxine Roach</PERSON>, viola; <PERSON>Eileen M. Folson</PERSON>, Cello.
   
   A listener needs a change now and again, and this disc from the
Uptown String Quartet is spring cleaning for jaded ears.
   The name gives a clue _ a marriage of the string quartet with
the sounds from far uptown, beyond 110th Street in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. A big
shot of jazz, a little rag, a little blues, a lot of Polish.
   Listen to ``Midnight Child'' and it's evident why the mix is so
convincing. The virtuoso note-bending of the blues and gospel
singers was born for the violin. So, too, were the strutting
rhythms of ``Calvary,'' and doggone if <PERSON>Scott Joplin</PERSON> didn't have
strings in mind when he wrote ``Easy Winners.''
   It helps, too, that the four players are demon fiddlers, whose
various experiences include the <LOCATION>Philadelphia Orchestra</LOCATION>,
``Dreamgirls,'' the <LOCATION>New York Philharmonic</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Frank Sinatra</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sammy
Davis Jr.</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Wynton Marsalis</LOCATION> and producer <PERSON>Max Roach</PERSON>'s Double Quartet.
   Yes, it may seem a little strange, but this is no <ORGANIZATION>Beethoven</ORGANIZATION>'s
Ninth for massed accordion band kind of stunt. Each of a dozen cuts
is perfectly idiomatic, fresh, piquant, just right.
   The Uptown String Quartet threatens to give crossover recordings
a good name.
   _ By <PERSON>Robert Barr</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press Writer</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891027-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-27-89 0812EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--RecordReviews Adv00-1stLd-Writethru b0882 10-27
0471</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Record Reviews, Adv 00 - 1st Ld-Writethru, b0882,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Anytime</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, The name ..., to correct typo, changing Polish
to polish.</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>In the Groove: Record Reviews</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   The Uptown String Quartet (<ORGANIZATION>Philips</ORGANIZATION>) _ <PERSON>Diane Monroe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lesa
Terry</PERSON>, violins; <PERSON>Maxine Roach</PERSON>, viola; <PERSON>Eileen M. Folson</PERSON>, Cello.
   
   A listener needs a change now and again, and this disc from the
Uptown String Quartet is spring cleaning for jaded ears.
   The name gives a clue _ a marriage of the string quartet with
the sounds from far uptown, beyond 110th Street in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. A big
shot of jazz, a little rag, a little blues, a lot of polish.
   Listen to ``Midnight Child'' and it's evident why the mix is so
convincing. The virtuoso note-bending of the blues and gospel
singers was born for the violin. So, too, were the strutting
rhythms of ``Calvary,'' and doggone if <PERSON>Scott Joplin</PERSON> didn't have
strings in mind when he wrote ``Easy Winners.''
   It helps, too, that the four players are demon fiddlers, whose
various experiences include the <LOCATION>Philadelphia Orchestra</LOCATION>,
``Dreamgirls,'' the <LOCATION>New York Philharmonic</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Frank Sinatra</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sammy
Davis Jr.</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Wynton Marsalis</LOCATION> and producer <PERSON>Max Roach</PERSON>'s Double Quartet.
   Yes, it may seem a little strange, but this is no <ORGANIZATION>Beethoven</ORGANIZATION>'s
Ninth for massed accordion band kind of stunt. Each of a dozen cuts
is perfectly idiomatic, fresh, piquant, just right.
   The Uptown String Quartet threatens to give crossover recordings
a good name.
   _ By <PERSON>Robert Barr</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press Writer</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   The Uptown String Quartet (<ORGANIZATION>Philips</ORGANIZATION>) _ <PERSON>Diane Monroe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lesa
Terry</PERSON>, violins; <PERSON>Maxine Roach</PERSON>, viola; <PERSON>Eileen M. Folson</PERSON>, Cello.
   
   A listener needs a change now and again, and this disc from the
Uptown String Quartet is spring cleaning for jaded ears.
   The name gives a clue _ a marriage of the string quartet with
the sounds from far uptown, beyond 110th Street in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. A big
shot of jazz, a little rag, a little blues, a lot of polish.
   Listen to ``Midnight Child'' and it's evident why the mix is so
convincing. The virtuoso note-bending of the blues and gospel
singers was born for the violin. So, too, were the strutting
rhythms of ``Calvary,'' and doggone if <PERSON>Scott Joplin</PERSON> didn't have
strings in mind when he wrote ``Easy Winners.''
   It helps, too, that the four players are demon fiddlers, whose
various experiences include the <LOCATION>Philadelphia Orchestra</LOCATION>,
``Dreamgirls,'' the <LOCATION>New York Philharmonic</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Frank Sinatra</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sammy
Davis Jr.</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Wynton Marsalis</LOCATION> and producer <PERSON>Max Roach</PERSON>'s Double Quartet.
   Yes, it may seem a little strange, but this is no <ORGANIZATION>Beethoven</ORGANIZATION>'s
Ninth for massed accordion band kind of stunt. Each of a dozen cuts
is perfectly idiomatic, fresh, piquant, just right.
   The Uptown String Quartet threatens to give crossover recordings
a good name.
   _ By <PERSON>Robert Barr</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press Writer</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06194158 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06194158 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; Photo: Judas Priest will be among the five heavy-metal acts at
Shoreline Sunday.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; SHOW; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THERE'S an invasion coming. It's big, it's bad, it's noisy, it packs some
awesome firepower, and if you get in its way it will roll over you like an M-1
tank.;    No. It isn't Desert Storm, The Sequel.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ROCK SLIDE
HEAP-O'-METAL TOUR WILL HAVE SONY ROLLING
IN HEAPS OF CASH  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  MUSIC
(box) Alice Cooper: still shocking, Page 22  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     It's <ORGANIZATION>Operation Rock &amp; Roll</ORGANIZATION>. And in its way, it's just as scary.;    Think
of it. Five head-banging acts -- <PERSON>Judas Priest</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alice Cooper</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Motorhead</ORGANIZATION>,
Dangerous Toys and <ORGANIZATION>Metal Church</ORGANIZATION> -- all on the same stage going leather-bent
for hell in a heavy-metal basket, all at <ORGANIZATION>Shoreline Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, all on
Sunday.;    Awwwwwwright! Rocknnnnnnnrollllll! Getdowwwwwwn! Boooooogie!;   
There.;    Now that we've gotten that off our chest, we can get on with the
business at hand. Which is, oddly enough, the business of rock 'n' roll, which
is the basis of <ORGANIZATION>Operation Rock &amp; Roll.</ORGANIZATION>;    You thought this was an inspired
match made in metal heaven? Think again.;    <ORGANIZATION>Operation Rock &amp; Roll</ORGANIZATION> might be a
fan's delight -- six hours of metal madness. But it is also a part of the new
trend to market tours  like a <ORGANIZATION>Kellogg's Variety Pack</ORGANIZATION>. No more of those one-act
"An Evening With . . ." numbers. It's safety -- and ticket sales -- in
numbers, with groups being loaded onto tours to draw as many fans as
possible.;    In the case of the other tours such as the recent Gathering of
the Tribes and the upcoming <LOCATION>Lollapalooza</LOCATION> and Gang of Four/Public Enemy/Sisters
of Mercy/Warrior Soul slugfest, there has been an attempt to contribute to a
new openness in the music scene with an eclectic assortment of acts.;    But
not with <ORGANIZATION>Operation Rock &amp; Roll</ORGANIZATION>. It is strictly business. Pocket-calculator
time.;    All of the acts on this tour are allied in their affiliation with
the <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> and Epic records labels (which are part of <ORGANIZATION>Sony Music</ORGANIZATION>). They
don't hang out at the local bar, swigging brewskies and clanging chords. Their
people got together with the <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> people and all of them decided that it was
time to cash in. (Ticket sales to the event are sluggish, tour sources say.); 
  And how will they cash in? Let us count the ways.;    For starters, there's
the "promotion-only" Operation Rock &amp; Roll audio cassette which comes with
songs by the five participating groups. A quarter-million of these have been
printed up for the tour to be used as giveaways in conjunction with local
shows. The first few thousand fans who get to each venue will also get free
copies. Nice, eh? Yes, but the cassette also comes with songs by other
<ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> and Epic acts, including <LOCATION>Fishbone</LOCATION>, War Babies and Cycle Sluts From
Hell, all the better to promote their records.;    Then there is the <ORGANIZATION>Operation
Rock &amp; Roll</ORGANIZATION> edition of <ORGANIZATION>MJI Broadcasting</ORGANIZATION>'s syndicated "Metalshop" program,
which was aired <DATE>July 4</DATE>. It came with interviews with the tour's groups and
selections of their music.;    Then there is the new "Operation Rock &amp; Roll"
video (<ORGANIZATION>Sony Music</ORGANIZATION>) that was released <DATE>July 2</DATE>, just in time for start of the
tour <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION>. It comes with videos by the groups of the
tour, for <MONEY>$19.95</MONEY>.;    Have we forgotten anything?;  Yes, there is music
involved in all of this. And -- given its metal base -- some of it might be
quite good. With its legal problems of <DATE>1990</DATE> resolved -- remember the <ORGANIZATION>Reno</ORGANIZATION> case
in which the group was exonerated of charges that its lyrics prompted a
suicide? -- Judas Priest seems to be alive and kicking.;    The same could be
said of the lovely and talented <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>. <PERSON>Mr. Cooper</PERSON>, to you, baffled critics and
fans and common sense by going platinum with his <DATE>1989</DATE> album, "Trash." It was a
real comeback -- professionally and musically -- with a Gothic rock sound that
was the equal of his classics. He should pull out all the props for this
tour.;    <ORGANIZATION>Motorhead</ORGANIZATION> is Motorhead. If I have to explain that to you, you
probably wouldn't understand anyway. For a decade and much more, this band has
made metal that is an unalloyed pleasure, untarnished by such trivial matters
as good taste and listenability.;    Mixing business and pleasure;  <ORGANIZATION>Metal
Church</ORGANIZATION> and Dangerous Toys haven't got the Big Names -- or the fanciful names
-- of their tour counterparts, but they might be interesting opening acts.;   
All of which makes the business side of this tour all the more annoying.
Operation <ORGANIZATION>Rock &amp; Roll</ORGANIZATION> could be fun and a real deal for the fans. But all the
marketing and promotional tie-ins prove that metal has become as much a
business as a pleasure.;     <ORGANIZATION>Operation Rock &amp; Roll</ORGANIZATION>; When: <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>;
Where: Shoreline Amphitheater, One Amphitheater Parkway, Mountain View;
Tickets: <MONEY>$22.50</MONEY>/<MONEY>$18.50</MONEY>, (408) 998-2277 or (415) 762-2277.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  HARRY SUMRALL, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910712  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  21  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  801  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday July 12, 1991
00194158,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06194090 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06194090 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFILE; MUSIC; PROFESSIONAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  LET'S get to the most important question first: Is there a snake in Alice
Cooper's new act?;    "We do have a new snake for this tour," says Alice,
laughing. "We call him Salt Lake Sidney. He's a Mormon snake. He doesn't drink
coffee and he doesn't work on Sundays."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SCHOOL'S OUT, AND HERE COMES ALICE COOPER  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  MUSIC  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Cooper, 43, is calling from <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION>, where Operation Rock &amp; Roll
played this week (the show touches down here at <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Shoreline
Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>). That explains the snake's name, he says.;    Fans will walk out
changed;    <PERSON>Sidney</PERSON>, it seems, is part of what the all-time master of
theatrical rock describes as "a real <PERSON>Alice Cooper</PERSON> show. We've got a set of our
own, very high-tech, with loads of real oooooo-ahhhh effects. At one point in
the act, we take fans from the crowd and put them on a <LOCATION>Frankenstein</LOCATION> table and
we lift it to the ceiling and when they come out, they're (pause) different.";
   In what way, <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>?;    "I really don't want to give anything away," he
says with another laugh. For such a gothic kind of guy, <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> is downright
upbeat.;    Keep in mind, we are talking about <PERSON>Alice Cooper</PERSON>, he of the
guillotine and black eye makeup and coiling snakes; the man who, in the '70s,
put the shock into rock. Along the way, he recorded a rock classic or two --
"I'm 18," "School's Out" -- and had a comeback platinum record, <DATE>1989</DATE>'s
"Trash.";    What sort of rock fans come to see <PERSON>Alice Cooper</PERSON>, these days?
Young, old or what?;    "I think the older ones come but they mostly sit in
the back. When I look at the crowd from the stage, the ones in the front are
usually about 15. You know, the ones with tattoos and no teeth.";    He's
laughing again.;    It's all about hits;    How has he been able to do it lo
these many years? Alice lowers his voice and gets down to business:;    "It's
about hits. 'I'm 18' is one of those songs that anyone can relate to. The
angst lives on. Theatrics without hits is novelty and that would get boring
after a while. But if you have the theatrics and the hits, that makes a show
with meaning. When we get the effects going and play the hits, we get 10,000
people going 'Oh, wow!' ";    To <PERSON>Alice Cooper</PERSON>, that's no laughing matter.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  HARRY SUMRALL, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910712  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  22  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  399  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday July 12, 1991
00194090,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06025208 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06025208 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Hurt and Farrow: Stuck in an upper-class rut (color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MOVIE; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  LIKE her namesake in Wonderland, Woody Allen's Alice finds things becoming
curiouser and curiouser as she tumbles through her own mixed-up life. Unlike
Lewis Carroll's wanderer, Allen's heroine, played by Mia Farrow in the
souffle-airy "Alice," is fully grown and all too willing to play the
proverbial babe in the woods.;    Indeed, her friends refer to her (behind her
back) as "Miss Mouse . . . so trusting."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Weekend  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MIA IN WOODYLAND: MAGIC AND MIRACLES
ALLEN ABANDONS HIS USUAL ANGST FOR A SLIGHT,
SWEET FAIRY TALE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Film Review
See also related story on this page.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     That <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>'s heroine eventually sorts things out -- learns who's
dependable, who's not; what's up, what's down -- is more the result of luck,
coincidence and old-hat legerdemain than any real resourcefulness on her
part.;    <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> is, for all intents and purposes, a surrogate for <ORGANIZATION>Allen</ORGANIZATION>'s
classic schlemiel. She even has that oh-so-; For page 7E;    Woody habit of
whining when no one's listening.;    <ORGANIZATION>Farrow</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>, however, is in a
marvelous state of grace, where much befalls her but nothing does any real
harm. Alice is <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>'sFilm Review; dream-child or cockeyed optimist, someone
who can take the worst that life has to shell out without becoming jaded,
cynical.;    And life does throw <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> a few unexpected curves, including a
smug, philandering husband (<PERSON>William Hurt</PERSON>) and a pack of rich, devious
girlfriends (played by <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Judy Davis</PERSON>, among others).;    "I'm one of
those women who shop all day and have pedicures. I want to do more with my
life," <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> sort of complains.;    <ORGANIZATION>Alice</ORGANIZATION>'s salvation comes during one of her
regular visits to the beauty salon/health spa. That's where she learns about a
<LOCATION>Chinatown</LOCATION> acupuncturist/magician named <PERSON>Dr. Yang</PERSON> (the late <PERSON>Keye Luke</PERSON> of
"Gremlins"). Yang pronounces <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>'s chronic backache psychosomatic. He
prescribes hypnotism and an assortment of "special herbs." The hypnotism takes
her back to the start of her problems; the herbs have a more extreme effect,
causing her to become completely uninhibited and then -- shades of <PERSON>H.G. Wells</PERSON>!
-- invisible.;    The joke is that the timid-to-transparent <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> is at her
most vital and decisive as the Invisible Woman.;    It's while under another
of <ORGANIZATION>Yang</ORGANIZATION>'s spells that <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> approaches <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, a jazz musician whose daughter
attends the same kindergarten as <ORGANIZATION>Alice</ORGANIZATION>'s daughter. In this uptown fairy tale's
funniest bit, the usually skittish <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> seduces Joe with every conceivable
saxophone double-entendre. Joe, played by <PERSON>Joe Mantegna</PERSON> of "Godfather III," is
understandably amazed.;    So how are we to take all this? <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> tips us off
with his music, which ranges from <ORGANIZATION>Dixieland</ORGANIZATION> jazz to deliriously romantic
standards (such as "Moonlight Becomes You") to canned studio music. This is
<PERSON>Allen</PERSON> doing a schizoid Noel Coward/naughty satyr routine. Little wonder the
results run the gamut from silly to sardonic.;    Enchanting and almost
frivolous, "Alice" has the feel of <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> on sabbatical from the angst-ridden
types of "<DATE>September</DATE>," "Hannah and Her Sisters," "Another Woman" and, indeed,
the much-overrated "Crimes &amp; Misdemeanors." In tone, <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>'s latest most
closely matches "A <ORGANIZATION>Midsummer Night</ORGANIZATION>'s Sex Comedy" and the director's
contribution to "New York Stories." Like those works, this one is loosely
structured to the point of being haphazard, distracted. In spots, it feels
like <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> taking <PERSON>Dr. Yang</PERSON>'s advice to Alice -- doing whatever feels right at
the moment.;    <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>'s casting is certainly strange. Trading on his status as
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s most individualistic film maker -- the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> <PERSON>Ingmar Bergman</PERSON>, if
you will -- <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> has filled minor roles with such notables as <PERSON>Alec Baldwin</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Cybill Shepherd</PERSON>, <PERSON>Blythe Danner</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gwen Verdon</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bernadette Peters</PERSON>. Baldwin
appears as the ghost of an old beau; <ORGANIZATION>Shepherd</ORGANIZATION> is a suddenly disdainful friend
with a real career; <PERSON>Peters</PERSON> is <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>'s amusingly bossy muse.;    Talking of
muses, in some respects this is <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> forsaking his inner voice for the voices
of others -- among them, <PERSON>Dickens</PERSON>, <PERSON>Carroll</PERSON>, <PERSON>Preston Sturges</PERSON> and, for a Peter
Pan-inspired joyride over <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>J.M. Barrie.</LOCATION>;    The latter adventure is
the perfect metaphor for this lighter-than-air concoction, which attempts to
sneak up on serious matters about self-worth. The strategy doesn't always
work, as <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> scores his biggest laughs with his most obvious bits (about
bored homemakers and jaded <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> cabbies), but it does make for a pleasant
enough diversion, like a promenade along Fifth Avenue in the fall.;    More,
it gives <PERSON>Farrow</PERSON> her best screen role since "The Purple Rose of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>." <PERSON>Farrow</PERSON>,
who has never looked lovelier, really comes into her own with this one. Here
finally is the opportunity to show her true range as a comedian, a range that
encompasses screwball antics and a waif-like girlishness.;    <PERSON>Like Alice</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Farrow</PERSON> has been at a crossroads for some time. With her 11th feature with
<PERSON>Allen</PERSON>, the actress commits to a definite path and demonstrates a playful
sexuality that's darn-near irresistible.; <LOCATION>Alice</LOCATION>; (star)(star) 1/2; Rated:
PG-13 (slight profanity); Cast: <PERSON>Mia Farrow</PERSON>, <PERSON>William Hurt</PERSON>, <PERSON>Joe Mantegna</PERSON>;
Director-writer: <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  GLENN LOVELL, Mercury News Film Critic  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910125  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  817  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday January 25, 1991
00025208,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06086037 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06086037 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  DEAR ANN -- Last summer my mother-in-law, "Alice," was diagnosed with
Alzheimer's disease. If this dear lady had died, the entire community would
have grieved with us, but as it is, well-meaning friends, who know nothing
about Alzheimer's and happen to visit Alice on one of her good days, think we
are terrible people.;    We get calls asking why we haven't been to visit
Alice in several weeks when, in fact, we go to see her every day. She gets on
the phone and tells people she is in terrible pain and that we refuse to spend
money on a doctor to find out what is wrong. The truth is we have spent $8,000
on diagnostic tests and the results show that she is in excellent health. The
nursing home we have placed her in costs $3,100 a month.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  IGNORANCE INTENSIFIES PAIN OF ALZHEIMER'S  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Yesterday a friend of <ORGANIZATION>Alice</ORGANIZATION>'s phoned to plead that we take her "out of
there." She said, "The poor dear is so lonely and hates being in an
institution." I tried to explain that we cannot keep her at home because she
needs around-the-clock care. I didn't want to mention her urinating on the
floor, the need to change her bed linens four or five times a day, or the
times she has wandered outside totally unclothed.;    With the grief of
<PERSON>Alice</PERSON>'s illness and dealing daily with her problems, the added stress of these
"friends" is more than we can take. Do you have solutions for handling these
people?;    -- <LOCATION>C.H.</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION>;    DEAR <LOCATION>SPOKANE</LOCATION> -- It is difficult for those
who haven't had experience with Alzheimer's to understand the heartbreak. It
kills twice. First, the mind, then the body.;    You can get guidance on how
to deal with well-meaning but ignorant friends from the <ORGANIZATION>Alzheimer's
Association</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 5675-AL, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION> 60680-5675. You need a support
group and they will help you find it. Good luck.;    DEAR ANN -- My girlfriend
and I have a problem and I admit it's my fault. Molly (not her real name) has
slept with several other men, and most of them are from my hometown.;   
Whenever <PERSON>Molly</PERSON> and I attend a party, there is a good chance that at least one
of her former bed partners will be there. When this happens, I can think of
nothing but that guy in bed with her and my evening is wrecked.;    <PERSON>Molly</PERSON>
asks, "What's the matter?" When I tell her, she says I'm being juvenile and we
end up in a terrible argument. When we get intimate, I have a tough time
blocking out thoughts of the other guys and it ruins my mood.;    How can I
get rid of these thoughts that are wrecking our relationship?;    -- Matter
Over Mind in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>; DEAR MIND -- Too bad <PERSON>Molly</PERSON> broke one of the most
important rules of developing a new relationship: Never divulge the names and
numbers of previous players.;    Try a few sessions with a counselor. You may
then be able to accept <PERSON>Molly</PERSON> for what she is and forget the past. If this
doesn't work, tell her goodbye because you'll never make it together. P.S.
Don't ask your next girlfriend any nunovyerbizniz-type questions.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Ann Landers column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910326  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  532  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday March 26, 1991
00086037,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06198166 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06198166 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Cooper  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW; MOUNTAIN-VIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  WHAT if they gave a rock show and nobody came?;    Operation Rock &amp; Roll
invaded Shoreline Amphitheater on Sunday. But it was no Desert Storm. In fact,
if one added up all the musicians of Judas Priest, Alice Cooper, Motorhead,
Metal Church and Dangerous Toys (who made up the tour) with all of their
roadies and toadies and groupies, the bottom line probably would have
outnumbered the fans who came out to see the performance.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  METAL SHOW HEAVY ON THE CLICHES, LIGHT ON
TURNOUT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Music Review  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Not really. But barely a quarter of <ORGANIZATION>Shoreline</ORGANIZATION>'s 20,000 seats were filled by
the time <ORGANIZATION>Metal Church</ORGANIZATION> began the metal slugfest at about <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> And for the
next seven hours, the turnout was roughly proportionate to the quality of
music presented onstage.;    What is the Iraqi word for "dismal"?;    <ORGANIZATION>Metal
Church</ORGANIZATION> had the thankless job of opening this debacle. And it must be said that
the group did have a raw power and energy that got the crowd -- what there was
of it -- up and moving. Vocalist <PERSON>Mike Howe</PERSON> and his mates have a trace of the
punk-based bite that they did when they started out 10 years ago, and they
used it in a set that was, if nothing else, exciting. But, in fact, there was
nothing else to Metal Church.;    Nor to Dangerous Toys, which displayed the
usual metal cliches with an arena-rock slickness that was boring and annoying.
The Metal Book says that every group should play noisy rock and have a shrill
vocalist and guitarists who squeeze off volleys of notes. And all the troops
of Operation Rock &amp; Roll obviously have been doing their reading.;    One of
the guys who wrote that book, <PERSON>Lemmy</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Motorhead</ORGANIZATION>, was on hand for the event.
In the '70s, it was <PERSON>Lemmy</PERSON> who helped to reduce metal from a viable creative
form to a sort of tag-team contest of sound. And, at this show, he was in
form, shouting out his lyrics like a wino in search of a street corner.
Motorhead performed with a monolithic abandon, with guitarist <PERSON>Wurzel</PERSON> providing
an errant blues phrase or two to remind us where metal came from eons ago. But
for the most part its set wasn't about songs as much as sound -- pure,
ear-melting sound.;    <ORGANIZATION>Cooper</ORGANIZATION>'s conviction intact;    <PERSON>Alice Cooper</PERSON> came next.
Now, <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON> isn't a real metalist. He uses the style as an aural scrim on
which he projects his theatrical visions. With metal blaring in the
background, he entered the stage from the gaping mouth of a skull and --
depending on one's tastes in such matters -- got either better or worse from
there. At various points he hugged a snake -- the lovely and talented Salt
Lake <PERSON>Sidney</PERSON> -- and grabbed a "fan" from the crowd, strapped her onto a
"Frankenstein table" and turned her into a monster, which he proceeded to
assault and cast aside. During "School's Out," he kicked a bunch of gigantic
balloons into the crowd, sticking them with a saber, which made them explode
into clouds of multicolored confetti.;    Whew!;    Yes, it was silly and
hokey. And in his black, studded leather tights, <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON>'s stooped posture made
him look like a hilarious version of the Alien (although that creature would
never have worn such flashy eye makeup).;    But <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON>'s garish set also came
with <ORGANIZATION>Cooper</ORGANIZATION>'s songs, which made the effects worth the time and bother. "I'm
18" is one of the teen angst classics of all time, and <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON> sang it with a
conviction that masked his 43 years. And <DATE>1989</DATE>'s "Poison" was equally
wonderful, not metal as much as unalloyed pop. And his new "Hey Stoopid" had a
hook-laden grandeur that was smashing; it even survived a thorough trashing
from guest guitarist <PERSON>Joe Satriani</PERSON>. Cooper endures because his music does the
same, and he and it made his performance a pleasure.;    A tired Judas Priest;
   <ORGANIZATION>Judas Priest</ORGANIZATION> has endured, as well. But not, as it were, well.;    Vocalist
<PERSON>Rob Halford</PERSON> came onstage on his <PERSON>Harley</PERSON>, the way he usually does. And K. K.
Downing and <PERSON>Glenn Tipton</PERSON> provided the fleeting and screaming guitar licks that
have provided <LOCATION>Priest</LOCATION>'s punch over its long career. And with its high-tech set
and glaring and arcing spotlights and explosions and the rest, Priest did give
the crowd its money's worth.;    But the group seemed archaic and tired, as if
it had done one tour too many along the line. Even newer songs like "A Touch
of Evil" and the title cut from its most recent album, "Painkiller," sounded
like the Priest was playing on the sound of its past instead of trying
anything fresh.;    But then metal has never had much to do with such things.
It's about street-warrior poses and the same old licks and a "rebellious"
attitude that is oddly conservative in its conformity. In modest doses, its
various idiocies can be enjoyable and charming in their way.;    But seven
hours of it at one sitting was too much of a bad thing.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  HARRY SUMRALL, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910716  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  833  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday July 16, 1991
00198166,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920220-0115
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920220-0115.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Film: An Old Man's Travels in His Memory
   ----
   By Julie Salamon
</HL>
<DATE>
02/20/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A11
</SO>
<LP>
   Every once in a while a movie feels as if it's come out of
your own dreams -- even if nothing in it remotely resembles
the details of your real life or your fantasy life. "Night of
the Shooting Stars," for example, was such a film for me,
though nothing in my memory resembled the movie's surreal
story of Tuscan peasants fleeing their village in the final
days of World War II.
   "Toto Le Heros," a mesmerizing new Belgian film,
deliberately sets out to be a movie of dreams. It's the story
of an old man's determination to figure out what his life has
been -- if it's been anything at all -- before he dies. The
life has been depressing, but director Jaco Van Dormael turns
the old man's journey through memory and fantasy into a
startling, buoyant adventure.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mr. Van Dormael</PERSON>, directing a full-length feature for the
first time here, performed as a clown for <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>'s Big
Flying Circus before he turned to film. That makes perfect
sense. "Toto" has the spirit of a great circus -- exciting
and delightful yet sad and dangerous as well.
   <PERSON>Michel Bouquet</PERSON> is intense and perfectly unsentimental
playing "Toto" as a cranky old man who's been deposited in a
nursing home. His real name is <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, but he thinks of
himself, secretly, as Toto, an action hero modeled on a
television hero. He dreams of rebellion. When a nurse dumps
pills in a cup for him he fantasizes about grabbing her and
stuffing a whole bottle of the pills down her throat.
   But mainly he's obsessed with murdering someone named
<PERSON>Alfred</PERSON>. "I'll kill you, I'll kill you Alfred" are the first
words he utters in the film.
   He's convinced that <PERSON>Alfred</PERSON> stole his life, that he and
<PERSON>Alfred</PERSON> were switched at birth in a hospital fire, and that he
should have lived the charmed life he's sure <PERSON>Alfred</PERSON>'s been
living. Like everything in <LOCATION>Thomas</LOCATION>'s imagination, that fire is
vividly presented on screen, a nightmarish vision of a
nursery on fire. And even though <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> believes that fire
was real, he's also convinced his life was a bore. "Nothing
ever happened is this guy's story," he says.
   His life as a child, however, was fantastic, the way <PERSON>Mr.
Van Dormael</PERSON> shows it, as a playful fable told from the point
of view of a little boy with a lively mind. Young <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>
remembers his parents telling him he fell from the sky and
was found by his parents, a cheery couple who have the bouncy
pep and humor of a '60s sitcom mom and dad.
   Dad, an airplane pilot, does magic tricks for his kids and
sings them funny songs. That memory is staged like an antic
bit from a <ORGANIZATION>Vincente Minelli</ORGANIZATION> musical. Dad sings "The Singing
Fool" (with the lyric "Boom] The sun goes boom]") while
bright tulips sway to the beat on the front lawn.
   That glorious vision wasn't entirely accurate, even in the
golden period of Thomas's youth. Not everything was perfect.
Thomas's little brother had Down's syndrome, but was
good-natured even when neighborhood kids tormented him.
Thomas had to endure the ridicule of his next-door neighbor
<PERSON>Alfred</PERSON>, the smug rich boy who <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> believed was living with
the wrong parents. Still, <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>'s older sister, was
perfection, the exquisite object of a little boy's vaguely
incestuous adoration. When <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> begins to flirt with <PERSON>Alfred</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> finds new, urgent reasons to hate the boy next door.
   The scenes between <PERSON>Thomas Godet</PERSON>, the actor playing little
<PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Sandrine Blancke</PERSON> as <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> are exquisite. He
worships her. You can see it in the way he looks at her, even
before he informs her that the Egyptian queen <PERSON>Nefertiti</PERSON>
married her brother. Skinny little <PERSON>Ms. Blancke</PERSON> has a
remarkable presence. You understand why <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> gets so
shivery when she climbs into bed with him and casually asks
him if he likes her hands, her feet, her legs.
   Still, things were pretty ideal until they went "boom."
Thomas's father was killed flying goods across the English
Channel for <ORGANIZATION>Alfred</ORGANIZATION>'s father. When the film moves into the
middle years of <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>'s memory, the brightness is gone. He's
become a drab bureaucrat, played with acute misery by <ORGANIZATION>Jo De
Backer</ORGANIZATION>.
   Thomas has never stopped being obsessed by his sister and
has never been able to replace the warm goofiness of his
childhood home. One day he sees a woman who resembles his
sister and he follows her. For a time he's brought back to
life, only to find that she's married to his old neighbor,
<PERSON>Alfred</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Van Dormael</PERSON>, who also wrote the screenplay, skips
around time, as he sifts through <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>'s memory, as <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>
tries to understand his lifelong feud with <PERSON>Alfred</PERSON>. The scenes
from <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>'s childhood seem to take place in the '60s,
judging by artifacts like cars and television sets. That puts
the "contemporary" scenes of Thomas as an old man somewhere
in the future. The movie feels timeless, the way memory does,
picking an instance from one era to make a connection with
something that may have happened a dozen years later. There's
no fake, insulting uplift in this story of missed
opportunities and lost lives. But when you walk out of the
theater you'll feel just wonderful.
   ---
   VIDEO TIP: <PERSON>John Boorman</PERSON> beautifully mingled nostalgia with
horror in "Hope and Glory," his picture about his boyhood
experiences during the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> blitz. Though it's quite
different from "Toto Le Heros" in style and story, its spirit
seems strangely similar to that of the <ORGANIZATION>Van Dormael</ORGANIZATION> film.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880224-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-24-88 1443EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-Cooper     02-24 0191</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Cooper,0195</SECOND>
<HEAD>Singer Alice Cooper Says He is Write-In Candidate for Governor</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Shock-rock star <PERSON>Alice Cooper</PERSON>, who says he
bought his first car years ago from impeached <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Evan
Mecham</PERSON>, has half-serious plans to run for political office in his
home state.
   ``I'm definitely a write-in candidate,'' said the Phoenix-born
singer. ``Hey, I'm a native. I'm a registered voter. I represent
the <ORGANIZATION>Wild Party</ORGANIZATION> and I even have a campaign slogan: `<PERSON>Alice Cooper</PERSON> _ A
troubled man for troubled times.'''
   Cooper, 39, is in <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> for a show <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> that will
end the American leg of his year-long comeback tour.
   Cooper, born <PERSON>Vincent Furnier</PERSON>, a minister's son, said he bought
his first automobile from <PERSON>Mecham</PERSON>, who owned and operated a <LOCATION>Pontiac</LOCATION>
dealership in nearby <LOCATION>Glendale</LOCATION>. Cooper went on to fame with his
outrageous makeup and performances, as well as such hits as
``School's Out.''
   The Republican governor, who took office in <DATE>January 1987</DATE>, was
recently indicted by a state grand jury for attempting to conceal a
<MONEY>$350,000</MONEY> campaign loan. Mecham is facing both a criminal trial this
month and a <DATE>May 17</DATE> recall election.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890922-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-22-89 1013EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:James Adv25   09-22 0719</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: James, Adv 25,0740</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Mon PMs, Sept 25 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Kind of Cooperative Victorian Women Could Have Used</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE DREYFOUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the J-K volume of a recent
<ORGANIZATION>Encyclopedia Brittanica</ORGANIZATION>, the writer <PERSON>Henry James</PERSON> has a six-column
entry. His sister, <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>, is given no mention at all.
   The 19th-century diarist never succeeded in establishing herself
as a talent, which seemed a literary crime to the small group of men
and women who founded a writers' collective in her name.
   <PERSON>Alice James Books</PERSON>, an independent press that emphasizes women's
work, was conceived in <DATE>1972</DATE> as a strike against not only Victorian
mores, but also against the male-dominated reading lists most
college freshmen were studying in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   ``At the time, the people who sat in the important chairs at the
publishing houses were men,'' said <PERSON>Marjorie Fletcher</PERSON>, a poet and
co-founder. ``It was far easier to get a book on baseball into print
than one by a woman or about women's issues.''
   The collective publishes about 2,100 copies each of two books of
poetry every <DATE>summer</DATE> and <DATE>spring</DATE>. Its authors vary in age, race and
lifestyle, but they all share in the ideals from which the
non-profit enterprise grew.
   When <PERSON>Alice James</PERSON> writers agree to join the cooperative, they
agree to nurture their colleagues as well as their own work.
   So far about 70 authors have made the two-year commitment, during
which they guide their own book into print. Three have received
<PERSON>Beatrice Hawley Awards</PERSON>, a grant named after the poet that allows
poets outside of <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> to publish.
   <PERSON>Rosamond Rosenmeier</PERSON> is just wrapping up work on her first
collection, ``Lines Out,'' which appears this <DATE>fall</DATE>.
   ``The experience is extraordinary,'' says <PERSON>Rosenmeier</PERSON>, a writing
   With the help of a ``buddy,'' a veteran collective member who's
already been through the process, she has taken her book from pen
and paper to its final production stages.
   ``It's definitely my book,'' <PERSON>Rosenmeier</PERSON> said. ``I've had a hand
in everything: choosing the print, negotiating with the typesetter,
picking the cover design. We even did the paste-up.''
   That participation and the support collective members lend one
another are part of the philosophy inspired by <PERSON>Alice James</PERSON>, who
struggled in the shadow of her five brothers, including <PERSON>Henry</PERSON> and
<PERSON>William</PERSON>, a prominent psychologist.
   <PERSON>Henry James</PERSON>, the author of such works as ``Portrait of a Lady''
and ``The Ambassadors,'' was so unsettled by his sister's diaries,
which he considered an invasion of privacy, that he burned his copy,
according to biographers..
   ``She was a talented woman who never had a chance to develop,''
<PERSON>Fletcher</PERSON> said of <PERSON>Alice James</PERSON>, who died at the age of 43.
   Today, <PERSON>Fletcher</PERSON> says, it's a whole new ballgame. Women have
gained widespread acceptance, so much so that the collective has
begun casting its net wider and more actively soliciting minority
writers.
   Inclusion is the idea.
   Rosenmeier chuckles to think of the group's regular <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
afternoon meetings. ``We're all so different,'' she says. About a
dozen writers from all walks of life gather at one member's home,
bringing with them plenty of pasta salad, fruit, cheese and wine.
   Fletcher says it's funny to watch everyone file in when the
meeting convenes.
   ``Everybody finds a chair that somehow issues from her
personality. Some sit on the floor, the clubby people sit on the
couch. I sit on a chair,'' she says.
   The business of running and promoting <PERSON>Alice James</PERSON> is always high
on the meeting's agenda. The authors take no salary, but revenue
from limited sales through catalogs, book fairs and a few stores is
far from enough to sustain the collective's budget.
   The press relies in large part on state, federal and private
grants, which <PERSON>Fletcher</PERSON> said have dwindled steadily, particularly
under the strain of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>' current fiscal crisis.
   But <PERSON>Jenney Milner</PERSON>, a part-time office manager and the only paid
employee, said the gatherings inevitably swerve from the pragmatic
to a free-for-all.
   ``That's when they get interesting,'' she said, ``when we talk
about the philosophy of the press.''
   And, adds <PERSON>Fletcher</PERSON>, ``The vagaries of the commercial world or
damned luck can't change our commitment to empowerment, to fairness,
to our philosophy.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PM Mon Sept. 25</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880225-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-25-88 0924EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     02-25 0859</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0887</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names In The News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW, Idaho (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jazz legend <PERSON>Lionel Hampton</PERSON> announced that a
<MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> grant the <ORGANIZATION>National Endowment</ORGANIZATION> for the Arts is giving to a
foundation under his control will be channeled to a music school
named in his honor.
   Hampton spoke <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>Moscow Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> while
visiting the <ORGANIZATION>Panhandle</ORGANIZATION> college town to headline the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Idaho</ORGANIZATION>'s jazz festival and receive an honorary degree.
   ``I always enjoy coming out here because this is a place where
high school students, college students, professional people and
educators and jazz musicians can come together in a common cause to
listen and improve the great art we foster,'' <PERSON>Hampton</PERSON> said.
   Dozens of the world's top jazz performers have come out of
<LOCATION>Hampton</LOCATION>'s bands. But he said he has gotten the most pleasure from
having the university's <ORGANIZATION>Lionel Hampton School of Music</ORGANIZATION> named after
him, which he said is ``like going to heaven.''
   Hampton started his career in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>. When he joined <PERSON>Benny
Goodman</PERSON>'s quartet in <DATE>1936</DATE>, he broke a color barrier that had kept
black musicians out of American entertainment's front ranks.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jazz legend <PERSON>Lionel Hampton</PERSON> announced that a
<MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> grant the <ORGANIZATION>National Endowment</ORGANIZATION> for the Arts is giving to a
foundation under his control will be channeled to a music school
named in his honor.
   Hampton spoke <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>Moscow Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> while
visiting the <ORGANIZATION>Panhandle</ORGANIZATION> college town to headline the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Idaho</ORGANIZATION>'s jazz festival and receive an honorary degree.
   ``I always enjoy coming out here because this is a place where
high school students, college students, professional people and
educators and jazz musicians can come together in a common cause to
listen and improve the great art we foster,'' <PERSON>Hampton</PERSON> said.
   Dozens of the world's top jazz performers have come out of
<LOCATION>Hampton</LOCATION>'s bands. But he said he has gotten the most pleasure from
having the university's <ORGANIZATION>Lionel Hampton School of Music</ORGANIZATION> named after
him, which he said is ``like going to heaven.''
   Hampton started his career in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>. When he joined <PERSON>Benny
Goodman</PERSON>'s quartet in <DATE>1936</DATE>, he broke a color barrier that had kept
black musicians out of American entertainment's front ranks.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jazz legend <PERSON>Lionel Hampton</PERSON> announced that a
<MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> grant the <ORGANIZATION>National Endowment</ORGANIZATION> for the Arts is giving to a
foundation under his control will be channeled to a music school
named in his honor.
   Hampton spoke <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>Moscow Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> while
visiting the <ORGANIZATION>Panhandle</ORGANIZATION> college town to headline the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Idaho</ORGANIZATION>'s jazz festival and receive an honorary degree.
   ``I always enjoy coming out here because this is a place where
high school students, college students, professional people and
educators and jazz musicians can come together in a common cause to
listen and improve the great art we foster,'' <PERSON>Hampton</PERSON> said.
   Dozens of the world's top jazz performers have come out of
<LOCATION>Hampton</LOCATION>'s bands. But he said he has gotten the most pleasure from
having the university's <ORGANIZATION>Lionel Hampton School of Music</ORGANIZATION> named after
him, which he said is ``like going to heaven.''
   Hampton started his career in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>. When he joined <PERSON>Benny
Goodman</PERSON>'s quartet in <DATE>1936</DATE>, he broke a color barrier that had kept
black musicians out of American entertainment's front ranks.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jazz legend <PERSON>Lionel Hampton</PERSON> announced that a
<MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> grant the <ORGANIZATION>National Endowment</ORGANIZATION> for the Arts is giving to a
foundation under his control will be channeled to a music school
named in his honor.
   Hampton spoke <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>Moscow Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> while
visiting the <ORGANIZATION>Panhandle</ORGANIZATION> college town to headline the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Idaho</ORGANIZATION>'s jazz festival and receive an honorary degree.
   ``I always enjoy coming out here because this is a place where
high school students, college students, professional people and
educators and jazz musicians can come together in a common cause to
listen and improve the great art we foster,'' <PERSON>Hampton</PERSON> said.
   Dozens of the world's top jazz performers have come out of
<LOCATION>Hampton</LOCATION>'s bands. But he said he has gotten the most pleasure from
having the university's <ORGANIZATION>Lionel Hampton School of Music</ORGANIZATION> named after
him, which he said is ``like going to heaven.''
   Hampton started his career in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>. When he joined <PERSON>Benny
Goodman</PERSON>'s quartet in <DATE>1936</DATE>, he broke a color barrier that had kept
black musicians out of American entertainment's front ranks.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MALIBU, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jazz legend <PERSON>Lionel Hampton</PERSON> announced that a
<MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> grant the <ORGANIZATION>National Endowment</ORGANIZATION> for the Arts is giving to a
foundation under his control will be channeled to a music school
named in his honor.
   Hampton spoke <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>Moscow Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> while
visiting the <ORGANIZATION>Panhandle</ORGANIZATION> college town to headline the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Idaho</ORGANIZATION>'s jazz festival and receive an honorary degree.
   ``I always enjoy coming out here because this is a place where
high school students, college students, professional people and
educators and jazz musicians can come together in a common cause to
listen and improve the great art we foster,'' <PERSON>Hampton</PERSON> said.
   Dozens of the world's top jazz performers have come out of
<LOCATION>Hampton</LOCATION>'s bands. But he said he has gotten the most pleasure from
having the university's <ORGANIZATION>Lionel Hampton School of Music</ORGANIZATION> named after
him, which he said is ``like going to heaven.''
   Hampton started his career in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>. When he joined <PERSON>Benny
Goodman</PERSON>'s quartet in <DATE>1936</DATE>, he broke a color barrier that had kept
black musicians out of American entertainment's front ranks.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06235036 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06235036 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  I SHALL invent a woman. I shall make her a lawyer. She has gone to a good
college and then to law school, and now works in a Washington firm. She earns
good, not great, money and it's too soon to tell if she'll make partner. She
is 5 feet 6 inches tall and attractive -- at least I think so. Her name is
Alice, and several times a year she is called upon to celebrate what she
considers to be her relative failure.;   What does she mean by that? It's
this. You may have noticed from the description above that Alice is not
married. She has no children either. She is 30 (did I tell you that?); not
old, but neither is it young. It is slowly dawning on Alice that she may never
marry.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ALICE IN SINGLEHOOD: WHEN IS HER TURN, SHE WONDERS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cohen is a columnist for the Washington Post.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Alice is not yet panicked. Anyway, she has a plan. If she is not married
by, say, 35, she will adopt a child. But even before that, she intends to
register at various department stores. She will stipulate her choice in
silverware and china and -- why not? -- linens as well. She will tell her
friends where she is registered, and then she will invite them all to mark
with her the passage of that 35th year, when, she feels, she will pass
irrevocably into singlehood. Why should only married people get to have all
the gifts?;   It sometimes seems to <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> that her life is a wearying round of
parties and weddings, showers and more parties. She is asked to celebrate what
she is coming to see as reminders of her own failure: the engagements,
weddings and babies of others. Each invitation is like a flunking report card.
Alice has a nightmare. She is on a treadmill, loaded with gifts from <ORGANIZATION>Tiffany's</ORGANIZATION>
and Baccarat, price tags trailing behind her, trudging from one party to
another against a stiff wind, getting no closer to her goal.;   <ORGANIZATION>Alice</ORGANIZATION> operates
on her own fiscal year of <DATE>September</DATE> to <DATE>September</DATE>. This has been an expensive
year. Alice has bought a crystal bourbon decanter from <ORGANIZATION>Tiffany's</ORGANIZATION>. She has
bought a sandbox kit for a child's birthday. She has bought ceramic bookends,
a nightgown, a silver casserole set, some flatware, a crystal bowl, two
crystal wine coasters and some china -- a plate, a bowl and a cup. She lists
these items, always citing the manufacturer and approximate price. Alice
thinks she spent about <MONEY>$600</MONEY> on such gifts. It's a bit of change.;   But the
money is the least of her complaints, although it's not unimportant. Instead,
she resents the effort that she expends on people who, it seems to her, are
already blessed. Why should the single be called on to celebrate the married?
Why should the childless have to buy gifts for the people with children? Why
do the unfortunate have to celebrate the good fortune of the fortunate? This
is what's bothering <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>. When, oh when, will her turn come?;   How did this
happen? Alice doesn't really know. There were guys, some close calls, an
engagement made or nearly made or maybe one broken. Alice kept exercising
choice -- not just bumper sticker "choice" about abortion, but other choices
as well. She chose this college and that graduate school and this career and
that guy and this city and then another guy and then another career and then.
. . . And then, somehow, <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> ran out of choices.;   <ORGANIZATION>Alice</ORGANIZATION> is out shopping
right now. She is shopping a lot of the time. When she is not actually
shopping, she is thinking about it. She plans her gifts. She cares about what
she will give. When she sees something in a store, she makes a note of it. She
started doing this kind of thing years ago. She assumed, without actually
thinking it out, that when her time came, people would buy gifts for her just
as carefully. Reciprocity, she thought. She hoped. So far, though, nothing has
come back.;   A colleague is pregnant. Alice, come to the party. A friend is
getting married. Alice, here's your invitation. Alice's college roommate has
given birth, her second. Alice, can you come to the party -- at their <DATE>summer</DATE>
home on the dunes? Children have birthdays and the divorced remarry and the
single get hitched. The invitations arrive like Scuds, tiny thuds that build
in intensity as the years go by. Before one hits real close, <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> is going to
announce her own celebration and register for her stuff.;   <ORGANIZATION>Alice</ORGANIZATION> is my
invention. She did not go to college or to law school and does not now
practice law -- trademark infringement, actually. She is not single and
childless and she did not spend <MONEY>$27.10</MONEY> on a monogrammed sandbox kit for a
child that someone else had. Alice, my invention, does not exist. If she did,
she'd break your heart.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Richard Cohen column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910822  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  814  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, August 22, 1991
00235036,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06106013 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06106013 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  DANCE; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  ALONZO King doesn't abide much by bourgeois affectations such as costumes and
sets for his chamber ballet, Lines Dance Company.;    Its spring season at the
Cowell Theater was as austere as it could be: four abstract works in
more-or-less flesh-colored unitards, assisted only by Wendy W. Gilmore's
delicate lighting.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  KING OF SUBTLETY
LINES DOES FINE WITH GREAT MUSIC, DANCE;
'ADVENTURES OF ALICE' OFF TO A GOOD START  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Dance Reviews  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     King is a talented maverick who does what he wants, his way, without paying
much attention to the questions of marketing and audience appeal that bedevil
most arts organizations. So what if all my pieces look alike? he seems to
shrug. They're not.;    The subtle distinctions between them are organic,
coming directly out of the music, which is invariably ambitious, unusual and
sophisticated. This program featured off-the-beaten-track <PERSON>Bach</PERSON>; <PERSON>Donald
Fontowitz</PERSON>, a frequent collaborator; and <PERSON>Charles Valentin Alkan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sofia
Gubaidulina</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Bohuslav Martinu</PERSON> -- not exactly household names but all makers
of wondrous music.;    "Without Wax" (<DATE>1990</DATE>), made for BalletMet of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, is a very special work, and its title says a great deal about King. It
comes from a custom in Roman times, when sculptors signed their work "sine
cereus" to show that no artificial smootheners were used to disguise nicks,
flaws and cracks. It's an indication of integrity, though it may leave the art
looking grainy or rough-hewn.;    So with the piece. King's company has strong
women and weak men, but he presents all proudly: These are his dancers; take
them for all in all.;    Much of it is danced to silence, which demands great
ensemble awareness and instinct; the silvery, thin, celestial streaks of
"Rejoice for Violin and Cello" by <ORGANIZATION>Gubaidulina</ORGANIZATION>, a contemporary Soviet composer,
are less musical background than evocative sound effects. There's an
invocation for men, a response for the women, a finale for all; and at the
center, a sumptuous pas de deux for <PERSON>Summer Lee Rhatigan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gregory Dawson</PERSON>,
set to a heart-breaking score by <PERSON>Martinu</PERSON> (1890-1952).;    The program also
included revivals of "Toccata in D minor" (<DATE>1990</DATE>), the duet from "Alkan"
(<DATE>1989</DATE>), by far the best section of <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s one-act homage to the eccentric
French pianist and composer (1813-88); and "Awake in the Dream," made for
<LOCATION>Sacramento Ballet</LOCATION> in <DATE>1988.</DATE>;    The last is a post-apocalyptic dreamscape for a
single woman in blue (<ORGANIZATION>Katherine Warner</ORGANIZATION>) and a heartless group who turn on her.
King seems determined not to give us any clues about the internal narrative,
and the ballet's edge of menace is somewhat dulled by his elliptical
story-telling.;    <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Balletland</LOCATION>; "The Adventures of Alice," the
ambitious new <DATE>spring</DATE> production of <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Dance Theater</ORGANIZATION>, is the start of a
wonderful children's ballet. Only the start, mind you, but a good healthy
one.;    This immense work -- 120 dancers, 160 costumes, seven flexible
set-pieces called periaktoi (their origin is in Hellenic theater), lights and
fog, a commissioned score for 11 instrumentalists, vocal quartet and
electronics -- was put together in just three months. This in itself is a
miracle. Getting the bugs out can be left for next year, for the company would
like to make "Alice" an annual event, on the order of "Nutcracker.";    More
words;  Right now, it badly needs a libretto, and probably a voiceover
narrator. What has been created by choreographer <PERSON>Jody White</PERSON>, a dance teacher
from <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION>, is not so much "The Adventures of Alice" as
"Episodes From 'Alice.' " There are a few scenes and characters from "Alice in
<LOCATION>Wonderland</LOCATION>," but the bulk of the ballet is taken from the less familiar
"Through the Looking-Glass.";    I would be tempted to scrub the "Alice"
sections entirely and expand the piece into a "Looking-Glass" ballet, except
the noble polonaise for the <ORGANIZATION>Gryphon</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Mock Turtle</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> is very
beautiful and, moreover, the high point of composer <PERSON>Henry Mollicone</PERSON>'s charming
score.;    In rehearsal, to help the dancers (<PERSON>Jennifer Larsen</PERSON> as the <ORGANIZATION>Gryphon</ORGANIZATION>
and <PERSON>Griffin Dong</PERSON> as the Mock Turtle) establish the proper mood, White was
inspired to say, "Think of the <ORGANIZATION>Gryphon</ORGANIZATION> as an endangered species." They caught
on immediately, and the dance is fragile and wistful, steps from a bygone
era.;    White's most effective device is to have <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> (15-year-old <PERSON>Sharon
Wehner</PERSON>) end the ballet by leaving the stage and opening one of the exit doors
of the house, where golden sunlight streams in, returning her to reality.;   
Other good episodes are "Jabberwocky," featuring <PERSON>David Roxander</PERSON>, White's son,
a former principal dancer with the <ORGANIZATION>National Ballet of Canada</ORGANIZATION>, as the <PERSON>Beamish</PERSON>
Boy; the war of the chess pieces, accomplished by strobe lights and the
harmless but showy explosions of flash pots; and the Queen of Hearts' garden,
where the white roses are painted red by the gardening staff.;    On the down
side, there are a lot of terrific costumes wasted on characters who barely
appear, such as the Mad Hatter, the <DATE>March Hare</DATE> and the Dormouse. And the
senior dancers of the company dribble by in a floral episode that has nothing
to do with the story.;    When I saw the piece at dress rehearsal, it was
severely overcast by machine-made fog, and the lights, by <PERSON>Brad Belleville</PERSON>,
were prosaic. Some of these problems may have been corrected for the
performances; if not, there's always next year.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JUDITH GREEN, Mercury News Dance Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910415  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  880  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 15, 1991
00106013,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891109-0243 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-89 0646EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--TurntableTips 3takes Adv10 11-09 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Turntable Tips, 3 takes, Adv10,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv10</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Friday, Nov. 10, and thereafter</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06012217 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06012217 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: 'The Godfather Part III' begins in a Catholic church;
PHOTO: In 'Alice,' Mia Farrow fights middle-aged angst with dreams of becoming
Mother Teresa  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MOVIE; RELIGION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A '60s teen-ager, Jewish by birth, rebels against her free-spirited mother by
affecting nunlike attire and installing a crucifix and icons of the saints in
her bedroom.;    An aging Mafia don, long out of touch with his faith,
confronts his bloodstained past during a heart-rending encounter with a priest
who will be pope.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Religion &amp; Ethics  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SAINTS, SINNERS, CINEMA
FILMMAKERS SEEK SALVATION IN THE LITURGY,
HISTORY AND IMAGERY OF ROMAN CATHOLICISM  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cover Story  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     A young <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> matron, unhappy with her pampered but sterile life, finds
escape by realizing her childhood dreams of  helping the poor a la Mother
Teresa.;    Catholicism -- its institutions, rituals and unique moral and
ethical world view -- has long fascinated filmmakers, both of and outside the
faith, and it seems to be everywhere on screen lately.;    Its presence is
nowhere so pronounced as in "The Godfather Part III," in which <PERSON>Michael
Corleone</PERSON> enlists the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> in his final maneuver to make the family business
legitimate -- and unexpectedly finds in the sacrament of confession some
measure of personal redemption.;    From the start, the church has always
figured in the "Godfather" saga -- think of all the weddings, baptisms and
other ceremonies <PERSON>Francis Ford Coppola</PERSON> has used as set pieces. In this third
installment, <PERSON>Coppola</PERSON> has made it a major player in the <PERSON>Corleone</PERSON> family's
fortunes.;    The film depicts the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> at its best and
worst. A principal villain is a corrupt <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> treasurer, who proves to be no
more trustworthy than any of the mob figures <PERSON>Michael</PERSON> has dispatched over the
years.;    On the advice of an old Sicilian mentor, <PERSON>Michael</PERSON> approaches a
friendlier power broker, <ORGANIZATION>Cardinal Lamberto</ORGANIZATION>. But Lamberto sincerely cares about
<PERSON>Michael</PERSON>'s soul, and the price he exacts for his cooperation is <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>'s
confession.;    <PERSON>Michael</PERSON> initially demurs. He can confess, he tells Lamberto,
but he cannot repent.;    But the cardinal gently insists, and reluctantly
<PERSON>Michael</PERSON> sketches out a lifetime of cold-blooded murder capped by the
"Godfather II"-closing assassination of his own brother.;    As he actually
speaks the unspeakable, however, something happens: In one of <PERSON>Al Pacino</PERSON>'s most
powerful performances in the film, <PERSON>Michael</PERSON> breaks down. It's an unforgettable
scene that is also as eloquent an endorsement of the faith as has been seen on
the big screen.;    Salvation of another sort is the carrot that lures <PERSON>Winona
Ryder</PERSON>, as <ORGANIZATION>Cher</ORGANIZATION>'s adolescent daughter <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, to Catholicism in "Mermaids."
Cher's character, <PERSON>Rachel Flax</PERSON>, is a gypsy soul whose obvious love for her two
daughters doesn't quite compensate for her inability to handle the commitment
required to maintain a stable home or even cook a normal meal.;    <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>
may not know what she's looking for, but she's certain it isn't her mom's
endless parade of lovers and annoying habit of moving to a new town whenever a
love affair ends.;    Out of some conviction that the sins of the mother can
be expiated by the daughter, <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> turns to Catholicism, a religion imbued
with the kind of discipline so lacking in her home life. She sets up shrines
in her bedroom, dreams of becoming a nun (one way of avoiding the kind of
messy situations her mother's love life creates) and, when her own nascent
sexuality rears its bothersome head, consults religious tracts for advice.;   
There's plenty of comedy to be mined from the spectacle of a pretty young
Jewish girl trying desperately to solve her problems by wearing black dresses
and clunky shoes and quoting the saints -- and director <PERSON>Richard Benjamin</PERSON>
doesn't let any opportunity go by.;    In the end, <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>'s Catholicism is
only an adolescent passion; she embraces and outgrows it much the way other
kids go through a heavy metal or punk phase. Small wonder her mother never
worries about it too much: It's a lot less noisy than rock 'n' roll.;    In
<PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON>'s "Alice," <PERSON>Mia Farrow</PERSON> plays a good Catholic girl who has lost her
way in the material world of the '80s. She has everything money can buy but is
poor in the intangibles that really matter. Under the ministrations of a
Chinese herbalist (played by <PERSON>Keye Luke</PERSON>), she cuts through the pretenses that
have been cushioning her pain and finds in herself the idealist who once
wanted only to do good for others.;    <ORGANIZATION>Farrow</ORGANIZATION>'s Catholicism, however, is like
<PERSON>Allen</PERSON>'s Judaism: Its main attribute is a persistent sense of guilt that keeps
her loyal to her faithless and patronizing husband. You don't see her hanging
around churches or going to a priest with her problems. At first, she doesn't
even realize she has them, and it's the forthright Chinese herbalist who acts
as her father confessor.;    <ORGANIZATION>Allen</ORGANIZATION> isn't really out to paint a full-blown
portrait of a Catholic woman. Alice's faith is a manifestation of her basic
goodness: The point is to show up the people that surround her as selfish,
uncaring jerks.;    Ultimately, <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>'s story is that of a woman who takes off
her rose-colored glasses and learns to look for answers, not in any
pre-fabricated social or religious framework, but within herself.;    <ORGANIZATION>The
Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> has long been a presence in films from <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, which is not
surprising, since the histories of the continent and the church are
inseparable.;    Over the years, there have been Catholic-themed comedies
("Nuns on the Run" and a remake of "We're No Angels" recently), murder
mysteries ("True Confessions") and horror films ("The Exorcist" and its
sequels).;    There are many reasons why the <ORGANIZATION>Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> pops up in so
many films: the rich visual imagery of Catholicism, its lush liturgical music,
its history and rituals lend a majesty that is lacking in contemporary
American life.;    It's a faith that has weathered drastic social change with
minimal change outside the abandonment of the Latin mass and permitting the
consumption of meat on Fridays.;    <PERSON>Like Judaism</PERSON>, Catholicism is a religion
that people can't get away from, even those who give it up (ever hear of a
lapsed Protestant?) -- and that makes it almost an ethnicity.;    All of this
is fine fare for filmmaking. There's a metaphor for almost everything in
Catholicism, and a faith this grounded in tradition provides a fine framework
for almost any consideration of our secular society. There may be a shortage
of priests, but, in movies, Catholicism is thriving.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  YARDENA ARAR, Los Angeles Daily News  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Los Angeles  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910112  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,053  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, January 12, 1991
00012217,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891116-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-16-89 0625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--TurntableTips 3takes Adv17 11-16 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Turntable Tips, 3 takes, Adv17,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv17</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Friday, Nov. 17, and thereafter</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following are the top record hits and leading popular
magazine. Copyright <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Billboard Publications, Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Reprinted
with permission.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121390-0083 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 321583 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 13, 1990, Thursday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Ventura County Life; Part J; Page 21; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
602 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THEATER REVIEW 'RECKLESS'; 
</P>
<P>
CRUEL YULE; 
</P>
<P>
IF ALICE FELL DOWN THE RABBIT HOLE, RACHEL IS A CAT BEING DRAGGED THROUGH A 
KNOTHOLE. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ANN VAN DER VEER, SPECIAL TO THE TIMES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Craig Lucas</PERSON>' black comedy "Reckless" has found the right director. Pope 
<PERSON>Freeman</PERSON>'s intense multilayered production at <ORGANIZATION>Santa Barbara City College</ORGANIZATION>'s 
Studio Theater is reminiscent of Antonin Artaud's "theater of cruelty." And it 
corroborates <PERSON>Jerzy Grotowski</PERSON>'s theory that the content of theater should be 
"myths of the blood" rather than fictions bearing on social life and behavior. 
</P>
<P>
The plot has <PERSON>Rachel</PERSON>, a sort of <ORGANIZATION>20th-Century Alice</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wonderland</LOCATION>, catapulted 
through a series of events that ostensibly have to do with social life and 
behavior -- but which may be fantasy, dream, memory or all three. Catapulted is 
not a strong enough image; if <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> fell down the rabbit hole, <PERSON>Rachel</PERSON> is a cat 
being dragged through a knothole. 
</P>
<P>
It starts on <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION>. Rachel is a normal, if slightly hysterical, wife in 
her own home, happily stuffing Christmas stockings for her children, chatting 
to her husband who suddenly informs her that he has taken out a contract on her 
life. 
</P>
<P>
Cut to a roadside telephone booth in the snow. Rachel, in robe and slippers, 
gets a ride with a stranger, <PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON>, who takes her home to live with him and his 
deaf paraplegic girlfriend (who isn't really deaf and who may be his mother). 
Rachel changes her name, gets a job and life goes on. 
</P>
<P>
On the next <PERSON>Christmas Eve</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rachel</PERSON>'s husband arrives at the door with a bottle 
of champagne. Within minutes, he and the paraplegic girlfriend (who is clad in 
reindeer horns and a fake red nose) die a horrible death by poisoning. 
</P>
<P>
Cut to <PERSON>Rachel</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON> (comatose and wearing a <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> suit), who are back 
in the car running away to a new life, where they will change their names 
again. Lloyd will refuse to take off the <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> suit or stop drinking 
champagne until the next <DATE>Christmas</DATE>, when he dies too. 
</P>
<P>
Rachel is on the road again, and we follow her through several more bizarre 
Christmases, interspersed with scenes in which she tries to explain to various 
obtuse psychiatrists what has happened. 
</P>
<P>
The funny thing is that it could all be true. <PERSON>Freeman</PERSON> has directed the actors 
to play it straight, as if it were true. This somehow creates a chilling effect 
that activates a seldom used section of our funny bone: We find ourselves 
laughing hysterically when <PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON> finally keels over in his <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION> suit; 
then we feel embarrassed when we realize that we are laughing at his death. But 
before we can buffer that, we are whisked off to the next incredible event. 
Nothing comes to rest in itself. Every event calls forth a new horror clothed 
in everyday dress. 
</P>
<P>
The issues become life, death, sanity, recurrence, betrayal, recognition, 
salvation . . . the list is unfinished but it leads further away from mere 
social life and behavior. 
</P>
<P>
The mise-en-scene deserves a paragraph -- the stage is a claustrophobic jumble 
of all the scenery and props needed for 20 scenes. Thus as two characters sit 
on the double bed, they are inches from the red automobile they will drive in 
the next scene. Two hanging video screens record some of the action. The effect 
is disturbing, disorienting, dreamlike and wholly effective. <ORGANIZATION>Douglas Tal 
Sanders</ORGANIZATION> is scenic and lighting designer. 
</P>
<P>
There are some good performances by <PERSON>Tom Rearden</PERSON>, <PERSON>Peter Alexander Flanders</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Rachel Marie Bargiel</PERSON>, <PERSON>Even Caston</PERSON> and <PERSON>Aaron Levin</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Lucas is an interesting playwright. His "Prelude to a Kiss" is on Broadway and 
was nominated for a Tony Award last year. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
WHERE AND WHEN 
</P>
<P>
"Reckless" at the Studio Theater, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Barbara City College West Campus</ORGANIZATION>, 721 
<ORGANIZATION>Cliff Drive</ORGANIZATION>. Plays at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, <DATE>Friday</DATE> and <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. Tickets are <MONEY>$7</MONEY>, <MONEY>$5</MONEY> 
students and seniors. Call 965-5935. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, ON THE COVER: Pete Flanders as Lloyd prepares to pick up Melissa 
Phipps as Rachel. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Play Review; Infobox 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900101-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-01-90 1244EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Names     01-01 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Names,0246</SECOND>
<HEAD>James, Elizabeth Most Popular Names for 1989 British Babies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   James and <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>, the names of British kings
and queens, were the most popular names for babies born in <DATE>1989</DATE>,
according to the social editor of the Times of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> newspaper.
   Of the 2,780 boys whose births were announced in the newspaper
last year, 392 had <PERSON>James</PERSON> as one of their names, 120 ahead of the
runner-up, <LOCATION>William</LOCATION>, said social editor <PERSON>Helen Beard</PERSON>.
   Of the 2,645 birth announcements for girls, 254 had <LOCATION>Elizabeth</LOCATION>
among their names, 106 ahead of the second most popular choice,
<LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, she said.
   Of the first names chosen, <PERSON>James</PERSON> was also the most popular for
boys, as it has been every year since <DATE>1964</DATE>, <PERSON>Ms. Beard</PERSON> wrote in her
annual letter to the editor outlining parents' selections. James
was followed by <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, <PERSON>William</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Edward</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Charles</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Oliver</PERSON>, <PERSON>George</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Henry</ORGANIZATION>.
   Elizabeth was only the 10th most popular choice as a first name
for girls, the newspaper reported. Charlotte was the top choice, a
position acquired in <DATE>1983</DATE> but surrendered to <LOCATION>Emma</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> in <DATE>1987</DATE>
and <DATE>1988</DATE> respectively.
   Charlotte was followed by <PERSON>Emily</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sophie</PERSON>, <PERSON>Emma</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Olivia</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Alexandra</PERSON>, <PERSON>Katherine</PERSON>, Lucy and then <LOCATION>Elizabeth</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> has had two queens named <LOCATION>Elizabeth</LOCATION>, including the
current monarch, <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, and two <LOCATION>King James</LOCATION>. William, <LOCATION>Edward</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Charles</PERSON>, <PERSON>George</PERSON>, <PERSON>Henry</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> and <PERSON>Alexandra</PERSON> are also
names associated with the royal family past and present.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06245150 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06245150 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (4); PHOTO: David Lee Roth, so popular in past years, had to cancel his
summer tour because of poor ticket sales.; PHOTO: Alice Cooper; ... Bad draw;
PHOTO: The bearded boys of ZZ Top, who performed to a sold-out crowd at San
Jose's Spartan Stadium in August, were among the few winners in this poor rock
'n' roll season, with the second-highest grossing tour after the Grateful Dead
(color).; PHOTO: This season's popular Lollapalooza tour, headlined by Jane's
Addiction, above, sold out two shows at Shoreline, but other tours featuring
such acts as Sisters of Mercy, Public Enemy, Judas Priest and Alice Cooper
haven't fared well (color).  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ENTERTAINMENT; TREND; RELATION; ECONOMY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AS THE Labor Day Weekend rolls through and the summer rock season rolls out,
the receipts have been tabulated and the winners are: the Grateful Dead, the
Lollapalooza tour and rap/dance music in general.;   But the big news was the
losers, which included just about everyone else.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Arts &amp; Books  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GROUPS ARE PLAYING TO EMPTY STADIUMS -- OR STAYING
HOME  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Entertainment and the Recession; See also related stories on pages 17, 24, 25
of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The old geezers in the Dead topped the national mid-year revenue totals
with <MONEY>$22.6 million</MONEY>. Dominating the local concert scene, the 21-city, nine-act
Lollapalooza tour -- headlined by <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s Addiction -- and the <ORGANIZATION>KMEL Summer</ORGANIZATION> Jam
rap/dance spectacular sold out two shows apiece at Mountain View's Shoreline
Amphitheatre.;   But these few successes were eclipsed by the stunning decline
in the business itself. The Fresno-based concert business publication Pollstar
listed mid-year revenues for the Top 100 shows at <MONEY>$76 million</MONEY>, down by <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT> from the record <MONEY>$110 million</MONEY> of 1990.;   One of the most highly touted
tours at the start of the pop <DATE>summer</DATE> season was one that included the <ORGANIZATION>Sisters
of Mercy</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Public Enemy</ORGANIZATION> and Gang of Four. But when the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> leg of that
tour was canceled because of poor ticket sales, its title, "The Tune In, Turn
On, Burn Out Tour," came to symbolize the state of the rock concert business.
In <DATE>1991</DATE>, the fans did tune in and turn on, but they didn't turn out in the
record-smashing numbers of the past.;   Other touring "festivals" of the
season didn't fare much better. Operation Rock And Roll (Judas Priest, <PERSON>Alice
Cooper</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Motorhead</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Metal Church</ORGANIZATION> and Dangerous Toys) drew barely 5,500 fans to
the 20,000-seat Shoreline Amphitheatre in <DATE>July</DATE> (in <DATE>1990</DATE>, <LOCATION>Judas Priest</LOCATION> drew
13,000 fans to a show in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>) and did the same poor business in other
parts of the country. And the nostalgia-infused Gathering of the Tribes II,
with nine acts including <ORGANIZATION>Fishbone</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Primus</LOCATION>, drew 7,000 to <LOCATION>Shoreline</LOCATION>; its
tour was canceled after three shows.;   <PERSON>David Lee Roth</PERSON>, who had sold out the
<ORGANIZATION>Cow Palace</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Daly City</LOCATION> in past years, was forced to cancel his <DATE>summer</DATE> tour
because of disappointing ticket receipts.;   And while the Guns N' Roses tour
has done well in many venues (the group sold out its two-night stand at
<LOCATION>Shoreline</LOCATION>), it hasn't done sellout business in several of the cities where two
shows were scheduled -- a major disappointment given the group's stature in
the scene.;   <ORGANIZATION>Pollstar</ORGANIZATION> editor <PERSON>Gary Bongiovanni</PERSON> cites several factors in the
poor showing of various tours and venues: the recession; competition from
other forms of entertainment; and a continuing trend of escalating ticket
prices.;   "This is the first time that a recession has adversely affected the
business," he says. "And with fewer entertainment dollars out there, these
shows have had to compete with movies like 'Terminator 2' and with places like
<LOCATION>Great America</LOCATION> and with activities like going to the beach. It's been a rough
year.";   He also notes that for the first time the business has seen
"resistance on the part of the fans to escalating prices" of tickets, which
have gone up <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> from <DATE>1990.</DATE>;   <LOCATION>The Bay Area</LOCATION> has suffered a decline in
business (although it hasn't been affected as much as other parts of the
country, particularly the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>).;   Promoter <PERSON>Bill Graham</PERSON>,
whose <PERSON>Bill Graham</PERSON> Presents books <PERSON>Shoreline Amphitheatre</PERSON>, said business at that
venue was off approximately <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> so far this year. "But
while our business hasn't been as good as in previous years it wasn't that
bad. We're like a baseball player who usually hits .400 and is now hitting
.350 this season.";   While <PERSON>Graham</PERSON> also blames the recession, he said there
haven't been as many shows on the touring circuit. "In <DATE>1990</DATE> we did 58 shows at
Shoreline," he said, "but this year we did 45.";   Given the decline in the
concert business, many groups were reluctant to tour during the usually prime
<DATE>summer</DATE> season. Acts such as Queen and R.E.M. released new records (R.E.M.'s
"Out of Time" was No. 1 on the charts at one point) but declined to tour. And
acts such as Dire Straits and New Kids on the Block postponed tours they had
initially scheduled for the <DATE>summer</DATE> because of the dreary commercial climate.; 
 The absence of the stadium tours by the usual blockbuster names was also
partly to blame for the season's poor showing. In past years, seasonal
revenues have been bolstered by the stadium tours of such acts as U2, <PERSON>Bruce
Springsteen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Paul McCartney</PERSON>. But this season the only consistent stadium
draw was the Grateful Dead, which averaged approximately 47,000 tickets per
show. (Those bewhiskered galoots of ZZ Top, who had the second-highest
grossing tour at mid-year with revenues of <MONEY>$18.5 million</MONEY>, did divert from
their arena tour to play a sold-out show at <LOCATION>Spartan Stadium</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> <DATE>Aug.
10</DATE>.);   But if the blockbuster acts haven't been present in this <DATE>summer</DATE> pop
season, blockbuster ticket prices have. <PERSON>Graham</PERSON> says the responsibility for
that resides with the artists.;   "One of the misconceptions on the part of
the fans," <PERSON>Graham</PERSON> says, "is that it is the promoter who establishes the prices
of tickets. But those are predicated by the amount that the acts are charging.
If an act decides to charge, hypothetically, <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> (to perform), I have to
adjust what we are charging for tickets. Any time that an act is willing to
play for less, I will charge less.";   Is he saying the acts are greedy?;  
"When it comes to the ticket prices," <PERSON>Graham</PERSON> said, "the superstars could care
less" about the fans.;   But with fans resisting those prices, <PERSON>Graham</PERSON> thinks
there could be an upside to all of this. "I think the poor showings of these
tours might force them to rethink what they will charge.";   A few of the
tours, such as the one that came with Damn Yankees and Bad Company, lowered
their ticket prices and, Pollstar reports, ended up making as much money as
other tours while performing to vastly greater numbers of fans. And with one
of the primary roles of tours being record promotion, that arguably translates
to wiser  career enhancement. (But even that did not work out for <ORGANIZATION>Roth</ORGANIZATION>, who
lowered the ticket prices to <MONEY>$9</MONEY> for lawn seats at his various "shed" shows.); 
 "It's been a wacky year," <PERSON>Bongiovanni</PERSON> says. "But the business is cyclical and
it looks as if the latter part of the year and the next year should improve.";
  At this point, demand for tickets for a tour by the consistently
best-selling Van <PERSON>Halen</PERSON> (which comes to the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> <DATE>Sept. 13-14</DATE>) has been
relatively heavy. And other acts that are set to begin tours include <PERSON>Tom
Petty</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Prince</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Paula Abdul</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Luther Vandross</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Bob Seger</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Metallica</ORGANIZATION>. And
there is speculation that U2 and <PERSON>Springsteen</PERSON> could be touring in <DATE>1992.</DATE>;   But
at the moment, until these heavy-hitters hit the circuit, all the business can
do is tend its wounds and hope that the recession and its woes will go away.
(box)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  HARRY SUMRALL, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910901  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  16  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,292  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, September 1, 1991
00245150,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06337116 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06337116 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Keaton  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  TELEVISION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE love that illuminates "Wildflower," a hauntingly beautiful movie on
cable's Lifetime channel Tuesday at 9 p.m., flows through it like sunlight
through stained glass.;   The tale, set in rural Depression-era Georgia and
directed by actress Diane Keaton, has the timelessness of a parable. It's
almost biblical in its simplicity.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DIANE KEATON'S LATEST STARRING ROLE: DIRECTOR  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Patricia Arquette</PERSON> stars as a beautiful, neglected 17-year-old girl
imprisoned by her wicked stepfather because she is "touched by the devil" --
deaf and epileptic.;   <PERSON>Reese Witherspoon</PERSON> plays 13-year-old <PERSON>Ellie Perkins</PERSON>, a
neighbor who discovers the grimy, half-wild girl locked away in a chicken
coop. She is unwashed, illiterate, and barely capable of speech.;   <PERSON>Ellie</PERSON> and
her 18-year-old brother, <PERSON>Sammy</PERSON> (<PERSON>William McNamara</PERSON>), befriend <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>, against the
vehement wishes of their father, <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Beau Bridges</ORGANIZATION>, in a masterly
performance), a widower still locked in his grief.;   They help <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> emerge
from her ignorance and isolation, and when conflict looms with <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>'s father,
papa <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> is forced out of his own emotional isolation.;   At the same time,
young <PERSON>Sammy</PERSON> realizes that his unsophisticated friend is rapidly becoming a
beautiful woman, and he doesn't quite know what to make of his feelings.;  
<PERSON>Sara Flanigan</PERSON>'s script, based on her books, treats these kinds of love with
great feeling and without a trace of greeting-card sentimentality.;   Here is
the unselfish love of humankind; here is redemptive love; here is familial
love (as well as its cancerous absence); and here, happily and unhappily, is
the love of a man and a woman.;   <ORGANIZATION>Arquette</ORGANIZATION>'s portrayal of a profoundly
hearing-impaired girl is utterly believable. According to production notes,
she researched the role by listening to speech tapes of hearing-impaired
children before and after cochlear implants. She also worked with a speech
therapist, and was coached by a girl who has a hearing loss similar to
<ORGANIZATION>Alice's</ORGANIZATION>.;   "Wildflower" is a superb movie, a fully realized, sophisticated
piece of film-making. But try telling that to its director, and you can
practically hear her blush over the telephone.;   Although the movie is billed
as director <PERSON>Keaton</PERSON>'s first dramatic feature, she demurred at calling
"Wildflower" a movie.;   "I don't see it as a film, I see it as a television
show," she said. "You have to plan the whole movie according to these
breaks.";   To ease the transition shock, <PERSON>Keaton</PERSON> designed thematic "bumpers,"
