<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890216-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-16-89 0133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Britain-Rushdie     02-16 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Britain-Rushdie,0767</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anger Runs Deep In Moslem Community; Vengeance Does Not</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Satanic Verses, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Thursday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAGGIE JACKSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The anger over <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> and his novel ``The
Satanic Verses'' is quick to flare and shared by many in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s
Moslem community, from the sweetmeats shopkeeper to the Bangladeshi
banker.
   But while they spare no insult for the author they accuse of
blasphemy, many in the city's narrow East End streets don't seek
vengeance and reject <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON>'s order to execute
him.
   The Imams and <ORGANIZATION>Mosque council</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> issued an appeal to ``all
imams'' _ Moslem clergymen _ to respect British law.
   An information office representing Prince <PERSON>Reza Pahlavi</PERSON>, son of
the late <PERSON>Shah</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>, said the Iranian government's reaction
exemplifies the ``brutal and arbitrary intolerance that is rampant
in <LOCATION>Khomeini</LOCATION>'s Islamic Republic.''
   The statement, however, said the prince was sympathetic to
objections to the book.
   In conversations with immigrants in the East End's Brick Lane
shops, some cheered the death call. But many said the author, who
has canceled a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> tour and dropped from sight, should live.
   ``To kill him is not going to solve the problem,'' said <PERSON>Naim
Sheikh</PERSON>, the owner of a shop selling leather goods who called for a
law that would prevent such books from being written again.
   ``There must be some way that governments can approve a
resolution that in future no writer should have a right to write
against any prophet _ Mohammed, Jesus or Moses,'' he said.
   Moslems revere Mohammed as the prophet who brought <ORGANIZATION>Allah</ORGANIZATION>'s
revelations to mankind in the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, the holy book of Islam.
   ``But do I personally agree with the ayatollah? It doesn't
matter,'' said <PERSON>Sheikh</PERSON>, one of the many Moslem Bangladeshis living in
the Brick Lane area.
   ``You can't stop the ayatollah. You can't stop the people who
will do the job ... Anyone who kills <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> will become a hero in
the Islamic world.''
   Like Sheikh, most Moslems acknowledged they haven't read the
book. Most learned about it at one of the five mosques located in a
one-square-mile area of this district, from leaflets, or from
television reports.
   ``He insulted our prophet, our religion. From TV we know this,''
said a shopkeeper selling sticky sweets who refused to give his name.
   Even though they haven't read the book, they are sure it insults
their prophet and are quick to say so when the novel is mentioned.
   ``Our older people read it, they say it's wrong, so we believe
them,'' <PERSON>Nassim Khan</PERSON>, a Pakistani Moslem, said as he ate lunch at a
modest tandoori restaurant. ``They've been studying for years and
years and they should know.''
   <PERSON>Maqbool Ali-Kassam</PERSON>, waiting for his takeout tea, boomed from
across the room: ``Anyone who denies the religion of Islam shall be
killed.''
   Ali-Kassam, a taxi cab radio controller who calls himself a
follower of the ayatollah, said he believes <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> deliberately
meant to insult Islam.
   Dozens of drivers from his company stayed at the office until
early <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, he said, arguing about the book and the
execution order. ``Some said he didn't mean anything about Islam,
others wanted him killed.''
   Many Moslems believe <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>, 41, insults Mohammed by portraying
him as a character called Mahound, a prophet of a city called
Jahilia. Mahound was a medieval corruption of the word Mohammed.
   They are especially angered by one sequence in which prostitutes
are given the names of some of Mohammed's nine wives and by the
book's implication that Mohammed, not Allah, may have been the real
author of the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>.
   Rushdie was born into a Moslem family in <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, and
educated in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>. He lives in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. His novel has sold more
than 100,000 copies since it was published in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>September</DATE>
to critical acclaim.
   ``Previously Mohammed has been criticized, but not in this naked
way,'' said <PERSON>Abul Khair</PERSON>, a top officer at the <ORGANIZATION>Sonali Bank</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>'s state bank, on Brick Lane. ``It is intolerable for
Moslems.''
   But he doesn't agree with the ayatollah. ``We don't want
violence. Islam is a peaceful religion,'' he said.
   Restaurant manager <PERSON>Asaad Ramjaun</PERSON>, a Mauritian immigrant, said of
Rushdie: ``I think he's the devil himself.''
   ``We understand this is a free society, but I think this is
freedom of abuse,'' he said. ``But since this is a free society _ he
shouldn't be killed. He should be given a chance.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890308-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-08-89 2036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Hostages-Text     03-08 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Hostages-Text,0352</SECOND>
<HEAD>Text of Revolutionary Justice Statement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Justice Organization</ORGANIZATION>, as translated from Arabic by <ORGANIZATION>The
Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>:
   In the name of the Almighty.
   After a thourough reading of ``The Satanic Verses'' book and its
contents that insult Islam and the Arab prophet, and after examining
the study of the so-called <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Justice
Organization</ORGANIZATION> declares that it has completed its preparations to
execute the just sentence issued by the esteemed cleric and the
great struggler <PERSON>Ayatollah Khomeini</PERSON> against <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>. Hence, it
puts forward the following evidence for carrying out the sentence:
   1 _ Insulting Islam and the Arab prophet is an insult to the
latest and greatest human civilization represented by revolutionary
Islam.
   2 _ <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>'s record indicates that he was a branch member
of the Freemasons' movement in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. Immediately after the
publication of his ``Satanic Verses'' book, he was promoted to full
official membership of the Freemasons' highest council in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>
(or the church of organized atheism) which combats divine religions,
especially christianity and Islam and their great prophets.
   3 _ <PERSON>Imam Ayatollah Khomeini</PERSON>, with his acute awareness of the
grave consequences against the future of the divine religions
emanating from this Freemasonic and Zionist attack, has handed down
his verdict when the Arabs and those who claim to be the protectors
of Islam and speak for all the Moslems remained in tight silence.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Justice Organization</ORGANIZATION> also declares that before
taking any measures it will find itself compelled to attack British
police posts assigned to protect <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> in order to get to
him to carry out the sentence. We hold the British government
responsible in advance for the human and material losses among the
British police and their posts that could result from the attacks on
them. This warning applies to all countries that are currently
negotiating with the British government to extend asylum and
protection to <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>.
   Victory to the oppressed,
   Glory and immortality to the martyrs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890308-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-08-89 1243EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Lebanon-Rushdie-Text     03-08 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Lebanon-Rushdie-Text,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>Text of Revolutionary Justice Statement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following is the text of a statement
holds American hostages in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>. The Arabic-language statement
was translated by <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   In the name of the Almighty.
   After a thorough reading of The Satanic Verses book and its
contents that insult Islam and the Arab prophet, and after examining
the study of the so-called <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Justice
Organization</ORGANIZATION> declares that it has completed its preparations to
execute the just sentence issued by the esteemed cleric and the
great struggler <PERSON>Ayatollah Khomeini</PERSON> against <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>. Hence, it
puts forward the following evidence for carrying out the sentence:
   1. Insulting Islam and the Arab prophet is an insult to the
latest and greatest human civilization represented by revolutionary
Islam.
   2. <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>'s record indicates that he was a branch member
of the Freemasons' movement in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. Immediately after the
publication of his Satanic Verses book, he was promoted to full
official membership of the Freemasons' highest council in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>
(or the church of organized atheism) which combats divine religions,
especially christianity and Islam and their great prophets.
   3. Imam <PERSON>Ayatollah Khomeini</PERSON>, with his acute awareness of the grave
consequences against the future of the divine religions emanating
from this Freemasonic and Zionist attack, has handed down his
verdict when the Arabs and those who claim to be the protectors of
Islam and speak for all the Moslems remained in tight silence.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Justice Organization</ORGANIZATION> also declares that before
taking any measures, it will find itself compelled to attack British
police posts assigned to protect <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> in order to get to
him to carry out the sentence. We hold the British government
responsible in advance for the human and material losses among the
British police and their posts that could result from the attacks on
them. This warning applies to all countries that are currently
negotiating with the British government to extend asylum and
protection to <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>.
   Victory to the oppressed
   Glory and immortality to the martyrs
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890215-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-15-89 1435EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Kemp     02-15 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kemp,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mrs. King Tells Kemp: Follow Through on Housing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Coretta <PERSON>Scott King</PERSON> told new <ORGANIZATION>HUD</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Jack
Kemp</PERSON> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> he had raised expectations about the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
administration's commitment to easing urban problems and now must
deliver.
   Kemp, in his first duties as the new secretary of housing and
urban development, completed a high-visibility tour of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s
poor black neighborhoods and pledged to work to increase the
availability of afffor low-income people through
both public and private efforts.
   ``You have really raised our hopes and excited people about the
prospects of something happening with housordable housing ing and jobs,''
<PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON>,
widow of the late civil rights leader <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON>, told
<PERSON>Kemp</PERSON>.
   ``From what we've heard you say, we think you mean business,''
she said. ``If something happens and there is not the follow
through, you're going to have a lot of disappointed people.''
   Kemp met privately with <PERSON>Mrs. King</PERSON> and her sons, then attended a
meeting with black leaders.
   Kemp, an unsuccessful Republican presidential hopeful who has
sought to broaden the party's appeal to blacks, promised to work to
eliminate discrimination in housing, to support affirmative action
efforts and to encourage more housing for the poor.
   ``I'm commited to a vigorous effort to expand the housing stock,
both public and ot going to solve the problem,'' said <PERSON>Naim
Sheikh</PERSON>, the owner of a shop selling leather goods who called for a
law that would prevent such books from being written again.
   ``There must be some way that governments can approve a
resolution that in future no writer should have a right to write
against any prophet _ Mohammed, Jesus or Moses,'' he said.
   Moslems revere Mohammed as the prophet who brought <ORGANIZATION>Allah</ORGANIZATION>'s
revelations to mankind in the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, the holy book of Islam.
   ``But do I personally agree with the ayatollah? It doesn't
matter,'' said <PERSON>Sheikh</PERSON>, one of the many Moslem Bangladeshis living in
the Brick Lane area.
   ``You can't stop the ayatollah. You can't stop the people who
will do the job ... Anyone who kills <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> will become a hero in
the Islamic world.''
   Like Sheikh, most Moslems acknowledged they haven't read the
book. Most learned about it at one of the five mosques located in a
one-square-mile area of this district, from leaflets, or from
television reports.
   ``He insulted our prophet, our religion. From TV we know this,''
said a shopkeeper selling sticky sweets who refused to give his name.
   Even though they haven't read the book, they are sure it insults
their prophet and are quick to say so when the novel is mentioned.
   ``Our older people read it, they say it's wrong, so we believe
them,'' <PERSON>Nassim Khan</PERSON>, a Pakistani Moslem, said as he ate lunch at a
modest tandoori restaurant. ``They've been studying for years and
years and they should know.''
   <PERSON>Maqbool Ali-Kassam</PERSON>, waiting for his takeout tea, boomed from
across the room: ``Anyone who denies the religion of Islam shall be
killed.''
   Ali-Kassam, a taxi cab radio controller who calls himself a
follower of the ayatollah, said he believes <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> deliberately
meant to insult Islam.
   Dozens of drivers from his company stayed at the office until
early <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, he said, arguing about the book and the
execution order. ``Some said he didn't mean anything about Islam,
others wanted him killed.''
   Many Moslems believe <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>, 41, insults Mohammed by portraying
him as a character called Mahound, a prophet of a city called
Jahilia. Mahound was a medieval corruption of the word Mohammed.
   They are especially angered by one sequence in which prostitutes
are given the names of some of Mohammed's nine wives and by the
book's implication that Mohammed, not Allah, may have been the real
author of the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>.
   Rushdie was born into a Moslem family in <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, and
educated in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>. He lives in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. His novel has sold more
than 100,000 copies since it was published in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>September</DATE>
to critical acclaim.
   ``Previously Mohammed has been criticized, but not in this naked
way,'' said <PERSON>Abul Khair</PERSON>, a top officer at the <ORGANIZATION>Sonali Bank</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>'s state bank, on Brick Lane. ``It is intolerable for
Moslems.''
   But he doesn't agree with the ayatollah. ``We don't want
violence. Islam is a peaceful religion,'' he said.
   Restaurant manager <PERSON>Asaad Ramjaun</PERSON>, a Mauritian immigrant, said of
Rushdie: ``I think he's the devil himself.''
   ``We understand this is a free society, but I think this is
freedom of abuse,'' he said. ``But since this is a free society _ he
shouldn't be killed. He should be given a chance.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1621EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Rushdie Bjt   12-24 0646</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Rushdie, Bjt,0809</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rushdie Embraces Islam, Won't Seek Paperback `Satanic Verses'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LON16</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BARR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that he has embraced
Islam and has given up his push for paperback publication of ``The
Satanic Verses,'' the book which brought him a death sentence from
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> nearly two years ago.
   He also pledged, in a statement released by a local Islamic
leader, that he would permit no further translations of the book.
   However, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> defended his book as a ``moral fable'' about a
character who ``has lost his mind because he has lost his faith.''
   Rushdie has been in hiding under police guard since <DATE>February
1989</DATE>, when Iranian leader <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON> sentenced him
to death for blasphemy.
   Iran offered a <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> bounty for <ORGANIZATION>Rushdie</ORGANIZATION>'s death, and
Iranian authorities reconfirmed the death sentence and the bounty
earlier this month.
   Rushdie's statement was released by <PERSON>Dr. Hesham el-Essawy</PERSON>,
president of the Islamic Society for the <ORGANIZATION>Promotion of Religious
Tolerance</ORGANIZATION>. He said <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> typed the statement himself following a
meeting with Islamic scholars.
   In his statement, the author declared that he did ``not agree
with any statement in my novel `The Satanic Verses' uttered by any
of the characters who insults the prophet Mohammed, or casts
aspersions upon Islam, or upon the authenticity of the holy <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>,
or who rejects the divinity of Allah.''
   <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> said in a telephone hookup with a news conference that
it is up to Iranian leaders whether to withdraw the death sentence.
But he added, ``I feel a lot safer tonight than I felt yesterday.''
   Many Moslems worldwide objected to <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s use of the names of
the Prophet <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON>'s wives for the prostitutes in his novel and
the implication that <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> wrote the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, Islam's holy book,
instead of receiving it from God.
   El-Essawy said <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> now had a ``clean slate'' with the Moslem
world because he had only now professed his belief that ``there is
no God but <LOCATION>Allah</LOCATION> and that <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> is his last prophet.''
   In addition to el-Essawy, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> met with two imams from the
<ORGANIZATION>Regent</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Park Mosque</LOCATION> - <PERSON>Dr. Zaki Badawi</PERSON>, principal of the <ORGANIZATION>Moslem
College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Dr. Hohammed Ali Mahgoub</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s secretary
of state for endowment and head of the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Council for Islamic
Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, as well as <PERSON>Yousef el-Sharkawy</PERSON>, second secretary at the
<ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Embassy</ORGANIZATION>.
   Rushdie's statement was welcomed by other Moslem leaders, who
nonetheless demanded that the book be withdrawn entirely from
circulation.
   ``Until the book is completely removed our campaign goes on,''
said <PERSON>Sher Azam</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Council</ORGANIZATION> for Mosques in <LOCATION>Bradford</LOCATION>, where the
book had been publicly burned.
   <PERSON>Iqbal Sacranie</PERSON>, joint convener of the <ORGANIZATION>United Kingdom Committee
on Islamic Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s statement was a positive step,
but also called for ``the withdrawal from circulation of this
blasphemous book.''
   El-Essawy argued that <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> could not be sentenced to death as
an apostate because he had not been a believing Moslem when he
wrote the novel.
   He characterized <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> as a ``convert,'' and quoted the author
as saying, ``There is no difference between <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> and Islam.''
   ``This is the community that is close to my heart,'' <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>
told the news conference. ``To come closer to it has given me a
great deal of joy.''
   He said he would not permit any further translations of the book
``while any risk of further offense exists,'' and added that he
would ``continue to work for a better understanding of Islam in the
world, as I have always attempted to do in the past.''
   No one was available for comment <DATE>Monday</DATE> at Viking Penguin,
publishers the hardback book. However, the publisher had previously
shown no enthusiasm for a paperback, a position that had drawn
criticism from <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>.
   If there was no paperback, he said in an interview in <DATE>January</DATE>
with the Independent on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> newspaper, ``in a few years the book
simply won't be there for anyone who wants to read it. It will, in
all practical terms, have been suppressed.''
   ``The Satanic Verses'' has sold more than 1 million copies in
English - almost three-quarters of those in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> - and
was on the <DATE>Sunday</DATE> Times of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s best-seller list for nearly a
year. It has been translated into 15 languages and banned in more
than 20 countries.
   Rushdie, born in <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, and now a naturalized British
citizen, has been in hiding since <DATE>Feb. 14, 1989</DATE>. His native country
was the first to ban the book, in <DATE>October 1988</DATE>.
   In <DATE>September 1989</DATE>, a trade survey found booksellers in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>
divided on the question of stocking any paperback edition. Forty
percent said they would not handle it, <PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT> said they would,
according to <ORGANIZATION>Publishing News</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1414EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Rushdie 3rdLd-Writethru a0498 12-24 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Rushdie, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0498,0968</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rushdie Says He Will Not Authorize `Satantic Verses' Paperback</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with comment from Rushdie and Moslems.
No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BARR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> has embraced Islam and promised not
to authorize a paperback version of his controversial novel ``The
Satanic Verses,'' a group of Islamic and Egyptian officials
announced today.
   Earlier this year, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> had insisted on the need for a
paperback version, but a spokeswoman for his defense committee
confirmed that the statement was genuine.
   In a statement released by <PERSON>Dr. Hesham el-Essawy</PERSON>, president of
the Islamic Society for the <ORGANIZATION>Promotion of Religious Tolerance</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> also declared that he did not agree with any statement
uttered by characters in the book that cast aspersions on Islam,
questioned the authenticity of the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, or rejected the divinity
of Allah.
   He also agreed not to authorize any further translations of the
work.
   Rushdie did not disavow the book, but insisted today that it was
a moral fable. All the things that Moslems found insulting, he
said, ``take place in the dream of a man who has lost his mind. He
has lost his mind because he has lost his faith.''
   In a telephone hookup with a news conference organized by
el-Essawy, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> said it was up to the government of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> to
remove the death sentence against him. ``I feel a lot safer tonight
than I felt yesterday,'' he added.
   Rushdie has been in hiding under police guard since <DATE>February
1989</DATE>, when Iranian leader <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON> said the
writer deserved death as a blasphemer. Iran offered a <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>
bounty for <ORGANIZATION>Rushdie</ORGANIZATION>'s death.
   ``This is the way we hope that will earn <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s release from
his predicament. This is how we intend to make him a free man,''
said el-Essawy.
   El-Essawy argued, as he has in the past, that <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> could not
be sentenced to death as an apostate because he was not a believing
Moslem.
   Now that <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> has embraced the faith, by ``declaring there is
no God but <LOCATION>Allah</LOCATION> and that <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> is his last prophet,'' el-Essawy
said that ``the slate is wiped clean.''
   El-Essawy characterized <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> as a ``convert,'' and quoted the
author as saying, ``There is no difference between <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> and
Islam.''
   Other British Moslems who have been prominent in the controversy
demanded more from <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>.
   ``It puzzles me that he hasn't gone far enough to remove the
hardback, if that's the intention. The Moslem community has been
suffering for a long time,'' said <PERSON>Sher Azam</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Council</ORGANIZATION> for
Mosques in <LOCATION>Bradford</LOCATION>, where the book had been publicly burned.
   ``Until the book is completely removed our campaign goes on,''
<PERSON>Azam</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Iqbal Sacranie</PERSON>, joint convener of the <ORGANIZATION>UK Committee on Islamic
Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s statement was a positive step. However,
``It seems to us that the most appropriate course of action ... is
the withdrawal from circulation of this blasphemous book.''
   Rushdie recently has come out of hiding for a television
interview, and on <DATE>Dec. 5</DATE> he appeared at a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> bookshop to sign
copies of his latest book, ``Haroun and the Sea of Stories.''
   Iran severed diplomatic relations with <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> over ``The
Satanic Verses'' but ties were restored in <DATE>October</DATE> after an
18-month break. On <DATE>Dec. 9</DATE>, however, Iranian Minister of Culture
<PERSON>Mohammad Khatami</PERSON> said the death sentence against <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> could not
be revoked.
   El-Essawy said he met with <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> in a secure
location.
   He said they were joined at the meeting by <PERSON>Dr. Mohammed Ali
Mahgoub</PERSON>, an Egyptian government official who heads the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme
Council of Scholars of Islamic Affairs</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Youssef Ahmed El Sharkawy</PERSON>,
2nd Secretary at the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Embassy</ORGANIZATION> and two clergy from the
<ORGANIZATION>Regent's Park Mosque</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   According to el-Essawy, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> made four points in the
statement:
<PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> is his last prophet.
   ``2. To declare that I do not agree with any statement in my
novel `The Satanic Verses' uttered by any of the characters who
insults the prophet Mohammed, or casts aspersions upon Islam, or
upon the authenticity of the holy koran, or who rejects the
divinity of Allah.
   ``3. I undertake not to publish the paperback edition of `The
Satanic Verses' or to permit any further agreement for translations
into other languages while any risk of further offense exists.
   ``4. I will continue to work for a better understanding of Islam
in the world, as I have always attempted to do in the past.''
   ``The Satanic Verses'' has sold more than 1 million copies in
English - almost three-quarters of those in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> - and
was on the <DATE>Sunday</DATE> Times of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s best-seller list for nearly a
year. It has been translated into 15 languages and banned in more
than 20 countries.
   Rushdie, born in <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> and now a naturalized British citizen,
has been in hiding since <DATE>Feb. 14, 1989</DATE>.
   Moslems worldwide objected to <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s use of the names of the
Prophet <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON>'s wives for the prostitutes in his novel and the
implication that <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> wrote the Koran, Islam's holy book,
instead of receiving it from God.
   In <DATE>September 1989</DATE>, a trade survey found booksellers in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>
divided on the question of stocking any paperback edition. Forty
percent said they would not handle it, <PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT> said they would,
according to <ORGANIZATION>Publishing News</ORGANIZATION>.
   A <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> newspaper, The Observer, reported last year that <PERSON>Viking
Penguin</PERSON> had decided to publish the paperback in <DATE>1990</DATE>, but the
company never made any announcement.
   In <DATE>January</DATE>, the company said it was unlikely to announce its
plans in advance because of the security implications.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890214-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-14-89 1122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SatanicVerses-Rushdie     02-14 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Satanic Verses-Rushdie,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>Author of Satanic Verses Says Islamic Fundamentalists Need Criticism</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Satanic Verses</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE> the furor caused by his
book ``The Satanic Verses'' shows Moslem fundamentalist leaders in a
bad light and makes him wish he had been more critical.
   ``Frankly, I wish I had written a more critical book,'' he told
<ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> ``This Morning.'' ``I mean, a religion that claims, that is able
to behave like this; religious leaders, let's say, who are able to
behave like this, and then say that this is a religion which must be
above any kind of whisper or criticism, that doesn't add up.''
   He added: ``It seems to me that Islamic fundamentalists could do
with a little bit of criticism right now.''
   Rushdie regretted the violence caused by opposition to his book,
but denied that it was blasphemous, as some Moslems contend.
   ``It's not true that this book is a blasphemy against Islam.
   ``I doubt very much that (Iranian Ayatollah Ruhollah) <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON> or
anybody else in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> has read the book or more than selected
extracts out of context.
   ``Obviously it's horrifying that people are willing to proceed in
this way against what is, after all, one novel in the face of the
entire history of Islam.''
   Asked how he reacts to a death threat from <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> said:
   ``I think I have to take them very seriously indeed.''
   He told <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> ``Nightline'' on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>:
   ``The blood is on the hands of people who inflame the feelings of
people who unfortunately have not and cannot read the book ...
   ``The idea that this is somehow an attack on the religion shows
an absolute failure to understand what fiction is,'' he said.
   Of the novel itself, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>:
   ``The sad thing is, of course, the book isn't really about Islam.
It's about migration and metamorphosis and all sorts of things.
There's one section where there are two dream sequences in the book,
in which what I've tried to do is write about the birth of a
religion which obviously is like Islam, but is a fictional departure
from Islam, and in that I've done it from a secular point of view.
   ``If you can't believe in the literal truth of God transmitting
words to a prophet ... then it seems to be a legitimate fictional
exercise to say what's really happening, what goes on, what is the
nature of revelation? ... How does a religion come into the world,
what compromises does it face, is it tolerant or intolerant?''
   He spoke about one section where a creature appearing to be like
Mohammed, the prophet Moslems believe is a messenger of <LOCATION>Allah</LOCATION>, is
given the name for the devil.
   ``The novel is about showing how devils are not always
devilish,'' <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>. ``One of the novel's major emphases is
to reclaim negative images ...''
   ``My views don't have to be the same as the views of a fictional
character. Finally, the fictional character is actually losing his
mind, he's going insane, he's a paranoid schizophrenic.
   ``Now, when you've gone to that length to write fiction, it's
very odd to have it judged as if you were writing some kind of, as
they say, thinly veiled attack. It was never my intention.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021589-0078 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 18823 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 15, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 13; Column 1; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1099 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
KHOMEINI SAYS AUTHOR OF 'SATANIC VERSES' SHOULD BE KILLED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES P. WALLACE and DAN FISHER, Times Staff Writers 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NICOSIA, Cyprus 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As anger over an allegedly blasphemous novel continued to gather force in the 
Islamic world, <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s spiritual leader, the <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON>, said 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that the author and publishers of the book should be killed. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Tehran Radio</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON> issued a statement saying in part: "I inform the 
proud Muslim people of the world that the author of 'The Satanic Verses,' a 
book which is against Islam, the prophet and the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, and all those involved 
in its publication who were aware of its content, are hereby sentenced to 
death." 
</P>
<P>
Author <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>, an Indian-born British citizen, told the <ORGANIZATION>British 
Broadcasting Corp.</ORGANIZATION> that he takes <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>'s threat "very seriously indeed." Not 
long afterward, he was reported to be in hiding and under police protection 
somewhere outside <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> offices of his publishers, the <ORGANIZATION>Penguin Group</ORGANIZATION>, were also under police 
guard. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Outraged Responses 
</P>
<P>
What <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON> called a "sentence of death" was the latest in a series of 
outraged responses to the "The Satanic Verses." 
</P>
<P>
Although few in the Muslim world say they have read the prize-winning 
allegorical novel about <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s treatment of its colonial subjects, the book 
has provoked widespread outrage. In <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, where the book was first 
published, there have been public book burnings in areas that have large Muslim 
communities. 
</P>
<P>
The book has been banned in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South 
Africa</LOCATION>. In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, Islamic militants have called for it 
to be withdrawn from the market and for Rushdie to publicly ask "forgiveness 
from <LOCATION>Almighty Allah</LOCATION> for the great insult which he has brought up." 
</P>
<P>
Publication of the book in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> sparked two days of rioting in 
Muslim areas of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>. Over the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, demonstrators stoned the 
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Cultural Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION> and five people were killed when riot police 
fired at the demonstrators. An Indian was killed <DATE>Monday</DATE> at a demonstration in 
<LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, where protests continued <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Khomeini was quoted as 
saying <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that "The Satanic Verses" was written and published "in 
opposition to Islam." 
</P>
<P>
"I call on all zealous Muslims to execute them quickly, wherever they find 
them, so that no one will dare to insult Islamic sanctity," <ORGANIZATION>Tehran Radio</ORGANIZATION> quoted 
him as saying. "Whoever is killed doing this will be regarded as a martyr and 
will go directly to heaven." 
</P>
<P>
The Iranian government declared today a day of national mourning to protest 
against the decision to publish "poisonous and insulting subject matter 
concerning Islam, the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION> and the blessed prophet." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Tour Being Reconsidered 
</P>
<P>
Followers of Islam believe that the Prophet <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> is God's messenger on 
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and that the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, Islam's holy book, consists of revelations from the 
<LOCATION>Almighty</LOCATION> as given to Mohammed. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, a spokesman for <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s agent, <PERSON>Gillon Aitken</PERSON>, said a planned book 
promotion tour of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, scheduled to begin later this week, is now 
under review. 
</P>
<P>
British Foreign Secretary <PERSON>Geoffrey Howe</PERSON> expressed his "very real concern," and 
the British government was generally adopting a cautious stance on the threat 
to <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>, for fear of jeopardizing the safety of a British citizen imprisoned 
in <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> as an alleged spy. 
</P>
<P>
Iranian Information Minister <PERSON>Mohammed Mohammedi-Reyshahri</PERSON> was quoted by the 
official news agency <ORGANIZATION>IRNA</ORGANIZATION> as saying that a court has completed its proceedings 
against British businessman <PERSON>Roger Cooper</PERSON>, held since <DATE>December, 1985</DATE>, and had 
imposed a "heavy sentence" on him. The minister added, without elaborating, 
that final judgment is still under consideration. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> resumed diplomatic relations last <DATE>November</DATE>, and the British 
authorities had hoped that <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON> might be released as part of an amnesty 
announced to mark <DATE>last week</DATE>'s 10th anniversary of the Islamic revolution. 
</P>
<P>
Despite expressing concern about the danger to his life, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>, in his 
interview with the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION>, was not in a mood to back down. 
</P>
<P>
"Obviously, at a personal level it's very worrying," the 41-year-old, 
Bombay-born author said in a brief film clip shown on the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Independent 
Television News</ORGANIZATION> here <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. "But I think, beyond that, it shows this is 
a later stage in a campaign which began with smears and vilifications and 
distortions of the book which has escalated to all sorts of levels of violence. 
And, frankly, I wish I had written a more critical book. 
</P>
<P>
"A religion that is able to behave like this -- religious leaders, let's say, 
who are able to behave like this -- and then say that this is a religion that 
must be above any kind of whisper of criticism; I mean, that doesn't add up. It 
seems to me that Islamic fundamentalists could do with a little criticism right 
now." 
</P>
<P>
In a statement distributed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>, <ORGANIZATION>Penguin</ORGANIZATION>'s Viking unit, whose 
trademark appears on the British and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> editions of <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s novel, 
commented: "Neither we nor the author of this novel published the book with 
intent to offend. We very much regret the distress the book has caused." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'<ORGANIZATION>Tragic Loss of Life</ORGANIZATION>' 
</P>
<P>
Referring to six people killed in anti-Rushdie demonstrations, the Viking 
statement said, "We are appalled at the tragic loss of life that has already 
occurred and deplore calls to future violence." 
</P>
<P>
A spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Penguin Group</ORGANIZATION> confirmed that it has stepped up its security 
precautions after the <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON> threat. The spokesman refused to elaborate. 
</P>
<P>
The threat to <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> is being taken seriously. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> has about a million 
Muslims among its 55 million people, and they have been an increasingly 
militant minority. 
</P>
<P>
The People's Moujahedeen of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>, a dissident exile group, called <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>'s 
action "absurd" and "hysterical." 
</P>
<P>
Rushdie, who was born in <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> but came to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> as a 14-year-old schoolboy, 
has described himself as a lapsed Muslim but insists that his book is not 
intended to be anti-religious. A British reviewer termed it "a sort of 'Last 
Temptation of Mohammed,' " in the spirit of the controversial Greek novel and 
American film, "The Last Temptation of Christ." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> said in an interview last <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with the Guardian newspaper that he 
was "very upset" by the deaths that resulted from demonstrations against his 
book in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>. However, he said: "The deaths are not on my conscience. I am 
a writer trying to deal with real issues. I have not arranged any marches on 
embassies or arranged for shots to be fired. . . . I am completely horrified. 
The idea that people should directly or indirectly be dead as a result of (the 
book) is hard to believe." 
</P>
<P>
Wallace reported from <LOCATION>Nicosia</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Fisher</PERSON> from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Forced Into Hiding Salman Rushdie holding his controversial novel, "The 
Satanic Verses," at a London reception last month. Iran's Ayatollah Khomeini 
said Tuesday that the author and publishers of the book have been "sentenced to 
death," and Rushdie reportedly went into hiding. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
KHOMEINI, RUHOLLAH (AYATOLLAH); CENSORSHIP; THREATS; BOOKS; RUSHDIE, SALMAN; 
ISLAM; MUSLIMS; ENGLAND -- FOREIGN RELATIONS -- IRAN; PRISONERS -- IRAN; 
SATANIC VERSES (BOOK) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890223-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-23-89 0512EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ThatBook     02-23 0875</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-That Book,0897</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Lyrical, Satirical _ And Bewildering _ `Satanic Verses'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Thursday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILLEL ITALIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>'s ``Satanic Verses'' is a dizzying
547-page journey through countless plots, subplots, satire and
philosophical discussions.
   It also is That Book, the work that has so enraged the Islamic
world that the author has been condemned to death. The controversy
has revived age-old questions of censorship and freedom of religion.
   Lyrical, scathing, inquisitive and at times bewildering, the
novel deals with preconceptions of good and evil, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s
treatment of illegal aliens, the desire by Indians to become
assimilated into British culture and, most notably, the birth of the
Islamic faith.
   Rushdie, a 41-year-old <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> native of Moslem parents, writes in
a stream-of-consciousness style that leaves the reader alternately
exhilarated, bewildered and _ depending on one's religious and
political orientation _ outraged.
   The novel has been condemned by Moslems for its dream sequences
that portray the prophet <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> as a womanizer, a coward willing
to compromise his faith for general acceptance and a conniving
businessman who makes up laws to suit his own purposes.
   It also contains a sequence in which a Persian scribe alters the
holy laws as dictated by <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON>, who is referred to in the book as
Mahound.
   Moslems revere Mohammed as the prophet who brought them <ORGANIZATION>Allah</ORGANIZATION>'s
revelations in the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, the holy book of Islam.
   The book prompted <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON> to put a
price on the author's life, sending <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> into hiding, along with
his wife.
   ``The Satanic Verses'' begins with terrorists blowing up a jet en
route to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. Two passengers _ <PERSON>Gibreel Farishta</PERSON>, an Indian actor
who specializes in religious roles, and <PERSON>Saladin Chamcha</PERSON>, a British
radio star able to reproduce a myriad of voices _ fall from the
plane and survive. Rushdie writes:
   ```To be born again,' sang Gibreel Farishta tumbling from the
heavens, `first you have to die. Ho ji! Ho ji! To land upon the
bosomy earth, first one needs to fly. Tat-taa! Taka-thun! How to
ever smile again, if first you won't cry? How to win the darling's
love, mister, without a sigh? Baba, if you want to get born again
...'''
   The two men emerge on an English coast. Gibreel begins to assume
an ``angelic glow,'' while <PERSON>Saladin</PERSON> grows horns and hooves and is
arrested as an illegal immigrant.
   The novel's turning point comes when Gibreel, whose halo dazzles
police, denies to authorities that he knows <PERSON>Saladin</PERSON>. By having
Gibreel commit an evil act wearing a halo and subjecting <PERSON>Saladin</PERSON> to
the brutal treatment of the English police, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> confounds
reality. Which one is evil? Which one is good?
   The book's second, fourth and sixth chapters, ``Mahound,''
``Ayesha'' and ``Return to Jahilia,'' contain the most controversial
elements.
   Gibreel dreams about the city of <LOCATION>Jahilia</LOCATION>, built entirely of sand.
One of <LOCATION>Jahilia</LOCATION>'s citizens is Mahound, a
``businessman-turned-prophet'' who is starting a new religion.
Unfortunately for Mahound, the city already has 360 gods and little
use for more.
   Mahound's chance for recognition comes when the head of the
city's ruling council proposes a deal: If <ORGANIZATION>Mahound</ORGANIZATION>'s Allah (the
Islamic god) will accept three of the local gods (Lat, Uzza and
Manat) as archangels in his sect, his religion will receive
certification and <ORGANIZATION>Mahound</ORGANIZATION> will have a seat on the council.
   Mahound, always the practical businessman, sees the deal as a
good opportunity to attract converts. So he climbs a mountain to
consult with the archangel, none other than Gibreel himself. Rashdie
writes of Mahound's moral dilemma:
   ```The souls of the city, of the world, surely they are worth
three more angels? Is Allah so unbending that he will not embrace
three more to save the human race?''
   Although he does not actually hear an answer, Mahound undergoes
what he considers a revelation in the archangel's presence,
believing he should make the deal.
   But he soon learns that the supposedly divine message did not
come from <PERSON>Gibreel</PERSON> but the Devil, who had been impersonating the
archangel. Mahound renounces the satanic ``verses'' and substitutes
these words, which closely follow the spirit of the actual <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>,
about Lat, Uzza and Manat:
   ``They are but names you have dreamed of, you and your fathers.
Allah invests no authority in them.''
   Rushdie takes the story a step further by having Gibreel claim
that both answers came from him, blurring the distinction between
God and Satan.
   Mahound and his followers eventually settle in the ``friendly
oasis'' of Yathrib, just as Mohammed journeyed from <LOCATION>Mecca</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Medina</LOCATION>.
In Yathrib, Mahound proceeds to dictate to the Persian scribe Salman
the rules of the new religion as proscribed by <ORGANIZATION>Gibreel</ORGANIZATION>.
   However, <PERSON>Salman</PERSON> becomes convinced that Mahound is making up the
rules himself and decides to test his leader by deliberately
changing what is recited to him. The scribe, fearing for his life if
Mahound discovers his trick, flees <PERSON>Yathrib</PERSON> and concludes his part of
the story by stating, ``It's his Word against mine.''
   Rushdie has said his characters ``seek to become fully human by
facing up to the great facts of love, death and (with or without
God), the life of the soul. Outside it, the forces of humanity are
on the march.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890213-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-13-89 1508EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pakistan-Book 1stLd-Writethru a0546 02-13 0839</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Book, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0546,0857</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fundamentalist Moslems Say Rushdie Novel Must be Banned</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf ``Rushdie was ...'' with 2 grafs with more background.</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto ISL1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY RENFREW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem fundamentalists around the
world demand that <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>'s novel ``The Satanic Verses'' be
banned as blasphemy against Islam, and this <DATE>weekend</DATE> the campaign
turned violent.
   At least five people were killed and more than 80 injured <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
when police fired on a mob trying to storm the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Information
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>. The protesters demanded the book be banned in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   Fundamentalists say the book does not recognize Islam as the one
true religion and ridicules the most precious Moslem beliefs.
Pakistan and other Moslem nations banned the book after its
publication last year.
   Rushdie, 41, was born in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to Moslem parents and educated in
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, where he lives. His other books include ``Midnight's
Children,'' which won <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s prestigious Booker prize, ``Shame''
and ``The Jaguar Smile.''
   The literary success of ``The Satanic Verses,'' a complex work
that focuses on good and evil, has been confined to a fairly small
intellectual readership in Western nations. In <DATE>November</DATE>, the book
won the ``new novel'' category in the annual literary competition
sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Whitbread</ORGANIZATION> brewing giant, but it did not win the
overall <ORGANIZATION>Whitbread</ORGANIZATION> prize.
   Leaders of the <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION> march said it was intended to be
peaceful but police reacted improperly.
the protest apparently was inspired by reviews last week in
international news magazines. One official said: ``The reviews had
the first details anyone had about the book. Nobody here has read
the book.''
   ``The Satanic Verses'' is a rambling fantasy on the birth of
religion, modern history and human relations. It begins with two men
tumbling skyward from a jumbo jet destroyed by a terrorist bomb and
chronicles their adventures.
   A part of the novel fictionalizes certain episodes from the
<LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, the Moslem holy book, and the life of the prophet Mohammed in
what Western book critics say is clearly satire. They have praised
the book for imaginative vision and depth.
   The author says his book is a work of fiction that does not
attack Islam, contains no blasphemy and is not intended to offend
anyone.
   ``It is not a source of satisfaction to me to be banned in the
Moslem world,'' he said in a recent interview with the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>, a
Pakistani magazine.
   Moslem leaders describe the novel as an attack on Mohammed
intended to insult Moslems and lead them astray.
   Syed <PERSON>Mohammed Younus Kazmi</PERSON>, a Pakistani Moslem leader, said:
``The book has fictitious characters that carricature the holy
prophet and his companions. The book contains insulting and
derogratory remarks.''
   Kazmi and other Islamic theologians say the book must be banned
because it does not treat Mohammed as the prophet of the world's one
true religion. They believe <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> and the Koran must be portrayed
only as representing divine truth.
   ``<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> has offended millions of Moslems around the world,''
<PERSON>Kazmi</PERSON> said in an interview. ``Such a person cannot be allowed to do
these things.''
   Fundamentalist leaders claimed <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s march was not an
anti-American protest, even though many of their followers see the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> as a corrupt secular culture and enemy of Islam.
Protesters chanted ``American dogs'' and other slogans against the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   ``It was not an attack on the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. We just hoped to
create moral support for our cause to stop this unholy book being
printed again,'' <PERSON>Kazmi</PERSON> said.
   Leaflets circulated by fundamentalist groups characterize the
novel as a blasphemous, semi-pornographic attack that says the
prophet was inspired by the devil, his wife was a prostitute and his
companions were evil.
   ``There are insulting remarks in this book,'' said <PERSON>Mohammed
Sadiq</PERSON>, a theology student. ``There are lies in this book. We want
this book banned in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and around the world.''
   According to the author, his novel has been distorted by
fundamentalists who have not read it and oppose any idea that does
not reflect their fanatical literal faith. He said he has received
death threats.
   Rushdie has declared himself fascinated by religion and its
development and role in history.
   He has been quoted as saying religions are ``codes with which
human beings have tried to understand their presence on the planet
and discuss their moral behavior. My point of view is that of a
secular human being. I do not believe in supernatural entities,
whether Christian, <LOCATION>Jewish</LOCATION>, Moslem or Hindu.''
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Benazir Bhutto</PERSON> and other government leaders called
the protest at the American center an attack by fundamentalist
parties trying to drive her from office by straining relations with
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s ally, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   Rushdie says he has every right to deal with Islam in a creative
fashion, and ``I am not going to run away from the subject because
it is my subject and it is my birthright and nobody can take that
away from me.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1521EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-RushdieText     12-24 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Rushdie Text,0205</SECOND>
<HEAD>Text of Statement by Salman Rushdie</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Britain-Rushdie, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Following is the text of a statement by <PERSON>Salman
Rushdie</PERSON> released <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <PERSON>Dr. Hesham el-Essawy</PERSON>, president of the
Islamic Society for the <ORGANIZATION>Promotion of Religious Tolerance</ORGANIZATION> in the
<LOCATION>United Kingdon</LOCATION>:
   ``In the presence of his excellency the Egyptian secretary of
state for endowment and head of the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Council of Scholars of
Islamic Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Dr. Mohammed Ali Mahgoub</PERSON>, and a group of Islamic
scholars:
<PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> is his last prophet.
   ``2. To declare that I do not agree with any statement in my
novel ``The Satanic Verses'' uttered by any of the characters who
insults the prophet Mohammed, or casts aspersions upon Islam, or
upon the authenticity of the holy <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, or who rejects the
divinity of Allah.
   ``3. I undertake not to publish the paperback edition of ``The
Satanic Verses'' or to permit any further agreement for
translations into other languages while any risk of further offense
exists.
   ``4. I will continue to work for a better understanding of Islam
in the world, as I have always attempted to do in the past.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900908-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-08-90 0351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Rushdie-Response     09-08 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Rushdie-Response,0502</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rushdie Publisher to Issue Book That Answers `Satanic Verses'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOMBAY, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Islamic scholar has written a book he
says will refute ``The Satanic Verses,'' the novel that sent author
<PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> into hiding to escape death at the hands of enraged
Moslems.
   The new book is scheduled for release next <DATE>April</DATE> by Penguin,
which also published the Rushdie novel in <DATE>1988</DATE>, setting off
worldwide protests, riots, diplomatic standoffs and debates on
freedom of expression.
   The Bombay-born <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>, now a naturalized British citizen, has
been in hiding since <DATE>Feb. 14, 1989</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s late leader, the
<PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON>, ordered Moslems to execute <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> for
blasphemy.
   <PERSON>Rafiq Zakaria</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> Moslem whose 70,000-word manuscript has
been accepted by the London-based Penguin publishing company, said
his book is to expose the ``baselessness of whatever Rushdie
attributed to the prophet'' Mohammed.
   He described his book, ``Muhammad and the Quran,'' as ``a case
for Islam.''
   ``I believe that the evidence is so overwhelmingly against what
<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> has written that the best answer is to convict him
intellectually and not physically,'' <PERSON>Zakaria</PERSON> said.
   Moslems worldwide objected to <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> using the names of
Mohammed's wives for prostitutes in his novel and the implication
that the prophet wrote the Koran _ Islam's holy book _ instead of
receiving it from God.
   A week after <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>'s death edict, <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> became the
flashpoint of anti-Rushdie protests that spread to other Indian
cities. In the following days, at least 19 people died in riots and
clashes with police in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and neighboring <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and several other countries banned ``The
Satanic Verses.'' Later, <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> severed diplomatic ties with <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>,
accusing the British government of supporting <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>.
   ``I have traced the campaign of calumny against Islam right from
the birth of the prophet and culminating in <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s book,'' said
<PERSON>Zakaria</PERSON>.
   A senior editor of <ORGANIZATION>Penguin Books Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> said a paperback
edition of ``Muhammad and the Quran'' will be published by <DATE>April</DATE>.
   The editor said, however, the book was not planned as a reaction
to ``The Satanic Verses.''
   ``It is an incredibly impressive study of the thinking of Islam
looking at Western prejudices,'' she said, speaking on condition of
anonymity.
   Zakaria, a 64-year-old academician and author of seven previous
books, described his latest effort as ``maybe a reaction to the
vituperative attacks and innuendos by <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> and his
predecessors.''
   ``I have tried to show how most of it is based on deep-rooted
prejudice first between Moslems and Jews and then between Moslems
and Christians,'' he said.
   The author attributed the ``unfortunately'' large sales of
<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s book to <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>'s death threat but said he neither
condemned the order nor upheld it because, ``by doing so I take a
pontifical position.''
   Nobody can take a pontifical position in Islam because the
religion does not recognize priesthood and teaches that there is no
intermediary between man and God, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890307-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-89 0240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Britain-Moslems     03-07 0993</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Britain-Moslems,1026</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rushdie Case Reveals Gap Between Europeans, Moslem Minorities</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The furor over <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>'s novel ``The
Satanic Verses'' highlights a gulf between <LOCATION>Western Europe</LOCATION> and its
Moslem minorities. Here is a report from an English city with a
large Moslem community.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRADFORD, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The furor over <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>'s novel ``The
Satanic Verses'' highlights a gulf between <LOCATION>Western Europe</LOCATION> and its
Moslem minorities. Here is a report from an English city with a
large Moslem community.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901027-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-27-90 1951EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-Rushdie     10-27 0259</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Rushdie,0294</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rushdie Says He Wants Reconciliation With Islam</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> says he is optimistic that he can
work out a reconciliation with Moslems, but an Iranian leader says
the death sentence against the Indian-born author of ``The Satanic
Verses'' can never be lifted.
   ``I have to hope that the atmosphere is gradually changing. I
think there's various signs that it might be,'' <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>CBS
News</ORGANIZATION> correspondent <PERSON>Mike Wallace</PERSON> in an interview for <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s
edition of ``60 Minutes.''
   In a separate interview, Rajei-Khorrasani, a powerful leader in
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s parliament, said the death sentence cannot be lifted
``because it is a religious fact, which remains there forever.''
   Rushdie, 43, a Bombay-born British subject, has been in hiding
under police guard since <DATE>Feb. 14, 1989</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s spiritual
leader, <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON>, declared his novel an affront
to Islam and ordered Moslems to kill him. Khomeini died <DATE>June 3,
1989</DATE>.
   Iranian clerics offered a <MONEY>$5.2-million</MONEY> bounty for <ORGANIZATION>Rushdie</ORGANIZATION>'s
assassination.
   Among parts of the ``The Satanic Verses'' many Moslems find
offensive are a scene in which prostitutes are given the names of
the prophet <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON>'s wives, and implications that <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> wrote
the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, the Moslem holy book.
   <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> said he never meant to insult the Moslem world.
   ``If I'm accused of calling the prophet's wives whores, I didn't
do it,'' he said.
   ``I'm not this kind of creature with horns and a tail that's
been painted,'' he said. ``There is actually very little in
`Satanic Verses' that hasn't been, in fact, quite commonplace
discussion in the Moslem world for hundreds of years.''
   <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said he met with the author at a police officers' club
on the outskirts of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890329-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-29-89 1756EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Belgium-Islam     03-29 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Belgium-Islam,0564</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Moslem Leader, Aide Shot Dead At Brussels Mosque</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PHILIPPE NEURAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The leader of Moslems in <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, the
<LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION> and his aide were shot and killed
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, five weeks after the imam distanced himself from <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s
death sentence for author <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>.
   Imam <PERSON>Abdullah Al Ahdal</PERSON>, a 36-year-old Saudi Arabian and moderate
Moslem, and <PERSON>Salem El Behir</PERSON>, a 40-year-old Tunisian who headed the
<LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> mosque's social services and library, were shot at close
range in the imam's office in the mosque, police said.
made. Police said there were no witnesses and that no one heard the
gunshots.
   The two men each were shot twice, once in the head and once in
the neck, police said. Unconfirmed reports said three hooded men
were seen jumping from a van, entering the mosque and then coming
out again.
   The bodies were found by members of the Islamic community early
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>.
   On <DATE>Feb. 14</DATE>, Iranian revolutionary patriarch <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah
Khomeini</PERSON> issued a death sentence for <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> for ``The Satanic
Verses,'' a novel many Moslems consider blasphemous.
   In a <DATE>Feb. 20</DATE> interview on <ORGANIZATION>RTBF</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>'s French-language
television network, Ahdal agreed that <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s book was
blasphemous.
   But he said of <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>'s death sentence: ``One should not have
done that. Rushdie should have first appeared (before an Islamic
tribunal). He should have explained himself, defend himself. He
should have been asked to repent.''
   In democratic societies ``everyone has the right to speak his
thoughts, to express himself as he wants,'' <PERSON>Ahdal</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Claude van Engeland</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>RTBF</ORGANIZATION> reporter, said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the
network had received angry phone calls after the interview from
callers who claimed Ahdal, who spoke in Arabic, was improperly
translated.
   Ahdal's mosque, in a park near the <ORGANIZATION>European Economic Community</ORGANIZATION>
headquarters, is part of the London-based World Islamic League.
   After the killings, police cordoned off the building.
   At one point a woman wearing a black veil emerged from the
building and threatened a reporter with a handgun. Several police
officers struggled with the woman and wrested the gun from her.
They said later she was Ahdal's widow.
   Rushdie, a Briton who was born in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to a Moslem family but
no longer practices religion, is in hiding in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. Moslems
object to ``The Satanic Verses'' because of a brothel scene in
which prostitutes take the names of the Prophet Mohammed's wives
and because it suggests Mohammed wrote the holy Koran instead of
receiving it from <LOCATION>Allah</LOCATION>.
   Members of the Islamic community told reporters outside the
building their mosque takes a very conciliatory tone.
   ``We respect everybody,'' one said on condition of anonymity.
``We do not take radical positions.''
   Ahdal had been in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> for six years heading the Moslem
community in <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION>. His aide had
been here for about 10 years.
   Mohammed Sulim, a professor of Islamic religion, asked the
Moslem community to remain calm.
   He said, ``We are a few days from the <LOCATION>Ramadan</LOCATION>,'' which Moslems
mark with a month of fasting during the day.
   ``These are days for prayer. One must not seek revenge. The imam
was a tolerant man, a generous man, he lent his money to several
people.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06002097 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06002097 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  EDITORIAL; BOOK; WRITING; PROFESSIONAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IS Salman Rushdie a born-again Muslim, seeking, as he wrote in the Dec. 28 New
York Times op-ed page, to "enter into the body of Islam after a lifetime spent
outside it"?;    Or is he tired of nearly two years of hiding from fanatics
who pledged to carry out the Ayatollah Khomeini's death sentence on the
heretical author of "The Satanic Verses"?  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Editorial  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SALMAN'S SEA OF STORIES
DESPITE HIS CONVERSION, RUSHDIE'S RIGHT TO
WRITE REMAINS UNDER ATTACK  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Editorials  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Anyone who's read one of <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s multi-layered, allegorical, fantastical,
satirical novels would suspect that nothing <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> says has only one
meaning.;    After a <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION> meeting with six moderate Muslim leaders,
<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> issued a statement saying "I do not agree with any statements in my
novel . . . uttered by any of the characters who insult the prophet Mohammed,
or cast aspersions upon Islam, or upon the authenticity of the holy <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, or
who reject the divinity of Allah.";    About 1.2-million English-language
copies of "The Satanic Verses," about the improbable adventures of a Muslim
immigrant in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, have been sold (though not necessarily read), and the
book has been translated into 15 languages.;    <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> described the book in
his op-ed piece as "a parable of how a man can be destroyed by loss of faith .
. . the dreams in which all the so-called 'insults' (to Islam) occur are
portraits of his disintegration and explicitly referred to in the novel as
punishments and retributions.";    While not withdrawing the book from stores,
<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> promised not to permit new translations of "The Satanic Verses," or an
English-language paperback edition, and pledged "to work for a better
understanding of Islam.";    <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> may be able to sit and schmooze with
leaders of the Islamic Society for the <ORGANIZATION>Promotion of Religious Tolerance</ORGANIZATION> in the
<LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Council of Scholars of Islamic Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, but
he's still having trouble with the ayatollah's heirs.;    An editorial in the
newspaper Tehran Abrar promptly rejected his apology, saying the ayatollah's
death sentence "is irrevocable even if (Rushdie) repents.";    On the other
hand, <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s new leaders are prone to playing good mullah, bad mullah, and
some believe <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s recantation eventually will do the trick.;    The
religious thugs' attempt to silence <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> is an affront to human freedom. It
is distinctly unpleasant to see a novelist forced to beg forgiveness and
suppress wider publication of his own book.;    Still, the writer is not only
alive, he's writing.;    In <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s new book, "Haroun and the Sea of
Stories," which is dedicated to his son, the boy <PERSON>Haroun</PERSON> undertakes a quest to
free his father, the <ORGANIZATION>Shah of Blah</ORGANIZATION>, from storytellers' block caused by the
fanatical Khattam-Shud, who has poisoned the Ocean of the Streams of Story. As
the enemy of "stories and fancies and dreams" explains to Haroun: "Your world,
my world, all worlds are there to be Ruled. And inside every single story,
inside every Stream in the <LOCATION>Ocean</LOCATION>, there lies a world, a storyworld, that I
cannot Rule at all. And that is the reason why.";    And that is the reason
why <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> must not be silenced.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910102  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  512  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday January 2, 1991
00002097,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900112-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-12-90 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-KoranComic 1stLd-Writethru a0596 01-12 0901</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Koran Comic, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0596,0924</SECOND>
<HEAD>Koran in Comic Book Form Angers Some</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th graf, ``In February ...'' to CORRECT typo in Rushdie
name.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A colorful, easy-to-read version of the Koran in
comic book form has won approval from some Islamic authorities, but
one scholar has condemned it, calling the author ``a new Salman
Rushdie.''
   ``Si Le Coran M'etait Conte'' _ ``If the Koran Were Told To
Me,'' is geared to readers aged 12 to 16, said its author, <PERSON>Youssef
Seddik</PERSON>.
   The Koran is the sacred book of Islam. According to Islamic
belief, it contains the words of God as revealed to the prophet
Mohammed.
   The comic books, which cost about <MONEY>$10</MONEY> each, have been approved
and even encouraged by some religious authorities such as <PERSON>Ayatollah
Mehdi Rouhani</PERSON>, spiritual leader of the Shiite Moslem community in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
   ``I don't see any problem with the comic books, as long as you
know there is a precedent _ an illustrated version of the Koran
published in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> <DATE>15 years ago</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Rouhani</PERSON> said in an interview at
his <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> home.
   Rouhani called comic books ``the language of the <DATE>20th century</DATE>.''
   ``I'm all for comic books, and would encourage them if they do,
in fact, get across the idea of God to young people,'' he said.
   But <PERSON>Mohammed Faidallah</PERSON>, head of Islamic Jurisprudence at <ORGANIZATION>Kuwait
University</ORGANIZATION>'s Islamic Studies faculty, was quoted <DATE>Friday</DATE> as saying
the comic books could spark a furor like that over <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s novel,
``The Satanic Verses.''
   In <DATE>February 1989</DATE>, <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON> said <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>
should die because his novel blasphemed Islam. Rushdie has been in
hiding ever since.
   Faidallah said the comic books constituted a ``criminal act that
ridicules the sanctity of the holy Koran,'' and called for their
condemnation, the <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION> newspaper Al-Qabas reported.
   He was quoted as calling Seddik ``a new Salman Rushdie recruited
to carry out this ugly task.'' Faidallah urged Arab and Islamic
embassies in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> ``to pressure official bodies there with a view
to halting such violation of Islamic values,'' the daily said.
   Seddik, a Tunisian-born journalist who has written extensively
on Arab culture, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> he was ``deeply saddened'' by
<ORGANIZATION>Faidallah</ORGANIZATION>'s reaction and disputed the scholar's right to judge the
issue.
   ``Islam is my emotional and spiritual roots. Nothing, no one can
ever take it away from me,'' he said.
   ``I'm deeply attached to the principle that distinguishes Islam
from <PERSON>Judaiism</PERSON> and Christianity: that it does not accept the idea of
the clergy. Only the knowledge, competence and good intentions of
the humblest Moslem can judge our actions.''
   In an earlier interview, <PERSON>Seddik</PERSON> said he was motivated to adapt
the Koran because of his frustration from studying the text as a
child.
   ``I remember feeling very sad that we had to learn the text by
heart, without any comprehension or understanding of what it
meant,'' said <PERSON>Seddik</PERSON>, 46. ``I was one of the lucky ones _ my father
was a learned man and he would explain things to me at home.''
   Seddik said the drawings and simple language can help young
readers follow the narrative development of the Koran's many
episodes, while avoiding its ``inextricable forest of syntactic,
lexical and theological difficulties.''
   Volume One, ``The Cursed Peoples,'' contains vivid pictures of
dessert peoples worshiping idols, living in sin, and deaf to pleas
of the prophets to change their ways and worship a single God.
   The drawings, which <PERSON>Rouhani</PERSON> described as ``naive and
simplistic,'' are accompanied by exact quotations from the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>,
complete with chapter and verse references. The prophets are not
represented, but evoked by flashes of light.
   Seddik said he was careful not to offend or blaspheme in any
way, and even destroyed 10,000 copies of a <DATE>1986</DATE> edition that
displeased religious leaders.
   The new version, he said, got the OK from religious bodies in
<LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tunisia</LOCATION>.
   A spokesman for the rector of the <LOCATION>Grand Mosque</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> was less
enthusiastic. ``Comic books dealing with transcendental issues have
no instructive value, and, in fact frustrate the development of the
adolescent imagination,'' said <PERSON>Jhaothy Hadjeddine Sari</PERSON>.
   ``Imposing an image of the transcendental on a young person is
tantamount to castration,'' he said. ``I can't see teaching the
Koran in comic books any more than I can imagine teaching
philospohy or math.''
   Seddik said his desire to publish the comic books was
politically motivated.
   ``The rise of Arab fundamentalism is partly a result of the way
the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION> is being taught as something opaque and incantatory,
understood by the elite few who run Islam like a secret society to
which only they have access,'' he said.
   Seddik said the wisdom of the Koran should be available to
everyone ``so people can draw their own conclusions and decide how
to live their lives.''
   Seddik admits that comic books violate one of the key tenants of
Islam: the reproduction of images. ``Of course, it's a taboo, but
I'm willing to assume full responsibility,'' he said.
   Seddik says he respects the sacredness of Islam.
   ``I don't blaspheme, I don't portray Aicha as a prostitute,'' he
said, referring to a passage in ``The Satanic Verses'' about
Mohammed's child bride that offended many Moslems.
   Seddik said the seven-volume project was financed by <PERSON>Hocine
Meddahi</PERSON>, an Algerian industrialist who lives in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. Three
volumes have already appeared, in French and Arabic, and an English
translation is in progress.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890428-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-28-89 2152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SatanicVerses     04-28 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Satanic Verses,0496</SECOND>
<HEAD>Britain Taking Threats Against Diplomats Seriously</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Office</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> it is taking
seriously death threats against British diplomats in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> in
connection with <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>'s book ``The Satanic Verses.''
   Senior diplomatic officials were singled out in letters written
by a group calling itself The Defenders of Islamic Purity, a
spokesman said, speaking anonymously in keeping with British
practice.
   He said ``appropriate action'' was taken, but no details were
being revealed about people threatened or in what countries they
worked.
   Many Moslems around the world say <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s novel blasphemes
Islam. The book includes a scene in which prostitutes take the
names of the prophet <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON>'s wives, and it suggests Mohammed
wrote the holy <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, instead of receiving it from <LOCATION>Allah</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Feb. 14</DATE>, <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s leader <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON> issued a
death sentence against <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>, who remains in hiding. Rushdie,
born in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> of Moslem parents, now is a British citizen.
   The <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> newspaper <PERSON>Libre Belgique</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> in an article
signed by crime reporter <PERSON>Roger Rosart</PERSON> that the <ORGANIZATION>British Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> received threats.
   An embassy spokesman in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> confirmed that, but said no
staff were singled out by name and no staff were moved to other
posts, reported <ORGANIZATION>Press Association</ORGANIZATION>, the British domestic news agency.
   Belgian authorities would not comment.
   Rosart said three letters from The Defenders of Islamic Purity
which came into the hands of Belgian police blamed the British
attitude in the <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> affair and listed British diplomats who
were to be killed soon. It said two of the letters went to the
embassy.
   The paper reported that the threats warned family and friends to
steer clear of intended victims lest they be harmed, too. It said a
large number of these diplomats either returned to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> or were
transferred elsewhere.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Office</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said: ``Similar letters have gone
to various embassies in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. These threats are always taken
seriously and we have acted accordingly.''
   Libre <PERSON>Belgique</PERSON> said Belgian authorities were arranging strict
protective measures in view of the <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> murder of <PERSON>Imam Abdullah
Al-Ahdal</PERSON> and his aide on <DATE>March 29</DATE>.
   Ahdal, a Saudi cleric and leader of the Moslems of <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, was shot after receiving death
threats for opposing <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>'s death sentence on <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>.
   In other <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> developments:
   _<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> strongly protested the showing and sale of a few copies of
``The Satanic Verses'' during <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION>'s International Book Fair. A
statement issued by the <ORGANIZATION>Iranian Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Bern</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> said the
action violates Swiss laws calling for respect of religious beliefs
and insults the rights of more than 90,000 Moslems living in
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
   _A judge in <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION> ruled on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in favor of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s
Islamic Center, saying publication of ``The Satanic Verses''
violated religious freedom. The Islamic Center, representing
Venezuelan Moslems, had brought suit against a publisher planning
to bring out the book.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890215-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-15-89 2324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SatanicVerses 4thLd-Writethru a0817 02-15 1055</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Satanic Verses, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0817,1085</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Satanic Verses' Author Scrubs U.S. Trip; Iranians Announce Bounty</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs to UPDATE with report death squads headed
for Britain. Pick up 13th pvs, `On Tuesday...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LON7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BARR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> placed a <MONEY>$2.6 million</MONEY> bounty on the head of
world's Moslems. Rushdie dropped from sight and canceled a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
promotional tour due to start <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Police guarded <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s home and his publishers.
   ``If the executioner is a foreigner he will receive a <MONEY>million
dollars</MONEY>,'' said <PERSON>Hojatoleslam Hassan Saneie</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>15th Khordad
Relief Agency</ORGANIZATION>, according to the Iranian news agency.
   The reward for an Iranian, however, will be 200 million rials, or
<MONEY>$2.6 million</MONEY>, the <ORGANIZATION>Islamic Republic News Agency</ORGANIZATION> quoted Saneie as
saying.
   The Times of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> quoted a former Pakistani
minister of information and religious affairs, <PERSON>Moulana Kausar Niazi</PERSON>,
as saying death squads from <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> and other Moslem states were on
their way to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> to kill <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>, who lives in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Tehran Radio</ORGANIZATION> denounced the book as ``a shameless onslaught on the
sacred character of Islam's prophet'' and protesters shattered
windows at the <ORGANIZATION>British Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>.
   The radio said <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s ambassador to the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Salman Ghaffari</PERSON>,
urged Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> to ``seriously oppose'' the publication of
the Italian translation of the book ``and prove that he defends
religion and spirituality.''
   ``With a glance at the writer of this book one may see the hidden
hands of world imperialism and the devious role of arrogance in the
activities of publication agencies which serve it,'' said a <ORGANIZATION>Tehran
   About 2,000 noisy protesters appeared at the <ORGANIZATION>British Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>, Charge d'Affaires <PERSON>Nick Browne</PERSON> told BBC-TV, but he said
authorities protected the embassy and the seven people inside.
   ``There was never any question of any of us being in danger,''
<PERSON>Browne</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Tehran Radio</ORGANIZATION>, monitored by the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION>, reported other protests
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Kashan</LOCATION>, southeast of the holy city of <LOCATION>Qom</LOCATION>, and
Firuzukh, east of <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>.
   Six people were killed and 82 injured when police opened fire
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> on demonstrators against the book who stormed a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cultural
center in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>. One person was killed in another
protest <DATE>Monday</DATE> in northern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Moulana</PERSON> led the demonstration in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION> and
headed the movement to have the book banned in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Tehran Radio</ORGANIZATION> quoted <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON> as
saying <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> and his publishers ``are hereby sentenced to death.''
   ``I call on all zealous Moslems to execute them quickly, wherever
they find them, so that no one will dare to insult Islamic
sanctity,'' it quoted <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON> as saying.
   Rushdie _ a Moslem born in <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, and educated at
<LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> _ was reported to be under police guard <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with his
wife, American novelist <PERSON>Marianne Wiggins</PERSON>.
   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, spokesman <PERSON>Paul Slovak</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Viking Penguin Inc.</ORGANIZATION> read a
statement representing ``the agreed joint position by the publisher
<PERSON>Viking</PERSON> and the author <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>.''
   It said events in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and threats made against
<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> and others ``led us to conclude that the current climate is
not appropriate for a promotional tour in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> as previously
planned.''
   The statement said no offense was intended in writing or
publishing the book and ended, ``It is also our unalterable position
that freedom of speech, freedom to publish and freedom to read must
be guaranteed internationally.''
   ``The Satanic Verses'' has sold more than 100,000 copies since it
was published in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>September</DATE> to critical acclaim.
   At least five countries have formally banned the novel: <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   Christian <PERSON>Bourgois</PERSON>, a French publishing house that bought the
rights to the novel, said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> it was delaying publication.
   Britain recently reopend its embassy in <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign
Office</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Browne</PERSON> was seeking a meeting with Iranian authorities to
clarify the situation.
   Foreign Minister <PERSON>Ali Akbar Velayati</PERSON> told diplomats in <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> the
government would order the closure of cultural centers of nations
that permit publication of the book, <ORGANIZATION>Tehran Radio</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   ``There has been no direct impact on ties so far,'' <ORGANIZATION>IRNA</ORGANIZATION> said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, ``but by being the first to allow the book to be
published on its soil, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> could pay a heavy price for ignoring
the strong sentiments of over <MONEY>1 billion</MONEY> Moslems worldwide.''
   <PERSON>Mostafa Barzegar</PERSON>, spokesman for <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s Culture and <ORGANIZATION>Islamic
Guidance Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, announced a ban on books published by Viking and
other imprints of the <ORGANIZATION>Penguin Group</ORGANIZATION>, and said <PERSON>Penguin</PERSON>'s invitation
to the second <ORGANIZATION>Tehran International Book Fair</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>May</DATE> has been
canceled, <ORGANIZATION>IRNA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Playwright <PERSON>Harold Pinter</PERSON> led a delegation to Prime Minister
<PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON>'s residence at 10 Downing St. to deliver a letter
denouncing the Iranian threats.
   ``Salman Rushdie lives in this country and must be given full
protection, along with the other people involved,'' said the letter,
whose signatories included authors <PERSON>Fay Weldon</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Marina Warner</ORGANIZATION> and
<PERSON>Hanif Kureishi</PERSON>, publisher <PERSON>Liz Calder</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stuart Weir</PERSON>, publisher of
the left-leaning New Statesman magazine.
   In The <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, opposition lawmakers appealed to Foreign
Minister <PERSON>Hans</PERSON> van den Broek to cancel a planned trip to <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>.
   Police were posted outside <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s home and the office of his
publisher, Viking, and <PERSON>Kureishi</PERSON> said <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> had gone into hiding.
``He is obviously very frightened,'' said <PERSON>Kureishi</PERSON>. ``These people
are completely nutters,'' said <PERSON>Kureishi</PERSON>, who wrote the script for
the film ``My Beautiful Laundrette.''
   A major character in <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s book is named Mahound, a medieval
corruption of the name of the prophet Mohammed. Moslems have
complained the book represents the prophet's wives as prostitutes
and suggests that he wrote the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, rather than receiving it from
God.
   The title refers to verses which Mohammed removed from the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>,
Islam's holy book, believing they had been inspired by the devil.
   Before he went into hiding, <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> expressed no apologies for
his book.
   ``Frankly, I wish I had written a more critical book,'' he said
in an interview with BBC-TV on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``A religion that claims it is able to behave like this,
religious leaders who are able to behave like this, and then say
this is a religion which must be above any kind of whisper of
criticism, that doesn't add up,'' <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890904-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-04-89 0528EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-LondonExplosion 1stLd-Writethru a0469 09-04 0617</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-London Explosion, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0469,0633</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb-Warning Caller Links Blast to Rushdie</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with Liberty's saysing its Penguin shop recently
closed, store doesn't stock Rushdie book. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GRAHAM HEATHCOTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associate Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> Yard's anti-terrorist squad <DATE>today</DATE> said it
was investigating a bomb blast linked to the campaign against <PERSON>Salman
Rushdie</PERSON>, the target of death threats for his novel ``The Satanic
Verses.''
   Police said an anonymous caller, who mentioned <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s book,
telephoned with a bomb threat shortly before the device exploded
late <DATE>Sunday</DATE> outside Liberty's department store in central <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. A
woman passer-by was injured.
   The store was closed at the time, but by day the area is one of
the busiest in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s congested West End.
   Until recently, <ORGANIZATION>Liberty</ORGANIZATION>'s housed a Penguin bookstore concession.
``The Satanic Verses'' was published last year under the Viking
imprint, which is part of the Penguin group.
   The novel angered religious Moslems around the world, who claim
it blasphemes their religion.
   Viking Penguin received death threats against its staff after the
Islamic campaign began and two <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> bookstores, one specializing
in Penguin books, were damaged in arson attacks on <DATE>April 9</DATE>.
   ``There used to be a Penguin paperback bookshop in the store, on
the ground floor near the area of our present bookshop, but it
closed a couple of months ago,'' said a spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>Liberty's</ORGANIZATION>.
   The new bookstore does not stock ``The Satanic Verses,'' she
said, requesting anonymity.
   The injured woman, who was not identified, underwent surgery for
leg injuries and was in satisfactory condition at <ORGANIZATION>University College
Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   She is the first person known to have been hurt in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in the
worldwide campaign by Moslem zealots against the novel.
   Detective chief superintendent <PERSON>Derek Willison</PERSON> said that 10 or 15
minutes before the blast police received an anonymous telephone
warning which mentioned ``The Satanic Verses.'' He would not give
other details.
   As police were searching the area, the bomb went off on the
sidewalk in <LOCATION>Great Marlborough Street</LOCATION> near a window of the Liberty
department store where books were displayed.
   <PERSON>Willison</PERSON> said <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s book was not among them, but books issued
by his publishers, <PERSON>Viking Penguin</PERSON>, were in the window.
   Liberty's, established in <DATE>1875</DATE> and housed in a mock Tudor
black-and-white building on the corner of <ORGANIZATION>Regent Street and Great
Marlborough Street</ORGANIZATION>, has an international reputation as a fashion
leader in textiles.
   <PERSON>Willison</PERSON> described the bomb as ``small'' and other police
officers said there was no damage to buildings. But <PERSON>Tracy Ryan</PERSON>, 23,
who was looking in a store window across the street spoke of a large
blast.
   ``Suddenly there was a huge bang. It was really frightening and
the pavement (sidewalk) shook. It was a terrible bang,'' she said.
   Early today, police sealed off the area around the store and were
checking for clues and taking photographs. They finally left at <TIME>5
a.m.</TIME>, removing barrier tapes. There was a bloodstain on the sidewalk
where the woman was injured.
   Rushdie has been in hiding since <DATE>February</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s late
religious leader, <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON>, called on Moslems
worldwide to kill him for his novel allegedly blaspheming Islam. Two
Iranian clerics have offered a <MONEY>$5.2 million</MONEY> bounty for <ORGANIZATION>Rushdie</ORGANIZATION>'s
death.
   Rushdie's American wife, <PERSON>Marianne Wiggins</PERSON>, has said she left him
five weeks ago because she could not stand the strain.
   Moslems in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> have burned the novel and demonstrated against
it. In <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, at least a score of people have been
killed and hundreds injured in riots protesting the book.
   In the novel, prostitutes are named after the wives of the
prophet Mohammed prophets and that <PERSON>Mohammed</PERSON> wrote the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>, Islam's
holiest book, instead of receiving the words from <LOCATION>Allah</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890216-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-16-89 1120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-SatanicVerses 3rdLd-Writethru   02-16 0855</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Satanic Verses, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0516,0879</SECOND>
<HEAD>Suicide Squads Reported En Route To Britain To Kill Author</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with details on bomb threats, Egyptian
cleric opposing execution order, Italy agreeing to publish book. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL WEST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem fundamentalist leaders in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> said <DATE>today</DATE>
that suicide squads were preparing to carry out the ``death
sentence'' imposed on novelist <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> and his publishers by
<PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON>.
   The declaration on <ORGANIZATION>Tehran Radio</ORGANIZATION> followed other reports that death
squads from Islamic countries were en route to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in search of
the writer, whose novel ``The Satanic Verses'' has outraged many
Moslem fundamentalists.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, which reopened its embassy in <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> in <DATE>December</DATE> for the
first time in eight years, condemned the threats and announced it
had frozen plans to ``build up further our embassy.''
   <ORGANIZATION>United News of India</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>British Broadcasting Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said
telephone callers threatened to bomb British planes to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> unless
<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> appeared in public. Two airlines, <ORGANIZATION>British Airways</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Air
Europe</LOCATION>, said they were taking the threat seriously.
   The Indian news agency said a man claiming to speak for the
previously unheard of <ORGANIZATION>Iranian Guards</ORGANIZATION> telephoned its <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> office
today with the threats.
   <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s government demanded the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> ban
the book and that all copies of it be destroyed. Six people died in
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> during a weekend riot over the book.
   An Iranian cleric on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> offered up to <MONEY>$2.6 million</MONEY> for
<ORGANIZATION>Rushdie</ORGANIZATION>'s murder, and the author canceled a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> promotional tour
that was scheduled to begin <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   A leading Islamic theologian in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> said <DATE>today</DATE> <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON> erred
