<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-StormKoryn 1stLd-Writethru a0728 01-14 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Storm Koryn, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0728,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Typhoon Heads North of Island Territory</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with typhoon headed north of
Saipan, storm's position, storm believed to have reached peak,
water service partly restored on Guam, residents leaving Guam
shelters; picks up 10th graf, `The Guam ...' Monday is cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SAIPAN, Northern Marianas Islands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon Koryn headed
north of this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> island commonwealth in the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Monday</DATE> with winds gusting to 110 mph, and forecasters believed the
storm had hit its peak, officials said.
   On <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, crews worked to clear damage and restore water and
power service cut when the storm hit <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   By noon <DATE>Monday</DATE> (<TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> EST), <PERSON>Koryn</PERSON>'s center was 40 miles
north of <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION>, and the storm was moving north-northeast at 8 mph,
said <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Lt. <PERSON>Diane Crittenden</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon Warning Center</ORGANIZATION>
on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>.
   The typhoon, with maximum sustained winds of 85 mph and gusts
reaching 110 mph, was believed to have reached its peak, she said.
   If the storm kept to its course, it would not hit any other
islands in the <LOCATION>Northern Marianas</LOCATION>, but might hit the Japanese island
of Minami-Tori, according to <PERSON>Ms. Crittendon</PERSON>.
   Residents on <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> boarded up houses, put boats to sea and
moved to community shelters, said <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> coordinator <PERSON>Felix
Sasamopo</PERSON>. The airport was closed.
   On <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, water service was restored to about <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the
island's population of 130,000, and <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> remained without
electricity, said <PERSON>Ben Reyes</PERSON>, a staff officer with <ORGANIZATION>Guam Civil
Defense</ORGANIZATION>.
   Winds tore tin roofs off two houses in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and forced more than
500 people into emergency shelters <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, but only a few remained
in shelters after the storm passed, said <PERSON>Reyes</PERSON>. Two minor injuries
were reported.
   The <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> airport was reopened after the typhoon passed. Guam is
also home to <ORGANIZATION>Andersen Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>.
   Both <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Northern Marianas</LOCATION> are located west of the
<ORGANIZATION>International Date Line</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880816-0074 </DOCNO>
<HL> Bonds of Guam, Northern Marianas Aren't Tax Exempt </HL>
<AUTHOR> John Connor (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> TAXES FREST </CO>
<IN> BON </IN>
<G> IRS </G>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Internal Revenue Service</ORGANIZATION> notified <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Northern Mariana Islands</LOCATION> that interest on <MONEY>$380 million</MONEY> of municipal bonds issued by the two <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> jurisdictions isn't tax-exempt. 

   But the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> made it clear it hasn't reached the point of moving to tax interest income earned by bondholders. 

   The Territory of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> sold <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> of bonds as tax-exempt securities in <DATE>October 1985</DATE>. 
The Commonwealth of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Mariana Islands</ORGANIZATION> sold <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY> of bonds as tax-exempts in <DATE>December 1984</DATE>. 
Both issues were underwritten by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> grand jury in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> late last year cited the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Northern Mariana Islands</LOCATION> bond issues, among others, in a 52-count indictment charging <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright Executive</ORGANIZATION> Vice President <PERSON>Arthur Abba Goldberg</PERSON> and a one-time company consultant with promoting a nationwide fraud involving more than <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> in municipal bonds. 
<PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON> has pleaded innocent. 
His trial isn't expected to get under way until next year. 
The company has denied any wrongdoing. 

   "After thorough consideration, we have concluded that interest on the (<LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>) bonds is not tax-exempt under section 103 of the Code," <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> Commissioner <PERSON>Lawrence Gibbs</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>Guam Gov. Joseph Ada</ORGANIZATION> in a letter. 
The same message was delivered to Gov. <PERSON>Pedro Tenorio</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Mariana Islands</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The action wasn't wholly unexpected. 
Gov. <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> told a congressional panel earlier this year that the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> was going to declare the <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> issue taxable. 

   <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> officials have refused to discuss the bonds in question, and a spokesman declined yesterday to comment on the issues. 
Officials of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Mariana Islands</ORGANIZATION> couldn't be reached immediately for comment. 

   Attorney <PERSON>David Aufhauser</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Williams &amp; Connolly, Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>'s law firm, emphasized the view that the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>'s conclusions are "only preliminary." 
He said <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> is confident the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>'s conclusions will be "reconsidered and changed" in due course. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> said in the letters, "If desired, we will also consider whether there are good and sufficient reasons for finally resolving this matter through the use of a closing agreement," explaining that under such agreements, "the service forgoes taxing the interest in the hands of the bondholder but collects all or an appropriate percentage of such lost revenues from the issuer." 

   Guam and the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Mariana Islands</ORGANIZATION> separately have filed lawsuits against parties involved in the issuance of the bonds, including <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0531EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Koryn     01-14 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Koryn,0336</SECOND>
<HEAD>Typhoon Sweeps by Guam, Heads for Marianas</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon Koryn, packing sustained winds of 75
mph and gusts to 90 mph, swept past this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Pacific territory
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> before heading toward the <LOCATION>Northern Mariana Islands</LOCATION>,
authorities said.
   High winds and heavy rains knocked out electricity over <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, cutting power to 56 of the island's 90 water
wells, officials said.
   Winds ranging from 35 to 55 mph ripped tin roofs off two houses
and forced 21 people into emergcy shelters, the officials said.
   There were two reports of minor injuries. A 50-year-old man
suffered a cut ear while trying to put up shutters and a
46-year-old woman was injured when she was blown into a pole. Both
were treated and released from <ORGANIZATION>Guam Memorial Hospital</ORGANIZATION>, a hospital
spokesman said.
   As of <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> (<TIME>4 a.m. EST</TIME>), <PERSON>Koryn</PERSON> was 44 miles northeast of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>,
moving to the northwest at 8 mph, according to <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Lt.<PERSON>j.g. Ken
Minogue</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon Warning Center Rapid Response Team</ORGANIZATION>.
   The typhoon was forecast to pass to the north of Rota, the most
southern of the <LOCATION>Northern Marianas</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth, some 40
miles north of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Minogue</PERSON> said.
   Rota was getting heavy rains and winds up to 50 mph, the same
conditions the <LOCATION>Mariana</LOCATION> islands of <LOCATION>Tinian</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> could expect
<DATE>Monday</DATE>, he said.
   On <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, all <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> aircraft were placed in hangers for protection
against the strong winds, and the USS Haleakala was sent out to sea
to weather the storm, said Lt. <PERSON>Dave Lee</PERSON>. Three other warships were
allowed to remain in port, he said.
   Twelve planes, including 11 B-52s, at <ORGANIZATION>Andersen Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> on
the north coast of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, were parked behind fortifications as the
storm approached, said base spokesman Capt. <PERSON>Wayne Perry</PERSON>.
   A tropical storm has sustained winds ranging from 39 to 73 mph.
A typhoon has a minimum sustained surface wind of 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901221-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-21-90 0449EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TyphoonRuss     12-21 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Typhoon Russ,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guam Hit Hard by Typhoon Russ</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon <PERSON>Russ</PERSON> raked <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> today with wind up to
135 mph and pummeled the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory's southern coast with huge
waves that caused severe flooding.
   No serious injuries or deaths were reported, but power and water
service were disrupted in many areas and police reported some
looting, <PERSON>Ken Booth</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Guam Cable TV</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The storm was the strongest to hit this western <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> island
in more than a decade. Its eye moved within 15 miles of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s
southern coast <DATE>early today</DATE>, and wind hit 135 mph in the south and
90 mph with gusts of 115 mph in central and northern areas, said
Lt. <PERSON>Diane Edson</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon Warning Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   Fifteen minor injuries and no deaths were reported, <ORGANIZATION>Booth</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``It was quite a blow, but not as bad as had been expected,'' he
said.
   Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON> said about 500 families in the southern town of
Agat were displaced, <ORGANIZATION>Booth</ORGANIZATION> reported. About 2,500 people sought
shelter during the storm.
   Power and water service remained down in many areas, and
officials said it would be three days before full power was
restored, according to <LOCATION>Booth</LOCATION>.
   Booth said police reported looting in some areas. The duty-free
store in the central town of Tumon reported being robbed of
<MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> in Rolex watches and an undetermined amount of other
jewelry. There were reports of looting in other areas as well. No
arrests were made.
   Waves cresting as high as 24 feet caused severe flooding in
southern <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, uncovering corpses in the cemetery in the town of
Inarajan, <ORGANIZATION>Booth</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Several large concrete utility poles installed after the last
major typhoon, <PERSON>Pamela</PERSON> in <DATE>1976</DATE>, snapped in half from the force of
the waves, <ORGANIZATION>Booth</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Russ damaged or destroyed only the few wooden homes remaining on
the island. Concrete structures built after <PERSON>Pamela</PERSON> escaped serious
damage.
   <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> said he planned to ask for federal disaster relief
assistance.
   Booth said the capital of <LOCATION>Agana</LOCATION> looked like a ``war zone,'' with
trees, traffic lights, poles and signs strewn about and flooding
everywhere.
   The storm center was out to sea and headed toward the
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> with sustained winds of 145 mph and gusts of 175 mph,
<PERSON>Edson</PERSON> said. It was moving at 15 mph, but was expected to weaken
before it reached the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900115-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-15-90 0503EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-TyphoonKoryn     01-15 0367</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Typhoon Koryn,0380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Typhoon Skirts Commonwealth Capital</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAIPAN, Northern Mariana Islands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon Koryn, packing
110 mph gusts, knocked down trees and cut electrical power in the
capital of this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth before moving away today,
authorities said.
   No serious injuries were immediately reported.
   The typhoon with maximum sustained winds of 85 mph swept past
<LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> and was moving to the northeast at 8 mph, said <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
Maj. <PERSON>Joel Martin</PERSON>, a meteorologist with the Guam-based <ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon
Warning Center Rapid Response Team</ORGANIZATION>.
   As of <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> (<TIME>1 a.m. EST</TIME>), <PERSON>Koryn</PERSON> was 65 miles north of <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said.
   There were reports of downed trees and power lines before
communications were cut with <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said, but added the
storm's path ``seemed to have spared them a lot of the heavier
winds.''
   Forecasters predicted the typhoon would not affect any other
islands before it lost power.
   The winds damaged power lines, cutting electricity on the island
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, said <PERSON>Jean-Louis M. Pierrefeu</PERSON>, assistant executive
director for the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth Utilities Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s power branch.
   As the storm approached, residents boarded up houses, put boats
to sea and moved to shelters, said <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> coordinator <PERSON>Felix
Sasamopo</PERSON>. The airport was closed.
   Conditions on <ORGANIZATION>Rota</ORGANIZATION>, the most southern of the <LOCATION>Marianas</LOCATION>, were not
known because of poor communications, <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said.
   The first island to feel the typhoon was <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, just to the south
of the <LOCATION>Northern Marianas</LOCATION>.
   Koryn skirted the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory to the west <DATE>Sunday</DATE> night with
heavy rains and 90 mph gusts, knocking out power and sending more
than 500 people to shelters. Without electricity, the island's
130,000 residents were without water.
   By tonight, electricity had been restored to at least <PERCENT>65 percent</PERCENT>
of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the island had running water, said <PERSON>Ben
Reyes</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION>.
   Island residents had been warned to keep a three-day supply of
water, <PERSON>Reyes</PERSON> said.
   All of the people who had sought shelter had returned to their
homes except for the 59 members of four families, who were provided
emergency housing, he said.
   Updated reports showed four people suffered minor injuries from
the storm, while the tin roofs of two houses were blown off, <PERSON>Reyes</PERSON>
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-TyphoonJack 1stLd-Writethru a0498 12-26 0252</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Typhoon Jack, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0498,0255</SECOND>
<HEAD>Powerful Typhoon Threatens Guam, Saipan</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with typhoon weakening, new course to miss
Saipan. No pickup. Note Wednesday in 2nd graf is cq; `today' in 7th graf
refers to Tuesday.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Residents of this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory were advised
to stock up on emergency supplies as a powerful typhoon stalled 200
miles to the east.
   Typhoon <PERSON>Jack</PERSON>, unusually late in the season for a major storm,
had sustained winds of 125 mph with gusts to 155 mph at <TIME>1 a.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and was gradually weakening, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Joint
Typhoon Warning Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   Forecasters said the typhoon was expected to drift slowly toward
the northwest during the <DATE>next 18</DATE> to 24 hours on a course that would
take it 57 miles north of <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION>.
   Before it stalled in the western <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>, the storm had been on
a track that would take it between <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION>, the capital of
the Commonwealth of the <LOCATION>Northern Mariana Islands</LOCATION> north of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>.
   ``The potential for erratic movement is high,'' said hourly
advisories issued by the center.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> sent B-52 bombers to <LOCATION>Okinawa</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> ordered
its large ships to sea to ride out the storm, officials said.
   Banks closed today and the 125,000 residents of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and the
30,000 people on <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> were advised to get supplies of food,
water, batteries and the like.
   Guam is under a Tropical Cyclone Condition 2, meaning a storm
could hit the island within 24 hours.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--TyphoonJack 1stLd-Writethru a0469 12-27 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Typhoon Jack, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0469,0187</SECOND>
<HEAD>Typhoon Jack Weakens, But Still Threatens Guam</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 2nd graf with 2 grafs to update position, weakening.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A weakening Typhoon <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> began to drift
toward this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory in the western <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE> and was
forecast to at least brush the island on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, according to civil
defense officials.
   At <TIME>1 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, (<TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> EST), the storm was 190 miles
east of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, moving west-southwest at about 3 mph. Its sustained
wind speed was 85 mph with gusts to 100 mph. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, its
sustained winds were 135.
   Lt. <PERSON>Richard Bouchard</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon Warning Center</ORGANIZATION> here
said at the rate the storm was weakening it could lose typhoon
status _ sustained wind speed of at least 74 mph _ before it passes
south of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>.
   ``Forecasters can't determine how close it will come, but it's
expected to pass <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> during the day <DATE>Friday</DATE>,'' said <PERSON>George Toves</PERSON>, a
<ORGANIZATION>Guam Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> officer. ``We'll get some portion of it.''
   The storm had been stalled about 200 miles east of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> since
early <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890421-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-21-89 0709EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-TyphoonAndy     04-21 0221</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Typhoon Andy,0227</SECOND>
<HEAD>Typhoon Bypassing U.S. Territory</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon <PERSON>Andy</PERSON>, packing winds reaching 185 mph,
sent 1,100 people fleeing to shelters and forced the military to
ferry 17 airplanes to <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> as a precautionary measure,
authorities said.
   There were no reports of major structural damage or injuries
associated with the storm, according to police officer <PERSON>John
Thornton</PERSON>.
   As of <TIME>this afternoon</TIME>, the center of the typhoon with sustained
winds of 155 mph was located 113 miles east-southeast of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>,
moving to the northeast at 10 mph, the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon Weather Center</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   The typhoon was expected to head into the <LOCATION>Northern Mariana
Islands</LOCATION>, bypassing Rota by 115 miles, before missing <LOCATION>Tinian</LOCATION> and the
capital city of <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> by 155 miles, the center said.
   <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory with a population of 105,000, is the
largest of the <LOCATION>Mariana Islands</LOCATION> in the western <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>.
   Earlier today, <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> was hit with 50 mph winds and gusts to 65
mph that knocked out <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of the island's electric power for
a few hours.
   Thornton described the weather as ``not too bad.'' He said,
``You feel it in small cars when you're driving.''
   However, the island's banana and mango crops were hard hit, <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>
<ORGANIZATION>Cablevision</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   About half of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory's schools were being used as
shelters, <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901222-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-22-90 1726EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-TyphoonRuss     12-22 0248</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Typhoon Russ,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guam Picks Up After Typhoon Russ</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon Russ damaged or destroyed more than
2,000 homes and injured 88 people in this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory in the
<LOCATION>Western Pacific</LOCATION>, but no one was killed, officials said.
   The storm, packing wind that gusted up to 150 mph, swept over
the island of 145,000 residents on <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> sent a letter to President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>,
requesting a disaster declaration to release federal funds to help
in the recovery.
   A disaster declaration from <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is unlikely for several days,
said <PERSON>Bart Stinson</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> spokesman. There was no
immediate estimate of total damage, he said.
   Electricity and water service had been restored to about <PERCENT>20
percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> by <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, <PERSON>Stinson</PERSON> said. Telephone service,
however, remained intact because most of the cables are buried, he
said.
   <PERSON>Stinson</PERSON> said damage to <ORGANIZATION>Guam Community College</ORGANIZATION>, which is adjacent
to <ORGANIZATION>Guam University</ORGANIZATION>, was extensive.
   ``It looks more like a tornado hit it than a typhoon,'' he said.
   The wooden buildings were splintered and desks strewn around the
campus, where trees were twisted and not just blown down, he said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> said a preliminary survey by <ORGANIZATION>Federal Emergency Management
Agency</ORGANIZATION> teams found 341 homes destroyed, 460 with major damage and
1,210 with minor damage to the point they were uninhabitable.
   Hospitals reported treating 88 people, mostly for punctures,
cuts and scratches from wind-blown debris.
   The <ORGANIZATION>FEMA</ORGANIZATION> teams were already on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> when Typhoon <PERSON>Russ</PERSON> hit. They
had come to coordinate recovery operations on islands in the
<LOCATION>Federated States</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Micronesia</LOCATION> that were hit by Typhoon Owen three
weeks ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891002-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-02-89 0636EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i PM-BRF--PacificStorm     10-02 0174</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Pacific Storm,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Territory Prepares for Colleen</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm <PERSON>Colleen</PERSON> moved toward this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
territory and the Commonwealth of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Mariana Islands</ORGANIZATION>
packing winds up to 45 mph.
   Colleen was expected to intensify to typhoon status, with 75 mph
winds, when it sweeps within 70 miles south of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the
<ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon Warning Center</ORGANIZATION> said.
   At <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> (<TIME>10 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> EDT), <PERSON>Colleen</PERSON> was at 11.5
degrees latitude and 148.6 degrees longitude, or 247 miles
east-southeast of <ORGANIZATION>Andersen Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, the center said.
   As of <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>, maximum winds were 40 to 45 mph and the storm was
moving to the west-northwest at 12 to 14 mph.
   Guam's <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> issued a tropical-storm alert and said
<PERSON>Colleen</PERSON> could hit the island within 72 hours.
   Military officials were meeting to determine when airplanes and
ships should be moved for protection.
   The storm formed <DATE>Sunday</DATE> 500 miles east of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>.
   The term ``typhoon'' is used for hurricanes west of the
international date line.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Koryn 1stLd-Writethru   01-14 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Koryn, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0616,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Off Guam Upgraded To Typhoon</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 8 grafs to UPDATE with storm upgraded to typhoon,
details. Pickup 7th graf `All Navy...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical storm Koryn became a full-fledged
typhoon <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, lashing this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Pacific territory with strong
winds and heavy rains, toppling trees and flooding low-lying areas,
structures.
   As of <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> (<TIME>2 a.m. EST</TIME>), <PERSON>Koryn</PERSON> had sustained winds of 75 mph,
with gusts to 90 mph, according to <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Lt. <PERSON>Joe Atangan</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon Warning Center Rapid Response Team</ORGANIZATION>.
   The storm's center was located 45 miles east of the northern tip
of the island, where <ORGANIZATION>Andersen Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> is located, <PERSON>Atangan</PERSON>
said.
   The typhoon was ``quasi stationary'' but was expected to move
off to the north-northwest, skirting the northern coast, he said.
   Guam and the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Mariana Islands</ORGANIZATION> remained under a typhoon
alert, although the projected path of the storm would take it south
of the <LOCATION>Marianas</LOCATION> and away from any other islands, <PERSON>Atangan</PERSON> said.
   There were reports on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> of intermittent power outages because
of downed lines, and flooding was reported in many areas, the
<ORGANIZATION>Pacific Daily News</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``There's lots of coconuts on the roads,'' <PERSON>Atangan</PERSON> said.
   All <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> aircraft were placed in hangers for protection against
the strong winds, and the USS Haleakala was sent out to sea to
weather the storm, said Lt. <PERSON>Dave Lee</PERSON>. Three other warships were
allowed to remain in port, he said.
   The 12 planes at <LOCATION>Andersen</LOCATION>, including 11 B-52s, were parked
behind fortifications as the storm approached, said base spokesman
Capt. <PERSON>Wayne Perry</PERSON>.
   A tropical storm has sustained winds ranging from 39 to 73 mph.
A typhoon has a minimum sustained surface wind of 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901128-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-28-90 2249EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-TyphoonOwen     11-28 0215</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Typhoon Owen,0241</SECOND>
<HEAD>Island of Yap Threatened by Typhoon</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Thursday in lead is cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>YAP, Federated States of Micronesia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon <PERSON>Owen</PERSON> bore
down <DATE>Thursday</DATE> on Yap after killing two men and leaving more than
1,000 people homeless elsewhere in this sprawling <LOCATION>Western Pacific</LOCATION>
republic.
   The storm passed 20 miles south of the island of <LOCATION>Woleai</LOCATION>, but
there was no immediate word on the fate of the 300 residents, a
civil defense spokesman said.
   Owen, with sustained winds of 130 mph and gusts to 160 mph,
moved west-northwest at 14 mph and was expected to pass near the
island of Yap late <DATE>Friday</DATE>, said Lt. <PERSON>j.g. Richard Jeffries</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon Warning Center</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. Yap island has about
12,000 residents.
   <LOCATION>Micronesia</LOCATION> is in the western <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>, north of the equator
and south of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory. The principal island groups
include the <PERSON>Caroline Islands</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Nauru</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Gilbert Islands</LOCATION>, the
<ORGANIZATION>Northern Mariana Islands</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Marshall Islands</LOCATION>.
   Two men were electrocuted <DATE>Saturday</DATE> by downed power lines when
the typhoon toppled a tree in the Micronesian capital of <LOCATION>Pohnpei</LOCATION>,
said <PERSON>Tony Palomo</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Interior</ORGANIZATION>
on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>.
   The typhoon lashed the state of <LOCATION>Truk</LOCATION>'s sparcely-populated outer
islands with 125 mph winds <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, destroying many homes, said
<PERSON>Ismael Dobich</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Truk</LOCATION> state spokesman. No injuries were reported.
   Truk is about 1,488 miles southeast of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880226-0005 </DOCNO>
<HL> IRS to Make Taxable $300 Million of Bonds, Guam Governor Says </HL>
<AUTHOR> (WSJ Special) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> TAXES FREST </CO>
<IN> BON </IN>
<G> IRS </G>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Guam Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Internal Revenue Service</ORGANIZATION> soon will declare taxable a <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> Guam housing-bond issue underwritten by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Gov. <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> told a <ORGANIZATION>House Interior</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee he met with the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> last week on the bonds' tax status, and said, "They are coming out and declaring the <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> (issue) taxable soon." 

   An attorney for <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>, a small Wall Street bond house, said he had no information on any <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> decision to tax the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> bonds. 
A senior <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> official declined all comment on the matter. 

   The <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> bonds were issued as tax-exempt securities in <DATE>1985</DATE>. 

   Two authorities on municipal bonds said they couldn't remember the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>'s having declared an issue taxable retroactively. 

   "I don't think it has ever happened," said <PERSON>James Lebenthal</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> bond firm <ORGANIZATION>Lebenthal &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Richard Ciccarone</PERSON>, senior research analyst of <ORGANIZATION>Van Kampen Merritt Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, securities concern, said he couldn't recall it happening in his more than 10 years in the business. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901220-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-20-90 2332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-TyphoonRuss     12-20 0260</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Typhoon Russ,0301</SECOND>
<HEAD>Typhoon Russ Roars over Guam</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Residents waited behind boarded windows or
fled to shelters early <DATE>Friday</DATE> while <PERSON>Typhoon Russ</PERSON> battered the
island with winds topping 100 mph.
said.
   Russ was the strongest typhoon to hit this western <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>
island in more than a decade. It toppled trees, pushed surf to more
than 20 feet high and made movement around the 30-mile-long island
virtually impossible.
   ``Everybody's just sitting tight,'' <ORGANIZATION>Guam Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> spokesman
<PERSON>Mike Franquez</PERSON> said. ``We'll wait for the winds to pass and then
assess the damage.''
   About 145,000 people live on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. The last storm to cause major
damage here was Typhoon Pamela in <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   Winds were clocked at 90 mph with gusts to 115 mph when the
storm made its closest pass before dawn, said <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Capt. <PERSON>Dieter
Rudolph</PERSON>, commander of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Typhoon Warning Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   The wind readings were taken at the typhoon center, near the
north end of north-south lying island. The storm's center brushed
<LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s south coast, and southern areas were pummelled by the
strongest winds.
   The storm's maximum sustained winds were 145 mph, with gusts to
175 mph, <PERSON>Rudolph</PERSON> said. It was moving west-northwest at 13 mph.
   About 2,300 people went to shelters at schools. The windows of
most buildings had been boarded up, <PERSON>Franquez</PERSON> said.
   To avert the potential problem of dangling live wires if power
lines break, electricity was shut off to most of the island. Water
also was cut off. Some coastal roads were closed because the high
surf left them strewn with debris.
   ``There's downed power lines, downed trees, flooded streets,''
said <PERSON>Dave Ecret</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>KGUM Radio</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's just an eerie kind of
feeling.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890926-0267 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-26-89 1554EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Guam-Fraud     09-26 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Guam-Fraud,0441</SECOND>
<HEAD>Executive Gets 18 Months in Mail Fraud Case</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Wall Street executive who pleaded guilty to
three counts of mail fraud for for allegedly bribing a former
governor of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> has been sentenced to 18 months in prison.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Jesse W. Curtis</PERSON> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> also placed <PERSON>Arthur
Abba Goldberg</PERSON> on five years' probation, fined him <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> and
ordered him to repay the <ORGANIZATION>United States</ORGANIZATION> <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON>, executive vice president of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> bond
underwriting firm of <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>, pleaded guilty <DATE>July 14</DATE> to
three counts of mail fraud.
   He had been accused of funneling <MONEY>$70,000</MONEY> to former Guam Gov.
<PERSON>Ricardo J. Bordallo</PERSON>'s unsuccessful <DATE>1986</DATE> re-election campaign. In
exchange, <PERSON>Bordallo</PERSON> allegedly agreed to generate support for a <MONEY>$300
million</MONEY> housing bond issue underwritten by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>.
   Bordallo was acquitted in <DATE>February 1986</DATE> of accepting bribes from
<PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> but was convicted on 10 counts of government corruption.
He served as governor from 1975-79 and from 1983-87.
   <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> had faced a maximum 15 years' imprisonment and a
<MONEY>$750,000</MONEY> fine in addition to restitution payments, according to
<PERSON>William O'Connor</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> attorney from <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>.
   The three counts referred to money bilked from the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Program
Development Fund</ORGANIZATION> and a ``lulling letter'' assuring fund authorities
that the transactions were legal.
   A <DATE>December 1987</DATE> indictment charged <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> with preparing phony
invoices that were sent to the bank entrusted with the fund money.
   The bank paid the money to <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON>, who spent <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> to buy
campaign paraphernalia _ including parasols, shirts and hats _ for
<PERSON>Bordallo</PERSON>'s unsuccessful re-election bid, <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> has said.
   Authorities said <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> made his contributions after <PERSON>Bordallo</PERSON>
was promised that he would receive campaign contributions if he
supported the bond issue to build homes. The bond was approved by
the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Legislature</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> has denied any
wrongdoing.
   In exchange for <ORGANIZATION>Goldberg</ORGANIZATION>'s guilty pleas, 46 other counts
alleging bribery, conspiracy, and wire and mail fraud were
dismissed. The case was moved from <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, 3,800 miles west of
<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, because of extensive pretrial publicity on the island.
   Twelve of the original counts against <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> were related
directly to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. The balance referred to fraud involving the use
of the <ORGANIZATION>Commercial Bank of Americas</ORGANIZATION> in transactions that did not
involve the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory.
   In <DATE>August 1987</DATE>, Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON> sued <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> for the
return of <MONEY>$14 million</MONEY> in fees the firm had received, as well as
<MONEY>$250 million</MONEY> in punitive damages. <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> said in <DATE>July</DATE> the suit
had been settled, but he released no details.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901128-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-28-90 1255EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-TyphoonOwen     11-28 0241</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Typhoon Owen,0270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Compact But Powerful Typhoon Sweeps Through Micronesia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon <PERSON>Owen</PERSON>, a fierce storm with 125 mph
winds, slammed into the <LOCATION>Federated States</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Micronesia</LOCATION> today,
killing two people and leaving more than 1,000 people homeless,
officials said.
   The two men were killed in the Micronesian capital of <LOCATION>Pohnpei</LOCATION>
when they were electrocuted by downed power lines, said <PERSON>Tony
Palomo</PERSON>, a representative of the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Department of the Interior</ORGANIZATION>.
   Early reports estimated that well over 1,000 people were left
homeless after the powerful storm packing winds of 125 mph and
gusts of 155 mph battered the outer islands of Pulap, <ORGANIZATION>Ruo</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Nomwin</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Fananu</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Murilo</ORGANIZATION> and Tamatam in the state of <LOCATION>Chuuk</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Ismael
Dobich</PERSON>, public affairs director of <ORGANIZATION>Chuuk</ORGANIZATION>.
   Each island has about 500 residents. <LOCATION>Micronesia</LOCATION> is in the
western <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>, north of the equator. The principal island
groups include the <PERSON>Caroline Islands</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Nauru</LOCATION>, the <PERSON>Gilbert Islnads</PERSON>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Mariana Islands</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Marshall Islands</LOCATION>.
   Owen destroyed nearly every home on Pulap and <ORGANIZATION>Ruo</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Dobich</PERSON> said.
The entire banana, coconut, taro and bread fruit crops were
destroyed on <ORGANIZATION>Ruo</ORGANIZATION>, Dobich.
   ``In Pulap, all of the homes were destroyed with the exception
of one concrete structure,'' <PERSON>Dobich</PERSON> said. Most of the homes were
made of wood and tin.
   Owen was expected to regain supertyphoon status by late <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
or early <DATE>Friday</DATE>, with forecasters predicting winds of 150 mph and
gusts to 180 mph.
   <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, 1,488 miles from <LOCATION>Chuuk</LOCATION>, remains on a typhoon alert status.
Owen was about 405 miles south of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, an American territory,
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900823-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-23-90 0645EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-GuamAbortion 3rdLd-Writethru a0507 08-23 0494</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Guam Abortion, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0507,0503</SECOND>
<HEAD>Federal Judge Strikes Down Guam's Abortion Law</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to ADD background on charges against ACLU
lawyer; PICKS UP 6th graf pvs, ``I'm still ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge today struck down <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s
virtual ban on abortion as unconstitutional. The measure was the
nation's most restrictive abortion law.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Alex Munson</PERSON> declared that <PERSON>Roe vs. Wade</PERSON>, the
<DATE>1973</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> decision establishing the right to an abortion,
``applied with equal force and effect to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>.''
   The law, signed by Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON> on <DATE>March 19</DATE>, banned abortions
except when the mother's life is in danger. But <PERSON>Munson</PERSON> on <DATE>March 23</DATE>
blocked its enforcement while he weighed a challenge to the law
from abortion-rights forces.
   The law carried a penalty of up to a year in jail and a <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>
fine for obtaining an illegal abortion or soliciting a woman to
have an abortion. Performing an illegal abortion was punishable by
up to five years in prison.
   Two days after the law went into effect, an <ORGANIZATION>American Civil
Liberties Union</ORGANIZATION> lawyer, <PERSON>Janet Benshoof</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, was charged
with violating the measure by publicly encouraging women to seek
abortions in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. The charges later were dropped; prosecutors
said the lawsuit challenging the law was a higher priority.
   The governor said he did not know whether he would appeal
today's ruling.
   ``I'm still very pro-life, and I believe that a fetus is a human
being and should be given life,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION>, a Roman Catholic like
the vast majority of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s residents.
   The challenge to the law was brought by an unidentified pregnant
woman who wanted an abortion, the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Society</ORGANIZATION> of Obstetricians and
Gynecologists, the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Nurses Association</ORGANIZATION>, an Episcopal priest and
three doctors.
   <PERSON>Anita Arriola</PERSON>, a lawyer for the abortion-rights side, had argued
that the law _ introduced by her mother, territorial <PERSON>Sen. Elizabeth
Arriola</PERSON> _ was contrary to <PERSON>Roe vs. Wade</PERSON> and was passed to promote a
particular religious belief.
   <PERSON>Katherine A. Maraman</PERSON>, representing the government of this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
possession in the <LOCATION>Western Pacific</LOCATION>, had argued that <PERCENT>99 percent</PERCENT> of
all abortions on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> were not necessary but were for the
convenience of the mother.
   In his ruling, <PERSON>Munson</PERSON> said sections of the law are vague and
that the provision against soliciting an abortion violates the
right to free speech.
   <PERSON>Arriola</PERSON> said the decision ``sends a very clear signal to
<ORGANIZATION>Governor Ada</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Legislature</ORGANIZATION> and other legislatures around
the country.''
   ``This decision means that <PERSON>Roe vs. Wade</PERSON> is still the law of the
land,'' said <PERSON>Lou Leon Guerrero</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>People for Choice</ORGANIZATION>.
   Dawn <PERSON>C. Leon Guerrero</PERSON>, chairwoman of the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Pro-Life
Coalition</ORGANIZATION>, said she expected the ruling, ``because the judge has to
follow legal precedent.''
   ``We figured that it wouldn't be an easy climb,'' said <PERSON>Roland
Rivera</PERSON>, vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Guamanians United for Life</ORGANIZATION>. ``There is
just the next higher level to pursue.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GuamAbortion     03-25 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guam Abortion,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Sets Trial Date for Anti-Abortion Law</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge on <DATE>Monday</DATE> extended a
restraining order against enforcement of the most restrictive <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
abortion law.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Alex Munson</PERSON> had issued a temporary
restraining order <DATE>Friday</DATE>, a few hours after a group of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>
residents and medical groups filed a class-action suit. On <DATE>Monday</DATE>,
he extended the order until <DATE>May 8</DATE>, when a trial on the suit is
scheduled to begin.
   ``We're very happy,'' said <PERSON>Anita Arriola</PERSON>, the plaintiffs'
attorney.
   The law prohibits abortions except when a pregnancy endangers
the life of the mother. It makes it a third-degree felony to
perform an abortion or aid in the procedure, a misdemeanor for a
woman to solicit or have an abortion and a misdemeanor for a person
to solicit a woman to have an abortion.
   The law in this <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> territory is seen by abortion opponents
as a potential vehicle to challenge the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Roe
vs. Wade</PERSON> decision that legalized abortion.
   The <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> law provides for a referendum in the <DATE>Nov. 6</DATE> general
election for <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> voters to decide whether to retain or reject the
abortion ban.
   <PERSON>Janet Benshoof</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>American Civil Liberties Union's
Reproductive Freedom Project</ORGANIZATION> defied the law <DATE>last Tuesday</DATE> when she
publicly encouraged women seeking abortions to have them done in
<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. She was charged in the territorial <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> with
solicitation to commit abortion, a misdemeanor.
   Among those named in the suit is Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON>, who signed the
measure into law <DATE>March 19</DATE>.
   The plaintiffs include ``<PERSON>Maria Doe</PERSON>,'' a <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> woman who is eight
weeks pregnant and wants an abortion; the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Society</ORGANIZATION> of
Obstetricians and Gynecologists, the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Nurses Association</ORGANIZATION>, an
Episcopal priest and three <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> doctors.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 0326EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TyphoonRuss 1stLd-Writethru a0431 12-24 0264</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Typhoon Russ, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0431,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>10 on Fishing Boat Crew Missing After Typhoon Russ</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS in 3 grafs with search suspended, no sight of missing;
pick up 4th graf, `The Marguarita ...'.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> today called off a search for
10 crew members of a South Korean fishing boat missing for three
days since Typhoon <PERSON>Russ</PERSON> swept the area, officials said.
   A military transport ship located the partially submerged hull
of the 68-foot Marguarita I 35 miles off the southern tip of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, but there was no sign of the crew, the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> cutter <LOCATION>Assateague</LOCATION> and a C130 aircraft searched a
19,000-square-mile area but didn't locate any crew members, said
Lt. <PERSON>Bob Ritchie</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard Rescue Center</ORGANIZATION> on this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
island territory in the <LOCATION>Western Pacific</LOCATION>. He said the search was
called off today.
   The Marguarita I sailed from <LOCATION>Agana</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, even though it
was well known the typhoon was bearing down on the island, said
<ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> Lt. <PERSON>Jeffrey Lee</PERSON>, duty officer for the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Rescue
Coordination Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>.
   The fishing vessel radioed its agent here late <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that it
was disabled with a clutch problem, <PERSON>Lee</PERSON> said.
   Communication with the boat was lost <DATE>Friday</DATE> when electrical
power went out on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> as Typhoon <PERSON>Russ</PERSON> battered the island with
wind up to 150 mph.
   <ORGANIZATION>Federal Emergency Management Agency</ORGANIZATION> officials said the storm
damged or destroyed more than 2,000 homes and injured 88 people. No
deaths were reported.
   <ORGANIZATION>Guam Power Authority</ORGANIZATION> officials said they expected to have
electrical power restored to <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the island today. Water
service remained disrupted in many areas because pumps were without
electrical power.
   Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON> has asked President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to declare the island a
disaster area.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900831-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-31-90 2052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-GuamPrimary     08-31 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guam Primary,0564</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop Encourages Guamanians to Vote Against Pro-Choice
Candidates</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The fight to keep abortion legal on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> is
being overshadowed in <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s primary elections by the
possibility that the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory may have its first woman and
non-native governor.
   Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON> is unopposed on the Republican ballot as he
seeks a second term.
   Democrats face a choice between <PERSON>Sen. Madeleine Z. Bordallo</PERSON>, a
native of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> and widow of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s former governor, or former
Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Rudy Sablan</PERSON>. The winner will face <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Nov. 6</DATE>.
   Guam's 21-member unicameral legislature unanimously approved a
bill virtually banning abortions <DATE>March 8</DATE> after <PERSON>Archbishop Anthony
Apuron</PERSON> threatened in a television interview to excommunicate any
Roman Catholic senator who voted against it.
   Ada signed the bill into law, saying: ``In my heart, I believe
that a fetus is a human being.''
   The law carried a penalty of up to a year in jail and a <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>
fine for obtaining an illegal abortion or soliciting a woman to
have an abortion. Performing an illegal abortion was punishable by
up to five years in prison.
   Last week, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Alex Munson</PERSON> struck down the law
as unconstitutional. Munson declared that <PERSON>Roe vs. Wade</PERSON>, the <DATE>1973</DATE>
<ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> decision establishing the right to an abortion,
``applied with equal force and effect to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>.''
   Ada has not indicated whether he will seek an appeal.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Bordallo</PERSON> has said she also opposes abortion.
   <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> said he's running on his record of the past four years. He
said he is confident he and his running mate, Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Frank Blas</PERSON>,
will win re-election.
   On <DATE>Jan. 31</DATE>, <PERSON>Mrs. Bordallo</PERSON>'s husband, <PERSON>Ricardo</PERSON>, chained himself to
a statue, wrapped himself in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s flag and shot himself in the
head. That occurred less than four hours before he was to fly to
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to begin serving a four-year prison term for witness
tampering and obstruction.
   Ada defeated <PERSON>Bordallo</PERSON> in the <DATE>1986</DATE> election after <PERSON>Bordallo</PERSON> had
been indicted on the federal charges.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Bordallo</PERSON> wants to be <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s first woman governor and the
first governor who is non-Chamorro, the name for native Guamanians.
   ``Women are moving ahead today. They are leading countries.
Right next door, we have a housewife leading 60 million people,''
said <PERSON>Mrs. Bordallo</PERSON>, referring to Philippine President <PERSON>Corazon
Aquino</PERSON>.
   Some 130,000 people life on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, an island about 1,500 miles
east of the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Bordallo</PERSON>, 57, came to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> in <DATE>1948</DATE> when her father accepted
a position as principal of <ORGANIZATION>George Washington High School</ORGANIZATION> here.
   <PERSON>Sablan</PERSON>, 58, served as Gov. <PERSON>Bordallo</PERSON>'s lieutenant governor from
<DATE>1974</DATE> to <DATE>1978</DATE>, unsuccessfully challenged <PERSON>Bordallo</PERSON> in the Democratic
primaries in <DATE>1978</DATE> and <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Sablan</PERSON>, who also opposes abortion, said one of his priorities as
governor would be to set up a territorial tax structure that is not
tied to the federal tax system.
   The archbishop issued a pastoral letter published in newspapers
this week calling for voters to vote down pro-choice candidates.
   ``Like a modern day <ORGANIZATION>Pontius Pilate</ORGANIZATION>, a legislator or official may
attempt to wash his or her hands of abortion,'' <PERSON>Apuron</PERSON> said.
``However, the legislator cannot wash away the blood of the
innocents he or she has consciously declined to protect. Nor can
the voter sit idly by in apathy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870810-0086 </DOCNO>
<HL> Guam, Saipan
Sue Underwriter
On Bond Issues
---
Matthews &amp; Wright Misled
About Funding Projects,
Pacific Islands Charge
---
By Ken Wells
<DD> 08/10/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MW
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON)
SECURITIES INDUSTRY (SCR) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The governments of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> islands of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> filed separate damage suits against <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION> alleging fraud and breach of contract in the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> bond firm's underwriting of huge bond issues there. 

   The suits, among a growing number of civil complaints against the Wall Street concern, seek <MONEY>$350 million</MONEY> in punitive damages and ask for a return of about <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> in underwriting fees collected by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Filed in district courts of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territories, the suits also seek additional damages for "injuries suffered" to both islands' economies, said <PERSON>Donald C. Williams</PERSON>, an attorney representing the islands. 
The suits also name <PERSON>George Benoit</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>'s president and chairman; <PERSON>Arthur Abba Goldberg</PERSON>, its executive vice president; <PERSON>Frederick Mann</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> businessman who served as an "authorized representative" in the bond issues; and a score of lawyers and consultants who helped package the bond issues. 

   <PERSON>Gerald A. Feffer</PERSON>, a Washington-based lawyer representing <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>, said, "We haven't seen the complaint" and therefore couldn't comment on the issue. 
In <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Mann</PERSON> didn't return phone calls seeking comment on the suits. 

   As previously reported, both the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> issue, for <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> to finance low-income housing, and the <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> issue, which was to fund <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY> in housing projects, are among more than 20 <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> bond issues under federal investigation. 
Many of the issues, all completed in <DATE>1985</DATE> and <DATE>1986</DATE> and representing about <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> in investments, are suspected of having been sham transactions designed largely to reap huge fees for the underwriter, federal officials close to the investigation have said. 

   In some cases, the underwriter is suspected of creating phony sales to beat a federal tax exemption deadline, and in others of coaxing municipalities into floating projects so huge and unrealistic that they were never viable. 
Investigators close to the case say that in some instances <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> is suspected of doing both. 
A number of grand juries investigating the bond issues, including one on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, also are investigating suspicions that <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> in some cases made payoffs to selected public officials to win their support for the bond issues. 
Attorneys hired by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> to conduct an internal company investigation have said they found no evidence of bribery. 

   The federal probe, as reported, extends beyond <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> to perhaps a half-dozen other underwriters and involves another 80 municipal issues representing an additional <MONEY>$9 billion</MONEY>. 
All of the issues are so-called arbitrage or escrow bonds, a controversial type of financing that since has been greatly restricted by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. 
Until projects could get off the ground, proceeds from such low-interest bonds could be invested in higher-interest instruments that would provide income to issuers, fees to underwriters and returns to investors -- whether projects got built or not. 
In some cases, the proceeds in escrow were invested in a way that would protect the bond investors should the projects be scrapped. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, in <DATE>1985</DATE>, decided to severely curb arbitrage, arguing it gave issuers little incentive to complete projects and led to abuses. 
The congressional action set off a stampede of last-minute arbitrage bond filings in <DATE>December 1985</DATE> and <DATE>August 1986</DATE> in advance of two deadlines. 

   On both <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION>, no projects have yet been built under the bond issues, something common to many of the <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> issues. 
The bonds were structured so that the proceeds in escrow were kept from developers, thus preventing the financing for the projects to get under way. 
As a result, local contractors with limited skills and few resources were left to raise huge amounts of money in the interim, a task most have found impossible, according to investigators who have looked at many of the <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> issues. 

   In their lawsuits, <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> allege that <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>, and its various consultants, breached promises and commitments to help obtain such financing, or misled local contractors about the availability or ease of obtaining financial backing for bond projects. 
The islands fear that the bond-issue problems might shut them out of the municipal credit markets in the future. 

   In a separate issue, the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> suit also seeks to overturn an agreement between <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> and a <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> economic development agency that essentially limits the liability of the underwriter to <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> in its preparation of the bond issue, shifting the liability to the government. 
The suit charges that the agreement represents an unauthorized "modification" to the original legislation authorizing the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> bonds. 

   Guam is a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> trust territory of about 100,000 residents about 7,500 miles southwest of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION>, a neighboring island, has about 20,000 residents and is the capital of a multi-island chain known as the Commonwealth of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Marianas Islands</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880824-0082 </DOCNO>
<HL> IRS Won't Amplify On Move Involving Municipal Bonds </HL>
<AUTHOR> John Connor (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> TAXES </CO>
<IN> BON SCR </IN>
<G> IRS </G>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior <ORGANIZATION>Internal Revenue Service</ORGANIZATION> official refused to say if the agency is likely to issue more letters, such as those sent to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Northern Mariana Islands</LOCATION>, specifying that certain municipal bonds sold as tax-exempt securities are not tax-exempt. 
But he said the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> is "not unaware" of a number of additional problem municipal issues. 

   "We just can't discuss anything we've got in-house," the official said, explaining that the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> is barred by law from discussing taxpayer matters, including municipal bond deals suspected or deemed to have failed the tests for tax exemption. 

   At the same time, he said the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> is "not unaware of a number of other bond issues" believed to have tax problems. 

   Former <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> tax attorney <PERSON>Joseph Krolikowski</PERSON>, now in private law practice in <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, said the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> letters to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Northern Marianas</LOCATION> "may open up a new era of the service quasi-publicly declaring bonds taxable." 
The <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> action is "a healthy development," he said. 
As previously reported, <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> Commissioner <PERSON>Lawrence Gibbs</PERSON> recently told the governors of the Territory of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and the Commonwealth of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Mariana Islands</ORGANIZATION> that interest on <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> bonds sold in <DATE>October 1985</DATE> and on <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY> of <LOCATION>Northern Marianas</LOCATION> bonds sold in <DATE>December 1984</DATE> "is not tax exempt." 
The agency concluded the bonds were arbitrage bonds. 
Both bond issues were underwritten by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which said it believed the bonds were validly issued and are tax-exempt. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Gibbs</PERSON> said in his letters that the bond issuing agencies are entitled to a conference where additional facts or legal arguments could be presented regarding the tax status of the bonds. 
He further stated: "If desired, we will also consider whether there are good and sufficient reasons for finally resolving this matter through use of a closing agreement. 
Generally, under such agreements the service foregoes taxing the interest in the hands of the bondholders but collects all or an appropriate percentage of such lost revenues from the issuer." 

   Some lawyers involved in the matter, noting the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> letters set no deadlines for talks or for any closing agreement, speculated that the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> could let things stand as they are indefinitely, without actually taxing bondholders. 
However, there are clear indications the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> doesn't plan to let the matter remain pending indefinitely. 

   Some market participants following the slowly unfolding arbitrage bond saga said they expect a number of other "not-tax-exempt" letters to come from the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>. 
They cited as leading candidates for such treatment the so-called <LOCATION>South Tucson</LOCATION> bonds, three bond issues totaling <MONEY>$368 million</MONEY> from three <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> communities. 
Several market people said privately there are billions of dollars of questionable bonds sold earlier in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> that could warrant "not tax-exempt" treatment by the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> on the same grounds cited in the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Northern Marianas Islands</LOCATION> letters. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880616-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-16-88 2109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Drugs-Territories     06-16 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drugs-Territories,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pacific Islands Representatives Seek Federal Aid to Combat Drug
Problems</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY MARGASAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territories told a
congressional panel <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that they have increasing drug
problems, and need the additional federal aid included in pending
legislation.
   The bill, introduced by Rep. <PERSON>Don de Lugo</PERSON>, D-Virgin Islands,
would provide training, equipment and money for <ORGANIZATION>American Samoa</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Northern Mariana Islands</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin
Islands</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Palau</ORGANIZATION>.
   De <PERSON>Lugo</PERSON>, who presided at the hearing as chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House
Interior</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee on insular and international affairs, said he
expected the legislation to become part of a planned comprehensive
drug bill this year.
   The legislation would provide <MONEY>$11.5 million</MONEY> in assistance in the
first year, and <MONEY>$5.5 million</MONEY> annually in subsequent years.
   Gov. <PERSON>Alexander A. Farrelly</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION> said his
territory has become a major transit point for drugs moving from
<LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mainland.
   But the governor and <PERSON>Iver Stridiron</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>Virgin
Islands</LOCATION> legislature, said significant amounts of the drugs remain
in the territory and are causing a large increase in violent crimes.
   ``It really has our community under siege,'' <PERSON>Stridiron</PERSON> said. But
he added that with additional resources, the island territory could
become a model of combatting the drug problem in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territories.
   Farrelly said his major problem is resources, commenting that
the assignment of a single <ORGANIZATION>Drug Enforcement Administration</ORGANIZATION> agent in
the islands indicates either ``non-recognition of a serious
problem'' or lack of interest in solving it.
   Gov. <PERSON>Joseph F. Ada</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> said his territory is experiencing a
resurgence of heroin abuse after cleaning up the problem following
the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   ``In <DATE>1985</DATE>, there was not one single case of heroin possession in
the territory of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>,'' he testified. ``In <DATE>1986</DATE>, 12 heroin arrests
were made by our police department.
   ``In <DATE>1987</DATE>, there were 108 cases of heroin possession, with 56
still pending laboratory analysis and confirmation. By any
definition, this is an alarming rise,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The governor said <PERCENT>91 percent</PERCENT> pure heroin from <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> has
been entering <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> through <ORGANIZATION>Palau</ORGANIZATION>. But after law enforcement
officers discovered the route, the drugs began coming to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> via
the <LOCATION>Northern Marianas</LOCATION>, he said.
   Asked by de <PERSON>Lugo</PERSON> if he could put a cost on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s drug problem,
<ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> said the law enforcement price tag could be <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$3
million</MONEY>, but added the real cost could only be measured in trauma
and shattered lives _ not dollars.
   Responding to a question by Rep. <PERSON>Fofo I.F. Sunia</PERSON>, D-American
<LOCATION>Samoa</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> said he would fire anyone in his administration abusing
drugs with ``no questions asked.''
   A written statement submitted by <ORGANIZATION>American Samoa</ORGANIZATION> Gov. <PERSON>A.P. Lutali</PERSON>
said the ``most pervasive and growing illegal substance abuse
problem'' in his territory is marijuana, followed by cocaine.
   Referring to the marijuana problem, <PERSON>Lutali</PERSON>'s statement said,
``What 10 years ago was a situation involving a relatively small
number of individuals importing the drug through the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mail has
now become a cultivation enterprises market by extended families
producing in excess of seven tons per year.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890715-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-89 0219EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GuamFraud     07-15 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guam Fraud,0485</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bond Firm Executive Pleads Guilty to Fraud Involving Guam</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUINN LOTA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> executive accused of pumping money
into the campaign of a former governor of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> in exchange for a
political favor pleaded guilty <DATE>Friday</DATE> to three counts of mail fraud.
   <PERSON>Arthur Abba Goldberg</PERSON> entered the plea before <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge
Jesse Curtis</PERSON>, said <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney, <PERSON>Bill O'Connor</PERSON>. In exchange
for his guilty plea, 46 counts alleging bribery, conspiracy, wire
and mail fraud, and violation of interstate racketeering statutes
were dismissed.
   ``In dismissing the counts, the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> issues were dissolved,''
<PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> said. ``Other issues are on the table if another
jurisdiction sees fit to follow through.''
   Twelve of the counts were related directly to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
territory since <DATE>August, 1950</DATE>, said <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON>. The balance of the
counts related to fraud involving use of the <ORGANIZATION>Commercial Bank of
Americas</ORGANIZATION> in transactions that did not involve <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> said.
   Although <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON>, executive vice president of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> bond
underwriting firm of <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>, only pleaded to three of the
dozen counts, <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> was satisfied with the outcome.
   ``<PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON>'s plea gave the same latitude of sentencing than
if he went to trial,'' <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> said. ``We, of course, will
recommend jail time and a heavy fine.''
   Goldberg faces a possible 15 years imprisonment, a <MONEY>$750,000</MONEY> fine
and restitution payments, <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> said in a telephone interview
from his <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> office. Sentencing was scheduled in <PERSON>Curtis</PERSON>' court
<DATE>Sept. 11</DATE>.
   One of <ORGANIZATION>Goldberg</ORGANIZATION>'s attorneys, <PERSON>Howard L. Weitzman</PERSON>, said he had no
immediate comment. A receptionist who answered a call made after
business hours to another defense attorney, <PERSON>Bruce Hochman</PERSON>, said
<PERSON>Hochman</PERSON> had gone for the day.
   The three mail fraud counts concerned <MONEY>$57,500</MONEY> bilked from the
<ORGANIZATION>Guam Program Development Fund</ORGANIZATION> and a letter assuring fund authorities
that transactions were above board, while fraud was taking place.
   Goldberg prepared phony invoices that were sent to the bank
entrusted with fund money. ``The bank paid the money <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON>
exerted for his purposes and ... he attempted to cover up later with
false papers in the files,'' <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>O'Connor</PERSON> said <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> was ``used to buy campaign paraphernalia _
parasols, hats, shirts, junk like that'' for Guam Gov. <PERSON>Ricardo J.
Bordallo</PERSON>'s unsuccessful <DATE>1986</DATE> re-election bid.
   The funds were funneled to Bordallo after he was promised the
money in exchange for his support on a bond issue, <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> of
which was sold by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>.
   The bond was approved by the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Legislature</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp;
Wright</ORGANIZATION> deny any wrongdoing.
   Bordallo was acquitted in <DATE>February, 1986</DATE>, of accepting bribes
from <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> but convicted on 10 counts of government corruption.
   The case is among about 25 municipal bond deals nationwide
involving <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> under investigation by the <ORGANIZATION>Securities
and Exchange Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880120-0005 </DOCNO>
<HL> Goldberg Pleads Innocent In Guam Bond Fraud Case </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> MW FREST </CO>
<IN> BON </IN>
<DATELINE> AGANA, Guam (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Arthur Abba Goldberg</PERSON>, executive vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> bond underwriting firm, pleaded innocent to charges he orchestrated a bogus <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> bond issue on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. 

   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Cristobal Duenas</PERSON> allowed <PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON> to be freed on a <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> unsecured bond. 
He is represented by <ORGANIZATION>Stanley S. Arkin</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Frederick L. Mann</PERSON>, a Canadian citizen and former consultant to <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>, were indicted <DATE>Dec. 10</DATE> on 52 counts of bribery, conspiracy, wire fraud and mail fruad, and violation of interstate anti-racketeering statutes in a scheme to amass more than <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY> in fraudulent bond issues in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Palau</LOCATION>, the Commonwealth of the <LOCATION>Northern Marianas</LOCATION> and cities across the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   <PERSON>Mr. Mann</PERSON>, who also was scheduled for arraignment yesterday, did not appear. 
Prosecutors said they did not know his whereabouts. 

   <PERSON>Edward K. Strauss</PERSON>, legal counsel to <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> on the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> bond, pleaded guilty last week to a charge of withholding knowledge of Messrs. 
<PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON>'s and <PERSON>Mann</PERSON>'s actions. 
He agreed to disclose knowledge of their alleged schemes in exchange for a recommendation of no prison term. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032190-0065 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 192571 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 21, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 4; Column 5; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
492 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FIRST CHARGES FILED TO TEST STRICT GUAM ABORTION LAW 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By NANCY YOSHIHARA, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
AGANA, Guam 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Guam's attorney general, seeking a constitutional test of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territory's 
day-old anti-abortion law, on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> filed a complaint against a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 
woman who had disseminated information here about terminating pregnancies. 
</P>
<P>
Guam's law, signed by Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, is the most restrictive 
abortion legislation in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and has riveted national attention on 
this tiny <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION> island. 
</P>
<P>
The law makes it a felony to perform an abortion even in cases of rape, incest 
and fetal abnormality. An abortion is allowed only if two independent doctors 
determine a pregnancy would endanger the life of a mother or gravely impair her 
health. 
</P>
<P>
It also makes it a misdemeanor to have an abortion or "knowingly solicit" 
pregnant women to have one. 
</P>
<P>
In the complaint filed in Superior Court here, Atty. Gen. <PERSON>Elizabeth 
Barrett-Anderson</PERSON> said that <PERSON>Janet Benshoof</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Reproductive Rights 
Project</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>American Civil Liberties Union</ORGANIZATION>, violated the law when she 
encouraged pregnant women seeking abortions to leave <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> for <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Barrett-Anderson had previously advised both the governor and the <ORGANIZATION>Guam 
Legislature</ORGANIZATION> that the abortion law was unconstitutional and said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that 
her action was designed to force a constitutional test. 
</P>
<P>
"My decision to bring a criminal charge under the new law will provide the 
basis for the courts to decide the question as quickly as possible. I believe 
this will be in the best interests of the government and of all persons 
affected by the new law," Barrett-Anderson said. 
</P>
<P>
Voters in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> have an opportunity to repeal the legislation in a referendum 
scheduled in <DATE>November</DATE>. The law was passed by the territorial Legislature after 
the archbishop of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> had threatened to excommunicate those who opposed the 
measure, although most of the legislators said they were unaware of the threat. 
More than <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of the population on the island is Roman Catholic. 
</P>
<P>
In signing the legislation on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, Gov. <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION> had insisted the law was a local 
issue. "I am not taking this action today to affect anyone's life in the 50 
states. I believe that this is a community issue and a community concern, first 
and foremost." 
</P>
<P>
But abortion foes and abortion rights supporters have seized upon the law as a 
possible test of the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>'s willingness to temper or undo its historic 
<PERSON>Roe vs. Wade</PERSON> decision, which guaranteed women a right to an abortion. 
</P>
<P>
Idaho and <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> are currently studying abortion legislation, but the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> 
law caught activists by surprise. Benshoof arrived in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> over the weekend 
proclaiming that the new statute cannot coexist with <PERSON>Roe vs. Wade</PERSON> and likened 
the bill to a "<LOCATION>Pearl Harbor</LOCATION> for women." 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> she acknowledged that she was breaking the law in providing the 
name, address and phone number of a <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> group that could help women get an 
abortion. The attorney general's complaint was filed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. 
Benshoof's arraignment was set for today. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
GUAM -- LAWS; LEGISLATION -- GUAM; ABORTION 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900320-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-20-90 0739EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-GuamAbortion 1stLd-Writethru a0468 03-20 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Guam Abortion, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0468,0583</SECOND>
<HEAD>Foes, Advocates of Legalized Abortion Square Off in Guam</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, ``In my...' to delete redundant first
reference to Ada. FIXES category code. Arraignment scheduled for
mid-morning EST.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. <PERSON>Joseph Ada</PERSON> said a fetus is a human being
in signing a bill creating the most restrictive <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> abortion
statute, but abortion rights advocates already are challenging the
measure.
   <PERSON>Janet Benshoof</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>American Civil Liberties Union</ORGANIZATION> lawyer,
immediately violated the law by telling women in a speech where to
go to have an abortion, and the territory's attorney general _ who
personally opposes the measure _ pressed charges.
   Territorial Attorney General <PERSON>Elizabeth Barrett-Anderson</PERSON> says
prosecuting the case will be ``a heavy burden,'' but a
responsibility of her job.
   Benshoof made a court appearance <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> time, but
Superior Court <PERSON>Judge Ramon V. Diaz</PERSON> said he could not hear the case
because he did not feel he could render a fair and impartial
decision.
   Benshoof is scheduled to be arraigned today.
   The law, which passed despite a ruling by Barrett-Anderson that
it is unconstitutional, makes it a third-degree felony for a person
to perform or help in an abortion. Seeking or having an abortion or
soliciting someone to have an abortion are misdemeanors.
   The law also sets a referendum during the <DATE>Nov. 6</DATE> general
election for residents of this <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION> island about 1,500
miles east of the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> to decide whether to keep the law.
   ``In my heart, I believe that a fetus is a human being,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION>,
the Republican governor, said in signing the bill, which prohibits
abortion except when the mother's health or life are endangered.
   <PERSON>Benshoof</PERSON> said she immediately violated a provision of the law by
advising women in a speech at the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Press Club</ORGANIZATION> later in the day
to go to <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> to have legal abortions.
   ``I was very specific in my breaking of the law,'' <PERSON>Benshoof</PERSON>
said. ``The information that I gave, which is now a crime, came
from the <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION> Yellow Pages.''
   Barrett-Anderson filed a misdemeanor complaint charging <PERSON>Benshoof</PERSON>
with violating the ban on soliciting someone to have an abortion.
Benshoof faces up to a year in jail and a <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> fine if convicted.
   ``It's a matter of public record that I advised the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>
Legislature ... that in my opinion the bill was unconstitutional by
operation of the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>'s decision in <PERSON>Roe v. Wade</PERSON>,''
<PERSON>Barrett-Anderson</PERSON> said later in a statement.
   ``My advisory role has now shifted to one of enforcement. This
is a heavy burden, but ... I will enforce this statute to the
extent that the law allows.''
   <PERSON>Benshoof</PERSON>, who went to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> to try to persuade Ada not to sign
the bill, was not arrested but appeared in court voluntarily.
   Guam's 21-member unicameral Legislature unanimously approved the
bill <DATE>March 8</DATE> after <PERSON>Archbishop Anthony Apuron</PERSON> threatened in an
interview with a television reporter to excommunicate any Roman
Catholic senator who voted against it. All but one of the senators
is <LOCATION>Catholic</LOCATION>, as is <ORGANIZATION>Ada</ORGANIZATION>. However, most of the senators said they
were unaware of the threat.
   Among those hailing the new law was the <ORGANIZATION>National Right to Life
Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This is great news,'' group spokeswoman <PERSON>Nancy Myers</PERSON> said in a
telephone interview from her <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> office. ``The people of
<LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> are largely pro-life as reflected by the unanimous vote in the
Legislature, and they have made a strong statement.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880213-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-13-88 0443EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-PoliticalBriefs     02-13 0283</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Political Briefs,280</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Picks Up Four Territorial Votes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four delegates were chosen today to represent
say they support Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> for president.
   Those selected at the territory's Republican convention included
territorial Gov. <PERSON>Joseph F. Ada</PERSON>, who said of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>: ``He knows where
<LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> is. His heart is in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. He told me that one of these days
the people of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> are going to vote for president.''
   Although residents of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> are American citizens, they are not
allowed to cast ballots in presidential elections.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said of the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> results: ``This victory is a tribute to
the hard work and dedication of our organization there.''
   About 200 party members who attended the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> gathering approved
a number of resolutions that will be given to all <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> presidential
candidates.
   One of the resolutions supports the drive to give territorial
residents the right to vote in presidential elections, while
another presses for <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> to become a commonwealth of the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<HEAD>Portsmouth Herald Endorses Dole, Dukakis In New Hampshire Primary</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTSMOUTH, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four delegates were chosen today to represent
say they support Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> for president.
   Those selected at the territory's Republican convention included
territorial Gov. <PERSON>Joseph F. Ada</PERSON>, who said of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>: ``He knows where
<LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> is. His heart is in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. He told me that one of these days
the people of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> are going to vote for president.''
   Although residents of <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> are American citizens, they are not
allowed to cast ballots in presidential elections.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said of the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> results: ``This victory is a tribute to
the hard work and dedication of our organization there.''
   About 200 party members who attended the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> gathering approved
a number of resolutions that will be given to all <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> presidential
candidates.
   One of the resolutions supports the drive to give territorial
residents the right to vote in presidential elections, while
another presses for <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> to become a commonwealth of the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880115-0078 </DOCNO>
<HL> Attorney Agrees To Cooperate In Guam Inquiry --- Strauss Enters Guilty Plea In Matthews &amp; Wright Municipal Bond Scandal </HL>
<AUTHOR> Ken Wells (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> FREST MW </CO>
<IN> BON SCR </IN>
<G> JUS </G>
<TEXT>
   A key player in the <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION> municipal bond scandal agreed to cooperate as a prosecution witness in a <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> federal grand jury investigation of a top <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> executive and a former company consultant. 

   The agreement was disclosed in documents filed in federal court on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Edward K. Strauss</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> attorney, who provided tax opinions on numerous <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> bond issues, and <PERSON>William O'Connor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> attorney. 
<PERSON>Mr. Strauss</PERSON>, according to the documents, pleaded guilty to concealing knowledge of "cognizable felonies" allegedly committed by <PERSON>Arthur Abba Goldberg</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>'s executive vice president, and <PERSON>Frederick Mann</PERSON>, a Canadian who served as a <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> consultant. 

   In exchange for <PERSON>Mr. Strauss</PERSON>'s plea and cooperation, federal authorities pledged not to seek additional criminal charges against him unless he provides "deliberately false or misleading" testimony, <PERSON>Mr. O'Connor</PERSON>, the federal attorney, said. 
<PERSON>Mr. Strauss</PERSON>, a partner in the firm of <ORGANIZATION>Berkman Ruslander Pohl Lieber &amp; Engel</ORGANIZATION>, was said to be traveling and couldn't be reached for comment. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Strauss</PERSON>'s surprising guilty plea would appear to strengthen the government's case against Messrs. 
<PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mann</PERSON>, who were charged last month by a <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> federal grand jury in a 52-count indictment alleging fraud, bribery and obstruction of justice. 
The indictments stem largely from their handling of a <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> housing bond issue on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>; an <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY> housing issue on the neighboring island of <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION>; and a <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> bond issue for the island of Palau. 

   Those issues are among some 20 <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> bond offerings, representing about <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>, that are being investigated by several federal jurisdictions. 
Federal prosecutors suspect that many were bloated, sham transactions rushed to market by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> to beat a federal tax deadline and generate huge underwriting fees. 

   In court documents filed as part of his plea agreement, <PERSON>Mr. Strauss</PERSON> stated that he "knew or had reason to suspect" that 13 separate bond issues allegedly bought by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> were fraudulent transactions "conducted by <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mann</PERSON>" using worthless checks processed through an unlicensed <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION> bank controlled by <PERSON>Mr. Mann</PERSON>. 

   Those issues -- representing about <MONEY>$2.1 billion</MONEY> -- include a <MONEY>$125.3 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>East St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, resource recovery bond; a <MONEY>$223.7 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>East St. Louis</LOCATION> port development bond; a <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>Washington County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, revenue bond; a <MONEY>$335 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>City of Chester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, resource recovery bond; a <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>East Chicago Heights</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, resource recovery bond; and the <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> Palau bond. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Strauss</PERSON> also stated that he knew or suspected that <PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON> had committed federal mail fraud in <DATE>January 1986</DATE> by submitting <MONEY>$57,500</MONEY> of "false or fraudulent" invoices to a <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> government agency for consulting services never performed. 

   The charge to which <PERSON>Mr. Strauss</PERSON> pleaded guilty is punishable by a fine of up to <MONEY>$500</MONEY> and three years in jail. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON>, who has taken a voluntary leave of absence from <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>, will voluntarily appear on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> next week where he is expected to plead not guilty to the 52-count indictment. 
His attorney, <PERSON>Stanley S. Arkin</PERSON>, said <PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON>, despite <PERSON>Mr. Strauss</PERSON>'s agreement with federal prosecutors, "steadfastly maintains his innocence." 

   Authorities have sworn out an arrest warrant for <PERSON>Mr. Mann</PERSON>, who has denied the charges against him. 

   An attorney with <ORGANIZATION>Williams &amp; Connolly</ORGANIZATION>, the law firm representing <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> continues to insist it engaged in no wrongdoing. 
"It's still the company's position they relied on <PERSON>Strauss</PERSON>'s counsel," he said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871210-0013 </DOCNO>
<HL> Matthews &amp; Wright Aide and Consultant
Indicted Over $300 Million Bond Issue
---
By Ken Wells
<DD> 12/10/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MW FREST
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON)
SECURITIES INDUSTRY (SCR)
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS) </IN>
<TEXT>
   A federal grand jury on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> returned a 52-count indictment against <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s executive vice president <PERSON>Arthur Abba Goldberg</PERSON> and company consultant <PERSON>Frederick L. Mann</PERSON>, alleging bribery, fraud and obstruction of justice. 

   Most of the charges stem from the roles of Messrs. 
<PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mann</PERSON> in the company's handling of a <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> housing bond issue in <DATE>1985</DATE>, <PERSON>William O'Connor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> attorney, said. 
Some of the counts also relate to their handling of an <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY> housing issue for <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>'s neighboring island, <LOCATION>Saipan</LOCATION>, and a <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> issue for the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> island of <ORGANIZATION>Palau</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. O'Connor</PERSON> added. 

   The indictments are the first to come from a wide-ranging federal criminal investigation -- believed to include at least five other grand juries in the mainland <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> -- of the tiny Wall Street bond house. 
The <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> bond issue is among more than 20 <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> municipal issues, representing about <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>, that federal authorities believe may have been sham transactions put together by <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> to beat a federal tax deadline. 

   Few, if any, projects have been built from the issues but they reaped enormous profits for the company and its principals while duping and defrauding some of the poorest municipalities in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, officials close to these investigations believe. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON> will be ordered to post a <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> recognizance bond and report to the island on <DATE>Jan. 15</DATE> for a hearing in <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. O'Connor</PERSON> said. 
The court also has issued an arrest warrant for <PERSON>Mr. Mann</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>J.D. Moore &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> investment concern, and decreed that he be held in jail in lieu of <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> bail. 
<PERSON>Mr. Mann</PERSON> is a felon convicted by Canadian courts in <DATE>1984</DATE> of swindling a dying widow out of <MONEY>$65,000</MONEY>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> court records show. 

   Neither <PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON> nor <PERSON>Mr. Mann</PERSON> could be reached immediately for comment. 

   In the indictments, which don't name <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> itself, <PERSON>Messrs. 
Goldberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mann</PERSON> are accused of channeling <MONEY>$70,000</MONEY> in bribes -- part of <MONEY>$350,000</MONEY> in bribery offers -- to former <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Ricardo Bordallo</PERSON> for use in his <DATE>1986</DATE> election campaign in exchange for <PERSON>Mr. Bordallo</PERSON>'s approval of the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> issue. 

   The indictments also charge that a substantial portion of the funds paid to <PERSON>Mr. Bordallo</PERSON> were illicitly diverted from a <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> government fund that had been set up by the island's legislature to support local developers' efforts to construct housing to be financed by the <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> housing issue. 

   The indictments also allege that <PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON> supervised the billing of <MONEY>$27,500</MONEY> to the fund in the name of a non-existent company and in another case obtained a <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> fund payment "for work which was not done." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Bordallo</PERSON> earlier this year was acquitted of bribery charges related to the <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> payoffs but was convicted on unrelated bribery and extortion charges in connection with business on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>John Gilliam</PERSON>, a former aide to <PERSON>Mr. Bordallo</PERSON>, pleaded guilty in <LOCATION>U.S. District Court</LOCATION> <DATE>last summer</DATE> to a wire-fraud charge in connection with the <MONEY>$70,000</MONEY> bribery payment, records in <LOCATION>Guam U.S.</LOCATION> District Court show. 

   The indictment also alleges an "overarching scheme" by Messrs. 
<PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mann</PERSON> to obtain "more than <MONEY>$11 million</MONEY>" in fees for the company and themselves by a "complex wire and mail fraud scheme involving a number of small, financially unsophisticated <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> and stateside local jurisdictions." 
The indictment contends that the two men, by using an "unlicensed" bank on Saipan controlled by <PERSON>Mr. Mann</PERSON>, "bogus checks and bank accounts and world-wide wire transactions" promoted a "nationwide fraud." 

   In one example, the indictment charges that Messrs. 
<PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mann</PERSON> "willfully and knowingly" misrepresented the need for a <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> bond issue for "undefined, speculative projects" on the tiny <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> island of <ORGANIZATION>Palau</ORGANIZATION>, which has 10,000 residents. 

   The documents allege that through a "series of bogus paper transactions" <PERSON>Mr. Goldberg</PERSON>, with the help of certain other <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> officials, duped the island's government into believing that its bond issue had been sold, when in fact it hadn't. 

   The indictment charges that certain <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> officials went to the extent of contracting with <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> computer concerns to print "bogus statements" aimed at convincing Palau officials that the bond transactions were legitimate and had taken place. 

   Also named, but not charged, in the indictment as "relevant" to the <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> scheme were: <PERSON>Edward K. Strauss</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> attorney for the company; <PERSON>George W. Benoit</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> founder and its chief executive officer; <PERSON>Roger J. Burns</PERSON>, the company's chief financial officer; <PERSON>Joseph Craven</PERSON>, identified as a <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> "junior executive"; <PERSON>Joel Schwarz</PERSON>, manager of <ORGANIZATION>New American Federal Credit Union of Jersey City</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>; <PERSON>John C. Zaccaro</PERSON>, identified only as a <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> employee; and <PERSON>Phillip J. Kieffer</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Matthews &amp; Wright</ORGANIZATION> consultant. 
None of those listed could be reached immediately for comment. 
