<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900726-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-26-90 1714EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StolenArt     07-26 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stolen Art,0446</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dallas Museum to Store Stolen Medieval Art Until Ownership Settled</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The heirs of an American soldier accused of
pilfering medieval art treasures from a German church during World
War II have given the trove to a <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> museum for safekeeping
while their ownership is settled.
   The Quedlinburg treasures will not be displayed publicly at the
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Museum of Art until the ownership is decided by a <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
District Court</ORGANIZATION> judge, museum director <PERSON>Richard R. Brettell</PERSON> said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Brettell</PERSON> said professionals and scholars might be allowed to see
the treasures if the court and both sides in the lawsuit agree. The
public likely will get to see the art once ownership is clear.
   ``Each party was interested in eventually displaying the art for
the people in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Brettell</PERSON> said.
   The pieces will be moved from rural <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, about 60 miles
north of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, to the downtown museum within a week, he said.
   The Lutheran Stiftskirche-Domgemeinde church of Quedlinburg
claims that <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON> stole the trove while his <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> unit
was guarding a mine shaft where the items had been hidden.
   Attorneys for <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jane Meador Cook</PERSON>, the brother and
sister of the soldier, have been negotiating with the church to
have the treasures kept in a neutral place while they haggle over
ownership.
   Meador, who died in <DATE>1980</DATE>, bequeathed the artwork to his
siblings. The heirs claim to have several, but not all, of the 14
treasures sought by the church. The treasures include a 9th- or
10th-century wood reliquary, a container; a jeweled ivory-and-gold
comb; a Byzantine rock crystal flask; four small reliquaries in the
form of turrets, and a small heart-shaped reliquary.
   Two jeweled medieval manuscripts believed held by the Meadors
for several years were sold recently on the European art market.
   <PERSON>Brettell</PERSON> said he did not know how many objects the museum would
receive. He said they included gold, silver, ivory and crystal
articles from the 8th to 14th centuries.
   ``The Quedlinburg treasury is undoubtedly the most important
Carolingian treasury of the Germanies,'' he said. ``The objects
were made for important kings. They were in a repository which was
among the three or four greatest medieval repositories.''
   The Carolingian period refers to the reign of emperor
<PERSON>Charlemagne</PERSON> and his successors in the 8th through early 10th
centuries.
   Brettel refused to assign a value to the treasures.
   ``Important Carolingian objects have not traded hands on the
open market for the last generation and therefore it's impossible
to give a real and correct evaluation,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900803-0128
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900803-0128.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Art Crime Update:
   German Booty in Texas
   ----
   By Constance Lowenthal
</HL>
<DATE>
08/03/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A8
</SO>
<LP>
   An American soldier's theft of German church treasures at
the end of World War II began to surface this April. The New
York Times reported that a government-funded German
foundation had paid a $3 million "finder's fee" for the
Quedlinburg Gospels, a magnificent illuminated Carolingian
manuscript written in gold. The seller reportedly had
threatened the manuscript would be sold to a Japanese buyer.
John S. Torigian, a Dallas attorney acting for anonymous
clients, had arranged the transfer in Switzerland through
Heribert Tenschert, a Bavarian dealer in rare books and
manuscripts. Reaction to the sale was mixed. While pleased
that the Gospels might return to their home when
reunification takes place, many were incensed at the
extortion and disturbed by the secrecy of the seller's
identity.
   The Gospels and other medieval works of art from the
Quedlinburg cloister's treasury were stored for safety in a
mine shaft outside Quedlinburg in 1945 when American troops
approached. The U.S. Army knew treasures were missing, but by
1949, Quedlinburg was part of the Russian zone and later East
Germany, and the Army dropped its investigation.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Among medievalists, the disappearance of the Quedlinburg
treasures was considered a major war loss. The convent had
especially beautiful things, 10th- and 11th-century gifts
from the Ottonian imperial family. The medieval works from
Quedlinburg now in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> include a silver reliquary with
enamel plaques and carved ivory panels, a small group of rock
crystal vessels, crucifixes of gold and silver, and a carved
ivory comb.
   Shortly after the sale of the Gospels, <PERSON>Willi Korte</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Prussian Cultural Heritage</ORGANIZATION> administration traveled
to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and followed a trail to the town of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>
in <LOCATION>northeast Texas</LOCATION>, and to its bank, where heirs of Lt. <PERSON>Joe
T. Meador</PERSON>, who served in the unit that occupied Quedlinburg,
had deposited the treasures as collateral for a loan. Meador
apparently stole more than 10 works from the Quedlinburg
treasury. Witnesses who served with <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> have come forward
to tell of the theft from the mine shaft. Meador died of
cancer in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Church of Quedlinburg</ORGANIZATION> has brought suit in <ORGANIZATION>Federal
District Court</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> to recover the items, and the West
German government will foot the legal bill. A restraining
order will keep the treasure safe until its ownership is
determined. Meador's sister and brother are defendants and,
along with <PERSON>Mr. Torigian</PERSON>, subjects of a criminal investigation
seeking to discover whether they knew the objects were stolen
before transporting the manuscript to <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION> for sale.
It later was reported that the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> also is looking into their
possible tax liability, putting additional pressure on <PERSON>Jane
Meador Cook</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON> to settle this deeply
embarrassing situation.
   ---
   In mid-July, <PERSON>Judge Vincent L. Broderick</PERSON> denied the
Metropolitan Museum of Art's motion to dismiss a <DATE>1987</DATE> lawsuit
filed by the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Turkey</ORGANIZATION> to recover more than 200
ancient silver and gold artifacts that <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION> calls the
Lydian Hoard and the Met labels "East Greek." Turkey claims
the objects were plundered from a burial mound in <LOCATION>Ushak</LOCATION> and
smuggled out for sale. Although almost 20 years had passed
since the Met acquired the objects through purchases totaling
more than <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> and through gifts from the two dealers
who made the sale, the court ruled that the museum could not
use the statute of limitations defense. Turkey's assertion
that the Met was not a good-faith purchaser needed to be
tested, the court ruled, adding that the museum may have been
aware of the artifacts' illicit export and may have
deliberately concealed their acquisition. The ruling cleared
the way to trial.
   ---
   <PERSON>Van Gogh</PERSON>'s centenary exhibition in <LOCATION>Amsterdam</LOCATION> just closed
after drawing 1.2 million visitors, who admired, among other
paintings, three van Goghs from the Kroller-Muller Museum
recovered by Dutch police earlier this year. Meanwhile,
however, the <ORGANIZATION>Noord Brabant Museum</ORGANIZATION> in nearby s'Hertogenbosch
suffered the theft of three paintings from the artist's early
years in <LOCATION>Nuenen</LOCATION>. On the <TIME>night</TIME> of <DATE>June 27</DATE>, a window was
broken, the alarm system failed, and in the morning the
museum discovered it was missing works it values between <MONEY>$2.7</MONEY>
and <MONEY>$5.4 million</MONEY>.
   ---
   On <DATE>July 4</DATE>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> lost three paintings from three museums.
A small Renoir portrait of a woman, on display near a
staircase in the <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Pavilion</LOCATION> des <PERSON>Flores</PERSON>, was cut from
its frame during museum hours. About an hour later, the theft
of <PERSON>Ernest Hebert</PERSON>'s portrait of "Monaluccia" was discovered at
the <PERSON>Musee Hebert</PERSON>, a small museum on the <ORGANIZATION>Left Bank</ORGANIZATION>. It too was
cut from its stretcher without tripping the alarm attached to
the frame. A third picture, a landscape of <DATE>1816</DATE> by <PERSON>Paul Huet</PERSON>,
was discovered missing from the museum of the city of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Musee Carnavalet</ORGANIZATION>.
   Reaction was swift. The next day <PERSON>Jacques Sallois</PERSON>, the
director of the national museums, announced an unusual
decision: Five small museums in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> would close until
further notice. In addition to the <PERSON>Musee Hebert</PERSON>, the <PERSON>Gustave
Moreau</PERSON>, <PERSON>Eugene Delacroix</PERSON>, Ennery, and <PERSON>Jean-Jacques Henner</PERSON>
museums will admit visitors only in pre-arranged groups and
for lectures. These museums were the homes or studios of the
artists, and the security staff in each could only be
described as minimal. Increased security was announced for
three of the capital's most popular tourist attractions, the
<LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Musee d'Orsay</ORGANIZATION>, and the Palace of <LOCATION>Versailles</LOCATION>.
   ---
   Print dealers in the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> area are relieved that
the Doremus twins, <PERSON>Paul Drake</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kevin</PERSON>, are in police
custody. The brothers allegedly worked together, one
distracting gallery staff while the other took prints, then
rolled or folded them, before the two left the gallery. The
"system" then required a visit to a paper conservator to
repair the damage and to alter the edition numbers. Once
framed, the stolen prints were consigned for auction.
Cooperation among victims, specialists at <ORGANIZATION>Butterfield</ORGANIZATION>'s
auction house and Detective <PERSON>William Martin</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles
Police Department</ORGANIZATION>'s Art Theft Detail resulted in the arrests
and several felony counts for the brothers.
   ---
Foundation for Art Research</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>IFAR</ORGANIZATION>).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910424-0170
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910424-0170.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Art Crime Update:
   The Quedlinburg Quagmire
   ----
   By Constance Lowenthal
</HL>
<DATE>
04/24/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   Forty-six years after an American soldier took medieval
treasures from the cave where they were stored, his heirs --
almost $3 million richer as a result of their brother's
misdeed and a German foundation's willingness to pay -- have
agreed to return the precious objects to Germany. The
settlement did not, however, "settle" all the issues in this
momentous repatriation, and the flap should continue on other
levels and in other jurisdictions.
   The parties to the Dallas lawsuit announced earlier this
year that they were settling out of court. "Final wording has
yet to be worked out," said Thomas R. Kline, who represents
the Quedlinburg church and Germany's Cultural Foundation of
the States. After the settlement, the art is expected to be
exhibited for two months at the Dallas Museum of Art before
it makes the return voyage.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The soldier's heirs want the church and the foundation to
tell <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> authorities that they are content with the return
of the objects, an implicit request that the government not
pursue the defendants. Transporting the manuscript to
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION> for sale may have been a violation of the
National Stolen Property Act, and estate taxes may have been
due on the treasure, but no charges have yet been brought.
Final wording might characterize the exchange of Quedlinburg
treasures for cash as something other than a sale, putting
the money outside the reach of the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>. A private settlement,
however, would not be binding on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government officials.
   Last <DATE>spring</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Cultural Foundation</ORGANIZATION> of the States agreed
to pay a "finder's fee" of <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> for Quedlinburg's
<ORGANIZATION>Samuhel Gospels</ORGANIZATION>, a highly important luxury manuscript of the
Carolingian period. The seller represented <PERSON>Jane Cook Meador</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON>, the brother and sister of the soldier who
died in <DATE>1980</DATE>. The transaction was widely reported and led to
the discovery of more objects from Quedlinburg in a bank
vault in <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Meadors</ORGANIZATION>' hometown. The
priceless works were there as a collateral for a loan. The
Quedlinburg church then sued for their return. The settlement
assures both sides an end to a long legal wrangle of
uncertain outcome. The Germans will get all the Quedlinburg
objects that were in the bank for somewhat less than they had
agreed to pay for the Gospels manuscript alone.
   In agreeing to pay the heirs of a thief, the German
foundation has opened itself to further "offers" from others
who possess <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON>'s war booty. He gave an unknown
number of objects to friends and casual acquaintances in his
social circle in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>. If charges are not brought against
the heirs, what will deter the others from trying to arrange
similarly lucrative exchanges?
   It is hoped that the liturgical objects will return to
Quedlinburg, the medieval cloister to which they were given
by the Ottonian dynasty in the 10th and 11th centuries. When
added to the 20 still in <LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, the 10 objects from
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> would almost restore the treasury to its original size.
A suitably secure housing to display the newly famous works
is needed, an expensive proposition for a poor East German
town. The treasure would undoubtedly compensate for these
costs by attracting tourists and scholars to Quedlinburg.
   In a parallel turn of events, a <DATE>March</DATE> settlement for
"undisclosed consideration" allowed a <PERSON>Hans Baldung Grien</PERSON>
drawing, missing since World War II, to be carried back to
the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>. It was returned by the estate of <PERSON>Ian
Woodner</PERSON>. A year ago, the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> announced that it was
actively seeking the return of works from a collection of old
master drawings formerly belonging to financier <PERSON>Franz
Koenigs</PERSON>, who fell on hard times in the early '30s. The
government published a fully illustrated catalog of the 526
missing works from this superb collection of more than 3,000
drawings, which was purchased for the Museum Boymans in
<LOCATION>Rotterdam</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Koenigs</LOCATION>'s bankers as they fled from Hitler's
advance.
   The drawings soon caught the eye of Hitler's grand
acquisitor, <PERSON>Hans Posse</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Dresden Picture
Gallery</ORGANIZATION>, who was amassing art for the <ORGANIZATION>Fuhrer</ORGANIZATION>'s proposed
museum in <LOCATION>Linz</LOCATION>. As the military prospects of the Third <PERSON>Reich</PERSON>
dimmed, <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON> shelved his museum plans and stored the art in
a <LOCATION>Saxon</LOCATION> castle. When the Soviets liberated the area,
thousands of works of art were carried to the <LOCATION>U.S.S.R.</LOCATION> The
Koenigs drawings are believed to be there too, but some
surfaced in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, and the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>
realized that a major effort would be timely, given the new
openness in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   The drawing in question, a "Virgin and Child" by the
16th-century German master, turned up in the prominent <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> collection of <PERSON>Ian Woodner</PERSON>. The <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> approached
<PERSON>Mr. Woodner</PERSON> to ask for its return; rebuffed, it brought suit.
As is common, the trial was delayed by procedural motions,
and, indeed, a time-consuming translation of voluminous Dutch
documents and legal statutes was under way when <PERSON>Mr. Woodner</PERSON>
died. His heirs decided not to continue the fight.
   One of the fascinating issues that might have been
determined in trial is whether the decrees of the Dutch
government in exile, declaring invalid such sales of national
treasures for worthless Reichmarks, would have been
recognized by a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> court.
   ---
   An ancient marble <PERSON>Jupiter Capitolinus</PERSON>, just 10 inches
tall, was stolen from the <ORGANIZATION>Daedalus Gallery</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>'s
57th Street last fall. It was recovered, only three blocks
away, in <DATE>March</DATE>. That morning, <PERSON>Judith Nugee</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s
expert in antiquities, was in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> reviewing possible
consignments. She was leafing through the <DATE>January</DATE> issue of
<ORGANIZATION>IFAR</ORGANIZATION> reports and recognized the <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> she had just examined
in storage.
   Christie's counsel, <PERSON>Patricia Hambrecht</PERSON>, called <ORGANIZATION>IFAR</ORGANIZATION> with
the news, then telephoned Detective <PERSON>Joseph Keenan</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>New
York Police Department</ORGANIZATION> to come to collect the object. Later
that afternoon, <ORGANIZATION>Daedalus</ORGANIZATION>'s director, <PERSON>Thomas Swope</PERSON>, identified
the sculpture in police offices. Christie's then asked the
would-be consignor to come in to sign a contract, and upon
leaving the auction house, the suspect was met by the police.
After questioning, the police arrested him; the man is said
to be cooperating, and the investigation continues.
   ---
Foundation for Art Research</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>IFAR</ORGANIZATION>).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA050190-0162 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 212512 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 1, 1990, Tuesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 2; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
186 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WORLD; 
</P>
<P>
PRICELESS ANCIENT GOSPELS, LOST 45 YEARS, TO RETURN TO GERMANY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
FRANKFURT, West Germany 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A priceless 9th-Century manuscript of the Gospels that disappeared near the end 
of World War II will return to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, a government-run foundation said <DATE>today</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The manuscript, called the Samuhel-Evangeliar in German, disappeared in <DATE>April, 
1945</DATE>, in the town of Quedlinburg, apparently after <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military forces 
discovered an underground cache of artworks. 
</P>
<P>
"The manuscript is now in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Erika Lancelle</PERSON>, an official with 
the foundation. It represents "one of the masterpieces of Carolingian (8th- to 
late 9th-Century) book illumination," the foundation said. 
</P>
<P>
Lancelle said there will be a formal ceremony in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> to mark the 
reacquisition of the manuscript, the name of which she translated as <ORGANIZATION>Samuhel 
Gospels</ORGANIZATION>. It comes from the year 842 and is named after the scribe who wrote and 
elaborately decorated it. 
</P>
<P>
Lancelle said that a German antique dealer bought the manuscript from an 
American lawyer and that the priceless Gospels were then bought by the 
foundation. The foundation called the <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> it paid a "finder's fee." 
</P>
<P>
It was not explained how the lawyer acquired the Gospels. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2308EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StolenArt     07-01 0642</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stolen Art,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trail of Art Treasures Reads Like Hollywood Script</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lost treasure. International intrigue. A lone
adventurer.
   The script for a Hollywood movie? Nope, this is a job for <PERSON>Willi
A. Kotre</PERSON>, an investigator who followed a trail of musty documents,
Cold War secrets and just plain luck to discover the lost treasure
of the <ORGANIZATION>Quedlinburg Cathedral</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>.
   ``But please, don't call me <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Jones,'' the soft-spoken
German said.
   The 36-year-old <PERSON>Kotre</PERSON>, a researcher for the <ORGANIZATION>Prussian Cultural
Heritage Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>, in <DATE>May</DATE> pinpointed a local bank as
the place where a dead former <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> officer's heirs were
keeping the missing gifts of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s earliest kings.
   Now, the art's original owner, the <ORGANIZATION>Lutheran Church of
Quedlinburg</ORGANIZATION>, is suing the family of former Lt. <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON> for
return of the treasures. Meador died in <DATE>1980</DATE>, bequeathing the
artwork to his brother, <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON>, and sister, <PERSON>Jane Cook</PERSON>.
   Lawyers for the church contend <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> stole the treasures in the
final days of World War II, mailed them to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and kept them
in his hometown of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, about 60 miles north of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
German officials want to bring the artwork home as a symbol of
German reunification.
   ``It is very difficult to take a historical account and
successfully trace a missing item to an individual,'' <PERSON>Korte</PERSON> said.
``Usually, you need some kind of postwar event _ like someone
trying to sell the art _ and then you have a case.
   ``That's what happened here.''
   An East German who helped in the case, <PERSON>Gunter Wermusch</PERSON>, told <ORGANIZATION>The
Dallas Morning News</ORGANIZATION> in a telephone interview from <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> that Nazi
officials hauled the cathedral's treasures into the cave as Allied
troops approached in early <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   Soon after <PERSON>Korte</PERSON>'s search began, a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> book dealer offered
one of the missing treasures, a 9th-century illuminated manuscript,
to the researcher's employer.
   Officials said the <MONEY>$9 million</MONEY> offer was rejected in late <DATE>1988</DATE>
because of the price and potential problems from buying art taken
from another country. But it provided a clue that the dealer
apparently worked for a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> resident, they said.
   <PERSON>Korte</PERSON> said he began looking for detailed accounts of <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> units
near <LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION> in <DATE>April 1945</DATE>. Spending months in the <ORGANIZATION>National
Archives</ORGANIZATION> records tracing <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> operations, he then went to the
<ORGANIZATION>National Personnel Records Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, the military's
service records repository.
   More than 1,000 names of soldiers assigned to the area were
found by <PERSON>Korte</PERSON> in over a week of research. He then turned to East
Germans and medieval art experts for further clues.
   Bavarian manuscript dealer <PERSON>Heribert Tenschert</PERSON> in <DATE>February</DATE> was
offered the illuminated manuscript, which had been in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
without a buyer for two years, the newspaper said.
   Tenschert said he relayed the offer to the Foundation of the
States, a private German cultural group. The foundation paid <MONEY>$3
million</MONEY> to <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>John T. Torigian</PERSON> in <DATE>April</DATE> for the
manuscript, said <PERSON>Aoachim Fischer</PERSON>, a foundation director.
   Torigian termed himself a proxy for an unnamed <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> client,
<PERSON>Fischer</PERSON> said.
   Dealers left out of the sale immediately began talking, said
<PERSON>Korte</PERSON>.
   ``Eventually, I learned the name of the bank, and it was short
work once I had that,'' he said.
   In <DATE>May</DATE>, <PERSON>Korte</PERSON> went to the <ORGANIZATION>First National Bank of Whitewright</ORGANIZATION>,
which was holding the artwork for the <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> family. Bank president
<PERSON>John Farley</PERSON> said he talked with <PERSON>Korte</PERSON> but gave him no information
about the treasures.
   Checks of his lists and a call to a <LOCATION>Grayson County</LOCATION> veterans'
group produced <PERSON>Joe Meador</PERSON>'s name, said <PERSON>Korte</PERSON>. The Germans
negotiated in successive weeks with the bank and <PERSON>Torigian</PERSON>, who
represents the <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> family, the foundation said.
   But talks stalled on <DATE>June 16</DATE>, when word surfaced of a second
manuscript in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION> that was offered for <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY>.
   A <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> judge has barred movement of the artwork.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920110-0116
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920110-0116.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   IRS Says Stolen Art Treasures Are Subject to Estate Tax
   ----
   By Scott R. Schmedel
</HL>
<DATE>
01/10/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<CO>
   TAXES
</CO>
<NS>
TAXES (TAX)
</NS>
<GV>
INTERNAL REVENUE SERVICE (IRS)
</GV>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
TEXAS (TX)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   After Joe Tom Meador of Whitewright, Texas, died in 1980,
his sister, serving as his executor, filed a state
inheritance-tax return showing an estate of about $120,000 in
stock, real estate and life insurance.
   The amount was too small to require a federal estate-tax
return. However, it failed to take account of Mr. Meador's
secret hoard of religious and art treasures that he stole in
Germany and France at the end of World War II while a first
lieutenant in the U.S. Army artillery. At his death, the
stolen art passed to his heirs.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> cache included medieval manuscripts and
reliquaries from the Quedlinburg, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, cathedral. It came
to the attention of the public in <DATE>1990</DATE>, when <PERSON>Mr. Meador</PERSON>'s
heirs sold a ninth-century illustrated manuscript of the four
Gospels to a foundation representing the Quedlinburg church
for a "finder's fee" that some reports say was as much as <MONEY>$3
million</MONEY>.
   Now the <ORGANIZATION>Internal Revenue Service</ORGANIZATION> claims that the stolen
works are subject to federal estate tax. In a private ruling
dated last <DATE>Aug. 30</DATE> that has just come to light, the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> also
declares that:
   -- The value of each item for tax purposes is the price it
would have brought, at the time of <PERSON>Mr. Meador</PERSON>'s death, on the
open market -- including the illicit market of international
traffickers in stolen art.
   -- The estate isn't entitled to reduce its taxable value
by deducting recovery claims made by the Quedlinburg church
and other theft victims against <PERSON>Mr. Meador</PERSON>'s sister and
executor, <PERSON>Jane Meador Cook</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>Mesquite</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and their
brother <PERSON>Jack</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>. The two siblings inherited the
stolen art. The <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> contends they knew something of its
origins and value.
   Attorneys for the heirs say they would have income-tax
liability for any money received in settling the recovery
claims or disposing of the art objects. But the attorneys
insist that there can be no estate tax on <PERSON>Joe Meador</PERSON>'s
estate, because he never had legal title to the treasures.
   The <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> position is that <PERSON>Joe Meador</PERSON> had the economic
equivalent of ownership of the objects for 35 years and at
his death was able to transfer the same benefits to his
heirs. While the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> found no such precedent in estate-tax
law, it said <PERSON>Joe Meador</PERSON> clearly would be treated as the owner
under income-tax law and, therefore, must be for estate-tax
purposes.
   But, says <PERSON>Randal Mathis</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> lawyer for the heirs,
"We think the ruling is in error, and we're quite confident
that in the long run a court will so determine." <PERSON>Donald Lan
Jr.</PERSON>, a partner of <PERSON>Mr. Mathis</PERSON> in the firm <ORGANIZATION>Strasburger &amp; Price</ORGANIZATION>,
adds: "It's a very big stretch to extend to estate taxes the
principles of income-tax law."
   Lawyers for the <PERSON>Meadors</PERSON> and the church say no overall
valuation has been placed on the collection. The recently
issued public version of the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>'s private ruling doesn't try
to set a value and doesn't name any of the parties to the
matter. But the facts described clearly relate to the
Quedlinburg-treasures affair, which was widely reported
starting in mid-1990.
   The treasures are being stored for safekeeping at the
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Museum of Art, pending the final settlement of a
tentative agreement to restore them to the church. The <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>
heirs agreed a year ago to give up all of the objects in
return for a sum that hasn't been disclosed. Lawyers for the
family and the church won't discuss the dollar figure but say
it is less than the German foundation originally agreed to
pay for the single manuscript.
   <PERSON>Mr. Mathis</PERSON> says the final agreement has been delayed by
the difficulties of communication and of working within
different legal systems. He says the documentation ending the
church's civil suit against the heirs should be completed
amicably within two weeks, after which the financial terms
would be disclosed.
   <PERSON>Mr. Mathis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Lan</PERSON> say that they haven't discussed a
settlement with the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> and that they are awaiting a formal
deficiency notice. At that point, the <ORGANIZATION>Meadors</ORGANIZATION> could appeal to
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Tax Court</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> could add claims for interest or for civil
penalties for such things as negligence or failure to file a
return. If it prevails, it could claim the heirs are liable
for the estate tax.
   The <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> won't discuss confidential matters about specific
taxpayers. But a spokesman for <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> state tax authorities
says: "Our file on the <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> case is open. We've been in
contact with federal authorities about it."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900620-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-20-90 1526EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany-Art     06-20 0746</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany-Art,0775</SECOND>
<HEAD>East German Church Determined to Recover Lost Treasures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>QUEDLINBURG, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Rev. <PERSON>Friedemann Gosslau</PERSON>
said his heart soared when he heard that medieval artworks
belonging to his church are believed to be in a <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> bank.
   He has complete faith priceless objects that disappeared in <DATE>1945</DATE>
at the end of World War II will be found and restored to his
500-member parish and Quedlinburg's 12th-century cathedral.
   ``We must defend the interests of the church. When the pieces
are here again, we will show them, but this time we'll need help
with security,'' <PERSON>Gosslau</PERSON> said with a smile.
   The treasures, among <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s most famous artworks, are the
subjects of an international struggle. The Lutheran church in
<LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION> has filed suit in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to try to recover a collection
that includes a silver, ivory and gold reliquary from the 9th or
<DATE>10th century</DATE>, a 10th-century Byzantine rock-crystal flask with
sides shaped like birds, and an ivory comb inlaid with precious
stones.
   It is believed the works were taken to <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> by the
late <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON>, a former <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> lieutenant who served in
Quedlinburg in <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   During the war, the objects were removed from the Romanesque
cathedral to a mine shaft to keep them safe from Allied bombing.
They disappeared in <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   Gosslau came to Quedlinburg 25 years ago and learned about the
missing works by studying cathedral archives.
   ``I thought maybe we'd find traces and then convince the people
to give the pieces back peacefully. I dreamed of it, but I never
counted on it,'' <PERSON>Gosslau</PERSON> said in an interview in his home.
   The Lutheran minister said it was always thought the missing
pieces could have been taken by ordinary Germans during the chaotic
end of the Third <PERSON>Reich</PERSON>; by Nazi SS forces who seized the cathedral
at the start of the war; or by the American soldiers who occupied
the town.
   Then in <DATE>May</DATE> there was news that a private West German foundation
that searches for stolen artworks had recovered a 9th-century
illuminated manuscript of the Four Gospels.
   ``We had no idea where it was. It's fantastic news and it's sure
it comes from the church because it is described in the
inventory,'' <PERSON>Gosslau</PERSON> said.
   A second illuminated manuscript also noted in church archives
was recovered in <DATE>June</DATE>. Full details of how those works were
recovered have not been made public and they have not been returned
to the church.
   A federal judge <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> ordered the <ORGANIZATION>First National Bank of
Whitewright</ORGANIZATION> to open its vault for inventory by the cathedral.
   ``We were proud of what we have, and about what we didn't have
anymore,'' <PERSON>Gosslau</PERSON> said. ``The cathedral treasure is small, but it
is exquisite.''
   He would like any pieces found in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to join the rest of the
treasure that is kept in glass cases in the cool stone vault
constructed in the Middle Ages to hold the priceless objects.
   The part of the collection still in Quedlinburg is a dazzling
display that includes a Syrian vase brought back by crusaders, a
4th-century translation of the <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION>, and a 13th-century
gem-encrusted illimunated manuscript.
   In the <ORGANIZATION>Middle Ages</ORGANIZATION>, the vault guard was a nun trained to watch
over the works, which were used in services that the royal family
attended.
   Tourists taking the cathedral's guided tour are allowed to look
at the treasure vault, a small room with tiny windows at the top of
a staircase on the edge of the nave.
   During a tour this week, the guide did not mention the lost
treasures. Nor were they mentioned in the small guidebook to the
church on sale at the entrance.
   The town had no chance to seek recovery of the lost valuables
once it became part of <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> in <DATE>1949</DATE>. Contact was limited
until the country's former Communist leaders opened the country's
borders last year.
   ``We knew the crates were broken into and some things taken
away. But we didn't know where they went,'' said <PERSON>Walter Gold</PERSON>, the
city's cultural adviser.
   ``Because the world was divided, we had no contact with the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>
so we couldn't do anything about it.''
   The remains of Heinrich I, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s first king, and his wife
<PERSON>Mathilde</PERSON> are buried inside the cathedral. Heinrich I died in 936.
   While the cathedral is still state property, <PERSON>Gosslau</PERSON> maintains
that according to old laws the treasure belongs to the parish and
should be returned to the vault.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-4635</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DLBCKAHRFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931202
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 DEC 93 / FT Traveller, Zurich (15): Start at 'The Gates of Hell' -
The city is blessed with enough museums, gardens and galleries to keep the
visitor busy for a week or more. But check admission times: some are open
only in the afternoons
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KAREN SIMON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Where is the largest collection outside <LOCATION>Scandinavia</LOCATION> of the work of <ORGANIZATION>Edvard
Munch</ORGANIZATION>? And where is one of the finest private collections of European art?
Where is the only museum in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> entirely devoted to native American
Indians? And where is the only museum showing the influence of coffee on
social and cultural life? Where did the Dada movement begin?
Where can one view a collection of 20th-century art, dominated by the works
of <PERSON>Augusto</PERSON> and <PERSON>Giovanni Giacometti</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Giovanni</ORGANIZATION>'s son, <PERSON>Alberto</PERSON>? Where is one
of the world's finest museums of Asian and African art? And which European
city threatens its graffiti artists with imprisonment?
The answer to all these question is, of course, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION>. The city is blessed
with enough museums, gardens and galleries to keep the most enthusiastic
observer busy for a week or more.
The smaller contemporary art galleries tend to open only in the afternoons,
so it is a good idea to visit the main collections in the mornings.
Why not start your tour at 'The Gates of Hell' by <PERSON>Rodin</PERSON> outside the entrance
to the ultra-modern Kunsthaus in <LOCATION>Heimplatz</LOCATION>? Here, you can acquaint yourself
with the work of the leading Swiss 20th-century painter, <PERSON>Ferdinand Hodler</PERSON>.
There is also an excellent range of paintings, drawings and sculptures of
old masters and <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> artists from the <DATE>15th century</DATE> to the present. It is
here that one can see so much <ORGANIZATION>Edvard Munch</ORGANIZATION> and so much space devoted to the
Giacomettis.
The Kunsthaus is on the circuit for full-dress exhibitions of artists of
international repute and often has smaller studio presentations of
contemporary and local artists.
The <ORGANIZATION>Swiss National Museum</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Schweizerische Landesmuseum</ORGANIZATION>) is a neo-Gothic
building which looks like an old castle complete with gate tower and wings
built around a central courtyard. It is across the street from the main
railway station and acquired notoriety in the late <DATE>1980s</DATE> when drug addicts
converged in the adjacent <LOCATION>Platzspitz</LOCATION> park. The addicts have since been
shooed away and the park has been restored.
It displays artefacts of Swiss culture from the stone age to present,
including weapons, flags, uniforms, armour, toy armies, costumes, coins,
jewellery, seals, glass painting, religious painting and sculpture, whole
house interiors, watches, musical instruments and farm and industrial tools.
In short, one can discover a well-presented and informative illustrated
history of <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>Rietberg Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Gablerstrasse</LOCATION> is housed in the grounds of an
exquisite 19th-century neo-classical mansion, <PERSON>Villa Wesendonck</PERSON>, built for a
German merchant in imitation of the Roman Villa Albani. It long served as a
retreat for musicians and writers. <PERSON>Richard Wagner</PERSON> spent several years here,
and there is a monument to him.
After the <ORGANIZATION>City of Zurich</ORGANIZATION> acquired <PERSON>Baron Eduard Van der Heydt</PERSON>'s famous Asian
and African collections in <DATE>1956</DATE>, this villa became a public museum for
non-European art.
The <ORGANIZATION>Bellerive Museum</ORGANIZATION>, housed in another neo-classical villa in <LOCATION>Hoschgasse</LOCATION>,
is devoted to arts and crafts, including art nouveau textiles, tapestries
and modern furniture. Sadly, the display space is limited, but the care
which is taken in presenting the frequently changing displays make it well
worth a visit. In the <DATE>summer</DATE> the courtyard contains a sculpture exhibition.
Across the street from the Bellerive is the unique <PERSON>Heidi Weber</PERSON> Private
Museum. This was the last building built by Le Corbusier and is the only
modern example of 'total concept art', where architecture, sculpture, and
painting live in supposedly perfect harmony. It is open only from <DATE>June</DATE> to
<DATE>October</DATE>.
The <ORGANIZATION>Buhrle Collection</ORGANIZATION> (Stiftung Sammlung EG <PERSON>Buhrle</PERSON>), built on the fortune of
the great Zurich-based weapon makers, <PERSON>Oerlikon Buhrle</PERSON>, is small, but
contains some of the finest European paintings from several periods. The
impressionist and post-impressionist works are particularly dazzling. Here
one sees <PERSON>Manet</PERSON>'s Swallows, <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION>'s Little <PERSON>Irene</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Cezanne</ORGANIZATION>'s Boy in the
<LOCATION>Red Waistcoat</LOCATION>, among other masterpieces. The collection is open only on
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoons</TIME> from 2pm to 5pm but alone is worth a trip to
<LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION>.
If North American Indians are of special interest, the Indianermuseum in
Feldstrasse 89, with some 1,400 items in part of an old schoolhouse, is
worth a visit. On the same theme, try to find the Museum Leuengasse in
Leuengasse 10. This unusual exhibition space - it is an old nuclear bomb
shelter - is devoted exclusively to North and South American Indian and
Eskimo art and culture. It houses not only ancient works but also the
occasional contemporary artists on two levels proceeding ever deeper into
the earth.
In addition to these formal collections, the city's main churches are
repositories of wonderful works of art.
The 12th-century Fraumunster in Munsterhof is best known for the narrow
stained glass windows created by <PERSON>Marc Chagall</PERSON> in the chancel and south
transept and by <PERSON>Augusto Giacometti</PERSON> in the north transept. If you have time,
you can see the remains of the Romanesque cloisters on the south side of the
church, decorated with frescoes by <PERSON>Paul Bodmer</PERSON> representing the legend of
the foundation of the abbey as well as that of Grossmunster and the
<LOCATION>Wasserkirch</LOCATION>.
Across the Munsterbridge the Grossmunster cathedral, with the south tower
crowned by a colossal statue of <LOCATION>Charlemagne</LOCATION>, can be clearly seen. The
Grossmunster also dates from the Carolingian period, and it was here that
<PERSON>Huldrych Zwingli</PERSON> set off the Reformation in <DATE>1519</DATE>.
The bronze doors of the north and south portals are by <ORGANIZATION>Edvard Munch</ORGANIZATION> and
inside are stained glass windows by <PERSON>Augusto Giacometti</PERSON>. The crypt under the
choir is the best example of early Romanesque architecture in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>,
and it contains the original statue of <LOCATION>Charlemagne</LOCATION>. The one on the south
tower is a copy.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>CHZ  Switzerland, West Europe.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8412 Museums and Art Galleries.
    P8422 Botanical and Zoological Gardens.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920226-0026
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920226-0026.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Texas Family Drops Claim
   On German Art Treasures
</HL>
<DATE>
02/26/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
GERMANY (GE)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
TEXAS (TX)
UNITED STATES (US)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   DALLAS -- A Texas family that inherited religious and art
treasures in 1980 formally agreed to drop its claim to the
treasures and allow them to be returned to the German
cathedral where they were housed before World War II.
   The settlement, signed by the last of 14 members of Joe
Tom Meador's family, ends an almost two-year-old dispute
between the family and the Lutheran Church of Quedlinburg,
Germany. The works were taken from Quedlinburg in 1945, when
Mr. Meador was stationed there as a first lieutenant in the
U.S. Army artillery.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mr. Meador</PERSON> brought the works, including medieval
manuscripts and reliquaries, to <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, where
they remained until <DATE>1990</DATE>, when some heirs agreed to sell an
illustrated manuscript to a German cultural foundation. The
church sued the family in federal court in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> later that
year. A tentative settlement of the suit was reached in
<DATE>January 1991</DATE>.
   Specific terms of the settlement weren't provided, but
both sides said the <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> family will receive less than the
<MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> that they were to receive for the illustrated
manuscript. The accord also calls for the art and religious
works to be exhibited at the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Museum of Art before
returning to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
   The settlement didn't resolve a preliminary ruling by the
<ORGANIZATION>Internal Revenue Service</ORGANIZATION> that the trove should have been
listed as part of <PERSON>Mr. Meador</PERSON>'s estate. "In the event that
ruling becomes final, we fully expect to challenge it in
court," said <PERSON>Randal Mathis</PERSON>, a lawyer for the <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> family.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900629-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-29-90 0634EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StolenArt     06-29 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stolen Art,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>Meador Confided in Friend About Smuggled Medieval Art</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> soldier accused of smuggling medieval
treasures out of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> near the end of World War II confided to a
longtime friend that he took the trove, a newspaper reported today.
   For years before his death in <DATE>1980</DATE>, <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON> was torn over
whether to keep the artwork or return it, <PERSON>Owen Hunsaker</PERSON>, <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s
college classmate in the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, told <ORGANIZATION>The Dallas Morning News</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``When he looked at it he'd get a dreary, transported look on
his face because he knew what he had _ he loved it _ and he
couldn't part with it,'' <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON> was quoted as saying.
   ``He struggled with that a lot,'' said <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON>, a 71-year-old
retired airline executive who lives in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON> said his friend told him he found the treasures in a
cave in <DATE>1945</DATE> in <LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, now in <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, and had simply
wrapped them in brown paper and used an <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> post office to ship
them to his home in <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, 60 miles north of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   Hunsaker is the first person to explain how Meador allegedly
discovered the artwork and moved it. Reports about the case first
surfaced in The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Times two weeks ago.
   The treasures included manuscripts, crucifixes and ancient
coins, which church officials said were gifts to the Quedlinburg
Cathedral from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s earliest kings.
   Lawyers for the <ORGANIZATION>Lutheran Church of Quedlinburg</ORGANIZATION> contend that
<PERSON>Meador</PERSON> stole the treasures while serving as an <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> lieutenant
among troops that occupied the area in <DATE>April 1945</DATE>.
   Meador left the cache to his brother and sister, <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Jane Meador Cook</PERSON>. They are disputing the church's claim of
ownership and trying to keep the items, which are worth millions.
   The <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> family is asking the church's permission to display
the treasures at the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Museum of Art or the <ORGANIZATION>Kimball Art Museum</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION> while the lawsuit over ownership is pending, the News
reported today.
   ``We have not as yet spoken with either museum,'' the family's
attorney, <PERSON>Randal Mathis</PERSON>, told the newspaper. ``We think that they
would be appropriate places for safekeeping.''
   <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON> was in the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> during World War II while his friend
fought in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. He said that during a visit to <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> in
<DATE>1948</DATE>, <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> showed him artwork that he said he had wrapped in
brown paper, marked as ``old books'' and deposited in a mailbox at
<ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> headquarters.
   He said <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> told him that he found the artwork in <DATE>1945</DATE> in a
cave filled with treasures of gold and silver, and filled his <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>
jacket with ``as many treasures as he could hold'' before returning
to his headquarters.
   <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> reports indicate the treasures were removed from a
mine shaft near <LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION> within three days after Allied troops
occupied the area in <DATE>April 1945</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON>, the News reported, said <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> did not tell him
whether anyone helped him remove the artwork or whether he returned
to the cave later to get more items.
   He said they sat for hours paging through a manuscript with an
elaborate cover of gold encrusted with jewels, and highlighted with
a silver figure of Jesus Christ with his hand risen in benediction.
   ``It was unbelievable,'' <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON> said. ``I knew I was touching
ancient history.''
   <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON> said he frequently tried but failed to persuade <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>
to turn over the artwork to authorities.
   ``Joe knew he had a hot potato,'' said <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON>. ``He couldn't
let everybody know about it, and he certainly couldn't sell it.''
   <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON> said he last talked to <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> a few years before he
died.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900615-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-15-90 0411EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StolenArt Bjt   06-15 0653</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stolen Art, Bjt,0670</SECOND>
<HEAD>German Art Has Town Talking, Lawyers Negotiating</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DN2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE MITTELSTADT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WHITEWRIGHT, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People who knew <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON> say they
can't believe the quiet hardware store owner stole millions in
medieval art from a German church while he was a soldier during
World War II.
   The possibility that <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> stashed the precious cache in a
<LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> bank vault was the talk of this farm town <DATE>Thursday</DATE>,
when The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> quoted unidentified sources as saying he
was responsible for one of the century's biggest art thefts.
   ``I just don't believe he was that kind of a man,'' said
73-year-old <PERSON>Mary Bryant</PERSON>, who said she had visited <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s home but
could not remember seeing any sumptuous works of art.
   ``He didn't seem the type of guy to me that would do something
like that,'' said <PERSON>Troyce Spencer</PERSON>, who also lives in this town of
1,760 people about 60 miles north of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   The newspaper said <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>, in the final days of World War II,
took the objects from a church in <LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, an ancient castle
town in what is now <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>. The Times based its report on
interviews with art experts, lawyers and neighbors of <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>.
   Stolen was a small, silver display case inlaid with enamels and
precious stones, with side panels of carved ivory; a liturgical
ivory comb; a manuscript dated <DATE>1513</DATE>; several rock crystal flasks
and gold and silver crucifixes, and other treasures.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> investigated the theft but dropped the matter in <DATE>1949</DATE>
when Quedlinburg became part of <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Dietrich Kotzsche</PERSON>, a German authority in medieval decorative
art, said the Quedlinburg treasures, dating to the 9th and 10th
centuries, could be worth millions.
   The Times reported today that the church in <LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION> has
retained two lawyers to seek the return of the art.
   Meador died in <DATE>1980</DATE> at age 64. He co-owned a family hardware and
farm tool business and grew orchids in a greenhouse behind the
two-story Victorian home he shared with his mother, <PERSON>Mabel</PERSON>.
   ``He was the type of fellow that didn't mix with people much,''
said <PERSON>Odell Caraway</PERSON>, a member of <ORGANIZATION>American Legion Post</ORGANIZATION> 225 to which
<PERSON>Meador</PERSON> once belonged. ``As far as I know he's never been involved
in any kind of crooked stuff.''
   <PERSON>Willi A. Korte</PERSON>, a West German government official who
specializes in the repatriation of cultural property, and <PERSON>Thomas R.
Kline</PERSON> of the law firm <ORGANIZATION>Andrews &amp; Kurth</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>,
said they planned a trip to <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> today to negotiate with <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s
relatives, the <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Neither those lawyers nor <PERSON>John S. Torigian</PERSON>, an attorney for
<PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s brother, <PERSON>Jack</PERSON>, could be reached for comment <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by
<ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>.
   Meador was an officer in the <ORGANIZATION>87th Armored Field Artillery</ORGANIZATION>, which
occupied Quedlinburg and guarded a mine shaft where the <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said
the treasures were kept. The items disappeared a few days after
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops took over the area in <DATE>1945</DATE>, the newspaper said.
   Three longtime <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> employees said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> they had never
known their boss to show off any art works.
   The Times reported that a source it did not identify said the
treasures are in the vault of the <ORGANIZATION>First National Bank of
Whitewright</ORGANIZATION>, reportedly as collateral for a loan. <PERSON>Harrell Stowers</PERSON>,
the bank's executive vice president, would not confirm that
information <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when asked by <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON>, his wife, <PERSON>Jean</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s sister, <PERSON>Jane Meador
Cook</PERSON>, also would not comment <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   How the treasures got to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> is a secret that may have died
with <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>.
   Most of the people interviewed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> said they didn't know
<PERSON>Meador</PERSON> had even been in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> or World War II.
   ``We haven't had this much excitement since the machine gun
deal,'' said Mayor <PERSON>Clarence Tillet Jr.</PERSON>, who explained that a judge
once charged four machine guns in the town's name to avoid paying
sales tax.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900726-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-26-90 1323EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-StolenArt     07-26 0342</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stolen Art,0352</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dallas Museum to Exhibit Stolen Medieval Art While Lawyers
Negotiate</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Art treasures allegedly pilfered by an American
soldier at the end of World War II have been given to a <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>
museum while attorneys for his family and an East German church
haggle over ownership of the treasure.
   Attorneys for the church in Quedlinburg and for the heirs of
former <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> Lt. <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON>, who allegedly took the centuries-old
objects, announced the agreement today at the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Museum of Art.
   The museum agreed to provide a ``temporary, neutral safe
haven,'' said museum director <PERSON>Richard R. Brettell</PERSON> in a statement.
However, the pieces will not be displayed publicly until the
lawsuit brought by the church is settled.
   ``Claimants presently contemplate permitting the museum
subsequently to display the objects ... with terms for any display
to be negotiated later,'' the statement said.
   The objects to be brought to the museum include articles of
gold, silver, ivory and crystal dating from the 8th to 14th
centuries, the museum said.
   The agreement was reached today between law firms representing
both sides.
   The items have been in <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, about 60 miles north of
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> since <DATE>1945</DATE>, the museum said.
   The artworks have been stored recently in safety deposit boxes
in banks in those cities.
   The Lutheran church, Stiftskirche-Domgemeinde of Quedlinburg,
claims <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>, who lived in <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, stole the trove while his
unit was guarding a mine shaft where the items had been hidden.
   Attorneys for <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Jane Meador Cook</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Mesquite</ORGANIZATION>, brother and sister of the deceased soldier, have been
negotiating a proposed move of the treasures to the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> museum.
   The ownership lawsuit is being heard by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge
Sidney Fitzwater</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, who is expected to review the
agreement. Fitzwater on <DATE>July 9</DATE> ordered the heirs and the church to
agree on a facility to store the items until the case is settled.
   Meador, who died in <DATE>1980</DATE>, bequeathed the artwork to his siblings.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900716-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-16-90 1527EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-GermanArt     07-16 0422</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-German Art,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>East German Church To Get Help With Missing Treasures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUD S. BEELMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An East German church is getting help
from <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> to retrieve art treasures believed pilfered by an
American soldier at the close of World War II, a West German
official said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   East and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> also agreed to build an information
database aimed at the return of other art works that vanished when
the Third <PERSON>Reich</PERSON> fell.
   Litigation to retrieve the so-called Quedlinburg treasures from
bank vaults in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> is already under way. The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>
said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> would pay the legal costs.
   <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>'s help in meeting the expense will be a major boost for the
<ORGANIZATION>Lutheran Church of Quedlinburg</ORGANIZATION>, which claims its treasures were
stolen at the end of World War II, said <PERSON>Klaus Maurice</PERSON>, director of
the <ORGANIZATION>West German Cultural Foundation</ORGANIZATION> of the States.
   ``Nobody knew until now who had to pay, but they will pay and
this is marvelous,'' <PERSON>Maurice</PERSON> said.
   The Quedlinburg treasures include two rare medieval manuscripts,
a jeweled, ivory-carved container for relics and several
rock-crystal and ivory objects. They were allegedly removed from a
mine shaft where they had been hidden in the final days of the war.
   <PERSON>Maurice</PERSON> said there was no doubt the art works in question were
authentic.
   The Quedlinburg treasures, among <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s most famous art
works, were allegedly taken by a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> army officer stationed in
<LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, now <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1945</DATE>, and brought to his hometown
of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   The church is suing the sister and brother of the officer, the
late <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON>, to recover the treasures.
   <PERSON>Maurice</PERSON> said officials have no clear idea of how many other
works were allegedly looted from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s artitistic heritage in
the final months of the war.
   ``The problem up to now is that we had two states and it wasn't
easy to speak with <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Maurice</PERSON> said. ``Now, this is
easier.''
   Maurice spoke after attending a two-hour meeting to dicuss
coordinated approaches toward retrieving lost German art. Also
attending the meeting was a <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Culture</ORGANIZATION> representative from
<LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, which is expected to formally unite with its Western
neighbor in <DATE>December</DATE>.
   The new database is to be established in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> and collect
information from museums, churches and other institutions
throughout the two Germanys, <PERSON>Maurice</PERSON> said. The database will
compare pre-World War II inventories with current records in an
attempt to get a complete picture of what is missing, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-3596</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DCOCJADAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930315
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 MAR 93 / Arts: Parisian cathedral of culture - Architecture
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By COLIN AMERY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
I do not often sit down to a candlelit dinner in a French cathedral but last
week I had the opportunity, between mouthfuls of lamb and couscous, to study
the Romanesque sculptures of the cathedral of <ORGANIZATION>St Lazare</ORGANIZATION> at Autun. At the
same time I was able to contemplate the outstanding 12th-century carvings of
the tympanum of the Vision of the Apocalypse at the abbey church of <LOCATION>Moissac</LOCATION>;
and I scarcely had to turn my head to see the remarkable relationship
between architecture and sculpture at the basilica of <ORGANIZATION>St Madeleine</ORGANIZATION> at
<LOCATION>Vezelay</LOCATION>. Within reach of my table were the slender sculptures from <LOCATION>Chartres</LOCATION>
as well as columns, capitals, chancels and Carolingian conceits from all
over <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
I was, of course, in a cathedral of culture, at an elegant Parisian event to
mark the re-opening of the <ORGANIZATION>Musee National des Monuments Francais</ORGANIZATION> at the
<ORGANIZATION>Palais de Chaillot</ORGANIZATION>. The story of this museum goes back to the <DATE>1880s</DATE> when the
architect Eugene-Emanuel Viollet-le-Duc (1814-1879) had the idea that the
French public should have the chance to see, in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, the high points of
French architecture and sculpture of the Middle Ages. He put together this
remarkable assembly of cast copies of important elements of buildings in
what was then the new Palais du <ORGANIZATION>Trocadero</ORGANIZATION>, which had originally been
designed by the architect <PERSON>Davioud</PERSON> for the <ORGANIZATION>Paris Universal Exhibition</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1878</DATE>.
The display was always intended to be didactic, offering the visitor the
opportunity to make comparative analyses of stylistic developments.
Viollet-le-Duc was a scholar and historian and his architectural activity
consisted principally of repair and restoration, including work on monuments
including <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Sainte Chapelle</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. He wrote a dictionary
of French architecture and this museum is an effective monument to his
conviction that architects can and should learn from the past. He saw the
parallels between Gothic structures and the development of 19th-century
engineering.
As the original progenitor of the museum, <PERSON>Viollet-le-Duc</PERSON> would have approved
of the way it has suddenly taken on a new lease of life. The original
<ORGANIZATION>Trocadero</ORGANIZATION> was transformed in <DATE>1937</DATE> by the architect <PERSON>Carlu</PERSON> into the <LOCATION>Palais de
Chaillot</LOCATION>, as the centrepiece of the <ORGANIZATION>Paris Universal Exposition</ORGANIZATION> of that year.
Today these former exhibition buildings gather around the steps and stylish
fountains of the Trocadero, paying homage to the <ORGANIZATION>Eiffel Tower</ORGANIZATION>. They remain
resolutely of the <DATE>1930s</DATE> and provide an extraordinary contrast to the
architectural collections housed there.
For a long time the casts have been seen as little more than dusty relics,
stranded in the <DATE>1930s</DATE> splendour of the Chaillot. It has taken the dramatic
energy of <PERSON>Mr Jack Lang</PERSON> and his ministry of education and culture to see the
potential of this important museum. It has also taken an enormous amount of
work and inspiration from the young curator  - <PERSON>Mr Guy Cogeval</PERSON>, who came here
from the <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION>; in only six months he has achieved a considerable
transformation.
It begins in the new entrance hall which has been designed by a young
architect, <PERSON>Jean-Christophe Denise</PERSON>. This is a handsome light space in the
spirit of Carlu. It has a most stylish cafe-restaurant with a marvellous
view of the fountains of the Trocadero and the <ORGANIZATION>Eiffel Tower</ORGANIZATION> (the furniture
is based on <ORGANIZATION>Carlu</ORGANIZATION>'s original art deco designs); there is also a new
bookshop. The clean lines of this hall provide a cool setting for the four
giant fragments of the reproduction of the sculpture - 'la danse de
Carpeaux' - originally created by <PERSON>Paul Landowski</PERSON> in <DATE>1931</DATE>. These look
dramatic and surreal, mounted at a high level on large plinths.
The hall is accessible to all visitors to the museums in the <LOCATION>Palais de
Chaillot</LOCATION>, including those of the theatre and cinema. (The <ORGANIZATION>Musee du Cinema</ORGANIZATION> is
likely to enjoy a close relationship with the renovated <ORGANIZATION>Musee</ORGANIZATION> national des
Monuments Francais because of <PERSON>Mr Cogeval</PERSON>'s great interest in film and his
plans to create events that explore both the plastic and the cinematic
arts.)
To visit the great halls upstairs that house the maquettes, casts and models
is a thrilling experience, although in time the displays will probably be
reordered and captioned to make them both more instructive and more
enjoyable. <PERSON>Mr Cogeval</PERSON> is anxious to make more of the amazing collections of
topographical and architectural photographs stored here. They will form part
of the large programme of temporary exhibitions.
The first exhibition to be held is called '<LOCATION>Marseille</LOCATION> a <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>', a version of
the very successful exhibition held in <LOCATION>Marseilles</LOCATION>. Its subject is the city
in the <DATE>19th century</DATE>, considering both the physical character of the changing
city and the artistic activity within it at the time. A large variety of
artefacts ranging from contemporary models and maps to paintings and plans,
drawings and sculptures is displayed to convey the commerce and creativity
of one entire city at a peak moment of its growth. (The installation here is
sometimes inevitably in conflict with the permanent installation of the
museum, but in <DATE>1994</DATE> there will be a full-scale temporary exhibition space.)
Marseilles grew and prospered in the <DATE>19th century</DATE>, its artistic flowering as
aesthetically mixed as any other city at the time. It is probably right to
show the whole range so that comparisons of quality can be made. Relatively
unknown history painters are shown as seriously as old masters, and posters
and plans rub shoulders with fine drawings. It is a complex and dense
exhibition, giving a sense of a city touched by the exoticism of its African
trade and yet solidly rooted in the <ORGANIZATION>Second Empire</ORGANIZATION> in its architecture and
monuments.
The renewal of this museum in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> is important for the broadening of our
architectural culture. It will take a lot of imagination to build on the
solid foundations of the unique collection. The resurrection has just begun,
but I am sure <PERSON>Mr Cogeval</PERSON> will ensure that it continues with both scholarship
and excitement. It is a museum to watch.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>FRZ  France, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8412 Museums and Art Galleries.
    P8712 Architectural Aervices.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900629-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-29-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StolenArt     06-29 0466</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stolen Art,0485</SECOND>
<HEAD>Friend: World War II Officer Confided About Smuggled Medieval Art</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The late World War II <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> officer accused of
stealing priceless German art treasures at the end of the war
stumbled onto them during a battle and simply shipped them home in
a plain brown wrapper, a friend says.
   <PERSON>Owen Hunsaker</PERSON>, a college classmate of <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON>, said his
friend agonized over whether to return the stolen Medieval
artworks, but loved them too much to part with them, <ORGANIZATION>The Dallas
Morning News</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   He said <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> was running for cover during fighting near
<LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> when he ended up in a mine shaft and
discovered an ``Aladdin's Cave.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> lieutenant filled his jacket with ``as many treasures
as he could hold,'' <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON> said. He then mailed the artworks home
in a box wrapped in plain brown paper and marked ``old books.''
   <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON>, 71, of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> said <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> told him the story during
a visit in <DATE>1948</DATE>. They had been college classmates in the <DATE>1930s</DATE> and
kept in touch until a few years before <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s death in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   The religious treasures stored in the mine shaft for safekeeping
from retreating Nazi forces disappeared in <DATE>April 1945</DATE>. They
belonged to <ORGANIZATION>Quedlinburg Cathedral</ORGANIZATION>.
   Lawyers for the Quedlinburg church contend <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> stole the
treasures and kept them in his hometown of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, a
tiny town about 60 miles north of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   The church wants the treasures returned and has asked a federal
judge to prevent <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s heirs from moving or disposing of the
artworks, believed to be stored in nearby bank vaults.
   <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON>'s account is the first offering an explanation of how
<PERSON>Meador</PERSON> allegedly discovered and shipped the artworks that include a
bejeweled gold-covered manuscript, crucifixes and ancient coins.
   The artworks were gifts to the church from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s earliest
kings.
   During <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON>'s <DATE>1948</DATE> visit to <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> took the
so-called illuminated manuscript ``wrapped in an old <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> quilt''
from a bedroom closet, he said.
   ``It was unbelievable,'' said <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON>. ``I knew I was touching
ancient history.''
   He said it had an elaborate cover of gold encrusted with jewels,
highlighted with a silver figure of Christ with his hand risen in
blessing.
   <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON> said he frequently urged <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> to turn over the
artwork to authorities.
   ``When he looked at it he'd get a dreary, transported look on
his face because he knew what he had _ he loved it _ and he
couldn't part with it. He struggled with that a lot,'' <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON>
said.
   Meador considered taking the artworks to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> to obtain phony
ownership papers, but abandoned the plan because he feared border
police, he said.
   ``Joe knew he had a hot potato,'' <PERSON>Hunsaker</PERSON> said, ``He couldn't
let everybody know about it, and he certainly couldn't sell it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900614-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-14-90 2306EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StolenArt     06-14 0533</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stolen Art,0553</SECOND>
<HEAD>Priceless Art Reports News to People Here</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WHITEWRIGHT, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Word that a local hardware and farm
tool vendor may have pulled off one of the century's biggest art
thefts while a soldier in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> during World War II was the talk
of this town of 1,760 <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   There were more reporters than residents on the town's main
drag, about 60 miles north of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   ``Not much happens here,'' said <PERSON>Carolyn Flaughter</PERSON>, ``You see
cameramen walking up and down the street. You just don't see that
every day.''
   According to a <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> report <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON>
transported the priceless pieces to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> from Quedlinburg, an
ancient castle town in what is now <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> investigated the theft but dropped the matter in <DATE>1949</DATE>
when Quedlinburg became part of <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>.
treasures are in the vault of the <ORGANIZATION>First National Bank of
Whitewright</ORGANIZATION>, reportedly as collateral for a loan.
   Bank officials declined to comment on the reports. <PERSON>Harrell
Stowers</PERSON>, bank executive vice president, said he could not confirm
whether the treasures are or ever have been in the vault.
   Meador died in <DATE>1980</DATE>. His brother, <PERSON>Jack</PERSON>, and his sister-in-law,
<PERSON>Jean</PERSON>, declined to comment <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The Times based its report on interviews with art experts,
lawyers and neighbors of <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>.
   The treasures include a small silver reliquary, inlaid with
enamels and precious stones, with side panels of carved ivory; a
liturgical ivory comb; a manuscript dated <DATE>1513</DATE>; several rock
crystal flasks and gold and silver crucifixes. Some of the
treasures were gifts from kings and emperors who ruled German
states in the 9th and 10th centuries.
   Meador was an officer with the <ORGANIZATION>87th Armored Field Artillery</ORGANIZATION>, the
unit that occupied Quedlinburg and guarded the mine shaft where the
treasures reportedly were kept. They disappeared a few days after
American troops took over the area in <DATE>1945</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Three years after <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> died, his brother-in-law, <PERSON>Dr. Don H.
Cook</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>Mesquite</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, sought to have two medieval manuscripts
evaluated, <PERSON>John Carroll Collins</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> estate appraiser, told
the newspaper.
   A former employee of <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s, speaking on condition of
anonymity, said <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> reportedly showed his employees richly bound
gold and silver manuscripts.
   But three longtime <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> employees said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> they'd never
known their boss to show off any art works when they were around.
The three declined to give their names.
   Most of the people interviewed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> said they didn't know
<PERSON>Meador</PERSON> had even been in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> or World War II.
   ``<PERSON>Joe</PERSON> was a quiet man. I think <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, in my way of thinking, was a
very, very intelligent man ... he seemed to mind his own
business,'' Mayor <PERSON>Clarence Tillett</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Tillett</PERSON> said he'd visited <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> in the house he shared with his
mother but didn't recall any unusual works of art.
   ``It wouldn't have surprised me for anything to come out of
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Tillett</PERSON> said.
   Many residents recalled <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> as a loner whose most memorable
trait was his passion for growing orchids.
   ``He didn't seem like the type of guy to me who would do
something like that,'' said <PERSON>Troyce Spencer</PERSON>, a resident.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061590-0058 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 233922 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 15, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 16; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
891 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GERMAN WWII ART CACHE MAY BE IN TEXAS BANK; 
</P>
<P>
CRIME: THE SEARCH FOCUSES ON A SOLDIER, NOW DEAD, WHOSE UNIT GUARDED THE WORKS. 
ONE OBJECT WAS RETURNED FOR A $3-MILLION 'FINDER'S FEE' IN APRIL. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By J. MICHAEL KENNEDY, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HOUSTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In the tiny <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> town of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, hard on the <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> border, a scandal 
is brewing in which a man who raised prize orchids and ran a hardware store 
before his death 10 years ago may have been the perpetrator of one of the 
largest art thefts ever recorded. 
</P>
<P>
His name was <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON>, by all accounts a quiet, unassuming man who served 
honorably in World War II and ended his service stationed in what is now <LOCATION>East 
Germany</LOCATION> in <DATE>1945</DATE>. His unit was in charge of guarding a mine shaft that contained 
some of the world's most valuable art objects, hidden there at the time for 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Federal Bureau of Investigation</ORGANIZATION> and a West German investigator are now 
looking to a bank vault in <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s hometown of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, population 1,800, 
as the place where the treasures might at last be recovered. The investigation 
was disclosed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I am going to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to try to put some more nails in some coffins," said <PERSON>Willi 
Korte</PERSON>, the German investigator, in a telephone interview. "I have been to 
<LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> before, and it wasn't because Triple-A recommended it." 
</P>
<P>
The first break in the case occurred <DATE>last April</DATE>, when, for a <MONEY>$3-million</MONEY> 
"finder's fee," one of the missing works was returned to a West German 
foundation, with the stipulation that the names of the sellers, as well as the 
name of the lawyer who negotiated the deal, would never be disclosed. 
</P>
<P>
At the time the deal was cut for the artwork -- a 9th-Century jewel-encrusted, 
illustrated manuscript of the Four Gospels -- a spokesman for the foundation 
said the manuscript was taken to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> by an American GI at the end of the war. 
That and other treasures were hidden in the mine shaft near <LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, a 
medieval castle town in <LOCATION>Saxony-Anhault Province</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The arrangement for the manuscript was carried out in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, where such 
sales are protected by law. 
</P>
<P>
The lengthy report in the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> pointed to <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> as the thief and his 
heirs as the people who arranged for the sale of the manuscript. Numerous calls 
to the relatives elicited a string of "no comments." The lawyer named as the 
intermediary in the transaction, <PERSON>John S. Torigian</PERSON>, left word that he would be 
taking depositions for the rest of the week. 
</P>
<P>
The president of the bank where the remainder of the treasures are purportedly 
being kept would not discuss the matter. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> agent <PERSON>Mike Satimauro</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> office said the matter is under 
investigation. 
</P>
<P>
"We're intent on getting a better handle on what's supposed to be missing," he 
said. "We're trying to see if we do, in fact, have stolen articles and, if we 
do, we will do our best to get them back." 
</P>
<P>
While the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> is investigating, the town of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> went into an absolute 
swoon <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Television crews in helicopters flashed overhead and the 
telephones never seemed to stop ringing. 
</P>
<P>
"This has thrown us into an uproar," said Mayor <PERSON>Clarence Tillett</PERSON>. "The whole 
town will be talking about this for some time to come. There's 1,800 people 
here and people usually know what's going on with everyone else in town. But I 
can tell you, all of us were surprised about this news about <PERSON>Joe Meador</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Larry Kennealy</PERSON>, the chief of police, said: "Nobody knows anything about this." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Korte</PERSON>, the investigator, said these kinds of thefts usually follow a similar 
pattern, in which art was taken, the thief dies and the heirs try to cash in on 
the treasure. In this case, the family members allegedly consulted with a 
number of experts about two manuscripts. Most of the experts told the family 
that the manuscripts probably were stolen. 
</P>
<P>
"There was not a whole lot of sophistication, or they wouldn't have exposed 
themselves by having so many appraisals," <PERSON>Korte</PERSON> said. "I hope the family has 
some valuable information and some additional items." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Korte</PERSON> said his first nibble came early this year, when word went out through 
the art world that one of the manuscripts could be had for the <MONEY>$3-million</MONEY> 
finder's fee. That was two years after the first word that the Quedlinburg 
treasures might be for sale, for the right price. 
</P>
<P>
"The offer clearly smelled like it was coming out of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Korte</PERSON> was somewhat circumspect about how the field was narrowed to 
<LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, he said documents at the <ORGANIZATION>National Archives</ORGANIZATION> had been extremely 
beneficial. He said he had been looking for an officer to be the thief. Meador 
was a lieutenant when the war ended. 
</P>
<P>
He said experience had shown that most such postwar thefts were "under the eyes 
of an American officer or with the participation of an American officer." 
</P>
<P>
After the war, <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>, who had studied art in college, came back to <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> 
after his father became ill. By all accounts, he led a very normal life, 
waiting on people at the hardware store and raising orchids in the three 
greenhouses behind the family home. He never married. At graduation time, 
<PERSON>Meador</PERSON> provided free orchids to the seniors. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Marshall Hasty</PERSON>, one of the pallbearers at <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s funeral, said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>: "I 
heard from several people that <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> used to bring those manuscripts in the 
hardware store once in a while and left them laying right out there on the 
counter. 
</P>
<P>
"The consensus in town is he didn't know the value of them. If he did, I don't 
think he would have laid them out on a counter in a hardware store downtown." 
</P>
<P>
Times researcher <PERSON>Lianne Hart</PERSON> contributed to this story. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, The late Joe T. Meador in 1960. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ART THEFTS; ART -- EAST GERMANY; ART -- WEST GERMANY; INVESTIGATIONS; ROBBERIES 
-- WEST GERMANY; ROBBERIES -- EAST GERMANY; ARMY (U.S.) -- PERSONNEL 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900620-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-20-90 0549EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StolenArt     06-20 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stolen Art,0394</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Orders Inventory of Stolen German Art Treasure</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARNIE STAPLETON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge has ordered an inventory of
medieval artwork believed stolen by a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> soldier from a German
mineshaft during World War II and stashed in a small-town bank
vault in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Sidney A. Fitzwater</PERSON> ordered <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that the
time and place of the inspection be kept secret to protect the
inspectors and the objects, which have been valued in the millions
by German art experts.
   The Lutheran cathedral in <LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, is suing to
recover the artwork from the <ORGANIZATION>First National Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> and
the family of <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON>.
   Meador, a former <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> lieutenant, is believed to have stolen the
objects and stashed them in his hometown of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>, about 60
miles north of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   The treasure disappeared in <DATE>1945</DATE> from a mine shaft in
<LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, a castle town occupied by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops at the end of
World War II. Meador died of cancer in <DATE>1980</DATE>, and his family put the
objects in the bank for safekeeping, said branch President <PERSON>John
Farley</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> said he never knew the art had been stolen and had been
trying to mediate the dispute over its ownership. ``We wanted to do
what was right,'' he said.
   Government officials have said it is unclear whether charges can
be brought in the case because of statutes of limitations on thefts
of art.
   The judge on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> dictated the circumstances of the inventory
down to the type of flash to be used in photographing the items,
the placement of the cameras and a requirement that all inspectors
wear cotton gloves.
   The lawsuit alleges at least 14 objects were taken by <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>,
including a silver, ivory and gold reliquary from the 9th or <DATE>10th
century</DATE>, a 10th century Byzantine rock-crystal flask and an ivory
comb inlaid with precious stones.
   Also listed as stolen are two manuscripts, one from about <DATE>1300</DATE>
and the other from <DATE>1515</DATE>, bound in precious metals and encrusted
with gems.
   Meador's brother and sister, <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Jane
Meador Cook</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Mesquite</ORGANIZATION>, have refused to comment.
   <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> said the bank will ask to be dropped from the lawsuit
because <ORGANIZATION>First National</ORGANIZATION> never claimed to own the relics.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901018-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-18-90 0857EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a PM-BRF--StolenArt     10-18 0164</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Stolen Art,0174</SECOND>
<HEAD>477-Year-Old Manuscript Taken During War Returned to Germany</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 477-year-old manuscript taken from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> by an
American soldier at the end of World War II has been returned to
its homeland.
   The law firm <ORGANIZATION>Andrews &amp; Kurth</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the Evangelister
manuscript, noted for its silver cover containing the figure of
Jesus Christ, was returned earlier this month and is being restored
in <LOCATION>Munich</LOCATION>.
   American soldier <PERSON>Joe T. Meador</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>1980</DATE>, brought the
manuscript and several other items to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> in <DATE>1945</DATE> from
Quedlinburg. They eventually wound up in the hands of <ORGANIZATION>First
National Bank of Whitewright</ORGANIZATION>.
   This is the second piece of Quedlinburg treasure recovered by
the <ORGANIZATION>German Cultural Foundation</ORGANIZATION> of the States. The <ORGANIZATION>Samuhel Gospels</ORGANIZATION>,
made in the <DATE>10th century</DATE>, was recovered in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION> for a <MONEY>$3
million</MONEY> finder's fee, according to reports from the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Lutheran Church</ORGANIZATION> is suing for the return of the other works,
which are being held in a <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> museum.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900623-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-23-90 2310EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StolenArt     06-23 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stolen Art,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>Attorneys for German Church Say Family Is Hiding Treasures</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attorneys for an East German church trying to
recover medieval treasures stolen during World War II allege that a
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> family moved or hid some of the items in the last two weeks.
   In court documents, the attorneys accuse relatives of <PERSON>Joe T.
Meador</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> of moving the articles from bank vaults in
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> so the lawyers wouldn't find them.
   Meador, who died in <DATE>1980</DATE>, allegedly stole the items, including
centuries-old manuscripts of the Gospels, from the church in
Quedlinburg at the end of World War II.
   Motions filed in federal court <DATE>Friday</DATE> allege that <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>'s
siblings, <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jane Meador Cook</PERSON>, ``have been linked to
more than half'' of about 18 artworks taken from a mine-shaft
hiding place near Quedlinburg in <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   The Meadors allegedly inherited the trove, valued in the
millions, when their brother died of cancer.
   <PERSON>Raymond A. Krell</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> attorney for the <PERSON>Meadors</PERSON>, did not
return phone calls <DATE>Saturday</DATE> from <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Alan Harris</PERSON>, an attorney for the church, declined to comment on
the motions <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   No court action was taken <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the motions.
   The church filed a lawsuit <DATE>Monday</DATE> after three weeks of
negotiations with the family reached an impasse.
   The lawsuit, which also names the <ORGANIZATION>First National Bank of
Whitewright</ORGANIZATION> as a defendant, seeks unspecified damages. The bank has
held some of the artwork for at least the last three months, its
lawyer said.
   A <ORGANIZATION>U.S. State Department</ORGANIZATION> legal adviser said this week that the
lawsuit was filed after East German officials learned the treasures
were about to be moved to <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, where secrecy laws would
make them impossible to trace or recover.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Sidney A. Fitzwater</PERSON> granted a 10-day
temporary restraining order <DATE>Monday</DATE> barring movement of the trove,
pending a decision in the case. But he denied a plea by church
lawyers that the items be placed in court custody for safekeeping.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, he ordered the church be allowed to examine,
photograph and inventory treasures being stored in vaults at the
<LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> bank and the <ORGANIZATION>First Interstate Bank of Dallas</ORGANIZATION>.
   During an examination <DATE>Thursday</DATE> of <PERSON>Mrs. Cook</PERSON>'s safe-deposit boxes
in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, only one item believed to be a Quedlinburg treasure was
found, the church contends.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Cook</PERSON> removed several of the other items last week, the
church says, and an unidentified person rented a new safe-deposit
box and ``placed certain items'' into it. The objects were not
identified.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900619-0191 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-19-90 2236EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StolenArt 1stLd-Writethru a0734 06-19 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stolen Art, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0734,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Orders Inventory of Stolen German Art Treasure</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf to add indeterminate value; SUBS 8th graf
`Meador died...' to CORRECT location of Denison; picks up 9th graf,
`Farley told...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ARNIE STAPLETON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> ordered the small-town
bank that has been holding a cache of stolen medieval art to open
its vault for inventory by the East German cathedral that claims
the treasure.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Sidney A. Fitzwater</PERSON> also ordered that the
time and place of the inspection be kept secret to protect the
inspectors and the objects.
   The art is believed to have been stolen from a German mine shaft
at the end of World War II by a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> soldier from <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. German art
experts have said the treasures are worth <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY>, but
no specific estimate is available.
   The president of a <ORGANIZATION>First National Bank</ORGANIZATION> branch in the town of
<LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> said he never knew the art had been stolen and has been
trying to mediate the dispute over its ownership.
   ``We wanted to do what was right,'' branch President <PERSON>John Farley</PERSON>
said in an interview published <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <ORGANIZATION>The Denison Herald</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Lutheran cathedral in <LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, is suing to
recover the artwork from <ORGANIZATION>First National</ORGANIZATION> and the family of <PERSON>Joe T.
Meador</PERSON>, a former <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> first lieutenant who is believed to have
stolen the objects and stashed them in his hometown of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>,
about 60 miles north of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   The treasure disappeared in <DATE>1945</DATE> from a mine shaft in
<LOCATION>Quedlinburg</LOCATION>, a castle town occupied by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops at the end of
World War II.
   Meador died of cancer in <DATE>1980</DATE>, and his family put the objects in
the bank for safekeeping, <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> said. He oversees the <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>
branch but is based at <LOCATION>Denison</LOCATION>, about 70 miles north of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   Farley told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> the bank will ask to be dropped
from the lawsuit because <ORGANIZATION>First National</ORGANIZATION> never claimed to own the
relics. He declined to answer further questions about the case.
   A church representative met with <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> on <DATE>May 7</DATE> to demand
return of the treasures. The lawsuit alleges at least 14 objects
were taken by <PERSON>Meador</PERSON>, including a silver, ivory and gold reliquary
from the 9th or <DATE>10th century</DATE>, a 10th century Byzantine rock-crystal
flask with sides shaped like birds and an ivory comb inlaid with
precious stones.
   <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> and his attorney, <PERSON>Timothy Powers</PERSON>, told <ORGANIZATION>The Denison Herald</ORGANIZATION>
the bank had been negotiating with the church and the <PERSON>Meador</PERSON> family.
   The talks broke down last week when the story broke and
international attention focused on the bank and <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION>,
population 1,760, <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> said.
   He said keeping the treasures did not affect the bank's daily
business or financial status.
   ``We're on the sidelines,'' he said. ``I'm sorry that we were
not able to get the parties to agree. It's not in anyone's best
interest to incur litigation costs.''
   Fitzwater revised his inventory order <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> after conference
calls with attorneys on both sides of the dispute.
   He also ruled on a defense request that had been informally made
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, but his office declined to reveal the nature of the
decision or the request until the request is formally filed with
the court <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Fitzwater dictated the circumstances of the inventory down to
the placement of cameras and a requirement that all inspectors wear
cotton gloves.
   Attorneys for the defendants did not return phone calls seeking
comment.
   Meador's brother and sister, <PERSON>Jack Meador</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Whitewright</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Jane
Meador Cook</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Mesquite</ORGANIZATION>, have declined to comment.
   Government officials have said it is unclear whether criminal
charges could be brought in the case because of statutes of
limitations on thefts of art and antiquities.
   <PERSON>Ely Maurer</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> assistant legal adviser for
cultural property, said criminal charges might be pursued under the
National Stolen Property Act. The law prohibits interstate or
international transport of stolen art or artifacts.
   The law might be extended to heirs if they knew the art was
stolen and transferred it across state lines, <PERSON>Maurer</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900619-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-19-90 0259EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StolenArt     06-19 0547</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stolen Art,0564</SECOND>
<HEAD>East German Church Files Lawsuit in Artwork Case</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An East German church has filed a lawsuit
demanding the return of medieval artwork believed stolen by an
American officer in the final days of World War II.
   After hearing oral arguments by telephone <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District
<PERSON>Judge Sidney A. Fitzwater</PERSON> barred movement of the church treasures
without a court order.
   Fitzwater also ordered that representatives of the Lutheran
