<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1347EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-17 0499</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0517</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREAT FALLS, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fifth-grade teacher <PERSON>Susan Nardinger</PERSON> is
rallying the faithful in this river city to defend its short
reputation, which has been assaulted once again by river rats in
<LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore</LOCATION>.
   Students in <ORGANIZATION>Nardinger</ORGANIZATION>'s class touched off the battle <DATE>two years
ago</DATE>, when they petitioned the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION> to
declare the 201-foot-long <LOCATION>Roe River</LOCATION> northeast of Great Falls the
world's shortest river.
   Guinness editors agreed, and the Roe displaced <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>'s D
River in the <DATE>1988</DATE> edition of the record book.
   But <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION> was not about to be sold short.
   They remeasured the D River and announced that it was 120 feet,
mysteriously smaller than the last measuring. And, <ORGANIZATION>Guinness</ORGANIZATION> editors
notified the <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln City Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> recently that the D
River would be back in the books by the <DATE>1991</DATE> edition _ unless a
shorter river is found.
   Well, that's just what students in Great Falls intend to do, and
they'll look no farther than the Roe.
   Nardinger said the Roe could claim a length of only 30 feet
because it has two forks, and the students submitted the longer of
the two for consideration of the record.
   ``I stand behind the kids <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT>,'' she said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   She dismissed the D River as an ``ocean water backup,'' not a
river at all and suggested <ORGANIZATION>Guinness</ORGANIZATION> officials take a look for
themselves.
   <PERSON>Molly Peterson</PERSON>, one of the students who helped petition on
behalf the Roe, took a more philosophical approach. She said the
Roe is still the shortest river, but ``records are made to be
broken.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MIRA LOMA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fifth-grade teacher <PERSON>Susan Nardinger</PERSON> is
rallying the faithful in this river city to defend its short
reputation, which has been assaulted once again by river rats in
<LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore</LOCATION>.
   Students in <ORGANIZATION>Nardinger</ORGANIZATION>'s class touched off the battle <DATE>two years
ago</DATE>, when they petitioned the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION> to
declare the 201-foot-long <LOCATION>Roe River</LOCATION> northeast of Great Falls the
world's shortest river.
   Guinness editors agreed, and the Roe displaced <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>'s D
River in the <DATE>1988</DATE> edition of the record book.
   But <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION> was not about to be sold short.
   They remeasured the D River and announced that it was 120 feet,
mysteriously smaller than the last measuring. And, <ORGANIZATION>Guinness</ORGANIZATION> editors
notified the <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln City Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> recently that the D
River would be back in the books by the <DATE>1991</DATE> edition _ unless a
shorter river is found.
   Well, that's just what students in Great Falls intend to do, and
they'll look no farther than the Roe.
   Nardinger said the Roe could claim a length of only 30 feet
because it has two forks, and the students submitted the longer of
the two for consideration of the record.
   ``I stand behind the kids <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT>,'' she said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   She dismissed the D River as an ``ocean water backup,'' not a
river at all and suggested <ORGANIZATION>Guinness</ORGANIZATION> officials take a look for
themselves.
   <PERSON>Molly Peterson</PERSON>, one of the students who helped petition on
behalf the Roe, took a more philosophical approach. She said the
Roe is still the shortest river, but ``records are made to be
broken.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880812-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-88 0114EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ShortestRiver     08-12 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shortest River,0527</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oregon Town Refuses to Concede Shortest River Title to Montana</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LINCOLN CITY, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thanks to the meddling of a group of
sharp-eyed <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> fifth graders, <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>'s ``D River'' has lost its
30-year title as the world's shortest river, but not without a
fight from miffed local officials.
   Editors of the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION> agreed to give the
title to the <LOCATION>Roe River</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Great Falls</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>, after students there
spent the past school year researching the river, which flows
through a state park.
   The students concluded the Roe is 201 feet, far shorter than the
440-foot D River near <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>, and submitted their evidence to
the Guinness editors.
   ``On the basis of that, the Roe River was shorter,'' assistant
editor <PERSON>Cyd Smith</PERSON> said from the publisher's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> office.
   News of the change was not well-received in <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>,
however, where the D River has held the title of shortest named
river for 30 years.
   ``Where a river begins and ends may be in the eye of the
beholder,'' Mayor <PERSON>Dell Isham</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   In fact, <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION> now insists the D is only 120 feet long,
give or take 5 feet. City officials are preparing documentation to
convince <ORGANIZATION>Guinness</ORGANIZATION> editors that they were right the first time and
that the D River should regain its rightful title in the book's
<DATE>1990</DATE> edition. The deadline is past for next year's edition.
   Of course, the question being asked in Great Falls is: How can a
river shrink from 440 feet to 120 feet? At first it was funny, but
fewer people are laughing now that it's clear <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION> is
serious.
   ``It's fun to a point, but it has no end when people can come
back and keep shortening it until it's kind of ridiculous,'' said
<PERSON>Susie Nardinger</PERSON>, the Great Falls teacher who led her class in the
river study.
   The <PERSON>Roe River</PERSON>'s acceptance into the records book is a matter of
pride to the community's 60,000 residents, she said.
   ``Our students went about it perfectly innocently,'' she said.
``The victory has been marred because <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> came out with its
claims and, in a sense, stole the limelight at the peak of their
success.''
   Signs soon will grace the banks of the Roe to proclaim its
world-class status. About 625 miles away in <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>, similar
signs remain along the D River and there are no plans to remove
them.
   Isham says the dispute is simply a matter of setting the record
straight. Lincoln City insists previous estimates of the river's
length inaccurately measured from a point in the river that
actually is part of Devil's Lake.
   That point looked like part of the river because a landfill had
closed in the banks of the lake, <PERSON>Isham</PERSON> said.
   A spokesman for Gov. <PERSON>Neil Goldschmidt</PERSON> says the states' governors
could get out their yardsticks and settle the issue once and for
all.
   ``If it's a good, honest fight, we'll be there,'' <PERSON>Gregg Kantor</PERSON>
said. ``But it'll always be the shortest river in our hearts.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880420-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-20-88 1554EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     04-20 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JUMPERTOWN, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rural high school science students who
sent <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> bugs to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> are anxiously awaiting a
return shipment of insects from the <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> Zoo.
   Science teacher <PERSON>Doug Fleury</PERSON> said the work started after students
wanted to recognize Soviet scientific achievements and he began
corresponding with the Soviets for them. Samples of unicorn
beetles, about the size of hen eggs, and velvet ants, a type of
wingless wasp, were sent to <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   Now two kinds of giant walking sticks and a giant roach are en
route to this rural area of northeast <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   Fleury is pleased.
   ``It's just not done _ a country school swapping bugs with a
major international zoo,'' he said recently.
   On <DATE>May 2</DATE> and <DATE>3</DATE>, Jumpertown High pupils, with former pupils at
<ORGANIZATION>Thrasher High School</ORGANIZATION> where the work began, will celebrate the
project.
   <PERSON>Brad Fugitt</PERSON>, 18, of <LOCATION>Booneville</LOCATION>, who graduated from Thrasher last
year, said he had been collecting insects for Fleury for five years
and some of his insects have been sent as far as <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
   ``It kind of feels like an honor,'' he said.
   Fugitt is waiting for a response to a letter he wrote recently
to the <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> Zoo to invite Russian scientists to participate in an
insect-collecting expedition in <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> in <DATE>June</DATE> or <DATE>July</DATE>.
   Fleury said he has two hopes for the bug exchanges: to send some
of the pupils to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> with a shipment of live insects
and to bring someone from <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> to northeast <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   ``It's not unusual for zoo people to have a bigger view of the
world than just geographical boundaries,'' <PERSON>Fleury</PERSON> said. ``The
scientific discipline doesn't have geographical boundaries. It has
biological boundaries.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GREAT FALLS, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rural high school science students who
sent <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> bugs to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> are anxiously awaiting a
return shipment of insects from the <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> Zoo.
   Science teacher <PERSON>Doug Fleury</PERSON> said the work started after students
wanted to recognize Soviet scientific achievements and he began
corresponding with the Soviets for them. Samples of unicorn
beetles, about the size of hen eggs, and velvet ants, a type of
wingless wasp, were sent to <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   Now two kinds of giant walking sticks and a giant roach are en
route to this rural area of northeast <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   Fleury is pleased.
   ``It's just not done _ a country school swapping bugs with a
major international zoo,'' he said recently.
   On <DATE>May 2</DATE> and <DATE>3</DATE>, Jumpertown High pupils, with former pupils at
<ORGANIZATION>Thrasher High School</ORGANIZATION> where the work began, will celebrate the
project.
   <PERSON>Brad Fugitt</PERSON>, 18, of <LOCATION>Booneville</LOCATION>, who graduated from Thrasher last
year, said he had been collecting insects for Fleury for five years
and some of his insects have been sent as far as <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
   ``It kind of feels like an honor,'' he said.
   Fugitt is waiting for a response to a letter he wrote recently
to the <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> Zoo to invite Russian scientists to participate in an
insect-collecting expedition in <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> in <DATE>June</DATE> or <DATE>July</DATE>.
   Fleury said he has two hopes for the bug exchanges: to send some
of the pupils to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> with a shipment of live insects
and to bring someone from <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> to northeast <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   ``It's not unusual for zoo people to have a bigger view of the
world than just geographical boundaries,'' <PERSON>Fleury</PERSON> said. ``The
scientific discipline doesn't have geographical boundaries. It has
biological boundaries.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880501-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-01-88 1537EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     05-01 0572</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LINCOLN CITY, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They've had to call out a team from
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> to resolve the question of which river
is the world's shortest.
   A fifth-grade class at Lincoln elementary school in <LOCATION>Great Falls</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>, recently had <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Roe River</LOCATION> measured and declared the
world's shortest, replacing <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>'s D River in the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness
Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Roe River</LOCATION> flows between 275 and 307 feet from a <DATE>spring</DATE> into
the <LOCATION>Missouri River</LOCATION>. The D River flows from <LOCATION>Devil</LOCATION>'s Lake into the
<LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>.
   However, the record book's entry listing the D River as 440 feet
long was based on an outdated survey a century old; a variety of
state agencies in <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> say the river could be as short as 100
feet long.
   The answer about which river wins the trophy for shortness is
expected soon.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ANAHEIM, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They've had to call out a team from
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> to resolve the question of which river
is the world's shortest.
   A fifth-grade class at Lincoln elementary school in <LOCATION>Great Falls</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>, recently had <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Roe River</LOCATION> measured and declared the
world's shortest, replacing <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>'s D River in the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness
Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Roe River</LOCATION> flows between 275 and 307 feet from a <DATE>spring</DATE> into
the <LOCATION>Missouri River</LOCATION>. The D River flows from <LOCATION>Devil</LOCATION>'s Lake into the
<LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>.
   However, the record book's entry listing the D River as 440 feet
long was based on an outdated survey a century old; a variety of
state agencies in <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> say the river could be as short as 100
feet long.
   The answer about which river wins the trophy for shortness is
expected soon.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SOUTH HAVEN, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They've had to call out a team from
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> to resolve the question of which river
is the world's shortest.
   A fifth-grade class at Lincoln elementary school in <LOCATION>Great Falls</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>, recently had <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Roe River</LOCATION> measured and declared the
world's shortest, replacing <LOCATION>Lincoln City</LOCATION>'s D River in the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness
Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Roe River</LOCATION> flows between 275 and 307 feet from a <DATE>spring</DATE> into
the <LOCATION>Missouri River</LOCATION>. The D River flows from <LOCATION>Devil</LOCATION>'s Lake into the
<LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>.
   However, the record book's entry listing the D River as 440 feet
long was based on an outdated survey a century old; a variety of
state agencies in <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> say the river could be as short as 100
feet long.
   The answer about which river wins the trophy for shortness is
expected soon.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881021-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-21-88 1418EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     10-21 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0575</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WADSWORTH, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It might be just another <PERSON>Loch Ness</PERSON>
``Nessie'' or Lake Tahoe ``Tessie'' _ water beasts that catch the
imagination but somehow are never trapped themselves.
   But at least a couple of people near <LOCATION>Wadsworth</LOCATION> have reported
seeing an alligator in the <LOCATION>Truckee River</LOCATION>, and state game wardens
are taking the claim seriously enough to set baited traps for the
reptile.
   So far, however, the 'gator, described as 3-4 feet long and 3 or
4 years old, has given authorities the slip.
   <PERSON>Jim Curran</PERSON>, the state's regional fisheries supervisor, said the
reported alligator is too small to pose a threat and might not
survive the near-freezing winter waters anyway. The reptiles
normally live in tropical rivers and marshes.
   ``We figure this one must have been someone's pet,'' <PERSON>Curran</PERSON>
said. ``When it got too big, they dumped it in the river.''
   The first reported sighting came <DATE>Oct. 14</DATE> when <PERSON>Jack Maughan</PERSON> said
he spotted the snub-nosed reptile in the river while taking his
daily walk along the bank. And <PERSON>Maughan</PERSON>'s son, <PERSON>Bryan</PERSON>, says he saw
the animal <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The story of the <LOCATION>Wadsworth</LOCATION> 'gator sightings isn't being ignored
by the town, located about 10 miles east of the Reno-Sparks area.
   <PERSON>Tom Peterson</PERSON>, the local fire chief and owner of the <ORGANIZATION>Wadsworth
Inn</ORGANIZATION>, has made T-shirts boasting the town is the state's 'gator
capital. And this <DATE>weekend</DATE> the fire department volunteers are
hosting an Indian taco feed featuring ``super-hot 'gator sauce.''
   Meanwhile, the story continues to grow.
   ``Yeah, it's 3 to 4 long, but at 11 o'clock, after a few beers,
that 'gator gets to be a 16-footer,'' claims <PERSON>Peterson</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BURLINGTON, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It might be just another <PERSON>Loch Ness</PERSON>
``Nessie'' or Lake Tahoe ``Tessie'' _ water beasts that catch the
imagination but somehow are never trapped themselves.
   But at least a couple of people near <LOCATION>Wadsworth</LOCATION> have reported
seeing an alligator in the <LOCATION>Truckee River</LOCATION>, and state game wardens
are taking the claim seriously enough to set baited traps for the
reptile.
   So far, however, the 'gator, described as 3-4 feet long and 3 or
4 years old, has given authorities the slip.
   <PERSON>Jim Curran</PERSON>, the state's regional fisheries supervisor, said the
reported alligator is too small to pose a threat and might not
survive the near-freezing winter waters anyway. The reptiles
normally live in tropical rivers and marshes.
   ``We figure this one must have been someone's pet,'' <PERSON>Curran</PERSON>
said. ``When it got too big, they dumped it in the river.''
   The first reported sighting came <DATE>Oct. 14</DATE> when <PERSON>Jack Maughan</PERSON> said
he spotted the snub-nosed reptile in the river while taking his
daily walk along the bank. And <PERSON>Maughan</PERSON>'s son, <PERSON>Bryan</PERSON>, says he saw
the animal <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The story of the <LOCATION>Wadsworth</LOCATION> 'gator sightings isn't being ignored
by the town, located about 10 miles east of the Reno-Sparks area.
   <PERSON>Tom Peterson</PERSON>, the local fire chief and owner of the <ORGANIZATION>Wadsworth
Inn</ORGANIZATION>, has made T-shirts boasting the town is the state's 'gator
capital. And this <DATE>weekend</DATE> the fire department volunteers are
hosting an Indian taco feed featuring ``super-hot 'gator sauce.''
   Meanwhile, the story continues to grow.
   ``Yeah, it's 3 to 4 long, but at 11 o'clock, after a few beers,
that 'gator gets to be a 16-footer,'' claims <PERSON>Peterson</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890522-0278 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-22-89 1015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-Peru-DeepestCanyon Adv30-1stLd-Writethru b0149 05-22
0733</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Peru-Deepest Canyon, Adv 30 - 1st Ld-Writethru, b0149,0754</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tues PMs May 30 or Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>World's Deepest Canyon Still Lost in Time</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf to CORRECT to foreword sted forward</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT SEAVEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLCA CANYON, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From a condor's perch on this gorge in
southern <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> you could look down on 10 of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s World Trade
Center towers stacked end on end.
   The 60-mile-long <ORGANIZATION>Colca Canyon</ORGANIZATION> formed by the <LOCATION>Colca River</LOCATION> is the
deepest land gorge on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of
World Records</ORGANIZATION>.
   This mysterious land of desert-dry moonscapes, exotic
vegetation, active volcanoes and scattered pre-Columbian ruins is
just now emerging from obscurity.
   The canyon and surrounding <LOCATION>Colca Valley</LOCATION> are home to thousands of
Indians, descendants of pre-Inca tribesmen who settled here 3,000
years ago.
   ``The whole history of Peruvian man is summarized in this
startling landscape, which until only a few years ago was
incommunicado with the rest of <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>,'' wrote the Peruvian novelist
<PERSON>Mario Vargas Llosa</PERSON> in the foreword to the recently published
``Discovering The <LOCATION>Colca Valley</LOCATION>,'' one of the few books on the
region.
   Terraced fields painstakingly carved from the slopes still yield
corn and potatoes, the Indians' traditional staples. Ancient
irrigation canals keep the land productive.
   Some farms and hamlets rest precariously on canyon ledges,
giving the appearance of defying gravity or tempting fate.
   Most Indians still build their homes from adobe or rocks and
rely on the wool of their alpaca herds for clothing.
   They share these cloud-swept highlands with Andean condors and
scores of rare flora and fauna, such as giant cactuses and the
guanaco, an elusive cousin of the llama.
   From surrounding mountain ridges, the <LOCATION>Colca</LOCATION> plummets 14,339 feet
to the <LOCATION>Colca River</LOCATION>, according to <ORGANIZATION>Guinness</ORGANIZATION>. The World Trade Center
in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is 1,350 feet high.
   The opposing lower wall descends 10,607 feet, nearly double the
depth of <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Grand Canyon</ORGANIZATION>.
   Spanish conquistadors reached the <LOCATION>Colca</LOCATION> in the mid-1500s. They
built churches and towns atop Indian villages, and then left, said
<PERSON>Mauricio de Romana</PERSON>, one of the authors of ``Discovering The <LOCATION>Colca
Valley</LOCATION>.''
   Americans <PERSON>Robert Shippee</PERSON> and <PERSON>George Johnson</PERSON> led an expedition
into <LOCATION>Colca</LOCATION> and published an article in the <DATE>January, 1934</DATE>, issue of
<ORGANIZATION>National Geographic</ORGANIZATION>, calling it ``a lost valley of the Incas.''
   It was a brief interlude in the obscurity of the <LOCATION>Colca</LOCATION>, whose
wonders stayed forgotten until a gravel road was forged in the
mid-1970s, linking it with <LOCATION>Arequipa</LOCATION>, 115 miles south.
   <LOCATION>Arequipa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>'s second largest city, is 545 miles southeast of
<LOCATION>Lima</LOCATION>.
   ``To the surprise of Peruvians and foreigners alike, this
important setting, full of history and culture, appeared to the
world,'' <PERSON>Romana</PERSON> said in an interview.
   The road brought change to the Indians' traditional
self-sufficient lifestyle, tourists and spreading fame.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Guinness</ORGANIZATION> book recorded the <LOCATION>Colca</LOCATION>'s depth for the first time
in the mid-1980s, <PERSON>Romana</PERSON> said.
   The road now carries travelers on a rugged five-hour journey in
the shadow of the Andes' majestic spine, across the barren and cold
altiplano and skirting volcanic cones.
   The canyon rim offers a bird's eye view of walls plunging
thousands of feet to the rushing <LOCATION>Colca River</LOCATION> and of condors gliding
on thermal winds over farms and villages.
   The most dramatic places are several days farther by foot and
mule and are seen by just a hearty handful of the 10,000 to 15,000
tourists who reach the Colca yearly, according to <LOCATION>Romana</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Anthony Holley</PERSON>, an <LOCATION>Arequipa</LOCATION> guide, said some visitors are
discouraged because they cannot easily reach the deepest zone.
   The arduous journey by road, a shortage of lodgings and
generally unsafe conditions signal some of the major problems
facing Peruvian tourism.
   In the <DATE>last several years Peru</DATE> has been hit by spreading social
and economic chaos, fueled by its worst recession of the century.
   Tourism officials say the country does not have the money to
invest substantially in tourism infrastructure or even protect what
already exists.
   But officials say the <LOCATION>Colca</LOCATION> so far seems to have been spared
from a recent upsurge in highway banditry and the bloody guerrilla
insurgency plaguing many other areas of the country.
   Romana, a director of the <ORGANIZATION>Colca Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, which seeks to
preserve the zone, said the arrival of the modern world has not yet
had a serious impact on the <LOCATION>Colca</LOCATION> or its people.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Tues PMs May 30</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880427-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-27-88 0204EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     04-27 0592</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0613</SECOND>
<HEAD>On The Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW LONDON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two <ORGANIZATION>Connecticut College</ORGANIZATION> sophomores set
a world record for Frisbee-tossing but finally succumbed to the
need for sleep and ended their marathon session after more than
four days.
   <PERSON>Jeremy Tubb</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Fischer</PERSON> beat the previous record of 110
hours, 40 minutes at <TIME>7:40 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, and ended their streak at
<TIME>3:36 p.m. after 118 hours</TIME> and 36 minutes, said <PERSON>Daniel MacAlpine</PERSON>, a
college spokesman.
   The two had planned to toss the disk until <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, but
were beginning to hallucinate because of lack of sleep, <PERSON>MacAlpine</PERSON>
said.
   Tubb of <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Fischer</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Maplewood</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, played
catch on a green between two dormitory buildings during daytime
hours and moved inside a student center building between <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> and
<TIME>6 a.m.</TIME>
   They were entitled to a five-minute break every hour, but
accumulated their time to take a nap at <TIME>6 a.m. each morning</TIME>.
   The old record was set by <PERSON>Jamie Knerr</PERSON> and <PERSON>Keith Ziery</PERSON> between
of World Records</ORGANIZATION>.
   To beat the record they had to make a 45-foot toss at least
13,282 times within the time period. The rules permitted record
challengers to drop the flying disk, but no one could help them
retrieve it.
   <ORGANIZATION>Cyd Smith</ORGANIZATION>, assistant editor of the Guinness Book in <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION>, said new records must be logged by witnesses and exceed
previous marks by a half-hour or an hour.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two <ORGANIZATION>Connecticut College</ORGANIZATION> sophomores set
a world record for Frisbee-tossing but finally succumbed to the
need for sleep and ended their marathon session after more than
four days.
   <PERSON>Jeremy Tubb</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Fischer</PERSON> beat the previous record of 110
hours, 40 minutes at <TIME>7:40 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, and ended their streak at
<TIME>3:36 p.m. after 118 hours</TIME> and 36 minutes, said <PERSON>Daniel MacAlpine</PERSON>, a
college spokesman.
   The two had planned to toss the disk until <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, but
were beginning to hallucinate because of lack of sleep, <PERSON>MacAlpine</PERSON>
said.
   Tubb of <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Fischer</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Maplewood</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, played
catch on a green between two dormitory buildings during daytime
hours and moved inside a student center building between <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> and
<TIME>6 a.m.</TIME>
   They were entitled to a five-minute break every hour, but
accumulated their time to take a nap at <TIME>6 a.m. each morning</TIME>.
   The old record was set by <PERSON>Jamie Knerr</PERSON> and <PERSON>Keith Ziery</PERSON> between
of World Records</ORGANIZATION>.
   To beat the record they had to make a 45-foot toss at least
13,282 times within the time period. The rules permitted record
challengers to drop the flying disk, but no one could help them
retrieve it.
   <ORGANIZATION>Cyd Smith</ORGANIZATION>, assistant editor of the Guinness Book in <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION>, said new records must be logged by witnesses and exceed
previous marks by a half-hour or an hour.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880802-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-02-88 0531EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BridgeDangle     08-02 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bridge Dangle,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Paraplegic Dangles in Wheelchair from Brooklyn Bridge</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIRGINIA BYRNE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100 years after <PERSON>Stephen Brodie</PERSON>
supposedly took his famous dive off the <LOCATION>Brooklyn Bridge</LOCATION> and lived
to brag about it, a paraplegic dangled off the span in a wheelchair
for a shot at the record books.
   <ORGANIZATION>Ramond Masa</ORGANIZATION>, 40, carrying fireworks and samurai swords, lowered
himself on a rope <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> from the middle of the bridge and
dangled 75 feet above the <LOCATION>East River</LOCATION> for more than an hour.
   Police finally persuaded him to lower himself further so he
could be guided on to a police launch.
   The Cuban refugee, who came to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in <DATE>1969</DATE>, called
himself ``<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s No. 1 Stuntman,'' although it was his first
stunt. Masa claimed he had dangled from the 105-year-old landmark
for seven hours.
   ``I planned for three months to do something real crazy to get
into the Guinness record book,'' he said. Originally, he had
planned to don a Ninja costume, light six M-80 firecrackers and
hold two, 3-foot-long samurai swords and plunge off the bridge.
   But he changed his plans after the two nylon bags of equipment
made the 75-foot leap without him.
   Masa, who lost use of both legs after a shooting in <DATE>1977</DATE>, said
his making the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION> would inspire other
paraplegics. ``They think that because they're in wheelchairs their
life is ended,'' he said.
   Masa was booked on charges of disorderly conduct, illegal
possession of a knife and dealing with fireworks, said police
spokesman Sgt. <PERSON>John Clifford</PERSON>.
   Masa, who also uses the name El-Shah Muhammed El-Ratuli and has
a minor criminal record dating to <DATE>1977</DATE>, was given a summons to
appear in court <DATE>Sept. 19</DATE>.
   He initially told reporters his name was ``Megaman.'' He handed
out red, white and blue business cards that proclaimed, ``Living on
the edge is my business _ American No. 1 Stuntmen.''
   He said he was dropped off in the center of the span about
midnight by his brother, whom he refused to identify by name.
   Dragging his wheelchair and bags containing the swords and
firecrackers behind him, Masa crawled to the edge of the span,
where he tied a nylon cord used by mountain climbers around his
waist, through the wheelchair and secured it to a 5-inch thick
piece of bridgework. He then pushed the wheelchair off the bridge
and shimmied down the rope after it.
   Masa said he was not afraid while dangling. He was noticed after
dawn by a tugboat.
   According to the legend, in <DATE>July 1886</DATE>, <PERSON>Brodie</PERSON>, a 23-year-old
shoeshine man, took the leap from the bridge.
   Reporters were on hand to see what appeared to be a man dive 135
feet and emerge unscathed from the river. However, skeptics believe
that <PERSON>Brodie</PERSON>, with the help of cohorts, threw a weighted dummy into
the river.
   Masa expressed no remorse over the rush-hour traffic jam his
stunt caused. ``This is <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. They (the commuters) like the
excitement on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-67562 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpten014___94029" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEN-94-014 </AU>
JPRS 
Environmental Issues 

<DATE1>  16 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NEAR EAST/SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> BANGLADESH </F>
<H3> <TI>   Commentary Urges Timely Solution to Water Sharing Issue </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Commentary Urges Timely Solution to Water Sharing Issue </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK1705132294 Dhaka Radio Bangladesh Network in Bengali 1430 
GMT 16 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1705132294 </F>
<F P=104>  Dhaka Radio Bangladesh Network </F>
<F P=105>  Bengali </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Station commentary] </F>
  [Text] The historic Farakka Day is being observed today. 
Eighteen years ago on <DATE>May 16, 1976</DATE> the late leader of the 
suffering people, <PERSON>Maulana Abdul Hamid Khan Bhasani</PERSON>, brought out 
a huge procession comprising several hundred thousand people to 
demand an equitable share of the <LOCATION>Ganges River</LOCATION> water. People 
from all walks of life in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Teknaf</LOCATION> [southernmost 
tip of the country] to Tetulia [northernmost tip of the country] 
joined this long march, which was led by <PERSON>Maulana Bhasani</PERSON>. This 
long march started at 1000 from <LOCATION>Dhaka</LOCATION> on <DATE>May 16</DATE>. The 
processionists travelled (?456) miles and made an overnight halt 
at <LOCATION>Chapainawabganj</LOCATION> [District]. On the <TIME>morning</TIME> of <DATE>May 17</DATE> when 
this procession marched toward the border at that time the whole 
path was converted into a huge sea of agitated people. The 
procession stopped at a spot [name indistinct] about three miles 
inside the border at <DATE>1600</DATE>. On that day, the people of <LOCATION>South Asia</LOCATION> 
and the whole world witnessed through this massive procession 
the demand raised by the people of <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> for a fair share 
of the waters of the <LOCATION>Ganges River</LOCATION>. The world was amazed to see 
this huge procession by the people of this country to realize 
their legitimate share of the water of an international river. 
The world had extended its support to this cause of the people 
of <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> long before this procession took place. 
  The adverse effect created in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> due to the 
construction of the Farakka Barrage on the <LOCATION>Ganges River</LOCATION> is now 
discernible. The situation has further deteriorated. Vast 
tracts of land in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> are becoming deserts due to this 
withdrawal of the Ganges water at <LOCATION>Farakka</LOCATION>. The part of the 
<LOCATION>Ganges River</LOCATION> that flows into <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> is known as the <LOCATION>Padma</LOCATION>. 
This <PERSON>Padma</PERSON> was once a mighty river, and the people living along 
its banks led a very affluent and prosperous life. The part of 
<LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> through which this river flows was once lush, green, 
and full of crops. At present, these coastal areas have been 
turned into deserts. The vast bed of the <LOCATION>Padma River</LOCATION> has now 
turned into a desert and has become sandy. Many parts of the 
<LOCATION>Padma River</LOCATION> have also become grazing ground for cattle. The 
river has become totally unnavigable in several areas. The level 
of underground water in the areas adjoining the <LOCATION>Padma River</LOCATION> has 
fallen tremendously due to the shortage of water in the river. 
This has led to the destruction of agricultural lands and 
trees. Scarcity of water in the river has also severely 
affected navigation and shipping transport. This has directly 
affected the life of about 30 million people living on the banks 
of the <LOCATION>Padma River</LOCATION> and has posed a threat to their livelihood. 
  This situation has created a negative impact on the economy 
of a least developed country like <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> wants 
to be relieved from this unbearable situation and demands its 
legitimate share of the water of the <LOCATION>Ganges</LOCATION>, which is an 
international river. <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> is making efforts at the 
bilateral level for a peaceful settlement of the water sharing 
issue. In this regard, several meetings were held in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> at different levels. It is unfortunate that no remedy 
has been found yet for this problem. [Words indistinct] This 
<LOCATION>Ganges River</LOCATION> problem is a life and death problem for about 30 
million people in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>. 
  Since the present democratic government came to power, it 
has 
been holding direct talks with the <ORGANIZATION>Indian Government</ORGANIZATION> at 
different levels with a view to resolving this Ganges water 
sharing problem. So far the talks have not yielded any positive 
results. On the other hand, the talks have become long and 
drawn out. During her visit to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Khaleda 
Zia</PERSON> held talks with the Indian prime minister, <PERSON>Narasimha Rao</PERSON>, on 
the issue of resolving this Ganges water problem. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> gave 
its assurance that it would take active measures to resolve this 
problem. After this, several rounds of talks were held between 
the officials of the two countries for working out a solution to 
the problem, but no progress has been made. <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> has 
raised this issue regarding the sharing of the <LOCATION>Ganges River</LOCATION> 
water at the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION> summit, the <ORGANIZATION>Nonaligned Movement</ORGANIZATION>, and 
in various international forums. It has also held talks with 
different countries of the world seeking their active 
cooperation in securing an equitable share of the <LOCATION>Ganges River</LOCATION> 
water. The world has extended its support to the demand raised 
by <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> for an equitable share of the <LOCATION>Ganges River</LOCATION> water. 
Diplomatic efforts have also been made for a peaceful solution 
of the <LOCATION>Ganges River</LOCATION> water problem but no progress has been made 
in this regard. 
  Today is 16 <DATE>May</DATE>. It commemorates the historic <ORGANIZATION>Farakka Day</ORGANIZATION>. 
On this day, the people of <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> demand an early solution 
to the water sharing problem -- which is their life and death 
question. This demand was also raised at the discussion 
meetings, seminars, symposia, and rallies held <DATE>today</DATE> in 
observance of the day. The Ganges water sharing issue is solely 
a humanitarian problem. It is not a political problem. It 
would be inhuman to consider this problem as a political issue. 
We hope that in the interest of good neighborly relations, 
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> will take effective measures for an early solution to this 
problem. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880414-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-14-88 0049EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     04-14 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>On The Lite Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT MADISON, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's not much you can buy for a
penny these days. But with 1,000,131 of them, you can make your way
   This <DATE>weekend</DATE>, a local group trying to raise money for a <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY>
playground will try to lay down at least that many coins in a high
school gymnasium to set a world record in length for a line of
pennies.
   Volunteers plan to begin creating 58 lanes 3 feet wide and 44
feet long on the gym floor <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. When they are finished
sometime <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, they hope to have 1,540,500 pennies set down in
rows an inch apart, creating a line 13.66 miles long.
   The Guinness-recognized record is 1,000,130 one-cent coins put
down in a 12.29-mile line <DATE>Nov. 15, 1985</DATE>, by students at <ORGANIZATION>Blacktown
Girls</ORGANIZATION>' High School in <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   ``We figured out that, in order to accomplish the whole thing in
a 12-hour period, we would have to lay down something like 30
pennies a second,'' volunteer coordinator <PERSON>Carolyn Smith</PERSON> said.
   Coordinators have lined up 30 people for each two-hour shift of
penny-laying. The group also has planned ahead how to get the
pennies picked up after the record attempt.
   ``We'll start vacuuming them up on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>,'' said
volunteer <PERSON>Martha Wolf</PERSON>.
   The group received donations for the effort from children,
businesses and service groups. One problem, however, was that the
three banks in <LOCATION>Fort Madison</LOCATION> only keep about <MONEY>$300</MONEY> each in pennies at
one time.
   The banks arranged for 800,000 pennies to be shipped in by
armored car from <LOCATION>Davenport</LOCATION>, and paid <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> to have the pennies
wrapped and shipped, which took about three weeks.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's not much you can buy for a
penny these days. But with 1,000,131 of them, you can make your way
   This <DATE>weekend</DATE>, a local group trying to raise money for a <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY>
playground will try to lay down at least that many coins in a high
school gymnasium to set a world record in length for a line of
pennies.
   Volunteers plan to begin creating 58 lanes 3 feet wide and 44
feet long on the gym floor <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. When they are finished
sometime <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, they hope to have 1,540,500 pennies set down in
rows an inch apart, creating a line 13.66 miles long.
   The Guinness-recognized record is 1,000,130 one-cent coins put
down in a 12.29-mile line <DATE>Nov. 15, 1985</DATE>, by students at <ORGANIZATION>Blacktown
Girls</ORGANIZATION>' High School in <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   ``We figured out that, in order to accomplish the whole thing in
a 12-hour period, we would have to lay down something like 30
pennies a second,'' volunteer coordinator <PERSON>Carolyn Smith</PERSON> said.
   Coordinators have lined up 30 people for each two-hour shift of
penny-laying. The group also has planned ahead how to get the
pennies picked up after the record attempt.
   ``We'll start vacuuming them up on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>,'' said
volunteer <PERSON>Martha Wolf</PERSON>.
   The group received donations for the effort from children,
businesses and service groups. One problem, however, was that the
three banks in <LOCATION>Fort Madison</LOCATION> only keep about <MONEY>$300</MONEY> each in pennies at
one time.
   The banks arranged for 800,000 pennies to be shipped in by
armored car from <LOCATION>Davenport</LOCATION>, and paid <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> to have the pennies
wrapped and shipped, which took about three weeks.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-15041</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CAMBUABVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920113
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 JAN 92 / Construction Contracts: River crossing in Bangladesh
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
The USDollars 500m (Pounds 267m) <LOCATION>Jamuna Bridge</LOCATION> project in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> has
been given the go-ahead by the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> after a further internal review of
the economic return of the project.
Tender documents are expected to relate to a bridge designed for road, but
with the potential to be adapted to road plus rail at a future date and at
minimum extra cost.
This evaluation was in broad agreement with the conclusion reached earlier
by the bank's consulting engineers, RENDEL <ORGANIZATION>PALMER &amp; TRITTON</ORGANIZATION> together with
Dutch consultants NEDECO and <LOCATION>BANGLADESH</LOCATION> CONSULTANTS.
The bridge will be the first fixed transport link across the <LOCATION>Jamuna</LOCATION> river in
<LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>. The river forms a 15km barrier, separating the western side,
with its fertile north-west zone, from the eastern side containing the
commercial centre, <LOCATION>Dhaka</LOCATION> and the country's primary port, <LOCATION>Chittagong</LOCATION>.
The only fixed crossing of the river to date in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> is the power line
interconnector supported on caissons 110 metres deep, believed to be the
deepest in existence and for which RPT were the engineers. The crossing will
comprise a bridge structure about 5km long, major river training works and
road embankments on the flood plain between the river training works and the
high banks.
Mobility of the river banks is such that the final location of the 2,700
metre long guide bunds, and hence the length of the bridge can only be
determined at the time of construction. Cost estimates, design and the
proposed contract documents have been set down to accommodate this somewhat
unusual situation.
The bridge is 4,800 metres long, bounded by the guide bunds of the river
training works. The substructure will be 80 metres long, 2.5 metres in
diameter raking steel piles in bents of two or four. These will support a
composite steel box girder and concrete slab superstructure in spans of 100
metres.
An alternative design including a segmental pre-stressed concrete box girder
of similar span will be included in the tender documents.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 9 Map (Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890603-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-03-89 1527EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     06-03 0752</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0778</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XKNE1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They met on the bus and became friends on
the bus. So when it came to getting married <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, it seemed
only natural that <PERSON>Claude Methot</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jan Cole</PERSON> should board the Metro
to take their vows.
   The couple left a wake of smiles and horn-honking motorists as
their wedding bus cruised to a luncheon after the onboard ceremony.
The bus was decked out with crepe paper, paper bells and strings of
tin cans tied to the bumper. And, of course, a ``Just Married''
sign.
   ``Both of us are bus people,'' said <PERSON>Methot</PERSON>, 40, a paper company
employee who lives in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Methot</PERSON> said he and his bride became
close friends a few months after they met while riding the bus to
work together.
   ``There are some very nice people on the bus, but I never
thought I'd meet anyone, and never thought I'd get married, on a
bus,'' said the 41-year-old bride, who works as a salesperson.
``It's one of the craziest things I've done in my life.''
   Metro General Manager <PERSON>Sarah deDoes</PERSON> said she was for the ceremony
from the start. ``Being a romantic myself, when they asked me, I
thought it was just great,'' she said.
   Asked about the couple's honeymoon plans, <PERSON>Methot</PERSON> said, ``It
won't be Greyhound, that's for sure. We're going to <LOCATION>Bermuda</LOCATION> in the
fall _ they have a good bus system there.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MYRTLE BEACH, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They met on the bus and became friends on
the bus. So when it came to getting married <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, it seemed
only natural that <PERSON>Claude Methot</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jan Cole</PERSON> should board the Metro
to take their vows.
   The couple left a wake of smiles and horn-honking motorists as
their wedding bus cruised to a luncheon after the onboard ceremony.
The bus was decked out with crepe paper, paper bells and strings of
tin cans tied to the bumper. And, of course, a ``Just Married''
sign.
   ``Both of us are bus people,'' said <PERSON>Methot</PERSON>, 40, a paper company
employee who lives in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Methot</PERSON> said he and his bride became
close friends a few months after they met while riding the bus to
work together.
   ``There are some very nice people on the bus, but I never
thought I'd meet anyone, and never thought I'd get married, on a
bus,'' said the 41-year-old bride, who works as a salesperson.
``It's one of the craziest things I've done in my life.''
   Metro General Manager <PERSON>Sarah deDoes</PERSON> said she was for the ceremony
from the start. ``Being a romantic myself, when they asked me, I
thought it was just great,'' she said.
   Asked about the couple's honeymoon plans, <PERSON>Methot</PERSON> said, ``It
won't be Greyhound, that's for sure. We're going to <LOCATION>Bermuda</LOCATION> in the
fall _ they have a good bus system there.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AVALON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They met on the bus and became friends on
the bus. So when it came to getting married <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, it seemed
only natural that <PERSON>Claude Methot</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jan Cole</PERSON> should board the Metro
to take their vows.
   The couple left a wake of smiles and horn-honking motorists as
their wedding bus cruised to a luncheon after the onboard ceremony.
The bus was decked out with crepe paper, paper bells and strings of
tin cans tied to the bumper. And, of course, a ``Just Married''
sign.
   ``Both of us are bus people,'' said <PERSON>Methot</PERSON>, 40, a paper company
employee who lives in <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Methot</PERSON> said he and his bride became
close friends a few months after they met while riding the bus to
work together.
   ``There are some very nice people on the bus, but I never
thought I'd meet anyone, and never thought I'd get married, on a
bus,'' said the 41-year-old bride, who works as a salesperson.
``It's one of the craziest things I've done in my life.''
   Metro General Manager <PERSON>Sarah deDoes</PERSON> said she was for the ceremony
from the start. ``Being a romantic myself, when they asked me, I
thought it was just great,'' she said.
   Asked about the couple's honeymoon plans, <PERSON>Methot</PERSON> said, ``It
won't be Greyhound, that's for sure. We're going to <LOCATION>Bermuda</LOCATION> in the
fall _ they have a good bus system there.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890206-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-06-89 0555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-HolyFair     02-06 0758</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Holy Fair,0781</SECOND>
<HEAD>15 Million Hindus Wash Away Sins At Giant Festival</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALLAHABAD, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An estimated 15 million Hindus _ holy men
from their Himalayan cave homes, naked recluses from forest dens and
ordinary pilgrims from across <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> _ began immersing themselves at
the confluence of two sacred rivers today.
   Today's bathing is the high point of the seven-week <PERSON>Kumbh Mela</PERSON>
the largest religious gathering on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The ceremonial bathing began at <TIME>4 a.m.</TIME> with the blowing of conch
shells and the chanting of hymns by the faithful, who believe a dip
in the rivers on this astrologically auspicious day will free them
from the cycle of reincarnation and allow them to achieve salavation.
   Hindus believe that <PERSON>Lord Brahma</PERSON>, creator of the world in the
Hindu religion and a member of the supreme trinity in the pantheon
of Hindu gods, awakens at <TIME>4 a.m.</TIME> and therefore the day should start
at that hour.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Kumbh Mela</ORGANIZATION> is celebrated every 12 years, according to the
lunar calendar, at the time of a rare planetary convergence: <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>
in Taurus, the sun and moon in <LOCATION>Capricorn</LOCATION>, and a series of
complicated calculations of Hindu astrology.
   But today takes on added significance, for it is also the day of
the new moon, another good omen.
   Two people died in the early hours of the mass bathing. A
50-year-old man collapsed on the river bank after his bath and soon
died, and a woman drowned when her boat capsized, according to a
police officer who spoke on condition of anonymity. In <DATE>1954</DATE>, about
800 pilgrims died in a stampede at the holy festival.
   ``Either these people are crazy or there must be something we
can't see or understand,'' said <PERSON>Nina Marshall</PERSON>, a 23-year-old student
from <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> who was among dozens of Americans that came to
see the religious spectacle.
   ``It is vibrating,'' she said, pointing to the barefoot pilgrims
trekking to the junction of the Ganges and <LOCATION>Jamuna</LOCATION> rivers.
   For the faithful, the bathing is often a once-in-a-lifetime
opportunity.
   ``I planned this trip five years back when we had a good crop,''
said <PERSON>Sarju Mahato</PERSON>, a farmer from <LOCATION>Bihar</LOCATION> state, as he tended the
blisters on his two sons' feet. ``We saved money and came here.''
   The festival takes the name <ORGANIZATION>Kumbh Mela</ORGANIZATION> from a story in Hindu
mythology in which a god seized a pot of nectar that made gods
invincible in their war against the demons. ``Kumbh'' means pot, and
``mela'' means fair.
   A drop of nectar from the pot is thought to have fallen at
<LOCATION>Allahabad</LOCATION> where the Ganges and Jamuna rivers come together. A bath
at the exact spot where the nectar fell is supposed to bring
salvation from the cycle of birth and rebirth.
   The bathing at the <ORGANIZATION>Kumbh Mela</ORGANIZATION> began with processions of holy men,
their order determined from days of yore according to the importance
of their sects, dipping at the confluence of the <LOCATION>Ganges</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Yamuna</LOCATION>
and the mythical Swaraswati.
   The Swaraswati cannot be seen, but Hindus believe it flows
beneath the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s surface where the two other rivers meet.
   There was color everywhere _ a profusion of saffron, scarlet,
white and gold robes.
   Some holy men wore only loincloths. Some had their foreheads
smeared with vermilion and sandalwood paste, and some wore garlands
of basil wreaths around their necks, wrists and arms.
   Some had shaven heads, others matted hair tied in knots atop
their heads.
   The ``nagas,'' or naked recluses, smeared their bodies with
ashes. They wore garlands of marigolds around their necks and blew
conch shells to drive away evil spirits.
   They danced holding spears, lances, staffs and small rocks
representing some of the Hindu faith's 32 million gods and goddesses.
   There were camels draped in brightly embroidered cloths, adorned
with feathers, beads and mirrors, with bells on their feet that
tinkled when they walked.
   Some pilgrims pulled chariots holding the holiest of the holy
men, who offered blessings to the others.
   The bathing followed the initiation of new nagas. Young men are
inducted into the naked order only once every 12 years during the
Kumbh Mela.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, 1,500 nagas-to-be shaved their heads, burned their
clothing and performed their last rites.
   ``From this moment they have renounced the material world and
since they will not depend on anyone anymore, they themselves
perform their last rites as if they are already dead from this
world,'' explained <PERSON>M.P. Ashnata</PERSON>, the fair's chief spokesman.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890606-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-06-89 1944EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Merrimac     06-06 0495</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Merrimac,0509</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hydroelectic Plant Afloat, Headed Upriver</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NU2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA ASHTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world's largest prefabricated power plant
began a slow journey <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> under tow up the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION>, the
same body of water that it eventually will use to generate
electricity.
   Cables groaned when two tugboats in front pulled and two tugs in
back pushed the massive power plant, the Merrimac, off a dry dock at
a suburban <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> shipyard to begin its 208-mile journey
upriver.
   ``I feel real good. I've been working on this thing for 13 years.
We started literally from scratch,'' said <PERSON>Sidney Murray</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Catalyst-Old River Hydroelectric Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, one of the investors. ``It's
been exciting for everybody.''
   Murray videotaped the 12-story beige structure as it edged away
from its dock. About 75 spectators cheered from the dock.
   The power plant is 12 stories high, 456 feet long and weighs
about 25,000 tons. Company officials said that although the Merrimac
is smaller than some of the world's largest ships, it is believed to
be the largest structure to ever travel up the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION>.
   The Merrimac is headed for a point 40 miles south of <LOCATION>Vidalia</LOCATION>,
where it will be fitted for operation in a channel where water will
run from the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION> through the power plant turbines and
into the <LOCATION>Atchafalaya River</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s first hydroelectric plant should be fully operational
by <DATE>July 1, 1990</DATE>, said <PERSON>Bill Fox</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Ebasco</ORGANIZATION>, an engineering firm that
worked on the <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> project.
   The Merrimac will creep upriver at 2 to 4 mph and should arrive
in <LOCATION>northeast Louisiana</LOCATION> over the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, he said.
   ``This is a major milestone,'' <ORGANIZATION>Fox</ORGANIZATION> said. ``It's been thought out
extremely well. Saving anything less than a hurricane, we ought to
be able to bring it in without any trouble.''
   The major obstacle is already anticipated _ the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Highway 190
bridge at <LOCATION>Baton Rouge</LOCATION>. The bridge is too low for the tall structure,
so the plant must be partially submerged while it passes underneath.
   The Merrimac will probably be sunk 40 to 50 feet to leave a
clearance of at least five feet between the top of the plant and the
bottom of the bridge.
   The 10- to 20-hour process will be done by pumping water into
large hollow compartments that enable the structure to float. After
the plant clears the bridge, the water will be pumped out and the
<ORGANIZATION>Merrimac</ORGANIZATION> will resume its journey.
   Once in place near the Old River Control Structure, the Merrimac
will divert water from the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION> through eight giant
turbines. The water will then flow through a two-mile-long channel
into the <LOCATION>Atchafalaya River</LOCATION>, a 17-foot drop.
   The plant is designed to generate 192 megawatts of electricity,
enough to light a city of 200,000 people.
   Owners of the power plant are the <ORGANIZATION>Merrimac Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Dominion Capital Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>. The town of Vidalia shared
licensing for the project.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890815-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-15-89 0115EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-OkeechobeeMonster 1stLd-Writethru a0413 08-15 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Okeechobee Monster, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0413,0406</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report of 18-Foot Gator Fuels Start of Hunting Season</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 13th graf to CORRECT length of gator to feet sted inches;
picks up 14th graf, ``That was ...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEWISTON, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A giant, 18-foot-long alligator is living
in <LOCATION>Lake Okeechobee</LOCATION>, boaters and fishermen claim, but a state
wildlife expert says he doubts it.
   ``It looks monstrous, bigger than our boat, and we have a
<DATE>19-footer</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Rebecca Dunn</PERSON>, who has been fishing on the lake with her
fishing-guide husband since <DATE>1966</DATE>, said recently.
   ``We see it all the time,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Dunn</PERSON>, who said she believes
the alligator is a female. ``She throws her food up in the air, way
up, then catches and eats it, mostly fish and birds.''
   <PERSON>Mrs. Dunn</PERSON> has named the alligator Hendrietta, for <LOCATION>Hendry County</LOCATION>,
one of five counties surrounding <LOCATION>Lake Okeechobee</LOCATION>, which is about 100
miles northwest of <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> and at 700 square miles is <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s
largest lake.
   Bass fisherman <PERSON>Sonny Pease</PERSON> said he saw the creature sunning
itself on shore with its tail curled around itself like Lady
<ORGANIZATION>Godiva</ORGANIZATION>'s hair.
   <PERSON>Pease</PERSON> said that when he took his boat closer to the gator, he
kept repeating, ``Oh, my God, that alligator is long. Nobody's going
to believe this.''
   When he got within about 200 yards of the big reptile, it started
swimming toward his 18-foot boat.
   It ``was all of my boat's size,'' <PERSON>Pease</PERSON> recalled.
   An 18-foot alligator would break <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s longest alligator
record by nearly 4 feet.
   However, wildlife biologist <PERSON>Mike Jennings</PERSON> of the state Game and
<ORGANIZATION>Fresh Water Fish Commission</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Gainesville</LOCATION> said an 18-foot-long
alligator would be highly improbable.
   The longest gator caught since records were first kept in <DATE>1977</DATE>
measured just over 14 feet and weighed 714 pounds, and was trapped
last month in the <LOCATION>Apalachicola River</LOCATION> southwest of <LOCATION>Tallahassee</LOCATION>.
Trappers estimated it was 100 years old.
   The heaviest gator, caught in <DATE>April</DATE> near <LOCATION>Gainesville</LOCATION>, weighed
1,043 pounds and was 13 feet long. It took a tow truck to lift it
and three scales to weigh it.
   ``That was a very healthy gator,'' <PERSON>Jennings</PERSON> said. ``I would've
questioned it, if I hadn't seen it myself.''
   The giant gator's real length may be determined after <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>,
when <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s monthlong alligator season starts.
   ``Every hunter who has a permit will be going for him,'' said
<PERSON>Pease</PERSON>'s 22-year-old son, <PERSON>Keith</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880625-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-25-88 1722EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     06-25 0598</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONTPELIER, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The strawberry shortcake was anything but
short <DATE>Saturday</DATE> as cooking school students put together a 216-foot
version of the summertime goodie.
   ``Rush! Speed! Speed!'' shouted <PERSON>Tammy Wood</PERSON>, a second-year
student at the <ORGANIZATION>New England Culinary Institute</ORGANIZATION>, as teams began
building what they hope will be officially recognized as the
world's largest strawberry shortcake.
   First down on the tables were the 31 sheet pans of shortcake cut
into 4-inch-wide strips. Next went about 7,200 strawberries, and
finally, 18 gallons of whipped cream.
   ``Step back, I need a picture of this,'' roared <PERSON>Richard Wobby</PERSON>,
the event's organizer, before the whipped cream went on. He also
brought the world its longest dish of maple sugar on snow in <LOCATION>Barre</LOCATION>
<DATE>two years ago</DATE>, a quarter-mile-long affair.
   As the students put the finishing touches on their cake, the
rain picked up, and the crowd lining the sidewalks rushed to the
center of State Street for one, or maybe more, of the 2,400 pieces.
   The largest strawberry shortcake, according to <ORGANIZATION>Wobby</ORGANIZATION>'s research,
was 6 feet in diameter. By square footage, <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s
long-and-narrow version was considerably larger, <PERSON>Wobby</PERSON> said.
   There is currently no separate entry in the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of
World Records</ORGANIZATION> for largest strawberry shortcake, but the students
are hoping to get recognition.
   ``It's a good gag,'' <PERSON>Wobby</PERSON> said. ``It's something we'll think
start thinking about and say, `That's impossible.' Then, all of a
sudden, the blood just turns on, and we find we have the motivation
to do it, and we do it.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SHIRLEY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The strawberry shortcake was anything but
short <DATE>Saturday</DATE> as cooking school students put together a 216-foot
version of the summertime goodie.
   ``Rush! Speed! Speed!'' shouted <PERSON>Tammy Wood</PERSON>, a second-year
student at the <ORGANIZATION>New England Culinary Institute</ORGANIZATION>, as teams began
building what they hope will be officially recognized as the
world's largest strawberry shortcake.
   First down on the tables were the 31 sheet pans of shortcake cut
into 4-inch-wide strips. Next went about 7,200 strawberries, and
finally, 18 gallons of whipped cream.
   ``Step back, I need a picture of this,'' roared <PERSON>Richard Wobby</PERSON>,
the event's organizer, before the whipped cream went on. He also
brought the world its longest dish of maple sugar on snow in <LOCATION>Barre</LOCATION>
<DATE>two years ago</DATE>, a quarter-mile-long affair.
   As the students put the finishing touches on their cake, the
rain picked up, and the crowd lining the sidewalks rushed to the
center of State Street for one, or maybe more, of the 2,400 pieces.
   The largest strawberry shortcake, according to <ORGANIZATION>Wobby</ORGANIZATION>'s research,
was 6 feet in diameter. By square footage, <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s
long-and-narrow version was considerably larger, <PERSON>Wobby</PERSON> said.
   There is currently no separate entry in the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of
World Records</ORGANIZATION> for largest strawberry shortcake, but the students
are hoping to get recognition.
   ``It's a good gag,'' <PERSON>Wobby</PERSON> said. ``It's something we'll think
start thinking about and say, `That's impossible.' Then, all of a
sudden, the blood just turns on, and we find we have the motivation
to do it, and we do it.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CANON CITY, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The strawberry shortcake was anything but
short <DATE>Saturday</DATE> as cooking school students put together a 216-foot
version of the summertime goodie.
   ``Rush! Speed! Speed!'' shouted <PERSON>Tammy Wood</PERSON>, a second-year
student at the <ORGANIZATION>New England Culinary Institute</ORGANIZATION>, as teams began
building what they hope will be officially recognized as the
world's largest strawberry shortcake.
   First down on the tables were the 31 sheet pans of shortcake cut
into 4-inch-wide strips. Next went about 7,200 strawberries, and
finally, 18 gallons of whipped cream.
   ``Step back, I need a picture of this,'' roared <PERSON>Richard Wobby</PERSON>,
the event's organizer, before the whipped cream went on. He also
brought the world its longest dish of maple sugar on snow in <LOCATION>Barre</LOCATION>
<DATE>two years ago</DATE>, a quarter-mile-long affair.
   As the students put the finishing touches on their cake, the
rain picked up, and the crowd lining the sidewalks rushed to the
center of State Street for one, or maybe more, of the 2,400 pieces.
   The largest strawberry shortcake, according to <ORGANIZATION>Wobby</ORGANIZATION>'s research,
was 6 feet in diameter. By square footage, <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s
long-and-narrow version was considerably larger, <PERSON>Wobby</PERSON> said.
   There is currently no separate entry in the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of
World Records</ORGANIZATION> for largest strawberry shortcake, but the students
are hoping to get recognition.
   ``It's a good gag,'' <PERSON>Wobby</PERSON> said. ``It's something we'll think
start thinking about and say, `That's impossible.' Then, all of a
sudden, the blood just turns on, and we find we have the motivation
to do it, and we do it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111190-0168 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 306524 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 11, 1990, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
935 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
REFLECTIONS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JEANETTE AVENT, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Tired of <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> winters, literature professor <PERSON>James Simmons</PERSON> chucked his 
job at <ORGANIZATION>Boston University</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1973</DATE> and started driving. About 13,000 miles and 
four months later, he turned off the freeway in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> and fell in love with 
the warm climate and postcard-perfect beaches. It took him another year to find 
out he could turn his passion for travel into a paying job. Now a free-lance 
writer specializing in adventure travel, he authors articles and books, 
including one on his favorite corners of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and another about Americans 
as others see us. <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Pacific Beach</LOCATION> resident, was interviewed by <ORGANIZATION>Times 
Staff</ORGANIZATION> writer <PERSON>G. Jeanette Avent</PERSON> and photographed by <PERSON>Vince Compagnone</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
 While I was teaching, I had been doing a lot of traveling on my own, but it 
was a real different kind of traveling from what I do now. I'd spend three 
months traveling through <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> by myself. It was pretty solitary, which was 
fine. But, once I started doing adventure travel with naturalists along, I was 
hooked. You get into a group of people with shared interests and it becomes a 
traveling seminar. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1974</DATE>, I did the best trip I've ever done, a 30-day cruise to <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> 
which was real frontier at that time. There were about 80 of us on board, 
including six naturalists and <PERSON>Roger Tory Peterson</PERSON>, the No. 1 name in 
ornithology. We spent five days doing the first tourist exploration of <LOCATION>South 
Georgia Island</LOCATION>, which had been the center of the Antarctic whaling industry. 
That was all closed down, but everything was intact. You'd walk up to the dock, 
and all the whaling vessels were there with their big harpoon guns. There was 
the chart room, the dining room china, the galley. Sitting out in a mud bank 
was a well preserved, Norwegian three-masted whaling vessel from <DATE>1885</DATE>. You'd go 
into the movie house, and the walls were all lined with posters advertising 
<PERSON>Randolph Scott Westerns</PERSON> from the <DATE>'30s</DATE> and a <PERSON>Gary Cooper</PERSON> film from <DATE>1943</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
We had some good weather, and we went south where the pack ice had split up. We 
went into areas where there were no docks and you had to go over the side of 
the ship in <LOCATION>Zodiacs</LOCATION>, which are small, 16-foot inflatable motorboats. Antarctica 
is so splendid. It has one of the great profusions of wildlife in the world. It 
has penguin rookeries where there are 2 million birds. There are no predators 
on land in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> so you can walk right up and practically touch a penguin. 
It boggles the mind. 
</P>
<P>
I suppose the most dangerous trip was the one down the <LOCATION>Omo River</LOCATION> in 
southwestern <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>. We had a hippo attack on the boat. The Omo was the last 
pocket of territory to be explored by Westerners. I went in <DATE>1975</DATE> on the first 
commercial expedition, and the first natives we saw had never seen Westerners. 
It was <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> the way it was 150 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
We were 25 days on the river and covered about 300 miles. For the <DATE>first half</DATE>, 
we were at the bottom of a canyon at 4,000 feet, which had some splendid 
scenery and excellent white water. The second half was savannah country, and 
that's where the people were. The trip was wonderful but what made it dangerous 
is the difference between African river running and American river running. If 
you flip over in a raft at the bottom of the Grand Canyon, you know exactly 
what to do. You have your life jacket on, and you go into the rapids feet first 
and you come out. In <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, when you come out in the calm water, you've got 
the crocodiles to contend with. 
</P>
<P>
We never had a boat flip, but you always knew if something happened, it'd be 
you and the crocodiles. They're big ones, 18 to 20 feet long, and we'd see six 
or eight of them at a time lying on the bank. We had these croc rocks so when 
the crocodiles came close to the boat we were supposed to shout obscenities and 
throw these croc rocks. That was a requirement. 
</P>
<P>
At the time of the hippo attack, we were going through a place on the river 
called hippo alley where as many as 500 to 600 hippos have been counted passing 
through during the day. What hippos do in the heat of the day is walk on the 
bottom of the river. They come up every five minutes for air and then go back 
down. You have to be careful to stay in shallow water so you don't have hippos 
coming up underneath you. One of our boatmen got careless and wasn't in shallow 
water, and a hippo surfaced right along side of the boat. The hippo panicked. 
These enormous jaws opened and he bit down on the boat. He just missed a 
passenger by a foot. It was over in two seconds, and then the hippo was gone. 
We had to go ashore and fix the pontoon. We just all thought it was a great 
adventure. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>March</DATE>, I spent my birthday on <LOCATION>Pitcairn Island</LOCATION> where the Bounty mutineers 
ended up in <DATE>1790</DATE>. Pitcairn celebrated its 200th anniversary this year. We were 
the first cruise boat to stay overnight. It was interesting seeing <ORGANIZATION>Pitcairn</ORGANIZATION> 
through <ORGANIZATION>Pitcairn</ORGANIZATION> eyes. At the top of a hill was a house, so we asked them about 
that. That's our vacation house, they said. That's where we come when we want 
to get away from the sound of the sea. It's fascinating because everywhere you 
turn there's the ghost of the Bounty. In the town square there's an anchor from 
the <LOCATION>Bounty</LOCATION>. In one of the houses, there's was a canon from the Bounty. The 
Bible from the <LOCATION>Bounty</LOCATION> is in the church. One of the very earliest homes is built 
from the planks of the Bounty. Nearly half of the population has the last name 
of Fletcher Christian. You can see the cave where he hid out. It's a 
ghost-ridden island. That's why they landed there; it was uninhabited. It is 
way off the shipping lanes. I love end-of-the-world places. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Sixteen years ago, literature professor James Simmons traded the world 
of the Victorian novel for a career photographing and writing about 
end-of-the-world places. VINCE COMPAGNONE 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Interview 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881102-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-02-88 1507EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     11-02 0718</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0749</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief^</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SHELBYVILLE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hickory, dickory, dock. The mice are
eating the pot.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Shelby County Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION> says a gang of rodents has
infiltrated the agency's storage room and pilfered bags of marijuana
kept as evidence for upcoming trials.
   Authorities believe the perpetrators are mice seeking refuge from
the cold. It's not the first time this has happened, said <PERSON>Sheriff
Rick D. Isgrigg</PERSON>. ``But this year is the worst,'' he said.
   The rodents have chewed through several 29-ounce and 1-pound bags
of marijuana.
   ``They're playing havoc with the stuff,'' <PERSON>Isgrigg</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
``From all indications, they must be rolling in it.''
   The mice have discriminating tastes, however. They've passed up a
bag of potato chips held as evidence in a grocery burglary, in this
area southeast of <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>.
   Because the pests refuse to rat on each other, <PERSON>Isgrigg</PERSON> has placed
mounds of rodent-killer in the 20-by-25-foot property room.
   ``We have to nip this in the bud _ or nip it in the bag,'' the
sheriff said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WADSWORTH, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hickory, dickory, dock. The mice are
eating the pot.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Shelby County Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION> says a gang of rodents has
infiltrated the agency's storage room and pilfered bags of marijuana
kept as evidence for upcoming trials.
   Authorities believe the perpetrators are mice seeking refuge from
the cold. It's not the first time this has happened, said <PERSON>Sheriff
Rick D. Isgrigg</PERSON>. ``But this year is the worst,'' he said.
   The rodents have chewed through several 29-ounce and 1-pound bags
of marijuana.
   ``They're playing havoc with the stuff,'' <PERSON>Isgrigg</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
``From all indications, they must be rolling in it.''
   The mice have discriminating tastes, however. They've passed up a
bag of potato chips held as evidence in a grocery burglary, in this
area southeast of <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>.
   Because the pests refuse to rat on each other, <PERSON>Isgrigg</PERSON> has placed
mounds of rodent-killer in the 20-by-25-foot property room.
   ``We have to nip this in the bud _ or nip it in the bag,'' the
sheriff said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALTON, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hickory, dickory, dock. The mice are
eating the pot.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Shelby County Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION> says a gang of rodents has
infiltrated the agency's storage room and pilfered bags of marijuana
kept as evidence for upcoming trials.
   Authorities believe the perpetrators are mice seeking refuge from
the cold. It's not the first time this has happened, said <PERSON>Sheriff
Rick D. Isgrigg</PERSON>. ``But this year is the worst,'' he said.
   The rodents have chewed through several 29-ounce and 1-pound bags
of marijuana.
   ``They're playing havoc with the stuff,'' <PERSON>Isgrigg</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
``From all indications, they must be rolling in it.''
   The mice have discriminating tastes, however. They've passed up a
bag of potato chips held as evidence in a grocery burglary, in this
area southeast of <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>.
   Because the pests refuse to rat on each other, <PERSON>Isgrigg</PERSON> has placed
mounds of rodent-killer in the 20-by-25-foot property room.
   ``We have to nip this in the bud _ or nip it in the bag,'' the
sheriff said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880516-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-88 0248EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BusCrash-List     05-16 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bus Crash-List,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>List Of Recent Domestic Bus Disasters</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Bus Crash, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The deadliest bus accident recorded in the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of
World Records</ORGANIZATION> occurred in <DATE>1973</DATE> in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, when a bus plunged into a
canal, killing 127 people.
   What is believed to be the worst bus accident in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history
occurred on <DATE>Sept. 17, 1963</DATE>, when a bus collided with a train near
<LOCATION>Salinas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, killing 32 farm workers.
   Here is a list of some other recent domestic bus accidents:
   _<DATE>May 21, 1976</DATE>, a school bus carrying 53 <LOCATION>Yuba City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, High
School students plunged off a freeway ramp near <PERSON>Martinez</PERSON>.
Twenty-eight students and a teacher were killed.
   _A school bus from <LOCATION>Prestonsburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>, plunged into the Levisa
Fork of the <LOCATION>Big Sandy River</LOCATION> on <DATE>Feb. 28, 1958</DATE>, killing 26 students
and the bus driver.
   _A speeding <ORGANIZATION>Starline Sightseeing Tours</ORGANIZATION> coach wrecked in a
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> canyon on <DATE>May 30, 1986</DATE>, killing 21 passengers. The
driver was sentenced to four years in prison.
   _A tour bus carrying mostly senior citizens from <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Branson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, plunged into a 40-foot ravine near <LOCATION>Jasper</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, on
<DATE>June 5, 1980</DATE>, killing 20 people and injuring 13.
   _A commuter bus crashed through a guardrail near <LOCATION>Quantico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>,
and down an 80-foot embankment into a creek on <DATE>Feb. 18, 1981</DATE>,
killing 11 people and injuring 13.
   _Raging floodwaters of the <LOCATION>Guadalupe River</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> carried away
a bus and a van carrying 43 people on <DATE>July 17, 1987</DATE>, killing 10
teen-agers from a church camp.
   _A high school wrestling team's bus collided with a tanker truck
near <LOCATION>West Glacier</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Jan. 21, 1984</DATE>, killing nine people
aboard the bus and injuring 19.
   _A bus carrying school children to a state convention left a
rural road near <LOCATION>Uno</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, and overturned on <DATE>March 25, 1983</DATE>,
killing four students and five teachers.
   _A bus carrying worshipers to a Christmas revival collided with
a truck near <PERSON>Devers</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Dec. 24, 1983</DATE>, killing nine people
and injuring 14.
   _A <ORGANIZATION>Continental Trailways</ORGANIZATION> bus rammed the rear of a truck near
<LOCATION>Livingston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and plunged 40 feet into a creek on <DATE>Nov. 30,
1983</DATE>, killing six passengers and injuring the driver and five
others.
   _A tractor-trailer and a bus carrying mentally retarded and
handicapped adults crashed near <LOCATION>New Berlin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>April 5, 1983</DATE>,
killing five passengers and injuring 16 others.
   _A truck crossed a center line and slammed into a school bus
near <LOCATION>Snow Hill</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>May 31, 1985</DATE>, killing five children and
injuring 20.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102190-0039 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 295563 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 21, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 5; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1500 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ADVENTURE TRAVEL: THE EYES WILL HAVE IT IN BRAZIL'S LUSH PANTANAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SCOTT DOGGETT, Doggett is an editor for the Los Angeles Times-Washington 
Post News Service and an adventure traveler. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
PORTO JOFRE, Brazil 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It was the blackness that made the brilliant eyes so captivating. At the end of 
my flashlight beam, like glowing embers on a sea of black velvet, the 
fire-orange eyes of a thousand caimans reflected back at me. 
</P>
<P>
Under a starry sky, the field stretching out before me seemed to practically 
grow caimans -- enormous toothy reptiles that are often mistaken for 
alligators. Every sweep of the flashlight lit up scores of eyes, some not 20 
yards from the raised dirt road where I stood. 
</P>
<P>
The eerie sight of the caimans was just one of many unforgettable sights that 
greeted me at seemingly every turn in the 150,000-square-mile wetlands at the 
center of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, an area called the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Although lacking the fame of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION> is home to at least 1,100 
species of butterflies, 400 species of fish, 650 species of birds and 80 
species of mammals. According to the World Wildlife Fund, only <LOCATION>East Africa</LOCATION>'s 
savannas offer more in natural richness, both of flora and fauna. 
</P>
<P>
Pantano means "swamp" in Portuguese, but in fact the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION> is not a swamp at 
all. Rather, it is the world's largest wetland -- a single, low-lying ecosystem 
formed by the dozens of rivers that flow into the mighty <LOCATION>Paraguay River</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Depending on the season, the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION> is either flooded or drying out. During 
the dry season, from <DATE>May to November</DATE>, vast expanses of savannas are exposed. 
During the rainy season, from <DATE>December</DATE> to <DATE>April</DATE>, the rivers swell and deep mud 
and washed-out bridges often halt traffic on the Transpantaneira. 
</P>
<P>
Rolling across the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION> is like having pages of the <ORGANIZATION>National Geographic</ORGANIZATION> 
come to life around you. 
</P>
<P>
Exotic birds dart from spindly trees. Caimans plunge into waters that are milk 
chocolate in color. Giant anteaters lasso termites with their footlong tongues. 
Fishermen under broad straw hats sweep rivers in dugout canoes, catching 
20-pound catfish and filling baskets with piranha. 
</P>
<P>
In spite of its fantastic beauty, the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION> has been a great unknown until 
recent years. Lack of roads kept the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION>'s wildlife-rich inner <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>, an 
area about the size of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in central-west <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, out of reach to all but 
the most zealous explorers. 
</P>
<P>
It was in <DATE>1974</DATE> that an elevated dirt road -- the Transpantaneira -- was 
completed, linking the <ORGANIZATION>Pantanal</ORGANIZATION>'s interior with its northern boundary at the 
town of Pocone. Still, it wasn't until just three years ago that tourists 
outnumbered scientists visiting the area. 
</P>
<P>
I flew to the nearest city -- <LOCATION>Cuiaba</LOCATION> -- in <DATE>late June</DATE> during the dry season, 
when wildlife in the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION> can best be seen. With a bottle of local rum, 
three cameras and a guide, <PERSON>Luiz Roberto</PERSON>, who could identify what seemed like a 
million animals, I set out for a weeklong adventure into the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION>'s 
largest breeding grounds. 
</P>
<P>
After an hour's drive past 10-home villages and miles of parched, rugged 
country, we arrived in dusty Pocone and loaded up on soft drinks -- ammo 
against 95-degree days. 
</P>
<P>
Just outside <LOCATION>Pocone</LOCATION>, a carved sign hung over the road announcing the beginning 
of the Transpantaneira, and it might well have included the message: "Where 
city dwellers become nature lovers." 
</P>
<P>
No sooner had we begun our journey into the heart of lightness than we slowed 
to cross one of the 123 wooden bridges on the Transpantaneira, which stretches 
90 miles from <LOCATION>Pocone</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Porto Jofre</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
From our Land Cruiser we peered into ponds on both sides of the bridge, and to 
my pleasant astonishment, we spied the first of hundreds of caimans we would 
see in coming days. 
</P>
<P>
By day, literally millions of Pantanal caimans take sun beside waterways and 
marshy pools. At dusk, they submerge to feast on piranha and an occasional land 
animal ambushed while drinking at water's edge. Whether seen by day or by 
night, the toothy reptiles, some up to 10 feet long, are an impressive sight. 
</P>
<P>
A few minutes past the bridge we came upon a towering tree that wore its leaves 
like crowns on its highest branches. About two-thirds of the way up the tree, 
where the trunk finally flared off into branches, two jabiru storks -- white 
birds measuring a full four feet tall with scarlet collars, black hoods and 
six-foot wingspans -- had built a nest the width of a desk. 
</P>
<P>
On a nearby branch, a crested quero-quero -- a hawklike bird named after its 
sound -- "I want, I want" -- eyed the nest's eggs. Should the storks, who mate 
for life, abandon their nest even for a minute, it would spell certain death 
for their offspring, <PERSON>Luiz</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
In the miles that followed, we came upon kingfishers, yellow-beaked toucans, 
roseate spoonbills, American wood storks, tiger herons, spectacled owls and 
more than a few macaws. 
</P>
<P>
Without even leaving the truck, we also spotted marsh deer, two giant anteaters 
and dozens of capybaras -- web-footed rodents the size of wart hogs with 
guinea-pig faces and bearlike coats. There were other animals, but simply to 
list them does not do justice to the pleasing emotions they evoke when seen in 
sweeping savannah unspoiled by man's often-destructive touch. 
</P>
<P>
We spent our first night at the Hotel Pixaim, a 10-room lodge with bath, good 
food and a friendly staff. Typical of the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION>'s hotels, this one was clean 
and comfortable though lacking in luxury. 
</P>
<P>
Built on stilts at a bend in the <LOCATION>River Pixaim</LOCATION>, the hotel rises above a marshy 
area popular with caimans. At night, amid the sounds of crickets, bullfrogs, 
owls and monkeys, I could sometimes hear the rustle of caimans beneath me. 
</P>
<P>
The next morning, like most of my mornings in the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION>, began with Luiz and 
me racing out to a vantage point he knew to watch a breathtaking sunrise. 
</P>
<P>
Before the sun broke, the siren of a million crickets would be joined by a 
cacophony of birdcalls. Monkeys entered the ruckus with howls that reached a 
crescendo. It was like a movie soundtrack played at full volume, quieting as 
sunlight swept the plain. 
</P>
<P>
The rest of the day would be spent cruising the Transpantaneira or paddling 
around in a canoe, which took us down narrow waterways far from the road and 
into lowland rain forest. 
</P>
<P>
Gliding quietly in a canoe allowed us to slip unnoticed beneath leaning trees 
bustling with howler monkeys and common iguanas. In front of the canoe, dorados 
and pacus -- fish often weighing 20 pounds or more -- heaved themselves out of 
the muddy water to announce their presence, while scores of birds, many with 
long, elegant wings, flew an arm's length above the river. 
</P>
<P>
One day, Luiz and I took a canoe out with an old Pantaneiro who could spot 
monkeys in trees before I could see them with my 200-millimeter lens. He 
pointed out a clearing where a jaguar had been, and once we paddled to within 
20 feet of a family of capybaras before the giant rodents ran off. 
</P>
<P>
Often I'd see what appeared to be the head of a snake poking out of the water, 
only to be told it was a snake bird -- a semi-aquatic bird whose head resembles 
a bushmaster when the bird comes up for air. 
</P>
<P>
On occasion, with Luiz translating, we'd stop and chat with locals. One, a 
young biologist, was most anxious to criticize sport fishermen for depleting 
the rivers' stocks; most ignore fishing limits, he said, leaving the area with 
hundreds of animals caught in a single weekend. 
</P>
<P>
On our last night in the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Luiz</LOCATION> and I drove back to <LOCATION>Pocone</LOCATION>, then headed 
east about 30 miles to the tiny village of <LOCATION>Porto Cercado</LOCATION>, where we climbed into 
a motorized canoe that would take us upriver to Cabanas do <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION>, an 18-room 
lodge accessible only by boat. 
</P>
<P>
In the blackness of the moonless night, our canoe shot across piranha-filled 
water ringed by caiman. Our boatman flicked on a flashlight every so often 
during the 20-minute ride to warn other boatmen of our presence. 
</P>
<P>
On the shores, dusk had turned the ivy-covered trees into menacing silhouettes, 
and fireflies flitted off and on like grandma's white Christmas lights. It was 
<ORGANIZATION>Disneyland</ORGANIZATION>'s "Pirates of the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>" minus the pirates, at a wind-whipped 30 
knots. 
</P>
<P>
The hotel would have met <ORGANIZATION>Hemingway</ORGANIZATION>'s approval. Its ceiling sagged, and the 
walls were boards of bright wood decorated with colorful maps of the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION> 
and photos of the area's wildlife, including jaguars, ocelots, anacondas and, 
of course, caimans. 
</P>
<P>
Behind the bar were jars containing cachaca -- clear and punchy Brazilian rum. 
Each jar also contained an oddity such as a root or piece of bark, stuff that 
when aged in cachaca is said to produce a concoction that will increase 
potency, produce arms of steel and so on. 
</P>
<P>
The hotel's bedrooms were nothing special, but there was a gorgeous lime-green 
tree frog clinging to my shower wall and, perched on a ledge near the ceiling, 
a small snake giving the frog a good look. 
</P>
<P>
That night, like most we spent in the <LOCATION>Pantanal</LOCATION>, we drank cachaca in a fire's 
glow and recounted the day's exotic sightings 
</P>
<P>
Monkeys playing . . . fish leaping . . . exotic birds in flight . . . scenes as 
memorable as the field of caimans that peered into my flashlight a few light 
years from civilization. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Web-footed capybara rodents abound in the Pantanal wetlands. JACK 
MILLER; Photo, COLOR, Brazil: Haunting, wildlife-rich Pantanal wetland is no 
longer a scientist's secret. SCOTT DOGGETT; Map, THE PANTANAL/BRAZIL, GEORGE 
CAREY / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880313-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-13-88 2027EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-CongaLine     03-13 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Conga Line,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Celebrators Conga Their Way To Apparent World Record</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES MARTINEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Forming the world's longest conga line with almost
120,000 dancers was no problem <DATE>Sunday</DATE> for members of the crowd that
filled the streets of <LOCATION>Little Havana</LOCATION> for the <ORGANIZATION>Calle Ocho</ORGANIZATION> festival.
   ``It's very easy: Just face toward downtown, grab the shoulders
of the person in front of you _ and dance,'' <PERSON>Juan Carlos Sanchez</PERSON>,
organizer of the event.
   <PERSON>Anna Nicholas</PERSON>, a representative of the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of World
Records</ORGANIZATION>, confirmed a record had been set at 119,986 dancers,
shattering the old mark of a 10,442-person chain formed last <DATE>August</DATE>
in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   ``There's no way it could fail. As soon as the music plays, we
just grab on to somebody and hang on,'' said <PERSON>Nuvia Valdez</PERSON>, one of
about 1.5 million who turned out for the food and fun of what is
billed as the nation's largest Hispanic festival.
   The river of people along 23 blocks of <ORGANIZATION>Eighth Street _ Calle
Ocho</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish _ began to move when <PERSON>Gloria Estefan</PERSON> and the <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>
Sound Machine blared their hit ``Conga'' from loudspeakers.
   On the street, 96 volunteers with bullhorns attempted to direct
the traffic of dancing feet, while <PERSON>Ms. Estefan</PERSON> shouted to the
crowd: ``Is everybody ready? Let's conga!'' A special computer
program helped count the dancers, and 30 observation posts were set
up.
   Since the street was clogged, forming a single line was
difficult, and untold thousands of people formed in a bevy of
smaller lines in addition to the mega-line that made the Guinness
tally.
   ``I've never seen this many people in one place in my life,''
said <PERSON>Jean-Louis Levasseur</PERSON>, who was vacationing from <LOCATION>New Brunswick</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. ``There's more people on this one street than in all of the
Maritime Provinces.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890114-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-89 1152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     01-14 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0646</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENTON, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Like many people who have ``a certain age,''
<PERSON>Maggie Grubb Lambeth</PERSON> gets a little offended when asked how old she
is.
   ``I'm not that old,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Lambeth</PERSON>, who along with her
identical twin sister turned 105 on <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Lambeth</PERSON>'s sister, <PERSON>Allie Grubb Hill</PERSON>, doesn't mind talking
about her age, but then she's a few minutes younger.
   The sisters, who are listed as the world's oldest living
identical twins by the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION>, celebrated at
their home in the <LOCATION>Mountain Vista Health Park</LOCATION>. The two women lived in
<LOCATION>Davidson County</LOCATION> all their lives, never more than two miles apart,
and moved to the rest home two years ago.
   ``It's the Lord that has kept us here this long,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Hill</PERSON> said.
   Between them, <PERSON>Mrs. Hill</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mrs. Lambeth</PERSON> had 20 children, 15 of
whom are living. They have 48 grandchildren, 90 great-grandchildren
and 31 great-great-grandchildren.
   <PERSON>Hazel Briles</PERSON>, 67, the second-youngest of <PERSON>Mrs. Lambeth</PERSON>'s nine
children, said her mother kept her house spotless and her yard raked
until she was in her 90s.
   ``She just enjoyed doing things like that,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Briles</PERSON> said.
``She was a real active person. Most everybody in our family is real
active.''
   The two sisters rely on each other for companionship, and somehow
manage to keep each other going, <PERSON>Mrs. Briles</PERSON> said.
   ``They just don't make them like that anymore,'' she said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>OMAHA, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Like many people who have ``a certain age,''
<PERSON>Maggie Grubb Lambeth</PERSON> gets a little offended when asked how old she
is.
   ``I'm not that old,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Lambeth</PERSON>, who along with her
identical twin sister turned 105 on <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Lambeth</PERSON>'s sister, <PERSON>Allie Grubb Hill</PERSON>, doesn't mind talking
about her age, but then she's a few minutes younger.
   The sisters, who are listed as the world's oldest living
identical twins by the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION>, celebrated at
their home in the <LOCATION>Mountain Vista Health Park</LOCATION>. The two women lived in
<LOCATION>Davidson County</LOCATION> all their lives, never more than two miles apart,
