<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030790-0143 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 186073 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 7, 1990, Wednesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 3; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1293 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DANCE; 
</P>
<P>
DEDICATION FUELED BALLET DANCER'S LEAP TO FAME; 
</P>
<P>
PERFORMANCE: JULIO BOCCA, YOUNGEST PRINCIPAL DANCER IN AMERICAN BALLET THEATRE 
HISTORY, SAYS ALL HE EVER WANTED TO DO IS DANCE. THIS WEEK HE AND THE ABT 
PERFORM IN COSTA MESA. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHRIS PASLES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
At the unprecedented age of 19, <PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON> became a principal dancer with 
<ORGANIZATION>American Ballet Theatre</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, the youngest principal ABT ever had. How did 
the Argentine youngster do it? 
</P>
<P>
Winning the gold medal at the <ORGANIZATION>Fifth International Ballet Competition</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> 
in <DATE>1985</DATE> certainly helped. But it was more the result of <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON>'s longtime 
single-minded dedication to establishing a dance career. 
</P>
<P>
"I went only for seven years to school, then I stopped," <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON> said recently 
from <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, where he was staying with friends before heading to <LOCATION>Costa Mesa</LOCATION> for 
his appearances this week with <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Orange County Performing Arts Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I was pretty determined to be a dancer," said <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON>, who was born in <ORGANIZATION>Buenos 
Aires</ORGANIZATION> and turned 23 on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. He started his dance training with his mother 
when he was 4. 
</P>
<P>
He went on to study at the <ORGANIZATION>National Ballet</ORGANIZATION> school at the <ORGANIZATION>Teatro Colon</ORGANIZATION>, joined 
the <ORGANIZATION>International Ballet</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION> at 15 and became a principal dancer with 
<ORGANIZATION>Teatro Colon</ORGANIZATION> at 17. 
</P>
<P>
Bocca studied and coached with dancers from the Ballets Russes, from whom he 
imbibed a respect for classical line and a deep love of classical roles. 
</P>
<P>
Was it hard for a young man to study ballet in a country dominated by machismo? 
</P>
<P>
"If someone said something to me, I didn't care," he said. "It was their 
problem, not mine." 
</P>
<P>
His meteoric rise to fame occurred after he won the gold medal for dancing four 
virtuosic pas de deux, including "Corsaire," "<PERSON>Don Quixote</PERSON>," "Nutcracker" and 
"Tango" (created by Argentine choreographer <PERSON>Gustavo Molajoli</PERSON>). 
</P>
<P>
But winning not only changed his life -- he talked of one performance before 
100,000 people in <LOCATION>Buenos Aires</LOCATION> -- it raised the dance consciousness of his 
compatriots. 
</P>
<P>
"After the competition, we had this dance explosion in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>," he said. 
"The same thing happened with tennis player <PERSON>Guillermo Vilas</PERSON>. No one played 
tennis before he was a star. Now tennis is fine -- everyone plays. That has 
happened now with ballet. There's a big difference now. Now they have someone 
to see and admire. Now, ballet is for everyone." 
</P>
<P>
International companies came calling too. American Ballet Theatre invited him 
to join the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> company as a principal dancer. His first ballet with <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> 
was the "Nutcracker," followed by the full-length "<PERSON>Don Quixote</PERSON>." During the 
past two years, <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> audiences have seen him in "<PERSON>Don 
Quixote</PERSON>" pas de deux, the "Nutcracker," "The Sleeping Beauty" and "Etudes." He 
said he has done all the classical roles with <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> except "Swan Lake." 
</P>
<P>
In these ballets, he has often been partnered with <PERSON>Cheryl Yeager</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Cheryl</PERSON> was so incredibly nice to me from the beginning," <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON> said. "It was 
my first year in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> as a principal dancer, when other people 
have to work maybe 10 years to be a principal. . . . She would try to 
understand me and try to explain things to me. She was incredible." 
</P>
<P>
It was for them that former <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> artistic associate <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON> choreographed 
her newest work, "Brief Fling," which received its premiere last week in <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION>. The two will dance it in <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"I like the classical roles more than the other things," <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON> admitted. "But 
sometimes, you have to do other things so you can be better and grow up, right? 
When you have this possibility to do a new ballet from <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON>, I do it and 
enjoy it. I also have a new ballet for me by Roland Petite. . . . But at this 
point, for me, I am interested mostly in the classical roles, just to keep 
growing in the classical roles." 
</P>
<P>
Bocca also will dance Romeo opposite the Juliet of <PERSON>Alessandra Ferri</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> 
and <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, and <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON>'s "Theme and Variations" with <PERSON>Yeager</PERSON> on 
<DATE>March 16</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
" 'Romeo' is great," he said. "I love to do it. You just enjoy it, listen to 
the music, be sexy with your partner. . . ." 
</P>
<P>
What about <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON>'s "Theme and Variations"? 
</P>
<P>
"That's hard, definitely hard, it has so many steps," he said. "It's one of the 
most difficult ballets, technically. . . . You have to be secure, keyed in, 
like nothing is happening, and also, you can't do a lot of emotional explosion 
because it's not like that, not like the '<PERSON>Don Quixote</PERSON>' pas de deux. There you 
are very free to do whatever you want. This is so compact, very clean, perfect, 
quiet. It's so difficult." 
</P>
<P>
He recalled <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>'s former artistic director <PERSON>Mikhail Baryshnikov</PERSON> saying to him, 
"If you can do a good 'Theme and Variations,' you can do a good everything 
else." 
</P>
<P>
Bocca has been trying to do "a good everything else" both in and outside the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1988</DATE>, he joined the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Danish Ballet</ORGANIZATION> as a guest artist for 
two months, and more recently also danced with <PERSON>Natalia Makarova</PERSON> in "Romeo and 
Juliet" for the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Ballet</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, as well as with the Bolshoi and 
the Kirov ballets in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
After all that, how does the <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> experience stack up? 
</P>
<P>
"I don't like to compare one company or one dancer to another one," <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON> said. 
"I enjoy dancing, I love dancing. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"I'm happy with the people in the company," he said. "Sometimes, you want to go 
into a large company, you go work and that's it. The point for me is to try to 
make a good relationship with all the company." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON> does miss his home in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, which he visits as often as <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>'s 
schedule permits. 
</P>
<P>
"In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, when maybe I have two days off, I fly back just to be there even 
for a couple of hours," he said. "I have all my best friends, my family, my 
house, my dog there." 
</P>
<P>
Although he appears slightly self-conscious about his accent, <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON> has no 
trouble expressing himself in English. 
</P>
<P>
"My first year, I still had a little problem with English. Now, it's just 
fine," he said. "I can say something terrible to everyone. I know all the bad 
words." 
</P>
<P>
 American Ballet Theatre principal dancer <PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON> will dance <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON>'s 
new "Brief Fling" with <PERSON>Cheryl Yeager</PERSON> at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Orange County 
Performing Arts Center</ORGANIZATION>, 600 Town Center Drive, in <LOCATION>Costa Mesa</LOCATION>. Bocca also is 
scheduled to dance <PERSON>Romeo</PERSON> opposite the Juliet of <PERSON>Alessandra Ferri</PERSON> in <ORGANIZATION>MacMillan</ORGANIZATION>'s 
"Romeo and Juliet" at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> and at <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>; <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON>'s "Theme 
and Variations" at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>March 16</DATE>; "Brief Fling" at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>March 17</DATE>, and "La 
Bayadere" Act II at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>March 18</DATE>. Tickets: <MONEY>$10</MONEY>-<MONEY>$40</MONEY> for mixed repertory 
programs; <MONEY>$16</MONEY>-<MONEY>$47</MONEY> for "Romeo and Juliet." Information: (714) 556-2787. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Ballet <LOCATION>Pacifica</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Laguna Beach</LOCATION> will represent the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> region at the <ORGANIZATION>Fourth 
International Ballet Competition</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>June 29</DATE> in <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss</LOCATION>. The 28-year-old 
troupe will dance <PERSON>Norbert Vesak</PERSON>'s "Gift to Be Single," set to traditional 
Shaker hymns, on a bill with four other regional dance companies -- the <ORGANIZATION>Central 
Pennsylvania Youth Ballet</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Fort Wayne Ballet</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Augusta Ballet</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> 
Metropolitan Ballet. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>International Ballet Competition</ORGANIZATION> was founded in <LOCATION>Varna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bulgaria</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1964</DATE> 
and is considered one of the most prestigious competitions in dance. It is held 
every four years, rotating between <LOCATION>Varna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Helsinki</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Hoag Foundation of Los Angeles</ORGANIZATION> has given <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> to Opera Pacific to help 
fund outreach programs for mentally handicapped children in seven <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> 
schools. 
</P>
<P>
The schools, to be visited by <ORGANIZATION>Opera Pacific's Overture Company</ORGANIZATION> between <DATE>April 17</DATE> 
and <DATE>June 19</DATE>, are: the <ORGANIZATION>Adams School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Canyon Hills TMR</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION>; 
<ORGANIZATION>Currie Middle School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tustin</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Esperanza Special Education</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Mission Viejo</LOCATION>; 
Hope School in <LOCATION>Buena Park</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Huntington Beach Guidance Center</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Marion 
Parsons Special Education</ORGANIZATION> school in <LOCATION>Costa Mesa</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The grant is the foundation's first to <ORGANIZATION>Opera Pacific</ORGANIZATION>'s special education 
program, which is in its third year. Earlier funding had been provided by <ORGANIZATION>Very 
Special Arts National</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Opera America</LOCATION>, and local organizations. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Julio Bocca, at a rehearsal, says that although he's eager to do "Brief 
Fling," "I like the classical roles more than the other things." GEORGE OLSON / 
For The Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BOCCA, JULIO; DANCERS; DANCING; AMERICAN BALLET THEATRE; ARGENTINA -- CULTURE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-12685 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes070_l_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-070 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ISRAEL </F>
<H3> <TI>   Italian Observers Arrive in Hebron, Comment </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Italian Observers Arrive in Hebron, Comment </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   LD1104213194 Rome RAI Uno Television Network in Italian 1800 
GMT 11 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD1104213194 </F>
<F P=104>  Rome RAI Uno Television Network </F>
<F P=105>  Italian </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] The mission of the international observers in <LOCATION>Hebron</LOCATION> 
is now under way. This is the first operation of its type in 
the territories occupied by <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>. Giovanni Bocco reports: 
  [Bocco] It was a lightning visit by the delegation of 
international observers in <LOCATION>Hebron</LOCATION>. Two officers from the 
Italian carabinieri force were also present. They spoke with 
the Palestinian mayor of the city and with the Israelis about 
the organizational aspects of the mandate. 
  There will be 35 Italian observers, but only 15 will be 
permanently stationed in <LOCATION>Hebron</LOCATION>. After leaving the private 
room, the negotiators entered the council chamber, which was 
full of people. There was a handshake between the mayor, a UN 
delegate, and <ORGANIZATION>Yitzhaq Rabin</ORGANIZATION>'s representative. However, the 
smiles did not hide the fact that there were still many things 
to be decided. The two Italian delegates are Colonel Pietro 
Pistolese and Major <PERSON>Giovanni Trullio</PERSON>. They come from the 
<LOCATION>Tuscagna</LOCATION> carabinieri parachute regiment, which has already seen 
action in <LOCATION>Somalia</LOCATION> as part of the Ibis mission. Here is the head 
of the Italian delegation, Colonel Pistolese: 
  [Pistolese] This is the first contact... 
  [Bocco, interrupting] Have you overcome the obstacle of 
security? 
  [Pistolese] No. For the moment there are no security 
problems. We are welcomed and we hope to be good guests. 
  [Bocco] Will you be completely disarmed. I have heard that 
this will be so? 
  [Pistolese] We are working on this. We are just at the 
beginning of our mandate. It is premature... 
  [Bocco, interrupting] How do you think that this meeting has 
gone? 
  [Pistolese] Well. 
  [Bocco] The 160 UN observers: 90 Norwegians, 35 <LOCATION>Danes</LOCATION>, and 
35 
Italians will have to operate in a difficult situation. Hebron 
is a fortress of the Islamic fundamentalists, but four 
kilometers away there is a colony of some 5,000 Jewish settlers. 
Friction is the order of the day. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-13287 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes075_l_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-075 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  17 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ISRAEL </F>
<H3> <TI>   Peres on Importance of International Observers </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Peres on Importance of International Observers </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   LD1704204494 Rome RAI Uno Television Network in Italian 1800 
GMT 17 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD1704204494 </F>
<F P=104>  Rome RAI Uno Television Network </F>
<F P=105>  Italian </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Let us turn to the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION>. After having 
ordered the closure of the occupied territories for 10 days 
following the latest round of massacres, the government in 
<LOCATION>Jerusalem</LOCATION> has decided to allow some 20,000 Palestinians involved 
in social and humanitarian work to be allowed back in. Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Rabin</PERSON> has also announced a plan for the withdrawal of 
Israeli troops from the <LOCATION>Golan Heights</LOCATION>. Our correspondent 
<PERSON>Giovanni Bocco</PERSON> interviewed Israeli Foreign Minister Shim'on 
Peres: 
  [Begin recording] [<LOCATION>Bocco</LOCATION>, in English, translating his own 
question into Italian] The <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> peace negotiations have 
restarted: When do you think an agreement over <LOCATION>Gaza</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Jericho</LOCATION> 
will be reached? 
  [<LOCATION>Peres</LOCATION>, in English, with correspondent providing Italian 
translation] It appears to me that both ourselves and the <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> 
are respecting the agreements. I believe that the most 
difficult part of the negotiations has been overcome. The 
majority of the workload is behind us. If all goes well, then 
in two or three weeks time we will leave the <ORGANIZATION>Gaza Strip</ORGANIZATION>. 
  [Bocco] The international observers are arriving in <LOCATION>Hebron</LOCATION>. 
There are 35 Italians among these observers: What do you think 
about this? 
  [Peres] I believe that this is an important contribution to 
the peace process. The international presence is truly welcome, 
at least on our part, because it is important in bringing normal 
living conditions to <LOCATION>Hebron</LOCATION> and for preventing acts of violence. 
This welcome extends to the Italian contingent. 
  [Bocco] What do you think of the arrival of the Palestinian 
police force? 
  [Peres] I think that the Palestinians can and must provide 
security measures. They must police themselves. We cannot be 
the policemen of the Palestinians who have every right to have 
their own security force. We are happy that the police force is 
on its way. You cannot imagine how truthful my words are. [end 
recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-13278 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes075_x_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-075 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  17 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ISRAEL </F>
<H3> <TI>   Peres on Importance of International Observers </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Peres on Importance of International Observers </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   LD1704204494 Rome RAI Uno Television Network in Italian 1800 
GMT 17 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD1704204494 </F>
<F P=104>  Rome RAI Uno Television Network </F>
<F P=105>  Italian </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Let us turn to the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION>. After having 
ordered the closure of the occupied territories for 10 days 
following the latest round of massacres, the government in 
<LOCATION>Jerusalem</LOCATION> has decided to allow some 20,000 Palestinians involved 
in social and humanitarian work to be allowed back in. Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Rabin</PERSON> has also announced a plan for the withdrawal of 
Israeli troops from the <LOCATION>Golan Heights</LOCATION>. Our correspondent 
<PERSON>Giovanni Bocco</PERSON> interviewed Israeli Foreign Minister Shim'on 
Peres: 
  [Begin recording] [<LOCATION>Bocco</LOCATION>, in English, translating his own 
question into Italian] The <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> peace negotiations have 
restarted: When do you think an agreement over <LOCATION>Gaza</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Jericho</LOCATION> 
will be reached? 
  [<LOCATION>Peres</LOCATION>, in English, with correspondent providing Italian 
translation] It appears to me that both ourselves and the <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> 
are respecting the agreements. I believe that the most 
difficult part of the negotiations has been overcome. The 
majority of the workload is behind us. If all goes well, then 
in two or three weeks time we will leave the <ORGANIZATION>Gaza Strip</ORGANIZATION>. 
  [Bocco] The international observers are arriving in <LOCATION>Hebron</LOCATION>. 
There are 35 Italians among these observers: What do you think 
about this? 
  [Peres] I believe that this is an important contribution to 
the peace process. The international presence is truly welcome, 
at least on our part, because it is important in bringing normal 
living conditions to <LOCATION>Hebron</LOCATION> and for preventing acts of violence. 
This welcome extends to the Italian contingent. 
  [Bocco] What do you think of the arrival of the Palestinian 
police force? 
  [Peres] I think that the Palestinians can and must provide 
security measures. They must police themselves. We cannot be 
the policemen of the Palestinians who have every right to have 
their own security force. We are happy that the police force is 
on its way. You cannot imagine how truthful my words are. [end 
recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031290-0098 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 188521 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 12, 1990, Monday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 2; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
709 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DANCE AND MUSIC REVIEWS; 
</P>
<P>
STAR-CROSS'D CASTING THROWS A WRENCH INTO 'ROMEO AND JULIET' ROMANCE AT CENTER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEWIS SEGAL, TIMES DANCE WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
COSTA MESA 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Star-cross'd casting kept a weekend of American Ballet Theatre "Romeo and 
Juliet" performances in <LOCATION>Costa Mesa</LOCATION> only fitfully satisfying. 
</P>
<P>
Now familiar from stage, screen and television, <PERSON>Kenneth MacMillan</PERSON>'s <DATE>1965</DATE> dance 
drama earned its reputation through inspired collaborations -- initially, of 
course, between <PERSON>Margot Fonteyn</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rudolf Nureyev</PERSON>, but also <PERSON>Lynn Seymour</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Christopher Gable</PERSON>, for whom the ballet was choreographed. Ballet Theatre, 
however, seems to assume that <PERSON>Romeo</PERSON>, Mercutio and <ORGANIZATION>Benvolio</ORGANIZATION> are interchangeable 
roles -- and that audiences somehow don't notice when the the lovers are cast 
from cynical (or is it desperate?) expediency. 
</P>
<P>
Certainly, pairing <PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON> with <PERSON>Alessandra Ferriq</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> was pretty much 
the same as marrying <PERSON>Juliet</PERSON> off to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. Bocca is a brilliant virtuoso but 
scarcely ideal for Romeo either in physical proportions, partnering ability or 
acting skill. In contrast, <PERSON>Ferri</PERSON> is one of the great Juliets of our time, a 
dancing actress of astonishing originality who creates a specific reality in 
each performance -- one that <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON>'s bland obviousness continually 
contradicted. 
</P>
<P>
When this <PERSON>Juliet</PERSON> danced, it was always a declaration to her Romeo -- while he 
invariably remained absorbed in showing off feats to the audience. They even 
clashed in death: <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON>'s stylized throes and soft, slow, self-protective fall 
to the floor versus <PERSON>Ferri</PERSON>'s wild explosion of suicidal despair. 
</P>
<P>
The <DATE>Saturday</DATE> matinee leads proved no more compatible -- but they, at least, 
were thrown together by happenstance. Scheduled to dance with other partners, 
<PERSON>Leslie Browne</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wes Chapman</PERSON> found themselves cast opposite one another in 
this ballet for the first time because of an injury to <PERSON>Browne</PERSON>'s designated 
<PERSON>Romeo</PERSON> (<PERSON>Ricardo Bustamante</PERSON>). 
</P>
<P>
They responded like pros, of course. Chapman partnered conscientiously, soloed 
capably (though some of the bravura looked underpowered) and showed promise of 
developing a notably sweet and refined characterization: Romeo as dream-prince. 
On this occasion, <PERSON>Browne</PERSON> muted her distinctively sophisticated and contemporary 
interpretation (very post-Seymour) but danced faultlessly. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, <PERSON>Kevin McKenzie</PERSON> made a mature, almost world-weary Romeo 
renewed by the virginal innocence of <PERSON>Amanda McKerrow</PERSON>'s Juliet -- more like 
<PERSON>Albrecht</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Giselle</LOCATION>, perhaps, than these <PERSON>Montague</PERSON> and Capulet lovers, but 
clearly the most potent combination of the weekend. 
</P>
<P>
Although a strained actor, <PERSON>McKenzie</PERSON> had strength and generosity as a partner 
that always made a powerful statement on its own terms -- and it allowed 
<PERSON>McKerrow</PERSON> maximum daring in the great duets. Unlike <PERSON>Ferri</PERSON> and <PERSON>Browne</PERSON>, she didn't 
show Juliet growing wiser or deeper from adversity: She died the same child 
we'd seen playing with a doll. But in her purity of belief and vulnerability, 
she broke your heart. 
</P>
<P>
Beyond showcasing its tragic lovers, <PERSON>MacMillan</PERSON>'s "Romeo and Juliet" represents 
a spectacular company vehicle and these first Orange County performances 
boasted a number of high-profile portrayals. 
</P>
<P>
Among the most artful: <PERSON>Georgina Parkinson</PERSON>'s alternately steely and volcanic 
Lady Capulet (<DATE>Friday</DATE> and <DATE>Saturday</DATE> nights), <PERSON>Victor Barbee</PERSON>'s complex, formidable 
<LOCATION>Tybalt</LOCATION> (<DATE>Friday</DATE>), <PERSON>Alexander Minz</PERSON>'s cerebral <PERSON>Friar Laurence</PERSON> (<DATE>Friday</DATE> and <DATE>Saturday</DATE> 
<TIME>evening</TIME>) and <PERSON>Kathleen Moore</PERSON>'s grandmotherly Nurse (<DATE>Friday</DATE> and the <DATE>Saturday</DATE> 
matinee). 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Guillaume Graffin</PERSON> danced unevenly in his first performance as <ORGANIZATION>Benvolio</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>Friday</DATE>) 
-- but in looks and temperament this is clearly a born Romeo paying his dues. 
As Mercutio, both <PERSON>Johan Renvall</PERSON> (<DATE>Friday</DATE> and <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>) and <PERSON>John 
Gardner</PERSON> (<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>) settled for lightweight, boyish interpretations put 
over with sharply honed technique. <PERSON>Michael Owen</PERSON> made a conventionally brutish 
<LOCATION>Tybalt</LOCATION> (<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>) and <PERSON>Kevin O'Day</PERSON> (<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>) turned the 
character into Brandoesque trade, obviously waiting around <LOCATION>Verona</LOCATION> for someone 
to invent the motorcycle. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jack Everly</PERSON> and <PERSON>Charles Barker</PERSON> alternated as conductor in the three 
performances. Sign of progress: The <ORGANIZATION>Mandolin Dance</ORGANIZATION> solo in Act II is no longer 
Mercutio's property but belongs, as <ORGANIZATION>MacMillan</ORGANIZATION> originally intended, to a 
divertissement dancer (<PERSON>Robert Wallace</PERSON> at the first two performances, then <PERSON>Keith 
Roberts</PERSON>). It makes so much more sense that way. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Dance Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06090159 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06090159 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO:; Julio Bocca and Cheryl Yeager dance delicately as the lovers  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  DANCE; REVIEW; SAN-FRANCISCO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  'COPPELIA" is cute, and American Ballet Theater's "Coppelia," as with
everything that bears the ABT stamp, is big and cute -- a baby elephant with a
pink ruffle and toe shoes.;    Oh, well. It's nice to see this charming
meringue of a ballet done so stylishly, though ABT probably spent six times
what San Jose Cleveland Ballet did for its "Coppelia" to achieve precisely the
same result.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ABT'S FANCIFUL AND FROTHY 'COPPELIA'  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Dance Review  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     And speaking of SJCB, what a surprise to discover that the first act of its
and <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>'s "Coppelia" are practically photocopies. Though billed as new, <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>'s
is really the <DATE>1968</DATE> production staged by former ballet master <PERSON>Enrique Martinez</PERSON>.
It apparently made an indelible impression on SJCB's director, <PERSON>Dennis Nahat</PERSON>,
who danced in it.;    Both, of course, are based on <PERSON>Arthur Saint-Leon</PERSON>'s <DATE>1870</DATE>
original, which avoids all the dark sides of <ORGANIZATION>E.T.A. Hoffmann</ORGANIZATION>'s story. <PERSON>Dr.
Coppelius</PERSON>, the toy-maker, is a Svengali in the story; in the ballet, a
harmless eccentric.;    On opening night <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <PERSON>Cheryl Yeager</PERSON> and <PERSON>Julio
Bocca</PERSON> were the lovers, <ORGANIZATION>Swanilda</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Franz</PERSON>, who quarrel over <LOCATION>Franz</LOCATION>'s
infatuation with the life-size mechanical doll, <LOCATION>Coppelia</LOCATION>. (They'll repeat the
roles tonight.) Their sparky exchanges, jubilant delivery and youthful romance
are a delight to watch.;    Other standouts in this cast were <PERSON>Kathleen Moore</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Roger van Fleteren</PERSON>, who led the harvesters' mazurka with panache, and the
slow-burning, luxurious <PERSON>Christine Dunham</PERSON> as the allegorical "Prayer" in the
wedding divertissement.;    There will be multiple casts over the <DATE>weekend</DATE>,
including some to stretch your willing suspension of disbelief -- such as the
tall and mature <PERSON>Cynthia Gregory</PERSON>, who dances <DATE>Sunday</DATE> evening with <PERSON>Jeremy Collins</PERSON>
as Franz. In that performance, <PERSON>Michael Smuin</PERSON>, former director of <LOCATION>San Francisco
Ballet</LOCATION>, will chase the bats from <PERSON>Dr. Coppelius</PERSON>' belfry.;    This storybook
"Coppelia" has a surprisingly stodgy set by <PERSON>Tony Straiges</PERSON>, who would have
seemed to be a natural for fairy tales after designing "Into the Woods." Here
he converts an Alpine village to a colorized version of the industrial city of
Frankfurt.;    <PERSON>Patricia Zipprodt</PERSON>'s costumes, however, are beautiful excursions
into peasant territory. <PERSON>Jack Everly</PERSON> led the orchestra, which was barely
passable in the first act but respectable in the other two.;     American
Ballet Theater; '<ORGANIZATION>Coppelia</ORGANIZATION>'; When: 2 and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today-Sunday</DATE>; Where: <ORGANIZATION>War
Memorial Opera House</ORGANIZATION>, 301 <LOCATION>Van Ness Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; Tickets: <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$65</MONEY>.
(415) 621-3838  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JUDITH GREEN, Mercury News Dance Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910330  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  403  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday March 30, 1991
00090159,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910702-0149
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910702-0149.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   All the World's on Stage in New York
   ----
   By Dale Harris
</HL>
<DATE>
07/02/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A11
</SO>
<LP>
   American Ballet Theatre's recent stopover at the
Metropolitan Opera House lasted only nine weeks, but seemed
to go on for years. During one of the season's particularly
arid periods -- when "Coppelia," say, or "Don Quixote" was
the sole work in the repertoire -- one could have sworn that
the company had been running longer than "Cats." "Coppelia,"
which received 11 performances, has already been reviewed in
these pages, "Don Quixote," which received 10, has not.
Originally staged for ABT by Mikhail Baryshnikov, the old
warhorse has now been revised by the Bolshoi's Vladimir
Vasiliev, who has managed the feat of transforming an
unsatisfactory production into a wretched one, by adding
coarse new choreography and even coarser sight gags.
   Most of ABT's ballerinas appeared in the role of the
heroine, Kitri, though only Sylvie Guillem, the company's
newest guest star, drew big houses. Ms. Guillem, who began
her career as a gymnast, still looks like one: Dancing for
her is clearly less important than the demonstration of
physical prowess. In the third act pas de deux of "Don
Quixote," her protracted balances brought down the house --
not because, like the late Margot Fonteyn's, they looked
effortless, but because they looked powerful, a series of
strenuous attempts to overcome the limitations of gravity.
The fact that Ms. Guillem failed to maintain her poses with
perfect steadiness did nothing to spoil her success. Every
falter was taken as further testimony to the ballerina's
indomitable sense of purpose, and incited the crowd to
further acclaim.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Except in her exquisite, if expressionless, face, the
Amazonian <PERSON>Ms. Guillem</PERSON> shows none of the feminine grace
usually associated with classical ballet. Broad-shouldered,
hyper-extended and commandingly tall, she nonetheless adopts
a shy and modest demeanor that contrasts disconcertingly with
the force of her dancing and the implicit willpower it
expresses. In tackling parts like the mischievous innkeeper's
daughter in "<PERSON>Don Quixote</PERSON>" and the remote but passionate
temple dancer in "La Bayadere," she offers less a portrayal
than an impersonation.
   Nowhere was the discrepancy between physical identity and
characterization more glaring than in <LOCATION>Agnes de Mille</LOCATION>'s "Fall
River Legend." As the inhibited <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> spinster <PERSON>Lizzie
Borden</PERSON>, who chops up her parents, <PERSON>Ms. Guillem</PERSON> was an
unconvincing wolf in sheep's clothing. "Fall River Legend" is
not merely a poor choice for her particular gifts, it is a
poor ballet. A pop version of one of <PERSON>Martha Graham</PERSON>'s cloudy
psychodramas, "Fall River Legend" is psychologically
imperceptive and choreographically vacant. It is also
ludicrously overwrought, though not enough to be genuinely
funny. Along with the now lifeless works of <PERSON>Antony Tudor</PERSON>, it
is part of the barren heritage that <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> needs to junk if it
is ever to get anywhere.
   <PERSON>Ms. Guillem</PERSON> is by no means the only talented dancer at <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>
who doesn't know what roles she looks good in. <PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON>
cut a better figure in "Giselle" midway in the season than he
had done in "Coppelia" on opening night, but nowhere as good
a one as he did last year in <PERSON>Mark Morris</PERSON>'s "Drink to Me Only
With Thine Eyes" and <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON>'s "Brief Fling." In neither
of these ballets, however, did he appear this time around.
Apparently, he finds both assignments unrewarding. What he
obviously doesn't understand is that in <PERSON>Mr. Morris</PERSON>'s richly
inventive work, he has a role that, though made for <PERSON>Mikhail
Baryshnikov</PERSON>, suits him to perfection, and that in "Brief
Fling," especially created for him by <PERSON>Ms. Tharp</PERSON>, his gifts of
energy, speed, virtuosity and charm were used so brilliantly
that for the first time he looked like a star.
   Lacking in self-knowledge though he is, <PERSON>Mr. Bocca</PERSON> at least
has had the chance to work with a genuine choreographer at a
crucial stage in his development. Most of the other talented
young dancers in the company have been less lucky. <PERSON>Amanda
McKerrow</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alessandra Ferri</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gabrielle Brown</PERSON>, <PERSON>Amy Rose</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Christina Fagundes</PERSON>, <PERSON>Julie Kent</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kathleen Moore</PERSON>, <PERSON>Cynthia
Anderson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Christine Dunham</PERSON>, <PERSON>Isabella Padovani</PERSON> -- all have
notable qualities that a first-rate choreographer could no
doubt bring properly into focus. To judge from the fate of
<PERSON>Cynthia Gregory</PERSON>, the chances that this will happen are
slight. During her 26 years with the company, <PERSON>Ms. Gregory</PERSON> has
given many fine performances. Somewhere along the way,
though, the poetical beauty that marked her dancing in the
early <DATE>1960s</DATE> with the <LOCATION>San Francisco Ballet</LOCATION> was replaced by an
all-purpose competence, and a great ballerina got lost.
   The gifts of the young <PERSON>Fernando Bujones</PERSON>, though not as
remarkable as <PERSON>Ms. Gregory</PERSON>'s, were nevertheless conspicuous,
too. Unfortunately, during his two decades with <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>, he
failed to realize them just as surely as she failed to
realize hers. This season, <PERSON>Mr. Bujones</PERSON>, who now dances less
frequently than in the past, was invited to re-stage the
company's "Raymonda, Act III," originally adapted by <PERSON>Mikhail
Baryshnikov</PERSON> from the <DATE>1898</DATE> choreography of <PERSON>Marius Petipa</PERSON>.
Again, <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> has exchanged a weak production for a dismal one.
<PERSON>Mr. Bujones</PERSON>'s "Raymonda" revealed so fundamentally incoherent
a concept of classicism that his cast looked hobbled by
stylistic indeterminacy. Moreover, the character dances,
designed to provide a contrast with the classical passages,
were depressingly limp.
   Nevertheless, at <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> these days some of the best
performing is to be found in character roles, especially
those that call for mime. In <PERSON>Kathleen Moore</PERSON> and <PERSON>Victor
Barbee</PERSON>, especially, the company has two of the most
persuasive dancer-actors of today. Perhaps <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> could lend
them to <LOCATION>New York City Ballet</LOCATION> when the latter revives "The
Sleeping Beauty" next <DATE>spring</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900627-0098
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900627-0098.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Dance: Euroschlock Threatens ABT
   ----
   By Dale Harris
</HL>
<DATE>
06/27/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A10
</SO>
<LP>
   New York -- It's difficult to feel much optimism about the
future of American Ballet Theatre. Unless ABT starts showing
more signs of creative integrity than it has so far under its
new directors, Jane Hermann and Oliver Smith, the company is
hardly likely to survive for very long. Though such an
appraisal may seem premature, the interviews Ms. Hermann and
Mr. Smith have been giving do not inspire confidence in their
artistic judgment.
   What they are planning is to give ABT an infusion of
Euroschlock -- works by those drearily familiar figures, some
of them expatriate Americans, who have made careers out of
portentousness rather than steps: James Kudelka, Maguy Marin,
Glen Tetley and Jiri Kylian. Next season is to bring Mr.
Kylian's meretricious "Sinfonietta," last seen at the Met in
1979 during the visit of Mr. Kylian's own Netherlands Dance
Theater. To help us survive the two years it apparently is
going to take for this choreographer to come forth with a new
ballet for ABT, we are to get a re-working by the Bolshoi's
Vladimir Vasiliev of Mikhail Baryshnikov's version of that
old warhorse, "Don Quixote."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In none of their interviews did the directors say a single
word about <PERSON>Mark Morris</PERSON>, whose "Drink to Me Only With Thine
Eyes," commissioned by <PERSON>Mr. Baryshnikov</PERSON> in <DATE>1988</DATE>, is both
surpassingly beautiful and -- though it only was accorded two
performances in the current <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> season -- a crowd pleaser.
They said scarcely more about <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON>. From what they did
say, it's hard to believe that <PERSON>Ms. Hermann</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON>
realize how fortunate they are to have a new ballet by her in
the current season's repertoire, as well as enough hits by
her to make up an entire evening.
   There's little doubt that this <PERSON>Tharp</PERSON> triple bill excited
the audience as much as anything presented all season. "Push
Comes to Shove," it's true, wanted edge. But, then, it's no
less an ensemble piece than a star vehicle, and the ensemble
looked under-rehearsed, while <PERSON>Gil Boggs</PERSON>, in the role created
in <DATE>1976</DATE> by <PERSON>Mr. Baryshnikov</PERSON>, showed none of the latter's comic
flair. "In the Upper Room" also looked as if it needed more
rehearsal, but came off better. Its association of order with
energy is theatrically potent, and the audience greeted the
final curtain with the kind of roar that signifies
identification as well as excitement. "Nine <PERSON>Sinatra Songs</PERSON>,"
new to the repertoire, sent waves of euphoria rolling through
the auditorium.
   The <PERSON>Sinatra</PERSON> ballet is a good example of what <PERSON>Ms. Tharp</PERSON> has
to offer ABT -- apart, that is, from a brilliant work, in
which ballroom dancing, enhanced by virtuosity, illuminates
behavior, feelings and the vagaries of human nature. At the
same time, the piece does wonders for the performers,
especially those who, like <PERSON>Susan Jaffe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Christine Dunham</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Amanda McKerrow</PERSON>, have talent but seem incapable of realizing
it fully without better artistic guidance than they evidently
get at <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>. Apart from <PERSON>Leslie Browne</PERSON>, all the cast responds
to the technical challenges of "Nine Sinatra Songs" with a
whole heartedness that transmutes proficiency into art. The
metamorphosis of <PERSON>Ms. McKerrow</PERSON> was one of the season's big
pleasures. For the first time, she looked not like a
promising neophyte but a mature artist. Maybe in due course
<PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON> could even rescue <PERSON>Ms. Browne</PERSON>.
   The choreographer's ability to isolate the essential gifts
of a particular dancer has never been more clearly in
evidence than in her handling of <PERSON>Cheryl Yeager</PERSON>, whom <PERSON>Ms.
Tharp</PERSON> cast as the female lead in her new piece for <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>,
"Brief Fling." Until <PERSON>Ms. Yeager</PERSON> appeared in this ballet, her
artistic resources seemed limited to a combination of
pertness and a disarming, if unfocused buoyancy. "Brief
Fling" gave her the chance to show that she has something
more interesting to offer. In the case of her partner, <PERSON>Julio
Bocca</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ms. Tharp</PERSON> has extended his range and concentrated his
gifts.
   Both <PERSON>Ms. Yeager</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Bocca</PERSON> perform at breathtaking
speed the most dazzling steps and combinations. Because the
choreographer has so clear an understanding of the different
capabilities of male and female dancers, she makes their
prowess complementary as well as competitive, and thus a
metaphor of sexual harmony. In demonstrating the resources of
classical ballet technique, <PERSON>Ms. Tharp</PERSON> tests the pair to the
limits of speed, precision, daring and stamina. The results
are exhilarating -- not simply because the dancers exemplify
an ideal freedom from ordinary physical limitations, but
because they also embody an energy that transcends mere
physicality.
   In composing these dances, as well as those for the two
pairs of demi-soloists -- <PERSON>Claudia Alfieri</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gil Boggs</PERSON>, and
<PERSON>Isabella Padovani</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Wallace</PERSON> or <PERSON>Johan Renvall</PERSON> -- <PERSON>Ms.
Tharp</PERSON> shows a thorough mastery of ballet technique. The same,
unfortunately, cannot be said of <PERSON>Mr. Kylian</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mr. Kudelka</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mr.
Tetley</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ms. Marin</PERSON>, nor of that current ABT favorite, <PERSON>Agnes
de Mille</PERSON>, whose foolish and glib "Fall River Legend" has just
been disinterred by the new <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> management.
   Like so many of <PERSON>Ms. Tharp</PERSON>'s works, "Brief Fling"
juxtaposes classical ballet with the choreographer's
idiosyncratic postmodern choreography, the latter wonderfully
performed by <PERSON>Jamie Bishton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kevin O'Day</PERSON>, <PERSON>Keith Roberts</PERSON> and
<LOCATION>Shelley Washington</LOCATION>. There is no conflict between the two
kinds of dance, only an illuminating dissimilarity. "Brief
Fling" is at once about co-existence and variety. Properly
understood, the piece demonstrates how ballet can survive
after the death of <LOCATION>Balanchine</LOCATION>, whose work has brought an
entire phase of the art to a glorious but inhibiting
conclusion.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031090-0035 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 187412 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 10, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 7; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
912 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BALLET REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
ABT'S BRIEF AND FRENZIED FLING WITH THARP 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARTIN BERNHEIMER, TIMES MUSIC/DANCE CRITIC 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A year go, <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON> was a provocative fixture at <ORGANIZATION>American Ballet Theatre</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mikhail Baryshnikov</PERSON> -- the matinee idol who ran the company when he wasn't too 
busy making movies or acting in plays or dancing elsewhere -- had elected the 
irresistibly iconoclastic choreographer as his "artistic associate." Going 
straight, in her finely frenzied fashion, <PERSON>Tharp</PERSON> disbanded her touring ensemble 
and joined the <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> team. 
</P>
<P>
She took some of her specialized repertory with her, not to mention a few of 
her own dancers. The collaboration with <ORGANIZATION>Baryshnikov &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> produced some 
appealingly gutsy work as well as some lavish show-bizzy fizzles. Then came the 
explosion. 
</P>
<P>
Baryshnikov quit Ballet Theatre in a managerial huff. Tharp's name disappeared 
from the managerial roster. 
</P>
<P>
Her future with the company remains clouded. Her present, however, remains 
dazzling, and pleasantly disturbing. 
</P>
<P>
The latest addition to the Tharp oeuvre, first applauded in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> a 
week ago and introduced at the <ORGANIZATION>Orange County Performing Arts Center</ORGANIZATION> on 
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>, is a legacy of the <PERSON>Baryshnikov</PERSON> era. It bears what may be a prophetic 
title: "Brief Fling." 
</P>
<P>
In this case, the fling refers -- or at least pretends to refer -- to a 
charming highland ritual. This is <ORGANIZATION>Tharp</ORGANIZATION>'s Scottish symphony. 
</P>
<P>
Never mind searching for sylphides. Tharp's fling is fast and furious, taut and 
tense. It is refined on the surface yet rough inside. Or is it vice-versa? One 
is never quite sure, and that adds to the compelling intrigue. 
</P>
<P>
At the outset, the ballet looks reasonably polite. It strikes amusing, even 
dainty poses. Then it takes off in potentially suicidal flights, often for 
their own frantic sake. Eventually, <PERSON>Tharp</PERSON> chooses some shocking structural and 
dynamic detours. 
</P>
<P>
The quaint becomes dangerous. The cheer turns dark. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Michel Colombier</PERSON> provided the loud -- too loud -- musical impetus for this 
fusion of strict classicism and feverish adventure. Manipulating the 
technological miracles of tape and computer, he concocted a sonic tapestry that 
innocently explores the country gardens and stranded Handels of <PERSON>Percy Grainger</PERSON>, 
only to succumb to the easy dissonances and portentous rumbles we associate 
with horror flicks. 
</P>
<P>
The score may suggest candy-coated modernism. The choreography, thank goodness, 
does not. 
</P>
<P>
It toys brazenly with a tippy-toe tattoo. It showcases a frenzied ballerina in 
a tartan tutu, partnered by a fearless, airborne cavalier. It adds the casual 
counterforce of some muscular modernists who happen to specialize in bravura 
funk. In a bizarre, perfectly coordinated, essentially symmetrical suite of 
fugues and gigues, flirtations and confusions, the twain eventually meet. 
</P>
<P>
If the clash of impulses is unsettling, its progress is organic and its 
resolution strangely comforting. <PERSON>Cheryl Yeager</PERSON>, the brilliant ballerina, and 
<PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON>, her firebrand partner, become more interesting as they shed their 
royal manners. Resident Tharpians -- the devastating <PERSON>Shelley Washington</PERSON>, 
accompanied by <PERSON>Kevin O'Day</PERSON>, <PERSON>Keith Roberts</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jamie Bishton</PERSON> -- become even more 
compelling when they stretch for classical impact. 
</P>
<P>
The supporting corps includes such energetic paragons as <PERSON>Claudia Alfieri</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Isabella Padovani</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gil Boggs</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Wallace</PERSON>. They sustain the aura of 
mock-nationalistic unity and bridge the stylistic gap with splendid, overwound 
bravado. 
</P>
<P>
In this ultracompact 20-minute opus, <PERSON>Tharp</PERSON> redefines conventional rules of 
partnering. She mocks the traditions she observes. More important, perhaps, she 
understands the tradition she mocks. 
</P>
<P>
"Brief Fling" bristles with nervous outbursts, yet dares unwind just when one 
expects a final zonking climax. It shouts its abstract drama. That makes its 
occasional whisper of lyricism all the more affecting. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Isaac Mizrahi</PERSON> has decorated the piece with a bizarre jumble of parody costumes. 
Misplaced plaids and tilted tams adorn a generally courtly corps. Some of the 
men sport formal kilts but no shirts. Baggy slacks coexist with prissy toe 
shoes. The sartorial worlds collide neatly, tellingly. 
</P>
<P>
One sees obvious texts and complex subtexts here. Tharp has much going on. Too 
much, perhaps, for one to absorb in a single viewing. The prospect of 
repetitions -- many and frequent -- is reassuring. 
</P>
<P>
ABT surrounded the novelty with familiar fare. When, one had to wonder, will 
<PERSON>Tharp</PERSON> come up with the full-length ballet she owes us. 
</P>
<P>
The evening opened with the ubiquitous "Kingdom of the Shades" episode from "La 
Bayadere." <PERSON>Susan Jaffe</PERSON> served as a radiant <LOCATION>Nikiya</LOCATION>, nobly partnered by <PERSON>Kevin 
MacKenzie</PERSON> as Solor and unevenly seconded by <PERSON>Leslie Browne</PERSON>, <PERSON>Cynthia Anderson</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Christine Dunham</PERSON> as her fluttery attendants. 
</P>
<P>
The 24 ghostlets in white executed their <LOCATION>Petipa</LOCATION> arabesques rather shakily. The 
brisk tempos favored by <ORGANIZATION>Emil de Cou</ORGANIZATION> hardly reinforced the aura of otherworldly 
languor, but <PERSON>Ron Oakland</PERSON> (uncredited in the program) performed the violin solos 
exquisitely. 
</P>
<P>
A kind and gentle performance of <PERSON>Agnes de Mille</PERSON>'s "Rodeo" completed the bill. 
<PERSON>Shawn Black</PERSON> -- still ranked a member of the corps de ballet -- undertook the 
central conflicts of the cowgirl for the first time, and did so sweetly if a 
bit sketchily. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Ethan Brown</PERSON> didn't strut much stuff in his debut as the head wrangler, and 
<PERSON>Julie Kent</PERSON> seemed content to be blandly pretty in her first outing as the other 
woman. <PERSON>John Gardner</PERSON> returned as the sympathetic, soft-grained champion roper. 
Leading the excellent <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Symphony</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Jack Everly</PERSON> served <LOCATION>Copland</LOCATION> heartily in 
the pit. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, (Orange County Edition) Cheryl Yeager and Julio Bocca in a scene from 
American Ballet Theatre's "Brief Fling" at the Center. ; Photo, (Orange County 
Edition) Cheryl Yeager and Julio Bocca have their own fling while performing in 
"Brief Fling" at the Center. JOHN FUNG / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Dance Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880614-0104 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Dance: Choreography's the Trouble at ABT </HL>
<AUTHOR> Dale Harris </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> New York  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Let's hope that the gala performance by American Ballet Theater that opened the <ORGANIZATION>First New York International Festival</ORGANIZATION> of the Arts on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> was not a paradigm for the entire monthlong celebration. 
Though the evening got off to a brilliant start with <PERSON>Mark Morris</PERSON>'s "Drink to Me Only With Thine Eyes," it then, suddenly and irrevocably, fell flat on its face. 

   The problem, as usual, was the choreography -- on this occasion, two works new to the <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> repertory: <PERSON>Antony Tudor</PERSON>'s "Fandango," originally created 25 years ago for the long-vanished Metropolitan Opera Ballet Company; and <PERSON>Clark Tippet</PERSON>'s "S.P.E.B.S.Q.S.A," a world premiere. 

   For the resuscitation of "Fandango," underwritten by the <ORGANIZATION>Festival</ORGANIZATION>, there's really no excuse. 
The ballet, a sophomoric joke about the rivalry of five female dancers (<PERSON>Shawn Black</PERSON>, <PERSON>Deirdre Carberry</PERSON>, <PERSON>Christina Fagundes</PERSON>, <PERSON>Marianna Tcherkassky</PERSON> and <PERSON>Cheryl Yeager</PERSON>), set to some slight keyboard pieces by <PERSON>Antonio Soler</PERSON>, looked choreographically negligible when it was new. 
It still does, even though nowadays it's a great deal better danced than it was in <DATE>1963</DATE>. 
The genius of <PERSON>Antony Tudor</PERSON> lasted only a few years: from "Lilac Garden" of <DATE>1936</DATE> to "Romeo and Juliet" of <DATE>1943</DATE>. 
What came before was apprentice work; what came after was a series of earnest, often tedious, failures, interspersed with a number of inconsequential trifles. 
Most of these have been deservedly forgotten. 
It does no service to <ORGANIZATION>Tudor</ORGANIZATION>'s memory to interfere with the workings of a just oblivion. 

   "S.P.E.B.S.Q.S.A." -- surely the worst ballet title since <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON>'s "Glinkaiana" -- stands for the Society for the Preservation and Encouragement of Barber shop Quartet Singing in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. 
Its music is a string of old-fashioned popular songs, such as "Wait Till the <LOCATION>Sun Shines</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Nellie</PERSON>." 
They are sung from the orchestra pit in close (and not-so-close) harmony by the Cracker Jacks. 
"S.P.E.B.S.Q.S.A." is plainly meant to be a lighthearted romp. 
Indeed, for the undemanding gala audience, it proved a big hit. 
Nevertheless, it's hard to see what future it could possibly have in the regular repertory of <LOCATION>ABT</LOCATION>, since it contains virtually nothing in the way of dance interest. 

   Though conceived, formally speaking, in terms of a vaudeville act, the ballet is less like a professional show than an all-male college romp, in which a group of ordinary fellas -- on this occasion, four of them -- do a lot of horsin' around, mainly to the delight of one another. 
There's the usual joke about the fella who kisses another fella, who mimes mock outrage and disgust. 
There's the inevitable skit in which one of these regular guys dresses up in drag and plays a comic vamp, complete with breasts made of watermelon halves. 
There's the familiar soft-shoe number, in which they wear striped shirts, suspenders and straw hats. 
There's the inescapable number that, right at the end, introduces a serious note into the hitherto comic proceedings. 

   Despite the built-in problems of such a concept (which include the fact that a barbershop quartet makes less impact in a house the size of the Met than a solo piano), it's just conceivable that the piece might nevertheless have turned out to be charming had it been staged by someone who, like <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON>, is both an inventive choreographer and an aficionado of popular music and dance forms. 
<PERSON>Mr. Tippet</PERSON>, alas, is neither, and the results are merely dull. 
Until, that is, the final, serious number, when, without warning, "S.P.E.B.S.Q.S.A." descends into bathos and becomes a ballet about male bonding. 
In what is clearly intended as the climax of the work (the equivalent of "But seriously, folks . . ."), the choreographer presents a pair of lyrical pas de deux, a celebration, in other words, of the buddy beautiful. 
And this -- without a hint of irony -- is set to "America the Beautiful." 
Even as danced by four of <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>'s most talented males, <PERSON>John Gardner</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robert Hill</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kevin McKenzie</PERSON> and the astonishingly agile <PERSON>Robert Wallace</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mr. Tippet</PERSON>'s latest work is tough going. 

   With this artistically uneven program, which ended with <PERSON>Leonide Massine</PERSON>'s joyless "Gaite Parisienne," <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> brought its annual eight-week engagement at the Met to a close. 
Apart from <PERSON>Mr. Morris</PERSON>'s "Drink to Me Only With Thine Eyes," the rewards of the season have been less creative than interpretive. 
One of the most memorable events of this sort was the pair of "Bayadere" performances danced, with hardly any warning to the public, by two guests from <LOCATION>Leningrad</LOCATION>'s Kirov Ballet, <LOCATION>Altynai Assylmuratova</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Farukh Ruzimatov</PERSON>. 
Though <PERSON>Ms. Assylmuratova</PERSON> is not a stranger to American audiences, she had never before been given the opportunity to show them the full extent of her gifts. 
At the Met, she enjoyed a well-deserved triumph. 
Above all, she is a dancer whose every movement is informed by intimations of the classical ideal. 
In the second act of "La Bayadere," she performed the steps with a combination of precision and passion, of impersonal beauty and emotional depth that no one has displayed in this role since the heyday of <PERSON>Dame Margot Fonteyn</PERSON>. 

   However, she is unlike anyone but herself. 
She shows, it's true, many of the characteristics of the Kirov school, including the consolidation of expressive power in the torso rather than in the legs, which suffer from the weakness of all dancers trained in <LOCATION>Leningrad</LOCATION>. 
Nevertheless, she is something new in current Soviet dance: a ballerina whose force of personality stems, not from overly dramatic accentuation in phrasing, but from an all-pervasive lyric energy. 
That energy is manifest whether she is moving or still, for which reason she remains part of the dance even when standing on the sidelines. 
Her musicality -- an exceedingly rare quality at the Kirov -- helps too. 
So does her remarkable beauty. 
Her small, exquisitely molded head, set on a long tapering neck and framed by sleek black hair, distills the beauty of her movements into a drama that has less to do with personality than with spirit. 

   Her partner, <PERSON>Mr. Ruzimatov</PERSON>, though the Kirov's finest male dancer by far, is less extraordinary, a performer who, at his best, pleases rather than thrills. 
He may not jump very high, for example, but he lands with pantherine grace. 

   Met audiences, brainwashed by the untiring advocacy of Soviet ballet that appears in the local papers, seem to believe that all male dancers from the <LOCATION>U.S.S.R.</LOCATION> are superhuman. 
At any rate, every time that <PERSON>Mr. Ruzimatov</PERSON> made a move, they gasped in, for the most part, entirely unwarranted disbelief. 

   As it happens, more than one of the males on <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>'s regular roster can eclipse <PERSON>Mr. Ruzimatov</PERSON> in sheer technical brilliance -- <PERSON>Robert Wallace</PERSON>, for example, or <PERSON>Wes Chapman</PERSON>. 
Or the 21-year-old <PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON>, whose gifts are simply prodigious. 
What the Soviet performer has over his <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> counterparts, however, is coaching. 
When <PERSON>Mr. Bocca</PERSON> appeared as <PERSON>Albrecht</PERSON> during the last week of the season, his dancing, though breathtaking, had nothing to do with his characterization, or even with the way he presented himself to the audience. 
The steps were astounding, the other aspects of his performance virtually nonexistent. 
It's a problem <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> needs to address. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-16666</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DGBCVADVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930702
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 JUL 93 / Arts: New York Balanchine bonanza - David Vaughan attends
the final gala performance
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID VAUGHAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>New York City Ballet</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Balanchine Celebration</ORGANIZATION>, about which <ORGANIZATION>Clement Crisp</ORGANIZATION>
wrote in its early stages, came to a triumphant end on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with a gala
performance that began at 4 in the afternoon and lasted until 10.30 in the
<TIME>evening</TIME>, with intermissions when cocktails and zakouski (Russian hors
d'oeuvres) or American dessert (brownies and carrot cake) were served, and a
longer break when you could get a box supper prepared according to
<PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON>'s own recipes.
As for the dancing, the programme reprised the chronological format of the
season as a whole, but with an international flavour to illustrate the fact
that <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON> generously gave his ballets to companies all over the world.
Guest artists from the <LOCATION>Kirov</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Paris Opera</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Ballet</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>American
Ballet Theatre</ORGANIZATION>, Dance Theatre of <LOCATION>Harlem</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco Ballet</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Pacific
Northwest Ballet</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>) appeared alongside City Ballet dancers.
Thus, there was a multinational Apollo with the Danish/American <PERSON>Nilas
Martins</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Zhanna Ayupova</ORGANIZATION> (Kirov), <PERSON>Patricia Barker</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>Isabelle
Guerin</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>) as his muses. The sensation of the <TIME>evening</TIME> was <PERSON>Darcy Bussell</PERSON>
in the pas de deux from Agon (with <PERSON>Lindsay Fischer</PERSON>), proving that she is a
born <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON> dancer. In Who Cares? Viviana Durante danced 'The Man I
Love' with <PERSON>Robert LaFosse</PERSON> and <PERSON>Elizabeth Loscavio</PERSON> (<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>) spun
vertiginously through 'My One and Only.' At the end dancers and audience
joined in a vodka toast to <PERSON>Mr B.</PERSON> The waiter with the drinks for <PERSON>Peter
Martins</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Lincoln Kirstein</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Jerome Robbins</PERSON> was none other than <PERSON>Mikhail
Baryshnikov</PERSON>.
As <PERSON>Clement Crisp</PERSON> indicated, the heroines of this extraordinary marathon were
<PERSON>Kyra Nichols</PERSON> and <PERSON>Darci Kistler</PERSON>, to whom I would add <PERSON>Nichol Hlinka</PERSON>, who gave
a delicious account of <ORGANIZATION>Donizetti Variations</ORGANIZATION> with <PERSON>Nikolaj Haabbe</PERSON>, the
company's latest Danish recruit and of <ORGANIZATION>Columbine</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Harlequinade</LOCATION>, opposite a
mercurial <PERSON>Damian Woetzel</PERSON>, and, with <PERSON>Peter Boal</PERSON>, realised all the tragic
poetry of the Divertimento from 'Le Baiser de la fee'. It must be added that
some ballets were sadly undercast, most conspicuously when <PERSON>Nilas Martins</PERSON>,
the son of <PERSON>Peter Martins</PERSON>, ballet master in chief, attempted roles like
Orpheus and Apollo.
There is a dwindling number of dancers in the principal ranks who knew
<PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON>. The next generation will come from the <ORGANIZATION>School of American
Ballet</ORGANIZATION>, whose senior students also danced a selection of <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON> excerpts
in this year's 'Workshop' performances, as well as one complete ballet,
<ORGANIZATION>Symphonie Concertante</ORGANIZATION>, in acknowledgment of the fact that it was originally
made for the school, in <DATE>1945</DATE>. <DATE>Nearly 50 years later</DATE>, the very promising
<PERSON>Rachel Rutherford</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tara Keim</PERSON> danced the leading roles. Rutherford,
partnered by the elegant <PERSON>Peter Hansen</PERSON>, was also ravishing in 'Tales from the
<LOCATION>Vienna Woods</LOCATION>' from <LOCATION>Vienna Waltzes</LOCATION>.
Symphonie Concertante was also in the repertory of American Ballet Theatre
this year at the <ORGANIZATION>Metropolitan Opera House</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Kevin McKenzie</PERSON>, the highly
respected dancer who has taken over the artistic direction, announced before
the season that he intended to take the company back to its old policy of
emphasising the 'theatre' aspect of the company's title. No brand-new works
were given, but the company took into its repertory <PERSON>Kenneth MacMillan</PERSON>'s
<PERSON>Manon</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Christian Holder</ORGANIZATION>'s Les Liaisons dangereuses. Concerning the
latter, I can only echo <ORGANIZATION>Clement Crisp</ORGANIZATION>'s remark about <PERSON>Glen Tetley</PERSON>'s La Ronde:
'it lasts - was that all? - 50 minutes.' Manon is probably the best of
<ORGANIZATION>MacMillan</ORGANIZATION>'s full-length ballets, certainly the one most accessible to
companies other than the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Ballet</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Alessandra Ferri</PERSON> and <PERSON>Cynthia Harvey</PERSON>
have both danced the title role there, and are thoroughly at home in it.
<PERSON>Ferri</PERSON> was partnered by <PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON>, not the subtlest of dance actors. But
the supporting company, led by such artists as <PERSON>Gil Boggs</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Wallace</PERSON>
(who both danced <PERSON>Lescaut</PERSON>), <PERSON>Kathleen Moore</PERSON>, <PERSON>Victor Barbee</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Ethan Brown</PERSON>,
showed that they can form an acting ensemble worthy of comparison with the
<ORGANIZATION>Royal Ballet</ORGANIZATION> itself.
The revival of <PERSON>David Blair</PERSON>'s production of <ORGANIZATION>Swan Lake</ORGANIZATION> looked rather dated,
but it is at least a straightforward rendering of the traditional
choreography. <PERSON>Nina Ananiashvili</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bocca</PERSON> gave it the old fashioned star
treatment, neither to their own nor to the ballet's advantage. Otherwise, it
was the ballets with the highest dance values that came off best, notably
<PERSON>Ashton</PERSON>'s Symphonic Variations and <PERSON>Mark Morris</PERSON>'s Drink to me only with thine
eyes.
Another <PERSON>Mark Morris</PERSON> work was seen in the brief season at the <ORGANIZATION>City Center of
Les Grands Ballets Canadiens</ORGANIZATION>: Paukenschlag, to <ORGANIZATION>Haydn</ORGANIZATION>'s Symphony No. 94 (the
'Surprise'). Morris is sometimes criticised for being too close to the
music, but what he does in a ballet like this is wittily and inventively to
clarify the music's structure.
Morris has been busily turning out new pieces for his own company, which
will be seen later in the <DATE>summer</DATE> at <LOCATION>Edinburgh</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ   United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7922 Theatrical Producers and Services.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 15
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900509-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-09-90 0929EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-Dance     05-09 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Dance,0471</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two NY Premieres and Fracci at Ballet Theater</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Ballet Theater dancers looked wonderful
on the second night of the company's season at the Metropolitan
Opera. The program was two <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> premieres, a dazzling ``Black
Swan'' pas de deux and ``Lilac Garden'' starring <PERSON>Carla Fracci</PERSON>.
   The Italian ballerina returned to <ORGANIZATION>American Ballet Theater</ORGANIZATION> as a
guest to perform in an excerpt from ``Lilac Garden'' at <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s
gala opening and the entire <PERSON>Antony Tudor</PERSON> ballet on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   The entire ballet, to <PERSON>Chausson</PERSON>'s ``Poeme,'' was as achingly
romantic as it is meant to be. The young bride-to-be, danced by
<PERSON>Miss Fracci</PERSON> with subtlety and gentle beauty, is stoical but
suffering because in love with a younger man. He was danced with
romantic yearning by <PERSON>Kevin McKenzie</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Ross Stretton</PERSON> as the Man She Must Marry was stiff with his
bride-to-be but softer when he met An Episode in His Past in the
lilac garden. She, danced by <PERSON>Martine Van Hamel</PERSON>, seemed a strong
survivor but she was hurting, too.
   The evening began with ``Birthday Offering,'' which <PERSON>Frederick
Ashton</PERSON> choreographed for the 25th anniversary of the <ORGANIZATION>British Royal
Ballet</ORGANIZATION>. It gives important solos to seven ballerinas, showing each
one's strength. Ballet Theater added it to its repertory last
<DATE>October</DATE> in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the star ballerina was <PERSON>Susan Jaffe</PERSON>, partnered by
<PERSON>Stretton</PERSON>. The others were <PERSON>Cheryl Yeager</PERSON>, <PERSON>Amanda McKerrow</PERSON>, <PERSON>Julie
Kent</PERSON>, <PERSON>Leslie Browne</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alessandra Ferri</PERSON> and <PERSON>Christine Dunham</PERSON>. All
looked good.
   <PERSON>Fernando Bujones</PERSON>, back this season as a guest, having been
greatly missed, and <PERSON>Cynthia Harvey</PERSON> danced the ``Black Swan'' pas de
deux. Both were in the highest, exciting form. Toward the end of
the duet, <PERSON>Miss Harvey</PERSON> danced only 16 of the famous 32 fouettes,
whipped-leg turns. The audience murmured, fearing she had felt a
muscle tear, but she finished the duet flawlessly.
   The evening ended with the half-hour ``Brief Fling'' which <PERSON>Twyla
Tharp</PERSON> choreographed for the company. This eclectic, quite enjoyable
ballet had its premiere in <DATE>February</DATE> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   In it, <PERSON>Cheryl Yeager</PERSON> and <PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON>, in <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>, do formal ballet
dancing to ``I'm a Little Teapot'' played on amplified piano.
Shelley <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, loose-limbed as <PERSON>Miss Tharp</PERSON> was as a dancer,
looked like an urchin being tossed around by <PERSON>Jamie Bishton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kevin
O'Day</PERSON> and <PERSON>Keith Roberts</PERSON> in mini-kilts. <PERSON>Claudia Alfieri</PERSON>, <PERSON>Isabella
Padovani</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gil Boggs</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Wallace</PERSON> wore red plaid.
   During the 10 sections of ``Brief Fling'' there also was a jig
and music which sounded like minimalism meeting a cement mixer. The
music was by <PERSON>Michel Colombier</PERSON>. Clever costumes were by <PERSON>Isaac
Mizrahi</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Dennis Cleveland</PERSON> played the violin solo in ``Lilac Garden.'' The
orchestra sounded thin, as though too small for the requirements of
the music.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06088236 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06088236 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: American Ballet Theater's performance of 'Sinfonietta' was one
of the more successful works in a mixed program.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-FRANCISCO; DANCE; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE NEW American Ballet Theater and the bad old ABT jockeyed for supremacy at
the company's opening Tuesday, parading a most discomfiting case of artistic
split personality to the gala crowd.;    On the one hand, there was "Ballet
Imperial," a piece of routine Balanchine, in a slipshod performance that
looked as if the corps had last rehearsed it a year ago.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ABT IS CAUGHT AT CROSS-PURPOSES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Dance Review  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     On the other, there was the commanding "Sinfonietta," a <DATE>1978</DATE> work by Czech
choreographer <PERSON>Jiri Kylian</PERSON>, just acquired by <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> for the current season.;   
And in between, there was "Other Dances," an exquisite <PERSON>Jerome Robbins</PERSON>
miniature, danced to perfection but programmed for the wrong reasons.;    It's
not fashionable to like the neo-romantic <PERSON>Kylian</PERSON> these days, but I love his
gleaming physical response to complex music. This piece, like "Forgotten Land"
(in <LOCATION>San Francisco Ballet</LOCATION>'s repertory), is set in a wide, allusive landscape,
which it pulls down to human scale by discovering real emotions in its
abstract world.;    "Sinfonietta" calls for a chamber company of seven couples
-- small forces to challenge the brooding, brass-heavy score by <PERSON>Kylian</PERSON>'s
countryman, <PERSON>Leos Janacek</PERSON>. This magnificent piece calls for 25 brass players,
including 12 (!) trumpets. Unfortunately, either there weren't enough strings
for all this brazen glory, or else the pit muffled them. The performance,
though sensitively led by <PERSON>Jack Everly</PERSON>, seemed a bit thin.;    <PERSON>Kylian</PERSON>'s dancers
shape this sound into movement with a breathtaking combination of exuberance
and yearning, their springy, sinewy leaps seemingly suspended in mid-air.
Unlike "Forgotten Land," whose movements come from the ebb and flow of the
tide against the shore, this piece is grounded in the earth's energy -- like
the mythological giant <ORGANIZATION>Antaeus</ORGANIZATION>, who literally renewed his strength every time
he made contact with his mother, Gaia (the earth).;    Everything about the
piece added to its powerful beauty, from the performances -- all so resonant
that I can't single any out -- to the simple, almost monastic costumes (by
<PERSON>Walter Nobbe</PERSON>) to the aquarelle backdrop (also by Nobbe). Under <PERSON>Joop Caboort</PERSON>'s
lighting, this striated, horizontal landscape was sometimes arid, sometimes
verdant.;    "Other Dances" replaced <PERSON>Mark Morris</PERSON>' wonderful "Drink to Me Only
With Thine Eyes" because the estate of the woman who commissioned the former
work in <DATE>1976</DATE> -- the retired ballerina <PERSON>Eugenia Delarova Doll</PERSON>, who died last
year -- just gave <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> to <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>. Money not only talks, it seems, but also
sometimes dances.;    However, barring the slavishness of the gesture, it's a
lovely suite for two well-tuned dancers -- here, <PERSON>Alessandra Ferri</PERSON> and <PERSON>Julio
Bocca</PERSON>, worthy successors to <PERSON>Natalia Makarova</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mikhail Baryshnikov</PERSON>, for whom
it was made.;    <PERSON>Paul Connelly</PERSON>, who is one of the conductors vying for the San
Jose Symphony post, played the score -- four mazurkas and a waltz by Chopin --
beautifully, though one wished the piano had been as well tuned as the
dancers.;    Let's not dwell on "Ballet Imperial" (<DATE>1941</DATE>), except to say that
<PERSON>Susan Jaffe</PERSON> was the only real dancer on stage. <PERSON>Jaffe</PERSON>, who is married to
<LOCATION>Connelly</LOCATION>, substituted for the indisposed <LOCATION>Cynthia Harvey.</LOCATION>;    I don't know what
those other 30 folks were doing up there, except going through the motions.
<PERSON>Ricardo Bustamante</PERSON>, the cavalier, performed with a long-suffering expression,
while poor <PERSON>Amanda McKerrow</PERSON>, a charming dancer, was imprisoned in a pink tutu
that washed out her pale coloring.;    The rest of the ballet suits its score,
<ORGANIZATION>Tchaikovsky</ORGANIZATION>'s grand and empty Piano Concerto No. 2. Instead of taking a bow,
pianist <PERSON>Michael Boriskin</PERSON> should have spent intermission in the pit with a
broom, sweeping up all the notes he dropped.;    <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>'s revival of "Coppelia"
-- <PERSON>Enrique Martinez</PERSON>'s <DATE>1968</DATE> choreography gussied up with new sets and costumes
-- opens tonight. The company performs in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> through <DATE>April 7.</DATE>; 
American Ballet Theater; '<ORGANIZATION>Coppelia</ORGANIZATION>'; When: 8 <DATE>tonight-Friday</DATE>, 2 and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Saturday-Sunday</DATE>; Where: <ORGANIZATION>War Memorial Opera House</ORGANIZATION>, 301 <LOCATION>Van Ness Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>; Tickets: <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$65</MONEY>. (415) 621-3838  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JUDITH GREEN, Mercury News Dance Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910328  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  665  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday March 28, 1991
00088236,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06084164 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06084164 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (4); PHOTO: Cynthia Harvey will dance in 'La Bayadere,' above, and
'Coppelia' during the San Francisco visit; PHOTO: Co-director Jane Hermann has
been running the company.; PHOTO: Sylvie Guillem dances the title role in 'La
Bayadere.'; PHOTO: French ballerina Sylvie Guillem, here in 'Swan Lake,' makes
her American Ballet Theater debut as the company's only guest artist this
season.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  DANCE; THEATER; US; TRIP; SHOW; SAN-FRANCISCO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE trouble with anniversaries is that the day after each one is the first day
of the rest of your life. American Ballet Theater, which will play San
Francisco this week and next, found this out after its 25th, its 30th, its
40th and last year after its 50th birthday.;    This is the off-year: an
asymmetrical, unround 51. It's a year of questions about identity and artistic
direction, and, of course, financial woes. (So how is that different from any
other dance company in America?)  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Arts &amp; Books  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TOEING THE LINE
A MORE MODEST ABT MAKES ITS ANNUAL VISIT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Dance  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The finances have had more impact than the company likes to admit. Once the
most traveled ballet in the world, <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> has pulled back its tours to just a few
key cities. Its repertory, geared to splashy, big-budget ballets for
star-struck audiences, is even less consequential than in some other years:
The company can't afford to challenge its patrons.;    The question of
artistic leadership continues to bedevil <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>. Ever since <PERSON>Mikhail Baryshnikov</PERSON>
quit in a huff just as plans for the 50th-anniversary gala were set in motion,
the dance world has wondered who is running the company. It is, in fact, being
run by co-director <PERSON>Jane Hermann</PERSON>, but no one wants to believe this is more than
a temporary situation -- except <PERSON>Hermann</PERSON>, an arts administrator who; controls
casting and chooses repertory as if she had come up through the ranks of
dance.;    In the meantime, many of the promises made last <DATE>fall</DATE>, when <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>
announced its <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> season, have melted. The roster of guests is down
to just one: <PERSON>Sylvie Guillem</PERSON>, the long-stemmed French ballerina who will make
her <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> debut as the company plays <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Orange County</ORGANIZATION>. Farukh
Ruzimatov of the <ORGANIZATION>Leningrad Kirov Ballet</ORGANIZATION>, announced with fanfare, isn't coming.
Andris Liepa of the <ORGANIZATION>Bolshoi Ballet</ORGANIZATION> parted company with <PERSON>Hermann</PERSON> more than a
year ago and went back to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union.</LOCATION>;    Because principal dancer <PERSON>Clark
Tippet</PERSON> is not well, his new ballet isn't ready, and he is the only in-house
choreographer in the company, which once presented the newest ballets of major
choreographers before the ink had dried.;    The repertory for the <DATE>1991</DATE> tour
includes two full-length ballets: the charming "Coppelia" (Thursday-next
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>) and the languorous "La Bayadere" ("The Temple Dancer") (<DATE>April</DATE> 5-7).;  
 "Coppelia," a favorite of <LOCATION>San Jose Cleveland Ballet</LOCATION> audiences, who saw it in
<DATE>1989</DATE> and <DATE>1990</DATE>, is a comic ballet about a life-size mechanical doll who causes
havoc between the lovers Franz and Swanilda.;    This production is billed as
"new," but it's a revival of the <DATE>1968</DATE> staging by ballet master emeritus
<PERSON>Enrique Martinez</PERSON>, after <PERSON>Arthur St.-Leon</PERSON>'s 1870 original. The music is by <PERSON>Leo
Delibes</PERSON>. There are new costumes and scenery by Tony Award-winning designers
<PERSON>Patricia Zipprodt</PERSON> ("Sweet Charity" and "Cabaret") and <PERSON>Tony Straiges</PERSON> ("Into the
Woods" and "<DATE>Sunday</DATE> in the Park With George").;    The roles of <ORGANIZATION>Swanilda</ORGANIZATION> and
Franz will be danced by <PERSON>Cheryl Yeager</PERSON> and <PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON> (<DATE>Thursday</DATE> and <DATE>Saturday</DATE>);
<PERSON>Amanda McKerrow</PERSON> and <PERSON>Danilo Radojevic</PERSON> (<DATE>Friday</DATE>); <PERSON>Cynthia Harvey</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wes Chapman</PERSON>
(<DATE>Saturday</DATE> matinee); <PERSON>Marianna Tcherkassky</PERSON> and <PERSON>Johan Renvall</PERSON> (next <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s
matinee); and <PERSON>Cynthia Gregory</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jeremy Collins</PERSON> (next <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>).;   
<PERSON>Dr. Coppelius</PERSON>, the crackpot toy-maker who has built the almost-human doll,
traditionally steals the show, and he probably will next <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, when
<PERSON>Michael Smuin</PERSON>, former director of <LOCATION>San Francisco Ballet</LOCATION>, returns to his <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>
roots to perform the role. Coppelius also will be performed by <PERSON>Terrence Orr</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Gil Boggs</PERSON> and <PERSON>Victor Barbee.</PERSON>;    "La Bayadere" is a revival of <PERSON>Natalia
Makarova</PERSON>'s staging, which when new was the first full-length production of
this classic Russian imperial ballet to be performed by a Western company. Its
showpiece is the opening of Act II, "The Kingdom of the Shades," whose slow,
repeated arabesques are a litmus test for the women of the corps. Many people
who know little about ballet will recognize this sequence, for it was the
image that ran beneath the title credits of the film "The Turning Point.";   
<PERSON>Guillem</PERSON> will dance the title role, with <PERSON>Kevin McKenzie</PERSON> as her lover and <PERSON>Susan
Jaffe</PERSON> as the wicked <PERSON>Gamzatti</PERSON>, <DATE>April 5</DATE>. Other casts are: <PERSON>Tcherkassky</PERSON>, <PERSON>Radojevic</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON> (<DATE>April 6</DATE> matinee and <DATE>April 7</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>); <PERSON>Jaffe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ricardo Bustamante</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Leslie Browne</PERSON> (<DATE>April 6</DATE>); <PERSON>McKerrow</PERSON>, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Christine Dunham</PERSON> (<DATE>April 7</DATE>
matinee).;    The company's mixed repertory has been kept reasonably compact
for this tour: two programs, with one alteration in the second.;    The first,
to be seen <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, includes <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON>'s "Ballet Imperial," a
tribute to the Russian tradition, set to <ORGANIZATION>Tchaikovsky's Piano Concerto No.</ORGANIZATION> 1;
<PERSON>Mark Morris</PERSON>' "Drink to Me Only With Thine Eyes," a beautiful company
showpiece, which replaces Tippet's unfinished ballet; and <PERSON>Jiri Kylian</PERSON>'s
setting of <PERSON>Leos Janacek</PERSON>'s virile "Sinfonietta.";    The second, to be seen
<DATE>April 2-4</DATE>, includes Sir <PERSON>Kenneth MacMillan</PERSON>'s "Concerto," to music of <PERSON>Dmitri
Shostakovich</PERSON>; and <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON>'s "Brief Fling." On <DATE>April 2</DATE> and 4, the program
will include "Fall River Legend," <PERSON>Agnes de Mille</PERSON>'s dramatic retelling of the
<PERSON>Lizzie Borden</PERSON> story; on <DATE>April 3</DATE>, the program will finish with Act II (the swan
scene) of "Swan Lake," in <PERSON>David Blair</PERSON>'s <DATE>1966</DATE> setting.;    <PERSON>Cynthia Gregory</PERSON>, who
often performs with <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Cleveland Ballet</ORGANIZATION> as a guest artist, will dance
the Swan Queen, with <PERSON>Peter Morrison</PERSON> as the Prince and <PERSON>Michael Owen as
Rothbart</PERSON>, the sorcerer. She will also play <PERSON>Lizzie</PERSON> in the <DATE>April 4</DATE> performance
of "Fall River Legend." The cast for <DATE>April 2</DATE> is yet to be announced.;   
Opening night of "Coppelia" is a benefit for <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>, with the top tickets priced
at <MONEY>$150</MONEY>-<MONEY>$200</MONEY>. For these special tickets, which include pre- and
post-performance events, call (212) 477-3030.;    The <DATE>April 2</DATE> mixed-rep
performance is a benefit for six Bay Area AIDS relief agencies. Tickets are
<MONEY>$20</MONEY>-<MONEY>$500</MONEY>, available from (415) 621-6557. (box);  American Ballet Theater;
Opens: <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>; Through: <DATE>April 7</DATE>; Where: War Memorial <ORGANIZATION>Opera House</ORGANIZATION>, 301 <LOCATION>Van
Ness Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; Tickets: <MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$65</MONEY>; (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JUDITH GREEN, Mercury News Dance Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910324  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,061  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday March 24, 1991
00084164,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022290-0202 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 180024 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 22, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 5; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
863 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DANCE REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
ABT'S BIRTHDAY BASH HITS THE ROAD 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARTIN BERNHEIMER, TIMES MUSIC/DANCE CRITIC 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN FRANCISCO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The massive party took place last month at the <ORGANIZATION>Metropolitan Opera House</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New 
York</LOCATION> when American Ballet Theatre celebrated its 50th birthday. No one 
pretended that the event was coherent, but a lot of push-button sentimentalists 
enjoyed the glitzy rituals. 
</P>
<P>
This, after all, was a very big socio-aesthetic deal. A good seat cost <MONEY>$1,200</MONEY>. 
The on-stage guest list included such bona fide ballerinas as <PERSON>Alicia Alonso</PERSON> 
(dancing in the face of dotage), <PERSON>Carla Fracci</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gelsey Kirkland</PERSON> and <PERSON>Natalia 
Makarova</PERSON>. Agnes de <ORGANIZATION>Mille</ORGANIZATION> contributed a few testy words. <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON> made a 
surprise appearance shoving a delirious danseur out of her epochal "Push." 
</P>
<P>
Only one beloved body was conspicuously missing. It belonged to <PERSON>Mikhail 
Baryshnikov</PERSON>, who had abandoned his company in the wake of a major managerial 
imbroglio. 
</P>
<P>
Whether his self-imposed absence made the collective heart grow fonder became a 
moot point. <PERSON>Fernando Bujones</PERSON>, a rival matinee idol, provided compensation of 
sorts, returning to the fold from which he had been ousted. Moreover, one could 
find distraction in home movies, production numbers, nostalgia indulgences and 
orgies of self-congratulation. 
</P>
<P>
Had all gone as planned, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> would have caught up with some 
manifestation of the anniversary festivities this <DATE>summer</DATE>. The projected <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> 
engagement at the <PERSON>Dorothy Chandler Pavilion</PERSON> was canceled, however, when the 
<ORGANIZATION>Music Center</ORGANIZATION> failed to reconcile an unfortunate booking dispute with the 
company. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Ergo</ORGANIZATION>, the version of the historic event mustered <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night at the <ORGANIZATION>War 
Memorial Opera House</ORGANIZATION> provided <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> with its only exposure to the great 
balletic bash. As the ever-perverse fates would have it, alas, this Gala didn't 
turn out to be particularly gala. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> got the economy-size road-show version. The top ticket fetched a 
paltry <MONEY>$250</MONEY>. The only live guest in sight was <PERSON>Makarova</PERSON>, who, having finally 
hung up her toe shoes, rambled through some charming, ultra-affectionate 
anecdotes. Not incidentally, <PERSON>Bujones</PERSON> had been promised by <PERSON>Jane Hermann</PERSON>, the new 
executive director, but he didn't show. 
</P>
<P>
Each half of the three-hour would-be extravaganza began with a razzle-dazzle 
overture energetically conducted by <PERSON>Jack Everly</PERSON>. Then came tantalizing -- and 
frustrating -- collages of film clips. Some were ancient and some recent, some 
rare and some commonplace. 
</P>
<P>
The often fuzzy, nearly subliminal images on the screen flitted forward and 
backward in time, reducing significant art to stream-of-consciousness snippets. 
The musical pastiches on the sound track sometimes forced the protagonists to 
dance to the wrong tune. The uncredited, hyperbolic narration, voiced-over by 
<PERSON>Peter Donat</PERSON>, proved notable neither for good grammar nor for good taste. 
</P>
<P>
When it came to show time, the company mustered a little bit of this, and a 
tiny bit of that. The dancers plucked highlights from highlights, strung 
together in willy-nilly chaos. Place the accent on nilly. 
</P>
<P>
The viewer was allowed no sense of context. No continuity. No edification. No 
substance. 
</P>
<P>
Turning 50, <ORGANIZATION>American Ballet Theatre</ORGANIZATION> turned to a slick collection of variety 
acts. The tone was flashy, the pace fast, fast, fast. Here was another fancy 
installment in the annals of balletic vaudeville, conceived and directed by 
<PERSON>Michael Smuin</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Finding specific things to savor in the hippety-hop jumble seemed akin to 
picking the peanuts out of a box of <ORGANIZATION>Cracker Jack</ORGANIZATION>. One's hands got sticky, yet 
the rewards -- beyond indigestion -- remained small. 
</P>
<P>
The company performed chunklets of 25 repertory items frantically, and often 
well. Although <PERSON>Baryshnikov</PERSON>'s dancers may not command instantly compelling 
personalities, they are strong technicians and careful stylists. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Amanda McKerrow</PERSON>, sympathetically supported by <PERSON>Kevin McKenzie</PERSON>, floated 
exquisitely through a moment from <PERSON>Antony Tudor</PERSON>'s "The Leaves Are Fading." 
<PERSON>Alessandra Ferri</PERSON>, sensitively partnered by <PERSON>John Gardner</PERSON>, arched poignantly amid 
the "Lindenduft" of <PERSON>Eliot Feld</PERSON>'s "At Midnight," and ignored a chronically 
off-pitch mezzo-soprano in the process. <PERSON>Susan Jaffe</PERSON>, nobly seconded by <PERSON>Ricardo 
Bustamante</PERSON>, exuded lyric refinement as the White Swan. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Johan Renvall</PERSON> glittered as the Bronze Idol of "La Bayadere." <PERSON>Julio Bocca</PERSON> 
gobbled space ferociously as Solor, and <PERSON>Cynthia Harvey</PERSON> breathed refinement as 
his <PERSON>Gamzatti</PERSON>. <PERSON>Martine van Hamel</PERSON> defined <LOCATION>Petipa</LOCATION> grandeur as <ORGANIZATION>Raymonda</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Cynthia 
Gregory</PERSON>, the obvious audience favorite, sustained the poetic balances of the 
Rose Adagio even better in the flesh than she had on the screen. 
</P>
<P>
No one, unfortunately, had a chance to establish a serious interpretive 
statement. There was no time to set, much less develop, a specific mood. 
Everything and everyone passed in a pretty blink. 
</P>
<P>
The choreography of "La Sylphide" melted into "Giselle," which blurred into 
"The Sleeping Beauty." Tudor got scrambled, <PERSON>Baryshnikov</PERSON> got slighted, and, 
inexplicably, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> Tippet got snubbed. 
</P>
<P>
At the end, <ORGANIZATION>Smuin &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> trivialized <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON>'s "Theme and Variations," 
transforming the elegant finale into a motley costume parade. This act of 
violence heralded the arrival of tinsel streamers, balloons and curtain calls 
for the anonymous administrators. 
</P>
<P>
The applause wasn't deafening. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, The final bows at the American Ballet Theatre Gala, as presented Tuesday 
in San Francisco. FRED MERTZ / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Dance Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900613-0138
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900613-0138.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Dance:
   Baryshnikov Repudiated
   ----
   By Dale Harris
</HL>
<DATE>
06/13/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   New York -- According to the power press here, American
Ballet Theatre currently is in the process of "reclaiming its
soul." "Soul," of course, has never been easy to define.
However, in this case it probably signifies little more than
the state of bliss in which, according to some, ABT existed
before 1980. That year Mikhail Baryshnikov took over as
director from Lucia Chase and Oliver Smith and, many believe,
betrayed the company's spirit.
   Among those who subscribe to this view of ABT's recent
history, it would appear, are Jane Hermann and Oliver Smith,
the team that supplanted Mr. Baryshnikov last year.
Apparently forgetting that Mr. Baryshnikov was brought in to
rescue ABT from the artistic chaos to which his immediate
predecessors had reduced it, Ms. Hermann and Mr. Smith now
are busy trying to dismantle his accomplishments.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   To this end, they have repudiated <PERSON>Mr. Baryshnikov</PERSON>'s
attempts to create a genuine ensemble in place of what was
essentially a showcase for visiting stars; his efforts to
extend the company's artistic reach by engaging modern-dance
choreographers such as <PERSON>Merce Cunningham</PERSON>, <PERSON>Twyla Tharp</PERSON>, <PERSON>Karole
Armitage</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mark Morris</PERSON>; his partiality for the ballets of
<PERSON>George Balanchine</PERSON>; his determination to place greater
emphasis on classical than on demi-caractere dancing. While
there hasn't been enough time for the new administration to
eradicate all evidence of its predecessor's taste -- the
general outlines of <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>'s current season at the <ORGANIZATION>Metropolitan
Opera House</ORGANIZATION> were devised by <PERSON>Mr. Baryshnikov</PERSON> before his
precipitous departure -- the artistic orientation of <PERSON>Ms.
Hermann</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON> has begun to manifest itself.
   For one thing, guest artists, abjured for the most part
since <DATE>1980</DATE>, are again very much in evidence. <PERSON>Fernando
Bujones</PERSON>, who left <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> after a disagreement with <PERSON>Mr.
Baryshnikov</PERSON>, returned for "Black Swan," "Giselle" and "The
Sleeping Beauty." In the last, he partnered <PERSON>Ludmila
Semenyaka</PERSON>, flown in from the <LOCATION>U.S.S.R.</LOCATION> at short notice to
replace an injured <PERSON>Cynthia Gregory</PERSON>. <PERSON>Ekaterina Maximova</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Vladimir Vasiliev</PERSON>, from the <LOCATION>Bolshoi</LOCATION>, danced a single
"Giselle," and <PERSON>Ms. Maximova</PERSON> also performed <PERSON>Mr. Vasiliev</PERSON>'s
brief "Elegie."
   None of these appearances were exactly satisfying: <PERSON>Ms.
Maximova</PERSON>, after all, is 51, and <PERSON>Mr. Vasiliev</PERSON> 50. <PERSON>Mr. Bujones</PERSON>,
though merely 35, also has passed his zenith. As for <PERSON>Ms.
Semenyaka</PERSON>, her dancing is only too clearly characterized by
the unmusicality and technical weaknesses of <LOCATION>Leningrad</LOCATION>'s
Kirov, where she began her career, and the affectations of
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Bolshoi</LOCATION>, where she is the ranking ballerina.
   Whether or not such guests are good for the box office is
far from certain. That they are bad for the company's
artistic standing can hardly be doubted. Not only do they
undermine what remains of the stylistic coherence <PERSON>Mr.
Baryshnikov</PERSON> was trying to instill into <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>, they also serve
to derogate the importance of choreography. Like the old
duumvirate, the new one prefers to promote the cult of
personality over the art of dance. To see the shambles <PERSON>Ms.
Semenyaka</PERSON> made of the text -- not to mention the spirit -- of
"The Sleeping Beauty" should be warning enough of the dire
consequences of casting by publicity value instead of
capability. <PERSON>Ms. Maximova</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Vasiliev</PERSON> are artistically
far superior to <PERSON>Ms. Semenyaka</PERSON>, but they have little to offer
a company in desperate need of aesthetic direction.
   <PERSON>Ms. Maximova</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Vasiliev</PERSON> at least excited the
audience, many of whom, no doubt, remembered the pair from
their days of glory. <PERSON>Ms. Semenyaka</PERSON>, on the other hand, left
the house cold. So, invariably, does the company's newly
engaged premier danseur <PERSON>Faruk Ruzimatov</PERSON>, formerly of the
Kirov Ballet. <PERSON>Mr. Ruzimatov</PERSON> made his <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> debut with the
company in "Giselle," followed two weeks later by "Bayadere,
Act II." Both roles cruelly expose his technical weakness.
They also expose his lack of magnetism.
   It's true that the very first sight of him is enough to
produce gasps from the audience, an expectant hush, a round
of applause. But, then, few dancers at <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION> have ever adopted
so startlingly tragic a demeanor, kept their mouths so
constantly open, as if in perpetual self-astonishment, or
worn such heavy eye makeup. It's when <PERSON>Mr. Ruzimatov</PERSON> starts to
dance that the enthusiasm dwindles -- as it noticeably did on
both occasions.
   In <PERSON>Balanchine</PERSON>'s "Theme and Variations" and, especially,
"Stravinsky Violin Concerto," <PERSON>Mr. Ruzimatov</PERSON> fell even
flatter. The technical demands made by abstract works like
these cannot be finessed by adopting an air of tragic
suffering -- as to some extent they can be in certain
narrative or situational ballets -- and the Soviet dancer was
forced to simplify the steps in a way that sabotaged the
choreographer's patent intentions. In "Stravinsky Violin
Concerto," there was a certain amount of diversion in seeing
someone so completely out of place -- <PERSON>Mr. Ruzimatov</PERSON> danced
this bracingly astringent work as if he were thinking about
the Last Judgment -- but that was hardly enough to save the
performance. The engagement of the ex-Kirov dancer looks all
too symptomatic of the new directors' inability to see where
their priorities lie. Instead of ensuring that the talented
dancers already in the company are properly nurtured, they
prefer to scour the <LOCATION>U.S.S.R.</LOCATION> for a possible box-office
sensation, whether the dancer in question is good or bad.
   Among those on <ORGANIZATION>ABT</ORGANIZATION>'s regular roster in need of guidance is
