<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-35218 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes035_m_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-035 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> JORDAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   King Hosts Yemeni Accord Signing Ceremony </TI></H3>
<H4>   Signatories of Accord Document Listed </H4>
<F P=102> JN2002174594 Amman Jordan Television Network in Arabic 1450 
GMT 20 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> JN2002174594 </F>
<F P=104>  Amman Jordan Television Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Arabic </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [List of members of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Political Forces Dialogue </F>
Committee</ORGANIZATION>, Yemeni political parties, and organizations 
designated as signatories of the Yemeni document of pledge and 
accord, read by <PERSON>Ahmad Jabir 'Afif</PERSON>, rapporteur of the <ORGANIZATION>Dialogue 
Committee</ORGANIZATION>, on 20 <DATE>February</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Hashemite Court</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Amman</LOCATION> 
--live] 
  [Text] In the name of God, the merciful, the 
compassionate. The following are the names of the brother 
members of the <ORGANIZATION>Political Forces Dialogue Committee</ORGANIZATION>, listed 
alphabetically: 
  Ahmad Jabir 'Afif; 
  Isma'il Bin-Ahmad al-Wazir; 
  <PERSON>Anis Hasan Yahya</PERSON> 'Awad; 
  Ahmad 'Abd-al-Rahman Qarhash; 
  Ahmad Kalaz; 
  <ORGANIZATION>Jarallah Sa</ORGANIZATION>'d 'Umar Muhammad Mus'id 'Umar; 
  Haydar Abu-Bakr al-'Attas; 
  <PERSON>Husayn Sharaf</PERSON> al-Kibsi; 
  <PERSON>Hammud Hashim</PERSON> 'Abdallah al-Dharihi; 
  <PERSON>Salim Hasan</PERSON> al-Ma'mari; 
  Sadiq 'Ali al-Dabab; 
  <PERSON>Salih Nasir Nasran</PERSON>; 
  Salah Bin-Ahmad Fulaytah; 
  'Abd-al-'Aziz 'Abd-al-Ghani; 
  'Abd-al-Wahhab Ahmad al-Anisi; 
  'Abd-al-Qadir Hasan Muhammad al-Qiyari; 
  'Abd-al-Quddus Yaha al-Midwahi; 
  'Abd-al-Karim 'Ali Yahya al-Iryani; 
  'Abdallah Ahmad Ghanim; 
  'Abdallah Salih al-Bar; 
  'Abdallah Muhsin al-Akwa'; 
  'Abd-al-Wahid Hawwash; 
  'Umar 'Abdallah al-Lijawi; 
  <PERSON>Fadl Muhsin</PERSON> 'Abdallah; 
  Muhsin Muhammad Abu-Bakr Bin al-Farid; 
  Muhammad Ragh Sa'id; 
  Muhammad 'Abdallah al-Busayyil; 
  Muhammad 'Abd-al-Malik al-Mutawakkil; 
  <PERSON>Yahya Muhammad al-Shami</PERSON>. 
  Secretaries or heads of the political parties and 
organizations, listed alphabetically: 
  <PERSON>Ahmad Muhammad al-Shami</PERSON>, secretary general of the al-Haqq 
[Right] Party; 
  <PERSON>Hamud Muhammad Baydar</PERSON>, secretary general of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni 
Revolution Strugglers Organization</ORGANIZATION>; 
  <PERSON>Khalid Fadl Mansur</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Unionist Grouping 
Party</ORGANIZATION>; 
  <PERSON>Sinan 'Abdallah Abu-Luhum</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>National Forces 
Union</ORGANIZATION>; 
  'Abd-al-Rahman '<PERSON>Ali Muhammad al-Jifidi</PERSON>, head of the League 
of the Sons of <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>; 
  'Abd-al-Malik 'Abd-al-Jalil al-Makhlafi, secretary general 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Nasirite Popular Unionist Organization</ORGANIZATION>; 
  <PERSON>Dr. Qasim Sallam</PERSON>, secretary of the <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> command of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Arab Socialist Ba</ORGANIZATION>'th Party; 
  <PERSON>Mujahid Yahya Abu-Shawarib</PERSON>, an independent. 
  Forgive me, brothers, I have inadvertently skipped the name 
of brother Ibrahim Bin-'Ali al-Wazir, secretary general of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Popular Forces Union</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-60433 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes101_j_94009" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-101 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  24 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ARABIAN PENINSULA </F>
<F P=101> Yemen </F>
<H3> <TI>   Ali Nasir Muhammad Rejects Post, Secession </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Ali Nasir Muhammad Rejects Post, Secession </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PM2405155994 London AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT in Arabic 24 May 94 p3 </F>
<F P=103> PM2405155994 </F>
<F P=104>  London AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by Salwa al-Ustuwani: "'Ali Nasir Rejects the <ORGANIZATION>New </F>
State</ORGANIZATION> in the South and Urges Cancellation of the Secession and 
Resumption of Dialogue"] 
  [Excerpts] <LOCATION>Damascus</LOCATION> -- '<PERSON>Ali Nasir Muhammad</PERSON>, former south 
Yemeni president, has confirmed the statement made by '<PERSON>Abdallah 
Ahmad Ghanim</PERSON>, the Yemeni justice minister in the <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION> 
government, to the effect that 'Ali Salim al-Bid had telephoned 
'<PERSON>Ali Nasir Muhammad</PERSON>, who lives in <LOCATION>Damascus</LOCATION>, and offered him the 
post of vice president in the Democratic Republic of <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> which 
was declared three days ago, on the basis that al-Bid would 
resign six months later and '<ORGANIZATION>Ali Nasir Muhammad</ORGANIZATION> would become 
head of state. 
  President '<PERSON>Ali Nasir Muhammad</PERSON> told AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT that he 
rejected the offer which he saw as tantamount to partition of 
<LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> which would be "a crime against unity." He added: "They 
tried to persuade me by all means in three contacts. I told 
them that I could not accept." He said that "'Ali Salim al-Bid 
offered to send today -- that is immediately -- a special plane 
to take me to him in <LOCATION>Hadramaut</LOCATION>. I refused and told him that I 
was prepared to return on certain conditions. The first was 
restoration of unity. And I said that I would be willing to 
work for a cease-fire and a return to dialogue and prevent the 
country's destruction. I asked him to postpone everything for 
48 hours, not to make any decisions, and revoke south <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>'s 
secession decision and return to dialogue and a cease-fire, and 
said that I would be willing to hold contacts with <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> to promote dialogue and understanding." 
  'Ali Nasir Muhammad added: "I rejected al-Bid's offer 
because I care about <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>'s unity and because I still maintain 
my principled position stated before and after these events, 
namely that I am opposed to infighting and secession. I 
emphasized in all their contacts with me and my contacts with 
them that the Yemeni solution must be within the framework of 
the unity state not outside it, that whatever the problems and 
mistakes encountered throughout the unity march, they did not 
justify secession at all, and that a distinction should be made 
between disagreement with the Yemeni president and the cause of 
<LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>'s unity. Individuals disappear but unity and the people 
live on." [passage omitted] 
  Asked what he thought were the chances of survival for south 
<LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>'s secession, he said "I can confirm that the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni 
Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION> [YSP] played a significant part, along with the 
other political groups and the <ORGANIZATION>General People's Congress</ORGANIZATION> [GPC], 
in achieving unity, that the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> derived its strength from its 
support for unity, and that abandoning unity now would mean 
suicide and would mean the end of the party." [passage omitted] 
  President '<PERSON>Ali Nasir Muhammad</PERSON> said that he did not know if 
the Gulf states or any state had any intention of recognizing 
the new south Yemeni state. He said they would have to think 
hard before taking such a step. 
  Commenting on (north) Yemeni President 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah 
Salih</PERSON>'s 
position on what has happened, '<PERSON>Ali Nasir Muhammad</PERSON> said: "In a 
telephone conversation I had with President <PERSON>Salih</PERSON> yesterday, he 
assured me that he would never accept the secession which is 
considered as high national treason, that there would be no 
going back on unity, that he would not accept the secession of 
the south as a fait accompli, and that he was prepared to hold a 
dialogue with the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> or with the unionist forces within the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> 
to rescue <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> and its unity. I, in turn, stressed to him the 
need for a dialogue with the unionist forces in the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> and 
asked him to keep the door open for dialogue despite the wounds." 
  The former Yemeni president also said: "I am now 
endeavoring and trying, along with some of the people who 
support unity and who are loyal to the Yemeni people, to promote 
such a dialogue between President 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON> and the 
<ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION>. That is what I am working for in my current contacts." 
  Asked if Arab mediation has been suspended, he said: "There 
is no Arab mediation. There is <ORGANIZATION>Arab League</ORGANIZATION> mediation. Arab 
<ORGANIZATION>League Secretary General Dr.</ORGANIZATION> 'Ismat 'Abd-al-Majid has, in a 
telephone conversation, assured me that 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON> has 
left the door open for dialogue with the <ORGANIZATION>Arab League</ORGANIZATION> and the 
Arab states." 
  On the reports claiming that a number of his supporters 
including the newly appointed Defense Minister 'Abd-Rabbuh <PERSON>Hadi 
Mansur</PERSON>, Social Security Minister Muhammad 'Abdallah al-Batani, 
and Colonel al-Khadr al-'Aqil, were killed in a car accident, 
giving rise to widespread speculations, '<PERSON>Ali Nasir Muhammad</PERSON> 
said: "That is not true. I contacted them a short while ago 
and spoke to them personally and reassured myself about their 
health. What was published about them having been killed is not 
true. They are alive and well." 
  The former Yemeni president showed annoyance at the 
appointment of <ORGANIZATION>Sulayman Nasir Mas</ORGANIZATION>'ud, formerly one of his 
supporters, as a member of the southern <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>. 
He said: "I have nothing to do with that appointment or with 
him. I was not consulted. As a matter of principle I reject 
the secession and I naturally reject his appointment. It is not 
just a question of rejecting the appointment. I reject the 
whole idea. He does not represent me and I have nothing to do 
with him." [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-37805 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes122_c_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-122 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  23 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Egypt </F>
<H3> <TI>   Twenty-two Repentant `Terrorists' Released </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Twenty-two Repentant `Terrorists' Released </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC2306155694 Cairo MENA in Arabic 1540 GMT 23 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC2306155694 </F>
<F P=104>  Cairo MENA </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Excerpt] <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, 23 Jun (MENA) -- The second group of 
terrorists to repent and denounce extremism after realizing the 
corrupt nature of their ideas and false beliefs was released 
from <LOCATION>Tura Prison</LOCATION> <TIME>this afternoon</TIME>. 
  Some 22 people were released -- 18 from <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, two from 
al-Fayyum, and two from <PERSON>Bani Suwayf</PERSON>. They were arrested after 
joining the extremist terrorist groups. 
  They were named as: <PERSON>Ashraf Sabir Muhammad</PERSON>, 'Izzat '<PERSON>Awad 
Sulayman</PERSON>, 'Isam Muhammad Muhammad 'Abd-Rabbuh, 'Abd-al-Mun'im 
<PERSON>Mustafa Mahfuz</PERSON>, <PERSON>Muhammad Ibrahim al-Sayyid Khafajah</PERSON>, 
'Abd-al-'Alim '<PERSON>Ali Husni</PERSON>, <PERSON>Usamah Ahmad Huraydi</PERSON>, 'Abd-al-'<PERSON>Aziz 
Mahmud Salamah</PERSON>, Muhammad al-Sayyid 'Ali al-Hadini, <PERSON>Hani Imam</PERSON> 
'Abd-al-'<PERSON>Aziz Salih</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sayyid Isma'il Hasanayn</PERSON>, <PERSON>Karam Muhammad 
Nash</PERSON>'at, Ashraf 'Abd-al- <PERSON>Sami' Bakr</PERSON>, '<PERSON>Isam Fawzi</PERSON> 'Abd-al-'Al, 
<PERSON>Yasir Anwar Muhammad 'Ali</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mustafa Fawzi</PERSON> 'Abd-al-'Al, Ibrahim 
Muhammad 'Abd-al-'Aziz, <PERSON>Muhammad Muhammad Ramadan Rizq</PERSON>, Ayman 
'Abd-al-'<PERSON>Al Hasan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jamal 'Abd-al-Fattah Nasrallah</PERSON>, <PERSON>Muhammad 
Ahmad Mutawalli Mahmud</PERSON>, and Sabir 'Abd-al-Sattar Muhammad. 
  The released expressed their satisfaction and joy over 
Interior Minister <PERSON>Hasan al-Alfi</PERSON>'s decision to release those who 
repent, denounce all forms of violence and terrorism, and return 
to society's ranks as good citizens. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-60217 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes099_j_94045" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-099 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ARABIAN PENINSULA </F>
<F P=101> Yemen </F>
<H3> <TI>   South Yemen Takes Steps To Form Government </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    South Yemen Takes Steps To Form Government </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC2205060294 Paris AFP in English 0049 GMT 22 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC2205060294 </F>
<F P=104>  Paris AFP </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 22</DATE> (AFP) -- A five-man 
presidential council for the independent state newly proclaimed 
in <LOCATION>south Yemen</LOCATION> was named overnight <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, it was officially 
announced in <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>. 
  Its members were appointed by the provisional <ORGANIZATION>Council of 
National Salvation</ORGANIZATION> -- a body composed of elected parliamentary 
deputies from the south, religious leaders and representatives 
of political parties and political leaders. 
  The five include the leader of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION> 
(YSP) 'Ali Salim al-Bid, who spearheaded the break with <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>. 
  Members were named as: 

  -  al-Bid 
  -  <PERSON>Salim Salih Muhammad</PERSON> -- <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> deputy secretary-general 
  -  'Abd-al-Rahman Ja'far -- secretary-general of the opposition 
"Sons of <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> Party" 
  -  'Abd-al-Qawi Makkawi -- Opposition figure resident in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> 
  -  <PERSON>Sulayman Nasir Mas</PERSON>'ud -- a supporter of former <LOCATION>South Yemen</LOCATION> 
president '<ORGANIZATION>Ali Nasir Muhammad</ORGANIZATION>. 


    Al-Bid proclaimed overnight <DATE>Friday</DATE> an independent <LOCATION>Yemen 
Democratic Republic</LOCATION> in what was formerly <LOCATION>Marxist South Yemen</LOCATION> 
amid a two-week civil war with forces loyal to President 'Ali 
'<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON>, a northerner. 
  The break came four years to the day after <LOCATION>South and North 
Yemen</LOCATION> were reunified. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-59338 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes092_j_94034" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-092 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ARABIAN PENINSULA </F>
<F P=101> Yemen </F>
<H3> <TI>   New Heads of Command Structures Named </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    New Heads of Command Structures Named </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PM1205094694 London AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT in Arabic 11 May 94 p2 </F>
<F P=103> PM1205094694 </F>
<F P=104>  London AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Reports by Salwa al-Ustuwani in <LOCATION>Damascus</LOCATION> and AL-SHARQ </F>
AL-AWSAT bureau in <LOCATION>Amman</LOCATION>: "Restructuring of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern and 
Southern Commands</ORGANIZATION> Paves the Way for a New Phase in the Yemeni 
War"] 
  [Excerpts] According to Yemeni military sources, battles 
raged yesterday in the town of <LOCATION>Zinjibar</LOCATION> and extended to 
al-Bayda' Governorate in the north in the areas of al-Kawd and 
al-'Urqub and all the way to Mukayris. It seems that the 
northern al-'Amaliqah forces deployed there are drawning their 
last breath. The northern command had pinned great hopes on them 
for victory and for the occupation of <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>, and they were 
considered the pincers in the area to the north of <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>. 
  As regards the other forces which have been trying to 
besiege 
<LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> from the north and the west in the 
Ta'izz-al-Rahidah-Mawiyah axis, they have withdrawn from the 
borders and from the areas they had occupied to the north of 
Ta'izz Governorate. [passage omitted] 
  In the course of the re-formation of the southern command, 
new appointments have been made in the various sectors as 
follows: 
  1. The eastern front (the governorates of <LOCATION>Shabwah</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Hadramaut</LOCATION>): The operations there are supervised by <PERSON>Salih 
Abu-Bakr Bin-Husaynun</PERSON>, former oil and mineral resources minister 
and chief of staff in the south. 
  2. The Abyan-al-Bayda' front is under the command of <ORGANIZATION>Abyan 
Governor Muhammad 'Ali Ahmad</ORGANIZATION>. 
  3. The <PERSON>Kirsh</PERSON> front is under the command of <ORGANIZATION>Colonel Qasim 
Bin-Yahya</ORGANIZATION>. 
  4. The Maqtabah front is under the command of Salih 'Ubayd 
Ahmad, former deputy prime minister who was defense minister 
before the unity. 
  5. The Ta'izz and Ibb brigades are under the command of 
Housing and Planning Minister Muhammad Sa'id 'Abdallah (Muhsin) 
and Culture Minister <PERSON>Jarallah</PERSON> 'Umar (both members of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Political Bureau</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION> [YSP]), and 
Sultan al-Sami'i, the formerly independent deputy. 
  As regards the northern command, it has been formed as 
follows: 
  1. Ahmad Musa'id <PERSON>Husayn</PERSON> (member of the <ORGANIZATION>General Committee</ORGANIZATION> -- 
the <ORGANIZATION>Political Bureau</ORGANIZATION> -- of the <ORGANIZATION>General People's Congress</ORGANIZATION> [GPC]): 
Command of the <LOCATION>Shabwah</LOCATION> front. 
  2. 'Abd-Rabbuh <PERSON>Mansur Hadi</PERSON>, the new defense minister, and 
Ahmad 'Abdallah al-Husayni: Al-Bayda' command. 
  All three of them [as published] are former south Yemeni 
President '<ORGANIZATION>Ali Nasir Muhammad</ORGANIZATION>'s men. 
  3. 'Abd-al-'Aziz 'Abd-al-Ghani, <PERSON>Muhammad Salim Basindwah</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Ahmad Faraj</PERSON>, and 'Abdallah al-Qadi: Ta'izz command. 
  4. 'Abd-al-Karim al-Iryani and a group of central areas 
officers: Ibb command. 
  5. (Central Security Commander) Muhammad '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON>, 
(<ORGANIZATION>Air Force Commander</ORGANIZATION>) '<PERSON>Ali Salih al-Ahmar</PERSON>, (1st Armored Division 
Commander) '<PERSON>Ali Muhsin al-Ahmar</PERSON>, and (Information Minister) 
Hasan al-Lawzi: <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION> area command. The aim is to purge it of 
the political parties and others who sympathize with the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION>. 
  6. 'Abd-al-Rahman Muhammad 'Ali 'Uthman, 'Abd-al-Rahman 
al-zayn, and other leadership and staff members: Command of 
al-Hudaydah front. 
  Meanwhile, AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT has obtained some information 
about the arrest of a group of Sudanese and Iraqis in <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> and 
the arrest of 60 members of the extremist Afghan Jihad members 
in al-Dali'. There is information confirming that <LOCATION>Eritrea</LOCATION> has 
admitted into its airports a group of northern civilian planes 
which were taken to <LOCATION>Asmara Airport</LOCATION> out of fear that they might 
have been a target of attack at the airports of Ta'izz, <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>, 
and al-Hudaydah. 
  Although <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> sources have refused to confirm that Eritrean 
airports were used in the Yemeni war, some reports say that the 
southerners bombed <LOCATION>Asmara</LOCATION> airport after discovering that 
northern military aircraft had taken off from there. 
  The reports add that the north paid Eritrean President 
<PERSON>Isaias 
Afewerki</PERSON> <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> for allowing the planes into his country's 
airport. 
  Sources close to the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> have told 
AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT that the southern '<ORGANIZATION>Abbud Brigade</ORGANIZATION>, in 
cooperation with the public in al-Dali' Directorate in the <LOCATION>Lahij 
Governorate</LOCATION>, successfully confronted the attack launched by 
northern forces loyal to President 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON> 
consisting of al-Hamzah Brigade reinforced by selected 
Republican Guard forces. The <ORGANIZATION>Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> said the 
result was a "crushing" defeat for the northern forces which had 
to retreat. 
  The sources said that the '<ORGANIZATION>Abbud Brigade</ORGANIZATION>'s forces, which are 
under the command of Defense Minister Staff Brigadier General 
<PERSON>Haytham Qasim Tahir</PERSON>, captured 15 tanks and destroyed 10 tanks 
and a number of vehicles and troop carriers, but the <ORGANIZATION>Defense 
Ministry</ORGANIZATION> did not give the human losses on both sides. 
  Sanaa has not denied that report to close politicians and 
reporters, who are finding it difficult to contact the outside 
world and who see <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>'s silence about these battles of the 
past two days as an indication that the results were not in its 
favor. 
  Sources of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> in the south said 
that 
four of <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>'s Russian-made aircraft were shot down as they 
attacked civilian targets in <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>. Two of the pilots were 
captured. One of them is an Egyptian Islamic extremist and the 
other an Iraqi from the <ORGANIZATION>Iraqi Air Force</ORGANIZATION>. The other two were 
killed when their two aircraft exploded in mid-air. 
  The sources attribute the use of Iraqi pilots in the Yemeni 
war to the weakness of north Yemeni pilots and the warm 
relations between President 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON> and Iraqi 
President <PERSON>Saddam Husayn</PERSON>. Before the outbreak of battles, 
political and press sources said that a number of Iraqi military 
experts had arrived in <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>. [passage omitted] 
  In a telephone statement to AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT in <LOCATION>Damascus</LOCATION>, 
Yemeni military sources said that the planes which bombed <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> 
were Yemeni planes which took off from military airfields in 
<LOCATION>Eritrea</LOCATION> and were flown by Iraqi pilots. It seems that <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION> 
entered the battle through <LOCATION>Eritrea</LOCATION> after the latter was paid 
large sums of money. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-46391 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jptot024__l94068" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TOT-94-024-L </AU>
JPRS 
Terrorism 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  FOUO </ABS>
<DATE1>   5 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> NEAR EAST/SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> EGYPT </F>
<H3> <TI>   Interior Minister's Attackers Named in Court </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Interior Minister's Attackers Named in Court </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC0506120294 Cairo MENA in Arabic 1125 GMT 5 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC0506120294 </F>
<F P=104>  Cairo MENA </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, 5 Jun (MENA)--<ORGANIZATION>The Supreme Military Court</ORGANIZATION> 
today held its first session to consider the case of the attempt 
to assassinate the interior minister, which involves 17 
defendants, including 3 fugitives. 
  The court held its session amid strict security measures. A 
number of lawyers, family members of the defendants, and 
representatives of the Egyptian and international media were 
present. 
  The trial began by calling the names of the defendants, who 
are: Muhammad Rashad 'Abd-al-Hamid <PERSON>Hijazi</PERSON>, Muhammad 
'Abd-al-'<PERSON>Alim Muhammad Khalifah</PERSON>, Mas'ud al-'<PERSON>Arif Ibrahim</PERSON>, Tariq 
Ahmad 'Abd-al- <PERSON>Samad</PERSON>, <PERSON>Usamah Muhammad Rashad</PERSON> (fugitive), Hisham 
Na'im al-Husayni, <PERSON>Badr Muhammad Mutawalli</PERSON> (fugitive), <PERSON>Ahmad Nasr 
Khalil</PERSON>, <PERSON>Muhammad Hazin Hasan Isma'il</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hamdi Muhammad Qarni</PERSON> 
(fugitive), <PERSON>Ahmad Sayyid Muhammad Hammad</PERSON>, 'Abd-al-'Al Hulayyil, 
'Abd-al-Hamid <PERSON>Mursi Muhammad</PERSON>, <PERSON>Furayj Salam Furayj</PERSON>, <PERSON>Salim Ahmad 
Salim</PERSON>, 'Ali Ramzi 'Abd-al-Hadi, and Hasan 'Uways Wahbah. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-35287 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes104_j_94016" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-104 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ARABIAN PENINSULA </F>
<F P=101> Yemen </F>
<H3> <TI>   Sanaa Radio Reports Ministers Take Oath of Office </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Sanaa Radio Reports Ministers Take Oath of Office </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   JN2805132794 Sanaa Yemeni Republic Radio Network in Arabic 
1200 GMT 28 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> JN2805132794 </F>
<F P=104>  Sanaa Yemeni Republic Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Before brother Lieutenant General 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah 
Salih</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION> chairman, brothers 'Abd-al-Qadir 
<ORGANIZATION>Ba Jammal</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Faysal Bin-Shamlan</PERSON> took the Constitutional oath on 
their appointments as deputy prime minister and minister of oil 
and mineral resources respectively. The oath-taking ceremony 
was attended by <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad</PERSON> Sa'id al-<PERSON>'Attar</PERSON>, the acting prime 
minister. 
  Brother '<ORGANIZATION>Abdallah 'Awad Ba Matraf</ORGANIZATION> also took the 
Constitutional oath before Lt. Gen. 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION> chairman, on his appointment as governor of 
<LOCATION>Lahij Governorate</LOCATION>. The oath-taking ceremony was attended by <PERSON>Dr. 
Muhammad</PERSON> Sa'id al-<PERSON>'Attar</PERSON>, the acting prime minister, and <PERSON>Dr. 
Muhammad Hasan Dammaz</PERSON>, minister of local administration. 
  Brothers Muhammad al-Ra'di, <PERSON>Mansur</PERSON> 'Abd-al-Jalil, and Ahmad 
Muhammad al-Mutawwakil also took the Constitutional oath on 
their appointment as our country's ambassadors to <LOCATION>Sudan</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> respectively. The oath-taking ceremony 
was attended by <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad</PERSON> Sa'id al-<PERSON>'Attar</PERSON>, the acting prime 
minister, and <PERSON>Muhammad Salim Basindwah</PERSON>, the foreign minister. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-60294 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes100_j_94013" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-100 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  24 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ARABIAN PENINSULA </F>
<F P=101> Yemen </F>
<H3> <TI>   Salih Issues Decree Granting General Amnesty </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Salih Issues Decree Granting General Amnesty </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   JN2405051794 Sanaa Yemeni Republic Radio Network in Arabic 
0430 GMT 24 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> JN2405051794 </F>
<F P=104>  Sanaa Yemeni Republic Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Brother Lieutenant General 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON>, 
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>, has issued a republican 
decree under Law No. 1 for <DATE>1994</DATE>, declaring a general amnesty. 
The following is the text of the decree: 
  The chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>, taking cognizance 
of the Constitution of the Republic of <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> and out of faith in 
the efficiency of the democratic process to bolster the 
victories of the Yemeni revolution; as an embodiment of the 
genuine spirit of tolerance existing in the mind and conscience 
of our people; out of absolute commitment to the duty of 
preserving the unity of the homeland and the cohesion of the 
Yemeni society in the various parts of the Republic of <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>; 
out of concern that all the sons of the Yemeni people will 
participate in the march of national construction and contain 
the regrettable repercussions of the internal sedition caused by 
the rebellion of criminal secessionist elements against the 
constitutional legitimacy and the subsequent explosion of the 
military situation and the direct threat posed to the unity of 
the homeland and the security and stability of citizens; in view 
of all this and due to the requirements of the supreme national 
interest; and following the approval of the <ORGANIZATION>Council of Ministers 
and Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>, decrees the following: 
  Article 1: With the exception of the secessionist elements 
whose names are given in the arrest warrant issued by the public 
prosecutor of the republic on 23 <DATE>May</DATE>, a general amnesty shall be 
granted to all the civilian and military men who, under the 
hegemony of the criminal secessionist clique, acted or behaved 
in a manner conflicting with the Constitution and punishable 
under the law. According to this decree, they will enjoy their 
full political and civilian rights and will continue to assume 
their responsibilities in the various places of work and 
production under commitment to constitutional legitimacy. 
  Article 2: Everyone who abides by the constitutional 
legitimacy shall benefit from this amnesty. 
  Article 3: This decree shall be valid as of the date of its 
issuance and shall be published in the official gazette. 
  Issued at the <ORGANIZATION>Republic's Presidency</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION> on 12 Dhu 
al-Hijjah <DATE>1414</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Hegira</ORGANIZATION>, corresponding to 23 <DATE>May 1994</DATE>. 
  [Signed] Lt. Gen. 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON>, chairman of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>; 
  <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad</PERSON> Sa'id al-'Attar, acting prime minister 
  An arrest warrant had earlier been issued by the republic's 
public prosecutor, stating the following: 
  Based on the Constitution of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Republic</ORGANIZATION> and the 
Penal Code and Procedural Law in force, the public prosecutor 
has decided the following: 
  I. Based on the constitution and the laws in force, and in 
view of the public actions they have committed, the persons 
named below are hereby charged with the following crimes: 
Violating the constitution; attacking citizens and public and 
private property; issuing orders in contravention of the law; 
and organizing rebellion and disobedience against public order. 
  Those persons are, in alphabetical order: 
  1. Ahmad 'Ubayd Bin-Daqr 
  2. Anis Hasan Yahya 
  3. Haydar Abu-Bakr al-'Attas 
  4. Salim Muhammad Jubran 
  5. Sulayman Nasir Mas'ud 
  6. Salih Abu-Bakr Bin-Husaynun 
  7. Salih Shayib 
  8. Salih Munassar al-Siyayli 
  9. Salih 'Ubayd Ahmad 
  10. 'Ali Salim al-Bid 
  11. 'Abd-al-Rahman al-Jifri 
  12. Basim 'Abd-al-Rabb 
  13. Qasim Yahya 
  14. Muhammad 'Ali al-Qayrahi 
  15. Muthanna Salim 'Askar 
  16. Haytham Qasim Tahir 
  II. All the members of the <ORGANIZATION>Public Prosecution</ORGANIZATION>, officers 
responsible for judicial arrest, and personnel of the <ORGANIZATION>Armed 
Forces</ORGANIZATION> and security agencies are requested to take legal 
measures that ensure the arrest of all the defendants named 
above or anyone of them and to hand them over to the nearest 
office of the <ORGANIZATION>Public Prosecution</ORGANIZATION> in any governorate of the 
republic. Then they will be interrogated and referred to the 
judicial authorities, as stipulated by the law. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-38107 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes124_c_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-124 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Egypt </F>
<H3> <TI>   National Dialogue Participants Listed </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    National Dialogue Participants Listed </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC2506152794 Cairo MENA in Arabic 1220 GMT 25 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> NC2506152794 </F>
<F P=104>  Cairo MENA </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, 25 Jun (MENA)--The names of the members of 
the <ORGANIZATION>National Dialogue General Congress</ORGANIZATION>, which was opened by 
President <PERSON>Husni Mubarak</PERSON>, were announced today. It has been 
decided that <PERSON>Dr. Mustafa Khalil</PERSON> will be secretary general of the 
congress. The congress includes the following members: The 
representatives of the political parties: The <ORGANIZATION>National 
Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> [NDP], the <ORGANIZATION>National Progressive Unionist 
Grouping</ORGANIZATION> [NPUG], the <ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Liberal Party</ORGANIZATION>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Socialist Arab Party of Egypt</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Ummah Party</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Greens 
Party</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Social Justice Party</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Unionist 
Party</ORGANIZATION>. Among the congress members are 36 members from the 
People's Assembly and 29 from the <ORGANIZATION>Consultative Council</ORGANIZATION>. In 
addition there are the chiefs of professional associations and 
trade unions, and a number of prominent journalists and media 
men, including <PERSON>Mustafa Najib</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>MENA Board</ORGANIZATION> chairman and chief 
editor. The congress members also include a number of 
university professors, teaching staff club members, researchers, 
and scientists in the scientific research centers, members of 
local councils, youths and sports committees, chambers of 
commerce, industry, and tourism, businessmen as well as 
individuals who are interested in the fields of youths and 
sports, economists, and representatives of women, 
nongovernmental societies, the general federation of 
cooperatives, a number of winners of state awards, artists, 
public figures, the specialized national councils, and 
university student unions. 
  The following are the names of the <ORGANIZATION>National Dialogue 
Congress</ORGANIZATION>, which were announced today: 
  The political parties: 
  For the <ORGANIZATION>NDP</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Dr. Yusuf Wali</PERSON>, deputy prime minister, 
agriculture minister and <ORGANIZATION>NDP</ORGANIZATION> secretary general; <PERSON>Safwat 
al-Sharif</PERSON>, information minister and <ORGANIZATION>NDP</ORGANIZATION> assistant secretary 
general; <PERSON>Kamal al-Shadhili</PERSON>, minister of state for the People's 
Assembly and <ORGANIZATION>Consultative Council</ORGANIZATION> affairs and <ORGANIZATION>NDP</ORGANIZATION> assistant 
secretary general 
  For the NPUG: <PERSON>Khalid Muhyi-al-Din</PERSON>, NPUG leader; <PERSON>Lutfi Wakid</PERSON>, 
NPUG deputy leader; <PERSON>Dr. Rif</PERSON>'at al-Sayyid, <ORGANIZATION>NPUG</ORGANIZATION> secretary 
general; <PERSON>Dr. Judah 'Abd-al-Khaliq</PERSON>, the economic committee 
secretary 
  For the <ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION>: Engineer <PERSON>Ibrahim Shukri</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION> 
leader; <PERSON>Muhammad Mahmud 'Azzam</PERSON>; 'Adil Muhammad Husayn; Major 
General Tal'at <ORGANIZATION>Ahmad Musallam 
  For the Liberal Party</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Mustafa Kamil Murad</PERSON>, party leader; 
Engineer 'Abd-al-Fattah al-Shurbaji, party secretary general; 
<PERSON>Dr. Yasir Ramadan</PERSON>, member of the party presidium; <PERSON>Dr. Huda</PERSON> 'Afifi 
  For the <ORGANIZATION>Socialist Arab Party of Egypt</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Jamal Rabi</PERSON>', party 
leader; <PERSON>Dr. Hasan Muhammad Kamal</PERSON>, deputy leader; <PERSON>Dr. Mahmud 
Kamil al-Rayyis</PERSON>, deputy leader; <PERSON>Dr. Salah Hidayat</PERSON>, chairman of 
the party's advisory committee 
  For the <ORGANIZATION>Social Justice Party</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad</PERSON> 'Abd-al-'Al, 
party 
leader; <PERSON>Muhammad Mahmud al-Kurdi</PERSON>; <PERSON>Dr. Midhat 'Aziz Balawah</PERSON>; <PERSON>Dr. 
Amani Bushra Faraj</PERSON> For the <ORGANIZATION>Ummah Party</ORGANIZATION>: Ahmad al-Sabahi, 
party leader; Muhammad Hamid 'Amarah; Muhammad Badr Abu-Hadid; 
'Abd-al-Rahman Muhammad 'Abd-al-Hafiz 
  For the Greens Party: <PERSON>Kamal Kirah</PERSON>, party leader; <PERSON>Dr. Ibrahim 
Muhammad Kilani</PERSON>; Dr. 'Abd-al-Mun'im 'Ali al-'A'sar, member of 
the party's higher committee; <PERSON>Dr. Baha</PERSON>'-al-Din <PERSON>Hafiz Bakri</PERSON>, 
deputy party leader 
  For the Democratic Unionist Party: Ibrahim Muhammad 
'Abd-al-Mun'im Turk, party leader; Ahmad 'Abd-al-Muhsin Farahat; 
<PERSON>Zaki Faraj</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Muhammad Mustafa al-Sharqawi 
  People's Assembly</ORGANIZATION> members: <PERSON>Ahmad Hamadi</PERSON>; Muhammad 'Abdallah; 
<PERSON>Dr. Amin Mubarak</PERSON>; Engineer Abu-Bakr al-Basil; Salah al-Taruti; 
<PERSON>Al-Sayyid Sarhan</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Kamal Henry Abadir; Sa</ORGANIZATION>'d al-Shirbini; Muhammad 
Tulbah 'Uwaydah; Ahmad Fu'ad 'Abd-al-'Aziz; Husayn al-Sayrafi; 
<PERSON>Muhammad Muhammad Juwayli</PERSON>; <PERSON>Dr. Zakariya</PERSON> 'Azmi; <PERSON>Dr. Faruq Rakha</PERSON>; 
Tariq al-Jundi; <PERSON>Ahmad Haykal</PERSON>; <PERSON>Edward Ghali</PERSON> al-Dhahabi; <LOCATION>Fathi 
Bayyumi</LOCATION>; Ahmad Abu-Zayd; <LOCATION>Hamdi</LOCATION> al-Tahhan; 'Abd-al-Fattah Diyab; 
Tal'at <LOCATION>Mustafa</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Ahmad Khayri</LOCATION>; 'Abd-al-Rahman Barakah; <ORGANIZATION>Sa</ORGANIZATION>'d 
<LOCATION>Bahnasawi</LOCATION>; 'Abd-al-Wahhab Qutah; Muhammad Abu-Sudayrah; Muhammad 
Abu-al-Hasan Ghanim; <PERSON>Muhammad Khalil Hafiz</PERSON>; <LOCATION>Ahmad Taha Ahmad</LOCATION>; 
<PERSON>Husayn al-Mahdi</PERSON>; Muhammad Abu-al-Fadl al-Jizawi; <PERSON>Muhammad Mahmud 
Hasan</PERSON>; <PERSON>Husayn Wishahi</PERSON>; <PERSON>Mustafa Sulayman</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Muhammad al-Sandayuni 
  Consultative Council</ORGANIZATION> members: 'Abd-al-'Al al-Jarihi; <PERSON>Ahmad 
Fathi Mursi</PERSON>; <LOCATION>Ahmad Rashad Musa</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Muhammad Zaki Malik</PERSON>; <PERSON>Dr. 
Mahmud Mahfuz</PERSON>; Engineer Ahmad 'Abd-al-Akhir; Dr. Isma'il Salam; 
<PERSON>Muhammad Hilmi</PERSON> al-Sharif; Ma'mun <PERSON>Salih Mashali</PERSON>; Engineer Fu'ad 
Abu-Zaghlah; Engineer Muhyi-al-Din 'Abd-al-Latif; Engineer 'Ali 
'Abd-al-'Azim Abu-Jaziyah; <PERSON>Dr. Husayn Muhammad Hijazi</PERSON>; Engineer 
Rushdi al-Sharqawi; <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad</PERSON> 'Abd-al-Fattah al-Qassas; <PERSON>Dr. 
Hamdi</PERSON> al-Hakim; <PERSON>Dr. Fathi Muhammad</PERSON> 'Ali; Dr. 'Abd-al-Rahim Imam 
<LOCATION>Bayyumi</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad Tal</PERSON>'at 'Abd-al-'Aziz; Engineer Husayn 
'Uthman 'Uthman; <PERSON>Mahmud Najib Husni</PERSON>; <PERSON>Nabil Muhammad Mansi</PERSON>; 
<PERSON>Muhammad Ahmad Qurashi</PERSON>; <PERSON>Muhammad Kamal Sulayman</PERSON>; <PERSON>Muhammad Rajab 
Ahmad</PERSON>; 
<PERSON>Jamal al-Mahdi</PERSON>; Muhammad 'Id Adam; 'Abd-al-'Aziz Yusuf; 
'Abd-al-'<PERSON>Aziz Jabr</PERSON> 
  For the Professional Associations: Ahmad al-Khawajah, 
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Lawyers' Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Hamdi al-Sayyid</PERSON>, 
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Doctors' Association</ORGANIZATION>; Engineer <PERSON>Hasaballah 
al-Kafrawi</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Engineers' Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. 
Muhammad Hilmi Nammar</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Traders' Association</ORGANIZATION>; 
<PERSON>Thuraya Lubnah</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Social Workers' Association</ORGANIZATION>; 
Engineer <PERSON>Ahmad Abu-Ghanimah</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Applied Artists' 
Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Sulayman Hajar</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Athletes' 
Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Zakariya Jad</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Pharmacists' 
Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Abu-al-Futuh 'Abd-al-Latif</PERSON>, president of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Teachers' Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Ibrahim Nafi</PERSON>', president of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Journalists' Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Faruq 'Afifi</PERSON>, president of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Agriculturalists' Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. 'Ali Musa</PERSON>, president of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Veterinarians' Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Yusuf 'Uthman</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Film 
Industry Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Hamdi Ghayth</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Actors' 
Association</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Munib Shafi'i</PERSON>, president of the Chamber for Film 
Industry 
  For the trade unions: Sayyid Rashid, <ORGANIZATION>Labor Federation</ORGANIZATION>; 
<PERSON>Mustafa Manji</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Labor Federation</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Husayn Mujawir</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Labor 
Federation</ORGANIZATION>; 'A'ishah 'Abd-al-Hadi, <ORGANIZATION>Labor Federation</ORGANIZATION> 
  For the press, media, and prominant writers: Muhammad 
Tharwat 
Abazah; <PERSON>Makram Muhammad Ahmad</PERSON>; <PERSON>Salah Muntasir</PERSON>; Lutfi al-Khawli; 
<ORGANIZATION>Ibrahim Sa</ORGANIZATION>'dah; <PERSON>Amin Basyuni</PERSON>; <PERSON>Samir Rajab</PERSON>; Mahmud al-Tihami; 
Mahmud 'Abd-al-Mun'im Murad; <PERSON>Samir Sarhan</PERSON>; 'Abd-al-'Azim 
<LOCATION>Ramadan</LOCATION>; Sa'd-al-Din Wahbah; <LOCATION>Jalal</LOCATION> 'Isa; <LOCATION>Mustafa Najib</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Nabil</ORGANIZATION> 
'Uthman; 
<PERSON>Muhammad Jalal Duwaydar</PERSON>; <LOCATION>Labib Yunan</LOCATION>; 'Abd-al-'Aziz 
Sadiq;'Abd-al-Sattar al-Tawilah; <ORGANIZATION>Rajab</ORGANIZATION> al-Banna; <ORGANIZATION>Mahfuz</ORGANIZATION> 
al-Ansari; 'Abd-al-Wahhab Mutawi'; <PERSON>Mursi</PERSON> Isma'il 'Atallah; <PERSON>Raja</PERSON>' 
al-Naqqash; Mamduh al-Laythi; <PERSON>Usamah al-Ghazali Harb</PERSON>; 
<LOCATION>Hamdi</LOCATION> al-Kunayyisi; Dr. 'Adil 'Izz; <PERSON>Dr. Lutfi</PERSON> 'Abd-al-Khaliq; 
<PERSON>Dr. Muhammad Kamil</PERSON>; Dr. 'Ali Hubaysh 
  Universities and teaching staff club members: <PERSON>Dr. Mufid 
Shihab</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Cairo University</ORGANIZATION> president; Dr. 'Abd-al-Wahhab 
'Abd-al-Hafiz, 'Ayn <ORGANIZATION>Shams University</ORGANIZATION> president; <PERSON>Dr. 'Isam Salim</PERSON>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Alexandria University</ORGANIZATION> president; <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad Raja'i al-Tahlawi</PERSON>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Asyut University</ORGANIZATION> president; <PERSON>Dr. Ramzi</PERSON> al-Sha'ir, al-Zaqaziq 
<ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> president; <PERSON>Dr. Saqr Muhammad Saqr</PERSON>, al-Minufiyah 
<ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> president; <PERSON>Dr. Jamal Abu-al-Makarim</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>al-Minya 
University</ORGANIZATION> president; <PERSON>Dr. Shawqi al-Sayyid Khatir</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Tanta 
University</ORGANIZATION> president; <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad Duwaydar</PERSON> 'Abduh, <ORGANIZATION>Suez Canal 
University</ORGANIZATION> president; <PERSON>Dr. 'Ali Ramzi</PERSON>, 'Ayn <ORGANIZATION>Shams University</ORGANIZATION> vice 
president; <ORGANIZATION>Dr. Sa</ORGANIZATION>'d al-Khawaliqah, <ORGANIZATION>Alexandria University</ORGANIZATION> vice 
president; <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad 'Umar Hashim</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>al-Azhar University</ORGANIZATION> vice 
president; <PERSON>Dr. 'Abd-al-Ahad Jamal-al-Din</PERSON>, a professor at the 
'Ayn <ORGANIZATION>Shams University</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad Sabri al-Shabrawi</PERSON>, a 
professor at the <ORGANIZATION>American University</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Midhat 
Darwish</PERSON>, head of the teaching staff club of the 'Ayn <ORGANIZATION>Shams 
University</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad Ibrahim Ramadan</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Alexandria University</ORGANIZATION> 
vice president; <PERSON>Dr. Ramadan Abu-al</PERSON>-'Ula, a professor at 
<ORGANIZATION>Alexandria University</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Kamal Muhammad Qandil</PERSON>, chief of the 
teaching staff club of <LOCATION>Alexandria University</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad 
al-Shaykh</PERSON>, chief of the teaching staff club of the al-Zaqaziq 
University; <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad Isma'il Khidr</PERSON>, a former university 
president; <PERSON>Dr. Samir Tubar</PERSON>, al-Zaqaziq <ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> vice 
president; <PERSON>Dr. Mustafa al-Sa</PERSON>'id, a professor at the economics 
college at <ORGANIZATION>Cairo University</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Mahir 'Abd-al-Wahhab</PERSON>, a 
professor at the engineering college in <LOCATION>al-Minya University</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Dr. 
Ahmad al-Sayyid al-Sawi</PERSON>, a professor at <ORGANIZATION>Cairo University</ORGANIZATION> law 
college; <PERSON>Dr. Ibrahim Shalabi</PERSON>, a professor at <ORGANIZATION>Cairo University</ORGANIZATION> 
economics college; <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad Hasanayn</PERSON> 'Abd-al-'Al, a 
professor at <ORGANIZATION>Cairo University</ORGANIZATION> law college; Dr. Su'ad 
al-Sharqawi, a professor at <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> university law college; <PERSON>Dr. 
Ahmad Mashhur</PERSON>, a professor at <ORGANIZATION>'Ayn Shams University</ORGANIZATION> college of 
medicine; Dr. al-Sa'di Farhud, <ORGANIZATION>al-Azhar University</ORGANIZATION> former 
president. Dr. '<PERSON>Atiyah Saqr</PERSON>, al-Azhar former deputy imam; Dr. 
'Abd-al-Salam 'Abd-al-Ghaffar, 'Ayn <ORGANIZATION>Shams University</ORGANIZATION> former 
president; <PERSON>Dr. Muhammad</PERSON> Sa'id 'Abd-al-Fattah, <ORGANIZATION>Alexandria 
University</ORGANIZATION> former president; <PERSON>Dr. Isma'il al-Diftar</PERSON>, a professor 
at the principles of religion college; <PERSON>Dr. Abu-al-Wafa 
al-Taftazani</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Sufi School</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Cairo University</ORGANIZATION> vice 
president; <PERSON>Dr. Abd-al-Fattah al-Shaykh</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>al-Azhar University</ORGANIZATION> 
president; <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad Kamal Abu-al-Majd</PERSON>, a professor at the <ORGANIZATION>Cairo 
University</ORGANIZATION> law college 
  Economics and banking experts: Dr. '<LOCATION>Ali Lutfi</LOCATION>; Dr. Isma'il 
Sabri 'Abdallah; 
Dr. Sa'id al-Najjar; Dr. 'Ali-al-Din Hilal; <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad</PERSON> al-Safti; 
<PERSON>Dr. Hazim al-Biblawi</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Ahmad Ahmad Nuh</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Hamid</PERSON> al-Sayih; <PERSON>Dr. 
Khallaf</PERSON> 'Abd-al-Jabir Khallaf; Tawfiq 'Abduh Isma'il; 
'Abd-al-'Aziz Mustafa Ahmad; Yahya 'Abd-al-Fattah; 'Isam 
al-Ahmadi; Mahmud 'Abd-al-'Aziz; 'Isam Rif'at; <PERSON>Usamah Saraya</PERSON>. 
  General Cooperatives' Federation: <PERSON>Sayyid Zaki 'Abd-al-Hadi</PERSON>, 
president of the general federation; <PERSON>Muhammad Idris</PERSON>, president 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Agricultural Union; Mahmud Abu-Gharib</ORGANIZATION>, member; <PERSON>Ahmad 
Tandin</PERSON>, member; Ahmad 'Isawi, member; 'Abd-al-Rahim al-Ghul, 
member; 'Abd-al-Hamid Ghazi, member; Fayiz al-Tunayhi, member 
  Representatives of women and national societies: <PERSON>Dr. 
Farkhundah Hasan</PERSON>, professor at the <ORGANIZATION>American University</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>; 
<PERSON>Dr. Aminah al-Jundi</PERSON>, secretary general of the <ORGANIZATION>Higher Council</ORGANIZATION> for 
<LOCATION>Childhood</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Salwa</PERSON> 'Abd-al-'<PERSON>Aziz Fahmi</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Consultative Council</ORGANIZATION> 
member; <PERSON>Dr. Fawziyah</PERSON> 'Abd-al-Sattar, professor at <ORGANIZATION>Cairo 
University</ORGANIZATION>'s Law School; <PERSON>Mrs. Sakinah</PERSON> Fu'ad, journalist; <PERSON>Nazli 
Mu'awwad</PERSON>, professor at <ORGANIZATION>Cairo University's College of Economics</ORGANIZATION>; 
<PERSON>Dr. Shafiqah Nasir</PERSON>, professor at the Qasr al-'Ayni Medical 
School; <PERSON>Dr. Huda Razqanah</PERSON>, professor at the <LOCATION>Banha</LOCATION> Medical 
School; <PERSON>Mrs. Suhayr</PERSON> al-Atrabi from the media sector; <PERSON>Dr. Zaynab</PERSON> 
al-Sabki; <PERSON>Mrs. Munah Makram 'Ubayd</PERSON>, professor at the <ORGANIZATION>American 
University of Cairo 
  Artists</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Mahmud Yasin</PERSON>; 'Adil Imam; <PERSON>Husayn Fahmi</PERSON>; <PERSON>Aminah Rizq</PERSON> 
  Public figures: '<PERSON>Atif Sidqi</PERSON>, prime minister; <PERSON>Dr. Fathi 
Surur</PERSON>, 
People's Assembly speaker; <PERSON>Dr. Mustafa Kamal Hilmi</PERSON>, president of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Consultative Council</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Dr. Sufi Abu-Talib</PERSON>, former speaker of 
the People's Assembly; <PERSON>Mr. Fikri Makram</PERSON> 'Ubayd; <PERSON>Dr. Mamduh Jabr</PERSON>; 
Counsellor 'Abd-al-Rahman Faraj Muhsin; <PERSON>Mr.</PERSON> 'Abd-al-Hamid 
Barakat; <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad Mahdi</PERSON> 'Abd-al-Halim 
  Specialized national councils: <PERSON>Dr. 'Abd-al-Qadir Hatim</PERSON>, 
president of the national councils; <PERSON>Dr. Sulayman Hazin</PERSON>; <PERSON>Dr. 
Ibrahim Badran</PERSON>; <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad</PERSON> <LOCATION>Muharram</LOCATION>; Dr. Abu-Salih al-Alfi; 
<ORGANIZATION>Shaykh Ibrahim al-Dasuqi 
  University</ORGANIZATION> students' unions: <PERSON>Mr. Muhammad 'Ali Ahmad</PERSON>, 
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Asyut University Union</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Salah Muhammad 
Hasaballah</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Hulwan University Union</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Karam 
Ibrahim 'Uthman Salam</PERSON>, member of the 'Ayn <ORGANIZATION>Shams Medical School 
Union</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Iman Ahmad al-Jundi</PERSON>, vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>Tanta 
University Students' Union</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Ashraf Rashad 'Ali</PERSON>, treasurer of the 
<ORGANIZATION>al-Azhar College of Dentistry Union</ORGANIZATION>; Ihab 'Abd-al-Jawad from the 
union of <ORGANIZATION>Cairo University's College of Sciences</ORGANIZATION> 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-60656 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes103_j_94025" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-103 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  26 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ARABIAN PENINSULA </F>
<F P=101> Yemen </F>
<H3> <TI>   Former President on Proposal To End Crisis </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Former President on Proposal To End Crisis </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   JN2605111394 Amman AL-DUSTUR in Arabic 26 May 94 pp 1, 17 </F>
<F P=103> JN2605111394 </F>
<F P=104>  Amman AL-DUSTUR </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> ["Exclusive" report] </F>
  [Text] Former South Yemeni President '<PERSON>Ali Nasir Muhammad</PERSON> 
has told AL-DUSTUR that he and <PERSON>Shaykh Mujahid</PERSON> Abu-Shawarib are 
currently working on an initiative to stop the Yemeni war. In 
the meantime, sources close to the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION> [YSP] 
leadership said forces loyal to President 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON> 
have reached the environs of the <LOCATION>Hadhramaut Governorate</LOCATION>, which 
is adjacent to the <LOCATION>Shabwah Governorate</LOCATION>. 
  <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> sources expressed doubts that the president's forces 
will 
be able to continue to advance to al-Mukalla, the capital of 
<LOCATION>Hadhramaut</LOCATION>, where 'Ali Salim al-Bid, who declared himself 
now present. They say these forces cannot deploy over a vast 
area and maintain their cohesion at the same time. 
  These sources believe that the opening of the eastern front 
by the forces of legitimacy in <LOCATION>Shabwah</LOCATION> was not meant to achieve 
military as much as political and economic gains represented in 
sharing the <LOCATION>Shabwah</LOCATION> oil revenues. 
  Reached by telephone in <LOCATION>Damascus</LOCATION>, the former Yemeni 
president 
told AL-DUSTUR that he and <PERSON>Shaykh Mujahid Abu-Shawarib</PERSON>, the 
well-known national figure, will propose an initiative aimed at 
preserving the Yemeni unity and effecting a cease-fire. 
  '<ORGANIZATION>Ali Nasir</ORGANIZATION> declined to elaborate on this initiative at 
present as its publication may undermine the current efforts and 
contacts with the two parties to the conflict, indicating that 
he himself had earlier announced his rejection of 'Ali Salim 
al-Bid's secession decision. He said: We want a solution that 
guarantees the Yemeni unity, spares blood, leads to a 
cease-fire, and solves problems within the framework of the 
state of unity. He expressed hope that the anticipated solution 
may lie in an agreement by the two warring parties to 
simultaneously announce the following: 
  1. Preserving unity and canceling the secession decision. 
  2. Ceasing fire immediately. 
  3. Lifting the siege clamped on <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>. 
  The former Yemeni president said this can be followed by 
searching for a new formula that guarantees the existence of one 
central state that is capable of survival. 
  Asked by AL-DUSTUR if these are the main points of the 
initiative he and <PERSON>Shaykh Mujahid</PERSON> Abu-Shawarib are proposing, he 
said the initiative contains other details. 
  '<ORGANIZATION>Ali Nasir Muhammad</ORGANIZATION> denied a statement by '<PERSON>Abd-al-Qawi 
Makkawi</PERSON> two days ago that 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON> and 'Ali Salim 
al-Bid have agreed to meet in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. He said: We are still 
contacting the two men in order to reach a cease-fire first. We 
will arrange for a meeting between the two at a later stage. 
  In a related development, <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> sources expressed surprise at 
the delay in Kuwaiti recognition of the Democratic Republic of 
<LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> and said that <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION> was expected to be the first state to 
recognize the new state and that Kuwaiti Foreign Minister <PERSON>Shaykh 
Sabah</PERSON> al-Ahmad was expected to visit <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> and announce his 
country's recognition from there. The sources attributed this 
delay to possible strong foreign pressure by international 
powers like the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and other regional forces. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-14691 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes061_m_94010" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-061 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  30 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> JORDAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Bombing Suspects' Organization, Ties Detailed </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  JN2903193894 </F>
<F P=103> JN2903193894 </F>
<F P=104></F>



<TEXT>
Article   Type:BFN 

  [Editorial Report] <LOCATION>Amman</LOCATION> AL-BILAD in Arabic on 30 <DATE>March</DATE> 
publishes on page 5 an approximately 4,000-word report on the 
suspects charged in connection with a spate of recent explosions 
in <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION>. 
  AL-BILAD, "an independent political weekly," claims to have 
accompanied Major <PERSON>Muhannad Hijazi</PERSON>, the public prosecutor of the 
<ORGANIZATION>State Security Court</ORGANIZATION>, and the defendants to the sites targeted 
for explosions. The defendants were reported to have been in 
good health. They were also reported to have said that they are 
"heroes" because they carried out these bombings. The argument 
that they advanced is that they were carrying out God's 
injunction against "debauchery." They reportedly planned to 
establish a caliphate, assassinate intelligence and army 
personnel, and kill the Jordanian and Palestinian peace talks 
teams to halt the march of "capitulation," as they put it. 
  The weekly states that 'Abdallah Kamil al-Shuraydah 
al-Hashayikah is the principal defendant in the series of 
bombings that have recently taken place in <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION>. The weekly 
notes that al-Hashayikah, a member of the Muslim Brotherhood, 
<ORGANIZATION>Suwaylih Branch</ORGANIZATION>, left <LOCATION>Amman</LOCATION> in <DATE>1990</DATE> to work as a teacher of 
Arabic in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, where he also taught at the al-Imam 
al-Shafi'i Foundation. This foundation is supervised by <PERSON>Jamal 
Khalifah</PERSON>, also known as Abi-Bara', a Saudi national and an 
in-law of <PERSON>Usamah Bin-Ladin</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Saudi</LOCATION> national of Yemeni origin 
currently living in <LOCATION>Khartoum</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sudan</LOCATION>. Khalifah, <PERSON>Bin-Ladin</PERSON>'s 
right hand-man, is reported to be close to the ruling <PERSON>Saudi</PERSON> 
family. 
  According to the paper, al-Hashayikah discussed with 
<PERSON>Khalifah</PERSON> 
the idea of launching of an organization in <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION> to "eradicate 
forbidden conduct by force" in order to lay the groundwork for 
establishing a caliphate in <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION>. This idea was well received 
by <PERSON>Jamal Khalifah</PERSON>. The recruits of the organization would be 
Jordanians who received military training in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> during 
the war with the Soviets. The only thing the organization 
needed was financing. The report states that this all happened 
while the two were in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. Al-Hashayikah returned 
to <LOCATION>Amman</LOCATION> early this year to launch his organization so that he 
might receive the promised finances from Bin-Ladin, and <PERSON>Jamal 
Khalifah</PERSON>, "the mastermind of Bin-Ladin's terrorist operations in 
the Arab world." 
  The article continues, noting that the organization 
al-Hashayikah used had already taken its final shape before he 
left for the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. It had a joint command consisting of 
himself, as well as Jihad al-Tanjir, <PERSON>Zakariyah Muhammad Dawud</PERSON>, 
and Isma'il al-'Amayirah. They used mosques and places of 
worship to "concoct conspiracies." The recruits of the 
organization received refresher courses in military training 
during further visits to <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> via <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>. 
  According to the paper, "Bin-Ladin's group" received the 
recruits in <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION> upon their arrival there, and provided 
them with the necessary visas and air tickets to <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, where 
they then traveled to <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>. Shaykh 'Abd-al-Majid 
al-Zandani, representative of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Reform Grouping</ORGANIZATION> at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>, is reported to have provided the 
Afghan Arabs stopping over in <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> en route to <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> with 
the necessary visas and air tickets, as well as "his constant 
financial support for the organization." 
  The weekly also claims that some of the organization members 
remained in <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION> to plan bomb attacks and recruit other 
members. Having faced difficulties in acquiring the necessary 
explosives in <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION>, the organization sent <PERSON>Zakariyah Muhammad 
Dawud Qasim</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>, where he was trained in how to manufacture 
sophisticated explosives. He was also trained in detonating 
explosives by remote control. 
  The paper explains that, in order to achieve its objectives, 
the organization believed that it had to kill Arab and Muslim 
leaders who do not apply the Islamic sharia in their countries. 
It also believed that it had to resist the ongoing <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> 
peace negotiations by all means, including the use of force. 
The organization also planned to blow up movie theaters, 
nightclubs, bars, tourist areas, liquor stores, and public areas 
where the two sexes mingle, such as the <ORGANIZATION>Housing Bank Complex</ORGANIZATION>. 
The organization also planned to assassinate senior 
intelligence, army, and public security personnel in order to 
pave the way for the creation of a caliphate in <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION>. 
  Noting a plan by the organization to assassinate the 
Jordanian and Palestinian peace talks negotiators, AL-BILAD 
says: "In addition to carrying out bombings, the organization 
members entertained the idea of drawing up a full-fledged plan 
to liquidate Jordanian and Palestinian peace negotiators, headed 
by Prime Minister <PERSON>Dr. 'Abd-al-Salam al-Majali</PERSON>, former head of 
the Jordanian delegation to the peace talks. 
  According to the paper, the group found al-Majali's home 
telephone number, and telephoned him, telling him they were 
journalists working for a local daily. They asked for a date 
for an important press interview with him. Al-Majali agreed to 
grant them an interview. Al-Majali was meant to be assassinated 
during this bogus interview, according to the report, which it 
said was planned with a great deal of cleverness. A date was 
set for the interview and forty-eight hours before the interview 
was scheduled to take place, the organization leadership had 
drawn up a detailed plan to assassinate al-Majali by explosive 
charges and other weapons to be carried by the bogus press team, 
which would have consisted of reporters and cameramen. 
  The paper says it was only divine providence that intervened 
to save al-Majali, who was assigned an official mission outside 
<PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>. This mission required him to travel to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> ahead 
of the time set for the implementation of the assassination 
plan. Thus, the bogus interview date was postponed to a later 
date. However, this date has never materialized because the 
culprits were apprehended. 
  The weekly paper goes on to say that, having failed in their 
bid to liquidate al-Majali, the organization members attempted 
to assassinate members of the Palestinian delegation to the 
<LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> peace talks, including Faysal al-Husayni and Hanan 
'Ashrawi. However, stringent security precautions and the 
secrecy with which al-Husayni and 'Ashrawi surround their moves 
thwarted the defendants' scheme. Undeterred by their failure, 
the defendants recruited an employee of the <ORGANIZATION>Grand Palace Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, 
where the Palestinian peace negotiators stayed. The hotel 
employee was asked to plant explosive charges in the peace 
negotiators' rooms. Once again, strict security precautions 
thwarted their scheme. 
  According to the report, the failure of the organization's 
assassination scheme prompted the organization command to 
endorse a plan of explosions in <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION> to convince <PERSON>Jamal 
Khalifah</PERSON> to finance the organization. This resulted in 
explosions at movie theaters in <LOCATION>Amman</LOCATION> and al-Zarqa'. However, 
attempts to carry out further explosions elsewhere in <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION> 
failed. 
  Muhammad '<PERSON>Ali Shihadah</PERSON> is reportedly the "organization's 
mastermind responsible for picking explosion targets." 
  The paper's investigations indicated that '<PERSON>Abdallah Diyyah</PERSON>, 
a 
prominent Suwaylih-based Muslim Brotherhood member, was 
acquainted with the organization's scheme by 'Abdallah 
al-Hashayikah. However, Muslim Brotherhood sources ruled out 
<ORGANIZATION>Diyyah</ORGANIZATION>'s involvement in this scheme. 
  Elaborating further on this issue, the paper says: "Several 
quarters insinuated that the Muslim Brotherhood could be 
implicated in these explosion incidents, particularly since 
al-Hashayikah was a Brotherhood leader in <LOCATION>Suwaylih</LOCATION>, not to 
mention the fact that <PERSON>Diyyah</PERSON> was close to the hawkish wing of 
the Muslim Brotherhood. Meanwhile, informed sources ruled out 
this possibility, which has not been confirmed by the 
interrogations conducted with the defendants. 
  "AL-BILAD has learned that 23 persons have been implicated 
in 
the recent spate of explosions. They will stand trial at the 
<ORGANIZATION>State Security Court</ORGANIZATION> within the next two weeks. If found 
guilty, they could receive punitive measures, including the 
death sentence. These defendants are the following: 'Abd <PERSON>Salih 
Husayn al-Jahalin</PERSON>, Muhammad '<PERSON>Ali Husayn Shihadah Abu</PERSON>-'Ayyad, 
<PERSON>Yasin Hasan Muhammad Zahrah</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hasan Hamdan Hasan</PERSON> 'Abd-al-Qadir, 
<PERSON>Muhammad Salih Musa 'Aqil</PERSON>, Sulayman Ahmad 'Abd-al-'Al Bisah, 
Muhammad Ahmad 'Abd-al-Fattah al-'Adharibah, <PERSON>Samir Ahmad 
Muhammad Tilagh</PERSON>, 'Abd-al-Nasir Mahmud Muhammad Yunus, Fa'iq 
Salih Yusuf al-Shawish, '<PERSON>Umar Jibril Muhammad al-Shawahin</PERSON>, 
'Abdallah Kamil al-Hashayikah, Jihad Ahmad Khalid al-Tanjir, 
<PERSON>Khalil Tawfiq Muhammad 'Alqam</PERSON>, Muhammad Ahmad al-Shaykh 
al-Fahmawi, <PERSON>Salim Musa Yusuf</PERSON>, <PERSON>Zakariyah Muhammad Dawud Qasim</PERSON>, 
Isma'il Sa'id al-'Amayirah, <ORGANIZATION>Muhammad Sa'id Muqbil Dar</ORGANIZATION>-'Awdah, 
Walid Muhammad 'Ashsha, <PERSON>Muhammad Amin al-Shamasinah</PERSON>, Ra'd 
Khalil, and 'Abd-al-Majid al-'Adharibah." 
  AL-BILAD concludes its report by promising to provide its 
readers with further details as they unfold when the <ORGANIZATION>State 
Security Court</ORGANIZATION> begins to investigate this case. 
  No further processing planned. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-59088 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes091_j_94039" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-091 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ARABIAN PENINSULA </F>
<F P=101> Yemen </F>
<H3> <TI>   GPC's al-'Ansi Rejects Arab Intervention </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    GPC's al-'Ansi Rejects Arab Intervention </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PM1005143094 London AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT in Arabic 9 May 94 p2 </F>
<F P=103> PM1005143094 </F>
<F P=104>  London AL-SHARQ AL-AWSAT </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Interview with 'Abd-al-Salam al-'Ansi, member of the </F>
<ORGANIZATION>Political Bureau</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>General People's Congress</ORGANIZATION>, by Salwa 
al-Ustuwani in <LOCATION>Damascus</LOCATION>; date not given] 
  [Text] 'Abd-al-Salam al-'Ansi, member of the <ORGANIZATION>General 
Committee</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Political Bureau</ORGANIZATION>) of the <ORGANIZATION>General People's Congress</ORGANIZATION> 
[GPC] and head of its <ORGANIZATION>General Department</ORGANIZATION>, has announced that the 
<LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION> government and people reject any Arab military 
intervention, and called on the Arab states to stop their media 
vituperation. 
  <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>, he said, will solve its own problems and the battles 
will settle the situation. The Yemeni official arrived in 
<LOCATION>Damascus</LOCATION> two days ago to meet with Yemeni leaders and figures 
and with Syrian officials to explain the explosive situation in 
his country and convey his party's views on the situation. 
  Al-'<PERSON>Ansi</PERSON> said he did not believe that the unity [of <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>] 
was at an end because "unity is the fate and destiny of the 
Yemeni people. That is what we will fight for." He added that 
intervention by Arab forces would mean promotion of secession. 
Our unity, he said, is not a unity between two peoples to 
warrant comparison with the Syrian-Egyptian unity. <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> has 
been united since the beginning of time. 
  He also said: "We do not want to be carried away with the 
Western and Arab media which are now claiming that there is 
civil war. That is a misconception. What is taking place in 
<LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> is not civil war. A civil war is a war between members of 
the public or between tribes, sects, or parties." 
  What is going on, he emphasized, is fighting between armed 
forces upholding constitutional legitimacy and forces rebelling 
against legitimacy "and we consider that to be military mutiny 
which must be destroyed by military means." 
  Then, speaking tactically, he said that "the civil war 
description applies to some southern governorates where there is 
a conflict in the governorates of <LOCATION>Abyan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Shabwah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hadramaut</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Lahij</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> between the people there, between those 
supporting the unity line and the renegade secessionist forces 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION> [YSP]." 
  [Al-Ustuwani] Would you bet on anyone in the south? 
  [Al-'Ansi] Yes, we bet on the unionist forces within the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> 
and we bank on them to settle the issue and to rebel against the 
leadership which we do not consider to be legitimate. In <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>, 
the army which is fighting the renegade and secessionist forces 
is being described by news agencies and the media as the 
northern army. It is not the northern army. It is the army of 
unity and it includes people from the south and the north. The 
opposing forces, which they describe as southern, include 
elements from the north and the south. 
  The north's big wager is on the unionist forces in <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> and 
in the armed forces. Currently there are reports that Muhammad 
'Ali Ahmad and large groups loyal to former southern President 
'<PERSON>Ali Nasir Muhammad</PERSON> are beginning to respond to <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> appeals and 
take up arms inside <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>. Battles are raging in <LOCATION>Lahij</LOCATION>, Radfan, 
al-Dali', <PERSON>Mukayris</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Abyan</LOCATION>. There is a conflict between the 
unionists and the secessionists. But there is no fighting in 
Ibb, Ta'izz, or <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>. There is no fighting between the people 
nor between one force and another there. 
  [Al-Ustuwani] What, in your view, is the solution? 
  [Al-'Ansi] It is to uphold the constitution, the will of the 
people, and constitutional legitimacy. What is now being said 
about Arab mediation is a thing of the past and no longer valid. 
If, in a calm atmosphere, the mediations in <LOCATION>Amman</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Salalah</LOCATION> 
failed, what would happen against a background of military 
conflict? 
  I urge the Arab states to refrain from mediation because 
they 
only want to take positions in the media. There are more of 
such states but they know that it would be futile to intervene 
because when guns speak, reason disappears. I urge the states 
now initiating mediations to look for something else to do. We 
Yemenis are sensitive people. Above all, we say to those who 
want to exploit the current war by internationalizing the issue 
or by sending Arab forces, or anything else, we say frankly 
that, throughout history, <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> has been the graveyard of 
invaders. That is why we reject intervention. 
  What scares us about this talk of sending forces and of 
mediation is that they are talking about Egyptian mediation and 
dispatch of forces to disengage the warring parties. That is a 
thing of the past. The Egyptians raised it two weeks ago and a 
month ago but we rejected it because the presence of forces 
would mean partition and revival of the secession. We tell 
them: Play another game, for that is out of the question as far 
as we are concerned. 
  [Al-Ustuwani] So, in your view, what is the alternative 
solution? 
  [Al-'Ansi] They should leave us alone and let us act and 
solve our own problems by military or political means. They 
would then have a clear conscience. 
  [Al-Ustuwani] Do you believe that the solution lies in the 
disappearance of the current leaderships? 
  [Al-'Ansi] Why disappearance of the leaderships? The 
solution hs been spelled out in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>. 
It used the legitimate card and dismissed 'Ali Salim al-Bid and 
<PERSON>Salim Salih Muhammad</PERSON> from their posts in the state as 
<ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION> members. That is a part of the solution. 
  As far as the north is concerned we have invoked 
constitutional legitimacy and the people's will. 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah 
Salih</PERSON> is there by popular demand. When the people tell 'Ali 
Salim al-Bid to go then he must go. But for him to impose a 
rule of fire and the sword on the people, exploit the crisis, 
and, against a background of mediation, sidestep the results we 
have achieved for our people, that is totally rejected. It is 
not a personal matter between 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON> and 'Ali 
Salim al-Bid. I am not revealing a secret when I say that some 
members of the <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> have proposed two 
names for membership of the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION> to replace 'Ali 
Salim al-Bid and <PERSON>Salim Salih Muhammad</PERSON>. They are (former 
southern President) '<PERSON>Ali Nasir Muhammad</PERSON> and '<PERSON>Abd-al-Qawi 
Makkawi</PERSON>. These are two patriotic figures with a formidable 
struggle record, respected by the Yemeni people. (It is well 
known that the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION> consists of five members who 
are: 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON>, 'Abd-al-'Aziz 'Abd-al-Ghani, 
'Abd-al-Majid al-Zindani, 'Ali Salim al-Bid, and Salim Salih 
Muhammad). 
  [Al-Ustuwani] Do you believe that the pledge and accord 
document could still be implemented or should a new document or 
a new solution be considered? 
  [Al-'Ansi] The document is still suitable as far as we are 
concerned but the mechanism must change. Once 'Ali Salim al-Bid 
and <PERSON>Salim Salih Muhammad</PERSON> are out and are replaced in the 
Presidential Council by others, matters begin to crystallize and 
solutions to be implemented. 
  [Al-Ustuwani] So you are against the war decision? 
  [Al-'Ansi] Nobody wants war. It was "force majeure." Our 
war was limited and the military eruptions and escalations were 
on a limited scale, but when this war started three days ago our 
forces were hit in <LOCATION>Abyan</LOCATION>, the central security units in <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> 
were besieged and hit, and the power station in <LOCATION>Dhummar</LOCATION> was 
suddenly hit to disrupt the power supply to <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>, and the camps 
in Dhummar were hit. It was premeditated aggression. The 
<ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Army</ORGANIZATION> (northern) could not possibly remain idle. The war 
was imposed on us and we are fighting it in defense of 
legitimacy and to strike at the centers of mutiny. 
  I wish to stress that in many of the current battles, the 
main parties involved are not northern and southern forces but 
forces of mutiny and popular forces now fighting and resisting 
the rebels in the southern governorates. 
  [Al-Ustuwani] According to some reports, the northern 
forces have reached the outskirts of <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>. Do you believe it is 
possible to take control of <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>? 
  [Al-'Ansi] God willing, the situation will certainly be 
decided and control will be gained, and the brothers will lay 
down their arms. If they want destruction for their country, 
then they should continue their aggression but we ask them to 
lay down their arms and to stop the war. 
  [Al-Ustuwani] What is the purpose of besieging <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>? 
  [Al-'Ansi] To bring them down, arrest them, and refer them 
to trial because they are the ones who triggered the war. 
  [Al-Ustuwani] Are the north Yemeni forces fighting fit, 
enough to settle the situation in <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>? 
  [Al-'Ansi] It is not just a question of fitness. We are 
fighting for what is right and we are the stronger in that 
respect. We are fighting for a cause. I am optimistic that 
<ORGANIZATION>Aden</ORGANIZATION> will be brought under control very soon, not because we are 
the stronger in authority and in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> but because the people 
are against mutiny and secession. 
  [Al-Ustuwani] If <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> is brought under control, what would 
be the steps to follow? 
  [Al-'Ansi] (Defense Minister) <PERSON>Haytham Qasim</PERSON> will be referred 
to trial according to the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>'s decision, 
because he is to blame for the war. Those responsible for the 
Dhummar and 'Imran massacres will also be referred to trial. 
Regarding the other brothers in the south, the people have 
dismissed them from the leadership, but 'Ali Salim al-Bid cannot 
be dismissed from the post of party secretary general. What is 
important is that the party should be a party in the full sense 
of the word, without militia, without forces, and without an 
iron fist. There should be a peaceful assumption of authority. 
That is what we and the Yemeni people want. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-40762 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpnea007___94012" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-NEA-94-007 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Near East &amp; South Asia 

</HEADER>

<ABS> </ABS>
<DATE1>     7 February 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> NEAR EAST </F>
<F P=101> SAUDI ARABIA </F>
<H3> <TI>   Consultative Council Committees' Members Named </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  94AE0068A Jeddah 'UKAZ in Arabic 6 Jan 94 p 5 </F>
<F P=103> 94AE0068A </F>
<F P=104>  Jeddah 'UKAZ </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Arabic </F>
Article Type:<ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FÊP=106> [Article by 'Abdallah al-'Urayfij, Muhammad al-Sahli, and </F>
'Abd-al-Rahman al-Nawwash: "Consultative Council Committees 
Formed and Their Members Nominated"] 
  [Text] <LOCATION>Riyadh</LOCATION>--The <ORGANIZATION>Consultative Council</ORGANIZATION> has continued its 
ordinary sessions, and council committees have been formed and 
their members named. Selections for each committee were as 
follows: 
<H5>  Educational, Cultural, and <ORGANIZATION>Information Affairs Committee </H5>
  Dr.</ORGANIZATION> 'Abd-al-Rahman Ibn al-Tayyib al-Ansari (committee 
chairman). Dr. Fahd al-'Arabi al-Harithi (deputy chairman). Dr. 
<PERSON>Rida Ibn Muhammad</PERSON> 'Ubayd (member). Dr. Sa'id Ibn Muhammad 
al-Mulays (member). <PERSON>Dr. Salih</PERSON> Ibn Sa'ud al-'Ali (member). Dr. 
'Abd-al-Rahman Ibn Salih al-Shubayli (member). Dr. 'Ali Ibn 
Ibrahim al-Namlah (member). Dr. Muhammad Ibn Ibrahim al-Jarallah 
(member). Dr. Muhammad al-Ahmad al-Rushayd (member). Muhammad 
Ibn 'Abdallah al-Humayd (member). <PERSON>Dr. Mansur</PERSON> Ibn Ibrahim 
al-Hazimi (member). 
<H5>  Social and <ORGANIZATION>Health Affairs Committee </H5>
  Ahmad Ibn Hamad al-Yahya</ORGANIZATION> (committee chairman). <PERSON>Dr. Falih Ibn 
Zayd</PERSON> al-Fatih (deputy chairman). Dr. Zuhayr Ibn Ahmad al-Siba'i 
(member). <PERSON>Dr. Salih Ibn</PERSON> 'Abdallah al-Malik (member). 
'Abd-al-Rahman Ibn 'Abdallah Aba-al-Khayl (member). '<ORGANIZATION>Abdallah 
Ibn Hamad</ORGANIZATION> al-Qar'awi (member). <PERSON>Dr. Mansur</PERSON> Ibn Muhammad al-Nuzhah 
(member). 
<H5>  <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Affairs Committee </H5>
  Dr. Nizar 'Ubayd Madani</ORGANIZATION> (committee chairman). Dr. Muhammad 
'Abd-al-'Aziz al-Mu'ammar (deputy chairman). Sulayman Ibn 
'Abd-al-Rahman al-Salih (member). 'Abd-al-Rahman Ibn 'Abdallah 
Aba-al-Khayl (member). Dr. 'Abd-al-'Aziz Ibn Ibrahim al-Fayiz 
(member). Dr. 'Abdallah Ibn 'Abd-al-Muhsin al-Sultan (member). 
Dr. Hashim 'Abduh Hashim (member). 
<H5>  <ORGANIZATION>Security Affairs Committee </H5>
  Retired Lieutenant General Ibrahim Ibn Muhammad</ORGANIZATION> al-Faris 
(committee chairman). Retired Major General <PERSON>Jamil Muhammad</PERSON> 
al-Miman (deputy chairman). <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad Ibn Sayr Mubaraki</PERSON> 
(member). Major General 'Abd-al-'Aziz Ibn Muhammad Al al-Shaykh 
(member). Dr. 'Abdallah Ibn 'Abd-al-Muhsin al-Sultan (member). 
Retired Major General <PERSON>Kamal Ibn</PERSON> Siraj-al-Din al-Mirghalani 
(member). Dr. Nizar '<ORGANIZATION>Ubayd Madani</ORGANIZATION> (member). 
<H5>  Rules and <ORGANIZATION>Administration Committee </H5>
  Dr.</ORGANIZATION> 'Abd-al-'Aziz Ibn 'Ali al-Nu'aym (committee chairman). 
Dr. Ziyad Ibn 'Abd-al-Rahman al-Sudayri (deputy chairman). 
Ibrahim Ibn Qadahi al-Qadahi (member). Ahmad Ibn Hamad al-Yahya 
(member). <ORGANIZATION>Shaykh Salih Ibn 'Abdallah Ibn Humayd</ORGANIZATION> (member). 
Muhammad Ibn 'Abdallah al-Nafi' (member). 
<H5>  <ORGANIZATION>Islamic Affairs Committee </H5>
  Dr. Hamad Ibn Muhammad</ORGANIZATION> al-Faryan [or al-Furayyan] (committee 
chairman). <PERSON>Dr. Ahmad Ibn Sayr Mubaraki</PERSON> (deputy chairman). 
Ibrahim Ibn 'Abd-al-Fattah Julaydan (member). <PERSON>Dr. Usamah Ibn 
'Abdallah Khayyat</PERSON> (member). Dr. Zahir Ibn 'Awwad al-Alma'i 
(member). <PERSON>Dr. Salih Ibn Zayn</PERSON> al-'Abidin al-Shaybi (member). 
Al-Shaykh Salih Ibn 'Abd-al-Rahman al-Mazru' (member). Al-Shaykh 
<ORGANIZATION>Salih Ibn 'Abdallah Ibn Hamid</ORGANIZATION> (member). Dr. 'Abd-al-Rahman Ibn 
al-Tayyib al-Ansari (member). Dr. 'Ali Ibn Ibrahim al-Namlah 
(member). Al-Shaykh Muhammad Ibn 'Abdallah al-Salim (member). 
<H5>  Economic and <ORGANIZATION>Financial Affairs Committee </H5>
  Khalid Ibn Muhammad</ORGANIZATION> al-Qusaybi (committee chairman). Tawfiq 
<PERSON>Ibn Ibrahim Tawfiq</PERSON> (deputy chairman). <ORGANIZATION>Bakri Ibn Salih Shata</ORGANIZATION> 
(member). <PERSON>Dr. Jamil Ibn</PERSON> 'Abdallah al-Jashi (member). Dr. Ziyad 
Ibn 'Abd-al-Rahman al-Sudayri (member). Dr. 'Abd-al-Rahman Ibn 
Ahmad al-Ja'fari (member). Dr. 'Abd-al-'Aziz Ibn Ibrahim 
al-Fayiz (member). Dr. <PERSON>Ali Ibn Talal</PERSON> al-Jahni (member). 
'Abd-al-Latif Ibn Hamad al-Jabr (member). Muhammad Ibn Ahmad 
Zaynal (member). Muhammad Ibn 'Abdallah al-Sharif (member). 
<H5>  <ORGANIZATION>Public Services and Utilities Committee </H5>
  Dr. Faysal Ibn Ahmad Zaydan</ORGANIZATION> (committee chairman). '<ORGANIZATION>Umran Ibn 
Muhammad</ORGANIZATION> al-'Umran (deputy chairman). Engineer Zuhayr Ibn Hamid 
Fayiz (member). <PERSON>Dr. Suhayl Ibn Hasan Qadi</PERSON> (member). Engineer 
'Abd-al-Qadir Ibn <PERSON>Hamzah Kawshak</PERSON> (member). 'Abd-al-'<ORGANIZATION>Aziz Ibn 
Muhammad Abu-Milhah</ORGANIZATION> (member). '<ORGANIZATION>Abdallah Ibn Muhammad</ORGANIZATION> 
al-Ghulayqah (member). Muhammad Ibn 'Abdallah al-Sharif (member). 
  On the occasion of the formation of the <ORGANIZATION>Consultative Council</ORGANIZATION> 
committees and the nomination of their members, committee 
chairmen expressed their thanks and appreciation to the members 
for their confidence in them and for selecting them as chairmen. 
  In this regard, Dr. 'Abd-al-Rahman al-Ansari, the Education, 
Culture, and <ORGANIZATION>Information Committee</ORGANIZATION> chairman, has said in a 
statement to 'UKAZ that the committee will discuss whatever 
pertains to education, culture, and information and to the rules 
connected with these areas. It will also discuss whatever issues 
the council refers to it for study and for an opinion. The 
committee is scheduled to hold its meetings every <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>. 
  Dr. 'Ali al-Namlah, an Education, Culture, and <ORGANIZATION>Information 
Committee</ORGANIZATION> member, has expressed his great happiness at becoming 
a member of this committee, which studies and examines issues 
pertaining to several important areas, namely education, 
culture, and information--areas concerned with developing the 
citizen and enhancing his skills and intellectual capacities. 
  On his part, retired Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Ibrahim al-Faris</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Security 
Affairs Committee</ORGANIZATION> chairman, has expressed in a statement to 
'UKAZ his pride in the confidence shown in him through his 
selection to the committee chairmanship. He has said, "First of 
all, I thank God, may He be praised and exalted, for the help 
and success He has given me. I then thank the custodian of the 
two holy mosques for the noble and precious confidence he has 
shown in me by selecting me to be a council member. I also thank 
His Excellency [Council] President al-Shaykh <PERSON>Muhammad Ibn Jubayr</PERSON> 
and all my colleagues the council members for their confidence 
and good opinion of me." Al-Faris pointed out that the <ORGANIZATION>Security 
Affairs Committee</ORGANIZATION> will concern itself with whatever touches on 
the security and military sector generally and that it will 
study all issues and matters referred to it by the council 
president. He also noted that the committee will examine the 
rules and proposals connected with the security and military 
sectors. 
  In a statement to 'UKAZ, <PERSON>Ahmad al-Yahya</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Health and 
Social Affairs Committee</ORGANIZATION> chairman, has also expressed his pride 
in the confidence his colleagues the council members showed in 
him by selecting him committee chairman. Al-Yahya emphasized 
that he will coordinate firmly with the committee members to 
produce the fruits for which the council aspires from this 
committee. He said that the committee will tend social issues, 
such as social security and welfare, and labor and workers' 
affairs, in addition to environmental issues and to whatever is 
connected with health, plus whatever other issues are entrusted 
to this committee. He added that the committee will meet every 
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-59526 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes094_j_94018" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-094 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ARABIAN PENINSULA </F>
<F P=101> Yemen </F>
<H3> <TI>   Yemeni Socialist Party Offers Cease-Firea Plan </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Yemeni Socialist Party Offers Cease-Firea Plan </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    YSP Official on Conditions </H4>

<F P=102> JN1305195094 Paris Radio Monte Carlo in Arabic 1741 GMT 13 
May 94 </F>

<F P=103> JN1305195094 </F>
<F P=104>  Paris Radio Monte Carlo </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Interview with <PERSON>Salim Salih Muhammad</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION> </F>
member and assistant <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> secretary general, by <PERSON>Salim Badawi</PERSON>; 
place and date not given; from the weekly "The Event" 
program--recorded] 
  [Text] [Muhammad] Following the eruption of battles in 
<LOCATION>Sufyan</LOCATION> and the 3d Brigade, the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION>] 
called for the formation of an inquiry commission. Regrettably, 
the incidents continued. The <ORGANIZATION>Ba Suhayb Brigade</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Dhamar</LOCATION> was 
also attacked, after which the military situation exploded. We 
really regret the accusations. We also urge the stopping of 
this bleeding, this crushing war raging among the sons of the 
Yemeni people, which claims the lives of <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>'s sons. 
  [<PERSON>Badawi</PERSON>] Concerning the nature of war, <PERSON>Mr. Salim Salih 
Muhammad</PERSON>, the northern Yemenis claim that the fighting is taking 
place between the Constitutional legitimacy and the rebelling 
forces of the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> leadership, as they put it. What is the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION>'s 
viewpoint on the nature of the raging conflict? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Muhammad</ORGANIZATION>] Are we not also part of the legitimacy? Have we 
not assumed power in light of the results of elections in the 
country? Are we not part of the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Council of Ministers</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>, and the 
other state institutions? We do not come from islands in the 
<LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>. We come from <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>. We are <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>'s sons. We 
have been representatives of a state and a recognized legitimate 
power. We have achieved unity on an equal basis with our 
brothers in the north. Such claims do not render any service. 
In fact, they further exacerbate the conflict. Very 
regrettably, they also open a very deep wound in Yemeni unity 
and national unity. 
  [<PERSON>Badawi</PERSON>] The northerners' conditions for a cease-fire are 
represented by the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> leadership's adherence to Constitutional 
legitimacy, and the submission to the legitimacy led by 'Ali 
'<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON>, as they say. Are you willing to accept these 
conditions? What are your conditions, as the <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION>, to stop 
fighting? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Muhammad</ORGANIZATION>] The <ORGANIZATION>YSP</ORGANIZATION> has never proposed that 'Ali 'Abdallah 
Salih should be finished or go, or that the existing legitimacy, 
represented by the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Council of 
Ministers</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, or the other existing state 
institutions, should go. However, he who has made the war 
decision, and who is waging it now against his sons, army, and 
people, to prove that he is the strongest and the triumphant, he 
is the one who will eventually lose history and the people. 
  [<PERSON>Badawi</PERSON>] What are your conditions for a cease-fire? 
  [Muhammad] We have no conditions other than actually 
beginning to implement the pledge and accord document, to 
recognize people's rights and duties, and to build the modern 
Yemeni state. Some sides believe the military option will give 
them the upper hand over everything, and enable them to 
establish their regime the way they want, in accordance with 
their own interpretations. Such a decision, I believe, is a 
crazy decision. The <ORGANIZATION>Yemeni Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> and Yemeni 
installations are now being destroyed. Innocent people are 
being killed, the Yemeni people in <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>, al-Dali', <LOCATION>Abyan</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Shabwah</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Dhamar</LOCATION>. These people are the victims of this crazy 
war which will not achieve the objectives of those who ignited 
the war. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Badawi</ORGANIZATION>] President 'Ali '<PERSON>Abdallah Salih</PERSON> was quoted as saying 
that he wants to try 'Ali Salim al-Bid and his men, or to allow 
them to leave the country. What is your opinion about this? 
  [Muhammad] I have not heard such a thing. What I ask for 
now, from he who has reason and really wants to avoid further 
involvement in these crazy battles which, as I said, claim the 
lives of the sons of the Yemeni people, we ask them at this 
critical moments when the homeland is suffering from an ordeal 
and fragmentation, to stop the war immediately and resort to the 
language of dialogue, logic, and reason. 
  [<PERSON>Badawi</PERSON>] What about the dismissal decisions that affected 
senior southern officials, led by 'Ali Salim al-Bid? The 
northerners say that southern deputies participated in the 
voting sessions. Is that true? 
  [Muhammad] In your opinion, and in view of the current 
conditions, the state of emergency, and in view of the campaigns 
of physical liquidation we heard about in <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>, who would 
participate in such sessions? What kind of democratic, peaceful 
atmosphere would they have in a state of war? The world, the 
Arabs, and the Yemenis must understand what is going on in <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION> 
now. The situation is serious. It needs assistance from all 
our brothers and friends. 
  [<PERSON>Badawi</PERSON>] With regard to the rumors about appointing a 
successor to 'Ali Salim al-Bid and others in the central 
government in <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>, especially in the Presidential Council -- a 
probable candidate is rumored to be 'Ali Nasir Muhammad -- how 
do you view such reports? 
  [Muhammad] These issues are presented as bargaining chips in 
order to be used in haggling. In my opinion, the people have 
this right. The people gave their votes to their 
representatives in areas from which we came. These people have 
this right. 
  [<PERSON>Badawi</PERSON>] Now that the situation cannot be decided on the 
battlefield -- a week has passed since the outbreak of 
hostilities -- what are the chances that a return to dialogue 
will be effected and unity saved? 
  [Muhammad] There is no other way, regardless of the battles. 
The warring sides must eventually negotiate. I think that 
regardless of the harshness of the situation or the number of 
victims, we must preserve what is left and resort to the correct 
method, the method of dialogue, irrespective of differences. As 
for the war methods, regardless of their quick results, it will 
have very serious consequences in the future. It will not only 
cause wounds but will lead to a great suffering and moving the 
Yemeni people 30 to 40 years backward. 
  [<PERSON>Badawi</PERSON>] In your view, is it possible to save the unity? 
  [Muhammad] In my opinion, if the political will that was 
available when the unity was reached is still there, the answer 
is yes. However, judging by the methods that are being used in 
the battlefields and the vindictive way military personnel are 
dealing with unarmed civilians in towns and villages, deep 
wounds have been caused in national Yemeni unity. 
  [<PERSON>Badawi</PERSON>] Do you expect mediation, especially Arab mediation, 
to result in positive results, particularly in the foreseeable 
future? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Muhammad</ORGANIZATION>] There is mediation and there are Arab efforts, 
but 
regrettably the brothers in <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION> are rejecting all this. They 
believe the military solution is the ideal solution. This 
reading of the situation and of reality is tantamount to 
gambling. We wish them guidance from God. We wish they are 
guided to the right path. 
  [<PERSON>Badawi</PERSON>] In case Arab mediation fails, will you demand 
international intervention by the <ORGANIZATION>UN Security Council</ORGANIZATION> and the 
<ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Muhammad</ORGANIZATION>] So far, I have not been informed of any decisions 
from the brothers at home but we will consult on all 
possibilities, because everything is possible. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-37340 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes118_j_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-118 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  17 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ARABIAN PENINSULA </F>
<F P=101> Yemen </F>
<H3> <TI>   South's `Presidential Council' Member Meets Ibrahimi </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    South's `Presidential Council' Member Meets Ibrahimi </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   EA1806133094 Aden Democratic Republic of Yemen Radio Network 
in Arabic 2045 GMT 17 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> EA1806133094 </F>
<F P=104>  Aden Democratic Republic of Yemen Radio Network 
in Arabic 2045 GMT 17 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=105> Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Brother <PERSON>Salim Salih Muhammad</PERSON>, member of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Presidential Council</ORGANIZATION>, who arrived in <LOCATION>Jeddah</LOCATION> lately, met <LOCATION>Lakhdar 
Ibrahimi</LOCATION>, envoy of the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> secretary general to <LOCATION>Yemen</LOCATION>. 
  During the meeting, brother <PERSON>Salim Salih Muhammad</PERSON> was 
briefed on the results of the contacts conducted by the envoy of 
the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> secretary general, and highly praised the efforts exerted 
by <LOCATION>Ibrahimi</LOCATION> for implementing the <ORGANIZATION>Security Council</ORGANIZATION>'s Resolution 
No. 924. 
  Brother <PERSON>Salim Salih Muhammad</PERSON> stressed the importance of 
ceasing the hostilities immediately and stopping the random 
bombardment of the civilian residential quarters and areas in 
the capital, <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> as a result of which hundreds of innocent 
citizens, including children, women and old people, have fallen 
victim, and halting the continued destruction process of public 
services by the ruling military regime in <LOCATION>Sanaa</LOCATION>. 
  Brother <PERSON>Salim Salih Muhammad</PERSON> highlighted the current 
suffering of the inhabitants of the city of <LOCATION>Aden</LOCATION> as a result of 
the siege and the random shelling, and pointed out the heroic 
steadfastness in confronting this destructive war in defense of 
honor and safeguarding the lives of the innocent. He stressed 
the need to condemn and stop this aggression by all people, 
Arab, international organizations, and other bodies to prevent 
the dangerous repercussions which increase day by day. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-21787 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jptot014__l94087" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TOT-94-014-L </AU>
JPRS 
Terrorism 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  FOUO </ABS>
<DATE1>   8 April 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> NEAR EAST/SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> JORDAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Update on Suspects Arrested for Cinema, Other Bombings </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Update on Suspects Arrested for Cinema, Other Bombings </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Suspects' Organization, Ties, Other Plans </H4>

<F P=102> JN2903193894 </F>
<F P=103> JN2903193894 </F>
<F P=104></F>



<TEXT>
BFN 
