<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1453EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     02-04 0918</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0953</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Robert Duvall</PERSON> has prepared himself for
roles by hanging out with bums on the <LOCATION>Bowery</LOCATION>, riding horses with
the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Rangers</ORGANIZATION> and tramping through a <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> swamp with an
alligator hunter.
   He's not sure if it was all worth it.
   ``You could do all the research in the world _ sometimes it pays
off, sometimes it doesn't,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> says in the <DATE>March</DATE> issue of
Smart magazine. ``Sometimes you don't have time. You got to be a
human being up there. That's the most important thing.''
   <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON>, who won an Oscar for ``Tender Mercies'' and starred in
``The Godfather'' and ``The Great Santini,'' says he's a stickler
for detail in his characters and in films in general.
   ``When actors start acting bigger than life, bigger than the
people they play, then they're in trouble,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> said. ``For
example, I can't even talk about `Gone With the Wind.' You don't
see people in the South like that. It's a joke.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Robert Duvall</PERSON> has prepared himself for
roles by hanging out with bums on the <LOCATION>Bowery</LOCATION>, riding horses with
the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Rangers</ORGANIZATION> and tramping through a <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> swamp with an
alligator hunter.
   He's not sure if it was all worth it.
   ``You could do all the research in the world _ sometimes it pays
off, sometimes it doesn't,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> says in the <DATE>March</DATE> issue of
Smart magazine. ``Sometimes you don't have time. You got to be a
human being up there. That's the most important thing.''
   <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON>, who won an Oscar for ``Tender Mercies'' and starred in
``The Godfather'' and ``The Great Santini,'' says he's a stickler
for detail in his characters and in films in general.
   ``When actors start acting bigger than life, bigger than the
people they play, then they're in trouble,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> said. ``For
example, I can't even talk about `Gone With the Wind.' You don't
see people in the South like that. It's a joke.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Robert Duvall</PERSON> has prepared himself for
roles by hanging out with bums on the <LOCATION>Bowery</LOCATION>, riding horses with
the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Rangers</ORGANIZATION> and tramping through a <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> swamp with an
alligator hunter.
   He's not sure if it was all worth it.
   ``You could do all the research in the world _ sometimes it pays
off, sometimes it doesn't,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> says in the <DATE>March</DATE> issue of
Smart magazine. ``Sometimes you don't have time. You got to be a
human being up there. That's the most important thing.''
   <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON>, who won an Oscar for ``Tender Mercies'' and starred in
``The Godfather'' and ``The Great Santini,'' says he's a stickler
for detail in his characters and in films in general.
   ``When actors start acting bigger than life, bigger than the
people they play, then they're in trouble,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> said. ``For
example, I can't even talk about `Gone With the Wind.' You don't
see people in the South like that. It's a joke.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Robert Duvall</PERSON> has prepared himself for
roles by hanging out with bums on the <LOCATION>Bowery</LOCATION>, riding horses with
the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Rangers</ORGANIZATION> and tramping through a <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> swamp with an
alligator hunter.
   He's not sure if it was all worth it.
   ``You could do all the research in the world _ sometimes it pays
off, sometimes it doesn't,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> says in the <DATE>March</DATE> issue of
Smart magazine. ``Sometimes you don't have time. You got to be a
human being up there. That's the most important thing.''
   <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON>, who won an Oscar for ``Tender Mercies'' and starred in
``The Godfather'' and ``The Great Santini,'' says he's a stickler
for detail in his characters and in films in general.
   ``When actors start acting bigger than life, bigger than the
people they play, then they're in trouble,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> said. ``For
example, I can't even talk about `Gone With the Wind.' You don't
see people in the South like that. It's a joke.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GREENSBORO, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Robert Duvall</PERSON> has prepared himself for
roles by hanging out with bums on the <LOCATION>Bowery</LOCATION>, riding horses with
the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Rangers</ORGANIZATION> and tramping through a <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> swamp with an
alligator hunter.
   He's not sure if it was all worth it.
   ``You could do all the research in the world _ sometimes it pays
off, sometimes it doesn't,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> says in the <DATE>March</DATE> issue of
Smart magazine. ``Sometimes you don't have time. You got to be a
human being up there. That's the most important thing.''
   <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON>, who won an Oscar for ``Tender Mercies'' and starred in
``The Godfather'' and ``The Great Santini,'' says he's a stickler
for detail in his characters and in films in general.
   ``When actors start acting bigger than life, bigger than the
people they play, then they're in trouble,'' <PERSON>Duvall</PERSON> said. ``For
example, I can't even talk about `Gone With the Wind.' You don't
see people in the South like that. It's a joke.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06235017 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06235017 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2), Charts (2); PHOTO: Gates; PHOTO: Packard  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  WEALTH; MONEY; PERIODICAL; RANKING; CHART; NAME; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The rich got a tad richer this year despite the global economic slowdown,
Fortune magazine reports in its annual tally of the wealthiest billionaires.; 
 The list, which has 202 names this year vs. 182 last year, shows the average
wealth of each entry rose to $2.7 billion from $2.6 billion in 1990.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE BILLIONAIRES' CLUB
RICH GET RICHER DESPITE SAGGING ECONOMY, FORTUNE
SAYS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Chart attached at end of article  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The oil-rich Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> remains the wealthiest man for the fifth
straight year with a <MONEY>$31 billion</MONEY> hoard, the magazine estimates. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s
Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON> is the richest woman with <MONEY>$10.7 billion.</MONEY>;   Still, the
slowing world economy had an impact on the Fortune ranking, which appears in
the business glossy's <DATE>Sept. 9</DATE> editions, which go on sale <DATE>Monday</DATE>. Twenty-six
names on the list last year were gone, supplanted by a surge of new arrivals.;
  Newcomers to the list include <ORGANIZATION>GAF Corp.</ORGANIZATION> owner and former federal prosecutor
<PERSON>Samuel Heyman</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, with <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY>, and the Gap clothing chain
founders <PERSON>Donald</PERSON> and <PERSON>Doris Fisher</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> with <MONEY>$1.9 billion.</MONEY>;   Two
other <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> residents made the list: <PERSON>San Franciscan Gordon Peter Getty</PERSON>, who
with his brother <PERSON>John Paul Getty</PERSON> ranked 30th with <MONEY>$3.8 billion</MONEY>, and <PERSON>David
Packard</PERSON> and family of <LOCATION>Los Altos Hills</LOCATION>, who ranked 90th with <MONEY>$1.9 billion.</MONEY>; THE
WORLD'S 10 RICHEST; According to Fortune magazine, here are the 10 wealthiest
people and families in the world.;                            Sources         
          Wealth; Name                        of wealth           (in
billions); ...; Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>            Oil, gas, real estate       <MONEY>$31.0</MONEY>;
<PERSON>Sam Moore Walton</PERSON>            Wal-Mart stores              21.1; <ORGANIZATION>King Fahd      
            Oil</ORGANIZATION> and gas                  18.0; <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers         
Real estate, securities      12.8; Mars family                 <ORGANIZATION>Mars Inc</ORGANIZATION>.      
             12.5; <PERSON>Newhouse</PERSON> family             Publishing, broadcasting    
12.1; <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth II</PERSON>          Real estate, investments     10.7;
Taikichiro Mori             Real estate                  10.0; <ORGANIZATION>John Werner
Kluge           Metromedia Co.</ORGANIZATION>, real estate   7.1; <PERSON>Kenneth R. Thomson         
Publishing</PERSON>, retailing         6.7; Source:  Fortune magazine; <ORGANIZATION>Mercury News</ORGANIZATION>;
..............................................................; HIGH-TECH
FORTUNES; These billionaires made their fortunes; with high-technology
ventures.; Name/age                      Source               Wealth; home    
                   of wealth           (in billions); ...; <PERSON>William Gates</PERSON>
III/35     <PERCENT>33.5%</PERCENT> of software             <MONEY>$3.9</MONEY>; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>                  giant
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft Corp.</ORGANIZATION>; ...; <PERSON>William B. Ziff/61       Ziff Publications</PERSON>, publisher  
2.2; <LOCATION>Manalapan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.          of computer magazines; ...; <PERSON>David</PERSON> Packard/79    
    <PERCENT>13%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co</ORGANIZATION>.     1.9; <LOCATION>Los Altos Hills</LOCATION>      ...; <PERCENT>Paul
Allen/38            15%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, owner of     1.9; <ORGANIZATION>Seattle               
  Portland Trailblazers</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Asymetrix</ORGANIZATION>  ...; Source:  Fortune magazine; <ORGANIZATION>Mercury
News</ORGANIZATION>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910822  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  391  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, August 22, 1991
00235017,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06185012 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06185012 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Queen Elizabeth II  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  UK; GOVERNMENT; LEADER; FAMILY; PERSON; WEALTH; TAX; SURVEY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Queen Elizabeth II, one of the world's richest women, pays no income tax. A
large majority of Britons think that's wrong, by one poll, and legislator
Simon Hughes is trying to do something about it.;    Hughes planned to present
a bill in the House of Commons today proposing that the queen pay income taxes
levied on all of her considerable assets, the exact value of which are kept
secret.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  QUEEN FACES TAX DEBATE
LEGISLATION WOULD FORCE HER TO PAY FEE ON
INCOME  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The Liberal Democrat's bill apparently stands no chance of becoming law
because both the Conservative government and the leadership of the opposition
<ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION> oppose it. They don't want to upset the monarchy or its
supporters.;    But the bill was expected to test parliamentary opinion on an
issue that has attracted much media attention.;    Conservative legislator
<PERSON>Anthony Beaumont-Dark</PERSON>, Labor legislator <PERSON>Brian Wilson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hughes</PERSON> called in an
Independent Television program last week for the queen to pay taxes.;    The
rest of the royal family pays taxes.;    An opinion poll published by The
Independent on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> some weeks ago said <PERCENT>79 percent</PERCENT> of 1,090 Britons
questioned in <DATE>February</DATE> thought the queen should be taxed. The newspaper gave
no margin of error.;    Hughes estimates the <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> could raise <MONEY>$11.2
million</MONEY> a year if the queen's income were taxed. He told the <ORGANIZATION>British
Broadcasting Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in a radio program <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>: "It is completely unfair that
the richest woman in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> should be exempt.";    <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION>
officials say the queen's fortune, which includes jewel and art collections,
race horses and real estate, is a private matter. Media estimates of its worth
vary widely.;    The British magazine Harpers and Queen in <DATE>February</DATE> named her
as the world's richest woman with assets of <MONEY>$10.5 billion</MONEY>. Fortune magazine
estimated the value of her investments alone at the end of the <DATE>1980s</DATE> at <MONEY>$3.5
billion.</MONEY>;    But the Independent said <DATE>today</DATE> it was a myth that she has
billions invested. It said palace officials were content with estimates
valuing her investments at <MONEY>$192 million.</MONEY>;    A survey by the Independent today
said that elsewhere in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, the Spanish, Swedish, Belgian and Dutch royal
families all pay tax on their private fortunes. It said only the Norwegian and
Danish monarchies do not pay taxes, but they are among the royal families on
the continent with the fewest holdings.;    The queen's defenders say she
already contributes to the Exchequer through her <PERSON>Crown Estates</PERSON>, which include
farmland and <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> real estate, officially valued at nearly <MONEY>$3.8 billion</MONEY> last
year.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  London  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910703  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  12A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  411  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday July 3, 1991
00185012,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890823-0211 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-23-89 0905EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Fortune-Billionaires 1stLd-Writethru   08-23 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fortune-Billionaires, 1st Ld-Writethru,0510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fortune Billionaires List Swells With 32 New Entries</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS lead to CORRECT 27 to 32 new billionaires, SUBS 3rd graf
with editing changes to clarify; picks up 4th graf, Taiwanese investor
...</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world has 32 new billionaires this year,
according to a list compiled by Fortune magazine, including indicted
junk-bond chieftan <PERSON>Michael R. Milken</PERSON> and a Taiwanese tycoon with
holdings in insurance, hotels and soy sauce companies.
   Meanwhile, the same five individuals or families who topped last
year's list also lead the <DATE>1989</DATE> ranking, the magazine reports in its
<DATE>Sept. 11</DATE> edition, due on newsstands today.
   The list swelled to 157 members this year with the addition of 32
members, although five others fell off the ranking. The list
includes individuals and nuclear families with net worth Fortune
estimates at <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> or more.
   Taiwanese investor <PERSON>Tsai Wan-Lin</PERSON>, 64, joined the list at the No. 6
spot. The former poor farmer saw his <PERCENT>65 percent</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Cathay Life
Insurance</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> skyrocket in value and his net worth increase to
<MONEY>$9 billion</MONEY> as the <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> stock market took off, Fortune said.
   <PERSON>Milken</PERSON>, 43, who faces trial on federal charges that he violated
securities laws, joined the list at No. 125, with an estimated
fortune of <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY>.
   The Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, who presides over the small oil-rich nation
near the <LOCATION>South China Sea</LOCATION>, is still the world's wealthiest man with
an estimated fortune of <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>, the magazine stated.
   King Fahd of <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION> and his family are next with <MONEY>$18
billion</MONEY>, followed by <ORGANIZATION>Forrest E. Mars Sr.</ORGANIZATION> and the Mars candy-bar
clan, who are estimated to be worth <MONEY>$12.5 billion</MONEY>.
   Ranked fourth after the Mars family was the world's richest
woman, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, who is worth an estimated <MONEY>$10.9
billion</MONEY> compared with <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY> last year, Fortune reported.
   Fifth on the list were New York-based publishing magnates <PERSON>Samuel
I. Newhouse Jr.</PERSON> and <PERSON>Donald E. Newhouse</PERSON>, worth an estimated <MONEY>$10
billion</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart Stores</ORGANIZATION> mogul <PERSON>Sam Moore Walton</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Bentonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, was
seventh with <MONEY>$8.9 billion</MONEY>; the <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers _ <PERSON>Albert</PERSON>, <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Ralph</PERSON> _ whose Ontario-based <ORGANIZATION>Olympia &amp; York</ORGANIZATION> is the largest owner of
<LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> commercial real estate, are eighth with <MONEY>$8.4 billion</MONEY>;
British real estate tycoon <PERSON>Gerald Grosvenor</PERSON> is ninth with <MONEY>$6.9
billion</MONEY>; and <PERSON>Kenneth Roy Thomson</PERSON>, who controls <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Thomson
Newspapers Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, was ranked No. 10 with estimated wealth of <MONEY>$6.9
billion</MONEY>.
   Among other newcomers are <PERSON>Carl C. Icahn</PERSON>, the takeover strategist
who also is chairman and chief stockholder of <ORGANIZATION>Trans World Airlines
Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and worth an estimated <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY>; <ORGANIZATION>Turner Broadcasting System</ORGANIZATION>
Chairman <PERSON>Ted Turner</PERSON>, <MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Kirk Kerkorian</PERSON>, helped by the
sale this year of <ORGANIZATION>MGM-UA Communications Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY>; and
<PERSON>Ronald O. Perelman</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Revlon Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$3.2 billion</MONEY>.
   Of those on the list, there are 58 in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 54 in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, 23 in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, including 11 Japanese, and 22 others.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900822-0216 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-22-90 0239EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Fortune-Billionaires     08-22 0738</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fortune-Billionaires,0763</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fortune Billionaires Club Worth Nearly Half A Trillion</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY43 of Aug. 21.</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With BC-Billionaires-List</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If you wondered why oil is worth fighting for,
take a look at Fortune magazine's latest ranking of the world's
billionaires.
   The two richest people on the face of the earth are oil barons,
the magazine reported <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Sultan <PERSON>Haji Hassanal Bolkiah</PERSON>, oil-rich leader of the tiny
<LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> sultanate of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, retained Fortune's top title for the
fourth straight year with an estimated worth of <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>,
unchanged from <DATE>1989</DATE>.
   Saudi Arabia's <ORGANIZATION>King Fahd</ORGANIZATION> and clan, a focus of the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>
crisis, ranked second with assets worth <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>, also unchanged
from last year.
   Fortune spokeswoman <PERSON>Emma Dockendorff</PERSON> said those estimates were
based partly on oil prices in mid-July, when one barrel of crude
fetched about <MONEY>$18</MONEY>.
   Prices have since surged to about <MONEY>$28</MONEY> a barrel following <LOCATION>Iraq</LOCATION>'s
<DATE>Aug. 2</DATE> invasion of <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> move to protect neighboring
<LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>. That price jump would make the sultan and the king
potentially even wealthier.
   The ranks of Fortune's richest _ bankrolled by assets ranging
from oil to sneakers to ball bearings _ swelled by 25 names this
year to 182 individuals and families, controlling a combined empire
worth <MONEY>$471.3 billion</MONEY>.
   That's up about <PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT> from last year and enough to erase the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> budget deficit, trade deficit and a good chunk of the savings
&amp; loan bailout tab.
   Fortune released the fourth annual ranking in its <DATE>Sept. 10</DATE>
issue. It said the average entrant's wealth was only slightly
higher compared with last year after adjusting for inflation.
   But the average fortune was still worth about <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY>,
which if invested in <PERCENT>7.5 percent</PERCENT> <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Treasury</ORGANIZATION> bills would earn
<MONEY>$534,000</MONEY> a day.
   ``True, you shouldn't feel too sorry for folks who have their
own islands and castles, use Reniors for wallpaper and control, in
the aggregate, <MONEY>$471.3 billion</MONEY>,'' Fortune said.
   As competitor Forbes magazine did in its annual list released
last month, Fortune ditched the Sultan of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Donald J.
Trump</PERSON>, whose real estate and casino empire is bogged down in debt.
The magazine had estimated his holdings at <MONEY>$1.7 billion</MONEY> last year.
   Fortune placed <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> in a separate category of fallen tycoons,
who also included troubled takeover strategist <PERSON>James Goldsmith</PERSON> and
convicted financier <PERSON>Michael Milken</PERSON>.
   Ranked third on Fortune's list was the reclusive Mars family of
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, whose holdings include <ORGANIZATION>Mars Inc.</ORGANIZATION> candy bars,
<ORGANIZATION>Uncle Ben</ORGANIZATION>'s Rice and Kal-Kan pet food, worth <MONEY>$12.5 billion</MONEY>.
   Fourth was <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, the wealthiest woman,
with an untaxed personal fortune of <MONEY>$11.7 billion</MONEY> in riches ranging
from 267,000 acres of <ORGANIZATION>Royal</ORGANIZATION> real estate to racehorses, crown jewels
and a vast stock portfolio.
   Fifth was the <PERSON>Newhouse</PERSON> family of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, owners of a
large media empire, worth <MONEY>$11.5 billion</MONEY>; sixth was the <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON>
family of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, with extensive real estate holdings valued at
<MONEY>$11.1 billion</MONEY>; tied for seventh were <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s
richest industrialist, and <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> retailing mogul <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>,
both valued at <MONEY>$7.3 billion</MONEY>; eighth was <PERSON>John W. Kluge</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>, owner of media giant <ORGANIZATION>Metromedia Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, valued at <MONEY>$7.0
billion</MONEY>; ninth was <PERSON>Tsai Wan-lin</PERSON> and family of <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>, owners of a
construction and insurance empire worth <MONEY>$6.5 billion</MONEY>; 10th was the
<ORGANIZATION>Thomson</ORGANIZATION> family, owners of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s biggest newspaper chain, at <MONEY>$6.2
billion</MONEY>.
   American newcomers included the <PERSON>Stephens</PERSON> family of <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>,
owners of investment banking, energy and real estate holdings worth
<MONEY>$1.7 billion</MONEY>; the <PERSON>Parfet</PERSON> family of <LOCATION>Kalamazoo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, owners of a
large stake in the <ORGANIZATION>Upjohn Co.</ORGANIZATION> drugmaker, worth <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY>; and
<PERSON>Philip Knight</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Nike Inc.</ORGANIZATION> athletic footwear maker, <MONEY>$1.3
billion</MONEY>.
   Foreign newcomers included <PERSON>Alicia</PERSON> and <PERSON>Esther Koplovitz</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>,
owners of a <MONEY>$2.2 billion</MONEY> construction and banking fortune; <PERSON>Hiroshi
Termachi</PERSON>, owner of a <MONEY>$1.8 billion</MONEY> Japanese ball bearing business;
and <PERSON>John Spyros Latsis</PERSON>, European head of a Saudi Arabian shipping
and oil-refinery network worth <MONEY>$1.8 billion</MONEY>.
   The magazine based estimates of net worth on what it called
``published information or appraisals of asset values.'' To
qualify, each prospect needed a net worth of <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> or more
after subtracting debt.
   Fortune said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> remained home to the greatest
number of billionaires at 58. Twenty were from the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, 15
from <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, nine from <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, and eight in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, down from
12 last year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910822-0080
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910822-0080.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Sultan of Brunei Is Richest
   In the World, Says Fortune
</HL>
<DATE>
08/22/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B2
</SO>
<CO>
   TWX
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Brunei's Sultan, Haji Hassanal Bolkiah
Mu'Izzaddin Waddaulah, is still the world's richest man --
and considerably richer than he was last year, says Fortune
magazine.
   The sultan, whose wealth is mainly in oil and gas reserves
and real estate, now has $31 billion, up from $25 billion in
1990, according to Fortune's annual survey of billionaires.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   This year, there are 202 billionaires on Fortune's list,
up from 182 in <DATE>1990</DATE>, with 41 new billionaires added and 26
delisted. Average net worth is <MONEY>$2.7 billion</MONEY>, up <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>
form <DATE>1990</DATE>'s average.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> has 60 billionaires, the most of any country,
including the second-biggest billionaire, <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, who is
worth, along with his family, <MONEY>$21.1 billion</MONEY>. <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> has 23
billionaires, including <PERSON>Prince Albert</PERSON> von Thurn und Taxis; at
eight years old, he is the youngest billionaire on Fortune's
list. <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> have 23, 14 and 12,
respectively.
   Newcomers to the list are <PERSON>Donald</PERSON> and <PERSON>Doris Fisher</PERSON>, <MONEY>$1.9
billion</MONEY>, who founded the <ORGANIZATION>GAP Inc.</ORGANIZATION> clothing chain; and <PERSON>Samuel
Heyman</PERSON>, <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY>, who owns most of chemical maker <ORGANIZATION>GAF</ORGANIZATION>.
Among the fallen are <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Harold Simmons</PERSON>, both
victims of wilting stocks.
   The magazine also profiled 13 billionairesses. Leading the
pack was Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, whose net worth was reported at
<MONEY>$10.7 billion</MONEY>. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> cosmetics queen <PERSON>Estee Lauder</PERSON> and
family are second, with <MONEY>$5.2 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880225-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-02-25-88 1244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Rich     02-25 0581</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Rich,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Queen Tops List of Britain's Wealthiest 200</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL WEST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, whose personal fortune is a
closely guarded secret, is <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s richest person worth an
estimated <MONEY>$5.87 billion</MONEY>, according to a list of the nation's 200
richest people.
   The list was front-page news in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, with racy
tabloid headlines ranging from ``Filthy Rich'' in the Sun to
``Millionaires Galore'' in the Daily Mail.
   Money Magazine, which complied the list, said the
second-wealthiest Briton as 92-year-old Sir <PERSON>John Moores</PERSON>, founder of
the <ORGANIZATION>Littlewoods</ORGANIZATION> soccer pools empire, a weekly game for small-time
gamblers based on soccer results. It estimated his fortune at <MONEY>$2.99
billion</MONEY>.
   It listed the third-wealthiest Briton as supermarket chain owner
<PERSON>Garfield Weston</PERSON>, 60, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Associated British Foods</ORGANIZATION>, with an
estimated personal fortune at <MONEY>$2.64 billion</MONEY>.
   In fourth place is the 36-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Duke of Westminster</ORGANIZATION>. His
inherited holdings include large chunks of highly desireable real
estate in central <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, huge tracts of farmland and sweeping
acres of remote northern moorland. The magazine said his personal
fortune was about <MONEY>$2.46 billion</MONEY>.
   Money Magazine says <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> has seven billionaires, 18 families
and individuals worth more than <MONEY>$440 million</MONEY> each, and 20,000
millionaires as measured in pounds.
   The magazine's estimate of the 61-year-old queen's wealth makes
her the world's eighth-richest individual. It said the world's
richest person is the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, with an estimated fortune
equivalent to <MONEY>$24.64 billion</MONEY>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of Records</ORGANIZATION> lists the richest person in the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> as <PERSON>Sam Moore Walton</PERSON>, founder of <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> discount
stores in <LOCATION>Bentonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, whose personal wealth was estimated in
mid-1987 at <MONEY>$4.5 billion</MONEY> ``and rising.''
   Money Magazine said financier Sir <PERSON>James Goldsmith</PERSON> _ fifth in its
list of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s wealthiest 200 with an estimated <MONEY>$1.76 billion</MONEY> _
was the only British billionaire to have made all his money since
the end of World War II in <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   The youngest person in the top 200 is 31-year-old <PERSON>Sophie Mirman</PERSON>,
with an estimated <MONEY>$52.8 million</MONEY>. She and her husband, <PERSON>Richard Ross</PERSON>,
created the popular Sock Shop chain.
best-selling raunchy novels. It said they are worth an estimated
<MONEY>$26.4 million</MONEY> between them.
   Editor Sue <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> said it took six months to compile the list,
``consulting public sources of information and talking extensively
to analysts in the <LOCATION>City</LOCATION>,'' <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s financial district.
   ``The people we did not talk to were the 200 themselves because
we wanted to keep the list under wraps until the last possible
minute. Many of the super-rich are very secretive,'' she said.
   Asked how it estimated the queen's wealth in view of the secrecy
maintained by her <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> bankers, <ORGANIZATION>Coutts and Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mrs. Thomas</PERSON> said:
``We found out as much as we could about the different headings
under which her wealth falls _ her castles and other properties,
her land holdings, her vast share portfolio, her stamp collection,
her art collection, her jewelry collection and so forth and we
talked to a lot of people with information.
   ``We arrived at what we estimate to be a minimum net worth for
all the people on our list.''
   It said 53 of the 200 fortunes stemmed from property. Five
percent of those listed came from abroad and only <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> belong
to the British aristocracy. The self-made rich outnumbered those
who inherited their wealth by 2-1.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110989-0089 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 132211 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 9, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 1; Column 4; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1119 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
'ROYAL WATCHER' KEEPS TABS ON ALL THE WINDSOR RICHES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By GARRY ABRAMS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Queen of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> is worth well over 2,000 times her weight in gold. 
</P>
<P>
Roughly. 
</P>
<P>
In mere money, the 126-pound monarch, almost certainly the world's richest 
woman at any weight, possesses somewhere between <MONEY>$1.72 billion</MONEY> and <MONEY>$2.04 
billion</MONEY>. And -- here's the good part -- it's all tax free. 
</P>
<P>
Moreover, a good chunk of the royal private fortune derives from gifts, some 
dating back to the days of <PERSON>Queen Victoria</PERSON>, of jewels, land and hefty sums of 
cash from maharajahs, sheiks, sultans and subjects who show no signs of turning 
off the tap to the sovereign -- or her family. 
</P>
<P>
These estimates are made by <PERSON>Andrew Morton</PERSON>, professional "royal watcher," who 
traced the British royal family's private holdings -- in precious gems, 
estates, art, investments, race horses, automobiles, even a stamp collection -- 
to come up with what he claims is the best guess yet of how rich the royal 
family really is. 
</P>
<P>
Of course estimates of the royal riches are cranked out regularly, in what 
amounts to a mini-industry. Last <DATE>September</DATE>, Fortune magazine put the queen's 
worth at <MONEY>$10.9 billion</MONEY>. Other estimates have varied wildly over the years from 
a few paltry millions to as much as <MONEY>$26 billion</MONEY>, all of which <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> maintains 
are skewed by questionable motive or bad information. 
</P>
<P>
"There is this huge wall of secrecy surrounding anything to do with the royal 
family," <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> said in an interview in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. "Everybody thinks they 
know everything about the Windsors. They know nothing. The often used image is 
that the Windsors live in a goldfish bowl. If it's a goldfish bowl, it's one 
that's been blacked out." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Morton</PERSON> has laid out his stalking of the royal finances in a new book published 
simultaneously here and in <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, where it was excerpted in a national 
newspaper and is due to be serialized in other publications. 
</P>
<P>
"Theirs Is the Kingdom: The Wealth of the British Royal Family" is studded with 
the usual royal tidbits: a Canadian air force jet being dispatched to return 
Prince <PERSON>Charles</PERSON>' "beloved" crocodile shoehorn left behind on a visit to 
<LOCATION>Winnipeg</LOCATION>, the queen diverting her yacht so that she could mail a letter, for 
instance. 
</P>
<P>
But the core of the book is a cold-eyed banker's assessment of the origins and 
disposition of the private wealth that supports the <ORGANIZATION>House of Windsor</ORGANIZATION>. One 
chapter traces the development of the family's finances from Queen <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON> to 
the present, including deductions based on the limited evidence available about 
the current queen's stock portfolio, apparently brimming with mining and 
electronic issues and estimated to be worth <MONEY>$595 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$680 million</MONEY> by 
<PERSON>Morton</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I hired somebody for two months who was a proper stocks and shares expert to 
look into this thing because their (the royal family's) stocks and shares are 
disguised by something called the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> nominee accounts, which were 
set up by the government in order specifically to shield the queen's 
investments from investigation," <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> explained. 
</P>
<P>
The book's appendix includes an inventory of "known" royal jewels, estimates of 
land values and income from estates and other holdings, including a shopping 
center. 
</P>
<P>
The inventory of Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>'s private jewelry -- as opposed to the crown 
jewels and other property held in public trust -- includes a tiara last seen in 
public in <DATE>1911</DATE> with an estimated value of <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> and a 94.4-carat diamond 
valued at <MONEY>$9.5 million</MONEY>. The assessment made for <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> puts the total value of 
the diamonds, emeralds, rubies, pearls and sapphires at <MONEY>$60.6 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$71 
million</MONEY>. It is a conservative estimate and does not include the market value -- 
up to 10 times or more of assessed worth -- that would be added because of 
their royal ownership, according to <PERSON>Morton</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
During his investigation, <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> said he bumped into a lot of obstacles -- laws 
that shroud royal investments in secrecy, uncooperative sources close to the 
royal family and the family's own fierce protection of its privacy. For 
example, since the time of Queen <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON>, royal financial advisers have taken 
"the secrets that they have to the grave," he said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Morton</PERSON> is the author of seven books about the royal family, a former newspaper 
correspondent who covered the royal beat and now proprietor of <ORGANIZATION>Palace Press</ORGANIZATION>, an 
independent news agency specializing in news and features about the royal 
family. But even for him, <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> admitted, much of royal life is unknown 
territory. Not only that, but the royals are protected by a "global myth 
machine" that further obscures the difference between royal image and reality, 
<PERSON>Morton</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"The royal family, like the best actors, put on a very good display for the 
public but in private they are very different people," he continued. "They're 
not everything that the public thinks. For example, the royal family today 
lives very much the way Queen <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON> did. Prince <PERSON>Charles</PERSON>, this man who is 
described as 'everyman, the crusading prince,' still goes grouse shooting with 
kings, dines with billionaires and millionaires in exactly the same way that 
<PERSON>Edward VII</PERSON> did a hundred years ago." 
</P>
<P>
One instance of royal obfuscation occurred in <DATE>1986</DATE> when a sapphire and diamond 
ensemble was omitted from the list of official gifts made to the Prince and 
Princess of <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION> by the Sultan of <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> said. The ensemble, estimated 
to be worth <MONEY>$1.7 million</MONEY> and designated as a private gift, was only admitted to 
exist a year later when the Princess happened to wear them in public, he added. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Morton</PERSON> theorized that this royal reluctance "rightly shows the embarrassment 
they feel" about receiving such lavish gifts. 
</P>
<P>
Like the monarchy itself, the giving of gifts to the royal family is an 
enduring anachronism, <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> said. "I find the psychological and sociological 
aspects of it just fascinating," he said. "Why give to the richest woman in the 
world? . . . In a sense it shows that we're not really that far off from 
primitive tribes, that we live in a global village and that we still look to 
the equivalent of the squire on the hill." 
</P>
<P>
Morton contends, however, that the royal family will not always be able to 
protect its private wealth and enjoy unique privileges. 
</P>
<P>
In his book he notes, "The Windsors have shrewdly used the shield of their 
public duties to construct an armor of legal concessions, ranging from their 
wills to their shares, to deflect the arrows of outrageous inquiry. 
</P>
<P>
"It is a question of fine judgment for the royal family -- and ultimately 
Parliament -- about how long their legal and tax advantages, secured by dint of 
their public role, can coexist alongside their increasingly vocal demands to be 
left a lone and treated as ordinary people. Ironically the very success of the 
<LOCATION>Windsor</LOCATION> dynasty may prove to be its undoing." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Andrew Morton, on probing royal family finances: "There is this huge 
wall of secrecy surrounding anything to do with the royal family." MINDY 
SCHAUER; Photo, Queen Victoria: Jewels, lands, cash. ; Photo, (South Bay 
Edition) All that glitters: the Queen of England Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ENGLAND -- ROYAL FAMILY; WEALTHY PEOPLE -- FINANCES; SECRECY; ELIZABETH II 
(QUEEN OF ENGLAND); MORTON, ANDREW; FINANCIAL DISCLOSURE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880824-0291 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-24-88 2132EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Fortune-Billionaires     08-24 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fortune-Billionaires,0395</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magazine Says Mars Candy Bar Family Richest in America</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: For release 6 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Mars candy-bar clan is worth <MONEY>$12.5 billion</MONEY>,
surpassing the <ORGANIZATION>Newhouse</ORGANIZATION> publishing dynasty as the richest family in
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, Fortune magazine reports.
   If Fortune's estimate is correct, the worth of the Marses could
buy about 25 billion regular-size Snickers bars, which if laid end
to end would circle the planet Mars nearly 32 times.
   The magazine's calculation is more than any previous estimate of
the wealth of the secretive family, which shuns publicity about
itself and its candy bar company, maker of Snickers and M&amp;Ms.
   ``Mars's assets are often underestimated because the company is
as loose with information as its McLean, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, neighbor, the <ORGANIZATION>CIA</ORGANIZATION>,''
<PERSON>Fortune</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in an advance press release about its <DATE>1988</DATE>
Billionaires List, to be carried in the <DATE>Sept. 12</DATE> issue available on
newsstands next <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The magazine said it based the estimate of the Marses' wealth on
what comparable food concerns have sold for recently.
   ``Thus, <ORGANIZATION>Forrest Mars</ORGANIZATION> and his three children, <PERSON>Forrest Jr.</PERSON>, <PERSON>John
and Jacqueline</PERSON>, overtake the <PERSON>Newhouse</PERSON> publishing magnates as the
richest Americans,'' Fortune said.
   Still, the Marses rank No. 3 on Fortune's worldwide list. The
richest remains the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, whose oil wealth makes him
worth <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>. Next is King Fahd of <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION> and family,
worth <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>.
   Fourth is <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Queen Elizabeth II with <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY>; next
is the <LOCATION>Newhouses</LOCATION>, whose communications holdings are worth <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY>; in sixth place is retail king <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, founder of
<ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION> stores, and family, worth <MONEY>$7.4 billion</MONEY>; seventh is
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> family, with <MONEY>$6.3 billion</MONEY> in assets that range
from swank <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> real estate to interests in railroads and
utilities.
   Eighth is <PERSON>Kenneth Irving</PERSON> and family, a Canadian clan that owns
400 companies worth <MONEY>$6.2 billion</MONEY>; ninth is <PERSON>Kenneth Thomson</PERSON> and
family, Canadian owners of a publishing, retailing, energy and real
estate empire worth <MONEY>$6 billion</MONEY>; and in 10th place is <PERSON>Gerald
Grosvenor</PERSON> and family, British land barons worth <MONEY>$5.4 billion</MONEY>.
   Of the 129 individuals and nuclear families that comprise this
year's list, there are 51 in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 38 in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, 19 in
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> _ including 12 Japanese _ 13 Arabs and eight others, Fortune
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06188066 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06188066 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: AP File Photograph; Queen Elizabeth's fortune is exempt from
taxes  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  UK; LEADER; WOMAN; FINANCE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Is she or isn't she the world's richest woman? And should she or shouldn't she
pay taxes on her income, just like everyone else? Those brash questions about
Queen Elizabeth II were raised in Parliament this week by Liberal Party Member
of Parliament Simon Hughes, in a move that reflected the opinion of a majority
of citizens.;    More than 70 percent of the British, polls show, believe her
income should be subject to taxes. Or as Hughes put it, "When so many people
in my (London) constituency are scraping along and asked to contribute tax on
very low incomes, it seems grossly unfair that the person with the highest
income escapes. And there's no reason a modern constitutional monarch
shouldn't pay taxes."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COUNTING QUEEN ELIZABETH'S MILLIONS
ESTIMATES PLACE MONARCH'S WEALTH AT $7.4
BILLION  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The queen's personal net worth has long been a matter of considerable
speculation and argument, since, unlike <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> heads of state, she is not
required to make public the amount of her wealth and she has not volunteered
the information. Estimates range on the high side -- Fortune magazine
estimates it at <MONEY>$7.4 billion</MONEY>, with an annual income of perhaps <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> a
day; <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> snorts that such a sum is "grossly exaggerated." There
also is a more modest estimate that her income is <MONEY>$35 million</MONEY> annually.;   
Over the years, researchers have tried to estimate the queen's personal
capital and income. Those assets are different from the institutions of the
monarchy, including the crown jewels in the Tower of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and the official
residences of <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Castle</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Windsor Castle</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Holyrood Castle.</ORGANIZATION>;    As
far as current official income goes, she receives from the British government
-- in what is called the Civil List -- 7.9 million pounds, or about <MONEY>$12.5
million</MONEY>. That sum is much more than her royal household expenses, giving her a
comfortable surplus this year. (Her employees, incidentally, pay taxes on
their salaries.);    But the queen has other major resources: Whatever money
she inherited from her father, <PERSON>King George VI</PERSON>; a vault full of precious jewels
-- crowns, tiaras, diamonds, rubies, emeralds; <ORGANIZATION>Faberge</ORGANIZATION> eggs; and the royal art
collection with 900 <PERSON>Leonardo Da Vinci</PERSON> drawings, 26 Van Dycks and works by
other masters. There is also one of the world's most valuable stamp
collections.;    Further, she owns hundreds of thousands of prime agricultural
acres, as well as valuable property in central <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. Then there are <LOCATION>Balmoral</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Sandringham</LOCATION> castles with 64,000 acres between them. Not to be forgotten
are the royal stud farms and stables.;    The queen's major source of income
may be her private investments, which have accrued tax-free over a long
period. In <DATE>1971</DATE>, to quiet speculation, the palace let it be known that her
investment portfolio in stock shares did not exceed 50 million pounds.;   
Taking an even lower figure of 35 million pounds, <PERSON>Andrew Morton</PERSON>, author of
"Theirs Is the Kingdom: The Wealth of the Windsors," consulted experts who
estimated that, if reasonably wisely invested, the portfolio would be worth
600 million pounds today. He estimates the queen's personal wealth at <MONEY>1.2
billion pounds</MONEY>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  London  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910706  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  13A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  513  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday July 6, 1991
00188066,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900521-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-21-90 0130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--ThriftyQueen     05-21 0179</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Thrifty Queen,0185</SECOND>
<HEAD>Queen Elizabeth Grumbles at Clothes Costs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, believed to be the world's
richest woman, grumbles about the price she has to pay for her
clothes and is happier wearing a pair of comfortable old shoes,
according to her favorite couturier.
   Sir <PERSON>Hardy Amies</PERSON> says in the <DATE>May 23</DATE> issue of the Woman's Own
weekly that the queen is not a ``clothes person.''
   The designer, who will be 81 in <DATE>July</DATE>, is Dressmaker by
Appointment to Her Majesty the Queen, a title granted by <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham
Palace</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``She grumbles about our prices, drops hints and things, but she
has been told ... that those are the prices,'' <PERSON>Amies</PERSON> said.
   He said the queen often ignores his advice.
   ``She doesn't care, basically. She listens to our advice, then
goes off and wears shabby shoes because they're comfortable.
   ``In my opinion that is perfectly all right. It's only the hoi
polloi who criticize,'' he said.
   Princess <PERSON>Anne</PERSON>, the queen's daughter, ``won't pay our prices and
she's happy with the way she dresses,'' said Amies.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06094183 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06094183 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Martin takes a Tracy role; PHOTO: Queen Elizabeth is very
wealthy.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ENTERTAINMENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IT MIGHT interest Americans to recall that Queen Elizabeth, who will be
visiting the United States in May, is the richest woman in the world
(according to the new Charles Higham-Roy Moseley book "Elizabeth and
Philip").;    Will the queen visit her cotton plantation in Scott, Miss.? It
is known as the Delta and Pine Land Company, and consists of 38,000 acres of
rich soil, a factory and a mill. It was worth about $44 million back in 1968.
In Texas, will she visit the wealthy Standard-Oil-of-New-Jersey heir, William
S. Farish? She visited Farish and his wife soon after the Falklands War at
their beautiful farm and estate in Kentucky. (This Texas millionaire and the
queen have horse breeding in common.)  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WILL QUEEN VISIT HER U.S. HOLDINGS?  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Grapevine  </MEMO>
<TEXT>   BRIDAL SEARCH: <PERSON>Phoebe Cates</PERSON> (<PERSON>Mrs. Kevin Kline</PERSON>) was all set for the role of
the blushing, virginal, newlywed-to-be in the <PERSON>Charles Shyer-Nancy Myers</PERSON> remake
of the <ORGANIZATION>MGM</ORGANIZATION> classic, "Father of the Bride." (This team did "Baby Boom" and
"Private Benjamin.") Then Mother Nature stepped in. Cates became pregnant, but
her agents thought she could play the part before this became evident. The
producers didn't agree. So <PERSON>Cates</PERSON> is now out of the movie and her replacement
is still being sought.;    From what I hear, blushing, virginal young things
are hard to find in <LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION>. Reps for the film have even gone to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> to
look, with no success. It seems most young actresses these days dress and look
so sophisticated, so polished, so "tough" if you will, that even the truly
virginal among them seem to have been "through the mill.";    According to
<LOCATION>Sandollar</LOCATION> producer <PERSON>Howard Rosenman</PERSON>, this remake will be a straight update of
the <DATE>1950</DATE> original. <PERSON>Steve Martin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Diane Keaton</PERSON> are to play the <PERSON>Spencer
Tracy-Joan Bennett</PERSON> roles. <ORGANIZATION>Martin Short</ORGANIZATION> will be the supercilious "wedding
coordinator." And whatever sweet young thing takes over from <PERSON>Cates</PERSON> will have
the burdensome knowledge that she is doing a role <PERSON>Elizabeth Taylor</PERSON> made
famous.;    Actually, in <DATE>1950</DATE>, <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> was a virginal young thing.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  From Liz Smith in New York  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910403  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  357  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday April 3, 1991
00094183,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900709-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-09-90 1548EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-World'sRichest 2ndLd-Writethru f0154 07-09 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World's Richest, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0154,0722</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japanese Developer Again Tops Billionaires List, But Trump Missing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf pvs to CORRECT day of week. Also moving on
general news wires.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With BC-World's Richest-List</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY13, Graphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BART ZIEGLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Japanese developer again topped a list of the
world's richest people, but the annual tally has one conspicuous
deletion this year: <PERSON>Donald J. Trump</PERSON>.
   Despite the financial troubles of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> developer, the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> continues to contain the world's largest number of
billionaires _ 62 _ according to estimates by Forbes magazine. In
addition, there are 37 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> families with fortunes over <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>,
<ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> says in its <DATE>July 23</DATE> issue.
   Forbes, in estimates released <DATE>Monday</DATE>, says the world's
wealthiest person for the fourth straight year was <PERSON>Yoshiaki
Tsutsumi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, whose railroad and real estate empire includes
golf courses, ski resorts and hotels. Forbes estimated his net
worth at <MONEY>$16 billion</MONEY>, up about <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> from last year.
   That estimate was far greater than that of rival business
magazine Fortune, which put Tsutsumi's net worth at <MONEY>$3.1 billion</MONEY>
last <DATE>September</DATE>.
   Fortune said the world's richest person is the Sultan of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>,
at <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>. Forbes excludes heads of state from consideration.
   Following the 56-year-old <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON> on the Forbes list was
Japanese developer <PERSON>Taikichiro Mori</PERSON>, a former economics professor
who now owns 78 office buildings. Forbes put Mori's net worth at
<MONEY>$14.6 billion</MONEY>.
   Ranked third was the family of <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, founder of <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart</ORGANIZATION>,
the third-largest <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>retail chain. Forbes estimates that the
Waltons, who also were third-ranked last year, are worth <MONEY>$13.3
billion</MONEY>, up from <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1989</DATE>.
   America's du <PERSON>Pont</PERSON> family was fourth, with a net worth estimated
at <MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY>. They were followed by <PERSON>Hans</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gad Rausing</PERSON>, two
Swedish brothers who control a packaging empire worth <MONEY>$9.6 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Kitaro Watanabe</PERSON>, a Japanese real estate owner, was sixth at <MONEY>$9.2
billion</MONEY>. He was followed by <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers, owners of
the <ORGANIZATION>Olympia &amp; York</ORGANIZATION> real estate company, at <MONEY>$9 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Kenkichi Nakajima</PERSON> and his family, founder of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s largest
maker of pachinko machines, a gambling game similar to pinball,
were eighth at <MONEY>$8.4 billion</MONEY>.
   <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Shin Kyuk-ho</PERSON>, who owns a candy and real estate
empire, was ninth at <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY> to <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>; and <PERSON>Forrest E. Mars</PERSON>
and family of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, of Mars candy fame, were 10th at
an estimated <MONEY>$6 billion</MONEY>.
   Other American families with net worth exceeding <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>
included the <ORGANIZATION>Newhouse</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Hearst</ORGANIZATION> and Cox families, which derive their
fortunes from publishing and broadcasting; the Bass family of
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>; the <PERSON>Mellon</PERSON> family of banking fame; the <PERSON>Dorrance</PERSON> family,
whose wealth comes from <ORGANIZATION>Campbell Soup Co.</ORGANIZATION>; and <PERSON>Bill Gates</PERSON>, founder
of the computer software company <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>John Werner Kluge</PERSON> remained the richest American individual,
according to <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Kluge</PERSON>, founder of the media company
<ORGANIZATION>Metromedia</ORGANIZATION>, has an estimated net worth of <MONEY>$5.2 billion</MONEY>, placing him
in a tie for 12th place on the worldwide list with the Newhouses.
   As for <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> put his net worth last year at <MONEY>$1.7
billion</MONEY>, but it dropped sharply this year as the value of his real
estate and airline empire plummeted. In <DATE>April</DATE>, the magazine said he
was worth about a half <MONEY>a billion dollars</MONEY>. Some sources peg it even
lower.
   Forbes says one trend it noticed in compiling this year's list
was the number of wealthy Germans. The magazine identified 38 West
German billionaire families _ far more per capita than in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> or
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The list includes 40 Japanese and 99 American individuals or
families with a net worth over <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   Forbes says it identified 271 billionaire individuals or
families worldwide, up from 226 last year. The compilation is based
on recent stock valuations, comparable real estate valuations and
currency exchange rates, among other factors.
   The magazine says it excludes from consideration royal families
and heads of state because their wealth ``derives more from
political heritage than from economic effort.''
   But it doesn't exclude drug dealers. Among the billionaires it
lists are <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON>, the head of the
<LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cocaine cartel, at about <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>, and <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON>
family, at about <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA033090-0046 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 196894 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 30, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 5; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
630 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BOOK REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
ARTISTIC SENSE INFUSES A RICH CHARACTER STUDY; 
</P>
<P>
A CLOUD ON SAND BY GABRIELLA DE FERRARI, KNOPF $19.95, 323 PAGES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ELAINE KENDALL 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Born in <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> to Italian parents and educated in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Gabriella De 
Ferrari</PERSON> has written her first novel in her third language. Though trained as a 
diplomat, she became director of <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>'s Museum of Contemporary Art, then 
curator of the renowned <ORGANIZATION>Fogg Museum</ORGANIZATION>. All three national cultures and both 
professional disciplines figure significantly in "A Cloud on Sand," which 
begins in a small Italian coastal village, moves on to a provincial South 
American city with a sizeable Italian population, and is suffused throughout 
with an artistic sensibility to landscape, color and form. 
</P>
<P>
The fact that the book is written in the English taught to an adult instead of 
the language naturally acquired by a child lends the prose a formal and 
somewhat dated quality perfectly suited to a story set abroad in the period 
from <DATE>1920</DATE> to the end of World War II. There's a lushness here, a sense of 
hyper-reality and an expansiveness of character that contrasts strongly with 
our contemporary home-grown pragmatism. The frame of reference is never taken 
for granted, but generously supplied by a variety of sensory images, so that 
the reader not only visualizes the exotic settings, but perceives the 
particular sounds, tastes and textures. At first the structure seems somewhat 
arbitrary and obscure. A woman named <PERSON>Marta</PERSON>, unidentified until the end of the 
novel, is asking questions of <LOCATION>Antonia</LOCATION>, eliciting the detailed answers that 
become the novel proper. After a brief prologue that takes place on a ship 
leaving <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON> for the fictional town of <LOCATION>Pica</LOCATION>, in the country of Yayaku 
adjoining <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, we're transported back to <LOCATION>Antonia</LOCATION>'s girlhood in a small 
fishing village on the Italian Riviera. 
</P>
<P>
The time is the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, and <LOCATION>Artemisia</LOCATION> is generally by-passed by foreign 
travelers eager to get from <LOCATION>Genoa</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Florence</LOCATION>. Artemisia has few attractions, 
though it does boast a grand white stone villa set squarely in the midst of the 
crumbling medieval streets. This is <LOCATION>Antonia</LOCATION>'s home, built as her father's 
capitulation to the wishes of her mother, <PERSON>Dora</PERSON>. After their wedding, <PERSON>Antonia</PERSON>'s 
father had taken his capricious peasant bride to <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, where he was one of 
the newly prosperous Italian settlers. After one look at <ORGANIZATION>Buenos Aires</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Dora</PERSON> 
refused to disembark, returning to <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> on the boat that brought her. Bowing 
to her indomitable will, her husband built the grand villa in <LOCATION>Artemisia</LOCATION>, 
visiting his family twice a year. In his long absences, <PERSON>Dora</PERSON> conducted herself 
as a single woman, taking a succession of casual lovers but soon settling upon 
the gentle and devoted Count <PERSON>Mora</PERSON>. He would be her protector for the rest of 
her days, acting in loco parentis for <PERSON>Antonia</PERSON> and her brother <PERSON>Marco</PERSON>, mitigating 
Dora's often baleful influence upon the children. 
</P>
<P>
In turn, <PERSON>Antonia</PERSON> falls in love and marries an Italian businessman living in 
<LOCATION>Yayaku</LOCATION>. Her character strengthened by the count's lofty ethical principles, 
<PERSON>Antonia</PERSON> remains in the remote outpost in which she finds herself, though she is 
still enough her mother's daughter to insist on living according to her own 
instincts and desires, not caring if she outrages Pica's tightly-knit and 
conservative Italian community. She becomes a strong and capable woman, a wife 
perhaps more adored than adoring, but essentially content with her 
extraordinary existence. 
</P>
<P>
De <ORGANIZATION>Ferrari</ORGANIZATION> gives us a spacious gallery of domestic interiors and landscape 
studies, re-creating the curious atmosphere of a European colony two continents 
away from its source; trapped in a time warp even more alienating than mere 
geographical distance. Against these rich, dense backgrounds, her characters 
grow in strength and vitality, welcoming us into a mysterious, vanished world. 
</P>
<P>
Next: "Springs of Living Water" by <PERSON>Karen Lawrence</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Villard Books</ORGANIZATION>). 
</P><P></P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Book Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920303-0091
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920303-0091.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- The Gallery:
   MoMA Gets Former CBS CEO's Art Trove
   ----
   By Jack Flam
</HL>
<DATE>
03/03/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   New York -- The late William S. Paley, founder and
longtime chairman of CBS, was widely considered to be about
as tough as they come. But he was also an enthusiastic
collector of modern paintings and an avid supporter of the
Museum of Modern Art -- and in those areas of his life he
seems to have given rein to his gentler and more generous
impulses. "The William S. Paley Collection," in which the
more than 80 works that he recently bequeathed to MoMA are
being shown together publicly for the first time, provides a
double reason for celebration.
   The first reason is that this extraordinary collection
contains a number of important and beautiful works that will
complement and fill out the museum's own permanent collection
in significant ways. The second is that Mr. Paley had the
generosity, good sense and good taste to allow the museum to
display his collection as it sees fit. Unlike a number of
other major collectors, who insist that their collections be
exhibited intact regardless of the best interests of the
institutions that receive them, and who even bargain with
museums on that basis, Mr. Paley made his bequest with no
strings attached. This kind of generosity reaffirms the
viability of MoMA's admirable policy of not dividing its
permanent collections into little monuments to big egos, by
refusing to accept collections that come with the proviso
that they must be displayed separately forever and for all
time.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   But then again, <PERSON>Mr. Paley</PERSON> was a very particular kind of
collector who had a very special relationship to <ORGANIZATION>MoMA</ORGANIZATION>. He
became a trustee of the museum in <DATE>1937</DATE>, when it was only
eight years old, and he served on its board for many years
before he went on to become president in <DATE>1968</DATE>, and eventually
chairman, during the museum's crucial years of expansion
between <DATE>1972</DATE> and <DATE>1985</DATE>. When he died in <DATE>1990</DATE>, he was chairman
emeritus.
   Moreover, although he put together an exceptional
collection, <PERSON>Mr. Paley</PERSON> was not a collector in the usual sense.
He began to buy modern pictures in <DATE>1935</DATE>, at a time when doing
so was not particularly fashionable, and he bought them by
following his own tastes and enthusiasms rather than by
pursuing some ideal "wellrounded" or "comprehensive"
collection. He once stated his rule of thumb for collecting
as "Don't buy it unless you can't live without it." And
indeed, most of the pictures in his collection seem to
reflect the more passionate preoccupations of the man who
acquired them. They tend to be richly painted and rather
intimate in scale and feeling-contemplative rather than
dramatic, and sensuous rather than showy. In the fullest
sense, his collection was part of his private, rather than
his public life. He shunned publicity related to it, was
reluctant to lend works from it, and got most of his ego
gratification in places other than the art world.
   <PERSON>William Rubin</PERSON>, director emeritus of <ORGANIZATION>MoMA's Department of
Painting</ORGANIZATION> and Sculpture, has installed the <PERSON>Paley</PERSON> collection
with great sensitivity to its particular strengths. The works
are thoughtfully arranged in a setting that is at once
spacious but intimate, and that is as attentive to the rich
physical presence of the pictures as to the ideas and
historical lessons implicit in them. As a result, little gems
like <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION>'s delightful "Strawberries" or Manet's tiny but
electric rendering of "Two Roses on a Tablecloth" come across
as vividly as the larger and historically more important
pictures, such as <PERSON>Derain</PERSON>'s brilliantly colored "Bridge Over
the Riou" of <DATE>1906</DATE>, which is a significant addition to the
museum's fauve collection.
   The tone of the exhibition is nicely set by the first work
you see, <PERSON>Gauguin</PERSON>'s beautifully painted "The Seed of the
Areoi." In it, a nude Tahitian woman holds in her hand a
flowering seed, a potent symbol of her own sensuality and
procreative force, which is further reinforced by the
resonant colors and rich visual textures of the picture as a
whole. As in many other paintings in the show, the
wonderfully fresh surface offers a further delight to the
eye. Similarly, the haunting poetry of <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s famous "Boy
Leading a Horse" of 1905-06 is wonderfully intensified by its
matte surface, which emphasizes the picture's seductive
combination of austere idealization and insistent
physicality. In <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s lessknown but almost equally
impressive "Nude With Joined Hands" of <DATE>1906</DATE>, the fresh,
shimmering pinks of the background envelop the woman's body
in an incandescent glow.
   Both <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION> considered Cezanne to be a god of
painting, and the master of <LOCATION>Aix</LOCATION> might well be considered
MoMA's household deity. It is thus especially gratifying to
see the museum finally acquire a self-portrait by <ORGANIZATION>Cezanne</ORGANIZATION>,
bearded and sporting a rather jaunty straw hat. The museum's
already fine Cezanne collection will also be markedly
enhanced by the addition of a grand and richly painted
L'Estaque landscape and of a powerfully composed and
vigorously painted still life.
   Although MoMA has one of the best <ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION> collections in
the world, it has been surprisingly weak in works from the
socalled Nice Period, from <DATE>1918</DATE> to <DATE>1930</DATE>. The <PERSON>Paley</PERSON> collection
includes four Matisses from this period. A small <DATE>1918</DATE>
landscape, which has the freshness of a colored drawing, and
a charming little <DATE>1923</DATE> "Woman With Anemones" are fairly
typical of <ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION>'s somewhat low-key work during this
period. But the two others are among the most impressive
pictures <PERSON>Matisse</PERSON> did during the <DATE>1920s</DATE>. The vibrant "Odalisque
With a Tambourine" of <DATE>1926</DATE> is painted with an extraordinary
combination of virtuosity and abandon, while the enigmatic
"Woman With a Veil" of <DATE>1927</DATE> combines the ambition and
pictorial complexity of <ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION>'s earlier, more abstract
works with the directness and sensuality that he cultivated
at Nice.
   From such heights, <PERSON>Mr. Paley</PERSON>'s collecting trailed off
after World War II, and his holdings in more recent American
art are distinctly less significant than those in earlier
French art. Nonetheless, there are some pleasant surprises.
Chief among these is the unexpectedly painterly "Homage to
the Square in Green Frame" by <PERSON>Joseph Albers</PERSON>, which is one of
that rather chilly artist's least impersonal works. Even in
the cool world of geometrical abstraction, <PERSON>Mr. Paley</PERSON> was able
to find at least a tremor of sensuality.
   "The <PERSON>William S. Paley</PERSON> Collection" is accompanied by a
thorough and informative catalog written by <PERSON>William Rubin</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Matthew Armstrong</PERSON>. The exhibition will be on view at <ORGANIZATION>MoMA</ORGANIZATION>
through <DATE>April 7</DATE>. After that, it will travel to <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>
before it returns to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to be integrated into the
museum's permanent collections in the <DATE>spring of 1994</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-6126</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DE3ARADQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930529
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  29 MAY 93 / Seriously Rich: Brazil - the beautiful and the damned /
Christina Lamb describes trillionaire life in the country with the biggest
gap between rich and poor
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CHRISTINA LAMB
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>BRAZIL</LOCATION> is perhaps the only country in the world where the entire working
populace are millionaires. Unfortunately, most are also poor. With a million
cruzeiros now worth Dollars 25, to be seriously rich in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> one must have
a good few trillion stashed away.
And plenty such people exist. Forget the <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> of economic crises, growing
slums, ailing Indians and Dollars 2,000 per capita income. Instead, welcome
to the country which is second only to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> in purchase of private jets
and where high society is so flourishing that the <ORGANIZATION>Association of Columnists</ORGANIZATION>
boasts more than 500 working members and even the <ORGANIZATION>Journal of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> has a
large gossip column.
Wealth is flaunted. At one favourite hangout, <LOCATION>Leopoldos</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Sao Paulo</LOCATION>,
diners watch images of themselves and other customers projected on to a
giant videoscreen, enabling close scrutiny of who is wearing what and
flirting with whom. In tropical Rio, fur wraps are de rigueur for true
socialites.
These are the authentic beautiful and the damned. 'Beautiful' because in the
world capital of plastic surgery, nobody with money is allowed to retain
nature's imperfections. Nose jobs, face lifts, bottom tucks, cellulite
removal, breast implants - the decision is not if but when the next cut
should come. <PERSON>Ivo Pitanguy</PERSON> is <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s high priest of plastic surgery;
fittingly, he has become a member of the serious rich himself, owning an
island south of Rio.
'Damned' because <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has the world's biggest income gap between rich and
poor - a contrast particularly obvious in <LOCATION>Rio</LOCATION>, where luxury apartments rub
shoulders with sprawling slums. Already the crime rate is so high that even
the only-slightly-rich live behind bars protected by armies of security
guards and drive bullet-proof cars. Sometimes, sipping cocktails on their
penthouse terraces, rich Brazilians look at the lights of the surrounding
slums and wonder how long before the masses swarm upon them, demanding
justice.
Meantime, they are having a ball. 'The Brazilian elite are like a bunch of
people having a wild champagne party on a boat which is heading towards the
edge of <ORGANIZATION>Niagara Falls</ORGANIZATION>,' says a World Bank official.
The day starts late for <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s seriously rich. For the women it begins
with exercises or a jog along the beach, followed by a light lunch at a
restaurant such as Antiquarius to discuss the events of the previous night.
Then it is a trip to the hair salon, perhaps tea at the <LOCATION>Copacabana Palace</LOCATION>,
then home to prepare for a party or dinner at one of Rio's classy French
restaurants - Le <ORGANIZATION>Bec</ORGANIZATION> Fin, <PERSON>Claude Troisgros</PERSON> or Le Meridien. For the younger
set, preferred hangouts are Banana cafe or Gattopardos, followed by dancing
at Hippopotamus.
Weekends are spent messing about on boats, jetskis and microlites in the
coastal resorts of <LOCATION>Angra</LOCATION> dos <PERSON>Reis</PERSON> or <LOCATION>Buzios</LOCATION>, or horse-riding in the
mountains of <LOCATION>Petropolis</LOCATION>. There are also frequent trips to the requisite
fazenda in the country, and to <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> where rich
Brazilians descend on fashion houses like <ORGANIZATION>Chanel</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Balenciaga</ORGANIZATION>, practising
the French that it is so chic to speak at home.
Although <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s security problems have caused a few of the rich to flee
permanently, most return. According to <PERSON>Jeff Thomas</PERSON>, a leading society
writer: 'They love to see their names in the papers; abroad, they are not
celebrities.'
There is nothing like being rich in a developing country. Even the
moderately well-off can maintain armies of servants, including
white-uniformed nannies to walk the baby and handlers to exercise the dog.
And while strict import laws meant that, until recently, some trappings of
wealth, such as cell phones and smart cars, were unobtainable, even for the
richest, they could still live like kings.
Behind the high brick walls surrounding the estate of 'Baby' <PERSON>Monteiro de
Carvalho</PERSON>, one of Rio's most favoured sons, you encounter mansion after
mansion (one for each of his children) on the long drive until finally
reaching the colonnaded main house, which is like something out of a de
Mille movie.
Brazilian governments have seemed exclusively interested in improving the
lot of the rich, preferring to spend money on subsidies and incentives for
large industry and agriculture rather than social welfare. Monopolies have
been protected, land reform carefully skirted.
The coffee and sugar barons of the past have been replaced by
industrialists, media moguls and bankers, the latter scooping profits from
the soaring inflation rate. Owners of construction companies have also grown
rich from huge development projects at inflated costs which are responsible
for much of the <ORGANIZATION>Third World</ORGANIZATION>'s largest foreign debt.
Proving that crime pays in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, the serious rich also include a fair
number of organised crime bosses, plus corrupt politicians and officials.
Former president <PERSON>Fernando Collor</PERSON> and his frontman, P C <PERSON>Farias</PERSON>, transformed
from a used car salesman to a multi-millionaire, have not let disgrace
interfere with their lifestyles. <PERSON>Orestes Quercia</PERSON>, who recently resigned as
head of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s largest political party, is alleged to have built a fortune
of as much as <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 1bn during stints as governor of <LOCATION>Sao Paulo</LOCATION>.
In spite of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s social apartheid, the serious rich do not let
themselves be troubled by such things as conscience. You will rarely catch
the rich wives of Rio dirtying their hands in good works. As one society
woman told me: 'The poor are always robbing us, my dear, so why should we
give them money ?'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BRZ  Brazil, South America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P99   Nonclassifiable Establishments.
    P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page II
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102990-0056 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 299721 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 29, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
745 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
STAGE REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
CHILLING GROUND OF 'SECRET RAPTURE' 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SYLVIE DRAKE, TIMES THEATER WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Rapture seems an unlikely term with which to associate the majority of the 
venal, weak, self-centered characters in <PERSON>David Hare</PERSON>'s "The Secret Rapture" at 
<ORGANIZATION>South Coast Repertory</ORGANIZATION>. The word is not used in the scuba diving sense, as in 
rapture of the deep, although spiritual euphoria is part of the mystery Hare 
attempts to evoke. As he explains it, "The 'secret rapture' is that moment at 
which a nun expects to be united with Christ. In other words, it's death." 
</P>
<P>
If that sends a shiver through you, it should. A kind of chill stalks "The 
Secret Rapture" from the moment light slices through blackout as a woman 
nervously opens a door and is startled to find her sister sitting in the dark 
room. Their father has died; his body is on the bed. Lives will be changed, not 
by the event of death, which is only a trigger, but by the forces of 
interpersonal and public politics that will rush in to fill the void. 
</P>
<P>
Hare has not made a secret of his fascination with how larger societal forces 
shape our private ends. He tackled that notion in "Plenty," a psychological 
dissection of post-World War II <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> seen through the collapse of one woman. 
In "Rapture," he has taken the fallout of Thatcherism and created an unlikely 
morality play through the secular canonization of another. 
</P>
<P>
Of the sisters mentioned earlier, <PERSON>Marion</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Bairbre Dowling</ORGANIZATION>) is a junior minister 
in a hidebound conservative government while <PERSON>Isobel</PERSON> (<PERSON>Caroline Goodall</PERSON>) is an 
artist. They have only one thing in common: their late father's widow, 
<PERSON>Katherine</PERSON> (<PERSON>Libby Boone</PERSON>), a much younger woman, alcoholic and incapable of 
coping responsibly. She becomes their unequally shared responsibility. 
</P>
<P>
Isobel loves, lives and works with <PERSON>Irwin</PERSON> (<PERSON>Simon Templeman</PERSON>), another artist with 
whom she ekes out a contented living. She is interior, tender, idealistic. 
Marion is exterior, self-righteous and, by her own eventual admission, 
incapable of feeling ("I don't have the right equipment"). She is married to 
<PERSON>Tom</PERSON> (<PERSON>Hal Landon Jr.</PERSON>), a born milquetoast and born-again Baptist who heads 
something called Christians in Business. 
</P>
<P>
The road to destruction is subtle, even if <PERSON>Hare</PERSON>'s play isn't always. First 
<PERSON>Marion</PERSON> allows <PERSON>Katherine</PERSON> to inflict herself on Isobel. Later <PERSON>Marion</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tom</PERSON> in a 
"Christian" desire to "help," bedevil <PERSON>Isobel</PERSON>'s and <PERSON>Irwin</PERSON>'s life with 
self-serving temptations that alter chemistries and wreak ultimate chaos. 
</P>
<P>
The play, which achieves this with uneven success, ends with a tortured 
epiphany that won't bear repeating. "Secret Rapture" is not about plot or 
cause, but about effect. It's about the malice of weakness and the 
powerlessness of strength. It's about currents and resistance, humanity and 
honor. In short, it is dangerous, difficult stuff. After such plays as 
"Speed-the-Plow," "Serious Money," "Glengarry <PERSON>Glen Ross</PERSON>," "Palladium Is Moving" 
and even "Other People's Money," "The Secret Rapture" is, as <PERSON>Hare</PERSON> himself 
recognizes, an attempt "to buck the trend. Unfashionably," says he, "I have a 
heroine." 
</P>
<P>
And then some. Under <PERSON>David Emmes</PERSON>' spare and precise direction, the production 
at <ORGANIZATION>SCR</ORGANIZATION> is a part of <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>'s ongoing Festival of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. The design 
team and the cast are a hands-across-the-sea mixer, with the excellent <PERSON>Goodall</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Templeman</PERSON> hailing from <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, along with set designer <PERSON>Robert Jones</PERSON>, whose 
supply of ever-changing, meticulously detailed locales would seem to defy the 
logistics of storage and wing space. 
</P>
<P>
Boone is a vibrant manic-depressive as <PERSON>Katherine</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Dowling</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Marion</PERSON> is 
shrill and obnoxious enough in her tailored suits to conjure up the inevitable 
associations. <PERSON>Elizabeth Dennehy</PERSON> provides some entertaining man-eating moments 
as her shallow assistant <PERSON>Rhonda</PERSON>, while <PERSON>Landon</PERSON>'s apologetic piety and limpness 
seem a loaded act of perpetual self-erasure. But the play pivots around the 
complex <PERSON>Isobel</PERSON> and, only because he is so inextricably the instrument of her 
fate, around <PERSON>Irwin</PERSON>. Templeman manages to embody weakness with plenty of 
presence, while <PERSON>Goodall</PERSON>'s generous and inviting Isobel thoroughly eludes 
self-pity. 
</P>
<P>
This is a play destined to arouse polemics, but it is curious to recall that it 
did so earlier this year for the wrong reasons, when <PERSON>Hare</PERSON> challenged <ORGANIZATION>New York 
Times</ORGANIZATION> critic <PERSON>Frank Rich</PERSON> to a duel of words after Rich reacted negatively to the 
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> production Hare had directed. Rich declined, but the furor persisted 
-- unfortunately so. The play deserves to be talked about not for its Rich 
review, but for the richness of its content. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, (Orange County Edition) Libby Boone as Katherine with her late husband's 
family in "The Secret Rapture" at South Coast Repertory. ; Photo, Bairbre 
Dowling enters the room where Caroline Goodall is mourning their father in "The 
Secret Rapture." KARI RENE HALL / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Play Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890314-0193 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-14-89 2000EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-RoyalPay     03-14 0656</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Royal Pay,0674</SECOND>
<HEAD>Royal Family Gets Pay Increase of 4.6 Percent, Below Inflation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON> and her family got a pay
increase in <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s annual budget of <PERCENT>4.6 percent</PERCENT>, which was lower
than inflation but still means they will cost the taxpayers <MONEY>$10.6
million</MONEY>.
   The increase of 273,000 pounds (<MONEY>$466,800</MONEY>) brought the total to
6,195,300 pounds (<MONEY>$10,594,000</MONEY>), and was too much for some <ORGANIZATION>Labor
Party</ORGANIZATION> legislators whatever its relation to the cost of living.
   ``For the royal family, it looks as though Christmas has come
early,'' Labor member <PERSON>Max Madden</PERSON> said in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Commons</ORGANIZATION>.
   An increase of <PERCENT>4.6 percent</PERCENT> for the Civil List, as the royal
allowances are known, compares with annual inflation of <PERCENT>7.5 percent</PERCENT>,
up from <PERCENT>3.3 percent</PERCENT> a year ago.
   Members of the royal family are paid for carrying out such
official duties as receiving ambassadors, presenting awards, opening
hospitals, visiting the armed forces and making foreign tours.
   Most of the money goes to salaries for the 350 royal household
staff, from private secretaries to coachmen, gardeners and window
cleaners at <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION> and the other royal residences.
   Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>, rich in in her own right, will receive <MONEY>4.65
million pounds</MONEY> (<MONEY>$7.96 million</MONEY>) in the <DATE>1989-90 fiscal year</DATE>, up from
<MONEY>4.55 million pounds</MONEY>.
   Her 88-year-old mother, <ORGANIZATION>Queen Mother Elizabeth</ORGANIZATION>, will get 404,000
pounds (<MONEY>$691,000</MONEY>), and <PERSON>Prince Philip</PERSON>, her husband, will be paid
225,300 pounds (<MONEY>$385,000</MONEY>).
   The queen's youngest son <PERSON>Prince Edward</PERSON>, 25, who quit the <ORGANIZATION>Royal
Marines</ORGANIZATION> and now works as a production assistant for a theater
company run by composer <PERSON>Andrew Lloyd Webber</PERSON>, does not get a raise.
He has received 20,000 pounds (<MONEY>$34,200</MONEY>) a year since <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   Prince <PERSON>Charles</PERSON>, heir to the throne, and his wife <PERSON>Diana</PERSON> are not on
the list because he is Prince of <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION> and lives on income from the
Duchy of <LOCATION>Cornwall</LOCATION> estates. That amounted to <MONEY>1.4 million pounds</MONEY> (<MONEY>$2.4
million</MONEY>) last year.
   The largest percentage raise was for the queen's second son,
<PERSON>Prince Andrew</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Duke of York</ORGANIZATION>, a naval lieutenant on a destroyer. His
state allowance rises from 86,500 pounds (<MONEY>$148,000</MONEY>) to 155,400
pounds (nearly <MONEY>$266,000</MONEY>), or more than <PERCENT>79 percent</PERCENT>. He also will get
21,000 pounds (nearly <MONEY>$36,000</MONEY>) in service pay plus allowances.
   Andrew has been accused of taking too much leave and not handling
enough royal duties to justify his allowance.
   <PERSON>Madden</PERSON> called the raise a ``monster increase'' that would ``amaze
and astonish'' most people, who he said would not find much benefit
for themselves in the budget.
   Andrew's raise will pay for his office at <ORGANIZATION>Buckingham Palace</ORGANIZATION>,
established in <DATE>1986</DATE> when he married <PERSON>Sarah Ferguson</PERSON>, now <ORGANIZATION>Duchess of
York</ORGANIZATION>. Their staff includes a private secretary, a full-time
lady-in-waiting, up to four clerks, a chauffeur and a dresser to
look after the duchess's clothes.
   Labor legislator <PERSON>Chris Mullin</PERSON> said the royal family should pay
tax on their state grants and claimed the queen could afford it
because she is ``one of the richest people in the world.''
   <PERSON>Harold Brooks-Baker</PERSON>, publishing director of <PERSON>Burke</PERSON>'s Peerage, said
she pays the equivalent of <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> tax on the income from her
estates and invested wealth, double the top rate of her richest
subjects.
   ``The queen is the most heavily taxed person in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>,'' he
said, and estimated royal revenues at <MONEY>50 million pounds</MONEY> (<MONEY>$85.5
million</MONEY>) a year, of which the queen would retain <MONEY>10 million pounds</MONEY>
(<MONEY>$17.1 million</MONEY>).
   ``That is the same as being taxed at <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT>,'' <PERSON>Brooks-Baker</PERSON>
said.
   In the time of <PERSON>King George III</PERSON> in the <DATE>18th century</DATE>, he said,
monarchs found they could not live on their income and agreed to
surrender all revenues in return for the Civil List, a sum
Parliament deemed sufficient for their needs.
   Each monarch since has opted for the Civil List at the start of a
new reign, but because today's royal revenues are much greater than
before, the queen has been allowed to keep a portion, <PERSON>Brooks-Baker</PERSON>
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880708-0259 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-88 0128EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-World'sRichest     07-08 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-World's Richest,0466</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tsutsumi Heads Forbes List of Billionaires for Second Year</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON> is a bit poorer than he was
last year _ make that less wealthy _ but the Japanese railroad
magnate still ranks as the world's richest person, according to
Forbes magazine.
   Tsutsumi, head of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Seibu Railway Group</ORGANIZATION>, has a personal
net worth of at least <MONEY>$18.9 billion</MONEY>, making him the world's richest
person for the second straight year, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The magazine, in a report on the richest people outside the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, estimated <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON>'s fortune at approximately <MONEY>$20
billion</MONEY> last fall in its first survey of the world's richest people.
   The story appears in the magazine's <DATE>July 25</DATE> issue.
   The designation for <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON> again puts Forbes at odds with
Fortune magazine. In its compilation of the world's billionaires
last <DATE>October</DATE>, Fortune estimated <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON>'s holdings in railroads,
hotels and golf clubs were worth a far smaller _ but still
substantial _ <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   The second richest person on <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON>' list is also Japanese.
<PERSON>Taikichiro Mori</PERSON>, a former economics professor who owns 68 office
buildings in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, is worth <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>, the magazine estimated.
In the previous survey, <PERSON>Mori</PERSON>'s fortune was put at <MONEY>$15 billion</MONEY>.
   Following the two Japanese are the <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>,
who have built a <MONEY>$9 billion</MONEY> fortune in real estate, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Shin Kyuk-ho</PERSON>, a South Korean with interests in candy making,
hotels and real estate, is ranked No. 4 (<MONEY>$8 billion-plus</MONEY>), and
<PERSON>Kenneth Cole Irving</PERSON>, a Canadian with interests in oil distribution,
paper and land, is No. 5 (<MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>).
   The survey identifies 119 non-American individuals or families
around the world whose personal net assets are worth more than <MONEY>$1
billion</MONEY>, up from 90 in the previous list.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> still accounts for more billionaires than any
other country, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> noted. The magazine said at least 47 American
individuals and 20 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> families are worth more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>,
compared with 32 individuals and families in second-place <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and
16 in third-ranked <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>.
   The leading American billionaire is <PERSON>Sam Walton</PERSON>, the head of
major retailer <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart Stores</ORGANIZATION>, who ranks seventh worldwide with a
net worth of <MONEY>$6.5 billion</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> estimates.
   Not all the fortunes listed in <LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION>' list were amassed in a
respectable way.
   Three of them belong to people the magazine identified as
Colombian drug dealers, two individuals and one family, who are all
part of the notorious <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cocaine cartel.
   Two of the Colombian cocaine fortunes, those of <PERSON>Pablo Escobar
Gaviria</PERSON> and the <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON> family, are each more than <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>
said. It estimated the third, amassed by <PERSON>Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha</PERSON>,
at between <MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY> and <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890709-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-09-89 1411EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-World'sRichest Bjt   07-09 0584</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World's Richest, Bjt,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japanese Businessman Tops Forbes Billionaires List Third Straight
Year</HEAD>
<HEAD>Embargoed Until 6:30 p.m. EDT; Time set by source.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-World's Richest-List</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six of the 10 richest people in the world are
Japanese but the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> still leads the world in the total
number of billionaires, according to estimates compiled by Forbes
magazine.
   For the third straight year, <PERSON>Yoshiaki Tsutsumi</PERSON> led <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' list
of private billionaires even though his wealth wasn't quite as much
as it had been 12 months earlier.
   Tsutsumi, head of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Seibu Railway Group</ORGANIZATION>, has a personal net
worth of at least <MONEY>$15 billion</MONEY> _ nearly <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY> less than
estimated last <DATE>summer</DATE> due mainly to a rise in the value of the
dollar against other major currencies, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The estimate was far greater than the <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> that Fortune
magazine placed as <ORGANIZATION>Tsutsumi</ORGANIZATION>'s worth in its <DATE>September 1988</DATE> ranking of
those it considered the world's richest people.
   In last year's list, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> estimated <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON>'s net worth as
<MONEY>$18.9 billion</MONEY>.
   The magazine reports in its <DATE>July 24</DATE> issue that <PERSON>Tsutsumi</PERSON> edged out
second-ranked Taikichiro Mori by less than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   Mori, a former economics professor who owns 72 office buildings
in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, has an estimated net worth of <MONEY>$14.2 billion</MONEY>. In last
year's survey, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> placed Mori's worth at about <MONEY>$18 billion</MONEY>.
   The third-richest on the list was American <PERSON>Sam Moore Walton</PERSON>,
founder of the third-largest retailer in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Wal-Mart
Stores Inc</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> and his family are worth an estimated <MONEY>$8.7
billion</MONEY>, up from <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>' <DATE>1988</DATE> estimate of <MONEY>$6.5 billion</MONEY>.
   After the Waltons came <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Reichmann</PERSON> brothers, owners of the
<ORGANIZATION>Olympia &amp; York</ORGANIZATION> real estate empire, with a combined net worth of
about <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>.
   The rest of the 10 richest people in the world, their country and
industries, according to <LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION>, were: <PERSON>Shin Kyuk-ho</PERSON>, <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>,
candy, real estate, <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Hirotomo Takei</PERSON> and family, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>,
publishing, real estate, <MONEY>$7.8 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Kitaro Watanabe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real
estate, hotels, <MONEY>$7 billion-plus</MONEY>; <PERSON>Haruhiko Yoshimoto</PERSON> and family,
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, real estate, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>; <PERSON>Hans</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gad Rausing</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>,
liquids packaging, <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>; and <PERSON>Eitaro Itoyama</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, land, <MONEY>$6.6
billion</MONEY>.
   Forbes said it identified 226 individuals or families around the
world with personal assets worth more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was the country with the most billionaires,
with 55 individuals qualifying for that title. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> ranked second,
with 41, and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> was third with 20.
   American also accounted for the most billionaires in the <DATE>1988</DATE>
survey, 47, followed by <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s 32 and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s 16.
   Among the richest of the world's rich are people who didn't
necessarily come by their money in an honest way.
   <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s cocaine barons, for instance, are still putting away
piles of money from selling the illegal drug even though profit
margins in the cocaine trade have been shrinking during recent years.
   Three of them made Forbes ``World Billionaires'' list, including
<PERSON>Pablo Escobar Gaviria</PERSON>, leader of the notorious <LOCATION>Medellin</LOCATION> cocaine
cartel, with an estimated personal net worth of <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>. The
other cocaine kingpins on the list were the <PERSON>Ochoa</PERSON> family, worth more
