<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7691 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas061_n_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-061 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Philippine President Continues Visit </TI></H3>
<H4>   Meets With Prime Minister </H4>
<F P=102> BK3003012994 Hanoi VNA in English 1421 GMT 29 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK3003012994 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 29</DATE> -- Prime Minister [<LOCATION>P.M.</LOCATION>] <PERSON>Vo Van 
Kiet</PERSON> and Philippine President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> today had an exchange 
of views on the development of the Vietnam-Philippine 
relationship and cooperation. 
  Also present were Foreign Minister <PERSON>Nguyen Manh Cam</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Minister 
of Agriculture and Food Industry Nguyen Cong Tan</ORGANIZATION>, and Trade 
Minister Le Van Triet. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> and President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> 
expressed their pleasure at the fine development of the 
after the Vietnamese prime minister's visit to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> 
<DATE>early 1992</DATE>. 
  P.M. Kiet outlined orientations and measures to further 
promote the Vietnam-Philippine cooperation in the fields of 
commerce, economy, culture, tourism, science and technology on 
the basis of agreements on cooperation signed recently in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>. 
The prime minister said he hoped that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> would receive 
cooperation and assistance from the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> in the areas of 
science and technology, personnel training and natural calamity 
preparedness. He said <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> was ready to cooperate with the 
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> in health care and aquaculture. 
  For his part, President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> spoke highly of the 
progress and growth of the economic, commercial cooperation 
between the two countries in the past, as well as of the 
orientations and measures to develop the two countries' 
long-term cooperation in the future. The Philippine president 
said that with a sense of creating security and stable 
environment in the region, the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Government</ORGANIZATION> would 
strive to push up the multi-faceted cooperation for mutual 
benefit with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, encourage businessmen to invest in 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, be prepared to share experiences with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, and help 
it train economic and technological personnel. 
  P.M. Kiet and President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> also compared notes on the 
developments in the region and international issues of common 
concern. The two sides agreed that all outstanding problems 
should be settled in conformity with the interests of the 
region. They also held that only peace and security in the 
region be maintained, can development in each country be ensured. 
  Later, <ORGANIZATION>Prime Minister Kiet</ORGANIZATION> gave a dinner to President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7539 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas060_n_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-060 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Philippines President Arrives on Visit 28 Mar </TI></H3>
<H4>   Welcomed by Le Duc Anh </H4>
<F P=102> BK2803151294 Hanoi VNA in English 1431 GMT 28 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2803151294 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 28</DATE> -- Philippine President <PERSON>Fidel V. 
Ramos</PERSON> arrived here <TIME>this morning</TIME>, beginning an official 
friendship visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> as guest of President Le <PERSON>Duc Anh</PERSON>. 
  He was accompanied by many other <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>' Government 
officials and businessmen. 
  State ceremony to welcome the Philippine guests was held at 
the Presidential Palace which were attended by President Le <PERSON>Duc 
Anh</PERSON>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Nguyen Manh 
Cam</PERSON> and other Vietnamese high-ranking officials. 
Representatives of the diplomatic corps and international 
organizations were also on hand. Speaking at the reception after 
the ceremony, President Le <PERSON>Duc Anh</PERSON> said he and Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo 
Van Kiet</PERSON> expressed their pleasure to welcome Philippine 
President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> and his entourage to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and hoped this 
visit would mark a new development in the relations between the 
two countries. 
  President <PERSON>Le Duc Anh</PERSON> said that the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
are neighbouring countries which have many things to share, 
therefore the two countries should exchange views on important 
issues of common concern aimed at promoting the multi-faceted 
ties for the interest of each country. 
  For his part, Philippine President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> expressed his 
sincere thanks to President Le <PERSON>Duc Anh</PERSON>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van 
Kiet</PERSON> and other Vietnamese officials for their warm welcome. He 
also expressed his wish that his country and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> should 
build friendly and cooperative relation with other Southeast 
Asian countries, thus making active contributions to peace, 
stability, development and prosperity in the region. 
  Later in the day a banquet was held by President <PERSON>Le Duc Anh</PERSON> 
in honour of the Philippine guests. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-53743 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas099_n_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-099 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Vo Van Kiet Arrives in Kuala Lumpur on Visit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Vo Van Kiet Arrives in Kuala Lumpur on Visit </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK2305070594 Hanoi VNA in English 1403 GMT 22 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2305070594 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>May 22</DATE> -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
arrived in <LOCATION>Kuala Lumpur</LOCATION> today to attend the forum of leaders of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Basin Economic Cooperation Council</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>PBEC</ORGANIZATION>) at the 
invitation of Malaysian Prime Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamad</PERSON> and 
Chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>PBEC</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>Mr. T. Bahdia</PERSON>. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> was welcomed at the airport by 
Prime Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamad</PERSON>, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Abdullar Ahmad 
Badawi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> and chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>PBEC T. Bahdia</ORGANIZATION> and 
others. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7331 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas059_n_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-059 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   NHAN DAN Previews President Ramos' Visit </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK2803065594 Hanoi VNA in English 0610 GMT 28 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2803065594 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 28</DATE> -- Philippine President <PERSON>Fidel V. 
Ramos</PERSON>'s official friendship visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> expected here today 
is a significant event in the friendly and cooperative relations 
between the two countries, says NHAN DAN in an editorial today. 
  The editorial continues: <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> have 
had 
time-honoured culture and trade exchanges. Over the past recent 
years, there have been positive changes in the cooperative 
relations between the two countries. Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van 
Kiet</PERSON>'s official visit to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> in <DATE>1992</DATE> is a great 
landmark in the promotion of mutual understanding and trust, 
creating and impetus to their economic-trade cooperation. The 
two-way trade value increased to nearly USD [<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars] 50 
million in <DATE>1993</DATE> from USD 12 million in <DATE>1988</DATE>. The <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> 
has 11 investment projects in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> with a total capital of 
USD 60 million, ranking 18th among foreign countries investing 
in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 'As neighbour, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> have a 
common aspiration for each country's socio-economic progress, 
for peace, stability, cooperation, and development in the 
region. The <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> have had a common voice in 
seeking peaceful solutions, conforming to their interests as 
well as international laws and pratices, to solve problems left 
behind by the history and foster the friendly and cooperative 
relations between the two countries'. 
  The paper wishes President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON>'s visit a success, thus 
contributing to further promoting the Vietnam-Philippines 
relations for happiness and prosperity of the two nations, and 
for peace, stability, cooperation and development in the region 
and all over the world. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-46936 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas004_h_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-004 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SOUTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Brunei, Malaysia &amp; Singapore </F>
<H3> <TI>   Mahathir, Delegation To Visit Manila 3 Feb </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0601134194 Kuala Lumpur Radio Malaysia Network in Malay 
1300 GMT 6 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0601134194 </F>
<F P=104>  Kuala Lumpur Radio Malaysia Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Malay </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] Prime Minister <PERSON>Datuk Sri Dr Mahathir</PERSON> will make a 
three-day official visit to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> beginning 3 
<DATE>February</DATE>. The visit is at the invitation of President <PERSON>Fidel 
Ramos</PERSON>. 
  The prime minister will be accompanied by his wife, <PERSON>Datuk 
Sri 
Datin Paduka Dr. Siti Hasmah</PERSON>, several cabinet ministers, senior 
government officials and local businessmen. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> made this announcement today. 
  During the visit, the prime minister will hold talks with 
President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> on bilateral, regional and international issues. 
The cabinet ministers, who will be acompanying him, will hold 
talks with their Filipino counterparts. 
  While in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, the prime minister and the 
delegation will also visit the metropolitan areas, <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Baguio City</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Davao</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-54139 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas102bb_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-102 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTER-ASIAN AFFAIRS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Further on Pacific Basin Economic Council Meeting </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Further on Pacific Basin Economic Council Meeting </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    More on Vo Van Kiet, Mahathir Talks </H4>

<F P=102> BK2505121094 Hanoi Voice of Vietnam in English 1000 GMT 25 
May 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK2505121094 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi Voice of Vietnam </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Malaysian Prime Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON> and his 
Vietnamese counterpart, <PERSON>Mr. Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>, have held an official 
talk in <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> prime minister was in <LOCATION>Kuala Lumpur</LOCATION> to 
attend the <ORGANIZATION>27th International General Conference</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific 
Basin Economic Council</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Voice of Vietnam</ORGANIZATION> summarizes the 
talks between the two prime ministers: 
  <PERSON>Mr. Mahathir</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Kiet</PERSON> discussed bilateral multilateral 
relations and international issues of common concern. They 
expressed their satisfaction at the positive developments in the 
countries in the <DATE>last two years</DATE>. During this time, the two 
countries have repeatedly exchanged visits of high-level 
delegations. In <DATE>January 1992</DATE>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
visited <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> and in <DATE>April</DATE> of the same year, Malaysian Prime 
Minister Mahathir officially visited <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. In <DATE>March 1994</DATE>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Vietnamese Party General Secretary Do Muoi</ORGANIZATION> also visited 
<LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>. The visits have all helped broaden mutual 
understanding, consolidate mutual trust, and promote mutual 
comprehensive cooperation. 
  At present, <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> is among six <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> countries who have a 
large investment in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> worth about <MONEY>$75 million</MONEY>. Two-way 
trade turnover between the two countries at present is 20 times 
larger than <DATE>1985</DATE> figure of <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>. During the talks this 
time in <LOCATION>Kuala Lumpur</LOCATION>, the two prime ministers discussed concrete 
measures to strengthen cooperation in the production of 
construction materials, industrial construction, and tourism. 
  Concerning the situation in <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>, 
the two prime ministers expressed their satisfaction at the 
increasing trend for peace and cooperation in the region and 
stated: Nations in the region must join their efforts for 
consolidation of this trend, through which all disputes should 
be solved in the principle of mutual respect and respect for 
internatonal law and practices. 
  Prime Minister Mahathir once again affirmed the support for 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s admission to <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> as a full member which will benefit 
both <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> and cooperation for prosperity in the 
region. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-28470 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas025_h_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-025 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SOUTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Brunei, Malaysia &amp; Singapore </F>
<H3> <TI>   Commentary Hails Enhanced Ties </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0502113294 Kuala Lumpur Voice of Malaysia in English 0800 
GMT 5 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0502113294 </F>
<F P=104>  Kuala Lumpur Voice of Malaysia </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Station commentary] </F>
  [Excerpts] Bilateral trade, economic and business ties 
between <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> are set to grow at a steady 
pace from now on with the Malaysian prime minister <PERSON>Dr. Mahathir 
Mohamed</PERSON>'s official four-day visit to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> which began 
on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 
  The Malaysian leader's visit can be described as historic in 
the sense that it is the first official trip by a Malaysian 
prime minister to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, since the two countries 
established diplomatic ties in <DATE>1964</DATE>. It also reciprocates the 
visit of Philippine President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> last year. 
[passage omitted] 
  <PERSON>Dr. Mahathir</PERSON>'s entourage includes some cabinet ministers 
holding key portfolios as well as about 60 corporate leaders and 
businessmen which demonstrates the seriousness that is being 
attached to increase economic and business cooperation. This 
cooperation entered concrete term on the very first day of the 
visit with the signing of the nine memoranda of understanding or 
<ORGANIZATION>MOUs</ORGANIZATION>, involving the private sectors of the two countries. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>MOUs</ORGANIZATION> may lead to deals worth billions of ringgit. Apart 
from injecting much-needed capital into the Philippine economy, 
the deals are also in line with <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>'s policy to boost 
reverse investment. While the <ORGANIZATION>MOUs</ORGANIZATION> will be signed, officials of 
the two countries got down to details of an investment guarantee 
agreement, IGA, which is likely to be signed in the course of 
the visit. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-4945 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas042_h_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-042 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brunei, Malaysia &amp; Singapore </F>
<F P=101> Malaysia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Commentary Discusses Philippines Economic Ties </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0203103994 Kuala Lumpur Voice of Malaysia in English 0800 
GMT 2 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0203103994 </F>
<F P=104>  Kuala Lumpur Voice of Malaysia </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Station commentary] </F>
  [Text] The prime minister <PERSON>Datuk Sri Dr. Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON>'s 
official visit to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, the first by a Malaysian 
premier to that country, is already yielding results. The 
<ORGANIZATION>Philippine Government</ORGANIZATION> is keen and serious about enhancing trade 
relations with <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>. And this should be the case with 
[words indistinct] <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION>. In response to <PERSON>Dr. Mahathir</PERSON> and his 
delegation's visit to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> in <DATE>February</DATE>, a 
high-powered multimember delegation from the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> paid a 
two-day visit <DATE>last weekend</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Territory</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Labuan</LOCATION> 
off the East Malaysian state of Sabah. The Philippine delegation 
was truly interested in knowing more about the development of 
<LOCATION>Labuan</LOCATION> as an offshore financial center and also about foreign 
investment opportunities in both the East Malaysian states of 
Sabah and <LOCATION>Sarawak</LOCATION>. What is encouraging is that the visit showed 
the commitment of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Government</ORGANIZATION> to the development 
of the <LOCATION>East ASEAN Growth Area</LOCATION>. The visiting mission was given a 
detailed briefing on the investment opportunities available in 
<LOCATION>Labuan</LOCATION> as well as in <LOCATION>Sabah</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sarawak</LOCATION>. 
  It is noteworthy that the Philippine delegation's visit was 
the first by a well-represented government and private sector 
mission from that country. What seemed to interest them was the 
function of <LOCATION>Labuan</LOCATION> as an international offshore financial 
center, or <ORGANIZATION>IOFC</ORGANIZATION>. The delegation included a group of bankers who 
appreciated the <ORGANIZATION>IOFC</ORGANIZATION> concept being adopted in <LOCATION>Labuan</LOCATION>. The 
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine National Bank</ORGANIZATION> has been quoted as 
saying his bank was considering setting up an offshore bank in 
<LOCATION>Labuan</LOCATION>. The bank would like to finalize joint financial 
undertakings not only with the <ORGANIZATION>Malaysian Government</ORGANIZATION> but also 
with the private sector. 
  Cooperation between the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> is 
certainly 
on the way up. One of <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>'s leading companies is currently 
involved in the development of infrastructure in the 
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. Malaysian participation in the power supply, stock 
development, and telecommunication sector will also be welcomed 
in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. [Words indistinct], both countries can help 
each other to promote their respective tourism industry. The 
idea of setting up a regional air link needs serious 
consideration. The visit by the Philippine president, <PERSON>Fidel 
Ramos</PERSON>, to <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> last year and the reciprocal visit by <PERSON>Dr. 
Mahathir</PERSON> have opened the way for increased cooperation between 
the two <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> partners. The private sector of the two countries 
should take this opportunity to go into joint ventures for their 
mutual benefit. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-5187 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas043_n_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-043 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Commentary Reviews Ties With ASEAN Countries </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK2602160694 Hanoi Voice of Vietnam in English 1000 GMT 25 
Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK2602160694 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi Voice of Vietnam </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Station commentary] </F>
  [Text] Comprehensive development has taken place in 
relations between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> member countries. Trade 
and economic ties between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> countries have 
rapidly increased. In <DATE>1992</DATE>, two-way trade between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and 
the <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> reached <MONEY>$220 million</MONEY>. It was <MONEY>$158 million</MONEY> with 
<LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>, <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> with <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>, <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> with 
<LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>, and <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> with the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. 
  By the end of <DATE>1993</DATE>, about 100 projects for <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> countries 
with invested capital of hundreds of millions of dollar were 
licensed in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. ASEAN investment in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> has increased 
10 times as against <DATE>1990</DATE>, now accounting for <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> of the 
total foreign investment in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. More than 30 agreements on 
economic, scientific and technical, trade, payment, credit, 
aviation, and navigation have been signed between <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> 
countries and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  In late <DATE>July last year</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>State Committee for Foreign 
Investment of Vietnam</ORGANIZATION> signed an agreement of cooperation with a 
prime company of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION> which will see the latter invests in 
major projects in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. In late <DATE>1991</DATE> and early <DATE>1992</DATE>, the 
Vietnamese Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> visited all six <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> 
member countries. This helped the region to have a better 
understanding about the current reform in this country. 
  In visiting <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, all leaders of <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> member countries 
demonstrated sympathy with the problems and difficulties <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
has been confronting, and promised to share experiences with the 
Vietnamese in national development. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Chuan Likphai</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> is committed to 
create favorable conditions for further multi-sided cooperation 
between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and his country. President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> of the 
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> has assured <ORGANIZATION>Vietnamese National Assembly</ORGANIZATION> chairman 
<PERSON>Nong Duc Manh</PERSON> that the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> has always been <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s 
friend, and hoped that bilateral ties would be further 
developed. It is the common voice of leaders and people of 
<ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> member countries. 
  Most recently, during his visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> 
secretary general, <PERSON>Mr. Ajit Singh</PERSON>, informed <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> of the 
decision by <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN Secretariat</ORGANIZATION> to allow <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to participate 
and observe in various programs in science, technology, 
environment, culture, information, public health, tourism, and 
development sources. <PERSON>Mr. Ajit Singh</PERSON> said the secretariat will 
send senior officials to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to exchange views on concrete 
issues of <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION>'s concern. 
  These developments show how much bilateral and multi-sided 
cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> member countries has been 
increasing. At the recent foreign ministerial conference held 
in <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION> by <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> countries appreciated <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s 
achievements in its renovation process, and welcomed <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s 
participation in a forum on regional security. Relations 
between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> has created a new atmosphere in 
<LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>. 
  Malaysian Prime Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON> once declared that 
he would be glad to contribute to national reconstruction and 
economic development in <LOCATION>Indochina</LOCATION>, with the confidence that 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Cambodia</LOCATION> would be stable and developed. It 
would contribute to peace, stability, and prosperity in the 
region. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-28469 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas025_h_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-025 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SOUTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Brunei, Malaysia &amp; Singapore </F>
<H3> <TI>   MOUs on Economic Cooperation Signed With Manila </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0702122194 Kuala Lumpur NEW STRAITS TIMES in English 4 Feb 
94 p 2 </F>

<F P=103> BK0702122194 </F>
<F P=104>  Kuala Lumpur NEW STRAITS TIMES </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Thurs.</LOCATION> -- Economic cooperation between 
<LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> entered more concrete terms today 
with the signing of nine memorandums of understanding (MOUs) 
involving the respective private sectors. 
  While representatives from the various companies worked on 
the details of the projects involved, officials from the two 
governments sat down to finalise details of an investment 
guarantee agreement (IGA), which may be signed in the next few 
days. Prime Minister <PERSON>Datuk Sri Dr. Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON> and 
President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> witnessed the signing ceremonies at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Malacanang Palace</ORGANIZATION>, the latter's official residence, here this 
afternoon. 
  <PERSON>Dr. Mahathir</PERSON>, who arrived here this afternoon for a four-day 
visit, the first by a Malaysian prime minister since the two 
countries established diplomatic ties in <DATE>1964</DATE>, hailed the 
signing of the agreements as "the start of a new phase in our 
relations." "I think we have made very good progress," he told a 
joint news conference after the signings. Asked if more 
investments from <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> could be expected, he replied: "Yes." 
  The nine <ORGANIZATION>MOUs</ORGANIZATION> could lead to deals worth billions of ringgit. 
Apart from injecting much-needed capital into the growing 
Philippine economy, which rose by <PERCENT>2.3 percent</PERCENT> last year compared 
with one per cent in <DATE>1992</DATE>, the deals are also in line with 
<LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>'s policy to boost reverse investment. The <ORGANIZATION>MOUs</ORGANIZATION>, signed 
behind closed doors, are for a hotel project on <LOCATION>Samal Island</LOCATION> in 
<LOCATION>Mindanao</LOCATION>; partial acquisition of the <ORGANIZATION>Associated Bank</ORGANIZATION>; highway 
and mass transit systems construction and the implementation of 
a RM [Malaysian ringgit] 50-million waterwork project; water 
treatment for <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> Base; gaming houses; production of 
refrigerators, the construction of Metro <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> waterworks 
sewerage system; and a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> $72-million power plant. 
  The nine MOUs were signed between <ORGANIZATION>Johan Holdings Bhd</ORGANIZATION>. 
[Limited]/<PERSON>George Kent</PERSON> and Metropolitan Cebu Water District; 
<ORGANIZATION>Johan Holdings Bhd.</ORGANIZATION>/<PERSON>George Kent</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Bases Conversion Development 
Authority Berjaya Topgroup</ORGANIZATION> (HK) <ORGANIZATION>Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Team Asia Corp Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; 
<ORGANIZATION>Berjaya/Wy Sdn</ORGANIZATION>. Bhd. [Private Limited] and <ORGANIZATION>Fun Characters Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; 
<ORGANIZATION>Ekran Bhd.</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Department of Tourism/Philippine 
Tourism Authority</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Ekran Bhd.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Associated Bank</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Renong 
Bhd.</ORGANIZATION>/Mara and <ORGANIZATION>Public Estates Authority</ORGANIZATION>; and <PERSON>Datuk Eugene Campos</PERSON> 
and <ORGANIZATION>Louis Cosan</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The signing of the <ORGANIZATION>MOUs</ORGANIZATION> reflects the determination of both 
countries to step up investment and bilateral trade after ties 
had been held back for so long by the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Government</ORGANIZATION>'s 
claim over <LOCATION>Sabah</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>'s investment in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> has 
been unpredictable. On an uptrend during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, investments 
dipped after <DATE>1989</DATE> and in <DATE>1992</DATE>, no new capital from <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> 
flowed into the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. 
  Last year some <MONEY>193 million pesos</MONEY> (RM16.3 million) in 
Malaysian investments went into power generation plants, poultry 
breeding, and electronic manufacturing projects in the republic. 
  <ORGANIZATION>MBf Asia Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>MCA Power Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, together with a 
third Canadian partner, entered into a deal for a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> $<MONEY>2 
billion</MONEY> (RM5.5 billion) power plant irrigation and flood control 
system. Hong <ORGANIZATION>Leong Engineering</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Sarte Teodore</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Associates</ORGANIZATION> 
clinched a deal on the manufacturing of computer software in the 
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> for export. 
  Al-Bakara <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> also took a slice of the pie in a deal 
with a group, led by <LOCATION>Mindanao</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Mastura</PERSON> family to rehabilitate 
the state- owned <ORGANIZATION>Amanah Bank</ORGANIZATION>, now privatised. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7678 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas061_n_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-061 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  30 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Philippine President Continues Visit </TI></H3>
<H4>   Hanoi `Receptive' to Ramos Proposal </H4>
<F P=102> BK3003054594 Bangkok BANGKOK POST in English 30 Mar 94 p 6 </F>
<F P=103> BK3003054594 </F>
<F P=104>  Bangkok BANGKOK POST </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] A call by Philippine President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> for more 
contacts among claimants of the disputed <LOCATION>Spratly Islands</LOCATION> in the 
<LOCATION>South China</LOCATION> Sea which will eventually lead to "demilitarisation" 
of the area drew a receptive response from <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, a senior 
Philippine government official said here yesterday. 
  President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> arrived in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> for a three-day 
official visit. He held talks with Vietnamese President <PERSON>Le Duc 
Anh</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> chief Do Muoi and Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van 
Kiet</PERSON>. 
  The <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> are among six claimants of the 
<LOCATION>Spratly Islands</LOCATION>. With the exception of <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, the two 
countries along with <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>, have maintained 
various degrees of military presence in the area. 
  Speaking at a press conference before heading for southern 
<LOCATION>Ho 
Chi Minh City</LOCATION> yesterday <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> said his proposal for more 
contacts as well as for joint resources development in the 
<LOCATION>Spratlys</LOCATION> is aimed at defusing tension in the region. 
  "We agreed on the need to devise confidence-building 
mechanisms -- cooperative ventures in the area -- that will 
assure the claimant countries and the rest of the region that 
the <LOCATION>South China</LOCATION> Sea can be transformed from waters of contention 
to an area of cooperation," he said. 
  Ramos added that he also mentioned to the Vietnamese leaders 
"the need to agree on demilitarisation" of the Spratlys. 
  Elaborating on his president's remarks, Undersecretary for 
Foreign Affairs <PERSON>Rodolfo Severino</PERSON> told reporters that 
demilitarisation of the Spratlys should be achieved in an Asian 
way, which is "gradual, step by step, in a consensual manner." 
  The Philippine and Vietnamese leaders also said they would 
like to encourage informal contacts from top level down to local 
commanders among the claimant parties, with a view to reducing 
tension in dealing with the <LOCATION>Spratlys</LOCATION>, according to <PERSON>Severino</PERSON>. 
  <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> has constantly reiterated its sovereignty over the 
Spratlys and the Paracels in which the latter is also in 
bilateral contention with <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 
  Stressing that the proposal for joint studies towards 
military reduction and joint resource development is new to 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Severino</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> nevertheless found this "an 
interesting" idea. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN Regional Forum</ORGANIZATION>, to be held this <DATE>July</DATE> in <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION> 
and 
to which <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> is invited to attend, will steer clear from 
controversial issues such as disputed claims over the <LOCATION>Spratlys</LOCATION>, 
he said. 
  While in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> also presided over the 
signing of several bilateral agreements covering trade, culture, 
tourism and the set-up of a <ORGANIZATION>Joint Commission for Bilateral 
Cooperation</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The two countries said they would try to increase bilateral 
trade, which last year amounted to only <MONEY>US$48 million</MONEY>, 
facilitate Vietnamese rice for Philippine fertiliser barter 
arrangements, as well as work to establish direct shipping 
services. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-54138 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas102bb_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-102 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  24 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTER-ASIAN AFFAIRS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Further on Pacific Basin Economic Council Meeting </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Further on Pacific Basin Economic Council Meeting </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    SRV, Malaysian Prime Ministers Meet </H4>

<F P=102> BK2405144394 Hanoi VNA in English 1357 GMT 24 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2405144394 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>May 24</DATE> -- Malaysian Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Mahathir Mohamad</PERSON> received in <LOCATION>Kuala Lumpur</LOCATION> yesterday Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> who is on an unofficial visit to <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> 
and attended the forum of the leaders of the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Basin 
Economic Council</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>PBEC</ORGANIZATION>) there. 
  P.M. Mohamad and <ORGANIZATION>P.M. Kiet</ORGANIZATION> expressed their full 
satisfactiona 
at the fine development of the friendship and multi-faceted 
cooperation between the two countries. They also exchanged 
views on concrete measures with a view to expand the 
Vietnam-Malaysia cooperation in the fields of industry, 
manufacture, building materials, tourism and industrial zone 
construction. 
  On the situation in <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>, the two 
prime ministers expressed their pleasure at the development of 
the trend for peace and cooperation. They stressed that 
regional countries should do their utmost to contribute to the 
consolidation of such trend, through negotiation to settle any 
difference on the basics of respect to each other and respect of 
international law. 
  P.M. Mohamad reaffirmed that <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> fully supported for 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in its preparation to joint in <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> as a full member. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7111 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas057_n_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-057 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  24 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Do Muoi Arrives in Kuala Lumpur 24 Mar </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK2403163194 Hanoi VNA in English 1514 GMT 24 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2403163194 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 24</DATE> -- General Secretary Do <PERSON>Muoi</PERSON> and 
his entourage arrived in <LOCATION>Kuala Lumpur</LOCATION>, this morning beginning 
his official friendship visit to <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> as guest of Prime 
Minister Mohamed. <PERSON>Mr Do Muoi</PERSON> was welcomed at the airport by 
Foreign Minister <PERSON>Abdullah Ahmad Badawi</PERSON> and accompanied Minister 
<PERSON>Daud Taha</PERSON>. 
  After the official welcomed ceremony held in the 
Parliamentary Square, General Secretary Do Muoi and Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON> reviewed the honour guards of 
Malaysian armed forces. <PERSON>Mr. Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON> introduced <PERSON>Mr Do 
Muoi</PERSON> the <ORGANIZATION>Malaysian Government</ORGANIZATION>'s officials. Among those present 
at the event on the Malaysian side were Deputy Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Anwar Ibrahim</PERSON>, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Abdullah Ahmad Badawi</PERSON>, Cabinet 
Minister <PERSON>Abang Abu Bakar Mustapha</PERSON>, and <ORGANIZATION>Defence Minister Najib 
Tun Razak</ORGANIZATION>. Vietnamese Ambassador to <ORGANIZATION>Malaysia Ngo Tat</ORGANIZATION> To and 
members of diplomatic corps attended the ceremony. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-6819 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas055_n_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-055 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Reportage on Visit of Cuban Foreign Minister </TI></H3>
<H4>   Meets With Vo Van Kiet, Nguyen Manh Cam </H4>
<F P=102> BK2103144494 Hanoi VNA in English 1418 GMT 21 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2103144494 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 21</DATE> -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
received here this afternoon Cuban Foreign Minister [F.M.] 
<PERSON>Roberto Robaina Gonzales</PERSON> who is on an official visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  Also present at the reception were Foreign Minister <PERSON>Nguyen 
Manh Cam</PERSON> and Cuban Ambassador to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> <PERSON>Mrs. Tania Maceira 
Delgado</PERSON>. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> expressed his pleasure at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Cuban Government</ORGANIZATION> and people's efforts to overcome temporary 
difficulties, develop the economy, firmly keep political 
stability and expand relations with other countries in the 
world. He said he believed that with the tradition of heroism 
and determination, the Cuban people would certainly overcome 
such difficulties and successfully build a prosperous country. 
He wished for the success of <PERSON>F.M. Gonzales</PERSON>'s visit, thus 
contributing to the further consolidation and development of the 
traditional friendship and cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. 
  For his part, Minister <PERSON>Gonzales</PERSON> conveyed President <PERSON>Fidel 
Castro</PERSON>'s letter to Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>. He informed the 
Vietnamese leader of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s positive changes in the course of 
integration into international community. 
  He affirmed that his current visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> would 
contribute to the fraternal relationship and cooperation between 
the two countries. 
  Also <TIME>this afternoon</TIME>, <PERSON>F.M. Nguyen Manh Cam</PERSON> held talks with 
<PERSON>F.M. Gonzales</PERSON>. The two sides informed each other of the 
situation in each country and exchanged views on international 
issues of common concern. 
  <PERSON>F.M. Cam</PERSON> reaffirmed the persistent friendship and solidarity 
of the party, government and people of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> towards the 
party, government and people of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> in their great efforts to 
overcome present difficulties in order to successfully build and 
defend their countries. 
  On behalf of the party, government and people of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, 
Minister <PERSON>Gonzales</PERSON> expressed his sincere thanks to the party, 
government and people of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> for their valuable support and 
solidarity to <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> which he considered a great encouragement to 
the Cuban people. 
  Also on hand, at the talks were Deputy Foreign Minister Le 
Mai and Cuban Ambassador to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> <PERSON>Mrs. Tania Maceira Delgado</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7465 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas060_n_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-060 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Philippines President Arrives on Visit 28 Mar </TI></H3>
<H4>   Do Muoi Receives Ramos </H4>
<F P=102> BK2803152494 Hanoi VNA in English 1453 GMT 28 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2803152494 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 28</DATE> -- General Secretary Do Muoi of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party of Vietnam Central Committee</ORGANIZATION> received here 
this afternoon Philippine President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON>. 
  The Vietnamese leader hailed President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON>' visit as an 
important event in the friendly and cooperative links between 
the two countries. 
  For his part, President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> expressed his thanks to 
General 
Secretary Do Muoi, other senior officials and the Vietnamese 
people for their warm welcome and hospitality. 
  The two leaders informed each other of the situation in 
their 
respective countries and compared notes on issues of common 
concern. 
  President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> said his government is willing to help 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in personnel training and share experience with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
in fields <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> is interested. Philippine businessmen are 
encouraged to invest in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  President Ramos invited General Secretary Do Muoi to visit 
the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> at a convenient time and <PERSON>Mr Do Muoi</PERSON> accepted the 
invitation with pleasure. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7328 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas059_n_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-059 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  26 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Do Muoi Continues Official Visit to Malaysia </TI></H3>
<H4>   Holds Talks With Mahathir </H4>
<F P=102> BK2703070194 Hanoi VNA in English 1354 GMT 26 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2703070194 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 26</DATE> -- General Secretary of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Communist Party of Vietnam</ORGANIZATION> (CPV) <ORGANIZATION>Central Committee Do Muoi</ORGANIZATION> held 
talks with Prime Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Kuala Lumpur</LOCATION> on 
<DATE>March 25</DATE>, the 2nd day of his official visit to <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>. 
  The talks were also attended, on the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> side, by <PERSON>Le 
Phuoc Tho</PERSON>, Politburo member, secretary of the party <ORGANIZATION>Central 
Committee</ORGANIZATION> and head of its <ORGANIZATION>Commission for Organization</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Nguyen 
Manh Cam</PERSON>, Politburo member of the party <ORGANIZATION>Central Committee</ORGANIZATION> and 
minister for foreign affairs; <LOCATION>Hong Ha</LOCATION>, secretary of the party 
<ORGANIZATION>Central Committee</ORGANIZATION> and head of its <ORGANIZATION>Commission for External 
Relations</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Tran Duc Luong</ORGANIZATION>, member of the party <ORGANIZATION>Central 
  Foreign Minister <PERSON>Abdullah Ahmad Badawi</PERSON> and other 
Malaysian-ranking officials were also present. 
  During the talks, General Secretary Do Muoi highly 
appreciated the great achievements recorded by the Malaysian 
people and their experiences in national development and 
construction. 
  On behalf of the Vietnamese party, government and people, 
General Secretary Do Muoi thanked the Malaysian Government for 
sharing their precious experiences in economic development and 
management. He applauded the <ORGANIZATION>Malaysian Government</ORGANIZATION>'s policy 
which attaches great importance to the promotion and 
strengthening of its relations with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. He held the two 
countries have great potentials for further expansion of their 
multi-faceted cooperation, especially in the oil and gas, 
industry, electronics, rubber and palm oil production, 
construction of infrastructure, urban management, tourism and 
labour cooperation. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON>, for his part, praised the 
tradition of heroic struggle of the Vietnamese people and the 
important achievements they obtained in their renovation 
process. He hailed the Vietnamese party and government's open 
diversified and multilateralized foreign policy and considered 
it an important contribution to the cause of peace, stability 
and cooperation in the region. 
  The Malaysian prime minister also expressed his support for 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s participation in regional forums like the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific 
Economic Cooperation Council</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>PECC</ORGANIZATION>), the East-Asia Economic 
Caucus (<ORGANIZATION>EAEC</ORGANIZATION>), and the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Basin Economic Council</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>PBEC</ORGANIZATION>), 
and he said hoped that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> would soon become a full member 
of the <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Referring to the relations between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>, 
Prime Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON> underlined the <ORGANIZATION>Malaysian 
Government</ORGANIZATION>'s desire and determination to strengthen the 
friendship and effective cooperation with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, promote the 
exchange of experiences, encourage the Malaysian businesses to 
invest in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, and expand trade relations with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. He 
also said that <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> would be ready to help <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in 
personnel training. 
  The two sides also exchanged views on some international 
issues of common concern. Touching on the issue of human 
rights, the two leaders unanimously held that it is a universal 
issue, but it is necessary to take each nation with its own 
specific characteristics into consideration the greatest right 
of human beings is to live in peace, independence, democracy and 
development, and freedom of each person should be linked to his 
responsibility to the community. [sentence as received] <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> are prepared for talks and cooperation, but then 
protest against any attempts to use the human rights issue to 
interfere into the internal affairs of other countries. 
  On this occasion, General Secretary Do Muoi invited Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamed</PERSON> to visit <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. The latter accepted 
the invitation with pleasure. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7472 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas060_n_94009" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-060 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Vo Van Kiet Meets Mitsubishi Group President </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK2803152694 Hanoi VNA in English 1453 GMT 28 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2803152694 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 28</DATE> -- <PERSON>Mr. Minoru Makihara</PERSON>, president 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Group of Japan</ORGANIZATION>, who is now attending the 
<ORGANIZATION>Williamsburg Conference</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, today paid a courtesy visit 
to Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> welcomed <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Group</ORGANIZATION> in 
particular, and many other Japanese economic groups in general, 
who have been and are interested in promoting cooperation with 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, and held that his <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> visit was a fine 
manifestation of this goodwill. He also said that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
needed capital and experience in management, which were 
considered strong points of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> as well as other countries in 
the region. This is the premise for broadening cooperation in 
other fields for mutual benefit. The prime minister wished 
<ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Group</ORGANIZATION> great success in implementing cooperative 
investment projects in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Minoru Makihara</PERSON> said to <PERSON>Mr. Kiet</PERSON> that his group's 
concern 
to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> is shifting from its former cooperation in trading to 
investment cooperation in the fields of oil exploration and 
exploiting, cement production, and constructing power stations. 
He affirmed that <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Group</ORGANIZATION> would promote cooperation with 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in its experienced fields, and assist <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in 
personnel training for prosperity of each country. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-4586 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas064_m_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-064 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Thailand </F>
<H3> <TI>   Vietnam Should be Allowed To Join ASEAN </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Vietnam Should be Allowed To Join ASEAN </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0304105194 Bangkok THE SUNDAY NATION in English 3 Apr 94 p 
A10 </F>

<F P=103> BK0304105194 </F>
<F P=104>  Bangkok THE SUNDAY NATION </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Editorial: "Time Has Come To Admit Vietnam Into ASEAN"] </F>
  [Text] The honor guard at <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>'s international airport has 
probably never been so busy. Since <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lifted its 
three-decade-old economic embargo on <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in <DATE>February</DATE>, the 
formerly shunned communist bastion has been besieged by 
diplomatic visitors. 
  Leading the rush, have been the heads of the <ORGANIZATION>Association of 
South East Asian Nations</ORGANIZATION> (ASEAN), all eager to look at 
investment prospects and assess <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>'s ambitions to join their 
privileged group. Within the space of a little over a month, 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> has hosted visits from the secretary general of <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> 
and the leaders of <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>, and the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. 
  Communist Party chief <PERSON>Du Muoi</PERSON> was a guest of <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> <DATE>last 
week</DATE>, and President <PERSON>Le Duc Anh</PERSON> is due to visit <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> in <DATE>late 
April</DATE>. The visits coincide with a diplomatic offensive on the 
part of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, which is trying to widen ties with <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> and 
pave the way for its own entry into the group. 
  The official exchanges mark the second major diplomatic 
offensive <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> has launched following the break up of the 
Soviet bloc. Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> visited all six <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> 
members between <DATE>October 1991</DATE> and <DATE>July 1992</DATE> as <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> searched 
for new economic partners. At the time, most observers 
predicted that it would be at least five years before <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
would be admitted. But in a reflection of the sweeping 
political changes that are occurring across the region, 
<LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION> Prime Minister <PERSON>Goh Chok Tong</PERSON> announced in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> that 
he thought <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> may be formally discussed in 18 months. 
Philippine President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> was even more optimistic, 
calling for the immediate acceptance of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  Political differences between communist <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and the six 
capitalist <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> members have been swept aside with <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>'s 
market reforms and the signing of the <LOCATION>Cambodia</LOCATION> peace agreement 
in <DATE>1991</DATE>. 
  Goh said <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s communist ideology was no obstacle to 
membership of the bloc, founded when most of its members were 
aligned against <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> during the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War. 
  "It (<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s communism) should not be an obstacle," he 
said. "It depends on whether it can contribute to <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION>." 
  Vietnam contends that its political system is not going to 
change anytime soon and that the important thing is stability 
for economic development, a line that fits in nicely with the 
way most <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> governments feel about the "soft autocratic" 
style of democracy they practice. 
  Other <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> officials have argued that the speed at which 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> is integrated will depend on the pace of its economic 
development and market reforms <LOCATION>While Vietnam</LOCATION> is about 30 to 40 
years behind <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION> and possibly some 20 years behind in 
development compared to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, the wide 
disparity within <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> itself would suggest that this is not an 
obstacle. 
  However, <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> officials have said that before membership 
can 
be granted, <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> must prove its ability to contribute to the 
group's technical projects and resolve administrative and 
financial obstacles. These include the need to boost English 
language skills and accounting practices. 
  Once again it seems <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION>'s ability to zero in on petty 
bureaucratic priorities when faced with the opportunity of 
taking bold action will only reinforce its reputation as a 
hide-bound forum for endless talk and little achievement. 
  Hanoi is upgrading its technical capabilities to accelerate 
its admission but <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> continues to talk of admitting <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
only at an "appropriate time" when it is sure it can make a 
contribution to the regional group. 
  In one frequently cited area, education, it is going to be 
years if not decades before <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> can contribute but in 
possibly the most important area -- security -- <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> is ready 
to make a valuable contribution now. 
  As <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>'s only strong 
supporter in the regional grouping noted, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s 
"incorporation into <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> is an imperative of Southeast Asian 
peace, security and prosperity." 
  "Over the next generation, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> is certain to become one 
of <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>'s most important states and a major force in 
the balance of power," <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> said during his recent visit to 
<LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>. 
  Of particular interest to <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> and the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> is the 
dispute <LOCATION>Spratly Islands</LOCATION>. ASEAN has been reluctant to take an 
assertive stand on the atolls which are claimed in part by four 
of its members, as well as <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and have 
long been regarded as the most likely source of conflict in the 
region. 
  In <DATE>1992</DATE>, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> acceded to the <ORGANIZATION>Bali Treaty</ORGANIZATION> in which the 
original <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> members pledged to settle their disputes 
peacefully. <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> refuses to sign the treaty and its use of 
force against <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to settle claims in the <LOCATION>South China Sea</LOCATION> is 
becoming increasingly troubling. 
  ASEAN was born out of fear of the spread of communism and 
conflict from <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. Whether it is a member of <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> or not, 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> remains crucial to continued peace and prosperity in the 
region. 
  By admitting <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> will be better placed to work 
toward a solution of the <LOCATION>Spratly Islands</LOCATION> issue and also prosper 
if the <LOCATION>South China Sea</LOCATION> can in the words of Ramos, "be 
transformed from waters of contention to an area of cooperation." 
  As <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> admits itself, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s membership is no longer a 
matter of policy or principle but merely procedure and time -- 
an that time has come. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7466 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas060_n_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-060 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Philippines President Arrives on Visit 28 Mar </TI></H3>
<H4>   Meets With Le Duc Anh </H4>
<F P=102> BK2803154494 Hanoi VNA in English 1521 GMT 28 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2803154494 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 28</DATE> -- Vietnamese President Le <PERSON>Duc 
Anh</PERSON> held talks here this afternoon with his Philippine 
counterpart <PERSON>Fidel V. Ramos</PERSON>, now on an official friendship visit 
to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  At the talks, President Le <PERSON>Duc Anh</PERSON> hailed the (?first) visit 
to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> by President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> and his party as an event of 
significant importance which he said ushered in a new page in 
the friendship and multi-faceted cooperation between the two 
countries, contributing to the trend of peace, stability and 
cooperation in the region. 
  President <PERSON>Le Duc Anh</PERSON> informed President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> of the 
achievements recorded by the Vietnamese people in their 
renovation process. He affirmed <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s continued efforts in 
pursuing its foreign policies of independence, 
self-determination, openness, diversification and 
multilateralization of which special attention is paid to the 
enhancement of relations with countries in the region. 
  President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> stressed that since the establishment 
development, now have more opportunities for their strengthening 
in line with the interest and wish of each country, for peace, 
stability, friendship, cooperation and development in the region 
of <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>. The two sides held that their potentials 
were great, and discussed concrete measures to strengthen ties 
in the fields of economy, trade, culture, tourism, scientific 
technology, training and education. 
  The two sides exchanged views on international and regional 
issues of common concern. The Philippine side hailed and 
expressed their support for <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s participation in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. 
The Vietnamese side highly appreciated that goodwill of the 
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, and affirmed that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> was carrying out 
multi-faceted cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> through the 
latter's specific projects. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-30021 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas037_n_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-037 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  24 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Vo Van Kiet Receives Outgoing Indonesian Envoy </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK2302162594 Hanoi VNA in English 1524 GMT 23 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2302162594 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>Feb. 23</DATE> -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
received here today Indonesian Ambassador to <PERSON>Vietnam Mr. Juwana</PERSON> 
who paid him a farewell visit at the end of his term of office 
in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  At the reception, Premier <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> and Ambassador <PERSON>Juwana</PERSON> 
expressed their joy at the encouraging development of the 
fields, especially in commerce and investment. 
  Ambassador <PERSON>Juwana</PERSON> said that <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> would continue to do 
their best for further development of the bilateral relations 
which have been ushered in a new stage following the exchange of 
the visits of the two countries' leaders. He thanks <ORGANIZATION>Vietnamese 
Government</ORGANIZATION> and Premier Kiet for helping Indonesian businessmen 
in their cooperation with Vietnamese. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> hailed the Indonesian 
ambassador's 
contributions to the consolidation and promotion of the 
friendship and cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7659 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas061_l_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-061 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  30 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Philippines </F>
<H3> <TI>   Ramos on Results of Talks With SRV Officials </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK3003111094 Quezon City Radio Filipinas in English 0230 GMT 
30 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK3003111094 </F>
<F P=104>  Quezon City Radio Filipinas </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> <DATE>today</DATE> said that his meeting 
with top Vietnamese leaders have greatly enhanced 
Philippine-Vietnamese relations, which he describes as a 
critical factor for the solidarity of <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> and the 
peace and progress of the region. The president said he had 
friendly and powerful meetings with President <PERSON>Le Duc Anh</PERSON>, 
General Secretary Do Muoi of the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party of Vietnam</ORGANIZATION>, and 
Vice President <PERSON>Nguyen Thi Binh</PERSON>. The chief executive said he was 
looking forward for his luncheon meeting with the prime 
minister, <LOCATION>Vo Van Kiet</LOCATION>. 
  President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s leaders are all acutely aware 
of their country's need for regional stability so that they can 
have a breathing spell after two generations of almost 
continuous conflict to set their economy on the road to 
self-sustaining growth. 
  The president said that during his meetings with the 
Vietnamese leaders, he was able to explore new avenues of 
possible cooperation in the <LOCATION>South China</LOCATION> sea in order to reduce 
tension in the area and promote its joint development as called 
for in the <DATE>1992</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Manila Declaration</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>South China Sea</LOCATION>. The two 
countries also agreed on the needs to devise confidence-building 
mechanisms or cooperative ventures that will begin to assure 
countries with claims over the area in the rest of the region 
that the <LOCATION>South China Sea</LOCATION> can transform from waters of contention 
to an area of cooperation. 
  On the repatriation of Vietnamese refugees still in the 
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, the president said, and I [newscaster] quote, We 
agreed that the increasingly favorable economic situation in 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> should make it easier for our two countries to work out 
the repatriation of the Vietnamese asylum seekers in the 
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, unquote. 
  President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> paid tribute to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s revolutionary 
leader <PERSON>Ho Chi Minh</PERSON> by laying a wreath at his mausoleum at the <ORGANIZATION>Ba 
Dinh Square</ORGANIZATION>. The president and his official delegation arrived 
at <TIME>8:00 A.M. yesterday</TIME> and briskly walked towards the mausoleum 
escorted by the curator and a guard. After laying the wreath, 
the president proceeded to the <PERSON>Ho Chi Minh</PERSON> residence, located 
inside the compound of the Presidential Palace. The two-room 
house is made of wooden materials. The president accompanied by 
the caretakers stopped by the pond and attempted to fish out but 
failed to catch any. After this, Representative <PERSON>Antonio Cuenco</PERSON> 
told reporters that the <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN Inter-Parliamentary Organization</ORGANIZATION> 
[<ORGANIZATION>AIPO</ORGANIZATION>] will invite <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to attend the forthcoming <ORGANIZATION>AIPO</ORGANIZATION> 
meeting in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> in <DATE>September</DATE>. The invitation will be relayed 
today by the Philippine legislators accompanying President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> 
during his official visit in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>. Representative <PERSON>Cuenco</PERSON> said 
that during the <ORGANIZATION>AIPO</ORGANIZATION> meeting in <LOCATION>Manila Vietnam</LOCATION> will be offered 
an associate member status, which will make it a dialogue 
partner. Vietnam currently has an observer status in the <ORGANIZATION>AIPO</ORGANIZATION>. 
  President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> visited the assembly plant of <ORGANIZATION>Vietnam Motors 
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a joint venture of Filipino and Vietnamese businessmen. 
In extemporaneous remarks during his visit to the plant site, 
the president said the linking up of the two countries in the 
joint economic endeavor is a breakthrough in business 
partnership. He said this partnership is a new arithmetic in 
business in the global economy. The president said that so far 
<MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY> worth of spare parts have been imported from the 
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> for the plant, which assembles 9,200 <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> and [word 
indistinct] vehicles a year. The plant employs a number of 
Filipino managers and technicians. <ORGANIZATION>Vietnam Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is a 
joint venture between <ORGANIZATION>Colombia Motors Group</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> 
and <ORGANIZATION>Hoa Binh Automotive</ORGANIZATION> factory of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>70 
percent</PERCENT> equity in the firm. The plant started operations in 
<DATE>1992</DATE>. 
  President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON>, recalling that the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
made solemn commitments to respect each other's territorial and 
sovereign integrity in <DATE>1978</DATE> and in <DATE>1992</DATE>, <TIME>last night</TIME> proposed the 
holding of regular consultations among all states with claims on 
the Spratlys. According to the president, in the <LOCATION>South China 
Sea</LOCATION>, where both the countries are involved, attention needs to 
be focused not on mutual suspicions but on cooperative ventures 
that build mutual confidence and trust among the claimant 
states. The president said regular consultations on the 
Spratlys can result in greater cooperation in local confidence 
building, marine research, environmental protection and joint 
exploratory activities. 
  According to President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> the foundation for the 
friendship between the two countries were laid when they 
established diplomatic relations soon after the reunification of 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. The commitments that they made to each other were 
given substance and strength by a joint communique issued in 
<DATE>1978</DATE> by then President <PERSON>Marcos</PERSON> and then Premier <PERSON>Pham Van Dong</PERSON>, 
and they were reaffirmed by Prime minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> and 
President Aquino in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> in <DATE>1992</DATE>. 
  According to President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON>, and I quote, By this solemn 
undertaking, we pledge peace between us, resolving to settle 
peacefully any disputes and to cooperate for the common good for 
our people. This pledge I reaffirm, <PERSON>Mr. President</PERSON>, on behalf of 
my government and the Filipino people, unquote. 
  The chief executive said <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> was privileged to be the 
host 
two years ago of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s accession to the <ORGANIZATION>Treaty of Amity</ORGANIZATION> and 
Cooperation in <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s acceptance as 
observer in the <ORGANIZATION>Association of Southeast Asian Nations</ORGANIZATION>. It was 
during the same occasion in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> that <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> issued the <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> 
Declaration of the <LOCATION>South China Sea</LOCATION>, which <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> immediately 
endorsed. President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> noted that his delegation also looked 
intensively into the opportunities for counter trade and 
investments and joint ventures in each other's economy. The 
chief executive also offered the help of the Philippine 
industrialists, academics, managers and technologist in 
rebuilding <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s infrastructure and financial management and 
legislative policy formulation, and in running their tourist 
facilities. 
  According to the president, they also agreed during their 
meeting to collaborate in science and technology, education, and 
public health. The two countries also agreed to exert every 
effort to raise the level of trade and to take every advantage 
of complimentarity, adding that the trade protocol signed 
yesterday identified a long list of products that could 
profitably be exchanged between the two countries. According to 
President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> and I quote, We proposed and they agreed that we 
establish a joint commission to deal comprehensively with the 
whole range of our relationship and nurture its steady 
expansion, unquote. To promote tourism in both countries, 
President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> cited the just concluded tourism and cultural 
agreement between the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and the Vietnamese officials. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-5025 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas042_n_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-042 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Singaporean Prime Minister Visit, Talks Reported </TI></H3>
<H4>   Arrival on Official Visit </H4>
<F P=102> BK0203164494 Hanoi VNA in English 1452 GMT 2 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK0203164494 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpt] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 2</DATE> -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Goh Chok 
Tong</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION> and his wife arrived here this afternoon, 
beginning an official friendship visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> as guest of 
Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>. 
  Present at a state welcome ceremony held here this afternoon 
were Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> and his wife, Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Nguyen Manh Cam</PERSON>, Chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>State Committee for Cooperation</ORGANIZATION> 
and Investment <PERSON>Dau Ngoc Xuan</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Minister Le Van Triet</ORGANIZATION>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Finance Minister Ho Te</ORGANIZATION>, Mayor of <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> Le At Hoi and other 
senior officials. 
  Members of the diplomatic corps and representatives of 
several international organizations in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> and Singaporean 
ambassador to <PERSON>Vietnam Toh Hock Ghim</PERSON> was also present at the 
event. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5639 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas071_l_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-071 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Philippines </F>
<H3> <TI>   Romulo on Dispute With Malaysia Over Maids </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Romulo on Dispute With Malaysia Over Maids </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK1104063794 Quezon City Radio Filipinas in English 0230 GMT 
11 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1104063794 </F>
<F P=104>  Quezon City Radio Filipinas </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Leading Malaysian journalist has criticized what he 
called the highhandedness of his country's enforcement agencies 
dealing with immigrants. <PERSON>Kadir Jasin</PERSON>, editor of <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>'s 
influential NEW STRAITS TIMES, was referring in its <DATE>Sunday</DATE> 
weekly column to the roundup by Malaysian police on <LOCATION>Palm</LOCATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> 
of more than 1,000 Filipino maids in front of a Catholic church 
in <LOCATION>Kuala Lumpur</LOCATION>. In his column, <PERSON>Kadir</PERSON> said he did not think 
many Malaysians were pleased by the highhandedness by 
enforcement agencies in the operations against foreigners. 
  In the operations, 711 Filipino maids were detained. All but 
33 of them were later released after their employers produced 
their work permits. Malaysian Prime Minister <PERSON>Mahathir</PERSON> bin 
Mohamed directed authorities, including the police, to exercise 
greater care when carrying raids of suspected illegal workers in 
places of worship. As this developed, Prime Minister Mahathir 
is reported sending to <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> a personal emissary to meet with 
President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> on the <LOCATION>Palm</LOCATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> arrest. 
  Meantime, <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Roberto 
Romulo</PERSON> 
says the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Government</ORGANIZATION> has reached what he called a 
meeting of the minds with <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> on how to cool down the 
dispute. <PERSON>Romulo</PERSON> said he and the Malaysian Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Abdullah</PERSON> bin <PERSON>Haji Ahmad Badawi</PERSON> have agreed to discuss the matter 
in a joint commission set up last year. That commission carries 
the task of improving bilateral relations chilled by a 
30-year-old Philippine claim of <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Sabah State</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Speaking of <LOCATION>Sabah</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Ramos</PERSON> has evaded making a 
direct 
response to a proposal raised in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for the revival of the 
country's claim to <LOCATION>Sabah</LOCATION>. Speaking to reporters in <LOCATION>Cebu</LOCATION> in the 
<LOCATION>Visayas</LOCATION>, the president said <PERSON>Malacanang</PERSON> [presidential office] 
will issue a statement today on its position on the proposal. 
Senator <PERSON>Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo</PERSON> presented a proposal the other 
day asking President Ramos to again assert the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>' 
territorial claim of Sabah. Arroyo made the proposal shortly 
after <PERSON>Senator Ernesto Herrera</PERSON> suggested that the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine 
Government</ORGANIZATION> withdraws its invitation to <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>'s ceremonial 
king to visit <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> beginning this <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-52588 </DOCNO>
<HT>      "dreas092_n_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-092 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Vo Van Kiet Begins Official Visit in Rangoon </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Vo Van Kiet Begins Official Visit in Rangoon </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Received by Burmese Counterpart </H4>

<F P=102> BK1105151794 Hanoi VNA in English 1422 GMT 11 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK1105151794 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>May 12</DATE> -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> and 
his wife arrived in <LOCATION>Rangoon</LOCATION> today, beginning his four-day 
official friendship visit to <LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION> [<LOCATION>Burma</LOCATION>] following the 
invitation of his Burmese counterpart, <ORGANIZATION>Senior General Than Shwe</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> was given a red carpet welcome at 
the airport by Prime Minister <PERSON>Than Shwe</PERSON>, his wife, many other 
senior officials and representatives of the Burmese people of 
all walks of life. 
  Receiving Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> and his entourage, 
Prime 
Minister Than Shwe welcomed the <LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION> visit of his Vietnamese 
counterpart and held that the visit is a fine symbol of the 
desires from both sides to strengthen the friendship and 
cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION>. 
  For his part, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> thanked Prime 
Minister Than Shwe and other leaders of the Burmese State Law 
and <ORGANIZATION>Order Restoration Council</ORGANIZATION> for their warm welcome and was 
confident that his <LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION> visit would be successful and make a 
new important step in the friendly and cooperative ties between 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-30186 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas039_n_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-039 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Vo Van Kiet Sees Cuban, Austrian Delegations </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK2502155294 Hanoi VNA in English 1450 GMT 25 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2502155294 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA Feb 25 -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
received here <TIME>this morning</TIME> a delegation of the <ORGANIZATION>Cuban National 
Bank</ORGANIZATION> led by its First Vice President <PERSON>Osvaldo F. Torres</PERSON>, now on a 
working visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. While here, the delegation paid a 
floral tribute to the late President <PERSON>Ho Chi Minh</PERSON> at his 
mausoleum. It has working sessions with officials of the <ORGANIZATION>State 
Bank</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Commercial Bank of Vietnam</ORGANIZATION> during which the two 
sides affirmed their determination to continue broadening their 
cooperation and exchanging experience in the field of banking 
activities in each country in order to effectively implement the 
agreements between the two countries signed during Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>'s visit to <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> last year. Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> hailed the results of the two sides' working 
sessions as a new manifestation of the friendly and cooperative 
relations between the fraternal and reliable peoples of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. He said the friendship, cooperation and mutual 
assistance between the two countries were elements of important 
significance to the national construction and defence of each 
country in that cause and would learn much from <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s valuable 
experience. 
  Vice President <PERSON>O.F. Torres</PERSON> highly appreciated the 
achievements recorded by the Vietnamese people in the renovation 
process which he said would be an encouragement to the Cuban 
people in its struggle to overcome immediate difficulties and 
firmly safeguard its revolutionary gains in a new stage. 
  Yesterday afternoon, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> also 
received 
an Austrian trade mission led by <PERSON>Leopold Maderthaner</PERSON>, president 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Austrian Federal Economic Chamber</ORGANIZATION>, and representatives of 
45 Austrian major companies who arrived here on <DATE>Feb. 23</DATE>. While 
here, the Austrian mission compared notes with <PERSON>Doan Duy Thanh</PERSON>, 
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Vietnam Commerce and Industry Chamber</ORGANIZATION>, and 
other ministries and branches concerned on possibilities of 
expansion of economic and commercial cooperation between the two 
countries. 
  At this reception, <PERSON>Mr Maderthaner</PERSON> stressed that the 
cooperation development between <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> was in the 
right direction. Besides expanding trade ties, his country would 
assist and cooperate with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in manufacture of machines in 
service of agriculture and water resources, equipment for water 
supply, and training personnel for economic management. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Maderthaner</PERSON> informed Prime Minister <PERSON>Kiet</PERSON> of his 
government's decision to sponsor a seminar on economy to be held 
in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and to finance a feasibility study in manufacturing 
machines. Speaking to his guests, the Vietnamese prime minister 
said that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> welcomes and is ready to create favourable 
conditions for Austrian businessmen to come to inquire into 
possibilities and carry out investment projects in the interest 
of the two countries. Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> expressed his 
hope that <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION> would be a reliable partner of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in 
economic, trade cooperation and investment in future. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7329 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas059_n_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-059 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  27 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Do Muoi Continues Official Visit to Malaysia </TI></H3>
<H4>   Activities Detailed; Departs 27 Mar </H4>
<F P=102> BK2703155594 Hanoi VNA in English 1514 GMT 27 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2703155594 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 27</DATE> -- General Secretary Do <PERSON>Muoi</PERSON> and 
his party arrived in <LOCATION>Ho Chi Minh City</LOCATION> <TIME>this afternoon</TIME>, concluding 
a 4-day official visit to <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> from <DATE>March 24-27</DATE>. On <DATE>March 
26</DATE>, General Secretary Do Muoi and his party toured the state 
<LOCATION>Melaka</LOCATION>. In <LOCATION>Melaka</LOCATION>, the Vietnamese delegation call at the oil 
refinery <ORGANIZATION>Petronas Melaka</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>Petronas Company</ORGANIZATION>. On this 
occasion, the leadership of <ORGANIZATION>Petronas Company</ORGANIZATION> gave a banquet in 
honour of General Secretary Do Muoi and his party. In the 
afternoon, the Vietnamese delegation called on the Teac-Malaysia 
company, and the cultural tourist attraction of village <PERSON>Zir 
Keroh</PERSON> in the suburbs of <LOCATION>Melaka</LOCATION>. Later, the delegation paid a 
visit to the <ORGANIZATION>Independence Memorial Museum</ORGANIZATION> and a number of 
historical relics in <LOCATION>Melaka City</LOCATION>. Also on <DATE>March 26</DATE>, Governor of 
<ORGANIZATION>Melaka State Ahmad Mahmud Shahabudin</ORGANIZATION> and Prime Minister <PERSON>Rahim 
Thamby Chik</PERSON> paid a courtesy visit to General Secretary Do Muoi. 
On this occasion, the <ORGANIZATION>Melaka Government</ORGANIZATION> gave a banquet in 
honour of the Vietnamese guests. 
  Present at the banquet were Governor <PERSON>Ahmad Shhabudin</PERSON>, Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Rahim Thamby Chik</PERSON>, and a number of government's 
officials and businessmen. On his last day in <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>, General 
Secretary Do Muoi visited <LOCATION>Kelang Port</LOCATION>. Before leaving <PERSON>Kuala 
Lumpur</PERSON>, the Vietnamese were given a luncheon by <ORGANIZATION>Renong Group</ORGANIZATION>, 
whose companies are implementing investment or joint venture 
projects in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. Speaking to the businessmen, <PERSON>Mr. Do Muoi</PERSON> 
welcomed the group's investment projects in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and wished 
them success, thus contributing to the promotion of the friendly 
  Upon leaving <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> for home, General Secretary Do Muoi 
sent a message of thanks to Prime Minister <PERSON>Mahathir Mohamad</PERSON>. 
  The message says in part: `The fine results of the visit and 
the useful and constructive exchanges of views that we had with 
Your Excellency and the other excellencies have further affirmed 
our determination to promote the relations of friendship and 
interests of our two peoples, and of peace and development in 
the region and the world as a whole'. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7679 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas061_n_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-061 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Philippine President Continues Visit </TI></H3>
<H4>   Visit Called `Most Significant' </H4>
<F P=102> BK3003011894 Hanoi Voice of Vietnam in English 1000 GMT 29 
Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK3003011894 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi Voice of Vietnam </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] Filipino President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> has described his 
tour of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> as one of the most significant visits he has 
ever made. He told the media on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> before leaving <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> 
that the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, together with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and other countries 
in <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>, wish to share a common destiny and there is 
no other alternatives than promotion of economic cooperation and 
construction of peace among them. The president supported 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s succession to <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION>. He expressed readiness to share 
his country's experience to build infrastructure and a legal 
system in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. He maintained that the two countries have 
large opportunities in scientific, technological, educational, 
and health cooperation. 
  Before leaving <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON> held a press 
conference. 
  [Begin Ramos recording in English] I have, like other heads 
of government in other parts of the world, been covering [words 
indistinct]. In an effort to develop [word indistinct] 
activities in our foreign relations, [word indistinct] the 
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> cannot [word indistinct] with the vigorous economies 
of <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>. I regard this trip to the Socialist Republic 
of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> as a one of the most significant I have made. With 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and the other Southeast Asian states, the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> 
has a shared destiny. There is no alternative for peace than 
economic cooperation among us in this region that we are 
inhabit. In <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> in <DATE>1992</DATE>, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> acceded to the <LOCATION>Bali</LOCATION> Treaty 
of the <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> nations which binds signatories to settle regional 
disputes peaceably. <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s full membership in <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> is now a 
matter [words indistinct] in principle but mainly of time and 
procedure. I reiterated to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s leaders the consistent 
support of the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> to help facilitate <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s entry 
into <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION>. They in turn informed me of their intensive 
preparations for full participation in <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> activities. 
  Philippine-Vietnamese relations are a critical factor for 
the 
solidarity of <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> and consequently for the peace and 
progress of the region. I believe my visit greatly enhances 
these relations. I had friendly and fruitful meetings with 
President <PERSON>Le Duc Anh</PERSON>, General Secretary Do Muoi of the <ORGANIZATION>Communist 
Party of Vietnam</ORGANIZATION>, and Vice President <PERSON>Nguyen Thi Binh</PERSON>; and I look 
forward to our meeting with Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> later 
today. 
  Like our own leadership, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s leaders are all acutely 
aware of their country's need for regional stability so that 
they can have the breathing spell after four generations of 
almost continuous conflict to shape their economy and [word 
indistinct] self- sustaining role. With them I explored avenues 
of possible cooperation among the claimants to areas of the 
<LOCATION>South China</LOCATION> Sea and other nations of <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> in order to 
reduce tensions in the area and to promote joint development as 
called for in the <DATE>1994</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Manila Declaration</ORGANIZATION>. We agreed on the 
need to devise confidence building mechanisms, cooperative 
ventures in the area that will begin to assure the claimant 
countries of the archipelagoes that the <LOCATION>South China</LOCATION> Sea can be 
transformed from waters of contention into an area of 
cooperation. We agreed that the increasingly favorable economic 
situation in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> should make it easier for our two countries 
to work out the repatriation of the Vietnamese asylum seekers in 
the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. My delegation also looked intensively into the 
opportunities for countertrade and into investments and joint 
ventures in each other's economies. 
  We offered the help of our industrialists, academics, 
managers, and technologists in the building of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s 
infrastructure, in financial management, in legislative policy 
formulation, and in running the tourist facilities. We agreed 
there is great room for our two countries to collaborate in 
science and technology, education, and public health. And we 
agreed to exert every effort to raise the level of trade between 
us and to make and to take every advantage of complimentarities 
between our two economies. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7467 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas060_n_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-060 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Philippines President Arrives on Visit 28 Mar </TI></H3>
<H4>   Cooperation Agreements Signed </H4>
<F P=102> BK2803153194 Hanoi VNA in English 1512 GMT 28 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2803153194 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>March 28</DATE> -- Vietnamese Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Nguyen Manh Cam</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Philippine</LOCATION> Foreign Minister <PERSON>Roberto R. 
Romulo</PERSON>, signed here this afternoon an agreement on the 
establishment of a <ORGANIZATION>Vietnam-Philippines Intergovernmental 
Commission on Bilateral Cooperation</ORGANIZATION>. 
  On the same day an agreement on tourist cooperation was also 
signed here by Philippine Foreign Minister <PERSON>Romulo</PERSON> and head of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Vietnam General Department of Tourism</ORGANIZATION>, Do <ORGANIZATION>Quang Trung</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Vietnamese Trade Minister Le <PERSON>Van Triet</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Philippine 
Minister of Trade and Industry M. Rizalino Navarro</ORGANIZATION> signed a 
protocol on the export and import of goods and services between 
the two countries. 
  The signing ceremonies were witnessed by Vietnamese 
President 
Le <PERSON>Duc Anh</PERSON> and Philippine President <PERSON>Fidel Ramos</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-47756 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas011_n_94019" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-011 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  18 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Vo Van Kiet Receives French Minister </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK1701150394 Hanoi VNA in English 1452 GMT 17 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK1701150394 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>Jan. 17</DATE> -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
received here this afternoon <PERSON>Mr. Gerard Longuet</PERSON>, minister of 
industry, post-telecommunication and trade, who is leading an 
economic-trade delegation of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  Present at the reception were Minister of Trade Le Van Triet 
and French Ambassador to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> <PERSON>J.F. Nougarede</PERSON>. 
  Minister <PERSON>Longuet</PERSON> reaffirmed the <ORGANIZATION>French Government</ORGANIZATION>'s interest 
in developing its cooperation with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, not only in the 
economic and trade field but also in the fields of science, 
technology, healthcare, personnel training, and so on. <PERSON>Mr. 
Longuet</PERSON> said that concerning trade between the two countries, 
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> had got export surplus, that was why to keep the 
import-export balance, it was necessary to encourage French 
businessmen to further invest in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> so that many products 
could be made and exported to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and other countries in the 
Asia-Pacific region. The minister affirmed that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> could 
enjoy <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s support to develop its cooperation with <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> 
countries, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> will invest in and transfer technology to 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> with a view to helping it turn out programme on 
infrastructure construction in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, the French minister 
said. For his part, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> expressed his 
satisfaction at the new steps of development in the two 
countries' friendly and cooperative relations following the 
visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> of the French president early last year. The 
prime minister said that both countries have basis and 
advantages to bring their cooperation for mutual benefit to a 
new stage. He also expressed his wish that after <PERSON>Mr. Longuet</PERSON>'s 
would be developed in all fields and with higher effectiveness, 
especially in the economic-trade and investment fields. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-27797 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas021_n_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-021 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  1 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Vo Van Kiet Receives Algerian Ambassador </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK0102144294 Hanoi VNA in English 1425 GMT 1 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK0102144294 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>Feb. 1</DATE> -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
received here today Algerian ambassador to <PERSON>Vietnam Mr. Maamar 
Ahmed</PERSON> who paid him a courtesy visit. Ambassador <PERSON>M. Ahmed</PERSON> 
expressed his pleasure at the expansion of the relationship and 
cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION> in the fields of 
healthcare, education and university. He held that in current 
international situation <LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> should further 
develop such relations in the interest of each country, and for 
peace, friendship and development in the world. He wished that 
Vice President <PERSON>Nguyen Thi Binh</PERSON>'s coming visit to <LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION> would 
be successful, thus ushering in a new phase of the friendship 
and cooperation between the two countries. For his part, Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> expressed his thanks to the state and 
people of <LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION> for their assistance to the Vietnamese people. 
He affirmed that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> always ataches importance to the 
consolidation and development of fraternal friendship and 
cooperation between the two countries. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-6720 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas054_n_94007" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-054 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>
