<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-43914 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr012_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-012 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  19 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Issues Decree Reshuffling Cabinet 18 Jan </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB1901115494 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 0630 GMT 19 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1901115494 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Decree No. 94/037/BM reshuffling the <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso </F>
Government</ORGANIZATION>, issued in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> on 18 <DATE>January</DATE> by Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Youssouf Ouedraogo</PERSON> and President <PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON>] 
  [Text] The president of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, chairman of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Council of Ministers</ORGANIZATION>, considering the Constitution; considering 
Decree No. 92/160 of 16 <DATE>June 1992</DATE> appointing the prime minister; 
considering Decree 93/276/PM of 3 <DATE>September 1993</DATE> reshuffling the 
<ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso Government</ORGANIZATION>; based on the prime minister's proposal, 
decrees: 
  Article 1: The Government of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> is reshuffled as 
follows: 
  Minister of <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION>--<LOCATION>NABAHO</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Kanidoua 
  Minister of Territorial Administration</ORGANIZATION>--KABRE, <ORGANIZATION>Vincent Te 
  Minister of Justice</ORGANIZATION>, Keeper of the Seals--<LOCATION>LARBA</LOCATION>, Yarga 
  Article 2: This decree shall be published in the official 
gazette. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-974 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr052_e_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-052 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  17 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Prime Minister Ouedraogo's Appointment Terminated </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB1703103594 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 0630 GMT 17 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1703103594 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Decree No. 94120 terminating the appointment of the prime </F>
minister, issued by President <PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> on 
16 <DATE>March</DATE>] 
  [Text] The president of the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> and 
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Council of Ministers</ORGANIZATION>, 
  Considering the Constitution; 
  Considering Decree No. 92173 of 16 <DATE>June 1992</DATE> appointing the 
prime minister; 
  Considering Decree No. 93276/PM of 3 <DATE>September 1993</DATE> and 
Decree No. 94037/PM of 18 <DATE>January 1994</DATE> reshuffling the <ORGANIZATION>Burkina 
Faso Government</ORGANIZATION>; 
  Considering the resignation letter of <PERSON>Youssouf Ouedraogo</PERSON> 
dated 16 <DATE>March</DATE>, decrees: 
  Article 1: The appointment of <PERSON>Youssouf Ouedraogo</PERSON> as prime 
minister is terminated. 
  Article 2: In application of the provisions of Article 69 of 
the Constitution, the members of government shall carry out 
current ministerial business until a new government is formed. 
  Article 3: The present decree shall be published in the 
official gazette of <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-1087 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr054_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-054 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  20 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   President Names Kabore New Prime Minister </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB2003210594 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1900 GMT 20 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB2003210594 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The speculation is over. The news is finally out. 
The president of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> has just appointed the second 
prime minister of the <ORGANIZATION>Fourth Republic</ORGANIZATION>. The appointment deed 
reads as follows: 
  Decree Number 94(-?121) Appointing the Prime Minister. The 
president of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Council of Ministers</ORGANIZATION>, 
in accordance with the Constitution, decrees the following: 
  Article 1. <PERSON>Mr. Roch Marc Christian Kabore</PERSON> is hereby 
appointed 
prime minister. 
  Article 2. This decree shall be published in the official 
gazette of the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Done in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> on 20 <DATE>March 1994</DATE>. 
  Signed, <PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-1205 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr056_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-056 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Announces New Cabinet Members </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB2203234094 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 2220 GMT 22 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB2203234094 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] We bring you the list of the new 23-member 
government that has been appointed. The president of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Council of Ministers</ORGANIZATION>, considering 
the Constitution; considering Decree Number 99-121/PES of 20 
<DATE>March 1994</DATE> relating to the nomination of the prime minister, and 
on the recommendation of the prime minister decrees: 
  Article 1. The composition of the government of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> 
is as follows: 
  <PERSON>Kanidoua Naboho</PERSON>, minister of state for defense; 
  <PERSON>Herman Yameogo</PERSON>, minister of integration and African 
solidarity; 
  <PERSON>Salif Diallo</PERSON>, minister in charge of special duties of the 
Presidency of <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION>; 
  <PERSON>Zephirin Diabre</PERSON>, minister of economy, finance, and 
planning; 
  <LOCATION>Yarga Larba</LOCATION>, minister of justice, and keeper of the seals; 
  (<PERSON>Ablasseh Ouedraogo</PERSON>), minister of external relations; 
  (<PERSON>Vincent Tekabre</PERSON>), minister of territorial administration; 
  (Souley Mohamed), minister of industries, commerce, and 
mines; 
  <PERSON>Melegue Maurice Traore</PERSON>, minister of secondary and higher 
education and scientific research; 
  <PERSON>Alice Tiendrebeogo</PERSON>, minister of primary education and mass 
literacy; 
  <PERSON>Thomas Sanou</PERSON>, minister in charge of relations with 
parliament; 
  <PERSON>Joseph Kabore</PERSON>, minister of public works, housing, and town 
planning; 
  (<PERSON>Arguima Alphonse Ouedraogo</PERSON>), minister of employment, 
labor, and social security; 
  <PERSON>Juliette Bonkoungou</PERSON>, minister of civil service and 
administrative modernization; 
  <PERSON>Jena-Paul Sawadogo</PERSON>, minister of agriculture and animal 
resources; 
  (<PERSON>Nourcior Claude Somda</PERSON>), minister of communications and 
culture and government spokesman; 
  <PERSON>Christopher Dabire</PERSON>, minister of health; 
  <PERSON>Anatole G. Tindregeogo</PERSON>, minister of environment and 
tourism; 
  (<PERSON>Joseph Nongodo Ouedraogo</PERSON>), minister of water resources; 
  <PERSON>Ibrahim Traore</PERSON>, minister of youth and sports; 
  <PERSON>Ouala Koutiebou</PERSON>, minister of transport; 
  <PERSON>Akila Belombaogo</PERSON>, minister of social affairs and family; 
  <PERSON>Celestin Tiendrebeogo</PERSON>, minister delegate at the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry 
of Economy and Finance</ORGANIZATION>; 
  Article 2. The present decree will be published in the 
Official Gazette of <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION>. 
  Issued in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> on 22 <DATE>March 1994</DATE> and signed by <PERSON>Blaise 
Compaore</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-48134 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr092_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-092 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Diplomatic Ties Established With South Africa </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Diplomatic Ties Established With South Africa </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AB1205071594 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1900 GMT 11 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1205071594 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>

<F P=105>  French </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION>'s delegation to the swearing-in 
ceremony of the new South African president, led by the <ORGANIZATION>Assembly 
of People's Deputies</ORGANIZATION>' speaker <PERSON>Arsene Bongnessan Ye</PERSON>, was granted 
audience today by <ORGANIZATION>His Excellency Nelson Mandela</ORGANIZATION>. Other members 
of the delegation are External Relations Minister <PERSON>Ablasseh 
Ouedraogo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Salif Diallo</PERSON>, minister of special duties at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Presidency of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The delegation delivered a special message from President 
<PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON> to President <PERSON>Mandela</PERSON> and had a meeting with 
Foreign Minister <PERSON>Alfred Nzo</PERSON> of the Republic of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. 
During the discussions the two sides decided to establish 
diplomatic relations between <LOCATION>Burkina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> effective 
today, 11 <DATE>May</DATE>. Documents to this effect have been signed and 
exchanged at the <ORGANIZATION>South African Ministry of Foreign Affairs</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-24978 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr024_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Diplomatic Relations Reestablished With Taiwan </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB0302152394 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1900 GMT 2 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB0302152394 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The Government of <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Government</ORGANIZATION> of 
the Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, determined to promote bilateral bonds of 
decided to resume diplomatic relations at ambassadorial level as 
of 2 <DATE>February</DATE>. The designation of ambassadors will be done 
through diplomatic channels. 
  The agreement was signed in <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> on 2 <DATE>February</DATE>, 
corresponding to the <DATE>second day of the second month</DATE> of the [word 
indistinct] year of the Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. It was signed for 
the <ORGANIZATION>Government of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> by External Relations Minister 
<PERSON>Thomas Sanon</PERSON> and for the <ORGANIZATION>Government</ORGANIZATION> of the Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> by 
acting Foreign Minister <PERSON>Chin-Yen Fang</PERSON>. 
  In line with the resumption of diplomatic relations between 
<LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Burkinabe Government</ORGANIZATION> has issued a 
statement, which is read here by <PERSON>Theodore Kilimite Hien</PERSON>, the 
communications minister and government spokesman: 
  [Hien] <DATE>Today</DATE>, 2 <DATE>February</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Government of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> and 
the <ORGANIZATION>Government</ORGANIZATION> of the Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, have decided to resume 
their diplomatic relations which were suspended in <DATE>1973</DATE>. The 
resumption of relations with the Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> is based on 
the <ORGANIZATION>Burkinabe Government</ORGANIZATION>'s willingness to establish relations 
and bonds of cooperation with all countries of the world for 
mutual benefit. 
  At a time when African countries are confronted with 
terrible 
economic difficulties that are even threatening national unity, 
it is imperative for <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> to widen the circle of her 
friendship and to find partners in every part of the world, who 
are willing to support her development efforts in a continuous 
manner. By resuming normal relations with <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Burkinabe 
Government</ORGANIZATION> has obtained the assurance from the Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> 
that it will help our country on its path toward achieving 
progress through the following channels: Self-sufficiency in 
food production through a special agricultural development 
program, namely rice and soya bean production, the promotion of 
the informal sector, the reduction of unemployment, the 
revamping of youth employment schemes, the development and 
improvement of the health sector, and the building of a sports 
infrastructure, including the construction of a sports complex 
in <LOCATION>Bobo Dioulasso</LOCATION> and a sports stadium in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>. This 
initial program will be pursued through a wider range of 
operations in the future. 
  In resuming relations with <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Burkinabe Government</ORGANIZATION> 
remains faithful to the fundamental option of its external 
policy, which is based on realistic views and adjustment to the 
changes that are now marking international society. It is in 
line with the same policy of loyalty that <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> hereby 
reaffirms its willingness to maintain, to pursue, and to 
  Signed in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> on 2 <DATE>February 1994</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-11726 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes063_s_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-063 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  31 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Iran </F>
<H3> <TI>   Velayati Meets Burkina Faso Officials, Departs </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Velayati Meets Burkina Faso Officials, Departs </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC3103071594 Tehran Voice of the Islamic Republic of Iran 
First Program Network in Persian 0230 GMT 31 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> NC3103071594 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran Voice of the Islamic Republic of Iran 
First Program Network </F>

<F P=105>  Persian </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] In the second phase of his visit to African 
countries, our foreign minister met the president and other 
officials of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> yesterday. The Burkina Faso president 
described their talks as positive and called for increased 
political contacts and agricultural and development cooperation 
as well as for exhibitions of Iranian products in his country. 
  Velayati expressed <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s readiness to train people from 
<LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION> in the diplomatic, insurance, and banking fields. 
Our foreign minister described his meeting with <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> 
officials as significant; it led to agreements on forming joint 
economic commissions, offering Iranian goods to <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, 
and on cooperation in the field of commerce. 
  Velayati also met the prime minister of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> 
yesterday. The two sides expressed hopes that a joint bilateral 
economic commission and exhibitions of Iranian goods in <LOCATION>Burkina 
Faso</LOCATION> would further expand bilateral relations. 
  Velayati and his delegation left <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> for <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION> 
<TIME>last night</TIME>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-26388 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi025_g_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-025 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Sub-Saharan Africa </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Suspends Diplomatic Ties With Burkina Faso </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0502112294 Beijing XINHUA in English 1053 GMT 5 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0502112294 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, <DATE>February 5</DATE> (XINHUA) -- The Chinese 
Government has lodged a strong protest with the <ORGANIZATION>Government of 
Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> and declared the suspension of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s diplomatic 
relations with <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. 
  According to reports from <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Li Yongqian</PERSON>, Chinese 
ambassador to <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, made serious representations with 
the <ORGANIZATION>Government of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> yesterday. He solemnly stated 
that as the <ORGANIZATION>Government of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> had "restored" the 
so-called "diplomatic relations" with the <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> authorities, 
the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese Government</ORGANIZATION> lodged a strong protest with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Government of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> and declared the suspension of 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s diplomatic ties with <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Li pointed out that by doing so, the <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso Government</ORGANIZATION> 
had gone back on its solemn commitment contained in the 
communique of <DATE>September 15, 1973</DATE> on the establishment of 
diplomatic relations between <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> that it 
the sole legal government representing the entire Chinese 
people, seriously undermining the existing friendly relations 
between the two peoples. 
  He announced that the Government of the People's Republic of 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> decided, therefore, to suspend its diplomatic relations 
with <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> as of that day. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-26116 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi023_v_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-023 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> TAIWAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Report on Foreign Minister's Visit to Boston </TI></H3>
<H4>   Views Resuming Burkina Faso Ties </H4>
<F P=102> OW0302083894 Taipei CNA in English 0717 GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0302083894 </F>
<F P=104>  Taipei CNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By <PERSON>David Wang</PERSON> And <LOCATION>Sofia</LOCATION> Wu] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 2</DATE> (CNA) -- The Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> [ROC] 
will send agricultural experts to <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> to help the west 
African country develop its agriculture and economy, Foreign 
Affairs Minister <PERSON>Chien Fu</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [2 <DATE>February</DATE>]. 
  Chien, who is currently on a speaking tour here, made the 
statement shortly after the <ORGANIZATION>ROC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> issued a joint 
communique in <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> on the resumption of full diplomatic 
relations. 
  The ROC first established diplomatic ties with <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, 
then known as <LOCATION>Upper Volta</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1961</DATE>, but suspended such ties in 
<DATE>1973</DATE> after the African nation recognized <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>. 
  Chien said the <ORGANIZATION>ROC</ORGANIZATION> stationed an agricultural mission in 
<LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1960</DATE>. "Many Burkina Faso people still 
remembered the achievements of our agricultural mission in 
helping raise their rice production," he noted. 
  The ROC and <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> began discussion of resuming 
diplomatic ties two years ago. The Burkina Faso cabinet 
formally agreed to resume ties with the ROC in <DATE>January</DATE>, <PERSON>Chien</PERSON> 
said. 
  With an area of 274,000 square kilometers and a population 
of 
9.5 million, <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> became an independent nation in <DATE>1960</DATE> 
after decades of French colonial rule. It is rich in mineral 
resources and produces large quantities of cotton and livestock. 
Its political situation is stable, <PERSON>Chien</PERSON> said. 
  Moreover, <PERSON>Chien</PERSON> added, <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> has great influence on 
other west African nations. "The resumption of diplomatic ties 
with <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> will facilitate our effort to promote 
exchanges with that part of the world," he noted. 
  The ROC now maintains full diplomatic ties with eight 
African 
nations -- <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Liberia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Guinea-Bissau</LOCATION>, the Central African Republic and <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. 
  It has opened a consulate general in <LOCATION>Calabar</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nigeria</LOCATION> and 
set 
up representative offices in <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> 
bearing the <ORGANIZATION>ROC</ORGANIZATION>'s full national title. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-24800 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr021_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-021 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  1 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   President Compaore, PRC Minister Discuss Cooperation </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB2901125094 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 0700 GMT 29 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB2901125094 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The deputy <ORGANIZATION>PRC</ORGANIZATION> foreign minister was received 
yesterday by the president of the Republic. Discussions between 
the two statesmen centered on developing existing relations 
between <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-11682 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes062_s_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-062 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  31 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Iran </F>
<H3> <TI>   Commentary on `New Look' Toward Africa </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Commentary on `New Look' Toward Africa </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   NC3103082394 Tehran Voice of the Islamic Republic of Iran 
First Program Network in Persian 0345 GMT 31 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> NC3103082394 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran Voice of the Islamic Republic of Iran 
First Program Network </F>

<F P=105>  Persian </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Commentary by the <ORGANIZATION>News Research</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Commentaries Group</ORGANIZATION>] </F>
  [Text] Foreign Minister '<PERSON>Ali Akbar Velayati</PERSON> arrived in 
<LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION> yesterday as part of his trip to six African 
countries and held talks with the local officials. Even though 
the visit to <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Velayati</PERSON> and the high-ranking 
political delegation accompanying him is the second phase of our 
foreign minister's tour that began on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the delegation 
actually stopped in two countries before arriving in <LOCATION>Burkina 
Faso</LOCATION>. In addition to meeting and talking with officials of 
<LOCATION>Guinea</LOCATION>, the delegation stopped briefly at the airport in the 
Chadian capital, <LOCATION>Ndjamena</LOCATION>, on its way to <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION> and talked 
with the Chadian foreign minister. 
  During the meeting between the Iranian and Chadian foreign 
ministers, <LOCATION>Chad</LOCATION> requested that the Islamic Republic of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> 
assist in exploiting its oil resources as part of cooperation 
among countries of the South. This request is vitally important 
to <LOCATION>Chad</LOCATION>, especially after the discovery of an important oilfield 
in southern <LOCATION>Chad</LOCATION>. 
  In Guinea the Iranian delegation held detailed talks on 
economic, political, and cultural cooperation between <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Conakry</LOCATION>, including discussions on cooperation in the 
exploitation of bauxite mines, energy, the construction of 
hydro-electrical dams, and the construction of railways. 
  In <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> our foreign minister and his delegation met 
with the prime minister and discussed political and economic 
relations between the two countries. During this meeting, the 
initial basis for the expansion and consolidation of economic 
and commercial cooperation was laid, and with the formation of a 
joint commission in this field, a new era began in the economic 
cooperation between <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>. To acquaint the 
government and nation of Burkina Faso with our country's high 
economic potential, it was decided that a trade exhibition 
including products and industries of Islamic <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> be set up in 
<LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>. 
  Iran's diplomatic activities in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> are of interest to 
political experts and analysts for various reasons. The first 
is that this diplomatic initiative by the Islamic Republic of 
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> strengthens the position of Muslims in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, especially 
in <LOCATION>Black Africa</LOCATION>. The second is that this activity is 
significant to the expansion of South-South relations vis-a-vis 
the array of forces by the North against the South. The third 
is that meeting mutual needs in the economic, cultural, and 
political fields and helping deprived countries, especially with 
experts and know-how from the rich scientific and industrial 
experiences that our country has among the Third World, is an 
important objective in our country's diplomatic policy. 
  At any rate, <ORGANIZATION>Tehran</ORGANIZATION>'s new look toward <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> has attracted 
the attention of many political experts. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-43687 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr009_e_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-009 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   President on Devaluation, Restoring `Credibility' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB1201173694 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1300 GMT 12 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1201173694 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The president of Burkina Faso whom our reporter met 
this morning sounded reassuring. <PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON>, who traced 
the background of the <LOCATION>Dakar</LOCATION> meeting which led to the devaluation 
of the <ORGANIZATION>CFA</ORGANIZATION> franc, commented on the consequences of this measure 
on <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. Here is President <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON>, speaking to Rock 
<PERSON>Patrice Ouedraogo</PERSON>. 
  [Begin recording] It is true that generally speaking the 
devaluation will affect our debt. We will certainly have a 
bigger debt to pay. It will affect household spending, 
particularly certain goods which are consumed domestically but 
which used to be imported and, surely, there will be the problem 
of revamping the economy. But, generally speaking, with a 
number of backup measures geared toward reducing debt, 
preserving the industrial atmosphere, protecting the consumption 
of essential commodities, and also with the support of the 
international community in financing our investments and 
programs and in some employment generating sectors, we believe 
all this will restore a measure of credibility to our country. 
This will particularly guarantee a higher national production 
and put us in better position to export our products by, 
naturally, boosting agricultural output. And, of course, there 
will definitely be increased external investments. Domestic 
savings was also one area identified as one that should offer 
more support to our economies. In short, therefore, with all 
these measures, coupled with a system of safeguarding what I 
earlier referred to as the industrial atmosphere, we hope that 
our economies will be put in a better position to face 
international competition and sustain the welfare of our people. 
[end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-43380 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr003_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-003 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  5 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Air Afrique Chief Assesses Difficulties, Progress </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB0401225294 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1300 GMT 4 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB0401225294 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <PERSON>Burkina Faso</PERSON>, a member country of the <ORGANIZATION>Air Afrique 
Company</ORGANIZATION>, is following with interest the evolution of this 
multinational company. Yves <PERSON>Rolland Billecart</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Air Afrique</ORGANIZATION>'s 
managing director, is here in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> to hold discussions 
with Burkinabe authorities concerning the necessary change in 
this indispensable tool for air transportation. 
  After arresting the company's financial loss a few years 
ago, 
and after making important investments, such as the purchase of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Airbus</ORGANIZATION> which increased the transportation capacity of the 
company -- after this stage of spectacular rehabilitation -- <ORGANIZATION>Air 
Afrique</ORGANIZATION> is faced with new difficulties which demand increased 
support from its member countries. This will be the topic of 
the heads of state meeting which opens on 10 <DATE>January</DATE> in <LOCATION>Dakar</LOCATION>. 
After his audience with Prime Minister <PERSON>Youssouf Ouedraogo</PERSON> <TIME>this 
morning</TIME>, <PERSON>Yves Rolland Billecart</PERSON> talked to <PERSON>Gerard Sawadogo 
Koudaogo</PERSON> this. 
  [Begin recording] [<LOCATION>Billecart</LOCATION>] This visit to <PERSON>Burkina Faso</PERSON> is 
meant to examine problems specific to <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. We have 
noted with satisfaction that the exportation of agricultural 
products is going on well this year, thanks to greater 
discipline shown by exporters. It is also due to their 
commitments that <ORGANIZATION>Air Afrique</ORGANIZATION> has been able to meet the 
corresponding challenges. These were the major topics of my 
discussions with the prime minister. Earlier, I held a working 
session with the minister of transport, then with the minister 
of employment and labor, and with the minister of culture, whose 
many activities demand traveling, as well as with the minister 
of tourism. So, as you can see, the purpose of my visit was to 
discuss the general problems of the company for the <LOCATION>Dakar</LOCATION> 
conference as well as to discuss (?traveling issues). 
  [Koudaogo] Let us then talk with <PERSON>Rolland Billecart</PERSON> about all 
these problems facing <ORGANIZATION>Air Afrique</ORGANIZATION>. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Billecart] Air Afrique</ORGANIZATION> is suffering from insufficient 
funds. 
When I took over the management of the company, there was no 
more capital because it was less than <MONEY>15 billion CFA francs</MONEY>. 
Thanks to efforts made by <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> as well as our results for 
first four years, we were able to build up capital, which was 
good, but still insufficient. Presently, we have capital 
totaling <MONEY>15 billion CFA francs</MONEY>, but we have a long-term debt of 
80 billion, which came purchasing aircrafts and modernizing our 
installations. Therefore, we need to balance the funds. We had 
drawn up a program which consisted of an assistance from the 
<ORGANIZATION>African Development Bank</ORGANIZATION> [ADB]. Unfortunately, the <ORGANIZATION>ADB</ORGANIZATION> board of 
governors did not accept the suggestion of its president and we 
ended up suggesting a new plan which I negotiated with the 
<ORGANIZATION>French Government</ORGANIZATION>. And it is this program which will be 
examined in <LOCATION>Dakar</LOCATION>. If, as I expect, this program is accepted, 
<ORGANIZATION>Air Afrique</ORGANIZATION> might be able to arrange [words indistinct] as far 
its capital or a permanent fund is concerned, and have a more 
balanced financial structure. Contrary to what was said, we 
have not envisaged a restructuring of the company. It was 
restructured in <DATE>1989</DATE>. As you know, this resulted in the 
retrenchment of workers and this time, there is no question of 
retrenching workers. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-130 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr063_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-063 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  30 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Iran's Velayati Meets Parliamentary Speaker </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Iran's Velayati Meets Parliamentary Speaker </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   LD3003201594 Tehran IRNA in English 1815 GMT 30 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> LD3003201594 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran IRNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <DATE>March 30</DATE>, (IRNA) -- Foreign Minister '<PERSON>Ali Akbar 
Velayati</PERSON> in meeting with Speaker of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National 
Assembly Bonghessan Arseney</ORGANIZATION> here today said that the parliaments 
of the two countries could play an important role in the 
expansion of mutual ties. 
  He proposed that <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> could provide its legislative 
experiences to the national assembly of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Arseney in reply said that Muslims in <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION> need 
mosques, clinics and schools, and called on <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> to provide such 
services to the Muslims of his country. 
population of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-26302 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi025_g_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-025 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Sub-Saharan Africa </F>
<H3> <TI>   Spokesman Views Ties Suspension </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0502120694 Beijing XINHUA in English 1128 GMT 5 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0502120694 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, <DATE>February 5</DATE> (XINHUA) -- A <ORGANIZATION>Chinese Foreign 
Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said here today that the setback in 
<LOCATION>Sino-Burkina Faso</LOCATION> relations is not what the Chinese side wishes 
to see, and the responsibility for it rests entirely with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Government of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>. 
  On <DATE>February 2</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Government of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, in disregard 
of the long-standing friendly relations and cooperation between 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, announced the so-called "restoration" of 
"diplomatic relations" with <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>, the spokesman said, adding 
that the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese Government</ORGANIZATION> has lodged a strong protest with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Government of Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> and announced the suspension of 
diplomatic relations with <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> and cessation of 
implementation of all agreements between the two governments. 
  In recent years, the spokesman pointed out, the <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> 
authorities, taking advantage of the temporary economic 
difficulties of some countries, have gone out of their way to 
pursue "money diplomacy" in an attempt to create "two Chinas" or 
"one <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, one <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>". 
  This indecent trick, he noted, goes entirely against the 
fundamental interest of the Chinese nation and is bound to meet 
the opposition of the people on both sides of the <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> straits. 
  "The scheme of the <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> authorities is doomed to failure," 
he said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-48204 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr094_e_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-094 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Minister, Unions Discuss Salary Increases </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Minister, Unions Discuss Salary Increases </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AB1405153494 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1300 GMT 13 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1405153494 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>

<F P=105>  French </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] The highlight of <TIME>this morning</TIME> is the resumption of 
the consultations between the government and the labor unions. 
The meeting was convened to present the government's responses 
to workers' demands contained in the memorandum submitted to the 
prime minister by the labor unions on 1 <DATE>May</DATE>. Here is Braimah 
Ouedraogo with a report. 
  [<PERSON>Ouedraogo</PERSON>] A pay rise is out of the question. According to 
the explanations of the budget minister, an increase of 40 to <PERCENT>50 
percent</PERCENT> will result in a budget deficit of 93 billion and 97 
billion respectively. Therefore, there are no funds to finance 
such a pay rise. Fuel prices cannot also be reduced since they 
are no longer standardized. 
  The commerce, industry, and mines minister, who was present, 
talked about the establishment of a market street which would 
enable small traders to obtain cheap stalls. He also talked 
about the <ORGANIZATION>National Grains Office</ORGANIZATION> [OFNACER] and the Faso <PERSON>Yaar</PERSON> 
[state-owned marketing organization]. OFNACER has already been 
liquidated and the minister assured consumers in high-risk areas 
that cereal shortages could be covered by SONAGES [expansion 
unknown]. However, the Faso <PERSON>Yaar</PERSON> could not be rehabilitated 
despite the unions' demands. This is a sector that the state 
has transferred to the private sector in order to make it more 
efficient. The state is reported to have lost more than <MONEY>6 
billion CFA francs</MONEY> in organizations such the Faso <PERSON>Yaar</PERSON>. 
  Finally, concerning pharmaceuticals, the health minister 
outlined a number of measures taken to protect people's pockets. 
These include negotiations with the <ORGANIZATION>French Pharmaceutical 
Producers Union</ORGANIZATION> for the latter to reduce wholesale prices. With 
the <MONEY>2 billion</MONEY> granted by <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> as post-devaluation subsidy for 
pharmaceutical imports, there are plans for price cuts of 20 to 
<PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> in the next few days. The health minister promised 
to reduce the number of pharmaceutical importers, which should 
lead to a considerable reduction in retail prices for the people. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-26601 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi121_v_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-121 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  23 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> TAIWAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Burkina Faso President To Visit Taipei 18-22 Jul </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Burkina Faso President To Visit Taipei 18-22 Jul </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW2306081794 Taipei CNA in English 0710 GMT 23 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2306081794 </F>
<F P=104>  Taipei CNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By <PERSON>Danielle Yang</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 23</DATE> (CNA) -- Burkina Faso President 
<PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON> is scheduled to visit the Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> 
[ROC] <DATE>July 18-22</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> [23 <DATE>June</DATE>]. 
  Burkina Faso resumed diplomatic relations with the ROC on 
<DATE>February 2, 1994</DATE>. 
  Compaore's visit is at the invitation of President <PERSON>Li 
Teng-hui</PERSON>. He will exchange views with Li on international 
situation and matters of mutual concern as well as visit local 
agricultural and economic establishments. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-23844 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr116_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-116 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Authorities Report Attack by Tuareg Rebels </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Authorities Report Attack by Tuareg Rebels </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AB1506195894 Paris AFP in English 1825 GMT 15 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> AB1506195894 </F>
<F P=104>  Paris AFP </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 15</DATE> (AFP) -- Authorities in <LOCATION>Burkina 
Faso</LOCATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [15 <DATE>June</DATE>] that an attack by "Tuareg rebels" 
had been carried out on its territory, the first time such an 
incident has been officially acknowledged. 
  Interior Ministry Secretary General <PERSON>Pascal Benon</PERSON> said the 
group, probably from <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>, opened fire on a coachload of 
passengers on <DATE>June 9</DATE> near <LOCATION>Djibo</LOCATION>, 190 kilometres (120 miles) 
north of <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> and injured three of them. The group also 
intercepted an official car, <PERSON>Benon</PERSON> said. 
  Several other clashes have been reported since <DATE>last 
December</DATE>. 
  The Tuareg rebellion has been raging in neighbouring <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION> 
and 
<LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> since the early <DATE>1990s</DATE>, leading some 7,000 people to seek 
refuge in <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION>. 
  Military reinforcements were sent to the area at the start 
of 
the week. <PERSON>Benon</PERSON> said the situation was "very tense" and 
stressed that there was a danger local people might decide to 
"settle their scores with the Tuaregs for themselves." 
  The refugees have gradually been relocated in a camp run by 
the <ORGANIZATION>UN High Commissioner</ORGANIZATION> for Refugees at the village of Ferrelio 
to the north of Djibo. 
  The authorities in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> want the <ORGANIZATION>UNHCR</ORGANIZATION> to move the 
camp away from the border. However, the <ORGANIZATION>UNHCR</ORGANIZATION> wants <PERSON>Burkina 
Faso</PERSON>, one of the poorest countries in the world, to pay the 
costs, estimated at <MONEY>184 million CFA Francs</MONEY> (330,000 dollars). 
  The country's 1,000-kilometre (600-mile) frontier with <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION> 
and the 500-kilometre (300-mile) one with <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> are considered 
practically uncontrollable by the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1940EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BurkinaFaso 1stLd-Writethru a0594 12-25 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burkina Faso, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0594,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burkina Faso Reports Coup Foiled</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 2 grafs on no details known.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OUAGADOUGOU, Burkina Faso (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government said <DATE>Monday</DATE> it
foiled an attempted coup against the 2-year-old government of
President <PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON>, but denied reports that it executed
seven of those arrested.
   Justice Minister <PERSON>Antoine Komi Sambo</PERSON> told a news conference
``foreign mercenaries'' were among those arrested, but he refused
to provide any details.
   He said those arrested would be brought before the courts of
this landlocked West African former French colony, once known as
<ORGANIZATION>Upper Volta</ORGANIZATION>.
   Burkina Faso, with a population of more than 8.5 million, gained
independence in <DATE>1960</DATE>.
   In <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Burkinabe League of Human Rights</ORGANIZATION> issued a
statement protesting the arrests and what it called repression by
the country's ``military dictatorship.''
their number is likely to double in the days to come, according to
disquieting information coming from <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION>,'' it said.
quoted what it called well-informed sources in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> as
saying seven people were executed <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>,
and about 30 others, mostly soldiers, were arrested.
   Compaore took power <DATE>Oct. 15, 1987</DATE>, in a military coup that left
President <PERSON>Thomas Sankara</PERSON> among those slain. Officials reported
another aborted coup last <DATE>September</DATE> and said four alleged plotters
were executed summarily, including the men who were No. 2 and No. 3
in <LOCATION>Compaore</LOCATION>'s government.
   The justice minister did not disclose on <DATE>Monday</DATE> when any of the
latest events took place, nor did he disclose any details of the
coup attempt.
   The <ORGANIZATION>League of Human Rights</ORGANIZATION>, a Paris-based group of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>
exiles, said it had no further specifics on the attempt.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-1206 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr056_e_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-056 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   New Prime Minister's Background Outlined </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB2203171794 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 0630 GMT 22 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB2203171794 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] New Prime Minister <PERSON>Roch Marc Christian Kabore</PERSON> 
yesterday granted an exclusive interview to <ORGANIZATION>Radio Burkina</ORGANIZATION>. The 
current prime minister, appointed by presidential decree, is not 
new to the political scene. He is 37 years old and has held 
successive posts as minister of transport and communications 
from <DATE>1989</DATE> to <DATE>1990</DATE>, minister of state from <DATE>1990 to 1992</DATE>, minister 
of state in charge of finance and planning from <DATE>1992</DATE> to <DATE>1993</DATE>, 
and then minister in charge of relations with institutions. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-25366 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr032_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-032 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  16 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Niger Minister, Tuareg Leader Resume Negotiations </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB1502163194 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 2200 GMT 14 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1502163194 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpt] Negotiations among Nigerois resumed this 
afternoon in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>. The Coordination of Armed Resistance 
-- which includes all the Tuareg movements -- and a <ORGANIZATION>Niger 
Government</ORGANIZATION> delegation were received in turn by President 
<PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> in the <TIME>early evening</TIME>. The first group to arrive in the 
country was the eight-member Tuareg delegation and were the 
first to be received by President <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON>. The half-hour 
audience granted to each group enabled them to remove the final 
obstacles and pave the way for the beginning of a new round of 
talks at the same table scheduled for 15 <DATE>February</DATE>. There was 
much optimism at the end of the meeting. The <ORGANIZATION>Niger Government</ORGANIZATION>'s 
position was put forward by the <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> foreign minister. 
Abdourahamane Hama, who is leading the government delegation, is 
interviewed by <PERSON>Yannick-Laurent Bayala</PERSON>. He thinks that 
everything is ready for the resumption of talks with the Tuareg 
rebels. 
  [Begin recording] [Hama] This is indeed a great moment for 
Nigerois. We finally have this opportunity here in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> 
to discuss a problem which is very vital to our country's future. 
  [<LOCATION>Bayala</LOCATION>] Can the meeting effectively begin on 15 <DATE>February</DATE>? 
  [Hama] We think that as far as the <ORGANIZATION>Niger Government</ORGANIZATION> is 
concerned there is no reason why the meeting should not begin. 
  [<LOCATION>Bayala</LOCATION>] How can you be sure of that? 
  [Hama] I think that for now, we will not discuss the problem 
in detail for now. Negotiations need to be prepared. The fact 
that we will be meeting to see how we will proceed in the coming 
months and weeks to solve the problem is already a big step. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Niger Government</ORGANIZATION> is prepared to find a solution to the 
problem; President <PERSON>Mahamane Ousmane</PERSON> said so when he took office 
and he reiterated that at the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>. I think the fact 
that such an important government delegation, including at least 
five or six ministers, and high-ranking members of <ORGANIZATION>Air</ORGANIZATION> and 
Azaouak are here in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> is an important sign of our 
goodwill. 
  [<LOCATION>Bayala</LOCATION>] President <PERSON>Mahamane</PERSON> has met Tuareg traditional 
rulers. Does it mean that the different sides have finally got 
to the point where they have set aside their differences in 
spite of the recent violence? Several people have recently 
died from that. 
  [Hama] I think that contacts and dialogue between the two 
sides were never broken off. Today, we are simply formalizing 
that dialogue to solve the problem in concrete terms. 
  [<LOCATION>Bayala</LOCATION>] The Tuareg delegation leader, <PERSON>Mano Dayak</PERSON>, speaks of 
the magnitude of the problem and reaffirms his delegation's 
willingness to find a negotiated solution. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Dayak</ORGANIZATION>] Our problem is a regional problem and it should be 
seen in that light. We are pleased about efforts being made by 
<ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> to find a solution to the problem as soon as 
possible. 
  [<LOCATION>Bayala</LOCATION>] <PERSON>Mr. Mano Dayak</PERSON>, several opportunities have been 
missed. Will this one be grasped? 
  [Dayak] There have certainly been several missed 
opportunities in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> indeed but that was not the 
resistance's fault: We were the ones who suggested that the 
first meeting should be held in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>. There were 
definitely problems which have made it impossible for us to meet 
here up until now. We are here now and that is the main thing. 
We can now say that things are really going to get under way. 
  [<LOCATION>Bayala</LOCATION>] There has been fresh violence lately in <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> and 
the government has blamed it on the Tuareg resistance. Do you 
deny responsibility? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Dayak</ORGANIZATION>] The truce ended at the beginning of <DATE>June</DATE>. We are, 
therefore, unfortunately in a war situation. We are sorry about 
that, but we hope that there will be a solution and we are ready 
for that. I think if there is a conflict or if tension resumes 
in the subregion, no one can be blamed or criticized for that. 
We would like to put an end to that situation. We are calling 
on the <ORGANIZATION>Niger Government</ORGANIZATION> to embark on frank and sincere dialogue 
as soon as possible to end these kinds of actions. 
  [<LOCATION>Bayala</LOCATION>] <PERSON>Mano Dayak</PERSON>, people are very much in favor of 
Algerian and French representatives taking part in the 
<LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> negotiations. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Dayak</ORGANIZATION>] The Algerian Government has always been involved in 
various negotiations and discussions. <LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION> is part of the 
subregion and wants to find a solution to the problem. Right 
from the beginning it has endeavored -- just as <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> is 
doing now -- to find a solution. It will be involved in ongoing 
negotiations as one of the observer countries. 
  [<LOCATION>Bayala</LOCATION>] Just like <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Dayak</ORGANIZATION>] Yes, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> will be present at the negotiation as a 
mediator. We did not come to <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> for the negotiations 
proper. That will take some time. It is a technical meeting to 
determine which countries will be mediating, what the future 
political negotiations will be, and where they will be held. 
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION> will be certainly involved in the 
negotiations. The coordination's demands will be contained in a 
document which we will publish in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>. This is very 
important for us because our problem is an African one. We 
would therefore like to find a solution within and African 
context and <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION> is an ideal place for that. We will be 
demanding a minimum of rights for our people who have always 
been marginalized in <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION>. They should now be entitled to the 
same rights as other <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> communities. That is what we are 
calling for now, otherwise there will unfortunately be no peace. 
We are calling for regional autonomy for the whole community 
politically and economically. [end recording] [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890919-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-89 2117EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-BurkinaFaso-Coup     09-19 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burkina Faso-Coup,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Coup Plotters Executed in Burkina Faso</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four men were executed after security
agents uncovered at the last minute a plot to overthrow President
<PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON>, the official <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso News Agency</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Two of the four were in the top echelon of the government, it
reported.
   The agency said agents thwarted the plotters' attempt to arrest
<PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> upon his return from a trip to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> late <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Reached by telex from <LOCATION>Abidjan</LOCATION>, the agency quoted government
spokesman <PERSON>Clement Ouedraogo</PERSON> as saying the coup leaders planned to
seize the airport and if they met resistance, to shoot down
<PERSON>Compaore</PERSON>'s plane when it approached.
   Ouedraogo spoke at a news conference <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>,
capital of the impoverished Sahelian nation. The agency said <PERSON>Burkina
Faso</PERSON> was calm, and that no fighting has taken place.
   <PERSON>Ouedraogo</PERSON> said Maj. <PERSON>Jean-Baptiste Boukary Lingani</PERSON> and Capt. <PERSON>Henri
Zongo</PERSON>, effectively the No. 2 and No. 3 men in <LOCATION>Compaore</LOCATION>'s Popular
Front military government, were executed along with two other
military plotters, not identified.
   The agency quoted <PERSON>Ouedraogo</PERSON> as saying Capt. <PERSON>Gilbert Diendere</PERSON>, in
charge of presidential security, discovered the scheme just before
<PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> returned.
   The executions mark the final breakup of a clique of young
officers who came to power with Capt. <PERSON>Thomas Sankara</PERSON> in <DATE>Aug. 4,
1983</DATE>. Zongo and <PERSON>Lingani</PERSON>, like <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> close friends of <LOCATION>Sankara</LOCATION>,
supported <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> in his overthrow and killing of <LOCATION>Sankara</LOCATION> on <DATE>Oct.
15, 1987</DATE>.
   First word of the coup attempt came in a communique read on the
government-controlled radio. It said, ``Our people and revolution,
and its militants at all levels, have just escaped, on the <TIME>night</TIME> of
<DATE>Sept. 18, 1989</DATE>, a cowardly plot fomented by military and fascist
elements led by some ambitious and anti-revolutionary people who are
at the very top of the political leadership.''
   It specifically named <PERSON>Lingani</PERSON> and <PERSON>Zongo</PERSON> and said their objectives
``were to dissolve the Popular Front and all the political
organizations and to restore fascist authority.''
   Burkina Faso, victim of recurring droughts in the <DATE>past two
decades</DATE>, has experienced six military coups since independence from
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>1960</DATE>. It is listed by the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> as one of the world's
poorest nations with personal income averaging <MONEY>$190</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The West African nation has a population of about 6 million and
covers 105,870 square miles. More than <MONEY>2 million</MONEY> Burkinabe have left
their country to seek work in <LOCATION>Ivory Coast</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-562 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr071_e_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-071 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> EAST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Kabore Refutes Rumors of 15-Percent Salary Increase </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Kabore Refutes Rumors of 15-Percent Salary Increase </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AB1104152094 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 0630 GMT 11 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1104152094 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>

<F P=105>  French </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Head of Government <PERSON>Roch Marc Christian Kabore</PERSON> on 9 
<DATE>April</DATE> publicly announced the counter proposals made by the labor 
unions in response to the government's 5 <DATE>April</DATE> proposals. The 
issue that has set a lot of tongues wagging is certainly that of 
salary increase, heightened by rumors of a hypothetical 
15-percent increase said to have been authorized by the <ORGANIZATION>World 
Bank</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>. This has once again sparked off the debate 
over whether or not to believe the government, which has been 
telling the whole world that budgetary constraints resulting 
from the structural adjustment program do not enable it to 
significantly increase salaries. Prime Minister <PERSON>Kabore</PERSON> refutes 
these rumors and also gives some facts on the sales tax the 
government is levying on fuel. 
  [Begin Kabore recording] We have been hearing here and there 
that the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> have authorized the government 
to increase salaries by <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> and that it is refusing to do 
so, in the hope that by bullying workers it could get them to 
accept its proposals. I would like to dispel any doubts on the 
matter, which I believe was reported by JEUNE AFRIQUE news 
magazine which I would say is not a negotiator between these 
institutions and our country. I would also like to reaffirm 
that at no time was <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> authorized, under the current 
program, to effect a 15-percent salary increase. It is 
therefore important for us to dispel such doubts since the 
rumors being circulated could cause some confusion among workers 
and Burkinabe in general. We need to remove all such doubts on 
the matter. 
  The other problem is that when people look at the price 
structure they accuse the government of levying too many taxes, 
especially in regard to fuel and a certain number of items. I 
would simply like to draw everyone's attention to the fact that 
the basic revenue -- the 6 billion we have been talking about -- 
constitutes earnings generated from taxes levied on various 
products. Thus, logically speaking, if we (?invest) 126 
billion, in light of the taxes we are collecting today, it is 
obvious that if we reduce the value of these taxes, we would 
actually be reducing the state's revenue and it would therefore 
be unreasonable to demand salary increases. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-37228 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes118_d_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-118 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  18 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Libya </F>
<H3> <TI>   Visit by Presidents of Mali, Niger, Burkina Faso </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Visit by Presidents of Mali, Niger, Burkina Faso </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Statement on Visit by African Presidents </H4>

<F P=102> LD1806205894 Tripoli Libyan Television Network in Arabic 
1930 GMT 18 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD1806205894 </F>
<F P=104>  Tripoli Libyan Television Network </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] A press statement was issued today in <LOCATION>Tripoli</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Bamako</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Niamey</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>, following the visit of 
Presidents <PERSON>Blaise Campaore</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Alpha Oumar Konare</PERSON> 
of <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Mahamane Ousmane</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Great Jamahiriyah</LOCATION>. 
Here follows the text of the statement: 
  In the framework of the fraternal relations linking the 
Great 
Socialist People's Libyan Arab Jamahiriyah [RSPLJ] with <PERSON>Burkina 
Faso</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of Niger</ORGANIZATION>, and the Republic of <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>, and 
proceeding from the principles and objectives of the <ORGANIZATION>OAU</ORGANIZATION>, and in 
eagerness to strengthen the relations of brotherhood and good 
neighborliness between their countries, Presidents <PERSON>Blaise 
Campaore</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mahamane Ousmane</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Alpha 
Oumar Konare of Mali</ORGANIZATION> paid a business and fraternal visit to the 
<DATE>RSPLJ from 15 to 18 June</DATE>. 
  Brother Colonel Mu'ammar al-Qadhdhafi, leader of the great 
al-Fatih revolution, had metings with the guest presidents, and 
intensive talks were held between them on relations between 
their countries in the political and economic spheress, and on 
regional, African, and international issues of common interest. 
The leaders expressed satisfaction at the tangible development 
of relations and cooperation between them, and they stressed the 
importance of relations between their countries in the 
political, economic, and security-related domains, and the 
founding of the appropriate organs toward this end. 
  The leaders expressed their great concern over the situation 
in <LOCATION>Rwanda</LOCATION>. They condemn the massacres being repeatedly 
perpetrated against civilians in <LOCATION>Rwanda</LOCATION>. In this respect, they 
stressed the importance of an immediate cease-fire between the 
parties to the conflict, and the need to find a radical solution 
that would bring security and stability to <LOCATION>Rwanda</LOCATION>. 
  With the aim of bolstering collective relations between 
their 
states, the leaders underscored the importance of activating the 
group of states bordering the <LOCATION>Sahara</LOCATION>, and of promoting 
cooperation between them in order to secure stability and 
security, and to resolve the problems in the region, which would 
become an element toward a linkage and not separation between 
the north and south of the <LOCATION>Sahara</LOCATION>, and in order to secure 
collective cooperation between them in harmony with the 
historic, social, and cultural ties between their peoples. 
  The leaders reviewed the efforts being made to carry out the 
national charter in the Republic of <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>, and the talks underway 
in order to put an end to the armed rebellion in northern <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION>. 
They stressed the importance of finding a final solution to 
these questions out of their commitment to preserving security 
throughout the region. Therefore, the leaders agreed that a 
meeting be held by the foreign ministers of the concerned states 
in the <LOCATION>Republic</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION> in order to prepare for the convening of 
a summit in the RSPLJ. Toward this end, the foreign ministers 
have been assigned the task of intensifying contacts and 
meetings and exchanging information. 
  The leaders also reiterated their solidarity and that of 
their peoples with the people of the RSPLJ in facing up to the 
measures imposed on the Arab Libyan people. They expressed 
their support for the Arab, African, and international efforts 
being made in order to find a just, honest, and rapid solution 
so as to put an end to these measures, which affect all the 
peoples of the region. 
  At the conclusion of the visit, the presidents expressed 
their thanks and gratitude to brother leader Mu'ammar 
al-Qadhdhafi, the leader of the great al-Fatih revolution, and 
the Arab Libyan people, for the warm welcome and hospitality 
offered to them. 
  Signed in <LOCATION>Tripoli</LOCATION> on 9 <LOCATION>Muharram</LOCATION>, corresponding to 18 <DATE>June 
1994</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-14017</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EDVCVABAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940422
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 APR 94 / Pledge over female mutilation: World Bank and IMF win
commitment by Burkina Faso
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By GEORGE GRAHAM
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
In an unusual broadening of their role into social and cultural issues, the
government of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> to take steps to combat female genital
mutilation.
The commitment is included in <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION>'s policy framework paper, a set
of medium-term economic policy priorities negotiated with the international
financial institutions as the basis for receiving assistance loans.
The practice of female genital mutilation, sometimes referred to as female
circumcision, is widespread in many countries of <LOCATION>sub-Saharan Africa</LOCATION>. Besides
ritually reinforcing the subordination of women, the mutilation brings
severe risks of infection and starkly increases health risks in later life.
World Health Organisation officials estimate that genital mutilation doubles
the risk of death at childbirth and increases the risk of still-birth by
three or four times.
Besides the WHO, donor countries such as the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> have sought to
discourage the practice. The <ORGANIZATION>United Nations Human Rights Commission</ORGANIZATION> last
month agreed to a special investigation into violence against women, but
referred only obliquely to genital mutilation as 'the harmful effects of
certain traditional or cultural practices.'
Burkina Faso is in the middle of a radical economic adjustment programme
begun in <DATE>1991</DATE> but intensified this year by the 50 per cent devaluation of
the <ORGANIZATION>CFA</ORGANIZATION> franc agreed by members of the currency zone in <DATE>January</DATE>.
The <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> last month agreed to lend the Burkina Faso government Dollars 25m
(Pounds 17m) from its enhanced structural adjustment facility, which
provides subsidised loans for very poor countries.
The adjustment programme contains a number of measures designed to alleviate
the impact of the devaluation on some of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>'s most vulnerable
population groups. They included steps to spread price increases for
essential consumer goods such as kerosene and generic drugs over a six- to
12-month period, and an expansion of primary health and basic education
services.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>BFZ  Burkina Faso, Africa.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9431 Administration of Public Health Programs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-43457 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr005_e_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-005 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Ghana </F>
<H3> <TI>   President Meets Delegations From Burkina, Zimbabwe </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB0601164394 Accra Ghana Broadcasting Corporation Radio 
Network in English 1800 GMT 5 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB0601164394 </F>
<F P=104>  Accra Ghana Broadcasting Corporation Radio 
Network </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The president, Flight Lieutenant <PERSON>Jerry John 
Rawlings</PERSON>, today received the envoys from <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Burkina 
Faso</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Castle Osu</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The Zimbabwean minister of defense, <PERSON>Mr. Woven Enock Mahachi</PERSON>, 
who is the leader of the military team currently touring the 
country, delivered a special message from President <PERSON>Robert 
Mugabe</PERSON> to President <PERSON>Rawlings</PERSON>. <PERSON>Mr. Mahachi</PERSON> and his colleagues 
are assessing infrastructure and logistic facilities available 
in the country on which Zimbabwean troops will rely during the 
peace keeping duties in <LOCATION>Liberia</LOCATION>. He said their troops are ready 
but funds have not yet been made available and hoped when 
everything is set, the Zimbabwean troops will be able to cope 
with the situation. 
  President <PERSON>Rawlings</PERSON> said though the Liberian situation is an 
economic drain, with assistance it is manageable. He promised 
that the country will make available any information that will 
help the smooth deployment of troops. The command structure of 
the new UN force is also yet to be resolved. <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Uganda</LOCATION> were selected by the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> to join 
Monitoring Group</ORGANIZATION>] troops in peacekeeping duties in <LOCATION>Liberia</LOCATION>. 
  A three-man delegation from <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> made up of the 
minister of commerce, industry, and mines, <PERSON>Mr. Zephirin Diabre</PERSON>, 
and the chief of staff at the president's office, <PERSON>Mr. Gilbert 
Diendere</PERSON>, also delivered a message from President <PERSON>Blaise 
Compaore</PERSON> to President <PERSON>Rawlings</PERSON>. The message contained an 
invitation to President <PERSON>Rawlings</PERSON> to attend the commissioning of 
a hydroelectric project in <LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-1022 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr053_e_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-053 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  17 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Premier's Resignation Blamed on Discord With Workers </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB1703160094 Dakar PANA in English 1410 GMT 17 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> AB1703160094 </F>
<F P=104>  Dakar PANA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>, 17 <DATE>March</DATE> (PANA) -- The resignation of 
the Burkinabe prime minister, <PERSON>Youssouf Ouedraogo</PERSON>, was caused by 
the failure of negotiations with workers following the 
[17 March] in <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>. They point out that even if he was 
supported by President <PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON>, he was not able to meet 
the demands of the trade unions. 
  The workers were demanding better living conditions, a 
substantial salary increase and maintaining prices at a 
reasonable level. In spite of the signing on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> of a 
joint communique between the government and the unions which 
increased salaries, the trade unions are still threatening to 
strike because they consider the salary increases insufficient. 
Some of the trade union leaders who signed the accord later 
rejected it saying that concessions made by the government were 
not enough. 
  <PERSON>Youssouf Ouedraogo</PERSON>, who resigned on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, is 
portrayed in his country as a brilliant technocrat, with a solid 
academic, administrative and political experience in <LOCATION>Burkina 
Faso</LOCATION>. Nominated prime minister on 16 <DATE>June 1992</DATE>, <PERSON>Ouedraogo</PERSON>, an 
economist, has been a lecturer at the <ORGANIZATION>Economic Sciences 
Institute of the University of Ouagadougou</ORGANIZATION>. A member of the 
People's Assembly (ADP- <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION>) since the last general 
elections of <DATE>1992</DATE>, <PERSON>Ouedraogo</PERSON> was planning and popular 
development minister (<DATE>September 1984-August 1987</DATE>), cooperation 
and planning minister (<DATE>November 1987-April 1989</DATE>) and president 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Economic and Social Council</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>April 1989-May 1992</DATE>). 
  During the general convention of the <ORGANIZATION>Organisation for 
Popular 
Democracy Labour Movement</ORGANIZATION> (ODP/MT), which has majority in 
<LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> with 79 seats <PERSON>Ouedraogo</PERSON> who was not an active 
political leader, was elected senior vice president of the 
party, on 19 <DATE>April 1993</DATE>. His nomination as prime minister 
raised many controversies in the ODP/MT. He reshuffled his 
government two times during his two year term. The first was on 
3 <DATE>September 1993</DATE> and the second on 19 <DATE>January 1994</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880312-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-12-88 0010EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BurkinaFaso     03-12 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burkina Faso,0412</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burkina Faso President Welcomes Foreign Interests</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCO WERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON> of Burkina
Faso outlined his government's new program <DATE>Friday</DATE> and made it clear
that he will give business and foreign interests a warmer welcome
than his predecessor did.
   In a radio broadcast monitored in <LOCATION>Abidjan</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> said that
with <PERSON>Burkina Faso</PERSON>'s ``limited resources, the state alone cannot
pretend to do anything.''
   Compaore led the <DATE>Oct. 15</DATE> coup in which President <PERSON>Thomas Sankara</PERSON>
was killed. It was the fifth coup in the poor West African nation
independence from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>1960</DATE>. Both men were army captains and
<PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> was a close aide of <ORGANIZATION>Sankara's</ORGANIZATION>.
   Sankara had antagonized business people and Western governments
and creditors with his policies and statements attacking Western
imperialism.
   <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> his government will work with national,
foreign and private sectors, an apparent reference to his efforts
to improve government relations with national trade unions,
commercial interests and foreign neigbors.
   The new program, published later <DATE>Friday</DATE> in the official daily
Sidwaya newspaper, pledged to continue some economic reforms begun
under <PERSON>Sankara</PERSON>.
   The program called for a ``reinforcement of industrial
production and the rehabilitation of factories that are underused
or currently dormant.''
   The plan pledged to ``enlarge and reinforce democracy.'' Its
most striking change was abolition of <ORGANIZATION>Sankara</ORGANIZATION>'s feared
<ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Defense Committees</ORGANIZATION> in favor of smaller organizations
with a social and cultural focus. The organizations would be
separate groups of rural peasants, blue collar workers, youth,
civil servants, women and the elderly.
   Compaore avoided offending elements sympathetic to <PERSON>Sankara</PERSON>.
Without directly naming <PERSON>Sankara</PERSON>, he noted his speech borrowed ideas
from the political program <PERSON>Sankara</PERSON> laid out in a <DATE>1983</DATE> speech made
shortly after taking power.
   Compaore's foreign relations program was more moderate than the
radical policies of <LOCATION>Sankara</LOCATION>, which criticized <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>
policy and its involvement in <LOCATION>Chad</LOCATION>. The <PERSON>Sankara</PERSON> program troubled
many of Burkina Faso's neighbors, whose relations with Libyan
leader <PERSON>Moammar Gadhafi</PERSON> have been strained.
   <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> said his program was drawn up after a review of the
four years of <ORGANIZATION>Sankara</ORGANIZATION>'s government. He offered no direct criticism
of <PERSON>Sankara</PERSON> and only briefly referred to his seizure of power as a
``rectification process.''
   Compaore also pledged to continue the government crackdown on
corruption and laziness begun when <PERSON>Sankara</PERSON> took power in <DATE>1983</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-43773 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr010_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-010 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  14 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Commerce Minister Warns Against Price Hikes </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB1301174394 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 0630 GMT 13 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1301174394 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] Following the devaluation of the <ORGANIZATION>CFA</ORGANIZATION> franc, the 
industry, commerce, and mines minister would like to inform the 
public and traders that price increases may only be effected 
with prior approval from the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Industry</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, and 
<ORGANIZATION>Mines</ORGANIZATION>. Anybody found violating this measure will be prosecuted 
and punished since price, profit margin, and stock controls were 
instituted yesterday. The standardization of prices and 
proceeds of locally manufactured goods has also been instituted. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-1544 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr062_e_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-062 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  30 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Guinea </F>
<H3> <TI>   Iranian Foreign Minister Concludes Visit </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  LD3003133394 Tehran IRNA in English 1311 GMT 30 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> LD3003133394 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran IRNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Conakry</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 30</DATE>, IRNA -- Foreign Minister of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> 
'<PERSON>Ali Akbar Velayati</PERSON> left here for <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION> today at the end 
of his two-day visit and was seen off at the airport by his 
Guinean counterpart <PERSON>Ibrahima Sylla</PERSON> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [30 <DATE>March</DATE>]. 
  During his stay here, <PERSON>Velayati</PERSON> conferred with Guinean 
President <PERSON>Lansana Conte</PERSON>, and conveyed to him a message from 
President '<PERSON>Ali Akbar Hashemi-Rafsanjani</PERSON>. Velayati, who arrived 
here <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> after a stopover in <LOCATION>Chad</LOCATION>, also held talks with 
<PERSON>Sylla</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Guinean Minister of Natural Resources Toumani Dakoum 
Sako</ORGANIZATION>. He also attended a large gathering of Guinean Muslims at 
the <ORGANIZATION>Jame' Mosque</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Conakry</LOCATION> where he called for expansion of 
bilateral ties in all grounds. 
  Waving the flags of the Islamic Republic of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and 
carrying 
pictures of the father of the Islamic revolution, the late <PERSON>Imam 
Khomeyni</PERSON>, and the present leader of the Islamic Republic of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> 
'<PERSON>Ali Khamene'i</PERSON>, Guinean Muslims in <LOCATION>Conakry</LOCATION> warmly welcomed the 
Iranian delegation. 
  Velayati is to visit <PERSON>Burkina Faso</PERSON> on the second leg of his 
six-nation tour of African states which will also take him to 
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Uganda</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA020589-0047 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 14352 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 5, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 24; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
515 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
EMPEROR OF THE MOSSI TRIBE; 
</P>
<P>
IN BURKINA FASO, MOGHO NABA LIVES ON 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JEAN-LOUP FIEVET, Reuters 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
OUAGADOUGOU, Burkina Faso 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Every <DATE>Friday</DATE> at dawn, a crowd gathers outside a dilapidated palace here in 
<LOCATION>Burkina Faso</LOCATION>'s capital to attend a ritual faithfully repeated for centuries. 
</P>
<P>
The ceremony involves traditional chiefs bearing the title of "Ministers," a 
lavishly-bedecked stallion and a mighty monarch called the <PERSON>Mogho Naba</PERSON>, or 
emperor of the Mossi tribe. 
</P>
<P>
His great influence over local chieftains has survived French colonial rule and 
even the revolution initiated since <DATE>1983</DATE> by left-wing soldiers in this West 
African state. 
</P>
<P>
The Mossi, <ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>'s majority tribe, built one of the oldest and most 
prestigious kingdoms of <LOCATION>West Africa</LOCATION>, dating back to the <ORGANIZATION>12th Century</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The ritual derives from an old legend that each week the emperor asks for a 
horse to be prepared to fetch his favorite wife who has gone up-country to 
visit her father. 
</P>
<P>
The brief ceremony, which allows a rare sight of the <ORGANIZATION>Mogho Naba</ORGANIZATION>, flanked by 
pages and young girls, ends when the saddled horse is taken back inside the 
walled compound, banned to visitors. 
</P>
<P>
Nobles wearing richly embroidered caps, court drummers and minstrels seated in 
the dust at a respectful distance from the scarlet-robed <PERSON>Mogho Naba</PERSON> burst into 
applause when two shots are fired from a musket. 
</P>
<P>
The emperor, revered as "the Rising Sun" by the Mossi people, is assisted by a 
court made up of <PERSON>Naba</PERSON> (chiefs, in the More language). They include the <PERSON>Gouaga 
Naba</PERSON>, head of the imperial infantry, and the <PERSON>Kamsogho Naba</PERSON>, the chief eunuch in 
charge of the harem. 
</P>
<P>
So-called ministers in flowing robes -- traders, dentists or teachers in 
private life -- arrive at the <DATE>Friday</DATE> ceremony in battered cars, on mopeds or 
even bicycles to pay allegiance to the <PERSON>Mogho Naba</PERSON>, a burly man in his early 30s 
and the 37th emperor of the Mossi. 
</P>
<P>
Regarded as a semi-god by his people, he cannot be addressed directly and 
speaks through the <PERSON>Widi Naba</PERSON> (literally the commander of the imperial cavalry) 
and his de facto prime minister. 
</P>
<P>
Mossi warriors fought French army columns with spears and poisoned arrows until 
the then-Mogho <PERSON>Naba</PERSON> fled into exile into neighboring <LOCATION>Ghana</LOCATION> in <DATE>1897</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
But his successors retained considerable influence over peasants, who make up 
<PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of the population. 
</P>
<P>
Relations between the chieftaincy and the government of independent <ORGANIZATION>Burkina 
Faso</ORGANIZATION>, formerly <LOCATION>Upper Volta</LOCATION>, deteriorated sharply after radical president <PERSON>Thomas 
Sankara</PERSON> came to power in <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
He tried to break the powers of elders and chiefs, regarded by him as feudal 
lords keeping the peasants in slavery. He antagonized them by giving extensive 
power to grass-roots militia. 
</P>
<P>
The government also stopped paying part of the <PERSON>Mogho Naba</PERSON>'s expenses. 
</P>
<P>
Sankara was slain in <DATE>October, 1987</DATE>, by fellow officers. "The late president 
humiliated the <PERSON>Mogho Naba</PERSON> and local chiefs by denying them all consideration. 
Today, his successors are trying with some success to win back their hearts," 
an Ouagadougou-based diplomat said. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Sankara</PERSON> waged an unnecessary battle against the traditional chiefs. One cannot 
make a revolution against them in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>," President <PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON> 
acknowledged in a recent interview. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-25353 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr032_e_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-032 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  16 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Timetable Under Discussion </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB1502165694 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1300 GMT 15 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1502165694 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The preparations for negotiations are currently in 
place at <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>, where delegations of the <ORGANIZATION>Niger Government</ORGANIZATION> 
and the Tuareg opposition have arrived for a technical meeting 
to fix a timetable for negotiations to end the Tuareg conflict 
in <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION>. The dispute has been going on for nearly three years 
now. Yesterday evening, the head of state received the two 
delegations separately. Each audience lasted about one hour. 
Today, the Burkinabe envoys are pursuing their discussions with 
the two delegations in order to establish a working program 
likely to bring everyone around the same table. Radio Burkina 
contacted the leaders of the two delegations who showed optimism 
about the effective takeoff of these trilateral consultations. 
  Kriska, of the <ORGANIZATION>Coordination of Armed Resistance</ORGANIZATION>, which 
includes all the Tuareg movements, says this slowdown is caused 
by technical problems. A few modifications need to be made, 
however that these are not necessarily preconditions. As for 
the head of the government delegation, <PERSON>Abdourahamane Hama</PERSON>, who 
is <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION>'s foreign affairs and cooperation minister, the 
consultations remain informal because this enables them to 
proceed prudently. Both claim that a joint meeting is probable 
either this evening or tomorrow morning. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-43987 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr015_e_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-015 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   New Political Umbrella Group Formed </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB2301225394 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1900 GMT 23 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB2301225394 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The political landscape has changed since yesterday 
with the formation of the Convention of the <ORGANIZATION>Forces of Progress</ORGANIZATION> 
[<ORGANIZATION>Convention des Forces</ORGANIZATION> du Progres], which brings together the 
<ORGANIZATION>Group of Democrats</ORGANIZATION> and Patriots, the <ORGANIZATION>Union of Social Democrats</ORGANIZATION>, 
the Movement of Progressive Democrats, the <ORGANIZATION>Union of Democrats</ORGANIZATION> 
and Patriots of <LOCATION>Burkina</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Alliance for Progress</ORGANIZATION> and Freedom, 
the <ORGANIZATION>Popular Movement for Freedom and Development</ORGANIZATION>, UDPM 
[expansion unknown], MDS [expansion unknown], the <ORGANIZATION>League for 
Progress and Development</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Workers Party</ORGANIZATION>. 
It aims to contribute to the setting of major guidelines for 
national policy and ensuring the success of the program of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Broad Rally for Development</ORGANIZATION> and Democracy. It also plans to 
promote consultations and solidarity among member parties, to 
reinforce democracy for the construction of a state of law and 
the development and consolidation of the alliance of progressive 
forces. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-25443 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr034_e_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-034 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  18 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Niger </F>
<H3> <TI>   First Round of Niger Government-Tuareg Talks Ends </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB1802065094 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1900 GMT 17 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1802065094 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>



<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> French </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpts] The first phase of talks between the <ORGANIZATION>Niger 
Government</ORGANIZATION> and Tuareg delegations ended <TIME>this afternoon</TIME>. [passage 
omitted] 
  The chairman of the talks said the next meeting will be held 
in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> by the end of <DATE>March</DATE>. The negotiations on all aspects 
of the dispute will be carried under the joint mediation of 
<ORGANIZATION>Burkina Faso</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Ismael Diallo</PERSON>, special 
adviser to the president of the Republic, reads the communique: 
  [Begin Diallo recording] The Government of <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> and the 
coordinating committee of the armed resistance promised to do 
all they can to find a negotiated and lasting solution, in the 
interest of the people of <LOCATION>Niger</LOCATION> and of stability and peace in 
the subregion. The coordinating committee of the armed 
resistance handed over to the participants at the meeting its 
policy statement. [end recording] [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-1069 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr053_e_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-053 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  17 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Further on Political Upheavals </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  AB1703192394 London BBC World Service in English 1705 GMT 17 
Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1703192394 </F>
<F P=104>  London BBC World Service </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "Focus on Africa" program] </F>
  [Text] There have been some political upheavals in <LOCATION>Burkina 
Faso</LOCATION>. The country's leader, Captain <PERSON>Blaise Compaore</PERSON>, has 
dissolved the government and the prime minister, <PERSON>Youssouf 
Ouedraogo</PERSON>, has resigned. The prime minister has been on the job 
since <DATE>June 1992</DATE>, but it seems he might have been giving jobs to 
people that ruling party militants did not approve of. On the 
line to <LOCATION>Ouagadougou</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dan Isaacs</PERSON> asked our correspondent, <PERSON>Pierre 
Kazoni</PERSON>, if any reasons have been given for the prime minister's 
resignation: 
  [Begin recording] [Kazoni] Well, no official reasons have 
been given, but according to the general public it is said that 
the pressure put on him to resign came from the militants of the 
majority party, the ODP-MT [Organization for Popular 
Democracy-Labor Movement], which is also President <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON>'s 
party. He is also accused of not being [word indistinct] with 
conviction, and that he does not appoint the militants of the 
ODP to top positions. Well, these are the unofficial reasons, 
according to the people here, that have motivated his 
resignation. 
  [<PERSON>Isaacs</PERSON>] So is it simply that the prime minister has been 
appointing ministers who are not from the majority party, the 
ODP- MT, he has been giving posts to other people? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Kazoni</ORGANIZATION>] Yes. I think the ODP-MT, which is the majority 
party, they want everything for themselves. It was said clearly 
during the <ORGANIZATION>National Assembly</ORGANIZATION>, in the <ORGANIZATION>National Assembly</ORGANIZATION>'s session 
here that the majority in the government should rule and those 
who are not in the government should oppose. This was said 
clearly by a member of parliament who is a militant of the 
ODP-MT. But this is not the vision that <PERSON>Youssouf Ouedraogo</PERSON> has. 
He is a technocrat and he believes in the right man on the 
right job. 
  [<PERSON>Isaacs</PERSON>] From what you are saying the prime minister, <PERSON>Mr. 
Ouedraogo</PERSON>, sounds less like a technocrat and more like somebody 
who really is his own man and wanted good men in good positions. 
Was he a popular prime minister? 
  [Kazoni] You may say that he was popular in a sense, in a 
sense that he achieved something during his during his term of 
office, and the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> have openly declared 
their satisfaction with the way <PERSON>Mr. Ouedraogo</PERSON> handles the <ORGANIZATION>SAP</ORGANIZATION>, 
the Structural Adjustment Program. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Isaacs</ORGANIZATION>] So will the new government, when it has been 
announced, be totally dominated by dominated by the majority 
party, the ODP-MT? Is that what we can look forward to now? 
  [Kazoni] Very much, because since it is the outcry of the 
majority. I think <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> may probably listen to them. But it 
does not really rule out completely that <PERSON>Compaore</PERSON> will put in 
somebody who is not probably a member of the majority party. 
This is possible. We can always expect something like that. 
[end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-48205 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr094_e_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-094 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> WEST AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Burkina Faso </F>
<H3> <TI>   Commercial Cooperation Accord Signed With Ghana </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Commercial Cooperation Accord Signed With Ghana </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AB1505145694 Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio in French 1900 GMT 13 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> AB1505145694 </F>
<F P=104>  Ouagadougou Radiodiffusion Nationale du Burkina 
Radio </F>

<F P=105>  French </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Excerpt] The <LOCATION>Ghana</LOCATION> Exports Promotion Council [GEPC] and 
the <ORGANIZATION>Burkinabe National External Trade Board</ORGANIZATION> [ONCEB] have signed 
a draft cooperation agreement. From now on, the institutional 
relations between the ONCEB and the GEPC will be governed by the 
terms of this draft agreement according to which the two 
countries have agreed to consult each other at least once a year 
to establish and strengthen increased trade contacts between 
them and to facilitate the participation of their businessmen in 
trade fairs, exhibitions, and all other commercial activities 
organized in each of the two countries. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-37227 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes118_d_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-118 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  17 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Libya </F>
<H3> <TI>   Visit by Presidents of Mali, Niger, Burkina Faso </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Visit by Presidents of Mali, Niger, Burkina Faso </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Burkinabe, Niger Presidents Leave </H4>

<F P=102> LD1706154994 Tripoli Great Jamahiriyah Radio Network in 
Arabic 1230 GMT 17 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD1706154994 </F>
<F P=104>  Tripoli Great Jamahiriyah Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Arabic </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Excerpts] President <PERSON>Blaise Campaore</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Burkina 
Faso</ORGANIZATION>, and the accompanying delegation left <LOCATION>Tripoli</LOCATION> <TIME>this morning</TIME> 
at the end of a visit to the <ORGANIZATION>Great Jamahiriyah</ORGANIZATION>. [passage 
omitted] 
  President <PERSON>Mahamane Ousmane</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Republic of 
Niger</ORGANIZATION>, and the accompanying delegation also left <LOCATION>Tripoli</LOCATION> at noon 
today at the end of a visit to the <ORGANIZATION>Great Jamahiriyah</ORGANIZATION>. [passage 
omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-4900 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas066_c_94020" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-066 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  1 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> North Korea </F>
<H3> <TI>   Kang Song-san Hails Burkina Faso Premier </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Kang Song-san Hails Burkina Faso Premier </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   SK0104110794 Pyongyang KCNA in English 1014 GMT 1 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> SK0104110794 </F>
<F P=104>  Pyongyang KCNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 
