<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901003-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-03-90 2350EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BaseballBeginnings     10-03 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baseball Beginnings,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pre-Doubleday, Pre-Cartwright Account of Baseball Game Found</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Baseball historians were thrown a curve
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with a newspaper report that <PERSON>Alexander Cartwright</PERSON>
possibly wasn't the inventor of their game.
   The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> said that a newly discovered newspaper report
and box score show that other teams were already playing baseball
in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> a year earlier than when <PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON> supposedly
invented the game in <DATE>1846</DATE>.
   The story also reported that baseball probably evolved from a
number of enthusiasts in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in the mid-1840s, rather than
springing fully formed from the imagination of anyone in
particular.
   According to the <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION>, which published the story in its
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> editions, the discovery was made by <PERSON>Edward L. Widmer</PERSON>, a
<ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> graduate student who was doing research for his doctoral
dissertation at the <ORGANIZATION>New York Historical Society</ORGANIZATION>.
   In a copy of <ORGANIZATION>The New York Morning News</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Widmer</PERSON> reportedly found
an account of a game on <DATE>Oct. 21, 1845</DATE>, between the ``<LOCATION>New York Ball
Club</LOCATION> and a team from <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>.'' Like the <DATE>1846</DATE> game credited by
historians as the first, the earlier game was played at the <ORGANIZATION>Elysian
Fields</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, then a bucolic area easily reachable from
<LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> by ferry.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Morning News</ORGANIZATION> said that <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> won 24-4, aided by a grand
slam, or in the vocabulary of the time, ``four aces'' off a single
hit.
   ``At the conclusion of the match, both parties sat down to a
dinner ...'', the newspaper reported, reflecting baseball's origins
as a social event between gentlemen.
   The account of the <DATE>Oct. 21, 1845</DATE> game in <ORGANIZATION>The New York Morning
News</ORGANIZATION> indicates that the popularity of baseball was spreading
rapidly at the time. ``Two more Base clubs are already formed in
our sister city,'' <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>, the story related.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Morning News</ORGANIZATION> did not say which rules were used, an important
question to specialists.
   In popular myth, baseball was invented in <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Abner
Doubleday</ORGANIZATION>. Historians seeking the true progenitor have instead
credited <PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> bank clerk, who is said to have
drawn up the rules and organized the first game in <DATE>1846</DATE> for the
<ORGANIZATION>Knickerbocker Base Ball Club</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Elysian Fields</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901004-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-04-90 0726EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BaseballBeginnings 1stLd-Writethru a049 10-04 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Baseball Beginnings, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0496,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Clues Surface in Search for Origin of Baseball</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, `Abner Doubleday's ...' to CORRECT Cooperstown,
Ohio, to Cooperstown, N.Y. Version also moving on sports circuits.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> graduate student combing archives
uncovered new clues in the search for the origin of baseball in an
<DATE>1845</DATE> newspaper sports story and box score.
   Abner Doubleday's ``invention'' of baseball in a <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, cow pasture has been debunked as a popular myth. The city of
<LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, then claimed the first game was played there in
<DATE>1846</DATE>.
   The story and primitive box score appeared in a copy of <ORGANIZATION>The New
York Morning News</ORGANIZATION> and recount a game played <DATE>Oct. 21, 1845</DATE>, between
the ``<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Ball club'' and a team from <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>, The <ORGANIZATION>New York
Times</ORGANIZATION> reported today.
   The find by <PERSON>Edward L. Widmer</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> doctoral candidate
researching his dissertation at the <ORGANIZATION>New York Historical Society</ORGANIZATION>,
indicates baseball had been in existence for some time when the
story was written.
   The newspaper account began: ``A friendly match of the
time-honored game of Base was played yesterday ...''
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> won 24-4, aided by a grand slam, or in the vocabulary
of the time, ``four aces'' off a single hit.
   The newspaper account went on to say two new <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> teams had
formed recently.
   After it was proved that <PERSON>Doubleday</PERSON> did not create baseball,
historians credited <PERSON>Alexander Cartwright</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> bank clerk
said to have drawn up the rules and organized the first game in
<DATE>1846</DATE> for the Knickerbocker ``Base Ball Club'' at the <ORGANIZATION>Elysian Fields</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION>.
   The game reported in the <ORGANIZATION>Morning News</ORGANIZATION> also was played at <ORGANIZATION>Elysian
Fields</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Widmer</PERSON> found another clipping recounting a rematch <DATE>Oct.
24, 1845</DATE>, that was played in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>.
   The find indicates that ``<LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> is the cradle of
baseball,'' said <PERSON>David Q. Voigt</PERSON>, a baseball historian and professor
at <ORGANIZATION>Albright College</ORGANIZATION> in Reading, <LOCATION>Pa</LOCATION>.
   ``Baseball was a city game, not a rural or farm game,'' he said,
adding that the find supports his theory that baseball developed in
stages.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900111-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-90 0603EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     01-11 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0754</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOBOKEN, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor <PERSON>Patrick Pasculli</PERSON> says <ORGANIZATION>New Yorkers</ORGANIZATION> who
claim the <ORGANIZATION>Empire State</ORGANIZATION> is the birthplace of baseball are way off
base.
   Pasculli announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the formation of <ORGANIZATION>American Baseball
Heritage Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a non-profit organization formed to pitch this
mile-square city as baseball's home and lobby nationally for
``Baseball Day,'' to be celebrated annually <DATE>June 19</DATE>. Hoboken will
create a museum to chronicle the contributions of <PERSON>Alexander J.
Cartwright</PERSON>.
   Pasculli said the first game of baseball was played on <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION>'s
Elysian Fields during the afternoon of <DATE>June 19, 1846</DATE>. He credits
<PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON> _ a surveyor, amateur athlete and inventor _ with
refining the game.
   ``Once and for all we're going to destroy the fabrication that
<PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON> invented the game, and that <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, was
its birthplace,'' <PERSON>Paculli</PERSON> told a news conference.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON>, however, disagrees.
   Cuomo signed a bill in <DATE>April</DATE> that will allow New Yorkers to
order license plates donning the picture of a ball and the words,
``Birthplace of Baseball.''
   <PERSON>Stephen Speiser</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION> group, thinks <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON>'s
out in left field.
   The game really evolved from the British games of cricket and
rounders, <PERSON>Speiser</PERSON> said. Cartwright refined it, wrote down the
rules, and umpired the first game, he said.
   League historians at the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> agree that
<PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON> played an important role early in the game. But they say
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> has a better claim than <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, by at least a year, of
fielding the first match.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor <PERSON>Patrick Pasculli</PERSON> says <ORGANIZATION>New Yorkers</ORGANIZATION> who
claim the <ORGANIZATION>Empire State</ORGANIZATION> is the birthplace of baseball are way off
base.
   Pasculli announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the formation of <ORGANIZATION>American Baseball
Heritage Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a non-profit organization formed to pitch this
mile-square city as baseball's home and lobby nationally for
``Baseball Day,'' to be celebrated annually <DATE>June 19</DATE>. Hoboken will
create a museum to chronicle the contributions of <PERSON>Alexander J.
Cartwright</PERSON>.
   Pasculli said the first game of baseball was played on <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION>'s
Elysian Fields during the afternoon of <DATE>June 19, 1846</DATE>. He credits
<PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON> _ a surveyor, amateur athlete and inventor _ with
refining the game.
   ``Once and for all we're going to destroy the fabrication that
<PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON> invented the game, and that <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, was
its birthplace,'' <PERSON>Paculli</PERSON> told a news conference.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON>, however, disagrees.
   Cuomo signed a bill in <DATE>April</DATE> that will allow New Yorkers to
order license plates donning the picture of a ball and the words,
``Birthplace of Baseball.''
   <PERSON>Stephen Speiser</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION> group, thinks <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON>'s
out in left field.
   The game really evolved from the British games of cricket and
rounders, <PERSON>Speiser</PERSON> said. Cartwright refined it, wrote down the
rules, and umpired the first game, he said.
   League historians at the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> agree that
<PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON> played an important role early in the game. But they say
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> has a better claim than <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, by at least a year, of
fielding the first match.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MIAMI BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor <PERSON>Patrick Pasculli</PERSON> says <ORGANIZATION>New Yorkers</ORGANIZATION> who
claim the <ORGANIZATION>Empire State</ORGANIZATION> is the birthplace of baseball are way off
base.
   Pasculli announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the formation of <ORGANIZATION>American Baseball
Heritage Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a non-profit organization formed to pitch this
mile-square city as baseball's home and lobby nationally for
``Baseball Day,'' to be celebrated annually <DATE>June 19</DATE>. Hoboken will
create a museum to chronicle the contributions of <PERSON>Alexander J.
Cartwright</PERSON>.
   Pasculli said the first game of baseball was played on <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION>'s
Elysian Fields during the afternoon of <DATE>June 19, 1846</DATE>. He credits
<PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON> _ a surveyor, amateur athlete and inventor _ with
refining the game.
   ``Once and for all we're going to destroy the fabrication that
<PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON> invented the game, and that <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, was
its birthplace,'' <PERSON>Paculli</PERSON> told a news conference.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON>, however, disagrees.
   Cuomo signed a bill in <DATE>April</DATE> that will allow New Yorkers to
order license plates donning the picture of a ball and the words,
``Birthplace of Baseball.''
   <PERSON>Stephen Speiser</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION> group, thinks <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON>'s
out in left field.
   The game really evolved from the British games of cricket and
rounders, <PERSON>Speiser</PERSON> said. Cartwright refined it, wrote down the
rules, and umpired the first game, he said.
   League historians at the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> agree that
<PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON> played an important role early in the game. But they say
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> has a better claim than <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, by at least a year, of
fielding the first match.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor <PERSON>Patrick Pasculli</PERSON> says <ORGANIZATION>New Yorkers</ORGANIZATION> who
claim the <ORGANIZATION>Empire State</ORGANIZATION> is the birthplace of baseball are way off
base.
   Pasculli announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the formation of <ORGANIZATION>American Baseball
Heritage Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a non-profit organization formed to pitch this
mile-square city as baseball's home and lobby nationally for
``Baseball Day,'' to be celebrated annually <DATE>June 19</DATE>. Hoboken will
create a museum to chronicle the contributions of <PERSON>Alexander J.
Cartwright</PERSON>.
   Pasculli said the first game of baseball was played on <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION>'s
Elysian Fields during the afternoon of <DATE>June 19, 1846</DATE>. He credits
<PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON> _ a surveyor, amateur athlete and inventor _ with
refining the game.
   ``Once and for all we're going to destroy the fabrication that
<PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON> invented the game, and that <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, was
its birthplace,'' <PERSON>Paculli</PERSON> told a news conference.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON>, however, disagrees.
   Cuomo signed a bill in <DATE>April</DATE> that will allow New Yorkers to
order license plates donning the picture of a ball and the words,
``Birthplace of Baseball.''
   <PERSON>Stephen Speiser</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION> group, thinks <PERSON>Cuomo</PERSON>'s
out in left field.
   The game really evolved from the British games of cricket and
rounders, <PERSON>Speiser</PERSON> said. Cartwright refined it, wrote down the
rules, and umpired the first game, he said.
   League historians at the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> agree that
<PERSON>Cartwright</PERSON> played an important role early in the game. But they say
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> has a better claim than <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, by at least a year, of
fielding the first match.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900326-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-26-90 1331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-BaseballDebate Bjt   03-26 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baseball Debate, Bjt,0573</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanians Claim Oina Inspired Baseball</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROB GLOSTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Sports Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fans across <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> might eagerly be
awaiting the start of the oina season if an American here had not
changed a few rules and renamed it baseball, according to a
Romanian sports official.
   Adding his voice to the decades-old debate over the origin of
baseball, <PERSON>Cristian Costescu</PERSON> said the American pastime derived from
the ancient game of oina, which was introduced to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
by a pair of Transylvanians.
   Costescu, president of the new <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Baseball Federation</ORGANIZATION>,
says the two immigrants from the Romanian village of <LOCATION>Alba Iulia</LOCATION>
joined the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> and taught the game to their comrades.
   Among their comrades was a young officer named <PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON>,
who changed a few rules and created baseball in <DATE>1839</DATE>, <PERSON>Cotescu</PERSON> said
in an interview.
   ``We are not saying that <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> invented baseball. We would not
like someone else to tell us oina was invented by others,'' said
<PERSON>Costescu</PERSON>. ``But we are saying this: some little inspiration for
baseball was from oina. Baseball is more sophisticated than oina,
but the structure is the same.''
   Romanians claim oina was invented by shepherds in the <DATE>first
century</DATE> and say documents from <DATE>1310</DATE> describe a variation of the
game called hoina being played in southern <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>.
   Oina has 11 men per side, with one team batting and the other in
the field. Each side is allowed one at-bat, in which all 11 players
take the plate.
   A pitcher is provided by the team at bat and he serves up a lazy
underhand toss. The batter tries to hit the ball as far as
possible, then has to run 120 yards through nine bases.
   But if the batter is tagged by a fielder or hit by a thrown
ball, the fielders can score points _ so teams can score even while
not at bat.
   Oina uses a ball almost the same size as a baseball but filled
with horse hair. The bat is similar to a cricket bat and fielders
do not wear gloves.
   Oina still is a Romanian national sport, with forms of the game
being played in various regions of the Balkan country. Though there
are 1,675 teams around <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, as opposed to about 15 baseball
teams in the country, its popularity has slumped in recent years.
   ``Fifty years ago everybody was playing oina, all the high
schools and elementary schools,'' <PERSON>Costescu</PERSON> said through a
translator. ``But handball, basketball and volleyball appeared and
oina started disappearing.''
   It has been a quarter-century since the heyday of <PERSON>Eugen Cocut</PERSON>,
the Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> of oina whose height and huge hands allowed him to
hit powerful shots and fire the ball with terrifying speed.
   If <PERSON>Costescu</PERSON> is successful in his post with the 2-month-old
baseball federation, he may assure that the next Cocut plays
baseball instead of oina.
   Costescu used to head the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Oina Federation</ORGANIZATION>, back in the
days when baseball was banned as ``a capitalist sport.''
   That stigma was removed after the <DATE>December</DATE> revolution that
overthrew dictator <PERSON>Nicolae Ceausescu</PERSON>, and the baseball federation
was formed.
   ``Baseball will be more popular than oina in cities, but in the
villages oina will remain,'' <PERSON>Costescu</PERSON> said. ``Even though I am the
head of the baseball federation now, oina is always in my heart.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA080590-0188 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 257613 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 5, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 3; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1684 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HALL OF FAME CAN'T ANSWER BASEBALL'S BIG QUESTION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARK HYMAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
COOPERSTOWN, N.Y. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
that real fans don't take lunch breaks. 
</P>
<P>
About half-past noon, the main exhibit hall on the museum's first floor is 
teeming with activity. For one day, visitors are taking their nourishment from 
bats, balls and the other 6,000 items that tell a remarkable story. 
</P>
<P>
A young couple and their two children are watching a TV monitor, and being 
thoroughly entertained by <PERSON>Abbott</PERSON> and <PERSON>Costello</PERSON>'s hilarious "Who's On First?" 
comedy routine. A few steps away, visitors are clustered around "The Three 
Umpires," <PERSON>Norman Rockwell</PERSON>'s classic painting of the stone-faced arbiters braced 
against some industrial-strength rain drops. Hanging in a place of prominence 
are 6- to 7-foot-long banners emblazoned with the photographs of <PERSON>Jim Palmer</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Joe Morgan</PERSON>, the 205th and 206th inductees into baseball hallowed Hall. 
</P>
<P>
It's baseball as you've probably never experienced it. Baseball in <LOCATION>Sensurround</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1990</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> and Museum is an impressive repository of baseball 
history, not to mention a mighty tourist attraction. When it opened for 
business in <DATE>1939</DATE>, the museum welcomed more than 25,000 visitors, and, as 
recently as <DATE>1984</DATE>, yearly attendance hovered just above 200,000. But <DATE>several 
years ago</DATE>, the explosion in baseball's popularity finally reached this remote 
country outpost in <LOCATION>upstate New York</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1989</DATE>, visitors to the Hall topped 
410,000, with the majority coming during the peak months of <DATE>June</DATE>, <DATE>July</DATE> and 
<DATE>August</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
They might have come to see the jersey worn by <PERSON>Orel Hershiser</PERSON> in the fifth game 
of the <DATE>1988</DATE> World Series, <PERSON>Bo Jackson</PERSON>'s cap from the <DATE>1989</DATE> All-Star Game or 
<PERSON>Mickey Mantle</PERSON>'s Yankee Stadium locker. They're all here. 
</P>
<P>
Or maybe they made the pilgrimage hoping to pick up a handy fact or two about 
the game. Like the young boy in a <ORGANIZATION>Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> cap who stood in front of a display 
case that held items belonging to the dynastic Yankees of the <DATE>1940s</DATE>, '50s and 
'60s. Among the treasures was a fielder's glove and a pair of spikes used by 
<PERSON>Phil Rizzuto</PERSON>, the famous shortstop turned TV pitchman. 
</P>
<P>
As he stood beside the window, the boy made a startling discovery. Then, in a 
tone of utter astonishment, he asked his dad, "You mean the guy from The Money 
Store ... was a baseball player?" 
</P>
<P>
Yes, the museum is full of surprises. 
</P>
<P>
It's also an excellent place to go in search of baseball's origins and secrets, 
the trouble being that most of the deepest secrets have to do with who gave us 
baseball in the first place and, most important, where. There is no shortage of 
theories on this point. Ask the citizens of <LOCATION>Hoboken</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, who recently 
proclaimed their town "The real birthplace of baseball," and hired a 
public-relations firm to convince the rest of us. But if you're interested in 
making friends during your visit to <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, only one answer will do. 
</P>
<P>
The historians pretty much agree now that there isn't a baseball birthplace and 
that there almost certainly wasn't a first baseball game. Instead, baseball 
probably evolved slowly during the <DATE>1830s</DATE> and <DATE>'40s</DATE> from a game known as 
"Townball" that was played in any number of cow pastures where men gathered 
with their bare hands and handlebar mustaches. 
</P>
<P>
No matter. <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> has been recognized as the cradle of baseball since the 
early <DATE>1900s</DATE>, when <PERSON>A.G. Spalding</PERSON>, the sporting-goods manufacturer, suggested a 
commission be appointed to resolve the question of baseball's birth once and 
for all. In <DATE>1907</DATE>, the seven-member panel announced its decision, which was that 
the first game was played here and that it had been created in largest part by 
one <PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON>, a Civil War hero and a career military officer. 
</P>
<P>
The commission considered lengthy testimony from a number of sources, but its 
conclusion was based largely on the recollections of a man named <ORGANIZATION>Abner Graves</ORGANIZATION>, 
an elderly mining engineer, who reported that baseball had been "invented" by 
<DATE>Doubleday</DATE> between <DATE>1839</DATE> and <DATE>1841</DATE>. Doubleday wasn't in a position to either 
confirm or deny this; he'd died in <DATE>1893</DATE> in <LOCATION>Mendham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
In reporting its findings, the commission outlined its reasons for finding that 
<LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> was the birthplace of baseball, and praised its star witness, 
referring to Graves as a "reputable gentleman." But years later, there's more 
reason than ever to challenge both conclusions. Among them: About 20 of 
<ORGANIZATION>Doubleday</ORGANIZATION>'s journals survive, but none mentions baseball; Graves was 5 and 
<DATE>Doubleday 20</DATE> when the former claimed the two were classmates; in his final 
years, Graves was judged criminally insane after he shot and killed his wife. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Baseball Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> and Museum doesn't answer the question of baseball 
origins any more convincingly than Graves did. But there are fascinating 
exhibits that speak to the game's earliest chapters. In the <ORGANIZATION>Cooperstown Room</ORGANIZATION>, 
on the museum's ground floor, is a glass case containing the museum's first 
acquisition -- a brown, bruised, crudely shaped baseball literally bursting out 
of its seams. <PERSON>Steven C. Clark Sr.</PERSON>, one of <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>'s richest and most 
civic-minded citizens, bought the ball for <MONEY>$5</MONEY> from another local who claimed it 
was one of those used by <DATE>Doubleday</DATE> and the boys. Ball in hand, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> began 
pitching the idea of a baseball museum to a skeptical baseball Commissioner 
<PERSON>Kenesaw Mountain Landis</PERSON>, who began to see the genius of the idea only when 
<PERSON>Clark</PERSON> offered to pay for it. 
</P>
<P>
Under the heading of relics, there's a gem in the display that traces the 
evolution of baseball equipment. It's the original catcher's mask, invented in 
<DATE>1876</DATE> by the captain of the <ORGANIZATION>Harvard College</ORGANIZATION> baseball team. While it won't win 
any beauty contests, the mask is a first, and firsts are a rare thing even in 
this building. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Peter Clark</PERSON>, the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame's registrar, considers this one of the museum's 
most precious possessions because "it's one of the few things in the collection 
that you actually can point to as the first, the start of all catcher's masks." 
He pauses to consider the enormity of it. "It's almost like seeing the first 
baseball," <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> said. "If such a thing existed, can you imagine how 
overwhelming that would be?" 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Clark</PERSON> is one of the museum executives who shoulder the heavy responsibility of 
deciding what new items should be added to the collection. The group, which 
also includes the museum's librarian and curator, meets each <DATE>Friday</DATE> to discuss 
letters and calls that have come in with offers of everything from <LOCATION>Babe Ruth</LOCATION> 
autographed baseballs to a <DATE>1925</DATE> Hudson automobile whose owner claimed it 
belonged to <PERSON>Ty Cobb</PERSON>. Most offers (the museum does not purchase items) are 
politely turned down on the grounds that the museum already is well-stocked in 
that area. Balls signed by <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> are particularly plentiful -- <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> estimated 
the museums owns 50 to 60 balls with his signature -- and more are offered 
almost every week. "There's so many out there, it kind of makes you wonder how 
he had time to play baseball," <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The museum accepted 373 items last year, including 15 autographed baseballs, 
four uniforms and five items that fall under the heading of "books and 
publications." Among those gifts was a letter to <PERSON>Jackie Robinson</PERSON> from <PERSON>Sen. John 
F. Kennedy</PERSON> dated <DATE>July 1, 1960</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Items high on the museum's wish list are old uniforms, especially if they date 
back to the <DATE>19th century</DATE>. "If we could come up with something going back to the 
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> Red Stockings period, that would be a real coup," <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> said. That's 
not as much of a long shot as it may sound. Three years ago, a man from <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> 
phoned the museum with an offer of six <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> Cubs uniforms from <DATE>1909</DATE>, 
including one that had belonged to <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Famer Frank Chance</ORGANIZATION>. The man's 
grandfather had been a florist in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, and the players, many of whom were 
customers, presented them as gifts. 
</P>
<P>
The museum's executives use a rigorous system of checks and double checks to 
satisfy themselves that all the items they accept are the real thing. First, 
they examine the items closely. After you've seen <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s signature a couple 
hundred times, it's not too difficult to spot a phony. When it becomes 
necessary, they also quiz the donors to determine things like where they 
obtained the item and from whom. If they don't get the right answers, the gift 
isn't accepted. That's what happened with the <ORGANIZATION>Cobb</ORGANIZATION> car. 
</P>
<P>
Sometimes the matter of authenticity is trickier than others. On the first 
floor, in the east wing, most of one wall is given over to a display of 
baseballs from no-hit games dating back to <PERSON>Bob Feller</PERSON>'s no-no (<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 1, 
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 0) on <DATE>April 16, 1940</DATE>. Most of the balls are autographed, and on some 
the winning pitcher also has scrawled the final score and date. 
</P>
<P>
The problems come in determining just what balls you are looking at. <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> says 
the museum tries to get the last ball used in the game because "there's 
something about the last pitched ball that people will ooh and aah about." But 
it isn't always successful in doing that, according to a random poll of two 
no-hit pitchers who live in the <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> area. The museum has the ball used to 
record the last out of <ORGANIZATION>Rex Barney</ORGANIZATION>'s no-hitter. The <ORGANIZATION>Baltimore Orioles</ORGANIZATION> 
public-address announcer, who pitched for the <ORGANIZATION>Brooklyn Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1940s</DATE>, 
vividly recalls being asked to autograph the ball for display at <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jim Palmer</PERSON>, on the other hand, says the only place his no-hit ball is on 
display is in his garage -- it's in a plastic bag, along with a baseball from 
his <DATE>1966</DATE> World Series victory over <PERSON>Sandy Koufax</PERSON>. The most likely explanation is 
that the museum received a ball -- but not THE ball -- from his big game. 
</P>
<P>
There are no doubts about what you are seeing in a special room on the first 
floor, the one with the cathedral ceiling and the bronze faces on the walls. 
The Hall of Fame gallery is quieter than most places in the museum. It's the 
kind of place that makes people think about removing their hats, or maybe 
taking off their shoes. Something about being in the company of Ruth's plaque 
-- or the plaques of <PERSON>Walter</PERSON> "Big Train" <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> or, yes, <PERSON>Brooks Calbert 
Robinson Jr.</PERSON> -- has that effect on a baseball fan. 
</P>
<P>
This <DATE>weekend</DATE>, they'll add two more faces to the collection. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910408-0161
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910408-0161.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Imagine Romania,
   Of All Places, Having
   A Shortage of Bats
   ---
   Ceausescu Would Turn Over
   In His Grave If He Knew
   That Baseball Had Arrived
   ----
   By Roger Thurow
</HL>
<DATE>
04/08/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
</RE>
<LP>
   BUCHAREST -- As a new Major League Baseball season opens
with millionaire outfielders whining about their measly
wages, spare a cheer for a league so impoverished that the
batters have to wear their own motorcycle helmets to the
plate.
   "We would have liked to start our season in April or May,
but we don't have enough equipment yet. So maybe we will
start in June," says Cristian Costescu, the president of the
Romanian Baseball Federation. "Some teams have only one bat.
We need more balls. But our biggest disaster is gloves. Some
teams don't have a full set. It is very difficult to practice
when you have to share gloves."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   As <DATE>spring</DATE> comes to the <LOCATION>Balkans</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> is taking its
first swing at <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s national pastime. The league
president is a former national champion swordsman who has
never played an inning of baseball. Enough coaches have
signed up to form 29 teams around the country, but there are
only six proper fields. The amateur players are veterans of
"oina," the beloved sport of <LOCATION>Transylvania</LOCATION> that is played on a
rectangle instead of a diamond and bears as much resemblance
to baseball as <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth</ORGANIZATION> does to <LOCATION>Dracula</LOCATION>.
   But never mind all that. "What the Romanians lack in
equipment and expertise, they make up for in desire to play,"
says <PERSON>Allen Docal</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>American Information Center</ORGANIZATION> director in
<LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> and unofficial talent scout. "They know they aren't
<PERSON>Reggie Jackson</PERSON> and the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Yankees."
   They aren't even the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> Cubs. But at least it is a
start, which, given baseball's history here, is quite an
achievement.
   "We are orphans in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, too," says <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>,
comparing his fledgling league to the thousands of babies
abandoned during the Communists' reign, when both birth
control and baseball were officially banned. "As we start
with our baseball activity, you can put a big 0 on our
scoreboard."
   Pitching the shutout was that renowned spoilsport, <PERSON>Nicolae
Ceausescu</PERSON>, the Communist dictator who feared that if baseball
came to <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, capitalism would be sure to follow. For
various other reasons, he also banned Scrabble, bridge,
martial arts and field hockey.
   <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>, a stocky man with silver hair, lives, eats
and drinks baseball in a little office at the end of a dark
corridor on the seventh floor of the gloomy <ORGANIZATION>Ministry of
Sports</ORGANIZATION> building, where the elevator rarely works. A miniature
cardboard cutout of former <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mets Manager <PERSON>Davey
Johnson</PERSON> looks on from the bookshelf. A wooden ball sits on
the desk, like a paperweight. On the wall behind hangs a
banner from <ORGANIZATION>Topps</ORGANIZATION>, the American baseball-card maker. "Team
U.S.A. today, big leagues tomorrow," it says.
   Even though it is only 8 in the morning, <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>
offers an American visitor a glass of plum schnapps. "A
Romanian tradition," he explains. He proposes a toast to
baseball and settles into his chair.
   "I saw my first game in <DATE>1985</DATE>. It was in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>," he says,
beginning the saga of baseball in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>, then
the head of the oina federation, returned home with tales of
what he had witnessed, a baseball instructional video and a
rule book, all of which he shared with a couple of physical
education teachers. For the next two years, this group
covered the rudiments of the game, translating the rules into
Romanian, scouting potential fields and publishing some
articles in the local sports newspapers to whip up interest.
A few trial games were even played under the nose of the
security police, who figured it was a mutant strain of oina.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON> committed an error. He boldly
approached <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s sports officials with an application to
set up a baseball federation, which would have made the sport
eligible for government funding. He didn't get to first base.
   "They told me, `No, baseball is a capitalist sport and we
will never allow such propaganda for capitalism in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>,'
" recalls <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>. "You see, the government knew
baseball is a sport very much loved by American people. It
isn't a Soviet sport, but an American sport. And <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> is
the No. 1 capitalist country."
   The baseball advocates argued that the game is also the
national sport of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. They also pointed out that Romanians
play volleyball and basketball, two other American sports. To
no avail. "After that, we had to go underground," <PERSON>Mr.
Costescu</PERSON> says with a conspiratorial grin. Clandestinely, he
and the others continued to plan for the day when baseball
would be free. They drew up a mock schedule based on a
fantasy league. It was the longest off-season in history.
   Then, during <DATE>Christmas of 1989</DATE>, a popular revolution
overthrew the Communists and <PERSON>Mr. Ceausescu</PERSON> was executed. On
<DATE>Feb. 4, 1990</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Romanian Baseball Federation</ORGANIZATION> was born.
   Soon, <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>, with the sponsorship of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Information Agency</ORGANIZATION>, was off to <LOCATION>Williamsport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, home of
<ORGANIZATION>Little League Baseball</ORGANIZATION>, to watch and learn. Next stop was
<LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION> to visit the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Olympic baseball training
operation. Then it was on to <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> with 13 other Romanians
for a two-week coaching clinic. Back in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, practice
started for the first season. But the troubles weren't over.
   "You know the economic situation in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>
moans. "There isn't enough money for all the sports, so the
authorities give aid only to federations with good results.
They told us to find some sponsors, but the sponsors are only
interested in championship teams. It is a vicious circle.
Without sponsors there is no possibility to develop. Without
development, there are no sponsors." He has the desperate
sound of a man caught in an eternal rundown.
   Enter the Americans. <PERSON>Mr. Docal</PERSON>, who has been named
honorary president of the baseball federation, found some
equipment in the attic of the embassy. The <ORGANIZATION>International
Baseball Association</ORGANIZATION>, based in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, sent some bats and
balls. <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON> wrote letters to American
sports-equipment companies. One replied. It sent umpiring
gear.
   Still woefully short of the basics, <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON> is now
turning to the free market, just as the old dictator feared.
He has taken a bat to a Romanian wood carver and some gloves
to a Romanian shoemaker and has asked them to see what they
can do. He would like to work out a joint venture with an
American partner to make sports equipment in <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>.
   Why not just use oina equipment, he is asked. <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>
pours another glass of schnapps and proceeds to diagram an
oina game. "It is difficult to explain to a foreigner," he
cautions.
   The oina bat is thin and equally proportioned, like a
stickball bat. The ball is soft, stuffed with horse hair. No
one uses gloves. There are two teams of nine players, one at
bat, one lined up in three rows on a rectangular field. The
batter hits the ball, pitched by a member of his own team,
and proceeds to run between the rows of fielders. The
fielders try to hit the runner by throwing the ball at him.
If they do, they get two points. If they don't, the batter
gets two points. When all the batters are out, the teams
switch sides. They play one inning. Then the game is over.
   <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON> opens a filing cabinet and retrieves a stack
of papers that tell a curious story. It seems some military
officers from <LOCATION>Transylvania</LOCATION> emigrated to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> about 150
years ago. There, they put on an oina exhibition. Perhaps one
of the onlookers, so goes the Romanian tale, was <PERSON>Abner
Doubleday</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> officer who is traditionally credited
with inventing baseball.
   "Maybe oina had some influence on baseball. Who knows?"
says <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>. "We say oina is the Romanian national
sport, but we don't know who invented it. Some say it was
invented in the Turkish empire."
   Still, baseball has something oina doesn't. "From the
beginning I loved baseball because it has a moral quality,"
says <PERSON>Mr. Costescu</PERSON>. "Fair play is the fiber of baseball. It is
a game that can teach you many things."
   He gets misty-eyed as he talks about his favorite element
of baseball. "The sacrifice bunt," he proudly announces. "One
player sacrificing himself to help another. I think it is a
very nice play."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910712-0107
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910712-0107.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- On Sports:
   An Old-Time Board Game
   ----
   By Frederick C. Klein
</HL>
<DATE>
07/12/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A9
</SO>
<LP>
   In an era when "expensive" and "entertainment" go
together, even (especially?) when children are involved, it's
nice to see that All-Star Baseball is marking its 50th
birthday this year in good style.
   I don't mean the real baseball game that teams
representing the National and American leagues played Tuesday
night in Toronto. I mean the board game, produced by Cadaco.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The game is a classic, not in the sense of those
every-week golf tournaments in places like <LOCATION>Hattiesburg</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Coal Valley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, but by the <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>'s New World
Dictionary definition (No. 6) of "continuing in fashion
because of its simple style." Come to think of it, it also
meets the dictionary's definition No. 1, "of the highest
class." Best, it's cheap, usually retailing between <MONEY>$11</MONEY> and
<MONEY>$15</MONEY>. That's a miniscule price to pay for endless hours of
pleasure.
   I experienced many such hours as a boy, happily choosing
lineups from among the game's best active players (<ORGANIZATION>DiMaggio</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Musial</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Schoendienst</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Spahn</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Roberts</PERSON>) or such golden oldies as <PERSON>Ruth and Cobb</PERSON>, inserting
the cardboard discs containing the heroes' offensive
propensities into the holder, and plinking the spinner to
determine their, and my, fate.
   This was before (long before) computer games, where
players made of colored dots pitch, hit and run the bases
before our very eyes. But <ORGANIZATION>All-Star Baseball</ORGANIZATION> is better,
because it's played in the stadium of the mind. What pile of
dots, however animated, can match the thought of <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>
stealing second base in a cloud of dust, or <PERSON>Musial</PERSON> uncoiling
to slash a double down the right-field line?
   As a lad plinking away, I didn't know, or much care, how
this wonderful game came to be. As a reporter, I found out.
That's a wonderful thing about being a reporter.
   Turns out that All-Star Baseball was invented by a
baseball player; not an All-Star, perhaps, but a very good
one nonetheless. He's <PERSON>Ethan Allen</PERSON>, who spent 13 seasons in
the outfields of the Major Leagues, from <DATE>1926</DATE> through <DATE>'38</DATE>,
with six different teams. Among his achievements was a .300
career batting average. His best season was <DATE>1934</DATE>, when, as a
<LOCATION>Philadelphia Phillie</LOCATION>, he hit .330 and tied for the <ORGANIZATION>National
League</ORGANIZATION> lead in doubles with 42.
   Batting .300 is a bigger thing now than in that hit-crazy
period, but the <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> native still stood out, for his
scholarly bent. At a time when collegians were rare in
professional baseball, he earned a bachelor's degree in
education from the <LOCATION>U. of Cincinnati</LOCATION> in <DATE>1927</DATE>, while a
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> Red, and a master's degree from <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, in <DATE>1932</DATE>,
while a <ORGANIZATION>New York Giant</ORGANIZATION>.
   Later, he produced films and wrote books on baseball
strategy and technique, and spent 23 years -- from <DATE>1946</DATE>
through '68 -- as baseball coach at <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>. Among his players
was <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>, a first baseman on the <DATE>1947</DATE> and '48 squads.
   "<PERSON>George</PERSON> was an excellent fielder and good team man, but
mediocre at bat," says <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>, now 87 years old and living in
<LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>. And no, he did not vote for <PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON> for
president. "I'm an ex-Republican," he declares.
   <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> got the idea for All-Star Baseball while still
wearing spikes. "It occurred to me that a player's batting
record could be graphed on a circle -- his percentage of
singles, home runs, walks, strikeouts and so forth," he says.
"Once I hit upon that, putting the game together wasn't
difficult."
   Selling it was harder: "Every big toy executive threw me
out of his office at least once," <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> notes. Then, in <DATE>1941</DATE>,
he visited Cadaco, a fledgling Chicago-based firm owned by
the brothers <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> and <PERSON>Donald Mazer</PERSON> and named for their
first initials (C and D and Co.). "<PERSON>Don Mazer</PERSON> heard me out,
banged his desk and said `Good idea] We'll make it]'" the
inventor recalls.
   <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> cemented the deal by delivering agreements from the
top players of the day to use their names and records. No
money changed hands. "I drew up a little form and asked them
to sign," he says. "The ones who did I thanked. To the rest I
said, `We'll do without you.'"
   There's more to that now, of course. A Cadaco contract
active players for a <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> royalty, and separate permissions
must be obtained to use such late greats as <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Cobb</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Wagner</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gehrig</PERSON> and <PERSON>Clemente</PERSON>. The Babe's estate collects an
annual fee of <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY>.
   Cadaco still is in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, a division of <ORGANIZATION>Rapid Mounting &amp;
Finishing Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which makes sales-display materials. In
addition to <ORGANIZATION>All-Star Baseball</ORGANIZATION>, Cadaco produces BasKet, a
basketball game utilizing baskets, spring-operated levers and
a ping-pong ball, and Photo (formerly Photo-Electric)
Football, which uses offensive and defensive play
transparencies to simulate gridiron action. I played both in
boyhood. They're wonderful, too.
   <PERSON>Waymon Wittman</PERSON>, a toy industry veteran, is Cadaco's
president. He says the company doesn't know how many All-Star
Baseball games have been sold, but believes the number surely
runs to several million. Annual sales in recent years have
ranged between 75,000 and 165,000 units. "When <ORGANIZATION>Nintendo</ORGANIZATION> gets
hot, we drop, and vice versa," he explains. "It also helps
when Toys `R' Us or <ORGANIZATION>Kmart</ORGANIZATION> features us in their ads."
   All-Star Baseball has its cult aspects, with leagues and a
newsletter. The game is on display at the <ORGANIZATION>Baseball Hall of
Fame</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y. Nostalgia</LOCATION>, too, plays a role in its
prosperity. "At every toy show, at least one buyer'll corner
me to say how much he loved the game as a kid," <PERSON>Wittman</PERSON> says.
"We get letters from men who say their dads played it, they
did, and now their children do."
   There have been attempts to change All-Star Baseball over
the years, with inventor <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> in the lead. He'd like to see
it become more complex, and to that end has fashioned a
multidisc version that provides for balls and strikes,
squeeze bunts, pickoff plays and the like. It was marketed
for a time as Strategic All-Star Baseball, but was withdrawn
for poor sales.
   "The game succeeds for two main reasons: It's simple and
playable," observes <PERSON>Wittman</PERSON>. "After 50 years, I think we'll
keep it the way it is."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06162149 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06162149 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); (2) PHOTOS: (former USC lineman John Wayne)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  HUMOR; SPORT; BRIEF  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Used to be Southern Cal football players and Youth for Nixon were
indiscernible. Times have changed.;    Seven Southern Cal football players
have been arrested or charged since last year. "I don't feel we have thugs in
this program," Coach Larry Smith says. "I don't feel that we have criminals
running around here. I don't feel our football team is a threat to society.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  USC FOOTBALL IMAGE NOT SO WHOLESOME ANYMORE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  OFF THE WALL  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "We've been indicted, tried and convicted of being bad people, a bad
program, bad everything.";    <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said he's keeping closer tabs on players.
"We've got to work very hard to clean up our image.";    Somewhere, former <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>
lineman <PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON> (left and right) is crying.;  CAN'T WAIT TO SIC TYSON ON
HIM; On the basis of his 12-second knockout of <PERSON>Derrick Dukes</PERSON>, we still have no
idea whether former <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> goon <PERSON>Mark Gastineau</PERSON> can box. So get a load of this
hype from <PERSON>Rich Parker</PERSON>, the promoter of <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s alleged bout:;    "This
shows he is a legitimate fighter. We're going to take it slow, but I can see
down the road where Mark will be challenging (undisputed heavyweight champion)
<LOCATION>Evander Holyfield</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mike Tyson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Razor Ruddock</PERSON>. It will be one of the biggest
events in boxing. The public will demand it.";  A GAME DAY PRECEDING
DOUBLEDAY; Of course <PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON> didn't invent baseball in <DATE>1839</DATE>.
Historians in <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, have found a notice in the <DATE>July 13, 1825</DATE>,
edition of the Delhi (<LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>) <ORGANIZATION>Gazette</ORGANIZATION>, in which nine men in <LOCATION>Hamden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>,
challenged any group in <LOCATION>Delaware County</LOCATION> to a game of baseball at the home of
<PERSON>Edward B. Chace</PERSON> for <MONEY>$1</MONEY> each, per game.;  'I will be back. I'll come back a new
man. I may come back <PERSON>Vincent Jackson</PERSON>.  '-- <PERSON>Vincent Edward 'Bo' Jackson</PERSON>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Information for this column was compiled from Mercury News wire services by
Colin Seymour.  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910610  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  301  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday June 10, 1991
00162149,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900314-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-14-90 0042EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Baseball-Media Bjt   03-14 0836</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Baseball-Media, Bjt,0864</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baseball Lockout Forces Media Companies to Make Alternate Plans</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If the baseball lockout never ends, what will
the sports media write and talk about this <DATE>summer</DATE>?
   Some media companies already are juggling their plans even as
they hope they will never have to answer that question.
   The lockout has blocked the opening of <DATE>spring</DATE> training camps for
nearly a month, and it already has cost the ESPN cable network five
of the 10 <DATE>spring</DATE> training games it planned to televise this year.
   Potential problems loom for <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>, which is to begin broadcasting
baseball in <DATE>April</DATE>; The National, the new daily sports newspaper,
and The Sporting News, the sports weekly.
   ``It hasn't affected us yet, but baseball is the only game in
town in the summertime,'' said <PERSON>Tom Osenton</PERSON>, president and chief
executive of <ORGANIZATION>The Sporting News Publishing Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. ``If
you take the game away, you have nothing to write about.''
   ESPN is in the first season of its <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> contract to
carry up to 175 games in each of the next four years.
   ``Getting that contract was such an exciting moment for us,''
said <PERSON>Mike Soltys</PERSON>, manager of programming information for <ORGANIZATION>ESPN</ORGANIZATION>. ``To
start out in this manner is certainly discouraging.''
   The network filled the gaps created by the lost games with live
tennis, auto racing and other programming it had originally planned
to tape for later replay, he said.
   Plans are to substitute a college basketball playoff game, a
college baseball game and college wrestling, among other events if
the remaining <DATE>spring</DATE> training games are canceled, <PERSON>Soltys</PERSON> said.
   He said the network is sticking with its plans to run a baseball
show, <ORGANIZATION>Baseball Tonight</ORGANIZATION>, seven nights a week starting as scheduled
next <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   If the lockout continues, the show will deal with developments
in negotiations between the players and owners and may feature
coverage of minor league baseball, he said.
   But <ORGANIZATION>ESPN</ORGANIZATION> faces a more serious problem in <DATE>April</DATE>, when it planned
to begin carrying six games a week. The network has hired 19
commentators to handle the nightly baseball show and the games,
<PERSON>Soltys</PERSON> said, and has sold more than <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of its season's
advertising inventory in the games.
   <PERSON>Soltys</PERSON> said the advertisers are being given the options of
appearing on the replacement programs, holding off until the games
start or getting refunds.
   But he said the lockout has hurt the climate for selling
advertising. ``There is no way of knowing where we would be without
this,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Soltys</PERSON> said ``there are provisions for lost games'' under the
network contract with baseball, but he refused to describe them. A
source familiar with the contract said <ORGANIZATION>ESPN</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> will be given
additional games in the next three years for games lost this year.
   The lockout has posed a less serious problem so far for <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>,
which agreed to pay <MONEY>$1.06 billion</MONEY> for the right to broadcast 16
regular season games, the All-Star game, the playoffs and World
Series every year for four years.
   CBS' first baseball broadcasts are scheduled for <DATE>April 14</DATE> and
<DATE>April 21</DATE>, but its third broadcast is not scheduled until <DATE>June 16</DATE>.
   CBS Sports spokesman <PERSON>Tony Fox</PERSON> said the network has not decided
what sports programs will replace the <DATE>April</DATE> game broadcasts.
   Fox said more than half of <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>' advertising inventory for
baseball had been sold, but he declined to discuss what plans were
being made for advertisers if games are canceled.
   The network plans to run its baseball season preview show on
<DATE>March 31</DATE> as scheduled no matter what happens with the lockout, <ORGANIZATION>Fox</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   As at <ORGANIZATION>The Sporting News</ORGANIZATION>, the lockout has had little impact so
far on The National, according to editor-in-chief <PERSON>Frank Deford</PERSON>. The
newspaper debuted <DATE>Jan. 31</DATE> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Deford</PERSON> said readers of <ORGANIZATION>The National</ORGANIZATION> usually are interested in
several sports, and there has been plenty of activity recently in
college and professional basketball, boxing and hockey to interest
them.
   But if the baseball lockout continues into mid-summer, ``that
would be a real blow to us, there is no question.''
   At <ORGANIZATION>The Sporting News</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Osenton</PERSON> said plans are being made to beef
up basketball and hockey coverage over the next few weeks and said
if the lockout persists, the tabloid may increase coverage of minor
league baseball.
   <PERSON>Deford</PERSON> said it was unlikely The National would start covering
minor league or Japanese baseball because he doen't think readers
want it. ``You can't give people something they don't want,'' he
said.
   He said if the lockout continued into <DATE>June</DATE>, there probably would
be more coverage of major tennis, soccer, golf and swimming events.
He said the paper also could be trimmed to 32 pages from the 40-48
pages it has been running.
   Deford professes to be unconcerned and has made no contingency
plans. ``My best judgment is I cannot conceive of a situation where
they will not be back by <DATE>June</DATE>,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900525-0065
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900525-0065.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   All He Wanted Was
   A Chance to Save
   A Rickey Henderson
   ---
   Roger Hall's Breakaway Bases
   Protect Ankles in Slides;
   But Baseball Isn't Buying
   ----
   By Bradley A. Stertz
</HL>
<DATE>
05/25/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<IN>
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<LP>
   ELIZABETHTOWN, Pa. -- Baseball has many heroes. Roger Hall
isn't one of them.
   He might, however, hold two baseball records, if
statisticians knew about them. He's probably slid into bases
more times than Lou Brock, and he's probably toiled more
often in the field of dreams than Ray Kinsella.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   For years, <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON> has been tinkering on what he calls
"Rogers Break Away Bases," baseball bases that are designed
to pop up under extraordinary force and thus reduce injuries
that can result from bad slides. He began his crusade when he
watched a friend tear out a kneecap sliding into a standard,
stationary base. "It was horrible," the wiry former infielder
and <ORGANIZATION>Elizabethtown College</ORGANIZATION> volunteer coach recalls. "I went
right out to find bases that might be safer. But I couldn't
find anything and decided I'd have to rig something
together."
   In <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON>'s perfect world, his base would work something
like this: <PERSON>Rickey Henderson</PERSON> gets a late jump trying to steal
second and has to slide hard to avoid a strong throw from the
catcher.
   Ordinarily, players hate to slam into traditional bases
this way for fear of injuring a knee, ankle or wrist, when
they slide headfirst. But this ball park is equipped with
"Rogers Break Away Bases."
   The <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> outfielder's wrist rams into the base well
ahead of the tag. The sell-out crowd gasps, thinking he'll be
hurt. Instead of the all-star's joints buckling, the base
gives with a pop-pop-pop, detaching completely from the
rubber plugs holding it down on the field. <PERSON>Mr. Henderson</PERSON>, who
maintains contact with the flush-mounted rubber plate still
in the ground, stands unhurt and waves to the cheering crowd.
   It's a good dream, one that could have made <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON> a
hero. But though he's found success in one unlikely sector --
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government -- baseball has been mostly unresponsive.
Minnesota Twins Manager <PERSON>Tom Kelly</PERSON> says flatly, "Who needs
them?"
   According to medical reports, plenty of people do. A
two-year <ORGANIZATION>University of Michigan</ORGANIZATION> study found <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON>'s bases
virtually eliminated base-path injuries on amateur diamonds
around <PERSON>Ann Arbor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, while fields that used traditional
stationary bases saw one sliding injury every 14 games.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> calculated that
breakaway bases could save <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> a year in medical
treatments to the more than 40 million Americans playing
organized ball every year. That's more money than the federal
government spent last year on AIDS research and treatment.
   What <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON> didn't realize is that change comes slower
to the national pastime than pitches from a sore-armed
reliever. The <ORGANIZATION>National Hockey League</ORGANIZATION> adopted detachable,
magnetized goals five years ago to cut down on injuries. The
<ORGANIZATION>National Basketball Association</ORGANIZATION> went to breakaway rims when
ill-timed slam dunks raised the potential for player harm.
   But baseball treats its past with holy reverence, and the
15-inch-square bags that give the game its name are sacred.
"Baseball looks at innovations like these bases and asks, `If
the game has worked for the past 100 years, why change it?'"
says <PERSON>Bill Deane</PERSON>, a history reseacher at the <ORGANIZATION>National Baseball
Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> and Museum in <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> "It's a very
conservative sport."
   Indeed, the <ORGANIZATION>Official Baseball Rules</ORGANIZATION> covering bases haven't
changed significantly in the past 104 years, though people
have often tried. In <DATE>1875</DATE>, <PERSON>John C. O'Neill</PERSON> of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>
patented an "Enunciating Base." It featured a built-in bell
so "the touching of the base by the runner is clearly
announced to the umpire," thereby avoiding "dissatisfaction
and squabbles arising from erroneous observations and
decisions."
   More than 70 years later, two inventors devised a base
without "hazardous corners and side walls." Baseball has also
seen detachable bases -- in velcro, which didn't work once
they got dusty, and with magnets, made by the inventor of the
detachable hockey net.
   <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON> has spent 17 years perfecting his base. In the
early stages of his work, he sold his house and moved with
his wife, <PERSON>Wilma</PERSON>, into a cramped mobile home. There he tested
model after model, sliding into them on his small, sloping
lawn. To keep going, he took odd jobs, like painting houses
and running deliveries around this small, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Dutch
town. He sold his wife's <PERSON>Ford Pinto</PERSON>, and, for a time, gave up
meat.
   "It got to the point where we couldn't afford to go to the
dentist and I stopped buying clothes for myself," <PERSON>Mrs. Hall</PERSON>
says. "It was very depressing, but something said to us to go
on a little further. His dream was so strong and I just
prayed the Lord would carry us through."
   Last month, the Halls thought some of their prayers had
been answered when top officials from two major league teams,
the <ORGANIZATION>Detroit Tigers</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Blue Jays</ORGANIZATION>, expressed serious
interest in trying the bases. The <ORGANIZATION>Blue Jays</ORGANIZATION> used them on
fields at their <LOCATION>Dunedin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, <DATE>spring</DATE> training complex. Both
clubs agreed to use them with some of their minor league
clubs.
   "If we save just one player who the organization's spent a
lot of money to develop, these bases are worth the money,"
says <PERSON>Bob Gilson</PERSON>, general manager of the <ORGANIZATION>London Tigers</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>'s class AA farm team. "Then when these guys get to
the pros and start earning <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> a year the stakes get
even higher. The players become assets teams have to
protect."
   In one recent game, a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> Tiger outfielder thought he
was certain to injure his legs on a hard slide into third.
   "I knew I was going to jam something, but then the base
just came off and tumbled a few feet away," says 23-year-old
<PERSON>Steve Green</PERSON>. "Those bases may have kept me from really
hurting myself, but I wouldn't have known they were there
otherwise."
   But <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON> had his sights set on the majors, not the
minors. Problem is, by the time a player is in the big
leagues, he knows how to slide. Detroit shortstop <PERSON>Alan
Trammell</PERSON> says he can't think of anyone who was seriously hurt
because of the traditional bases, held down by steel posts in
cement anchors. American League President <PERSON>Bobby Brown</PERSON> wrote
this to the <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION>: "In my experience,
sliding injuries . . . resulting from abrupt violent contact
with the base by the runner has not been a problem in
professional baseball."
   Still, there are millions of Americans playing ball in the
minor or little leagues or on city and suburban recreational
fields. Wouldn't their organizations want to prevent
base-path injuries to baby Ruths and middle-aged Mantles?
   The <ORGANIZATION>Little League</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>American Softball Association</ORGANIZATION>
seem to have nothing against the concept, but they want
royalties in exchange for endorsements. The Little League
asks <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> on the sale of each base. It's a price the
financially strapped <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON> says he can't possibly pay.
   The city of <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, has been a firm believer in <PERSON>Mr.
Hall</PERSON>'s bases. But recently, city officials sent back a number
of them saying they had come unglued. The quality problems
scared a lot of recreational directors on thin budgets; a set
of three Break Away bases costs nearly <MONEY>$400</MONEY>, compared with
<MONEY>$80</MONEY>-<MONEY>$160</MONEY> for ordinary ones.
   <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON> says quality will no longer be a problem, now
that he's finally wrested his product from the company that
was producing them.
   Though spurned by the majors so far, <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON> did find one
big-league fan: the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government. Last year, the safety
benefits of breakaway bases were the subject of a <ORGANIZATION>House
Appropriations</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee hearing. Testimony there led to
the use of the <ORGANIZATION>Rogers Break Away Base</ORGANIZATION> at several military
bases and federal penitentiaries.
   <PERSON>Keith Marshall</PERSON>, sports specialist at a minimum-security
prison in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, praises <PERSON>Mr. Hall</PERSON>'s bases: "People come
into an institution like this not knowing how to slide, and
you get plenty of ankle injuries in the intramurals and
leagues and tournaments we have with outside teams," he says.
"I'm a firm believer."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030990-0004 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 186732 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 9, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 6; Column 1; Editorial Writers Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
292 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SEASON OPENS ON TIME (WE WISH) 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
This is the season of our soul's renewal. This is the time when expectation, 
like the sun, rises a little higher as each new day marks the hurtling of 
winter into <DATE>spring</DATE> with delicious inevitability toward Opening Day. 
</P>
<P>
Baseball: No other game whispers so sweetly of the spirit's secret yearnings. 
Its rhythms are those of the seasons: Hope in springtime, industry through the 
<DATE>summer</DATE>, bountiful harvest or brittle failure in the <DATE>fall</DATE>. Thus it was in that 
gentle, rural <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> imagined in our common memory, a half-invented <ORGANIZATION>Eden</ORGANIZATION>, a 
garden of innocent promise. Baseball is an annual reminder that -- to turn 
<PERSON>Robert Frost</PERSON>'s line on its head -- we Americans were the land before the land 
was ours. 
</P>
<P>
Then, of course, there is the game itself. We do not call contests between 
baseball teams "matches," but games. (And when we refer to baseball, we do not 
call it a "sport," but the national pastime.) In it, we approach the infinite 
on our own terms: Theoretically every baseball game could go on indefinitely. 
The field itself is a green and open place, a memorial to that time when such 
things were not a luxury. 
</P>
<P>
Baseball is as we would like to be, and imagine we once were. For that reason, 
we are uniquely forgiving of those who betray it. No one would speak of <PERSON>Joe 
Jackson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Benedict Arnold</PERSON> in the same breath. And nobody laughed at <PERSON>Pete 
Rose</PERSON>'s trouble. When we think of <ORGANIZATION>Shoeless Joe</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Charlie Hustle</PERSON>, we are sadly 
puzzled and hopeful of their redemption somewhere in time. 
</P>
<P>
We might even have forgiven the owners and the players' association -- if they 
had not let their quarrel over money stand between the rest of us and the 
promise of Opening Day. But some things are unforgivable -- and there's not 
much time left for redemption. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Editorial 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060589-0090 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 66412 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 5, 1989, Monday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
693 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK; 
</P>
<P>
SERVING SUSHI AT BASEBALL GAMES? SAY IT AIN'T SO, JOE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BOB SECTER, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
There has been considerable hand-wringing in recent years about <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> losing 
its competitive edge to the Japanese. We invent it, they make it. Cars, TVs, 
VCRs, computer chips, farm equipment, high-tech gizmos of all sorts. 
</P>
<P>
The Japanese are even gobbling up huge chunks of swank real estate, movie 
studios and other symbols of Americana. 
</P>
<P>
Well, maybe all that was inevitable, interest rates, labor costs, and 
free-market competition being what they are. But its time to take a stand. 
They're threatening to horn in on something that strikes at the very heart of 
our culture. We're talking social significance. We're talking moral outrage. 
We're talking baseball. 
</P>
<P>
Baseball may be the only hallowed American institution untouched by Japanese 
influence, the only one they've copied and still not been able to beat us at. 
In fact, its even good for the balance of trade. 
</P>
<P>
Every year, Japanese teams import a few dozen nearsighted sluggers and 
sore-armed pitchers, the real meatballs of the national pastime. No longer 
terrorized by the likes of a <PERSON>Roger Clemens</PERSON> on the mound or <PERSON>Dave Winfield</PERSON> at the 
plate, even the American rejects start banging and bopping the ball like 
all-stars and ship back a <MONEY>few million dollars</MONEY> apiece for their troubles. 
</P>
<P>
Now this last vestige of American dominance may be crumbling. Japanese 
influence is starting to trickle into major league stadiums. This season for 
the first time ever, they're selling sushi -- that's right, those dainty little 
globs of raw squid, grouper, shark, fish eggs and what have you -- at the old 
ballpark. 
</P>
<P>
Think about it. You're sitting in the grandstand on a sweltering <DATE>summer</DATE> day. 
It's the bottom of the ninth, a tense, scoreless pitcher's duel on the field, 
and that empty, gnawing feeling rumbles up from the pit of your stomach. You 
turn to your buddy in the next seat and say, "Gee, you know what would really 
hit the spot at a time like this? An ice cold brew and a hunk of eel, that's 
what." 
</P>
<P>
Ridiculous, right? Well, the <LOCATION>San Diego Padres</LOCATION> have been selling crab rolls 
along with the peanuts, popcorn and <PERSON>Cracker Jack</PERSON> ever since opening day this 
season. And fans have actually been snapping them up. 
</P>
<P>
What's worse, the Angels are slated to be next. <PERSON>Ed Elias</PERSON>, the general manager 
of the catering firm that runs concession stands at the Big A, says he hopes to 
offer sushi later this season or early in <DATE>1990</DATE>. If that sounds unpatriotic, get 
a load of this: The sushi shack is going to go in where an ice cream parlor now 
stands. 
</P>
<P>
Why would any red-blooded fan nibble on slimy, uncooked seaweed at the ballpark 
when they could choose from a virtual cornucopia of all-American favorites to 
munch on, dishes like nachos, tostadas and bratwurst? "Why do they eat baked 
potatoes, fish and chips or cinnamon rolls at a ballpark?" asked <LOCATION>Elias</LOCATION>, 
rhetorically. "I think the fans will eat about anything you offer them. We're 
even going to build a pasta house." 
</P>
<P>
Just because they'll eat it, Ed, doesn't mean you have to give it to them. I'm 
all for change, innovation and variety, but some things are sacred. With domed 
stadiums, artificial turf, designated hitters and mascots parading around the 
park in chicken costumes, hasn't the game already been perverted enough? 
</P>
<P>
Ever since <PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON> kicked dirt on his first umpire, generations of 
American youth have been raised to believe that a balanced ballpark diet meant 
a hot dog in one hand, a beer in the other and maybe a bag of peanuts on their 
lap. But these days, Angel fans are already munching on wilted seafood salads 
and sipping on sweet frozen daiquiris. No wonder snobby <ORGANIZATION>Easterners</ORGANIZATION> resisted 
letting the game move West for all those years. 
</P>
<P>
If fans here want the privilege of watching <ORGANIZATION>Big League</ORGANIZATION> games, the least they 
could do is eat like <ORGANIZATION>Big Leaguers</ORGANIZATION>. You think <PERSON>Joe DiMaggio</PERSON> or Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> ever 
slurped up a plate of raw mackerel on rice? 
</P>
<P>
No, the Babe had an appetite and thirst that was legendary. When the Yankees 
played in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, for example, he would sometimes duck out between innings to 
<PERSON>McCuddy</PERSON>'s Tavern across the street from the stadium. 
</P>
<P>
And you can bet it wasn't to order a watercress sandwich and a white wine 
spritzer. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BASEBALL; STADIUMS; SUSHI; FOOD 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911004-0152
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911004-0152.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   On Sports: Basketball at 100
   ----
   By Frederick C. Klein
</HL>
<DATE>
10/04/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   If James Naismith had a better sense of history, he would
have invented basketball a few weeks after he did, sometime
in late December of 1891. That would have given his sport's
centennial a Columbian parallel, and also would have made it
coincide with an Olympiad in which basketball is expected to
be a, and maybe the, featured attraction, thanks to the
recently named "dream team" of U.S. professional stars.
   Naismith, however, fashioned the game in response to a
more immediate imperative. In his 1941 book, "Basketball: Its
Origin and Development," he recounts how, as a new,
30-year-old gym instructor at the YMCA International Training
School in Springfield, Mass., now Springfield College, he was
put in charge of a class of administrators-in-training that
was bored to the point of mutiny with its daily winter
regimen of calisthenics. He'd badgered superiors with his
belief that if exercise could be made to seem like play
instead of work, the most re-calcitrant pupils would
participate willingly. One responded by giving him the
troublesome class, saying, in effect, "Put up or shut up."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "I went to work with this class," <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> wrote. "I tried
{having the men play} soccer and we smashed all the windows.
I tried lacrosse and smashed most of the fellows' arms. Rugby
football finished the students up, until they were ready to
quit on recreative games."
   He went on: "In a day or two I would have to report to the
faculty the success or failure of my attempts. So far they
had been all failures. How I hated the thought of admitting
that, after all my theories, I, too, had failed to hold the
interest of the class."
   So he repaired to his office to meditate on the sort of
game that might be played indoors and be challenging but not
rough. It must, of course, involve a ball -- didn't they all?
-- and be easy to learn. But what of the fun element?
   The most interesting game at that time was American rugby
(football), he mused, but it was inappropriate for indoors
because it involved tackling. Why? Because players were
allowed to run with the ball and it was necessary to stop
them. But . . . if they couldn't run with the ball, tackling
could be eliminated]
   "I can still recall how I snapped my fingers and shouted,
`I've got it]'" he wrote.
   The rest -- the elevated, horizontal goal and general
rules -- fell into place, and within days <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION>'s Y
charges were happily playing the game that would be the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>'s most important gift to sports. Baseball may be our
poets' choice, and football may be No. 1 on the domestic
tube, but basketball, with its free-flowing form and abundant
opportunities for individual virtuosity, is the American game
the world has chosen. <ORGANIZATION>FIBA</ORGANIZATION>, the Olympic regulator of the
sport, recognizes national governing bodies in 176 countries,
10 more than belong to the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>. Surveys I've seen
identify basketball as the world's foremost spectator sport.
   It is, furthermore, the game that is most purely "ours,"
baseball and football having direct British antecedents. My
encyclopedia mentions a 16th-century Aztec game called
"ollamalitzli," in which players tried to throw a ball
through an elevated stone ring. But it notes that any player
who succeeded was entitled to the clothes of all the
spectators, so it couldn't have been very high scoring.
   Several things about basketball's beginnings seem worth
mentioning in this centennial year. One is the biography of
<ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION>. This was a man of parts. Born and raised in the
northern <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION> hamlet of <PERSON>Bennie</PERSON>'s Corners, he was orphaned
at eight and at times had to drop out of public school to
support himself as a logger or farmhand. Nonetheless, he
would receive a degree in theology from <ORGANIZATION>McGill University</ORGANIZATION> and
an M.D. from <ORGANIZATION>Gross Medical School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>.
   He never held a pastorate, though, nor did he practice
medicine. He wrote that his aim in life was to "do good," and
he concluded that encouraging wholesome leisure pursuits
among the young would accomplish this best. A naturalized
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> citizen, he spent most of his working life at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Kansas</ORGANIZATION>, where he became chairman of the
physical education department. He died in <DATE>1939</DATE> at age 78.
   Secondly, we are reminded of the role of chance in
invention; many of basketball's most salient features just
kind of happened. For instance, <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> wanted boxes to
serve as goals, but the janitor he asked had only peach
baskets handy. They were placed 10 feet off the ground
because that was where the balcony of the <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION> gym, on
which they were nailed, began. And backboards were
introduced, in <DATE>1893</DATE>, to keep spectators from helping their
favorite teams by swatting away opponents' shots.
   Lastly, once basketball's foundations were laid, it was
remarkable how quickly it approached its present form. Free
throws after fouls were introduced in <DATE>1894</DATE>, the point system
of two points for field goals and one for free throws came in
<DATE>1896</DATE>, five-player teams were accepted in <DATE>1897</DATE> and the dribble
-- the most important change in <ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION>'s original plan --
was made legal in <DATE>1898</DATE>. In later life, he liked to remark
that the biggest difference between the game he devised and
the one that evolved was in the skill of the players.
   Over the next few months, the centennial will be marked in
a number of ways. The <ORGANIZATION>YMCA</ORGANIZATION>, which also spread the game
abroad, has various celebrations planned, and the game's <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>
of Fame in <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION> will host a series of events
culminating in a black-tie gala on <DATE>Dec. 21</DATE>. That's the day
set as the game's birthday, although nobody knows for sure.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Basketball Association</ORGANIZATION>, whose teams begin
practice this week, says its players will wear centennial
patches on their warmup suits in the coming season, and other
commemorations will be staged. But it's questionable how
<ORGANIZATION>Naismith</ORGANIZATION> would regard the league. He wrote that basketball
would be basketball as long as four things didn't change: The
large, light ball; the elevated, horizontal goal; and no
personal contact or running with the ball. Seems that NBAball
qualifies on only two of those counts.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06159225 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06159225 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-JOSE; JUDGE; RULING; BASEBALL; PRODUCT; LAWSUIT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  There was no locker-room language, and the air didn't smell like sweaty
socks.;    But a half-dozen baseballs, three pitching machines and an old-time
ballplayer made a federal courtroom resemble a gym when a San Jose magistrate
played umpire Thursday in an unusual patent case.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EX-BALLPLAYER CRIES FOUL ON HIS PITCHING
INVENTION  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Former pitcher <PERSON>Arthur Brophy</PERSON>, who threw left-handed in the old <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
Senators farm system in the '50s, charged that an <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> company stole his
idea for a simple pitching machine that tosses a ball softly into the air,
right in front of a practicing batter.;    But a team of lawyers fielded by
<ORGANIZATION>Atec Inc.</ORGANIZATION> countered that their "Soft Toss" machine, which is made in <LOCATION>Santa
Cruz</LOCATION>, is substantially different from the device <PERSON>Brophy</PERSON> perfected in his
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> garage after finishing gigs at local clubs as a jazz pianist.;   
After three hours of talks, both sides agreed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to end the game without
extra innings. They reached a confidential settlement that was approved by
<ORGANIZATION>Magistrate Edward Infante.</ORGANIZATION>;    <PERSON>Doug Boehner</PERSON>, executive vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Atec</ORGANIZATION>,
said the company has sold at least 4,000 Soft Toss machines to major leaguers
and schoolchildren. The machines retail for <MONEY>$299.</MONEY>;    But <PERSON>Brophy</PERSON>, who says he
does some scouting for the Orioles and runs a small sports equipment business
from home, has canceled checks to prove he sold copies of his invention to
ballplayers <PERSON>Carl Yastrzemski</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rickey Henderson</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Carney Lansford.</ORGANIZATION>;    During
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s hearing, <PERSON>Infante</PERSON> removed his robe and suit coat while lawyers for
both sides demonstrated their machines. Watching attentively as baseballs flew
lightly through the air, the judge at one point took a kneeling stance to
scoop a stray ball off the soft blue carpet.;    <PERSON>Brophy</PERSON> and his lawyer brought
in two machines that looked a bit battered and worn. Atec brought a shiny
model that looked like it was right off the showroom floor.;    But the most
colorful part of the hearing was <PERSON>Brophy</PERSON>. Sporting a deep suntan and an
open-necked, brown-and-bronze-patterned sport shirt, the 55-year-old athlete
had trouble sitting still.;    He tinkered with the chutes on his machine and
lobbed balls into the air, even while <ORGANIZATION>Atec</ORGANIZATION> lawyer <PERSON>Richard Doyle</PERSON> was earnestly
arguing his case. More than once, <PERSON>Brophy</PERSON>'s bow-tied attorney, <PERSON>James Hennefer</PERSON>,
signaled furtively for him to stop. Finally, <PERSON>Hennefer</PERSON> called his client's name
out loud, and <PERSON>Brophy</PERSON> meekly sat down.;    In the end, <PERSON>Brophy</PERSON> seemed happy with
the settlement and said he hasn't gotten discouraged from inventing things:
"I've got a couple more ideas to work on."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  BRANDON BAILEY, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910607  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  421  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday June 7, 1991
00159225,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA073090-0031 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 254451 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 30, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 5; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
755 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AMERICAN ALBUM: WHO'S ON FIRST? NO QUICK ANSWERS IN THIS GAMEIN THE FINNISH 
VERSION OF BASEBALL, PLAYERS ARE ALL OVER THE PLACE. NOW THEY'RE IN THE U.S., 
SEEKING A FOOTHOLD. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BOB SECTER, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HANCOCK, Mich. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
There were lots of reasons why <PERSON>Jimmy Piersall</PERSON> was known as a flake back when he 
played major league baseball, but one of the best came the day he hit a home 
run as a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Met and ran the bases backwards. 
</P>
<P>
All of which has little to do with the subject of this story except to 
illustrate the maxim that what may seem like buffoonery in one setting could 
make perfect sense in another. Had <PERSON>Piersall</PERSON> been playing in, say, <LOCATION>Helsinki</LOCATION> 
rather than <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>, he might have fit right in. 
</P>
<P>
Yes. Baseball has been Finlandized. 
</P>
<P>
The Finns call the game pesapallo and are so crazy about it that it's 
considered their national pastime. Of course they do it a little differently. 
They don't actually backpedal their way from base to base ala <PERSON>Piersall</PERSON> but, 
looking at it from a chauvinist American perspective, they do take a backwards 
route around the basepaths. 
</P>
<P>
First base is where third base ought to be, second is sort of around where 
first should be and third is somewhere out in left field. 
</P>
<P>
That's right, <LOCATION>Abbott</LOCATION>. Who isn't on first. I Don't Know is. Sort of. 
</P>
<P>
Anyway, Finnish emigres have spread the game to <LOCATION>Scandinavia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and even 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. And over the weekend they took their first crack at the toughest 
market of all -- the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, the guarantor of all that is pure and noble 
about baseball. 
</P>
<P>
Here in <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s rugged <LOCATION>Upper Peninsula</LOCATION>, the heart of Finnish America, two 
Canadian pesapallo teams squared off <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in a demonstration game before 
thousands of slightly befuddled spectators at an ethnic festival. In a real 
slugfest, the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Sisu</ORGANIZATION> eked out a <DATE>16-15</DATE> win over the archrival Thunder Bay 
Repais. 
</P>
<P>
Organizers of the annual FinnFest say that they hope to field enough domestic 
talent to stage home-grown pesapallo matches at future gatherings. Already, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Hancock High School</ORGANIZATION> baseball coach is talking about teaching the Finnish 
version to his team. 
</P>
<P>
The main selling point of pesapallo, devotees say, is action. There are no long 
pauses between pitches, the ball is almost constantly in play and both fielders 
and runners are forever scampering all over the place. 
</P>
<P>
"In American baseball, a runner on second is in scoring position but in our 
game he's just tired," winked <PERSON>Jari Leinonen</PERSON>, who plays for the Repais. "Usually 
when we get out there, we pack a lunch." 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Finland</LOCATION> was <PERSON>Lauri Pihkala</PERSON>, a professor who apparently 
was mesmerized by baseball during early 20th-Century study tours in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>. He combined the American game with some native ball-playing sports and 
pesapallo was born. 
</P>
<P>
Both baseball and pesapallo feature four bases, three outs an inning, nine 
innings, nine players on a side, a hard ball, mitts and a bat -- although the 
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> Slugger of <LOCATION>Finland</LOCATION> is called a <PERSON>Jarvinen Kanuuna</PERSON>. It's also safe to 
say that neither game will have <PERSON>Roseanne Barr</PERSON> sing the opening anthem in the 
future. 
</P>
<P>
That's where the similarities end. The pesapallo pitcher, for instance, stands 
next to the plate and tosses the ball up in the air, varying his delivery not 
with curves or sliders but by the height the ball goes. (<PERSON>Orel Hershiser</PERSON> please 
note: if the shoulder surgery doesn't work, a career could still beckon in 
<LOCATION>Finland</LOCATION>.) 
</P>
<P>
Instead of waiting in a dugout, teammates of the batter stand around what's 
roughly equivalent to the batter's box and scream out advice whether to swing 
or not at a pitch. The batter can hit as many as three fair balls before he has 
to run. And the route around the basepaths sort of zigzags first to the left, 
then the right, then the left again. 
</P>
<P>
Confused? Try this. A three-base hit is a kunnari, or home run. The batter 
scores, even though he's allowed to stay on third and score again if somebody 
knocks him in. But getting a kunnari is not easy because a ball that's knocked 
out of the park -- about 300 feet from home to the farthest point of the 
pesapallo outfield -- is considered a laiton (foul). 
</P>
<P>
When an outfielder catches a fly ball, that doesn't necessarily mean the batter 
is out. He might just be haava (wounded), a sort of purgatory state for 
sluggers that requires them to forfeit the turn at bat but doesn't exactly 
count toward ending the inning. And when someone does make an out, he's not 
just out, he's pallo (killed). This is no game for wimps, that's for sure. 
</P>
<P>
There's one other important difference. At the end of the game, American 
ballplayers hit the showers. "When we're done," said Thunder Bay shortstop 
<PERSON>Pavli Kaki</PERSON>, "we go off to the sauna." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, Michigan; Drawing, Baseball Field 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FINLAND -- ATHLETICS; ATHLETIC EVENTS; ATHLETIC TEAMS; BASEBALL; FINLAND -- 
CULTURE; SPORTS RULES AND REGULATIONS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081090-0137 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 260022 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 10, 1990, Friday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 6; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
633 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TOWN IS IN DANGER OF LOSING ITS CHARM 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN STEADMAN, BALTIMORE EVENING SUN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
COOPERSTOWN, N.Y. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Holding on to the past, as one might endeavor to preserve a childhood memory, 
is commendable but impossible. Downtown <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, a village with one traffic 
light and flower boxes attached to the windowsills of gracious Victorian 
houses, fronted by impeccable lawns, has undergone sudden change. 
</P>
<P>
It's going "carni." <LOCATION>Coney Island</LOCATION> has taken over. Commercialism rears its 
insatiable head and Main Street, which once offered old-fashioned store fronts, 
is in danger of heading for ruin. The warning signs are up. 
</P>
<P>
How much longer will the charm of <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> remain? It's here where we're 
told <PERSON>Abner Doubleday</PERSON> and barefooted farm boys played the first game of baseball 
and, even if it is a historical lie, as some researchers have suggested, the 
setting is ideal for accepting the fiction as some kind of poetic license for 
stretching the truth. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, as the cradle of baseball, might be mythical but is truly symbolic 
of a time 151 years ago when the grand American game was born. A visit to where 
baseball began is something of a spiritual experience. You are put in the 
proper frame as you walk the tree-shaded streets and view this special quality 
and pace of life. 
</P>
<P>
But none of what has transpired of late around town is for the best. It can't 
be defined as beneficial when <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> is showing signs of losing its 
character. Aesthetically, it has been rocked on its heels. There's shock. 
</P>
<P>
Tourists and the "townies" agree. They don't like it. Can something be done to 
put the brakes on the erosion of a memorable setting that author <PERSON>James Fenimore 
Cooper</PERSON> brought to the literary attention of the world in using these green 
hills and crystal waters as the backdrop for his wondrous adventures? 
</P>
<P>
The natives are particularly upset. At last count, nine stores selling baseball 
cards, a modern phenomenon, are open for business. Some establishments erect 
tables on the sidewalk to showcase their wares, selling all types of souvenirs 
such as T-shirts, pictures, bats, caps and uniforms. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Barbara Landers</PERSON>, who operates the Short Stop Restaurant, which was founded by 
her grandfather, <PERSON>Salvatore Sapienza</PERSON>, in <DATE>1921</DATE> and given its present name in 
<DATE>1939</DATE>, the year the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame opened, shook her head in dismay and said, 
"<LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> is getting too big for itself. We might have to put a stop to it. 
The trend is upsetting to all of us who truly care about <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
A member of the <ORGANIZATION>Baltimore Orioles</ORGANIZATION>' sales department, <PERSON>Lucy Kelly</PERSON>, recognizes 
what is taking place but insists <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> retains an appeal all its own. "I 
still find it a quaint little town," she said. "The <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame draws me and, 
of course, the striking beauty of the countryside." 
</P>
<P>
Dr. <PERSON>Michael Klein</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> has been coming here every <DATE>summer</DATE> since <DATE>1977</DATE> to 
enjoy the tranquility and the history that abounds. Asked for a comparison, 
covering two decades, he answered, "It used to be an original. Now it's getting 
like any other city. But I plan to keep coming back." 
</P>
<P>
Closer to the heart of the village is <PERSON>Marge Strait</PERSON>, who owns the <ORGANIZATION>Cooperstown 
Diner</ORGANIZATION>. She insists the "whole town is upset." Can anything be done? "The town 
trustees held a meeting to discuss it. But you can't lock the gate after the 
horse is out. Most of the change has happened in the last year. 
</P>
<P>
"We have to do something. It's getting trashy looking. Four new card shops have 
opened. How do you keep them out? The baseball memorabilia places, some of 
which pay the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame players money for signing autographs, set up tables 
on the street and even erected tents on their property. It's a shame." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION> has a fight on its hands to recover the identity and protect the 
indigenous characteristics that made it so distinctive. It'll survive, no 
doubt, but, hopefully, the scars that have been inflicted will be repaired. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890629-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-29-89 0135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     06-29 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHATTANOOGA, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A television personality's decision to
propose on the air didn't really surprise his girlfriend.
   <PERSON>Jed Mescon</PERSON> popped the question to <PERSON>Phyllis Bruce</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night
during ``Jed's Journal,'' his nightly feature segment WRCB-TV's
evening news broadcast.
   ``I feel like I owed <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION>. This is where I feel like I
became a professional and I wanted them to share in my joy,'' said
the 29-year-old <PERSON>Mescon</PERSON>.
   Mescon and <PERSON>Ms. Bruce</PERSON>, whom he describes as his best critic,
routinely watch his evening segment together, and when a camera crew
showed up at his apartment to catch her response to his taped
proposal, he told her it was to shoot a promotional spot. But she
suspected something was up.
   ``I was real nervous,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Bruce</PERSON>, 31. ``I started eating
coleslaw. I don't even like coleslaw. I couldn't swallow and there
was this camera in front of me.''
   She said yes.
   ``It was odd,'' <PERSON>Ms. Bruce</PERSON> said of the proposal, ``but I'm really
happy.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A television personality's decision to
propose on the air didn't really surprise his girlfriend.
   <PERSON>Jed Mescon</PERSON> popped the question to <PERSON>Phyllis Bruce</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night
during ``Jed's Journal,'' his nightly feature segment WRCB-TV's
evening news broadcast.
   ``I feel like I owed <LOCATION>Chattanooga</LOCATION>. This is where I feel like I
became a professional and I wanted them to share in my joy,'' said
the 29-year-old <PERSON>Mescon</PERSON>.
   Mescon and <PERSON>Ms. Bruce</PERSON>, whom he describes as his best critic,
routinely watch his evening segment together, and when a camera crew
showed up at his apartment to catch her response to his taped
proposal, he told her it was to shoot a promotional spot. But she
suspected something was up.
   ``I was real nervous,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Bruce</PERSON>, 31. ``I started eating
coleslaw. I don't even like coleslaw. I couldn't swallow and there
was this camera in front of me.''
   She said yes.
   ``It was odd,'' <PERSON>Ms. Bruce</PERSON> said of the proposal, ``but I'm really
happy.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SOUTH BEND, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
