<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06107047 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06107047 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SCIENCE; HEALTH; QA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Q What is the "dew point" that they are always mentioning on weather reports?;
-- F.J. Hoffbauer,  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Science &amp; Medicine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DEW RECIPE: TAKE MOIST AIR AND CHILL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Q&amp;A  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  Fostoria, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>; A The dew point is the temperature at which moisture would
start to condense out of air if the air were cooled. The reason the moisture
condenses out is because warm air can hold more water vapor than cool air
can.;    Suppose you were in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> in the <DATE>summer</DATE>, and the temperature was 80
degrees, with <PERCENT>91 percent</PERCENT> humidity. That would mean the air had <PERCENT>91 percent</PERCENT> of
the maximum amount of water vapor it could hold at 80 degrees. But if you took
that air and cooled it to 77 degrees, it would no longer be able to hold all
that moisture, and water would begin to condense out, according to <ORGANIZATION>San Jose
State University</ORGANIZATION> meteorologist <PERSON>Peter Lester</PERSON>. At 77 degrees, you would have
reached the dew point.;    On the other hand, if you were in the <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>
desert on an 80-degree day, with <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> humidity, the dew point would be a
mere 28 degrees. You would have to chill that dry desert air to below freezing
before any water would condense out.;    Although the humidity varies with the
temperature, the dew point depends solely on the moisture content of the air.
For example, if you cooled that 80-degree desert air, its humidity would rise
steadily until it finally reached <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT> at the dew point temperature of
28 degrees. But all those temperatures and humidities along the way would have
the same dew point -- 28 degrees -- as long as the amount of water in the air
didn't change.;    Meteorologists use the dew point as one of many indicators
of what kind of weather to expect. High dew points, for example, are good
predictors of thunderstorms. And if the dew point is not far below the air
temperature, that means fog is likely when the temperature drops at night.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MARCIA BARINAGA, Special to the Mercury News  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910416  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  322  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday April 16, 1991
00107047,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881020-0243 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-20-88 0754EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-Japan-SeaRights ADV26   10-20 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Sea Rights, ADV 26,0528</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv26</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Wed PMs, Oct. 26, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Japan Shoring Up Two Rocks to Preserve Sea Rights</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PHIL BROWN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   So what if two tiny, faraway rocks crumble or sink
into the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>? <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> might lose fishing and mining rights to
155,000 square miles of ocean, that's what, so it is spending about
<MONEY>$236 million</MONEY> to shore them up.
   The rocks called <LOCATION>North Dew</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>East Dew</LOCATION>, each barely large
enough for a person to sleep on, are <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s southernmost points
and hold the key to treasure in this age of national
economic-control zones extending 200 miles from shore.
   Since <DATE>April</DATE>, about 200 workers using helicopters and
ship-mounted cranes have surrounded them with thousands of
four-pointed steel blocks, like anchors. The blocks form protective
circles 165 feet in diameter on a coral reef about 10 feet below
the surface 1,100 miles south of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Haruo Aoki</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Construction Ministry</ORGANIZATION>'s coastal department
said the work has cost <MONEY>17 billion yen</MONEY> (<MONEY>$134 million</MONEY>) so far and
total is expected to be <MONEY>30 billion yen</MONEY>. He said the circles will be
filled with concrete, beginning next year.
   At high tide, the rocks extend 3 to 10 feet above sea level. If
the tide should cover them, the reef no longer could be defined as
an island and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> no longer could claim a 200-mile economic zone
around it.
   That means the nation's southermost point would move about 300
miles north, between the <LOCATION>Volcano Islands</LOCATION> on the east and the
<LOCATION>Yaeyama Islands</LOCATION>.
   North Dew and <LOCATION>East Dew</LOCATION> are about a mile apart on the reef, which
was an island called <ORGANIZATION>Parece Vela</ORGANIZATION> when it appeared on 17th century
Spanish navigation charts.
   The Japanese call it Okinotorishima (Remote Bird Island) and
official records say it was put under <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s jurisdiction in <DATE>1931</DATE>.
It is recognized as Japanese in the World War II peace treaty.
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> declared a 200-mile exclusive economic zone around the
reef in <DATE>1977</DATE>, following the international trend to such areas of
control.
   Both rocks are shaped like mushrooms with thin stems attached to
the submerged reef, which is about three miles square. North Dew is
about 15{ feet in diameter and <LOCATION>East Dew</LOCATION> just over half that size.
   Agriculture Ministry figures say 2,577 tons of bonito, tuna and
other fish were caught in the 200-mile zone around them in <DATE>1985</DATE>,
<MONEY>$7 million</MONEY> at the current rate of exchange.
   No signs of oil have been reported but surveys are continuing to
determine whether mining of cobalt, nickel and other metals would
be feasible on the undersea mountain capped by the reef, said
<PERSON>Motohiko Kato</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>International Trade and Industry Ministry's
National Resources and Energy Agency</ORGANIZATION>.
   The mountain rises 16,400 to 19,700 feet from the ocean floor.
   No estimate has been made of how much <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> would lose if the
rocks slipped below the surface and the area around Okinotorishima
became international, an <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Ministry</ORGANIZATION> official said.
   End Adv for Wed PMs, <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06299035 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06299035 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Jack Foley -- Mercury News; SWEET NOTHINGS -- Dew Drop the cow
appears to be whispering, possibly where the next $5,000 cow patty will be
dropped, to Holly Henry, a volunteer in the Reading Program.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  GILROY; FARM; ANIMAL; WASTE; PRODUCT; ....; CHARITY; CHILDREN; READING; PROGRAM  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The Reading Program has enlisted the help of a Gilroy cow called Dew Drop to
help in an annual fund-raiser.;   The idea is that people buy squares of a big
field for $10 each, Dew Drop is let loose on the field, and if she drops a cow
patty on your square you win $5,000. Proceeds benefit the Reading Program, a
South County literacy project.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COW PATTIES FOR LITERACY: DEW DROP DOES HER PART  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Also ran on page 2B of the Morning Final.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Dew Drop is owned by <ORGANIZATION>Adams 4-H Club</ORGANIZATION> member <PERSON>Melissa Linden.</PERSON>;   Last year,
the effort grossed <MONEY>$10,600</MONEY> and netted <MONEY>$5,600</MONEY> for the literacy project after a
winner walked away with <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>, said <PERSON>Pat Barrett</PERSON> of The Reading Program.;  
This year, the pot's been sweetened. In addition to a chance at <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>, every
ticket buyer also automatically gets a chance to win a door prize, a new
Specialized off-road bicycle and helmet.;   It costs <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> per year to run
the <LOCATION>South County</LOCATION> office of The Reading Program, but only a portion of that
comes from the <LOCATION>Santa Clara County</LOCATION> library system. The rest must be raised
though grants and fund-raisers, <PERSON>Barrett</PERSON> said.;   All proceeds from the cow
patty bingo game will be used to support programs of the <LOCATION>South County</LOCATION> office,
<PERSON>Barrett</PERSON> said.;   The <LOCATION>South County</LOCATION> office runs a tutoring program for adults
that, on average, has about 50 volunteer tutors working one-on-one with
students, he said.;   In addition, the office operates pilot reading programs
for children at <ORGANIZATION>Jordan School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Gilroy</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>P.A. Walsh School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Morgan Hill.</LOCATION>;
  In those programs, volunteers read to children who may not be read to at
home in order to increase their interest and skills in reading, according to
Barrett.;   The cow patty bingo game will begin at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>San
Martin Pumpkin Patch</ORGANIZATION>, 13865 <LOCATION>Monterey Road</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Martin.</LOCATION>; IFYOU'RE INTERESTED;
Tickets may be purchased at the <ORGANIZATION>Pumpkin Patch</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> until <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME>, and
before that at 42 <ORGANIZATION>Martin St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Gilroy</LOCATION>, or by calling The Reading Program at
848-5366.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JACK FOLEY, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  South County  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911025  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  375  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, October 25, 1991
00299035,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-5873</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CCBBHABDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920302
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 MAR 92 / Arts: Two 'Beauties' - The Cullen Theater, Houston
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MAX LOPPERT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
It must have seemed a splendid idea at the time - and <LOCATION>Houston Grand Opera</LOCATION>
during <PERSON>David Gockley</PERSON>'s 20-year directorship, has consistently traded in
lively ideas about expanding the repertory, as the company track record
shows.
A specially commissioned new 'Beauty and the <LOCATION>Beast</LOCATION>' opera, Desert of Roses
by <PERSON>Robert Moran</PERSON>, was to be played in alternation with an updating of
<ORGANIZATION>Gretry</ORGANIZATION>'s 1771 Zemire et <PERSON>Azor</PERSON>, which has the same theme. Both the new and the
old version of the fairytale would have English texts, the Zemire (by
Marmontel) translated by <PERSON>John Michael LaChiusa</PERSON>, the Desert of Roses
librettist. Both would be staged by <PERSON>John Dew</PERSON>, the Englishman resident in
<LOCATION>Bielefeld</LOCATION>. The Zemire production had originally been devised for that city;
the <LOCATION>Desert</LOCATION> is due to make the journey there later in the year.
A plausible package - but this time, alas, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>'s luck in arranging such
things ran out, for the wrapping proved both flashy and ill-finished, and
the contents, though in themselves by no means valueless, had been
injudiciously selected.
Last <DATE>November</DATE> Dew gave Covent Garden audiences that wretchedly empty,
poorly-warmed-over Les Huguenots in modern dress. In similar vein he had
conceived of <ORGANIZATION>Gretry</ORGANIZATION>'s lovely, tender, sturdily fashioned opera-comique fable
(which Londoners remember from the <DATE>1981</DATE> Camden Festival revival) as an
exercise in pop updating, with the <LOCATION>Beast</LOCATION> as a rock-singer, <ORGANIZATION>Beauty</ORGANIZATION>'s father a
vacuum-cleaner salesman, and other bits and bobs of added Americana.
The taste level was pitched low - so low, in fact, that <PERSON>Gockley</PERSON> (who
apparently acquired the staging sight unseen) asked for 11th-hour
improvements and amendments. At this point Dew left town, and both shows,
still credited to him, were patched together by assistants.
This Zemire may have amused those spectators who find the whole notion of
opera got up to look like bad television killingly funny - Dew's borrowings
from game shows, celebrity interviews and rock spectaculars were of
unwavering predictability. But it was still a distressing example of
Producer's Patronage - of an audience presumed stupid enough, and a work
presumed trashy enough, to need 'help' of this kind. Apart from praising the
bright-toned Zemire of <PERSON>Diana Amos</PERSON>, and relishing the promise of another
young soprano, <PERSON>Kimla Beasley</PERSON>, as her sister Fatime, one is probably well
advised to pass over the whole sorry thing without further comment.
Desert of Roses had a lot more going for it. <PERSON>Moran</PERSON>, a 54-year-old American
avant-gardist previously best known for his humorous music-theatre
extravagances (such his <DATE>1971</DATE> Hallelujah for 20 marching bands, 40 church
choirs, organs, carillons, rock and gospel groups, and the entire city of
<LOCATION>Bethlehem</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>), has come to 'straight' opera via The Juniper Tree
(<DATE>1985</DATE>), which he composed in collaboration with <PERSON>Philip Glass</PERSON>, and which <ORGANIZATION>HGO</ORGANIZATION>
performed in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
He has stripped his 'Beauty' of conceptual posturing, experimentalist
pranks, and indeed of all avant-garderie; the score, written for
chamber-forces plus delicately used synthesisers, is catchy in what one
might call a minimalist-plus vein, with tootling um-cha-um-cha
accompaniments (well handled by the <ORGANIZATION>HGO</ORGANIZATION> music director <PERSON>John DeMain</PERSON>) layered
upon harmonies high in sugar content.
Moran writes well for voices, and knows how and where to place his numbers;
where he and <PERSON>LaChiusa</PERSON> showed their inexperience was in being seldom able to
get to the point, economically and quickly. Both on the comic family scenes
 -Beauty here has an ugly brother as well as two ugly sisters - and on those
of sentiment I found myself itching to wield an editor's pruning shears.
Because of this, and the sweet-toothed idiom, the whole work seemed blander
than it should or could have. But maybe the production was also to blame: it
was sad that the apt prettiness of the decor (designed by <PERSON>Heinz Balthes</PERSON>) had
not been matched by a similar aptness in the direction of the comedy
characters - gross clowning is clearly a John Dew trademark.
There were two fine young sopranos to note: <PERSON>Jayne West</PERSON> (Beauty) dewy-fresh
and appealing, <PERSON>Stella Zambalis</PERSON> (Woman, a narrator-chorus figure) strikingly
rich-toned. About this 'Beauty' at least, and for all its imperfections,
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> need feel no embarrassment.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 13 Photograph Patricia Johnson, Jayne West, Heidi Jones and Eric
Perkins in Desert of Roses (Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA012890-0166 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 168442 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 28, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 19; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
101 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NEWSWIRE: STUDENT SAYS MIAMI QUARTERBACK PUNCHED HIM 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
University of <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> quarterback <PERSON>Craig Erickson</PERSON> allegedly punched another 
student four or five times in the face in a fight over a girl, according to a 
complaint filed with campus police in <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jay Dewing</PERSON>, 20, was treated at a hospital for a black eye, a bloody lip and 
bruises about his forehead after the altercation <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at a campus bar. 
<PERSON>Dewing</PERSON> said he would press charges <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Erickson</PERSON> is 6-2, 196 pounds; <ORGANIZATION>Dewing</ORGANIZATION> is 5-9, 150. 
</P>
<P>
Dewing, who filed the complaint, said he used to date <PERSON>Erickson</PERSON>'s girlfriend and 
had talked with her about 20 minutes before the altercation. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ASSAULTS -- FLORIDA; FOOTBALL PLAYERS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-5900</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DIAB3ACOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930901
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 SEP 93 / People: Dew quits Thornton
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
The weekend departure of <PERSON>Peter Dew</PERSON> from his post of managing director at
<ORGANIZATION>Thornton</ORGANIZATION> group, the fund manager owned by <ORGANIZATION>Dresdner Bank</ORGANIZATION>, was 'entirely
amicable and friendly and to do with a change in the management system,'
according to <PERSON>Lord Peter Walker</PERSON>, the former cabinet minister who chairs the
group.
'There is no longer any real role for a conventional chief executive,' says
<PERSON>Lord Walker</PERSON>, who wants to see <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON> engage itself more actively in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, with funds jointly managed in, for example, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. 'We will be producing more European products and I see expansion
both there and in the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>.'
Dew has long been regarded as a leading figure in <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION> investment, and
joined <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON> in <DATE>1988</DATE> after a period running his own property business.
Among his positions before that had been a 16-year stint as director of
<ORGANIZATION>Mercury Asset Management</ORGANIZATION>.
<PERSON>Thornton</PERSON> has plans to acquire <ORGANIZATION>Aetna UK</ORGANIZATION>'s unit trust business and <ORGANIZATION>Lord Walker</ORGANIZATION>
says 'we will be making a number of other expansions and acquisitions, and I
want to bring in a younger generation to manage the business over the next
15 years or so. I have made sure that <PERSON>Peter Dew</PERSON> has been treated very
generously; the parting has been very amicable.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Thornton Management.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6722 Management Investment, Open-End.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 14
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-4596</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BDRBUAFRFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910418
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  18 APR 91 / Green issues sway investors
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JULIET SYCHRAVA
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
INSTITUTIONS consider a company's environmental record before deciding
whether to buy its shares, according to a survey released yesterday by <PERSON>Dewe
Rogerson</PERSON>, the public-relations and marketing group.
Dewe-Rogerson said that, of 80 senior fund managers interviewed, 40 per cent
said the question was an important factor in their decisions.
A further 58 per cent said a coherent and effective environmental strategy
enhanced their view of a company, Dewe-Rogerson continued.
It said 67 per cent believed environmental factors had a significant effect
on a company's business.
Only 11 per cent believed they were unimportant, said Dewe-Rogerson.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 9
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891005-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-05-89 1304EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Newspaper-Abortion     10-05 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Newspaper-Abortion,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Fires Woman for Anti-Abortion Activities</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYA L. WESLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A newsroom receptionist fired for her
anti-abortion activities, including picketing, says her rights have
been infringed, but the newspaper says her actions violated its
long-standing ethics policy.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Milwaukee Journal</ORGANIZATION>'s dismissal of <ORGANIZATION>Diane Dew</ORGANIZATION> has prompted the
filing of a grievance by the newspaper employees union, an
investigation by a state agency and complaints by a religious
freedom organization.
   But Deputy Managing Editor <PERSON>Howard Fibich</PERSON> said the Journal stands
by its decision to fire Ms. Dew even though The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> and
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Post did not discipline employees in similar
circumstances.
   ``She was part of the news process,'' <PERSON>Fibich</PERSON> said. ``She did not
report the news but she handled the news. She took dictation from
reporters and that type of thing.''
   The newspaper's ethics code, established in <DATE>1973</DATE>, prohibits
newsroom employees from participating in many outside political
activities and also from accepting gifts from outside sources, the
newspaper said.
   ``The reason that it (code) is there is to make sure that we are
able to maintain an image of objectivity,'' <PERSON>Fibich</PERSON> said. ``In my
judgment, our credibility is a precious asset and nothing must
compromise that.''
   Attorney <PERSON>Craig Parshall</PERSON>, who represents <PERSON>Ms. Dew</PERSON>, said his client
was fired as a part-time receptionist-secretary in <DATE>July</DATE> after she
refused to sign a statement promising to end her anti-abortion
activities.
   <PERSON>Parshall</PERSON> said <PERSON>Ms. Dew</PERSON>'s activities were brought to the
newspaper's attention after a reporter saw her participating in an
anti-abortion protest.
   <PERSON>Ms. Dew</PERSON> said she feels compelled to protest abortion and that
the newspaper's restrictions violate her right to free speech and
religion.
   ``I can't just choose not to believe what I believe,'' she said.
``I'm responsible to speak out because I feel that abortion is
murder and murder is wrong.''
   <PERSON>Bob Dye</PERSON>, communications manager for <ORGANIZATION>Journal-Sentinel Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the
newspaper's parent company, said <PERSON>Ms. Dew</PERSON> was warned that her
actions violated the ethics code and was offered another job
outside the newsroom with no loss in pay, but turned it down.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Rutherford Institute</ORGANIZATION>, a Milwaukee-area group that
specializes in cases of religious liberty, filed a religious
discrimination complaint on <PERSON>Ms. Dew</PERSON>'s behalf.
   The <ORGANIZATION>State Equal Rights Division</ORGANIZATION> is investigating to determine if
<PERSON>Ms. Dew</PERSON> was a victim of discrimination, said <PERSON>John Kimble</PERSON>, program
supervisor of investigation in the agency <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION> office. If the
division finds there is probable cause to rule discrimination
occurred, the case will go to a hearing, he said.
   The <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION> chapter of the <ORGANIZATION>Newspaper Guild</ORGANIZATION>, a labor union,
filed a grievance with the Journal challenging the dismissal.
   ``We argued that her activities were protected by our contract
and that the company violated the contract by trying to force upon
her a different set of working conditions,'' local president <PERSON>Mike
Kuchta</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Fibich</PERSON> said <PERSON>Ms. Dew</PERSON>'s position on abortion played no role in her
dismissal. If she was a pro-choice activist the newspaper would
have taken the same action, he said.
   He cited an abortion rights march in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> <DATE>last spring</DATE> in
which reporters from the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Post
participated.
   ``I thought that was unacceptable,'' he said. ``If it had
happened here, the people involved would have been somehow
reprimanded.''
   Times editors disagreed with <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> correspondent <PERSON>Linda
Greenhouse</PERSON>'s decision to participate in the march, but they took no
punitive action, Assistant Managing Editor <PERSON>Warren Hoge</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Richard Harwood</PERSON>, ombudsman at the <ORGANIZATION>Post</ORGANIZATION>, said no disciplinary
action was taken against the few reporters who were involved in the
abortion rights march.
   ``People were reminded that this was inappropriate and that you
are not to take part in political activities if you work for The
Washington Post,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Harwood</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Post</ORGANIZATION>'s ethics code does not mention newsroom
secretaries and he could not say for certain if they are bound by
the code.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021189-0102 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 17211 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 11, 1989, Saturday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 16; Column 2 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
420 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
RALLY EARNS CAMARILLO SHARE OF TITLE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TIM BROWN, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Now that <ORGANIZATION>Camarillo High</ORGANIZATION> has won its half of the <ORGANIZATION>Marmonte League</ORGANIZATION> title, is it 
too late to start asking questions about these guys? 
</P>
<P>
Somewhere, an "inquiry" light is still flashing after the Scorpions' 65-57 win 
over <LOCATION>Newbury Park</LOCATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Newbury Park</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Scorpions have actually won their photo finish with co-champion <LOCATION>Simi 
Valley</LOCATION>. Based on a league point system, <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> (17-6, 9-3) will be the 
league's top-seeded team in the upcoming playoffs. 
</P>
<P>
But what about those questions? 
</P>
<P>
Is <PERSON>David Harbour</PERSON>, who leads the team in scoring and assists and is among the 
leaders in rebounding, really a sophomore? How many years did he stay back, 
anyhow? 
</P>
<P>
And how about point guard <PERSON>Rick Schnell</PERSON>? Why has nobody heard of his defense, 
his ballhandling? 
</P>
<P>
Did forwards <PERSON>Jason Hunt</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Scott Foster</ORGANIZATION> teethe on barbells as infants? These 
two look like they could bench-press the team bus. Heck, slap another Yugo on 
each side of the bar. 
</P>
<P>
And forward <PERSON>Frank Dews</PERSON>? The guy is too consistent. Mix in an off-game, <PERSON>Frank</PERSON>. 
Only Hunt and <PERSON>Dews</PERSON> are seniors. Is it too late to break up the Scorpions? 
</P>
<P>
Too late, perhaps, for the league, as <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> became the first team in four 
years other than <LOCATION>Simi Valley</LOCATION> to earn part of the league title. Against <ORGANIZATION>Newbury 
Park</ORGANIZATION>, the Scorpions did it with <PERSON>Harbour</PERSON>, who scored 23 points, including six of 
13 shots from three-point range. And <PERSON>Dews</PERSON>, who added 16, two from 12 feet away 
with 1:55 left that gave <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> a 58-54 lead. 
</P>
<P>
And Foster, who had 12 rebounds plus a layup with 12 seconds remaining to seal 
the win. And <PERSON>Schnell</PERSON>, who scored a sneaky 12 points. And Hunt, who played 
rugged defense despite a badly bruised right hamstring. 
</P>
<P>
All so simple? Not really. Newbury Park, led by <PERSON>Wayne Cook</PERSON>'s 20 points and 11 
rebounds, trailed, <DATE>45-35</DATE>, but rallied to take a 52-51 lead with 5:38 left on 
<ORGANIZATION>Cook</ORGANIZATION>'s 16-foot jump shot. 
</P>
<P>
However, free throws by <PERSON>Dews</PERSON> and Foster and <LOCATION>Harbour</LOCATION>'s sixth three-point basket 
gave the Scorpions a 56-52 lead they never relinquished. Harbour, who had 
struggled for two games, had finally broken out. 
</P>
<P>
Said Coach <PERSON>John Harbour</PERSON>: "He came through and hit some big shots for us. He 
(always) thinks he's going to make the next five. And that's a quality you've 
got to have." 
</P>
<P>
Certainly so against <ORGANIZATION>Newbury Park</ORGANIZATION> (13-10, 4-8), which but for some poor 
free-throw shooting (the <ORGANIZATION>Panthers</ORGANIZATION> missed the front end of five one-and-one 
opportunities), could have upset the Scorpions. 
</P>
<P>
The inquiry light, by the way, is out. Camarillo is heading to the payoff 
window. Or should that be playoff window? 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Shane Gallimore, left, of Newbury Park barges through a pack of 
Camarillo defenders in the second quarter Friday night. DAVID BOHRER / Los 
Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-3264</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DLIC6AFIFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931209
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  09 DEC 93 / International Company News: Pernod trades a whiskey for a
whisky
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN RIDDING and REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PARIS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Pernod Ricard</LOCATION>, the French drinks group, yesterday announced it would swap
one of its Irish whiskey brands for a Canadian whisky owned by <ORGANIZATION>Allied-Lyons</ORGANIZATION>
of the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>.
The French group said the exchange of <LOCATION>Tullamore Dew</LOCATION> for Royal Canadian would
allow it to expand its range of whiskies. It currently owns several Irish
whiskeys, including Jamesons and Bushmills; Scotch whiskies such as Abelour;
and a bourbon, <LOCATION>Wild Turkey</LOCATION>. However it does not have a Canadian whisky
brand.
The deal will also give <ORGANIZATION>Allied-Lyons</ORGANIZATION> its first Irish whiskey. 'It is a niche
premium brand which does well in international duty free,' said the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>
group. 'It is a good addition to our portfolio.'
The deal involves only the distribution of the whiskies. Pernod's
subsidiary, <ORGANIZATION>Irish Distillers</ORGANIZATION>, will continue to produce <ORGANIZATION>Tullamore Dew</ORGANIZATION>, while
<ORGANIZATION>Allied-Lyons</ORGANIZATION> will produce Royal Canadian. The Canadian whisky brand is
currently distributed by <PERSON>Hiram Walker</PERSON>, a subsidiary of the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> group.
Pernod said it would also receive payment for <ORGANIZATION>Tullamore Dew</ORGANIZATION> since it was
more profitable than Royal Canadian. However it declined to disclose the
amount.
Pernod's whisky business is its second-largest division, in terms of sales,
after its aperitif drink. The company said whisky was one of the fastest
growing segments of the French drinks market, although demand remained
depressed in international markets.
L'Union des Assurances de <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> (UAP), the French insurance group, announced
yesterday that the advisory banks for its privatisation were to be <ORGANIZATION>Banque
Lazard</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Banque Nationale de Paris</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Banque Worms</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Reuter</ORGANIZATION> reports from
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>UAP</ORGANIZATION> flotation is likely to go ahead after the sale of <LOCATION>Elf Aquitaine</LOCATION>,
scheduled for early <DATE>1994</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Pernod-Ricard.
    Allied-Lyons.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>FRZ  France, EC.
    GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2085 Distilled and Blended Liquors.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Company News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 29
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06124058 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06124058 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Sen. Ken Maddy; ... 'On business back East'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  CALIFORNIA; CONGRESS; OFFICIAL; TRIP; KENTUCKY; HORSE; RACING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  State Senate Republican leader Ken Maddy, a horse-racing buff, was excused for
official legislative business Thursday for an out-of-state trip that coincides
with this weekend's running of the Kentucky Derby.;    A Maddy spokesman, Carl
DeWing, denied knowing exactly where the Fresno lawmaker was and said only
that Maddy had been on "official business back East." DeWing referred other
questions to a Maddy aide who did not return telephone calls.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  RULES PANEL OKS ABSENCE OF DERBY FAN  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     But two other legislators and a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> staff member confirmed <PERSON>Maddy</PERSON> had
gone out of state to investigate horse racing issues and planned to be in
<LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> for at least part of the trip. The <ORGANIZATION>Kentucky Derby</ORGANIZATION>, the nation's most
prestigious horse race, is <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Churchill Downs</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Louisville.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Sen.
Bill Leonard</PERSON>, R-Upland, said he believed <PERSON>Maddy</PERSON> had gone to <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> to
study an innovative satellite racing system and planned to be in <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> over
the <LOCATION>weekend.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Maddy</PERSON> has attended the annual Kentucky Derby in past years.; 
  The excusal of <PERSON>Maddy</PERSON> for official business, which was approved by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate
Rules Committee</ORGANIZATION>, means he can continue to collect his legislative per diem
payments.;    <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> President Pro Tem <PERSON>David Roberti</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Los Angeles</LOCATION>, said he
didn't know if <PERSON>Maddy</PERSON> would actually claim the per diem money for all or part
of his trip. But <PERSON>Roberti</PERSON> said <PERSON>Maddy</PERSON> was not using other <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> funds to
finance his travels.;    <PERSON>DeWing</PERSON> said he was confident that <PERSON>Maddy</PERSON> would not
claim the expense money for any time he spent at the derby.;    <ORGANIZATION>Maddy</ORGANIZATION> missed a
long <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> floor session <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in which several senators had trouble
finding enough members to vote for their bills and motions.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  McClatchy News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Sacramento  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910503  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  285  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday May 3, 1991
00124058,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-10202</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CG4BOAE1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920731
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  31 JUL 92 / Coal adviser
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
THE government will appoint <PERSON>Dewe Rogerson</PERSON>, the marketing and communication
agency, as its adviser on the privatisation of British Coal, the <ORGANIZATION>Department
of Trade and Industry</ORGANIZATION> confirmed yesterday. Dewe <PERSON>Rogerson</PERSON> also advised the
government on the electricity privatisation.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-1729</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CLPCOAFQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921216
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 DEC 92 / Observer: Changing times
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
What are we to make of the government's decision to find a new public
relations and marketing adviser for the sale of its next tranche of <ORGANIZATION>BT</ORGANIZATION>
shares? With the reappointment of <ORGANIZATION>S G Warburg</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Linklaters &amp; Paines</ORGANIZATION>, it
looked as if the government intended to use the same old team of advisers.
However, it has replaced <PERSON>Dewe Rogerson</PERSON>, the undoubted pr king of the
privatisation world, with <ORGANIZATION>Brunswick</ORGANIZATION>, a relative upstart in the business. It
seems that the <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> simply wanted a change. But in the candyfloss world
of the pr merchants, it will be seen as a big blow for <ORGANIZATION>Dewe Rogerson</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920311-0059
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920311-0059.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Business Brief -- ITT Corp.:
   Air Force Awards Contract
   To Operate Radar Outposts
</HL>
<DATE>
03/11/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B4
</SO>
<CO>
   ITT
</CO>
<MS>
CONGLOMERATES (CGL)
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
AEROSPACE (ARO)
CONGLOMERATES (CGL)
</IN>
<NS>
DEFENSE CONTRACTS (DFC)
</NS>
<GV>
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF)
</GV>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   ITT Corp. said it received a one-year, $100 million
contract to continue operation and maintenance of the Distant
Early Warning Line, a string of 10 radar system outposts in
the Arctic Circle.
   The DEW Line, in operation since 1957, provides tactical
warning against manned bomber and cruise missile threats. New
York-based ITT has managed the system since it was
established, except for a three-year period in the mid-1970s.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The contract was awarded by the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Tactical Air
Command</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Langley Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> to <ORGANIZATION>ITT Federal
Services Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, part of the <ORGANIZATION>ITT Defense Inc.</ORGANIZATION> unit.
   An <ORGANIZATION>ITT</ORGANIZATION> spokesman noted that the existing DEW Line is
expected to be replaced with new technology in <DATE>1994</DATE>, a
contract on which <ORGANIZATION>ITT</ORGANIZATION> expects to bid.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871111-0116 </DOCNO>
<HL> What Is Our Man
Doing on Golf Course
At 4 in the Morning?
---
He Is Angling to Hook Up
With Some Dew Worms,
But They Turn on Him
---
By Gary Lamphier
<DD> 11/11/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> ARVA, Ontario  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It is <TIME>4 a.m.</TIME> on the front nine at <ORGANIZATION>Sunningdale Country Club</ORGANIZATION> with not a golfer in sight. 

   A can of worms is strapped to my right ankle, a can of sawdust to my left. 
A miner's lamp glows on my forehead as I hunt for my quarry: "Lumbricus terrestris," the Canadian dew worm, the American night crawler. 

   He is everywhere -- poking out of his burrow, lolling on the stubby grass, playing chicken with his predators, of which I am one. 

   I step gingerly, dip dewy fingers into sawdust for a better grip on the slimy creatures, crouch low and pinch. 
Fffft. 
A worm zips through my fingers and underground, leaving a sticky mucus as his calling card. 
"You don't know how to pick," scolds <PERSON>Ola Przyszlak</PERSON>, a sturdy woman who does. 
She will round up 3,000 worms tonight while I snag fewer than 50, not counting ones I accidentally tear in two. 

   Several thousand pickers like <PERSON>Mrs. Przyszlak</PERSON> hunt for worms starting in <DATE>April</DATE> and continuing until about now on golf courses and pastures in southern <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>. 
They catch about half the 2.5 billion worms that American anglers buy each year, says <PERSON>Alan Tomlin</PERSON>, the Canadian government's lone worm researcher. 
As a Canadian crop, dew worms aren't in a class with wheat, say, but they are "larger than <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s onion business, almost as big as tomatoes," he says. 

   Though worms help to aerate and mix the soil, they are generally reviled by all except the Maoris of <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, who consider certain varieties delicacies, and anglers, who revere them as bait for freshwater fish from bass to catfish. 
Worms hereabouts swarm to the surface on mild, damp nights, to soak up oxygen through their slimy skins. 
When conditions are just right, as after a rain, a top picker can grab 20,000 and earn about <MONEY>$380</MONEY>. 
But tonight is too hot and dry. 
Our dozen-member crew collects only 10,000 worms. 
My three wriggling handfuls bring about <MONEY>95 cents</MONEY>. 

   Picking worms is nauseating, backbreaking toil. 
"At least you didn't get sick," <PERSON>Mrs. Przyszlak</PERSON> tells me, recalling one first-time picker who did. 
The work is done mainly by Vietnamese and other new immigrants. 
As with the Hungarians who many say started <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s worm trade in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> or the Greeks and <LOCATION>South Koreans</LOCATION> who followed, the dew worm is their slippery ticket to a better life. 

   "No worms in <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. 
No business," says <PERSON>Bohdan Ciekanski</PERSON>, a bearded former tool-and-die maker who has been in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> just three weeks and is learning grassroots capitalism. 
"We are miners," he jokes, tapping his headlamp. 

   This can be underground work in other ways. 
The Canadian worm industry has no association, no regulators, no statistics and a wary view of outsiders. 
"A lot of these people don't pay taxes and don't want to advertise it," says <PERSON>Joseph Hubert</PERSON>, a worm wholesaler who stores his livestock in a warehouse under a <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> expressway. 

   One of the few places worm traders surface is the Cafe Santan, a spartan coffee bar sandwiched between a real-estate office and women's clothing shop in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>'s Greek neighborhood. 
Cafe Santan is the Comex of the worm world. 

   One morning, the surrounding streets are lined with dozens of boxy <PERSON>Dodge Maxivans</PERSON>, the trucks preferred for ferrying crews and worms to and from picking sites, sometimes 150 miles away. 
"After a good night, there might be 15 million worms on the street," says <PERSON>Carole Lynch</PERSON>, who runs a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>, wholesale business with her husband, <PERSON>Larry Hurlbut</PERSON>. 

   Almost 100 worm brokers and wholesalers crowd the coffee shop and the sidewalk outside, for one-on-one bargaining over the cargo in the trucks. 
Some shout and wave their arms, some whisper urgently. 
The same worms may change hands several times in a morning, and the wholesale price may move as much as <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> in a day. 
This season's price paid to wholesalers typically was <MONEY>$35</MONEY> or more for a thousand worms (in terms of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar), representing a markup almost <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> from the price paid to pickers. 
By the time the worms reach fishermen in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, the price typically exceeds <MONEY>$1</MONEY> a dozen, or <MONEY>$83</MONEY> a thousand. 

   Brokers buy and sell worms in a hurry because they don't have a place to store them. 
Wholesalers operate refrigerated warehouses where they store styrofoam cartons of dirt and hibernating worms. 

   The worms snuggle in their cartons as long as they think the sun is shining. 
But a stampede can start if someone accidentally turns off the warehouse lights. 
When that happened in <PERSON>Mr. Hurlbut</PERSON>'s warehouse, he says, he found 50,000 worms all over the floor and three or four feet up the walls. 

   For wholesalers with fixed costs, price fluctuations can be murder. 
<PERSON>George Alifagonis</PERSON> says his wholesale business went belly up in <DATE>1982</DATE> when he bought high-priced worms he couldn't sell. 

   Pickers face risks, too. 
Bulls in the pasture, for instance. 
"They chase our people. 
The animals are so big and our people are so small," says the Vietnamese foreman of my worm-picking crew. 

   More worrisome are worm thieves and poachers who gate-crash on pastures or golf courses leased to legitimate operators. 
<PERSON>Mr. Hurlbut</PERSON> says he pays about <MONEY>$2,275</MONEY> to lease a course like <LOCATION>Sunningdale</LOCATION> from dusk to dawn for a season. 
When poachers show up, fights can erupt. 
"That's a good part of the reason I have Goliath," says <PERSON>Mr. Hurlbut</PERSON>, patting his German shepherd. 

   Police in <LOCATION>Chatham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>, say marauders broke through the concrete wall of a warehouse there this <DATE>summer</DATE> and stole 200,000 worms. 

   Worms are picked commercially in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, mostly in <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>. 
Some <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> producers even use electric rods that somehow coax worms to come up. 
But, says <PERSON>Wayne King</PERSON>, a wholesaler in <LOCATION>Canton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, "there's more worms go into <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> after a good night's picking than all the worms produced in <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> in a whole year." 

   Why is this corner of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> so blessed with worms? 
<PERSON>Mr. Tomlin</PERSON>, the government researcher, believes <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s thick winter snow cover protects dew worms from predators and helps them live longer, multiply faster, and grow bigger than other worms. 
Because dew worms snooze for months in refrigerated coolers at temperatures that would kill other varieties of worms, he says, "Shelf life goes up -- you can ship them great distances." 

   <PERSON>Robert Lytle</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, wholesaler, says hotter, drier summers in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> limit worm picking except in the <DATE>spring</DATE> and <DATE>fall</DATE>. 
"Our season is short, so we can't attract people" to pick, he says. 
"There's more of a professional worm catcher in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>." 

   But <PERSON>Mr. Alifagonis</PERSON>, who now works for the bait-wholesaling business of his brother, <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>, says worms are getting harder to find in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and they are smaller than they used to be. 
"Something is wrong," he says, tugging his graying beard. 
"It must be the acid rain." 

   He also worries about a deteriorating work ethic. 
"You don't see young people picking worms. 
They want the easy life. 
I don't know what's going to happen with this generation," he frets. 
But after early stints as a cab driver and construction worker, he says, he plans to stay in the business he has been in for 17 years. 
"You know any work that's not hard?" he asks. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122990-0135 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 328893 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 29, 1990, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 11A; Column 5; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
413 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO SPORTS ET CETERA: HOST UCSD WOMEN WIN THEIR TOURNAMENT OPENER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Lisa Beaver</PERSON> scored 18 points and had 11 rebounds to lead UC <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to a 
59-45 victory over <LOCATION>Wheaton College</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>) in the first round of the three-day 
UCSD women's basketball tournament at <ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Cari Young</PERSON> added 14 points and led <ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION> with 14 rebounds. Sue <PERSON>Lankford</PERSON> scored 
11 points and <PERSON>Steph Higgins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jen Landry</PERSON> each had nine for <PERSON>Wheaton</PERSON> (5-2). 
</P>
<P>
UCSD (5-3) had a 28-24 halftime lead. 
</P>
<P>
St. Thomas (<ORGANIZATION>St. Paul</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>) built on a 11-point halftime lead to defeat 
<PERSON>William Smith Colleg</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>), 91-49. <PERSON>Laurie Trow</PERSON> scored 27 points and 
<PERSON>Suzi Bouquet</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ellen Hanson</PERSON> each scored 15 for <ORGANIZATION>St. Thomas</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Jill Brower</PERSON> led 
<PERSON>William Smith</PERSON> with 15 points. 
</P>
<P>
Millikin (<LOCATION>Decatur</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>) came back from a six-point deficit at halftime to 
defeat <ORGANIZATION>Smith College</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>North Hampton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>), 93-79. <ORGANIZATION>Smith College</ORGANIZATION>, which took a 
37-31 halftime lead, was led by <PERSON>Phoebe Jacob</PERSON> with 27 points. <PERSON>Barb Blume</PERSON> scored 
19 points for <LOCATION>Millikin</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>University of Scranton (Penn.</ORGANIZATION>) defeated <ORGANIZATION>Carroll College</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Wisc.</LOCATION>), 47-43. <PERSON>Karri 
Sears</PERSON> led <PERSON>Carroll</PERSON> with 14 points. 
</P>
<P>
San <ORGANIZATION>Diego State</ORGANIZATION> defeated visiting UC-Riverside, 94-61. Michelle Miles led <ORGANIZATION>SDSU</ORGANIZATION> 
with 31 points. Kieishsha <PERSON>Garnes</PERSON> added 19 points and led the Aztecs (5-4) with 
11 points. UC-Riverside (7-7) was led by <PERSON>Wendy Fleischer</PERSON> with 35. 
</P>
<P>
MEN'S BASKETBALL 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Neil Derrick</PERSON> scored 27 points to lead <ORGANIZATION>Washington State</ORGANIZATION> to a 103-78 victory over 
<LOCATION>UC San Diego</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Pullman</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash</LOCATION>. The Tritons (8-3) were led by <PERSON>Tim Rapp</PERSON>'s 20 
points and nine rebounds, while <PERSON>Gordon McNeill</PERSON> scored 12 points. <ORGANIZATION>Washington 
State</ORGANIZATION> also got 20 points from <PERSON>Terrence Lewis</PERSON>, 16 from <PERSON>Bennie Seltzer</PERSON> and 10 
rebounds from <PERSON>Ken Critton</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The Cougars blew the game open midway through the first half, scoring 10 
unanswered points to take a 28-13 lead. Derrick scored eight of those 10 
points. 
</P>
<P>
The Cougars never trailed and led by as many as 32 points late in the second 
half. 
</P>
<P>
It was the third time <ORGANIZATION>Washington State</ORGANIZATION> topped the 100-point mark this season 
and the first time in 25 years the Cougars have had three 100-plus games in a 
single season. 
</P>
<P>
Point <ORGANIZATION>Loma Nazarene College</ORGANIZATION> won its second round game by defeating <ORGANIZATION>Northwest 
Nazarene</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Nampa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ida</LOCATION>.), 80-69, in the <ORGANIZATION>Nazarene College Holiday Classic</ORGANIZATION> at 
<LOCATION>Olathe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan</LOCATION>. PLNC (7-4) was led by <PERSON>Frank Dews</PERSON> with 22 points and <PERSON>Mark Bulgin</PERSON> 
with 21. <PERSON>John Greer</PERSON> added 13 points and led the team with 12 rebounds. PLNC was 
26 for 30 from the free throw line and <PERSON>Dews</PERSON> went six for six. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Rick Sulvason</PERSON> scored 18 points and <PERSON>Mark Smith</PERSON> added 12 for <ORGANIZATION>Northwest</ORGANIZATION> (3-9). 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06333075 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06333075 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (4); PHOTO: Innocent-looking pitcher plant gobbles unsuspecting
insects.; PHOTO:; How they eat: A cephalotus pitcher plant, top, "yawns" to
invite unsuspecting insects to become its food; PHOTO: the Portuguese dewy
pine, above, smothers insects with sticky sap. (Color); PHOTO: Insects rarely
escape from the sticky dew of the spider sundew (Color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  INSECT; FOOD; PLANT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IF A hell for insects exists, surely its most infernal pit is California
Carnivores.;   The 1-year-old greenhouse in Forestville sells only
insect-eating flora, and its inhabitants wreak death in ways that would shock
even Bret Easton Ellis.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Garden  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EAT A BUG
THIS NURSERY FULL OF INNOCENT-LOOKING, EXOTIC
PLANTS IS A NOT-SO-LITTLE SHOP OF CARNIVORES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cover Story  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Under a blazing <LOCATION>Sonoma County</LOCATION> sun, 340 varieties spend their days
paralyzing, strangling, drowning and dissolving hapless bugs.;   The founder,
<PERSON>Peter D'Amato</PERSON>, has not escaped from these hearty eaters since <DATE>1965</DATE>. He was 10
when he found several specimens growing in a bog near his home in southern <LOCATION>New
Jersey.</LOCATION>;   "There's something hypnotic about them," he said. "They're always
involved in some kind of drama. I have to keep reminding myself that they
can't think.";   He is devoted not only to growing and selling carnivorous
plants -- many of which grow easily in <LOCATION>South Bay</LOCATION> climates -- but also to
improving their image, which has been sullied in recent years by movies such
as "Little Shop of Horrors.";   None of his wares, however, bring to mind the
grotesque potted man-eater in that film. Rather, they appear deceptively
innocent.;   The bladderworts look fragile on the surface, with dainty
blossoms nodding on wire-thin stalks. But underground, fast-moving suction
cups are lapping up nematodes.;   The sundews seem equally innocuous. They
resemble scrawny, long-armed cactuses misted with glistening dew -- a "dew" so
gluey that insects rarely break away from its grasp.;   Once the dew secures a
victim, the plant's arm slowly curls around the creature and consumes it with
a secretion of digestive juice.;   Only the nepenthes (nuh-PEN-theeze), loopy
tropical vines strung with potato-size pods full of liquid enzymes -- look
capable of violence.;   Purple veins streak their pods, and rows of horizontal
thorns run up the corners of the pods, serving as tiny ladders that lead bugs
and sometimes mice to doom.;   Despite these aggressive meal-acquisition
tools, no one was sure plants could eat insects until the <DATE>1860s</DATE>, when <PERSON>Charles
Darwin</PERSON> began experimenting with botanical carnivores.;   Sundews, he wrote at
the time, interested him more "than the origin of all the species in the
world." He spent years figuring out what and how they consumed.;   "He'd feed
them hard-boiled egg, which they will eat," <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> said. "They'll even eat
chocolate and cheese, which gives them indigestion.";   Thanks to <PERSON>Darwin</PERSON>'s
discoveries -- and thanks to improved glassmaking and heating technology,
which made greenhouses possible -- Victorians took a fancy to carnivores in
general and nepenthes in particular.;   The voracious vines gorged on indoor
pests until fuel shortages in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> during World War I
killed all but a few collections.;   Interest in them flagged until the <DATE>1970s</DATE>,
when back-to-nature enthusiasts flirted with almost every form of interior
greenery. But carnivores did not enjoy a long return to the limelight, mainly
because they often disappointed their inexperienced owners by dying.;   "It's
tricky to get the conditions right: the soil, the water, the humidity, the
light," said <PERSON>Geoff Wong</PERSON>, a long-time collector of carnivorous plants and a
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Carnivores customer. His most frustrating possession is a nepenthes
that adapted to life 9,000 feet up in <LOCATION>Borneo.</LOCATION>;   "It's 10 years old and one
inch wide, and in its natural state, it would be 10 feet high," said <PERSON>Wong</PERSON>, who
is a research chemist in <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. Although the plant is only a few inches
high, "people tell me I should be happy it isn't dead." D'Amato owns another
aged example of the same plant, also an inch wide and a few inches high.;  
"It's a matter of finding out what's important to them," said <PERSON>Bill Baumgartl</PERSON>,
a physician in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> who owns 30 carnivorous plants and frequents
<ORGANIZATION>California Carnivores</ORGANIZATION>. "They're very sensitive to soil pH, and you have to
water them with distilled water and you have to fertilize very carefully.";  
But <PERSON>Marilee Maertz</PERSON>, the greenhouse's general manager, who has accidentally
killed countless other houseplants and has mistaken the word "Dieffenbachia"
for a disease, finds carnivores easy to please. "Only once in a while do we
lose somebody," she said.;   She is a former ship inspector; <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> is a
former design engineer for <PERSON>Levi Strauss</PERSON>, and they have been friends since
<DATE>1973.</DATE>;   In <DATE>1989</DATE>, they displayed <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON>'s private collection at a garden show
in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, just for fun, and were swamped by purchase offers.;   To
sate the public's appetite, they set up a shop of carnivores. "We felt
terrible saying, 'Yeah, these are great, but you can't have any,' " she said.;
  According to the <ORGANIZATION>International Carnivorous Plant Society</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>California
Carnivores</ORGANIZATION> is the newest and one of the largest of the dozen all-carnivorous
retail nurseries in the country.;   Their 2,000-square-foot greenhouse stands
on the grounds of a winery; it once sheltered weeds used in allergy research.
It looks more like a botanical museum than a store: A half-dozen crowded
planters with long textual panels line one aisle, depicting the ways
carnivores can congregate in their natural settings.;   Several sundews spill
out of a green pottery horn of plenty. A baby sundew in the saddle of a pink
china horse will someday make its host resemble Pegasus.;   "Bizarre pots for
bizarre plants," said <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON>, who skips off in midsentence to mist a
nepenthes.;   School groups often tour the shop, as do the curious. Despite
the long hours of describing the wonders of carnivores and despite frequent
pleas to set off a Venus flytrap (requests that are usually ignored, since
flytraps hate to be teased), the staff members never tire of their subject.;  
"To this day," <PERSON>D'Amato</PERSON> said, "the simplest sundew still puts me in a state of
amazement."; IFYOU'RE INTERESTED; <ORGANIZATION>California Carnivores</ORGANIZATION> is located at <LOCATION>Mark
West Vineyards</LOCATION>, 7000 Trenton-Healsburg Road, <LOCATION>Forestville</LOCATION>, 95436; (707)
838-1630. The nursery is open daily <DATE>March through November</DATE>, but they recommend
calling ahead for a visit during the winter months.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  EVE M. KAHN, New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911128  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,030  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, November 28, 1991
00333075,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061390-0121 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 233021 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 13, 1990, Wednesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 6; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
570 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
'VERY MINOR' OIL SPILL HITS THE BEACH AT BOLSA CHICA; 
</P>
<P>
POLLUTION: OFFSHORE RIGS ARE SUSPECTED, BUT THE SOURCE IS UNCERTAIN. CLEANUP 
BEGINS ON FOULED STRETCH OVER A MILE LONG. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JEFFREY A. PERLMAN and MATT LAIT, TIMES STAFF WRITERS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HUNTINGTON BEACH 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
At least 168 gallons of oil fouled more than a mile of <ORGANIZATION>Bolsa Chica State Beach</ORGANIZATION> 
early <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> and investigators said leaking offshore oil rigs may be 
the source of the spill, <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> officials said. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> Lt. <PERSON>Vincent Campos</PERSON> said an emergency cleanup crew hired by <ORGANIZATION>Unocal</ORGANIZATION>, 
which operates three offshore oil platforms in the area, was dispatched to the 
scene. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a very minor spill," <PERSON>Campos</PERSON> said. "We don't have anything from Fish and 
Game yet, but it may have involved a couple of birds." 
</P>
<P>
Bolsa Chica is located just north of the main stretch of <LOCATION>Huntington Beach</LOCATION> that 
was soiled when almost 400,000 gallons of crude oil spewed from the crippled 
tanker American Trader 1.3 miles offshore in <DATE>February</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Although <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s spill was minor by comparison, it was enough to leave a mile 
and a quarter of the state beach covered with small patches of oil. Petty 
Officer <PERSON>Lindsay Dew</PERSON> said the heaviest patch was an eighth of a mile long, in 
some sections 12 to 15 feet wide. 
</P>
<P>
Several <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> officials estimated the total amount of oil spilled at four 
barrels, or 168 gallons, which they said can easily spread over large areas of 
ocean in a thin film. By <DATE>late Tuesday</DATE>, officials stressed the spill appeared to 
be minor. 
</P>
<P>
"We know of no animal life being affected," said Dew. "The oil has all washed 
up on shore. We don't believe there's any left in the water." 
</P>
<P>
State and federal wildlife officials were not immediately available for 
comment, but officials at the scene said only one duck had been found covered 
in oil. However, the grunion were supposed to run overnight and they too could 
be affected, officials said. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>California Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> and Game also dispatched a team to take 
samples of the sand and to observe wildlife in the area. 
</P>
<P>
Although the source of the spill was not yet determined, <ORGANIZATION>Unocal</ORGANIZATION> decided to take 
responsibility for the cleanup. Company spokesman <PERSON>Barry Lane</PERSON> said the firm's 
emergency crews would work with shovels to remove the contaminated sand by the 
sackful. He said the company took on the job because "We operate in that area 
and we have people there." 
</P>
<P>
A <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said a 20-person cleanup crew from <LOCATION>Long Beach-based 
Chempro</LOCATION>, the same company that worked on the American Trader oil spill, would 
work through the <TIME>night</TIME> and could have the entire spill cleaned by <TIME>early this 
morning</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
Lane said the firm operates platforms <PERSON>Eva</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edith</PERSON> and <PERSON>Esther</PERSON>, all of which are 
between one and three miles off the beach. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Shell Oil Co.</ORGANIZATION> also has platforms in the same area, the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s spill was discovered on the beach shortly after <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>, officials 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Huntington Beach Mayor <PERSON>Thomas J. Mays</PERSON> said a <ORGANIZATION>Shell Oil</ORGANIZATION> helicopter spotted the 
slick before it hit the beach. 
</P>
<P>
"It's really a shame we have to continue going through these problems," he 
said. "We've had minor problems with the platforms off the coast before, but I 
believe this is the first time the oil got to the beach." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Unocal</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Lane</PERSON> said his company reported a 10-gallon spill at <ORGANIZATION>Platform Eva</ORGANIZATION> to 
the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> but he said that incident is believed to be 
unrelated to the oil that washed up on <LOCATION>Bolsa Chica</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"We sent a crew out at dawn looking for any oil on the water and couldn't find 
any," <PERSON>Lane</PERSON> said of the <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> incident. He said a shield designed to trap 
oil had failed because of high winds, which sprayed the crude around the 
platform. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
COASTAL AREAS -- ORANGE COUNTY; HUNTINGTON BEACH (CA); OIL SPILLS -- ORANGE 
COUNTY; OCEAN POLLUTION -- ORANGE COUNTY; HAZARDOUS MATERIALS -- DISPOSAL; 
POLLUTION CONTROL; ENVIRONMENT; WILDLIFE; BEACHES; MARINE LIFE; UNOCAL CORP; 
BOLSA CHICA ECOLOGICAL RESERVE; BOLSA CHICA WETLANDS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880928-0123 </DOCNO>
<HL> Tax Report: A Special Summary and Forecast Of Federal and State Tax Developments </HL>
<AUTHOR> Scott R. Schmedel </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> GT GOVMT TAXES </CO>
<IN> INS </IN>
<G> IRS CNG </G>
<TEXT>
   THE FORM MUST CONFORM to inform, the <ORGANIZATION>GAO</ORGANIZATION> says of exempt groups' reports. 

   Over 300,000 exempt organizations file annual Form 990 reports so the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> and the public can check uses and sources of funds. 
A <ORGANIZATION>House Government Operations</ORGANIZATION> panel asked the <ORGANIZATION>General Accounting Office</ORGANIZATION> to evaluate the completeness of the reports and <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> procedures for making them public. 
Now a <ORGANIZATION>GAO</ORGANIZATION> draft report based on a sample of 450 forms for <DATE>1986</DATE> estimates that <PERCENT>48%</PERCENT> of 990s omit at least one schedule supplying details of such items as fund-raising, loans to and from officers, and mortgage debt. 

   Yet <PERCENT>95%</PERCENT> of the reports with omissions are treated as complete under <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> criteria, and the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> doesn't go after missing schedules, the <ORGANIZATION>GAO</ORGANIZATION> said. 
Its findings went to Rep. <PERSON>Barnard</PERSON> (D., <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>), who expressed his concern. 
But he said the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> plans to change its criteria and demand the missing schedules. 
As for providing 990s on request to the public, the <ORGANIZATION>GAO</ORGANIZATION> said the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> can do it if given a group's exact name. 

   Although a <DATE>1987</DATE> law requires groups to open their 990s to public inspection, the <ORGANIZATION>GAO</ORGANIZATION> expects the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> to continue to receive most requests for copies. 

   REMEMBER <DATE>1912</DATE>, before the income tax arrived? 
These homeowners should. 

   Since <DATE>1865</DATE>, a mutual company -- call it Ex-Tax -- owned by its 5,000 policyholders has sold homeowner's insurance for one refundable deposit. 
Example: A <MONEY>$2,400</MONEY> deposit buys an <MONEY>$80,000</MONEY> policy and may cost, in effect, only <MONEY>$144</MONEY> a year in forgone after-tax interest income. 
But wait, asked the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>, should that hypothetical interest income be imputed to policyholders and actually taxed? 
Now, in private ruling 8831004, it answers no -- for the time being. 

   When begun, long before the income tax was enacted in <DATE>1913</DATE>, the plan wasn't a tax-avoidance scheme, and that isn't its aim now. 
The deposit doesn't constitute a taxable interest-free loan. 
But the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> isn't ready to say whether there's a taxable "significant effect" on policyholders. 
<PERSON>Alan Hollander</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> tax lawyer, says the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> is likely to begin imputing income to them when it finally issues related regulations. 

   COL. BLIMP SMILES, as <ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION> wins <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> credits for British taxes. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> subsidiary had a <DATE>1973</DATE> loss for <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> tax purposes, because of deductions not allowed in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Carried back, the loss erased 1970-71 unit profits, so the unit got <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> refunds. 
But <ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION> had taken 1970-71 foreign-tax credits in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> for the unit. 
The <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> treated the unit's <DATE>1973</DATE> results as profit and denied <ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION>'s 1970-71 credits, citing the refunds. 
<ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION> paid a <MONEY>$791,241</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> claim, sued for a refund in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Claims Court</ORGANIZATION> -- and lost. 

   The credit formula includes a foreign unit's "accumulated profits." 
<ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION>'s complex suit actually turned on whether <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> law requires that sum to be computed under <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> law, as the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Claims Court</ORGANIZATION> agreed, or applicable foreign law, as <ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION> argued. 
Now the federal-circuit appeals court has sided with <ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION> and held that foreign law must be applied. 
"It's a surprising conclusion," says <PERSON>Steven Hannes</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Touche Ross &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, CPAs. 

   And while the ruling favors <ORGANIZATION>Goodyear</ORGANIZATION> now, <PERSON>Hannes</PERSON> says, it could work against companies in many other cases. 

   THAT LOST CHANCE to appeal a <MONEY>$102.3 million</MONEY> claim against the <ORGANIZATION>Bell</ORGANIZATION> companies looks more tragic to the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>, which missed by a day its appeal deadline last month. 
It also hoped to defeat <ORGANIZATION>Indianapolis Power &amp; Light</ORGANIZATION> on the same issue in a prior appeal. 
But now the seventh-circuit appeals court has rejected that <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> plea. 

   A MATH FOOTNOTE and headache: For the first time, <PERSON>Emil Sunley</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Deloitte Haskins &amp; Sells</ORGANIZATION>, CPAs, says, <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> rules include a quadratic equation (with two solutions). 
It concerns allocations of corporate interest costs between the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and abroad. 
The lower positive solution becomes "excess related-party indebtedness." 

   THE IRS WRONGLY SENT notices to an unknown number of people, asking why they haven't paid estimated taxes. 
The answer: They had credited refunds from their <DATE>1987</DATE> returns to cover estimated <DATE>1988</DATE> taxes. 
Taxpayers can clear up the notices with that explanation, the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> says. 

   DAISY-CHAIN MAIL was no armor for this outpost of mail-order ministers. 

   Universal Life Church schemes have been rejected often in court, yet still they pop up. 
Now comes "a perfidious twist" on the usual individual scam, says Tax Court <PERSON>Judge Parker</PERSON>. 
<PERSON>James Edward Dew</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> computer analyst, got a church charter by mail and took in 48 co-workers and friends, 25 of them "ordained," as members. 
Result: A "daisy chain" of "donors" who took charitable deductions for "gifts" and got back "parsonage allowances." 

   The group "simply exchanged checks in a transparent ploy to transmute their nondeductible personal . . . expenses into purported deductible charitable contributions," the judge found. 
The "well-educated" Dew, who appealed the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>'s disallowances, is the sole subject of the judge's opinion, which rejects 1980-81 deductions of <MONEY>$25,883</MONEY> and imposes civil negligence penalties. 

   The judge also orders Dew to pay <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> in damages for pressing a frivolous case despite <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> warnings. 

   BRIEFS: Alimony arrearages of <MONEY>$10,550</MONEY> for 1981-83 all are taxable when received in <DATE>1984</DATE>, not spread over the prior years, the <ORGANIZATION>Tax Court</ORGANIZATION> tells <PERSON>Caroline M. Coleman</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Lutherville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION> . . . 
Corporate tax departments' frequent failure to have backup computer storage of data is "a potential time bomb," says Peat Marwick Main, CPAs. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900225-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-25-90 0147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-Conigliaro 2ndLd-Writethru   02-25 0773</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Conigliaro, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0674,0797</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Red Sox Outfielder Tony Conigliaro Dies</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 3rd graf, ```He's been ...', with
quotes from mother, Red Sox; pick up 4th graf, `The man ...; SUBS
17th graf pvs, `Born in ...', to ADD birthdate; pick up 18th graf
pvs, `A year ...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY46, NY47</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Tony Conigliaro</PERSON>, whose brilliant baseball career
was cut short when he was hit in the face by a pitched ball at age
22, died <DATE>Saturday</DATE> of kidney failure. The former <ORGANIZATION>Boston Red Sox</ORGANIZATION>
outfielder was 45.
   <PERSON>Vinnie Martelli</PERSON>, <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON>'s uncle, said <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> died at
<ORGANIZATION>Salem Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Salem</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>. He entered the hospital <DATE>Thursday</DATE>,
and had been in poor health since suffering a heart attack in <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   ``He's been in a bad way since the attack several years back,''
<PERSON>Martelli</PERSON> said. ``He never quite recovered.''
   His mother, <PERSON>Theresa Conigliaro</PERSON>, said <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> required
constant care after his heart attack.
   ``We lost him after eight years. He's never really been back,''
<PERSON>Mrs. Conigliaro</PERSON> said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. ``The only consolation is he didn't
know what he was going through.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Dick Bresciani</PERSON> said, ``It was a very tragic
finish for Tony. The <ORGANIZATION>Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> are deeply saddened.''
   The man the fans called ``Tony C'' was, at age 22, the youngest
major league player to hit 100 career home runs.
   He was probably most widely known, however, for the beaning that
tragically cost him his career. On <DATE>Aug. 18, 1967</DATE>, during a game
with the <ORGANIZATION>California Angels</ORGANIZATION>, a pitch by <PERSON>Jack Hamilton</PERSON> hit <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON>
on the left side of the face, leaving him with a fractured
cheekbone, a dislocated jaw and blurred vision.
   The crowd fell silent at the sound of the pitch hitting
<PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON>'s face, recalled <PERSON>Dick Dew</PERSON>, who was a sportswriter
covering the game.
   ``It stopped everybody in the place because of the sound of it.
It was unmistakable,'' said Dew. ``You knew the injury was serious
the moment you heard it.''
   Conigliaro sat out the rest of the <DATE>1967</DATE> season, and all of <DATE>1968</DATE>
with vision problems.
   But in the <DATE>fall of 1968</DATE> he attempted a comeback as a pitcher in
the <ORGANIZATION>Florida Instructional League</ORGANIZATION> at age 23. His vision sharpened,
and the <DATE>1969</DATE> season found him back with the <ORGANIZATION>Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> in his familiar
right field position.
   At the end of the <DATE>1970</DATE> season, <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> was traded to the
Angels after having belted 36 homers and driving in 116 runs, both
career highs.
   Citing recurring vision problems, he retired after half a season
with <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> the following year.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> again attempted a comeback with <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, but
it ended after 21 games.
   <PERSON>Johnny Pesky</PERSON>, a former <ORGANIZATION>Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> coach who managed the team when
<PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> joined the club in <DATE>1964</DATE>, said, ``He was so good and you
could see it. You knew he was going to be a great player.
   ``It was a shame he got hurt when he did,'' Pesky said of the
pitching accident. ``With a few more years, he could have made the
Hall of Fame.''
   After the heart attack, Pesky said he visited <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> several
times.
   ``When I went over to see Tony I'd end up crying,'' Pesky said.
``He was such a big, strong kid you would have never thought that
something like that could have happened.''
   Born in <LOCATION>Revere</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION> on <DATE>Jan. 7, 1945</DATE>, <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> made a splash
as a rookie in <DATE>1964</DATE>, when he hit 24 homers and batted .290, despite
missing six weeks with two broken bones and other injuries.
   A year later he led the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> with 32 homers. A wrist
fracture that sidelined him for 24 games kept him from hitting
more. Still, at age 20, he was the youngest major leaguer ever to
win a home run crown.
   His lifetime major league batting average was .264, with 516
runs and 166 home runs.
   After his baseball career ended at age 30, <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> worked as
a sportscaster for television stations in <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. He also worked for a sports agent's firm in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>,
and ran a health food store north of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Jan. 7, 1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> auditioned for a spot on the <ORGANIZATION>Red Sox</ORGANIZATION>
telecasting team. <PERSON>Joseph Dimino</PERSON>, station manager of WSBK-TV, said
<PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> had been ``a leading candidate'' for the job.
   Two days later, <PERSON>Conigliaro</PERSON> suffered a heart attack, which put
him in a coma for four months. It also left him brain damaged and
affected his speech.
   He never recovered fully, but was able to walk with the aid of a
walker in his final years.
   <PERSON>Martelli</PERSON> said funeral arrangements were being planned.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021689-0082 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 19234 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 16, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Ventura County; Part 9; Page 15; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
771 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SOUTHERN SECTION PLAYOFF PREVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
SOME COACHES WOULD WAVE BYE; 
</P>
<P>
1ST-ROUND PLAYOFF BREAK CAN WORK AGAINST WELL-REGARDED TEAMS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By STEVE HENSON, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Bye should not mean a hasty farewell from the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Section</ORGANIZATION> basketball 
playoffs. 
</P>
<P>
Teams that performed best during the regular season earned the privilege of 
skipping the first playoff round, giving them more time to practice and allow 
injuries to heal. 
</P>
<P>
Generally, this is regarded as an advantage. However, coaches -- most of whom 
are prone to bouts of anxiety, anyway -- aren't sure if their byes are so good. 
</P>
<P>
"I'd rather there were no byes," said <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>John Harbour</PERSON>, whose team 
earned a first-round bye in the 4-AA Division by winning a share of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Marmonte League</ORGANIZATION> title. "Teams that play in the first round get their playoff 
jitters out of the way." 
</P>
<P>
Yet jitters aside, a bye advances a team one step closer to saying hello to a 
Southern Section championship. In addition to <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION>, county teams that 
begin play in the second round <DATE>Friday</DATE> are Buena (5-A), <LOCATION>Rio Mesa</LOCATION> (4-A) and <LOCATION>Santa 
Clara</LOCATION> (2-A). 
</P>
<P>
Because only 13 teams qualified for the 2-A playoffs, <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>, the 
top-seeded team, needs to win only three games to give Coach <PERSON>Lou Cvijanovich</PERSON> 
his 10th Southern Section title. When the <ORGANIZATION>Southern Section</ORGANIZATION> offered teams the 
chance to move up to a higher playoff division in <DATE>January</DATE>, several 2-A teams 
fled to the 2-AA. Avoiding the prospect of facing the Saints might have been a 
factor. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> (20-3) has lost only once on the court, a 39-38 loss to <ORGANIZATION>Edison</ORGANIZATION> in 
the <LOCATION>Estancia</LOCATION> tournament last <DATE>December</DATE>. The Saints, upset over what they felt 
was poor officiating, declined to return to the tournament and were assessed 
two forfeit losses. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Shon Tarver</PERSON>, a junior transfer from Rim of the World High, has provided <LOCATION>Santa 
Clara</LOCATION> with consistent scoring, averaging 23 points a game. The Saints also have 
a rugged inside game behind <PERSON>Bubba Burrage</PERSON> (17 points, eight rebounds) and <PERSON>John 
McGill</PERSON> (nine points, eight rebounds). 
</P>
<P>
Perhaps the most improved part of <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>'s game is the play of its guards. 
The Saints' ability to break a press, in fact, is a work of art -- point guard 
<PERSON>Art Santana</PERSON>, who also averages nine points, five rebounds and three assists. 
</P>
<P>
Channel League champion Rio <LOCATION>Mesa</LOCATION> (20-4), the third-seeded 4-A team, also boasts 
a top-flight flyer at point guard. Speedy <PERSON>Lester Smith</PERSON> has improved steadily as 
a ball handler and has become an excellent defensive player, according to Coach 
<PERSON>Steve Wolf</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"He handles all the pressure bringing the ball upcourt," <PERSON>Wolf</PERSON> said, "and he 
always guards the opponents' No. 1 player. He's our most consistent player and 
has legitimate Division I quickness." 
</P>
<P>
Forwards <PERSON>Jeff Garner</PERSON> and <PERSON>Eric Thomas</PERSON> give <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> two excellent scorers to feed. 
Garner is the Spartans' leading scorer, averaging 23 points a game, and <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> 
is a two-time All-County player who finished the league season with strong 
performances. 
</P>
<P>
Harbortown may be a financially troubled Ventura resort, but Harbour-town in 
<LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> is thriving as a school gymnasium. At <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION>, Coach <PERSON>John Harbour</PERSON> 
gives sophomore son <PERSON>David</PERSON> the green light to shoot from anywhere on the floor. 
Well, anywhere inside 25 feet. The younger <LOCATION>Harbour</LOCATION> is accurate, averaging 21 
points, and he also has found time to average six rebounds and lead <LOCATION>Camarillo</LOCATION> 
(17-6) with four assists a game. 
</P>
<P>
Senior forward <PERSON>Frank Dews</PERSON>, who Coach Harbour calls "as consistent a player as 
I've coached," adds a 15-point scoring average. Dews, a returning starter, has 
responded well in several clutch situations. 
</P>
<P>
Buena (19-4) lost three times to <LOCATION>Rio Mesa</LOCATION> during the regular season, twice in 
league play and once in a tournament. But the Bulldogs are in a different 
playoff division than the Spartans. 
</P>
<P>
The third-seeded Bulldogs play at a fast tempo and are led by versatile forward 
<PERSON>Adan Valencia</PERSON> and sharp-shooting point guard <PERSON>Jeff Oliver</PERSON>, both starters on last 
year's league championship team. 
</P>
<P>
Valencia, a senior, averages 16 points and 11 rebounds. Oliver, a junior who 
made a transition from off-guard this season, averages 17 points and seven 
assists. 
</P>
<P>
Buena, one of 10 5-A teams with a first-round bye, hopes to stay close to home 
when it begins play. The Bulldogs have had more success running the break than 
negotiating through traffic. <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> defeated Buena last season in the 
semifinals after the Bulldogs traveled 3 1/2 hours to the game. 
</P>
<P>
"It took a while to limber up and we had only 21 points at the half," <ORGANIZATION>Buena</ORGANIZATION> 
Coach <PERSON>Glen Hannah</PERSON> said. "This year, the travel could be even worse because 
divisions aren't laid out geographically." 
</P>
<P>
This season, enrollment was the sole factor in deciding a team's playoff 
division. And the byes the structure created will be cursed or lauded, 
depending upon the outcomes of <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s games. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Transfer Shon Tarver has had a big hand in Santa Clara's drive to the 
Southern Section playoffs. DAVID BUTOW / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-2367</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CIRBKAAXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920918
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  18 SEP 92 / Sterling and the UK Economy: Business faces up to life with
a stronger dollar
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By Our Industrial Staff
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
FOR UK industrialists bemused by the continued upheaval in European
currencies yesterday, one fact stood out. The sterling-dollar rate is now at
Dollars 1.77. At the start of the month it was at Dollars 2. Sterling is
thus 12 per cent lower than it was a fortnight ago.
For reasons that are partly historic, the dollar remains the most important
single currency for UK manufacturers dealing with the outside world. In
terms of actual trading, as opposed to the translation of overseas earnings,
a stronger dollar cuts three ways.
It is good for exporters and those competing against dollar-based goods at
home or abroad. It is bad for importers. And it is decidedly mixed for small
companies that cannot afford sophisticated currency hedging, since a
switchback dollar adds to their trading risks.
An excellent example of an industry that benefits is aerospace. This is a
business denominated in dollars. For UK manufacturers, the weak dollar has
compounded the difficulties caused by the recession in civil aviation and
government cuts in military spending.
<ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> aero-engine and industrial power group, said <DATE>yesterday</DATE>
that a stronger dollar was better for the company. 'We build in pounds and
sell in dollars,' a <ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION> official said.
<ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>earlier this month</DATE> that the weak dollar had reduced its
first-half profits by Pounds 10m compared with last year. The weaker dollar
also benefited <ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION>'s principal <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> competitors, <ORGANIZATION>General Electric</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Pratt &amp; Whitney</ORGANIZATION>.
A stronger dollar will also help UK aerospace companies such as British
Aerospace and components manufacturers such as <ORGANIZATION>Smiths Industries</ORGANIZATION>, TI-Dowty
and <PERSON>Lucas</PERSON>.
Sterling's fluctuations will have less impact on UK airlines. British
Airways explained yesterday that it sold tickets on both sides of the
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>. A firmer dollar resulted in improved <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> traffic while a stronger
pound boosted UK travel across the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>. The <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> currently accounts for
about 30 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>BA</ORGANIZATION>'s passengers.
Another beneficiary is the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>'s oil sector, where sterling's devaluation was
warmly welcomed. 'It's tremendously good news from a sterling oil company's
point of view,' said <PERSON>Mr John Walmesley</PERSON>, the finance director of <ORGANIZATION>Enterprise
Oil</ORGANIZATION>, the independent oil company. 'It will provide relief for a hard-pressed
sector.'
The devaluation will raise the sterling price of oil close to Pounds 12,
widely regarded among <LOCATION>North Sea</LOCATION> operators as a 'comfort' threshold.
In the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> motor industry, the effects are limited to specialist
manufacturers, since volume exports of cars from the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> to the UK and
continental <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> still play only a minor role in the European market.
Against that, <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce Motor Cars</ORGANIZATION>, the two UK luxury
carmakers, will both reap benefits from lower sterling as <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s main car
exporters to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> accounted for 44 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>'s worldwide turnover last
year of Pounds 693m, and the previous steep fall in the value of the dollar
has played a role in its mounting losses, totalling Pounds 226m last year.
For <ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce Motor Cars</ORGANIZATION>, the loss-making subsidiary of the UK engineering
group <PERSON>Vickers</PERSON>, <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> accounts for about 28 per cent of worldwide
turnover.
<ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION> have both suffered badly in the recessions in the UK
and <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>. In <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, however, fierce competition has meant that there
has been little scope to raise prices to compensate for loss of revenue
caused by the prolonged fall in the value of the dollar.
Devaluation of the pound against the dollar and D-Mark will also give an
important edge to the competitiveness of the UK luxury carmakers in <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION> against their main rivals, <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
Among losers from devaluation are companies that depend on
dollar-denominated raw materials.
The ambivalent effect of weaker sterling on smaller companies is illustrated
by The Rocking Horse Shop, a Yorkshire-based company that makes and
despatches rocking horse kits to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.'
The company's owner, <PERSON>Mr Tony Dew</PERSON>, said: 'It's knowing what prices to quote
at the time orders are taken which gives us the biggest headache.' <PERSON>Mr Dew</PERSON>
said miscalculating exchange rates between orders and despatch could have a
marked impact on a company with an annual turnover of around Pounds 250,000.
The latest dip in the value of the pound, he says, might give US export
business a boost. 'But then, we buy in some of our raw materials from
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, so that won't help.'
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900410-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-10-90 1727EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EditorsFired     04-10 0677</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Editors Fired,0696</SECOND>
<HEAD>Editors Fired for Anti-Abortion Activity, Religious Group Protests</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROGER MUNNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two editors complained <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that
their First Amendment rights of free speech and religion were
violated when they were fired from a small <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> newspaper for
organizing an anti-abortion group.
   The newspaper defended its actions and a lawyer for the <ORGANIZATION>Iowa
Civil Liberties Union</ORGANIZATION> said the editors didn't have a First
Amendment case.
   ``I guess my religious convictions are what brought it about,''
<PERSON>Terri Lambertsen</PERSON>, former People Page editor of the <ORGANIZATION>Fairfield
Ledger</ORGANIZATION>, said in a telephone interview. ``I have to believe that
serving the <ORGANIZATION>Lord</ORGANIZATION> is more important than my job.''
   The Ledger is a 5,000-circulation, six-day-a-week afternoon
newspaper published about 90 miles southeast of <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Lambertsen</PERSON> and News Editor <PERSON>John Kennedy</PERSON> were discharged
<DATE>Monday</DATE> when they refused to quit as leaders of the <LOCATION>Southeast Iowa</LOCATION>
Pro-Lifers, a newly-formed anti-abortion group. <PERSON>Ms. Lambertsen</PERSON> is
president and <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> is secretary of the group.
   Ledger Editor <PERSON>Jan Nierling</PERSON> said the newspaper was forced to fire
the two to protect its credibility, even though that left the paper
with only a managing editor, a reporter and sports editor.
   ``We take our business seriously. We just think it endangers
incredibly our perception of credibility and objectivity. A
newspaper's credibility is its most valuable asset,'' <PERSON>Ms. Nierling</PERSON>
said.
   The firings prompted a protest sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>Refocus Ministries</ORGANIZATION>,
a non-denominational ministerial group. About 40 protestors walked
in a circle in front of the Ledger office <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>.
   ``I have to agree with what <PERSON>John Kennedy</PERSON> said,'' said <PERSON>Larry
Rail</PERSON>, co-director of the group. ``He joined a group that is
pro-life. It doesn't mean his views as a newspaper reporter and
editor are going to change. So it's a blatant violation of his
rights.''
   The Ledger's policy is similar to many other news organizations,
according to <PERSON>William Hirschman</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> chapter of
the Society of Professional Journalists and the group's Freedom of
Information representative for the region that includes <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>.
   A common compromise, he said, is to permit reporters to
participate in some groups, but not as spokesmen or leaders, and to
prevent writers from covering events in which they are personally
involved.
   ``I would have hoped that the two sides would have sat down and
discussed it,'' he said.
   Last <DATE>October</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Milwaukee Journal</ORGANIZATION> fired a receptionist, <PERSON>Diane
Dew</PERSON>, for her anti-abortion activities. In <DATE>December</DATE>, the paper said
it made a mistake and agreed to pay her a settlement. The Journal
said it had decided that its code of ethics for newsroom employees
did not apply to <PERSON>Ms. Dew</PERSON>.
   Last <DATE>spring</DATE>, reporters for The New York Times and The Washington
Post were criticized by their newspapers for participating in an
abortion rights march in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. No punitive action was taken
at either paper.
   Kennedy, an eight-year employee of the Ledger, said his
involvement with the anti-abortion group did not interfere with his
newspaper duties. He said the newspaper could send another reporter
to cover an abortion-related story if it felt his objectivity was
compromised.
   Neither <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> nor <PERSON>Ms. Lambertsen</PERSON> would say if they planned to
pursue legal remedies.
   ``I've got three kids, aged 4, 6 and 7. My wife works part-time
as a church secretary for <MONEY>$37</MONEY> a week. I'm not sure yet what we'll
do, but the Lord will take care of us,'' <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Nierling</PERSON> said the newspaper has a longstanding policy of
prohibiting reporters from being officers of politically active
groups that receive news coverage.
   ``I'm disappointed that they didn't have a better attitude
toward their professional responsibilities,'' she said.
   <PERSON>Mark Bennett</PERSON>, general counsel for the <ORGANIZATION>Iowa Civil Liberties
Union</ORGANIZATION>, said the First Amendment was not at issue in the case. The
First Amendment, he said, applies only to governments that try to
infringe religious and speech rights, not to private enterprises,
such as a newspaper.
   An untested theory, he said, would be whether the paper violated
<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>'s civil rights laws, which prohibit discrimination on the
basis of creed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-9570</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKJC4ACLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931110
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 NOV 93 / Arts: Karetnikov's 'Till Eulenspiegel' - Opera
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW CLARK
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Few modern operas can claim a more tortuous genesis than <PERSON>Nikolai
Karetnikov</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Till Eulenspiegel</ORGANIZATION>, which has just received its stage premiere
at Bielefeld in <LOCATION>north Germany</LOCATION>. Karetnikov, born in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> in <DATE>1930</DATE>, comes
from the post-Shostakovich generation of Soviet composers who experimented
with new techniques and fell foul of the Communist authorities.
Till Eulenspiegel was hardly calculated to win official approval. A two-act
<ORGANIZATION>Singspiel</ORGANIZATION> completed in <DATE>1985</DATE>, it is a parable of Soviet repression and the
indomitable human spirit. The work first reached the West two years ago, in
a recording made piecemeal with help from off-duty members of the Soviet
Cinema Orchestra and scraps of tape from the cutting-room. Today, the only
obstacles to its performance in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> are financial. And so - with an irony
that suits <PERSON>Karetnikov</PERSON>'s style - <ORGANIZATION>Till Eulenspiegel</ORGANIZATION> has been premiered far
from the people to whom it would mean most.
Initial reactions to the recording were ecstatic. Gramophone went so far as
to hail it as 'one of the most powerful operas of recent times'. John Dew's
Bielefeld production hardly supports that verdict. Till Eulenspiegel comes
across as a good allegorical yarn - easy-to-follow, singable and
entertaining, but not strikingly original.
Karetnikov and his co-librettist, the film director <PERSON>Pavel Lungin</PERSON> (Taxi
Blues), used a novel by the <DATE>19th century</DATE> Belgian writer <PERSON>Charles de Coster</PERSON> as
their source. Till is more than the endearing prankster depicted in the
<PERSON>Strauss</PERSON> tone poem - he becomes an uncompromising fighter for justice and
freedom.
The setting is Flanders under the Hapsburg empire and the Spanish
inquisition. Till is exiled for making fun of a monk, his father is burned
as a heretic, his mother is murdered and he himself is nearly executed. From
first to last, death and freedom form two sides of the same coin - no more
so than in the final scene, when Till dies of poison and is mysteriously
resurrected.
Woven into the fabric of the story are bizarre clips of the Spanish court
and a role-call of stereotypes - a fishmonger who informs on his fellow
citizens, a fortune-teller, a quartet of prostitutes and Till's alter ego, a
vagabond named <PERSON>Lamme</PERSON>. All are wrapped into a polystilistic theatrical idiom
embracing mystery-play, pantomime, ballet, burlesque and satirical drama -
while running the musical gamut from renaissance song and baroque recitative
to Orthodox chant, Sprechgesang and 12-note variations. Karetnikov emerges
as a musical chameleon, a virtuoso impersonator, but lacking <PERSON>Schnittke</PERSON>'s
ability to mould his influences into something more personal.
Dew's production, designed by <PERSON>Thomas Gruber</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jose Manuel Vazquez</PERSON>, matches
the parodistic quality of the score, without losing sight of the pain and
violence beneath the surface. The stage is a 20th century prison of wire
mesh, divided into three playing areas to keep pace with the quick changes
of setting. No scene outstays its welcome, though some would have benefited
from a more identifiable sense of place.
The biggest drawback is the positioning of the orchestra behind the stage,
from where - despite amplification - <PERSON>Karetnikov</PERSON>'s subtle accompagnato makes
a sketchy impression. Give or take some predictable lapses of coordination
with his cast, <PERSON>Geoffrey Moull</PERSON> conjures an idiomatic range of sound. In the
baritone title role, <PERSON>William Oberholtzer</PERSON> is more worthy than charismatic.
The Bielefeld ensemble provides versatile support, with excellent
