<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110690-0061 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 303682 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 6, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 4; Column 5; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
306 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CARSON FIRED BY BROWNS AFTER 42-0 DEFEAT TO BILLS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
BEREA, Ohio 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <PERSON>Cleveland Browns</PERSON>, off to their worst start since <DATE>1984</DATE>, fired <ORGANIZATION>Coach Bud 
Carson</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the day after their worst home loss ever. 
</P>
<P>
Owner Art <PERSON>Modell</PERSON>, who promised last year that <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> would be his last head 
coach, changed his mind after <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s 42-0 loss to the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills. 
</P>
<P>
"It was an embarrassment for all of us," <PERSON>Modell</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Carson, the first coaching casualty of the season, was replaced by offensive 
coordinator <PERSON>Jim Shofner</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Modell asked <PERSON>Shofner</PERSON> to take over for at least the rest of the season. He 
becomes the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' ninth head coach. Carson's three-year contract runs through 
<DATE>1991</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Carson</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> he thought the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> (2-7) were back on track when they 
lost to the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers, <DATE>20-17</DATE>, on a last-minute field goal a week ago. 
</P>
<P>
"We expected to play well <TIME>last night</TIME>, and we did not do it," <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> said. "Not 
only did we not do it, we played as badly as we can play." 
</P>
<P>
Carson gambled by starting <PERSON>Mike Pagel</PERSON> at quarterback against the Bills, instead 
of <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON>. Kosar will start when the Browns play again on <DATE>Nov. 18</DATE> against 
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Shofner</PERSON> said. The <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> have a bye this week. 
</P>
<P>
Including playoff games, <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> was 12-14-1 with the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Carson, 59, replaced <PERSON>Marty Schottenheimer</PERSON> as the <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> coach on <DATE>Jan. 27, 1989</DATE>, 
after <PERSON>Schottenheimer</PERSON> left in a dispute with <ORGANIZATION>Modell</ORGANIZATION> over coaching styles. 
</P>
<P>
The Browns were 9-6-1 and <ORGANIZATION>AFC Central</ORGANIZATION> champions under <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> last year, making 
it to the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> title game before losing to <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. But <DATE>1990</DATE> has been a 
nightmare, with injuries, retirements and holdouts wiping out <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s 
offensive line and fouling up the defense. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't feel Bud was given a fair shake," said safety <PERSON>Felix Wright</PERSON>, who staged 
a bitter holdout before the season. "I'm disappointed. Who knows what would 
have happened if we were all together during training camp, and happy?" 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, (A2) Out of a Job: Bud Carson was fired as coach of the Cleveland Browns 
after the team's worst start since 1984. Jim Shofner will take over for the 
season. Out of a Job; Photo, Coach Fired: The Cleveland Browns fired Bud Carson 
as their coach later their worst start since 1984. Jim Shofner will replace him 
for the rest of the season. United Press International; Photo, COLOR, (Orange 
County Edition) COACH FIRED: The Cleveland Browns fired Bud Carson as their 
coach after their worst start since 1984. Jim Shofner will replace him for the 
rest of the season. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
DISMISSALS; COACHES; CARSON, BUD; CLEVELAND BROWNS (FOOTBALL TEAM); MODELL, ART 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011590-0106 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 162492 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 15, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 8; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
539 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AFC PLAYOFF NOTEBOOK; 
</P>
<P>
EX-RAM YOUNG IS A CATCH FOR BRONCOS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARK HEISLER, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
DENVER 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Once again, the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Raiders</ORGANIZATION> won't be meeting in the Super Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
How about an ex-Raider vs. an ex-Ram? 
</P>
<P>
OK, there's ex-Raider linebacker <PERSON>Matt Millen</PERSON> of the 49ers vs. ex-Ram and 
ex-UCLA Bruin receiver <PERSON>Michael Young</PERSON>, who helped quarterback <PERSON>John Elway</PERSON> and the 
Broncos break up <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s AFC championship game. 
</P>
<P>
Young, left unprotected by the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>last winter</DATE> and signed by the Broncos as a 
Plan B free agent, caught two passes -- one for 70 yards and a touchdown, the 
other for 53, setting up another touchdown. 
</P>
<P>
Was he surprised? 
</P>
<P>
"Coming here, I thought that if I made the team, I'd have a chance to 
participate and do some things," <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said. "But never to this extent. I never 
would have dreamed of having a game like this." 
</P>
<P>
Mad at the Rams? 
</P>
<P>
"They just had a change in philosophy," <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said. "There was a new offensive 
coordinator (<PERSON>Ernie Zampese</PERSON>) coming in and I wasn't his type of player. Hey, 
everybody has their opinion. I'm not upset at all at them. 
</P>
<P>
"I wish I could say I had animosity toward 'em but I'd be lying if I said that. 
I almost stayed there because I knew I had a secure job as a backup receiver. 
But I knew that being a backup receiver on the Rams was like being a tackle. I 
mean, I knew I was never going to see any kind of action unless someone got 
hurt. 
</P>
<P>
"I almost didn't leave because I liked it so much. But I tell you what, I like 
it a hell of a lot better here." 
</P>
<P>
The Broncos played the second half without rookie running back <PERSON>Bobby Humphrey</PERSON>, 
and it showed. 
</P>
<P>
Veteran <PERSON>Sammy Winder</PERSON> took over and gained 37 yards -- in 21 carries. 
</P>
<P>
Will <PERSON>Humphrey</PERSON> be ready for the Super Bowl? 
</P>
<P>
Coach <PERSON>Dan Reeves</PERSON> said he has two broken ribs. 
</P>
<P>
"Nah," said <PERSON>Humphrey</PERSON>, who will be X-rayed again today. 
</P>
<P>
Eight different <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> receivers caught passes, but when asked if <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s 
secondary could have done anything differently to stop them, cornerback <PERSON>Frank 
Minnifield</PERSON> failed to come up with answers. 
</P>
<P>
"They don't pay me to make that evaluation," <PERSON>Minnifield</PERSON> said. "I'm the <ORGANIZATION>CB</ORGANIZATION>, not 
the HC." 
</P>
<P>
HC? 
</P>
<P>
"Head coach." 
</P>
<P>
OK. But what about . . . ? 
</P>
<P>
"Don't even ask me," <PERSON>Minnifield</PERSON> said. "I didn't sit and watch the game. I 
played it. There was no thought process. They just pay me to cover wide 
receivers. You ask me to evaluate something, you ain't doing me no service 
whatsoever." 
</P>
<P>
It was <ORGANIZATION>Minnifield</ORGANIZATION> who slipped and fell, freeing Young for his 70-yard touchdown 
catch. 
</P>
<P>
Bud <PERSON>Carson</PERSON>, despite the loss, was satisfied with his first season coaching the 
Browns. 
</P>
<P>
"When we were down and out, everybody said we were finished," <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> said. "But 
we came back, week by week, every day except today. I'd say we made a hell of a 
run at it." 
</P>
<P>
What did <PERSON>Elway</PERSON> think of the crowd noise that drowned out <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> counterpart 
<PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON>'s signals? 
</P>
<P>
"I had trouble hearing when we had the ball," <PERSON>Elway</PERSON> said. "I can only imagine 
what it was like for <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
Denver radio station KHOW played a new tune all week, sung to the tune of the 
old Coasters hit, "<PERSON>Charlie Brown</PERSON>." It went: 
</P>
<P>
 <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
 They're real clowns, those <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
 They're gonna get beat, gonna miss the bus. 
</P>
<P>
 Why the <ORGANIZATION>Denver Broncos</ORGANIZATION> always pickin' on us? 
</P>
<P>
Times columnist <PERSON>Mike Downey</PERSON> contributed to this story. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
DENVER BRONCOS (FOOTBALL TEAM); CLEVELAND BROWNS (FOOTBALL TEAM); AMERICAN 
FOOTBALL CONFERENCE; FOOTBALL CHAMPIONSHIPS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100989-0011 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 118103 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 9, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 6; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
380 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MIAMI BEATS BROWNS WITH FIELD GOAL IN OT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MIAMI 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Miami Dolphins rookie <PERSON>Pete Stoyanovich</PERSON> may have saved more than a game with his 
35-yard field goal in overtime <DATE>Sunday</DATE> against the <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
He also may have saved his job. 
</P>
<P>
Stoyanovich missed a 46-yard field goal in the third period and a 45-yarder 
with three seconds left in regulation time, but gave the Dolphins a 13-10 
victory when he connected on <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s first possession in overtime. 
</P>
<P>
"This is a big, big kick in his career," Dolphin Coach <PERSON>Don Shula</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Stoyanovich, an eighth-round draft choice who became <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s kicker when 
veteran <PERSON>Fuad Reveiz</PERSON> was injured in training camp, said he was confident about 
the final kick despite his earlier misses. 
</P>
<P>
"It wasn't that far out," he said. "I had no doubt I was going to make it. I'm 
just really fortunate that the team gave me a second opportunity to win it for 
them." 
</P>
<P>
Cleveland took the kickoff to start overtime and drove 46 yards, but <PERSON>Matt Bahr</PERSON> 
was wide left on a 44-yard field-goal attempt. 
</P>
<P>
"We all miss," <PERSON>Stoyanovich</PERSON> said. "Nobody's perfect." 
</P>
<P>
The winner, with 8:32 left, capped a 55-yard drive that included two 
third-and-10 passes from <PERSON>Dan Marino</PERSON> to <ORGANIZATION>Fred Banks</ORGANIZATION>. On the first pass, <PERSON>Stephen 
Braggs</PERSON> was called for a 26-yard pass interference penalty at the <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 47. 
The second pass was a 20-yard completion to the <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 27. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s previous home games this season, both losses, also were decided on the 
game's final play. 
</P>
<P>
"There have been two games we should have won at the end, but we didn't," 
<PERSON>Marino</PERSON> said. "This will be a big boost for us." 
</P>
<P>
The Dolphins (2-3) and <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> (3-2) both had a chance to win the game in a wild 
final minute in regulation. 
</P>
<P>
Cleveland's <PERSON>Felix Wright</PERSON> returned an interception to the <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 37 with 1:08 
left, but <PERSON>Louis Oliver</PERSON> intercepted <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON>'s pass two plays later. Marino 
completed two passes for 23 yards before <PERSON>Stoyanovich</PERSON> missed. 
</P>
<P>
The Browns drove to <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s 45-yard line with five minutes to go in the <DATE>fourth 
quarter</DATE>. Two penalties set them back, and safety <PERSON>Jarvis Williams</PERSON> broke up a 
third-down pass at the <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 30. 
</P>
<P>
"We didn't do it when we had to," <ORGANIZATION>Browns Coach Bud Carson</ORGANIZATION> said. "We had our 
shots." 
</P>
<P>
Cleveland was hampered by eight penalties for 86 yards. 
</P>
<P>
"Sloppy, sloppy, sloppy football," <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> said. "Ten points don't win many 
football games." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011490-0104 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 161932 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 14, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 16; Column 4; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
927 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TELEVISION: MADDEN, WALSH TALK NOW, THEN LATER ON GAMES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LARRY STEWART 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
If you're a pro football fan, it's pretty hard to beat today's fare. Not one 
but two championship games. 
</P>
<P>
You're going to be hearing analysis before, during and after both games, and 
the main men are <PERSON>Bill Walsh</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Madden</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Walsh</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> newcomer, knows a lot about the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers, but 
circumstances dictate that he works the AFC game between the <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION> 
and the <LOCATION>Denver Broncos</LOCATION> at Mile High Stadium. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> has <PERSON>Madden</PERSON>, a former AFC coach, on the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> game between the Rams and the 
49ers at <LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Both commentators were interviewed last week. First, <PERSON>Madden</PERSON>'s views. 
</P>
<P>
Question: Can the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> beat the 49ers? 
</P>
<P>
Answer: The Rams are going to have to come up with their best defensive game of 
the year. If they don't, they're in trouble. Then it becomes a shootout, and 
they're going to have to score a hell of a lot of points. 
</P>
<P>
I mean, the Rams can score a lot of points. They're capable of doing that. But 
I really believe the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION>, defensively, are going to have to play above their 
heads. 
</P>
<P>
Q: Might the 49ers, who manhandled <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> <DATE>last weekend</DATE>, be a little 
overconfident and maybe a little complacent? 
</P>
<P>
A: If it was anyone but the Rams, they could be. If the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> had won, they 
could be. But they know first hand what the Rams can do. They have too much 
respect for the Rams. 
</P>
<P>
I've been working on my All-Madden team and have talked with some of the 49ers, 
and when I ask what team, besides the 49ers, is the best, every guy says the 
Rams. 
</P>
<P>
Q: Should the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> try to put a lot of pressure on <LOCATION>Joe Montana</LOCATION>? 
</P>
<P>
A: They're going to have to pressure him to stay in the middle, like they did 
(<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>'s Randall) <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON>. I don't think sacks, either way, are going 
to be a big thing in this game. What the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> have to do more than anything 
else is tackle the receivers as soon as they catch the ball. 
</P>
<P>
What they can't do is let <PERSON>Jerry Rice</PERSON> break away for a 70-yard touchdown after 
he catches a short pass, like he did against the Vikings. They can't let <PERSON>John 
Taylor</PERSON> break away like he did against them in that <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> game. The Rams 
look like they're tackling better since that game. 
</P>
<P>
You're not going to shut out Rice and <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>. But when they do catch the ball, 
you've got to tackle them, put the clamps on 'em. 
</P>
<P>
Q: You grew up with <PERSON>John Robinson</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Daly City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. He has been your 
lifelong friend and he once coached your running backs when you were coaching 
the <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Raiders</ORGANIZATION>. Last week, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> said, despite his reputation for being 
a running coach, that he has really been a passing coach all along. 
</P>
<P>
A: I don't believe that. I say that respectfully. It's just that I know <PERSON>John</PERSON> as 
well as anybody. He is a running coach. He knows more about runners and running 
backs than any coach in the league, maybe more than anyone who has ever coached 
in this league. 
</P>
<P>
But he's not dumb. He's smart enough to know that with the personnel he now 
has, passing is the way to go. It doesn't take a genius to figure that out, not 
when you have guys like <PERSON>Jim Everett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Flipper Anderson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Henry Ellard</PERSON>. 
They've even been working <PERSON>Ron Brown</PERSON> into the offense. 
</P>
<P>
Q: Looking at it from another point of view, what must the 49ers do to win? 
</P>
<P>
A: I think it's the same for the 49ers as the Rams. The team that tackles the 
best is going to win this game. The 49ers aren't going to get a lot of sacks. 
</P>
<P>
What the 49ers have to do is help <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> get into his rhythm. If he does that, 
the 49ers are going to be hard to beat. 
</P>
<P>
I'm not saying it can't be done. Once the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> beat <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, all they had 
to do to get to the Super Bowl was beat two teams they beat during the season, 
the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> and 49ers. And they've already done half of that. 
</P>
<P>
And now from <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Q: The last two times <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> met for the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> championship, the 
Broncos won both times, first on a 15-play, 98-yard drive and then when the 
<PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' <LOCATION>Earnest</LOCATION> Byner fumbled on the three-yard line. Might the Browns be a 
little gun-shy? 
</P>
<P>
A: That's a good point. If they have to measure every step and worry about 
making a mistake, they'll be in trouble. In a game like this, you have to let 
it fly. It's up to (Coach) <LOCATION>Bud Carson</LOCATION> to keep the team loose, and it's up to 
(owner) Art Modell not to put any extra heat on them publicly. 
</P>
<P>
Q: You were a passing coach. What's your opinion of the two quarterbacks in 
this game, <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>John Elway</PERSON>? 
</P>
<P>
A: They're two of the best quarterbacks in football. Elway is more active. 
<PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> has a quicker release and is more accurate on shorter passes. 
</P>
<P>
Q: And the receivers? 
</P>
<P>
A: Both teams also have a lot of talent in this area. It's really a tossup. 
<PERSON>Webster Slaughter</PERSON>, <PERSON>Reggie Langhorne</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ozzie Newsome</PERSON> and <PERSON>Eric Metcalf</PERSON> coming out 
of the backfield for the <ORGANIZATION>Browns</ORGANIZATION> is a very talented group. 
</P>
<P>
We talked to <PERSON>Elway</PERSON> about his receivers before the <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> game. He knows his 
people so well. He said <PERSON>Mark Jackson</PERSON> is the quickest and <PERSON>Vance Johnson</PERSON> is also 
quick, and more dependable. <PERSON>Michael Young</PERSON> has the best hands and runs the best 
routes. He is extremely good. When it's third down and they need the yards, 
Young is the guy <PERSON>Elway</PERSON> likes to go to. They don't use <PERSON>Ricky Nattiel</PERSON> that much, 
but he's good going downfield. And <PERSON>Steve Sewell</PERSON>, like <PERSON>Metcalf</PERSON> for the <LOCATION>Browns</LOCATION>, 
is good coming out of the backfield. 
</P>
<P>
Q: The consensus seems to be the Super Bowl winner will again come from the 
<ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION>. Do you agree? 
</P>
<P>
A: Well, <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> came close to the 49ers <DATE>last year</DATE> (the Bengals lost, 
20-16), so that shows anything can happen. But there is no question the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> is 
the stronger, more physical conference. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Interview 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
LOS ANGELES RAMS (FOOTBALL TEAM); SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS (FOOTBALL TEAM); FOOTBALL 
CHAMPIONSHIPS; FOOTBALL PLAYERS; SPORTSCASTERS; MADDEN, JOHN; WALSH, BILL 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090590-0127 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 271731 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 5, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 6; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1885 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AFC LOOKS PRETTY GOOD, BUT WILL IT BE SUPER?; 
</P>
<P>
PREVIEW: BENGALS AND OILERS, WITH HIGH-TECH OFFENSES, HAVE BEST CHANCE TO 
OVERCOME SIX SUPER BOWL LOSSES IN A ROW. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BOB OATES, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In each of the past six years, the <ORGANIZATION>American Football Conference</ORGANIZATION> has resembled 
an express train moving smoothly through the countryside toward the end of the 
line, where it spectacularly derails. 
</P>
<P>
AFC teams have played the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> on even terms each season since <DATE>1984</DATE>, winning 
their share of the annual interconference series. Then each time, their 
champions have gotten untracked on the <TIME>last afternoon</TIME>, losing six consecutive 
Super Bowls. 
</P>
<P>
"Nobody can really explain it," <LOCATION>Cincinnati Bengal</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Sam Wyche</PERSON> said the 
other day, reviewing the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s record slump. "But I can't see it going on much 
longer." 
</P>
<P>
Wyche's team, in fact, could reverse the momentum. The Bengals and <ORGANIZATION>Houston 
Oilers</ORGANIZATION> seem to be the best in their conference, and one or the other can be 
expected to represent the AFC in Super Bowl XXV, <DATE>Jan. 27</DATE> in <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Both are modern offensive teams. The Bengals play football the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 
49er way -- with a major new component, <PERSON>Wyche</PERSON>'s no-huddle approach -- and the 
Oilers have converted to the run-and-shoot formation, which makes use of four 
wide receivers at all times. 
</P>
<P>
But they converted only a few weeks ago. The run and shoot is a radical 
departure from conventional football, and the <ORGANIZATION>Oilers</ORGANIZATION> may need a season of 
seasoning. The Bengals don't. 
</P>
<P>
Their time-proven offense took <PERSON>Wyche</PERSON> to the Super Bowl only 18 months ago, and 
that day, <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> quarterback <PERSON>Boomer Esiason</PERSON> led <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON>'s team until 
the last minute, when <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, ending a 20-16 rouser, did what he usually does. 
</P>
<P>
This year, <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>'s problem is the potency of its own division, the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s 
strongest. 
</P>
<P>
The Bengals are looking for big trouble from all three of their <ORGANIZATION>Central 
Division</ORGANIZATION> rivals -- the <ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Houston Oilers</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland 
Browns</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
They also expect trouble from the evenly matched top four in the AFC West: the 
<ORGANIZATION>Raiders</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas City Chiefs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Denver Broncos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Diego Chargers</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
These are the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s big eight -- of whom only five can make the <DATE>1990</DATE> playoffs 
along with an <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> entry, the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Jets or <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills. 
</P>
<P>
Under a revised playoff system, three wild-card teams from each conference will 
compete with the six division winners, starting <DATE>Jan. 5-6</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Most coaches expect <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> to be one of the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s six. The Broncos are a more 
solid group than they seemed in <LOCATION>Super Bowl XXIV</LOCATION>, where <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> led the 49ers to 
a 55-10 victory. 
</P>
<P>
That was the third of four jolts that <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Dan Reeves</PERSON> has taken in the 
past four years. His recent heart attack followed three Super Bowl losses. 
</P>
<P>
"Bouncing back is what life is all about," he said last week. 
</P>
<P>
He's right about that, although this season, it will be either <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> or 
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The AFC top 10: 
</P>
<P>
1) <LOCATION>CINCINNATI</LOCATION> BENGALS 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback: <ORGANIZATION>Boomer Esiason 
</P>
<P>
Coach</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Sam Wyche</PERSON> (51-47) 
</P>
<P>
The Bengals and 49ers are both led by Bill Walsh-trained coaches, <PERSON>Wyche</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>George Seifert</PERSON>, and their modern offenses are similar. A possibly decisive 
difference is that the 49ers spend heavily for talent. In contrast, one of 
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>'s best two linemen, <PERSON>Max Montoya</PERSON>, went to the Raiders in the kind of 
Plan B exodus that <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> avoids by outbidding everyone else. Nor have 
the Bengals replaced injured back <PERSON>Ickey Woods</PERSON>. They can still win with <PERSON>Wyche</PERSON>'s 
no-huddle offense. 
</P>
<P>
2) <LOCATION>HOUSTON</LOCATION> OILERS 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback: <ORGANIZATION>Warren Moon 
</P>
<P>
Coach</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Jack Pardee</PERSON> (first year) 
</P>
<P>
Their opponents describe this team's talent as the best that ever lined up in 
the run-and-shoot formation, which <ORGANIZATION>Pardee</ORGANIZATION> previously brought to two other 
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> winners: the <ORGANIZATION>United States Football League</ORGANIZATION>'s Gamblers and the <ORGANIZATION>Southwest 
Conference</ORGANIZATION>'s Cougars. The <ORGANIZATION>Oilers</ORGANIZATION>' unsurpassed blocking starts with <PERSON>Bruce 
Matthews</PERSON>, the receiving with <ORGANIZATION>Drew Hill</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Ernest Givins</PERSON>. A defensive 
specialist, <PERSON>Pardee</PERSON> will address the problems on that side. The question is how 
fast they can adjust to a strange new offense. 
</P>
<P>
3) <LOCATION>DENVER</LOCATION> BRONCOS 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback: <PERSON>John Elway</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Coach: <PERSON>Dan Reeves</PERSON> (91-55-1) 
</P>
<P>
Their Super Bowl wipeout last winter is still held against the Broncos by the 
same people who seem to forget that in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s three-game playoff parade, the 
49ers rolled over the <LOCATION>Vikings</LOCATION> and Rams the same way. Last year, when the 
<ORGANIZATION>Broncos</ORGANIZATION>' ancient weaknesses evaporated with a new defense and runner, <PERSON>Bobby 
Humphrey</PERSON>, they were 6-0 over the AFC in oxygen-thin Mile High Stadium. Nobody 
in the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> comes close to matching <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>'s home-field edge. 
</P>
<P>
4) <LOCATION>PITTSBURGH</LOCATION> STEELERS 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback: Bubby Brister 
</P>
<P>
Coach: <PERSON>Chuck Noll</PERSON> (193-140-1) 
</P>
<P>
Having survived the winning '70s and slumping '80s, <PERSON>Noll</PERSON> hits the '90s with a 
good, young offense and improving defensive personnel. His <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Hoge-Tim 
Worley</ORGANIZATION> backfield became the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s best last year, and new coordinator <PERSON>Joe 
Walton</PERSON> will help the offense. The two questions: Is Brister an <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> comer? Can 
the defense hold the edge it got last year with coordinator <PERSON>Rod Rust</PERSON>, the new 
coach at <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>? The defensive standout is cornerback <PERSON>Rod Woodson</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
5) SAN DIEGO CHARGERS 
</P>
<P>
QB: <PERSON>Mark Vlasic</PERSON>, <PERSON>Billy Joe Tolliver</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Coach: <PERSON>Dan Henning</PERSON> (6-10) 
</P>
<P>
With either youngster pitching for <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, the question is whether the 
<LOCATION>Broncos</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Chargers</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Raiders</ORGANIZATION> or <ORGANIZATION>Chiefs</ORGANIZATION> will break out of the pack in a year when 
<LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> has the only established quarterback. At most other positions, <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 
could be slightly ahead with runner <PERSON>Marion Butts</PERSON>, receiver <PERSON>Anthony Miller</PERSON>, 
linebacker <PERSON>Billy Ray Smith</PERSON> and the depth stored by former General Manager <PERSON>Steve 
Ortmayer</PERSON> and the incumbent, <PERSON>Bobby Beathard</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
6) RAIDERS 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback: <PERSON>Jay Schroeder</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Coach: Art Shell (7-5) 
</P>
<P>
See paragraph above for a more exact placing of the <ORGANIZATION>Raiders</ORGANIZATION>, who, in various 
media surveys, have been ranked from first to last in their division -- and who 
have been mentioned by others for both the Super Bowl and the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> cellar. They 
seem clearly stronger defensively and in the offensive line, and they have the 
fastest receivers in football. All they want from <PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON> is occasional 
accuracy on their favorite missile, the long, long pass to one of those 
receivers. 
</P>
<P>
7) <LOCATION>KANSAS CITY</LOCATION> CHIEFS 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback: <PERSON>Steve DeBerg</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Coach: <PERSON>Marty Schottenheimer</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
(8-7-1) 
</P>
<P>
If for once DeBerg could play like <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> or <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON>, the Chiefs would 
jump to the head of the class in the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> and even worry the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> in the Super 
Bowl. They're sound enough elsewhere. They have a few receivers and a big 
running back, <PERSON>Christian Okoye</PERSON>, and at linebacker they line up an MVP-type in 
<PERSON>Derrick Thomas</PERSON> who would make any defense look good. When they have all their 
players, their secondary is among the finest. But it's really all up to <ORGANIZATION>DeBerg</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
8) <LOCATION>CLEVELAND</LOCATION> BROWNS 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback: <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Coach: <ORGANIZATION>Bud Carson</ORGANIZATION> (10-7-1) 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Carson</PERSON> was 58 last year when they finally gave him an <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> team, and he won a 
division title. Then the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> beat <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> in the playoffs before losing the 
<ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> title game again in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. Although their quarterback ranks with the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s 
best, the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> may otherwise be a touch short in talent. Still, some people 
say they'll win again with running backs <PERSON>Eric Metcalf</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kevin Mack</PERSON>, and with 
<PERSON>Clay Matthews</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael Dean Perry</PERSON> on defense. 
</P>
<P>
9) <LOCATION>BUFFALO</LOCATION> BILLS 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback: <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Coach: <PERSON>Marv Levy</PERSON> (31-26) 
</P>
<P>
In a slumping division, this team hasn't taken charge as surely as its fans 
thought it would with its intellectual coach, belligerent quarterback, diligent 
general manager, <PERSON>Bill Polian</PERSON>, and its assortment of defensive stars -- <PERSON>Bruce 
Smith</PERSON>, <PERSON>Shane Conlan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Cornelius Bennett</PERSON> and others. They say in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> that 
<PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>'s talent has been diluted by abrasive relationships with teammates, but 
there's probably nothing wrong with the Bills that more consistency wouldn't 
cure. 
</P>
<P>
10) <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> JETS 
</P>
<P>
QB: <PERSON>Ken O'Brien</PERSON>, <PERSON>Tony Eason</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Coach: <PERSON>Bruce Coslet</PERSON> (first year) 
</P>
<P>
A new general manager, <PERSON>Dick Steinberg</PERSON>, has brought in a new coach from the <PERSON>Bill 
Walsh</PERSON> school. And although the Jets in a rebuilding year might be over their 
heads in other divisions, they can make a run for it in the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> if either 
passer is up to it. Some <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> club executives are predicting that in time, 
<PERSON>Steinberg</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s other new general managers -- <PERSON>Beathard</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Kansas 
City</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Carl Peterson</PERSON> among them -- will end the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION>'s Super Bowl dominance. 
</P>
<P>
THE OTHERS 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
WEST 
</P>
<P>
After <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Raiders</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> line up one through four, 
there is only one place left for the <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Seahawks</ORGANIZATION>. It is improbable, 
though, that they'll actually finish fifth. Their coach, <PERSON>Chuck Knox</PERSON>, has a way 
of hanging tough against any odds, and his defense will improve when he gets in 
his first draft pick, flashy lineman <PERSON>Cortez Kennedy</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
In <PERSON>Knox</PERSON>'s offensive backfield, <PERSON>John L. Williams</PERSON> has the look of a run-and-shoot 
triple threat -- runner-receiver-blocker -- which is one reason the Seahawks 
may be in that formation more extensively than they now expect. 
</P>
<P>
Top to bottom, the AFC West has been called a strong division that would be one 
of the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s strongest if it had more quarterbacks of proven worth. The <PERSON>Elway</PERSON> 
contribution can be measured in one statistic: Of the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s 14 teams, the 
<LOCATION>Broncos</LOCATION> alone played in three <DATE>1980s</DATE> Super Bowls. 
</P>
<P>
Many scouts reason that the Chiefs and Chargers are set at most positions and, 
with <PERSON>Carl Peterson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bobby Beathard</PERSON> rounding up talent, both soon may stand 
with the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s leaders. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
CENTRAL 
</P>
<P>
In this division last year, in one of the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s closest races of all time, 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> finished 9-6-1, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> 9-7, <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 9-7 and <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 8-8. It 
will come as no surprise to most in the AFC Central if the standings are the 
same this year -- or if they're just the reverse, with the Browns a half-game 
behind the others. 
</P>
<P>
Few <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> teams match the quality of the <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> nucleus: blocker <PERSON>Anthony 
Munoz</PERSON>, receiver <PERSON>Eddie Brown</PERSON>, tight end <PERSON>Rodney Holman</PERSON>, runner <PERSON>James Brooks</PERSON>, 
passer <PERSON>Boomer Esiason</PERSON>, nose tackle <PERSON>Tim Krumrie</PERSON> and safety <PERSON>David Fulcher</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Cleveland quarterback <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> will have a fourth offensive coordinator in 
four years, <PERSON>Jim Shofner</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The primary AFC Central question is how much <PERSON>Warren Moon</PERSON> will shake things up 
in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>'s run and shoot, and the mystery team is <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, which, to many 
AFC critics, seems to be on the way up again. But <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>'s Brister is the 
least experienced quarterback in a division with three giants, <PERSON>Moon</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Esiason</ORGANIZATION> 
and <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
EAST 
</P>
<P>
Some of the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s most famous winners have come out of the franchises in this 
division -- the Jets with <PERSON>Joe Namath</PERSON>, the Dolphins with <PERSON>Bob Griese</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dan 
Marino</PERSON>, the Colts with <PERSON>John Unitas</PERSON> and <PERSON>Eric Dickerson</PERSON>, the Bills with <PERSON>O.J. 
Simpson</PERSON>, and, most recently, a <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> Super Bowl team. 
</P>
<P>
But to many in the <LOCATION>AFC East</LOCATION>, their division is in disarray -- although the 
Bills could still come back this year, and the Jets could come up. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dan Marino</PERSON> keeps asking to be traded. Maybe he's saying something 
more. At 29, he's still the world's best passer. The question is whether Coach 
<PERSON>Don Shula</PERSON>, 60, has enough help besides receiver <PERSON>Mark Clayton</PERSON> and cornerback <PERSON>Tim 
McKyer</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
When the Colts drafted <PERSON>Jeff George</PERSON> last <DATE>spring</DATE>, they disclosed that they had 
the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s next great quarterback -- but he won't prove it this year. With <PERSON>Eric 
Dickerson</PERSON> out, Coach <PERSON>Ron Meyer</PERSON> has been left with not much but a linebacker, 
<PERSON>Duane Bickett</PERSON>, who can't run the ball or pass it. 
</P>
<P>
The Patriots are stocked with above-average players, none of them at 
quarterback. Though well-coached by rookie <PERSON>Rod Rust</PERSON>, 61, they are unlikely to 
overtake anyone except <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Dan Reeves (left) and John Elway have taken the Broncos to three of the 
past four Super Bowls, but they have been routed each time. AL SEIB / Los 
Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile; List 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FOOTBALL TEAMS; AMERICAN FOOTBALL CONFERENCE; FOOTBALL PLAYERS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06037214 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06037214 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Belichick  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; BRIEF  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The Cleveland Browns made Bill Belichick the NFL's youngest coach on Tuesday,
hiring the New York Giants' defensive coordinator to resurrect the Browns from
the rubble of last season.;    Belichick, 38, was given a five-year contract
to replace Bud Carson, who was fired Nov. 5 after the Browns lost seven of
their first nine games. The contract reportedly is worth $2.5 million.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BELICHICK TO COACH BROWNS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Pro Football
Notebook  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Former offensive coordinator <PERSON>Jim Shofner</PERSON> finished the season as interim
coach but took his name out of the running.;    <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s 3-13 mark was the
worst in the franchise's 41-year NFL history.;    <PERSON>Belichick</PERSON>'s prospects of
becoming a head coach were enhanced by the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>' defensive performance last
season, including their <DATE>20-19</DATE> Super Bowl win over the <LOCATION>Buffalo Bills</LOCATION>. He also
was a candidate for the <LOCATION>Tampa Bay</LOCATION> vacancy, which went to former Bucs assistant
<PERSON>Richard Williamson</PERSON> on Monday.;    <ORGANIZATION>Browns</ORGANIZATION> owner Art <PERSON>Modell</PERSON> chose <PERSON>Belichick</PERSON> over
several other candidates, including <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Raiders quarterbacks coach
<PERSON>Mike White</PERSON> and former <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Rams defensive coordinator <PERSON>Fritz Shurmur.</PERSON>;  
 "I've been disappointed before, but I don't expect to be disappointed this
time." <ORGANIZATION>Modell</ORGANIZATION> said. "We're not a 3-13 team, nor are we a 13-3 team. I think we
are a competitive team. I will not give him nor myself a time frame. I tried
that before and it doesn't work.";    <ORGANIZATION>The Raiders</ORGANIZATION>' Art Shell, 44, had been the
<ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s youngest head coach.; NEW DEAL FOR DITKA: <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bears</ORGANIZATION> Coach <PERSON>Mike Ditka</PERSON>
agreed to a new three-year contract. The deal is worth an average of about <MONEY>$1
million</MONEY> a year, according to a report on WBBM-TV in <LOCATION>Chicago.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>ETC.</LOCATION>: <PERSON>Mouse
Davis</PERSON> will be named as coach of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Knights of the <ORGANIZATION>World League of
American Football</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> reported. . . . <PERSON>Earl Leggett</PERSON> will rejoin
the Raiders as a defensive-line coach. <PERSON>Leggett</PERSON> was a <ORGANIZATION>Raiders</ORGANIZATION> assistant from
<DATE>1980</DATE> until <DATE>1988</DATE>, then spent two seasons with <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Wire Services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910206  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  331  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday February 6, 1991
00037214,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011490-0106 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 161934 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 14, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 17; Column 3; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
462 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AFC PLAYOFF NOTEBOOK; 
</P>
<P>
CARSON EXPECTS BRONCOS TO BE IN A HURRY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
DENVER 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In light of the chaos caused by the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills' unexpected no-huddle offense 
last week, <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Brown Coach Bud Carson</ORGANIZATION> spent the week preparing for more 
of the same today from the <ORGANIZATION>Denver Broncos</ORGANIZATION> in the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> championship game. 
</P>
<P>
"The Bills found a couple weak spots, and they exploited them. We didn't do a 
very good job adjusting to them," <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> said. "They not only used a hurry-up 
game on us, they used an even more effective hurry-up game in that they weren't 
even audibling at the line of scrimmage. They were getting lined up and running 
plays quickly." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON> passed for 405 yards and four touchdowns against <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 
and nearly won the game before <PERSON>Clay Matthews</PERSON> intercepted a pass at the goal 
line with three seconds left to preserve the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' win. One play earlier, a 
potential touchdown pass glanced off the hands of <PERSON>Ronnie Harmon</PERSON> in the left 
corner of the end zone. 
</P>
<P>
Buffalo's first touchdown came on a no-huddle play that created confusion among 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s defenders. <PERSON>Matthews</PERSON> was feverishly trying to call a timeout as the 
ball was snapped, and <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> proceeded to hit a wide-open <PERSON>Andre Reed</PERSON> over the 
middle for a 72-yard touchdown play. 
</P>
<P>
Though Denver attempted to use a hurry-up offense without much success in a 
16-13 loss to the Browns in <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> on <DATE>Oct. 1</DATE>, <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> said he'd be surprised 
if the <PERSON>Broncos</PERSON> didn't try of it today. 
</P>
<P>
"We're anticipating 90,000 no-huddles. Our whole practice has been no-huddles," 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> are seeking their first Super Bowl appearance. The Broncos are after 
their third appearance in four years and fourth overall. They are 0-3. 
</P>
<P>
Denver had a 1,000-yard rusher and a 3,000-yard passer in the same season for 
the first time. Its attack is more balanced than <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>John Elway</PERSON> will supplement the passing game with <PERSON>Bobby Humphrey</PERSON>, who rushed for 
1,151 yards as a rookie and scored eight touchdowns. He is effective inside and 
out. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Elway</PERSON> did not have an outstanding season, but he did pass for 3,051 yards and 
18 touchdowns. He also threw 18 interceptions and was the team's third-leading 
rusher with 244 yards. 
</P>
<P>
Cleveland's defensive backs excel at going for the ball -- the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> led the 
AFC with 27 interceptions. 
</P>
<P>
The only snow fans at the game are likely to see will be capping the mountains 
in the distance. 
</P>
<P>
The forecast for today is mild and breezy, with increasing afternoon clouds and 
high temperatures in the low 50s. 
</P>
<P>
"It's perfect football weather," said weather service meteorologist <PERSON>Joe Baskin</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"It's cool enough for the players to enjoy it, and enough breeze to blow all 
the smoke out of the stands. Just a really nice day." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Baskin</PERSON> said snow could follow on the heels of the game, however, perhaps on 
<DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"Maybe for the ticker-tape parade," he said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FOOTBALL CHAMPIONSHIPS; DENVER BRONCOS (FOOTBALL TEAM); CLEVELAND BROWNS 
(FOOTBALL TEAM) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA092390-0129 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 281763 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 23, 1990, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 4; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
943 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CHARGERS CAN HELP LYNN SETTLE A SCORE; 
</P>
<P>
PRO FOOTBALL: DEFENSIVE COORDINATOR REKINDLES AN OLD RIVALRY WHEN HIS SQUAD 
GOES AFTER CLEVELAND QUARTERBACK BERNIE KOSAR. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By T.J. SIMERS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CLEVELAND 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
If you were from <LOCATION>Struthers</LOCATION>, just outside <LOCATION>Youngstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, you didn't take to 
the folks from neighboring <PERSON>Boardman</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"We're talking the Hatfields and the McCoys here," said <PERSON>Jim Fox</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Boardman 
High School</ORGANIZATION> teacher. "The kids from <ORGANIZATION>Struthers</ORGANIZATION> always had something to prove to 
the rich kids from <PERSON>Boardman</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Boardman</PERSON> had a better band, better shopping malls, better everything than 
<PERSON>Struthers</PERSON>," said <PERSON>Chuck Perazich</PERSON>, sports editor of the <ORGANIZATION>Youngstown Vindicator</ORGANIZATION>. 
"Except for sports -- when it came to sports, you never knew who was going to 
win. 
</P>
<P>
"In sports it was the cake-eaters from <PERSON>Boardman</PERSON>, against the blue-collar tough 
guys from <ORGANIZATION>Struthers</ORGANIZATION>. Bitter rivals," <PERSON>Perazich</PERSON> said. "That's why I imagine 
(<ORGANIZATION>Chargers</ORGANIZATION>' defensive coordinator) <PERSON>Ronnie Lynn</PERSON> has got to have a funny feeling 
about this game. I got to believe he's going to try a little harder. After all, 
he's from <PERSON>Struthers</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
And <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> is from <PERSON>Boardman</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Kosar also is the starting quarterback for the <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Browns</ORGANIZATION> (1-1), and 
today in front of a sellout crowd of 80,000 he will match brawn and wits with 
<PERSON>Lynn</PERSON>'s not-so-neighborly Charger defense. 
</P>
<P>
"I've known the guy for a long time," <PERSON>Lynn</PERSON> said. "His high school adviser (Fox) 
was my college roommate. I even tried to recruit <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON> to play at <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
Kosar went on to prosper for the <ORGANIZATION>University of Miami</ORGANIZATION>, but <DATE>today</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Lynn</ORGANIZATION> will be 
coming after him again. And he won't be alone. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Bernie</PERSON> knows he's going to get the good pass rush, maybe the great pass rush," 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> coach <PERSON>Bud Carson</PERSON> said. "Maybe the best in the AFC." 
</P>
<P>
This cannot be good news for <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>. In two games, he has been sacked 10 times; 
on 10 other occasions, he has released the ball and then has been decked. Four 
of his passes have been deflected by pass rushers. 
</P>
<P>
He wears an elastic wrap around a painted black plastic cup used to protect the 
elbow on his throwing arm, Maybe he should be padded from head to foot. 
</P>
<P>
"He's definitely a tough guy," linebacker <PERSON>Gary Plummer</PERSON> said. "As much as he's 
been knocked around in the last two weeks to still be standing -- you got to 
admire the guy." 
</P>
<P>
The Chargers, however, do not come to <LOCATION>Cleveland Stadium</LOCATION> to praise <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>. They 
come "to bury him," as defensive tackle <PERSON>Lee Williams</PERSON> pointed out. 
</P>
<P>
"He's the target," <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said. "We know where he's going to be, and we're 
coming after him. Full throttle." 
</P>
<P>
Protected by an offensive line that doesn't make the Chargers' offensive line 
look so bad anymore, <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> has struggled to be effective, and as a result, 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s offense ranks 26th in the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>. The Browns feature four new starters 
up front, and to hear the folks in <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, they'd be just as happy to go to 
war with the four old starters. 
</P>
<P>
It took the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> seven quarters of play to record their first offensive 
touchdown this season. They now have two. Their longest run from scrimmage has 
been 16 yards by <PERSON>Kevin Mack</PERSON>, who is now sidelined with a broken finger; their 
longest pass play is 27 yards, to <PERSON>Reggie Langhorne</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"They've had their problems, and they may do some things to keep extra 
protectors in there for <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON>," <PERSON>Lynn</PERSON> said. "But we're going to rush him. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Bernie</PERSON>'s a courageous guy. But he may throw some away, and if you get hit a 
number of times, I don't care how tough you are, you start to hurt and flinch. 
I can see some of that happening if we do what we're capable of doing." 
</P>
<P>
Now if the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> are capable of doing what they do best, then nobody scores, 
and these two teams go into overtime for the third time in their last five 
meetings. 
</P>
<P>
Like the Chargers, the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> try to construct a victory via defense. Their 
head coach is a former defensive coordinator, who was the architect of 
<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>'s "Steel Curtain." Their big-play linebacker, <PERSON>Clay Matthews</PERSON>, has 
been to five <LOCATION>Pro Bowls</LOCATION>. Their top pass rusher, <PERSON>Michael Dean Perry</PERSON>, leads the 
AFC in sacks, with four. 
</P>
<P>
In two games, they have yet to surrender a second-half touchdown, and as the 
Chargers are often reminded, they have yet to score in either the third or 
fourth quarters. 
</P>
<P>
"I know. I know," quarterback <PERSON>Billy Joe Tolliver</PERSON> said. "I'm sure they've got to 
feel pretty good about themselves. 
</P>
<P>
"But we're looking to change that. Not necessarily to score in the <DATE>fourth 
quarter</DATE>, but to score if we need to score. That's our goal." 
</P>
<P>
Bring on <PERSON>Fuad Reveiz</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"Where's the blindfold?" said the Charger kicker, whose job is on the line. 
"Coach (Dan) <PERSON>Henning</PERSON> hasn't made it easy for me putting me on the spot like 
this, but it's something that is part of the business." 
</P>
<P>
Reveiz, one-for-three in field-goal attempts, has been informed that future 
employment with the Chargers rests solely on how he does today. 
</P>
<P>
"You can't be panicking after two games," <PERSON>Reveiz</PERSON> said. "You've got a lot of the 
season to go, and you can't be looking after two games and think it's the end 
of the world." 
</P>
<P>
Maybe not, but an 0-3 start would be the first for the Chargers since going 
0-11 in <DATE>1975</DATE>. It would also put an end to all those high-flying expectations 
that greeted a fifth-place schedule and <PERSON>Bobby Beathard</PERSON>'s arrival. 
</P>
<P>
The last time, however, the Chargers sought victory in the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' ramshackle 
backyard, they were waylaid, 47-17. 
</P>
<P>
"We got no allies there," <PERSON>Lynn</PERSON> said. "We're gonna be warming up in front of the 
'Dawg Pound' (the dog bone-tossing section of Browns fans), and they'll be 
throwing things at us and calling us everything but free men. 
</P>
<P>
"It's an avid fan, a rabid fan. This is important to the people in <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>. 
These are the guys who come out of the mills wearing hard hats who just don't 
take them off <DATE>Friday</DATE> till <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. They live for their football. 
</P>
<P>
"I mean I got a ticket for my college roommate," <PERSON>Lynn</PERSON> said, "and he's rooting 
for <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON>." 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091790-0076 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 277493 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 17, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 9; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
348 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MCNEIL PLAYS OLD ROLE AS JETS DEFEAT BROWNS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Just two weeks ago, the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Jets waived <PERSON>Freeman McNeil</PERSON>, the team's 
all-time leading rusher with 7,146 yards. 
</P>
<P>
When the former <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> standout went unclaimed by another team, the Jets brought 
<PERSON>McNeil</PERSON> back for his 10th season. 
</P>
<P>
The move paid off <DATE>Sunday</DATE> against the <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION> as <ORGANIZATION>McNeil</ORGANIZATION> rushed for 62 
yards and caught three passes for 80 yards as the Jets beat the Browns, 24-21, 
to give <PERSON>Bruce Coslet</PERSON> his first victory as the team's coach. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Freeman</PERSON>'s too old," <PERSON>Coslet</PERSON> said with a big smile creasing his face after his 
successful home debut. "He can't do it anymore. You saw that." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>McNeil</PERSON> has been a starter in both of the Jets' games this season because <PERSON>Blair 
Thomas</PERSON> -- the Jets' No. 1 draft pick -- has been slowed by a hamstring injury, 
and <PERSON>Johnny Hector</PERSON> is just approaching peak shape after arthroscopic knee 
surgery. 
</P>
<P>
McNeil and quarterback <PERSON>Ken O'Brien</PERSON> connected on a 59-yard pass play in the 
<DATE>first quarter</DATE> that was the longest of <ORGANIZATION>McNeil</ORGANIZATION>'s career. He ran all the way to 
the one and <PERSON>Brad Baxter</PERSON> got the touchdown two plays later. 
</P>
<P>
The Jets' defense was stingy in the first half and pressured <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> 
throughout the game. <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, which had only 80 yards rushing last week, was 
limited to 44 against the Jets. 
</P>
<P>
Kosar completed 24 of 41 passes for 233 yards. O'Brien completed 13 of 21 
passes for 218 yards. 
</P>
<P>
The Browns (1-1) got off to a fast start when <PERSON>Eric Metcalf</PERSON> returned the opening 
kickoff 98 yards for a touchdown. 
</P>
<P>
But the Jets (1-1) came right back with a 68-yard, four-play drive highlighted 
by <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>' 55-yard run with a screen pass that set up <PERSON>McNeil</PERSON>'s two-yard scoring 
run. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> went ahead, 14-7, with a 90-yard drive that took just six plays. 
</P>
<P>
Again, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> was a key figure with a 25-yard run. On the next play, <PERSON>Anthony 
Blaylock</PERSON> was called for pass interference at the <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 27. 
</P>
<P>
Four plays later, Hector scored from the six. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Pat Leahy</PERSON> added a 47-yard field goal after the Jets recovered a Metcalf fumble, 
giving the Jets a 17-7 lead. 
</P>
<P>
"I was very surprised at how they came back after <PERSON>Eric</PERSON>'s touchdown," <ORGANIZATION>Browns 
Coach Bud Carson</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010690-0115 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 158401 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 6, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 3; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
721 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BILLS' DISCORD IS MUSIC TO THE EARS OF BROWNS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JERRY CROWE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CLEVELAND 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
All anybody here seems to want to talk about is an anticipated showdown for the 
<ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> championship next week between the <PERSON>Cleveland Browns</PERSON> and the <PERSON>Denver Broncos</PERSON>, 
who twice in the last three years kept the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> out of the Super Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
Up first for the <LOCATION>Browns</LOCATION>, however, are the embattled <ORGANIZATION>Buffalo Bills</ORGANIZATION>, their 
opponents today in an AFC playoff game at Municipal Stadium. 
</P>
<P>
The underdog Bills (9-7) staggered into the postseason, losing three 
consecutive games before closing the season with a 37-0 rout of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 
Jets. 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON>, whose abrasiveness was tolerated when the Bills were at 
their best, has been criticized by the fans, the media and his teammates. 
</P>
<P>
And in an even more surprising development, <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> has raised questions about 
his confidence, once thought to be unshakable. 
</P>
<P>
In-fighting among the Bills started in the <DATE>second week of the season</DATE>, when 
<PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> exchanged words with a receiver who was later released, and heated up 
three weeks later, when <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> suffered a separated left shoulder in a 37-14 
loss to the <LOCATION>Indianapolis Colts</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
At a news conference the <DATE>next day</DATE>, <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> blamed the injury on a missed block by 
tackle <PERSON>Howard Ballard</PERSON>. Angering his teammates further, <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> also said that 
<PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> was the weak link in the Bills' offensive line. 
</P>
<P>
Two weeks later, while watching a videotape of a 34-3 victory over the Jets, 
assistant coaches <PERSON>Nick Nicolau</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tom Bresnahan</PERSON> got into a fistfight. Nicolau 
reportedly punched <PERSON>Bresnahan</PERSON>, opening a cut on his chin, and also drove 
<PERSON>Bresnahan</PERSON>'s head through a plasterboard wall, opening a cut on his forehead. 
</P>
<P>
Kelly returned after being sidelined for three games, leading the Bills to a 
24-7 victory over the <LOCATION>Cincinnati Bengals</LOCATION> in Week 12 that established the Bills 
among the elite in the AFC. 
</P>
<P>
All seemed well, or well enough. 
</P>
<P>
But after <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> played poorly the next week in a 17-16 loss at <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, running 
back <PERSON>Thurman Thomas</PERSON> told a cable television audience that quarterback was the 
Bills' weak link. 
</P>
<P>
Then, after <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> saw three of his passes intercepted the next week in a 22-19 
loss to the <LOCATION>New Orleans Saints</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> was asked if his confidence had been 
shaken. 
</P>
<P>
"You might say that," he said. 
</P>
<P>
The next day, he was pulled aside for a pep talk by Coach <PERSON>Marv Levy</PERSON>, who had 
always defended <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>'s brashness, calling it more than mere bravado. 
</P>
<P>
Kelly threw three more interceptions in a 21-10 loss to the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 
49ers, but none in the romp over the Jets. 
</P>
<P>
Asked this week about the bickering among the Bills, <PERSON>Levy</PERSON> said: "That's behind 
us, and I'm not talking about it anymore." 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> (9-6-1) endured hard times of their own. 
</P>
<P>
Or some did, anyway. 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> has weathered his most trying season, being asked to 
lead an offense that was without <PERSON>Kevin Mack</PERSON>, the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' leading rusher in each 
of the previous five seasons, for all but the last four games. 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> was pulled in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE> of a 21-0 loss to the Bengals in 
<DATE>Week 13</DATE>, the Browns had scored 37 points in four games. 
</P>
<P>
In a poll conducted the next week by a <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> TV station, only <PERCENT>51%</PERCENT> of the 
record 28,500 respondents said they favored <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> as the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' quarterback 
over his backup, journeyman <PERSON>Mike Pagel</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>, who has led the Browns into the playoffs in each of his five <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> 
seasons, was angered by the lack of support from the fans and also was troubled 
by <ORGANIZATION>Coach Bud Carson</ORGANIZATION>'s refusal to support him publicly. <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> didn't announce 
his starter for the next week's game against the Colts until moments before the 
kickoff. 
</P>
<P>
Carson later claimed he was only trying to keep the Colts guessing and that 
<PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>'s job never was in jeopardy. 
</P>
<P>
Whatever the reasoning, <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> threw for 353 yards against the Colts. But the 
<PERSON>Browns</PERSON> lost, <DATE>23-17</DATE>, when <PERSON>Mike Prior</PERSON> intercepted a pass by <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> in overtime and 
returned it 58 yards for a touchdown. 
</P>
<P>
Winless in four games, the <LOCATION>Browns</LOCATION> then closed the season with victories over 
the <LOCATION>Minnesota Vikings</LOCATION>, 23-17 in overtime, and the <ORGANIZATION>Houston Oilers</ORGANIZATION>, 24-20. 
</P>
<P>
Mack, jailed for a drug conviction during most of the season, then suffered a 
knee injury. He gained 27 of his 62 yards in the game-winning drive against the 
<ORGANIZATION>Oilers</ORGANIZATION>, scoring on a four-yard run with 39 seconds left. 
</P>
<P>
Once again, the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> were AFC Central champions. 
</P>
<P>
Only a more troubled team stands between them and another AFC title game. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FOOTBALL GAMES; FOOTBALL TEAMS; BUFFALO BILLS (FOOTBALL TEAM); CLEVELAND BROWNS 
(FOOTBALL TEAM) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100990-0102 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 289863 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 9, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 4; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
331 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE DRIVE FINALLY GOES THE BROWNS' WAY, 30-29 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
DENVER 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Quarterback <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> finally turned the tables on the team that has so 
often tormented him, leading <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> to 10 points in the final 3:21 and a 
30-29 victory over the <LOCATION>Denver Broncos</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
The winning points came on <PERSON>Jerry Kauric</PERSON>'s 30-yard field goal as time expired 
after a 48-yard drive engineered by <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>. A few minutes earlier, <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> had 
completed a 24-yard touchdown pass to <PERSON>Brian Brennan</PERSON> that cut a 29-20 deficit to 
29-27. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> had scored only three offensive touchdowns in their four previous 
games. But <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> completed 24 of 38 passes for 318 yards and three touchdowns 
against the Broncos and could have had a fourth. A five-yard flip to <PERSON>Eric 
Metcalf</PERSON> for a touchdown was ruled a lateral and scored as a rushing touchdown. 
</P>
<P>
Cleveland (2-3) ended a three-game losing streak that had left <ORGANIZATION>Coach Bud 
Carson</ORGANIZATION>'s job in jeopardy. It came against a team that had beaten the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> 
three times in the last four <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> title games. 
</P>
<P>
"You can't say one game is the season, but if we had lost we would have been so 
far in the cellar we couldn't have dug ourselves out," said cornerback <PERSON>Frank 
Minnifield</PERSON>, who ended his holdout last week and had an interception <DATE>Monday</DATE> 
<TIME>night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
"This meant a lot to a lot of people," <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"It was almost a 'must' win for us." 
</P>
<P>
Denver (2-3), which suffered five turnovers in a loss to <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE>, 
took advantage of two <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> turnovers to overcome a 20-19 deficit early in 
the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Then came <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>. He completed a 24-yard pass to <PERSON>Vernon Joines</PERSON> on fourth and two 
from midfield, then threw his third touchdown pass of the game, a 24-yarder to 
<PERSON>Brennan</PERSON> with 3:21 left. 
</P>
<P>
The final drive started with 2:04 left. Kosar completed passes of 15 yards to 
<PERSON>Joines</PERSON>, 20 to <PERSON>Reggie Langhorne</PERSON> and 15 to <PERSON>Brennan</PERSON> on a third-and-eight play to 
set up the winning field goal. 
</P>
<P>
"There's been a lot of heat on the team this year, and to come back in the 
fourth period the way we did is a tribute to a lot of guys," <PERSON>Carson</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA120489-0024 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 143661 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 4, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 9; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
374 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BROWNS SHOOT BLANKS IN BATTLE OF OHIO; 
</P>
<P>
CINCINNATI: IT HANDS CLEVELAND ITS FIRST SHUTOUT AT HOME SINCE 1977. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CLEVELAND 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Cincinnati Bengals</ORGANIZATION> didn't realize how badly things were going for the 
<LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION> until they saw it in person <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"If you would have told me that we would shut out the Browns, I would have said 
it was impossible," <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> receiver <PERSON>Tim McGee</PERSON> said after catching four 
passes, including one on a 38-yard touchdown pass play, as the Bengals blanked 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, 21-0. 
</P>
<P>
Obviously, <PERSON>McGee</PERSON> hadn't been paying attention to the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' offensive problems 
in recent weeks. Their three-game total of 20 points is the lowest for any 
three-game span in franchise history. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s shutout was <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s first at home since <DATE>1977</DATE>, and it came against 
a <LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION> team that hadn't blanked anyone since <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"The defense lately has not been playing up to its potential," <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 
linebacker <PERSON>Reggie Williams</PERSON> said. "This week, we managed to turn it around. We 
got some hits on <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> early in the game. When you do that, it can be a 
long day for the quarterback." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> was benched after three quarters, more because of his ineffectiveness 
than his sore right elbow. <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>, who completed 15 of 30 passes for 130 yards, 
hasn't thrown a touchdown pass in 14 quarters. 
</P>
<P>
"It starts with the quarterback, and I want to take responsibility for the 
football team," said <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>, who bruised his elbow three weeks ago in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>. 
"I was disappointed. But I don't play the coach, and that's their decision to 
make. 
</P>
<P>
"There were a couple hits out there and the arm was a little sore, but I don't 
think it was anything of any significance." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>, who was warming his elbow on the sidelines between possessions because 
of the 18-degree temperature and minus-10 wind chill factor, was booed heartily 
by the sellout crowd of 76,236 throughout the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>. The stands were 
nearly empty by late in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Cincinnati quarterback <PERSON>Boomer Esiason</PERSON> completed 14 of 32 passes for 197 yards 
with two touchdowns and two interceptions as the Bengals (7-6) put themselves 
back in the <ORGANIZATION>AFC Central Division</ORGANIZATION> race, one game behind <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> (8-5) and a half 
game behind the Browns (7-5-1). 
</P>
<P>
The victory gave the Bengals their first two-game sweep in the annual "battle 
for Ohio" since <DATE>1984</DATE>. <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> beat <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, 21-14, <DATE>Sept. 25</DATE> at <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Tim McGee (left) and Boomer Esiaison celebrate a touchdown. Associated 
Press; Photo, In the grasp -- Wide receiver Tim McGee of Cincinnati hauls in a 
29-yard pass from Boomer Esiason in the Bengals' 21-0 victory over Cleveland. 
Story, C9. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011390-0123 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 161622 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 13, 1990, Saturday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 4; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
928 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
4 QUARTERBACKS, 1 SUPER BOWL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KEN MURRAY, BALTIMORE EVENING SUN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
This is the time of year that can make or break a quarterback. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Terry Bradshaw</PERSON> couldn't spell "cat" until he starred in a Super Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Phil Simms</PERSON> was never good enough in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> until he was perfect in a Super 
Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Doug Williams</PERSON> never got the payday he deserved until he broke down barriers in 
a Super Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
If this is <DATE>January</DATE>, then the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> spotlight must be on the quarterback. Heading 
into the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> championship games, this year's roll call of Final Four 
quarterbacks is typical of the times. 
</P>
<P>
There's <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Elway</PERSON> -- the unorthodox, side-arming flinger 
against the once golden boy -- in <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s AFC showdown between <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
There's <PERSON>Jim Everett</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Joe Montana</LOCATION> -- the new kid on the block against the 
master -- in the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION>'s matchup between the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Rams</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 
49ers. 
</P>
<P>
Somewhere in that group is a Super Bowl winner: if it's <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, a repeat 
winner, waiting the call of fame and fortune. 
</P>
<P>
Elway and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> know a little about the territory. Elway is a two-time Super 
Bowl loser with the Broncos, born of expectations that at times have been 
surrealistic. <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> is a three-time winner whose former coach was ready to 
phase him out as recently as <DATE>November 1988</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Indeed, of the four, only <PERSON>Everett</PERSON> has not been drummed through the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s school 
of hard knocks. <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> was booed this season in <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>. All he did was win 
four division titles in five years as a pro. Elway was booed in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. All he 
did was win a pair of <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> championships. 
</P>
<P>
"There (were) some unpleasant things said and <PERSON>John</PERSON> hasn't had an easy year," 
said <PERSON>Dan Reeves</PERSON>, <PERSON>Elway</PERSON>'s coach in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>. "But he has performed well, and he 
showed last week he still is able to do great things." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Elway</PERSON>, 29, became the third player in <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> history to have five straight 
3,000-yard seasons. <PERSON>Dan Marino</PERSON> and <PERSON>Boomer Esiason</PERSON> are the others. Counting <DATE>last 
week</DATE>'s come-from-behind win over <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, he has brought the Broncos back 16 
times with last-minute rallies. It was <PERSON>Elway</PERSON>'s crucial 36-yard completion to 
<PERSON>Vance Johnson</PERSON> on a flea-flicker that set up the <PERSON>Broncos</PERSON>' winning touchdown in a 
24-23 win over the <ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
If there's one thing <PERSON>Marty Schottenheimer</PERSON> appreciates in <LOCATION>Elway</LOCATION>, it's his 
competitive fire. 
</P>
<P>
"When you talk about his mobility and strong arm, the one thing people fail to 
recognize is that he probably is as great a competitor as there is," said 
<PERSON>Schottenheimer</PERSON>, head coach in <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> who lost two <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> title games to <PERSON>Elway</PERSON> 
while in <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I've coached him in the <LOCATION>Pro Bowl</LOCATION>, and I've seen enough of him to know the guy 
is a great competitor. And if you look at all four of these quarterbacks, 
that's one common thread they all have." 
</P>
<P>
Kosar's competitiveness helped him endure a year of insult and injury in 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>. The <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' quarterback bruised his right elbow in a Week 10 victory 
over <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>. He played through the pain, and in the next four games the Browns 
went 0-3-1. When he went 20 quarters without a touchdown pass, he was booed at 
home. 
</P>
<P>
"If you ask <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON> how he is, he won't ever say he's hurting," said <PERSON>Bud Carson</PERSON>, 
who replaced <PERSON>Schottenheimer</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>. "But we've discussed it with the 
doctors and they say he isn't in any career-threatening situation. He just has 
had some different arm problems. 
</P>
<P>
"When the time comes to throw the ball, especially in a big game when we have 
to have it, <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON> comes through. We were much more concerned about him <DATE>last 
week</DATE>, health-wise, than this week." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>, 26, has had elbow, shoulder and finger ailments this year. Last week, 
with various parts of his anatomy hurting, he completed 20 of 29 passes for 235 
yards, three touchdowns and no interceptions. Despite the injuries, <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> still 
passed for 3,533 yards and 18 touchdowns this season. 
</P>
<P>
It doesn't surprise <PERSON>Schottenheimer</PERSON>. "The thing that stands out is that at a 
point in time when everybody thought he would be at his worst, he got the job 
done," his former coach said. "That speaks volumes about <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON> as a winning 
quarterback." 
</P>
<P>
At a point in time when then-coach <PERSON>Bill Walsh</PERSON> was ready to pass the 49ers' 
quarterbacking torch from <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Steve Young</PERSON> last season, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> responded 
with some of the best football of his life. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers won seven of their last eight games a year ago, and with <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> 
showing the way, capped the season with a dramatic <DATE>20-16</DATE> victory over 
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Super Bowl XXIII</LOCATION>. His 92-yard drive at game's end produced the 
winning touchdown, a 10-yard scoring pass to <PERSON>John Taylor</PERSON>. This year, the 49ers 
are 15-2 going into <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s showdown, and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> has elevated his game still 
another notch. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, 33, completed a staggering <PERCENT>70.2 percent</PERCENT> of his passes this season and 
posted the highest passer rating in <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> history, 112.4. His 
touchdown-to-interception ratio of 26-8 is the best of his 11-year career. 
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> was named the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s MVP for his superior season. 
</P>
<P>
Said first-year 49ers Coach <PERSON>George Seifert</PERSON>, "Any superlative you can use to 
describe him fits." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s next playoff touchdown pass will tie him with <PERSON>Bradshaw</PERSON> for the league 
record of 30. 
</P>
<P>
As fate would have it, there are those who compare young Everett to the veteran 
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>. In his second full season as the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION>' starting quarterback, <PERSON>Everett</PERSON> 
passed for 4,310 yards and an NFL-high 29 touchdowns. He has a strong arm, 
quick release and soft touch. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a great compliment," <PERSON>Everett</PERSON> said of the comparison. "He (<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>) has 
proven time and time again he's a Super Bowl winner, and I think that's the 
judgment on quarterbacks. Comparisons are great, but I don't have a Super 
Bowl." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881115-0084 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Sports: Mediocrity's the Word Around NFL </HL>
<AUTHOR> Frederick C. Klein </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> Denver  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Politics has its Misery Index, which combines unemployment and inflation to gauge how well or poorly off we the people are. 
A similar measure can be applied to the <ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION>. 
Call it the Mediocrity Index, if you will. 
It measures how many teams are within a game of .500, a workable definition of the common stew. 

   A perusal of the standings at the cessation of hostilities <DATE>Sunday</DATE> revealed 11 of the 28 <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> teams to have been mediocre after 11 weeks, sporting won-lost records of 6-5, 5-5-1, 5-5 or 5-6. 
If that figure holds for the season as a whole, it would be the third highest of this decade, trailing only <DATE>1983</DATE>'s 16 and <DATE>1981</DATE>'s 12. 
That would make it a better than fair-to-middling year for mediocrity. 

   As the winter winds begin to sting the nose, the identity of the mediocre is as interesting as their number. 
The rank includes the defending Super Bowl champion <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Redskins, who were embearrassed on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> by <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, 34-14, in their own park, to drop their record to 6-5 and imperil their chances for a repeat. 

   The ever-popular <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers find unexpected mediocrity gravy on their jerseys as a result of a <DATE>Sunday</DATE> beating by their old neighbors, the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Raiders</ORGANIZATION>. 
Four of the five teams in the <ORGANIZATION>American Conference</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Division</ORGANIZATION> qualify. 
So do the <LOCATION>Seattle Seahawks</LOCATION>, who haven't been getting their Boz-worth out of their much-injured linebacker, <PERSON>Brian</PERSON>. 

   But whether your MI glass is half full or half empty depends on your perspective. 
The <PERSON>Denver Broncos</PERSON>, party of the second part in the past two <LOCATION>Super Bowls</LOCATION>, were smiling ear-to-ear over their 6-5 record at dusk here <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, while the <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION> were in the dumps over the same numbers. 
That's because the Broncos had just gobbled up a plateful of turnovers to dump the <LOCATION>Browns</LOCATION>, 30-7, and boost their playoff hopes at the <ORGANIZATION>Browns</ORGANIZATION>' expense. 

   The last time these two teams met, the only "m" word anyone was using was "marvelous." 
That was last season's AFC championship game in Mile High Stadium. 
The Broncs won it, 38-33, but not before the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> had come back from a 21-3 deficit and were an <ORGANIZATION>Earnest Byner</ORGANIZATION> stride from a tying, last-minute touchdown before a fumble thwarted them. 
Given the run of recent Super Bowls, it wouldn't have been a bad idea to end the season right there and decide the league champ by ballot. 
Alas, they played the thing, and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> beat the Broncs in a 42-10 ho-hummer. 

   Cleveland impressed enough to become a lot of people's pre-season title choice, and to put its tall quarterback, <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON>, on many a magazine cover. 
Storky <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON>, however, was casualty No. 1 in this year's quarterback injury plague by sustaining a sprained knee in game one, and spent the next six leaning on crutches while his mates relied on stout defense (the best in the conference before <DATE>Sunday</DATE>) to acquire a 4-3 mark. 

   Kosar returned on <DATE>Oct. 23</DATE> and led two victories, causing the <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> faithful to joyfully conclude that all was well. 
But the bad-boy <ORGANIZATION>Houston Oilers</ORGANIZATION> whopped the <ORGANIZATION>Browns</ORGANIZATION> country-style a week ago <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, and the <LOCATION>Broncos</LOCATION> followed suit <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 

   Not surprisingly, the supposed after-effects of the bruising administered by the Oilers came up frequently in the losers' dressing room here. 
Cleveland coach <PERSON>Marty Schottenheimer</PERSON> declared it had "absolutely nothing" to do with the latest setback, but some of his troops demurred. 
"We could have been a little drawn out from that game," said defensive end <PERSON>Carl Hairston</PERSON>. 
"They hit pretty hard." 

   The situation on the <PERSON>Broncos</PERSON>' side was a bit different. 
This gang had managed to retain a scrappy, underdog image while compiling the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s best regular-season record over the 1983-87 campaigns (54-24-1) and winning conference titles the past two years. 
But, perhaps surrendering to angst, they came out flat early this season and lost three of their first four. 

   Three wins perked things up, but the team surrendered 94 points in losses to <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> (!) and <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, and had all it could do to edge a <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Chiefs</ORGANIZATION> team that's so bad it has been denounced on the editorial page of the <ORGANIZATION>Kansas City Times</ORGANIZATION>. (Danders up, the Chiefs beat the 8-2 <LOCATION>Cincinnati Bengals</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
That's the kind of season it's been.) 

   "I don't know the reasons, but we weren't playing together the first couple months of this season. 
Nothing much was in synch," confirms veteran <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> guard <PERSON>Keith Bishop</PERSON>. 

   So unpromising was the <PERSON>Broncos</PERSON>' outlook (and so porous their worst-in-the-league defense against the run) that they entered <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s fray a three-point underdog even though they'd beaten the Browns nine straight times going back to <DATE>1974</DATE>. 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s game plan was to run straight at the <ORGANIZATION>Broncos</ORGANIZATION>' 260-pound defensive linemen, who are teeny weeny by <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> standards. 
Fullback <PERSON>Tim Manoa</PERSON> got the first call. 

   But -- oops! -- Bronco nose tackle <PERSON>Greg Kragen</PERSON> butted the ball from <ORGANIZATION>Manoa</ORGANIZATION>'s hands, defensive back <PERSON>Dennis Smith</PERSON> recovered on the <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> 22-yard line and, in the course of time, a Rich <PERSON>Karlis</PERSON> field goal gave <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> a 3-0 lead. 
The Broncos possessed the ball six times in the first half -- four times on <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> turnovers -- and each time they scored. 
The <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> went oh-for-seven, and took their half-time ease on the short end of a 30-0 count. 

   The second half was pro forma, with the <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> fans amusing themselves by floating paper airplanes onto the field and the Broncos finding sport in chasing <PERSON>Kosar</PERSON>, who runs like he's on stilts. 
They caught him six times, for 35 yards in losses. 

   As usual, the <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> offensive star was quarterback <PERSON>John Elway</PERSON>, who flipped, zipped and darted as in days of yore, which is to say last year. 
It was, he said later, "a good win, maybe one we can build on. 
It was nice to have a cushion for a change." 

   In the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' boudoir, veteran tight end <PERSON>Ozzie Newsome</PERSON> was saying that, perhaps, adversity would rally his team where high hopes had failed. 
"Maybe we'll circle the wagons, like the cowboys did when the Indians attacked," he said. 
I considered telling him about <PERSON>Custer</PERSON>, but thought better of it. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091789-0124 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 108562 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 17, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 14; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1258 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NFL CLUBS LEAN TOWARD DEFENSIVE SPECIALISTS AS HEAD COACHES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By GREG GARBER, The Hartford Courant 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Only a decade ago, defensive coaches in the <ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION> were a lot 
like <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> -- fine in their place but not generally considered chief 
executive officer material. 
</P>
<P>
"In <DATE>1979</DATE> we went to (Ray) <PERSON>Perkins</PERSON> as the head coach," <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants General 
Manager George Young</ORGANIZATION> said. "He was an offensive coordinator, one of the golden 
boys. (Bill) <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON>, (Joe) <PERSON>Gibbs</PERSON> and later (Dan) <PERSON>Reeves</PERSON> and (<PERSON>Mike</PERSON>) <PERSON>Ditka</PERSON> were 
the guys people were hiring. At the time, the defensive coaches in the league 
did not think they had a chance of becoming head coach. 
</P>
<P>
The Golden Boy Syndrome, as Young calls it, no longer prevails. Now, the 
league's owners are increasingly turning their teams over to defensive wizards. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s 28 head coaches are split; 14 are offensive specialists and 14 are 
defensive specialists. But of the six newcomers this season, five have a 
defensive resume. Three teams -- the <LOCATION>Kansas City Chiefs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Detroit Lions</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers -- made the switch from offense to defense. 
</P>
<P>
Although there are prevailing circumstances surrounding most new hires (for 
instance, <ORGANIZATION>Dallas Cowboys</ORGANIZATION> owner <PERSON>Jerry Jones</PERSON> was the roommate of Coach <PERSON>Jimmy 
Johnson</PERSON> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Arkansas</ORGANIZATION>), defense has become fashionable again in 
the fickle <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The laundry list: <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Marty Schottenheimer</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Wayne 
Fontes</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>; <PERSON>George Seifert</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Bud Carson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION>; 
<PERSON>Dan Henning</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Diego Chargers</LOCATION>. Only <PERSON>Henning</PERSON> has extensive experience on 
offense. 
</P>
<P>
"In the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>, we copy success and believe in reincarnation," said <PERSON>Ernie Accorsi</PERSON>, 
many of <PERSON>Vince Lombardi</PERSON>'s assistants were hired over the years. That's why 
people are loading up on defense after the (<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>) Bears and Giants won the 
Super Bowl. It's true with players and it's true with coaches." 
</P>
<P>
Accorsi says he interviewed seven defensive coordinators after <PERSON>Schottenheimer</PERSON> 
was fired over philosophical differences with owner Art <ORGANIZATION>Modell</ORGANIZATION>. With a 
successful quarterback, offensive coordinator and receivers coach already on 
board, <PERSON>Accorsi</PERSON> wanted to maintain offensive continuity. 
</P>
<P>
Most team executives interviewed for this story said that offensive or 
defensive expertise meant less than the character of the individual coach. 
However, most agreed that the bias toward offense that existed early in the 
<DATE>1980s</DATE> has subsided. 
</P>
<P>
"My feeling has never changed," <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said. "You have to run and play defense. 
Sure, there's a trend there, but it comes down to the individual. There were 
some non-football people at the beginning of the decade who thought getting an 
offensive coordinator, a fancy passing game, would solve everything. 
</P>
<P>
"The myth has been exploded. (Don) <LOCATION>Shula</LOCATION>, (Tom) <LOCATION>Landry</LOCATION>, (<PERSON>Chuck</PERSON>) <PERSON>Noll</PERSON>, (Weeb) 
Ewbank ... they all came from defense, but people forgot about it because that 
was a long time ago." 
</P>
<P>
In an effort to open up the game, the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> liberalized pass-blocking rules in 
<DATE>1977</DATE> and <DATE>1978</DATE>. The immediate result was more points. The long-term effect was a 
new premium on defense. 
</P>
<P>
Overmatched by offenses, defenses were forced to respond. As teams began to 
become more aggressive through blitzing in <DATE>1983</DATE>, defensive touchdowns increased 
sharply as offensive touchdowns began to decline. 
</P>
<P>
Oddly enough, <DATE>1983</DATE> was the year two defensive coordinators were elevated to 
head coaching jobs by their teams, <PERSON>Bill Parcells</PERSON> with the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Marion 
Campbell</PERSON> with the <LOCATION>Philadelphia Eagles</LOCATION>. Just after the announcements had been 
made following the <DATE>1982</DATE> season, the two men met at the Senior Bowl in <LOCATION>Mobile</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Ala</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"There's a lot of pressure on us," <PERSON>Campbell</PERSON> told <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON>. "A lot of defensive 
guys are looking to us. If we fail, they'll never get hired." 
</P>
<P>
Fortunately for the <ORGANIZATION>Carsons</ORGANIZATION> and Seiferts of the world, <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> 
made generally favorable impressions. At the same time, some of the league's 
defenses began to emerge as dominant. 
</P>
<P>
Despite a finesse label traceable to <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> and quarterback <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION> team that capped the <DATE>1984</DATE> season by winning Super Bowl XIX had a 
ruthless defense directed by <PERSON>Seifert</PERSON>. The <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bears of</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>1985</DATE> allowed three 
playoff opponents a ridiculous total of 10 points on the way to victory in 
Super Bowl XX. The <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>' savage defense was a chief factor in a 17-2 season, 
including a victory in Super Bowl XXI. 
</P>
<P>
And so, owners were not afraid to give defensive coaches a chance. <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 
defensive coordinator Buddy Ryan accepted the <ORGANIZATION>Eagles</ORGANIZATION>' head coaching job <DATE>Jan</DATE>. 
<DATE>29, 1986</DATE>, three days after his defense shredded the <ORGANIZATION>New England Patriots</ORGANIZATION> in the 
ultimate game. He has prospered in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> and last season gave the <LOCATION>Eagles</LOCATION> 
their first division title in eight years. 
</P>
<P>
Following that <DATE>1986</DATE> season, the <ORGANIZATION>Houston Oilers</ORGANIZATION> promoted defensive coordinator 
<PERSON>Jerry Glanville</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>New Orleans Saints</ORGANIZATION> hired <PERSON>Jim Mora</PERSON>, a successful <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
Football League coach who once served as the Patriots' defensive coordinator. 
Gene <PERSON>Stallings</PERSON>, <PERSON>Landry</PERSON>'s defensive backs coach for 14 seasons in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, was 
the choice of the <ORGANIZATION>St. Louis Cardinals</ORGANIZATION>. Glanville and <PERSON>Mora</PERSON>, who have led their 
teams to the playoffs, are considered saviors in their respective areas. 
</P>
<P>
This past off-season brought more turnover than usual at the top of <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> teams. 
<PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> and <PERSON>Landry</PERSON> retired, and <PERSON>Schottenheimer</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Frank Gansz</PERSON>, 
<LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Darryl Rogers</PERSON> and <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Al Saunders</PERSON> were all fired. 
</P>
<P>
"I didn't hire <PERSON>Marty</PERSON> just because he was a defensive coach," said <PERSON>Carl 
Peterson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>'s general manager and chief operating officer. "But you 
win with defense. It's logic. If you can build a good defense, you always have 
a chance to win. I've always believed that. That's why I hired <PERSON>Jim Mora</PERSON> for the 
(<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>) Stars (of the USFL)." 
</P>
<P>
Carson, the creative defensive coordinator of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Jets, was the first 
choice of the Browns. Accorsi was impressed with <PERSON>Carson</PERSON>'s knowledge of offense. 
</P>
<P>
"He's been defensing offenses for years," <PERSON>Accorsi</PERSON> said. "He knows which 
offensive schemes give him the most trouble and how to deal with them. 
</P>
<P>
"The whole idea that an offensive guy is that different from a defensive guy is 
the most overblown, ridiculous theory. People think they're different sports. 
Look at <LOCATION>Shula</LOCATION> and Landry ... they were defensive guys and they were still 
calling the plays on the sidelines." 
</P>
<P>
Carson devotes <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT> of his time to defense, something evident in 
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s 51-0 bombing of the <ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</ORGANIZATION> in last week's opener. He 
is content to let <PERSON>Marc Trestman</PERSON>, who tutored starter <PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON> as well as 
<PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON> and <PERSON>Vinny Testaverde</PERSON> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Miami</ORGANIZATION>, run the offense. 
</P>
<P>
Fontes was the defensive coordinator under <PERSON>John McKay</PERSON> at <LOCATION>Tampa Bay</LOCATION>, but when he 
was passed over in favor of <PERSON>Leeman Bennett</PERSON> on <PERSON>McKay</PERSON>'s retirement, he joined the 
Lions in <DATE>1985</DATE>. When <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> was fired with five games left <DATE>last season</DATE>, <PERSON>Fontes</PERSON> 
was named interim coach. He was retained by owner <PERSON>William Clay Ford</PERSON> because he 
won as many games as <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> (two) in six fewer tries. 
</P>
<P>
One of <PERSON>Fontes</PERSON>' first acts was hiring <PERSON>Mouse Davis</PERSON>, creator of the run-and-shoot 
offense, as his offensive coordinator. Although it is too early to call, 
<LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> is more likely to win games with its young defense this year. 
</P>
<P>
Ten years ago, <PERSON>Fontes</PERSON> might never have gotten the chance. 
</P>
<P>
"Saying that defensive guys can't be head coaches is like saying men make 
better engineers than women," <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said. "It's only because you see more men 
as engineers. Now that more women are in the field that mold has been broken. 
That's what's happening with defensive coaches in the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Wayne Fontes (in photo at left with Detroit Lion owner William Clay 
Ford) and Bud Carson (in photo at right with Cleveland Browns owner Art Modell) 
represent a new breed of NFL head coach. Associated Press; Photo, Defensive 
coordinator George Seifert replaced offensive genius Bill Walsh as 49ers head 
coach after Super Bowl-winning season. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1317EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ABCApology     10-14 0238</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-ABC Apology,0278</SECOND>
<HEAD>ABC To Make Amends To Cleveland</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ABC television will try to soothe bruised
feelings in <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> stemming from a joke in a promotion for the
situation comedy ``Coach,'' the mayor's office says.
   <PERSON>Robert A. Iger</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>ABC Entertainment</ORGANIZATION>, promised to air
an apology the night of <DATE>Oct. 22</DATE>, when <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> broadcasts the <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland
Browns</ORGANIZATION>' home game against the <LOCATION>Cincinnati Bengals</LOCATION>, a statement by
Mayor <PERSON>Michael R. White</PERSON>'s office said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   When the Browns played in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> against the <LOCATION>Broncos</LOCATION> on <DATE>Oct. 8</DATE>,
the network broadcast a brief promotion for ``Coach.''
   Actor <PERSON>Jerry Van Dyke</PERSON>, who plays an assistant college football
coach on the series, commented that even if the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON> beat <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>,
they would still lose ``because they have to go back to
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>.''
   White sent a letter to <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>, calling the remark insensitive and
disrespectful to the city.
   ``Any comedian or comedy show that uses <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> as the punch
line for a joke has never visited our city and is relying on what
has been for years the crutch of feeble comedians,'' <PERSON>White</PERSON> said in
his letter to <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>.
   Iger's letter explained that <PERSON>Van Dyke</PERSON>'s joke was done ``in
character'' and that no malice was intended. Iger noted that two
weeks earlier, during a <ORGANIZATION>Monday Night Football</ORGANIZATION> broadcast, Van Dyke
made the same comment about <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   ``We firmly believe this incident should be kept in the proper
perspective, and given the problems existing in the world today, we
urge you and the citizens of your fine city to take this in the
lighthearted spirit in which it was meant,'' <PERSON>Iger</PERSON> wrote.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06343241 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06343241 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; TELEVISION; GAME; STATISTIC  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Kickoff: 10 a.m., Cleveland Stadium; Line: Even.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DENVER BRONCOS VS. CLEVELAND BROWNS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The NFL/Week 15; Today's TV Matchups  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  Television: ch. 4, 8; Records: <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> is 9-4, tied with the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles
Raiders</ORGANIZATION> for the lead in the AFC <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> is 6-7, second in the <ORGANIZATION>AFC
Central</ORGANIZATION>. The Browns trail <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> by three games.; Series: <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> leads 12-5.;
Broncos update: Coach <PERSON>Dan Reeves</PERSON> can claim his 100th NFL regular-season
victory with a sixth win in eight games at <LOCATION>Cleveland Stadium</LOCATION>. <PERSON>John Elway</PERSON>
completed 18 of 25 passes for 215 yards with a TD in a 20-3 victory over <LOCATION>New
England</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE>. The Broncos have an AFC-leading 39 sacks and 19
