<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06232040 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06232040 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  MARRIAGE; END; RESULT; FAMILY; RELATION; REPORT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A third of divorced fathers over the age of 50 lose all contact with at least
one of their adult children, according to new research presented Sunday at the
fathers more than mothers when marriages end, and many fathers say their
ex-wives block their efforts to have a good relationship with the children,
said the authors of two other studies presented at the convention.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DIVORCED DADS LOSING CONTACT WITH KIDS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related article on page 1A of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Psychologist <PERSON>Charles Hoffman</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>California State University</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San
Bernardino</LOCATION>, said the findings indicate there should be an "affirmative action
program for divorced fathers," who currently lose custody of their children in
<PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of failed marriages.;   "Sex roles won't change until (divorced)
mothers and fathers parent equally," he said.;   Only half had weekly contact;
  The study of older divorced fathers, conducted by sociologist <PERSON>Peter
half of the 261 subjects had weekly contact with their adult children,
compared to <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of married men.;   But a third of the divorced men had
lost all contact with at least one of their children.;   "Adult children are
the principal source of care-giving to older people," he said. "(Older
divorced fathers) are not only lacking a spouse, they're also lacking children
who will come in and provide support." Uhlenberg cited data from his study
showing that only <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of divorced men turn to their children in an
emergency, compared to <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of married men.;   The study was of divorced
men over 50 who had at least one biological child over the age of 19. It did
not indicate at what age the men were divorced.;   Children side with mothers;
  In another study, psychologist <PERSON>Kathleen Welch</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Northridge</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Southern
California</LOCATION> discovered that children usually side with their mothers after
divorces and blame their fathers for the marital rift. That blame only gets
worse as the children age, she said.;   "Divorce loosens the bonds to
fathers," said Welch.;   Together, the new research suggests that fathers
suffer more long-term problems after divorce than was previously thought.;  
Earlier divorce research focused on such topics as the economic problems
suffered by women and children after divorce.;   Wives blamed;   <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON>'s
research on 142 divorced fathers between the ages of 22 and 67 showed that
half said their ex-wives sabotage their efforts to maintain a good
relationship with their children.;   "They often say they want to be involved,
and they say their ex-wives keep them from that involvement," said <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON>,
who cited earlier data showing that two-thirds of divorces nationwide are
initiated by women.;   <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON> called on the courts to order joint custody of
children far more often. "Mothers and fathers are equally capable to raise
their children," he said.;   Adult children of divorce -- both men and women
-- have more psychological problems, including anxiety, isolation and fears of
commitment, than children from intact marriages. But the father's active
involvement is especially critical for boys, who suffer more psychological
problems than girls when parents split up, said <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Bernard Bauer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910819  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  520  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, August 19, 1991
00232040,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06212065 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06212065 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  FEMALE; JUVENILE; CHILD; BIRTH; CAUSE; PROBE; REPORT; LIFESTYLE; CHANGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  One of the most troubling facts for social scientists and policy-makers alike
has been the high number of girls in their early teens who become mothers,
especially in America's inner cities.;    Now a novel theory proposes that
these young mothers are responding to a pattern in human evolution that
induces people growing up in extremely stressful circumstances to bear
children early and often. The theory has received considerable attention and
criticism.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SURVIVAL OF THE SUFFERING
THEORY LINKS TEEN PREGNANCY TO EVOLUTIONARY
IMPULSES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Drawing on sociobiology, it holds that these teen-age mothers are
implementing a reproductive strategy that, from an evolutionary viewpoint, is
a smart bet.;    Children who grow up in dangerous conditions, the theory
holds, are primed to boost the chances of having their genes survive into the
next generation by choosing earlier sex, earlier motherhood and more
children.;    "It's not a conscious, deliberate strategy. It's a biological
response. From an evolutionary perspective, life is about dispersing your
genes into the next generation," said <PERSON>Dr. Jay Belsky</PERSON>, a psychologist at
<ORGANIZATION>Pennsylvania State University</ORGANIZATION> and the leading formulator of the new theory.;  
 Earlier puberty;  One prediction of the theory is that girls who grow up in
households where there is great emotional stress, and especially where the
father is absent, will undergo puberty at an earlier age than other girls.;   
The main factors in determining the age of menarche, which is when a girl
begins to menstruate, are genetics, health and nutrition. While these factors
can account for differences of years in the age of menarche, childhood
experiences such as fights between divorcing parents might account for just a
few months' difference, in <LOCATION>Belsky</LOCATION>'s view.;    "It's a small effect
biologically, but quite meaningful, since the timing of menarche is so highly
biologically fixed that no one had thought there was room for psychological
influences at all," said <PERSON>Dr. Laurence Steinberg</PERSON>, a psychologist at <ORGANIZATION>Temple
University</ORGANIZATION> and a colleague of <ORGANIZATION>Belsky's</ORGANIZATION>.;    Though highly controversial, the
theory is receiving wide attention among psychologists and sociologists. Next
month it will be the lead article in the prestigious journal Child
Development.;    The theory already is under attack from other scientists. In
a commentary on the article in the same issue of <ORGANIZATION>Child Development</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Dr.
Eleanor E. Maccoby</PERSON>, a psychologist at <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>, favors a simpler
explanation for the earlier sexual activity and pregnancies of girls from
troubled families: that they receive less parental supervision.;    <PERSON>Terrie
Moffitt</PERSON>, a psychologist at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION> and co-author with
<PERSON>Belsky</PERSON> of one key study, believes that a hidden factor may be the mothers' age
of puberty, a factor that was not studied in his research.;    "It's a genetic
fact that girls tend to have the same age of menarche as their mothers,"
<PERSON>Moffitt</PERSON> said. "And it is also true that the earlier a girl develops sexually,
the earlier, on average, she will date and marry. And those who marry earliest
tend to have made the worst marital choices.";    In analyzing data from a
study of 501 girls in <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Moffitt</PERSON> found that of the 81 girls who
reached puberty at 12 or earlier, 40 had grown up in households in which the
father was absent for many years, most because of divorce.;    But of the 82
girls who did not reach puberty until age 14 or later, only 20 had fathers who
were absent.;    From turbulent homes;  <PERSON>Belsky</PERSON> also cites a study of 1,123
girls published in <DATE>1990</DATE> by <PERSON>Dr. Michele Surbey</PERSON>, a psychologist at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Toronto</ORGANIZATION>. Surbey found that those girls who had gone through
childhood in homes where their parents were fighting and finally divorced had
menarche about four months earlier, on average, than girls from homes with
little conflict.;    However, in preliminary analysis of data from 4,800 girls
in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dr. Andrew Cherlin</PERSON>, a sociologist at <ORGANIZATION>Johns Hopkins University</ORGANIZATION>,
found no difference in the age of menarche between girls whose parents had and
had not divorced.;    To many social scientists who have studied teen-age
pregnancies, seeking the causes in evolution seems fanciful.;    The
conclusion of <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION> sociologist <PERSON>Elijah Anderson</PERSON>,
published earlier this year, is that the more immediate cause of teen-age
sexuality and pregnancy is to be found in a lack of jobs, which leaves many
poor teen-agers with little sense that their futures hold any promise.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DANIEL GOLEMAN, New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910730  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  712  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday July 30, 1991
00212065,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031690-0158 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 190602 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 16, 1990, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 8; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
883 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CHILD'S 'BEST INTERESTS' GUIDE JUDGES' DECISIONS; 
</P>
<P>
LAW: DETERMINING WHO GETS CUSTODY IS A FREQUENTLY COMPLICATED PROCEDURE, AND 
ONE THAT HAS EVOLVED GREATLY IN THE PAST 40 YEARS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Children often find themselves in the middle of a tug of war when their parents 
get divorced. 
</P>
<P>
The scene is played out thousands of times a year in courtrooms across the 
country: A man and a woman realize that their crumbling marriage cannot be 
saved, so one or each of them files for divorce. If they have children, custody 
becomes an issue. And when both parents want custody, the result is often an 
emotional battle in which their kids are caught in the cross-fire. 
</P>
<P>
"Everyone thinks he or she is acting in the best interests of the child," said 
<PERSON>Dr. Stephen P. Herman</PERSON>, a child and adolescent psychiatrist with a practice in 
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. "But unfortunately, that's not always the case." 
</P>
<P>
Acting in a child's best interests is a legal requirement in child-custody 
cases. Moreover, it is being used as a guide to address emerging trends such as 
surrogate parents, unmarried parents, homosexual couples, frozen embryos and 
grandparents' rights. 
</P>
<P>
Determining a child's best interests is a delicate and frequently complicated 
procedure in which lawyers, psychiatrists, psychologists and social workers all 
make recommendations that are considered by a judge before he or she makes a 
decision. 
</P>
<P>
The recommendations of these experts are made after extensive interviews or 
counseling sessions with the parents and, usually separately, their children. 
Mental health experts are frequently called upon to testify for one side or the 
other, but sometimes the court will appoint its own expert to ensure impartial 
testimony. After weighing all the factors in a custody case, the judge will 
make a decision based on the <ORGANIZATION>Best Interests Standard</ORGANIZATION>, which has become the 
guide by which custody cases are decided. 
</P>
<P>
The Best Interests Standard, which <PERSON>Herman</PERSON> called "the guiding presumption of 
the courts today," has been in use for about 40 years and differs significantly 
from previous standards, in which the sex of the parent was the determining 
factor in almost all such cases. 
</P>
<P>
"For most of civilization, children were considered the 'property' of the 
father," <PERSON>Herman</PERSON> said. "This was laid down by Roman law and continued through 
the Renaissance until the last part of the <DATE>19th Century</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
By that time, children were no longer considered property; instead, they were 
viewed as "little people" who would be better cared for by their mothers. 
</P>
<P>
"Mothers were then seen as the so-called 'better-fit' parents," <PERSON>Herman</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
That led to the adoption of the <ORGANIZATION>Tender Years Doctrine</ORGANIZATION>, a legal standard that 
almost always gave custody of young children to their mothers. After the 
children turned 7, however, they were often returned to their fathers. 
</P>
<P>
"This really could have been very disruptive," <PERSON>Herman</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
For this and other reasons, notably the constitutional guarantee of equal 
protection under the law, the Best Interests Standard was established just 
after World War II and has since become what <PERSON>Herman</PERSON> called "the major trend 
that forms judicial opinion" in such cases. 
</P>
<P>
Although judges are guided by this standard, <PERSON>Herman</PERSON> added, "there is, in fact, 
a strong feeling among judges that mothers are better parents, especially of 
younger kids." 
</P>
<P>
This, he said, is borne out by the fact that in most cases, the mother gets 
custody of the children. Although there is no one organization or agency that 
compiles nationwide custody statistics, according to <PERSON>Herman</PERSON> and other 
professionals interviewed for this story, they all said that mothers get 
custody in the vast majority of uncontested cases, perhaps as much as <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of 
them. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Judge Stanley Novack</PERSON>, who has heard child-custody cases at <ORGANIZATION>Superior Court</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Stamford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, for the past 15 years, disagrees with <PERSON>Herman</PERSON>, saying that 
while mothers often get custody of their children, it is not because judges 
think they are better parents. 
</P>
<P>
"It does work out in many cases that the mother gets the child," <PERSON>Novack</PERSON> said. 
"But that is based on relationship. One of the factors to consider is, who is 
the psychological parent? To which parent is the child bonded? In many cases 
the child is bonded to his or her mother because he or she is with the mother 
most of the day. In that case the woman may get custody, but not simply because 
she is the mother." 
</P>
<P>
Novack also points out that since the institution of the <ORGANIZATION>Best Interests 
Standard</ORGANIZATION>, a greater number of fathers are winning custody. And he agrees with 
<PERSON>Herman</PERSON> that while mothers are still more likely to get custody, fathers win "a 
large percentage" of contested cases. 
</P>
<P>
"Women win a large number of custody cases that are uncontested," <PERSON>Herman</PERSON> said. 
"But when fathers decide to fight it, they win a good deal of the time. I'd say 
about <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT>." 
</P>
<P>
Perhaps the most difficult decision a judge has to make in a custody case is 
whether to give one parent sole custody or to award joint custody. <PERSON>Novack</PERSON> says 
that there are two kinds of joint custody. 
</P>
<P>
"Joint legal custody is when both parents share the decision-making about their 
child or children," he said. "Joint physical custody is when both parents share 
blocks of time with their children." 
</P>
<P>
Joint legal custody is common in situations where the children of a divorced 
couple live primarily with one parent, even though the other parent may have 
visitation rights or has been allowed to take the children for weekends, 
vacations or holidays. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CHILD CUSTODY; DIVORCE; UNITED STATES -- LAWS; CIVIL RIGHTS; UNITED STATES -- 
COURTS; CHILDREN 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042089-0108 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 46414 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 20, 1989, Thursday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 17; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1077 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
RESEARCH MAKES A CASE AGAINST JOINT CUSTODY FOR SOME 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When <PERSON>Kim</PERSON>, a young woman in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>, decided to have a baby, she 
assumed that the child would be hers to bring up as she pleased. After all, she 
was not married to the baby's father, and by the time the baby was born she and 
her boyfriend had irrevocably parted. 
</P>
<P>
But her boyfriend thought otherwise, and the courts agreed. To <PERSON>Kim</PERSON>'s dismay, 
the baby's father was awarded joint physical custody -- the baby boy must spend 
part of each week with his father and part with his mother. Kim has a stormy 
and bitter relationship with her former boyfriend. She said she fears for her 
baby's emotional well-being if he grows up splitting his time between parents 
who are so angry with each other. 
</P>
<P>
"The courts don't seem to be interested in a child's emotional and physical 
well-being," <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> said. "As the judge put it, he's looking for 'cigarette burns, 
bruises and broken bones.' " 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
No One's Best Interest 
</P>
<P>
Psychologist <PERSON>Judith Wallerstein</PERSON>, executive director of the Center for the 
Family in Transition in <LOCATION>Corte Madera</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, emphatically agrees with Kim 
that, in her case, joint physical custody is not in the best interest of 
anyone. 
</P>
<P>
Wallerstein and her colleagues have recently completed a study showing that 
joint physical custody is detrimental to children of divorce if their parents 
are warring. Even if the parents have an amicable relationship, joint custody 
has no effect on the emotional health of the children or on how parents adjust 
to the divorce. 
</P>
<P>
These findings on joint custody are based on three recent studies by 
<PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> and her colleagues. One experiment at <PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON>'s center looked 
at how children adjust to custody arrangements made voluntarily by parents. The 
researchers studied 101 children from a well-educated, middle-class suburban 
community for two years after their parents' divorce. 
</P>
<P>
In about one-third of the families, the parents had voluntarily selected joint 
custody. From a standard battery of tests and clinical interviews, the 
researchers concluded that joint custody makes no difference in these 
children's psychological well-being. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Boys Not Helped 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> was particularly disappointed that such joint-custody families did 
not help boys. Many therapists and social scientists have hoped that boys' 
longing for their fathers could be assuaged by joint custody. 
</P>
<P>
A second experiment, led by <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION> sociologist <PERSON>Janet Johnston</PERSON>, 
looked at 100 families from mixed social and economic classes who were engaged 
in bitter divorces. One-third of the children were in joint custody and the 
rest in sole custody. The researchers found that joint custody was actually 
worse for the children than sole custody. 
</P>
<P>
Girls, in particular, were hurt by these forced arrangements, <PERSON>Wallenstein</PERSON> said. 
"No longer part of her mother's protective orbit," the girl "loses her value 
and her identity as her mother's psychological extension and close ally and 
becomes instead either the fantasy rival, the fantasy traitor -- tainted by 
contact with the enemy -- or both." As a consequence, the girl "has protection 
nowhere," <PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
A third experiment, led by psychologist <PERSON>William Coysh</PERSON>, examined the parents of 
middle-class families to see whether custody arrangements made a difference in 
how parents adjusted to divorce. "One of the most persuasive arguments for 
joint custody has been that fathers feel much better about themselves and are 
better parents when they undertake joint custody of their children," 
<PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> said. But she was surprised by the result: Custody arrangements had 
no effect. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> said the findings "are not an argument against joint custody, but 
they also are not an argument that it will benefit the child." 
</P>
<P>
These results may not surprise experts in family studies, but they are 
politically difficult because they could take away from the gains of fathers' 
rights groups, which have argued for joint custody as a major way for fathers 
to have access to their children. Starting in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE>, joint custody 
became an option for the divorce courts in most states. 
</P>
<P>
Wallerstein's research flies in the face of the conventional wisdom that 
children of divorce do better if they split their time between their parents. 
Not surprisingly, many divorced men have hotly contested her findings. Some 
contend that the study was too small in scope and looked at the parents and 
children for too short a time to be conclusive. 
</P>
<P>
Many divorced men think <PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON>'s findings do not bode well for fathers 
seeking custody. If the courts are persuaded that joint physical custody is 
detrimental, they fear, sole custody will go to the mothers. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>James Cook</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Custody Assn.</ORGANIZATION>, a group with 3,000 members in 
43 states, said half-jokingly that "a natural extrapolation" of <PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON>'s 
study is that more fathers should get sole custody. But, he added, "I think 
that's not likely in today's society." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Disappointing Findings 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> is disappointed that her findings were not more optimistic. "It 
would be nice to feel that we could cut into a child's unhappiness." Children 
of divorce are often unhappy and troubled, regardless of what sort of custody 
arrangements are in place, <PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> said. She said she thinks the focus for 
the children of divorced parents should be on individual relationships with 
each parent, not custody issues. 
</P>
<P>
Researchers think that the most important influence on the emotional health of 
children is the quality of their relationships within their family, however 
that family might be structured, said <PERSON>Robert Emery</PERSON>, a psychologist at the 
<ORGANIZATION>University of Virginia</ORGANIZATION>. For example, psychologists used to think that boys 
needed their father within the home until at least age 7 or 8. Now they have 
discovered that the physical presence of a father in the family is less 
important to boys than are warm and supporting adults. 
</P>
<P>
This shift occurred "partly in recognition of the changing American family and 
the changing demographics of divorce. It is an appreciation of plurality," 
<PERSON>Emery</PERSON> said. But the focus on relationships also means that if divorced parents 
are angry and bitter, children will suffer and they will suffer more if they're 
exposed more to the conflict through joint custody. 
</P>
<P>
"Whether the child feels accepted or rejected is very important," <PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> 
said. "But custody doesn't convey that. It is a much more subtle, much more 
elusive issue of how the child perceives himself within the family." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081389-0171 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 94414 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 13, 1989, Sunday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 8; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
813 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CHILD'S RIGHTS NEED RESPECT TOO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY STARK, Amy Stark is a clinical psychologist in Tustin. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The No. 1 cause of death in children under the age of 1 is child abuse. In our 
media-saturated society, publicized cases of abuse tend to cloud the reality of 
the problem. Grim details and horrific tales of a deranged abuser give the 
image that the problem is only prevalent where there is a severely disturbed 
parent, such as the <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> woman who ran over her baby with the car and 
pleaded postpartum depression as an excuse. 
</P>
<P>
But what about the individual who is not overtly aggressive? Do we stop to 
consider the thousands of people that lead "normal" lives and beat their 
children as a form of punishment or a release of their own frustrations? We 
cannot turn our backs and say, "Well, I don't abuse children." Child abuse is 
not an individual's problem. It is society's problem. We need to work together 
to give children a life free of emotional and physical abuse. 
</P>
<P>
Child abuse appears in two general forms: physical abuse and emotional abuse. 
Physical abuse can and does consist of slapping, punching, biting, burning, 
scratching and sexual molestation. This mistreatment can both maim and kill a 
child. Emotional abuse, which is the most difficult to detect, is a subtle, 
insidious destruction of a child's self-esteem and psychological sense of self. 
This form of abuse can be the most dangerous to a child's psyche. A child that 
is constantly intimidated, belittled and neglected is going to have trouble 
interacting with peers, authority figures and society in general. An abused 
child has severe difficulty growing emotionally; this often leads to 
psychological problems later in life. 
</P>
<P>
Most abused children will not report their own suffering, fearing further abuse 
from their persecutor. Unexplained bruises, welts and burns, children who are 
consistently uncared for and hungry, abrupt changes in behavior and prolonged 
listlessness are all possible signs of child abuse and should be questioned. If 
abuse is reasonably suspected, a national referral service is readily available 
at (800) 4-A-CHILD. 
</P>
<P>
In order for a child to be freed from this suffering, the abuse must be 
reported. However, once the report is made, the situation can sometimes go from 
bad to worse. Abused children tend to develop a love-hate relationship with the 
abuser. Often an abused child will be removed from the home screaming for the 
same person that was abusing him or her, since the child prefers "hell" to the 
unknown. A child may also protect the abuser and deny the abuse in an attempt 
to win love or out of fear of the wrath that may result in admitting to the 
suffering. The child's hesitation to report the details is further complicated 
by the fact that the legal system is usually intent on reuniting a family. 
</P>
<P>
As a therapist, I cannot express how painful it is to help children protect 
themselves when the law cannot. By focusing intently on a parent's rights, the 
law often returns abused children to the parents, resulting in further abuse, 
and sometimes death. A child's rights must be considered to be equally 
important, if not more important, as a parent's, if only for the fact that a 
child is defenseless against an adult. A recent case in <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> shows the 
court's focus on parental rights and family reunification. 
</P>
<P>
A father had been abusing his 7-year-old daughter through repeated physical 
beatings, verbal harassment and sexual molestation. Once the abuse was reported 
and proven, the law intervened to separate the father and the child. 
</P>
<P>
After the separation, the courts wanted to give the father another chance -- 
even though there had been documented evidence of verbal, physical and sexual 
abuse. The father was allowed unsupervised, off-grounds visitation rights and 
the abuse continued. When it was finally realized that abuse was still 
occurring, the father was restricted to supervised visitations. This child 
suffered needless pain and psychological damage -- that may be irreversible -- 
in order to preserve the parent's rights. But what about the child's rights? 
Our legal system is so intent on reunification that it will be recommended even 
when it is not in the child's best interest. 
</P>
<P>
Why should a child's rights take a back seat to the parents'? Child-abuse 
legislation needs a change of focus. Parents should not always have the 
ultimate right, and reunification is not always the answer. 
</P>
<P>
Statistics show that once a family is reunited, child abuse usually occurs 
again. Children deserve the legal right not to be abused. 
</P>
<P>
Our courts need to set some precedence regarding children's rights. We need to 
offer alternatives and counseling to abusive parents, as well as the children. 
It must also be realized that depression and alcoholism do not relieve parents 
of their responsibilities. 
</P>
<P>
We must all work with the legal system by reporting child abuse and instituting 
laws that protect children before another child is afflicted. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Opinion 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880307-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-88 1054EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Scotus-Custody     03-07 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Scotus-Custody,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Refuses to Hear Appeal of Jehovah's Witness in Florida Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>The Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> today refused to hear the
appeal of a <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> woman who says she was denied custody of her
young child because she is a <ORGANIZATION>Jehovah</ORGANIZATION>'s Witness.
   The justices, without comment, let stand state court rulings
that bar <PERSON>Rita Mendez</PERSON> from exposing her daughter to any of her
religious beliefs.
   The state courts also awarded primary residential custody of the
girl to her father.
   In the appeal acted on today, <PERSON>Mrs. Mendez</PERSON> said her
freedom-of-religion rights were violated by the custody
determination.
   Rita and <PERSON>Ignacio Mendez</PERSON> were divorced in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>, after a
four-year marriage. Their daughter, <PERSON>Rebecca</PERSON>, was then 3.
   Marital difficulties arose in <DATE>1983</DATE> over <PERSON>Mrs. Mendez</PERSON>'s
involvement with the <ORGANIZATION>Jehovah</ORGANIZATION>'s Witnesses religion. Her husband is a
Catholic who, according to court documents, felt his wife had
``betrayed him'' by joining the <ORGANIZATION>Jehovah</ORGANIZATION>'s Witnesses.
   At a custody trial, <PERSON>Mendez</PERSON> testfieid that it was not in
<LOCATION>Rebecca</LOCATION>'s best interest to be raised as a <ORGANIZATION>Jehovah's Witness</ORGANIZATION>. Of the
485 pages in the divorce proceedings transcript devoted to child
custody, 249 pages contain references to the subject of religion.
   Two psychologists and one psychiatrist testified that <PERSON>Rebecca</PERSON>
should live with her mother, whom they called the child's ``prime
parent figure.''
   But the experts said contact with her mother's <ORGANIZATION>Jehovah</ORGANIZATION>'s Witness
religion was not in <LOCATION>Rebecca</LOCATION>'s best interest because she needs ``to
adapt herself to the mainstream of culture.''
   They testified that a Catholic upbringing ``would allow her to
adapt to society and have the freedom that Catholic children have
in the society.''
   Judge <PERSON>Phillip K. Knight</PERSON>, in awarding primary custody of <LOCATION>Rebecca</LOCATION>
to her father, ruled that <PERSON>Mrs. Mendez</PERSON> should enjoy ``regular,
frequent and liberal visitation, access and contact with the minor
child.''
   But he also barred <PERSON>Mrs. Mendez</PERSON> from exposing <PERSON>Rebecca</PERSON> to ``any
religious practices, attendances, teachings or events which are in
any way inconsistent with the religious teachings and practices of
the Catholic religion.''
   A state appeals court upheld the custody award, ruling that
``the record in this case does not support (<PERSON>Mrs. Mendez</PERSON>'s)
contention that the trial court made the father the primary
residential parent ... solely because the mother is a practicing
<ORGANIZATION>Jehovah</ORGANIZATION>'s Witness.''
   In a dissenting vote, one appeals court judge said granting the
father primary custody amounted to ``an abuse of discretion.''
   ``The child, exposed to the religious views of both parents for
two years, showed no evidence of emotional or psychological harm,''
the judge said, adding that the custody proceedings showed ``the
experts' personal biases against the mother's religion.''
   ``Their disdain for the mother's religion induced them to
speculate as to the possibility of harm to the child in the future
even though no evidence of harm existed,'' the dissenting judge
said.
   Lawyers for <PERSON>Mrs. Mendez</PERSON> told the justices, ``This court cannot
eliminate religious bigotry in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> but it can and should review
this decision, which has deprived a parent of her child because of
intolerance of her faith.''
   The appeal added, ``The trial court's order places <PERSON>Rita</PERSON> in the
anomalous position of having a constitutionally protected right to
speak to total strangers about her religion but not to her own
child.''
   The case is <PERSON>Mendez vs. Mendez</PERSON>, 87-1166.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06149108 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06149108 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawing; DRAWING: The Simpsons: intact TV family  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  TELEVISION; WOMEN; FAMILY; IMAGE; TREND  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  WHEN television producers Danny Jacobson and Norma Safford Vela were casting
their ABC situation comedy "Davis Rules" -- starring Jonathan Winters and
Randy Quaid as father and son raising Quaid's three boys -- they couldn't find
the right actress to play Quaid's wife. So, they killed her off before the
show began.;    Jacobson recalls that as they wrestled with that decision,
Vela balked, asking: "Is this going to be another dead-mom show?"  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHERE HAVE ALL THE TELEVISION MOMMIES GONE?  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Television  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Mothers, in case you hadn't noticed, are biting the dust in prime-time
comedies.;    Lately, there has been a weird sort of post-feminist backlash in
television's depiction of the American family, and the message is hardly
subliminal: If Mom's not going to stick around in the kitchen, then -- poof --
let's dump her.;    Sometimes, she has up and walked out (as in "Blossom," to
pursue a singing career, or as in "Wings," to serve time in prison for
embezzlement). Usually, though, she's dead, the victim of a car crash.;   
And, riotously or not, a hapless Dad, a la "<PERSON>Mr. Mom</PERSON>," is left to fend for
himself and the kids, often with the help of a male in-law.;    In <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>'s
sleeper "Full House," a father, his boyish-looking brother-in-law and his pal,
who does a lot of Popeye imitations, do their heartwarming best to look after
three girls.;    "The Family Man" on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> stars <PERSON>Gregory Harrison</PERSON> as a
firefighter who, with his father-in-law, raises four children.;    The <PERSON>Judith
Ivey</PERSON> series, "Down Home," and "Empty Nest," both on <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>, feature widowed
fathers dealing with their grown children.;    The Fox network has a new
father-son show called "Top of the Heap," a spinoff of "Married . . . With
Children" that stars <PERSON>Joe Bologna.</PERSON>;    Motherless families have long been a
staple of American television.;    Think back to the <LOCATION>Ponderosa</LOCATION> days of <ORGANIZATION>Pa</ORGANIZATION> and
<PERSON>Hoss</PERSON> on "Bonanza." Then there were "My Three Sons," "Bachelor Father," "The
Courtship of <PERSON>Eddie</PERSON>'s Father" and "Family Affair.";    Then, for a while, TV
moved closer to mirroring reality with fatherless series, most notably "One
Day at a Time" and "<PERSON>Kate</PERSON> and <PERSON>Allie</PERSON>.";    So why the resurgence now? Why are so
many television mothers missing? Is TV reflecting the culture, or offering a
fantasy? Could <PERSON>Marge Simpson</PERSON> be the next to go?;    "I shudder to think what
would happen if <PERSON>Marge</PERSON> weren't there to keep Homer from killing the kids," says
<PERSON>Matt Groening</PERSON>, creator of "The Simpsons," who has as keen an eye as anyone in
television for how dysfunctional families work.;    "In our culture, fathers
have schemed their way out of familial duties. These sitcoms without mothers
finally force them to do the parental thing.";    In truth, of course, most
American children are still being cared for by their mothers, not their
fathers, even though the majority of mothers work outside the home.;    But
the current rash of shows without mothers can be traced to a confluence of
psychological, sociological and economic factors, including the exploitation
of every working mother's most basic guilt about deserting her children and
the flip side of that -- a child's fear of abandonment caused by women's
changing roles in society.;    Television, says child psychologist <PERSON>Judith
Wallerstein</PERSON>, is simply ahead of the social sciences in reflecting an emotional
truth, if not reality.;    <PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON>, who is co-author, with <PERSON>Sandra
Blakeslee</PERSON>, of "Second Chances: Men, Women and Children a Decade After
Divorce," explains that a rising interest in father-child relationships has
been sparked by the fact that the mother's role has changed because of both
divorce and work.;    "The issue of mother as she used to be is vanishing,"
<PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> continues.;    "The children I see of divorces complain of this
all the time: 'There's nobody home. I come home to an empty house.' These
children are full of compassion about how hard Mom is working, so their anger
is inhibited by the compassion. But the sense of the mother not being there
accurately reflects the psychological experience and the longing and the
anger.";    <PERSON>Wallerstein</PERSON> points to recent data showing that about <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of
children from divorced households live with their mothers, many of whom are
beset by financial problems.;    But depending on custody arrangements, more
fathers are spending time alone with their children, and in two-career
marriages, fathers by necessity tend to be more involved parents.;    "What
these TV programs seem to be giving us," she says, "is a sense of the
vanishing mother," both symbolically and in reality.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JOY HOROWITZ, New York Times News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910528  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  751  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday May 28, 1991
00149108,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880922-0069 </DOCNO>
<HL> Children -- Coping With Change: Kids Are Often Losers in Joint Custody --- Constant Moves Between Parents Produce Strains </HL>
<AUTHOR> Clare Ansberry (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
      {Second of a Series}
   Meet the new kids on the block: two-household children. 

   Four-year-old <PERSON>Ryan Padwo</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> lives with Dad on <DATE>Mondays</DATE> and <DATE>Tuesdays</DATE>, with Mom on <DATE>Wednesdays</DATE> and <DATE>Thursdays</DATE>, and alternates the rest of the week with each of them. 
Asked by his mother if he wants to spend more time with his father, <PERSON>Ryan</PERSON> replies: "No, Mom, I want this to be fair for each of you." 

   Seven-year-old <PERSON>Jessica Toplin</PERSON> shuttles back and forth between her separated parents four times a week. 
"I wish I could just split myself in half," the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> youngster once told them. 
And then there's <PERSON>Amy</PERSON>, a 16-year-old who alternates weeks with her divorced parents, who live 30 miles apart. 
The Baltimore-area teen-ager, tagged "bag lady" by classmates because she often totes her clothes with her to school, says she's disappointed she can't see her friends more often. 
"My life is more complex, but it's worth it to see my dad," she says. 

   Children of divorced parents used to live with Mom and see Dad every other weekend. 
But with more mothers working and many fathers seeking a greater role in parenting, custody arrangements have become more flexible, producing some children who live out of suitcases, have their own frequent-flier cards and keep personal calendars taped to two refrigerator doors. 
For them, <DATE>Saturday</DATE> baseball leagues or piano lessons are often out of the question since weekend schedules are just too crazy. 
It's the price they pay to be equal children to parents who have gone separate ways. 

   Psychologists and child-custody specialists agree that joint or more-flexible sole custody agreements should be beneficial in assuring children that they haven't lost either parent. 
"How could a kid be harmed because both parents want to spend a lot of time with him?" asks <PERSON>Lynn Gold-Bilkin</PERSON>, a lawyer in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>. 

   But such arrangements often work better on paper than in practice. 
Even when the divorce is amicable, the simple logistics -- deciding who takes the child to and from school, to the dentist, and on shopping trips -- are difficult enough. 
It's doubly hard when anger and bitterness linger between the couple. 

   "The question is: Can you get along better after the divorce than before?" asks <PERSON>Albert J. Solnit</PERSON>, former director of the <ORGANIZATION>Yale University Child Studies Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
He believes that since a child remains close to both parents in a shared-custody arrangement, it's especially important for them to put aside their hurt and not undermine each other's parental role. 

   "Joint-custody arrangements sound so wonderful. 
Everything is in the 'best interest of the child,'" notes <PERSON>Clare Robinson</PERSON>, a child psychologist at the <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Clinic</ORGANIZATION>. 
But, she adds, too often the child becomes "a secondary consideration" for parents unwilling to care for kids full time or to bear the full financial burden. 

   For the child, the most direct impact of dividing time between parents is having to physically shuttle back and forth. 
"It makes me dizzy," says <PERSON>Michelle Black</PERSON>, an eight-year-old from <LOCATION>Kingsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md</LOCATION>. 
Although her mother has sole custody, she spends the school year with her mother, summers with her father, and alternate weekends at both houses. 
"Sometimes I don't know where I'm going," she says. 
"Sometimes I'm confused about whose house I'm supposed to be at." 

   Such moves are also exhausting. 
Last year, <PERSON>Bryce Hatch</PERSON>, director of pupil services at public schools in <LOCATION>Upper St. Clair</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, noticed that a few children were falling asleep <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>mornings</TIME>. 
Each had flown in <TIME>late Sunday night</TIME> or early <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> from weekend visits with a parent. 
"I think the parents' problems are so great they don't realize what they're doing to the kids," he says. 

   <PERSON>Judith Wallerstein</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, divorce researcher and clinical psychologist, worries about the effect on young children who may equate the shuttling as being sent away for bad behavior. 
<PERSON>Donald Freidheim</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> child psychologist, recalls a six-year-old boy, who commuted every other week between <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>. 
The boy appeared introverted and preoccupied with drawing pictures of black clouds. 
Those clouds started to disappear after the parents agreed he could stay longer with each parent. 

   Older children find the constant shifts disquieting as well. 
"I don't really feel like I have a home," says 16-year-old Laura. 
When her parents first separated, she lived with each for two weeks at a time. 
Then it was a month with each, and now she's living with her father until the Christmas holidays and then switches to her mother's. 

   "You have to be different for each parent. 
Mom is more lenient than Dad. 
So you behave differently. 
I don't have any sense of stability," says <PERSON>Laura</PERSON>, who admits to being "really depressed" at times. 

   For most two-household children, each home has a different personality and rules. 
One may use wheat bread, the other white. 
Bedtime is <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> at one house, and 9 at another. 
One young girl notes that soap operas are taboo at Dad's but OK at Mom's. 
While such differences may seem minor, they're often disquieting, specialists say. 

   <PERSON>Ms. Robinson</PERSON>, the psychologist, says that to cope, children tailor their behavior to their environment. 
<PERSON>Ryan Padwo</PERSON>'s room at his mother's home is filled with stuffed animals while super heroes fill his room at his father's. 
"It's like he has two separate identities," says his mother, adding: "I'm the read-the-book parent. 
His father is the play parent." 

   Understandably, children often feel caught in the middle since each parent has a say in their upbringing. 
"When I'm at Dad's, I ask him if I can do something. 
When I go back to Mom's and tell her, she wonders, 'Why didn't you ask me?'" says one 16-year-old girl. 
She asks: "Am I supposed to call back over there every time I need to do something?" 

   <PERSON>Risa Garon</PERSON>, a social worker, says constant shuttling makes it easier for parents and children to gloss over rather than solve problems. 
"It acts like an escape valve. 
When things get rough, you can pick up and go to the other house," she says. 
"Or when you start to work things out, it's time to pack up and leave. 
The continuity isn't there." 

   <PERSON>Ms. Garon</PERSON>, who runs a support group for children of divorced parents in <LOCATION>Columbia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, says that children too often get tangled up in their parents' bitterness. 
She cites a recent picnic where, even though a boy and his father were having a great time when his mother arrived at <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>, she "demanded the child leave because it was 'transfer time.'" 
And she says some parents have left a child with a baby sitter or at friend's home while they traveled on business because "it's not the other parent's week." 

   Ellen and <PERSON>Rick Toplin</PERSON> opted for joint custody because they believed <PERSON>Jessica</PERSON> needed both parents. 
"I couldn't be <PERSON>Jessica</PERSON>'s mother and equally <PERSON>Ellen</PERSON> couldn't be <PERSON>Jessica</PERSON>'s father," says <PERSON>Rick</PERSON>. 
There were also selfish motivations. 
Both have demanding careers and, says <PERSON>Ellen</PERSON>, "neither of us wanted to let go of her." 

   They've split everything evenly, even alternating years to claim <PERSON>Jessica</PERSON> as a tax deduction. 
They bail each other out in emergencies: If <PERSON>Jessica</PERSON> gets sick at school and the parent who has <PERSON>Jessica</PERSON> can't pick her up, the other parent steps in. 
"We get along better now than when we were married," says <PERSON>Ellen</PERSON>. 

   There are annoyances, of course. 
Vacations are hard to schedule, and it's bothersome having to check with each other before doing anything -- even scheduling a teacher's meeting. 
They've also had to battle well-meaning teachers, parents and even their marriage counselor who questioned their joint-custody decision. 

   "We had to fight against the odds," says <PERSON>Ellen</PERSON>. 
"But it's worth it. 
Jessica may have lost her family, but we didn't want her losing her parents." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06110152 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06110152 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  INFANT; HUMAN; HEALTH; CHILDREN; CHILD; FAMILY; MALE; MAN; MEN; BEHAVIOR;
PSYCHOLOGY; MENTAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  CHILDREN who are held, cuddled and showered with hugs and kisses are more apt
to grow into successful adults than those who "learn discipline" at an early
age, psychologists say.;    Following up on studies conducted 36 years earlier
on a group of 5-year-olds in Boston, the researchers say parental warmth has
more influence on adult social adjustment than any other factor.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WARMTH FROM DADS HELPS CHILDREN ADJUST AS
ADULTS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Family  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Although warmth from both parents is significant in a child's ultimate
success, the results lend particularly strong support to the notion that a
father's manner is important to development.;    The study compared mothers'
assessments of the way 5-year-olds were raised in <DATE>1951</DATE> with the psychological
and social well-being of those same children in 1987.;    "Adults whose
mothers and fathers were warm and affectionate were able to sustain long and
relatively happy marriages, raise children and be involved with friends and
recreational activities outside their marriage at midlife," the authors
concluded in a report released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in the Journal of Personality and
Social Psychology.;    In comparison, children of cold parents were more
likely to be depressed.;    On the other hand, contrary to the authors'
predictions, there was no significant correlation between "difficult
childhoods" or "parental harmony" and ultimate success.;    Original
information on the manners in which the 5-year-olds were being reared in <DATE>1951</DATE>
was conducted by a team of <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION> psychologists who interviewed
mothers and teachers of 379 kindergarten-aged children.;    The mothers were
asked to rate the amount of parental affection the child received in terms of
"hugs, kisses, holding and cuddling.";    Both mothers and kindergarten
teachers rated each child on how well he or she got along with other
children.;    In <DATE>1987</DATE>, psychologists <PERSON>Carol Franz</PERSON> and <PERSON>David McClelland</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Boston University</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Joel Weinberger</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Adelphi University</ORGANIZATION> located <PERCENT>78 percent</PERCENT>
of the original group for follow-up interviews.;    Their study is the first
to look at the long-term influence of parental warmth on the development of
social skills in adults.;    The researchers used complex statistical
calculations to draw associations between measurements of parental warmth
recorded in <DATE>1951</DATE> and measurements of social success 36 years later.;    The
"most important finding," they wrote, was a significant association between
cases in which mothers reported parental warmth in child rearing in <DATE>1951</DATE> and
the child's conventional social accomplishments at age 41.;    The term
"conventional social accomplishments" referred basically to an adult's ability
to maintain a marriage and friendships.;    "It was especially interesting
that father warmth was meaningfully related to later social accomplishment,"
they said. "These results provide more support for the notion that a father's
contribution to his child's well-being is important.";    Children whose
mothers saw them as sociable were not more likely to have higher levels of
social accomplishment.;    On the other hand, girls who did not seek lot of
help from their teachers and boys who got along well with their peers were
higher in social accomplishment.;    There was an odd relationship between a
girl's social class and her ultimate psychological success as an adult, the
psychologists reported: Women from middle-class families tended to be lower in
social accomplishment than women from lower-class families.;    "Perhaps
middle-class women, who were also more likely to get more education than
lower-class women, were more susceptible to cultural messages of the time
regarding alternative roles for women," the authors observed.;    Lower-class
women, on the other hand, may have had fewer options and therefore saw
traditional lifestyles more positively, the researcher suggested.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Cox News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910419  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  583  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday April 19, 1991
00110152,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890827-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-27-89 1144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Hilary'sHardship Bjt   08-27 0798</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hilary's Hardship, Bjt,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Child Turns 7 In Hiding As Custody Fight Continues</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID GINSBURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Hilary Antonia Foretich</PERSON> turned 7 <DATE>last week</DATE> in
hiding, with her father marking the birthday at a subdued Capitol
Hill ceremony and her mother nearing two years in jail for refusing
to disclose the little girl's whereabouts.
   Hilary has been missing for two years on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, since a
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> judge ordered her mother, <PERSON>Dr. Elizabeth Morgan</PERSON>, to
surrender the youngster for unsupervised visits with her father.
Morgan refused to comply and remains in jail on contempt of court
charges.
   Morgan claims that <PERSON>Hilary</PERSON>'s father, <PERSON>Dr. Eric Foretich</PERSON>, sexually
abused the girl. Foretich vehemently denies the allegation and
contends that his former wife is suffering from delusions.
   While the parents' struggle continues, mental health
professionals are questioning whether <PERSON>Hilary</PERSON> can survive the ordeal
without emotional scars.
   ``For any child, a separation from both parents on an abrupt and
sudden basis is very harmful and could cause serious long-term
consequences,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Jerry Wiener</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>American
Academy of Child</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Adolescent Psychiatry</ORGANIZATION>. ``There's no way that
she could not be significantly affected from this experience, and I
would think that any effects could not be undone.''
   <PERSON>Constance Ahrons</PERSON>, a noted <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> psychologist in the field of
child custody cases and author of the book ``Divorced Families,''
said <PERSON>Hilary</PERSON>'s separation from her parents could leave the child
feeling isolated, even under protective custody.
   ``This is bound to have a profound effect on her,'' <PERSON>Ahrons</PERSON> said.
``If she was close to her parents, she may feel abandoned. In a case
like this, the child is the most vulnerable because of her age and
because she has no control in what happens to her.''
   <PERSON>Linda Holman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hilary</PERSON>'s court-appointed attorney, declined to be
interviewed and said she refuses all media requests for interviews
concerning this case. She said such interviews ``contribute to the
long-term negative impact on <PERSON>Hilary</PERSON>.''
   District of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Superior Court</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>Judge Herbert Dixon</PERSON> has said
<PERSON>Morgan</PERSON> will remain in jail for contempt of court until she
surrenders <PERSON>Hilary</PERSON>.
the city's highest local court, ordered that Morgan be released.
However, the entire court overturned that decision on <DATE>Aug. 21</DATE> _
<PERSON>Hilary</PERSON>'s seventh birthday _ and ordered a new hearing on the case
before the full court next month.
   That same day, <PERSON>Foretich</PERSON> and about a dozen family members and
friends marked his daughter's birthday with a small ceremony on the
steps of the Capitol. Legislation passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and awaiting a
vote by the full <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> would limit the length of contempt jailings
in the nation's capital and, in effect, free <ORGANIZATION>Morgan</ORGANIZATION>.
   Later that same day, <PERSON>Foretich</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> he thinks
<PERSON>Hilary</PERSON> is suffering through an experience that could ultimately lead
to an early death.
   ``If my daughter is not brought back within the near future, it
will be too late. She will lose her ability to ever recover from
this,'' he said. ``I knew her to be a resilient child, but at some
point that resilience is going to fade. I don't want my daughter to
be an example, another statistic, of a teen-age suicide because she
feels abandoned by both parents and has been led to believe that her
father is a pervert and her mother is a crazy woman.''
   <PERSON>Morgan</PERSON> did not respond to a written request for an interview
relayed through jail officials.
   However, <PERSON>Mary Froning</PERSON>, a child psychologist who treated <PERSON>Hilary</PERSON>
for two years at her mother's request, said the only hardship that
the young girl has undergone is being apart from her mother for so
long.
   ``Her ordeal is being separated from her mother, the only person
in the world she trusts,'' <PERSON>Froning</PERSON> said. ``She is with the people
she chose to be with, so I have every reason to believe she is
safe.''
   Wiener, however, wondered whether the one-way communication that
he presumes <PERSON>Hilary</PERSON> receives isn't hurting the girl.
   ``One presumes she is told positive things about her mother and
negative things about her father,'' <PERSON>Weiner</PERSON> said. ``That is not
constructive, not at all.''
   <PERSON>Ahrons</PERSON> said she also was concerned that some problems could
result from the girl acting as a fugitive to disguise her real
identity.
   ``There are certainly possible problems with issues concerning
her own identity,'' said <PERSON>Ahrons</PERSON>. ``It could have some effect on her
life. A profound effect? Who knows?''
   <PERSON>Foretich</PERSON> has his own theory. ``At what point will Hilary cease to
even know who she is?'' he asked.
   ``I mean, how many times has her name been changed, has her hair
been colored? Does she even know who she is anymore? Her self-image
will soon be destroyed, if it hasn't already happened.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880427-0274 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-27-88 1607EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Abuse-Laura'sTorment Adv01-2Takes   04-27 0945</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Abuse-Laura's Torment, Adv 01-2 Takes,0966</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv01</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, May 1, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Battered Child Survives Three Fractured Skulls</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Spelling of Monahon, in 22nd graf, `Cynthia Monahon...,' is
cq.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY35,36 of April 26</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE ESPER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GREENFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A little more than a year ago, in the
darkest days of winter, <PERSON>Laura Lynn Lazarovich</PERSON> lay in a hospital bed
fighting for life.
   Her skull was fractured, her right side paralyzed, her right arm
and collarbone snapped like twigs. Two front teeth had been gouged
out, both her hazel eyes were swollen shut, dried blood caked her
lips, and her body was mottled with bruises from forehead to ankles.
   A monitor watched over her heart. Intravenous tubes sprouted
from her pitifully broken body.
   <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON> was 2{ years old.
   Prosecutors say her tormentors were her parents.
   Moreover, this was the child's third fractured skull in 28
months. <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON> was a double victim, not only of especially
brutal beatings, but also of a bureaucratic bungle that returned
her home for the last, almost fatal attack.
   Even as assault charges were pending in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> against her
parents, <PERSON>Roger</PERSON> and <PERSON>Janice Lazarovich</PERSON>, a Family Court judge there
had ordered her returned from the temporary custody of her maternal
grandparents to the Lazaroviches in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
   Now the law has caught up with the Lazaroviches, who had <PERSON>Laura
Lynn</PERSON> and two sons over three years, moved three times from three
states and were divorced in <DATE>February</DATE>.
   Today, both are in jail: <PERSON>Lazarovich</PERSON>, 25, is serving 15-20 years
after his conviction for mayhem and assault; his 23-year-old wife,
who had been scheduled to stand trial on the same charges <DATE>May 2</DATE>,
won a delay last week and will be tried in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   Superior Court <PERSON>Judge Charles Alberti</PERSON>, with 16 years on the
bench, said in sentencing <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON>'s father, ``I don't know if
I've dealt with a case, by virtue of this child's tender years,
where the child has been more brutalized.''
   The two still face extradition to <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> on two counts of
aggravated assault, according to <LOCATION>Camden County</LOCATION> prosecutor <PERSON>Sam
Asbell</PERSON>.
   The Lazaroviches drove 20 miles through heavy snow that
<DATE>Saturday, Jan. 24, 1987</DATE>, to bring their unconscious daughter from
their western <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> trailer home to a <LOCATION>Pittsfield</LOCATION> hospital.
They said she had ``fallen off her potty seat,'' according to court
papers.
   But prosecutors said she had been beaten for more than a week.
Court papers said she was bitten, choked and her head slammed
repeatedly into a countertop from about <DATE>Jan. 16</DATE> to <DATE>Jan. 24</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON>'s maternal grandmother, <PERSON>Pamela Christopher</PERSON>, could not
recognize the battered child when she visited her in the hospital
<DATE>several days later</DATE>. ``She didn't look like the little girl who had
left us,'' recalled <PERSON>Mrs. Christopher</PERSON>, who with her husband, <PERSON>Arthur</PERSON>,
had cared for the girl about a year.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Christopher</PERSON> asked if she could hold her, thinking it might
be for the last time. ``I questioned whether she would live,'' she
recalled. ``They had to prop her up to put her in my lap.''
   <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON> spent eight months in the hospital and a <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>
rehabilitation center. Upon her release in <DATE>September</DATE>, the courts
granted the <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Department of Social Services</ORGANIZATION> temporary
custody of the girl and her brothers, <PERSON>Anthony</PERSON>, 2{, and <PERSON>Timothy</PERSON>, 1{.
   <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON> was placed in a foster home in western <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
Her brothers are together in another home in the same region. The
Lazaroviches have not been granted visitation rights and say they
do not know their childen's whereabouts. No allegation of abuse of
the boys was ever raised.
   ``<PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON> is doing remarkably well,'' said <PERSON>Joseph Landolfi</PERSON>, a
spokesman for the social service department. ``The boys are in very
good shape.''
   Medical experts testified that <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON> suffered permanent
damage in the beating, including partial paralysis of her right arm
and loss of peripheral vision in her left eye.
   After her release from the hospital, she began showing signs of
<ORGANIZATION>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder</ORGANIZATION>, which is most commonly seen among
combat veterans who relive war experiences and exhibit anxiety,
irritability and rage.
   In <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON>'s case, she took to hitting, kicking and biting
her foster parents. In court records, a psychologist who treated
<PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON> last <DATE>December</DATE> quoted the child as saying: ``I don't like
Mummy. Mummy hurts me. Mummy pinches me and kicks me and hits the
wall with me.'' Of her father, she was quoted as saying, ``Where's
my very bad Daddy?''
   <PERSON>Cynthia Monahon</PERSON>, the psychologist, said <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON>'s recovery
from injury has been encouraging and she has made unexpectedly
rapid developmental gains because of her resilience and
extraordinary care by her foster parents. She said <PERSON>Laura Lynn</PERSON> is
severely traumatized and has just begun to deal with the
psychological impact of her abuse.
   ``While she has formed solid attachments in her new family and
takes enormous pleasure in her new life, <PERSON>Laura</PERSON> remains an anxious,
demanding and, at times, oppositional little girl whose functioning
ranges from 2-to-2{ years of age,'' the psychologist wrote. <PERSON>Laura
Lynn</PERSON> will be 4 on <DATE>Aug. 19</DATE>.
   Roger and <PERSON>Janice Lazarovich</PERSON> were each adopted at the age of 20
months, <PERSON>Roger</PERSON> by <PERSON>John</PERSON> and <PERSON>Marilyn Lazarovich</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Norwood</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>,
south of <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Janice</PERSON> by the <PERSON>Christophers</PERSON> who live near
were bright, but few other childhood similarities exist. The
<PERSON>Christophers</PERSON> considered their daughter's marriage a mismatch.
   Both <PERSON>Roger</PERSON> and social workers describe his childhood as
tumultuous: He was given to exchanging blows and insults with his
mother, petty thefts and setting fires at home and at school.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1447EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BerniceKing     06-17 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bernice King,0527</SECOND>
<HEAD>King's Youngest Daughter Begins Career As Minister, Lawyer</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SONYA ROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the world last looked, <PERSON>Bernice Albertine
King</PERSON> was a fidgety 5-year-old in white ribbons, piled sorrowfully
in her mother's lap at her father's <DATE>1968</DATE> funeral.
   Now, the baby daughter of the Rev. <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> is a
serene young woman, newly ordained as a Baptist minister and holder
of doctor of law and master of divinity degrees from <ORGANIZATION>Emory
University</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Ms. King</PERSON>, 27, is the only one of the slain civil rights leader's
four children to follow her father's career and join the clergy.
She has a long-range goal of starting a prison ministry that also
would provide inmates with some legal counseling.
   The broader goal of continuing the sweeping social change begun
by her father is not on her agenda, <PERSON>Ms. King</PERSON> explains. But she
understands why people would take her entry into the ministry as a
sign that she intends to go in that direction.
   ``That's part of being who I am,'' she explains. ``I've learned
to live with that.
   ``My father was more concerned with sociology, the sociological
reasons for behavior,'' she says. ``I am more interested in the
psychological. I like to analyze things, to look at how things
happened to figure out why they happened.''
   <PERSON>Ms. King</PERSON> describes herself as an ambitious but private person.
She carries herself with an air so coolly serious that friends
often tell her she needs to lighten up.
   <PERSON>Ms. King</PERSON> said she might begin to do that _ after a <DATE>summer</DATE> of
reading the <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION>, studying for bar exams and interviewing for jobs
with Atlanta-area law firms.
   She was ordained and received both her law and divinity degrees
all on the same day <DATE>last month</DATE>.
   Part of her serious nature, <PERSON>Ms. King</PERSON> said, stems from soul
searching in her early adulthood, when she ``spent a lot of time
running'' from the religious calling she felt at age 17.
   She thought briefly about a career as a television reporter. She
participated in some anti-apartheid protests, went to jail after
one of them. She also attended Democratic conventions, represented
her church at Baptist assemblies and spoke before the <ORGANIZATION>United
Nations</ORGANIZATION>.
   But by the time <PERSON>Ms. King</PERSON> earned a bachelor's degree in
psychology from <ORGANIZATION>Spelman College</ORGANIZATION>, she had a clearer idea of what she
wanted to do in life.
   She then enrolled at <ORGANIZATION>Emory</ORGANIZATION> and, in <DATE>1988</DATE>, gave a trial sermon
that whipped into a weeping frenzy the congregation at <LOCATION>Ebenezer</LOCATION>,
the Baptist church presided over by both her father and grandfather.
   At her ordination, the Rev. <PERSON>Joseph L. Roberts</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Ebenezer</ORGANIZATION>'s pastor
and one of <PERSON>Ms. King</PERSON>'s instructors at <LOCATION>Emory</LOCATION>, said she has ``not only
the oratorical gifts of her father but the sensitivity of her
father.''
   <PERSON>Ms. King</PERSON> said she considered taking broadcasting courses to
sharpen that powerful speaking ability.
   ``I always felt I needed to work on the way I choose words. I
still have difficulty with that,'' she said. ``And I've always
admired the way (broadcasters) speak.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06052126 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06052126 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawing; DRAWING: Kevin Kreneck -- Roanoke Times &amp; World-News  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  CHILD; DEVELOPMENT; RELATION; FAMILY; LIFESTYLE; OPINION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  LAST WEEK on "Designing Women," Mary Jo -- the cute, skinny, divorced one --
decided she wants to have another child before her biological clock runs out.
Her reasons were expressed purely in terms of personal gratification: The
happiest time of her life was when her children were babies and she now
"deserves" a new baby. She doesn't think she needs a husband, or that the baby
needs a father. Unsuccessfully seeking sperm from a former boyfriend, she
assured him, "It will just take a few minutes of your time.";    It struck me
that a show that tends to be heavy on politically correct message-sending was
broadcasting a socially devastating message: Babies are to make Mom happy; Dad
is disposable.;    In real life, a woman (or, more commonly, a girl) who has a
baby to meet her own emotional needs, with no regard for the child's needs,
tends to be a pretty miserable mother. And a father's job is not completed in
bed.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Editorial  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  KIDS ARE POOR WHEN DAD'S NOT AROUND  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Joanne Jacobs, who writes a column on Mondays and Thursdays, is a member of
the Mercury News editorial pages staff.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Kids Count, a <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> advocacy group, recently released results of its
national survey on the status of children. I'll summarize: Bad.;    In the
<DATE>'80s</DATE>, child poverty rose from <PERCENT>16 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>. The rate was <PERCENT>43.8
percent</PERCENT> for blacks; <PERCENT>38.2 percent</PERCENT> for Hispanic children.;    Why are so many
children poor? I'll summarize: No father.;    One in three families headed by
a single woman lives in poverty; the rate for married couples with children is
5 percent.;    More than <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of blacks are living in poverty; most are
children. But for blacks who graduated from high school, got a job, got
married and stayed married, the poverty rate is 6 percent.;    <ORGANIZATION>Divorce</ORGANIZATION> has
leveled off at a historically high rate, while births to unwed teen-agers rose
from <PERCENT>7.5 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>1980</DATE> to <PERCENT>8.2 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>1988.</DATE>;    In the wake of the
obvious failure of "do what feels right," the ideal of the two-parent family,
until recently as unfashionable as an avocado-colored kitchen, is making a
comeback.;    Speaking on "endangered children," <PERSON>Chester E. Finn Jr.</PERSON>,
professor of education and public policy at <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt University</ORGANIZATION>, zeroed in
on the failure of opinion leaders (and TV script writers are much more
powerful than Op-Ed columnists) to speak the "politically ticklish" truth:
"With rare exceptions . . . two-parent families are good for children,
one-parent families are bad, zero-parent families are horrible.";    <PERSON>Finn</PERSON>
calls it "astonishing" that knowing what we know about the dangers of
inadequate parenting, "we seem to attach more opprobrium to dropping out of
school, experimenting on a cat or uttering nasty remarks on campus than we do
to giving birth to what, not so many years ago, were called 'illegitimate'
children.";    In essence, society is sending the wrong message, <PERSON>Finn</PERSON> argues,
by failing to condemn what everybody knows to be dangerous behavior: having
kids without the security and support of marriage.;    Poverty isn't the only
problem. Many children today are being raised without the emotional support of
their fathers, without the model of a man who's demonstrably committed to his
marriage and his children.;    According to researchers, children of divorce
are more likely than children from intact families to have academic and
behavior problems in school, to abuse drugs, to require psychological
counseling; they are more prone to violent behavior, suicide and unwed
pregnancy. As adults, they are more likely to get divorced.;    Of course,
that doesn't mean all children from what used to be called "broken homes" will
have problems. I don't figure my kid to be a violent, suicidal, pregnant
drop-out, and I'm divorced. On the other hand, I'm not a single parent. My
daughter has two functioning parents.;    Children of divorce aren't
inevitably doomed to lose their fathers. Children who never had a father in
the family to begin with are in much worse shape.;    Of course, nobody really
knows how to get people to get married before they become parents.;   
<LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Tommy Thompson</PERSON> has a highly controversial proposal to reward
teen-age welfare mothers who marry with an <MONEY>$80</MONEY> a month bonus -- and to let the
married couple earn as much as <MONEY>$14,500</MONEY> without losing welfare aid.;    Unwed
teen-age welfare mothers would receive the same benefits they do now for the
first child, but if a girl had more babies, she wouldn't get any more money.; 
  Not many guys will marry for <MONEY>$80</MONEY> a month, but far more significant is that
<PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>'s proposal removes the marriage penalty for low-earning couples.
Currently, a young welfare mother has to consider whether her child's father
can support a family of three. If he doesn't earn much, which is likely, the
system rewards her for staying single and on welfare. But he's a lot more
likely to stick around if the relationship is official.;    <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>'s
proposal has yet to be approved by the <ORGANIZATION>Wisconsin Legislature</ORGANIZATION>, and requires a
denying extra benefits for additional children. Whatever the mother's
mistakes, a child needs food, clothing and shelter.;    That aside, I'd like
to see <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> experiment with rewarding marriage.;    It wouldn't do much
for a girl whose boyfriend has skipped out, and it wouldn't ensure that young
couples live happily ever after, but you can't have everything.;    And I
think <PERSON>Mary Jo</PERSON> should get herself a cute, cuddly Cabbage Patch doll.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Joanne Jacobs column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910221  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  923  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday February 21, 1991
00052126,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910715-0139
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910715-0139.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Law:
   Joint Custody Loses Favor for Increasing
   Children's Feeling of Being Torn Apart
   ----
   By Stephanie Simon
</HL>
<DATE>
07/15/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<IN>
LAW AND LEGAL AFFAIRS (LAW)
</IN>
<NS>
LAW &amp; LEGAL ISSUES, HEARINGS, RULINGS, LEGISLATION (LAW)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
FLORIDA (FL)
MASSACHUSETTS (MA)
MINNESOTA (MN)
MISSOURI (MO)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
SOUTH CAROLINA (SC)
UNITED STATES (US)
UTAH (UT)
</RE>
<LP>
   Joint custody, once hailed as the ideal child-rearing
arrangement for divorced couples, is coming under fire from
psychologists, lawyers and embittered parents.
   Joint-custody agreements, in which divorced parents share
custody of their children, became increasingly popular
throughout the 1980s. But many of these pacts are now
dissolving, and new studies suggest that early enthusiasm for
such arrangements was misguided.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "Joint custody was going to be a great panacea, the
ultimate solution," says <PERSON>Gary N. Skoloff</PERSON>, chairman of the
<ORGANIZATION>American Bar Association</ORGANIZATION>'s family law section. "Lawyers,
mediators, judges -- everyone said this was the way to save
the children. But it turned out to be the world's worst
situation. It was an experiment that failed."
   <PERSON>Robert Mnookin</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Stanford Center on
Conflict</ORGANIZATION> and Mediation, which conducted a child-custody study
of 1,100 families in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, says, "Where parents are
fighting and remain locked in conflict, joint physical
custody can be like carrying out <ORGANIZATION>King Solomon</ORGANIZATION>'s threat. A
child can be torn apart psychologically."
   Few nationwide statistics on custody arrangements are
available. Researchers estimate that the proportion of
divorce cases settled with joint physical custody, in which
children alternate between the parents' residences, ranges
from <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> to <PERCENT>18%</PERCENT> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. Joint legal
custody -- in which children have a single home but, in
contrast to sole custody, the parents share responsibility
for making important decisions -- is granted in up to <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of
divorce cases.
   But these numbers may represent a peak. "Social-science
data in the past five years has started to question the
applicability of joint custody, especially when the parents
are battling," says <PERSON>Amy Koel</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Middlesex
Divorce Research Group</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, which studied
divorce cases in the area. "It's too early to say whether the
courts will change, but they do seem responsive to the
national mood" of skepticism toward joint custody.
   The theory behind joint custody was simple: Judges would
no longer have to choose between parents, families would no
longer have to endure bitter court battles, and children
would no longer feel that their non-custodial parents were
visitors in their lives. Experts believed joint-custody
arrangements would reduce litigation time and encourage
parental cooperation.
   But a study of 700 divorce cases in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> by the
<ORGANIZATION>Middlesex Divorce Research Group</ORGANIZATION> found that couples with
joint legal custody were more than twice as likely to
relitigate their child-care agreements as couples with sole
custody.
   Moreover, joint legal custody "makes no difference in
terms of the amount of parents' contact with their kids, the
quality of communication between parents, or the rate of
compliance with child-support payments," says <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Mr.
Mnookin</PERSON>.
   Researchers say joint custody hasn't lived up to its
promise because most parents haven't embraced the concept
willingly. When joint custody was introduced, only the most
dedicated, cooperative parents requested it -- and they were
determined to make the novel arrangement work. Initial
successes prompted lawyers, judges and mediators to push
other parents to try joint custody -- and even to impose it
on unwilling couples.
   Within a few years, many of these nonvoluntary settlements
collapsed. "The willingness to share hasn't struck a chord in
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>," says <PERSON>Judith S. Wallerstein</PERSON>, a psychologist and
director of the Center for the Family in Transition in <LOCATION>Corte
Madera</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   Imposed joint custody is common both in and out of court.
The <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> study found that judges rejected more than
one-third of fathers' and one-fifth of mothers' requests for
sole custody. In all these cases (which include situations
where one parent requested joint and the other demanded
sole), the court mandated joint custody.
   In <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, where most divorce cases are settled with
mediators out of court, the <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> study similarly found
that <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of the mothers and <PERCENT>38%</PERCENT> of the fathers who requested
sole custody were denied it. Even when both parents agreed on
who should have sole custody, mediators pushed them into
joint custody in <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> of the cases, the study found.
   "Lawyers aren't trained to sit down with parents and
evaluate what will be best for a child they've never seen,"
says <PERSON>Ms. Wallerstein</PERSON>. "They're more likely to discuss
economic and legal issues, and they will make recommendations
to their clients based on what the court might favor" --
which often means joint custody.
   Some states, including <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, have
recently passed laws advocating joint custody. But several
states with joint-custody experience are moving the other
way. <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, a leader in the
joint-custody movement in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, recently revoked
statutes favoring joint custody. Courts in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South
Carolina</LOCATION> decided in <DATE>1989</DATE> that joint custody should only be
considered under exceptional circumstances because it doesn't
provide a stable home environment.
   Even when both parents request joint custody, it can cause
big problems. "My daughter can't eat, sleep or get her work
done when she has to switch homes," says <PERSON>Anita Brazer</PERSON>, a
40-year-old homemaker from <LOCATION>Lake Forest</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, "because she's
so worried about whether everything will be packed, whether
she'll remember to bring the English paper she's working on,
whether she'll have the right supplies for her art project."
   Joint decision making has proved difficult for the
parents. Says <PERSON>Ms. Brazer</PERSON>: "We fight about every little
nitpicky thing, from whether <LOCATION>Chad</LOCATION> should go to school for a
full day or a half day to whether <PERSON>Erika</PERSON> should be allowed to
chew gum."
   The father, <PERSON>Skip Brazer</PERSON>, agrees that the current
arrangement, in which the two children spend four-day
weekends with him every other week plus dinner once or twice
a week, is tough on them: "It's hello, goodbye, hello,
goodbye all the time," he says. A 42-year-old salesman in
<LOCATION>Libertyville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, he has proposed that the children spend
alternate weeks with each parent. "With longer blocks of
time, they wouldn't bounce around so much," he says.
   <PERSON>Ms. Brazer</PERSON>, however, wants to spend more time with her
children, not less. The couple will go to mediation next
month in an attempt to modify the custody arrangement for the
third time in two years.
   Some joint-custody arrangements survive, but with much
stress and strain. <PERSON>Carl Belcher</PERSON>, a 43-year-old engineer from
<ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, found joint custody worked best when he and
his former wife ignored "nitty-gritty details" outlined in
legal documents about such things as the exact times each
parent would pick up the children and who would pay for
clothing. "Instead, we worked hard to make sure the kids
wouldn't suffer," he says.
   <PERSON>Mr. Belcher</PERSON>'s joint-custody pact has survived 10 years,
largely because he and his ex-wife have remained flexible
about visitation. His daughter, now 18, has had trouble
adjusting to the joint parenting and attends counseling at
the <ORGANIZATION>Children of Separation and Divorce Center</ORGANIZATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>.
But overall, he says, the arrangement has worked: "I would
not have left the marriage under any other circumstances."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06065220 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06065220 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  INFANT; BIRTH; TECHNOLOGY; CONTROVERSY; SO-CALIF.  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Robert and Cynthia Moschetta, an infertile couple, hired a surrogate mother to
bear their child. But shortly before the baby was born, the surrogate learned
that the couple's marriage was in trouble.;    The surrogate, Elvira Jordan,
reluctantly agreed to let the couple take the baby home, provided they seek
marriage counseling.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DIVORCE MUDDLES LATEST SURROGATE-PARENTING
BATTLE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     But six months later, <PERSON>Robert Moschetta</PERSON> left his wife of nine years and took
the baby, fathered with his sperm, with him.;    Now all three "parents" --
husband, wife and surrogate -- are battling for custody.;    Legal scholars
say the case, <PERSON>Moschetta vs. Moschetta</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, could set a precedent in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> with broad implications, not just for future surrogate parent
contracts but for gay parents, stepparents and others who rear children in
non-traditional families.;    Like the nationally publicized lawsuit by
surrogate <PERSON>Anna M. Johnson</PERSON>, also of <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>, who is appealing a court
decision not to let her keep the child she bore, the latest case raises thorny
questions about the definition of parenthood.;    Winner will face the father;
 When the trial begins <DATE>March 25</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Orange County Superior Court Judge Nancy
Wieben Stock</ORGANIZATION> will first have to decide which woman is 9-month-old <PERSON>Marissa
Moschetta</PERSON>'s legal mother.;    Is it <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, the baby's genetic and natural
mother?;    Or is it <PERSON>Cynthia Moschetta</PERSON>? She has no biological link to the
child, but she planned for the birth, helped pay the surrogate, took a
maternity leave to care for <PERSON>Marissa</PERSON> and considers the baby her own.;    In yet
another unsettling legal twist, the woman who wins the motherhood contest will
then face off in court against <PERSON>Robert Moschetta</PERSON>, the biological father, who
wants to raise his daughter alone.;    In the so-called "Baby M" case, the <ORGANIZATION>New
Jersey Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> gave the biological father, <PERSON>William Stern</PERSON>, and the
surrogate mother, <PERSON>Mary Beth Whitehead</PERSON>, parental rights. Stern's wife, <PERSON>Betsy</PERSON>,
who helped raise the child, was given no legal rights.;    But <PERSON>Cynthia
Moschetta</PERSON> believes women in her position should not be shut out by the
courts.;    "I don't think it's fair for someone to have to fight like this,"
she said. "I believe she's my baby.";    At the moment, <PERSON>Robert Moschetta</PERSON> has
temporary custody of <LOCATION>Marissa</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Cynthia Moschetta</PERSON> has visitation two days a
week.;    Denied contact with child;  <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, who calls the baby <PERSON>Melissa
Jordan</PERSON>, said the Moschettas have allowed her to see the baby only once. So
far, the court has denied her any contact with the child.;    Friends say
<PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, 42, a divorced mother of three other children, believes it is the
couple who have breached their promise to provide the baby with a loving,
two-parent home.;    "To me, the fault lies entirely with the couple and not
the surrogate," said <PERSON>Nina F. Kellogg</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> psychologist who has
arranged more than 30 surrogate pregnancies, including this one.;    Attorneys
for the three say the <PERSON>Moschetta</PERSON> case is the first of its kind to come before a
court in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and perhaps in the nation. But they disagree about which
laws should apply -- contract law or family law on adoption, divorce and
custody.;    "We're on the new frontier," said <PERSON>Leslee J. Newman</PERSON>, the attorney
for <PERSON>Cynthia Moschetta.</PERSON>;    <LOCATION>Cynthia</LOCATION>, 51, has a 30-year-old son by a previous
marriage. Shortly before she met <PERSON>Robert</PERSON>, 35, she had her ovarian tubes tied.; 
  The couple considered adoption but settled on a surrogate mother, she said,
partly because they thought it would be faster and partly because her husband
"wanted it to be blood.";    No mention of divorce; The contract specified
that <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> would be paid <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> and made no mention of what would happen to
the child in a divorce. A clause barring a couple from divorcing would be
unenforceable, said <PERSON>Catherine M. Adams</PERSON>, who drafted the contract on behalf of
the Moschettas.;    In <DATE>November 1989</DATE>, <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> conceived through artificial
insemination. Five months later, <PERSON>Robert Moschetta</PERSON> told his wife he wanted to
divorce her and raise the baby himself.;    After consultations with <PERSON>Kellogg</PERSON>,
they agreed not to tell the surrogate, <PERSON>Cynthia Moschetta</PERSON> said.;    As soon as
<PERSON>Marissa</PERSON> was born <DATE>May 28, 1990</DATE>, <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> announced that she would not allow the
child to go home with the Moschettas.;    "Her stand was, 'I wanted the baby
to go into a stable home with two parents who love the baby,' " <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> said.;  
 But after intense negotiations, <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> agreed to let the Moschettas take the
baby home.;    However, according to <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> and others, <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> imposed several
conditions: that the Moschettas agree to undergo marriage counseling for at
least one year; that <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> would not finalize a formal adoption during that
period; and that <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> would still be paid. Jordan also wanted to be allowed
to visit the baby to make sure all was well, <PERSON>Kellogg</PERSON> said.;    The Moschettas
agreed, <PERSON>Cynthia</PERSON> said.;    On <DATE>Nov. 30</DATE>, <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> told <PERSON>Cynthia</PERSON> he was moving out of
their home and taking the baby with him, saying it would be better for Marissa
to be raised by him than to be shuttled between two homes.;    In legal
documents, his attorney argued that <PERSON>Cynthia</PERSON> is "no more than a stepmother" and
should not have parental rights.;    "I bathe her; I feed her; I change her; I
give her bottles," <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> said. "Once this situation is behind me and I get
things taken care of, I think I will have a wife and family and hopefully
another baby."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  SONNI EFRON, Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Santa Ana  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910305  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  896  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday March 5, 1991
00065220,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06064160 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06064160 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COURT; INFANT; CONTROVERSY; ORANGE; COUNTY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Robert and Cynthia Moschetta, an infertile couple, hired a surrogate mother to
bear their child. But shortly before the baby was born, the surrogate learned
that the couple's marriage was in trouble.;    The surrogate, Elvira Jordan,
reluctantly agreed to let the couple take the baby home, provided they seek
marriage counseling.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THREE 'PARENTS' BATTLING FOR CUSTODY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     But six months later, <PERSON>Robert Moschetta</PERSON> left his wife of nine years and took
the baby, fathered with his sperm, with him.;    Now all three "parents" --
husband, wife and surrogate -- are battling for custody.;    Legal scholars
say the case, <PERSON>Moschetta vs. Moschetta</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, could set a precedent in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> with broad implications, not just for future surrogate parent
contracts but for gay parents, stepparents and others who rear children in
non-traditional families.;    Like the nationally publicized lawsuit by
surrogate <PERSON>Anna M. Johnson</PERSON>, also of <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>, who is appealing a court
decision not to let her keep the child she bore, the latest case raises thorny
questions about the definition of parenthood.;    When the trial begins <DATE>March
25</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Orange County Superior Court Judge Nancy Wieben Stock</ORGANIZATION> will first have to
decide which woman is 9-month-old <PERSON>Marissa Moschetta</PERSON>'s legal mother.;    Is it
<PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, the baby's genetic and natural mother?;    Or is it <PERSON>Cynthia Moschetta</PERSON>?
She has no biological link to the child, but she planned for the birth, helped
pay the surrogate, took a maternity leave to care for <PERSON>Marissa</PERSON> and considers
the baby her own.;    In yet another unsettling legal twist, the woman who
wins the motherhood contest will then face off in court against <PERSON>Robert
Moschetta</PERSON>, the biological father, who wants to raise his daughter alone.;   
In the so-called "Baby M" case, the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> gave the
biological father, <PERSON>William Stern</PERSON>, and the surrogate mother, <PERSON>Mary Beth
Whitehead</PERSON>, parental rights. Stern's wife, <PERSON>Betsy</PERSON>, who helped raise the child,
was given no legal rights.;    But <PERSON>Cynthia Moschetta</PERSON> believes women in her
position should not be shut out by the courts.;    "I don't think it's fair
for someone to have to fight like this," she said. "I believe she's my baby.";
   At the moment, <PERSON>Robert Moschetta</PERSON> has temporary custody of <LOCATION>Marissa</LOCATION>, and
<PERSON>Cynthia Moschetta</PERSON> has visitation two days a week.;    <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, who calls the
baby <PERSON>Melissa Jordan</PERSON>, said the Moschettas have allowed her to see the baby only
once. So far, the court also has denied her any contact with the child.;   
Friends say <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, 42, a divorced mother of three other children, believes it
is the couple who have breached their promise to provide the baby with a
loving, two-parent home.;    "To me, the fault lies entirely with the couple
and not the surrogate," said <PERSON>Nina F. Kellogg</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> psychologist who
has arranged more than 30 surrogate pregnancies, including this one.;   
Attorneys for the three say that the <PERSON>Moschetta</PERSON> case is the first of its kind
to come before a court in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and perhaps in the nation. But they
disagree about which laws should apply -- contract law or family law on
adoption divorce and custody.;    "We're on the new frontier," said <PERSON>Leslee J.
Newman</PERSON>, the attorney for <PERSON>Cynthia Moschetta.</PERSON>;    <LOCATION>Cynthia</LOCATION>, 51, has a 30-year-old
son by a previous marriage. Shortly before she met <PERSON>Robert</PERSON>, 35, she had her
ovarian tubes tied.;    The couple considered adoption but settled on a
surrogate mother, she said, partly because they thought it would be faster and
partly because her husband "wanted it to be blood.";    The contract specified
that <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> would be paid <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> and made no mention of what would happen to
the child in a divorce. A clause barring a couple from divorcing would be
unenforceable, said <PERSON>Catherine M. Adams</PERSON>, who drafted the contract on behalf of
the Moschettas.;    In <DATE>November 1989</DATE> Jordan conceived through artificial
insemination. Five months later, <PERSON>Robert Moschetta</PERSON> told his wife he wanted to
divorce her and raise the baby himself.;    After consultations with <PERSON>Kellogg</PERSON>,
they agreed not to tell the surrogate, <PERSON>Cynthia Moschetta</PERSON> said.;    As soon as
<PERSON>Marissa</PERSON> was born <DATE>May 28, 1990</DATE>, <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> announced that she would not allow the
