<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901203-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-03-90 1922EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Magellan-Venus     12-03 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Venus,0570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan Finds Evidence Venus Still Has Active Volcanoes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pictures taken by the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft
suggest that volcanoes still spew Australia-sized lava floods on
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, and the planet didn't abruptly shut down after a
global-sized eruption 400 million years ago.
   ``Venus is not dead,'' <ORGANIZATION>Southern Methodist University</ORGANIZATION> scientist
<PERSON>Roger Phillips</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> during the <ORGANIZATION>American Geophysical Union</ORGANIZATION>'s
fall meeting.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> hasn't yet found direct proof that volcanoes are
erupting today on the planet, but ``it seems likely Venus is still
(volcanically) active today,'' said <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s
chief scientist at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>.
   The spacecraft's latest radar pictures of cloud-covered <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>
show there are absolutely no meteorite impact craters in an
Australia-sized portion of the planet's Sappho region, just north
of the Venusian equator, <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said.
   That means the huge area is covered by lava that was deposited
in a massive flood-like eruption sometime within the last tens of
millions of years - very young in geological terms, <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said.
   ``It raises the likelihood Venus is still active,'' the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>
researcher added.
   Venus ``has to be volcanically active, but demonstrating it is
going to be hard,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION> geologist <PERSON>Jim Head</PERSON>, a
member of the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> science team.
   To show conclusively that volcanoes now erupt on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
must fly over the same parts of the planet twice and look for
differences caused by active lava flows. That won't happen until
next <DATE>spring</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said last month that most of the meteorite impact
craters on Venus appeared relatively young and fresh. He said that
suggested older impact craters were obliterated by gargantuan
floods of lava.
   At the time, <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said that either lava gushed from numerous
cracks in the surface to flood <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of Venus during a single
catastrophe about 400 million years ago, or that a series of
somewhat smaller but still giant lava floods inundate various
regions of Venus during different times.
   The evidence <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> presented <DATE>Monday</DATE> supports the second
theory.
   If a single global lava flood created most of Venus' lowland
plains 400 million years ago, meteorite impact craters should
appear across much of the planet's landscape. But the pictures
showing the uncratered region of Sappho suggest that huge, but not
global, lava floods occur on different parts of the planet at
different times, <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said.
   That, in turn, indicates massive volcanic flooding is an ongoing
process of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, the second planet from the sun.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was launched from space shuttle Atlantis in <DATE>May 1989</DATE>,
went into orbit around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> and formally started making
maps and pictures of the planet on <DATE>Sept. 15</DATE>.
   As of <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> had orbited Venus 847 times, bouncing
radar off <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s surface to make maps and pictures during more
than 450 of the orbits, said <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> experiment representative
<PERSON>Steve Wall</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers reported <DATE>Monday</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was unable to map
Venus during 3{ orbits of the planet <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and obtained only
poor-quality pictures during two other orbits.
   A device that locates stars to help point <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> picked the
wrong star because of electronic static. That meant the
spacecraft's main antenna was unable to point properly and collect
radar echoes used to make pictures. Engineers fixed the problem
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> by sending new computer commands to <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901203-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-03-90 2350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Magellan-Venus     12-03 0224</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Magellan-Venus,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan Finds Evidence of Active Volcanoes on Venus</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft found evidence that
volcanoes may be erupting to this day on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and that they gushed
an Australia-sized flood of lava in recent geological times.
   The spacecraft's new radar pictures of the cloud-covered planet
suggest that ``at any given time, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is active in several
regions,'' said <PERSON>Roger Phillips</PERSON>, a scientist at <ORGANIZATION>Southern Methodist
University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>. ``Venus is not dead.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s pictures show there are no meteorite impact craters
in an Australia-sized portion of the planet, <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE>
during a meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>American Geophysical Union</ORGANIZATION>.
   That means the huge area is covered by lava that was deposited
sometime within the last tens of millions of years - relatively
recent in geological terms, <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said.
   ``It raises the likelihood Venus is still active,'' he added.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> hasn't yet found direct proof that volcanoes are
erupting today on the planet. To accomplish that, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> must fly
over the same parts of Venus twice and look for differences caused
by any active lava flows.
   And that won't happen until next <DATE>spring</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was launched from a shuttle in <DATE>May 1989</DATE>, went into
orbit around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> and started maing maps and pictures
in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   As of <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> had orbited Venus 847 times. It bounces
radar off the planet's surface to make images.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901108-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-08-90 0213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Magellan-Venus 1stLd-Writethru a0442 11-08 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Magellan-Venus, 1st Ld - Writthru, a0442,0465</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan Finds Signs Venus Was Deluged by Gargantuan Lava Flows</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th graf pvs, `Head said ...' to CORRECT attribution to
Saunders.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft has found
evidence that ocean-sized floods of molten rock once inundated more
than half the surface of Venus.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientists said they don't yet know if there was one great
outpouring of lava from cracks in <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> or a series of smaller
flows, each hundreds of thousands of square miles, that engulfed
parts of Venus at different times.
   The scientists at the space agency's Jet Propulsion Laboratory
reported the findings <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> uses radar to make pictures of cloud-covered <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>. The
spacecraft was launched from space shuttle Atlantis in <DATE>May 1989</DATE>,
went into orbit around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> and formally began making
maps and pictures of the planet on <DATE>Sept. 15</DATE>.
   Geologist <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist, said he
favors the view that the lava gushed out of cracks called vents in
a global set of eruptions that happened all at once, maybe 400
million years ago.
   <ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION> geologist and <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> scientist <PERSON>Jim Head</PERSON> said,
however, the evidence is incomplete.
   ``There's no question that the vast majority of the surface of
Venus has been formed by lava flows and volcanic activity,'' he
said. ``But the question is, did it all happen catastrophically?''
   The lava covers roughly <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the planet, according to
<PERSON>Saunders</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said he began to suspect <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> was subject to such
catastrophic volcanic activity because <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s pictures of Venus
show the planet has fewer large meteorite impact craters than
<ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s moon, and because ``the ones we find are all relatively
fresh.''
   That suggests ``there's a process of very widespread volcanism
that occurs from time to time that destroys all the craters - and
everything else,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' widespread lava flooding was similar to,
but much larger than, vast lava deposits such as <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s Deccan
Traps and the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Columbia River</LOCATION> basalts.
   The Deccan lava floods happened when <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s crust split open as
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> drifted away from <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> about 66 million years ago, allowing
huge volumes of molten rock to pour onto the landscape.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Columbia River</ORGANIZATION> basalts, which formed in massive eruptions
roughly 12 million to 20 million years ago, cover much of the
<LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION> east of the <ORGANIZATION>Cascade Range</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> map-making mission was suspended <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE>
because the sun is lined up almost directly between <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, impairing communications between controllers and the
spacecraft. The suspension also was meant to allow engineers time
to fix <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s wobbling solar power panels.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> hopes to resume mapping <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880519-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-19-88 1815EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-VenusVolcanoes 1stLd-Writethru a0681 05-19 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Venus Volcanoes, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0681,0701</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radio Waves Provide New Hints Of Venusian Volcanic Action</HEAD>
<NOTE>For release at 6 p.m. EDT; time set by source.</NOTE>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS wording of lead to show that two types of features
were detected, not three.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientists who bounced radio waves
off cloud-shrouded Venus detected huge blobs that may be lava flows
and rings that may be volcanic crater rims, both very bright and
possibly rich in fool's gold, a new study says.
   The study provides more evidence that <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' volcanoes erupted
within the last few million years and possibly within recent
centuries, said researchers from the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   Their findings appear in <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s issue of the journal Science,
coinciding with the 10th anniversary of the launch of the Pioneer
Venus orbiter, a spacecraft that still circles the second planet
from the sun.
   JPL radar scientists <PERSON>Ray Jurgens</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Martin Slade</ORGANIZATION> and geologist
<PERSON>R. Stephen Saunders</PERSON> transmitted radio waves from <LOCATION>Goldstone</LOCATION> to
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' equatorial region. Half the waves bounced back to three
210-foot-diameter, dish-shaped antennas at the Mojave Desert
facility.
   The fuzzy radar pictures revealed bright, or highly reflective,
rings of material on the surface, as well as bright blobs.
   The largest blob, measuring 350 miles long and 180 miles wide,
apparently is a large lava flow and has a large mound, possibly a
volcano, at its west end, <PERSON>Jurgens</PERSON> said.
   The largest ring is roughly 60 miles across and appears to be
the rim of a crater caused by a meteorite impact. But other rings
about 18 miles across may be rims of large volcanic craters called
calderas, he said.
   The researchers speculate the blobs and rings are so highly
reflective to radar because the lava flows and crater rims are rich
in iron pyrite or other metallic minerals blasted to the surface of
the planet by volcanic eruptions or meteorite impacts. Iron pyrite
is known as fool's gold because it looks like gold.
   Because fool's gold or other metallic minerals should decompose
and lose their reflectivity over time, the discovery ``certainly is
evidence of relatively recent volcanism,'' since old craters lack
bright rings, <PERSON>Jurgens</PERSON> said.
   It isn't possible to say whether ``recent'' means within the
last few million years or last few centuries because researchers
don't know how quickly rocks break down on Venus, said <PERSON>Jurgens</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Saunders</PERSON>, who is project scientist for the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan Venus Radar
Mapper</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft, set for launch next <DATE>April</DATE>.
   Radar readings from <ORGANIZATION>Pioneer</ORGANIZATION> suggested volcanoes existed on
Venus. Previous radar pictures made from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and by Soviet
spacecraft in <DATE>1983</DATE> revealed lava flows, volcanic craters and
craters from meteorite impacts.
   But researchers don't know if volcanoes still are active on the
planet, which is covered by thick, acid-laden carbon dioxide clouds
that prevent direct observation by telescopes.
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, scientists announced that Pioneer detected lightning
bolts and a 50-fold increase in sulfur dioxide concentrations in
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' atmosphere after <DATE>1978</DATE>. Because lightning and sulfur dioxide
can be caused by eruptions, the discoveries suggested a gargantuan
volcano may have erupted shortly before <DATE>1978</DATE>.
   Other studies also found highly reflective features on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>'
mountains, but scientists debated whether the brightness was from
volcanic metallic minerals or simply artificial brightness created
by rough landscape.
   The blobs and rings found by the <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION> study are the first highly
reflective features discovered on Venusian lowlands, and thus
support the theory that the brightness is caused by metallic
minerals, <PERSON>Jurgens</PERSON> said.
   ``It's a good working hypothesis to say these (blobs) are young
lava flows,'' but the radar images aren't good enough to determine
which rings are volcanic craters and which are impact craters, said
<PERSON>Harold Masursky</PERSON>, a planetary geologist with the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological
Survey</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Flagstaff</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>.
   ``We'll settle this argument with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>,'' which is scheduled
to reach Venus in <DATE>August 1990</DATE> and map most of the planet using
radar, he said.
   ``Some of the big volcanoes on Venus may still be active, which
would be ... interesting,'' <PERSON>Masursky</PERSON> said. ``The only other places
we have ongoing volcanism are the Earth and (<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s moon) Io.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021190-0025 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 174614 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 11, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
San Gabriel Valley; Part J; Page 1; Column 2 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1041 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FLYTRAPS CAPTURE BUGS AND MORE -- STUDENTS' ATTENTION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DENISE HAMILTON, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Questions erupted the moment <PERSON>Teri Uyemura</PERSON>'s sixth-graders opened their science 
books <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> and saw the color photo of a Venus' flytrap devouring a 
housefly. 
</P>
<P>
"How does it kill the fly?" 
</P>
<P>
"Will it bite my finger off too?" 
</P>
<P>
"Does the bug ever escape?" 
</P>
<P>
While the accompanying essay, "Insect eaters of the plant world," did its best 
to explain the phenomenon, Uyemura looked around her class and saw more than a 
few doubters. 
</P>
<P>
What would really drive her science lesson home, Uyemura thought, was a live 
demonstration of how bladderworts, pitcher plants, sundews or the exotic <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' 
flytraps actually captured and gobbled down their prey. 
</P>
<P>
That afternoon, on her way home from <LOCATION>Washington Middle School</LOCATION>, a sprawling, 
1920s building in <LOCATION>northwest Pasadena</LOCATION>, Uyemura stopped at a local nursery. On 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, she marched into class carrying five bona fide <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' flytraps 
she had purchased for <MONEY>five dollars</MONEY> each. 
</P>
<P>
"We don't get reimbursed for things like that, but I feel the kids have to see 
how it happens, so it's not just something they read in a book," Uyemura 
explained. "If that makes it more exciting for them, then it's worth it." 
</P>
<P>
Uyemura thought it especially important to grab her students' interest this 
week because it marks the beginning of the <DATE>spring</DATE> semester and a new lesson 
plan. 
</P>
<P>
All fall, the sixth grade had studied health science, learning about hearts, 
brains and human reproduction. From now on, they would focus on the natural 
sciences. Uyemura believed that carnivorous plants, which lured insects to 
their death by secreting drug-like poisons, were loaded with enough 
science-fiction-type drama to capture her students' imagination as surely as 
the <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' flytrap captured bugs. 
</P>
<P>
First came the book lesson. Uyemura called on students to read aloud while she 
wrote down key facts on the blackboard, her chalk slap-slapping against the 
greenish-black surface, her letters as neat and rounded as a sample in a 
penmanship book. 
</P>
<P>
"You'd better be writing down all these facts because you're going to need them 
for your reports," Uyemura admonished the class. 
</P>
<P>
"Oh man, I thought you said we only had to write down three facts," grumbled a 
voice from the back of the room. 
</P>
<P>
"No, I didn't say that," Uyemura answered evenly, and kept writing about how 
the <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' flytrap had hinged leaves with reddish centers that secreted a 
sweet-smelling liquid to attract insects. The plant also had tiny trigger hairs 
that caused the leaves to snap shut when the <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' flytrap sensed prey. 
</P>
<P>
Once ensnared, the plant secreted juices like stomach acids to break the insect 
down into needed nutrients. Botanists who sliced open these plants had found 
leftovers -- tiny undigested insect parts, Uyemura told the class. 
</P>
<P>
In the front of the room, <PERSON>Margaret Gonzalez</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lupe Jaramillo</PERSON> scrunched up 
their faces and exchanged looks of disgust. 
</P>
<P>
"I think those plants are nasty," added 12-year-old <PERSON>Miesha McCall</PERSON>, who wore a 
pink jacket and fashionable red shoes embossed with gold trim. "I think it's 
gross how they eat those flies." 
</P>
<P>
"I'd put the bug on the end of a straw and stick it near the plant," she added. 
"I don't want it to bite my finger off." 
</P>
<P>
Her friend <PERSON>Aisha Owens</PERSON>, wearing a pink warm-up suit, her long hair braided in 
cornrows, looked at her askance. 
</P>
<P>
"Nuh-uh, it's just a plant. It doesn't hurt if it touches your finger," <PERSON>Aisha</PERSON> 
advised her friend. 
</P>
<P>
Although neither girl had ever seen a Venus' flytrap before, they were familiar 
with the concept thanks to a <ORGANIZATION>Nintendo</ORGANIZATION> video game called <ORGANIZATION>Super Mario Brothers</ORGANIZATION>. 
In the game, players lead a little character through a danger-strewn path to 
rescue a princess. One of the recurring obstacles is a voracious <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' flytrap 
that pops up at unexpected moments to swallow the character. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, it was time to feed the flesh-and-blood flytraps. Uyemura 
divided the students into groups of six and placed a plant in front of each 
group. 
</P>
<P>
Next, she sent a five-student expedition into the woodsy corners of the 
sprawling campus to hunt down aphids, ants, pill bugs and whatever else they 
could scavenge. 
</P>
<P>
Some of the girls were aghast to learn that ladybugs also might be sacrificed 
as plant chow. 
</P>
<P>
"Oh, don't kill the ladybug. It's pretty and it's a good bug," begged <PERSON>Tonique 
Delaney</PERSON>, when one of her fellow hunters captured one of the round, red insects 
on a grassy slope. 
</P>
<P>
At first, Camea Gholar balked at touching bugs. But egged on by the others, she 
was soon poking into bushes in pursuit of more insects, as she cradled a lone 
pill bug gingerly in her hand. 
</P>
<P>
"I got me a whole family," said <PERSON>Shahe Demirjian</PERSON>, opening his palm to show a 
cache of rolled-up gray pill bugs, also known on the playground as roly-polys. 
</P>
<P>
As the kids returned, bearing their bugs in firmly clenched fists and 
scoop-shaped pieces of paper, the excitement mounted. 
</P>
<P>
"The students who captured the bugs get to feed them to the plant," Uyemura 
announced, to a chorus of disappointed moans. 
</P>
<P>
But there were plenty to go around. 
</P>
<P>
"Oooooh, get in there," the students exclaimed, helping the pill-bugs into the 
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' flytraps with the tips of pencils. 
</P>
<P>
"He's going in." 
</P>
<P>
"Where are the trigger hairs?" 
</P>
<P>
"Hey, somebody, give me some insects." 
</P>
<P>
For a moment they were silent. Then, a chorus of howls left from their throats, 
as group after group watched the plants snap shut, trapping the unfortunate 
insects inside. 
</P>
<P>
One plant closed around an insect's upper half, leaving the other end wriggling 
while the children clustered around in fascinated horror. 
</P>
<P>
"Boy, your plant is hungry." 
</P>
<P>
"That plant tried to bite <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>' finger off." 
</P>
<P>
Uyemura explained that the <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' flytraps would take at least half a day to 
digest their meals. Then they would reopen. Seven kids were so taken with the 
strange plants that they promised to bring <MONEY>$5</MONEY> to school the next day if Uyemura 
would buy them each their own pet plant. 
</P>
<P>
Just then, the lunch bell rang and, still flushed with excitement from their 
botany lesson, the sixth-graders of Room 115 headed off to eat their own meals. 
</P>
<P>
Later, <ORGANIZATION>Uyemura</ORGANIZATION> would assign the class to write essays about what they had just 
witnessed. 
</P>
<P>
Gerardo Frayre would phrase his thoughts most eloquently. 
</P>
<P>
Carnivorous plants, wrote Frayre, "are a death wish for insects." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Chris Spearman watches intently as a Venus' flytrap prepares to snare a 
snack. ; Photo, When a Venus' flytrap closes its leaves, prey can't escape. LOU 
MACK / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Series 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901011-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-11-90 0518EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Magellan-Venus     10-11 0278</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Magellan-Venus,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan Finds Sand Dunes on Venus</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Space Shuttle, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft has found sand
dunes on Venus despite low wind and little loose sediment on the
planet.
   ``They look a lot like sand dunes on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Ray Arvidson</PERSON>,
a geologist from <ORGANIZATION>Washington University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> and a <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
scientist at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   ``This is a fairly rare occurrence on Venus,'' he said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. ``This area just had a beautiful supply of sediment to
be reworked into dunes.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s pictures revealed the dune field in an area of Los
Angeles-sized meteorite craters. The field is 30 to 40 miles long,
and each dune is hundreds of yards wide, <PERSON>Arvidson</PERSON> said. <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
hasn't determined their height.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s images have shown <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> has very little loose
sediment. That's because the planet lacks water to erode rock.
   Surface winds on Venus measure only a few miles per hour, but
the atmosphere is so dense that even such light winds can lift
sediment, he said. Atmospheric pressure on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface is 90
times the pressure at sea level on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Arvidson</PERSON> said the sediment that was blown around to form the
dunes may have stemmed from a meteorite impact that shattered or
melted rock. Another possibility is that the meteorite was a
water-rich comet, he added.
   Magellan bounces radar off Venus to make pictures and maps of
the planet, which can't be photographed with optical cameras
because of its thick cloud cover.
   The pictures have shown numerous volcanoes, volcanic collapse
craters, long rivers of solidified lava, extensive faults, deep
valleys and towering ridges.
   Magellan began orbiting <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> after a roundabout trip
from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> of 948 million miles. The spacecraft was launched from
the shuttle Atlantis in <DATE>May 1989</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> were 158.6
million miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900926-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-26-90 0003EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Magellan-Venus     09-26 0408</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Magellan-Venus,0474</SECOND>
<HEAD>Old Volcanoes, Lava River, Giant Craters Seen in Magellan's Venus
Pictures</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s latest pictures of Venus show
meteorite craters the size of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, a river of solidified
lava 200 miles long and a collapsed volcano twice as deep as the
Grand Canyon.
   ``These are extremely jazzy images,'' said <PERSON>Gordon Pettengill</PERSON>, a
spacecraft's radar science team.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> displayed the pictures of the cloud-covered planet at the
<ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``Believe me, it's giving us a revolutionary new view of
Venus,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION> geologist <PERSON>Jim Head</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
scientist.
   With <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> only 10 days into its 243-day mission to map the
planet, Head advised: ``Don't touch your dial. We think we have a
blockbuster fall season.''
   <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist, displayed a
computer-generated videotape of three-dimensional images showing
Venus from the perspective of someone swooping down to and around a
crater on its surface.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> started its <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> picture- and map-making
mission <DATE>Sept. 15, two weeks later</DATE> than planned because engineers
temporarily lost radio contact with the spacecraft twice in <DATE>August</DATE>.
   One picture displayed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> shows two volcanoes, each with a
windblown fan of debris extending about six miles from the
mountain's summit crater. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said the fans look like ``fallout
from volcanic explosion plumes.''
   While <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> hasn't seen a volcano actually erupting, it has
made pictures of so many volcanic features that ``there is an
excellent possibility there is active volcanism somewhere on the
planet,'' Head said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> also spotted a caldera, or crater caused by the
collapse of a volcano's summit, almost two miles deep - roughly
twice the depth of the Grand Canyon and deeper than any other
caldera seen in the solar system, scientists said.
   A hardened lava river eight-tenths of a mile wide and about 200
miles long was mapped by <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> as well.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> also showed a picture of a meteorite impact crater about 28
miles wide. ``Greater <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> would fit approximately in the
floor of this crater,'' Head said.
   Another picture showed three big impact craters, one of them
even larger, with a width of about 30 miles.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was launched from the space shuttle Atlantis in <DATE>May
1989</DATE> and arrived at Venus after traveling a looping path of 948
million miles.
   Chief engineer <PERSON>John Slonski Jr.</PERSON> said a backup computer that
played a role in the radio blackouts still malfunctions
occasionally, so contact might be lost again.
   The cause of the problems remains unknown. Suspicion focuses on
possible damage to electronic components that happened when
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> started orbiting Venus <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> and on static in the wiring
linking its computers, <PERSON>Slonski</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910807-0088
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910807-0088.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Developing a Triffid-Sized Variety
   Should Take Care of the Poachers
   ----
   By Laurie M. Grossman
</HL>
<DATE>
08/07/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<MS>
CONSUMER NON-CYCLICAL (NCY)
</MS>
<IN>
DRUG MANUFACTURERS (DRG)
</IN>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
FAR EAST (FE)
GERMANY (GE)
JAPAN (JA)
NORTH CAROLINA (NC)
NETHERLANDS (NL)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   Being a Venus' flytrap is no snap.
   First, the plant's popularity with American children has
waned. And it got bad publicity in the film "Little Shop of
Horrors." Now thousands of them are being filched from the
few remaining spots where they grow.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Officials in <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> say the flytrap, the plant
with the bristled leaves that clamp shut on bugs, is in a
fight for survival. Developers and industry have crowded the
carnivore out of many of the wetlands where it once grew (in
the wild, it's now found in only 11 counties in the
<LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION>). The shrinking habitat and continuing demand
overseas have made the plant a poachers' favorite.
   "Whole savannas where flytraps were abundant have been
cleaned out," says <PERSON>Cecil Frost</PERSON>, coordinator of the <ORGANIZATION>North
Carolina Plant Conservation Program</ORGANIZATION>.
   The poaching problem has become so severe that, effective
<DATE>June 1</DATE>, the state's <ORGANIZATION>Plant Conservation Board</ORGANIZATION> stiffened the
penalties for picking flytraps. Fines can run <MONEY>$100</MONEY> to <MONEY>$500</MONEY>
per plant for a first offense and as much as <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> for a
second offense.
   Undaunted, more than 25 poachers are making a living by
digging up flytraps in the 50,000-acre <ORGANIZATION>Holly Shelter</ORGANIZATION> game
lands, estimates <PERSON>Herman Strickland</PERSON>, a state wildlife officer.
"As hot as it is, they'll walk eight to 10 miles to dig these
things," says <PERSON>Mr. Strickland</PERSON>. "They're taking the chance of
ticks, parasites and snakes. We know good well they're making
money to go to that trouble." The state estimates that a
poacher can make more than <MONEY>$200</MONEY> a day harvesting flytraps.
   Despite the run on wild flytraps, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> demand for them has
waned, according to the largest flytrap grower, <PERSON>James
Northrop</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Northrop</ORGANIZATION>'s Insectivorous Plant Farm in <LOCATION>Hampstead</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION> "Twenty-five years ago every kid had a Venus' flytrap,"
he laments. "Now they don't."
   But there are still buyers abroad. <PERSON>Lorenzo Marshall</PERSON>, a
nursery owner in <LOCATION>Harrison Creek</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, sells <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> of his
flytraps to <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. Most go to a German
pharmaceutical company that extracts a flytrap enzyme for a
drug used in cancer and AIDS cases. With stiffer fines
scaring away some illegal competition, <PERSON>Mr. Marshall</PERSON> gained
five international customers in recent months.
   The plants definitely have their local fans. "I'd love to
have a whole lot more around," says <PERSON>Milton McLean</PERSON>, another
wildlife officer. "They eat ticks."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890505-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-05-89 1026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Shuttle-Venus 1stLd-Writethru a0440 05-05 0753</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shuttle-Venus, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0440,0768</SECOND>
<HEAD>Venus, Earth's Ugly Sister, May Hold Secrets To Planetary Evolution</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4-5th grafs, `Lennard Fisk...', with 2 grafs to add distance
from sun of the two planets. Lennard is cq. Picks up 6th graf, `It has...'.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Space Shuttle, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Venus may be ``a terrible place to
live,'' but scientists believe the planet's torrid temperatures,
incredible pressures and sulfuric acid rain may be a great place to
learn about the solar system's evolution.
   A robot craft called <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, the first American space probe in
11 years, is on its way to survey <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> for clues to the forces
that molded all the inner planets orbiting the sun.
   The <MONEY>$550 million</MONEY> craft will use a powerful radar imaging system
to map <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface, where scientists believe the geologic
history of the planet is imprinted. By studying that history,
scientists hope to learn what's contained in the ``the missing
chapters'' of solar system evolution.
   <PERSON>Lennard Fisk</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist, said <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is known as the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s sister planet because it is about the same size as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
and close to the same distance from the sun, in astronomical terms.
Venus, the second planet from the sun, is 67 million miles away,
while <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, the third planet, is 93 million miles out.
   Despite the similarities, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> ``has evolved into ... a
substantially different object,'' <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said.
   ``It has an atmosphere that is 90 times that of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. It
has a runaway greenhouse effect. It has a surface temperature of
900 degrees. And it rains sulfuric acid,'' <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said. ``It would be
a terrible place to live.''
   The <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, along with <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> and Mars, are known as
the ``inner planets'' because of their grouping nearer to the sun
than the ``outer'' planets, such as <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus.
   The family of inner planets are all thought to have accreted, or
formed, 4.5 billion years ago. In the beginning, it's believed,
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> were near-twins in size and character.
   But while the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> went on to become a lovely, gentle world
thriving with life, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> became a hellhole _ so hot that lead
melts on its surface.
   ``You've got to ask yourself why?'' <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said. ``You've got to
ask yourself if our own environment is that fragile? With only
small changes, could Earth evolve into a different place?''
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> may help answer some of those questions.
   The spacecraft is scheduled to slip into <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' orbit in <DATE>August
1990</DATE>, and spend the following 243 days mapping the planet's surface
with the most sophisticated radar ever sent to deep space.
   Radar signals are able to penetrate the dense cloud cover that
conceals Venus from telescopes on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Radar views from <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
will be enhanced by <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> computers to give clear pictures of
powerful geologic forces at work on Venus.
   All the data could help experts ponder a fundamental question:
Is the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, like <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, fated to one day become a barren,
lifeless world backing in superheat and bathed by acids?
   Scientists expect to find thousands of volcanoes rising from the
baked Venusian plains. Venus also has vast mountain ranges with
peaks towering higher than the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Mount Everest</LOCATION>.
   Most scientists believe the runaway greenhouse effect on <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>,
caused by its thick atmosphere of carbon dioxide, long ago caused
all water on the planet to boil away.
   The experts also will look for indications of continental drift,
the force that causes rock plates to inch about the globe over
millions of years.
   If there is evidence of volcanism and crustal drift on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, it
will prove that the planet retains enough internal heat to melt
rock. The internal heat machine is what creates the lava for
volcanoes and drives the movement of continents.
   Meteors crashing into the shallow surface crust of the planet
are expected to have left craters in every sector of Venus. <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON>
said these scars will be of particular interest to experts. The age
of a solid planet or moon, he said, can be calculated by the number
and distribution of craters.
   ``Knowing whether Earth is a fluke or just one of the natural
consequences of the evolution of a generic solar system'' will help
answer such questions, said <PERSON>Laurence Soderblom</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Flagstaff</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>.
   He said <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> also may help scientists deduce ``the
probability you're going to find Earth-like planets _ and life _
somewhere else'' in the universe.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901024-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-24-90 2038EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Magellan-Venus 1stLd-Writethru a0767 10-24 0462</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Venus, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0767,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan Determines Large Circles on Venus Are Hawaii-Like `Hot
Spots'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf pvs, `Magellan is...,' to ADD that Magellan has
a more sophisticated radar to eliminate implication that Soviet
craft used some method other than radar to map the planet.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft found that
600-mile-wide circular features on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> are mile-high volcanic
bulges created as molten rock bubbles up from inside the planet, a
scientist said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   From a bird's-eye-view, the bulges look like nested sets of
concentric rings. Called coronas, the rings are ridges and valleys
that form huge circles. Numerous volcanoes and lava flows dot the
coronas.
   The coronas are formed by the same kind of upwelling of
underground plumes of molten rock that created the <LOCATION>Hawaiian
Islands</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Ellen Stofan</PERSON>, a geologist at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion
Laboratory.
   ``They're definitely formed by some sort of thermal pulse from
the interior of the planet'' that lasts hundreds of millions of
years, she said.
   In <DATE>1983</DATE> and <DATE>1984</DATE>, the Soviet Venera 15 and 16 spacecraft
identified about 30 coronas that measure from 75 miles to more than
600 miles across. But the Venera orbiters couldn't determine if
they were upward bulges or depressions in the ground caused by the
impacts of gargantuan meteorites.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is examining the planet with a more sophisticated
radar, which makes much more detailed pictures and also is able to
calculate surface topography. It found five more coronas and
determined they rise as much as one mile above the surrounding
terrain. <PERSON>Stofan</PERSON> said that shows they are hot spots rather than
impact craters.
   One corona that's 150 miles wide seems to be in the early stages
of bulging upward, suggesting that some of its small volcanic domes
and lava flows may be actively erupting, she said.
   Magellan won't be able to confirm the presence of active
volcanoes until the middle of next year, when it passes over the
same part of Venus a second time and can look for landscape changes
resulting from any ongoing eruptions.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers, meanwhile, said the sun will almost block
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s view of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> on <DATE>Nov. 1</DATE> when <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, the sun
and <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION> will be oriented in almost a straight line.
   That will cause a nine-day halt - starting sometime between
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <DATE>Monday</DATE> - in <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s use of radar to peer through
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' clouds and map the planet, said <PERSON>Phil Allin</PERSON>, administrative
assistant to <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s project manager.
   The astronomical lineup, called ``superior conjunction,'' also
may make <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> completely lose contact with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> for up to three
days, although engineers disagree on whether that will happen,
<PERSON>Allin</PERSON> said.
   The sun won't completely block Earth's view of Venus and
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> during the planetary lineup, but activity from the sun
already has impaired some communications, he said.
   Engineers twice lost touch with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August</DATE> due to a
yet-unidentified problem. If that happens again when the
Venus-sun-Earth alignment also makes communication difficult or
impossible, ``we worry about how quickly we would get things back
to normal,'' <PERSON>Allin</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was launched from space shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>May 4,
1989</DATE>, and arrived at the second planet from the sun on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900912-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-12-90 1916EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Magellan-Venus 1stLd-Writethru a0741 09-12 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Venus, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0741,0717</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Venus Pictures Released as Magellan Prepares to Resume
Mapping</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with three grafs to RESTORE planet name to lead and
CLARIFY reference to lava flow in 3rd graf. Picks up 4th graf, `The
images...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> restored high-speed communications
with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> for the first time in four weeks <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, then
released more of the spacecraft's pictures of jagged lava flows and
giant craters on Venus.
   The irregularly shaped craters _ one measuring 5 miles wide _
are called calderas. Each one probably formed when lava flowed out
from underneath the planet's volcanoes, causing the entire top of a
volcano to collapse, said <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project
scientist.
   A lava flow shown in another picture is ``much like flows on
Earth that are called by geologists `aa' (ah-ah), a Hawaiian word
that probably mimics the sound the ancients uttered while running
barefoot over the rough, jagged surface,'' <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said in a news
release.
   The images were made during an <DATE>Aug. 16</DATE> test of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s
picture-making radar, just before the spaceship temporarily lost
contact with <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> for the first time. Engineers at the <ORGANIZATION>National
Aeronautics and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory
spent <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> preparing <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> so that it can attempt to make
more pictures during a crucial test on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   They turned the spacecraft so its main antenna pointed toward
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, experiment representative <PERSON>Steve Wall</PERSON> said. That allowed
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> to send back information at up to 268,800 ``bits'' per
second, 6,720 times faster than was possible through its secondary
antenna, which has been used since the communications problems
developed.
   The secondary antenna has a broader radio beam, allowing it to
maintain contact with <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> more easily than the main antenna.
   Restoring the high-speed link was necessary so engineers could
play back the contents of an onboard tape recorder. The recorder
contains more of the radar picture data collected <DATE>Aug. 16</DATE> and
engineering information that may provide clues about <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s
troubles.
   The engineers still haven't identified the problem that made
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> lose radio contact with <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> for 14 hours starting <DATE>Aug.
16</DATE> and for 17{ hours beginning <DATE>Aug. 21</DATE>, <PERSON>Wall</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s computers rejected a command <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to turn off a
faulty gyroscope that developed problems when the spacecraft
started orbiting Venus <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>. The device is no longer needed to
help point <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, and engineers said it won't harm the mission.
   Plans call for <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> to formally start its <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY>
mission to use radar to makes maps and pictures of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>'
cloud-covered surface late this month, <PERSON>Wall</PERSON> said.
   But unless the tape playback reveals an unforeseen problem,
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s radar will be turned on <DATE>Friday</DATE> and tested <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. If
all goes well and <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> produces more highly detailed pictures,
officials might simply declare afterward that the formal mapping
mission started <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   One of the pictures released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> shows a basalt lava flow
11 miles wide and at least 15} miles long. It has lobed edges, is
extremely rough, and probably flowed in a ``thick, pasty'' manner
before it solidified, <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
   Another picture shows at least two volcanic calderas, similar to
those in the summit area of broad shield volcanoes such as <ORGANIZATION>Mauna
Loa</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. The largest measures 5 miles long by 2.2
miles wide.
   Calderas on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> usually are much larger than typical volcanic
craters. Hawaiian, Icelandic and apparently the Venusian calderas
were created when lava flowed from vents on the flanks of
volcanoes, causing their summits to collapse.
   Earth's biggest calderas were formed by extraordinarily
explosive eruptions. Examples include calderas at <ORGANIZATION>Yellowstone
National Park</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> and at <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Long Valley-Mammoth
Lakes</LOCATION> resort area.
   A third new Venus picture shows a valley, about six-tenths of a
mile wide, that formed when a block of land dropped down between
two faults as the area was being stretched apart, <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
The valley cuts through a series of older ridges and valleys, but
was partially flooded by later lava flows.
   Similar fault-bounded valleys are found in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>East
Africa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
   Magellan went into orbit around <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> after traveling a looping
948-million-mile path since its from the shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>May 4,
1989</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900914-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-14-90 1809EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Magellan-Venus     09-14 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Venus,0746</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan's Radar Turned on; Venus Mapping to Resume Saturday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Engineers turned on <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s radar
<DATE>Friday</DATE> for the first time in a month, preparing the sometimes
unruly spacecraft to start mapping the rugged landscape of
cloud-covered <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>.
   ``I personally am excited and jumping around,'' said <PERSON>Ed Sherry</PERSON>,
technical assistant to the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project manager at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet
Propulsion Laboratory.
   The last and only other time engineers used <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s radar was
during a picture-making test on <DATE>Aug. 16</DATE>, only hours before they
lost touch with the spacecraft for 14 hours. Radio contact was lost
again for 17{ hours starting <DATE>Aug. 21</DATE>.
   ``I am delighted to see the blue sky that we knew was at the end
of this tunnel,'' <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> after engineers received
confirmation at <TIME>8:14 a.m. PDT</TIME> that they successfully turned on the
radar.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s radar was to remain on standby until <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, when
it will be ordered to send radar waves through <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' thick clouds
and bounce them off the rugged surface. <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> then will collect
the reflected radar echoes and send the data to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, where it
will be made into pictures and maps.
   If all goes well, the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION> hopes to release new pictures of Venus early next
week, <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said.
   He cautioned that <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> may lose contact with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> again
because engineers have yet to determine the cause of the earlier
blackouts.
   But they have equipped <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> with new computer commands that
should allow them to restore contact within four to 24 hours if it
is lost again, then resume mapping within two weeks.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s official stance is that <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> mapping
mission won't start until late this month. But if everything works
well this <DATE>weekend</DATE>, officials may declare retroactively that mapping
began <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said.
   ``We're not being foolhardy and rushing into a restart of
operations,'' said <PERSON>David Okerson</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> engineer.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s first pictures of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> - made during the <DATE>Aug. 16</DATE>
radar test - showed surprisingly violent forces shape the planet.
   The pictures revealed vast flows of solidified lava, volcanic
cinder cones, huge meteorite impact craters, extensive
``Venusquake'' faults, numerous valleys and mountain ridges and
large calderas. The calderas are volcanic craters created when the
summit of a volcano collapses as lava flows out from vents on the
volcano's flanks.
   <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said that during the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will fly over
<LOCATION>Ishtar Terra</LOCATION> - a continent-like highland area about the size of
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> - and a plain on Ishtar that is named Lakshmi Planum.
   Optical cameras can't penetrate <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' thick clouds. <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s
radar penetrates the clouds to make pictures 10 times more detailed
than those produced by Earth-based radar or radar on the Soviet
Venera 15 and 16 spacecraft, which visited Venus in the mid-1980s.
   Magellan went into orbit around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> after a looping
948 million-mile voyage from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. It was launched from the space
shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>May 4, 1989</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s primary mission will last 243 days - the time it
takes for Venus to rotate once as <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> circles the planet in a
nearly polar orbit.
   The spacecraft should be able to map <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of
the surface during the initial mapping mission. But <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> officials
have said they expect to extend <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s mission so the entire
planet can be mapped.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> made its <DATE>Aug. 16</DATE> pictures during two orbits around
Venus. But only 1{ orbits worth of picture data were returned
before contact was lost. <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said half the remaining picture
information was radioed to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. Engineers
hoped to retrieve the remainder early <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Despite 900-degree Fahrenheit surface temperatures created by a
runaway ``greenhouse effect,'' <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is the planet most like <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
in terms of size, mass, density and distance from the sun.
   Scientists hope to learn the extent to which <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is shaped by
forces similar to those that sculpted <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s terrain.
tectonics, which is the movement of giant plates of crustal rock
that makes continents drift slowly across the face of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Many scientists doubt <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> has drifting plates, and believe its
crustal movements are caused by ``hot spots'' in which molten
material bubbles upward - the process that created the <LOCATION>Hawaiian
Islands</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA092690-0117 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 283374 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 26, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 4; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
796 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VENUS BARES ITS SOUL IN NEW RADAR IMAGES; 
</P>
<P>
SPACE: LATEST PHOTOGRAPHS SHOW CRATERS LARGE ENOUGH TO SWALLOW LOS ANGELES. JPL 
SCIENTISTS SEARCH FOR CLUES TELLING WHY PLANET TURNED OUT TO BE SO DIFFERENT 
THAN EARTH. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEE DYE, TIMES SCIENCE WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Venus, a planet that started out like the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> but took a dramatic turn 
somewhere along the way, is turning out to be a geological candy store as it 
lays bare its soul for the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft. 
</P>
<P>
Photographs released <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> show a planet 
that is pockmarked with giant impact craters large enough to swallow <LOCATION>Los 
Angeles</LOCATION> and a twisted, tormented landscape that has been molded by forces that 
are still not understood. 
</P>
<P>
"These are extremely jazzy images," said <PERSON>Gordon H. Pettengill</PERSON> of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>, principal investigator for <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s 
radar science team. The images were captured by an electronic "camera" that 
uses radar beams to pierce through the dense atmosphere that normally hides the 
surface of the hot, barren planet. 
</P>
<P>
Scientists hope that <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will help them understand why Venus -- the planet 
that is most like the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in size, mass and distance from the sun -- turned 
out to be so different: devoid of life, with surface temperatures hot enough to 
melt lead and a heavy atmosphere rich in carbon dioxide. 
</P>
<P>
After a troubled beginning, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> seems to be doing its best to help unravel 
the mysteries, but some of the images produce more questions than answers. 
</P>
<P>
The spacecraft has mapped the surface for more than 80 orbits as it flies in a 
polar trajectory around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>. The problems that caused the craft to sever its 
communications with Earth twice are not fully understood, said chief engineer 
<PERSON>John P. Slonski Jr.</PERSON>, so <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is not completely safe yet. 
</P>
<P>
"The problems may happen again," <PERSON>Slonski</PERSON> told a press conference at the 
<LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> lab. He said that even if the "root cause" of the blackouts has not 
been determined, engineers have at least narrowed the range of probabilities 
and taken steps to protect <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> as much as possible. 
</P>
<P>
Scientists said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that the images captured by <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> have demonstrated 
that <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is an extraordinary laboratory in which to test geological theories 
because the photographs are clear and reveal a geological record spanning 
hundreds of millions of years. 
</P>
<P>
On Earth, the evidence of earthquakes and volcanoes disappears over time 
because of vegetation and erosion. On <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, where there is no vegetation and 
very little erosion, the geological record stands out in brilliant clarity. 
</P>
<P>
One of the new images shows an extraordinary pattern of what appears to be a 
crosshatching of faults. 
</P>
<P>
"It's an extremely regular pattern," said <PERSON>James W. Head II</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION>, 
co-investigator on the radar science team. "The regularity is so remarkable," 
he said, that "we have no idea how these (patterns) would form." 
</P>
<P>
It is possible that there are similar areas on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, he said, but they must be 
hidden by vegetation or erosion. 
</P>
<P>
As expected, "erosion does not appear to be a fundamental process" on the 
surface of <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Head</PERSON> said. That is because there is no water to wash away the 
soil and produce sediments that could be transported by the wind, and the wind 
amounts to little more than a slight breeze. 
</P>
<P>
"We're so used to water eroding the surface of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>," Head said. "It's 
astonishing to see all this detail. When you create (a geological feature on 
Venus) it stays there a long time." 
</P>
<P>
If <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> can capture a photo of an active volcano on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, it would answer 
whether the planet is alive in a volcanic sense, but nothing in the images 
transmitted to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> shows that. 
</P>
<P>
Head pointed out that <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> has covered only <PERCENT>1 1/2%</PERCENT> of the surface of Venus 
so far. If you looked at that much of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s surface, you probably would 
not see any active volcanoes either, he said. 
</P>
<P>
Head indicated that he believes he already knows the answer. "It's very much 
alive," he said of Venus. 
</P>
<P>
The images from <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> reveal a surface that could be changing even as the 
spacecraft zips overhead. In addition to faulting and cratering, the newly 
released images show a "river" of lava hundreds of miles long. The images also 
show giant volcanoes similar to those in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The most spectacular image is a mosaic covering an area about half the size of 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. It was displayed at <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION> as a 10-foot-by-12-foot mural, and it shows 
giant craters up to 30 miles in diameter. 
</P>
<P>
One image shows an impact crater that is nearly two miles deep. All of the 
impact craters are at least five miles in diameter. Scientists said that is 
because only the largest objects survive the long journey through space to 
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface. Smaller meteoroids apparently break up as they crash through 
the dense atmosphere. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is expected to spend nearly a year mapping <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, and scientists said 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that they expect far more images and a lot of surprises. 
</P>
<P>
"Don't touch that dial," Head said. "We think we've got a blockbuster <DATE>fall</DATE> 
season coming up." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Three large impact craters, 23 to 30 miles in diameter, are revealed in 
some ofthe newest Magellan radar images of Venus' surface. This mosaic also 
shows evidence of volcanic activity in the many domes, some seven miles across, 
at lower right. ; Photo, Mosaic of images forms a pattern of faults whose 
regularity has baffled scientists; nothing quite like it is seen on Earth. The 
area shown covers about 23 by 48 miles. National Aeronautics and Space 
Administration 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
VENUS (PLANET); MAGELLAN VENUS RADAR MAPPER (SPACECRAFT); SPACE EXPLORATION; 
SPACE PROGRAMS -- UNITED STATES; GEOGRAPHY; PHOTOGRAPHS; ASTRONOMY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900915-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-15-90 1520EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Magellan-Venus     09-15 0529</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Venus,0624</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan Resumes Venus Mapping After Communications Woes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The spacecraft <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> bombarded Venus
with radar <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in the first attempt to make pictures of the
planet's cloud-shrouded surface since engineers temporarily lost
touch with it last month.
   ``Most people are sighing with relief,'' said <PERSON>Jim Scott</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> mission director at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory. ``We're just happy to
get into the position where we wanted to be.''
   Acting on computerized commands radioed 154.9 million miles from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> started bouncing radar off the planet during the
morning and engineers received confirmation 13 minutes later, <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>
said.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Deep Space Network</ORGANIZATION> tracking station at <LOCATION>Goldstone</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>,
started receiving data on the radar images, and computers will
assemble it into pictures that will be released to the public early
this week, said <PERSON>Ed Sherry</PERSON>, technical assistant to <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s
project manager.
   ``I'm just delighted. I'm happy as a clam,'' he said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> mission is designed to produce the most
detailed pictures yet of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface, totally concealed by
clouds, as well as a global map of the planet. It was launched from
the space shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>May 4, 1989</DATE>, and started orbiting
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>, after a looping 948 million-mile voyage from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The spacecraft's radar makes pictures 10 times more detailed
than those produced by Earth-based radar or radar on the Soviet
Venera 15 and 16 spacecraft, which reached Venus in the mid-1980s.
   Engineers lost radio contact with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> for 14 hours starting
<DATE>Aug. 16</DATE>, then for 17{ hours beginning <DATE>Aug. 21</DATE>. They still haven't
learned the cause of the temporary blackouts, which they believe
could happen again.
   But they gave <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> new computer instructions so it can
recover quickly from future communications breakdowns.
   The <DATE>Aug. 16</DATE> blackout happened only hours after <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> used its
radar for its first pictures of Venus during two orbits around the
planet. Only 1{ orbits worth of picture information was sent to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> before contact was lost.
   Half the remaining picture information was radioed to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and the rest was sent back <DATE>Saturday</DATE> before mapping
resumed, <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> said.
   The first pictures showed <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> has large flows of solidified
lava; pervasive ``Venusquake'' faults; big meteorite impact
craters; volcanic cinder cones; large collapsed volcanic craters,
called calderas; and parallel mountain ridges and valleys like
those in the <LOCATION>Great Basin</LOCATION> that covers most of <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> and western
<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s official position is that <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s formal mapping
mission won't begin until late this month. But if all goes well
through the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, officials may decide afterward that the
243-day mapping effort began <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said.
   Venus, the second planet from the sun, rotates once on its axis
every 243 Earth days. Magellan circles <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> in a nearly polar
orbit, so as <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> revolves beneath it the craft should be able to
map <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of the planet during its 243-day
mission. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>, however, has said it expects to use <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> for
additional 243-day cycles so the entire planet can be mapped.
   Venus is considered <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s virtual twin in terms of size, mass,
density and distance from the sun, although the planet's surface
has been heated to 900 degrees Fahrenheit by a runaway ``greenhouse
effect.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s goal to learn exactly what forces shape <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, and
whether its crust is broken into giant drifting plates like those
that carry continents across the face of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Many scientists believe Venusian crustal movements are
predominated by ``hot spots'' - rising subterranean plumes of
molten rock like those that created the <LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901110-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-10-90 1718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Magellan-Venus     11-10 0265</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Venus,0284</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan Resumes Radar Mapping of Venus</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> ended a two-week hiatus
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> and resumed its radar mapping of the surface of Venus.
   The lull in the spacecraft's <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> mission was necessary
because <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, the sun and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> were lined up in a way that
hindered communication between <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> and controllers at <ORGANIZATION>National
Aeronautics and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> engineer <PERSON>Cynthia Haynie</PERSON> said the orbiter began bouncing
radar waves off the cloudy planet at <TIME>4:11 a.m. PST</TIME>.
   The radar echoes are collected by <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> for transmission to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, where they are assembled into maps and pictures.
   ``Everything went great,'' <PERSON>Haynie</PERSON> said.
   The mapping had been suspended since <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE>.
   Engineers used the time to work on figuring out how to fix a
computer programming glitch that caused <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s twin solar
panels to wobble.
   A new program to stop the wobbling will be radioed to <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
and activated next week, said <PERSON>Ed Sherry</PERSON>, technical assistant to
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s project manager.
   The panels are essential for charging <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s batteries, but
the vibration hasn't prevented them from gathering solar energy.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> uses radar because the thick Venusian clouds prevent
optical cameras from photographing the planet's surface.
   The spacecraft was launched from space shuttle Atlantis in <DATE>May
1989</DATE> and went into orbit around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>. Mapping began in
<DATE>September</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> has made pictures of volcanoes, huge solidified lava
flows, extensive quake faults, city-sized meteorite craters and
600-mile-wide, mile-high bulges created as molten rock pushes
upward from inside the planet.
   It also found evidence that ocean-sized floods of molten rock
once inundated more than half the surface.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901117-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-17-90 0201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Magellan-Venus     11-17 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Magellan-Venus,0527</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lava Domes, Possible Fool's Gold, Found on Venus by Magellan Space
Probe</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thick, pasty lava once oozed onto the
surface of Venus to form 15-mile-wide domes that look like giant
pancakes or coconut macaroons in the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft's newest
pictures.
   Heat measurements made by the spacecraft show fool's gold or
other iron-rich metallic minerals coat the slopes of the planet's
tallest peak, 7-mile-high <ORGANIZATION>Mount Maxwell</ORGANIZATION>.
   Scientists released new radar pictures <DATE>Friday</DATE> during a news
Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   Engineers were relieved they were able to regain contact with
the spacecraft after a 40-minute blackout <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. It was the
third such communications failure in three months. Project manager
<PERSON>Tony Spear</PERSON> said it could happen again, but called <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s health
``very good.''
   Some pictures show 600-mile-long, 300-mile-wide horseshoe-shaped
features, each surrounding a meteorite impact crater 10 miles to 15
miles wide.
   The horseshoes may have been formed by shock waves triggered by
incoming meteorites or by windblown debris that settled to the
ground after being kicked up by the impacts, said geologist <PERSON>Ray
Arvidson</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Washington University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>.
   They are ``unique in the solar system,'' he said.
   The space agency also displayed a computer-processed videotape
that shows <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface from the perspective of someone swooping
over 130-mile-wide, half-mile-deep volcanic collapse craters and
38,000-foot-tall <PERSON>Mount Maxwell</PERSON>, the planet's tallest mountain.
   One of the new pictures shows seven lava domes, similar but much
larger than the lava dome inside the crater of <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state, said <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist.
   ``They look like coconut macaroons. They look like pancakes,''
he said. ``They're about 2,500 feet high and 15 miles across.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s heat measurements show some of the middle slopes of
<ORGANIZATION>Mount Maxwell</ORGANIZATION> contain ``mystery material'' that emits little heat,
said <PERSON>Gordon Pettengill</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of
Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   That means the slopes are coated with soil containing metallic
material, either iron pyrite - called fool's gold because it looks
like gold - or iron minerals called hematite and magnetite,
<PERSON>Pettengill</PERSON> said.
   Radar pictures show numerous mountain ridges and valleys created
by squeezing of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' hot, thin crust, said <PERSON>Sean Solomon</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION>.
In places, the mountains are no longer being squeezed upward, and
are collapsing down onto lowland plains, he added.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was launched from space shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>May 4,
1989</DATE>, arrived at Venus on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> and formally started mapping the
planet <DATE>Sept. 15</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> has used radar to peer through clouds and map <PERCENT>18
percent</PERCENT> of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' landscape, comparable to an area on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
stretching from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Reykjavik</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>, and covering
most of <LOCATION>North and South America</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s loss of contact with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> halted mapping for most
of the day. Engineers still don't know the exact cause but suspect
excess static sometimes disrupts one of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s computers, <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   Those malfunctions and other problems will add about <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY>
to <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> to the <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> cost of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s mission, <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION>
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900824-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-24-90 0631EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Magellan-Venus 1stLd-Writethru a0435 08-24 0643</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Magellan-Venus, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0435,0650</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Fixes Magellan's Computer Memory; More Venus Pictures Due</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `Magellan pictures . . .', with 2 grafs to
CORRECT that Saunders did not specify which pictures would be
released today; pick up 7th graf, `The Soviet . . .'. SUBS
penultimate graf with 1 graf to RESTORE full explanation for
communication problem. Pictures to be released after 3 p.m. EDT;
should stand.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Engineers performed a partial memory
transplant on one of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s computers as they tried to make
sure they don't lose touch with the unruly space probe for a third
time as it orbits Venus.
   Engineers haven't pinpointed the problem that made them
temporarily lose contact with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> twice during the past week.
They replaced the faulty computer memory because ``we're fixing the
symptoms,'' <PERSON>Ed Sherry</PERSON>, technical assistant to <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s project
manager, said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Scientists at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory today planned to
release more of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s early pictures of <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, made during a
test just before the first communications breakdown <DATE>Aug. 16</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautic and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> released
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s first Venus images <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, only hours before losing
radio contact with the wayward spacecraft the second time.
   The first batch of test pictures showed numerous ``Venusquake''
faults, old lava flows, craters, cinder cones, valleys and ridges
on Venus. That means at least part of Venus is shaped by some of
the same violent forces that sculpted <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   A laboratory official said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that one of the pictures
being released today showed an interesting crater on the planet's
surface.
   Earlier this week, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON>
said that unreleased <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> pictures showed a 20-mile-wide crater
that also had been seen by the Soviet Venera 15 and 16 spacecraft
in the mid-1980s.
   The Soviet pictures were about 10 times less detailed than
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s radar images, so it wasn't clear if the crater was
volcanic or caused by a meteorite impact.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s pictures clearly show it is an impact crater, but the
floor of the crater is extremely smooth, indicating it was flooded
by lava that later solidified, <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
   He said the crater may have filled with lava from an eruption
triggered when a meteorite punched completely through <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' crust.
Or the lava simply may have filled the crater much later in an
eruption unrelated to the impact.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is on a <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> mission to use its radar to peer
through the clouds of Venus and make the most detailed pictures and
maps yet of the second planet from the sun. It went into orbit
around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>, about 15 months after it was launched from
the shuttle Atlantis. It now is nearly 150 million miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said engineers don't yet know how long <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s
troubles will delay the official start of its mapping effort, which
was to begin the <DATE>first week of September</DATE>.
   The ultimate problem that caused the malfunction remains
unknown. But flight data show that <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> the spacecraft's
automatic safety systems were unable to maintain radio contact as
expected because part of the memory was ``corrupted'' in a backup
computer that helps point <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said. He said engineers
replaced the faulty contents of that computer's memory with a
rewritten version that was radioed to the spacecraft <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s main computer found ``something was not kosher'' in
the backup computer's memory and, as a result, assumed <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was
pointing in the wrong direction _ which it wasn't, <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said.
That made <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> try to turn to what it thought was the correct
position, but it actually turned its antenna away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,
losing contact.
   The series of malfunctions ``have shaken the spacecraft, but the
overall spacecraft remains very healthy, and we're very optimistic
we'll be back to a fruitful mission soon,'' <PERSON>Sherry</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901031-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-31-90 2100EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Magellan-Venus     10-31 0333</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Venus,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan to Resume Venus Mapping by Nov. 8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will resume making pictures of
Venus on <DATE>Nov. 7</DATE> or 8 after engineers fix a computer programming
flaw that is causing a wobble in the spacecraft's twin solar power
panels, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Meanwhile, a Soviet scientist working on the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project
praised the American mission, but said more spacecraft should be
sent to Venus to better learn how the planet works geologically.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is a beautiful mission. But this is not the end,''
geologist <PERSON>Alexander Basilevsky</PERSON> said during a weekly briefing on
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s closed-circuit television system.
   Basilevsky works for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences' Vernadsky
Institute of Geochemistry</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Analytical Chemistry</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>. He is
one of three Soviet guest investigators on the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> temporarily suspended its <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> mapmaking
mission <DATE>Friday</DATE> because of the solar panel problem and because its
communications with <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> were being impaired by a lineup of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>,
the sun and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Engineers determined that a flaw in the spacecraft's computer
software was causing the wobble, said <PERSON>Steve Wall</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
experiment representative at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   They problem should be fixed in time to resume mapping <DATE>Nov. 7</DATE> or
8, when the planetary alignment will no longer hinder
communications, <PERSON>Wall</PERSON> said.
   The solar panels are essential for recharging <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s
batteries to keep the spacecraft running. But the wobbling hasn't
hurt their ability to gather solar energy.
   The orbiter was launched from space shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>May 4,
1989</DATE>.
   At <TIME>9 p.m. EST</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the sun will be almost directly between
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>. That lineup started hindering <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s
communications with <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> more than a week ago.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> uses radar to penetrate <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' thick clouds to make
pictures and maps. It will map at least <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of
the planet's surface.
   Since mapping formally started <DATE>Sept. 15</DATE>, the orbiter has made
pictures of numerous volcanoes, huge solidified lava flows,
extensive quake faults, Los Angeles-sized meteorite impact craters
and 600-mile-wide, mile-high bulges created as molten rock pushes
upward from inside the planet.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900822-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-22-90 1043EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Magellan-Venus 2ndLd-Writethru a0482 08-22 0769</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Magellan-Venus, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0482,0786</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Loses Touch With Magellan Again; Venus Pictures Show Violent
Geology</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS two grafs after 3rd graf, `So the...', to UPDATE with
spacecraft not responding to commands. Picks up 4th graf, `Contact
was...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA11 of Aug. 21</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers today struggled to
restore radio contact with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> after losing touch with the
Venus-orbiting spacecraft for the second time in five days.
   Space agency engineers' failure <TIME>this morning</TIME> to hear from
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> after the link broke indicated the craft's computerized
emergency systems didn't immediately activate to help re-establish
communication with <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   So the engineers at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory repeatedly
sent new computer commands toward <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s presumed position
around <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> in an attempt to tell it to radio Earth, said <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
spokesman <PERSON>Bob MacMillin</PERSON>.
   Nothing was heard hours after the commands should have elicited
a response from <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>. Engineers met to plan their next step.
   ``Bad news. Nothing. Not a peep out of it,'' <PERSON>MacMillin</PERSON> said.
``It's kind of a mystery.''
   Contact was lost at <TIME>7:03 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> while <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> was tracking
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> with an antenna dish near <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, said
laboratory spokesman <PERSON>Jim Doyle</PERSON>.
   The latest blow to <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> mission to map <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>
came <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, <TIME>less than eight hours after</TIME> the space agency
released the craft's first snapshots of Venus.
   The pictures revealed a remarkably violent landscape shaped by
impact craters, quake faults, vast lava flows, and ridges and
valleys like those in the western <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The loss of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> would be another major blow to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>, which
grounded the space shuttle fleet temporarily because of fuel leaks
and found the <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION> was impaired by a flawed
mirror.
   The spacecraft's emergency systems allowed engineers to locate
the spacecraft on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, more than 14 hours after they lost
contact with it the first time. Eight hours later, they restored
steady contact by sending <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> a command to stop spinning and
keep one of its antennas pointed at <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s mission is to map up to <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface
using radar to peer through the planet's thick clouds, which
prevent the use of optical cameras. The spacecraft went into orbit
around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> after a roundabout, 948-million-mile trip.
It was launched from the shuttle <DATE>Atlantis 15 months ago</DATE>.
   When <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s first Venus pictures were released <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project manager <PERSON>Tony Spear</PERSON> said that as far as engineers
could tell, ``the spacecraft is healthy,'' despite last week's
malfunction.
   He and other engineers said they still hadn't figured out the
cause of the problem. But Spear had been optimistic enough to say
he still planned to have <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> start its Venus mapping mission
the <DATE>first week of September</DATE>.
   Jet <ORGANIZATION>Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> is known for its ability to overcome
problems with wayward spacecraft. After the twin Voyager probes
were launched in <DATE>1977</DATE>, one lost contact with Earth for eight days.
The radio link was restored and the probes went on to explore the
outer planets.
   Spacecraft system engineer <PERSON>John Slonski</PERSON> said one leading theory
to explain last week's loss of contact with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was that a
cosmic ray or a high-energy particle from the sun caused a blip in
its computer memory.
   ``We're not ruling out a software flaw or some hardware
problem'' or perhaps some unknown electrical fields surrounding
<LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Spear</ORGANIZATION> said.
   He also said cosmic ray ``hits'' on spacecraft electronics can
be expected to interfere with <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> about once each year.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> made its first pictures of Venus during a test
conducted just before <DATE>last week</DATE>'s malfunction.
   As promised by <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s first pictures are 10 times more
detailed than the best radar images of Venus made by two Soviet
probes and a giant radio telescope in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>. They show
details as small as 400 feet across.
   The pictures show ``Venus is intensely fractured and faulted,''
with at least part of its terrain shaped by geological forces
``even more violent than I imagined before,'' <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project
scientist <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The pictures cover a small portion of the planet near
Hawaii-like volcanic highlands.
   The pictures show plains covered by six- to 10-mile-wide lava
flows that solidified and then were cracked by faults. <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON>
said the flows resemble those in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> or along the <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Snake</ORGANIZATION> rivers in the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>.
   Also visible are a couple of volcanic cinder cones, a
20-mile-wide meteorite crater and long, parallel sets of two- to
three-mile-wide valleys and ridges that look like the basins and
ranges of <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900811-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-11-90 1618EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Magellan-Earth'sTwin Bjt   08-11 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Earth's Twin, Bjt,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan's Venus Exploration May Provide Clues to the Early Earth</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Geologists may get a glimpse of what
<ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s surface was like a few billion years ago when the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
spacecraft's radar pierces the clouds of Venus to reveal secrets of
an alien terrain.
   ``Venus is the last of the inner planets we are exploring in
detail, and probably is the most important from the point of view
of understanding the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Jim Head</PERSON>, a member of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> science team and a geology professor at <ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> fired its braking rocket and slipped into orbit around
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> after a 15-month, 948-million-mile voyage from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Engineers at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory monitored the
spacecraft's health <DATE>Saturday</DATE> so it will be ready by <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE> to use
its radar to peer through thick Venusian clouds and make the most
detailed pictures and maps yet of the planet's landscape.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> entered orbit so smoothly that it used very little
thruster fuel to point it properly while the rocket fired. So
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> weighs more and moves faster than expected, making the low
point in its orbit 183 miles above Venus instead of 171 miles as
planned, said navigation chief <PERSON>John McNamee</PERSON>.
   The orbit is so good that an adjustment maneuver planned for
<DATE>Aug. 28</DATE> will not be needed, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project manager <PERSON>Tony Spear</PERSON>
said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is designed to study the geology and geography of
<LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, heated to 900 degrees Fahrenheit by a ``greenhouse effect''
gone berserk.
   Venus' high temperature and crushing atmospheric pressure might
make rock in the planet's crust much thinner and more flexible than
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s, <PERSON>Head</PERSON> said.
   So Venus may resemble Earth before our home planet's crust
cooled off and broke into colossal plates. Those plates now drift
across the face of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, moving whole continents and colliding
to uplift mountain ranges and trigger volcanic eruptions and
earthquakes.
   Most of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s original surface was destroyed long ago by
erosion and plate movements, so ``we have grave difficulty
answering fundamental questions about the early history of the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' Head said.
   While <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is hot, dry and lifeless, ``it is very similar in
size and density and also is the closest planet to the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' he
said. ``That means it probably had the most similar conditions when
the planets formed (4.6 billion years ago). So if we want to study
another planet to learn something about the early <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is a
good candidate.''
   Learning how <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' crust moves and is deformed ``will tell us a
lot more about the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s chief
scientist for <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> may settle debate over competing theories that seek to
explain the creation of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' continent-like highlands, which
include Africa-sized <ORGANIZATION>Aphrodite Terra</ORGANIZATION>, Australia-sized Ishtar Terra
and Hawaii-like Beta Regio.
   Saunders believes ``hot spots'' of rising molten rock created
the highlands, just as hot spots created <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ``If you could look at a time-lapse movie over billions of
years, it might look like a big pot of thick porridge simmering,'
<PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said, adding <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' crust may feature ``a bunch of big
Hawaiis all over the place.''
   Some other scientists think <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' highlands are big pieces of
crust that solidified first as the planet's initial molten surface
cooled off.
   But Head believes plate movements formed the highlands.
Aphrodite Terra resembles <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s midocean ridges, the undersea
mountain ranges where molten rock emerges to add new material to
the drifting plates of crust.
   Ishtar Terra ``has many of the features that you would expect
where blocks of crust are colliding,'' including volcanoes such as
those along the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> coasts of <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> and
folded mountain belts such as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s Himalayas, which were created
because <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is smashing into <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>.
   Even if the Venusian crust hasn't yet broken into plates, ``we
probably will find faults like the <LOCATION>San Andreas</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,'' a
pretty sure sign that ``Venusquakes'' shake the second planet from
the sun, <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900717-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-17-90 1420EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-Venus-Glance Adv24   07-17 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Venus-Glance, Adv24,0452</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Tues AMs, July 24, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Magellan-Venus, b0442</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Planet Venus at a Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft goes into
orbit around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>, it will use radar to map the surface
of the cloud-covered planet. Here is some of what scientists
already know about the second planet from the sun:
   DIAMETER: About 7,520 miles, or <PERCENT>95 percent</PERCENT> as wide as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>;
sixth largest of the solar system's nine known planets.
   MASS: Venus weighs about <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> as much as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ATMOSPHERE: About <PERCENT>97 percent</PERCENT> carbon dioxide, with trace amounts
of nitrogen, sulfur dioxide, water vapor, argon, oxygen, carbon
monoxide, neon, and hydrochloric and hydrofluoric acids. The
planet's clouds contain sulfuric acid droplets. The atmosphere
traps heat in a runaway ``greenhouse effect'' that scientists
believe evaporated liquid water long ago, if there ever was any on
the planet. Large fluctuations in sulfur dioxide levels may
indicate that active volcanoes pump the gas into <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' atmosphere.
   SURFACE CONDITIONS: Temperature about 900 degrees Fahrenheit,
hot enough to melt lead, zinc or tin. Crushing atmospheric pressure
90 times that on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s surface, or equivalent to the pressure
2,700 feet beneath the surface of an ocean on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   THE CALENDAR: A day on Venus lasts longer than a year. A
Venusian year _ the time it takes for the planet to orbit the sun _
lasts 225 Earth days. A Venusian day _ the time the planet takes to
spin once on its axis _ lasts 243 Earth days. Venus also has
retrograde rotation, so the sun rises in the west and sets in the
east.
   DISTANCE FROM THE SUN: Venus is the second planet from the sun,
orbiting at a distance of 67.2 million miles. It is closer to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
than any other planet. Other than the sun and moon, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is the
brightest object in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s skies.
   MOONS: None.
   GEOLOGY: Earth-based and spacecraft radar revealed hundreds of
thousands of volcanoes on the Venusian lowlands, although
scientists don't yet know if any are active. Venus also has
meteorite impact craters and continent-like highlands with towering
peaks that dwarf Earth's tallest mountains. Scientists suspect
giant plates of rock may move in <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' crust in a process vaguely
like continental drift on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Venus' surface is about <PERCENT>65 percent</PERCENT>
rolling plains, <PERCENT>27 percent</PERCENT> flat lowlands and <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT> highlands
that may be similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s continents.
   GRAVITY: About <PERCENT>89 percent</PERCENT> as strong as on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   MAGNETIC FIELD: None detected so far, suggesting <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> now lacks
a liquid core, which is needed to generate a magnetic field.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tues AMs, July 24</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900811-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-11-90 0152EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Magellan-Venus Bjt   08-11 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Magellan-Venus, Bjt,0655</SECOND>
