<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880531-0217 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-31-88 2054EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Haiti     05-31 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti,0550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers, Peasants Clash in Northwest Haiti</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) _ Soldiers and peasants clashed in
the hamlet of Danti in <LOCATION>northwest Haiti</LOCATION> with a rural law officer
reported killed and many peasants wounded, radio stations in the
capital said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The report coincided with a plea by Foreign Minister <PERSON>Gerard
LaTortue</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> for international aid for this impoverished
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> nation. He told a news conference at <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Department of State</ORGANIZATION>, ``No democratic process can sustain itself if
it is not accompanied by economic development.''
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> suspended most of its aid to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> following
election violence last <DATE>November</DATE>.
   Section chief <PERSON>Leroy Ely</PERSON> was killed in <LOCATION>Danti</LOCATION> <DATE>last Thursday</DATE>,
touching off the clashes which reportedly continued until <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Section chiefs in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> are rural police officers with military
rank, responsible for supervising public works as well as
maintaining law and order. Under the 29-year <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> family
dictatorship, section chiefs exercised wide powers.
   Ely traveled to Danti to impose the authority of the capital
city of the section, <LOCATION>Le Borgne</LOCATION>. Peasants demanded their hamlet be
assigned to neighboring <PERSON>Gros Morne</PERSON> district and in subsequent
rioting, <PERSON>Ely</PERSON> was killed.
   Soldiers came to quell the unrest. Radio Lumiere, <ORGANIZATION>Radio
Metropole and Radio Haiti Inter</ORGANIZATION> reported that from <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to
<DATE>Monday</DATE>, Danti residents were beaten and arrested or forced to flee.
Their homes were pillaged and burned.
   Witnesses interviewed by <ORGANIZATION>Radio Metropole</ORGANIZATION> said many people were
wounded or forced to take flight. Radio <PERSON>Haiti Inter</PERSON> said 25
peasants were arrested.
   According to <ORGANIZATION>Radio Metropole, Danti</ORGANIZATION> is in a relatively fertile
zone and Le Borgne authorities did not want to lose it.
   Disputes over land have become common and violent in this arid,
mountainous and overpopulated nation that shares the island of
Hispaniola with the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>.
   Last <DATE>July</DATE>, hundreds of peasants clashed with landowners and
among themselves over property in the northwest village of <PERSON>Jean
Rabel</PERSON>. Dozens were killed.
   In asking for foreign help, <PERSON>LaTortue</PERSON> said in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto
Rico</LOCATION>, that ``For us Haitians, economic development means ... food
and water for the great majority of the population, and health
services, education and housing.''
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has been <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s biggest foreign aid donor,
contributing <MONEY>$103 million</MONEY> a year to the poorest nation in the
<LOCATION>Western Hemisphere</LOCATION>, with a population of 5.3 million.
   Most <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> aid was suspended following cancellation of <DATE>last
November</DATE>'s national elections because of violence, which the
then-ruling junta under Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Henri Namphy</PERSON> did little to curtail.
   <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> maintained their aid commitments to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, but
<MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> in loans.
   LaTortue, who spent 10 years in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> as part of his
25-year exile during the Duvalier dictatorships, criticized <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
officials for blocking aid to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> following controversial
national elections last <DATE>January</DATE>.
   He asked <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth, to make available
scholarships for Haitian students and do what it could to promote
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s economic development.
   Dictator <PERSON>Francois Duvalier</PERSON> ruled <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> since <DATE>1957</DATE>. His son,
<PERSON>Jean-Claude</PERSON>, took over at his death but fled <DATE>Feb. 7, 1986</DATE> during a
popular uprising. A president, <PERSON>Leslie Manigat</PERSON>, was chosen in
<DATE>January</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06279187 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06279187 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; ARRIVAL -- OAS delegates arrive in
Port-au-Prince in attempt to reverse coup.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ORGANIZATION; RELATION; HAITI; MILITARY; LEADER  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Diplomats from the United States and eight other nations met with Haiti's
military chief Friday and pressed him to restore President Jean-Bertrand
Aristide to power.;   After a two-hour meeting at the airport with Brig. Gen.
Raoul Cedras, the officials flew to Jamaica but were to return today. Asked if
they had made progress in convincing Cedras to reinstate Aristide, Argentine
Foreign Minister Guido di Tella said, "Enough to return tomorrow."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  OAS MISSION PRESSURES HAITI'S MILITARY CHIEF
DELEGATES TO RETURN FOR MORE TALKS TODAY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> met with Aristide in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said he was reluctant
to use <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military force to reverse <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s coup "except if American
citizens' lives are in any way threatened.";   Capital remains tense;
<LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, the capital, remained tense, with most shops and businesses
closed for the fifth day since the coup. Armed forces continued to patrol the
streets, but their presence appeared reduced from previous days.;   After
continuous radio reports of clashes between security forces and <PERSON>Aristide</PERSON>
supporters and a mounting death toll that <PERSON>Aristide</PERSON> said had reached about 500,
the army banned radio and TV broadcasts "inciting to violence.";   Soldiers
ransacked <ORGANIZATION>Radio Lumiere</ORGANIZATION>, a Protestant-run station, which the day before had
reported a massacre, according an official with the independent <ORGANIZATION>Radio Haiti
Inter.</ORGANIZATION>;   After giving the brief report of the attack, the official said <ORGANIZATION>Radio
Haiti Inter</ORGANIZATION>, too, was going off the air until the "soldiers come to their
senses.";    Stations silenced; By <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, nearly all the capital's
12 independent radio stations were off the air. Radio is the main source of
news for Haitians, many of whom are illiterate.;   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has sent
500 Marines to <LOCATION>Guantanamo Bay</LOCATION> naval station in neighboring <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> in case they
are needed to evacuate the estimated 15,000 Americans in <LOCATION>Haiti.</LOCATION>;   At a <ORGANIZATION>White
House</ORGANIZATION> photo session, <PERSON>Aristide</PERSON> evaded a reporter's question about whether his
7-month-old elected government could be restored without use of force.;   "We
are talking about going back in a democratic way. . . . Later we will talk
about something else," said Aristide.;   The nine-member delegation from the
<ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION> arrived in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> from
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. During the meeting, it read to Cedras an 11-point <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> resolution
demanding the military allow <PERSON>Aristide</PERSON>'s return.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Port-au-prince, Haiti  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911005  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  15A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  387  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, October 5, 1991
00279187,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-14335</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJRDWAASFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931018
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  18 OCT 93 / US stands by to intervene in Haiti
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> has not ruled out military intervention in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> to protect American
lives and restore democracy there, President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>'s ambassador to
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>yesterday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Reuter</ORGANIZATION> reports from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
Ms <PERSON>Madeleine Albright</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> was monitoring the situation closely
and was standing by to evacuate some 1,000 Americans if necessary.
'The protection of American lives is foremost in our minds,' she said. 'We
don't rule anything in or anything out. This is a very tense situation, but
one in which we have to maintain calmness about our response.'
Reports from <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> said hundreds of foreigners fled <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> yesterday
after a night of heavy gunfire in some of the capital's neighbourhoods.
The country's international airport was jammed with American and Canadian
citizens who were urged to leave <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> or take security precautions ahead of
stringent UN trade sanctions which come into effect at <TIME>midnight tonight</TIME> <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> time.
On <DATE>Saturday</DATE> the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> embassy flew in 30 additional Marine guards and set up a
telephone network to alert American citizens about potential violence.
The Canadian embassy has urged all 2,300 of its citizens to leave the
country immediately.
US warships and three Canadian vessels, some visible from the capital city,
will make sure that no fuel or arms are allowed to enter <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION>
sanctions also include freezing the foreign bank accounts of army chief
General <PERSON>Raoul Cedras</PERSON> and other military leaders.
Ms <PERSON>Albright</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> was still hoping that <PERSON>Gen Cedras</PERSON> would step aside
to power on <DATE>October 30</DATE>. Gen <PERSON>Cedras</PERSON> led the <DATE>1991</DATE> coup that ousted <PERSON>Mr
Aristide</PERSON>.
Gen Cedras refused to relinquish power on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, as had been scheduled
under a UN plan to return <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON> to power.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    HTZ  Haiti, Caribbean.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880918-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-18-88 1952EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Haiti 2ndLd-Writethru   09-18 0986</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti, 2nd Ld - Writethru,a0787,1011</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Duvalier Aide Seizes Military Power in Haiti</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS four grafs after 4th, `Frantz Lubin...' to UPDATE
with six reported dead, Namphy's home plundered; picks up 5th pvs:
Avril took....; DELETES 16th pvs, `The Dominican...' to remove
first reference to Romain and conform; picks up 17th graf: Avril
reported...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) _ Brig. Gen. <PERSON>Prosper Avril</PERSON>, a former
military adviser for the <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> dictatorship, declared himself
president on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> after ousting Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Henri Namphy</PERSON>.
   Avril, adjutant general of the army, said in an early morning
address on national television that the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Guard</ORGANIZATION> toppled
<PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> because it was ``sickened'' by the way <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>
governed. <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> was sent to the neighboring <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>.
   Residents reported hearing heavy gunfire <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> near the
presidential palace in what appeared to be fighting between
military factions.
   <PERSON>Frantz Lubin</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s director of information, said soldiers
were killed, but Avril mentioned no casualties.
   Haiti radio stations reported that at least six people were
killed in the capital in coup-related clashes, and that mobs
pillaged two homes owned by <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> and the home of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>
Mayor <PERSON>Franck Romain</PERSON>.
   The military government appealed in a national television
broadcast ``for calm, discipline and order in respect of individual
rights and liberties.''
   A witness told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> she saw two bodies in the
courtyard of Romain's luxurious house in the suburb of Delmas and
the property was occupied by soldiers.
   ``The house was stripped, doors were torn off the hinges. It was
a shell,'' the witness said.
   Avril took over a week after about 20 men armed with machetes,
handguns and steel pikes attacked the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> during
a Mass being said by the Rev. <PERSON>Jean Bertrand Aristide</PERSON>, a vocal
critic of the military government. Thirteen people were killed and
77 wounded. Opposition leaders blamed <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>'s government for the
attack and another church burning two days later.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, slum dwellers killed and burned the body of
one man and cheered when a soldier shot and killed another man
suspected of participating in the massacre. By midday, the city was
quiet, but the airport was closed.
   Avril, who was adviser to ousted President <PERSON>Jean-Claude Duvalier</PERSON>,
said <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> will respect all international treaties, liberties and
human rights and said that ``dialogue will be honored for the sake
of national reconciliation.''
   <PERSON>Lubin</PERSON> said <PERSON>Jean-Claude Paul</PERSON>, commander of the 700-man <ORGANIZATION>Dessalines
Barracks</ORGANIZATION>, was named commander-in-chief of the army, but <PERSON>Avril</PERSON> did
not mention <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>. Dessalines is the most feared unit in the
7,000-man army.
   <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>, who has been indicted on federal drug trafficking charges
in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, had been considered the most powerful figure in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>
after <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>. It was not known if <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> played a role in the coup,
but sources said <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> were at odds.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Anita Stockman</PERSON> said
noncommissioned officers of the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Guard</ORGANIZATION> captured <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>
in an apparently bloodless coup and persuaded Avril to take over.
   She said they were believed to be ``dissatisfied with recent
human rights violations and the general deterioration in the
security situation punctuated by attacks against the churches over
the past two weeks.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Stockman</PERSON> said <PERSON>Avril</PERSON> phoned the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ambassador and said he
was assuming the presidency. She said the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government still
wants <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> to answer the drug trafficking charges in court.
   Namphy arrived in a private plane at a private airport in <LOCATION>Santo
Domingo</LOCATION>, the Dominican capital, early <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, said <PERSON>Fabio
Herrera Cabral</PERSON>, deputy foreign minister of the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>,
which shares the island of Hispaniola with <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>.
   Namphy, in a military uniform, was accompanied by his wife and
daughter, <PERSON>Herrera Cabral</PERSON> said. They arrived with no luggage and
climbed into a waiting limousine, an airport employee said.
   They were taken to the <LOCATION>Dominican Concorde Hotel</LOCATION>, where former
President <PERSON>Leslie Manigat</PERSON> stayed after <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> toppled him in a <DATE>June
17</DATE> coup, <PERSON>Herrera Cabral</PERSON> said. It was not known if <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> would
remain in the Dominican capital.
   Avril reported <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>'s ouster at about <TIME>2:30 a.m.</TIME>, several hours
after shooting broke out at the main plaza in front of the
presidential palace. The gunshots sent dozens of people fleeing for
cover.
involved army factions and members of the <ORGANIZATION>Tonton Macoutes</ORGANIZATION>, the
dreaded agents that terrorized Haitians during the 29-year
dictatorships of the <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> family. Details were not known.
   In his speech to members of the Presidential Guard at the
palace, <ORGANIZATION>Avril</ORGANIZATION> declared himself president and promoted himself to
lieutenant general.
   ``The Presidential Guard, sickened by the way the country has
been governed since the seventh of <DATE>February, 1988</DATE> ... has been
forced to act again,'' he said.
   Avril, a bespectacled, slim man of medium height, was dressed in
a military uniform. He was introduced as ``the most honest officer
in the armed forces'' by a sergeant who wore full battle gear.
   Avril has been a key behind-the-scenes figure in a succession of
governments since nationwide riots forced <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> to flee to exile
in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> on <DATE>Feb. 7, 1986</DATE>. Duvalier had been president since the
<DATE>1971</DATE> death of his father, <PERSON>Francois Duvalier</PERSON>, who ruled since <DATE>1957</DATE>.
   Namphy led a military junta after <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> fled. Avril served as
an adviser to the junta, but resigned in early <DATE>1986</DATE> after
anti-government demonstrations demanded that he and other close
<PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> associates resign.
   In <DATE>March 1987</DATE>, voters overwhelmingly approved a new constitution
calling for elections under civilian control.
   Gunmen killed at least 34 voters on Election Day <DATE>Nov. 29</DATE>, and
the election was canceled. Soldiers from <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Dessalines Barracks</ORGANIZATION>
were blamed.
   Namphy scheduled new elections, but few people voted and <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>
was elected on <DATE>Jan. 17</DATE>.
   Manigat became involved in a dispute with the military over the
transfers of <LOCATION>Avril</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> and other military leaders. Avril played a
key role in <LOCATION>Namphy</LOCATION>'s <DATE>June 17</DATE> overthrow of <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901012-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-12-90 1814EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Haiti-Carter     10-12 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti-Carter,0352</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former President Carter Revisits Haiti</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Pess Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) - Former President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> spent
five hours in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> on a visit <DATE>Friday</DATE> in support of <DATE>December</DATE>
general elections here.
   ``The elections this year will be successful. They will be
honest and free and open, and also safe,'' <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> said in an
interview with the independent Radio Haiti-Inter.
   Elections are scheduled for <DATE>Dec. 16</DATE>. <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> was on his way to
<LOCATION>Guyana</LOCATION>, the South American country where preparations for elections
are also being made.
   He arrived by private plane at <LOCATION>International Airport</LOCATION> and was
welcomed by Foreign Affairs Minister <PERSON>Paul Christian Latortue</PERSON>.
<PERSON>Carter</PERSON> paid courtesy calls on President <PERSON>Ertha Pascal-Trouillot</PERSON> and
army chief of staff Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Herard Abraham</PERSON>.
   In the company of <ORGANIZATION>Electoral Council</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Jean-Robert
Sabalat</PERSON>, <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> inspected voter-registration bureaus in the
capital.
   <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> said registration in rural areas was very good, but in
some parts of the capital ``not many people have registered yet.''
   This poor <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> island nation has 3 million potential
voters. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, during the last attempt at free general elections,
<PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> of eligible voters registered. The election collapsed
when thugs supported by the army shot and hacked to death at least
34 voters. Hundreds were killed and wounded in pre-election
violence.
   The three-week voter-registration period began <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> arrived at <TIME>9:30 a.m.</TIME> and left for <LOCATION>Guyana</LOCATION> at <TIME>2:30 p.m.</TIME>
   It was his third visit to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> since <PERSON>Mrs. Pascal-Trouillot</PERSON>'s
provisional government took power in <DATE>March</DATE>. He had visited <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> in
<DATE>October 1987</DATE>.
   ``The army is giving full support to the election this time,''
<PERSON>Carter</PERSON> said.
   The president-elect will be sworn in on <DATE>Feb. 7, 1991</DATE>, on the
fifth anniversary of the overthrow of dictator <PERSON>Jean-Claude
Duvalier</PERSON>.
   Elections will be monitored by the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, the
Organization for <ORGANIZATION>American States</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Caribbean Community</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Carter Center</ORGANIZATION> observers. <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> said he would return himself in
<DATE>December</DATE>.
   He was accompanied on <DATE>Friday</DATE> by his wife <PERSON>Rosalynn</PERSON> and by <PERSON>Robert
Pastor</PERSON>, Latin American specialist at the <ORGANIZATION>Carter Center</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881007-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-07-88 2136EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Haiti-Clash 1stLd-Writethru a0619 10-07 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti-Clash, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0619,0765</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Killed In Clash Between Officials And Reform Demonstrators</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Two grafs SUB for 3d graf pvs, Radio Haiti-Inter ... YPDATING
with other, unrelated unreleated deaths. Picks up 4th graf, The
Tonton ... with minor editing to trim; ADDS 5 grafs on feuding
families</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) _ Officials in a small town clashed
with citizens demanding their ouster and a soldier guarding the
officials shot and killed one of the demonstrators, an independent
radio station reported <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Some Haitians said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s confrontation in <LOCATION>Desdunes</LOCATION>, 150
miles north of the capital, was one of several indicating the
military government is clamping down on the reform movement
launched by a <DATE>Sept. 17</DATE> soldiers' rebellion.
   In unrelated fighting about 50 miles south of <LOCATION>Desdunes</LOCATION>, two
people were killed <DATE>Friday</DATE> in a feud between members of two families
over land and hundreds of people fled their homes fearing a
massacre, according to <ORGANIZATION>Radio Haiti-Inter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Radio Haiti-Inter said the fight in <LOCATION>Desdunes</LOCATION> began after groups
representing youths, peasants and planters met to formulate demands
for disarming members of the <ORGANIZATION>Tonton Macoutes</ORGANIZATION> and repressive
government officials.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Tonton Macoutes</ORGANIZATION> were the private militia that supported the
29-year dictatorship of the <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> family.
   The demonstrators took to the streets intending to shut down
government offices, the broadcast said. Before they got to the
courthouse they were blocked by ``The Steamroller,'' a group of
henchmen and city officials led by Mayor <PERSON>Anthenor Mercius</PERSON>, the
radio said.
   The mayor's group, guarded by soldiers, threw rocks at the
protesters, and four soldiers protecting the demonstrators withdrew
to their barracks, the broadcast said.
   It said a soldier in the mayor's group, Sgt. <LOCATION>Detroit Valco</LOCATION>,
killed a youth identified as <ORGANIZATION>Evarol Racine</ORGANIZATION> and wounded another man
in the foot. Four other demonstrators were injured by rocks, the
radio said.
   <PERSON>Paul Latortue</PERSON>, an economist who ran for the region's <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> seat
in <DATE>November</DATE>'s violently aborted national elections, said the town
is a stronghold of the <ORGANIZATION>Tonton Macoutes</ORGANIZATION>.
   Latortue noted that on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the government said it was
temporarily suspending the search for <ORGANIZATION>Tonton Macoutes</ORGANIZATION>. On
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, soldiers killed a squatter in the capital, and on
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> they dispersed a demonstration in the town of
<LOCATION>Port-de-Paix</LOCATION>, he said.
   The government believes ``the social potential of the soldiers'
reform movement is too high, it must be reduced and checked,''
<PERSON>Latortue</PERSON> said.
   The enlisted men of the Presidential Guard overthrew the
military government of Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Henri Namphy</PERSON> in a bloodless coup on
<DATE>Sept. 17</DATE> and named Lt. Gen. Prosper Avril to replace him.
   The soldiers demanded an improvement in living conditions for
themselves, the ouster of unpopular military and government
officials, and a return to the <DATE>1987</DATE> Constitution, which <ORGANIZATION>Namphy</ORGANIZATION>
suspended.
   In the initial reaction to the coup, people across the country
chased down, killed and burned several <ORGANIZATION>Tonton Macoutes</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Latortue</PERSON> said <PERSON>Avril</PERSON> has consolidated his power and promoted
non-commissioned officers to bring them into line.
   ``Avril is successfully bringing off a vast seduction campaign
on behalf of American aid,'' <PERSON>Latortue</PERSON> said. ``But the fist in the
velvet glove is iron.''
   Radio-Metropole reported <DATE>Friday</DATE> that Haitian employees of the
resumption of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> assistance to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>.
   Two-thirds of the <MONEY>$90 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> aid package was cut off last
year when <DATE>November</DATE>'s elections were canceled. Thugs supported by
the army attacked and killed 34 people at the polls.
   <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> took over after dictator <PERSON>Jean-Claude Duvalier</PERSON> fled to
exile in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>February 1986</DATE>. Duvalier ruled after the <DATE>1971</DATE>
death of his father, <PERSON>Francois Duvalier</PERSON>, who took over in <DATE>1957</DATE>.
   Radio Haiti-Inter said its reporter in <LOCATION>Estere</LOCATION>, 100 miles north
of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, said one person was was shot to death, another
was killed by machete blows and ``many people'' were clubbed or
stoned in fighting <DATE>Friday</DATE> in the fertile <LOCATION>Artibonite Valley</LOCATION>.
   It said the feud involves members of the Hatier and Bercourt
families who have had violent disputes for years over land
ownership.
   The report said that after a fatal shooting, Hatier property
near <LOCATION>Estere</LOCATION> was invaded by members of the Desdunes-based Bercourt
and in the fighting, hundreds of residents fled the area in panic.
   It said police made one arrest and called for reinforcements to
help restore calm.
   In <DATE>July 1987</DATE>, more than 250 people were killed near the town of
<PERSON>Jean Rabel</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Artibonite</LOCATION> province in battles involving a dispute
between an association of landless peasants and a coalition of
landowners and sharecroppers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-13878</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJTC2AA3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931020
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 OCT 93 / Haitian ruler ignores peace plan as fleet gathers
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By AP
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
LT GEN <PERSON>Raoul Cedras</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s army commander, yesterday ignored demands to
respect the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations-brokered</ORGANIZATION> plan allowing the country's exiled
president to return, despite the re-imposition of an international embargo,
AP reports from <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>.
Six <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and three Canadian navy ships were offshore to enforce the embargo
yesterday, and a French frigate was on the way to join them. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> said it
would send a frigate.
Gen Cedras relaxed with aides at army headquarters early yesterday after the
midnight deadline for him to comply with the plan passed. News photographers
snapped shots of him smoking and joking.
Asked what the army would do if US troops came ashore to rescue Americans,
he said: 'I'm certain it will not reach such a point.'
The embargo aims to compel him to live up to an accord he signed to allow
Gen <PERSON>Cedras</PERSON> was a key part of the military coup which overthrew <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON> -
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s first popularly elected president - in <DATE>1991</DATE>.
The capital, <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, came to life slowly on the first day of the
embargo. 'Gas supplies are normal. There's no rationing, yet,' a pump
attendant said. Prices remained stable at about Dollars 1.50 (Pounds 1) a
gallon and there were no queues.
But schools, government offices and some shops remained closed for a second
day on <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON>'s orders, to mourn the assassination <DATE>last week</DATE> of <PERSON>Mr Guy
Malary</PERSON>, the justice minister, who was part of the transition cabinet
preparing for <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON>'s return. <PERSON>Mr Robert Malval</PERSON>, the prime minister,
has blamed military authorities for the murder.
The sanctions decreed by the <ORGANIZATION>UN Security Council</ORGANIZATION> include a ban on oil and
petrol shipments, a ban on weapons, and a freezing of overseas assets of
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s de facto authorities or 'their agents'.
While the blockade could stop tankers, the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> has taken no measures to halt
petrol shipments from the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>, which shares the island of
Hispaniola with <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>. The Dominican government is close to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s army,
and previous cross-border embargo violations had been reported.
The Haitian military is also believed to have stockpiled several weeks'
supply of oil reserves.
The dispute has raised tensions in <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>. Hundreds of residents
have fled to the countryside in anticipation of more army repression or a
foreign invasion.
Gen <PERSON>Cedras</PERSON> said the solution to the crisis lay in further negotiation, but
UN envoy <PERSON>Mr Dante Caputo</PERSON>, the architect of the plan to restore <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON>,
rejected that idea.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>HTZ  Haiti, Caribbean.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-14150</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJSC5AARFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931019
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 OCT 93 / Foreigners and Haitians flee amid rumours of invasion
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THOUSANDS of foreigners living in <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s capital, gathered
at its international airport yesterday in an effort to flee the country
following the broadcast of a statement by supporters of the military
government that all white foreigners should leave immediately.
An attempt by the military government, through another broadcast yesterday,
to retract the command appeared only to have added to the growing panic and
tension.
Meanwhile, Haitians are leaving the capital for the countryside in the wake
of rumours that a foreign military invasion is imminent as part of
international efforts to restore <PERSON>Mr Jean-Bertrand Aristide</PERSON> as president.
Clashes between factions supporting <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON> and those backing the
military government, which has refused to step down, claimed 16 lives over
the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, and appeared likely to continue yesterday as <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON>'s
supporters organised three days of mourning for <PERSON>Mr Guy Malary</PERSON>, the justice
minister who was assassinated on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
Diplomats said Haitians were convinced that foreign troops would land in a
matter of days unless the military rulers left office and made way for <PERSON>Mr
Aristide</PERSON> to return.
The fears of an invasion heightened at the <DATE>weekend</DATE> as warships from the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> took up positions off <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s coast to enforce an international
economic embargo aimed at forcing Gen <PERSON>Raoul Cedras</PERSON>, the military leader, and
other officers to step down in accordance with an agreement reached with <PERSON>Mr
Aristide</PERSON> in early <DATE>July</DATE>. Gen <PERSON>Cedras</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lt Col Michel Francois</PERSON>, the police
chief, have said they will not leave office.
The effectiveness of earlier attempts at an embargo have been frustrated by
hectic trading across the border between <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>,
which share the island of Hispaniola. The Dominican government has said it
will reinforce military patrols at the border, but businessmen in <LOCATION>Santo
Domingo</LOCATION>, the capital, said yesterday that this might not be enough to
prevent some soldiers and other smugglers from selling petrol and other
essentials to the Haitians.
Supporters of <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON> say factions in the military have plotted the
murder of several prominent Haitians, including <PERSON>Aristide</PERSON> supporters and
members of the civilian government, to frustrate further the return of <PERSON>Mr
Aristide</PERSON>.
The claim gained currency following the murder <DATE>last month</DATE> of <PERSON>Mr Antoine
Izmery</PERSON>, a businessman and supporter of <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON>, and that of <PERSON>Mr Malary</PERSON>
last week.
Likely targets of the campaign are reported to be <PERSON>Mr Robert Malval</PERSON>, the
prime minister, and <PERSON>Mr Evans Paul</PERSON>, the mayor of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> and a
supporter of <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>HTZ  Haiti, Caribbean.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880919-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-88 0051EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Haiti-Glance     09-19 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Haiti-Glance,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Haiti at a Glance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Haiti, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Facts and figures on <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Facts and figures on <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Facts and figures on <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Facts and figures on <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Facts and figures on <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880620-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-20-88 1616EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Haiti 7thLd-Writethru a0644 06-20 0989</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Haiti, 7th Ld-Writethru, a0644,1020</SECOND>
<HEAD>Namphy Declares Himself President of Haiti</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with Manigat arriving in the
Dominican Republic with family. PICKS up 6th graf pvs bgng, ``The
president betrayed ...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ED McCULLOUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) _ Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Henri Namphy</PERSON> today
declared himself president of <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> after troops stormed the
national palace and deposed civilian President <PERSON>Leslie Manigat</PERSON>.
   ``The future of democracy and liberty was at stake. The army
must protect the superior interests of the country and must head
the country,'' <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> said in a television broadcast <TIME>late this
morning</TIME> from the presidential palace.
   ``To this end, a military government has been formed with, as
president, Gen. <PERSON>Henri Namphy</PERSON>,'' he said.
   The coup ended four months of civilian government and put <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>
back in command of the nation he led for two years as head of a
three-man junta. It came less than a week after <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> fired
<PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> and tried to reorganize the military.
   Namphy was surrounded by military leaders, including Lt. Col.
<PERSON>Jean-Claude Paul</PERSON>, once <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>'s chief military ally. It was not
immediately known if <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> had aligned himself with <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> and his family arrived today in <LOCATION>Santo Domingo</LOCATION>, the
capital of neighboring <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>. Manigat was staying at
the <ORGANIZATION>Dominican Concorde Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, a hotel spokesman said. Haiti and the
<LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION> share the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> island of Hispaniola.
   ``The president betrayed your confidence and violated the
constitution he swore to observe,'' <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> said. ``He took a path
that led irrevocably to the most brutal form of dictatorship. To
this end, he attacked the army and shook its high command to make
it a docile instrument of personal power. He thus imperiled the
conquest of <DATE>Feb. 7</DATE>.''
   A few hours later, the military announced a new Cabinet of
ministers. The announcement said the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>House of Deputies</ORGANIZATION>
had been dissolved and that the new government would rule by decree.
   The new Cabinet, announced on state-run television by Col. <PERSON>Gary
Leon</PERSON>, general secretary of the armed forces, was made up of 11
members of the military and one civilian.
   <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> was inaugurated as president <DATE>Feb. 7</DATE>. The junta stepped
down after he took office.
   Manigat retired <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> as commander in chief of <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s
7,000-man army on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, charging him with insubordination in
ordering the transfer of <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> and other high-ranking officers three
days earlier.
   Namphy first appeared on state-run television at about <TIME>1:30 a.m.</TIME>
in a broadcast from the palace shortly after the coup.
   ``The army will lead the country this way,'' he declared, waving
an Uzi submachine gun and flanked by soldiers.
   There was no official word on casualties from the takeover.
   A man at <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>'s residence was on the telephone with the <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>
News when soldiers moved in. Jean Lescouflair identified himself as
director of the regional <ORGANIZATION>Information Ministry</ORGANIZATION> and a former <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>
teacher. He said <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> was upstairs with government ministers
discussing how to respond to <ORGANIZATION>Namphy</ORGANIZATION>'s statement when soldiers
arrived at about <TIME>3:08 a.m.</TIME>
   ``I am hearing some noise coming like a machine gun,'' he said,
lowering his voice. ``They are entering the yard now ... It seems
like they are smashing the cars in the yard.''
   At <TIME>3:20 a.m. Lescouflair</TIME> told the <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> News he could hear a
security guard shouting in French, ``Don't shoot! We're coming
out!''.
   A few minutes later, someone was heard yelling ``Hands up!'' in
French, the newspaper said. The last words from Lescouflair were,
``Call my wife. Goodbye.''
   Haitian journalists said troops loyal to <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> were killed
when soldiers backed by three tanks freed <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> from house arrest
and stormed the palace. <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> had been held at his residence in
<LOCATION>Bon Repos</LOCATION>, 15 miles outside the capital.
   The front of the palace did not appear damaged and showed no
sign of battle.
   The airport was closed today. By midday, the streets of the
capital were busy with cars, trucks and pedestrians.
   Early today, radio stations were not broadcasting news, only
music, and international operators refused to accept calls. One
operator said <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> ordered operators not to place calls, but it
was possible to dial directly.
   People on the streets were aware of what had happened, despite
the lack of radio reports.
   ``It's not good for democracy, what happened, but it may be good
for <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>,'' said one 22-year-old unemployed laborer. ``Maybe we
cannot talk, but maybe we can work.''
   The fighting began after a 10-minute blackout at about <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>. The streets of this <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> capital became deserted.
Automatic and heavy caliber gunfire broke out around the palace.
   Heard from a hotel two blocks away, it died down, then surged
for 1{ hours again just after <TIME>midnight</TIME>, when explosions also were
heard.
   Government sources said <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>, 57, was taken by ambulance from
his home to a military hospital. A Haitian journalist said <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>
would be expelled from the country.
   An <ORGANIZATION>Agence France-Press</ORGANIZATION> reporter spoke by telephone with <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>
early today and reported the president said he was uninjured.
   Earlier <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> retired the <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> police chef
and transferred about two dozen officers, including the head of the
presidential guard.
   ``The presidential guard went to get <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> and brought him to
the palace,'' said the Western diplomat, who spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   The army has controlled this impoverished nation during most of
its 184-year history. A junta ruled <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> for two years after
dictator <PERSON>Jean-Claude Duvalier</PERSON> fled to exile in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>February
1986</DATE>.
   The military ran the <DATE>Jan. 17</DATE> balloting in which <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> was
elected. The most popular candidates and most voters boycotted the
election, and it was widely criticized as rigged.
   An independently run election <DATE>Nov. 29</DATE> was thwarted by violence
that left more than 30 people dead.
   Paul's soldiers were blamed for much of the violence, after
which the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> withheld <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY> in aid. Paul was
indicted in <DATE>March</DATE> by a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> grand jury on drug trafficking charges.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-13870</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJTC2ABBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931020
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 OCT 93 / US Navy stops ship in Haiti blockade
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By Agencies
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
A <ORGANIZATION>US Navy</ORGANIZATION> frigate briefly stopped and boarded a ship from <LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION> bound for
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> yesterday in the first maritime interception since the reimposition of
a UN oil and weapons blockade on the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> country aimed at restoring
its exiled president, agencies report from <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>.
The ship's master reported he was carrying cement, an item not prohibited
under the embargo. The ship was allowed to proceed after an hour-long
inspection.
Six <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and three Canadian navy ships are off the coast of <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> to enforce
the embargo under Operation Support Democracy, and a French frigate is on
the way to join them. <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Netherland</LOCATION> said they would send
frigates, and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> is also considering sending vessels.
In <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Lt Gen Raoul Cedras</PERSON>, the army commander, ignored demands to
respect the UN-brokered plan for the return of President <PERSON>Jean-Bertrand
Aristide</PERSON>.
Gen Cedras relaxed with aides at army headquarters early yesterday after the
midnight deadline for him to comply with the plan passed. News photographers
snapped shots of him smoking and joking.
Asked what the army would do if US troops came ashore to rescue Americans,
he said: 'I'm certain it will not reach such a point.'
The embargo aims to compel him to live up to an accord he signed to allow <PERSON>Mr
Aristide</PERSON> to return to office on <DATE>October 30</DATE>. Gen <PERSON>Cedras</PERSON> was a key part of the
military coup which overthrew <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON> - <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s first popularly elected
president - in <DATE>1991</DATE>.
The capital, <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, came to life slowly on the first day of the
embargo. 'Gas supplies are normal. There's no rationing, yet,' a pump
attendant said. Prices remained stable at about Dollars 1.50 (Pounds 1) a
gallon and there were no queues.
But schools, government offices and some shops remained closed for a second
day on <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON>'s orders, to mourn the assassination <DATE>last week</DATE> of <PERSON>Mr Guy
Malary</PERSON>, the justice minister, who was part of the transition cabinet
preparing for <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON>'s return.
The sanctions decreed by the <ORGANIZATION>UN Security Council</ORGANIZATION> include a ban on oil and
petrol shipments, a ban on weapons, and a freezing of overseas assets of
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s de facto authorities or 'their agents'.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>HTZ  Haiti, Caribbean.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-248</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DI3C1AAWFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930930
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 SEP 93 / Haiti awaits Aristide's resurrection: Why the former
president may be back
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By WILLIAM SPINDLER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE likelihood of the safe return of President <PERSON>Jean-Bertrand Aristide</PERSON> to
lead <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> appears to have increased over the last week.
Violence and intimidation by supporters of the military leadership which
ousted the president two years ago last week looked likely to jeopardise the
implementation of an accord aimed at his safe return.
But the violence - at least in the capital, <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> - appears to have
subsided and a weekend decision to boost the UN presence in the country has
raised hopes that <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON> can return safely.
Around 600 US troops begin to arrive in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> next week in a
'non-confrontational' role as part of a 1,650-member UN mission in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> to
help in the restoration of democracy. The contingent is expected to contain
more than 500 police.
The agreement between military leaders and <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON> envisaging the
latter's return, was sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> and the governments of the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and signed on <DATE>July 3</DATE>. The accord contemplated
the appointment of a new Prime Minister by <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON> and his return on
<DATE>October 30</DATE>.
But since <PERSON>Mr Robert Malval</PERSON> took office as Prime Minister on <DATE>September 2</DATE>, he
and his cabinet have been obstructed and intimidated by government employees
appointed after the coup, who do not want to give up their posts. The
employees have been helped by bands of civilian police auxiliaries known as
'attaches' who have attacked government ministers and the mayor of
<LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr Evans Paul</PERSON>.
According to human rights groups, the 'attaches' are also responsible for
this month's violence against Aristide supporters, in which dozens of people
have been killed or have disappeared, including an important backer of the
President, <PERSON>Mr Antoine Izmery</PERSON>, who was pulled out of a church service and
shot dead.
The prosecutor in charge of investigating some of these killings, <PERSON>Mr Wilson
Ciceron</PERSON>, has resigned after receiving death threats. Ministers have been
subjected to intimidation which, in some cases, has prevented them going to
work. <PERSON>Mr Malval</PERSON> and his government cannot go anywhere without heavy police
protection.
The man whose job it is to provide it, the police chief, <PERSON>Lt Col Michel
Francois</PERSON>, has been accused by <PERSON>Mr Dante Caputo</PERSON>, special envoy of the
for <PERSON>Mr Izmery</PERSON>'s murder.
<PERSON>Mr Malval</PERSON>'s government has invited exiled Haitians to return to the country,
but there is no evidence that any of those returning are Aristide
supporters. Most appear to be supporters of the former <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON>
dictatorship, which ruled the country for three decades.
In an apparent attempt to keep the activities of the <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> supporters
above board, <PERSON>Mr Malval</PERSON> has legalised a Duvalierist party.
In spite of the violence, <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON> is adamant that he will return to
<LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> next month. He is planning to arrive with a number of
prominent international personalities, including the <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Peace Prize</ORGANIZATION>
winner Ms <PERSON>Rigoberta Menchu</PERSON> and possibly former <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> president <PERSON>Mr Jimmy Carter</PERSON>.
If he does, he will find mountains of refuse blocking the streets of the
capital, hunger and disease throughout the country, and an economy almost in
ruins. His first priority, nevertheless, will be to stay alive and to try to
stem the violence.
His task will not be helped by a new organisation calling itself the
'<DATE>September 30</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Group</ORGANIZATION>' after the date of the <DATE>1991</DATE> coup. It has been
distributing leaflets in the streets of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> threatening to
'eradicate' <PERSON>Aristide</PERSON>'s activists before his return.
'The days to come must be red with blood' they warn. They also pledge to
intervene immediately whenever an employee appointed since the coup is
fired. 'Our democracy', the leaflet states, 'consists of the law and the
machine gun'.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>HTZ  Haiti, Caribbean.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9111 Executive Offices.
    P9199 General Government, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-18690</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJCE7ABLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941003
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 OCT 94 / US Marines pulling out of Haiti
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CANUTE JAMES and AGENCIES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   KINGSTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>US Marines</ORGANIZATION> will begin withdrawing from <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> today, to be replaced by extra
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION> military police who are to help disarm forces loyal to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s military
rulers, <ORGANIZATION>Defence Department</ORGANIZATION> officials said <TIME>last night</TIME>, report <PERSON>Canute James</PERSON>,
in <LOCATION>Kingston</LOCATION>, and agencies.
US troops are being ordered to stop violence between Haitians when they
safely can, but a senior <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> official said yesterday that this did not
indicate a broadening of <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> policy.
Also today, about 300 soldiers from seven <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> countries will be
deployed in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> - the first non-US troops to arrive since the military
intervention began a fortnight ago.
The new Caribbean troops, part of a multinational force which is to assist
imposing order in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, have been training in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> for three weeks.
They will be assigned to the docks in <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s capital,
relieving <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> personnel.
The port area has been the scene of bloody clashes between factions
supporting the Haitian military and those backing the exiled President
<PERSON>Jean-Bertrand Aristide</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    HTZ  Haiti, Caribbean.
    XFZ  Caribbean.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880919-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-88 0429EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Haiti 2ndLd-Writethru a0464 09-19 0848</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Haiti, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0464, a0466,0868</SECOND>
<HEAD>Foreign Embassies Advise Citizens to Stay Off Streets After Coup</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: To CORRECT month of bloodless coup to June, sted January as
sent SUB 8th graf, `But for ... widely boycotted.' Picks up 9th
graf pvs, `On Nov. ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> _ Advocates of democratic reform expressed
hope that <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s new military leaders would open a dialogue with
the people after ousting Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Henry Namphy</PERSON>, who ran the country
for more than two years.
   Brig. Gen. <PERSON>Prosper Avril</PERSON>, the army's chief administrative
officer, went on national television <DATE>Sunday</DATE> and declared himself
president of the Western hemisphere's most impoverished nation.
   He said <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> was ousted by the 1,000-man Presidential Guard
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> because it was ``sickened'' by his rule, which was
marked by a tolerance for the murder of government opponents.
   Avril was a military adviser to <PERSON>Jean-Claude Duvalier</PERSON> before the
dictator's <DATE>February 1986</DATE> flight into exile and has since managed to
ally himself with the prevailing forces in the 7,000-man military.
   The government said an unspecified number of soldiers were
reported killed in the coup, and <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> was sent to the <LOCATION>Dominican
Republic</LOCATION>, which shares the island of Hispaniola with <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>.
   Port-au-Prince appeared calm <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, though the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and
Canadian embassies advised their citizens to stay off the streets.
Small groups of people milled in the streets and traffic was light.
Television and radio stations resumed their normal programming.
   The airport, which was closed <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, was expected to reopen
today.
   But for the four-month civilian presidency of <PERSON>Leslie Manigat</PERSON>,
which ended in <DATE>June</DATE> with a bloodless coup, <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> had run <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>
since <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON>'s departure, heading a military-led junta until
<PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> was elected in <DATE>January</DATE> in junta-run balloting that was
widely boycotted.
   On <DATE>Nov. 29</DATE>, independently run elections were thwarted by armed
thugs supported by the army who killed 34 people at the polls.
   And a week before the coup, about 20 men armed with machetes,
handguns and steel pikes attacked a <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> during a
Mass being celebrated by the Rev. <PERSON>Jean Bertrand Aristide</PERSON>, a vocal
critic of the <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> government. Thirteen people were killed and 77
wounded.
   Opposition leaders blamed the government for the attack and
another church burning two days later.
   Heavy gunfire was heard in the capital <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> shortly
before the coup, but <PERSON>Susan Clyde</PERSON>, spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION>
here, said ``it appeared to be mainly celebratory shooting in the
air, nobody shooting at anyone or anything.''
   <PERSON>Frantz Lubin</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s director of information, said an
unspecified number of soldiers were killed.
   Radio stations reported that at least six people were killed in
the capital in coup-related clashes and that mobs pillaged two
homes owned by <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> and the home of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Franck
Romain</PERSON>.
   Although motives for the coup were unclear, it appeared the
soldiers and non-commissioned officers of the elite Presidential
Guard were disenchanted with <ORGANIZATION>Namphy</ORGANIZATION>'s authoritarian rule.
   A Western diplomat, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said
the Presidential Guard had given the army's High Command a list of
19 demands for forming a new government, including democratic
reform and better living conditions for soldiers.
   All the demands were accepted, the diplomat said, except the
nomination of Col. <PERSON>Jean-Claude Paul</PERSON> as military commander-in-chief.
Paul has been indicted on federal drug-trafficking charges in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
   Paul, commander of the dreaded 700-man Dessaline unit, had been
regarded as the most powerful figure in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> after <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>. It was
not known if <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> played a part in the coup, but sources said he
and <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> were at odds.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Anita Stockman</PERSON> said
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> still wanted <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> extradited to face the drug
charges.
   Initial reaction to the coup from advocates of democratic reform
was positive, but cautious.
   ``I will support the military government if they say as soon as
possible when they will call elections,'' said <PERSON>Louis Dejoie II</PERSON>,
leader of the national <ORGANIZATION>Agricultural Industrial Party</ORGANIZATION>. ``We are
ready to speak with any government that respects human rights.''
   In his statement to the nation early <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>Avril</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>
will respect all international treaties, liberties and human rights
and that ``dialogue will be honored for the sake of national
reconciliation.''
   The statement was considered significant because it echoed a
recent offer for dialogue from opposition leader <PERSON>Marc Bazin</PERSON>, a
conservative leader of the <ORGANIZATION>Committee for Democratic Understanding</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Bazin</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Dejoie</ORGANIZATION> were among four leading candidates for
president in the <DATE>Nov. 29</DATE> elections and boycotted the elections won
by <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>.
   Dejoie said he expected the military to announce when elections
would be held in the next week or so.
   ``They must do it or they won't have any support,'' <PERSON>Dejoie</PERSON> said.
``The army right now has to regain its credibility. We want to give
them a chance with this new change of guard.''
   Avril has been a key behind-the-scenes figure in a succession of
governments since nationwide riots forced <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> to flee to
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. Duvalier had been president since the <DATE>1971</DATE> death of his
father, <PERSON>Francois Duvalier</PERSON>, who ruled since <DATE>1957</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-1104</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EIZD8AD9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940926
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 SEP 94 / US warns Haiti junta to co-operate after 10 die in clash
with marines
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JAMES HARDING, GEORGE GRAHAM
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
US officers bluntly warned <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s military chiefs yesterday that they must
co-operate with the intervention force, after <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> marines killed 10 Haitians
in a fierce gun battle at a police station at the <DATE>weekend</DATE>.
President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>, who will address the <ORGANIZATION>UN General Assembly</ORGANIZATION> today, said
he regretted the loss of life, but vowed US troops would continue to respond
to hostile action against them.
The outgoing Haitian strongman, General <PERSON>Raoul Cedras</PERSON>, was called,
grim-faced, to an airport meeting with the head of the US-led intervention
force, General <PERSON>Hugh Shelton</PERSON>, to discuss co-operation and flew by helicopter
to the site of the clash in the northern town of <ORGANIZATION>Cap Haitien</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>US</ORGANIZATION> said
other officers would be meeting the Haitian military to 'ensure their
co-operation'.
The clash on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> - the first involving US troops since they
landed a week ago - came after steadily rising tension between marines and
Haitian authorities in the town.
A <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> officer said pro-democracy demonstrators taunted armed men outside a
police station as marines arrived on patrol. When one of the armed men
raised a sub-machine gun, a marine shot him dead and a gunfight broke out,
the officer said. A <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> sailor was slightly hurt.
Gen Cedras accused the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> of atrocities and demanded the court-martial of a
marine colonel, but the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> brushed aside his angry reaction. Hundreds of
jubilant Haitians yesterday ransacked police stations and an army barracks
in the town, as soldiers and police abandoned their posts. The crowd carried
off beds, tables, desks, electric fans and stacks of papers, before <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
marines restored order.
A leader of the Haitian paramilitary voiced concern that violence could
spread to the capital, <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>. 'Things are getting tense,' he said.
'I feel in danger from the mobs.'
Dozens of demonstrators, emboldened by the presence of <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> troops in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>,
staged an unprecedented mock funeral for Gen Cedras outside the airport in
<LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>.
Senator <PERSON>Sam Nunn</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>US Senate</ORGANIZATION> armed services committee and a
member of former president <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>'s team that negotiated the Haitian
generals' agreement to leave power, warned there might be more conflict.
'This is the first bad incident we've had involving, directly, American
troops, but it won't be the last,' he said.
In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> <TIME>last night</TIME> had talks with UN secretary-general <PERSON>Mr
Boutros Boutros Ghali</PERSON> on plans for turning over the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> mission in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> to
UN peacekeepers. The weekend gun battle is likely to increase the pressure
on the <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> administration to get <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> troops out of <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> as quickly as
possible.
The exiled president, <PERSON>Mr Jean-Bertrand Aristide</PERSON>, whom the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> wants restored
to power, declared yesterday he would call the Haitian parliament into
session on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to consider the plan to grant an amnesty for the
military rulers who ousted him.
The military rulers agreed to step down when an amnesty is passed, and the
exiled president, who is still in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, clearly hopes to speed their
departure.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>HTZ  Haiti, Caribbean.
    USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-15253</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJMCRABAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931013
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 OCT 93 / Port-au-Prince tense as armed men roam the streets
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By WILLIAM SPINDLER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE Haitian capital of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> was tense yesterday, with many shops
and offices closed and heavily-armed men roaming the almost empty streets.
Public transport was at a standstill. Small-arms and machine-gun fire was
heard through the <TIME>night</TIME>, following <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s violent demonstrations which
prevented the landing of US troops on a UN mission intended to oversee the
restoration of democracy on the island.
The offices of national radio and television were occupied by plainclothes
police auxiliaries, known as 'attaches', who also led <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s
demonstrations.
The UN special representative in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr Dante Caputo</PERSON>, cancelled a planned
trip to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> because of the incident. He blamed the Haitian military
for <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s incident, saying the attacks were an insult to the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION> and a
clear violation of the agreements signed in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> between the army and
exiled president <PERSON>Mr Jean-Bertrand Aristide</PERSON>, due to return to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> at the
<DATE>end of this month</DATE> under the peace plan.
The USS Harlan County, carrying the troops, remained anchored outside port
yesterday as <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> officials tried to negotiate a plan for its safe arrival.
In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> <PERSON>Mr Warren Christopher</PERSON>, secretary of state, yesterday accused
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s military leaders of violating the UN-mediated accord and warned that
if sanctions were reimposed, they would be severe.
'By their actions, Gen (<ORGANIZATION>Raoul</ORGANIZATION>) <PERSON>Cedras</PERSON> and Chief of Police (<PERSON>Joseph Michel</PERSON>)
<PERSON>Francois</PERSON> are inviting reimposition of severe economic sanctions that could
affect their country and would also affect them personally,' <PERSON>Mr Christopher</PERSON>
said.
<PERSON>Gen Cedras</PERSON>, who led the <DATE>1991</DATE> coup which ousted <PERSON>Mr Aristide</PERSON>, condemned the
violence but said he sympathised with the Haitians' outrage at the threat to
their sovereignty.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>HTZ  Haiti, Caribbean.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9229 Public Order and Safety, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 7
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880621-0266 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-21-88 2257EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Haiti     06-21 0247</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Haiti,0259</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military Coup Won't Stop Haiti's Pursuit of Duvalier Millions</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Haiti, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GRASSE, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The military coup in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> will not
interrupt <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s efforts to regain millions of dollars allegedly
taken by dictator <PERSON>Jean-Claude Duvalier</PERSON> when he fled to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,
attorneys representing <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   A judge was to be selected <DATE>Monday</DATE> in this southern French city
to hear the case against <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON>, accused of misappropriating <MONEY>$120
million</MONEY> in public funds.
   In <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s capital of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Henri
Namphy</PERSON> re-established military rule by decree and named his own
government a few hours after ousting President <PERSON>Leslie Manigat</PERSON>'s
civilian government.
   The coup crushed hopes for the democracy promised two years ago
after <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> was toppled, ending his family's 29-year
dictatorship.
   ``We are not lawyers for the government but for the Haitian
state,'' said attorney <PERSON>Yann Colin</PERSON>, who represents <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> in its
French legal proceedings.
   In <DATE>April</DATE> a French court ruled it had jurisdiction in the case
against <ORGANIZATION>Duvalier</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Haitian national lottery, office of vehicle insurance,
gaming commission and <ORGANIZATION>Port-au-Prince Bank</ORGANIZATION> are demanding that
<PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> and members of his entourage reimburse the government.
   Colin claimed the <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY> requested represents only part of
what Duvalier diverted.
   Since arriving in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> <DATE>Feb. 7, 1986</DATE>, <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> has lived with
his wife, <PERSON>Michelle</PERSON>, and other family members in a luxurious mansion
in southern <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> rented from <LOCATION>Saudi</LOCATION> millionaire <PERSON>Adnan Kashoggi</PERSON>.
   Duvalier has declined to comment on political developments in
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> since his downfall.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880921-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-21-88 2252EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Haiti 1stLd-Writethru   09-21 0774</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0686,0793</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebellion Spreads In Army; Troops Fire On Crowd</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New grafs 1-14 UPDATE with deaths, soldiers firing on crowd;
other detail. Picks up 7th graf pvs, Organizers canceled ...
editing to conform</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) _ Soldiers who toppled the regime of
Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Henri Namphy</PERSON> mutinied against more commanders <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
and civilians rallied to join the uprising. Witnesses said a
12-year-old boy was killed when troops fired on a crowd.
   Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Prosper Avril</PERSON>, made president <DATE>Sunday</DATE> after a coup led
by <ORGANIZATION>Namphy's Presidential Guard</ORGANIZATION>, tried to quell the military
uprising <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by naming a new armed forces chief and retiring
nine unpopular commanding officers.
   ``The situation is precarious. After all, we are in the midst of
a general mutiny,'' a Western diplomat said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Coup leaders who put Avril in power demanded that he institute
democratic reforms, including free elections that <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> has not had
in 31 years. But even though Avril appealed for calm, the purge
that put him in power continued to spread to military barracks and
the streets.
   Radio <PERSON>Haiti Inter</PERSON> said army units opposed to Avril attacked a
crowd in this capital city at <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and that a
12-year-old boy, identified as <PERSON>Nilo Chailes</PERSON>, was killed and three
people were wounded.
   Witnesses said the crowd was on its way to pillage the home of a
sergeant known for his brutality when soldiers fired.
   The station said mutineers battled other soldiers, with one
soldier killed in a clash <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Jacmel</LOCATION>, about 45 miles south
of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>.
   Mutineers on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> were rounding up agents of <ORGANIZATION>Namphy's
Bureau of Criminal Investigatons</ORGANIZATION> and leaving them at army
headquarters in <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>. before cheering crowds, <ORGANIZATION>Radio Haiti
Inter</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   Radio stations said ousted military commanders were also being
dropped off _some in handcuffs _ at the headquarters, but their
fate was unclear.
   Radio Soleil, the Roman Catholic radio station, reported
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that <PERSON>Sergo Joseph</PERSON>, arrested <DATE>Aug. 5</DATE> for writing an
anti-government slogan on a wall, was freed by a judge <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME>.
   He was severely beaten after his arrest and the human rights
group <ORGANIZATION>Amnesty International</ORGANIZATION> campaigned for his release.
   In <ORGANIZATION>Cap Haitien</ORGANIZATION>, a crowd plundered the residence of <PERSON>Louis Noisin</PERSON>,
a former <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> president, <ORGANIZATION>Radio Haiti Inter</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, civilians supporting the mutineers engaged in mob
killings and workers at government companies struck to unseat
state-appointed managers, actions apparently aimed at wiping out
remnants of <ORGANIZATION>Namphy</ORGANIZATION>'s rule.
   ``The demands of the mutineers have been accepted; it has become
a people's army, at least for the moment,'' the diplomat said,
   Organizers canceled a demonstration at <ORGANIZATION>St. Jean Bosco Roman
Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> planned for <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to support the soldiers'
rebellion and rescheduled it for <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The organizers, members
of a leftist coalition, said they would meet instead with Avril and
Sgt. <PERSON>Joseph Heubreux</PERSON>, leader of <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s coup.
   ``I came to <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> from the country to participate in
the demonstration,'' said <PERSON>Andre-Juste Pierre</PERSON>, 32, an unemployed
welder from <LOCATION>Cabaret</LOCATION>, 20 miles north of the capital. ``I don't feel
frustrated because the military government is afraid. We'll
demonstrate tomorrow.''
   About 100 people gathered in front of the burned-out ruins of
the church, staring at the charred, mutilated body of a thug killed
by a mob <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Witnesses identified him as an ex-officer of the <ORGANIZATION>Tonton
Macoutes</ORGANIZATION>, the dreaded private army of the <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> dictatorship.
They said the man took part in the <DATE>Sept. 11</DATE> massacre of 13
parishioners at the church that provoked <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s coup.
   The government's dismissal of eight generals and a colonel
followed the ouster by soldiers of at least 11 commanders
nationwide since <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   In <ORGANIZATION>St. Marc</ORGANIZATION>, about 60 miles north of the capital, residents took
to the streets <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to punish thugs allegedly allied with the
local army commander. Soldiers fired rifles into the air to
disperse them, <ORGANIZATION>Radio Metropole</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   Among officers retired <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was former <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION> Minister Brig.
Gen. <PERSON>Williams Regala</PERSON>, despised in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> for his ties to the
dictatorship of Francois ``Papa Doc'' <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> and his son,
<PERSON>Jean-Claude</PERSON>. Namphy headed a three-man junta that ruled <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> after
the younger <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> was forced into exile on <DATE>Feb. 7, 1986</DATE>.
   Central Bank employees went on strike <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> demanding the
board of directors resign, <ORGANIZATION>Radio Metropole</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Employees of at least the state flour mill and electric company
joined the military mutiny and ousted their bosses <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
Unpopular managers of other government companies also were
expelled, radio stations said, but details were sketchy.
   Radio stations estimated that up to 12 <ORGANIZATION>Tonton Macoutes</ORGANIZATION> had been
killed by mobs and soldiers since <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881010-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-10-88 2230EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Haiti     10-10 0392</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>Demonstrations Banned In Second-largest City</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) _ The military commander of
<LOCATION>Cap-Haitien</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s second-largest city, has prohibited street
demonstrations until further notice, the independent radio station
Haiti-Inter reported <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Col. <PERSON>Carrel Occil</PERSON>, military commander of the northern coastal
town, issued the order on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in response to plans for
upcoming demonstrations, the radio said.
   Neighboorhood citizens' committees had been planning
demonstrations against unpopular government officials and in
support of the <DATE>Sept. 17</DATE> coup that initiated a nationwide movement
of reform, it said.
   Since the ouster of the military government of Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Henri
Namphy</PERSON> by rank-and-file soldiers of the Presidential Guard on <DATE>Sept.
17</DATE>, dozens of commanders with ties to the <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> regime were
removed throughout <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> and unpopular and repressive army officers
and government officials dismissed.
   An unidentified member of a Cap-Haitien neighborhood committee
told Haiti-Inter that ``nothing has changed,'' that anti-democratic
officials are still holding office.
   In recent declarations, such prominent political leaders as
<PERSON>Louis Dejoie Jr.</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sylvio Claude</PERSON> have been calling on the
government to make a clean sweep of members of the dreaded <ORGANIZATION>Tonton
Macoutes</ORGANIZATION> from public office.
   In a related development, club-swinging soldiers broke up a
demonstration <DATE>Sunday</DATE> against the rural police in Petite Riviere, a
town in the <LOCATION>Artibonite Province</LOCATION> 40 miles north of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>,
Haiti-Inter reported.
   The soldiers, from the garrison of <LOCATION>Gonaives</LOCATION> to the north of the
town, arrested two protesters and dispersed the crowd by shooting
into the air. None of the people who were clubbed was seriously
injured, Haiti-Inter reported.
   Last week in the same town, 2,000 people demonstrated without
incident.
   In recent days, however, the army has intervened to quell
rallies.
   Last <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, soldiers shot and killed a protester in a
demonstration of squatters in the capital, and two weekends ago, in
Cote-de-Fer, a small southern coastal town, a popular tribunal
composed of citizens and local soldiers was disbanded without
incident by the army.
   Dictator Francois ``Papa Doc'' <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON> ruled <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> since <DATE>1957</DATE>
and was succeeded by his son, <PERSON>Jean-Claude</PERSON>, who fled into exile in
<DATE>February 1986</DATE> in the midst of a popular uprising.
   Namphy led a three-man junta that governed this <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> island
nation until <PERSON>Leslie Manigat</PERSON> was elected president last <DATE>January</DATE> in
elections widely viewed as fraudulent.
   Namphy ousted <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> and declared himself president on <DATE>June 20</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900322-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-22-90 0258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Haiti     03-22 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Haiti,0578</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nineteen Killed in Wave of Indiscriminate Attacks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) _ In attacks political and civic
leaders blame on thugs angered by the shift from army to civilian
rule, marauding gunmen have killed at least 19 people this week,
officials and radio reports say.
   The victims included 11 members of a self-defense group hacked
to death in the town of Petit Goave, the birthplace of nationwide
demonstrations that forced Lt. Gen. Prosper Avril from power.
   In the capital of <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, assailants killed at
least four people and wounded eight, according to the reports. The
wounded included five members of a self-defense unit shot by gunmen
in speeding cars.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Unity Assembly</ORGANIZATION>, the political and civic coalition that chose
provisional President <PERSON>Ertha Pascal-Trouillot</PERSON> after <PERSON>Avril</PERSON> went into
exile <DATE>last week</DATE>, has urged the formation of self-defense units.
   There has been a dearth of police protection since Avril fled.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Unity Assembly</ORGANIZATION> said thugs and members of the
ill-disciplined, 6,000-man army _ the traditional power broker in
this impoverished <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> nation _ are angry at the military's
surrender of power to civilians.
   ``These acts of urban terrorism have been committed by
irreconcilable supporters of dictatorship,'' politician <ORGANIZATION>Rockefeller
Guerre</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Others said the attacks were aimed at
destabilizing the civilian government.
   An official at the state hospital in <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> said the
morgue received the bodies of two people shot before dawn
the hospital treated eight people _ including the five members of a
self-defense unit _ for bullet wounds.
   Privately owned <ORGANIZATION>Radio Haiti Inter</ORGANIZATION> said gunmen trying to hold up
a rice storehouse downtown killed security guard <PERSON>William Desir</PERSON> late
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and shot up the building before driving off and shooting
at passers-by.
   And it said fishermen in the seafront neighborhood of <ORGANIZATION>Carrefour</ORGANIZATION>
on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> found the body of an unidentified, naked man with his
hands tied behind his back.
   The Roman Catholic station <ORGANIZATION>Radio Soleil</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Radio Haiti Inter</ORGANIZATION> and
an independent source said 13 people, including 11 members of a
neighborhood self-defense group, were killed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Petit
Goave</LOCATION>, 50 miles southwest of the capital.
   Radio <PERSON>Haiti Inter</PERSON> said the 11 were hacked to death by a gang of
assailants while searching for the killers of an elderly couple who
were shot and disemboweled earlier in the day.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, 1,000 police at checkpoints in <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>
searched private vehicles for weapons, state television said.
   A soldier was shot to death in the capital by unknown assailants
<DATE>Monday</DATE>, and eight nuns at a Roman Catholic girls' school were
beaten and injured by machete-wielding assailants who broke into
their compound on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Haiti has had five governments since a <DATE>February 1986</DATE> popular
uprising forced dictator <PERSON>Jean-Claude Duvalier</PERSON> into exile in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   All but the current government were dominated by the military.
   Avril was elevated to power 18 months ago in a coup by
rank-and-file soldiers who said they were outraged with
state-sanctioned murder and corruption.
   His resignation followed a week of nationwide demonstrations
sparked by the killing by the army of an 11-year-old girl on her
porch in Petit Goave.
   If the current government holds general elections as promised,
the next government will be the first chosen by the people since
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> declared independence from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>1804</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880620-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-20-88 0603EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Haiti-Glance     06-20 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Haiti-Glance,0503</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Haiti, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a brief look at <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, where a military coup late <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
ousted the first country's first civilian-elected president in 30
years.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>THE LAND:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here is a brief look at <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, where a military coup late <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
ousted the first country's first civilian-elected president in 30
years.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>THE PEOPLE:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here is a brief look at <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, where a military coup late <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
ousted the first country's first civilian-elected president in 30
years.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>HISTORY:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here is a brief look at <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, where a military coup late <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
ousted the first country's first civilian-elected president in 30
years.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-14744</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJOCVABFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931015
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 OCT 93 / Haitian justice minister shot dead
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
ASSASSINS yesterday killed <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s justice minister and at least two other
people in an escalation of the violence that has set the country's military
leaders on a collision course with the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> administration, <ORGANIZATION>Reuter</ORGANIZATION> reports
from <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>.
Justic Minister Guy Malary was shot dead in <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, the capital,
shortly after President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> had warned Haitian military leaders to
restore democracy. <PERSON>Mr Malary</PERSON>, a wealthy lawyer, was a supporter of ousted
President <PERSON>Jean-Bertrand Aristide</PERSON>, who is intended to return to the country
under a <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> peace accord signed by General <PERSON>Raoul Cedras</PERSON>, the army
chief.
The Haitian government said that <PERSON>Mr Malary</PERSON>'s bodyguard and driver were also
killed and local radio said there were unconfirmed reports of a fourth
death. The minister's car was found riddled with bullets beside a church
where another supporter of President <PERSON>Aristide</PERSON> was shot dead last month.
In another show of defiance against international pressure, members of a
pro-military group marched into parliament, briefly held some legislators
hostage and expressed their support for <ORGANIZATION>Gen Cedras</ORGANIZATION>, local radio reported.
Nearly all cabinet ministers, who were sworn into office last month, have
received death threats from civilian gunmen known as 'attaches' for their
links to police and army. <PERSON>Mr Malary</PERSON> had been spearheading legislation to
separate <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s army and police, a crucial step in the UN accord.
Earlier yesterday, police chief <PERSON>Michel Francois</PERSON>, who controls
<LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, vowed he would not bend to international pressure and give
up power. 'I'm Haitian and I've chosen to die in my country,' he said.
His supporters said they would paralyse Port-au-Prince with a general strike
on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the day international sanctions imposed by the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>
take effect.
<PERSON>Mr Dante Caputo</PERSON>, the chief UN envoy to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, said even the immediate
resignation of <PERSON>Gen Cedras</PERSON> was not enough to call off the UN sanctions. He
said he wanted hard proof that the army would halt growing street violence
before the UN considered cancelling the planned oil embargo and freeze of
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s assets.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>HTZ  Haiti, Caribbean.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9229 Public Order and Safety, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880620-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-20-88 2342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Haiti 4thLd-Writethru a0835 06-20 0848</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0835,0872</SECOND>
<HEAD>Namphy Ousts Civilians, Declares Himself President</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with Manigat saying he's unhurt,
reportedly offered asylum in Venezuela, details; Restores Namphy's
earlier television quote. PICKUP 4th graf pvs `Except for...';
EDITS from 15th graf pvs `At first, ... to bottom to TRIM.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAP1; LaserGraphic NY15</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED McCULLOUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) _ Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Henri Namphy</PERSON> formed a
military government <DATE>Monday</DATE> with himself in charge, after deposing
the 4-month-old civilian administration of President <PERSON>Leslie Manigat</PERSON>.
   The 55-year-old career soldier named a 12-member Cabinet that
included only one civilian, and said he would rule by decree as the
new president.
   ``The army will lead the country this way,'' <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> declared on
national television shortly after the coup, waving an Uzi
submachine gun and flanked by soldiers.
   <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>, who was seized <DATE>Sunday</DATE> evening at his hillside villa
outside <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION>, arrived in neighboring <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Monday</DATE> with his family, said military sources in <LOCATION>Santo Domingo</LOCATION>.
   In a statement issued through a spokesman of the hotel where
<PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> and his family were staying, the 57-year-old ousted
president said he was not injured in the coup.
   The administration of President <PERSON>Joaquin Balaguer</PERSON> gave no
official statement, but <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> sources said <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> was a
``guest of the Dominican government'' and might travel <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
<TIME>afternoon</TIME> to <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, where he had been offered political asylum.
   Except for a few random shots heard, <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> was quiet
<DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. There were no reports of unrest in the provinces. Men
and women strolled past the national palace and children played
soccer at a closed gasoline station two blocks away.
   In a short live broadcast on state-run television from the
<ORGANIZATION>National Palace</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> said <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> ``betrayed your confidence and
violated the constitution he swore to uphold.''
   ``The future of democracy was at stake,'' said the general, who
was accompanied by elements of every unit in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s 7,000-member
armed forces. ``The army must protect the superior interests of the
country and must head the country. To this end, a military
government has been formed.''
   <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>, who spoke in French for about five minutes, pledged to
``guarantee that all the conquests of <DATE>Feb. 7</DATE> (when his three-man
junta turned over the government to <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>) will be respected. To
our powerful friends and to international organizations, I
guarantee the respect of all commitments.''
   <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Phyllis Oakley</PERSON> said in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>:
``The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> government strongly condemns this serious blow
to hopes for democracy in that troubled land.''
   Namphy's action halted, at least for now, the slow journey
toward democracy begun after President <PERSON>Jean-Claude Duvalier</PERSON> fled
the country <DATE>Feb. 7, 1986</DATE>, ending the 29-year dictatorship founded
by his father, <PERSON>Francois</PERSON> ``Papa Doc'' <PERSON>Duvalier</PERSON>.
   The general, who was <PERSON>Jean-Claude Duvalier</PERSON>'s chief of staff, led
the junta that ruled <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> until <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> won a presidential
election this year with the army's help.
   <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, a nation of 6 million people and the poorest country in
the <LOCATION>Western Hemisphere</LOCATION>, shares the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> island of Hispaniola
with the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>.
   Manigat began his disastrous confrontation with the army, the
traditional base of power since independence in <DATE>1804</DATE>, by removing
<PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> as commander on <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Manigat also reassigned two dozen
other officers <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, many of them <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>'s allies.
   He accused <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> of insubordination for ordering the transfers
of several officers without presidential permission, including
<PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>'s main military ally, Lt. Col. <PERSON>Jean-Claude Paul</PERSON>. The
barracks of <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>'s command, the 700-man <ORGANIZATION>Dessalines Battalion</ORGANIZATION>, is
directly behind the <ORGANIZATION>National Palace</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>, who has been indicted by a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> federal court on charges
of drug trafficking, was in the group standing around <LOCATION>Namphy</LOCATION> during
the television appearance <DATE>Monday</DATE>, but whether he had allied himself
with the general was unclear.
   The military announced a new Cabinet, dissolution of the
<ORGANIZATION>National Assembly</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Namphy</ORGANIZATION>'s intention to rule by decree.
   Col. <PERSON>Gary Leon</PERSON>, general secretary of the armed forces, read the
names of the Cabinet members on television. Gen. <PERSON>Williams Regala</PERSON>,
who was defense minister under <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> and signed the order
retiring <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON>, will be minister of defense and interior.
   No public opposition greeted <PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> on his first day back in the
palace. There were no rallies for <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON>, whose political
headquarters was ransacked.
   The international airport in <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> was closed, along
with most schools and businesses in the capital. Car and pedestrian
traffic was curtailed. Overseas telephone lines were closed down
and an employee at the government telephone company, <ORGANIZATION>Teleco</ORGANIZATION>, said
<PERSON>Namphy</PERSON> ordered it.
   Few soldiers were in the streets and there were no military
checkpoints.
   Namphy had been under house arrest but was freed <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>,
apparently with aid of the presidential guard and the Leopards
counter-insurgency unit using three tanks.
   Shooting began in front of the palace at about <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
as the presidential guard and Leopards battled <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Dessalines
Battalion</ORGANIZATION>. At <TIME>1:30 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Namphy</ORGANIZATION> announced the coup on
television in a broadcast from the palace.
   There were no official reports on casualties but Haitian
journalists said some soldiers loyal to <PERSON>Manigat</PERSON> were killed. <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Embassy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Jeffrey Lite</PERSON> said no Americans were injured.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880711-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-11-88 1628EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Haiti-Murder     07-11 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti-Murder,0660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Human Rights Activist Stabbed To Death in Haiti, Government Blamed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> (AP) _ <PERSON>Lafontant Joseph</PERSON>, a prominent human
rights activist, was found beaten and stabbed to death <DATE>Monday</DATE> in a
jeep near the <LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> airport, police said.
   ``This murder is a very serious incident,'' <PERSON>Jean-Claude Bajeux</PERSON>,
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Ecumenical Center for Human Rights</ORGANIZATION>, told <ORGANIZATION>The
Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>. ``It means that the lives of all militants for
human rights in <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> are in danger.''
   <PERSON>Paul Latortue</PERSON>, a former senatorial candidate who lives in exile
in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, blamed the murder on government leader Lt. Gen.
<PERSON>Henri Namphy</PERSON>.
   ``I have no doubt that this is a political killing,'' he said.
``It's connected with the government.''
   <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON>, 54, director of <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Center of Education for Human
Rights</ORGANIZATION>, was found dead in his four-wheel drive vehicle near <LOCATION>Mais
Gate International Airport</LOCATION>, just outside the capital. A passerby
recognized the dead man and contacted his family.
   The activist's nephew, physician <PERSON>Ronald Joseph</PERSON>, said <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> had
been stabbed once in his chest and two or three times in his back.
``The body looked mutilated,'' he said.
   Army Maj. <PERSON>Joseph Baguidy</PERSON>, head of <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Criminal
Investigation</ORGANIZATION>, said police found blood about 500 yards from the
car, indicating <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> was killed outside the vehicle.
   There appeared to be more than one assailant, <PERSON>Baguidy</PERSON> said. He
did not elaborate.
   The police official said the seats of the car were found in a
horizontal position and that police discovered a pair of women's
sandals in the vehicle.
   He said it was possible a woman may have been in the car with
<PERSON>Joseph</PERSON>, but that no other body had been located.
   ``We are now examining the blood to see whether there was
another victim,'' he said.
   Radio Metropole, an independent station, said <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> was last
seen alive by his wife, <PERSON>Raymonde</PERSON>, whom he dropped off at their home
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. <PERSON>Mrs. Joseph</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Haitian Women's
Committee Against Torture</ORGANIZATION>, was the first to identify her husband's
body.
   <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON>, a lawyer, founded the <ORGANIZATION>Center of Education for Human
Rights</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE> and was a co-founder of the <ORGANIZATION>League of Human Rights</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>November 1980</DATE>, under dictator <PERSON>Jean-Claude Duvalier</PERSON>, he was
arrested, jailed and tortured for his outspoken criticism of the
government. <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> was then ordered to leave <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, but refused to
do so.
