<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-13990</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DDUCWADAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930421
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  21 APR 93 / The Queens's Awards for Environmental Achievement 1993:
Little worms that commit insecticide - Agricultural Genetics Company
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CLIVE COOKSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
TINY worms which kill insect pests have won a joint environmental
achievement award for <ORGANIZATION>Agricultural Genetics Company</ORGANIZATION>, an independent
biotechnology company based in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Horticulture Research
International</ORGANIZATION>, the state-backed agency responsible for fruit and vegetable
research, writes <PERSON>Clive Cookson</PERSON>.
AGC's MicroBio subsidiary has been working for six years with <ORGANIZATION>HRI</ORGANIZATION>'s
<LOCATION>Littlehampton</LOCATION> research station in <LOCATION>Sussex</LOCATION> to develop natural pesticides based
on nematode worms. The first two products were launched in 1989/90: Nemasys
against glasshouse sciarids and Nemasys H against vine weevils. Both insects
are important horticultural pests, particularly of nursery stock.
The Nemasys products are in the forefront of what is likely to be a huge
wave of biopesticides introduced over the next decade. Their environmental
advantage is that, unlike synthetic chemical pesticides, they do not leave
harmful residues in crops and water supplies.
Worldwide sales of biological pesticides were worth about Dollars 120m last
year - only 2 per cent of the figure for chemical pesticides. Industry
predictions put the biopesticide market in <DATE>2000</DATE> in the Dollars 500m to
Dollars 2bn region.
So far the emerging market has been dominated by products based on Bacillus
thuringiensis, a naturally occurring bacterium that makes an insect-killing
toxin. The AGC-HRI partnership has lead the way on nematode-based
insecticides, though a Californian company, <ORGANIZATION>Biosys</ORGANIZATION>, is about to launch a
competitive product.
The achievement of <ORGANIZATION>AGC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>HRI</ORGANIZATION> researchers has been to identify nematode
strains with specific activity against their target pests and then develop a
technique for mass-producing the microscopic worms by large-scale
fermentation.
Nemasys is sold in packs, each containing at least 50m juvenile worms in a
moist, inert carrier which is applied to the compost or soil around the
plants. There the nematodes seek out and kill insect larvae (to be precise,
the actual killing is done by symbiotic bacteria that live inside the
worms). The nematodes reproduce inside the dead insect as it decomposes and
release a new generation of juveniles which move off into the compost in
search of more prey.
The next target for the AGC-HRI nematodes will be the flies that feed off
cultivated mushrooms, the most valuable horticultural crop in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>. A new
Nemasys product is being introduced this year for biological control of
sciarid flies in mushrooms. If it is adopted instead of chemical
insecticides, it will remove the environmental problem of disposing of
650,000 tonnes a year of spent pesticide-laden mushroom compost.
AGC is also working with the Agriculture and <ORGANIZATION>Food Research Council's Long
Ashton Research Station</ORGANIZATION> to develop biopesticides to control slugs and
snails.
Production of the slug control nematode has reached the pilot plant stage
and it is expected to reach the market in two to three years, after
extensive field trials.
'We are confident that our natural product will be as effective as chemical
control methods at a competitive cost to users,' says <PERSON>Peter Innes</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>AGC
MicroBio</ORGANIZATION> director.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Agricultural Genetics.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8732 Commercial Nonphysical Research.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880328-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-28-88 1952EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CornPest     03-28 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Corn Pest,290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Miscroscopic Worm May Help Curb Crop Pest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of the costliest crop pests of farmers and
home gardeners may one day be curbed by a natural enemy, a
microscopic killer worm that searches the soil for the corn
rootworm, the <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The tiny worm, or nematode, is called Steinernema feltiae. After
infecting the rootworm, the nematode releases a bacterium that
kills the pest. Then, said <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> entomologist <PERSON>Jan J. Jackson</PERSON>, the
nematode uses the larva's body as a place to reproduce while it
feasts on bacteria and larva tissue.
   About 10 days later, hundreds of new nematodes emerge and start
searching for more rootworms.
   ``That gives you an advantage over chemical controls,'' he said
in a report by the department's <ORGANIZATION>Agricultural Research Service</ORGANIZATION>. ``A
chemical just sits there and waits for the rootworm to come to it.
The nematode doesn't wait.''
   But <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> found that the nematodes don't persist in the ground
long enough to eliminate a rootworm infestation. In one field trial
where he works at the department's <ORGANIZATION>Northern Grain Insects Research
Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Brookings</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> applied 100,000 nematodes to
the base of each of several corn plants, reducing rootworm damage
by 11 percent
   <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> said that is not an acceptable level of control, but he
expects further research could lead to protection as good as from
chemical insecticides. A separate test with a chemical reduced root
damage by <PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT>.
   Rootworm larvae destroy corn roots, and adults feed on the
leaves, tassels and ears. <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> said <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> corn producers spend
nearly <MONEY>$350 million</MONEY> a year to fight the rootworms. Nematodes
probably could be produced at about the same cost, without the risk
of chemical injury to farmers and the environment.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870828-0059 </DOCNO>
<HL> TECHNOLOGY:
Bug-Eating Nematodes Hold
Promise as Natural Pesticide
---
By James P. Miller
<DD> 08/28/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CHV ECL
CHEMICALS, PLASTICS (CHM)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD) </IN>
<TEXT>
   BIOCONTROL, THE USE of naturally occurring organisms to combat agricultural pests, has been touted for years as an alternative to chemical pesticides. 
But to date, only a few of the products have been commercially feasible, and their uses are limited. 
As in many other areas of technology, the advances needed to commercialize innovations in biocontrol have come in grinding, small steps, rather than blinding breakthroughs. 

   So it is with the lowly nematode. 
Scientists have long known that while most varieties of this microscopic underground worm harm many major crops, a handful of nematode strains vigorously attack other underground pests and are innocuous to humans and plants. 
The helpful nematodes, however, aren't naturally plentiful enough to make much inroad against farm pests. 
And until the worms can be produced and applied in large quantities, they will be too expensive to compete with chemical pesticides. 

   Biosis, a <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, biotechnology company, is using both low and high technology in trying to hurdle these barriers. 
It has developed a stinking broth of enzymes and ground-up pig kidneys that fosters the nematodes in great abundance and at less expense than previous efforts to mass produce the worms. 
Biosis is propagating the worms by the billions in stoppered three-foot plastic tubes about six inches in diameter. 

   But the nematodes are voracious bug killers only during their juvenile life cycle. 
Biosis found a low-cost way to ensure that all the nematodes are at that stage: It runs them through detergent in a <ORGANIZATION>Whirlpool</ORGANIZATION> washing machine, and the detergent kills all forms of the bug except the durable juveniles. 

   Biosis also faced another major hurdle: how to package the worms in large quantities that can easily be transported, stored and applied. 
Although the worms can be kept in liquid, the containers have to be aerated. 
Instead, <PERSON>Biosis</PERSON> took an opposite tack that is simpler and less expensive -- it dries the worms and stores them in a state of suspended animation. 
To use the nematodes, farmers will only have to drop a pack of dried worms into a sprayer, add water to revive the organisms, and apply to fields or orchards. 
The nematodes then sift through the soil, seeking out and dining on subterranean bugs, including such farm pests as the root-weevil, termite and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> potato beetle. 
The worms feed on about 200 types of insects. 

   COMMERCIAL SUCCESS isn't assured, of course. 
One remaining giant step, fraught with problems, is to increase production to huge 40,000-liter tanks in a <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY>, high-volume plant that Biosis plans to build soon. 
Moreover, nematodes so far can only be used for underground pests or in a moist above-ground environment. 
Field tests, however, have shown enough promise to attract <ORGANIZATION>Chevron Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s chemical unit and <ORGANIZATION>Chemlawn Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, the lawn-care unit of <ORGANIZATION>St. Paul, Minn.-based Ecolab Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, as research partners. 

   "It's just a question of time and money" before strains that work above-ground are developed, says Biosis president <PERSON>Albert J. Morris</PERSON>. 
Biosis already has committed <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> to research and development. 
Field tests show that on certain crops the special nematodes work as well as chemical pesticides, <PERSON>Mr. Morris</PERSON> says. 
Biosis plans to begin commercial sales next year, initially focusing on high-value crops such as almonds and artichokes. 
As production costs drop, the company expects to expand its market to include control of termites, cockroaches, and a host of field and garden pests. 
"We'll be cost-competitive (with chemical pesticides) within the next few years" for a half-dozen types of crops, <PERSON>Mr. Morris</PERSON> says. 

   Laser May Aid Gene Altering in Grains 

   Scientists have long been stymied in their efforts to create superior new strains of commercial grains by artificially introducing foreign genetic material. 
But a laser-based gene-insertion technique developed at the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> may help solve the problem. 

   For years, scientists have tried in vain to manipulate the genetic makeup of grain plants such as corn and wheat. 
Such a DNA transfer, now fairly common in animal cells and in other plants, is a prerequisite to genetically engineering better-yielding grains. 

   To insert different DNA into an animal cell, scientists soften its outer membrane with solvents, then expose it to a specially engineered virus that penetrates the cell and carries the new genes in with it. 
For broadleaf plants such as tomatoes or tobacco, a similar procedure is applied, using bacteria instead of a virus. 
But scientists have been unable to find a similar "vector" to smuggle new genetic material into the cells of grain plants. 

   THE <LOCATION>IRVINE</LOCATION> RESEARCHERS have come up with a method they think could help. 
After suspending the target cells in a liquid that contains the DNA to be introduced, the researchers manipulate individual cells into the cross hairs of a microscope-mounted laser. 
When the cell comes into target, it is zapped with the tiny beam for a fraction of a second. 
Before the neat, self-sealing hole closes, the new DNA flows in, says <PERSON>Michael Berns</PERSON>, director of the university's <ORGANIZATION>Beckman Laser Institute and Medical Clinic</ORGANIZATION>. 
He says the process has been successfully tested on animal cells. 
Whether it can work with the thick cell walls of grain plants remains to be seen, although preliminary work has been promising, he says. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880309-0293 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-09-88 1959EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SoilSlurper     03-09 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soil Slurper,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Absorbent Material Helps To Counter Citrus Root Weevils</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An absorbent material called super slurper is
helping tiny worms to kill root weevils that threaten citrus trees,
   <PERSON>William J. Schroeder</PERSON>, an entomolgist in the department's
<ORGANIZATION>Agricultural Research Service</ORGANIZATION>, said the super slurper keeps soil
moist so that the microscopic worms, or nematodes, can survive and
kill weevils which chew the tree roots.
   In tests, <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the weevils were killed, compared with
only <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> without the help of the worms. <PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON> said that
weevils can kill up to <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of the trees in a grove if not
controlled.
   The nematodes haven't been used before as a natural weevil
control because they die quickly if soil dries out, <PERSON>Schoeder</PERSON> said.
   Other agency scientists are looking into the use of super
slurper and nematodes to see if they can control pests of corn and
vegetables.
   Agency scientists in <LOCATION>Peoria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, invented the cornstarch-based
super slurper 14 years ago. It has been successfully used in dozens
of commercial products, including body powder, medical dressings
and many other items.
   <PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON>, who works at the department's horticultural research
laboratory in <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, said he thought of super slurper in
<DATE>1985</DATE> when he observed nematodes dying in dry soil.
   Companies could mass-produce nematodes and ``package billions of
them alive'' for sale to growers, who then could mix the worms with
super slurper for application on tree roots before planting, he
said.
   For citrus groves already inhabited by the beneficial nematodes,
<PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON> said he is looking into the possibility of injecting
super slurper into the soil with a nozzle.
   The tiny worms, which survive as long as the soil is kept moist,
penetrate the weevils and release lethal bacteria, which don't harm
plants or other organisms, <PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06116155 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06116155 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  INSECT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  MILLIONS of tiny helpful worms grown in a laboratory can be dried out, put to
sleep and later revived to fight destructive insects in back yards, gardens
and orchards, says a U.S. Department of Agriculture scientist.;    "They're
still living and breathing, but they're dormant," said entomologist James E.
Lindegren, researcher at Fresno. He said microscopic nematodes can be dried
out quickly and conveniently.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Garden  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DRIED OUT, FLATTENED WORMS CAN BE REVIVED
TO FIGHT INSECTS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  What's New  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Lindegren</PERSON> explained that water is drawn from the insects' bodies using a
technique called osmotic desiccation. The dried nematodes are stored in a
refrigerator. All that's needed to revive them is water.;    "They're harmless
to humans, pets, plants and birds," said <PERSON>Lindegren</PERSON>. "But they are lethal to
carpenter worms, cutworms, army worms, fruit flies and root maggots," which
cause <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY>' damage to crops.;    "Once inside a pest," he
added, "the nematodes excrete a bacterium that kills the pest, is food for the
nematodes, and produces antibiotics that keep other bacteria at bay.";   
Shipping large numbers of beneficial nematodes from one place to another is a
major obstacle to widespread use, <PERSON>Lindegren</PERSON> said.;    The nematodes are dried
by dunking them in a solution that contains less water than there is inside
the nematodes. Once the nematodes are properly dried, the solution is filtered
off. The resulting paste of now very flat worms can be refrigerated in
containers at about 45 degrees for up to 35 days.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910425  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  232  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday April 25, 1991
00116155,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900104-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-04-90 1211EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--What'sNew-Biogel Adv08   01-04 0361</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--What's New-Biogel, Adv 08,0369</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv08</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Monday, Jan. 8, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Biologist Develops `Last Meal' for Insect Pests</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Insect pests could be quickly and safely
killed by enticing them to eat a gelatinous meal containing
parasites, a biologist says.
   Such ``biogel'' pesticides can't harm plants, animals or the
environment, but kill beetles, termites, cockroaches, boll weevils,
corn rootworms, tobacco worms and other insects within days, said
<PERSON>Frank Chang</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Temple University</ORGANIZATION> biology professor who developed it
with graduate student <PERSON>Michael Gehret</PERSON>.
   ``Biogel'' is a soft material that contains an insect
attractant, a feeding stimulant, food and nematodes _ insects'
natural enemies, <PERSON>Chang</PERSON> said. Nematodes live naturally in the soil
and farmers, to control pests, spray them in large quantities in
fields, a process <PERSON>Chang</PERSON> said is generally inefficient.
   ``The nematodes can be rendered harmless by lack of moisture,
ultraviolet light, and heat. It is most likely that many nematodes
die before killing any insects. At the same time, insects are able
somehow to detect the meatodes, and the pests will often avoid
these supersaturated areas.''
   By contrast, ``biogel'' placed in small containers attracts
insects while preventing detection of the nematodes. ``Biogel
reduces the use of nematodes by <PERCENT>99 percent</PERCENT>,'' <PERSON>Chang</PERSON> said. ``In
other words, instead of spraying 10 million nematodes per 225
square feet of soil, you only need 100,000.
   ``As the nematodes produce offspring in the remains of each
insect, the progeny return to the soil to repeat the infectious
cycle.''
   He estimated that corn farmers who spend an estimated <MONEY>$10</MONEY> an
acre for chemicals to control rootworms could halve their costs.
   <PERSON>Ray McAllister</PERSON>, director of regulatory affairs for the
Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>National Agricultural Chemicals Association</ORGANIZATION>, said
<PERSON>Chang</PERSON>'s work ``makes dramatic promises. As with all new products,
it must prove itself in the marketplace against some stiff
competition. ...
   ``It has potential, but it is not the cure-all and it is
certainly not the replacement for pesticides.''
   Attempts at biological control predate chemical pest control
strategies and often have had good results, he said, but they tend
to be specific to one pest rather than the variety that attack
crops.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 8</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880310-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-10-88 0059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     03-10 0718</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dogs, X-Rays To Screen Travelers For Illegal Plants, Food</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   International travelers arriving at some major
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> airports this <DATE>summer</DATE> will be greeted by <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION>
inspectors operating X-ray machines to see if their baggage harbors
illegal food or plants.
   The X-rays, in addition to sharp-nosed canine sniffers, will be
used to check arrivals at 11 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> international airports for
illegal sausages, mangoes and other contraband.
   ``Imported meats can carry exotic diseases that could devastate
American livestock,'' <PERSON>James W. Glosser</PERSON>, head of the department's
``Fruits and vegetable coming into the country can carry pests that
could seriously damage American crops.''
   Agency inspectors have used X-ray equipment in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> for departures for several years, with interceptions of
prohibited agricultural items doubling, he said.
   The new systems for arrivals were recently installed at
international airports in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>; and <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   Additional equipment soon will be installed at international
airports in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>; and
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> agency also is installing large signs at the 11
airports telling travelers that X-rays are being used to check
their baggage.
   ``Although most people willingly declare their agricultural
products, we do come across some intentional violators,'' <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON>
said. ``That's only natural, considering that we encountered an
estimated 43 million air travelers in <DATE>1987</DATE>. Some ignore the
regulations and others are not even aware of them, despite all our
information efforts.''
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the agency uses several methods to find smuggled
agricultural items, including trained beagles to sniff out the
errant braunschweiger here, the occasional mango or two there.
   ``Finally, we rely on the deterrent effect of penalties,'' he
said. ``We fine violators <MONEY>$25</MONEY> to <MONEY>$50</MONEY>, payable on the spot. We
currently collect about <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> per month, and we have collected
nearly <MONEY>$1.8 million</MONEY> since <DATE>1984</DATE>. Fines are deposited in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Treasury.''
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the travel industry plays an important role in
helping educate the traveling public, including the distribution of
booklets about agricultural items that may be brought into the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   A brochure also can be obtained by writing: <ORGANIZATION>Travelers Tips</ORGANIZATION>,
USDA-APHIS, G-187 Federal Building, <LOCATION>Hyattsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION> 20782.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   International travelers arriving at some major
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> airports this <DATE>summer</DATE> will be greeted by <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION>
inspectors operating X-ray machines to see if their baggage harbors
illegal food or plants.
   The X-rays, in addition to sharp-nosed canine sniffers, will be
used to check arrivals at 11 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> international airports for
illegal sausages, mangoes and other contraband.
   ``Imported meats can carry exotic diseases that could devastate
American livestock,'' <PERSON>James W. Glosser</PERSON>, head of the department's
``Fruits and vegetable coming into the country can carry pests that
could seriously damage American crops.''
   Agency inspectors have used X-ray equipment in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> for departures for several years, with interceptions of
prohibited agricultural items doubling, he said.
   The new systems for arrivals were recently installed at
international airports in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>; and <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   Additional equipment soon will be installed at international
airports in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>; and
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> agency also is installing large signs at the 11
airports telling travelers that X-rays are being used to check
their baggage.
   ``Although most people willingly declare their agricultural
products, we do come across some intentional violators,'' <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON>
said. ``That's only natural, considering that we encountered an
estimated 43 million air travelers in <DATE>1987</DATE>. Some ignore the
regulations and others are not even aware of them, despite all our
information efforts.''
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the agency uses several methods to find smuggled
agricultural items, including trained beagles to sniff out the
errant braunschweiger here, the occasional mango or two there.
   ``Finally, we rely on the deterrent effect of penalties,'' he
said. ``We fine violators <MONEY>$25</MONEY> to <MONEY>$50</MONEY>, payable on the spot. We
currently collect about <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> per month, and we have collected
nearly <MONEY>$1.8 million</MONEY> since <DATE>1984</DATE>. Fines are deposited in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Treasury.''
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the travel industry plays an important role in
helping educate the traveling public, including the distribution of
booklets about agricultural items that may be brought into the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   A brochure also can be obtained by writing: <ORGANIZATION>Travelers Tips</ORGANIZATION>,
USDA-APHIS, G-187 Federal Building, <LOCATION>Hyattsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION> 20782.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880329-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-29-88 0109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     03-29 0959</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lamb Production Expands For Second Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lamb production is at a seasonal peak because
of this year's earlier religious holidays and will ease down
somewhat in the next few months, says an <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION>
report.
   With Easter and Passover coming up this <DATE>weekend</DATE>, lamb production
in the <DATE>first quarter</DATE> may reach about 80 million pounds and then
drop back to around <MONEY>78 million pounds</MONEY> in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE>,
   ``Lambs on feed (for the slaughter market) were up <PERCENT>18 percent</PERCENT> on
<DATE>Jan. 1, 1988</DATE>,'' the report said. ``These supplies should be
available during the first half of the year and could push
production up about <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT>.''
   Lamb and mutton take a far-back seat with American consumers but
are still an important part of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> food and agricultural
sector. This year, for example, per capita consumption may be about
1.4 pounds, compared with an average of around 83 pounds of
poultry, 72 pounds of beef, 63 pounds of pork and 1.5 pounds of
veal.
   The <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> inventory of all sheep and lambs in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
rose <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT> from a year earlier to 10.8 million head, which
agency economists said represented ``the second year of expansion
following several years of profitability'' in the sheep business.
   ``The West showed the biggest increases in the ewe flock, about
<PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT> above a year ago,'' they said in the <DATE>April</DATE> issue of
Agricultural Outlook magazine. ``In the <LOCATION>Great Plains</LOCATION>, sheep
inventories increased a little over <PERCENT>2 percent</PERCENT> from a year ago. Most
of this expansion occurred outside of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which has the largest
inventory of any state.''
   Analysts said they were surprised by a decline in the sheep and
lamb inventory east of the <LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION>, including a <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT>
drop in the <LOCATION>North Central</LOCATION> states. The Southeast was down <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT>
on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> after a <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> increase a year earlier.
   But the declines in the inventories were not sharp enough to
offset larger numbers elsewhere, which the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Great
Plains</LOCATION> made up most of the breeding flock.
   Lamb prices averaged about <MONEY>$78</MONEY> per 100 pounds, liveweight, last
year, up from around <MONEY>$69</MONEY> in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Market prices may decline
somewhat in <DATE>1988</DATE>, however, according to <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> projections.
   Although lambs are a major part of the sheep business, so is
wool. And the rise in inventories boosted shorn wool production in
<DATE>1987</DATE> to <MONEY>85.8 million pounds</MONEY>, up <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> from <DATE>1986</DATE>. That was the
first year-to-year increase since <DATE>1981</DATE>, when shorn wool output rose
to 109.8 million pounds from 105.4 million in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   Wool output peaked at <MONEY>388 million pounds</MONEY> in World War II before
beginning its decline, reflecting the long-term slide in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sheep
production.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lamb production is at a seasonal peak because
of this year's earlier religious holidays and will ease down
somewhat in the next few months, says an <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION>
report.
   With Easter and Passover coming up this <DATE>weekend</DATE>, lamb production
in the <DATE>first quarter</DATE> may reach about 80 million pounds and then
drop back to around <MONEY>78 million pounds</MONEY> in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE>,
   ``Lambs on feed (for the slaughter market) were up <PERCENT>18 percent</PERCENT> on
<DATE>Jan. 1, 1988</DATE>,'' the report said. ``These supplies should be
available during the first half of the year and could push
production up about <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT>.''
   Lamb and mutton take a far-back seat with American consumers but
are still an important part of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> food and agricultural
sector. This year, for example, per capita consumption may be about
1.4 pounds, compared with an average of around 83 pounds of
poultry, 72 pounds of beef, 63 pounds of pork and 1.5 pounds of
veal.
   The <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> inventory of all sheep and lambs in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
rose <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT> from a year earlier to 10.8 million head, which
agency economists said represented ``the second year of expansion
following several years of profitability'' in the sheep business.
   ``The West showed the biggest increases in the ewe flock, about
<PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT> above a year ago,'' they said in the <DATE>April</DATE> issue of
Agricultural Outlook magazine. ``In the <LOCATION>Great Plains</LOCATION>, sheep
inventories increased a little over <PERCENT>2 percent</PERCENT> from a year ago. Most
of this expansion occurred outside of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which has the largest
inventory of any state.''
   Analysts said they were surprised by a decline in the sheep and
lamb inventory east of the <LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION>, including a <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT>
drop in the <LOCATION>North Central</LOCATION> states. The Southeast was down <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT>
on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> after a <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> increase a year earlier.
   But the declines in the inventories were not sharp enough to
offset larger numbers elsewhere, which the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Great
Plains</LOCATION> made up most of the breeding flock.
   Lamb prices averaged about <MONEY>$78</MONEY> per 100 pounds, liveweight, last
year, up from around <MONEY>$69</MONEY> in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Market prices may decline
somewhat in <DATE>1988</DATE>, however, according to <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> projections.
   Although lambs are a major part of the sheep business, so is
wool. And the rise in inventories boosted shorn wool production in
<DATE>1987</DATE> to <MONEY>85.8 million pounds</MONEY>, up <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> from <DATE>1986</DATE>. That was the
first year-to-year increase since <DATE>1981</DATE>, when shorn wool output rose
to 109.8 million pounds from 105.4 million in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   Wool output peaked at <MONEY>388 million pounds</MONEY> in World War II before
beginning its decline, reflecting the long-term slide in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sheep
production.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lamb production is at a seasonal peak because
of this year's earlier religious holidays and will ease down
somewhat in the next few months, says an <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION>
report.
   With Easter and Passover coming up this <DATE>weekend</DATE>, lamb production
in the <DATE>first quarter</DATE> may reach about 80 million pounds and then
drop back to around <MONEY>78 million pounds</MONEY> in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE>,
   ``Lambs on feed (for the slaughter market) were up <PERCENT>18 percent</PERCENT> on
<DATE>Jan. 1, 1988</DATE>,'' the report said. ``These supplies should be
available during the first half of the year and could push
production up about <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT>.''
   Lamb and mutton take a far-back seat with American consumers but
are still an important part of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> food and agricultural
sector. This year, for example, per capita consumption may be about
1.4 pounds, compared with an average of around 83 pounds of
poultry, 72 pounds of beef, 63 pounds of pork and 1.5 pounds of
veal.
   The <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> inventory of all sheep and lambs in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
rose <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT> from a year earlier to 10.8 million head, which
agency economists said represented ``the second year of expansion
following several years of profitability'' in the sheep business.
   ``The West showed the biggest increases in the ewe flock, about
<PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT> above a year ago,'' they said in the <DATE>April</DATE> issue of
Agricultural Outlook magazine. ``In the <LOCATION>Great Plains</LOCATION>, sheep
inventories increased a little over <PERCENT>2 percent</PERCENT> from a year ago. Most
of this expansion occurred outside of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which has the largest
inventory of any state.''
   Analysts said they were surprised by a decline in the sheep and
lamb inventory east of the <LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION>, including a <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT>
drop in the <LOCATION>North Central</LOCATION> states. The Southeast was down <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT>
on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> after a <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> increase a year earlier.
   But the declines in the inventories were not sharp enough to
offset larger numbers elsewhere, which the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Great
Plains</LOCATION> made up most of the breeding flock.
   Lamb prices averaged about <MONEY>$78</MONEY> per 100 pounds, liveweight, last
year, up from around <MONEY>$69</MONEY> in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Market prices may decline
somewhat in <DATE>1988</DATE>, however, according to <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> projections.
   Although lambs are a major part of the sheep business, so is
wool. And the rise in inventories boosted shorn wool production in
<DATE>1987</DATE> to <MONEY>85.8 million pounds</MONEY>, up <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> from <DATE>1986</DATE>. That was the
first year-to-year increase since <DATE>1981</DATE>, when shorn wool output rose
to 109.8 million pounds from 105.4 million in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   Wool output peaked at <MONEY>388 million pounds</MONEY> in World War II before
beginning its decline, reflecting the long-term slide in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sheep
production.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA092489-0058 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 111532 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 24, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Real Estate; Part 8; Page 10; Column 2; Real Estate Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
270 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GARDEN NEWS: BENEFICIAL WORMS? 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ROBERT SMAUS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
"But why are you pouring worms on the lawn?" asked my wife from a great 
distance, as I was trying to describe what nematodes are. One of the more 
fascinating of the new organic controls employs tiny (make that microscopic) 
worm-like nematodes that find, attack and kill larvae living underground, or 
close to the ground, such as cutworms, root maggots, wireworms, the 
helmet-headed larva of <DATE>June</DATE> beetles (which chomp on lawn grass roots and which 
were my intended target) and a host of other creatures that attack vegetables, 
flowers and lawns. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Biosys</ORGANIZATION>, a biological pest control company in <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> makes this 
product, called <ORGANIZATION>BioSafe Lawn</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Garden Insect Control</ORGANIZATION>. What you get in the 
large box is a plastic bottle with what looks like window screening inside, 
plus a package of "activator." 
</P>
<P>
The screening is coated with a gel that contains the dormant nematodes (which 
can be stored refrigerated for up to six months). You add water and the 
activator to release the nematodes and then put this mixture is a watering can 
or hose-end sprayer and apply it to the ground. 
</P>
<P>
Each box contains enough of the little creatures (probably billions) to treat 
an area 22.5 feet by 10 feet, or 225 square feet. Because it is not a poison, 
it is not harmful to the environment, people or pets. It is not yet commonly 
available at nurseries but is becoming available. Scanmask is a similar 
nematode product available through the mail, from Ringer, <LOCATION>9959 Valley View 
Road</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Eden Prairie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, 55344-3585, (800) 654-1047. One pint sells for 
<MONEY>$14.98</MONEY>. It treats 200 to 370 square feet depending on pest type. ROBERT SMAUS 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881026-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-26-88 0044EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     10-26 0887</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,890</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government To Send `Dear Farmer Jones' Letters To Late Borrowers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 90,000 farmers who are behind in their
loan repayments to the <ORGANIZATION>Farmers Home Administration</ORGANIZATION> will be getting
notices shortly after the <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE> election telling them to start
making arrangements for settlement.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> agency said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the notices will
be an attempt to collect about <MONEY>$8.8 billion</MONEY> in past-due loans.
   Spokesman <PERSON>Marlyn Aycock</PERSON> said rules implementing new credit
legislation will take effect <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE> and that ``Dear Farmer Jones''
notices will start going out soon thereafter to the delinquent FmHA
borrowers.
   <PERSON>Aycock</PERSON> said the notices will say: ``This is to inform you that
you're seriously behind in your loan payments and to inform you of
your options. Farmers who are more than 180 days late in making
payments have several options.''
   The notices will explain that the <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> borrowers must notify the
agency within 45 days if they intend to apply to make arrangements
for settling their debts. Details regarding the options, including
debt restructuring and write-offs, also will be provided.
   <PERSON>Aycock</PERSON> said the timetable for sending out the notices as promptly
as possible took into consideration the months of rulemaking,
periods for public comment and time for training <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> people to
handle the additional job load.
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> ordered <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> to revise its lending practices in the
Agricultural Credit Act of <DATE>1987</DATE>. The agency is often called the farm
lender of last resort because it makes loans only to those who
cannot qualify at banks or other commercial sources.
   The debt write-down, or forgiveness provision, is regarded as one
of the most important parts of the <DATE>1987</DATE> law. It allows <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> to
reduce a farmer's delinquent debt to the recovery value of the
collateral, which is usually land or farm equipment, depending on
cash flow and other factors.
   Also, as the result of lawsuits, the <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> is under court order to
redo many of its loan regulations and to hold up on foreclosures and
forced liquidations until those actions are completed.
   Estimates of the extent of <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> loan delinquencies and numbers of
farmers potentially threatened by foreclosure under the new rules
have varied.
   Last <DATE>May 23</DATE>, when the new regulations were proposed, <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> losses
resulting from write-offs and other settlements were estimated at
about <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY> and that about 118,000 borrowers were delinquent.
About 64,800 of those could be pushed into liquidation or
foreclosure because they couldn't qualify for help under the new law.
   Another major step was an interim rule announced on <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE>,
including procedures for making debt restructuring and write-downs.
Those were to take effect on <DATE>Oct. 14</DATE> on an interim basis and called
for final adoption on <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE> after a 60-day period for public
comments.
   In the <DATE>September</DATE> announcement, the earlier analysis was used
again which referred to 118,000 delinquent borrowers, including
about 65,000 who would be rejected for debt write-downs. The
potential losses were said to be as high as <MONEY>$9.4 billion</MONEY>, although
about <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> could be salvaged by the agency.
   <PERSON>Aycock</PERSON> said the current estimate of 90,000 delinquent borrowers
was based on figures <DATE>last fall</DATE>, when FmHA delinquencies are
historically lower than those in <DATE>January</DATE>, when the 118,000 were
reported.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 90,000 farmers who are behind in their
loan repayments to the <ORGANIZATION>Farmers Home Administration</ORGANIZATION> will be getting
notices shortly after the <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE> election telling them to start
making arrangements for settlement.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> agency said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the notices will
be an attempt to collect about <MONEY>$8.8 billion</MONEY> in past-due loans.
   Spokesman <PERSON>Marlyn Aycock</PERSON> said rules implementing new credit
legislation will take effect <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE> and that ``Dear Farmer Jones''
notices will start going out soon thereafter to the delinquent FmHA
borrowers.
   <PERSON>Aycock</PERSON> said the notices will say: ``This is to inform you that
you're seriously behind in your loan payments and to inform you of
your options. Farmers who are more than 180 days late in making
payments have several options.''
   The notices will explain that the <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> borrowers must notify the
agency within 45 days if they intend to apply to make arrangements
for settling their debts. Details regarding the options, including
debt restructuring and write-offs, also will be provided.
   <PERSON>Aycock</PERSON> said the timetable for sending out the notices as promptly
as possible took into consideration the months of rulemaking,
periods for public comment and time for training <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> people to
handle the additional job load.
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> ordered <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> to revise its lending practices in the
Agricultural Credit Act of <DATE>1987</DATE>. The agency is often called the farm
lender of last resort because it makes loans only to those who
cannot qualify at banks or other commercial sources.
   The debt write-down, or forgiveness provision, is regarded as one
of the most important parts of the <DATE>1987</DATE> law. It allows <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> to
reduce a farmer's delinquent debt to the recovery value of the
collateral, which is usually land or farm equipment, depending on
cash flow and other factors.
   Also, as the result of lawsuits, the <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> is under court order to
redo many of its loan regulations and to hold up on foreclosures and
forced liquidations until those actions are completed.
   Estimates of the extent of <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> loan delinquencies and numbers of
farmers potentially threatened by foreclosure under the new rules
have varied.
   Last <DATE>May 23</DATE>, when the new regulations were proposed, <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> losses
resulting from write-offs and other settlements were estimated at
about <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY> and that about 118,000 borrowers were delinquent.
About 64,800 of those could be pushed into liquidation or
foreclosure because they couldn't qualify for help under the new law.
   Another major step was an interim rule announced on <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE>,
including procedures for making debt restructuring and write-downs.
Those were to take effect on <DATE>Oct. 14</DATE> on an interim basis and called
for final adoption on <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE> after a 60-day period for public
comments.
   In the <DATE>September</DATE> announcement, the earlier analysis was used
again which referred to 118,000 delinquent borrowers, including
about 65,000 who would be rejected for debt write-downs. The
potential losses were said to be as high as <MONEY>$9.4 billion</MONEY>, although
about <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> could be salvaged by the agency.
   <PERSON>Aycock</PERSON> said the current estimate of 90,000 delinquent borrowers
was based on figures <DATE>last fall</DATE>, when FmHA delinquencies are
historically lower than those in <DATE>January</DATE>, when the 118,000 were
reported.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   About 90,000 farmers who are behind in their
loan repayments to the <ORGANIZATION>Farmers Home Administration</ORGANIZATION> will be getting
notices shortly after the <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE> election telling them to start
making arrangements for settlement.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> agency said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the notices will
be an attempt to collect about <MONEY>$8.8 billion</MONEY> in past-due loans.
   Spokesman <PERSON>Marlyn Aycock</PERSON> said rules implementing new credit
legislation will take effect <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE> and that ``Dear Farmer Jones''
notices will start going out soon thereafter to the delinquent FmHA
borrowers.
   <PERSON>Aycock</PERSON> said the notices will say: ``This is to inform you that
you're seriously behind in your loan payments and to inform you of
your options. Farmers who are more than 180 days late in making
payments have several options.''
   The notices will explain that the <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> borrowers must notify the
agency within 45 days if they intend to apply to make arrangements
for settling their debts. Details regarding the options, including
debt restructuring and write-offs, also will be provided.
   <PERSON>Aycock</PERSON> said the timetable for sending out the notices as promptly
as possible took into consideration the months of rulemaking,
periods for public comment and time for training <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> people to
handle the additional job load.
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> ordered <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> to revise its lending practices in the
Agricultural Credit Act of <DATE>1987</DATE>. The agency is often called the farm
lender of last resort because it makes loans only to those who
cannot qualify at banks or other commercial sources.
   The debt write-down, or forgiveness provision, is regarded as one
of the most important parts of the <DATE>1987</DATE> law. It allows <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> to
reduce a farmer's delinquent debt to the recovery value of the
collateral, which is usually land or farm equipment, depending on
cash flow and other factors.
   Also, as the result of lawsuits, the <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> is under court order to
redo many of its loan regulations and to hold up on foreclosures and
forced liquidations until those actions are completed.
   Estimates of the extent of <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> loan delinquencies and numbers of
farmers potentially threatened by foreclosure under the new rules
have varied.
   Last <DATE>May 23</DATE>, when the new regulations were proposed, <ORGANIZATION>FmHA</ORGANIZATION> losses
resulting from write-offs and other settlements were estimated at
about <MONEY>$8.7 billion</MONEY> and that about 118,000 borrowers were delinquent.
About 64,800 of those could be pushed into liquidation or
foreclosure because they couldn't qualify for help under the new law.
   Another major step was an interim rule announced on <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE>,
including procedures for making debt restructuring and write-downs.
Those were to take effect on <DATE>Oct. 14</DATE> on an interim basis and called
for final adoption on <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE> after a 60-day period for public
comments.
   In the <DATE>September</DATE> announcement, the earlier analysis was used
again which referred to 118,000 delinquent borrowers, including
about 65,000 who would be rejected for debt write-downs. The
potential losses were said to be as high as <MONEY>$9.4 billion</MONEY>, although
about <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> could be salvaged by the agency.
   <PERSON>Aycock</PERSON> said the current estimate of 90,000 delinquent borrowers
was based on figures <DATE>last fall</DATE>, when FmHA delinquencies are
historically lower than those in <DATE>January</DATE>, when the 118,000 were
reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890417-0232 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-17-89 1205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--FireAnts Adv20   04-17 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Fire Ants, Adv 20,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv20</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, April 20, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Spread Of Fire Ants Not Likely To Be Checked, Researcher Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELLIOTT MINOR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TIFTON, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Farmers and homeowners should probably just
learn to live with fire ants, says a researcher who has been
unsuccessful at stopping the imported pests whose sting sends
21,000 Americans a year to doctors.
   ``With today's technology, there's nothing out there that'll
eradicate them,'' said <PERSON>Stan Diffie</PERSON>, a researcher at the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Georgia's Coastal Plain Experiment Station</ORGANIZATION>. ``We can control
them, but we can't eradicate them.''
   Diffie and entomologist <PERSON>Craig Sheppard</PERSON> are evaluating chemical
and biological controls for the South American insect believed to
have entered the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in Mobile, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, about 60 years ago.
Since then, fire ants have spread to 270 million acres in the
<LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>.
   Fire ants reproduce quickly and spread rapidly. In <LOCATION>south
Georgia</LOCATION>, it's not uncommon to find 40 mounds per acre, which isn't
a problem in pastures, but in fields where machinery is used ``you
would have a problem,'' <PERSON>Diffie</PERSON> said.
   ``They're a nuisance _ a people pest, whether it's unsightliness
in your yards or stinging your kids,'' said <PERSON>Diffie</PERSON>. The ants'
painful stings force at least 21,000 people to seek medical
treatment each year, according to a survey of physicians in 13
states for the <ORGANIZATION>American Academy of Allergy</ORGANIZATION> and Immunology.
   Nearly <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of those treated were in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, according to
the survey, and <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> were in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. Thirty-two people died
from stings last year, mostly people especially sensitive to the
toxin and bitten more than once.
   ``People and physicians should take these stings seriously,''
said <PERSON>Dr. Robert Rhoades</PERSON>, a pediatrician at the <ORGANIZATION>Medical College of
Georgia</ORGANIZATION> who monitors medical problems caused by fire ants. People
allergic to other kinds of insect stings should be especially
cautious. The stings cause a burning sensation, usually followed by
formation of pus around the site within 24 hours.
   But fire ants also help farmers by attacking pests such as
ticks, worms and other insects that damage sugar cane, cotton and
pecans. Up to 250,000 ants can live in each mound, which can extend
up to six feet in the soil.
   ``They'll eat anything that's dead. You have to have something
out there to clean up the carcasses,'' <PERSON>Diffie</PERSON> said.
   In the search for effective controls, <PERSON>Diffie</PERSON> has studied baits,
pesticides and natural enemies such as nematodes and mites. He
makes bait from corn grits soaked with soybean oil and poison. The
bait, scattered on pastures and fields, is carried into fire ant
mounds and kills ants that consume the mixture.
   Only a few ants in each colony are capable of reproduction.
Fertile males and females have wings and mate in flight. Then the
males die and the females establish new colonies. ``You have got to
kill the queen,'' <PERSON>Diffie</PERSON> said. ``If you don't, she'll just keep
laying eggs.''
   Common pesticides can kill fire ants, but don't remain active
long enough in the soil to be a long-term solution, he said. ``It
would be nice if we could put them where we want them _ get them
out of the yard and put them in the pecan orchards and sugar cane
fields. But I'd rather see them gone altogether. If we didn't have
them, we'd find ways to control the other pests.''
   Concern about the environmental hazards has led researchers to
look for biological controls, including microscopic worms known as
nematodes, and straw-itch mites, which are a natural enemy of fire
ants.
   ``Nematodes were mixed in water and poured over a fire ant
mound. About 2 million nematodes could be mixed in two gallons of
water,'' <PERSON>Diffie</PERSON> said. Those tests weren't considered very
successful because only about <PERCENT>37 percent</PERCENT> of the colonies treated
with nematodes were destroyed.
   Mites were ``fairly successful,'' he said, ``But the cost is
prohibitive as treatments are <MONEY>$5</MONEY> per mound and two treatments are
necessary.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for April 20</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920306-0009
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920306-0009.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology &amp; Medicine:
   Mycogen Scientists
   Find New Strains
   Of Soil Bacterium
   ---
   Discovery Could Expand Use
   Of Biological Insecticides
   In Homes and on Farms
   ----
   By Amal Kumar Naj
</HL>
<DATE>
03/06/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B12
</SO>
<CO>
   MYCO
</CO>
<MS>
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
BIOTECHNOLOGY (BTC)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
MEDICAL &amp; BIOTECHNOLOGY, GENETIC RESEARCH, PROSTHETICS (MTC)
</IN>
<NS>
COMMODITIES MARKET (CMD)
SCIENCE &amp; TECHNOLOGY (SCN)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Scientists at Mycogen Corp. said they have discovered new
strains of a bacterium that could greatly broaden the use of
biological insecticides against pests around the home and on
farms.
   The discovery was of new strains of the common soil
bacterium, Bacillus thuringiensis, or simply B.t. Poisons or
toxins produced by B.t. bacteria are the subject of much
research in pest control because, unlike the synthetic
chemicals they aim to replace, they are harmless to humans
and other animals. Until now, however, the natural B.t.
toxins that have been found have been effective against only
a narrow range of agricultural pests, mainly caterpillars.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Mycogen</ORGANIZATION> researchers, in a study published in the
latest issue of the journal Bio/Technology, said they have
isolated B.t. strains that produce toxins that kill such
diverse organisms as amoeba, mites, flatworms, fleas, adult
houseflies, nematodes, snails and slugs.
   Researchers at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, company predicted
their discovery could lead to the development of a pest
control system totally based on the naturally occurring
toxins and could change the fledgling biopesticide industry.
The finding also might lead to medicines that can be targeted
against specific unwanted organisms in humans and animals,
they said.
   "It was beyond most peoples' wildest dreams to get (a
pesticide system that attacked) such a significant portion of
the million species of insects, the more than 100,000 types
of nematodes, the tens of thousands of flatworms, and the
tens of thousands of protozoans," said <PERSON>Leo Kim</PERSON>, executive
vice president of research at <ORGANIZATION>Mycogen</ORGANIZATION>.
   Pesticides made from the B.t. toxins currently account for
<MONEY>$107 million</MONEY> in sales in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, and until now the industry
was counting on sales of <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> by <DATE>1999</DATE>. With the new
finding "I expect the sales to be substantially more than
that," the executive said.
   G. <PERSON>Steven Burrill</PERSON>, who follows biotechnology at <ORGANIZATION>Ernst &amp;
Young</ORGANIZATION>, however, cautioned against excessive enthusiasm. He
said the new B.t. strains will have "a dramatic impact" on
biopesticide sales but "it is a long way between discovery
and sales." He said any new product will have to go through
the federal regulatory maze, which, based on the past
experience, hasn't been all that quick in giving its approval
for commercial sale for such products.
   <ORGANIZATION>Mycogen</ORGANIZATION> manufactures a variety of crop protection products
based on the B.t. gene that produces the toxin. Last year it
received <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</ORGANIZATION> approval for
two genetically engineered pesticide products, one against
the <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> potato beetle and one against the diamond-back
moth that attacks cabbage and broccoli. The company holds 22
of the 39 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> patents issued for new B.t. strains over the
last four years, according <PERSON>Mr. Kim</PERSON>.
strains of B.t. underscores the diverse nature of the
bacterium. Researchers at <ORGANIZATION>Mycogen</ORGANIZATION> and elsewhere had
encountered isolated cases where certain B.t. strains were
found effective against mosquitoes and nematodes. "But they
were considered anomalies," he said. "We didn't think there
were strains of B.t. that could be effectively targeted
against just about everything between amoeba and nematodes."
   He said <ORGANIZATION>Mycogen</ORGANIZATION> researchers isolated the novel B.t.
strains from sandy beaches, household dusts, soil on top of
leaves and other soil samples collected from 50 countries.
The strains were processed in its laboratories in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> in
collaboration with Japanese scientists.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-10343</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CKAABACRFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921031
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  31 OCT 92 / Gardening: Beating pests the natural way - Arthur Hellyer
discovers a friendly way of dealing with unwelcome visitors
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ARTHUR HELLYER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
A GREAT deal of natural biological control of insect pests goes on in the
garden quite naturally and without any particular help from the gardener,
except the obvious one of avoiding the use of chemical or other treatments
that might be harmful to the beneficial organisms.
This is now well understood, and the great reduction in the usage of garden
chemicals is partly due to the desire to preserve 'friendly' creatures -
such as ladybird larvae and lacewing flies - that are valuable scavengers in
the garden.
What is not so well known is that some methods of biological control
actually involve deliberately introducing organisms to the garden or
greenhouse.
One of the oldest of these is the white fly parasite, Encarsia formosa, a
tiny wasp which lays its eggs in the white fly scales that are attached to
the leaves of infested plants, sometimes in great numbers. The encarsia eggs
hatch into larvae which devour the scales, so preventing more adult white
flies appearing from them.
This parasite is not a native of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and must be artificially introduced
to the greenhouse in which there are white fly infested plants.
This is usually done by hanging up leaves that bear white fly scales already
infested with encarsia and leaving them to develop into adult wasps, which
will then carry on the good work.
In <DATE>winter</DATE>, due to lack of warmth and also of white fly scales to keep larvae
fed, this parasite usually dies out and has to be reintroduced the following
year. Of course, a parasite of any kind is dependant on its prey for its own
survival and so can never eliminate a pest altogether but, hopefully, it can
restrict it to tolerable levels.
A second predator that has been used with considerable success to control
the greenhouse red spider mites is called Pytoseiulus persimilis. It is
itself a mite, though of a different kind - one might say one that lives on
meat rather than on vegetables.
Both the adult stage of this mite and the nymph devour adult nymphs and eggs
of the greenhouse red spider mite. Again, if they do it too successfully,
they will automatically destroy themselves since they have no other food
supply.
More recently, a third predator has been added to this list of organisms
that can be used to control pests. This is a minute nematode - what
gardeners often refer to as an eelworm. Some are quite large but this one,
which feeds on the grubs of the vine weevil, is too small to be seen with
the naked eye. Unlike the other two predators this one is native to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>
but is not present everywhere and most likely will have to be introduced.
The method of introduction is quite different. The nematodes are despatched
in a moist, inert carrier and on arrival are mixed with water and applied as
a drench to the soil that is infested with vine weevil larvae. These
nematodes are as exclusive as encarsia and pytoseiulus in their feeding
habits and present no hazard to any other organism, including human beings
and their pets.
This parasite is marketed as Nemasys by <ORGANIZATION>Defender</ORGANIZATION>, a company that can supply
other predators and parasites. The address is P0 Box 131, <LOCATION>Ashford</LOCATION>, Kent TN25
5TQ. Defender is a branch of <ORGANIZATION>Biological Pest Control</ORGANIZATION>, which supplies growers
throughout the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
Both the adults and the grubs of the vine weevil damage vines and many other
plants. The weevil eats the edges of leaves, giving them an unsightly,
notched appearance, but the damage done by the larvae is much more serious,
though largely unseen. They work underground, gnawing away at roots, and
they attack many other plants beside grape vines.
This pest has been on the increase since the withdrawal of effective soil
insecticides and so the introduction of the parasitic nematode is a real
step forward. It needs a temperature of above 14'C to be fully active. It is
effective outdoors until the end of <DATE>September</DATE> and under glass for a much
longer period, even throughout the <DATE>winter</DATE> if there is adequate heating.
With most methods of biological control it is advisable to supplement the
treatment with chemical control in certain circumstances.
Thus, with white fly one could use a pyrethrum spray or aerosol to reduce
the number of white flies before introducing encarsia formosa, but there
should be an interval of about seven days before the parasite is introduced.
The adult vine weevils are not directly attacked by the parasitic nematode
but can be reduced in numbers with a spray of gamma HCH or pirimiphos
methyl.
An excellent leaflet on these matters has been prepared by <ORGANIZATION>ICI Garden
Products</ORGANIZATION> and should be available at most garden shops or direct from <ORGANIZATION>ICI</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Dept</LOCATION>. FF, <ORGANIZATION>Fernhurst</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Haslemere</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Surrey</LOCATION>, GU27 3JE. Tel: 0428-645454.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XV
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890227-0273 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-27-89 0213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Gardening:Pests     02-27 0667</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Gardening: Pests,0688</SECOND>
<HEAD>BC-SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>GARDENING: Pests</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY702</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PRUDENCE HELLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Root rot and crown rot, army worms and cutworms, blister beetles
and Japanese beetles, lace bugs, mealy bugs and spittle bugs: this
is just a sampling of the ills that plants are heir to.
   Some can be prevented; some treated by natural or chemical means.
   Many experts say that a healthy plant is less likely to succumb
to illness or damage, while others say this may be more coincidence
than direct cause and effect. But it's generally agreed that the
conditions that make the plant healthy are also likely to help curb
the spread of pests and disease.
   <PERSON>Joel Flagler</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Rutgers University</ORGANIZATION> agricultural-resources
management agent for <LOCATION>Bergen County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, says that for a plant to
be healthy, it must be suited to the conditions under which it will
grow. Soil, moisture and light must all be appropriate. He and
others suggest having soil tested. It can be done through the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Agriculture's Cooperative Extension</ORGANIZATION> services
throughout the country. And there are kits for testing soil oneself.
   Some pests can be avoided or controlled through ``companion
planting'' _ planting one plant as a decoy or pest repellent near
another that one is cultivating. <PERSON>Thalassa Cruso</PERSON>, in ``Making
Vegtetables Grow,'' suggests nasturtiums to lure aphids from
cucumbers, marigolds to control root nematodes (microscopically
small worms), and plenty of garlic as an overall repellent. She also
relays suggestions that dill will keep away tomato worms, mint
provides insurance against ants, and radishes protect cucumbers,
squash and melons.
   Rotating crops is another way to keep pests or disease from
getting established. And gardeners can buy certified seed and plants
bred to be disease-resistant. Also, isolate for a while any new
plant you acquire through gift or purchase, so you can determine
whether it is healthy.
   And don't forget the bugs that eat other bugs, and the birds with
their appetite for insects.
   A home gardener who has read up on the subject or had a bit of
experience may be able to diagnose some plant problems: Highly
visible white flies, the fine webs that spider mites leave on the
underside of leaves, Japanese beetles. If a plant is cut off at the
soil line, you may find a cutworm (a type of grub) in the
surrounding soil. Remove and squash it.
   Remove-and-squash is not a particularly attractive idea, but it's
also useful against tomato worms, slugs, Japanese beetles and the
Japanese beetle grub, which resembles a cutworm.
   Other plant ailments are harder to diagnose, and the gardener may
wish to follow the suggestion of ``1,000 Garden Questions, Vol.
II,'' edited by <PERSON>Marjorie Dietz</PERSON>, and send a sample to the nearest
Agricultural Experiment Station for analysis.
   In the case of some pests, a strong blast of water from a hose
may drive them away. A spraying with insecticidal soap is another
possible solution.
   Then there are the pesticides.
   Some _ rotenone and pyrethrum, for instance _ have organic
sources. They come from plants. Others are chemical compounds.
   Garden experts urge one to use any pesticide exactly as directed.
   They warn, too, that what harms the pest may also hurt other
insect or animal life. For instance, <PERSON>Elvin MacDonald</PERSON>, director of
special projects at the <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Botanic Garden</ORGANIZATION>, says that
systemic pesticides, working through the soil, may hurt friendly
bacteria as well as harmful ones.
   For anyone inclined to blame geography for his gardening
troubles, <PERSON>Dara Emery</PERSON>, a plant breeder at the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Botanic Garden</PERSON>, offers consolation of a sort: Most plant problems
can occur anywhere. True, he says, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> roses have less black
spot and rust, but mildew and spotted mites still cause problems.
And people in other parts of the country don't have the problem of
salts that get into the soil in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> through needed irrigation.
   Finally, the gardener pestered by pests can always resort to an
old-fashioned solution mentioned by <ORGANIZATION>MacDonald</ORGANIZATION>: Grow enough for
everyone, including the insects.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870312-0079 </DOCNO>
<HL> WHAT'S NEW:
Measuring Body
By Sound Waves
---
By Jerry E. Bishop and Richard Gibson</HL>
<DD> 03/12/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> IGNE
CHEMICALS, PLASTICS (CHM)
PHARMACEUTICALS, HOSPITAL SUPPLIES, MANAGEMENT (PHA) </IN>
<TEXT>
   {This is one of an occasional series of reports on technology that has reached the early stages of application.} 

   A new way to measure the body volume of humans is being developed. 

   If scientists and doctors know a person's weight and body volume they can determine the body's relative composition of water, fat, lean muscle and chemicals. 
This is important when, for example, doctors need to know if weight gains of premature infants and other patients are due to changes in fat, water or muscle content. 
Also, nutrition researchers, athletic teams and diet spas want to know whether people on various diets are either losing or gaining fat, muscle or just water. 

   A rough method of estimating body volume is to measure the thickness of a fold of skin. 
A more-reliable method is to immerse the body in water and measure how much water it displaces. 
But immersion is sometimes impractical or inconvenient. 

   Now a drier method is being developed by <PERSON>W. Gregory Deskins</PERSON>, a mechanical engineer at <ORGANIZATION>Hoover, Keith &amp; Bruce Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, an acoustical-engineering firm in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Deskins</PERSON>, aided by a grant from the <ORGANIZATION>National Institutes of Health</ORGANIZATION>, has developed a chamber into which a loudspeaker broadcasts a low-frequency sound. 
The chamber resonates, much as an empty soda bottle resonates when one blows across the bottle top. 
When a person is in the chamber, it resonates at a higher frequency; the change in frequency tells how much volume the body is occupying. 

   The chamber, which is about a year away from the manufacturing stage, probably will be used first by nutrition scientists in research on infants' body composition, <PERSON>Mr. Deskins</PERSON> says. 
In addition to sports teams and diet spas, users of the chamber might eventually include meat packers who seek to determine the fat composition of animals on the hoof. 

   Nematode Nemesis
   The nematode may be brought to heel by an extract of crab shells. 

   Nematodes are tiny parasitic worms that dwell in the soil and cause an estimated <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> of damage a year to crops and gardens. 
Unlike other soil microbes, the nematode larvae contain a complex sugar called chiten, explains <PERSON>Robert Milch</PERSON>, the president of <ORGANIZATION>Igene Biotechnology Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Columbia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md</LOCATION>. 
If extraneous chiten is mixed in the soil, it will trigger other soil microbes to produce an enzyme that destroys it. 
Thus, mixing chiten with soil sets off a kind of chemical warfare that destroys nematode larvae. 

   Crab, oyster and clam shells are rich in chiten and <ORGANIZATION>Igene</ORGANIZATION> has found an inexpensive way to extract it, <PERSON>Dr. Milch</PERSON> says. 
After extracting residual meat from crab-shell wastes to produce a flavoring compound, <ORGANIZATION>Igene</ORGANIZATION> dissolves away the calcium with an acid. 
This leaves a chiten-and-protein mix that <ORGANIZATION>Igene</ORGANIZATION> has turned into a product it calls ClandoSan. 
The protein spurs the growth of fungi and other microbes thought to attack adult nematodes. 

   Igene plans to market ClandoSan later this year, after tests of its effectiveness are completed at <ORGANIZATION>Auburn University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Hebrew University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>. 
Since chiten is a natural pesticide, formal federal approval may not be needed for ClandoSan, <PERSON>Mr. Milch</PERSON> says. 
Igene notes that most synthetic chemicals formerly used against nematodes have been banned because of environmental problems. 

   New Healing Salve
   A healing salve prepared from blood is being developed. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>University of Minnesota</ORGANIZATION> surgeon, <PERSON>David R. Knighton</PERSON>, explains that after a burn, cut or other wound the body produces substances that trigger tissue regrowth and healing. 
Some of these healing factors have been tracked to the platelets, tiny plate-shaped particles that help blood to clot. 
<PERSON>Dr. Knighton</PERSON>, working with <ORGANIZATION>CuraTech Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a small company in which the <ORGANIZATION>University of Minnesota</ORGANIZATION> holds a stake, has developed a "platelet-derived wound-healing formula" using platelets from a wounded patient's own blood. 
The formula is made into a salve applied with gauze. 

   Initial tests on burns, chronic ulcers and other wounds that are slow to heal are promising, although definitive controlled tests on burn patients are still to be completed. 
"It's not a miracle potion," <PERSON>Dr. Knighton</PERSON> says. 
But, he notes, "this is the way nature heals wounds; all we're doing is mimicking it." 
One theoretical attribute of the salve is that blood contains factors that turn off tissue regrowth the moment a wound is sealed. 
Thus, the salve should help reduce scarring. 

   The researcher is now working on ways to extend the shelf life of the salve and to see if the healing factors can be extracted from donated blood rather than just the wounded patient's own blood. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890619-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-19-89 0114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-BugBattles Bjt   06-19 0875</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bug Battles, Bjt,860</SECOND>
<HEAD>Technology, Mercenaries and Sex All Weapons in Battle Against Bugs</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: stands for PM-Farm Scene</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's that time of the year when the <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture
Department</ORGANIZATION>'s bug writers turn out reports about the creepy, crawly,
hoppy things that chew on crops and livestock.
   Some of the reports turned out by specialists in the department's
<ORGANIZATION>Agricultural Research Service</ORGANIZATION> involve space-age technology, foreign
entomological recruiting and even sex, one of the favorite weapons
of pest managers.
   And when a fierce insect predator attacks a lace bug ... well,
the details aren't for small children.
   Take the common grasshopper, a notorious villain with an appetite
for almost anything in the plant world. Or nematodes, ticks, weevils
and sundry other kinds of critters that make farmers, ranchers and
home gardeners fret.
   ``Grasshoppers like to sit in the sun,'' says <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> research
entomologist <PERSON>Raymond I. Carruthers</PERSON>. ``If it's cold, a grasshopper
can't develop quickly. It might not develop to adulthood at all
during its growing season _ from <DATE>May into September</DATE>.''
   Don't feel sorry for the hopper, though. Millions of them chew on
pastures each year, destroying almost a fourth of the forage grasses
in 17 of 22 Western states. And migrating grasshoppers also ravage
potatoes, alfalfa and other crops.
   The internal body heat of the sun-loving hoppers serves the
insects another way, by protecting them against certain diseases.
For example, <PERSON>Carruthers</PERSON> said one fungus _ Entomphaga grylli _ would
show promise as a biological control if it could stand the heat.
   <PERSON>Carruthers</PERSON> said the fungus can stand about 100 degrees Fahrenheit
for six to eight hours before starting to die. Grasshoppers in
laboratory tests have been shown to ``actually cure themselves by
basking in the light,'' he said.
   But a type of E. grylli from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> can stand greater heat
exposure and may be introduced on Western rangeland as early as this
<DATE>summer</DATE>, <PERSON>Carruthers</PERSON> said.
   In parts of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and other rangeland areas of the West,
snakeweed and other unwanted brush is a costly and persistent
problem for livestock producers. Maybe two South American insects
will help.
   A weevil named Heilipodus ventralis and a moth called Carmenta
haematica attack the roots of snakeweed, a plant that infests 143
million acres in western states.
   Entomologist <PERSON>Jack DeLoach</PERSON>, who works for the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> agency in
<ORGANIZATION>Temple</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, said federal approval has been granted to introduce
the weevil into the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. But the moth is still being
tested, he said.
   Agency scientists are looking at biological controls for brush
because chemicals are too expensive in areas where it takes 20 to 50
acres to provide grazing for one cow for a year, he said.
   Besides snakeweed, which can cause pregnant cows to abort,
targeted brush includes saltcedar, which infests about a million
acres along Western streams, and baccharis, a willow-like shrub
found from <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   Other possible brush enemies are being looked at, including some
from <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, and at least a dozen insect species from
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>.
   But sometimes a natural ally shows up no farther away than a
potted azalea at the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION>'s main research center in <LOCATION>Beltsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md</LOCATION>.
In this case, it was a natural enemy of lace bugs, the most serious
enemies of azaleas.
   Entomologist <PERSON>John W. Neal</PERSON> and colleagues discovered an insect
predator _ Stethoconus japonicus _ in <DATE>1985</DATE> on a U.S.-grown potted
azalea. Studies since have shown that a single female predator,
which has a needle-like snout, can consume five or six lace bugs
each day. The slightly smaller male handles two or three.
   ``The lace bug doesn't have a chance,'' <PERSON>Neal</PERSON> said. ``The predator
sidles up, undetected, and gives its unsuspecting victim a lethal
injection through its long, needle-like mouth. Holding onto the lace
bug with front legs, the predator then withdraws all body fluids and
tissue, leaving an externally intact but completely drained shell.''
   Down in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>, researchers have released 5.6 million
hybrid cattle fever ticks on <LOCATION>St. Croix Island</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin
Islands</LOCATION> to see if they might be used to keep cattle tick fever from
spreading into the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> along the U.S.-Mexico border.
   The hybrid male ticks are sterile and do not produce sperm, said
entomologist <PERSON>Ron Davey</PERSON>. The females are fertile but pass on the
sterility to male offspring. ``The result is a population crash,''
he said.
   Cattle fever, or babesiosis, kills up to <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of adult
cattle that are infected by it. All <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> breeds are susceptible,
<PERSON>Davey</PERSON> said, but humans do not get cattle tick fever and are not
bitten by the ticks.
   One of the most encouraging bits of news for many soybean farmers
is a new bean variety that could be available next year. The
variety, <PERSON>Cordell</PERSON>, will be the first commercial soybean resistant to
``Race 5'' nematodes, microscopic worms that infest as much as <PERCENT>70
percent</PERCENT> of the soybean acreage in the mid-South and Southeast.
   The so-called cyst nematodes are designated as specific ``races''
because of the types of soybeans in which they reproduce. <PERSON>Lawrence
D. Young</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> plant pathologist at <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Cordell</PERSON>
could be suited for planting in <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>,
southern <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, northern <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and parts
of <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920221-0150
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920221-0150.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Growing Appetite
   For Attack Insects
   Spawns an Industry
   ---
   Greenhouse Gardeners Spur
   Sales of Natural Enemies
   For the War on Parasites
   ----
   By Bob Hagerty
</HL>
<DATE>
02/21/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<MS>
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
BIOTECHNOLOGY (BTC)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
MEDICAL &amp; BIOTECHNOLOGY, GENETIC RESEARCH, PROSTHETICS (MTC)
</IN>
<NS>
COMMODITIES MARKET (CMD)
</NS>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
NETHERLANDS (NL)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   In the antenna-to-antenna combat of the insect world, the
predatory anthocorid wields terrifying powers.
   Just ask Bunting Biological Control Ltd. of Great
Horkesley, England. The company is breeding millions of the
three-millimeter Rambos. It aims to sell them this spring or
summer to greenhouse-vegetable growers in need of troops to
deploy against the dreaded Western flower thrip, an avid
muncher of peppers and cucumbers.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Bunting's brochure describes how the anthocorids operate:
"Both the adults and the nymphs feed by inserting their
proboscis-like mouthparts into the prey and sucking out the
body juices." Not just one or two helpings, either: Bunting
promises that its bugs will drain as many as 15 thrips a day.
The predators also snack on aphids and spider mites. If
nothing else is around, they devour one another.
   But it's a bug-eat-bug business, and greenhouse farmers
can't be too fastidious about the thuggish habits of some of
their allies, known in the trade as "natural enemies" or
"beneficial insects."
   For a few dozen mite-size European and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> companies,
finding and breeding these natural enemies is becoming a
fast-growing business.
   Although greenhouse farmers began dabbling with natural
enemies in the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, such pest control remained little more
than a curiosity for decades. After World War II, new
chemical pesticides proved so devastating that few farmers
bothered with any other weaponry. Then, in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and
<DATE>1970s</DATE>, some farmers began to doubt that it was healthy for
people who work in glasshouses to spray lots of chemicals
around.
   One of the doubters was Jan <PERSON>Pieter Koppert</PERSON>, a Dutch
greenhouse grower whose respiratory problems prompted him to
experiment with natural enemies for his own use in the late
<DATE>1960s</DATE>. Soon he was selling killer insects to his neighbors.
Now <ORGANIZATION>Koppert B.V.</ORGANIZATION>, owned and managed by the late <PERSON>Mr. Koppert</PERSON>'s
sons, exports brandname bugs as far afield as <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. In the past five years, the company's annual
sales have more than tripled to around <MONEY>30 million guilders</MONEY>
(<MONEY>$16.6 million</MONEY>). That, says export manager Cor-Jan van der
Elzen, makes <PERSON>Koppert</PERSON> "the main leader in the world" of
natural enemies. (The company also supplies bumble bees for
pollination work-along with bee food called BeeHappy.)
   Koppert and rival companies -- such as <LOCATION>Bunting</LOCATION> and Chr.
<PERSON>Hansen</PERSON>'s Bio Systems AS of <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> -- remain bullish on bugs.
Tough environmental rules in many countries are pressuring
farmers to use fewer chemical pesticides and making those
pesticides more expensive to develop. At the same time, some
consumers are clamoring for unsprayed fruit and vegetables.
   So far, most people aren't willing to pay the premium for
unsprayed produce. But <PERSON>Joop van Lenteren</PERSON>, an expert on
natural enemies at the <ORGANIZATION>Agricultural University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wageningen</LOCATION>,
the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, thinks the trend is toward fussier
consumers. "In <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>," he says, "they're even more keen on
clean food than we are here."
   To satisfy that demand, bug breeders scour the wilderness
for new predators and parasites. The trick is to track down
the most efficient killers. Frogs, for instance, may eat lots
of insects, but they can't be relied upon to go after any
particular pest. Certain types of mites, on the other hand,
zero right in on thrip larvae.
   So <PERSON>Koppert</PERSON> breeds mites and packs them into plastic
bottles marked Thripex. It advises cucumber growers to
sprinkle the mites over their plants like salt.
   Among other hired guns on the market are aphid midges,
lacewings, ladybird beetles, mealybug destroyers, gypsy moths
and onion maggots. The predatory snail (Rumina decollata)
stands ready to pounce on garden snails.
   Since no one can patent a snail or an insect, competition
can be fierce; new suppliers keep crawling out of the
woodwork. Two years ago, Biolab of <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> opened a
state-of-the-art bug plant near <LOCATION>Cesena</LOCATION>, partly financed by
government funds. Koppert is so wary of rivals that it
refuses to let visitors tour its labs or breeding plant. <PERSON>Mr.
van Lenteren</PERSON> says Russian scientists plied him with vodka,
unsuccessfully, to learn bug-production secrets.
   Even a few giant companies are getting involved. <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>BASF AG</ORGANIZATION>, for example, sells capsules full of ichneumon flies
to combat the infamous corn borer. <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Chemical
Industries PLC</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> doesn't sell insects but offers
chemical pesticides designed for use alongside them.
   Rather than breeding bugs, big chemical and drug companies
generally are more interested in developing bacteria, fungi
and viruses to serve as "biopesticides." County <ORGANIZATION>Natwest
WoodMac</ORGANIZATION>, a British stockbroker, estimates that the world
market for biopesticides -- most of them based on a bacterium
called Bt, or Bacillus thuringiensis -- totals <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY> a
year, or <PERCENT>0.5%</PERCENT> of the global market for agrochemicals. Natural
enemies constitute an even smaller business.
   Even <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON>, one of the world's leading
advocates of natural enemies and other types of biological
pest control, doesn't think they can render chemicals
obsolete.
   For now, natural enemies are unleashed mainly in
greenhouses. Outdoors, a bigger variety of pests and
unpredictable weather make it hard for warrior bugs to
perform reliably; most farmers stick to chemical weapons for
their field crops. Still, natural enemies are sometimes used
outdoors for strawberries, apples, cotton and corn.
   <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> thinks more outdoor applications are
possible. He preaches using natural enemies along with
chemical pesticides in a way that minimizes the need for the
latter.
   Toward that end, he and his colleagues in <LOCATION>Wageningen</LOCATION> are
using government grants to study bug warfare.
   Remember <PERSON>Pavlov</PERSON>'s dog? Meet van <ORGANIZATION>Lenteren</ORGANIZATION>'s insect. When a
young woman wore a potent perfume in the lab one day, <PERSON>Mr. van
Lenteren</PERSON>'s students were seized with an inspiration: Why not
teach parasitic wasps to respond to an artificial odor, such
as perfume? The students wafted various perfumes over the
wasps as they laid their eggs. Later the wasps associated
certain scents with egg-laying.
   "Now we know we can train them to many things -- to
shapes, to colors," marvels <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON>. Why bother?
Because, he says, insect breeders will be able to sell bugs
trained to search out a particular enemy more effectively.
<PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> says he's in negotiations to license the
technology to several companies.
   The professor also is teaming up with botanists to try to
make life easier for natural enemies. A case in point is
Encarsia formosa, a parasitic wasp used to counter the white
fly. "Encarsia formosa," <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> admits, "is a
rather stupid animal in several respects." Peering through
their microscopes, entomologists noted that the wasp kept
stumbling into the minute hairs on cucumber leaves as it
looked for white-fly larvae. "It's like a drunken man on a
sidewalk with many lamp posts," <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> explains.
   The obvious solution was to seek out a strain of cucumbers
with hairless leaves. But researchers found that Encarsia
formosa, when set loose on a hairless leaf, zipped around so
fast it was liable to pass over a juicy larva without even
noticing. Somehow, the wayward wasp had to be slowed down.
The answer: promote a type of cucumber with <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> less leaf
hair.
   With such discoveries, <PERSON>Mr. van Lenteren</PERSON> says, "we are
scoring in international journals."
   Suppliers boast about their lab feats, too. One of the hot
areas of research revolves around uses for nematodes.
   Bunting already is promoting its Nemasys brand of
nematodes as a scourge for sciarid flies and vine weevils.
Stored in a special gel, the nematodes come in convenient
packages of 50 million. <PERSON>James Finch</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Bunting</ORGANIZATION>'s marketing
manager, concedes it's difficult for customers to be sure of
the count in each pack. "They have to trust us," he says.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900221-0246 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-21-90 0614EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--Gardening Adv22   02-21 0853</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Gardening, Adv 22,0876</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv22</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Thursday, Feb. 22, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Plants Might Like a Little Good Companionship, Too</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>James Walters</PERSON> worked for the AP as a reporter
and editor from <DATE>1947</DATE> until he retired in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By JAMES E. WALTERS</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>James Walters</PERSON> worked for the AP as a reporter
and editor from <DATE>1947</DATE> until he retired in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thursday, Feb. 22</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06214204 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06214204 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  GARDEN; PLANT; GUIDELINE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  COMPANION planting is a friendly, old-time garden practice. It means growing
two or more kinds of plants close together with the hope that mutual benefits
will result.;    Companion planting is not the same as successive planting --
garden arrangements where an early-maturing crop is followed by a
late-maturing crop as soon as it has been harvested.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Garden  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COMPANION PLANTING GETS IT TOGETHER  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Technique  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     In short, companion planting uses several plantings in the garden at the
same time -- for example, radishes, <DATE>spring</DATE> onions or leaf lettuce can be
planted so rows of sweet corn, peppers or tomatoes can be sown between them.
The early crops mature before the taller crops shade them too much.;    One
plant may form support for another, for example, climbing green beans and tall
varieties of sweet corn planted close together. Tall plants also may become
windbreaks for tender, smaller plants growing nearby.;    Roots of some green
plants develop a symbiotic relationship with beneficial fungi in the soil
called micorrhiza. They may produce growth substances, or help the uptake of
nutrients such as phosphorous. Crops growing close together may share the same
micorrhiza, which improves growth and, it is thought, seems to indicate that
the plants "like" each other.;    There is some controversy about beliefs that
plants are able to protect each other against attack by some insects.;    A
few years ago, companion trial tests were made at <ORGANIZATION>Pennsylvania State
University</ORGANIZATION> to determine if radish could be matched with other plants for
striped cucumber beetle control; marigold with beans for Mexican bean beetle
control; thyme with cabbage for cabbage worm control; onion with carrot for
leaf hopper control; and catnip with eggplant for flea beetle control.;    The
results showed that none of these plants protected its companion from attack
by any pest.;    Another concept -- that marigolds protect nearby plants from
nematodes -- found no verification in tests at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Georgia</ORGANIZATION>. One
study showed that some marigolds attracted nematodes that are then killed
within the roots. A researcher reported this would only be useful to suppress
the buildup of nematodes but would not protect existing plants.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  EARL ARONSON, AP Newsfeatures  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910801  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3G  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  345  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday August 1, 1991
00214204,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880422-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-22-88 1357EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MoleCricket     04-22 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mole Cricket,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazilian Fly Released to Control Spreading Crop Pest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GAINESVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A red-eyed Brazilian fly was turned
loose <DATE>Friday</DATE> in an experimental effort to control the mole cricket,
which chews up <MONEY>$47 million</MONEY> worth of crops and lawns each year.
   The first release of 250 fly pupae in an <LOCATION>Alachua County</LOCATION> pasture
will probably be followed by others throughout the <DATE>summer</DATE>, said
<PERSON>Howard Frank</PERSON>, director of the project at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Florida's Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We're optimistic, but the whole thing is a big experiment,''
said <PERSON>Frank</PERSON>.
   The mole cricket, which probably arrived by ship from <LOCATION>South
America</LOCATION>, damages vegetation by tunneling through it.
   The pest is now spreading into <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South
Carolina</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Frank</PERSON> said
   The Brazilian fly, about the size of a house fly, comes to the
mating call of male mole crickets, and lays her living larvae on or
near the singer. The larvae then burrow into the male and his mates.
   Ten days later the mole cricket is dead, said <PERSON>Tom Walker</PERSON>, the
<ORGANIZATION>IFAS</ORGANIZATION> entomologist who will monitor the progress of the Brazilian
fly.
   ``We should know in a year if the larvae are surviving,'' said
<PERSON>Frank</PERSON>. ``And in two years we'll have a reasonable idea of whether
it's a success.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> granted permission to release
the flies after laboratory tests demonstrated they only attack mole
crickets.
   The fly is the third biocontrol agent that <ORGANIZATION>IFAS</ORGANIZATION> has unleashed in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> against mole crickets.
   A wasp that subdues mole crickets but does not sting people was
the first. Turned loose in <DATE>1981</DATE> near <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>, the colony is
holding its own there. They mainly attack a tropical mole cricket
that is only a pest in <LOCATION>South Florida</LOCATION>, however.
   Nematodes, microscopic worms, were released in <DATE>1985</DATE> and <DATE>1986</DATE> in
several <LOCATION>Alachua</LOCATION> pastures. Offspring are still there and seem to
have caused a decline in mole cricket populations at the release
sites, but <PERSON>Frank</PERSON> says the nematodes are harder to handle than the
Brazilian fly.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-21060 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpest007___94057" </HT>

