<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910128-0152
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910128-0152.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Theater: Sing a Song of Presidenticide
   ----
   By Melanie Kirkpatrick
</HL>
<DATE>
01/28/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A9
</SO>
<LP>
   New York -- For his new musical comedy, Stephen Sondheim
has chosen a preposterous and perverse subject -- the
assassins of presidents of the United States. More
specifically, "Assassins," which opened last night at
Playwrights Horizons, presents the stories of nine assassins,
four successes and five wannabes.
   This isn't the first time, of course, that Mr. Sondheim
has delighted in gruesome material. His "Sweeney Todd"
revolves around a murderous barber who has his victims baked
into meat pies. "Into the Woods" is a wicked treatment of
fairy tales. Even "West Side Story," whose lyrics Mr.
Sondheim wrote when he was a veritable Broadway baby, is the
brutal story of rival street gangs.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   All of <PERSON>Mr. Sondheim</PERSON>'s best work has a malicious humor that
is to musicals what <PERSON>Gary Larson</PERSON>'s "The Far Side" is to
cartoons. In "Assassins," the macabre <PERSON>Larson</PERSON> lurking inside
<PERSON>Mr. Sondheim</PERSON> shows his fangs more than ever, and right from
the start. In the opening scene, a carnival barker urges
folks to step right up to a game of "Shoot the President."
   If turning <PERSON>John Wilkes Booth</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Hinckley</PERSON> into merry
song-and-dance men sounds distasteful, well it is. The black
humor reaches squirm-in-your-seat proportions, however, only
when <PERSON>Lee Harvey Oswald</PERSON> makes his entrance late in the show.
Before that, "Assassins" is carried along by three enormous
assets: beguiling music, often hilarious comic turns, and
superb workmanship on the part of every member of the cast.
   <PERSON>Mr. Sondheim</PERSON>'s score counterpoints its characters' ghastly
doings with lovely music. Several songs draw heavily on
traditional American folk tunes. Three ballads, performed by
<PERSON>Patrick Cassidy</PERSON>, a glorious Irish tenor, sound as if they had
been written in <LOCATION>19th-century Appalachia</LOCATION>. And "Unworthy of
Your Love" is a heart-rendingly sweet love song in the manner
of a <PERSON>Carol King</PERSON> or <PERSON>Bob Dylan</PERSON> hit of the '60s.
   These melodious songs contrast eerily with the evil
weirdness of their singers' lives. "Unworthy of Your Love,"
for instance, is a duet sung by <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>'s assailant
<PERSON>John Hinckley</PERSON> (<PERSON>Greg Germann</PERSON>) and <PERSON>Squeaky Fromme</PERSON> (Annie
Golden), the <PERSON>Charles Manson</PERSON> follower who tried to kill <ORGANIZATION>Gerald
Ford</ORGANIZATION>. The lovers for whom the singers are pining are <PERSON>Manson</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Jodie Foster</PERSON>, the movie star <PERSON>Hinckley</PERSON> pursued with love
letters around the time he shot at <PERSON>Mr. Reagan</PERSON>.
<PERSON>Charles Guiteau</PERSON> (<PERSON>Jonathan Hadary</PERSON>) prances up and down the
The scene ends with <PERSON>Guiteau</PERSON> hanging from a noose. Similarly,
Undoubtedly, <PERSON>Mr. Sondheim</PERSON> is striving for the musical
equivalent of gallows humor, but his splendid melodies and
crafty lyrics are vastly out of tune with his subject.
   By far the weakest part of the score is the play's
signature song, "Everybody's Got the Right." This is
especially unfortunate since it is the song that opens and
closes the show. In both cases, the assassins, arranged in a
kind of zombies' parody of a Broadway chorus line, earnestly
belt out the lyrics, "Everybody's got the right to be
different. Everybody's got the right to their dreams." This
is meant, I think, as a satiric comment on the American dream
gone berserk, but it ends up sounding trite and mildly
didactic.
   <PERSON>Mr. Sondheim</PERSON> does better with the failed assassins than
with those who, to adopt the script's tone, bagged their
Prez. The bunglers are all fruitcakes, and, happily, <PERSON>Mr.
Sondeim</PERSON> and his scriptwriter, <PERSON>John Weidman</PERSON>, dispense with the
psychoanalysis that weighs down their treatment of <LOCATION>Booth</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Guiteau</PERSON> and <PERSON>Czolgosz</PERSON> and concentrate instead on the bunglers'
nuttiness.
   The actors ham it up deliciously. Lee Wilkof makes a manic
<PERSON>Samuel Byck</PERSON>, the man in a <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> suit who hijacked a plane
that he intended to crash into <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Debra Monk</ORGANIZATION> is brilliant as <PERSON>Sara Jane Moore</PERSON>, the terminally
bored housewife who brought along her small son when she
tried to shoot <PERSON>Gerry Ford</PERSON>. And <PERSON>Ms. Golden</PERSON> makes a marvelous
<PERSON>Squeaky Fromme</PERSON>, the spacy flower child who can't remember why
her father threw her out of the house -- was it because they
were fighting over her eye makeup or the war in <LOCATION>Cambodia</LOCATION>?
   For the first 75 minutes, then, the captivating music and
zany comedy create an appealing entertainment. <PERSON>Jerry Zaks</PERSON>'s
snappy direction and <PERSON>Loren Sherman</PERSON>'s inventive turntable sets
add to the pleasure. With the appearance of <PERSON>Lee Harvey
Oswald</PERSON>, however, in the penultimate scene, a shadow falls
over the stage, and the show never recovers. It's as if
<ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION> had tacked on the fearful ending of "King Lear"
to "As You Like It."
   The setting is, of course, the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Book Depository. The
time is just after noon, on <DATE>Nov. 22, 1963</DATE>.
   By this point, I'd grown a little fond of the gang of
assassins and their assorted quirks. But now the gang, led by
killing <PERSON>Jack Kennedy</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Sondheim</PERSON> gave himself an insoluble problem: how to
force one of the great evildoers of our time into a musical
comedy. I suppose we should be grateful he did not attempt a
"Ballad of <PERSON>Lee Harvey Oswald</PERSON>" to match the ballads he gives
the other successful assassins. He might have had <PERSON>Oswald</PERSON>
dance a jig or burst into song as <PERSON>Jack Ruby</PERSON> shoots him down.
That would have been even worse than the straight ending <PERSON>Mr.
Sondheim</PERSON> actually settled for. Sincerity and sanctimony end
up spoiling -- or should I say, assassinating? -- what
started off as an impertinent and amusing show.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06031197 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06031197 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; Photo: Sondheim  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  NEW-YORK; MUSIC; THEATER; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE American musical theater takes a bold leap into dark ground with Stephen
Sondheim's new musical, "Assassins," which opened Sunday at the 139-seat
Playwrights Horizons on West 42nd Street's Theater Row.;    At first sitting,
at least, the tabloid-sized show about presidential assassins and the society
that produced them looks like a small masterpiece of political theater. It is
pungent with satirical irony, grotesquely funny at times and consistently
disturbing.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SONDHEIM'S BULL'S-EYE
'ASSASSINS' IS NEW YORK'S HOTTEST TICKET  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Theater  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     For musical inspiration, <PERSON>Sondheim</PERSON> has relied largely on American forms --
folk ballads and traditional marches. A balladeer in overalls (<PERSON>Patrick
Cassidy</PERSON>) is the narrator. The music is simpler than <PERSON>Sondheim</PERSON>'s last two scores
("Into the <PERSON>Woods</PERSON>," "<DATE>Sunday</DATE> in the Park With George") and likely to disappoint
the composer's more fervent fans.;    A hot ticket;    A new <PERSON>Sondheim</PERSON> work is
always an event, but the shock waves caused by the composer-lyricist's choice
of subject has helped make this one the hottest ticket of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> theater
season. Promised a gallery of rogues in song, from <PERSON>John Wilkes Booth</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lee
Harvey Oswald</PERSON>, theatergoers have stood in line for hours for ticket
cancellations and returns.;    The production's two-month run for mostly
subscription audiences is scheduled to end on <DATE>Feb. 16</DATE>. Stories have circulated
about the critic for a major newspaper who turned blue in the outside line and
still didn't get a ticket. One Broadway producer of note complained that the
theater had turned down his request for tickets.;    <PERSON>Sondheim</PERSON> has shown
himself willing to upset audiences with the butchery of "<PERSON>Sweeney Todd</PERSON>," his
musical about a murderous barber. And he has tackled political theater in
"Pacific Overtures," a satire on <PERSON>Commodore Matthew Perry</PERSON>'s opening of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to
Western trade. For "Assassins" he has been rejoined by <PERSON>John Weidman</PERSON>, who wrote
the book for "Pacific Overtures.";    Based on an idea by <PERSON>Charles Gilbert Jr.</PERSON>,
of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>'s University of the Arts, "Assassins" brings together in a
hallucinatory afterlife nine people who made or planned attempts on the lives
of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> presidents.;    The musical makes the point that these nine are all
outsiders who have been denied their expected share of the American dream.
There is one chilling moment when Booth calmly explains to <PERSON>Lee Harvey Oswald</PERSON>
(<PERSON>Jace Alexander</PERSON>) that assassination is not just murder but a ticket to
immortality.;    Taken as a group, these people have the air of inmates of a
mental institution where the reigning delusion is not being a Napoleon but
rather a <PERSON>Charles Guiteau</PERSON> (<PERSON>Jonathan Hadary</PERSON>) shooting President <PERSON>Garfield</PERSON>, or a
<PERSON>Giuseppe Zangara</PERSON> (<PERSON>Eddie Korbich</PERSON>) missing <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> and hitting
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Anton Cermak</PERSON>. If they aren't all crazy, there is certainly an
appalling incoherence in the ultimate act they all commit -- an insane
disparity between motive and behavior.;    <PERSON>Terrence Mann</PERSON>'s immigrant workman
<PERSON>Leon Czolgosz</PERSON> is an expressionless force of righteous anger, ignited by a love
for <PERSON>Emma Goldman</PERSON> and gunning down <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON>. For comic relief, there
are <PERSON>Gerald Ford</PERSON> and the two addled women who bungled their mission. <PERSON>Charlie
Manson</PERSON>'s acolyte, <PERSON>Lynette</PERSON> "Squeaky" <PERSON>Fromme</PERSON> (Annie Golden), is a caricature of
the flower child of the '60s, playing mentor to a moony, guitar-playing <PERSON>John
Hinckley</PERSON> (<PERSON>Greg Germann</PERSON>), who shoots again and again at a smiling portrait of
<PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> without even creasing it. The formidable <ORGANIZATION>Debra Monk</ORGANIZATION> gives a
memorably nutty performance as the suburbanite <PERSON>Sara Jane Moore.</PERSON>;    The most
frighteningly funny character of all is the little-known <PERSON>Samuel Byck</PERSON>, a loser
who, it seems, planned to kill <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON> by crashing a plane into the
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>. Lee Wilkof gives this character's disordered mind a wild airing
as he talks to <PERSON>Leonard Bernstein</PERSON> on a tape recorder.;    A bit preachy;   
"Assassins" is not a perfect piece of work. There is some stupid show-business
nonsense about Booth killing because of bad reviews. (He is seen reading
Variety in a saloon.) There also is a tendency to hammer away at the theme of
social inequity, as if that explained everything. But on the whole, this is
provocative stuff, handled with imagination.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  WILLIAM B. COLLINS, Knight-Ridder News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910131  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  673  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday January 31, 1991
00031197,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870528-0067 </DOCNO>
<HL> Who's News:
Gerber Products Says Chief McKinley
Is Retiring Early for 'Personal Reasons'
---
By Jacob M. Schlesinger
<DD> 05/28/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> WNEWS GEB </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Gerber Products Co.</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>William L. McKinley</PERSON>, its 63-year-old chairman and chief executive officer, was taking early retirement for "personal reasons." 

However, the <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>, Mich.-based company said that <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON>, who became chief executive less than <DATE>two years ago</DATE>, will stay on as chairman until <DATE>July</DATE> "to provide for an orderly transition." 

   Messrs. 
<PERSON>McKinley</PERSON> and <PERSON>Goulet</PERSON> both refused to discuss the change further. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Goulet</PERSON>, in a prepared statement, said he didn't anticipate making any major changes in the company. 
He said that <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> "leaves the company with a strong financial structure . . . 
Our competitive position also is excellent in all market areas, particularly Gerber baby foods." 

   But Wall Street analysts, who have been sharply critical of <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON>'s performance during the past year, said they thought he was forced out under pressure from the directors, and perhaps the fear of a takeover bid. 
No bidder has emerged for the company. 

   "I think the board is being responsive to shareholders who were generally dissatisfied with the company's reluctance to maximize shareholder value," said <PERSON>John M. McMillin</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Prudential-Bache Securities</ORGANIZATION>. 
"It's a well-known feeling on Wall Street that management wasn't trying to do that." 

   Specifically, analysts criticized <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON>'s handling of the non-food businesses. 
"His non-food operations never performed up to snuff," said <PERSON>William Maguire</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch Research</ORGANIZATION>. 
He singled out the peformance of <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON>'s truck, furniture, and apparel operations. 

   The company's net income for the fiscal year ended <DATE>March 31</DATE> dropped <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> from the previous year for various reasons including stepped-up advertising. 

   "He was chairman over a pretty rough period of time," said <PERSON>Daniel F. Gerber</PERSON>, a board member and son of the company's founder. 

   Asked if the board asked <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> to resign, <PERSON>Mr. Gerber</PERSON> said, "I wouldn't have any comment about that. 
<PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> resigned simply for personal reasons." 

   <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON>, who has worked with <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> for 37 years, became chairman and chief executive in <DATE>November 1985</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Goulet</PERSON>, who has worked with <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> for 32 years, became president and chief operating officer in <DATE>February 1983</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870724-0124 </DOCNO>
<HL> Who's News:
Gerber's McKinley
Resigns as a Director,
Severing His Last Tie</HL>
<DD> 07/24/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> WNEWS GEB </IN>
<DATELINE> FREMONT, Mich.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Gerber Products Co.</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>William L. McKinley</PERSON> resigned from its board. 
The company previously announced that <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> stepped down as chief executive officer in <DATE>May</DATE>, and as chairman earlier this week. 

   Gerber has said <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON>, 63 years old, severed his ties with the company for "personal reasons." 

   The baby-food maker also said it expects to appoint a new chief executive officer within two months. 
Gerber appointed <PERSON>Leo D. Goulet</PERSON> to that post in <DATE>May</DATE>, but he died of a heart attack earlier this month. 

   <PERSON>Robert D. Carlson</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Crowley, Milner &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a Detroit-based department store chain, will fill out the final year of <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON>'s term. 

   Gerber also announced that <PERSON>George A. Purvis</PERSON>, 54, was given the newly created title of corporate vice president-research and development. 
He was previously a vice president in the same department. 
J. <PERSON>Ronald Lovasz</PERSON>, 54, was promoted to the newly created position of vice president-quality control, research division. 
He previously was director of corporate quality control. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890813-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-13-89 1222EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-MtMcKinley-Congress     08-13 0466</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mt McKinley-Congress,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congress Weighs Whether Mt. McKinley Should Be Mt. Denali Instead</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Add one more issue to the list of conundrums
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will have to unravel when it returns from its <DATE>summer</DATE>
recess next month: whether the tallest mountain in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>
should be renamed.
   It's a perennial duel between an <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> congressman protecting the
honor of <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON>, the 25th <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> president after whom the
peak is named, and an <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> senator defending his state's right to
name its own land features.
   The motives of <PERSON>Sen. Ted Stevens</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Alaska</LOCATION>, are easy to discern.
   ``His long-range goal is to see if the mountain can be renamed
with Alaskans' wishes,'' says <PERSON>Connie Godwin</PERSON>, his spokeswoman.
   It takes only a quick look at the background of Rep. <PERSON>Ralph
Regula</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Ohio</LOCATION>, to explain why he cares about the name of the
20,320-foot mountain in <LOCATION>central Alaska</LOCATION>, a continent away from the
people he represents.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> is from my district,'' <PERSON>Regula</PERSON> says.
   McKinley, assassinated in <DATE>1901</DATE>, was not only from <PERSON>Regula</PERSON>'s
district, but once held <PERSON>Regula</PERSON>'s seat in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and is buried in
the district. Regula is even a graduate of the <ORGANIZATION>William McKinley
School of Law</ORGANIZATION>.
   McKinley _ the mountain _ is in <LOCATION>Denali National Park</LOCATION>, which was
renamed in <DATE>1980</DATE> from <LOCATION>McKinley National Park</LOCATION>. Denali is an Indian
word for ``The Great One,'' and many Alaskans would like to see the
mountain bear the same name.
   ``It's owned by 230 million Americans,'' <PERSON>Regula</PERSON> said last week.
``<LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> gets <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in taxes, and taxpayers from the
entire country have a right to decide what happens there.''
   A provision forbidding the government to rename the mountain was
buried in the fine print of the annual <ORGANIZATION>Interior Department</ORGANIZATION> spending
bill that the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> passed <DATE>July 12</DATE>. When the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> approved its
version of the legislation two weeks later, the Mt. McKinley
language was removed.
   It's a legislative dance that has been going on for years, and
<PERSON>Regula</PERSON> has always prevailed.
   ``Ted goes along with a one-year prohibition, but not with
statutorily naming it <PERSON>Mt. McKinley</PERSON>,'' says <PERSON>Regula</PERSON>.
   Like most geographic features, <ORGANIZATION>Mt. McKinley</ORGANIZATION> was not given its
name by law. Rather, its name is officially recognized by the <ORGANIZATION>Board
of Geographic Names</ORGANIZATION>, a division of the <ORGANIZATION>Interior Department</ORGANIZATION>.
   It was named <ORGANIZATION>Mt. McKinley</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1896</DATE>, when <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> was <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>
governor and the Republican presidential candidate against Democrat
<PERSON>William Jennings Bryan</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> state legislature passed a resolution
requesting that the park and the mountain be renamed to <ORGANIZATION>Denali</ORGANIZATION>.
Congressional hearings were held <DATE>two years later</DATE>. In a compromise,
the park was renamed in <DATE>1980</DATE> but the mountain retained its name.
   Negotiators from the two chambers probably will meet next month
to work out a compromise bill.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870707-0036 </DOCNO>
<HL> Who's News:
Gerber Chief's Death Revives Speculation
On Company's Vulnerability to Takeover
---
By Jacob M. Schlesinger
<DD> 07/07/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> GEB WNEWS </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Gerber Products Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s 61-year-old president and chief executive officer, <PERSON>Leo D. Goulet</PERSON>, died after an apparent heart attack <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, and a retired chief executive will fill the job until the <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, company can find a permanent replacement. 

   News of the death reignited longtime rumors that the baby-food producer could face a hostile takeover bid, although none has been made public. 

   Many traders felt yesterday that trading in Gerber stock increased because of <PERSON>Mr. Goulet</PERSON>'s death, which some felt added to the continuing turmoil and increased the company's vulnerability. 
"A lot of arbs are in there today," said one arbitrager. 

   "His death causes some instability, and instability by nature makes a company more vulnerable," added <PERSON>John M. McMillin</PERSON>, an analyst for <ORGANIZATION>Prudential-Bache Securities</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> said it has hired an independent consultant to find a new chief executive, and said it would consider an outsider for the first time in its 59-year history. 
The move is apparently aimed in part at quelling Wall Street criticism of Gerber management. 

   "Independence is No. 1 on their list" of factors in seeking a new chief executive, said <PERSON>William E. Gould</PERSON>, the manager of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> firm conducting the search. 

   Until that person is found, <PERSON>Carl G. Smith</PERSON>, 66, will be acting chief executive. 
He held that post from <DATE>1982 through 1985</DATE>, and served as chairman from <DATE>1983</DATE> through <DATE>February 1986</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON> has remained a member of the board, and has been chairman of its executive committee. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Goulet</PERSON>'s death came less than six weeks after his appointment as chief executive. 
He was promoted from chief operating officer after <PERSON>William L. McKinley</PERSON>, 63, took early retirement for what the company said were "personal reasons." 
As previously announced, <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> will retain the chairmanship until later this month. 

   Gerber officials and directors had declined to elaborate on the reasons for <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON>'s departure as chief executive, but analysts suggested <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> was forced out because of shareholder dissatisfaction with the company's performance. 
Gerber net income in the <DATE>fiscal year ended March 31</DATE> was <MONEY>$36.4 million</MONEY>, down <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> from <MONEY>$45.5 million</MONEY> a year earlier. 

   A major reason for the drop in net was widespread publicity about glass allegedly found in some jars of <ORGANIZATION>Gerber</ORGANIZATION>'s baby food. 
Although those claims were never substantiated, the company was forced to substantially increase promotions and advertising. 
<PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> also was criticized for his management of the company's non-food operations, such as furniture and apparel. 

   Speculation about a takeover has been high because <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> is a relatively small company, is No. 1 in the baby-food market, and is considered an underperformer. 

   A company spokesman wouldn't comment on why <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> had decided to consider candidates outside the company, as well as insiders, for chief executive, although analysts said no obvious in-house replacements existed. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Gould</PERSON>, the search consultant, said his firm began its search before <PERSON>Mr. Goulet</PERSON>'s death because the company was looking ahead to the next generation of leadership. 
"A review of the company's executive succession plan was launched in <DATE>June</DATE> to assure continued strong leadership in the foreseeable future," <PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON>, the acting chief executive, said in a prepared statement. 

   Gerber wants someone "around 50 to 55 years old who can give them 10 to 15 years of leadership," <PERSON>Mr. Gould</PERSON> said. 
He added that he has already interviewed four internal candidates and expects to interview about a half-dozen external candidates. 
The company hopes to have a replacement in two to four months. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Gould</PERSON> declined to say whether <PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON> was being considered as the new full-time chief executive. 
The company doesn't require retirement at age 65, the spokesman said. 
<PERSON>Mr. Smith</PERSON> couldn't be reached for comment. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Goulet</PERSON>, a native of <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>, joined <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> in <DATE>1955</DATE> and spent most of his career in the company's international operations. 
In <DATE>1982</DATE>, he became executive vice president of the general merchandise division and was elected to the board. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881003-0295 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-03-88 1350EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s p BC-GovernorsAsPresident-List ADV09   10-03 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Governors As President-List, ADV 09,0487</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv09</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Oct 9, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>With BC-Governors As President</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seventeen Americans served as state or
territorial governors before becoming president, although most also
held senior elected or appointed federal office before winning the
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The two most recent exceptions are <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ronald
Reagan</PERSON>. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> hopes to become a third.
   The list of former governors who became president includes some
of the most distinguished chief executives and some who are
scarcely remembered.
<ORGANIZATION>American Revolution</ORGANIZATION>, tops the list. <PERSON>Jefferson</PERSON>, the third president,
doubled the size of the nation by purchasing the <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>
territory from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>1803</DATE>.
   He had some training along the way, being principle author of
the Declaration of Independence, negotiating the peace treaty with
<LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, then serving as ambassador to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and secretary
of state.
   <PERSON>James Monroe</PERSON>, another <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> governor, became the fifth
president after serving in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION>, as envoy to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, and as secretary of war and state.
   <PERSON>Andrew Jackson</PERSON> was territorial governor of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> four years
after defeating the Seminole Indians in that state.
   His successor, <PERSON>Martin Van Buren</PERSON>, was governor of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> after
serving in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION>, and was <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s secretary of state
and vice president.
   Other <DATE>19th century</DATE> presidents who had been governors include
<PERSON>William Henry Harrison</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <PERSON>John Tyler</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>James
Knox Polk</PERSON> and <PERSON>Andrew Johnson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Rutherford B. Hayes</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Grover Cleveland</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON>, the 25th president, was governor of <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> for
1892-96.
   <PERSON>Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON>, who was vice president and took office after
<PERSON>McKinley</PERSON>'s assassination, had been assistant <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> secretary before
resigning in <DATE>1897</DATE> to organize the Rough Riders in the
Spanish-American War. He was governor of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for 1899-1901.
   <PERSON>Woodrow Wilson</PERSON>, who had graduate degrees in law and political
science, was president of <ORGANIZATION>Princeton University</ORGANIZATION> before serving as
governor of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> in 1911-13. He was elected president in <DATE>1912</DATE>
and invaded <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in <DATE>1914</DATE>, the year that World War I began in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. He was re-elected in <DATE>1916</DATE> with the slogan, ``He Kept Us Out
of War,'' but declared war on <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> the following year.
   <PERSON>Calvin Coolidge</PERSON> served as governor of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> for 1919-20
and for 1921-23 was vice president to <PERSON>Warren Harding</PERSON>, who died in
office.
   <PERSON>Franklin Delano Roosevelt</PERSON> was governor of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for 1929-33,
after serving as assistant <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Secretary in 1913-20, a post which
deeply involved him in diplomacy and logistics in World War I and
prepared him for his leadership role in World War II.
   <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> served for one term as governor of <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> before
his election as president in <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>, a two-term <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> governor, defeated <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>
in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Oct 9</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870401-0019 </DOCNO>
<HL> Gerber to Post Drop
In 4th-Quarter Profit
Per Share, Cites Ads</HL>
<DD> 04/01/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> GEB
DOW JONES INTERVIEW (CEO) </IN>
<DATELINE> FREMONT, Mich.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Gerber Products Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman and chief executive officer said he generally agreed with analysts' forecasts that the company will post lower profit for its fiscal fourth quarter. 

   Analysts' estimates that the company earned about <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> to <MONEY>55 cents</MONEY> a share for the quarter ended yesterday are generally "accurate," <PERSON>William L. McKinley</PERSON> said. 
Year-earlier profit was <MONEY>60 cents</MONEY> a share. 
<PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> attributed the profit decline to a variety of factors, including the "very substantial" cost of a stepped-up advertising and promotion campaign in <LOCATION>Gerber</LOCATION>'s baby food business. 

   In the year-ago <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Gerber</ORGANIZATION> earned <MONEY>$12.3 million</MONEY> on sales of <MONEY>$242.7 million</MONEY>. 
<PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> estimated that sales in the quarter just ended increased to more than <MONEY>$280 million</MONEY>. 

   He said analysts' estimates that the baby products company will report profit for the fiscal year of about <MONEY>$1.75</MONEY> to <MONEY>$1.80</MONEY> a share are "reasonable." 
Sales for the year were more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>. 

Net income included a charge of <MONEY>$4.2 million</MONEY> for a plant closing. 

   <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> said the advertising and promotions campaign was launched to counter a consumer scare early last year when a wave of allegations about glass shards in the company's baby food surfaced. 
The complaints never were tied to <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON>'s production process, <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> said. 
He added that the number of complaints have dwindled to "nothing outside the normal." 

   <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> said some small charges associated with the restructuring of <ORGANIZATION>Gerber</ORGANIZATION>'s furniture business also hurt <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> profit. 
"I'm not talking more than a <MONEY>few cents</MONEY> a share, but it will adversely affect <DATE>this quarter</DATE>," he said. 

   The chief executive said the company's transportation group, which includes a trucking business, "isn't part of our long-term growth strategy," though he wouldn't say what the company plans to do with the business. 

   <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> wouldn't comment on whether the company plans any change in its 33-cent-a-share quarterly dividend. 
He said the company isn't expecting to pursue any new financing in the near term and has "nothing major" planned in the way of acquisitions. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890120-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-20-89 1255EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Reagan-Jinx     01-20 0260</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Reagan-Jinx,260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Breaks `Zero Year' Jinx</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Reagan Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, who admits to having a
superstitious nature, has all the same escaped a jinx that has long
haunted certain presidents.
   Reagan remains alive at the end of his presidency, even though he
was first elected in a year ending with zero.
   For nearly a century and a half, every president elected in such
a year had died in office. <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, despite a brush with cancer and
an assassination attempt, was the first to break the jinx.
   <PERSON>William Henry Harrison</PERSON>, elected in <DATE>1840</DATE>, died of pneumonia at the
age of 67 a month after taking office.
   <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>, elected in <DATE>1860</DATE>, was assassinated in <DATE>1865</DATE> at the
age of 56.
   <PERSON>James A. Garfield</PERSON>, elected in <DATE>1880</DATE>, was assassinated a few months
later at the age of 50.
   <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON>, re-elected in <DATE>1900</DATE>, was assassinated in <DATE>1901</DATE> at
the age of 58.
   <PERSON>Warren G. Harding</PERSON>, elected in <DATE>1920</DATE>, died of a heart attack in
<DATE>1923</DATE> at the age of 58.
   <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON>, elected to his third term in <DATE>1940</DATE>, died of
a cerebral hemmorhage in <DATE>1945</DATE> at the age of 63.
   <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON>, elected in <DATE>1960</DATE>, was assassinated in <DATE>1963</DATE> at the
age of 46.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, 77, survived an assassination attempt outside a
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> hotel in <DATE>1981</DATE> and underwent successful surgery for cancer
of the colon in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> has often invoked superstitious beliefs from the world of
show business and sports and declined to disavow first lady <PERSON>Nancy
Reagan</PERSON>'s reliance on astrology.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870916-0060 </DOCNO>
<HL> Who's News:
Gerber Products Appoints Entenmann's
David Johnson to Chief Executive Post
---
By Frank E. James
<DD> 09/16/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> GEB WNEWS </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Gerber Products Co.</ORGANIZATION> chose as its new top officer the executive who helped <ORGANIZATION>Entenmann's Inc.</ORGANIZATION> grow into a nationally recognized baked-goods company. 

<PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON>, currently a <ORGANIZATION>General Foods Corp.</ORGANIZATION> vice president, is also president and chief executive officer of that company's <ORGANIZATION>Entenmann</ORGANIZATION>'s subsidiary. 
<PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON> is scheduled to take over at <LOCATION>Freemont</LOCATION>, Mich.-based Gerber by <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE>. 

   The appointment was welcomed by Wall Street analysts, who viewed it as possibly signaling a return of stability to <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> management and speeding the company's financial turnaround, perhaps through a return to the core foods business. 

   At <ORGANIZATION>Gerber</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON> succeeds the late <PERSON>Leo D. Goulet</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>July</DATE> at age 61 after an apparent heart attack. 
The uncertainty following <PERSON>Mr. Goulet</PERSON>'s death had fueled long-standing rumors that management turmoil and weak earnings might make <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> vulnerable to a hostile takeover bid, driving up the company's stock price. 

   Yesterday in <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading, <ORGANIZATION>Gerber</ORGANIZATION> fell <MONEY>$2</MONEY>, to close at <MONEY>$49.625</MONEY> a share, amid a broad decline in the market. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Goulet</PERSON> had been chief executive for only six weeks before his death. 
He had succeeded <PERSON>William L. McKinley</PERSON>, 63, who took early retirement. 
Analysts have suggested <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> was forced out because of shareholder dissatisfaction with the company's performance. 
Gerber's profit for the year ended <DATE>March 31</DATE> fell <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> from a year earlier to <MONEY>$36.4 million</MONEY>. 

   "The company had been adrift without a sail," said <PERSON>John M. McMillin</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Prudential-Bache Securities</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
"But I'm pleased they could name such a very qualified person in so relatively short a time. 
This should add stability and mollify some takeover rumors." 

   <PERSON>Mr. McMillin</PERSON> added that <PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON> joins Gerber at a good time, because the company seems to be turning around. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON>, he said, will be in a position to accelerate that trend, "particularly if he divests those low-return businesses which don't make sense, like furniture, insurance and child-care centers." 
<PERSON>Mr. McMillin</PERSON> said <PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON>'s strong food-industry background makes it likely that he'll return Gerber to its core food business. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON> couldn't be reached for comment but <PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> issued a statement in <PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON>'s name indicating that he may do just that. 
"My initial mission will be a thorough review of our various businesses, building on our strengths, and reviewing our strategy on every segment of the business" to meet company and shareholder standards for high profitabilty, the statement said. 

   For the past eight years, <PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON> has headed <ORGANIZATION>Entenmann</ORGANIZATION>'s, which was acquired by <ORGANIZATION>General Foods</ORGANIZATION> from <ORGANIZATION>Warner-Lambert Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
During his tenure at <ORGANIZATION>Entenmann</ORGANIZATION>'s, the unit went from being an <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>, regional baking concern to a national marketer with sales that increased fourfold. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891023-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-23-89 0823EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv03   10-23 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv03,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday, Nov. 3</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <DATE>Nov. 3</DATE>, the <DATE>307th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 58
   Today's Highlight in History:
   Twenty-five years ago, on <DATE>Nov. 3, 1964</DATE>, President <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>
soundly defeated Republican challenger <PERSON>Barry Goldwater</PERSON> to win a
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> term in his own right.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1839</DATE>, 150 years ago, the first Opium War between <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> erupted as two British frigates and a fleet of war junks
clashed off the Chinese coast.
   In <DATE>1868</DATE>, Republican <PERSON>Ulysses S. Grant</PERSON> won the presidential
election over Democrat <PERSON>Horatio Seymour</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1896</DATE>, Republican <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON> defeated Democrat <PERSON>William
Jennings Bryan</PERSON> for the presidency.
   In <DATE>1900</DATE>, the first automobile show in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> opened
at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Madison Square Garden</ORGANIZATION> under the auspices of the
<ORGANIZATION>Automobile Club of America</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1903</DATE>, <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> proclaimed its independence from <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1908</DATE>, Republican <PERSON>William Howard Taft</PERSON> was elected the 27th
president of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, outpolling <PERSON>William Jennings Bryan</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1936</DATE>, President <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> won a landslide victory
over Republican challenger <PERSON>Alfred M.</PERSON> ``Alf'' <PERSON>Landon</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1957</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> launched Sputnik II, the second
man-made satellite, into orbit, carrying a dog named Laika.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON> was inaugurated president of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, the Rev. <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> launched his first campaign for
   In <DATE>1986</DATE>, Ash-Shiraa, a pro-Syrian Lebanese magazine, first broke
the story of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> arms sales to <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>, a revelation that would
escalate into the Iran-Contra affair.
   Ten years ago: Five radicals were killed when gunfire erupted
during an anti-Ku Klux Klan demonstration in <LOCATION>Greensboro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>,
after a caravan of Klansmen and <ORGANIZATION>American Nazis</ORGANIZATION> drove into the area.
Funeral services were held in <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION> for assassinated
President Park Chung-hee.
   Five years ago: The body of assassinated Indian Prime Minister
<PERSON>Indira Gandhi</PERSON> was cremated during an outdoor ceremony attended by
an estimated 400,000 mourners.
   One year ago: Israeli Prime Minister <PERSON>Yitzhak Shamir</PERSON> whose Likud
bloc won a narrow victory in parliamentary elections, began meeting
with representatives of religious and rightist parties, seeking
support for a coalition government.
   Today's Birthdays: <PERSON>Journalist James Reston</PERSON> is 80. Baseball
Hall-of-Famer <PERSON>Bob Feller</PERSON> is 71. Actor <PERSON>Charles Bronson</PERSON> is 68.
Actress <PERSON>Monica Vitti</PERSON> is 58. Massachusetts Governor <PERSON>Michael S.
Dukakis</PERSON> is 56. Actor-dancer <PERSON>Ken Berry</PERSON> is 56. Singer <PERSON>Lulu</PERSON> is 41.
Television critic <PERSON>Tom Shales</PERSON> is 41. Singer <PERSON>Adam Ant</PERSON> is 35.
   Thought for Today: ``Humor distorts nothing, and only false gods
are laughed off their earthly pedestals.'' _ Agnes Repplier
American essayist (1858-1950).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Friday, Nov. 3</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-12988</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-ED0DLADNFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940427
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 APR 94 / Observer: Inequitable?
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Ever since the assassination of President <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON> in <DATE>1901</DATE>, American
financial markets have always paid tribute to the death of heads of state by
shutting up shop.
But in closing down for an entire session to mark the passing of <PERSON>Richard
Nixon</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> has ruffled a few feathers - and not
solely because people feel that <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON>, the only US president to resign in
disgrace, might merit something less than the full treatment.
At least two other exchanges, <ORGANIZATION>Nasdaq</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>,
unabashedly say they would have preferred to remain open but were forced to
follow the <ORGANIZATION>Big Board</ORGANIZATION>'s lead for technical reasons only.
Wall Streeters were also quick to point out the damage that unscheduled
closings could inflict on the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> market's efforts to fend off its
competitors from overseas.
In deciding to close for the full session, the exchange is indeed affording
<PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> an honour denied another president 30 years ago.
In <DATE>1964</DATE>, trading was suspended for only half the day after <PERSON>Herbert Hoover</PERSON>
died.
But then <PERSON>Hoover</PERSON> just happened to be in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1929</DATE>, the year of
the mother of all stock market crashes.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6231 Security and Commodity Exchanges.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 23
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900117-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-17-90 0901EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-IRAArrests     01-17 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-IRA Arrests,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>Affidavit: IRA Suspect Claimed Link to Thatcher Bombing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN MURPHY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A suspected <ORGANIZATION>Irish Republican Army</ORGANIZATION>
terrorist bragged that the group's next target would be British
helicopters once it had control of a Stinger anti-aircraft missile,
according to court papers.
   <PERSON>Kevin McKinley</PERSON>, who also allegedly told federal undercover
agents that his group was responsible for a <DATE>1984</DATE> assassination
attempt against British Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> and other
bombings, was arrested <DATE>Friday</DATE> in a <LOCATION>Palm Beach</LOCATION> parking lot as he
tried to wedge a 5-foot Stinger missile in his car. Three other men
were also arrested.
   The four remained in prison today after a bail hearing was
postponed until <DATE>Friday</DATE> at the request of both sides.
   ``All have a viable defense and it will be pursued to the
highest degree,'' said <PERSON>Roger Colton</PERSON>, a lawyer for <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION>, 33;
<PERSON>Seamus Moley</PERSON>, 30 and <PERSON>Joseph McColgan</PERSON>, 39, all Irish citizens.
   Colton would not give details of a possible defense but said
entrapment is ``a possible avenue.''
   Co-defendant <PERSON>Sean McCann</PERSON>, 34, a Canadian, was represented by
attorney <PERSON>Michael Salnick</PERSON>.
   Agents posing as arms dealers arrested the men shortly after
<PERSON>Moley</PERSON> handed over <MONEY>$47,500</MONEY> for a hand-held Stinger missile and
<ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> was taken to a <LOCATION>West Palm Beach</LOCATION> warehouse to inspect the
weapon, authorities said.
   Agents had planned to follow McKinley from the warehouse, but he
was arrested on the spot after he discovered the Stinger did not
fit in his car, the federal <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Alcohol</ORGANIZATION>, Tobacco and Firearms
said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. The three other men were arrested in <LOCATION>North Palm
Beach</LOCATION>, about 65 miles north of <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.
   The Stinger, which weighs about 35 pounds, is used to launch a
single surface-to-air missile. The weapon was on loan from the
Marines and had no warhead.
   <PERSON>McKinley</PERSON> said the Stinger was to be used by the provisional wing
of the <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> against British helicopters in <LOCATION>Northern Ireland</LOCATION>,
according to court papers filed by Customs and <ORGANIZATION>ATF</ORGANIZATION>.
   McKinley also told agents ``his people'' were responsible for a
<DATE>1984</DATE> bombing of a hotel in <LOCATION>Brighton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> claimed
responsibility for the bombing, which killed five people, including
two senior Conservative Party figures. <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> escaped
unharmed.
   During several meetings from <DATE>Nov. 20</DATE> to <DATE>Jan. 12</DATE>, the suspects
also said they were seeking .50-caliber rifles, C-4 explosives and
grenade launchers. All are charged with violations of the Arms
Export Control Act and Neutrality Law and other weapons violations.
   Assistant <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Barbara Patras</PERSON> said they each could
convicted.
   The <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION>, a mainly Roman Catholic guerrilla group outlawed in
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, is fighting to end British rule over <LOCATION>Northern
Ireland</LOCATION> and unite it with the Irish Republic.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051489-0126 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 56902 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 14, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Westside; Part 9; Page 9; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
59 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SCHOOL ASSIGNMENT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Students graduating from <ORGANIZATION>McKinley Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> will attend <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln Middle 
School</ORGANIZATION> starting in the fall, rather than <ORGANIZATION>John Adams Middle School</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Santa Monica-Malibu School Board</ORGANIZATION> voted unanimously <DATE>Monday</DATE> to make <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> 
a feeder school to <LOCATION>Lincoln</LOCATION>. In addition to <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Franklin</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Roosevelt 
Elementary Schools</ORGANIZATION> are feeder schools to <LOCATION>Lincoln</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880105-0027 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Danaher Corp. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> DHR </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Danaher Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which agreed to sell its <ORGANIZATION>Mohawk Rubber Co.</ORGANIZATION> unit to <ORGANIZATION>McKinley Allsopp Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>McKinley</PERSON> notified <PERSON>Danaher</PERSON> that it is unable to obtain financing for the leveraged buy-out valued at <MONEY>$70 million</MONEY>. 

   The Washington-based maker of automotive and transportation products said the agreement hasn't been terminated, but indicated "there can be no assurance that the transaction" will be completed under the previously announced terms. 
<PERSON>Danaher</PERSON> said it intends to pursue, among other things, alternative transactions involving <LOCATION>Mohawk</LOCATION>. 

   In <DATE>November</DATE>, <PERSON>Danaher</PERSON> agreed to sell its <LOCATION>Akron</LOCATION>, Ohio-based tire maker to <ORGANIZATION>McKinley Allsopp</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Merchants Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a Boston-based holding company. 
Under those terms, <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> agreed to pay about <MONEY>$67 million</MONEY> in cash and <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> of preferred stock. 

   Mohawk was to be sold to <ORGANIZATION>Radial Acquisition Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a corporation organized by <ORGANIZATION>McKinley Allsopp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>McKinley Allsopp</ORGANIZATION> couldn't be reached for comment. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072189-0111 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 85053 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 21, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 30; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
523 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WILL BRADLEY; BAND LEADER, TROMBONIST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BURT A. FOLKART, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Will <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON>, a handsome, urbane studio trombonist who emerged from those 
anonymous ranks to lead what briefly was one of the most celebrated Big Bands 
of the early and mid-1940s, has died. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON>, noted for such popular 
hits of the day as "Beat Me, <LOCATION>Daddy</LOCATION>, Eight to the Bar," "Celery Stalks at 
Midnight" and "Strange Cargo," died <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Flemington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J</LOCATION>. He was 78. 
</P>
<P>
With drummer <PERSON>Ray McKinley</PERSON>, whom <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> lured from <PERSON>Jimmy Dorsey</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Will 
Bradley Band</ORGANIZATION> was a mainstay of ballrooms and hotels during the wartime years of 
sentimental ballads, jive tunes and boogie-woogie. 
</P>
<P>
Called by <PERSON>Glenn Miller</PERSON> "the best of all" the trombonists of his day, <PERSON>Wilbur 
Schwichtenberg</PERSON> had worked for years in recording studios before emerging to 
join the old <PERSON>Milt Shaw</PERSON> and Ray Noble bands (<PERSON>Miller</PERSON> was a fellow trombonist with 
Noble). In <DATE>1939</DATE> <PERSON>Schwichtenberg</PERSON> became <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wilbur</PERSON> became Will and he and 
<PERSON>McKinley</PERSON> (considered a co-leader although he sat at the back of the band) 
produced a series of sweet ballads and swing tunes for <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> records. 
</P>
<P>
With <ORGANIZATION>Freddie Slack</ORGANIZATION> at the piano the <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> band recorded "I Don't Stand a 
Ghost of a Chance," with <ORGANIZATION>Carlotta Dale</ORGANIZATION> on vocal, and "Old <PERSON>Doc Yak</PERSON>," with 
<ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> singing and playing drums. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Louise Tobin</PERSON>, then <PERSON>Harry James</PERSON>' wife, sang "Deed I Do" with <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> shortly 
before the band switched emphasis from ballads to boogie. 
</P>
<P>
Slack, later to form his own famous band, was the catalyst behind a white group 
of musicians playing what had been a black innovation. 
</P>
<P>
In <PERSON>George T. Simons</PERSON>' book "The Big Bands," <PERSON>McKinley</PERSON> recounts how the musicians 
were experimenting with instrumental arrangements based on the blues with an 
eight-to-the-bar piano boogie beat. 
</P>
<P>
"There was one point where I had a drum break and for some reason or other that 
night instead of playing the break, I sang out "Oh, beat me, daddy, eight to 
the bar!" After the set <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> encouraged the writing of a song with that 
title and it became the biggest of the <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> band's hits, selling more than 
100,000 copies. 
</P>
<P>
Bradley tried to chase that success with "Rock-a-Bye Boogie," "Scrub Me, <LOCATION>Mama</LOCATION>, 
With a Boogie Beat," "Fry Me, <LOCATION>Cookie</LOCATION>, With a Can of Lard" and others. 
</P>
<P>
But he quickly became disenchanted with the band's new sound, preferring the 
more solid tunes of the day, and he and <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> eventually split up, <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> 
to form his own group in <DATE>1942</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Bradley brought new talent into his band after <PERSON>McKinley</PERSON>'s departure, among them 
a young drummer named <PERSON>Shelley Manne</PERSON> and a trumpet player who called himself 
<ORGANIZATION>Shorty Rogers</ORGANIZATION>. These two were to become an integral part of modern jazz a few 
years later. 
</P>
<P>
But the wartime military draft decimated the ranks of the younger players and 
<PERSON>Simon</PERSON> writes of one engagement in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> in which <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> told him that six 
musicians moved from the bandstand to the recruiting station in a single week. 
</P>
<P>
After that <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> was forced to cancel many of his personal appearances and 
rely on studio musicians for recordings. Bradley himself soon returned to the 
studios where he had started. 
</P>
<P>
He is survived by his wife, <PERSON>Joan</PERSON>, a son, a daughter and a grandson. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Will Bradley 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Obituary 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910722-0058
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910722-0058.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Who's News:
   Bank South Fills 2 Posts
</HL>
<DATE>
07/22/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   BKSO WNEWS
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
ALL REGIONAL BANKS (BAR)
SOUTHERN U.S. BANKS (BAS)
ALL BANKS, BANKING NEWS AND ISSUES (BNK)
</IN>
<NS>
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
</NS>
<RE>
GEORGIA (GA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   ATLANTA -- Bank South Corp. tapped two senior executives
of C&amp;S/Sovran Corp. on the eve of a reported merger agreement
between C&amp;S/Sovran and NCNB Corp.
   Patrick L. Flinn was named president and chief executive
officer of Bank South. Mr. Flinn, 49 years old, had been
group executive vice president in charge of real estate and
mortgage banking for C&amp;S/Sovran in the Washington, D.C.,
region.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mr. Flinn</PERSON> had been with C&amp;S/Sovran and its predecessor
company, <ORGANIZATION>Citizens &amp; Southern Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, for 25 years. <PERSON>Mr. Flinn</PERSON>
succeeds <PERSON>Robert P. Guyton</PERSON> as chief executive officer. <PERSON>Mr.
Guyton</PERSON> resigned in <DATE>June</DATE> under pressure from the board.
   <PERSON>John E. McKinley</PERSON> was named senior executive vice president
and chief credit officer of <ORGANIZATION>Bank South</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON>, 47, was
<ORGANIZATION>C&amp;S/Sovran</ORGANIZATION>'s group executive vice president and chief credit
officer in corporate banking. He had been with C&amp;S for 22
years.
   <PERSON>Mr. McKinley</PERSON> succeeds <PERSON>C. Arnold Johnson</PERSON> as senior credit
officer; <PERSON>Mr. Johnson</PERSON> resigned in <DATE>April</DATE>. However, <PERSON>Mr.
McKinley</PERSON>, who will be second in command under <PERSON>Mr. Flinn</PERSON>, will
have a wider range of responsibilities in the post, <ORGANIZATION>Bank
South</ORGANIZATION> said.
   "These are two heavy hitters," said <PERSON>Bo Spalding</PERSON>, senior
vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Bank South</ORGANIZATION> and head of corporate
communications. "Everyone here is delighted to have gotten
them." Both men assume their new jobs <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Bank South</ORGANIZATION>, which has been hammered by large loan losses,
has seen turmoil in senior management recently, including the
exodus of four senior officers. Last week, it reported a
<DATE>second-quarter</DATE> net loss of <MONEY>$16.3 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>47 cents</MONEY> a
share, and suspended its common stock dividend.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06017243 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06017243 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  NEWARK; MAN; DEATH; AUTO; ACCIDENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A 35-year-old Newark man trying to help an injured dog in the middle of the
road died Tuesday after he was struck by a car in a freak accident in Union
City.;    Two women were also injured in the accident at 6 p.m. on Union City
Boulevard, south of Rose Way.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DRIVER KILLED TRYING TO HELP INJURED DOG  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The <ORGANIZATION>Alameda County Coroner's Office</ORGANIZATION> identified the dead man as <PERSON>Douglas
McKinley.;    McKinley</PERSON> was driving on <LOCATION>Union City Boulevard</LOCATION> when he hit a small
dog. He stopped to check on the animal, got out of his car and was struck by a
car driven by Lulalhati De <LOCATION>Padua</LOCATION>, 20, of <LOCATION>Union City.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Valencia Willis</PERSON>, 39,
of <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, was jogging in the area, saw the accident and stopped a passing
car to get help for McKinley.;    <PERSON>Willis</PERSON> was standing next to that car,
talking to the driver, <PERSON>Carmen Chapman</PERSON>, 35, of <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, when a car driven by
<PERSON>William Harmuth</PERSON>, 67, of <LOCATION>Alameda</LOCATION>, attempted to pass the accident scene on the
right side and struck <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>'s car and <PERSON>Willis</PERSON>, police said.;    <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> was
dead on arrival at <ORGANIZATION>St. Rose Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Hayward</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Willis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> were
treated at <LOCATION>Hayward</LOCATION> hospitals and released.;    No citations have been filed.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Staff Report  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910117  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  199  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday January 17, 1991
00017243,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881002-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-02-88 1123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-RunningMates Bjt   10-02 0770</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Running Mates, Bjt,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Experts Say Top of Ticket, Not Running Mates, Sways Voters' Choice</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrats who hope <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> will
help the ticket win his home state of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and perhaps the
presidential election could do well to regard the fate of <PERSON>Henry
Gassaway Davis</PERSON>.
   In case anyone doesn't remember, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> was Democrat <PERSON>Alton B.
Parker</PERSON>'s running mate when <PERSON>Parker</PERSON> ran for president against
<ORGANIZATION>Republican Teddy Roosevelt</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1904</DATE>.
   The voters chose between <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Parker</PERSON>, and their choice
was Roosevelt by a 3-2 margin.
   Experts concede that the vice presidential debate in <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> between <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> and Republican <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> may
make a difference, but they say the voters' final decision will
come down to a choice between the top of the tickets, Democrat
<PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> and Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>.
   ``Unless <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> is absolutely destroyed in the debate with
<PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>, I don't think it will hurt <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>,'' said <PERSON>Leo Ribuffo</PERSON>, a
specialist in political history at <ORGANIZATION>George Washington University</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   ``People will be looking for <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> to blow it,'' said <PERSON>Samuel H.
California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. ``If he can get through the debate in a
competent fashion where he looks unexceptional, it will be a real
success for him.''
   <PERSON>Eddie Mahe Jr.</PERSON>, a Republican political consultant, said, ``I
think it is reasonable to suggest that <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> would have won
<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Quayle</ORGANIZATION>'s home state) without <PERSON>Mr. Quayle</PERSON>, and with <PERSON>Mr.
Bentsen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mike Dukakis</PERSON> is still not going to carry <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. So you
wash that out.''
   ``I think the odds are that <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> will have little or no effect
on the ultimate choice,'' said <PERSON>Thomas Mann</PERSON>, program director for
   <PERSON>Elspeth Rostow</PERSON>, a political scholar at the <ORGANIZATION>Lyndon B. Johnson
School of Public Affairs</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>, said
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s choice of <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> ``doesn't seem to have too much effect on
the voters, at least so far.''
   ``I don't think, if indeed <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was disposed to choose <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> to
appeal to women, that so far it has had that effect,'' <PERSON>Ms. Rostow</PERSON>
said.
   ``I think the conventional wisdom that the selection of a
running mate is rarely decisive one way or another is absolutely
true,'' said <PERSON>Ribuffo</PERSON>.
   A survey conducted this year by the <ORGANIZATION>Hearst Corp.</ORGANIZATION> supports this
view.
   Eighteen percent of the 1,001 voters surveyed said they had
changed their minds about a presidential candidate at one time or
another because of their opinion of his running mate. Of those, <PERCENT>70
percent</PERCENT> said they voted against that ticket.
   Political experts agree that if a running mate has any effect,
he is more likely to hurt than help.
   Examples cited include President <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s selection of <PERSON>Sen. Robert
Dole</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, who was criticized for his slashing debating style
in <DATE>1976</DATE>, and <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>'s choice of <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, who
suffered from examination of her family's finances in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   ``Clearly in my opinion <PERSON>Bob Dole</PERSON> in <DATE>1976</DATE> in that debate (with
<PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>'s running mate) cost <PERSON>Jerry Ford</PERSON> votes,'' <PERSON>Mahe</PERSON>
said. ``Clearly in <DATE>1984</DATE> in my opinion, <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON> cost
<PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON> votes probably.''
   In <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>'s unsuccessful campaign of <DATE>1960</DATE>, some thought
that Republican vice presidential candidate <ORGANIZATION>Henry Cabot Lodge</ORGANIZATION> hurt
the ticket's chances by pledging that <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> would appoint a black
to the Cabinet _ a statement <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> disavowed.
criticized for taking naps and not campaigning hard enough. ``Some
have thought that if he had used his prestige from the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> more
effectively, <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> might have edged out <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Ms. Rostow</PERSON> said.
   There are exceptions to the rule that running mates don't help
much, the experts said.
   While there is disagreement over whether Lodge hurt <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> in
<DATE>1960</DATE>, almost everybody agrees that <PERSON>Lyndon B. Johnson</PERSON> helped Kennedy
by enabling him to carry <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   ``I don't think <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> would have won without <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>,''
<PERSON>Ribuffo</PERSON> said.
   Also, <PERSON>Ribuffo</PERSON> said, <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON> may have helped <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> win election
in <DATE>1976</DATE> by imparting legitimacy to the former <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> governor in
the eyes of skeptical liberals.
   Then there was the running mate that Republicans chose in <DATE>1900</DATE>
to help the colorless <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON> win a second term against
the dynamic Democrat, <PERSON>William Jennings Bryan</PERSON>. The ticket of
<ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> became known as ``the kangaroo ticket
because it had a kick in the tail,'' <PERSON>Ms. Rostow</PERSON> said.
   There haven't been many tickets in any other year, including
<DATE>1988</DATE>, with that much of a kick in the tail, the experts agree.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900531-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-31-90 2118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DisabledClimbers     05-31 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Disabled Climbers,0310</SECOND>
<HEAD>High Wind Keeps Deaf and Blind Climbers From McKinley Summit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TALKEETNA, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An international team that includes two
blind climbers, a deaf climber and an amputee nearly made it to the
top of <LOCATION>Mount McKinley</LOCATION>, but 50 mph winds forced them to turn around,
officials said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The group got up to at least 18,000 feet, said <PERSON>Roger Robinson</PERSON>, a
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Park Service</ORGANIZATION> ranger. At 20,320 feet, <ORGANIZATION>Mount McKinley</ORGANIZATION> is <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION>'s highest mountain.
   ``They've all descended. They're at 14,000 now. Indications are
they're not going back up,'' he said.
   ``They did very good considering that only about half the folks
that try McKinley make it to the top.''
   The ascent was attempted by 1,009 climbers last year; only 524
reached the summit.
   Adaptations were made for the disabled climbers.
   ``Apparently they've got ropes stretched out to the latrines when
they're at camps,'' said <PERSON>Bob Seiber</PERSON>, chief mountaineering ranger.
``They work extremely well together and develop their other senses,
I guess.''
   <PERSON>Patrick Reinhart</PERSON>, a member of the expedition and director of
<ORGANIZATION>Challenge Alaska</ORGANIZATION>, a group that helps develop recreational and sports
opportunities for disabled climbers, came up with the idea for the
ascent.
   <PERSON>Reinhart</PERSON>, who has an artificial foot, always wanted to climb
<ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION>. So did <PERSON>Ross Watson</PERSON>, a Canadian member of the expedition
who lost his sight at age 12 in a pellet gun accident.
   <PERSON>Patrick Hurst</PERSON>, a 27-year-old Englishman who teaches outdoor
sports to physically disabled people, also is blind.
   Lkakpa Sonam, a Sherpa from <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION>, is deaf.
   In overall charge of the expedition is <PERSON>George Rooney</PERSON>, a member of
the <ORGANIZATION>American Alpine Club</ORGANIZATION> who's been up <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> twice and tried
climbing <ORGANIZATION>Everest</ORGANIZATION> in a joint American-Polish expediton. He's also an
emergency medical technician and a specialist in mountain rescue.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06359186 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06359186 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  EDITORIAL; SAN-JOSE; SCHOOL; OFFICE; BUILDING; COST; CONTROVERSY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  FRANKLIN-McKinley School District's new $7 million headquarters is far more
than offices. The renovated warehouse doubles as a community service center
for the largely low-income district, including a clinic for free medical care,
counseling services and even programs like Project Crackdown.;   But still, $7
million?  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Editorial  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DELUXE DIGS
FRANKLIN-MCKINLEY'S NEW DISTRICT HEADQUARTERS
DOESN'T PUT STUDENTS FIRST  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Editorials  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Even factoring out special costs, like structural changes to the building,
construction experts say the office space was expensive. Some teachers and
parents grumble about its comparative luxury while schools are in disrepair.; 
 And there's another problem. The district says it was told by the state that
it had to use revenue from property sales to build offices or the state would
claim the money. State officials say that's not true: Their rules encourage
districts to spend money on classrooms; offices are the last priority. And
while community services are great, the state <ORGANIZATION>Allocation Board</ORGANIZATION> would place
direct school needs first.;   The fact is Franklin-McKinley never sought to
spend this money on classrooms. The board wanted to build an education center
-- its name for the community facility -- and decided to sell excess property
to pay for it.;   <ORGANIZATION>Board</ORGANIZATION> president <ORGANIZATION>Lolita Foster</ORGANIZATION> says that when the project was
planned, starting in <DATE>1988</DATE>, the district had programs in place to renovate
schools and build new ones, relying on state grants. The education center was
to round out the district's services.;   But state funding for classroom
renovations is inadequate, and the district has <MONEY>$21 million</MONEY> in unmet needs,
waiting in line for state funding.;   There are good arguments for the
community facility. Healthy, well-adjusted children learn better. But the
district was sloppy about clearing its plans with the state, and it appears to
have spent more than necessary for the space it gained. Some of that money
could have gone into the schools.;   Some controversial features in the new
building are common in the offices of private companies; the shower in the
superintendent's office, for instance. But the question isn't whether school
workers deserve those amenities. The question is how best to spend a
district's severely limited resources.;   Somebody at Franklin-McKinley should
have thought harder about that question.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911224  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  356  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, December 24, 1991
00359186,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032290-0106 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 193203 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 22, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
San Gabriel Valley; Part J; Page 2; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
181 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAN GABRIEL VALLEY DIGEST: POMONA; 
</P>
<P>
GANESHA BLVD. RENAMED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> voted <DATE>Monday</DATE> to bestow the name "Fairplex Drive" on <ORGANIZATION>Ganesha 
Boulevard</ORGANIZATION> and parts of <ORGANIZATION>McKinley Avenue</ORGANIZATION> and E Street to give increased 
recognition to <LOCATION>Fairplex</LOCATION>, the site of the <LOCATION>Los Angeles County</LOCATION> Fair and other 
expositions. 
</P>
<P>
Fairplex Drive will become the designation for the full length of <LOCATION>Ganesha</LOCATION>, from 
Route 71 north to <ORGANIZATION>McKinley Avenue</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Also redesignated as <ORGANIZATION>Fairplex Drive</ORGANIZATION> will be the portion of <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> west of 
<LOCATION>Ganesha Boulevard</LOCATION>, and E Street from <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> north to the city limits. The 
portions of <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> and E Street that are being renamed are along the 
perimeter of the Fairplex property. 
</P>
<P>
The change will require the state to replace the <LOCATION>Ganesha</LOCATION> off-ramp signs on the 
<LOCATION>San Bernardino Freeway</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Robert DeLoach</PERSON>, city public works director, said the 
name change will take effect after the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Transportation</ORGANIZATION> 
authorizes and makes the new freeway signs, which could take as long as nine 
months. He said the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles County Fair Assn.</ORGANIZATION> will pay the cost of the sign 
changes, estimated at <MONEY>$13,000</MONEY> for the freeway and <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> for city streets. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06178190 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06178190 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  BUDGET; CAUSE; PROGRAM; DECREASE; SCHOOL; SAN-JOSE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  There won't be any layoffs in the Franklin-McKinley School District next year,
the district's board of trustees decided Tuesday in approving a 1991-'92
budget.;    But the district will have to cut $2.2 million from its $38
million general fund.;    Here is what the cuts, approved unanimously Tuesday,
will mean to the Franklin-McKinley community next year:  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SCHOOL DISTRICT AVOIDS LAYOFFS
FRANKLIN-MCKINLEY BOARD APPROVES OTHER CUTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     (check) Grants to encourage innovative teaching will be pared from <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>
to <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY>.;    (check) The instrumental music program will be cut by a third,
going from three to two teachers.;    (check) There will be fewer classes that
mix students from different grade levels, because such classes require fewer
students and cost more than regular classes.;    (check) Schools will have to
pay the full cost of copying various printed matter, rather than having part
of this cost absorbed by the district's print shop.;    The budget approved
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> is final, though adjustments could be made once the level of state
funding is determined.;    There was no public comment at <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s meeting.; 
  "We hope the state doesn't put us through any more traumas," said board
Chairwoman Lolita Foster.;    Unlike employees in other school districts,
those at Franklin-McKinley will be spared layoffs. For the time being, they
can thank the fact that the district is growing.;    Next year, predictions
call for the student population to grow by <PERCENT>2.5 percent</PERCENT>. The district hasn't
yet reached the point where the cost of educating the new students outstrips
extra state money they generate.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MAYA SURYARAMAN, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910626  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  245  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday June 26, 1991
00178190,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06087276 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06087276 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SCHOOL; CHANGE; FAMILY; PROTEST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Whether parents like it or not, schools of choice are here to stay.;    That
was the message the superintendent bore at a meeting the Franklin-McKinley
School District called to air a controversial choice proposal of its own.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  East Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  STONEGATE PLAN SPARKS FIERY DEBATE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Also ran in EX4/1  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Under the proposal, scheduled for a vote <DATE>April 9</DATE>, Franklin-McKinley would
add seventh and eighth grades to <ORGANIZATION>Stonegate School</ORGANIZATION>, an elementary school in one
of its quieter residential neighborhoods. Families who live in the district,
but have left its schools, would have first claim to admission.;    At <DATE>last
Tuesday</DATE>'s meeting in a standing-room-only board room, several parents assailed
the plan as a form of economic discrimination and a vote of no confidence
against the district's two current middle schools -- <PERSON>J.W. Fair</PERSON> and
Sylvandale.;    "The decision to have a kindergarten through eighth grade at
<LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION> means the administration admits to rampant accusations that Fair . .
. does not have a nurturing environment, that they do not have a rigorous
academic curriculum, that they are not safe," said <PERSON>Cora Tomalinos</PERSON>, active in
the <ORGANIZATION>Parent-Teacher Association</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Fair.</LOCATION>;    Franklin-McKinley board members
offered little comment at the emotionally charged meeting.;    However,
Superintendent <PERSON>Dolores Ballesteros</PERSON> and other supporters defended the plan as a
means of luring back students who've been lost to other schools, by offering
them more choices within Franklin-McKinley. They called the nationwide trend
toward schools of choice a tide that can't be turned back.;    "Choice is
here, my dears, whether you like it or not," <PERSON>Ballesteros</PERSON> told the audience of
more than 50 parents, teachers and community members who turned out despite
the rain. "My personal opinion is that a majority of our students are always
going to go to our two middle schools. But it's pretty darn important that we
get those kids who've left our district back.";    Opponents of the <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION>
proposal argued that they did not object to choice but thought the choice
should be available to all district parents.;    "I have nothing against a
seventh and eighth grade at <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Ruth Smith</PERSON>, whose son attends
<LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION>. But she said she opposed a plan that favors students not in the
district's schools.;    "Just because I can afford private school for my child
should not be a determining factor as to what school my child goes to," she
said.;    But first granting admission to a seventh and eighth grades at
<LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION> to students already in district schools would not raise any new
money for Franklin-McKinley. And that was the whole idea behind the <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION>
plan.;    District administrators came up with the plan earlier this year, in
an attempt to minimize looming budget cuts. Because Gov. <PERSON>Pete Wilson</PERSON> is
proposing suspending Proposition 98, the initiative that guarantees public
schools a minimum level of funding, Franklin-McKinley faces <MONEY>$2.5 million</MONEY> in
cuts next year, or <PERCENT>9 percent</PERCENT> of what it currently spends.;    They claim that
about 125 middle school students eligible to attend Franklin-McKinley's
schools are now going elsewhere. If these students could be wooed back, the
district would get <MONEY>$350,000</MONEY> in new state revenue. After paying teachers'
salaries and other costs, that would earn the district <MONEY>$85,000</MONEY>, staff members
estimate.;    However, <PERSON>Debbie Elliott</PERSON>, registrar at <ORGANIZATION>J.W. Fair</ORGANIZATION>, said the
district had yet to offer her proof that 125 middle school students have fled
the district. At a previous meeting, she claimed the number at Fair was closer
to 10.;    Other parents argued the district had no proof the <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION>
proposal would entice back the parents the district hopes to reach.;   
"They're not here, they're not voicing their opinions," said <PERSON>Dina Arata</PERSON>,
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy School Parent-Teacher Association.</ORGANIZATION>;    According to
<LOCATION>Ballesteros</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION> proposal has generated interest among private
school families who heard about it by word of mouth. However, administrators
do not plan to initiate any contacts until the <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION> proposal is approved,
she said.;    Under the <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION> proposal, first choice would go to students
who live anywhere in the district but go to private schools or public schools
outside the district. Next in line would be those whose parents say they are
considering such a move.;    Third would come students with special needs,
such as those attending the <PERSON>Slingerland</PERSON> program at <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION> for dyslexic
children. Ballesteros said the <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION> proposal would be a godsend to
parents with sixth-graders in that program who fear their children will be
easily lost in the larger middle school atmosphere.;    "I have watched these
children just be decimated by the whole schooling experience," finally to meet
success in <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Slingerland</LOCATION> program, <LOCATION>Ballesteros</LOCATION> said. Many of these
parents are "very concerned about leaving that success and having their
children 'mainstreamed,' " she said.;    <PERSON>Tina Nielson</PERSON>, a parent of a dyslexic
child who went from <LOCATION>Stonegate</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Slingerland</LOCATION> to a district middle school,
agreed.;    Now all seventh- and eighth-graders in Franklin-McKinley go to the
district's two middle schools, <PERSON>J.W. Fair</PERSON> and Sylvandale.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MAYA SURYARAMAN, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910327  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  821  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday March 27, 1991
00087276,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871125-0053 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief:
Danaher Corp.</HL>
<DD> 11/25/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MCBKA DHR
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Danaher Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it agreed to sell its <ORGANIZATION>Mohawk Rubber Co.</ORGANIZATION> unit to <ORGANIZATION>McKinley Allsopp Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in a leveraged buy-out for about <MONEY>$70 million</MONEY>. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION> unit will pay about <MONEY>$67 million</MONEY> in cash and <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> of preferred stock for the <LOCATION>Akron</LOCATION>, Ohio-based tire maker, according to <PERSON>Danaher</PERSON>, a maker of automotive and transportation products. 

   McKinley, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, an investment-banking firm, is a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Merchants Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a Boston-based bank-holding concern. 

   McKinley will assume <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> of Mohawk industrial-revenue bonds. 
Danaher will retain <LOCATION>Mohawk</LOCATION>'s tubular-products division. 

   Completion of the transaction is expected within 30 days, <PERSON>Danaher</PERSON> said. 

   In <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading yesterday, <PERSON>Danaher</PERSON> closed at <MONEY>$7.875</MONEY> a share, up <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY>. 

   (Revised WSJ <DATE>Nov. 27, 1987</DATE>)
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891030-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-30-89 0730EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv08   10-30 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv08,0529</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv08</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday, Nov. 8</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>, the <DATE>312th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 53
   One hundred years ago, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> became the 41st state.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1793</DATE>, the world-famous <ORGANIZATION>Louvre Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> opened its
doors to the public.
   In <DATE>1837</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Mount Holyoke Seminary</ORGANIZATION>, a college exclusively for
women, opened in <LOCATION>South Hadley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1904</DATE>, President <PERSON>Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON>, who had succeeded the
assassinated <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON>, was elected to a term in his own
right as he defeated Democrat <PERSON>Alton B. Parker</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1923</DATE>, <PERSON>Adolf Hitler</PERSON> launched his first attempt at seizing
power in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> with a failed coup in <LOCATION>Munich</LOCATION> that came to be known
as the <ORGANIZATION>Beer-Hall Putsch</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1932</DATE>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> defeated incumbent
<PERSON>Herbert Hoover</PERSON> for the presidency of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1933</DATE>, President <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> created, by executive order, the
<ORGANIZATION>Civil Works Administration</ORGANIZATION>, designed to create jobs for more than 4
million unemployed.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, the play ``Life with Father,'' based on the book by
<ORGANIZATION>Clarence Day</ORGANIZATION>, opened on Broadway.
   In <DATE>1942</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Operation Torch</ORGANIZATION> began during World War II as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and
British forces landed in <LOCATION>French North Africa</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1950</DATE>, during the Korean War, the first jet-plane battle took
place as <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Lt. <PERSON>Russell J. Brown</PERSON> shot down a North
Korean MiG-15.
   In <DATE>1960</DATE>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> Sen. <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> defeated Vice
President <PERSON>Richard M. Nixon</PERSON> in their quest for the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, <PERSON>Edward W. Brooke</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> became the first
black to be elected to the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> by popular vote.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, former movie actor <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> was elected governor
of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, <PERSON>Democrat W. Wilson Goode</PERSON> was elected the first black
mayor of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, and Democrat <PERSON>Martha Layne Collins</PERSON> was
elected the first female governor of <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, 11 people were killed when a bomb planted by the <ORGANIZATION>Irish
Republican Army</ORGANIZATION> exploded as crowds gathered in <LOCATION>Enniskillen</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Northern Ireland</LOCATION>, for a ceremony honoring <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s war dead.
   Ten years ago: Gov. <PERSON>Edmund G. ``Jerry'' Brown Jr.</PERSON> announced his
   Five years ago: The space shuttle Discovery blasted off into
orbit in pursuit of two wayward satellites that the astronauts
would retrieve in a daring salvage mission.
   One year ago: Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> won the presidential
election, defeating <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>.
   Today's birthdays: Actress <PERSON>Katharine Hepburn</PERSON> is 80. Actor <PERSON>Norman
Lloyd</PERSON> is 75. Actress <PERSON>June Havoc</PERSON> is 73. Actor-director <ORGANIZATION>Gene Saks</ORGANIZATION> is
68. Heart surgeon <PERSON>Dr. Christiaan Barnard</PERSON> is 67. Singer <PERSON>Patti Page</PERSON>
is 62. CBS newsman <ORGANIZATION>Morley Safer</ORGANIZATION> is 58. Actor <PERSON>Alain Delon</PERSON> is 54.
Singer <PERSON>Bonnie Raitt</PERSON> is 40. TV personality <PERSON>Mary Hart</PERSON> is 38.
Singer-songwriter <PERSON>Rickie Lee Jones</PERSON> is 35. Singer-actor <PERSON>Leif Garrett</PERSON>
is 28.
   Thought for today: ``When writers come, I find I'm talking all
the time, exchanging thoughts I haven't exchanged for some time. I
get stupid in solitude.'' _ <PERSON>Mary McCarthy</PERSON>, American author
(1912-1989).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880911-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-11-88 2356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-McKinleySeason     09-11 0260</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-McKinley Season,0268</SECOND>
<HEAD>McKinley Hosts Record Number of Climbers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN GALLAGHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A record 916 people tackled <ORGANIZATION>Mount
McKinley</ORGANIZATION> during the mountaineering season, says the <ORGANIZATION>National Park
Service</ORGANIZATION>, which is thinking about putting another outhouse on <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION>'s tallest mountain.
   Sanitation on the 20,320-foot mountain has been a growing
concern, said <PERSON>Ranger Roger Robinson</PERSON>.
   According to <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, 562 of the 916 people who registered to
climb McKinley this <DATE>spring</DATE> and <DATE>summer</DATE> reported reaching the summit.
   Last year, 817 climbers tested themselves against the mountain.
Only about a third finished the climb.
   Two people died climbing <DATE>McKinley this year</DATE>, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Don Henry</PERSON>, a 71-year-old <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> lawyer, this year became
the oldest person known to have made the top.
   Robinson attributed some of the increased mountaineering to
foreigners who decided attractive currency exchange rates made this
the year for the climb they had long wanted to make.
   Climbers began arriving in <DATE>April</DATE> and some waited until late
<DATE>July</DATE>, but most planned their trips for <DATE>May</DATE> and <DATE>June</DATE>.
   ``We're trying to get more people to come in <DATE>July</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>
said. Rangers attempting to deal with the environmental effects of
increased activity want use of the mountain to be spread out.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Park Service</ORGANIZATION> asks climbers to use plastic bags for human
waste and put the bags in crevasses, but officials don't know how
many comply, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> said. There are two latrines on <ORGANIZATION>McKinley</ORGANIZATION>, one
two-thirds of the way up the peak. The <ORGANIZATION>Park Service</ORGANIZATION> hopes to
install an outhouse at 17,000 feet next year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881031-0242 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-31-88 0818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv08   10-31 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv 08,0524</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv08</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Tuesday, Nov. 8</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>, the 313th day of <DATE>1988</DATE>. There are 53
days left in the year. This is Election Day.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On <DATE>Nov. 8, 1923</DATE>, <PERSON>Adolf Hitler</PERSON> launched his first attempt at
seizing power in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> with a failed coup in <LOCATION>Munich</LOCATION> that came to
be known as the ``Beer-Hall Putsch.'' Hitler was imprisoned for
high treason.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1793</DATE>, the world-famous <ORGANIZATION>Louvre Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> opened its
doors to the public for the first time.
   In <DATE>1837</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Mount Holyoke Seminary</ORGANIZATION>, a college exclusively for
women, opened in <LOCATION>South Hadley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1889</DATE>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> became the 41st state of the union.
   In <DATE>1904</DATE>, President <PERSON>Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON> _ who had succeeded the
assassinated <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON> _ was elected to a term in his own
right as he defeated Democrat <PERSON>Alton B. Parker</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1932</DATE>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Governor <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> defeated
incumbent <PERSON>Herbert Hoover</PERSON> for the presidency of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1933</DATE>, President <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> created, by executive order, the
<ORGANIZATION>Civil Works Administration</ORGANIZATION>, designed to create jobs for more than 4
million unemployed.
   In <DATE>1942</DATE>, Operation ``Torch'' began during World War II as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
and British forces landed in <LOCATION>French North Africa</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1950</DATE>, during the Korean War, the first jet-plane battle took
place as <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Lieutenant <PERSON>Russell J. Brown</PERSON> shot down a
North Korean MiG-15.
   In <DATE>1960</DATE>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> Senator <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> defeated Vice
President <PERSON>Richard M. Nixon</PERSON> in their quest for the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, <PERSON>Edward W. Brooke</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> became the first
black to be elected to the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> by popular vote.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, former movie actor <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> was elected governor
of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, the Voyager 1 space probe discovered the 15th moon of
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> while speeding to a rendezvous with the ringed planet.
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, the space shuttle Discovery blasted off into orbit in
pursuit of two wayward satellites the astronauts would retrieve in
a daring salvage mission.
   Ten years ago: Artist <PERSON>Norman Rockwell</PERSON>, whose work graced
hundreds of covers of the ``<DATE>Saturday</DATE> Evening Post,'' died at his
home in <LOCATION>Stockbridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, at age 84.
   Five years ago: Democrat <PERSON>W. Wilson Goode</PERSON> was elected the first
black mayor of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>; Democrat <PERSON>Martha Layne Collins</PERSON> was
elected the first female governor of <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>.
   One year ago: Eleven people were killed when a bomb planted by
the <ORGANIZATION>Irish Republican Army</ORGANIZATION> exploded as crowds gathered in
