<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911101-0009
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911101-0009.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Letters to the Editor:
   Restoring Bryant Park
   To Its Former Beauty
</HL>
<DATE>
11/01/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A15
</SO>
<LP>
   We read with interest Raymond Sokolov's article on the
demise of Jennifer Bartlett's design for South Gardens at
Battery Park City at Manhattan's southern tip (Leisure &amp;
Arts, Oct. 16). As landscape architects for the Battery Park
City Master Plan and Phases I and II of the esplanade, we
agree with your writer Patti Hagan's assessment that the
gardens were inappropriate and unworkable.
   We should like to point out, however, that Mr. Sokolov's
article may have given the mistaken impression that Lynden B.
Miller had done the redesign of Bryant Park, behind the New
York Public Library. The new restoration work is based upon
designs by Hanna/Olin Ltd., the landscape architectural firm
retained by the Bryant Park Restoration Corp. in 1985. Since
that time, Hanna/Olin has been the prime landscape
architectural consultant for all aspects of the redesign and
restoration of the park. Ms. Miller is designing and
implementing one aspect of that restoration, the perennial
gardens. She is an excellent plants person and garden
designer, and has done an exemplary job in the restoration of
the Central Park Conservatory Gardens and new plantings
within the Central Park Zoo.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The goal of opening up the system of walls and hedges
mentioned in the article is but one of several proposed by
our office in <DATE>1986</DATE> that are based in part on research
previously performed by <PERSON>William H. Whyte</PERSON> and the Project for
Public Spaces. These include: increased visibility into the
park, increased circulation within the park, enhancement of
the formal French landscape design, increased public seating
and increased security.
   <ORGANIZATION>Christopher N. Allen
   Senior Associate
   Hanna/Olin Ltd</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031390-0119 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 188964 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 13, 1990, Tuesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
752 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NEW LOOK FOR PARK PROPOSED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By FRANKI V. RANSOM, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A landscape architect has been hired by disgruntled merchants to remove the 
grass in <LOCATION>Horton Plaza Park</LOCATION> and replace it with flowers and shrubs to discourage 
loitering by drug dealers and panhandlers. 
</P>
<P>
But before work can begin, the plans must be approved by the <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION>, said 
<PERSON>Ed Foster</PERSON>, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Horton Plaza Park committee</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"The grass will be taken out and replaced with seasonal flowers, with hedges 
around the perimeter," Foster said. "We will suggest that plaques be put up to 
designate that the park, including the fountain, is a historical site." 
</P>
<P>
Foster said the estimated cost of the changes is <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY>, which will be covered 
by surrounding business owners and a vendor selected by the city to sell food 
and merchandise. If approved, renovations are expected to be completed in <DATE>July</DATE>, 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
"The city wanted to improve access to the park, which has become dominated by 
street people, drug sellers and users, panhandlers, and people sleeping on the 
grass," said <PERSON>Daro Quiring</PERSON>, maintenance coordinator of <ORGANIZATION>Center City Assn</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
To prove their point, the Horton Plaza management last year installed a video 
camera for five days in a window of <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s, the only store with an entrance 
on Broadway. The tape was edited into a 13-minute video that showed drug deals 
being made, people putting beer in the fountain, fights, and men urinating in 
cups, said <PERSON>Ron Oliver</PERSON>, executive vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Central City Assn</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Any time of the day you go to the park, you will see drug deals, and there is 
always someone with a bottle of booze," <PERSON>Oliver</PERSON> said. "It is against the law to 
drink in a public park. The homeless aren't the problem, although one may be 
the symptom of the other. Some homeless people are substance abusers." 
</P>
<P>
"We want to move these people out of the park and give it back to working 
people and to the city people who pay taxes," <PERSON>Foster</PERSON> said. "If we move them 
out, then they will be forced to go the centers that can provide help for their 
drug abuse." 
</P>
<P>
After merchants began complaining in <DATE>1988</DATE> that the problems were hurting their 
businesses, <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> Manager <PERSON>John Lockwood</PERSON> asked Quiring to establish a task force 
to seek ways to solve the problem. 
</P>
<P>
Steps were taken to improve park conditions. Police patrols were added. 
Planters were removed because they were being used as urinals. Benches were 
removed, but will be returned after the renovations. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Oliver</PERSON> said that, after the city removed the benches near the <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s 
entrance, pedestrian traffic increased <PERCENT>62%</PERCENT> in two weeks. He said that people 
would sit on the benches and intimidate customers entering the store. 
</P>
<P>
This is not the first redesign for the park. In <DATE>1984</DATE>, while the shopping center 
was being built and the park was closed, a community participation process 
worked with landscape architect <PERSON>Lawrence Halprin</PERSON>. His design ideas -- including 
moving the fountain to the northwest corner of the park -- were rejected, and 
the city restored the park to its historical condition. The <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 
architect said of the seven-month, <MONEY>$125,000</MONEY> project: "It is stupid to spend all 
this money to patch up a pipsqueak of a park." 
</P>
<P>
About a year ago, Quiring and representatives of <ORGANIZATION>Horton Plaza</ORGANIZATION>, the Park and 
<ORGANIZATION>Recreation Department</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Police Department</ORGANIZATION> and nearby businesses 
began meeting monthly, and they agreed about a month ago on redesigning the 
park. 
</P>
<P>
To encourage more people to use the park, the city plans to present art 
exhibitions, musical entertainment, and office luncheons, <PERSON>Quiring</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Although such activities may bring "desirable people to the park," <PERSON>Ron Buckley</PERSON>, 
a member of the city <ORGANIZATION>Historical Site Board</ORGANIZATION>, said he is unconvinced that the 
proposal is complete or effective by itself. 
</P>
<P>
"We have the same problems in parks across the nation," he said. "And you don't 
see them rushing to change their parks' designs to solve their problems. An 
increase of police presence and enforcement will solve the problem." 
</P>
<P>
Foster, who is also marketing director of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Grant Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, said that, in 
the past two months, the hotel has lost <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> in contracts. 
</P>
<P>
"Our clients don't feel safe, especially walking at night and going to 
restaurants in the area," he said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Linda Scott</PERSON>, 40, said that she sleeps in the park because there are not enough 
shelters to house all the homeless people in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"This is home to a lot of people," she said. We lay out here and don't hassle 
anyone. We pick up our own trash. This is our home. If they remove the grass, 
they will leave us lying on the dirt." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, A young man tethers himself to a tree near the fountain in Horton Plaza 
Park. ; Photo, An overview of grassy Horton Plaza Park, which attracts drug 
dealers and panhandlers who repel shoppers at the plaza, officials say. ; 
Photo, Although benches have been removed, people find alternative places to 
sit, or lie, at Horton Plaza Park. TERESA TAMURA / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030889-0085 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 27992 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 8, 1989, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 1; Column 3; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1197 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DIRK SUTRO / ARCHITECTURE: NATIONAL CITY'S CIVIC CENTER PLAN FALLS SHORT OF 
BEING ALL IT COULD 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Dirk Sutro 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
What is it that stands out about <ORGANIZATION>National City</ORGANIZATION>? The Mile of Cars? A few great 
period Victorians? Beyond these images, many of us who don't live there have 
only hazy -- and not always positive -- impressions. 
</P>
<P>
City officials hope to change this with a new civic center in the heart of 
town, scheduled to break ground later this year. Designed by <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 
architects <ORGANIZATION>Wheeler Wimer Blackman &amp; Associates</ORGANIZATION>, the government complex is 
expected to spur a new era of economic vitality and set a high architectural 
standard. 
</P>
<P>
The positive economic impact seems probable, but, as design goes, the project 
falls several notches below what it could have been, looking too much like a 
speculative office building and not enough like a prestigious, people-oriented 
new soul of a city. 
</P>
<P>
City officials invited about a dozen local firms to bid on the job -- not with 
designs, but prices -- and <PERSON>Wheeler Wimer Blackman</PERSON> was selected simply because 
its proposed fee of <PERCENT>4.85%</PERCENT> of the construction cost was less than half the next 
lowest bid, according to <PERSON>Arnold Peterson</PERSON>, the city's community development 
director. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Lacks Aggressive Pursuit 
</P>
<P>
Such a process seems exactly opposite of the best way to get a good design, 
which is to choose the architect with the best ideas, then make a financial 
agreement. <ORGANIZATION>National City</ORGANIZATION>'s approach lacks the aggressive pursuit of fresh 
designs displayed recently by the cities of <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oceanside</LOCATION>. Both held 
well-publicized civic center design competitions entered by local and national 
firms. 
</P>
<P>
Despite the criticism from some local architects that such contests are useful 
mostly for generating publicity, both resulted in top-notch designs. And, 
despite local griping that locals get overlooked when the field is open to 
national stars, that didn't prove true. A local firm (PAPA) did <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>'s new 
<ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION>, and the nationally known <ORGANIZATION>Charles Moore &amp; Urban Innovations Group</ORGANIZATION> 
got the civic center job in <LOCATION>Oceanside</LOCATION>. And, in <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>, the public was 
invited to comment on designs before the architect was selected. In <ORGANIZATION>National 
City</ORGANIZATION>, comments have been heard only since selection. 
</P>
<P>
The project could have taken a number of directions, since there was no strong 
historic or neighborhood context. Nearby are used-car lots, auto body shops and 
other uses in older buildings of little architectural impact. The site is a 
sloping pie slice of land immediately south of the existing '60s civic center 
with its entrance on <ORGANIZATION>National City Boulevard</ORGANIZATION>, at the edge of <ORGANIZATION>Kimball Park</ORGANIZATION>, a 
wonderful green open space with tremendous potential. 
</P>
<P>
The architects responded with a building of white precast concrete and green 
glass. A circular plaza joining the new structure to the old civic center is 
the best thing about the design. Aligned with <ORGANIZATION>Civic Center Drive</ORGANIZATION>, this outdoor 
space will offer a warm invitation to pedestrians and motorists. Made of 
concrete and stone, with plenty of benches and a piece of public art at its 
center, this promises to be a great people place. Also commendable is the way 
the architects tucked two levels of parking out of sight, below street level. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
An Inspired Move 
</P>
<P>
Locating the council chamber at the back of this plaza, as a sort of link 
between the old and new buildings, is also an inspired move. Symbolically, it 
puts the seat of important decisions in full public view. Architecturally, the 
council chamber is a low, minimalist building with a free-standing 
aqueduct-like arch out front that gives a sense of importance to the complex. 
Adjacent conference rooms cantilevered over the park will have dramatic views. 
</P>
<P>
But, although the plaza sets up a main entry axis that leads into the council 
chamber, the main entrance to the big, new building, the place of prime 
importance to the public, is off to the side. This is a missed opportunity to 
guide users into the complex. 
</P>
<P>
Not only does it lack a strong entry treatment, but also this main building 
will tower over everything else nearby, including the park, with its expanses 
of lawns, palm trees and children's play areas. At seven stories, it will rise 
to about 120 feet in a neighborhood of one- and two-story buildings. 
</P>
<P>
Apparently, the city feels the size is needed as a flexing of economic muscle, 
as a catalyst for a new wave of intense development. As such, the civic center 
is too harsh a gesture toward the people who will have to look up at its green 
glass walls from the park side. 
</P>
<P>
There could have been some great interaction here. A public plaza at the edge 
of the building would have eased the transition between park and civic center. 
Instead, the design turns a cold green shoulder on the park -- there's only one 
narrow entrance from this side, and nothing that engages pedestrians. The 
building, at least in model form, looks more like a <ORGANIZATION>Holiday Inn</ORGANIZATION> from the park. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Seeing Workers Inside 
</P>
<P>
The architects say the green glass will allow people outside to see workers 
inside, giving some sense of human interaction to the project. But those of us 
who have wandered through the Golden Triangle or downtown <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> know that 
when strong daylight bounces off colored glass, it becomes nearly opaque. 
</P>
<P>
From the street side, the feeling will be friendlier, but, aside from the 
circular plaza, with its weak link to the main building, not inviting. In terms 
of massing, the architects had the right idea, stepping three elongated 
cylinders back from the street. From some angles, though, the composition is 
awkward, and a cynic might compare the whole thing to a stack of Dough Boy 
pools topped by a giant carrying handle. 
</P>
<P>
Vertical white fins on the outsides of these rounded volumes do a nice job of 
breaking up the expanses of glass; they also pick up the vertical details on 
the old civic center next door. The city requested a building that would look 
different from all angles, and <PERSON>Wheeler Wimer Blackman</PERSON>'s design meets this 
requirement. 
</P>
<P>
Call it a pet peeve, but it's hard to imagine people working in <LOCATION>San Diego 
County</LOCATION> and not being able to get fresh air. Yet the new civic center will have 
operable windows only on the top floor. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
No Natural Light 
</P>
<P>
Inside, the architects have organized the new building's offices around an 
interior atrium space. But it won't rise to the top of the building, so it 
won't let in natural light. Surely, there would have been a way to locate this 
dramatic five-story volume such that it could tap some bona fide daylight. 
</P>
<P>
Against the exciting new civic centers developing in <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oceanside</LOCATION>, 
both fresh designs made with people in mind, <ORGANIZATION>National City</ORGANIZATION>'s looks weak. That's 
not for lack of size (60,000 square feet) or budget (<MONEY>$10.6 million</MONEY>), but simply 
because the building doesn't maximize the opportunity for a people-oriented 
government center that opens itself to the beautiful park next door. Perhaps a 
formal competition process, one oriented toward good designs and not the bottom 
line, would have led to more adequate solutions, or spurred these architects on 
to new highs. 
</P>
<P>
Other than the architects, the city apparently didn't ask for outside design 
advice. The result makes a strong case for not putting city officials without 
design experience completely in charge of such a significant project. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, An architect's model of the planned park area and new Civic Center for 
National City. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051090-0116 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 216784 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 10, 1990, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 1; Column 5; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1183 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ARCHITECTURE: SYMPOSIUM TALK GRIM, NOT HOPELESS; 
</P>
<P>
URBAN DESIGN: THE SHAPE OF U.S. CITIES WAS CAUSE FOR CONCERN AT THE UCSD 
CONFERENCE, AT WHICH THE SPEAKERS URGED THEIR COLLEAGUES TO PUT PEOPLE FIRST. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DIRK SUTRO 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It's time to give the cities back to the people. 
</P>
<P>
At <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s "Shaping the City" symposium in <LOCATION>UC San Diego</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Mandeville 
Auditorium</LOCATION>, four internationally respected speakers hit relentlessly on the 
problems that those who shape cities -- architects, urban designers, planners, 
developers, politicians -- must solve if our planet, our country and <LOCATION>Southern 
California</LOCATION> are to be saved from self-destruction. 
</P>
<P>
The day served as a powerful warning that all is not well in <LOCATION>U. S.</LOCATION> cities. The 
heavy dose of social awareness came as a pleasant surprise, considering that 
last year's inaugural symposium was dominated by bold, egotistical designs 
rather than proposed answers to society's ills. Both events were intended as 
the single most visible means of generating interest in the university's new 
architecture school, scheduled to open in the <DATE>fall of 1992</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
This year's special guests' greatest works harmonize with cities. Uniformly, 
they called upon architects to think first of the people who use their 
buildings, instead of the grand illusions they can create. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> architect <PERSON>Barton Myers</PERSON> is a professor at <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> and heads his own 
large architecture firm. 
</P>
<P>
Urban planner and architect <PERSON>Stanton Eckstut</PERSON> has become legendary in 
architectural circles in recent years for his people-oriented master plan for 
<ORGANIZATION>Battery Park City</ORGANIZATION>, a huge development on the edge of <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Developer <PERSON>James Rouse</PERSON> has built huge retail projects, often on waterfronts, 
that have helped revitalize such cities as <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. Having retired from development, he founded the <ORGANIZATION>Enterprise 
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1982</DATE>, which has the lofty goal of housing all of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s 
estimated 30 million poor people within the next generation. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> architect and urban planner <PERSON>Daniel Solomon</PERSON> has written design 
guidelines for cities in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>. Much of his work has 
reintroduced courtyards and other human features to multifamily housing. 
</P>
<P>
(An exhibition of the speakers' work will be in the campus' <LOCATION>Mandeville Gallery</LOCATION> 
through <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Introductions and transitions between speakers were handled by moderator 
<PERSON>Richard Bender</PERSON>, former dean of the <ORGANIZATION>College of Environmental Design</ORGANIZATION> at the 
master plan for <ORGANIZATION>UC San Diego</ORGANIZATION> and setting up the new architecture school. 
</P>
<P>
Bender set up the day's agenda by introducing two ways of viewing the 
contemporary city: "catastrophic" and "optimistic." 
</P>
<P>
"Recently, most of what they're building is junk," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Having acknowledged extensive problems in today's cities, including foul air, 
<PERSON>Bender</PERSON> said that, even so, he is not pessimistic. New technologies in biology, 
materials and social and ecological awareness, if properly applied, can serve 
as "the impetus for a new generation of innovation," he said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Myers</PERSON> called for a "regional collective effort" from <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION>, a big-picture government coalition to coordinate the future of <LOCATION>Southern 
California</LOCATION>'s 200 cities. He said impoverished state and local governments have 
foisted community planning on developers, and that some new form of regional 
government needs to take back this responsibility. 
</P>
<P>
He coined the term vacant lottery to refer to existing zoning and planning 
ordinances "so crude and blunt" that they have a minuscule chance of producing 
good cities. 
</P>
<P>
Bad planning, not density and rapid growth, is the problem, <PERSON>Myers</PERSON> said, noting 
that, during the <ORGANIZATION>19th Century</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> doubled its population gracefully in 10 
years. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Myers</PERSON> derided the <DATE>1960s</DATE> notion of urban renewal through scraping down blocks of 
small, old buildings and replacing them with block-size developments. He called 
for a blend of old and new, a move away from skyscrapers as the dominant 
downtown building type. Allowing more and smaller developments, instead of 
mega-block monsters, would let more people participate in making cities, and 
this diversity would be healthy. 
</P>
<P>
In his idealized vision, <ORGANIZATION>Southern California</ORGANIZATION> could become an efficient series 
of small- and medium-size towns, knitted together by more efficient 
transportation systems. 
</P>
<P>
Eckstut carried on the theme of designing cities with their users in mind, with 
wonderful public spaces and street-scapes, not grandstanding buildings, as the 
most important goal for architects and planners. 
</P>
<P>
An explanation of his work on <LOCATION>Battery Park City</LOCATION> underscored how <PERSON>Eckstut</PERSON> feels 
about architecture. He set out to make a "real city, not an attraction." Noting 
that the most successful buildings surrounding Central Park are the most 
retrained, he said, "New Yorkers rely on buildings which are not famous." 
</P>
<P>
Fifty percent of <LOCATION>Battery Park City</LOCATION>'s 92 acres were left as public open space, 
the most significant being a waterfront esplanade for pedestrians. Both cars 
and pedestrians move through the project; <PERSON>Eckstut</PERSON> believes urban vitality is 
enhanced by carefully mingling the two. 
</P>
<P>
Perhaps the strongest evidence of <ORGANIZATION>Eckstut</ORGANIZATION>'s success in creating a peaceful, 
homey urban environment at <LOCATION>Battery Park City</LOCATION> is the building designed by 
architect <PERSON>Charles Moore</PERSON>, who has a tendency toward cartoonish abstraction. 
</P>
<P>
"Most people are not moved by it," <PERSON>Eckstut</PERSON> said of <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s low-key <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 
building, "and that's good." 
</P>
<P>
Rouse, at 76 the senior expert at the conference, summed up his philosophy when 
he said that "it's not shape, form, space, structure. It's people we've got to 
be building for." 
</P>
<P>
His talk, the only one presented without the aid of slides, came off more as a 
moving sermon on social responsibility than the practical advice handed down by 
other speakers. 
</P>
<P>
Rouse quoted these figures to make his point about the low-income housing 
crisis: a <PERCENT>26%</PERCENT> annual increase in the nation's homeless, of which there are now 
perhaps 750,000; an estimated 42,000 people in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> sleeping in cars, 
garages and other makeshift shelters; abut 16 million American households 
surviving on less than <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> a year, half of which goes toward rent. 
</P>
<P>
"Things have got to change in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Rouse</PERSON> said. "The people at the bottom 
have to become more important than the people at the top." 
</P>
<P>
Solomon drew applause when he opened by describing the "problem of affluence, 
the poverty of what affluence has bought," the mediocrity of expensive new 
developments. 
</P>
<P>
Local notables on hand included <LOCATION>San Diego City</LOCATION> Councilman <PERSON>Ron Roberts</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San 
Diego City</LOCATION> Architect <PERSON>Mike Stepner</PERSON>, developer <PERSON>Ernest Hahn</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Centre City 
Development Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Executive Vice President <PERSON>Pam Hamilton</PERSON> and home builder <PERSON>Tawfiq 
Khoury</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
At day's end, <PERSON>Bender</PERSON> led the four featured speakers through a joint discussion 
with the new dean of the <ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION> architecture school, <PERSON>Adele Naude Santos</PERSON>, who was 
sitting in to glean ideas for the new school. 
</P>
<P>
Santos stressed her commitment to making the school a "think tank" for solving 
social problems, and an active part of the community, rather than an "elitist, 
hermetic school sitting on top of the mesa." 
</P>
<P>
One left with some hope that, during the '90s, more architects will use their 
talents to address pressing urban problems they often ignored during the '80s. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, From left, architects James Rouse, Stanton Eckstut, Barton Meyers and 
Daniel Solomon. SEAN M. HAFFEY / For The Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011289-0018 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 4171 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 12, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 1; Column 5; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
946 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ARCHITECTURE: HOPE SEEMS INSPIRED IN SEAPORT PLAN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DIRK SUTRO 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
This city has been arched, peach-stuccoed and tiled to death in the quest for 
the elusive "regional style." Awkward combinations of these elements are 
marching across the county like so many Stepford wives. 
</P>
<P>
The planned expansion of <LOCATION>Seaport Village</LOCATION> could rise above it. 
</P>
<P>
Designed by <ORGANIZATION>San Diego's Hope Architects &amp; Engineers</ORGANIZATION>, this new cousin of the 
existing Disneyland-style tourist mall will take its cues from the old police 
station on Market Street, a large part of which will form the heart of the new 
project. 
</P>
<P>
Completed in the late <DATE>1930s</DATE>, the station was one of the last projects from the 
offices of <ORGANIZATION>Quayle Brothers &amp; Treganza</ORGANIZATION>. Some of its ornate Spanish Colonial 
details -- especially on two entry arches and a tower -- make it one of the 
finer remaining <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> buildings from the latter end of a romantic period in 
local architecture that began in <DATE>1915</DATE> with the richly detailed buildings in 
<LOCATION>Balboa Park</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The big question is this: Can we trust the <LOCATION>Seaport Village</LOCATION> developers, led by 
<PERSON>M. B. Taubman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lee Stein</PERSON>, to come through with the commitment the project 
deserves? 
</P>
<P>
Such a commitment will mean dollars, probably tens of thousands, to give the 
project the detailing it needs. Otherwise, it will join the ranks of the local 
Stepford family, just another drone. 
</P>
<P>
Hope, one of the biggest local firms, isn't an obvious choice for the project. 
Its work, spanning 60 years in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, has generally tended in recent years 
toward large, often disappointing corporate build 
</P>
<P>
ings. <ORGANIZATION>First National Bank</ORGANIZATION>, formerly <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Centre</ORGANIZATION>, at <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> and B Streets, 
is one example. Its greatest single shortcoming is its failure to involve 
pedestrians at the street level, a problem that would be even more intolerable 
at people-oriented <LOCATION>Seaport Village</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But, with the Seaport addition, the firm made a conscious decision to steer 
clear of a slick, easy solution. 
</P>
<P>
At Hope's downtown offices recently, project architect <PERSON>Bruce Green</PERSON> brought out 
the firm's initial design, an attempt to contrast, rather than work with, the 
police station. 
</P>
<P>
"Originally, I thought we needed a glass pavilion or something out front, like 
<PERSON>I. M. Pei</PERSON> added to the <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION>," Green said, pointing out just such a bauble. 
But, during four years of design work, the approach shifted to one of 
harmonizing with the police buildings. 
</P>
<P>
The project looks inviting. Arched police station entries to be preserved on 
Market and <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Highway</ORGANIZATION> will send a romantic call to pedestrians. A new 
entry on <ORGANIZATION>Kettner Boulevard</ORGANIZATION> near Market (soon to become the realigned Harbor 
Drive) appears to mirror the existing architecture in scale and form, but <ORGANIZATION>Green</ORGANIZATION> 
said the detailing has not yet been selected. 
</P>
<P>
You get the feeling that <ORGANIZATION>Green</ORGANIZATION>, who has historic-preservation background, would 
love to see authentic plaster-cast details applied. But such quality is rare in 
<DATE>1988</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
As for the inside of the project, it will emphasize shops and restaurants 
grouped around a large L-shaped courtyard the developers call their "Night 
Court." For one cover charge, patrons can do justice to a variety of 
restaurants and night spots, including a "jazz and blues club." 
</P>
<P>
Like the exterior decoration, the design details of the interior shop facades 
are still up for grabs. A soon-to-be-hired consultant will work with Hope on 
guidelines here. Inappropriate materials such as large commercial aluminum 
windows should be written out of the project. 
</P>
<P>
Compliments go to the developers for including people-oriented elements in 
their project, such as a 300-seat open-air amphitheater, a new water's-edge 
<PERSON>Ferris</PERSON> wheel and the wonderful <DATE>1890</DATE> Looff carrousel, to be moved to a central 
location next to a new, man-made pond. 
</P>
<P>
What's happening along the waterfront has as much to do with the spaces between 
buildings as with the buildings themselves. 
</P>
<P>
The realignment of <ORGANIZATION>Harbor Drive</ORGANIZATION> is just part of waterfront plans that also 
include the potentially stunning "linear park," now being created by landscape 
designers <PERSON>Peter Walker</PERSON> and <PERSON>Martha Schwartz</PERSON>, with local architects <ORGANIZATION>Austin Hansen 
Fehlman Group</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In fact, this long, narrow strip of landscaping and art, which will tie 
pedestrian, auto and trolley circulation neatly together, will extend down the 
new Harbor Drive nearly to the edge of the Seaport addition. 
</P>
<P>
Green said thick landscaping placed to camouflage the new parking garage and an 
extra-wide pedestrian strip at this corner will help relate <LOCATION>Seaport Village</LOCATION> to 
the linear park. 
</P>
<P>
Water figures prominently in the expansion. Taubman, founder and chairman of 
<LOCATION>Seaport Village</LOCATION>, has called the theme "water, water everywhere," including 
fountains and the new central pond by the carrousel. 
</P>
<P>
As for tying the project to the existing <LOCATION>Seaport Village</LOCATION>, the older complex 
doesn't have a thing to do with this '80s Spanish Colonial revisited, and it's 
a bit too theme-park-oriented anyhow. So scale, not style, will link the new 
Seaport to the old. The back of the addition will include smaller-massed 
buildings that open onto the pedestrian space behind it. 
</P>
<P>
Several fine old palms ring the police station, both singles and impressive 
clusters. Landscape architects <ORGANIZATION>ONA Inc.</ORGANIZATION> have recommended keeping them, which 
makes both historic and economic sense. According to <ORGANIZATION>Green</ORGANIZATION>, replacement 
groupings of six or so mature trees could cost <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
There are several good signs here. With this project, <ORGANIZATION>Hope</ORGANIZATION> has a chance to set 
an example for the other giant <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> architectural firms. If the architects 
are sticklers for detail, and the developers don't balk at spending for 
quality, the project's completion sometime in <DATE>1992</DATE> could prove that it is 
possible for corporate-size architecture machines to turn out sensitive, 
human-scale projects. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Drawing, The planned addition to Seaport Village will rise around the old 
police station on Market Street. Original village is in background. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042789-0139 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 49593 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 27, 1989, Thursday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 14; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
658 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DESIGNS FOR LOW-INCOME HOUSING -- WITH CHILD CARE IN MIND 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By R. DANIEL FOSTER, Foster is a regular contributor to Valley View. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The future of child-care facilities in the <LOCATION>San Fernando Valley</LOCATION> may be in the 
hands of 11 young architects from the <ORGANIZATION>Southern California Institute of 
Architecture</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The students recently gathered at the <ORGANIZATION>Warner Center Marriott</ORGANIZATION> to showcase their 
innovative designs for low-income family housing, which may be pooled and 
eventually built on a 7.8-acre site in <LOCATION>Canoga Park</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Integral to their designs are housing and commercial spaces that are tied 
together, providing a mini-community where residents would live and work -- and 
where child care would be available for their children. 
</P>
<P>
Instructors within ARCH (Architectural Response to <ORGANIZATION>Community Housing</ORGANIZATION>), a design 
studio at the school that promotes low-income housing, have guided the students 
for 15 weeks as they have drawn and built prototypes of their communities. Also 
advising the students are <ORGANIZATION>L.A. Family Housing Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which has developed 
affordable family housing for low-income working families for six years and the 
2-year-old Center for <ORGANIZATION>Childhood Creativity</ORGANIZATION>, run by <ORGANIZATION>Cal State Northridge</ORGANIZATION> in 
<ORGANIZATION>Warner Center</ORGANIZATION>, which creates and implements innovative child-care solutions. 
</P>
<P>
"I told the students of the importance for homelike environments," said <PERSON>Dianne 
Philibosian</PERSON>, project director of the childhood center. "We've begun to focus on 
providing spaces, but not what happens in those spaces. I tried to communicate 
that," she said, adding that one particular architect really understood her 
concepts. Philibosian walked to a scale model of The Village, designed by <PERSON>Robin 
Morris</PERSON>, a fourth-year student at the architectural institute. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Center of Model 
</P>
<P>
At the center of the model is a child-care center fronted by a park. Fanning 
out from the facility are commercial zones, including professional offices, 
restaurants and crafts stores for children. Residential units, as in all the 
students' designs, are above retail spaces. Families living in the housing 
units, which curve in a semi-circle around the child-care center, could easily 
look out on the park and center should they want to see their children at play. 
</P>
<P>
"I was thinking of the playful aspects of children when I designed the space," 
said <PERSON>Morris</PERSON>, 32, who lives in <LOCATION>Redondo Beach</LOCATION>. A pyramid-shaped, stepped fountain 
with mini waterfalls is near the child-care center, and water also flows around 
a circular entrance leading up from the underground parking facility and 
through the tree-lined park. A bridge spans <LOCATION>Canoga Avenue</LOCATION>, depositing visitors 
in the project's first retail zone, which contains clothing, video and 
convenience stores. 
</P>
<P>
"Children are people, and one needs to be in touch with them, rather than 
applying our adult concepts of what a children's area should look like," 
<PERSON>Philibosian</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"The whole idea behind this development is that you can work, live and play in 
one tight community," <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"The designs are very unlike <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Arnold Stalk</PERSON>, executive director of 
<ORGANIZATION>L.A. Family Housing Corp.</ORGANIZATION> "But that doesn't mean it won't work. It's an attempt 
to solve a multitude of problems with one development -- affordable housing 
needs, economic development and child care. 
</P>
<P>
"Land is so scarce and expensive now that you're going to see more residential 
and commercial development." 
</P>
<P>
Stalk said residents could lease commercial space or entire families could be 
sponsored by a business while their children are cared for nearby. Families 
would stay in the community for a maximum of five years until they were 
established financially to move on to their own enterprises. 
</P>
<P>
Stalk, ARCH and others are negotiating to purchase the land from the <ORGANIZATION>Los 
Angeles Department of Water and Power</ORGANIZATION>. Should the project be realized, the 
students will pool their ideas under the supervision of established architects 
in the area. 
</P>
<P>
"Part of the reason I designed the project was to realize and discover the 
child within me," <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said. "As we grow older, we grow full of logic. The 
playful aspect gets denied." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Sidebar 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-13590</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CGMA3ABEFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920713
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 JUL 92 / Arts: New York's oasis of the park - Architecture
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By COLIN AMERY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
It's summertime in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and the heat is driving you crazy. The streets
are steaming, the hydrants are streaming and only the oasis of the park can
help to keep you sane. There cannot be another city in the world where a
park is of such importance. It is like <ORGANIZATION>St. Mark</ORGANIZATION>'s Square in <LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION> - an
outdoor drawing room. But it is so much more than that. It really is rus in
urbe and it was intended to be by its nineteenth century creators.
When the Street Commissioners of <DATE>1807</DATE> impressed the island of <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> with
an immovable grid, they felt that the miles of waterfront around the
shoreline would be enough to give the city breathing space and plenty of
room for exercise and recreation. They were wrong. Commerce and the piers
took up the waterfront and soon the highways, the bridges, the entries and
exits from the tunnels filled up the desireable waterside places. There was
a need for a lung.
It was not until <DATE>1858</DATE> that the city held a competition for the <LOCATION>Central Park</LOCATION>.
It was won by a writer, <ORGANIZATION>Frederick Law Olmsted</ORGANIZATION> and an architect, <ORGANIZATION>Calvert
Vaux</ORGANIZATION>. Their scheme was called 'The <ORGANIZATION>Greensward</ORGANIZATION>'.
There was something very original about their plan at the time. It was
nothing to do with the classical ideas of the <DATE>eighteenth century</DATE> but it was
deeply romantic and picturesque. It was to look like untamed nature but
every inch of it was to be planned and designed. It was also to have whole
areas where the denizens of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> could promenade in a more formal manner
 -taking the air in a leisurely way - long before the advent of jogging and
manic movement. The Park was also to house some cultural activities and
among the rustic arbours and fountains music would be played and civilised
pleasures provided.
Many of the wishes of the founders of the park have been fulfilled over the
years. But there was a time when the joys of Central Park were overshadowed
by its dangers. In the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and <DATE>1970s</DATE> vandals and criminals began to ruin
the Prk systematically. Only in the recent past has the <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Parks Department</ORGANIZATION>, with the considerable help of the private fund raising
group known as The <LOCATION>Central Park Conservancy</LOCATION>, been able to reverse the
decline and begin the restoration of much of the park to the original
design.
One of the areas that has been the subject of much restoration work and
expenditure has been the park's mall, which stretches from 66th Street to
72nd Street on the east side of the park. An area just to the east of this
mall is known as the Concert Grounds and here stands the remarkably handsome
and appropriate <ORGANIZATION>Naumburg Band</ORGANIZATION> shell - a gift to the <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in <DATE>1921</DATE>
from a music enthusiast, <PERSON>Elkan Naumburg</PERSON>. The limestone band shell resembles
a giant ruined portion of a Roman building and its great coffered half-domed
ceiling, while looking marvellous also projects the sound of an orchestra or
band perfectly. The shell is inscribed 'Presented to the <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
and its Music Lovers', and it is not just a handsome object in the park but
also a monument to the generosity of a private citizen. It has hosted
concerts by <ORGANIZATION>Duke Ellington</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Percy Grainger</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sousa</PERSON>, <PERSON>Irving Berlin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Benny
Goodman</PERSON> and many others. It is, amazingly, to be demolished by <ORGANIZATION>The Parks
Department</ORGANIZATION>.
The row over this perverse decision has grown and grown and complex legal
proceedings are underway to try and save this part of the history of <LOCATION>Central
Park</LOCATION>. If it is demolished it will be a great loss and it is hard to
understand the reasons for its removal. These arguments are that it is
'obsolete for today's amplified concerts' and the <ORGANIZATION>Central Park Conservancy</ORGANIZATION>
are opposed to permanent concert sites in the park. I would have thought
that many musicians are anxious to play in 'natural' acoustic conditions
today, and that there is more than enough amplification of sound in a city
like <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. The other main argument seems to be that the shell was not
part of Olmsted's original design and that it partially blocks a view from
the newly restored <LOCATION>Wisteria Pergola</LOCATION>. The other argument seems very spurious
 -that the band shell attracts the homeless, drug dealers and vandalism. As
one opponent of the demolition has written, 'if that argument is used in
favour of the demolition of historic buildings then <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> should start
with the demolition of <ORGANIZATION>Grand Central Station</ORGANIZATION> and work down.'
The argument over the demolition of an agreeable, useful and important
monument in <LOCATION>Central Park</LOCATION> demonstrates how vulnerable historic buildings are.
I suspect that the 'improvers' of Central Park who give generously of time
and money think that they are doing the right thing.
But in fact they are demonstrating the fallibility those who believe in
'authentic restoration'. As the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> architect <PERSON>Robert Stern</PERSON> has written:
'Central Park is no longer a 'pure' work of Olmsted and <PERSON>Vaux</PERSON>'s. It is a
palimpsest with many layers . . . History demands that we take a longer
view, preserving all the best elements of the past, which is invariably more
complex and varied than simply returning the clock to a particular moment
will allow. The past should not be erased.'
How right he is. But will politicians see the subtlety of his point or will
they wantonly destroy one of the survivors of the <ORGANIZATION>City Beautiful Movement</ORGANIZATION>?
The band shell may be a small object in a great city, but the fight over its
future concentrates the mind on the complex history of our surroundings. It
is too easy to wipe out the generosity of the past and too easy to believe
in the false gods of 'authentic restoration' to remove anything that may get
in their way.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 9
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122189-0057 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 151551 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 21, 1989, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 22; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1198 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ARCHITECTURE REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
NO COHERENCE IN CENTER PLAN; 
</P>
<P>
DESIGN: THE SECOND PHASE OF ESCONDIDO'S CIVIC CENTER COMPLEX APPEARS TO HAVE 
ATTRACTIVE OUTDOOR SPACES, BUT OTHER ELEMENTS APPEAR PROBLEMATIC. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DIRK SUTRO 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ESCONDIDO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The problem of designing a large theater has challenges similar to those in 
creating a convention center: A boxy large space must somehow be concealed 
within a graceful shell. 
</P>
<P>
Architect <PERSON>Arthur Erickson</PERSON>, using bold repetitive forms in concrete, has made 
the gigantic new <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Convention Center a fine piece of design. His 
excellent exterior detailing makes this building attractive to those arriving 
by car or foot. It's a landmark project for downtown <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Architects <ORGANIZATION>Moore Ruble Yudell</ORGANIZATION> have not been nearly as successful in their 
design of the second phase of <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>'s Civic Center, a <MONEY>$55.4-million</MONEY> complex 
that will include 1,500- and 400-seat theaters for stage productions, an arts 
complex and a community meeting center. 
</P>
<P>
The final design for the project, to be built in <LOCATION>Grape Day Park</LOCATION> downtown, site 
of the new <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> completed in <DATE>1988</DATE>, was unanimously approved by the 
<ORGANIZATION>Escondido City Council</ORGANIZATION> this month. The city hopes to break ground next <DATE>fall</DATE>, 
with completion expected in <DATE>1993</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Although the architects have created wonderful outdoor spaces, the bulky 
100-foot-tall "fly tower," which houses the mechanical equipment above the 
stage, sticks out like a sore thumb, unbroken by architectural detailing or 
other visual devices that could make it attractive. Other potential problems 
include jarring combinations of roof treatments and a confusing variety of 
window and wall treatments used in an attempt to break down the mass of he main 
theater. 
</P>
<P>
There is also a possibility that the Civic Center complex will have 
insufficient daytime attractions such as food stands or recreation 
opportunities to make the park a success as a people place. 
</P>
<P>
Months of refining should have resulted in a well-composed treatment of the big 
box that will house the necessary stage equipment over the main theater; at 100 
feet, the "fly tower" will be the Civic Center's most noticeable feature. 
</P>
<P>
Instead, the theater, at least as depicted in model form, will sit hard by 
<LOCATION>Escondido Boulevard</LOCATION>, its bulk unbroken by details that could tie it to the rest 
of the Civic Center complex. Its flat roof, for instance, sets it oddly apart 
from the pavilion and gable roofs used on the other of the new buildings. 
</P>
<P>
Project architect <PERSON>Renzo Zecchetto</PERSON> said that softening the impact of this 
looming box was the architects' single toughest challenge. 
</P>
<P>
The designers elected to place most of the design interest at the middle level 
of this and the other buildings in the second phase of the Civic Center 
project. Groups of small windows, varied wall angles and assorted architectural 
detailing will break these facades into forms a human being can get close to 
without feeling overwhelmed. 
</P>
<P>
City officials and community leaders have expressed a desire for some softening 
of the theater's stark appearance. Suggestions include a screening wall in 
front of the building's prominent northern face, detailing on the building wall 
itself or a system of vine-covered trellises and palm trees. 
</P>
<P>
Zecchetto said the architects favor the last approach, partly because it is 
most economical. 
</P>
<P>
At this stage of the design game, though -- when at least a year has already 
gone into the project -- one expects a more polished design solution. 
</P>
<P>
Other aspects of the architecture are also disappointing. The choice of roof 
forms is puzzling. Some roofs will have the traditional pitched form, while 
others, as on a few small towers, will be flat. The flat towers don't always 
merge well with the slanted roofs nearby. It is difficult, though, to make a 
final pronouncement on these. The material has not been chosen, and these could 
make the actual buildings look much different from cardboard models. Flat tiles 
or a seamed metal are among the choices being considered. 
</P>
<P>
There is other evidence the architects did not arrive at a consistent, coherent 
design vision: Pedestrians will not notice from the ground level, but there is 
something jarring about the way the big theater's northern wall drops from a 
flat roof on top to a slanted roof above the first floor, with twin buttresses 
flying above it. 
</P>
<P>
It is at the level of the pedestrian, in fact, that the architects appear to 
have done their strongest design work. 
</P>
<P>
All along, the design of the entire Civic Center complex, including <PERSON>City Hall</PERSON>, 
has been driven by its situation in the 17-acre <LOCATION>Grape Day Park</LOCATION>, a huge open 
space in the heart of the city. The intention was always to keep this setting 
park-like, even with the addition of several buildings. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Moore Ruble Yudell</ORGANIZATION> put their buildings at the edges of the property, near the 
streets, preserving the interior as open space. A walk through the complex 
should prove to be an interesting stroll among the various plazas and 
courtyards. 
</P>
<P>
The main entrance to the new theater complex will be off <LOCATION>Escondido Boulevard</LOCATION> on 
the western edge of the project. Here, a wide plaza of slightly ascending 
levels will lead pedestrians in between the large theater to the north and the 
nearby community theater, set behind a pergola at <LOCATION>Escondido Boulevard</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Valley Parkway</LOCATION>. The pergolas, along with many rows of trees, will soften the 
experience of entering the complex. 
</P>
<P>
The pergolas here and elsewhere are the same sort of vine-covered 
column-and-trellis walkways that became the trademark of legendary <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 
architect <PERSON>Irving Gill</PERSON> early in this century. Some modern architects even use 
arches like the ones <PERSON>Gill</PERSON> favored. 
</P>
<P>
In the Civic Center project, every building has at least one courtyard related 
to it, and most have several. Some are intended to be used for various 
gatherings. A courtyard off the back of the smaller theater could, for example, 
become an outdoor performance space, <PERSON>Zecchetto</PERSON> said. He said that he hopes that 
the city will eventually have the money to add doors to the back of this 
theater's stage so that it can open onto the courtyard. 
</P>
<P>
Aside from the architecture, a larger concern has to do with the programming of 
the Civic Center complex -- the kinds of uses selected for this public park. 
The <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> and theaters will dominate the site, with the community meeting 
building and arts complex as secondary uses. What will the new complex offer 
the person who comes to the park in search of a recreational or cultural 
experience during daylight hours? 
</P>
<P>
A library might have been a good choice, but the city just built a new one 
three blocks away at 2nd Avenue and <ORGANIZATION>Kalmia Street</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
There are now no concrete plans for the kinds of things that make Balboa Park 
so successful: food pushcarts, small cafes, and many 
</P>
<P>
choices of exhibitions, performances, films and museums. 
</P>
<P>
Both Zecchetto and <PERSON>Rolf Gunnarson</PERSON>, assistant executive director of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Escondido Community Development Commission</ORGANIZATION>, say they have considered such 
ideas. A small food outlet and bar in the lobby of the larger theater might be 
open during daylight hours, and a kitchen in the community meeting building 
could be used to produce food for park visitors as well as for those attending 
meetings at the building. Food vendors are also a possibility. 
</P>
<P>
These kinds of people-oriented things will be essential to animating the 
well-planned outdoor spaces, which will undoubtedly be the new complex's 
triumph. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Model shows plans for the second phase of the Civic Center complex to be 
built at a cost of $55.4 million in Grape Day Park in Escondido. DON BARTLETTI 
/ Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Art Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-5675</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DK2DYACBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931129
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  29 NOV 93 / Arts: A field of the highest quality - Colin Amery reviews
three further finalists for the FT's architecture prize to be awarded today
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By COLIN AMERY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
We are almost there. Tomorrow's FT will publish the name of this year's
winner of the <ORGANIZATION>Financial Times Architecture Award</ORGANIZATION>. He or she will receive
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s most independent and highly regarded architectural prize at a
luncheon in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> today. The long period of judging and visiting is over
and there will be an opportunity in tomorrow's paper for an assessment of
the significance of the award and of the state of architecture in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>
today.
Previous articles have looked at five of the eight shortlisted schemes:
<LOCATION>Stansted Airport</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Cranfield Library</ORGANIZATION> by Sir <PERSON>Norman Foster</PERSON> and Partners;
and <ORGANIZATION>Bracken House</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Schlumberger Research</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Bedfont Lakes</ORGANIZATION> (IBM) Business
Park by <PERSON>Michael Hopkins</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Partners</ORGANIZATION>. The remaining three schemes on the
shortlist represent three very different types of building. The Queen's
Stand at <ORGANIZATION>Epsom Racecourse</ORGANIZATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Richard Horden Associates</ORGANIZATION>; the new car park in
<LOCATION>Chichester</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>Birds Portchmouth</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Russum</PERSON>; and <ORGANIZATION>Winchester City</ORGANIZATION> offices
designed by the <ORGANIZATION>Hampshire County Architects</ORGANIZATION> department.
Epsom clearly needed an elegant new stand that could comfortably house the
crowds on <ORGANIZATION>Derby</ORGANIZATION> day as well as provide a centre for functions and
entertainments throughout the year. The choice of <PERSON>Richard Horden</PERSON> and
<ORGANIZATION>Associates</ORGANIZATION> as architects was a brave one. The practice is known for its
structural and engineering expertise and its experimental approach to
building technology. The client, <ORGANIZATION>United Racecourses</ORGANIZATION>, has, by choosing a
radical approach that is both refined and practical, acquired a new stand
that is the acme of contemporary design.
The problem of new buildings in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s cathedral cities has been tackled
in two very distinctive and different ways in <LOCATION>Winchester</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chichester</LOCATION>.
Both cities have mixed reputations when it comes to new architecture, but it
is fair to say that both places take great care about any additions to their
ancient fabric.
Winchester has a county architects department that is one of the most
distinguished in the country. Under the direction of <PERSON>Colin Stansfield-Smith</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Hampshire</LOCATION> has acquired a high reputation, particularly for its new schools
and other educational buildings. The site of the new offices, which are
partly occupied by the architects' department, is a typical, tight
Winchester street, but one that had been spoiled in earlier days by the
erection of a large multi-storey car park. The new offices try to be both
modern and vernacular, adopting a traditional pitched roofline but lighting
the offices through a completely glazed wall. This gives it the appearance
of working in an atrium, except that it has a remarkable view over the city.
An agreeable courtyard garden designed around an existing tree is another
feature of the scheme, adding to its overall picturesque qualities. The
pavement passed close to one side of the new block and this facade has been
enlivened by the presence of specially commissioned stained glass windows.
Chichester had a problem. The city is keen on traffic management and car
parking is a crucial element of any traffic scheme. The decision to build a
large, new multi-storey car park on the edge of the city centre but outside
the old city walls was a controversial one. Chichester decided to commission
a relatively unknown young practice, Birds Portchmouth and <PERSON>Russum</PERSON>, and the
resulting building is extraordinary in many ways.
The architects decided not to diminish the scale of the whole operation but
to make the car park look like a new set of city defences. The length of the
building is broken up by the fat, circular staircase towers which are built
of perforated brick work. Once you have parked your car the journey from the
car park into the city centre takes you on a series of high level pedestrian
bridges from which you can view the ancient town.
Even in these recessionary years the quality of the best of British
architecture is very high. Choosing a winner for the FT award will not be
easy.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8712 Architectural Services.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 15
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121589-0045 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 148823 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 15, 1989, Friday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 1; Column 5; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1308 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ARCHITECTURE: CHANGES NEEDED IN ESCONDIDO CIVIC CENTER'S PHASE TWO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DIRK SUTRO 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ESCONDIDO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The problem of designing a large theater has challenges similar to those in 
creating a convention center: A large, boxy space must somehow be concealed 
within a graceful shell. 
</P>
<P>
Architect <PERSON>Arthur Erickson</PERSON>, using repetitive, bold forms in concrete, has made 
the gigantic new <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Convention Center a fine piece of design. His 
excellent exterior detailing makes this building attractive to those arriving 
by car or foot. 
</P>
<P>
It's a landmark downtown project for downtown <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Architects <ORGANIZATION>Moore Ruble Yudell</ORGANIZATION> haven't been nearly as successful in their design 
of the second phase of <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>'s Civic Center, a <MONEY>$55.4-million</MONEY> complex that 
includes 1,500- and 400-seat theaters for stage productions. 
</P>
<P>
The final design for the project, to be built in <LOCATION>Grape Day Park</LOCATION> downtown, which 
includes the new <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> completed in <DATE>1988</DATE>, was unanimously approved by the 
<ORGANIZATION>Escondido City Council</ORGANIZATION> last week. 
</P>
<P>
The city hopes to break ground next <DATE>fall</DATE>, with completion expected in <DATE>1993</DATE>. In 
addition to the theaters, the project will have an arts complex and a community 
meeting center. 
</P>
<P>
Although the architects have created wonderful outdoor spaces, the bulky 
100-foot-tall "fly tower," which houses the mechanical equipment above the 
stage, sticks out like a sore thumb, unbroken by architectural detailing or 
other visual devices that could make it attractive. 
</P>
<P>
Other potential problems include jarring combinations of roof treatments and a 
confusing variety of window and wall treatments used in an attempt to break 
down the main theater's mass. There is also 
</P>
<P>
a possibility that the Civic Center complex will have insufficient daytime 
attractions -- food stands, recreation and other forms of enjoyment -- to make 
the park a success as a people place. 
</P>
<P>
Months of refining should have resulted in a well-composed treatment of the big 
box that will house the necessary stage equipment over the main theater; at 100 
feet, this "fly tower" will be the Civic Center's tallest, most massive 
feature. 
</P>
<P>
Instead, the theater, at least as depicted in model form, will sit hard by 
<LOCATION>Escondido Boulevard</LOCATION>, bulk unbroken by details that could tie it to the rest of 
the Civic Center complex -- it's flat roof setting it oddly apart from the 
pavilion or gable roofs used on the rest of the new buildings. 
</P>
<P>
Project architect <PERSON>Renzo Zecchetto</PERSON> admitted that softening the impact of this 
looming box was the architects' single toughest challenge. Instead of calling 
attention to this mass with architectural fussiness, the designers elected to 
place most of the design interest at the middle level of this and the other 
buildings in the second phase of the Civic Center project. Groups of small 
windows, varied wall angles and assorted architectural detailing will break 
these facades into forms a human can get close to without feeling overwhelmed. 
</P>
<P>
Yet, instead of causing the larger theater's bulk to fade into the background, 
the lack of detailing up high only makes it stick out like the proverbial sore 
thumb, at least on the model. 
</P>
<P>
But the architects aren't finished yet, <PERSON>Zecchetto</PERSON> said. City officials and 
community leaders have expressed a desire for some softening of the theater's 
harsh mass. Options include a screening wall in front of the building's 
prominent northern face, detailing on the building wall itself or a system of 
vine-covered trellises and palm trees. 
</P>
<P>
Zecchetto said the architects favor the last approach, partly because it is 
most economical. 
</P>
<P>
At this stage of the design game, though, when at least a year has already gone 
into the project, one expects a more polished design solution. 
</P>
<P>
Other aspects of the architecture are also disappointing. The choice of roof 
forms is puzzling. Some roofs will have the traditional pitched form, while 
others, as on a few small towers, will be flat. Sometimes, the flat towers 
don't merge well with the slanted roofs nearby. 
</P>
<P>
It is difficult, though, to make a final pronouncement on these roofs. The 
material hasn't been chosen, and could make the actual buildings look much 
different than a cardboard model. Flat tiles or a seamed metal are among the 
options being considered. 
</P>
<P>
There is other evidence the architects didn't arrive at a totally coherent 
design vision, the type of consistency which makes the new <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Pacific 
Associates Planners</ORGANIZATION> and Architects of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> such a success. 
</P>
<P>
Pedestrians won't notice from the ground level, but there's something jarring 
about the way the big theater's northern wall drops from a flat roof on top to 
a slanted roof above the first floor, with twin buttresses flying above it. 
</P>
<P>
Along <LOCATION>Escondido Boulevard</LOCATION>, the architects have softened the theater's mass with 
many combinations of windows and wall forms, but the array of shapes and angles 
seems jarring, at least on the model. 
</P>
<P>
At the level of the pedestrian, the architects appear to have done their 
strongest design work. 
</P>
<P>
All along, the design of the entire Civic Center complex, including <PERSON>City Hall</PERSON>, 
has been driven by its location in the 17-acre <LOCATION>Grape Day Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>'s 
miniature <LOCATION>Balboa Park</LOCATION>, a huge chunk of open space in the heart of the city. 
</P>
<P>
The intention was always to keep this setting park-like, even with the addition 
of several new buildings. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Moore Ruble Yudell</ORGANIZATION> responded by pushing their buildings to the edges of the 
property, near the streets, preserving the interior as open space. A walk 
through the complex should prove to be an interesting stroll between the 
various plazas and courtyards. 
</P>
<P>
The main entrance to the new theater complex will be off <LOCATION>Escondido Boulevard</LOCATION> on 
the western edge of the project. Here, a wide plaza of slightly ascending 
levels will lead pedestrians in between the large theater to the north and the 
nearby community theater, set behind a pergola at <LOCATION>Escondido Boulevard</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Valley Parkway</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Pergolas here and elsewhere are the same sort of vine-covered 
column-and-trellis outdoor walkways that became legendary <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> architect 
<PERSON>Irving Gill</PERSON>'s trademark early this century. Some even use arches like the ones 
<PERSON>Gill</PERSON> favored. The pergolas, with many rows of trees, will soften the experience 
of entering the complex. 
</P>
<P>
Every building has at least one courtyard related to it; most have several. 
Some are intended to be used for various gatherings. A courtyard off the back 
of the smaller theater could become an outdoor performance space, <PERSON>Zecchetto</PERSON> 
said. Eventually, he hopes the city will have the money to add doors to the 
back of this theater's stage so that it can open to the courtyard. 
</P>
<P>
Aside from the architecture, a larger concern has to do with the programming of 
the Civic Center complex, the kinds of uses selected for this public park. City 
<PERSON>Hall</PERSON> and theaters will dominate the site, with the community meeting building 
and arts complex as secondary uses. What will the new complex offer the person 
who comes to the park in search of a recreational or cultural experience during 
daylight hours? 
</P>
<P>
A library might have been a good choice, but the city had already built a new 
one three blocks away at 2nd Avenue and <ORGANIZATION>Kalmia Street</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
There are no now concrete plans for the kinds of things that make Balboa Park a 
success: food pushcarts, small cafes, a variety of spontaneous performers and 
many choices of exhibitions, performances, films and museums. 
</P>
<P>
Both Zecchetto and <PERSON>Rolf Gunnarson</PERSON>, assistant executive director of <ORGANIZATION>Escondido's 
Community Development Commission</ORGANIZATION>, say they have considered such ideas. A small 
food outlet and bar in the lobby of the larger theater might be open during 
daylight hours, and a kitchen in the community meeting building could be used 
to produce food for park visitors, not just for meetings within the building. 
Food vendors are also a possibility. 
</P>
<P>
These kinds of people-oriented uses will be essential to animating the 
well-planned outdoor spaces, which will undoubtedly by the new complex's 
triumph. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Architectural model of the second phase of the Escondido Civic Center 
complex. DON BARTLETTI / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06008177 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06008177 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  Jack Vallette, a landscape architect and major force behind the Niles Flea
market, died unexpectedly last summer of a heart attack at the age of 57.;   
Tonight, the Fremont City Council may ensure that his name lives on.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TRIBUTE TO TAKE THE FORM OF A TREE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Inside Our Towns  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The city staff is recommending that one of <PERSON>Vallette</PERSON>'s favorite trees -- a
copper beech -- be planted in his memory at one of his favorite places in the
city -- <PERSON>Shinn</PERSON> Park.;    "We feel it will be a nice addition," said <PERSON>Catherine
McKenzie</PERSON>, a city analyst. "Presently, there are none growing at any city
park.";    <ORGANIZATION>Vallette</ORGANIZATION>, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Fremont Planning Commission</ORGANIZATION> and the
historical architectural review board, helped prepare the <ORGANIZATION>Shinn Park</ORGANIZATION> master
plan, which includes an arboretum.;    The historic <PERSON>Shinn</PERSON> ranch was one of the
first nurseries in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, and many of <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>'s 80,000 trees can trace
their ancestry to the <PERSON>Shinn</PERSON> operation. Some of the trees at the park are more
than 100 years old.;    <PERSON>Vallette</PERSON> owned and operated his own landscape
architecture business in <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> for more than 25 years and taught landscaping
at <LOCATION>West Valley College</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Saratoga.</LOCATION>;    Dedicating trees to people is rare in
<LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>, said city spokeswoman <PERSON>Karen George</PERSON>. The only record she could find
was the dedication of a 32-tree Central Park grove in <DATE>1969</DATE> by the family of
<PERSON>Jay Gomez.</PERSON>; WATER, MONEY FLOW: Speaking of trees, the landscaping price tag
for the <ORGANIZATION>Alameda County Water District</ORGANIZATION> project on <LOCATION>Mission Boulevard</LOCATION> near
Interstate 680 will top <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY>. But it includes a sidewalk, planting of
mature trees and a demonstration garden to show developers and property owners
how to landscape in a desertlike environment, district <ORGANIZATION>General Manager Jim
Beard</ORGANIZATION> said. The fee for the landscape architect, <PERSON>Andrea Lucas</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Associates</ORGANIZATION>,
is <MONEY>$11,650</MONEY> of that.;    Once the landscaping is in -- sometime this <DATE>spring</DATE> --
the big job begins. In back of the landscaping and wall already built in
<LOCATION>Mission San Jose</LOCATION> will go a <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY>, 21-million-gallon-a-day water
treatment plant that will cover the area's needs to the year <DATE>2010</DATE>. Southern
<LOCATION>Alameda County</LOCATION>'s water comes <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> from wells, with the rest coming from
the <ORGANIZATION>San Francisco Water Department</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Aqueduct.; MORE ON
TREES: A new <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> outlet on Albrae Street for the <ORGANIZATION>San Jose-based Tire
Service Co.</ORGANIZATION> (its first outside <LOCATION>Santa Clara County</LOCATION>) is involved in a plan to
plant 150 oak trees next month at <LOCATION>Shoreline Park</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Mountain View</LOCATION>. <PERSON>James
D'Amico</PERSON>, the company president, said that part of the proceeds from a recent
tire sale will pay for the project overseen by the 6-month-old <ORGANIZATION>Treedom Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
The tree-planting group was founded by two <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> businessmen, <PERSON>Gary
Cohn</PERSON> and <PERSON>Adam Snitzer</PERSON>. <PERSON>Snitzer</PERSON> said they hope to plant 10,000 trees in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> this year. He said that Treedom is looking for local groups to help
plant trees. For more information on Treedom, call 1-800-TREEDOM.; NAMES,
NAMES, NAMES: <PERSON>Jim Fallon</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> attorney running for school board,
celebrated the new year by falling in his tub and breaking a shoulder bone. He
said he may be lame for a month but he plans to run a regular campaign. The
other candidates, <PERSON>Joseph Neff</PERSON>, an engineer; <PERSON>Marianne Schumaker</PERSON>, a
small-business owner and incumbent <PERSON>Vernon Smith</PERSON> at last report were well.
Smith, by the way, was appointed to fill out term of <PERSON>Jim Klent</PERSON>, who appears on
the ballot even though he resigned in <DATE>November</DATE>. If voters "retain" Klent,
<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> will keep the job . . . Here are the nominees in the humanitarian
endeavors category for the outstanding service awards given by the <ORGANIZATION>Fremont
Human Relation Commission</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Gerry Beemiller</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ed Campbell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kathy DiVita</PERSON>, <PERSON>Larry
Epstein</PERSON>, <PERSON>Margaret Hsu</PERSON>, <PERSON>Harry McLane</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sharon Sarris</PERSON>. Group or business
nominees are the Candlelighters, <PERSON>Mervyn</PERSON>'s, <PERSON>Permanently Yours</PERSON>, <PERSON>Shoeber</PERSON>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Athletic Club</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Tri-City Volunteers</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Winchester Copy Center</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Dennis Rockstroh column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Alameda County/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910108  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  641  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday January 8, 1991
00008177,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021990-0089 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 178661 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 19, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 1; Column 2; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1286 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ARCHITECTURE: THE LANDSCAPE AS A PARABLE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEON WHITESON 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Amid the din of traffic and buzz of busy sidewalks, landscape architects <PERSON>Pamela 
Burton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Katherine Spitz</PERSON> take refuge in the tranquillity of a tiny downtown 
park they designed on Spring Street. 
</P>
<P>
"In this very urban space we've called upon metaphor, narrative and journey to 
evoke a special sense of place," <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> says. 
</P>
<P>
To begin with, this new vest-pocket park, named the <ORGANIZATION>Broadway Spring Center</ORGANIZATION>, 
celebrates <PERSON>Biddy Mason</PERSON>, a nurse, midwife and former slave who, a century ago, 
opened a refuge for black families at this location. A mural at the park's 
entrance memorializes <ORGANIZATION>Mason</ORGANIZATION>'s long and charitable life. 
</P>
<P>
In addition, because the graceful <DATE>1893</DATE> Bradbury Building backs onto the park, 
this urban space evokes the memory of Spring Street and Broadway in their 
social and commercial glory in the <DATE>first decades of the 20th Century</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Predating the architecture and the street itself is the recollection of the 
country lane in the midst of a cow pasture that later became Spring Street, 
once <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>' main financial thoroughfare. Burton explains that the grove 
of camphor trees in the center of the park "narrates" the site's country lane 
origins. 
</P>
<P>
A fountain -- composed of a series of pipes constructed of copper, stainless 
steel and concrete -- mimics the profile of an oil refinery, a metaphor for the 
industries that funded the city's early prosperity. The present is represented 
by the small retail outlets lining the park, businesses that represent 
Broadway's resurgence as a commercial hub, this time serving <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>' 
Latino community. 
</P>
<P>
Their imaginative emphasis on metaphor, narrative and journey has placed <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> among the leaders of a new wave of younger designers who are 
rethinking the role of landscape architecture in relation to the city. From 
their small office in a brick building in the industrial section of <LOCATION>Santa 
Monica</LOCATION>, the two women have collaborated with some of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>'s most 
avant-garde architects. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Morphosis</ORGANIZATION>' <PERSON>Thom Mayne</PERSON> says he "likes the way <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> deal with 
landscape as a set of emotional and intellectual ideas. They're are no longer 
mere pretty horticulturists supplying plants, but actual conceptualizers of the 
urban scene, and their concepts are deeply poetic, like the best architecture. 
Since both <PERSON>Pamela</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kathy</PERSON> were trained as architects as well as landscape 
designers, they understand how we think and so can integrate their ideas 
seamlessly with ours." 
</P>
<P>
The architects at <ORGANIZATION>Morphosis</ORGANIZATION> collaborated with <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> on the winning 
entry for the Performing Arts Pavilion in the proposed Arts Park in the 
<LOCATION>Sepulveda Basin</LOCATION>. The plans call for most of the complex to be underground, "to 
preserve the integrity of the surface plane and honor the urban grid that 
dominates the Valley," <ORGANIZATION>Mayne</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
Working with <ORGANIZATION>Barton Myers Associates</ORGANIZATION> in the design of the <ORGANIZATION>Cerritos Community 
Arts Center</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> helped knit the architecture with its 
surroundings by creating "outdoor rooms" such as an Actors' Garden, which 
expresses its dramatic metaphor in a symbolic "tragic" weeping willow and a 
"comic" monkey puzzle tree. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Burton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> create landscapes as parables," said <ORGANIZATION>BMA</ORGANIZATION> principal <PERSON>Jonathan 
Hankin</PERSON>. "Their depth of thought is wonderful and adds great resonance to the 
architecture." 
</P>
<P>
For their entry in the <ORGANIZATION>Napa Valley Domaine Clos Pegase Winery</ORGANIZATION> competition, with 
architect <PERSON>Robert Mangurian</PERSON> and sculptor <PERSON>James Turrell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> devised 
a Garden of Seven Mysteries that included a "Devil's Chase" and several "Spirit 
Mounds." The purpose of these landscape elements was "to symbolize the 
transition between day-to-day consciousness and the states of dreams, 
disturbances and ecstasies that wine provokes," according to the text that 
accompanied their submission. 
</P>
<P>
Trained as a painter before she became an architect and then a landscape 
architect, <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> is accustomed to the use of visual metaphors. 
</P>
<P>
"We have to ask, 'What are our myths?' That is always the first question," she 
said. "In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> we have the myth of the wilderness fused with an overlay 
of settlement expressed in landscape patterns imported from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. We have to experiment with the tensions this juxtaposition 
generates, and feel our way through at last to a truly local urban tradition. 
Developing our own landscape is vital to creating our own sense of identity in 
this strange and unique environment." 
</P>
<P>
Appropriately enough, <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> first met <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Pistoia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>'s nursery-garden 
capital. A native <LOCATION>New Yorker</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> had worked in a <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> plant nursery 
while still a student. <PERSON>Burton</PERSON>, who was born in <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION> but grew up in the 
<LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>, was employed by <PERSON>Frank Gehry</PERSON> as a model builder before she qualified 
as an architect (and later a landscape architect), and these varied backgrounds 
seemed to both partners to mesh perfectly. 
</P>
<P>
"We love working together, though we often disagree vehemently to the point of 
verbally duking it out," <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> said. "Pamela provokes the confrontation, while 
my way is to sulk. It's a great way to get on." 
</P>
<P>
Burton and <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> are in total agreement about the need to develop a truly local 
landscape philosophy for <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
They say that three main principles should form the basis of this regional 
philosophy: appropriateness; a vision of landscape as a true form of 
architecture, and an appreciation of the symbolic value of plants. 
</P>
<P>
Appropriateness demands that local landscape, now dominated by a "salad" of 
imported varieties from all over the world, should shift to patterns based on 
the region's native chaparral such as the manzanita and native live oak. As a 
form of architecture, landscape should be used to define spaces and knit 
buildings to the terrain to provide "direction, function and aesthetic 
pleasure." And as an appreciation of the symbolic value of plants, horticulture 
should be linked to its history, including its ancient or contemporary 
mythologies. 
</P>
<P>
"By consciously calling upon these symbolic values," <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> said, "landscapes 
can work at conceptual and metaphoric levels as well as the purely 
horticultural." 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>' fragmented urban sprawl <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> perceive an urgent 
need to "reinforce connections." They suggest that major boulevards, such as 
Olympic, should be developed as linear gardens scaled to the movement of cars. 
"The automobile is a permanent part of our urban landscape, and has played a 
major role in giving shape to the city," <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> said. "Yet few landscape 
architects have given thought to the ways in which we can make the experience 
of motoring through the city more pleasurable while taming the car and tuning 
it into the visual rhythms of the city." 
</P>
<P>
Such linear gardens need to be varied, the designers explain. Our endless 
boulevards pass through many different districts, and each stretch should be 
keyed to the character of its surroundings. 
</P>
<P>
As an example, <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> points to the section of <LOCATION>San Vicente Boulevard</LOCATION> that runs 
through <LOCATION>Brentwood</LOCATION>, marked by a central median planted with South African coral 
trees. She suggests that, by these distinctions, motorists as well as 
pedestrians are made aware of the contrasts between one part of town and 
another. 
</P>
<P>
Underlying such specific concepts, <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Spitz</PERSON> sense an urgent need to use 
landscape as a means to create a sense of comfort and meaning amid the stress 
and confusion of a modern metropolis. 
</P>
<P>
They quote UC <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> urban sociologist <PERSON>Clare Cooper Marcus</PERSON> to express the 
core of their philosophy: "Under the inexorable march of technology and urban 
growth, and the increasing sense of insecurity these advances bring in their 
wake, people yearn for a place to call home in a world in which almost everyone 
is in a sense homeless." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Katherine Spitz, left, and Pamela Burton at Biddy Mason Park, which they 
designed. MINDY SCHAUER 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ARCHITECTS; PARKS -- LOS ANGELES; DOWNTOWN (LOS ANGELES); LANDSCAPE 
ARCHITECTURE; LOS ANGELES -- DEVELOPMENT AND REDEVELOPMENT; SPITZ, KATHERINE; 
BURTON, PAMELA 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891026-0074 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891026 </DD>
<AN> 891026-0074. </AN>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
@  Jennifer Bartlett's Walled Garden: 24 Rms, No Rv Vu
@  ----
@  By Patti Hagan </HL>
<DD> 10/26/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<DATELINE> New York  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
In a letter to the BPCA, kelly/varnell called this "arbitrary and amateurish." 
