<DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890922-0053 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890922 </DD>
<AN> 890922-0053. </AN>
<HL> PPG Agrees to Buy
@  Clorox's Paint Lines
@  For $130 Million </HL>
<DD> 09/22/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> PPG CLX </CO>
<IN> TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> PITTSBURGH  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890921-0264 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-21-89 1600EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-PPG-Clorox     09-21 0170</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PPG-Clorox,0178</SECOND>
<HEAD>PPG Buys Paint Units from Clorox</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>PPG Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> it purchased
subsidiaries from <ORGANIZATION>Clorox Co.</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$130 million</MONEY>.
   PPG said the acquisition includes headquarters offices in
<LOCATION>Bellvue</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, and plants in <LOCATION>Ballard</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Batavia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>; and <LOCATION>Langley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>. It said the units
have about 350 workers.
   PPG said combined annual sales of the paint and stains
subsidiaries of oakland, calif.-based <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> exceed <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Eugene B. Mosier</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION> group vice president for coatings and
resins, said the addition of the Olympic and Lucite product lines
``will contribute to the profitable growth of our architectural
coatings business.''
   PPG markets paints under the <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> Paints name in <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>PPG Corona</ORGANIZATION> brand name in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Charles R. Weaver</PERSON> said in <DATE>June</DATE> his cmpany had
decided to sell the paints and stains businesses ``to focus
resources on its core business as a diversified manufacturer and
marketer of household grocery products.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060789-0092 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 67091 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 7, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 2; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
121 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BRIEFLY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Clorox Puts Unit Up for Sale: <ORGANIZATION>Clorox Co.</ORGANIZATION> put its <MONEY>$106.8-million</MONEY> Olympic stain 
and Lucite paint business on the block, conceding that the subsidiary failed to 
live up to expectations. <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> said it would solicit offers for its <ORGANIZATION>Olympic 
HomeCare Products</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary, which manufacturers and markets Olympic wood 
stains and Lucite interior and exterior house paint. Clorox bought Olympic in 
<DATE>1981</DATE> for <MONEY>$123 million</MONEY> and added the Lucite brand in <DATE>1983</DATE> for <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY>. The 
products, although profitable, have performed poorly compared to the rest of 
<ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION>'s product line. This year, analysts expect the subsidiary's sales to 
drop to <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> or less. One analyst said the division had only a <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> shot 
of turning a profit. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief; Corporate Earnings 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CLOROX CO; DIVESTMENT; OLYMPIC HOME CARE PRODUCTS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890811-0020 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890811 </DD>
<AN> 890811-0020. </AN>
<HL> Clorox Profit Fell
@  In Quarter, Year;
@  Planned Sale Cited </HL>
<DD> 08/11/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> CLX </CO>
<IN> DOW JONES INTERVIEW (CEO) </IN>
<DATELINE> OAKLAND, Calif.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Clorox Co.</ORGANIZATION> expects to report net income for the quarter and year ended <DATE>June 30</DATE> fell from a year-earlier, reflecting a write-down from the anticipated sale of its Olympic paints division. 

   The household-product concern's net for the year-ago quarter totaled <MONEY>$36.5 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>67 cents</MONEY> a share. 
Fourth-quarter sales rose about <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> from <MONEY>$360.8 million</MONEY> a year earlier. 

   Net for the previous year was <MONEY>$130.9 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$2.39</MONEY> a share. 
Sales grew <PERCENT>18%</PERCENT> from <MONEY>$1.15 billion</MONEY> the previous year. 

   Results for the prior periods were restated to reflect exclusion of the Olympic division's results as well as the exercise of a note by <ORGANIZATION>Henkel KGaA</ORGANIZATION>, a West German household-product and chemical company owning about <PERCENT>27.3%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION>'s 55.4 million common shares outstanding. 

   <PERSON>William F. Ausfahl</PERSON>, group vice president and chief financial officer, said that in <DATE>fiscal 1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> shipped record volumes of several established product lines, including liquid bleach, cat litter and barbecue sauce. 
Improved performance also reflects the absence of some charges against equipment and foreign investments taken in <DATE>last year's fourth quarter</DATE>. 

   "So our continuing businesses are very healthy," he said. 
However, the company lavished its highest-ever level of spending on several new product introductions -- including its <ORGANIZATION>Clorox Detergent</ORGANIZATION>, still in test-markets in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> and Southeast. 
The detergent has prompted a round of competitive products and promotions by giant Cincinnati-based <ORGANIZATION>Procter &amp; Gamble Co.</ORGANIZATION> and others. 
Thus, the anticipated date of the detergent's national introduction is still a closely guarded secret "for competitive reasons," <PERSON>Mr. Ausfahl</PERSON> added. 

   The planned sale of the Olympic paints division, a strategic move to concentrate on core household and food-service businesses is pending. 
The sale for an as-yet undetermined price will result in a write-down of unknown size, <PERSON>Mr. Ausfahl</PERSON> said. 

   This anticipated write-down -- which he declined to discuss -- depressed net to below last year's periods, "but we will still be profitable," he added. 

   Analysts have estimated that the paint division could fetch anywhere from <MONEY>$70 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY>, but <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> won't comment on such speculation. 
The company said it is still reviewing bids from several potential buyers. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891003-0143 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891003 </DD>
<AN> 891003-0143. </AN>
<HL> PPG Buys Clorox Subsidiaries </HL>
<DD> 10/03/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> PPG CLX </CO>
<IN> TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
HOUSEHOLD AND PERSONAL-CARE PRODUCTS (HHP) </IN>
<DATELINE> PITTSBURGH  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>PPG Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said it completed the purchase of <ORGANIZATION>Clorox Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Olympic HomeCare Products</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Lucite HomeCare Products</ORGANIZATION> subsidiaries for <MONEY>$130 million</MONEY>. 

   The glass, coating and specialty-chemicals concern said the acquisition will double its consumer-paint business. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890818-0087 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890818 </DD>
<AN> 890818-0087. </AN>
<HL> Business Brief -- Clorox Co.:
@  Fiscal 4th-Period Net Fell
@  Nearly 50% to $18.8 Million </HL>
<DD> 08/18/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> CLX </CO>
<IN> EARNINGS (ERN) </IN>
<TEXT>

   The household products company posted an <PERCENT>11%</PERCENT> increase in operating profit to <MONEY>$40.8 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>74 cents</MONEY> a share, for the <DATE>quarter ended June 30</DATE>. 
The write-downs stem from the planned sale of its Olympic stain and Lucite paint business. 

   For the year, <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> posted a <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> gain in operating profit to <MONEY>$145.6 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$2.63</MONEY> a share, from <MONEY>$130.9 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$2.39</MONEY> a share, in <DATE>fiscal 1988</DATE>. 
A <MONEY>$21.4 million</MONEY> loss from the discontinued operations made net <MONEY>$124.1 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$2.24</MONEY> a share. 

   For the previous year, a <MONEY>$1.6 million</MONEY> gain from discontinued operations made net <MONEY>$132.6 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$2.42</MONEY> a share. 

   Results for the year-ago periods were restated to reflect both the discontinued paint operations, as well as the conversion of a note payable to <ORGANIZATION>Henkel Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890921-0051 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890921 </DD>
<AN> 890921-0051. </AN>
<HL> Business Brief -- Clorox Co.:
@  Board Authorizes Buying 9%
@  Of Common Outstanding </HL>
<DD> 09/21/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> CLX </CO>
<IN> BUYBACKS, REDEMPTIONS, SWAP OFFERS (BBK)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<TEXT>
He said <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> believes it is "very close to a deal." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-3824</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DCNAOAC8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930313
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 MAR 93 / Books: In search of Olympia
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JACKIE WULLSCHLAGER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
ALIAS OLYMPIA by <ORGANIZATION>Eunice Lipton Thames &amp; Hudson Pounds 12.95</ORGANIZATION>, 181 pages
FOR EVERY one art lover who knows her name, thousands can instantly
recognise the face and body of <PERSON>Victorine Meurent</PERSON>. She was the bold model
with the tight little frame and steady, daring gaze whose depiction in
<LOCATION>Manet</LOCATION>'s Olympia and Le Dejeuner sur l'Herbe revolutionised European nude
painting and outraged the <DATE>19th century</DATE> art world. Contemporaries called
<PERSON>Meurent</PERSON> 'a female gorilla' and marched through the Salon with sticks and
umbrellas to attack her portrait. Now she is something of a feminist
heroine, the plucky naked girl who stares out of the canvas defying male
expectations of submission, the star of a sexy fete champetre who refuses
her part in the erotic script.
Who was the woman behind the image? Alias Olympia is subtitled 'a woman's
search for Manet's notorious model and her own desire', and began as <PERSON>Eunice
Lipton</PERSON>'s attempt to find out. Lipton is a distinguished art historian, but
she soon discovered that history had buried Meurent as a typical model -
prostitute, alcoholic, loser - nicknamed 'the Shrimp'. Meurent is known to
have painted as well as modelled, but records, documents and interest in her
were negligible. There seemed no book to be written.
But Meurent became for Lipton an obsession, and scholarly research a
detective trail of blazing personal urgency. With wit and perception, <PERSON>Lipton</PERSON>
describes how she lived, breathed and dreamt Meurent, how lacklustre
archivists and Parisian alleys drove her to paranoia, how she came to see
the Parisian model born a hundred years before her as an alter ego who
shared her own problems with family, lovers, feminism and the art
establishment. Biography merges into autobiography, art history into a novel
as she creates her own idealised Meurent: a defiant lesbian artist who
whizzes about <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, sells her paintings, drinks alone in bars, does her own
thing.
The result is a clever, unorthodox, enthralling book which combines
criticism and fiction in elegant symbiosis. Lipton's overarching theme is
the century-old treatment of women as objects in art and culture, and the
way this continues to condition how women see themselves. Here Meurent is
the breakthrough, 'resisting centuries of admonition to ingratiate herself',
consigned to (patriarchal) historical oblivion as punishment. Manet, who
after all created the radical image, gets no credit.
But you do not have to agree with <PERSON>Lipton</PERSON> to enjoy her story. Her format
allows a plethora of juicy digressions - sharp words on the pampered,
male-bonded lives of <PERSON>Berthe Morisot</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mary Cassatt</PERSON>, for example, snap into
an analysis of why <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION> and Manet and <ORGANIZATION>Monet</ORGANIZATION> endlessly depicted one other
painting, but never drew the women artists working. Lipton has inspired
hunches, admissions of uncertain assumptions or dead-end routes which a
narrower scholarly work would lose. Most dazzling is her confidence to turn
the tables on herself and unearth research that shows how pathetically an
ageing, down-and-out Meurent traded on the Manet connection: a final joke in
which Meurent refuses to play her author's game as trenchantly as she
declined to satisfy the <DATE>19th century</DATE> viewer.
Alias Olympia joins a small, impressive genre of post-modern criticism -
<PERSON>Richard Holmes</PERSON>' Footsteps, <PERSON>Cecily Mackworth</PERSON>'s offbeat account of <LOCATION>Freud</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>Lucy</LOCATION>'s Nose last year - where the academic search is the story, where loose
ends are not tied up and uncertainties are accepted and bring life to the
narrative. It is cultural history at once learned, provocative, original and
unstuffy.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2731 Book Publishing.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page X
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880908-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-08-88 2211EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EltonJohn     09-08 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Elton John,0333</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rock Star's Art Auction Tops $7 Million</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A sale of rock star Elton <PERSON>John</PERSON>'s diverse
collection of art objects, furniture, stage clothes and memorabilia
topped <MONEY>$7 million</MONEY> at a <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auction <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   John's stuffed toys, fantasy objects and designer clothing
fetched <MONEY>$144,000</MONEY> and his art collection sold for <MONEY>$1.3 million</MONEY>.
   The running total in the four-day sale reached <MONEY>$7.6 million</MONEY>, the
auction house said.
   Among items sold <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> was a replica of the state
throne of Egyptian pharaoh <LOCATION>Tutankhamun</LOCATION>, its wood frame covered in
gold leaf and enameled on the backrest with Egyptian hieroglyphics,
which fetched <MONEY>$15,800</MONEY>.
   More of <PERSON>John</PERSON>'s furniture, ceramics, sculpture and miscellaneous
items, including amusement machines and walking sticks, were to be
auctioned <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the final sale day.
   The entertainer's stage costumes, memorabilia, furniture,
ornaments and jewelry were sold <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   John, 41, has said he wants to make room in his mansion near
<LOCATION>Windsor</LOCATION>, west of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, to start new collections.
   Prices for about 300 lots of art, from Rembrandt etchings to art
nouveau posters and fashion designs, mostly went well above the
presale estimates, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auction house said.
   The top price was <MONEY>$119,000</MONEY> for a painting of a fish wearing a
rope of pearls by the Belgian surrealist, <PERSON>Rene Magritte</PERSON>. It was
bought by an anonymous customer from <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>.
   Two pictures by northern <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> artist <PERSON>L. S. Lowry</PERSON>, who mostly
painted industrial scenes, sold for a total of nearly <MONEY>$150,000</MONEY>, or
<MONEY>$64,200</MONEY> above estimate.
   A modern sculpture of a kneeling woman supporting a glass-top
table, by British artist <PERSON>Allen Jones</PERSON>, made <MONEY>$35,300</MONEY>.
   A <DATE>1934</DATE> costume design for a <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> theater by <ORGANIZATION>Erte</ORGANIZATION>, pseudonym of
<PERSON>Romain de Tirtoff</PERSON>, sold to a private collector for <MONEY>$27,000</MONEY>, a
record for the artist's work.
   Fantasy paintings by the living German artist <PERSON>Paul Wunderlich</PERSON>
also did well, one called ``Olympia with Leaf,'' based on <ORGANIZATION>Edouard
Manet</ORGANIZATION>'s famous nude courtesan, ``Olympia,'' sold for <MONEY>$26,000</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880821-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-21-88 1303EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OlympicArtist     08-21 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Olympic Artist,0535</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dallas Artist Accepts Olympian Order</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVAN RAMSTAD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Olympic Games don't open until next month, but
illustrator <PERSON>Bart Forbes</PERSON> has already won some artistic gold medals.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Postal Service</ORGANIZATION> chose designs submitted by Forbes for
both the <DATE>1988 Winter</DATE> and Summer Olympic commemoratives. The <DATE>summer</DATE>
stamp, which depicts a male gymnast, was issued <DATE>Friday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Olympic Training Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo</LOCATION>.
   In addition, <LOCATION>Forbes</LOCATION>, whose realistic depictions have graced the
covers of <ORGANIZATION>Time</ORGANIZATION>, Sports Illustrated and dozens of other magazines,
has been chosen by the <ORGANIZATION>Korean Olympic Committee</ORGANIZATION> as the official
artist of the <DATE>summer</DATE> games.
   Forbes, 49, was commissioned to finish 12 paintings before he
leaves for <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION> next month. He will paint about 20 more for a
museum that will commemorate the games.
   A golfer and sometime-tennis player, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> says he's not an
athlete, but his studio in a renovated century-old two-story
building in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>' arts district is trimmed with old baseballs,
hats and other sports paraphernalia.
   ``Sports is a subject matter I like to do,'' <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said,
calling the Olympics assignment a career highlight. ``It's fun.
It's exciting and timely.''
   Timely but not dated. Forbes believes well done art is timeless.
   ``I don't want to get caught doing finish-line illustrations,''
<PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> said of the typical sporting event depiction.
   ``The crux for any painter or illustrator is not being satisfied
with the first or most obvious solution,'' he said. The challenge,
he continued, is to portray the human spirit of the games, how
athletes respond to enormous pressure, for instance.
   ``Many of the athletes train four years for just one shot. It's
an incredible event. Sure, there are some who are just glad they
made it to the Olympics, but for so many they're there for only one
thing: a gold medal.''
   An art graduate of the <ORGANIZATION>University of North Carolina</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>
earned an advanced degree at the Art Center in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. Unsure
of his ability to break into the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> design industry, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION>
settled in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> for several years after school.
   Later, after spending five years in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> returned
with his family to <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>. He said he's lucky to be able to live
where he wants and work on a ``national scale.''
   Forbes paints with a simple realism he says is influenced by the
American artists <PERSON>Thomas Eakins</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Winslow Homer</ORGANIZATION>, among others.
   The <ORGANIZATION>KOC</ORGANIZATION> commission was something of a coincidence.
   When the <ORGANIZATION>United States Sports Academy</ORGANIZATION> in Mobile, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, honored
Forbes as its sports artist of the year in <DATE>1987</DATE>, he shared the
graduate school's spotlight with <ORGANIZATION>Korean Olympic Committee</ORGANIZATION> president
<ORGANIZATION>Chong Ha Kim</ORGANIZATION>.
   A few weeks after that meeting, <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> told Forbes he'd been chosen
the committee's official artist and invited him to <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION> for a week
to make preparations.
   Forbes' first 12 paintings, based on that visit, will be part of
a calendar the <ORGANIZATION>KOC</ORGANIZATION> will sell during the Olympics, which begin
<DATE>September 17</DATE>.
   In all, <ORGANIZATION>Forbes</ORGANIZATION> will create an original work depicting each
Olympic event as well as the opening and closing ceremonies.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910318-0013
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910318-0013.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Heard on the Street:
   PPG Paints a Bleaker Picture of the Future,
   Having Just Patted Itself on the Back for '90
   ----
   By James S. Hirsch
</HL>
<DATE>
03/18/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C2
</SO>
<CO>
   PPG
</CO>
<IN>
HEARD ON THE STREET (HRD)
STOCK MARKET, OFFERINGS (STK)
DIVERSIFIED INDUSTRIAL (IDD)
</IN>
<LP>
   PITTSBURGH -- Plenty of companies claim to have found
strategies to bullet-proof themselves against recession,
among them PPG Industries, whose stock has soared 46% from
its October low.
   Not only did the maker of glass, chemicals and coatings
post record results for 1990 but Chairman Vincent A. Sarni
found occasion to take a bow in the just-issued annual
report, declaring that the company's "strategy was tested and
it proved to be sound."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Well, not quite that sound.
   PPG startled Wall Street with last week's disclosure that
it expects <DATE>first-quarter</DATE> profit to drop as much as <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT>,
reflecting weak demand from its core automobile and
construction markets. So much for the company's recession
resistance.
   Although <PERSON>Mr. Sarni</PERSON> warned shareholders in the annual
report that <DATE>1991</DATE> might be a tough year, the stock tumbled
more than 2 points after the midweek announcement, before
recovering <DATE>Friday</DATE> to 50 1/4, up 1.
   Now, PPG is suddenly back to looking like a plain old
manufacturer that isn't invulnerable to the business cycle.
And on that basis, analysts say, the stock looks like a weak
performer going forward. It all goes to show that even if
"cyclical" stocks do outperform the market, as some people
expect, it's unwise for investors to blindly snap up the
shares of any company in a basic industry.
   Some analysts say the bad news for <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION> may not be over
even if the ecomony recovers. Although increased car sales
and housing starts would certainly help, those industries
have been heading down for five years. Worse, there's an
overcapacity in glass and in some of <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION>'s chemicals.
   As a result, some analysts believe the company may not
benefit, as it usually has, as an "early-cycle stock," or a
stock that prospers when the economy is coming out of a
cyclical downturn. Some PPG analysts also say the company
needs new products to drive earnings; it made an effort with
a foray into medical electronics systems, but that has been a
bust.
   "At the end of the day," says <PERSON>James Wilbur</PERSON>, an analyst at
<ORGANIZATION>Smith Barney, Harris Upham &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, "the biggest challenge is
how can the company continue to grow when its core products
-- glass and paint -- are in slow-growth markets?"
   It's not that <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION> hasn't been trying. In recent years, the
company has made considerble headway in diminishing its
dependence on longtime core businesses.
   The company has pushed aggressively overseas, with <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
now accounting for <PERCENT>43%</PERCENT> of earnings, up from zero in <DATE>1984</DATE>. PPG
has expanded its replacement-glass and coatings business to
ease its dependence on new-car sales. It wrung out costs,
beefed up the specialty chemicals line, introduced
high-technology coatings and bought Olympic and Lucite
paints.
   The strategy seemed to be working as the company generated
<DATE>1990</DATE> earnings of <MONEY>$475 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$4.43</MONEY> a share, on sales of
more than <MONEY>$6 billion</MONEY>. Investors applauded, and in the 12
months through <DATE>Feb. 28</DATE> the stock price jumped <PERCENT>33%</PERCENT>, far
outstripping a <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> gain in the <ORGANIZATION>Standard &amp; Poor</ORGANIZATION>'s 500-stock
index.
   But PPG is still at the mercy of its longtime markets, as
the <DATE>first quarter</DATE> of this year illustrates. <ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION>
remains its largest customer.
   "The notion that the company was less cyclical now hasn't
held true," says <PERSON>Charles LoCastro</PERSON>, an analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Donaldson,
Lufkin &amp; Jenrette</ORGANIZATION>, who acknowledges that he was taken aback
by the profit announcement. "I thought their earnings would
hold up much better."
   <PERSON>Mr. LoCastro</PERSON> has downgraded his position on the stock to
neutral from moderately attractive. He also has slashed his
earnings estimate for <DATE>1991</DATE> to <MONEY>$3.50</MONEY> a share from <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY>.
   A weak business climate isn't the only factor in <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION>'s
quarterly profit drop. In a terse statement projecting the
earnings decline, <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION> said that its <DATE>first-quarter</DATE> net will
include a one-time gain relating to a change in accounting.
The company further stated that the impact of this gain will
be reduced "by charges for the realignment of various
operations."
   The company won't elaborate and declined to comment for
this column. PPG, however, has indicated to analysts that the
write-off will essentially negate the accounting gain.
   One lesson that <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION> has learned is that overseas markets
don't help, because those markets can slump, too. New-car
sales are showing double-digit declines in three of <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION>'s
largest European markets, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. And in
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, no amount of diversification can compensate for a
<PERCENT>12.8%</PERCENT> falloff in <DATE>January</DATE> housing starts.
   Some people apparently saw <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION> heading for trouble. <PERSON>Steve
Pesek</PERSON>, a portfolio manager at <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Management &amp; Research
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, says the firm sold 3.5 million shares of <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION> common last
<DATE>summer</DATE>. "Their primary markets are still cyclical," he says.
"They can't repeal the economic cycle."
   ---
   <ORGANIZATION>PPG Industries</ORGANIZATION>
   (<ORGANIZATION>NYSE</ORGANIZATION>; Symbol: PPG)
                                                                                                       

   Business: Glass, coatings and chemicals
                                                                                                       

   Year ended <DATE>Dec. 31, 1990</DATE>:
   Net income: <MONEY>$475 million</MONEY>; <MONEY>$4.43</MONEY> a share
   Sales: <MONEY>$6.02 billion</MONEY>
                                                                                                       

   <DATE>Fourth quarter</DATE>, <DATE>Dec. 30, 1990</DATE>
   Per-share earnings: <MONEY>96 cents vs. 93 cents</MONEY> a share
                                                                                                       

                                                                                                       

   Common shares outstanding: 106 million
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-7869</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CEOAZAFTFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920515
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 MAY 92 / Arts: A deliciously scandalous painter - Fine art
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PATRICIA MORISON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
IF EVER a painter had the luck of the gods, it was <PERSON>Henri Gervex</PERSON>. Son of a
<LOCATION>Montmartre</LOCATION> piano-maker, Gervex floated up through French society with the
effortlessness of <ORGANIZATION>Montgolfier</ORGANIZATION>'s balloon. At his death in <DATE>1929</DATE> Gervex was
wealthy and fabulously well-connected. His daughter had married into the
aristocracy, and his paintings graced some of the grandest dining-rooms in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
Now, in a modest way, the Gervex balloon is once more on the way up, thanks
to an exhibition which has just opened in <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION>. (Next year, it travels
to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and Nice.) There has never been a retrospective of the great
arriviste, so tracking his canvasses to the homes of private collectors has
meant a good deal of sleuthing for the show's organisers. Not, however, that
Gervex is a totally unknown painter - above all, not in <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION>.
For half a century, '<ORGANIZATION>Rolla</ORGANIZATION>', the large, frothy scene of the morning-after in
a cheap hotel, has been the most popular painting in the museum's collection
 -and star of the postcard sales, far surpassing Titian, <PERSON>Veronese</PERSON> and even
<ORGANIZATION>Delacroix</ORGANIZATION>'s '<LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> on the Ruins of <LOCATION>Missolonghi</LOCATION>'. There was a nasty moment
when it seemed that the newly created Musee d'Orsay might reclaim the
<ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION>'s deposit, as it had every right to do. But <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, mindful for once of
local sensibilities, stayed its hand.
Gervex was 26 in <DATE>1878</DATE> when he exhibited '<PERSON>Rolla</PERSON>', unquestionably his
masterpiece, in the Salon. Already, he was well and truly launched after
winning a medal for the horribly squirming, but academically impeccable,
'Satyr playing with a Bacchante', which showed him to be every inch the
faithful pupil of the great <PERSON>Cabanel</PERSON>. But with '<ORGANIZATION>Rolla</ORGANIZATION>', Gervex showed himself
to be now a true believer in <LOCATION>Manet</LOCATION>'s gospel that artists must paint modern
life.
His nude, however, is no 'Olympia', the painting which over a decade before
had caused such a scandal. There was no risk of Gervex ever reneging on the
academic doctrine of ideal beauty of form in the matter of nudes. Throughout
his life, as we see in the upstairs rooms of the exhibition, paintings of
meltingly boneless nudes - usually redheads - were one of his stand-bys. In
old age, Gervex the dinosaur even reverted to Cabanalesque goddesses lolling
on the tops of waves.
It was with '<ORGANIZATION>Rolla</ORGANIZATION>', however, that Gervex showed his uncanny gift for public
relations. It was banned as immoral, for reasons well explained by <PERSON>Hollis
Clayson</PERSON> in her interesting study of prostitution in French 19th-century
painting, 'Painted Vice' (<ORGANIZATION>Yale University Press</ORGANIZATION>). A prostitute in her
corset, like Manet's '<PERSON>Nana'</PERSON>, was tolerable; discarded corsets and
petticoats, with <PERSON>Monsieur Rolla</PERSON>'s walking stick pointing at a provocative
angle, were quite another.
Undaunted, Gervex put it on exhibition in the <LOCATION>Chaussee</LOCATION> d'Antin; le tout
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> was invited to see, and for weeks the street was filled with
carriages. Gervex was now a deliciously scandalous painter, in addition to
being a perfectly delightful human being. In the <DATE>1880s</DATE> and <DATE>'90s</DATE>, Gervex was
irrepressible. The older generation of Impressionists loved him for his
raffishness.
Early success meant he could afford a famous mistress, <ORGANIZATION>Madame Valtesse de la
Bigne</ORGANIZATION>, whom we see in a large and glibly sub-Manet open-air portrait. He
thoughtfully introduced her to Zola, researching the background for his
immortal prostitute, <LOCATION>Nana</LOCATION>. Another little scandal, when he exhibited a
painting of a nude wearing a velvet mask, helped his reputation. Everyone
wanted to know whose wife she was, and a count sueing his sister for her
inheritance said she had been the sitter . . .
Gervex's industry was prodigious and he would never turn down a prestigious
commission, no matter how boring the subject. A brilliant stroke in <DATE>1889</DATE> was
to join up with the Belgian artist, <PERSON>Alfred Stevens</PERSON>, and paint a gigantic
'Panorama of the History of the Century', shown here in a modest copy from
<LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>.
Gervex had now shown himself as the republican patriot, honouring the
Revolution. People flocked to see it, and when a buyer did not come forward,
small pieces were given to each of the financial backers.
Clearly, here was the right artist to execute vast murals for public
commissions, such as still survive in the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Weddings</ORGANIZATION> at the mairie of
the <ORGANIZATION>XIX</ORGANIZATION> arrondissement and the ceiling of the buffet of the <ORGANIZATION>Gare de Lyons</ORGANIZATION>.
Onwards and ever upwards, Gervex painted millionaire's salons and ceilings
for the <ORGANIZATION>Elysees Palace</ORGANIZATION>. In the <ORGANIZATION>Belle Epoque</ORGANIZATION> years, his undoubted talent for
painting electric light made him favoured choice for showing high society
dining in the <ORGANIZATION>Bois de Boulogne</ORGANIZATION>.
Portraits were bread and butter to Gervex, although he showed no very great
talent for them. Singer <PERSON>Sargent</PERSON>'s bravura effects always eluded him. But
even as his commissions took him into the highest ranks of society - even
the Russian Royal Family, he still paid homage to early days. He was still,
a 'painter of modern life', follower - at however far a distance - of <LOCATION>Degas</LOCATION>
and Manet. Hence, we still find him painting scenes such as the wistful
cocotte, umbrella on the table, who anxiously awaits her companion for the
night in a smart restaurant in the <ORGANIZATION>Bois de Boulogne</ORGANIZATION>.
This is a hugely enjoyable exhibition, even though of a painter who rarely
rose above third-rate. Only now and then is he better than that, for
example, in oil sketches of his wife nursing their daughter or asleep on the
deck of the splendiferous yacht of the American tycoon, <PERSON>James Gordon Bennet</PERSON>.
The book accompanying the show will delight all who love the <ORGANIZATION>Belle Epoque</ORGANIZATION>,
and is rich above all in the contributions made by <ORGANIZATION>Gervex</ORGANIZATION>'s great-grandson.
And do keep your eyes skinned; propped in a cellar, or hanging in some
drawingroom, you just might happen to see a nude in a black velvet mask or a
<PERSON>Nana</PERSON> look-alike dressing in a theatre loge . . . There are many Gervexes yet
to be unearthed; with a vengeance, the arriviste master is coming in from
the cold.
Galerie des Beaux-Arts, <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION>, until <DATE>August 30</DATE>: <ORGANIZATION>Musee Carnavalet</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>
(<DATE>February 1</DATE> - <DATE>May 2 1993</DATE>); Musee des Beaux-Arts, Nice (<DATE>May 27</DATE> - <DATE>August 29</DATE>)
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-9991</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DHFBQADBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930806
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  06 AUG 93 / Arts: Second-hand images of the human body - Lynn MacRitchie
reviews the work of Marlene Dumas at the ICA gallery
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LYNN MACRITCHIE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The chimera that artists, especially younger ones, no longer paint, or if
they do they certainly do not paint people, hovers over much current chatter
about the visual arts. It is, of course, so much nonsense. The human figure
is still the chosen subject of many young painters, although they may not
approach it in the traditional manner of, say, <PERSON>Lucien Freud</PERSON>, whose lifetime
contemplation of the model in the studio will be celebrated at the
<ORGANIZATION>Whitechapel Gallery</ORGANIZATION> this <DATE>autumn</DATE>.
A considerable group of young artists in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> such as <PERSON>Raymond Pettibon</PERSON> or
<PERSON>Mike Kelley</PERSON> (some of whom were represented at the excellent '<ORGANIZATION>Irony &amp;
Ecstasy</ORGANIZATION>' show at the <ORGANIZATION>Salama Caro Gallery</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> earlier this <DATE>summer</DATE>) are
using drawing and painting to explore the representation of the figure.
Their source material, however, is much more likely to be found in the
detritus of contemporary media images of the body, porn magazines, comic
books and advertisements, than in the life class.
In <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, the leading exponent of this school of figuration is <PERSON>Marlene
Dumas</PERSON>, whose powerful and disturbing work can now be seen at the <ORGANIZATION>ICA</ORGANIZATION>.
Like many painters of the human form before her (<LOCATION>Degas</LOCATION> or Manet to name but
two), <PERSON>Dumas</PERSON> chooses to work from photographs. Unlike them, she works
exclusively from photographic images, either taken by herself with a
<ORGANIZATION>Polaroid</ORGANIZATION> camera or found in the pages of books, newspapers or magazines.
These make up a store of images from which she selects, exploring their
possibilities in series of oil paintings and watercolour drawings. 'It is
not the relationship between painting and photography that is the most
prominent question today,' she explains. 'The fact is that the photographic,
not photography as a specific medium but as a particular mode of signifying,
is affecting all the arts at the moment.'
Her subjects, even before she begins to work on them, have already been
through one process of transformation, leaving her free to remake them anew
in paint, or, as she expresses it, 'My people were all shot by a camera,
framed, before I painted them. They didn't know I'd do this to them . . .'
The earliest works in the show are portrait heads, of family, friends and
strangers, painted in light washes of intense colour. Titles are important.
'Evil is banal,' <DATE>1984</DATE>, shows a young woman whose orange gold hair stands out
in Bonnard-like contrast against a pale pink cheek and purple shadowed
shoulder. A large nude of <DATE>1987</DATE> titled 'The Particularity of Nakedness' is
the only male example in a series of studies of a horizontal, naked figure,
and the only one to function as a portrait, whose subject, echoing, Manet's
'Olympia', returns the viewer's stare.
Others show a naked woman, lying prone across a table in 'Waiting for
Meaning' <DATE>1988</DATE>, or, in 'Snowhite and the broken arm' representing the artist,
prone, helpless, polaroids scattered on the floor, camera clutched in her
useless hand, unable to shoot back at the greedy gaze of seven small boys.
The next series is scenes of children, photographed at school, in obedient
lines or groups. 'The Dance', <DATE>1992</DATE>, shows four little girls, seen from the
back, hand in hand before an empty, threatening space. Little girls remain a
dominant theme in her later work, while 'The First Humans' <DATE>1991</DATE>, portrays
four new born babies in studies the size of full length adult portraits. Her
latest works are based on photographs from porn magazines.
At <ORGANIZATION>Documenta 9</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Kassel</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>, <PERSON>Dumas</PERSON> filled a tiny turret room with
monochrome watercolour sketches of young girls, a series based on the story
of Salome. After the wide installation filled spaces below, their intimacy
was a shock, like finding oneself suddenly naked in front of strangers, a
state which although inadvertent may provoke harm. That is the condition of
<PERSON>Dumas</PERSON>' subjects. Caught first by the camera, then by the painter, something
indeed has been 'done' to them. In the process of their double
objectification, they have been transformed. These babies are not innocent,
but redolent with the possibility of evil. These children line up smiling in
the playground and we see gas chambers. The stained sheet held out labelled
'Evidence of Virtue' signifies its opposite, innocence betrayed. The '<ORGANIZATION>Peer
Group</ORGANIZATION>' child exposed naked by her playmates horrifies us with our own
thoughts of abuse.
All this is done with the simplest of means - naked bodies suggested by a
swift wash of watercolour in a manner which recalls the grace and economy of
<PERSON>Beuys</PERSON>, a use of oil paint in which sombre strokes of grey and blue are
pulled into meaning by vibrant details - the scarlet slippers in 'The
Window', <DATE>1991</DATE>, or the shocking pink mouth of 'Girl with Lipstick', <DATE>1992</DATE>.
<PERSON>Dumas</PERSON>' painterly exploration of these second-hand images of the body reminds
us that all human horrors have already been committed, recorded and wait
only to be repeated, by people just like ourselves. Only the porno
performers seem innocent, the watercolour sketches of their endless,
wearying display finally returning their bodies to the mystery of the
unknowable.
<PERSON>Marlene Dumas</PERSON>, 'Miss Interpreted', <DATE>July 28</DATE>- <DATE>September 19</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Institute of
Contemporary Arts</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>The Mall</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, SW1Y 5AH.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8412 Museums and Art Galleries.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880422-0041 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Clorox Co. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> CLX </CO>
<IN> ERN </IN>
<TEXT>
Sales rose <PERCENT>11%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$871.5 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$784.3 million</MONEY>. 
Per-share earnings for both periods were adjusted to reflect a 2-for-1 stock split last <DATE>June</DATE>. 

   The <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, Calif.-based company attributed its improved performance to increased shipments of the company's household grocery brands, food service products, and internationally marketed brands. 

   The maker of food, household products and architectural paints and stains said it expects to report an "excellent" fiscal year. 
Clorox added it anticipates "good" operating results for its <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE> while it moves ahead with its introduction of <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> Super Detergent. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA071090-0099 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 245173 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 10, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 4; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1288 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ART REVIEWS; 
</P>
<P>
THE PUSH AND PANT OF VIRTUE'S NORTHERN ENGLAND LANDSCAPES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CATHY CURTIS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
After a week of walking through fields and small towns in <LOCATION>Northern England</LOCATION> <DATE>last 
May</DATE>, I finally began to understand why <ORGANIZATION>John Virtue</ORGANIZATION>'s works look the way they 
do. After a while, the look of the landscape and the action of climbing and 
striding through it begin to merge, as if you couldn't visualize the view from 
a hill without recalling the pant and push to get there. 
</P>
<P>
On first glance, Virtue's large, shellac-stiffened black-and-white charcoal 
drawings appear to be regularly rising and falling abstract designs organized 
into grid formats. Closer inspection reveals a series of shadowy views of 
huddled villages, undulating hills, meandering fences, tipsy chimneys and 
shrouded Jane Eyre-ish houses. Puddles and lashings of black ink and drifts of 
white gouache envelop hill and dale in an elemental fury of wind, snow and 
rain. 
</P>
<P>
Virtue once worked as a postman in his native <LOCATION>Lancashire</LOCATION>, which obliged him 
constantly to walk around his own village. A decade ago, organizing the sheaves 
of small drawings he made into grid formats provided him a way out of his early 
impasse as a painter. 
</P>
<P>
In recent compositions he adeptly varies rhythm and mood by increasing or 
decreasing the amount of blackness, the size of the individual scene and the 
massing of images -- albeit always within a distinctly minor key. 
</P>
<P>
The pieces that don't work are the tiny single drawings. They're too flatly 
naturalistic and too sweetly miniaturized. Most disappointingly, they lack the 
insistent rhythmic effects of Virtue's vast patchworks of dark and light. 
Conversely, "Landscape No. 88," which contains 180 images, is the densest and 
richest piece in the show. A fine-grained all-over pattern, like an overgrowth 
of bracken, separates the imagery from the viewer much as tangled tree limbs 
screen the courtiers who've slept through 100 years in Act III of the ballet 
"Sleeping Beauty." 
</P>
<P>
Were Virtue a different kind of artist, one might see a social program here: a 
fond commentary on small towns slumbering through late 20th-Century upheaval. 
But he seems more preoccupied by the history of possibilities within the world 
of art: ways of expressing fidelity to what the eye sees, emotional attachment, 
and the coolly rational workings of the mind. 
</P>
<P>
His work is related in various ways to the dense, small-scale landscape 
etchings of his 18th-Century countryman <PERSON>Samuel Palmer</PERSON>, the art of his 
20th-Century countrymen and fellow walkers <PERSON>Richard Long</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hamish Fulton</PERSON>, the 
organizational strategies of Minimalism and the nervous, highly personal 
"handwriting" that came into its own with Abstract Expressionism. 
</P>
<P>
"Subversive Classicism Subverted" is the title for a miscellany of work by 
veteran <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> painter <PERSON>Llyn Foulkes</PERSON>, Austrian artist <PERSON>Arnulf Rainer</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Yasumasa Morimura</PERSON>, a young Japanese artist. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Foulkes</PERSON>' line-up of small portraits of men is disfigured by Elephant Man 
swellings, dried blood and various collaged elements: cartoon eyes, a 
Dada-esque mask, a TV screen. They seem to be ordinary guys in drip-dry shirts 
who got mixed up in some nasty business -- got their faces bashed in, their 
brains rearranged -- by the same faceless enemy, the callousness of modern 
life. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Rainer</PERSON>, who first came to avant-garde prominence in the <DATE>'50s</DATE> and <DATE>'60s</DATE>, when he 
covered paintings by various artists with monochromatic coats of paint, is 
probably best known for drawings on photographs of his own face and body. 
</P>
<P>
In the '70s he began using photographs of works by other artists. "Eight 
Paintings Over Works by <PERSON>F.X. Messerschmidt</PERSON>," from 1976-77, consists of large 
photographs of blandly classical sculptures of men's heads that <PERSON>Rainer</PERSON> defaced 
with a drizzle of black doodles. A darkly antic gesture, it suggests a primal 
rage against figures of perfection or authority, a need to make one's mark by 
cutting the other guy down to size. 
</P>
<P>
Morimura is the most genuinely "subversive" artist in the show. Although he 
belongs to the vast ranks of those who find sport in reworking paintings by 
icons of Western art, his elaborately rigged, posed and over-painted color 
photographs deal freshly and mischievously with cross-cultural and transsexual 
notions. 
</P>
<P>
In "Portrait (Fugato)," his largest set-piece, he inserts his own, 
incongruously blonde-wigged head and torso on <PERSON>Edouard Manet</PERSON>'s nude prostitute, 
<LOCATION>Olympia</LOCATION>. Various subsidiary elements in the famous painting of that name are 
spruced up with Japanese textiles, flashy ornaments and anachronistic 
brushwork. Most obviously, the piece mocks the longstanding passion among 
Japanese for tasteful French art, which has reached a crescendo in recent 
big-ticket Impressionist auctions. "Olympia," on the other hand, cuts too close 
to the bone. Olympia's blatant stare and the pride of place devoted to the 
black servant call into question some ticklish issues for the Japanese: the 
still-lagging emancipation of women, the role of sex in a prudish society and a 
homogeneous society's unwitting acceptance of black stereotypes. 
</P>
<P>
The imagery also plays on specifically Japanese artistic traditions. Posing as 
a woman has time-honored roots in Kabuki theater, in which certain male actors 
(onnagata) specialize in women's roles. The chief figures portrayed in Ukiyo-e 
woodblock prints, too, were either idle, sensuous woman, elaborately dressed, 
or actors who played women's roles. By slipping into the role of the onnagata, 
<PERSON>Morimura</PERSON> becomes the perfect commentator, at once embracing and unmasking his 
culture. 
</P>
<P>
 <LOCATION>L.A. Louver</LOCATION>, 55 <ORGANIZATION>N. Venice Blvd.</ORGANIZATION> and 77 Market St, <LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION>. Through <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Modern Classics: <PERSON>Alfred Stieglitz</PERSON> and <PERSON>Diane Arbus</PERSON> are the odd couple in <PERSON>G. Ray 
Hawkins</PERSON>' inaugural show at his gallery's new <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION> location. But both 
photographers are represented with what have come to be considered classic 
images. In <PERSON>Arbus</PERSON>' case, it shows how little time it takes to become a classic 
these days, and how quickly our eyes adapt to what was once widely thought 
downright peculiar if not repellent. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Stieglitz</PERSON> photogravures from the <DATE>first decade of the 20th-Century</DATE> are 
vintage prints originally published in <PERSON>Stieglitz</PERSON>'s famous modern art magazine, 
Camera Work, and suffused with the foggy grays beloved of the "pictorial" 
photographers. 
</P>
<P>
The familiar views of <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> are here: the uncluttered skyline of "Lower 
<LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>," with a steamer puffing smoke against billowing clouds, a huge 
construction scaffolding looming over quaint mansard roofs and a streetcar in 
"Old and <LOCATION>New New York</LOCATION>." Other old friends include "The Steerage," the 
much-reproduced image of anxious-looking immigrants waiting to dock. 
</P>
<P>
The 10 Arbus prints -- all but two printed by an assistant but signed by the 
artist -- date from <DATE>1962</DATE> to <DATE>1970</DATE>, a year before she died. Her most identifiable 
subjects were the kind of people children are taught not to stare at on the 
street, people who don't look "normal" either physically or mentally, or both. 
And yet it is the fidgeting, shouting boy -- identified in the accompanying 
description as retarded -- who shows the only spark of life in a portrait of a 
zombie-like <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> family out for a <DATE>Sunday</DATE> stroll. 
</P>
<P>
But this particular selection of photographs is largely composed of images more 
broadly about the rituals and relationships of contemporary middle-class life 
-- the way women chose to deck themselves out in makeup and teased hair, the 
cheesy plastic, fringe and tinsel-bedecked splendor of a <LOCATION>Levittown</LOCATION> living room 
at <LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION>, or the way each member of a suburban family relaxed in a private, 
touch-me-not cocoon on their spacious lawn. With a distance of two decades, 
<PERSON>Arbus</PERSON> seems to be more about style as a projection of the undercurrents of a 
culture. 
</P>
<P>
G. <PERSON>Ray Hawkins Gallery</PERSON>, 910 <LOCATION>Colorado Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>, to <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>. 
</P><P></P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, John Virtue's "Landscape No. 94" proffers multiple views of Northern 
England, seen in closer inspection. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Art Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA082890-0063 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 268003 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 28, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
834 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MURALIST ASKS CITY TO PAY FOR WHITEOUT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DOUG SMITH, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Before they disappeared, they were four of the most engaging faces in <LOCATION>Los 
Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
There was the middle-aged man in glasses -- solid, direct, slightly 
authoritarian as he looked you right in the eye. Opposite was his wife -- 
eyebrows arched over a gentle, worried smile. 
</P>
<P>
There was a younger man, dark and intense, staring across the street -- 
directly into the pretty, passive face of his wife. 
</P>
<P>
For four years, they brightened the gloomy Sunset Boulevard underpass in <LOCATION>Echo 
Park</LOCATION> with such a glow of personality that they landed on the cover of the book 
"<LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> Wall Art." 
</P>
<P>
The faces disappeared earlier this year when a contractor visited the underpass 
as part of an assignment to eradicate graffiti on city property. When the job 
was done, white paint covered the wall. 
</P>
<P>
The former gang member who painted the faces is locked in a tug of war with the 
city over who should be responsible when the government destroys a work of art. 
</P>
<P>
The artist, 29-year-old electrician <PERSON>Ruben Brucelyn</PERSON>, is not seeking compensation 
for loss of the mural -- merely to be reimbursed for his costs so he can 
repaint the work, which he created with private donations under the guidance of 
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> muralist <PERSON>Kent Twitchell</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Brucelyn has presented the city's <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Street Maintenance</ORGANIZATION> an invoice for 
<MONEY>$2,500</MONEY> to cover paint and supplies. 
</P>
<P>
Although conceding that it was probably a mistake to paint over the mural, city 
officials have so far ignored the request. The burden falls on muralists to 
remove graffiti from their works if they don't want the city involved, 
according to <PERSON>Curtis Bianchi</PERSON>, general superintendent in the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Street 
Maintenance</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Graffiti "must be taken care of very quickly or it's just like an explosion 
happens," <PERSON>Bianchi</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
He said the crew that painted over <LOCATION>Brucelyn</LOCATION>'s mural was acting under a policy 
calling for the removal of graffiti from city property within 48 hours. The 
city retains a private contractor, <ORGANIZATION>Graffiti Prevention Systems</ORGANIZATION>, to patrol 
public structures. 
</P>
<P>
The dispute dates to <DATE>Jan. 8</DATE>, when a crew was sent to the Sunset bridge, which 
crosses heavily traveled <ORGANIZATION>Glendale Boulevard</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"We've found that there are what I would consider to be unauthorized murals 
throughout the city," <PERSON>Bianchi</PERSON> said. "Many have been painted over." 
</P>
<P>
It turned out that <PERSON>Brucelyn</PERSON>'s <DATE>1985</DATE> work was not unauthorized. He had received 
approval of the design from the city's <ORGANIZATION>Cultural Affairs Department</ORGANIZATION> and had 
personally kept it free of graffiti for three years. He said he had applied a 
protective coating and only needed to rub the graffiti off with solvent and 
touch up the paint underneath. 
</P>
<P>
Brucelyn said he arrived on the scene just as workers were burying the faces 
under swaths of white paint. He protested, but they continued, he said. 
</P>
<P>
"I was crushed, devastated," the artist said in a letter of complaint to 
<PERSON>Bianchi</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Last month, he asked for funds to repaint the faces. If necessary, he will file 
a formal claim against the city, he said. 
</P>
<P>
The mural had more significance to Brucelyn and Echo Park than the commuter 
passing through the tunnel could have guessed. The faces were based on real 
people -- the younger man being Brucelyn himself. The others are those who 
helped him escape gang life. 
</P>
<P>
The older man in the mural was based on <PERSON>Harold Helms</PERSON>, pastor of <ORGANIZATION>Angelus Temple</ORGANIZATION>, 
the white domed church beside <LOCATION>Echo Park Lake</LOCATION>. He runs a Spanish-language 
ministry and outreach programs for gang members. 
</P>
<P>
"He used to be a real bona fide tough gang kid," muralist <PERSON>Twitchell</PERSON> said of 
Brucelyn. "He met his wife who was a Christian, a smart, savvy young woman. He 
began going to church with her. It changed his life into a positive life." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Twitchell</PERSON> also had a role in the turnaround. The two met in <DATE>1984</DATE>, when Brucelyn 
stopped on the Harbor Freeway to watch <PERSON>Twitchell</PERSON> work on the faces he was 
commissioned to paint on freeway walls for the Olympic Games. 
</P>
<P>
Twitchell created the stencil-like forms for the young electrician's first 
murals, the Olympic runners on the stairway west of <LOCATION>Echo Park Lake</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Brucelyn took a detour from his art projects in <DATE>1988</DATE> to write and produce a 
play, "Smile Now, Cry Later," depicting the ravages of the gang culture. Last 
year, he rebuilt his house in <ORGANIZATION>Eagle Rock</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
With all that going on, he admitted, he neglected the faces mural during <DATE>1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
At the least, <PERSON>Brucelyn</PERSON> said, the city should have warned him of its intentions 
before destroying his work. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bianchi</PERSON> said the contractor had no way of finding Brucelyn because he did not 
apply for permits to paint on city property. "We don't know who the artist is. 
We have no permit. We have no record," <PERSON>Bianchi</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
To prevent such mishaps in the future, <PERSON>Bianchi</PERSON> said he will propose permit 
guidelines so that anyone who comes to <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> with a mural proposal can be 
given a package listing the steps to be taken. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, <PERSON>Twitchell</PERSON> has some advice for his protege. 
</P>
<P>
"I'd stay away from underpasses," <PERSON>Twitchell</PERSON> said. "You can't win the fight 
against destruction. A creator can't win a fight against a destroyer." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, A woman stands by one of the since whited-out mural faces. JOHNFUNG / 
Los Angeles Times; Photo, Artist Ruben Brucelyn holds picture of the mural that 
once covered the underpass in background. RICARDO De ARATANHA / Los Angeles 
Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MURALS; ARTISTS; GRAFFITI; MISTAKES; ART -- LOS ANGELES; SUNSET BOULEVARD; LOS 
ANGELES -- CULTURE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011990-0028 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 163944 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 19, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 5; Column 5; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
86 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
EARNINGS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Service Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Clorox Co.</ORGANIZATION>: The Oakland-based home products maker said <DATE>second-quarter</DATE> earnings 
rose <PERCENT>6%</PERCENT> from the previous year to <MONEY>$27.02 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Sales rose <PERCENT>9%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$295.6 million</MONEY>. The year-ago quarter's results reflected an 
operating loss from the Olympic paints and stain business, which was sold. The 
company said total shipments of its products -- including <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> liquid bleach, 
Liquid plumr drain opener, Match Light and BBQ Bag charcoal briquettes and 
<ORGANIZATION>Hidden Valley Ranch</ORGANIZATION> bottled salad dressing -- were up. 
</P>
<P>
Tables, D8 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Corporate Earnings 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911126-0032
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911126-0032.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Looking to Latin America for the Next Big Art Boom
   ----
   By Alexandra Peers
</HL>
<DATE>
11/26/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C1
</SO>
<CO>
   BID U.CHR
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
</IN>
<RE>
ARGENTINA (AG)
COLOMBIA (CL)
CENTRAL AMERICA (CME)
EUROPE (EU)
MICHIGAN (MI)
MEXICO (MX)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
SOUTH AMERICA (SM)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
UNITED STATES (US)
VENEZUELA (VE)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Art dealers and auction houses are trying to
turn Latin American art into the next big-boom market,
capitalizing on the economic rebound in Latin America.
   Eighteen months ago, no painting by a Latin American
artist had sold for a million dollars. Now, five have cracked
the million-dollar barrier at auction in the U.S., including
three paintings sold just last week.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   A <DATE>1942</DATE> <PERSON>Diego Rivera</PERSON> portrait of a Mexican woman burdened
with a huge basket of flowers brought a record <MONEY>$2.9 million</MONEY>
at <ORGANIZATION>Christie's International PLC</ORGANIZATION>'s major Latin American
auction in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, and record prices were paid for works by
more than a dozen other Latin American artists.
   The interest in Latin American art comes at a time when
the auction houses are eager to find a new "hot market" amid
the slump in Impressionist and other traditional art markets.
While the auction houses have been phenomenally successful in
selling collectibles lately, toys, rock n' roll memorabilia
and comic books only fetch so much.
   Latin Americans have been active buyers at auctions of
jewelry and European paintings and furniture, and it is only
logical to target them as a major buying force. <PERSON>Christopher
Davidge</PERSON>, managing director of <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, says the
London-based auction house is targeting the Latin American
market because "the industrialization of third world
countries throws up great personal wealth."
   But Latin Americans at last week's series of auction sales
in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> proved to be no Japanese. The powerful, brooding,
expressive paintings of Latin American artists such as
<LOCATION>Rivera</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Rufino Tamayo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Roberto Matta</PERSON> still have a narrow
market. And despite the record prices, the sales were a mixed
bag.
   At <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s evening sale of Latin
American art last week, <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> of the paintings didn't sell, but
several paintings sold for multiples of the prices that the
auction house expected. <ORGANIZATION>Fidelio Ponce de Leon</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1941</DATE> portrait
"Five Women," once owned by director <PERSON>Alfred Hitchcock</PERSON>, sold
for <MONEY>$104,500</MONEY>, about five times what <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION> had expected.
   Altogether, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s raised about <MONEY>$12 million</MONEY> at its
three Latin American sales in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, a tidy sum
considering that sales from <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s flagship department,
Impressionist paintings, totaled <MONEY>$33 million</MONEY> this <DATE>fall</DATE>.
   But the next evening at <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, buyers' appetite for
Latin American art slacked off. About <PERCENT>58%</PERCENT> of the Latin
American art failed to sell, and few works sold for higher
than expected prices. There were even audible groans when
some works by name artists were marooned on the auction
block, including two sculptures by <PERSON>Fernando Botero</PERSON> and two
surrealist works by <PERSON>Matta</PERSON>; the Mattas were estimated by
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s relatively inexpensively at less than <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY>
each.
   A <PERSON>Botero</PERSON> sketch of oversized, fattened pears -- one of 20
<PERSON>Botero</PERSON> works that hit the auction block over the three-day
period -- received no bids whatsoever. The sketch was
estimated to sell for about <MONEY>$150,000</MONEY>.
   Despite the uneven market, collectors agree that
20th-century Latin American art, at its best, is comparable
to top-quality European and American works. At the top of the
Latin American art market are works painted by early
20th-century masters <PERSON>Diego Rivera</PERSON>, a muralist best known for
his paintings of Mexican workers, and <PERSON>Frida Kahlo</PERSON>, whose most
famous works are her intense and compelling self-portraits.
Later in the century, <PERSON>Roberto Matta</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wilfredo Lam</PERSON>, both
surrealist painters, dominated the Latin American paintings
field, along with <PERSON>Rufino Tamayo</PERSON>, a Mexican painter heavily
influenced by European cubists. Better-quality paintings by
these artists routinely fetch six figures.
   In contemporary art, the leading Latin American artists
include <PERSON>Claudio Bravo</PERSON>, whose "Self Portrait," a painting of
leather boots and blue jeans, sold for <MONEY>$495,000</MONEY> last week at
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, tripling his previous record. The Latin American
artist who is perhaps one of the best known in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Botero</PERSON>. His gargantuan, fat-faced figures are in
many <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> museum collections, and last week one of his works
fetched <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> at auction.
   With the surge in the Mexican stock market and economic
recovery in some Latin American nations, the auction houses
are trying to make the paintings of top Mexican, Venezuelan,
Argentinian and Colombian artists status symbols for wealthy
Latin American collectors.
   Meanwhile, as Americans and Europeans discover the
economies and stock markets of <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>, "the world is
discovering the artistic traditions of the region at a time
when people are looking for fresh art," says <PERSON>Robert D.
   Ironically, only <DATE>last April</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s saw the Latin
American market as so moribund that the auction house
canceled its <DATE>spring</DATE> sale of Latin American paintings and
strongly considered shutting down its Latin American art
department.
   However, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s changed its mind after <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s made
money at its <DATE>spring</DATE> Latin American sale. "Let's face it, the
dollar is what counts, and we rang up about <MONEY>$12 million</MONEY>,"
says <PERSON>Lisa Palmer</PERSON>, head of <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s Latin American art
department.
   Sotheby's realized it had some apologizing to do. <PERSON>Diana D.
Brooks</PERSON>, president of the company's <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's Inc.</ORGANIZATION> auction
unit, went on two separate business trips to <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>
<DATE>last month</DATE>. In <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, her five-person entourage included the
former No. 2 person in the firm's Impressionist paintings
department. On her second visit, <PERSON>Mrs. Brooks</PERSON> went to <ORGANIZATION>Rio de
Janiero</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Sao Paulo</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON> in a visit that some in
the art world dubbed the "eat crow" trip.
   "The decision we made was not to whitewash it, but to tell
our clients we made a mistake," <PERSON>Mrs. Brooks</PERSON> says.
Fortunately, "the Latin American clients are very forgiving."
   In each city, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s threw elaborate parties for
clients. At the final reception, held a week ago in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
on the eve of the <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s major Latin American paintings
sale a week ago, 300 people were expected, and 1,200 showed
up; the auction house ran out of clean glasses halfway
through the <TIME>evening</TIME>.
   The auction houses are getting help in trying to generate
excitement about Latin American art. <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> owns a few
paintings by <PERSON>Frida Kahlo</PERSON>, the Mexican artist who has recently
achieved near cult status in the art world; the rock star has
said in interviews that she has commissioned a screenplay in
which she would star as <PERSON>Kahlo</PERSON>.
   Moreover, the auction houses have timing on their side.
The approaching 500-year anniversary of <PERSON>Christopher
Columbus</PERSON>'s voyage to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, plus the Olympics in <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>,
"are going to make <DATE>1992</DATE> very much a Latin year," said
<ORGANIZATION>Goldman</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Mr. Hormats</PERSON>.
   But, now, amid the record prices, there's concern that
strength in the market for at least some Latin American
artists is a fad. "I'm not saying we're going to be `in'
forever," says <PERSON>Mary-Anne Martin</PERSON>, one of the leading dealers
in the field, who paid a record price for a Kahlo in <DATE>1990</DATE>.
"But if there is any worth in these {artworks}, they'll
manage to survive the fad. There are some very good things in
this market, and people see real value there."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880729-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-29-88 0551EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     07-29 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0479</SECOND>
<HEAD>On The Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLAMECY, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cat that apparently preferred <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> walked 620 miles to its old home here, the feline's
former owner says.
   <PERSON>Madeline Martinet</PERSON> said her cat, <LOCATION>Gribouille</LOCATION>, appeared on her
doorstep in this central French city <DATE>this week</DATE>, nearly two years
after he was reported missing from <LOCATION>Reutlingen</LOCATION>, a West German town
near <LOCATION>Stuttgart</LOCATION>.
   Gribouille was 2 months old when <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON> gave him away in
<DATE>July 1986</DATE> to her neighbor, who later moved to <LOCATION>Reutlingen</LOCATION>. The
former neighbor told <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON> that the cat disappeared in
<DATE>October 1986</DATE>.
   ``My son and daughter-in-law found him sick and sleeping in
front of my front door'' on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON> said. ``My
son said, `Why, it's Gribouille.' Then the cat lifted its head and
cried.''
   A veterinarian said the cat had an eye infection, and prescribed
antibiotics. Despite the infection and malnutrition, the cat seems
to be recovering, <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON> said.
   ``He has the same spots and a particular mew that he mews when I
speak to him,'' she said. ``It's definitely little Gribouille.''
   She said she told her former neighbor on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that
<PERSON>Gribouille</PERSON> had been found.
   ``But this time, we are going to keep him,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON>.
``I don't think he liked <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GARDENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cat that apparently preferred <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> walked 620 miles to its old home here, the feline's
former owner says.
   <PERSON>Madeline Martinet</PERSON> said her cat, <LOCATION>Gribouille</LOCATION>, appeared on her
doorstep in this central French city <DATE>this week</DATE>, nearly two years
after he was reported missing from <LOCATION>Reutlingen</LOCATION>, a West German town
near <LOCATION>Stuttgart</LOCATION>.
   Gribouille was 2 months old when <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON> gave him away in
<DATE>July 1986</DATE> to her neighbor, who later moved to <LOCATION>Reutlingen</LOCATION>. The
former neighbor told <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON> that the cat disappeared in
<DATE>October 1986</DATE>.
   ``My son and daughter-in-law found him sick and sleeping in
front of my front door'' on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON> said. ``My
son said, `Why, it's Gribouille.' Then the cat lifted its head and
cried.''
   A veterinarian said the cat had an eye infection, and prescribed
antibiotics. Despite the infection and malnutrition, the cat seems
to be recovering, <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON> said.
   ``He has the same spots and a particular mew that he mews when I
speak to him,'' she said. ``It's definitely little Gribouille.''
   She said she told her former neighbor on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that
<PERSON>Gribouille</PERSON> had been found.
   ``But this time, we are going to keep him,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Martinet</PERSON>.
``I don't think he liked <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880822-0133 </DOCNO>
<HL> PPG to Acquire Grow Group Inc. At $16.625 a Share </HL>
<AUTHOR> Clare Ansberry (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> PPG GRO </CO>
<IN> TNM CON </IN>
<DATELINE> PITTSBURGH  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>PPG Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, trying to bolster its paint business, said it agreed to buy <ORGANIZATION>Grow Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$16.625</MONEY> a share, or about <MONEY>$233 million</MONEY>. 

   PPG said the assumption of <ORGANIZATION>Grow Group</ORGANIZATION> debt would bring its total cost to about <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY>. 

   Grow <ORGANIZATION>Group</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ORGANIZATION> acted as its adviser in evaluating the offer. 
<ORGANIZATION>Drexel</ORGANIZATION> was retained by <ORGANIZATION>Grow Group</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>July</DATE>, shortly after an investor group including <PERSON>Edward S. Buchanan</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> banker, said it had acquired a <PERCENT>6.7%</PERCENT> stake and was considering a tender offer. 

   Last <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Grow Group</ORGANIZATION> announced that it was in talks with a possible buyer. 
After the announcement, its stock jumped <MONEY>$2.625</MONEY> to close at <MONEY>$15.625</MONEY>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION> announcement was made after the market closed. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Grow Group</ORGANIZATION> has 14 million shares outstanding on a fully diluted basis, including a Series C cumulative convertible preferred stock and <PERCENT>8.5%</PERCENT> convertible debentures, both of which are expected to be redeemed before the merger. 
The Series C will be redeemed at <MONEY>$100</MONEY> a share, and the convertible debentures, due in <DATE>2006</DATE>, will be redeemed at <MONEY>$1,068</MONEY> per <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> principal amount. 
The Series P nonredeemable cumulative preferred stock will remain outstanding. 

   Under the agreement approved by both boards, <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION> has the option to buy about 2.8 million shares of Grow's authorized but unissued common at <MONEY>$16.625</MONEY> a share. 
PPG also has the right to terminate the merger agreement during a due-diligence period ending <DATE>Sept. 6</DATE>. 

   The addition of <ORGANIZATION>Grow Group</ORGANIZATION>, a New York-based maker of trade paints and chemical coatings, should help expand PPG's own trade paint business. 

   Trade paints, used by consumers and contractors for homes and buildings, contribute only about <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY> of <ORGANIZATION>PPG</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$5.2 billion</MONEY> in sales. 
But the company has been trying to expand its share of the market, which is <MONEY>$37 billion</MONEY> world-wide. 

   "Grow Group has strength in that business and we're looking for ways to improve our performance in that area," PPG said. 
About <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Grow Group</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$380 million</MONEY> in sales is in the coatings and chemicals business, including trade paints. 
<ORGANIZATION>Grow Group</ORGANIZATION> also has a variety of consumer and professional products, including swimming pool chemicals, spray paints and varnishes. 

   <PERSON>John Frankola</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Parker Hunter Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>Grow Group</ORGANIZATION> will also provide PPG with a new distribution system. 
PPG changed its strategy for marketing its trade paints a few years ago by closing its retail <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> Paint stores. 
Since then, the company has been trying to establish new sources of distribution. 
"This could aid PPG in getting more trade paints into the market," he said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870320-0125 </DOCNO>
<HL> Clorox Says Henkel
Plans to Raise Stake
In Firm Up to 30%</HL>
<DD> 03/20/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CLX
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> OAKLAND, Calif. </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Clorox Co.</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Henkel KGaA</ORGANIZATION> plans to increase its <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> common stock holdings to as much as <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> from a current stake of <PERCENT>24.7%</PERCENT>. 

   <LOCATION>Dusseldorf</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> Germany-based <ORGANIZATION>Henkel</ORGANIZATION> will acquire the shares through purchases on the open market, <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> said, and won't increase its position beyond <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> "for the foreseeable future." 

   Clorox quoted the West German concern as saying <ORGANIZATION>Henkel</ORGANIZATION> views its holdings in the company as an investment, and has no plans to take an active role in <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> management. 
<ORGANIZATION>Henkel</ORGANIZATION> will continue to have two representatives on <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION>'s 15-member board. 

   A spokesman said <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> views <ORGANIZATION>Henkel</ORGANIZATION>'s increased stake as "a good development for the company and its shareholders." 
He cited a joint venture the two concerns operate in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and technology exchanges between the companies as evidence of the "close relationship" between them. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> is a grocery products concern that also makes paints, stains and products for the food-service industry. 
<ORGANIZATION>Henkel</ORGANIZATION> produces household products and chemical specialties. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Henkel</ORGANIZATION> currently owns <PERCENT>23%</PERCENT>, or an indicated 6,102,000, of <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION>'s 26.7 million common shares outstanding. 
The West German concern also holds a subordinated note convertible into 600,000 common shares, or an about <PERCENT>1.7%</PERCENT> additional stake. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> said the <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> ceiling on <ORGANIZATION>Henkel</ORGANIZATION>'s stake would include the equivalent shares represented by the note. 


</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-13266</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EDZEDADCFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940426
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 APR 94 / Arts: Impressionism - back to basics / At the Grand Palais,
William Packer finds the 1859 Paris Salon artists committed to realism
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By WILLIAM PACKER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The closer one looks into the origins of anything the more ambiguous they
become, and the further back they go. Where should we look for the origins
of Impressionism? To the landscape and genre realism of the Dutch 17th
century? Certainly: and to the English 18th and early 19th centuries,
<PERSON>Gainsborough</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, Constable and <PERSON>Turner</PERSON>? Indeed: and to late Titian?
Perhaps: and what about Rembrandt? Yes, if <ORGANIZATION>Courbet</ORGANIZATION> is to be considered in
such a context. And the Spanish connection, from <LOCATION>Velasquez</LOCATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Goya</ORGANIZATION>? Of
course, if Manet is to have anything to do with it.
But these are profound questions, that bespeak a whole ramification of
art-historical possibility. Whatever its implications, the splendid
exhibition at the Grand Palais addresses itself to a narrower period and
more immediate antecedents. This Origins of Impressionism is an exhibition
of French painting set in a French context, and one moreover that continues
ensemble the remarkable series by which the Reunion des musees nationaux,
these 15 years past, has been giving us definitive retrospective studies of
the Impressionist and post-Impressionist masters, one by one.
The starting point is the Salon of <DATE>1859</DATE> at which, of the future major
figures, only the young <PERSON>Pissarro</PERSON> was to be found. Ten years on and they were
all showing there, <ORGANIZATION>Monet</ORGANIZATION> and Manet, <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Degas</LOCATION>, almost as a matter of
course. The Salon indeed supplied the constant critical context for the art
of the period. The only pity is that more has not been made of it as an
actual presence: for the paintings taken to stand for it in <DATE>1859</DATE>, which
include <PERSON>Bouguereau</PERSON>, Puvis de Chavannes, <LOCATION>Corot</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Delacroix</LOCATION>, a
pre-Raphaelitesque <PERSON>Jules Breton</PERSON> and a magnificent large Daubigny riverscape,
are done with perfunctorily in the first two rooms.
Even so, the point is well made and two related myths usefully exploded:
that, though the Salon may have had its good years and its bad ('no
explosion: nothing of unknown genius' grumbled Baudelaire of <DATE>1859</DATE>), it was
never entirely hostile to the young or controversial; and nor were the young
themselves averse to taking their chances of selection. And how close these
young painters were, in their several ways, to the more general
preoccupations of the day; and, as yet, how far from Impressionism. Here we
follow those interests through the <DATE>1860s</DATE>, set out together in successive
galleries: history painting, with its admixture of symbolism; realism; the
nude; the portrait; the still-life; the landscape; the incidents of the
everyday.
The borders between these categories, of course, are never sealed nor even
clear, the cross-overs and mutual intrusions constant and instinctive. Degas
gives us a scene of medieval atrocity as conscientious in its detail as any
pre-Raphaelite, yet in the very pose of its nudes, it anticipates the figure
studies of his later years. The Manet of 'the Angels at the tomb of <ORGANIZATION>Christ</ORGANIZATION>'
is as dramatic in its presentation as a <ORGANIZATION>Caravaggio</ORGANIZATION> and, in the figure of
Christ himself, as confrontationally realist in its nudity as his own
'Olympia'.
This last, indeed, so provoked Courbet by her brazen, matter-of-fact
nakedness, that he replied with his own more suitably symbolic version of
the reclining and ecstatic woman, la Femme au perroquet. Manet replied in
his turn with his own 'Woman with a <ORGANIZATION>Parrot</ORGANIZATION>', though now a full-length
portrait of a young woman in a long white morning-gown, standing by her
pet's perch. All three are shown, altogether a most satisfying if
ill-tempered exchange of masterpieces.
The question of realism lies at the heart of it all. Yet in what does that
realism consist and to what degree should it be tempered? Is it the symbolic
realism of <PERSON>Degas</PERSON>' Spartan boys and girls of <DATE>1860</DATE>, or is it the no less
symbolic but plein air realism of <LOCATION>Bazille</LOCATION>'s young men at their bathing party
of <DATE>1869</DATE>? Is the truth of modern life rather the boats and light dancing on
the water at la Grenouillere, of <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Monet</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1869</DATE>, or that of <PERSON>Degas</PERSON>'
darkly ambiguous interior, le Viol, of the same year? At the <DATE>end of the
decade</DATE> we find <ORGANIZATION>Courbet</ORGANIZATION> still committed to realism in its social aspect, with
his poor village woman in the snow, with her child and goat and bundle of
firewood. And there beside it is Monet's magpie sitting on the gate, and the
image simply of farm and field and hedgerow in the snow, all pink and blue
and violet shadow.
This is an exhibition full of wonderful, ravishing things. But set out as it
is, and quite rightly so, neither by chronology nor by artist but in
thematic groups, it raises a question it can hardly answer. Here was the
modern painting of the day, and young artists who knew each other and even
worked together, but were clearly doing different things. Realism and
symbolism, yes: and the formal portrait and the nude, and the landscape and
the genre scene: but Impressionism? Not quite yet: indeed, the more we look
into it, the more we wonder whether there was ever to be any such thing at
all.
Impressionnisme: les origines 1859-1869 - <LOCATION>Grand Palais</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> 8me, until
<DATE>August 8</DATE>, then to the Metropolitan Museum of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>FRZ  France, EC.
    USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8412 Museums and Art Galleries.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880726-0142 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS: Time Off: Diversions and Excursions July 26-Aug. 8 </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
      ART
   <LOCATION>Los Angeles County</LOCATION> Museum of Art unveils six new galleries devoted to the ancient art of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Asia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. 
Highlights include huge carved stone panels (weighing more than a ton each) from the palace of the Assyrian king Ashurnasirpal II (883-858 B.C.); a selection of northern European metalwork, including Celtic bronzes from <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>; and two Roman marble sculptures, of the Hope <ORGANIZATION>Athena</ORGANIZATION> and the Hope <ORGANIZATION>Hygeia</ORGANIZATION> (late 5th and late 4th centuries B.C.), found together in <DATE>1797</DATE> in the ruins of a second-century public building at <LOCATION>Ostia</LOCATION>, the port of <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>. 5905 <ORGANIZATION>Wilshire Boulevard</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>: "Perennials: A Fiftieth Anniversary Selection From the Berg Collection" -- About 150 works from the library's <ORGANIZATION>Berg Collection</ORGANIZATION> of English and American Literature, a celebrated assortment of first editions, rare books, autograph letters and manuscripts. 
Of special interest are a first folio of <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s plays (1623); a rare first edition of <PERSON>Poe</PERSON>'s earliest book, "<LOCATION>Tamerlane</LOCATION> and Other Poems"; and a first edition of <PERSON>Lewis Carroll</PERSON>'s "Alice's Adventures in <LOCATION>Wonderland</LOCATION>" inscribed to the real <PERSON>Alice</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alice Pleasance Liddell</PERSON>. 
Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street. 
Through <DATE>Dec. 3</DATE>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>National Museum of Racing</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame, <LOCATION>Saratoga Springs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>: "Equine Art From the <PERSON>Paul Mellon</PERSON> Collection" -- The museum reopens after a 10-month, <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY> renovation with an exhibit of 42 paintings depicting racing scenes in 18th- and 19th-century <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. 
The works, assembled by philanthropist <PERSON>Paul Mellon</PERSON> over a 30-year period, are by artists including <PERSON>George Stubbs</PERSON>, <PERSON>Benjamin Marshall</PERSON> and <PERSON>James Pollard</PERSON>. 
Union Avenue, through <DATE>Oct. 10</DATE>. 

   Baltimore Museum of Art: "Navajo Textiles: 1860-1940" -- Rugs, blankets and women's dress from the museum's permanent collection of Native American art are on view through <DATE>Oct. 30</DATE>. 
On <DATE>Sept. 10</DATE> and 11, catch a demonstration of traditional Navajo weaving (3 <TIME>p.m.-5 p.m.</TIME> each day) and three short documentary films -- "Weavers of the West," "Painting With Sand: A Navajo Ceremony" and "Hopi: Songs of the Fourth World" (beginning at 1 p.m). 
Art Museum Drive. 

   <ORGANIZATION>IBM Gallery of Science</ORGANIZATION> and Art, <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>: "18th-20th Century European and American Painting and Sculpture: Highlights From the Collection of the Museum of Art, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> School of Design" -- Almost 70 paintings and sculptures by artists including <PERSON>William Merritt Chase</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Singleton Copley</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Cezanne</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Degas</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rodin</PERSON>. 
Look for <ORGANIZATION>Manet</ORGANIZATION>'s "Portrait of <PERSON>Berthe Morisot</PERSON>" (circa 1870), of the artist's sister-inlaw and colleague; for a pretty pair of Monets -- "The Basin at <LOCATION>Argenteuil</LOCATION>" (1874), painted in the same year as the first impressionist exhibition in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, and "The Seine at <LOCATION>Giverny</LOCATION>" (<DATE>1885</DATE>) -- and for <PERSON>Winslow Homer</PERSON>'s "On a Lee Shore" (<DATE>1900</DATE>), considered one of the artist's best. 
Madison Avenue at 56th Street, through <DATE>Sept. 10</DATE>. 

   FESTIVAL
   Viennese Sommerfest <DATE>'88</DATE>: "<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION> and the Musical Personality" -- Conductor <PERSON>Leonard Slatkin</PERSON> returns for the <ORGANIZATION>Minnesota Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>'s ninth annual celebration of the music and culture of <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>. 
Joining him in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> are artists-in-residence <PERSON>Joseph Silverstein</PERSON> (conductor and violin), <PERSON>John Browning</PERSON> (piano), <PERSON>Jeffrey Swann</PERSON> (piano) and <PERSON>Lynn Harrell</PERSON> (cello). 
A full concert performance of <ORGANIZATION>Puccini</ORGANIZATION>'s "Tosca" has soprano <PERSON>Leona Mitchell</PERSON> in the title role, baritone <PERSON>Sherrill Milnes</PERSON> as Scarpia and tenor <PERSON>Ruben Dominguez</PERSON> as <ORGANIZATION>Cavaradossi</ORGANIZATION>. 
Orchestra <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>, <DATE>1111</DATE> Nicollet Mall; and the adjacent <LOCATION>Peavey Plaza</LOCATION>. 
Through <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE>. (612) 371-5656. 

   MUSIC
   Classical Jazz -- <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln Center</ORGANIZATION>'s first jazz series opens its second season, under the artistic direction of <LOCATION>Wynton Marsalis</LOCATION>. 
Artists being honored are <ORGANIZATION>Duke Ellington</ORGANIZATION>, composer/arranger <PERSON>Tadd Dameron</PERSON> and drummer <PERSON>Max Roach</PERSON>. 
Also on offer: "<DATE>Saturday</DATE> Night Songbook," spotlighting the different types of classic jazz singing; and "Standards on Horn," which includes <PERSON>Mr. Marsalis</PERSON> performing for the first time with Sweets <PERSON>Edison</PERSON> and <PERSON>Doc Cheatham</PERSON>, two of his mentors. 
<PERSON>Alice Tully Hall</PERSON>, Broadway at 65th Street. 
Aug. 5-10. (212) 877-1800, ext. 514, for information; (212) 874-6770 for tickets. 

   Bryan Ferry: The debonair British song stylist makes his first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> tour since the demise of his influential band <ORGANIZATION>Roxy Music</ORGANIZATION>. 
Dates include: <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> (Tower Theatre), <DATE>Aug. 5</DATE>; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> (Great Woods), <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE>; <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> (Radio City), Aug. 9-11; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Chastain Park</LOCATION>), <DATE>Aug. 14</DATE>; <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> (Constitution Hall), <DATE>Aug. 15</DATE>; <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> (Forum), <DATE>Aug. 18</DATE>; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Nautica</ORGANIZATION> Stage), <DATE>Aug. 23</DATE>; <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION> (Performing Arts Center), <DATE>Aug. 26</DATE>; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> (Arie Crown Theatre), <DATE>Aug. 27-28</DATE>; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Northrup Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Aug. 30</DATE>; <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> (Olympic Saddledome), <DATE>Sept. 2</DATE>; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> (Fifth Avenue Theatre), <DATE>Sept. 6</DATE>; <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> (Greek Theatre), <DATE>Sept. 10</DATE>; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> (Red Rocks), <DATE>Sept. 13</DATE>; <LOCATION>Mesa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Mesa</LOCATION> Amphitheatre), <DATE>Sept. 15</DATE>; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> (Greek Theatre), <DATE>Sept. 18</DATE>. 
