<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900725-0235 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-25-90 1554EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-DeBeers-SovietDiamonds Bjt   07-25 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-De Beers-Soviet Diamonds, Bjt,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dominant Diamond Business De Beers In Deal For Soviet Output</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COTTEN TIMBERLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   De Beers tightened its grip on the global diamond
market <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with an exclusive five-year deal to sell the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s rough diamond output, which could total more than <MONEY>$5
billion</MONEY>.
   The financially strained <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, among the world's biggest
gem diamond producers, will get a <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> advance against future
diamond sales.
   De Beers' London-based marketing arm, the <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling
Organization</ORGANIZATION>, will strengthen its position as the world's dominant
diamond seller. It already markets <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of global rough
diamond production of some 100 million carats.
   The Soviets do not disclose their output.
   The nation reached the deal because it wanted to sell a huge
stockpile of diamonds without disrupting the stable world diamond
market, De Beers said.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> had refused to deal directly with the South
African-based company because of its home country's policies of
racial separation, but now is willing to do business openly with De
Beers' new Swiss arm, De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Centenary AG</ORGANIZATION>.
   De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> established the publicly-held
Swiss company in <DATE>May</DATE> to head the non-South African businesses of De
Beers, which is controlled by the wealthy Oppenheimer family of
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Centenary</ORGANIZATION> said in a statement released in <LOCATION>Lucerne</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION> and made available in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> that it reached the
agreement with Glavalmazzoloto of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> for the
exclusive export and sale of the <ORGANIZATION>USSR</ORGANIZATION> diamond production.
   Glavalmazzoloto is the main administration for precious metals
and diamonds under the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s council of ministers, De
Beers said.
   De Beers' Luxembourg-based subsidiary, <ORGANIZATION>Centenary Holdings SA</ORGANIZATION>,
has agreed to advance Glavalmazzoloto <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> against future
diamond deliveries. Repayment would be made over five years
beginning in <DATE>November</DATE>.
   The Soviet diamond stockpile will be held at De Beers'
London-based marketing arm, the <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, as
collateral for the advance, De Beers said.
   The organization, a 57-year-old cartel, has the financial
resources to hold large stocks of diamonds, which is how it keeps
the market stable.
   Although De Beers said it had had no direct contact with the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> since <DATE>1963</DATE>, diamond experts say De Beers already sells
most of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s West-bound diamonds.
   ``We have not had an official agreement with the Russians. In
the past, obviously, being major distributors of rough (diamonds),
Russian diamonds have found their way into the rough,'' said De
Beers spokesman <PERSON>Roger Van Eeghen</PERSON>. ``It came through other sources,
other channels.''
   All the world's major diamond producers, including <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, have sales contracts with
De Beers Centenary. The <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION> had sales of
<MONEY>$4.09 billion</MONEY> last year.
   De Beers must renegotiate several key contracts this year, which
experts have said might loosen its grip on the diamond market.
   The formal marketing of the Soviet diamonds, like those from
elsewhere, will take place in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Lucerne</LOCATION>, De Beers said.
   <PERSON>Julian Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON>, De Beers chairman, said the deal would
bring ``continued stability and prosperity of the international
diamond industry.''
   <PERSON>Nicholas Oppenheimer</PERSON>, deputy chairman of De Beers Centenary,
said the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, at a time of ``considerable financial
strain,'' was able to raise a <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> loan while signing a
contract assuring it of ``a steady flow of funds from diamonds''
over the next five years.
   Large-scale diamond mining began in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> in the
<DATE>1950s</DATE> and is concentrated in the <LOCATION>Yakutia</LOCATION> region of <LOCATION>North Eastern
Siberia</LOCATION>, De Beers said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900726-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-26-90 0649EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Soviet-Diamonds     07-26 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Soviet-Diamonds,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>De Beers Tightens Grip on Diamond Market With Soviet Deal</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COTTEN TIMBERLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> will get more badly needed
foreign hard currency by selling its rough diamonds exclusively
through the South African giant De Beers in a five-year
multibillion-dollar agreement.
   The company is advancing the Soviets <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> against future
diamond sales, said officials who announced the agreement on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, among the world's largest diamond producers,
reached the deal with De Beers because it wanted to sell a huge
stockpile of diamonds without disrupting the market, De Beers said.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> had refused to deal directly with the South
African company because of apartheid, but now is willing to openly
do business with De Beers' new Swiss arm, De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Centenary AG</ORGANIZATION>.
   South Africa-based De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, controlled
by the Oppenheimer family of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, established the
publicly-held Swiss company in <DATE>May</DATE>.
   De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Centenary</ORGANIZATION> said in a statement that it reached the
agreement with Glavalmazzoloto of the <ORGANIZATION>USSR</ORGANIZATION> for the exclusive export
and sale of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s diamond production.
   Glavalmazzoloto is the main administration for precious metals
and diamonds under the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s council of ministers, De
Beers said.
   It said its Luxembourg-based subsidiary, <ORGANIZATION>Centenary Holdings SA</ORGANIZATION>,
has agreed to make a secured advance of <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> to
Glavalmazzoloto against future diamond deliveries.
   Repayment would be made over five years beginning in <DATE>November</DATE>,
it said.
   <PERSON>Nicholas Oppenheimer</PERSON>, deputy chairman of <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Centenary</ORGANIZATION>,
said as a result of the agreement that the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, at a time
of ``considerable financial strain,'' was assured ``a steady flow
of funds from diamonds'' during the life of the contract.
   Company officials estimated the contract could be worth as much
as <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>.
   <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> has been seeking foreign credit as it tries to bring
market-oriented reform to an economy plagued by shortages.
   The Soviet diamond stockpile will be held at De Beers'
London-based marketing arm, the <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, as
collateral for the <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> advance, De Beers said.
   The organization, a 57-year-old cartel, has the financial
resources to hold large stocks of diamonds, which is how it keeps
the market stable.
   Although De Beers said it had had no direct contact with the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> since <DATE>1963</DATE>, diamond experts say De Beers already sells
most of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s West-bound diamonds.
   All the world's major diamond producers, including <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, have sales contracts with
De Beers Centenary. The <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, as a result,
markets <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the world's rough diamond production of some
100 million carats.
   The organization had sales of <MONEY>$4.09 billion</MONEY> last year.
   Large-scale diamond mining began in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> in the
<DATE>1950s</DATE> and is concentrated in the <LOCATION>Yakutia</LOCATION> region of <LOCATION>North Eastern
Siberia</LOCATION>, De Beers said. The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> doesn't disclose the value
of its output.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072690-0184 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 252832 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 26, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 7; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
322 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DE BEERS SIGNS DIAMOND DEAL WITH SOVIETS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
LONDON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
De Beers tightened its grip on the global diamond market <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with an 
exclusive five-year deal to sell the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s rough diamond output, which 
could total more than <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The financially strained <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, among the world's biggest gem diamond 
producers, will get a <MONEY>$1-billion</MONEY> advance against future diamond sales. 
</P>
<P>
De Beers' London-based marketing arm, the <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, will 
strengthen its position as the world's dominant diamond seller. It already 
markets <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of global rough diamond production of some 100 million carats. 
</P>
<P>
The Soviets do not disclose their output. 
</P>
<P>
The nation reached the deal because it wanted to sell a huge stockpile of 
diamonds without disrupting the stable world diamond market, De Beers said. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> had refused to deal directly with the South African-based 
company because of its home country's policies of racial separation, but now is 
willing to do business openly with De Beers' new Swiss arm, De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Centenary 
AG</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> established the publicly held Swiss company in 
<DATE>May</DATE> to head the non-South African businesses of De Beers, which is controlled 
by the wealthy Oppenheimer family of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Centenary</ORGANIZATION> said in a statement released in <LOCATION>Lucerne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, and 
made available in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> that it reached the agreement with Glavalmazzoloto of 
the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> for the exclusive export and sale of the <LOCATION>U.S.S.R.</LOCATION> diamond 
production. 
</P>
<P>
Glavalmazzoloto is the main administration for precious metals and diamonds 
under the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s council of ministers, De Beers said. 
</P>
<P>
De Beers' Luxembourg-based subsidiary, <ORGANIZATION>Centenary Holdings SA</ORGANIZATION>, has agreed to 
advance Glavalmazzoloto <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> against future diamond deliveries. Repayment 
would be made over five years beginning in <DATE>November</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The Soviet diamond stockpile will be held at De Beers' marketing arm as 
collateral for the advance, De Beers said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
DE BEERS CONSOLIDATED MINES LTD; DE BEERS CENTRAL SELLING ORGANIZATION; ENGLAND 
-- TRADE -- USSR; SOUTH AFRICA -- TRADE -- USSR; USSR -- FOREIGN POLICY; MINING 
-- USSR; DIAMONDS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900306-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-06-90 1321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-DeBeers     03-06 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-De Beers,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>South African Diamond Giant To Split Into Two</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COTTEN TIMBERLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, the huge South
African diamond mining concern, said <DATE>today</DATE> it would split itself in
two and base one of the newly formed companies in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
   The move appeared to be an attempt by the company to minimize
its exposure to potential political turbulence in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>,
where a newly energized black majority has vowed to nationalize
major industries if it wins power from the white minority.
   But De Beers Chairman <PERSON>Julian Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> denied that there
were political reasons for the company's split, saying it reflected
the international nature of De Beers and the diamond business and
that it was in the interests of shareholders and the industry. He
also said the company's earnings jumped <PERCENT>37 percent</PERCENT> <DATE>last year</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> made his comments at a <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION> news conference to
which <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> reporters were hooked up.
   De Beers' shares jumped 1.80 pounds, or <MONEY>$2.97</MONEY>, to 13.63 pounds,
or <MONEY>$22.49</MONEY>, on <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> today after <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> spoke.
   The South African company will continue to be called De <ORGANIZATION>Beers
Consolidated Mines</ORGANIZATION>. De Beers' foreign businesses, which accounted
for <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of De Beers' <DATE>1989</DATE> net profit, will be grouped under
a Swiss company to be called <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Centenary AG</ORGANIZATION>, it said.
   De Beers said it would split itself by giving existing
shareholders one share in the Centenary company for each De Beers
share they already own.
   <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> also denied that the decision was linked to the
failure of <ORGANIZATION>Minorco SA</ORGANIZATION>'s failed hostile takeover bid for the British
mining company <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Gold Fields PLC</ORGANIZATION> last year. That bid by
<ORGANIZATION>Minorco</ORGANIZATION>, which is controlled by De Beers and the <ORGANIZATION>Anglo American
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, was seen as a move by the gold and diamond mining empire to
diversify away from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> said the plan had been under active discussion
since <DATE>last year</DATE>.
   De Beers said its earnings for <DATE>1989</DATE> came to <MONEY>2.87 billion</MONEY> rand,
about <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY> at current exchange rates, vs. <MONEY>2.09 billion</MONEY> rand
in <DATE>1988</DATE>. Revenue rose <PERCENT>31 percent</PERCENT> to 4.2 billion rand from 3.2
billion rand.
   The company didn't break out quarterly or six-month results.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900307-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-90 0242EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-DeBeers     03-07 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-De Beers,0608</SECOND>
<HEAD>De Beers Plans To Split South African Operations From Foreign</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COTTEN TIMBERLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> plans to split
its foreign operations from its South African business in an
apparent move to shelter the huge diamond mining company from
political turmoil in <LOCATION>South African</LOCATION>.
   De Beers said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the plans were intended to focus attention
on the company's international nature and its true business value.
   ``Basically it's going to lose some, if not all of the discount
of being a South African share,'' said <PERSON>Rob Davies</PERSON>, a mining analyst
at <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman Hutton International</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   De Beers also announced its net profit soared <PERCENT>37 percent</PERCENT> last
year.
   Chairman <PERSON>Julian Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> denied there were political
reasons for the company's split.
   Speaking at a <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION> news conference that was relayed to
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, he said the split would give De Beers better access to
international capital markets; enable shareholders to better
identify earnings, dividends and assets attributable to the South
African and foreign sides of the business; and allow the two sides
to develop their businesses better.
   Analysts said the move would insulate the company _ which in
<DATE>1989</DATE> made <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of its profit from foreign businesses _ from
its South African ties and from moves to end white-minority rule in
that country.
   The <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> party has said it would
nationalize <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s mines and other major sectors of the
economy, if it comes into power.
   Furthermore, many investors are reluctant to invest in South
African companies because of its government policies of racial
separation. In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, government sanctions prohibit
Americans from making fresh investments in South African equities.
   ``It should open up the share to a wider market,'' <PERSON>Davies</PERSON> said
of the De Beers plan.
   <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> also denied that the plan was linked to <ORGANIZATION>Minorco
SA</ORGANIZATION>'s failed hostile takeover bid for the British mining company
<ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Gold Fields PLC</ORGANIZATION> last year.
   The bid by <ORGANIZATION>Minorco</ORGANIZATION>, which is controlled by De Beers and the
associated <ORGANIZATION>Anglo American Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, was seen as an attempt by <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>'s Oppenheimer family to diversify its gold and diamond
mining empire further outside <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   Under the proposed split, De Beers' South African company will
continue to be called De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Consolidated Mines</ORGANIZATION>. De Beers'
foreign businesses would be grouped under a Swiss company, <ORGANIZATION>De Beers
Centenary AG</ORGANIZATION>, although both companies will be headed by the same
board of directors.
   De Beers said it would give existing shareholders one share in
Centenary for each De Beers share they own. The two shares will be
tradeable only as a single unit on the nine exchanges where De
Beers shares are traded, the company said.
   De Beers said it would retain a <PERCENT>9.5 percent</PERCENT> stake in Centenary.
   <PERSON>John Taylor</PERSON>, an analyst at the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> investment firm <ORGANIZATION>James
Capel and Co.</ORGANIZATION>, said, ``Essentially, it's an extremely cheap share.
People were giving it a low rating because of the politics of
investing in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.''
   The split means ``the political risk to a certain extent has
disappeared,'' <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. De Beers can just allow shares in the
companies to trade separately if the situation in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>
deteriorates, he said.
   The plan is subject to final approval by South African
regulators, who have approved in principle. It also must be
approved by shareholders. Support already has been given by <ORGANIZATION>Anglo
American</ORGANIZATION>, which has a <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT> stake, and <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Botswana
Mining Co.</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Pty) Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, which holds <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870703-0111 </DOCNO>
<HL> De Beers Says Board to Get
2 Members From Botswana
---
<DD> 07/03/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> DBRSY AFRIC
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS) </IN>
<DATELINE> LONDON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> will add two directors from <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> and buy a diamond stockpile from the black African state, the company said. 

   De Beers, a South African company that controls <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the world diamond market, said it agreed to issue 20 million shares valued at about <MONEY>$225 million</MONEY> and to pay some additional cash to <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Botswana Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, jointly owned by the government of <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> and De Beers Consolidated. 

   After the share issue, De Beers <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> will own more than <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> of the South African concern's shares. 
In return, <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Consolidated</ORGANIZATION> will acquire a stockpile of diamonds built up by <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> during a diamond-market depression from <DATE>1982</DATE> to <DATE>1985</DATE>. 
De Beers wouldn't disclose the size of the cash payment or the diamond stockpile. 

   "We have had a relationship with <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> for 20 years; we discovered the diamonds and helped manage the mines," said <PERSON>Gary Ralfe</PERSON>, a director of the <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, De Beers's London-based marketing division that controls the international market in rough diamonds. 
He wouldn't comment on any political implications of naming persons from the black African state to the De Beers board. 

   De Beers <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> will choose the executives who will join the De Beers Consolidated board, <PERSON>Mr. Ralfe</PERSON> said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910426-0153
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910426-0153.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   De Beers Says Sales
   Of Diamonds Plunged
   During First Quarter
   ----
</HL>
<DATE>
04/26/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B4A
</SO>
<CO>
   DBRSY
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
</MS>
<IN>
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
INTERNATIONAL TRADE NEWS (TRD)
</IN>
<NS>
TRADE ISSUES (TRD)
</NS>
<RE>
SOUTH AFRICA (SF)
</RE>
<LP>
   LONDON -- Diamond sales of De Beers Consolidated Mines
Ltd. "fell substantially" in the first quarter, Julian
Ogilvie Thompson, chairman, said.
   Compared with the year-earlier period, first-quarter sales
slumped by a third to around $1 billion, De Beers officials
and dealers said.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The downturn, which is a continuation of poor sales in the
<DATE>second half of last year</DATE>, was the result of weakening
economies and uncertainty during the Gulf conflict, <PERSON>Mr.
Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> said.
   In the <DATE>first three months of 1990</DATE>, however, the sales
known as "sights" were unusually high, <PERSON>Mr. Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON>
said. Japanese dealers were then buying ahead of changes in
the turnover tax, he said. So the latest <DATE>first-quarter</DATE>
decline must be considered in perspective, he said at a
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> press conference.
   Nevertheless, trade is slower at the main diamond centers
of <LOCATION>Antwerp</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tel Aviv</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, De Beers officials said. As
a result, De Beers, which controls <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the world's rough
uncut diamonds, is supporting the market by reducing amounts
of diamonds sold to the centers, they said.
   Last year, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> imports of rough and polished diamonds
fell to 7.5 million carats worth <MONEY>$3.9 billion</MONEY> from 10.2
million carats valued at <MONEY>$4.3 billion</MONEY>, said the <ORGANIZATION>American
Diamond Industry Association</ORGANIZATION>. The volume of sales fared worse
than value because of a slump in low-quality diamonds, mainly
supplied by <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. A carat equals 1/142 of an ounce.
   Diamond markets in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> were better than in
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>, dealers said. But this year's surge of
the dollar has raised the price of diamonds in local
currencies, dealers said. Economies are also slowing down and
denting demand for luxury goods, they said.
   To counter the downturn in the market, De Beers's
marketing budget will be around <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY> this year, <PERSON>Mr.
Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> said. The diamond jewelry trade will also be
spending around <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY>, De Beers officials said.
   Meanwhile, De Beers is anxious to preserve its diamond
cartel of producers in the present weak market, dealers say.
It recently negotiated a contract to sell three quarters of
<LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>'s production and is discussing new contracts with key
producers <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, they said.
   De Beers is expected to sell all of <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s output, <PERSON>Mr.
Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> said. But negotiations with <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> will
continue for longer than expected, said <PERSON>Nicholas Oppenheimer</PERSON>,
a De Beers director. <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> wants to sell a much higher
proportion of its valuable gems independently on world
markets, dealers said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06123092 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06123092 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; The fully cut and polished Centenary diamond
weighed 273 carats, down from 599 in its rough state.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  COLLECTIBLE; LONDON  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Have more than $100 million to blow?;    If so, De Beers has a diamond for
you: the 273-carat Centenary diamond, the largest, modern-cut, flawless
polished diamond in the world.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GIGANTIC DIAMOND ON DISPLAY IN LONDON  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     De Beers unveiled the heart-shaped jewel in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, with a lot
of security and a touch of drama.;    The room was darkened, then a curtain
opened. A spotlight lighted up an egg-sized diamond, sparkling on a rotating
stand and reflecting colored light around the room.;    "A truly rare and
unique diamond," said <PERSON>Nicky Oppenheimer</PERSON>, deputy chairman of his family's
diamond-mining empire, <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>;    The gem is unique
and thus impossible to value, he said, though De Beers has insured it for at
least <MONEY>$100 million.</MONEY>;    There are only two larger diamonds in the world, and
<ORGANIZATION>Queen Elizabeth II</ORGANIZATION> owns them.;    The largest is the 530.2-carat Great Star of
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> in the imperial scepter, and the 317.4-carat Lesser Star of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> in
the imperial crown. They are kept in the Tower of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, and their value is
not known.;    Both were cut 86 years ago from one gem, the <PERSON>Cullinan</PERSON> diamond
that was 3,106 carat rough. Like the Centenary, it was found in De Beers'
Premier mine in <LOCATION>South Africa.</LOCATION>;    The <PERSON>Cullinan</PERSON> diamond was cut before the
"brilliant" cut was fully developed in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>. This involves cutting facets
to reflect the most possible light.;    The Centenary was found in the
mid-1980s through the normal mechanized mining process in the mine,
<ORGANIZATION>Oppenheimer</ORGANIZATION> said.;    The rough Centenary diamond, which weighed 599 carats,
was unveiled at the company's centenary celebrations in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> in <DATE>1988.</DATE>;
   It then took three years to prepare, cut and polish the jewel, <ORGANIZATION>Oppenheimer</ORGANIZATION>
said. The Centenary diamond is more than twice the size of the next largest
comparable stone, the company said.;    <PERSON>Gabi Tolkowsky</PERSON>, whose great-uncle
developed the modern cutting methods, cut the Centenary diamond in a cellar in
<LOCATION>Johannesburg.</LOCATION>;    The Centenary was a difficult stone to cut and polish
because its shape did not suggest an obvious approach for yielding the jewel
locked within, the company said. In its rough form, the diamond resembled an
irregular matchbox.;    "Every day I was looking at it, but at night, it was
looking at me," <PERSON>Tolkowsky</PERSON> joked.;    Finally, he said, it "talked to me and
said, 'This is the shape I want.' ";    De Beers intends to exhibit the
diamond around the world, <ORGANIZATION>Oppenheimer</ORGANIZATION> said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  London  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910502  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  429  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday May 2, 1991
00123092,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900726-0134
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900726-0134.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Soviets Will Sell Diamonds to De Beers's
   Swiss Arm, Borrow $1 Billion From Firm
   ----
   By Neil Behrmann
</HL>
<DATE>
07/26/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<CO>
   JAPAN FREST DBRSY
</CO>
<IN>
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
</IN>
<LP>
   LONDON -- The cash-strapped Soviet Union is selling
diamonds worth $5 billion to the Swiss arm of De Beers
Consolidated Mines Ltd. and is borrowing $1 billion from the
company.
   The contract between De Beers Centenary AG and
Glavalmazzoloto, the Soviet adminstration for precious metals
and diamonds, is for the exclusive sale of Soviet rough uncut
diamonds over five years, said Gary Ralfe, a director of De
Beers Centenary. The company also received $1 billion of
diamonds as collateral, and Mr. Ralfe said these diamonds
would be sold during the five-year period to redeem the debt.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The deal obviously suits both parties, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> diamond
dealers say. The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> has been having difficulty
paying its overseas trade creditors, and De Beers wants to
stop the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and other producing nations from
selling increasing amounts of diamonds outside the De Beers
diamond cartel.
   De Beers is negotiating new sales contracts with <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, so guaranteed diamond supplies from the
Soviets will encourage other members to toe the line, dealers
said. The South African cartel, which controls <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the
international rough diamond market, sells stones from its own
mines and those of other African countries, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and
elsewhere through its London-based <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling
Organization</ORGANIZATION>.
   While De Beers Centenary is a Swiss company, <PERSON>Mr. Ralfe</PERSON>
said the sale represented the first time in nearly three
decades that the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> had openly associated itself
with commodities dealings linked to a South African company.
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> are the world's biggest
producers of gold, platinum and a variety of strategic
metals, and in the past few years sometimes surreptitiously
cooperated on sales tactics, dealers say. The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>,
for example, sold its diamonds to the De Beers diamond cartel
through intermediaries, <PERSON>Mr. Ralfe</PERSON> said.
   "This is a very important deal for both the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>
and De Beers," said <PERSON>Nicholas Oppenheimer</PERSON>, deputy chairman of
De Beers. The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> is raising <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> at a time of
considerable financial strain, while the contract will
contribute to the continued stability and prosperity of the
international diamond industry, he said.
   Estimates that the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> produces 12 million carats
of diamonds a year, or <PERCENT>13%</PERCENT> of world output, are conservative,
<PERSON>Mr. Ralfe</PERSON> said. Its mines in the <LOCATION>Yaktia</LOCATION> region of
northeastern <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION> are rich, and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> are the two largest producers of gem diamonds in the
world, he said.
   <PERSON>Viktor Gerashchenko</PERSON>, chairman of <LOCATION>Gosbank</LOCATION>, the Soviet state
bank, announced previously that the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> would sell
and deposit gold and other commodities as collateral to raise
about <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>. Indeed, about 200 to 300 metric tons of
gold deposited as collateral with Western banks, has already
been "swapped" for foreign exchange, bullion dealers
estimate. The nation is forced to use commodities as
collateral for loans because delays in payments to suppliers
in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> are discouraging foreign banks from
lending it money, analysts say.
   Those sales may already be having an effect: Just
yesterday, a Japanese trade organization reported that
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s overdue payments for Japanese exports had leveled
off in <DATE>June</DATE>, after rising for six straight months. The group
said payment arrears by Soviet trading organizations totaled
<MONEY>$446 million</MONEY> at the end of <DATE>June</DATE>, only a <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> increase
from <DATE>May</DATE>. The trade group attributed the leveling off both to
increased payments by the Soviets and to the fact that
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s trading houses were more hesitant about doing
business with Soviet concerns.
   "I believe this problem is passing its peak," an official
of one major Japanese trading house told <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Kyodo news
service.
   <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s foreign borrowings amounted to as much as <MONEY>$43
billion</MONEY> at the end of <DATE>1989</DATE>, estimates the <ORGANIZATION>Bank for
International Settlements</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910313-0049
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910313-0049.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   International:
   De Beers's Net Fell 16%
   In `Quiet' Diamond Year
   ----
</HL>
<DATE>
03/13/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A10
</SO>
<CO>
   DBRSY
</CO>
<IN>
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
EARNINGS (ERN)
</IN>
<LP>
   JOHANNESBURG -- De Beers, the world's largest diamond
producer comprising Swiss-based De Beers Centenary AG and De
Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd. of South Africa, reported a 16%
drop in net income for 1990.
   Combined net income of the two companies in 1990 fell to
billion, or $2.96 a share, in 1989.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Total dividend distribution amounted to <MONEY>$1.113</MONEY>, compared
with <MONEY>$1.102</MONEY> the year before.
   <PERSON>Julian Ogilvie-Thompson</PERSON>, chairman of the De Beers diamond
group, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he is optimistic that the world diamond
market will improve in <DATE>1991</DATE>, after a "quiet year" in <DATE>1990</DATE>. He
said a decline in profits had been expected, although the
<LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> crisis aggravated the drop in retail sales.
   De Beers Centenary, which controls all group business
outside <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, including <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, and
accounts for about <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of total earnings, was established a
year ago to facilitate the group's access to international
markets. The South African business remains under the control
of De Beers Consolidated. The foreign and South African
securities trade as one unit.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890131-0280 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-31-89 1931EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Britain-DeBeers     01-31 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-De Beers,0392</SECOND>
<HEAD>Office of Fair Trading To Investigate Complaint Against De Beers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Office of Fair Trading</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> it was
investigating a complaint alleging anti-competitive practices by a
London-based diamond cartel controlled by <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s giant De
Beers diamond organization.
   The watchdog body said De Beers ``appeared to have'' a monopoly
on diamond trading in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and it was interested in establishing
whether there had been an abuse of the monopoly.
   <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Gold Fields PLC</ORGANIZATION>, a British mining concern with no
diamond interests, acknowledged that it filed the complaint as a
defensive move against a stalled takeover bid by Luxembourg-based
<ORGANIZATION>Minorco SA</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Minorco</ORGANIZATION> is <PERCENT>60.1 percent</PERCENT> owned by <ORGANIZATION>Anglo American Corp. of South
Africa Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, the gold and
diamond mining interests controlled by the Oppenheimer family of
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   The British government is expected to rule in the next few weeks
whether to allow <ORGANIZATION>Minorco</ORGANIZATION> to proceed with its 2.9 billion-pound
(about <MONEY>$5.1 billion</MONEY>) bid for Consolidated Gold following an
investigation by the <ORGANIZATION>Monopolies and Mergers Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
   A <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Gold</ORGANIZATION> spokesman, commenting on condition he was not
identified, said the company wanted to point up the ``monopolistic
tendencies'' of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s Anglo-American group of companies.
   De Beers' <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, which controls <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT>
of world diamond trading, has been based in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> for 60 years.
   As well as selling the stones mined by De Beers and other South
African companies, the organization trades on behalf of diamond
producers including <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Office of Fair Trading</ORGANIZATION> said it would first have to establish
whether it had jurisdiction over the <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>
because although it is based in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, De Beers is a South African
company.
   There is no time limit on the office's investigation. After it is
completed, the Office of Fair Trading may decide to refer the
complaint to the <ORGANIZATION>Monopolies and Mergers Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
   A spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION> said the <ORGANIZATION>Office
of Fair Trading</ORGANIZATION> notified the organization about the inquiry but
hadn't yet requested any information.
   ``It's still early'' in the investigation, said the spokesman,
commenting on condition he was not identified.
   De Beers's shares were unchanged <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> on the <ORGANIZATION>London Stock
Exchange</ORGANIZATION> at <MONEY>$12</MONEY> (<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900322-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-22-90 1355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Diamonds Adv25   03-22 1175</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Diamonds, Adv 25,1216</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv25</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, March 25, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Diamond Business Loses Some Sparkle</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also on financial wires.</NOTE>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto, Graphic</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By COTTEN TIMBERLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A stone's throw from the smelly <ORGANIZATION>Smithfield</ORGANIZATION> meat
market is an office building complex with no sign or anything to
attract the attention of Londoners hurrying by.
   Mounted cameras, jumpy guards and heavy doors keep out the
uninvited. The gold-colored interior is hushed and luxuriously
decorated.
   This is the <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, London-based marketing
arm of the De Beers diamond empire, controlled by the wealthy
Oppenheimer family of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. Its experts sort mounds of
rough diamonds constituting <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the world's annual
production.
   But scratch the surface of this secretive world, and the diamond
business loses some sparkle.
   Sales have declined sharply, and the 56-year-old cartel is
facing pressure to give producers better terms and allow them to
sell more of their own gems.
   Although its prosperity and control of the world diamond
industry looks unchallengeable, the pressures could loosen its grip
and crimp its profits.
   ``This year is going to be a critical one for De Beers,'' says
<ORGANIZATION>Diamond Intelligence Briefs</ORGANIZATION>, a trade publication.
   De Beers' South African interests face an uncertain future,
largely because of a newly energized political will by the black
majority in that country, an important diamond producer. The
<ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> has pledged to nationalize <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s
major sources of wealth if it takes power.
   Apparently attempting to limit risk, De Beers recently announced
it would split South African and foreign interests into two
publicly held companies, one based in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
   After growth spurts of <PERCENT>19 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>1987</DATE> and <PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> in
<DATE>1988</DATE>, rough diamond sales fell <PERCENT>2 percent</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$4.09 billion</MONEY> last year
because of slowing economies, high interest rates and the
organization's two double-digit price increases in <DATE>1988</DATE> and <DATE>1989</DATE>.
   The decline was sharpest in the <DATE>second half of the year</DATE>, when
sales fell <PERCENT>24 percent</PERCENT> from the first six months.
   ``There was a very definite, noticeable slack in demand,'' said
analyst <PERSON>Peter Miller</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Yorkton Securities Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   The decline has limited De Beers' scope for raising prices. This
past week, De Beers announced it was increasing prices <PERCENT>5.5 percent</PERCENT>,
compared to a <PERCENT>15.5 percent</PERCENT> increase a year earlier.
   The organization must this year renegotiate five-year contracts
with <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, the second biggest diamond producer in terms of
value, and <ORGANIZATION>Argyle Diamonds of Western Australia</ORGANIZATION>, the biggest
producer in terms of quantity.
   The government of newly independent <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, meanwhile, is
expected to demand a one-fifth stake in <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Diamond Mines</ORGANIZATION>,
De Beers' Namibian subsidiary.
   The organization sells most of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s West-bound
diamonds, but the Soviets, the biggest value producer, have been
acting more independently and squeezing the cartel's margins, the
experts say.
   <PERSON>Jack Lunzer</PERSON>, managing director of <ORGANIZATION>IDC Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, an independent
diamond distributor in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, said De Beers undoubtedly will
continue to control the major part of world production, but its
marketing arm's profits will fall.
   The effect hasn't been felt yet; De Beers' profit rose <PERCENT>37
percent</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1989</DATE>.
   Few diamond-producing countries dare sell their output outside
the organization, and some bold enough to leave have returned
because of the difficulty in peddling diamonds alone.
   Zaire returned in <DATE>1983</DATE> after a two-year split. <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>, which
broke in <DATE>1985</DATE>, has been negotiating its re-entry.
   ``We are as strongly in control of the diamond market as we have
been for many years,'' said <PERSON>Tim Capon</PERSON>, the cartel's director.
   The organization buys rough diamonds from De Beers' own mines,
which represent <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of world production, and from producers
in <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and
the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   It reveals few details about security. It was robbed once, in
the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, when some diamonds were snatched as couriers
carried them from one building to another.
   De Beers picks its 160 or so buying customers from thousands of
hopefuls. Ten times a year, at sales called ``sights,'' the clients
are offered a selection of diamonds chosen by the organization and
placed in a simple cardboard box. The buyer basically can take it
or leave it.
   The gems then go to cutters in the world's major diamond-cutting
centers: <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Tel Aviv</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Antwerp</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>; and <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>.
   Of all diamonds mined, only <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> will end up in jewelry,
but these represent <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the value of the world's diamond
production. The rest are put to industrial use.
   The organization is fighting the lackluster sales trend by
trying to create new demand. Last year, it spent <MONEY>$160 million</MONEY> on
advertising and promotion, trying, for example, to boost purchases
of men's diamond jewelry.
   De Beers's achievement over the decades has been to mass-market
what was once an aristocratic luxury without greatly diminishing
its value. Today, diamonds remain ``the gem of gems,'' although
millions of people own them.
   De Beers insists it seeks long-term stability and prosperity for
the industry, saying price fluctuations would undermine confidence
in the value of diamonds.
   So far, it has succeeded. While other commodities markets have
suffered repeated convulsions, rough diamond prices haven't fallen
since the organization started announcing price changes in <DATE>1964</DATE>.
   Even its fiercest competitors laud De Beers for putting up
considerable amounts of money and assuming the risks to develop
mines and support the market.
   During the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, when high interest rates caused the
worst diamond slump since the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, the organization prevented the
market's collapse by doubling its diamond stockpile to nearly <MONEY>$2
billion</MONEY> worth.
   But producers criticize the organization's secretiveness and
what they call its arbitrary valuation system. Some want more of
the industry's millions of jobs relocated in their own countries.
   Said <PERSON>Lunzer</PERSON>: ``It's not unnatural for people in the producing
countries to say, `Are we getting a proper share of the value of
our national resource?''' After reviewing a complaint filed by the
British mining company <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Gold Fields PLC</ORGANIZATION> alleging
anti-competitive practices, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Office of Fair Trading
decided in <DATE>August</DATE> against formally investigating whether the
organization abuses its monopoly.
   Gold Fields acknowledged the complaint was a defensive maneuver
against a hostile, and ultimately unsuccessful, takeover bid from
Oppenheimer-controlled <ORGANIZATION>Minorco SA</ORGANIZATION> last year.
   Formally known as <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, and based in
<LOCATION>Kimberley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, the company was formed in <DATE>1888</DATE> by the
British industrial colonialist <PERSON>Cecil Rhodes</PERSON>.
   Sir <PERSON>Ernest Oppenheimer</PERSON>, a diamond merchant, became chairman of
De Beers in <DATE>1929</DATE> and <DATE>five years later</DATE> formed <ORGANIZATION>Diamond Trading Co.</ORGANIZATION>,
the precursor of today's cartel.
   Oppenheimer, who linked the diamond business with his extensive
<ORGANIZATION>Anglo American Corp.</ORGANIZATION> gold-mining interests, is credited with
steering De Beers through the Depression. He died in <DATE>1957</DATE> and was
succeeded by his son, <PERSON>Harry Oppenheimer</PERSON>, who has made the company
more internationally minded and therefore less vulnerable.
   Now 81, <ORGANIZATION>Oppenheimer</ORGANIZATION> still serves on De Beers' board of
directors, of which he previously was chairman. His 44-year-old son
and heir apparent, <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON>, is deputy to Chairman <PERSON>Julian Ogilvie
Thompson</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, March 25</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030889-0127 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 28094 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 8, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 17; Column 4; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
492 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DIAMOND GIANT DE BEERS' PROFIT DOUBLES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Reuters 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
South African diamond giant De Beers said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that its profit more than 
doubled last year as the gem market made a sparkling recovery from a five-year 
slump. 
</P>
<P>
De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Consolidated Mines</ORGANIZATION>, which controls about <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the world's diamonds, 
said after-tax profit jumped to <MONEY>$836 million</MONEY> (2.09 billion rand) in <DATE>1988</DATE> from 
<MONEY>$416 million</MONEY> (1.04 billion rand) the year before. 
</P>
<P>
"A number of factors combined to enable us to come out with this pleasing 
result," De Beers Chairman <PERSON>Julian Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> told a news conference. 
</P>
<P>
"The results reflect both an increase in sales volumes and higher diamond 
prices, which were last raised in <DATE>May, 1988</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
Pretax profit rose <PERCENT>88%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$1.15 billion</MONEY> (2.87 billion rand) and the company 
lifted its total dividend to <MONEY>80 U.S. cents</MONEY> (200 South African cents) from <MONEY>44 
U.S. cents</MONEY> (110 South African cents). 
</P>
<P>
The company's soaring profit followed a report in <DATE>January</DATE> by De Beers' 
London-based Central Selling Organization that sales of rough gems and 
industrial diamonds soared <PERCENT>36%</PERCENT> to a record <MONEY>$4.17 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1988</DATE>, confirming a 
recovery in the diamond market since a deep slump that began in <DATE>1981</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"We don't expect retail diamond sales to grow quite as well this year as in 
<DATE>1988</DATE>, but indications are that our main markets are continuing to expand," 
<PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
De Beers was closely watching whether higher interest rates and the firm dollar 
would reduce sales, particularly in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> which accounts for <PERCENT>22%</PERCENT> of diamond 
jewelry sales. 
</P>
<P>
"There was some hesitation in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in the latter half of <DATE>last year</DATE>, but it's 
too early at this point to have firm figures for these markets," <PERSON>Ogilvie 
Thompson</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Stock market analysts said the earnings rise and marked increase in the 
dividend signaled De Beers' confidence that the extraordinary boom in the 
diamond market would continue, though probably at a slightly slower rate. 
</P>
<P>
"The broad picture seems that just about everything went well for them. The 
profit on the diamond account is restored to boom-time levels," said <PERSON>John 
Rogers</PERSON>, a partner at the <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION> stockbrokerage firm <ORGANIZATION>Edey, Rogers &amp; 
Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"The advance in the dividend particularly indicates that these results are not 
a flash in the pan," he added. 
</P>
<P>
Eager buyers pushed up De Beers' stock price by 60 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cents (1.50 rand) in 
brisk trading on the <ORGANIZATION>Johannesburg Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> to close at <MONEY>$22.40</MONEY> (56 rand) 
after the news. 
</P>
<P>
During the depression in the diamond business from <DATE>1981</DATE> to <DATE>1986</DATE>, De Beers 
substantially increased its stockpile of gems and reduced its allocation of 
rough uncut diamonds to dealers and jewelry manufacturers in <LOCATION>Antwerp</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tel Aviv</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and other diamond cutting centers. 
</P>
<P>
The tactic later paid off handsomely as demand slowly recovered in response to 
the tighter supplies. 
</P>
<P>
"If we felt there was a further hesitancy in the market, we would not hesitate 
ourselves to reduce our sales again," said <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON>. "That is our 
strategy and it is one that works." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Corporate Earnings; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
DE BEERS CONSOLIDATED MINES LTD 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-7702</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CHRBAADLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920815
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 AUG 92 / Man in the News: King of diamonds - Julian Ogilvie Thompson
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PHILIP GAWITH
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Mr Julian Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON>, chairman of De Beers, the South African company
that controls the world diamond market, spent yesterday in the <LOCATION>Northern
Transvaal</LOCATION>. It should have been a happy outing, attending the opening of De
Beers' new R1.1bn (Pounds 200m) <PERSON>Venetia</PERSON> mine, a project which should produce
5.9m carats of diamonds a year.
He could have been forgiven, however, if the prospect of more diamonds had
left him feeling slightly queasy. With unfortunate timing, the opening
coincided with what was probably the worst week for De Beers since the
collapse of the diamond market in 1981-82.
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s announcement from the board, meeting in <LOCATION>Kimberley</LOCATION>, that there
would probably be a 'substantial reduction' in the final dividend did not
only knock about 18 per cent off the share price but also precipitated a
heavy fall in the <ORGANIZATION>Johannesburg Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. It led to accusations that De
Beers had misled the market, thus dealing a blow to the credibility of one
of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s best-known companies.
The patrician, self-assured <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON>, also chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Anglo
American mining house</ORGANIZATION> and its offshore associate <ORGANIZATION>Minorco</ORGANIZATION>, may be the world's
most powerful mining executive, but he will have been ill-prepared for the
assault unleashed on his judgment and that of De Beers. Both in
<LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>, and to a lesser extent offshore, there has been widespread
criticism of the handling of the dividend cut.
De Beers sought to defend itself with a statement on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> which starts:
'The allegations that De Beers has lost credibility are unfair and
ill-founded.' Later in the statement, <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> adds: 'Our
credibility hinges on our being honest and I believe that is exactly what we
have been . . . it was precisely because we did not want to mislead the
market that we warned of a final dividend cut.'
There is little sympathy for this reasoning in <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>. When things are
going well, people are prepared to tolerate the high-handed behaviour for
which De Beers and <ORGANIZATION>Anglo</ORGANIZATION> are noted. But when a bitter pill is to be
delivered, companies need better investor relations than those enjoyed by De
Beers and <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> if a hostile reaction is to be avoided.
The nub of the problem is that until early <DATE>July</DATE>, <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> continued
to predict higher rough diamond sales by the Central Selling Organisation
(CSO) - the De Beers organisation which markets about 80 per cent of the
world's rough diamonds - in the <DATE>second half of 1992</DATE>. Although these bullish
sentiments were at odds with market signals, most observers chose to allow
De Beers the benefit of the doubt, given the company's record of accurate
forecasting.
But <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s announcement indicated that De Beers had got it wrong. The
dividend cut and the imposition of quotas, whereby the <ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> buys 25 per cent
less than its contractual commitment from producers, reflect the extent of
the error. The board said two factors - which only became fully apparent in
mid-July - combined to stymie their earlier forecast: flat demand, when an
economic upturn was expected, accentuated by the 'precipitous plunge' in
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Nikkei</ORGANIZATION> index; and the 'sudden and unprecedented explosion' in the
supply of illicit diamonds from <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>.
Some industry analysts do not believe the outlook for the market could have
changed as quickly as De Beers suggests. Of the two factors mentioned, there
is sympathy for the Angolan problem, but little for wrongly predicting an
economic upturn.
Critics suggest that De Beers should not have been so bullish. Part of the
reason why De Beers' announcement was greeted by such a furore this week is
that <ORGANIZATION>Anglo</ORGANIZATION> and De Beers are famous for their conservative financial
orientation. <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> exemplifies this conservative culture. Son of
a former Chief Justice of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, and a <LOCATION>Rhodes</LOCATION> scholar, he has grown
up in the image of the Oppenheimer family, following <PERSON>Harry Oppenheimer</PERSON>,
whose personal assistant he was for four years, to become chairman of the
two groups. Like his predecessor at De Beers, he has cultivated an
exquisitely polite, highly Anglicised manner - reflected in his preferences
for French wines, shooting and fishing.
His manner and tastes sit uneasily in the rough and tumble business world of
<LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>. Though his ability and voracious work appetite are
acknowledged, many in the South African investment community are riled by a
regal manner which is too obviously a 'cut above' for many people's taste.
He is regarded as the personification of <ORGANIZATION>Anglo</ORGANIZATION>'s arrogance: 'that arrogance
that people come to <ORGANIZATION>Anglo</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Anglo</ORGANIZATION> doesn't go the people,' in the words of one
observer.
There has been a simple reason for the stand-offishness - De Beers and <ORGANIZATION>Anglo</ORGANIZATION>
have been financially self-sufficient, neither having had a rights issue.
Neither has, therefore, needed the investment community, which they have
kept at arm's length. Complex interlocking shareholdings, pivotally
controlled by the Oppenheimer family, have also put the companies beyond the
reach of corporate raiders.
This week's controversy has again raised questions about the quality of
management at <ORGANIZATION>Anglo</ORGANIZATION>. The question is also being asked whether <PERSON>Ogilvie
Thompson</PERSON> isn't spreading himself too thinly by being chairman,
simultaneously, of three large companies.
Pressure is also mounting for improved disclosure from De Beers. Investors
are prepared to accept secrecy when De Beers gets things right, but not when
it gets things wrong.
At the <LOCATION>Venetia</LOCATION> opening yesterday, <PERSON>Harry Oppenheimer</PERSON> conceded that De Beers
was facing 'grave, immediate difficulties'. He went on, though, to say that
these are 'the sort that we understand and have faced successfully at many
times in the past'. Unfortunately, he was not talking about investor
relations. <PERSON>Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> may find it harder to rebuild trust with
investors than to bring supply and demand back into equilibrium in the
diamond market - though achieving the latter would doubtless help the
former.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870306-0171 </DOCNO>
<HL> De Beers Diamond Syndicate Flourishes
As Other Commodity Cartels Flounder
---
By Neil Behrmann
<DD> 03/06/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> DBRSY
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON) </IN>
<DATELINE> LONDON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Confounding predictions of its demise four years ago during the worst diamond slump since the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, the South African concern that controls <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the world's uncut-diamond market, is thriving. 

But De Beers not only halted a fall in rough-diamond prices, it raised them an average <PERCENT>14.5%</PERCENT> last year. 
Sales still soared <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> to a near-record <MONEY>$2.56 billion</MONEY>, double the <MONEY>$1.26 billion</MONEY> posted in the <DATE>1982</DATE> doldrums. 

   De Beers managed the comeback by convincing diamond producers, dealers and the jewelry industry that its marketing muscle was indispensable. 
"Selling diamonds is the business of dealers and jewelers; helping them to sell more is ours," says <PERSON>Stephen Lussier</PERSON>, a De Beers marketing executive. 

   De Beers helped with an advertising and promotion budget that swelled to <MONEY>$110 million</MONEY> this year, up from <MONEY>$43 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
Supplemented by <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> spent by the diamond trade, the De Beers campaign helped raise world sales of diamond jewelry to 47 million pieces valued at <MONEY>$21.6 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1985</DATE>, up from 42 million pieces valued at <MONEY>$16 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1979</DATE>. 
Figures for <DATE>1986</DATE> aren't yet available, but De Beers says it was another record. 

   The promotional budget covers market research, a world-wide network of as many as 200 public-relations officials, and advertising campaigns coordinated by the agencies <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer &amp; Son</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>J. Walter Thompson Co.</ORGANIZATION> in 27 other countries. 

   The master sales plan began in <DATE>1938</DATE>, when former De Beers Chairman <PERSON>Harry Oppenheimer</PERSON> asked Ayer to woo American couples to buy expensive diamond engagement rings. 
Today the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is the world's No. 1 market, with <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY> in annual retail diamond jewelry sales, or about a <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> share, even though a <DATE>1971</DATE> antitrust law prevents De Beers from operating directly there. 
About three-fourths of American women own diamond engagement rings that cost an average <MONEY>$1,300</MONEY>. 

   De Beers's strategy is two-pronged, says <PERSON>Mr. Lussier</PERSON>. 
General "diamond image" advertising aims at perpetuating the mystique of quality diamonds as "the ultimate expression of love," he says. 

   De Beers applied similar promotional techniques world-wide. 
One out of 17 Japanese couples bought engagement rings two decades ago. 
Now two-thirds do, and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is the second-largest diamond jewelry market, followed by <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>. 

   De Beers's <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, known as the Syndicate, is the pipeline between diamond mines and dealers based mainly in <LOCATION>Antwerp</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Tel Aviv</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
As the sole middleman, De Beers usually avoids the acrimony that has divided other cartels. 

   The Syndicate has purchase contracts with De Beers's own mines in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION> (a territory controlled by <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>), other African states such as <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Sierra Leone</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 

   De Beers offers its cache to select dealers 10 times a year at sales known as "sights." 
Each dealer gets a box containing uncut diamonds. 
The dealer must accept or reject the entire box, valued at between <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> and <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY>. 
If the dealer refuses to buy, De Beers may never invite him back. 

   This ritual has enabled De Beers to maintain price stability. 
The cartel hasn't cut prices since it was founded more than half a century ago. 
Despite grumbling, diamond dealers generally believe that a healthy international diamond market depends on the Syndicate. 

   <ORGANIZATION>OPEC</ORGANIZATION> members "tend to do what they like," says <PERSON>Jo Flies</PERSON>, chief economist of the <ORGANIZATION>Antwerp Diamond Council</ORGANIZATION>. 
But De Beers is unique, he says, in influencing production and consumption of diamonds. 
"People mesmerized by the producers' cartels forget that De Beers is an aggressive, ruthless and effective sales organization," says a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> dealer. 

   Some analysts warn, however, that De Beers's future may be affected by the surge in diamond output elsewhere, notably <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
World diamond production has soared to 88 million carats from 47 million carats in <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
A carat equals 1/142 of an ounce. 
About <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> of the prize diamonds are produced in southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, but the market is being flooded by cheaper diamonds mainly from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION>. 

   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, which produces an estimated 12 million carats of top-grade diamonds annually, is another unknown. 
De Beers has a sales arrangement with the Soviets, but <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> has dumped diamonds before and may prove difficult to keep in line. 
<LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> left the cartel last year, partly because it is involved in a bitter war with South African-backed rebels. 
Other African nations in the cartel want more control over distribution, dealers say. 

   "De Beers can't stop evolution," says <PERSON>Jack Lunzer</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>IDC Holdings Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a London-based diamond firm that sells diamonds for Guinea, an African nation that isn't a cartel member. 
While sales independence from De Beers "could be disastrous" for the market, <PERSON>Mr. Lunzer</PERSON> says, that won't deter those producers who want "more information and knowledge about final sales of their material." 

   But the fate of De Beers, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s most famous company, will depend largely on developments in that troubled country, dealers say. 
International sanctions, including a possible <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> import ban on South African diamonds, pose a growing threat. 

   Recent history indicates, however, that it would be hasty to write off the cartel. 
In <DATE>1981</DATE>, <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION>, which mines <PERCENT>22%</PERCENT> of world diamond output, left the cartel. 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> was about to open a huge diamond mine and a speculative boom had led to widespread dealer bankruptcies. 
The monopoly was threatened with extinction. 

   While average prices of De Beers's rough diamonds rose <PERCENT>37%</PERCENT>, prices of polished diamonds in dealers' stocks collapsed. 
The top-grade investment diamond, D-Flawless, tumbled to around <MONEY>$8,000</MONEY> a carat in <DATE>1985</DATE> from an average of <MONEY>$55,000</MONEY> in <DATE>1980</DATE>. 

   In a series of shrewd moves, De Beers forced <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION> to rejoin the cartel by dumping diamonds. 
Meanwhile, diamond demand by consumers increased, fueled by De Beers's promotion campaign and favorable economic trends. 

   Dealers say trade is buoyant again because of lower interest rates and a weak dollar that makes dollar-priced diamonds cheaper in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
Since <DATE>November 1985</DATE>, prices of D-Flawless diamonds have risen <PERCENT>56%</PERCENT> to around <MONEY>$14,000</MONEY> a carat. 

   "De Beers is powerful; it is everywhere," says <PERSON>Alfred Lachowsky</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Antwerp Diamond High Council</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The cartel will continue to control world diamond markets, <PERSON>Mr. Lachosky</PERSON> says. 
"You can't mix diamonds with oil." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910820-0090
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910820-0090.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   De Beers Holds Diamonds
   As Soviet Loan Collateral
   ----
</HL>
<DATE>
08/20/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A11
</SO>
<CO>
   DBRSY
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
</MS>
<IN>
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
</IN>
<RE>
AFRICA (AF)
EASTERN EUROPE (EEU)
EUROPE (EU)
FAR EAST (FE)
SOUTH AFRICA (SF)
SWITZERLAND (SZ)
SOVIET UNION (UR)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   JOHANNESBURG -- De Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd., the
world's largest diamond producer, said it is holding diamonds
in London as collateral against a $1 billion loan to the
Soviet Union in light of the country's political upheaval.
   De Beers Centenery AG, the company's Swiss arm, lent the
money to the Soviet Union in July 1990 as part of a five-year
deal to sell a $5 billion rough-diamond stockpile for the
Soviets.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In the deal, described at the time as the first of its
kind by a Western company, the loan was to be repaid over
five years beginning in <DATE>November 1990</DATE> to help meet the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION>'s import arrears.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> reached the deal with De Beers because it
wanted to sell a huge stockpile of diamonds without
disrupting the stable diamond market, De Beers said.
   De Beers established De Beers Centenery in <DATE>May 1990</DATE> to
head its non-South African business.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-2921</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BDZA8AG8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910426
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 APR 91 / Commodities and Agriculture: Soviet diamond loan honoured
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KENNETH GOODING
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
IN SPITE of the turmoil in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, the country has been
punctilious in making loan repayments and delivering diamonds against the
Dollars 5bn (Pounds 2.95bn), five-year sales agreement signed last year with
De Beers' international rough (uncut) diamond cartel.
The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, the world's second-largest diamond producer, joined the
cartel organised by De Beers, the South African mining group, last <DATE>July</DATE>. De
Beers loaned the country USDollars 1bn.
<PERSON>Mr Gary Ralfe</PERSON>, a De Beers director close to the Soviet deal, said yesterday
that the last Dollars 150m of the loan had been drawn down in <DATE>January</DATE>, about
three months later than first expected. Soviet diamond stockpiles, being
held as collateral, had been transferred to the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> offices of De Beers'
Central Selling Organisation (CSO).
Speaking in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> after De Beers published its annual report, <PERSON>Mr Ralfe</PERSON> said
that the Soviet diamond mines were working normally in spite of the
upheavals, possibly because they were in such a remote area and because the
standard of living was relatively good.
<PERSON>Mr Julian Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON>, chairman of De Beers, said he was now confident
that his group's diamond sales would this year match the Dollars 4.2bn
achieved in <DATE>1990</DATE>.
In the early part of this year the rough diamond market had been dominated
by the <LOCATION>Gulf</LOCATION> war, which curtailed polishing activity in <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> for several
weeks and reduced trading activity everywhere. But the first three of the
<ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION>'s monthly diamond sales were 'reasonably satisfactory, which indicates
the underlying confidence in the trade'.
The diamond industry was well-positioned to grow, he added.
De Beers' sales contract with <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, the world's most important rough
diamond producer in value terms, ended in <DATE>December</DATE>, but <PERSON>Mr Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON>
said he expected a new one would be signed in a matter of weeks. He also
expected the <ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> would continue to sell all <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s diamonds in spite of
the calls by some politicians for up to 20 per cent to be sold
independently.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 38
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870908-0047 </DOCNO>
<HL> De Beers Plans to Raise Diamond Prices
By 10% Next Month as Demand Surges
---
By Neil Behrmann
<DD> 09/08/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> DBRSY
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS) </IN>
<DATELINE> LONDON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Flexing its muscles as a cartel, <ORGANIZATION>De Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> is raising its diamond prices an average <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> next month. 

   The South African concern, which controls <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the world diamond market through its London-based <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, sells a vast array of diamonds, varying in quality and size, dealers say. 
So the increase could be as much as <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> on top-grade diamonds. 
The rise follows an average price increase of <PERCENT>14.5%</PERCENT> last year. 

   "The diamond price increase was expected," said <PERSON>Jacques Zucker</PERSON>, of <PERSON>Lachowsky Zucker</PERSON>, diamond dealers in <LOCATION>Antwerp</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>. 
By changing the mix of diamonds that it sells to dealers several months ago, De Beers signaled to the market that it intended to raise quotes, he said. 

   "Few listened to us two years ago when we advised clients to buy diamonds at depressed values," <PERSON>Mr. Zucker</PERSON> said. 
"Now they must accept higher prices." 

   "The price rise provides the necessary psychological lift to the market," said <PERSON>Peter Miller</PERSON>, a mining analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman Securities</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. 
It will help the diamond producers "consolidate their gains." 

   Prices of one-carat D-flawless diamonds have risen to about <MONEY>$14,800</MONEY> a carat from <MONEY>$12,000</MONEY> at the beginning of the year, dealers said. 
In <DATE>1985</DATE>, at the low point of a deep slump, a top quality stone was <MONEY>$8,500</MONEY> a carat, down from an average of <MONEY>$55,000</MONEY> in <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
A carat equals 200 milligrams. 

   De Beers decided to raise prices because rough diamonds were already trading at a premium over its own quotes on the open market, said <PERSON>Andrew Lamont</PERSON>, a company spokesman. 
Demand is especially buoyant in the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>. 
In the <DATE>first seven months of 1987</DATE>, Japanese imports of polished diamonds surged <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> from the similar period last year to <MONEY>$777 million</MONEY>, he added. 

   After the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is the second biggest diamond jewelry market, followed by <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>. 
Only one out of 17 Japanese couples bought engagement rings less than two decades ago; now more than two-thirds buy. 

   "The sharp appreciation of the yen reduced the cost of diamonds for Japanese buyers," <PERSON>Mr. Lamont</PERSON> says. 
Stronger currencies and lower interest rates in <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and other European countries also boosted diamond sales, he says. 
Diamonds are priced in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars. 

   Demand for polished diamonds in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, and the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> also raised exports of the leading diamond cutting and dealing centers, primarily <LOCATION>Antwerp</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tel Aviv</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   To meet growing orders from diamond dealers and cutters who supply the retail trade, De Beers sales of rough diamonds jumped to <MONEY>$1.56 billion</MONEY> in the first half of this year from <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> in the similar period in <DATE>1986</DATE>. 

   Sales of <MONEY>$2.56 billion</MONEY> last year were the highest since the <DATE>1980</DATE> boom when De Beers turnover reached <MONEY>$2.72 billion</MONEY>. 
Analysts are predicting sales of <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE>. 

   Yet some dealers worry because world diamond production surged to 89.6 million carats last year from <MONEY>47 million carats</MONEY> in <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
Only about <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> of the diamonds are gems, but De Beers must continue to find new markets, they say. 

   De Beers surprised skeptics and revived trade from the slump in the first half of the decade by withholding stocks and pursuing an intensive marketing campaign. 

   An advertising and promotion budget which rose to <MONEY>$110 million</MONEY> this year from <MONEY>$43 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1980</DATE> helped raise world-wide sales of diamond jewelry to a record 49 million pieces valued at <MONEY>$24.6 billion</MONEY> last year. 
In <DATE>1979</DATE>, about 42 million pieces valued at <MONEY>$16 billion</MONEY> were sold, De Beers says. 

   In more than half a century of its existence, the <ORGANIZATION>Central Selling Organization</ORGANIZATION>, which includes as members black African state producers, has outlasted other commodity cartels by never cutting diamond prices. 

   The cartel controls most of the world's rough diamond market via a "pipeline" that stretches from mines in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to diamond dealers and cutters. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-4588</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DCJCTAFKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930310
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 MAR 93 / International Company News: De Beers restricts dividend cut
to 29%
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PHILIP GAWITH
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   JOHANNESBURG
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
DE BEERS, the South African company which dominates the world diamond
market, yesterday pleased investors by holding the cut in its <DATE>1992</DATE> dividend
to <MONEY>29 per cent</MONEY> - to <MONEY>79.1 cents</MONEY> from <MONEY>112.1 cents</MONEY> - after announcing a 35 per
cent fall in earnings for the year.
Many analysts had predicted a much larger reduction in the payout. The
company's shares climbed after the announcement, closing at R68.85 (Dollars
21.61) - nearly 4 per cent up for the day.
Analysts agreed the size of the dividend cut indicated that De Beers'
financial health and the general state of the world diamond industry were
better than the market had expected.
<PERSON>Mr Julian Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON>, chairman, said the fall in earnings reflected
the difficult second half. Attributable profits at De Beers and Centenary,
its offshore arm, fell by 49 per cent in the second half, compared with a 26
per cent fall in first.
Pre-tax profits on the diamond account fell by 20 per cent to Dollars 644m
from <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 801m in <DATE>1991</DATE> reflecting the impact of the quotas.
Net interest income slumped 79 per cent to Dollars 30m from <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 141m.
This was due to lower cash balances after the company bought up diamond
supplies that bypassed the Central Selling Organisation (CSO), the De Beers
company that trades 80 per cent of world rough diamond output.
<PERSON>Mr Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> estimated that Dollars 500m to Dollars 600m worth of
diamonds which bypassed the <ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> - both legal and illegal - had come from
<LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> during the year, of which De Beers had bought about two-thirds.
Attributable earnings fell to <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 491m from <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 759m, while equity
accounted earnings fell to <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 757m from Dollars 1.07bn. Earnings per
share, excluding retained earnings of associates, fell <MONEY>35 per cent</MONEY> to <MONEY>129
cents</MONEY> from <MONEY>200 cents</MONEY>.
Cautious view of diamond market, Page 36
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>De Beers Consolidated Mines.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>ZAZ  South Africa, Africa.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P1499 Miscellaneous Nonmetallic Minerals.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>FIN  Annual report.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-48240 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr094_c_94016" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-094 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  26 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> REPUBLIC OF SOUTH AFRICA </F>
<H3> <TI>   * French Paper Reports Views on Economy </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    * French Paper Reports Views on Economy </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    * De Beers Cultivates ANC Ties </H4>

<F P=102> 94AF0187B Paris LE MONDE (Economic Supplement) in French 26 
Apr 94 p 4 </F>

<F P=103> 94AF0187B </F>
<F P=104>  Paris LE MONDE (Economic Supplement) </F>
<F P=105>  French </F>


<TEXT>
CSO 

<FP=106> [Article by M. de V.: "De Beers, the Untouchable"] </F>
  [Text] Founded more than a century ago, this conglomerate 
with a world monopoly on the diamond trade remains faithful to 
itself: secretive, hegemonic, paternalistic, and sure of its 
future... 
  "I know from experience that the only possible way to 
safeguard the stability of the sector is by limiting the supply 
of diamonds and selling through a single distribution network," 
Sir <PERSON>Ernest Oppenheimer</PERSON>, president of de Beers at the turn of the 
century, used to say. Faithful to itself, and faithful to this 
principle, the conglomerate founded in <DATE>1888</DATE> by <PERSON>Cecil 
Rhodes</PERSON>--creator of <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION>, obsessed by <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>'s 
expansion into <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>--owns half the world's production of uncut 
diamonds and markets <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT>. 
  Since <DATE>1931</DATE>, diamonds have escaped the almost constant 
erosion 
of prices of other raw materials. A miraculous survivor among 
luxury products, this "king of gems" and "teardrop of the gods" 
is still in insolently good health; and de Beers, a fairly 
accurate gauge of the industry's condition since it holds the 
monopoly on diamonds, is in equally excellent shape: The group's 
turnover for <DATE>1993</DATE> was <MONEY>$4.444 billion</MONEY>, compared to <MONEY>$3.640</MONEY> the 
preceding year. In this recessionary period, it is probably the 
only one to have recorded "record sales," and it displays a 
serenity and faith in its own future that would be the envy of 
many other companies. 
  Its assurance is expressed in more than mere words: de Beers 
is making long-term investments, on several fronts, with 
astonishing audacity: in the conquest of new markets--its budget 
for this is almost unequalled anywhere--in consolidation--with 
all its uncertainties!--in agreements with producer countries, 
in exploring new deposits, and above all in constantly keeping 
supply in balance with demand--even when stocks are 
excessive...and cost is no object. 
  Zaire thinks it is independent enough to start selling 
stones 
directly to Israeli diamond cutters? Well, then, de Beers just 
signs an exclusive contract with <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> and buys them up itself. 
The guerrillas in <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> have decided to go into the diamond 
business? It spends <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> to block the deal. <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION> 
"forgets" the protocols it signed? It renegotiates, slowly but 
surely convincing the backsliders--by what means?--to get back 
in line, i.e., the de Beers line. In addition, it monitors and 
controls the distribution system with such arrogant precision 
that it sells to its clients "only as much as is likely to be 
sold." It prefers to hoard all the rest, to make sure the 
cutters do not warehouse too much merchandise. 
<H5>  Hegemony </H5>
  Does de Beers behave like a sovereign government? Is it 
authoritarian, even hegemonic, behind its velvet facade? 
Certainly. But one must admit it has succeeded where 
international agreements and producer cartels have failed. 
Secretive--it seems to keep key information under wraps as part 
of its power strategy--and paternalistic, it is reaping the 
fruits of its founders' vision. 
  What did <PERSON>Harry Oppenheimer</PERSON>, son of <LOCATION>Ernest</LOCATION>, say back in <DATE>1948</DATE>? 
"All workers should participate in the success of their business 
and should benefit directly from its profits; apartheid, which 
amounts to disguised slavery in the mines, can lead only to 
impasse." And he supported the creation of miners' unions in the 
sector. Because stable labor relations, as he saw it, were key 
to steady production. 
  So de Beers today is cultivating "courteous" relations with 
<ORGANIZATION>Mandela</ORGANIZATION>'s entourage. In that regard, it is significant that the 
former secretary general of the miners' union, <PERSON>Cyril Ramaphosa</PERSON>, 
number-two man in the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION>, is the announced successor to <LOCATION>Mandela</LOCATION>. 
  This attractive blend of fine-tuned philanthropy and 
judicious liberalism is characteristic of de Beers. Neither 
<PERSON>Cecil Rhodes</PERSON> nor the Oppenheimer dynasty would take offense at 
the charming words the company's current president has to say 
about <ORGANIZATION>Mandela</ORGANIZATION>. Because the company has already taken appropriate 
precautions to protect its wealth: In <DATE>1990</DATE>, when the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION> 
revealed its intent to nationalize South African companies, de 
Beers immediately transferred its capital to <LOCATION>Lucerne</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>. 
  In <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> itself, nothing remains but the extraction 
company (<ORGANIZATION>de Beers Consolidated Mines, Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>). Whatever happens in 
South African politics, <PERSON>Julian Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON> can still sleep 
soundly on a pillow of diamonds. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880428-0170 </DOCNO>
<HL> De Beers Raising Diamond Prices An Average 13.5% </HL>
<AUTHOR> Neil Behrmann (WSJ Special) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> DBRSY </CO>
<IN> PCS </IN>
<TEXT>
   De <ORGANIZATION>Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> said it is raising the average price of rough uncut diamonds <PERCENT>13.5%</PERCENT> because the market is so buoyant. 

   Although dealers must wait for details when De Beers has a sale early next month, some said prices for quality diamonds valued at <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> or more could rise as much as <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT>. 

   A spokesman for the South African concern, which controls <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the diamond market, said retail jewelers, manufacturers and dealers have shrugged off the stock market crash and have been vigorous buyers of large and small gems. 

   Dealers said the diamond market has been strong during the past year mainly because of growing retail jewelry demand, rather than investment-market demand. 
Total sales of diamond jewelry rose to 57.6 million pieces valued at <MONEY>$31 billion</MONEY> last year from 52.4 million valued at <MONEY>$27.6 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, De Beers estimates. 

   In the months right after the stock market crash there was "hesitancy in the diamond markets," said De Beers's chairman, <PERSON>Julian Ogilvie Thompson</PERSON>, in the company's latest annual report. 
But De Beers "responded by severely reducing its sales" in <DATE>November</DATE> and <DATE>December</DATE> to steady the market, he said. 
The reduction in supplies and good Christmas sales restored confidence in recent months, the official said. 

   Some diamond analysts said dealers may find it difficult to absorb De Beers latest price increase, particularly since it followed a <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> rise in prices in early <DATE>October</DATE>. 
With the lastest increase, the company's average prices will have risen <PERCENT>52%</PERCENT> since <DATE>1982</DATE>, analysts said. 
The diamond market could also turn sour if stock markets begin to slide again, dealers said. 

   "The market is quiet at the moment; I don't believe that the timing is right," said <PERSON>Jo Flies</PERSON>, chief economist at the <ORGANIZATION>Antwerp Diamond High Council</ORGANIZATION>, a trade group in <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>. 

   But <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> jewelers at a large annual jewelry and watch fair this month in <LOCATION>Basel</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, said diamond sales would remain strong in fast-growing Far Eastern economies. 

   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> now accounts for <PERCENT>21%</PERCENT> of world diamond jewelry sales, after the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, which has a <PERCENT>39%</PERCENT> share, De Beers said. 
<LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> has slashed import duties so already firm consumption could improve further, the company said. 

   The investment market for diamonds remains quiet, although quotes of the D-Flawless investment diamond have risen to around <MONEY>$17,000</MONEY> a carat from <MONEY>$14,000</MONEY> <DATE>last fall</DATE>. 
Those prices compare with levels around <MONEY>$55,000</MONEY> in <DATE>1980</DATE>, prior to the diamond recession of the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>. 
