<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06022221 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06022221 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-FRANCISCO; PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; PLAYOFF; GAME; RESULT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The morning after was sunny and bright, but the 49ers' players and coaches
were still moving under a dark cloud Monday.;    "Think of it," running back
Harry Sydney said with a tone of amazement. "We've won two Super Bowls
back-to-back, we go 14-2 (in the regular season), we have a heck of a time,
but, still, you feel empty."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NINERS FACE DISAPPOINTMENT -- AND QUESTIONS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Pro Football
Additional information attached to the end of this article.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The 49ers came to their <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> training facility for a morning
meeting, to receive checkout physicals, to clean out their lockers and to try
to come to terms with their 15-13 loss to the <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION>
championship game.;    "We're not ashamed of our season," Coach <PERSON>George Seifert</PERSON>
said. "But I think we're all very frustrated that we came up short of what was
originally the goal.";    The goal of making history, of being the first team
to win three consecutive Super Bowls, died when <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> place-kicker <PERSON>Matt Bahr</PERSON>
kicked the winning field goal on the game's final play.;    "It's a sad
feeling," said tackle <PERSON>Steve Wallace</PERSON>. "In four seconds it all came to an end.";
   Defensive end <PERSON>Larry Roberts</PERSON> said, "We fell just short of a goal that may
never be tested again.";    The loss brought to the surface questions that had
been brewing all season, questions that the 49ers had hoped to postpone for at
least another week.;    One main question: How will the running game be
repaired? No one had an answer, but the inability to run the ball was
painfully obvious in the loss to the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>, when the Niners rushed for just
39 yards.;    "Guys like <PERSON>Lawrence Taylor</PERSON> were just laying their ears back and
coming at us," <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said. "Teams knew they didn't have to shut down our
run.";    Running back <PERSON>Roger Craig</PERSON> left the building without speaking to
reporters, but his erratic season, which ended with a crucial <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE>
fumble, created speculation about his future role with the team.;    "He'll be
back," receiver <PERSON>Jerry Rice</PERSON> said. "I'll make sure of that.";    <PERSON>Seifert</PERSON> would
only say, "<PERSON>Roger Craig</PERSON> is our starter at this time. When we go to camp, I
would foresee it being a very competitive situation.";    In upcoming weeks,
the <ORGANIZATION>Niners</ORGANIZATION> must make decisions on what positions they want to strengthen
through the possible signing of Plan B free agents and the draft. They also
must decide the current players they want to protect from Plan B free agency.;
   <PERSON>Seifert</PERSON> said it was too early to make personnel decisions.;    "I imagine
there will be changes on the team, which there is every year," he said.;   
Some players were already guessing that they would be part of that change.
Running back <PERSON>Spencer Tillman</PERSON>, who was in the last year of his contract and who
wasn't protected last season, said that he was sure he "won't be protected."
Linebacker <PERSON>Jim Fahnhorst</PERSON>, who spent most of the season on injured reserve,
also said he expected to be left unprotected.;    But <PERSON>Seifert</PERSON> said that he did
not plan sweeping changes for his team, which finished with an NFL-best 14-2
regular-season record.;    "It's been said that now we're supposed to stop and
rebuild and do this whole thing all over again," <PERSON>Seifert</PERSON> said. "A lot of
people are saying that the dynasty's over. I don't necessarily believe that's
the case. We can still be a good football team. We still have a number of very
good football players on the team.";    And the loss to the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> might make
the 49ers that much hungrier.;    "We'll cope with losing," <PERSON>Rice</PERSON> said before
he drove away. "We'll make this an incentive.";  49ERS' PLAYOFF LOSSES;   
(box) <DATE>1983</DATE> -- 49ers lost to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> 24-21 in the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> championship game. The
next season the 49ers went 15-1 and won Super Bowl XIX.;    (box) <DATE>1985</DATE> --
49ers lost to the <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION> 17-3 in the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> wild-card game. The next
season the 49ers went 10-5-1 and lost to the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> in the playoffs.;    (box)
<DATE>1986</DATE> -- 49ers lost to the Giants 49-3 in the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> semifinals. The next season
the 49ers went 13-2 and lost to <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> in the playoffs.;    (box) <DATE>1987</DATE> --
49ers lost to <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> 36-24 in the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> semifinals. The next year the 49ers
went 10-6 and won Super Bowl XXIII.; -- <PERSON>Ann Killion</PERSON>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  ANN KILLION, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910122  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  732  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday January 22, 1991
00022221,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA012990-0044 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 168634 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 29, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 3; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
472 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
49ERS WIN SUPER BOWL -- ROUT BRONCOS, 55-10; 
</P>
<P>
FOOTBALL: A RECORD-SETTING JOE MONTANA LEADS THE MOST LOPSIDED VICTORY IN THE 
TITLE GAME'S 24 YEARS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARK HEISLER, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW ORLEANS 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON> and his teammates staked their bids for greatness <DATE>Sunday</DATE> as the 
quarterback led the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers to a 55-10 rout of the <LOCATION>Denver Broncos</LOCATION> 
in Super Bowl XXIV. 
</P>
<P>
Montana threw five touchdown passes, a Super Bowl record. He now has a career 
total of 11, another record. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers became the first <ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION> team to win back-to-back 
championships in 10 years, since the <ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</ORGANIZATION> did it. 
</P>
<P>
"He's probably the greatest quarterback ever to play this game," said 49er 
Coach <PERSON>George Seifert</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers also tied the Steelers with their fourth Super Bowl victory. Like the 
<ORGANIZATION>Steelers</ORGANIZATION>, the 49ers have never lost. 
</P>
<P>
The Broncos tied the <LOCATION>Minnesota Vikings</LOCATION> with their fourth Super Bowl loss. Like 
the Vikings, the Broncos have never won. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> threw touchdown passes of 20, 38 and 28 yards to <PERSON>Jerry Rice</PERSON>; a 7-yarder 
to <PERSON>Brent Jones</PERSON>, and one for 35 to <PERSON>John Taylor</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, 33, completed <PERCENT>78.3%</PERCENT> of his passes in his three postseason games. He 
threw 11 touchdown passes and no interceptions. 
</P>
<P>
In the three first halves, when the games were marginally more competitive, 
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> was even better: <PERCENT>79.3%</PERCENT> with nine touchdowns. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s game was a mismatch. The Broncos came in 12-point underdogs, the 
largest spread in 20 years, and promptly fell behind, 7-0, when <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> drove 
the 49ers 66 yards on their first possession, finishing the drive with a 
20-yard pass to Rice. 
</P>
<P>
The Broncos closed to 7-3 on <PERSON>David Treadwell</PERSON>'s 42-yard field goal, then forced 
a <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> punt and took over in good field position, at their 49. 
</P>
<P>
However, halfback <PERSON>Bobby Humphrey</PERSON> fumbled and the 49ers' <PERSON>Kevin Fagan</PERSON> recovered. 
Montana drove the 49ers in again, throwing a 7-yard scoring pass to his tight 
end, <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Montana then drove the 49ers 69 yards for a 20-3 lead. Then, with 1:38 left in 
the <DATE>second quarter</DATE>, he took them 59 yards to score again, requiring 64 seconds 
to run five plays, the last a 38-yard pass to Rice behind <LOCATION>Bronco</LOCATION> safety <PERSON>Dennis 
Smith</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Denver's <PERSON>John Elway</PERSON> threw interceptions on the first two Bronco possessions of 
the second half. The 49ers converted both into touchdowns and led, 41-3. 
</P>
<P>
Elway went 10 for 26, was sacked four times and held to 8 yards in his four 
rushes. Coach <PERSON>Dan Reeves</PERSON> let backup <PERSON>Gary Kubiak</PERSON> finish the last 9:28. 
</P>
<P>
Records fell throughout the <DATE>second half</DATE>. The 49ers' 55 points eclipsed the 
record 46, set by the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bears</ORGANIZATION> in Super Bowl XX. Rice's three touchdowns 
and <PERSON>Roger Craig</PERSON>'s two gave each a career total of four in <LOCATION>Super Bowls</LOCATION>, tying 
them with the <ORGANIZATION>Steelers</ORGANIZATION>' <PERSON>Franco Harris</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Seifert became the second rookie coach to win a Super Bowl, joining <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>'s 
<PERSON>Don McCafferty</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers have won Super Bowls in <DATE>1982</DATE>, <DATE>'85</DATE>, '89 and <DATE>'90</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>National 
Conference</ORGANIZATION> has won the last six Super Bowls, since the <ORGANIZATION>AFC Raiders</ORGANIZATION>' victory in 
<DATE>1984</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Related Stories in Sports: C1, C3-C23 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, As Roger Craig watches, 49ers' Jerry Rice savors 1st touchdown in 
55-10 Super Bowl romp over Broncos. KIRK McKOY / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SUPER BOWL (FOOTBALL GAME); FOOTBALL CHAMPIONSHIPS; DENVER BRONCOS (FOOTBALL 
TEAM); SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS (FOOTBALL TEAM); MONTANA, JOE; SPORTS RECORDS; 
FOOTBALL TEAMS; FOOTBALL PLAYERS; ELWAY, JOHN 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06015214 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06015214 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; PLAYOFF; QA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Playoff quiz; (box) TODAY'S QUESTION: Which Bay Area quarterback set the NFL
record for touchdown passes in a postseason game? (Answer on Wednesday.)  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PLAYOFF QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     (box) Answer to <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s question: The six stadiums that have been the site
of only one Super Bowl: Rice Stadium in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Pontiac Silverdome</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Tampa
Stadium</ORGANIZATION> (which will have its second Super Bowl this month), <LOCATION>Stanford Stadium</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> <PERSON>Jack Murphy</PERSON> Stadium and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Joe Robbie Stadium.</PERSON>;  PLAYOFF ISSUE;
   (box)  TODAY'S ISSUE: Is <PERSON>Jay Schroeder</PERSON> a playoff-caliber QB?;    (box)
Responses to <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s issue -- how should the 49ers go about stopping the
<ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> championship game?;    "The 49ers don't have to worry
much about the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>' passing game. I think they should have a four-man line,
and they should also blitz one of their linebackers at various times from
different angles. That way they'll rattle <PERSON>Hostetler</PERSON> and possibly force him
into some mistakes."; <PERSON>Michael Garcia</PERSON>; <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>;    "If the Niners score early
and force <PERSON>Hostetler</PERSON> to try to catch up, the Giants are really going to have
trouble, because I really don't think he has the experience to come back from
a deficit against the 49ers' defense."; -- <PERSON>Tim Sullivan</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION>;  PLAYOFF
TRIVIA;    (box) You ask the questions this time. Call our <ORGANIZATION>Playoff Trivia
Hotline</ORGANIZATION>, (408) 920-5720, or fax us at (408) 920-5244 with questions and we'll
pick out one each day and answer it.;    (box) <DATE>Today</DATE>'s question: How many
times did the 49ers and <ORGANIZATION>Raiders</ORGANIZATION> play each other in the <DATE>'80s</DATE>, and who won each
time?; -- <PERSON>Charles Nwuzi</PERSON>,; <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>;    (box) Answer: The Raiders won two of
three meetings, defeating the 49ers 23-17 in <DATE>1982</DATE> and 9-3 in <DATE>1988</DATE> and losing
to them 34-10 in <DATE>1985</DATE>. Incidentally, the visiting team won each game.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910115  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  295  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday January 15, 1991
00015214,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06238203 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06238203 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawings (2); DRAWING: (49ers helmet logo); DRAWING: (Rams helmet logo)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; CLUB; SAN-FRANCISCO; LOS-ANGELES; RELATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  ABOUT THE SERIES: This long-running matchup is the most bitter for the 49ers.
As division and conference rivals dating to 1950, the 49ers and Los Angeles
Rams have met twice each season except for 1989, when they played three times
-- the third game being the NFC Championship Game, a comfortable 30-3 victory
by the 49ers at Candlestick Park.;   While the 49ers might hold the advantage
in postseason games against the Rams -- there has been only that one -- Los
Angeles clearly has the regular-season lock on this series, maintaining a
48-32 edge. There have been two ties, one on each team's home field.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Special Section  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHEN THESE TEAMS MEET, FORGET HOME-FIELD ADVANTAGE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  FOOTBALL '91. A SPECIAL SECTION; BAY AREA RIVALRIES; Additional information
attached to the end of this article  </MEMO>
<TEXT>   TURNING POINT: Now here's what makes this thing so interesting: Since <DATE>1981</DATE>,
the teams have split the annual series six times, with victories coming at the
opponent's ballpark. These days, that just about kills any notion about a
home-field advantage for a 49ers-Rams contest.;   Before then, however, the
<ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> made a habit of nailing the 49ers, sweeping them 15 times from <DATE>1950</DATE> to
<DATE>1981</DATE>. Longtime 49ers' fans will recall these as the down days when the local
team was, well, lousy.;   But thanks in part to the Rams, the tide turned in
<DATE>1981</DATE>, the year the 49ers bounced back from a 1-2 start to win 12 of their last
13 games and their first Super Bowl title, on a 26-21 victory over the
<LOCATION>Cincinnati Bengals</LOCATION>. The 49ers swept the Rams that season, but it took that
second victory, in <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> naturally -- a 33-31 comeback capped by a late Joe
Montana-led scoring drive and a <PERSON>Ray Wersching</PERSON> field goal -- to firmly
establish respectability in the minds of players and fans.; WHAT THEY SAY: <PERSON>Joe
Montana</PERSON>: "Our biggest rival has to be the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION>, because they beat us for years
when I first got here. . . . Well, everybody did. But they did it a little
more consistently than anybody else.";   Wide receiver <PERSON>Jerry Rice</PERSON>: "When two
teams really dislike each other -- like the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION>, they're right down the road
from us -- that's what really makes a good rivalry."; 49ERS VS. RAMS; (box)
FIRST GAME OF SERIES: In <DATE>1950</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> defeated the 49ers twice: 35-14 on
<DATE>Oct. 1</DATE> and 28-21 on <DATE>Nov. 5.</DATE>;   (box) SERIES RECORD: The <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> lead 48-32-2 in
regular-season games.;   (box) THE LAST TIME THESE TEAMS MET: They split games
last season: The Rams won at Candlestick 28-17 on <DATE>Nov. 25</DATE>, and the 49ers won
at <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> Stadium 26-10 on <DATE>Dec. 17.</DATE>;   (box) THE NEXT TIME THESE TEAMS MEET:
<DATE>Sept. 22</DATE> at <LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  -- Nancy Gay  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910825  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  13H  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  463  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, August 25, 1991
00238203,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06025137 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06025137 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, chart; PHOTO: AP File Photograph; GIVE HIM FIVE -- Bill Parcells is a
Jersey guy and proud of it; and, in turn, Jersey -- and New York -- are proud
of him.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; CLUB; NEW-YORK; COACH; PROFILE; CHART  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  New York Giants Coach Bill Parcells is a Jersey guy and proud of it.;    He
played high school football in Oradell, N.J., cheered for the Giants when he
was growing up and now lives in Upper Saddle River. He drives through the
Jersey swamplands to work every day, often stopping at a diner to talk with
Jersey guys about Jersey's finest team, the one he has in the Super Bowl for
the second time in five years.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Special Section  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PARCELLS DESERVES A PARCEL OF CREDIT
UNDER HIM, GIANTS ARE A WINNING PACKAGE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Super Bowl XXV: A Viewer's Guide  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "I walk into this joint the other day," <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> said <DATE>last week</DATE>, "and it
killed me. There are all of these guys sitting in there -- you know the way
they are. They see me, and from everywhere all I hear is, 'Hey Bill, goin'
beat them Beahs?' They're yelling it at me from the trucks, from behind the
counters, from everywhere.";    Sweet victory;  The Giants beat the Bears and
then the 49ers. The victory over the 49ers was quintessential <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON>, won
without a touchdown and with help from a bunch of skill-position players who
resemble fireflies when compared with the fireworks of the 49ers' offense.;   
"You saw a helluva game," <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> said afterward. "It might not have been as
wide open as some people would like, but I'm sure <PERSON>Woody Hayes</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bear Bryant</PERSON>
would have enjoyed it.";    <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON>, like those fellows, is blunt. He often
tells reporters, "Fellas, it's not that complicated.";    This attitude
probably has cost him a few coach-of-the-year votes along the way. Parcells is
perceived as the caretaker of an always-solid, rarely exciting team, a guy who
displays his rapport when he head-butts players in gratitude.;    Since taking
over the team in <DATE>1983</DATE>, his record is 84-52-1 -- fifth best among active
coaches -- including 7-3 in playoff games.;    He went 3-12 his first season
but hasn't won fewer than nine games in a full season since. This season's
<ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> are 15-3, and they head into the Super Bowl with only three offensive
and five defensive starters from their 39-20 victory over the <LOCATION>Denver Broncos</LOCATION>
in Super Bowl XXI.;    Putting trust in players; Parcells won in the playoffs
this season and during the <DATE>1986</DATE> season by placing his trust in several players
who might not get picked up if they were cut tomorrow.;    You have heard of
the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills' no-huddle offense? The <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> should bill theirs the
no-offense huddle.;    Their quarterback is career backup <PERSON>Jeff Hostetler</PERSON>.
Their only true running threat is <PERSON>Ottis Anderson</PERSON>, 33, who was considered
washed up three years ago. Their receivers are <PERSON>Mark Ingram</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stephen Baker</PERSON>,
neither of whom ranked in the top 20 in the NFC in catches or yards, and their
tight end, <PERSON>Mark Bavaro</PERSON>, is considering retirement.;    And although the
<ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>' defense is loaded with talent, remember that starting cornerback
<PERSON>Everson</PERSON> Walls was let go by <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> and that a rookie, <PERSON>Mike Fox</PERSON>, starts at
defensive end.;    Against the Bears, <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> used his extra week of
preparation to switch from his beloved 3-4 defense to a 4-3 that held the
Bears to 27 yards rushing, their lowest total in 23 years. Against the 49ers,
he and defensive coordinator <PERSON>Bill Belichick</PERSON> employed an extra defensive back
on first downs to try to discourage the 49ers from passing, then went back to
a 3-4 so the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> could blitz from any and all angles in an attempt to
rattle <PERSON>Joe Montana.</PERSON>;    <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> also cut the fleet <PERSON>Hostetler</PERSON> loose on
bootlegs and play-action rollouts that nullified the 49ers' rush, gave his
receivers extra time and capitalized on <PERSON>Hostetler</PERSON>'s uncanny accuracy on the
run.;    Then there's <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON>' ability to motivate. The <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> looked to be
struggling late in the season, losing three of their last six games, beating
only 6-10 <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, 5-11 <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> and 1-15 New England.;    <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> lit into
his players in a team meeting that spawned a players-only meeting. The players
-- particularly cornerback <PERSON>Mark Collins</PERSON> -- didn't appreciate it.;    But they
responded. And <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> is never one to get in the way of his players' freedom
of speech, as long as he has the freedom to respond.;    "I don't care what
they have to say," <PERSON>Parcells</PERSON> said, "as long as they realize that I might have
something to say, too.";    He was expected to have a lot to say this week as
reporters gathered around to hear how he beat the fearsome 49ers without
scoring a touchdown, with a gimpy backup quarterback, with a tread-worn
running back and an assortment of other handicaps that don't seem to faze this
<LOCATION>Jersey</LOCATION> guy.;    Remember his line: "Fellas, it's not that complicated."; 
<PERSON>Parcells</PERSON>' record; Regular season; Yr.     Team   W   <ORGANIZATION>L   T   Pct.</ORGANIZATION>; <DATE>1983</DATE>   
Giants  3  12  1   .219; <DATE>1984</DATE>    Giants  9   7  0   .563; <DATE>1985</DATE>    Giants 10  
6  0   .625; <DATE>1986</DATE>    Giants 14   2  0   .875; <DATE>1987</DATE>    Giants  6   9  0   .400;
<DATE>1988</DATE>    Giants 10   6  0   .625; <DATE>1989</DATE>    Giants 12   4  0   .750; <DATE>1990</DATE>   
Giants 13   3  0   .813;         Totals 77  49  1   .610; <LOCATION>Postseason</LOCATION>; Yr.     
Team   W   <ORGANIZATION>L   T   Pct.</ORGANIZATION>; <DATE>1984</DATE>    Giants  1   1  0    .500; <DATE>1985</DATE>    Giants  1  
1  0    .500; <DATE>1986</DATE>    Giants  3   0  0   1.000; <DATE>1989</DATE>    Giants  0   1  0   
.000; <DATE>1990</DATE>    Giants  2   0  0   1.000;         Totals  7   3  0    .700;
(box) <DATE>1984</DATE>: Won wild-card playoff against <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Rams</ORGANIZATION> 16-13; lost
divisional playoff to 49ers 21-10.;       (box) <DATE>1985</DATE>: Won wild-card playoff
against 49ers 17-3; lost divisional playoff to <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 21-0.;       (box)
<DATE>1986</DATE>: Won conference playoff against 49ers 49-3; won conference championship
against <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> 17-0; won Super Bowl XXI against <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 39-20.;       (box)
<DATE>1989</DATE>: Lost divisional playoff to <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> <DATE>19-13</DATE>, OT.;       (box) <DATE>1990</DATE>: Won
divisional playoff against <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 31-3; won conference championship against
49ers <DATE>15-13</DATE>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JIM SOUHAN, Minneapolis-St. Paul Star Tribune  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Tampa, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910125  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  18D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,005  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday January 25, 1991
00025137,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122589-0003 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 153323 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 25, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 7; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
321 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
49ERS FINISH DECADE IN FINE FASHION; 
</P>
<P>
SAN FRANCISCO: TEAM RECORD (14-2) IS EASILY BEST IN THE LEAGUE AFTER SHUTOUT 
VICTORY OVER BEARS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN FRANCISCO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The team of the '80s ended the decade with a bang <DATE>Sunday</DATE> while the once-mighty 
<ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bears</ORGANIZATION> went out with a whimper. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON> put the cap on a record-breaking regular season as the <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers beat the Bears, 26-0, and set their sights on the first Super 
Bowl of the '90s. 
</P>
<P>
"It's been an extremely exciting 10 years, no question about it," rookie Coach 
<PERSON>George Seifert</PERSON> said after the 49ers (14-2) wrapped up their second-best record 
ever. No other <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> team won more than 11 games. 
</P>
<P>
"I feel very fortunate to have been part of it," <PERSON>Seifert</PERSON> said. "The trick now 
is to keep it going." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> threw a 29-yard touchdown pass to <PERSON>Jerry Rice</PERSON> and set an <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> season 
record for highest quarterback rating as the 49ers won their fifth consecutive 
game and the Bears dropped their sixth straight. <PERSON>Mike Cofer</PERSON> kicked four field 
goals and won the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> scoring title with 136 points. 
</P>
<P>
"I think we feel good about what we did <DATE>today</DATE>," <PERSON>Montana</PERSON> said, shrugging off 
talk of personal achievements. "It took a while to get things going, but our 
defense just played a heck of a game." 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers, whose better record was 15-1 in <DATE>1984</DATE> en route to their second of 
three Super Bowl championships, will have a week off before playing host to an 
<ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> playoff game against either <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> or the <ORGANIZATION>NFC Central</ORGANIZATION> champion. 
</P>
<P>
Chicago Coach <PERSON>Mike Ditka</PERSON> vowed the Bears would bounce back after "hitting 
bottom" with 10 losses in their last 12 games. 
</P>
<P>
"Somewhere along the line we lost our confidence," <PERSON>Ditka</PERSON> said. "I don't really 
believe we're that bad a football team, although I guess you have to believe 
that after today. 
</P>
<P>
"It was a bad day and it's been a sad season, but they come and go. We've had a 
lot of great seasons. . . . If all of a sudden football passed us by in <DATE>'89</DATE>, 
and I don't think it did, then I'd say we change the system. But we just 
haven't executed very well." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> missed the playoffs for the first time since <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06025239 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06025239 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; CHAMPIONSHIP; CLUB; YEAR; STATISTIC  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  How Super Bowl winners fared the year following their championship (year
listed refers to regular season of year following championship):; Team  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Special Section  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HOW SUPER BOWL WINNERS FARED  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Super Bowl XXV: A Viewer's Guide  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  Result; <DATE>1967</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Green Bay Packers</ORGANIZATION>;  Beat <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> 33-14 in Super Bowl; <DATE>1968</DATE> Green
Bay Packers;  Did not make playoffs; 1969 <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Jets;  Lost to <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>
13-6 in <ORGANIZATION>AFL</ORGANIZATION> divisional playoff; 1970 <LOCATION>Kansas City Chiefs</LOCATION>;  Did not make
playoffs; <DATE>1971</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Baltimore Colts</ORGANIZATION>;  Lost to <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 21-0 in <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> championship; 1972
<LOCATION>Dallas Cowboys</LOCATION>;  Lost to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> 26-3 in <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> championship; <DATE>1973</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Miami
Dolphins</ORGANIZATION>;  <LOCATION>Beat Minnesota</LOCATION> 24-7 in Super Bowl; 1974 <LOCATION>Miami Dolphins</LOCATION>;  Lost to
<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> 28-26 in <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> divisional playoffs; <DATE>1975</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</ORGANIZATION>; Beat
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> 21-17 in Super Bowl; <DATE>1976</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</ORGANIZATION>;  Lost to <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> 24-7 in
<ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> championship; <DATE>1977</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Raiders</ORGANIZATION>;  Lost to <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 20-17 in <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>
championship; <DATE>1978</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Dallas Cowboys</ORGANIZATION>;  Lost to <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> 35-31 in Super Bowl;
<DATE>1979</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</ORGANIZATION>;  Beat <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Rams 31-19 in Super Bowl; <DATE>1980</DATE>
<ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</ORGANIZATION>;  Did not make playoffs; <DATE>1981</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Raiders</ORGANIZATION>;  Did not
make playoffs; <DATE>1982</DATE> 49ers;  Did not make playoffs (strike-shortened season);
<DATE>1983</DATE> Washington Redskins;  Lost to <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Raiders 38-9 in Super Bowl;
<DATE>1984</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Raiders</ORGANIZATION>;  Lost to <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> 13-7 in <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> first round; <DATE>1985</DATE>
49ers;  Lost to <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION> 17-3 in <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> first round; <DATE>1986</DATE> Chicago Bears; 
Lost to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> 27-13 in <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> divisional playoffs; <DATE>1987</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION>; 
Did not make playoffs (strike-shortened season); <DATE>1988</DATE> Washington Redskins; 
Did not make playoffs; <DATE>1989</DATE> 49ers;  Beat Denver Broncos 55-10 in Super Bowl;
<DATE>1990</DATE> 49ers;  Lost to <ORGANIZATION>N.Y. Giants</ORGANIZATION> 15-13 in <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> championship  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910125  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  26D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  281  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday January 25, 1991
00025239,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA123189-0097 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 155834 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 31, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 8; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1101 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NFL PLAYOFF PICTURE: IT'S THE NINERS AND NINE NOBODIES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By VITO STELLINO, BALTIMORE SUN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers seem to be in a league of their own as they enter the 
<ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> playoffs -- so much so that perhaps an appropriate title for this 
spectacular is the 49ers and the Nine Dwarfs. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers, attempting to become the first team in a decade to repeat as Super 
Bowl champions, posted a 14-2 regular-season record. They were two games better 
than any other team in the league and beat four of the other nine playoff 
teams. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers, one of six division champions with a bye today when the two 
wild-card games will be played, are on much more of a roll than they were a 
year ago, when they started 6-5, won four straight and then lost their 
regular-season finale to the Rams, 38-16. That loss knocked the <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION> 
out of the playoffs, leading Giant quarterback <PERSON>Phil Simms</PERSON> to complain that he 
watched the 49ers "lay down like dogs" against the Rams. 
</P>
<P>
This year, the 49ers routed the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bears</ORGANIZATION>, 26-0, in their finale, even 
playoffs. 
</P>
<P>
"In some respects, that was a very decisive win. But, as coaches, we look at 
certain things that we can do better," said 49er Coach <PERSON>George Seifert</PERSON>. "And 
we'll have to do them better in the playoffs." 
</P>
<P>
If the 49ers do as well as they did in the regular season, that would be good 
enough. 
</P>
<P>
They even seem to have history on their side. The <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> has a record of ending a 
decade with a team winning back-to-back titles. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Philadelphia Eagles</LOCATION> did it in <DATE>1948-49</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Baltimore Colts</LOCATION> did it in 
<DATE>1958-59</DATE> and the <LOCATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</LOCATION> did it in <DATE>1978-79</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers, who are considered by many to be the team of the decade, can join 
<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> as the only four-time Super Bowl champion. 
</P>
<P>
They also can become known as one of the best post-World War II teams, joining 
the 1946-55 <PERSON>Cleveland Browns</PERSON>, who won four titles in the old <ORGANIZATION>All-America 
Conference</ORGANIZATION> and three <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> titles; the <ORGANIZATION>Green Bay Packers</ORGANIZATION> of the <DATE>1960s</DATE>, who won 
five titles and the first two Super Bowls, and the Steelers of the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, who 
won four Super Bowls in six seasons. 
</P>
<P>
That's why all the focus is on the 49ers, who will play either the <LOCATION>Philadelphia 
Eagles</LOCATION> or the <LOCATION>Minnesota Vikings</LOCATION> in their first playoff game. If they win, 
they'd face either the Vikings, <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> or <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> in the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> title game. 
</P>
<P>
Of those four teams, the Rams seem to have the best shot of upsetting the 
49ers. They handed the 49ers one of their two losses this season and could have 
swept them if they hadn't blown two 17-point leads in the second game. 
</P>
<P>
The problem for the <ORGANIZATION>Rams</ORGANIZATION> will be getting to the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> title game. They will first 
have to win at Veterans Stadium in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, then at <ORGANIZATION>Giants Stadium</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>East 
Rutherford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
The weather is likely to be nasty in both places, and the Rams aren't noted for 
playing well in cold weather. They barely beat the <ORGANIZATION>New England Patriots</ORGANIZATION>, 24-20, 
in <LOCATION>Foxboro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers beat the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> and Eagles during the regular season, and the Vikings 
would have to face <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> on the road at <LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers beat the <LOCATION>Vikings</LOCATION>, 34-9, in the playoffs last season. The Vikings, 
whose home is the Metrodome in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, have become such a dome team that 
they're 1-8 in their last nine outdoor games. 
</P>
<P>
The Vikings upset the 49ers two seasons ago in the playoffs, 36-24, at 
<LOCATION>Candlestick</LOCATION> when the 49ers were 13-2. But quarterback <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON> was rusty and 
ineffective in that game after being injured at the end of the season. 
</P>
<P>
Although he's had trouble with his ribs this season, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> finished the 
season by hitting 10 of 21 passes against the Bears before coming out early in 
the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>. It wasn't vintage <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, but it was good enough to enable 
him to set the record for quarterback rating, with 112.4. Milt Plum of the 
<LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION> had the old mark of 110.4 in <DATE>1960</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> also finished the season by completing <PERCENT>70.2 percent</PERCENT> of his passes, the 
third-best mark in <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> history. <PERSON>Ken Anderson</PERSON> completed 70.55 of his passes in 
<DATE>1982</DATE>, the nine-game strike season, and <PERSON>Sammy Baugh</PERSON> completed 70.3 in <DATE>1945</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
If the 49ers hadn't pulled <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> so soon in the Bear game, he might have 
broken that record. 
</P>
<P>
"We didn't find out until there were three minutes left in the game," <PERSON>Seifert</PERSON> 
said. "Had we known earlier in the third period, we might have put him back in. 
But the plan was to do basically what we did." 
</P>
<P>
In the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>, a team will qualify for the Super Bowl only because that's the way 
the system works. The <PERSON>Denver Broncos</PERSON> were the only team to win more than nine 
regular-season games. They finished 11-5 and are favored to go to the Super 
Bowl for the third time in the last four seasons. But they lost at home to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Eagles and Giants</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback <PERSON>John Elway</PERSON> didn't have one of his better seasons, but <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> 
prospered when defensive coordinator <PERSON>Wade Phillips</PERSON> rebuilt the defense into a 
unit that ranked No. 2 in the AFC, No. 1 against the rush. 
</P>
<P>
The Broncos lost two of their last three games, and it may not be considered 
stunning if they lose in the playoffs. 
</P>
<P>
The team that might have the best chance of beating them is the <LOCATION>Cleveland 
Browns</LOCATION>, who defeated the Vikings and <ORGANIZATION>Houston Oilers</ORGANIZATION> in the final two weeks of 
the season. 
</P>
<P>
The addition of running back <PERSON>Kevin Mack</PERSON>, who was in jail on a drug charge 
earlier in the season, has added a dimension to the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' sputtering offense. 
</P>
<P>
Mack, who scored the winning touchdown against the Oilers with 39 seconds left 
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, said, "I guess when all the trouble started, it was hard to see 
ahead to the good times coming back again. But a lot of people believed in me, 
and now I'm back." 
</P>
<P>
At the start of the season, the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills and Oilers were given good shots 
of making the Super Bowl, but both teams are on the defensive after struggling 
down the stretch. The Bills lost three of their last four, and the Oilers lost 
their last two. 
</P>
<P>
Bill Coach <PERSON>Marv Levy</PERSON> said, 'We've been in first place for 32 straight games 
(two seasons). Sometimes it's hard to please people." 
</P>
<P>
That's mainly because they were only 9-7, and because the players don't seem to 
like quarterback <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Oilers</ORGANIZATION> also finished 9-7, and <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Jerry Glanville</PERSON> said, "We don't 
have to apologize for being one of the three (actually four) teams that have 
made the playoffs the last three years (along with the <LOCATION>Browns</LOCATION>, Vikings and 
49ers). There are 18 teams that wish they were in, but they're not." 
</P>
<P>
One team not apologizing is the <ORGANIZATION>Pittsburgh Steelers</ORGANIZATION>, the hottest team in the 
AFC. They won their last three games, although the games were against teams 
with losing records -- the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Jets, Patriots and <LOCATION>Tampa Bay Buccaneers</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Quarterback Joe Montana makes the difference for the 49ers. Associated 
Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Analysis; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06350200 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06350200 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3); PHOTO: Bill Walsh; ... Successful at Stanford; PHOTO: Bill Walsh;
... Genius with 49ers; PHOTO: Mercury News File Photographs; After taking
over, in 1979, a team that had gone 2-14 the previous season, Bill Walsh
struggled on the sideline, left, through two seasons, winning just eight of
his first 32 games. But in his third season, Walsh led the 49ers to their
first Super Bowl title. And in January 1985, Walsh walked off the field at
Stanford Stadium, above, with his second of three Super Bowl victories.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPORT; CELEBRITY; AWARD; NAME; LIST; NEWSPAPER; SF-BAY-AREA; SERIES  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  1957-59: In his first head-coaching job, Walsh took over a program at
Washington High School of Fremont that had gone 1-26 in the previous three
seasons. In '58 it went 9-1.;   (hbox)  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WALSH'S CAREER AT A GLANCE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Bay Area's Best of the Best; Best of the Best: Bill Walsh  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  1960-65: Served as assistant coach at <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> through <DATE>1962</DATE> and at <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> from
1963-65.;   (hbox); 1966-76: Moved to pro football, serving as an assistant
coach with the <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Raiders</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>'66</DATE>, head coach and general manager of San
Jose Apaches of the <ORGANIZATION>Continental League</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>'67</DATE>, and an assistant coach with
<ORGANIZATION>Cincinnati Bengals</ORGANIZATION> from 1966-75 and the <LOCATION>San Diego Chargers</LOCATION> in 1976.;   (hbox);
1977-78: Named head coach of <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION>, he went 17-7 over two seasons and won
two bowl games.;   (hbox); 1979-81: After taking over a team that went 2-14 in
<DATE>1978</DATE>, <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> struggled as well, going 2-14 and 6-10. But his team won 13 of 16
in the <DATE>1981</DATE> regular season and beat <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> for the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> title in a game
featuring the <PERSON>Joe Montana-Dwight Clark</PERSON> pass play known as <ORGANIZATION>The Catch</ORGANIZATION>. He then
gave the 49ers their first <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> title, with a 26-21 triumph over <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> in
Super Bowl XVI.;   (hbox); 1982-84: After missing the playoffs in <DATE>1982</DATE> and
reaching the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> championship game in the <DATE>1983</DATE> season, <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> coached the 49ers
to a 15-1 mark in <DATE>1984</DATE> and led them to victory in Super Bowl XIX by crushing
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 38-16 at <ORGANIZATION>Stanford Stadium.</ORGANIZATION>;   (hbox); 1985-88: The <DATE>1988</DATE> season marked
<PERSON>Walsh</PERSON>'s sixth straight in the playoffs. He capped it by beating <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>
20-16 in Super Bowl XXIII. He resigned after the <DATE>1988</DATE> season, winding up a
10-year <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> head-coaching career with a 92-59-1 record in the regular season
and 10-4 in the postseason.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911215  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  405  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, December 15, 1991
00350200,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA123190-0026 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 329422 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 31, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 10; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
688 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
YOUNG'S MONTANA-LIKE HEROICS GIVE 49ERS A WIN OVER VIKINGS; 
</P>
<P>
NFC: BACKUP QUARTERBACK'S TOUCHDOWN PASS PLAY WITH 29 SECONDS LEFT IS THE 
DIFFERENCE. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MINNEAPOLIS 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Steve Young</PERSON>, understudy to <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON>, used a <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> script to rally the <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers to a <DATE>20-17</DATE> victory over the <LOCATION>Minnesota Vikings</LOCATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Young, who relieved <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> in the <DATE>second half</DATE>, teamed with <PERSON>John Taylor</PERSON> on a 
34-yard touchdown pass play with 29 seconds left to enable the 49ers to finish 
the regular season 14-2, the best record in the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> has led countless comebacks. Last week, Young had the chance, but the 
49ers lost, 13-10, to <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Jerry Burns</PERSON> wasn't surprised by <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s heroics <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"It epitomizes the whole season. We had our chance to win the game and we 
couldn't stop them," <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> said. "I just had a premonition they'd go right down 
and score and we wouldn't stop them. The secondary play was sick. The pass 
rush. The whole thing. 
</P>
<P>
"They know how to win and this team doesn't. Anytime you win you can feed off 
that success. You know that, in the past, you've come back and won games. This 
team hasn't done it." 
</P>
<P>
NFC Central champions last season, the Vikings (6-10) finished in last place 
for the first time since <DATE>1984</DATE>. They ended the season with a four-game losing 
streak. 
</P>
<P>
"You really have to be scratching to find anything positive," <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> said. "When 
I saw that guy shoot that gun at the end, that was the most positive thing I 
saw." 
</P>
<P>
While <PERSON>Burns</PERSON>' most frustrating season finally ended, the 49ers will now begin 
concentrating on the playoffs in an effort to become the first NFL team to win 
three consecutive Super Bowls and five overall. 
</P>
<P>
"I had a decent day and I'm glad I've had the opportunity to catch 100 balls," 
said 49er receiver <PERSON>Jerry Rice</PERSON>, who caught nine passes for 118 yards and became 
the fourth player ever to reach the 100-reception mark in a season. "I think 
that's something to be proud of, but I'm just looking forward to the first 
playoff game." 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers' 18th consecutive road victory extended their own league record. 
However, they won't enjoy the "road-field advantage" in the playoffs, having 
clinched home-field throughout the playoffs two weeks ago. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>George Seifert</PERSON> said the victory wasn't insignificant. 
"Coming into the playoffs, winning the game instead of losing, allows us to 
have pride in ourselves," he said. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, which won 15 games in <DATE>1984</DATE> and 14 in <DATE>1989</DATE> and went on to win the 
Super Bowl those years, used victories over <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> to springboard to its 
last three championships. The Vikings' last three seasons have ended with 
losses to the 49ers. 
</P>
<P>
As he had planned to do before the game, <PERSON>Seifert</PERSON> started <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and used Young 
for the entire second half. <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> completed 10 of 20 passes for 88 yards and 
had one pass intercepted as the 49ers trailed, 10-0, and had a scoreless first 
half for the first time since <DATE>Dec. 17, 1989</DATE> against <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Young sparked the 49ers with his passing and scrambling. He was 15 of 24 for 
205 yards passing and added 59 yards in six rushes. 
</P>
<P>
On the winning drive, Young completed six of seven passes for 88 yards and also 
had a two-yard dive on fourth-and-one. <PERSON>Ken Stills</PERSON> was the closest <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> 
player to <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> when he caught Young's pass at the 16 and went untouched into 
the end zone. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a play that takes a while to develop," <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said. "I told the guys in 
the huddle that we needed a little extra tick to throw the ball." 
</P>
<P>
Young's 14-yard touchdown pass to Rice with 8:37 left -- which he set up with 
scrambles of 14 and 19 yards -- gave the 49ers a 13-10 lead. <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> came 
back to go up, 17-13, on <PERSON>Alfred Anderson</PERSON>'s one-yard run with 3:14 left before 
<PERSON>Young</PERSON> did a splendid impression of a <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> rally. 
</P>
<P>
The Vikings, who sacked <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and Young six times, with <PERSON>Ken Clarke</PERSON> getting 
three of the sacks, used an aggressive defense and <PERSON>Herschel Walker</PERSON>'s 
versatility to take their 10-point halftime lead. 
</P>
<P>
After <PERSON>Fuad Reveiz</PERSON>'s 34-yard field goal, <PERSON>Walker</PERSON> capped a 79-yard drive with a 
nine-yard touchdown run. Walker had four carries for 30 yards, caught an 
18-yard pass and threw a 12-yard halfback option pass to <PERSON>D.J. Dozier</PERSON> during the 
drive. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mike Cofer</PERSON>'s field goals of 29 and 35 yards made it 10-6 early in the <DATE>fourth 
quarter</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06288121 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06288121 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-FRANCISCO; PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; GAME; RESULT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  It has been a long time since the 49ers reached such depths. Here's the last
time it looked this bad for the team:;   (box) The 49ers were most recently
2-4 in 1982. They finished 3-6 in that strike-shortened season.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BAD NEWS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Falcons 39, 49ers 34  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     (box) The 49ers were most recently 2-4 in a non-strike season in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <PERSON>Bill
Walsh</PERSON>'s first as coach. The team finished 2-14.;   (box) The 49ers most
recently gave up 39 or more points in a regular-season game in <DATE>1982</DATE>, when the
<LOCATION>San Diego Chargers</LOCATION> beat them 41-37. After the <DATE>1986</DATE> season, the <ORGANIZATION>N.Y. Giants</ORGANIZATION>
beat the 49ers 49-3 in the first round of the playoffs.;   (box) The last time
the 49ers scored so many points and lost was the 41-37 <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> game in
1982.;   (box) The 49ers most recently lost to the <LOCATION>Atlanta Falcons</LOCATION> in <DATE>1988</DATE>,
falling 17-14 at <LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION>. The 49ers had won five straight against
<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> before Sunday.;   (box) The 49ers most recently allowed a kickoff to
be returned for a touchdown in the regular season in <DATE>1987</DATE>. <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Sylvester
Stamps</PERSON> ran it back 97 yards. In the Super Bowl, after the <DATE>1988</DATE> season,
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Stanford Jennings</PERSON> returned a kickoff 93 yards for a TD against
the 49ers.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  -- Edmundo Macedo  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911014  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  216  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, October 14, 1991
00288121,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06288142 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06288142 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Jose Luis Villegas -- Mercury News; EARLY SETBACK -- Atlanta's
Scott Case intercepts a pass intended for John Taylor. The play helped Atlanta
take an early 17-0 lead.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-FRANCISCO; PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; GAME; RESULT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A dismal situation in the NFC West just got a little worse for the 49ers.;  
Sunday, the New Orleans Saints won, going to a remarkable 6-0.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  49ERS FIND LAST PLACE TO BE A STRANGE PLACE
THE MIGHTY TAKE WORST FALL SINCE '82  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Falcons 39, 49ers 34  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Rams</ORGANIZATION> won, improving their record to 3-3.;   <DATE>Sunday</DATE>,
the <LOCATION>Atlanta Falcons</LOCATION> -- as the 49ers are so painfully aware -- also won,
improving to 3-3.;   But <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the 49ers lost, falling to 2-4 for the first
time since <DATE>1982</DATE>, and falling into last place in the <LOCATION>NFC West.</LOCATION>;   It is the
first time since <DATE>1979</DATE> that the 49ers had sole possession of last place this
late in the season. In <DATE>1979</DATE>, the 49ers finished 2-14.;   "We can't worry about
that right now, what place we're in," linebacker <PERSON>Bill Romanowski</PERSON> said. "Right
now, everybody's got to look at themselves and say, 'What the heck can I do to
improve this team and make this team win?' ";   But the ugly truth of the
matter is that the only <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> teams with worse records than the 49ers are Green
Bay and <LOCATION>Tampa Bay</LOCATION> (each 1-5). The 49ers have the same record as the lowly <LOCATION>New
England Patriots.</LOCATION>;   "The season isn't halfway over," guard Guy <PERSON>McIntyre</PERSON> said.
"This is the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>. One day you're down, and the next day you're on the top of
the world.";   The 49ers have a long way to go to get to the top of the world.
They have four more divisional games to play -- two against first-place <LOCATION>New
Orleans</LOCATION> and one each against <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> and the Rams.;   <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s game against
the Falcons was a critical one, as both teams were aware.;   "We said before
the game that whichever team won the game had a real shot at the playoffs,"
Falcons Coach <PERSON>Jerry Glanville</PERSON> said.;   If ever there was a "must-win" game for
the 49ers, this was it.;   "We needed the win," safety <PERSON>Todd Bowles</PERSON> said. "It's
a shock losing ball games. It hurts a lot. We'll see what we're made of now."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  ANN KILLION, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911014  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  364  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, October 14, 1991
00288142,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06021156 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06021156 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-FRANCISCO; PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; PLAYOFF; GAME; RESULT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The end of the 49ers' season unofficially came with just under 10 minutes to
play in Sunday's game.;    Quarterback Joe Montana dropped to the ground under
the weight of New York defensive end Leonard Marshall.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HIT ON MONTANA SIGNALS THE END FOR NINERS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  NFC Championship: Giants 15, 49ers 13
Additional information attached to the end of this article.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     A bone on the outside of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s right hand -- his passing hand -- was
fractured. His sternum was badly bruised.;    "If the 49ers had won <DATE>today</DATE>, <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>
would not have been able to play in next week's game," said <PERSON>Michael
Dillingham</PERSON>, the team physician, in a prepared statement.;    So that was it.
Even though the 49ers were leading 13-9, even though <PERSON>Steve Young</PERSON> is a fine
quarterback, even though the 49ers' defense continued to keep the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> out
of the end zone, as <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> lay huddled on the ground at the 20-yard line, the
life seemed to drain from the team.;    The 49ers eventually lost <DATE>15-13</DATE> on
<PERSON>Matt Bahr</PERSON>'s last-second field goal.;    "For any team to have a chance to (win
three Super Bowls) you have to have a player like <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON>," said tackle
<PERSON>Steve Wallace.</PERSON>;    <ORGANIZATION>The Giants</ORGANIZATION> figured that without <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> the 49ers were in
trouble. So they came after him.;    "We wanted to hit him as often as we
could," Giants linebacker <PERSON>Lawrence Taylor</PERSON> said. "We wanted to give him
something to think about.";    The hit <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> took in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE> was
the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>' third sack of the game. But he was under constant pressure.;   
"They didn't do anything they hadn't done before," said 49ers offensive-line
coach <PERSON>Bobb McKittrick</PERSON>. "It was just different forms of blitzes.";    In the
<DATE>second quarter</DATE>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> was hit by <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON>, who went past left tackle <LOCATION>Bubba
Paris</LOCATION>. In the <DATE>third quarter</DATE>, <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> and <PERSON>Erik Howard</PERSON> combined for a sack.;   
"We put a lot of pounding on him, and you could tell he was getting
frustrated," <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said.;    The Giants were even more motivated after 49ers
nose tackle <PERSON>Jim Burt</PERSON> leveled <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> quarterback <PERSON>Jeff Hostetler</PERSON>, who left the
game for three plays.;    <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said he told <PERSON>Burt</PERSON> after the play: " 'If
that's the way you want to play it, OK. Somebody else is going to lose a
quarterback.' We did it, but it wasn't a cheap shot.";    Within minutes,
<PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>'s threat was realized. On the 49ers' next possession, on third-and-10
from their 23, the line pushed inside, allowing <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> to roll to his right.
<PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> was cut down by <PERSON>Tom Rathman.</PERSON>;    <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> looked for an open receiver,
but <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> was coming at him and forced him to step back. By that time,
<PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> had gotten up off the ground and charged past <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, gaining
momentum.;    "After he was cut, I didn't think about him," <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> said. "I was
looking for the next person. Then he runs past.";    <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said: "<PERSON>Joe</PERSON> was
naked out there.";    <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> grabbed <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, and they both fell to the
ground. The ball flew out of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s hand and rolled 6 yards upfield, where
<PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> fell on it.;    "I'm not out to hurt anybody," <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> said. "I felt
bad that he got hurt.";    Everyone knew instantly how hard <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> had been
hit.;    "I heard it from 40 yards away," Giants cornerback <ORGANIZATION>Everson Walls</ORGANIZATION>
said. "It was like one of those NFL Films sound effects, but this was real."; 
  Young was the first to reach Montana.;    "I just wanted to make sure he was
OK," <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said. "It looked worse than normal.";    It was reminiscent of a
<DATE>January day four years earlier</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> was slammed to the ground by
<PERSON>Burt</PERSON>, then playing for the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>. As it was then, it was clear that this
injury was serious.;    After several minutes, with doctors and trainers and
<PERSON>Ronnie Lott</PERSON>, huddled around him, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> -- who had completed 18 of 26 passes
for 190 yards and a touchdown -- was helped to the bench, walking shakily.;   
He stayed there the remainder of the game.;    Afterward, the 49ers' locker
room was quiet. In the training room, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> lay on his back on the training
table, his arm raised in the air.;    The official injury report from
<PERSON>Dillingham</PERSON> was that <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> had a bruised sternum and that the fifth
metacarpal -- the bone below <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s little finger -- of his right hand was
fractured. Montana will be X-rayed again today and treatment for the injury
will be determined either today or <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. <PERSON>Dillingham</PERSON> said that an operation
on <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s hand was a possibility.;    When the locker room was almost
empty, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> -- flanked by security guards -- made his way out the door.;   
"I have no idea," <PERSON>Montana</PERSON> said, when asked how his hand, which was in a cast,
was broken. In a statement to 49ers public relations officials, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> said
he was having trouble breathing because of his bruised sternum.;    <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>
walked up the ramp from the locker room, back onto the <LOCATION>Candlestick</LOCATION> field,
where his wife, <PERSON>Jennifer</PERSON>, waited with a car.;    <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> got in the passenger
seat and was driven away, through the garbage blowing across the field in
empty Candlestick Park.; RIVALRY EXTENDS TO NEW DECADE; A look at the
49ers-Giants rivalry from the <DATE>1980s</DATE> to the '90s.; (box) <DATE>NOV. 23, 1980</DATE>: Before
either team was very good, the 49ers came away with a 12-0 win.;    (box) <DATE>NOV.
29, 1981</DATE>: The 49ers beat the Giants 17-10 during the regular season.;    (box)
<DATE>JAN. 3, 1982</DATE>: The 49ers meet the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> in the first of four playoff meetings
in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. The 49ers win 38-24, setting the stage for The Catch in the
championship-game win over <LOCATION>Dallas.</LOCATION>;    (box) <DATE>OCT. 8, 1984</DATE>: The 49ers beat the
Giants 31-10 during the regular season.;    (box) <DATE>DEC. 29, 1984</DATE>: The 49ers
beat the Giants 21-10 in the divisional playoffs on the way to Super Bowl
XIX.;    (box) <DATE>DEC. 29, 1985</DATE>: For the first time in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, the 49ers lose
to the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>, 17-3 in a wild-card playoff.;    (box) <DATE>DEC. 1, 1986</DATE>: The 49ers
lead 17-0 at halftime but lose to the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> 21-17 during the regular season.;
   (box) <DATE>JAN. 4, 1987</DATE>: The 49ers suffer what is now the fourth worst defeat in
<ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> postseason history, losing to the Giants 49-3 in the divisional playoffs.;
   (box) <DATE>SEPT. 11, 1988</DATE>: The 49ers beat the Giants 20-17 during the regular
season.;    (box) <DATE>NOV. 27, 1989</DATE>: The 49ers beat the Giants 34-24, bringing
their record against the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> to 7-3 in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> and to 10-12 overall.;   
(box) <DATE>DEC. 3, 1990</DATE>: The 49ers beat the Giants 7-3 in a battle of once-beaten
teams and go on to secure the home-field advantage for as long as they are
alive in the NFC playoffs.;    (box) <DATE>JAN. 20, 1991</DATE>: The 49ers fall to the
Giants 15-13 and their bid for a third straight Super Bowl title is ended.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  ANN KILLION, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910121  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,147  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday January 21, 1991
00021156,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011790-0152 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 163381 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 17, 1990, Wednesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part P; Page 11; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
808 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COMMENTARY; 
</P>
<P>
BRONCOS' TIMING-NOT THEIR TALENT -- IS PRETTY LOUSY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN EISENBERG, THE BALTIMORE SUN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It was hard not to feel a twinge of sympathy for the <ORGANIZATION>Denver Broncos</ORGANIZATION> even as 
they celebrated their third <ORGANIZATION>American Football Conference</ORGANIZATION> championship in four 
years after dispatching the <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
They were proud of making it back to the Super Bowl, and rightfully so. Two 
consecutive Super Bowl blowouts, the second against the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Redskins in 
<DATE>1988</DATE>, had forced them to look hard in the mirror and change their ways. Almost 
everything about them, from coaching staff to style of defense, had been 
overhauled. It was not easy. The Broncos went 8-8 in the <DATE>1988</DATE> season and failed 
to make the playoffs. 
</P>
<P>
But now, just <DATE>a year later</DATE>, they were back in the Super Bowl. And in their 
locker room <DATE>Sunday</DATE> the talk was that this year would be different, no Orange 
Crushed headlines the day after the Super Bowl. They were painfully earnest 
about all this and had worked hard to recover their pride. 
</P>
<P>
Even as they spoke, however, the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers were stamping out the Rams 
with such ferocity that women and children cowered from coast to coast. The 
Rams were on their knees begging for their lives at the end, or so went the 
inside scoop. 
</P>
<P>
The poor Broncos. Their timing is just plain poor. Had they made their return 
to the Super Bowl a year ago, when the 49ers were more vulnerable, they 
probably would not have taken another mega-beating. The <LOCATION>Cincinnati Bengals</LOCATION>, if 
you recall, were in the game all the way before a last-minute 49ers touchdown 
beat them. These Broncos are as capable as those Bengals. 
</P>
<P>
But this year's edition of the 49ers is many lengths superior. They lost only 
two games, as opposed to five a year ago. Their underrated defense has been 
particularly nettlesome. And, of course, <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON> is having a remarkable 
season: his best; one against which all great quarterbacking seasons may be 
compared. 
</P>
<P>
The Broncos just do not compare. It is true they have a more balanced offense 
and more physical defense than both of their Super losers, but they still are 
overmatched against these 49ers. Fact is, the 11 1/2-point betting line is too 
little. Not that that is an insult. No team in the parity-puffed, watered-down 
<ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION> could stay within two touchdowns of the 49ers right 
now. 
</P>
<P>
So it comes down to this: The Broncos, after all their soul-searching and 
reconstruction, are facing yet another paddling. Those who believe in justice 
had best avert their eyes. The <PERSON>Broncos</PERSON>' lot in life, it appears, is to be the 
well-paid, genial foil, the team that achieves much but, in the end, serves 
primarily as a pillow other teams kick and stomp as final proof of their 
prowess. 
</P>
<P>
It should be noted that one thing in the <PERSON>Broncos</PERSON>' favor is their motivation. 
Not in years has a Super Bowl qualifier stimulated such disrespect. The Broncos 
will play for the legitimacy of their name, and teams in such position play 
hard and, often, well. So maybe they have a chance if <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> falls off a train 
somewhere. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Broncos</PERSON>' window of opportunity is, simply, a peephole. It is important to 
understand the powerful sweep against which they are bucking. If not for one 
poor game in <DATE>January, 1988</DATE>, the 49ers would be on the verge of their third 
consecutive Super Bowl championship and their fourth in six years. It could be 
time to bring out the D-word: Dynasty. 
</P>
<P>
Two seasons ago, the 49ers finished the regular season with a 14-2 record that 
included 41-0 and 48-0 shatterings of the <ORGANIZATION>Rams and Chicago Bears</ORGANIZATION> in the last 
three weeks. But, inexplicably, they did not show up against the <LOCATION>Minnesota 
Vikings</LOCATION> in the playoffs, giving a four-loss Redskins team the chance to batter 
the <LOCATION>Broncos</LOCATION>. The Redskins won fair and square but they were not the best team 
that year. 
</P>
<P>
The 49ers rebounded to win the Super Bowl <DATE>last year</DATE> after a tumultuous regular 
season during which they lost five of their first 11 games. 
</P>
<P>
This year, the pieces fit perfectly. <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> is healthy now, and the nucleus of 
players has been together four or five years. The latter makes a big 
difference; the 49ers' combination of talent, teamwork and experience is just 
overwhelming. 
</P>
<P>
Watching <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s receivers get open so easily against <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> in the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> 
championship, one could not help imagining what damage the 49ers' <PERSON>Jerry Rice</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>John Taylor</PERSON> and <PERSON>Roger Craig</PERSON> could inflict if set loose in those open fields. 
Perhaps the only defense that could stop such a passing game is the 49ers' 
defense. 
</P>
<P>
Now, that would be worth watching. Let's say we pool our resources -- if every 
fan who watched the game contributed a dollar, we would have <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY> -- 
and buy the Super Bowl and give it to the 49ers. (Final: 34-14.) We would be 
spared another Bronco-bashing, and, instead, we could hold <PERSON>Super Scrimmage I. 
Jerry Rice</PERSON> against <PERSON>Ronnie Lott</PERSON>. That would be super. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Safety Ronnie Lott, left, and wide receiver Jerry Rice are two key 
players in establishing the 49ers' dominance this year. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06352222 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06352222 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; FOOTBALL; SAN-FRANCISCO; PLAYOFF; STATISTIC; CHART  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  In 1982, the last time the 49ers missed the playoffs . . .;   (box) They
finished 3-6 -- the second-worst record in the NFC -- in the strike-shortened
season. The 49ers were 0-2 before the strike. This season, they'll either be
10-6 or 9-7 for the season.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LAST TIME 49ERS MISSED THE PLAYOFFS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The NFL/Week 16  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     (box) They played at such a mediocre level that Coach <PERSON>Bill Walsh</PERSON> reportedly
contemplated quitting. There have been no reports that <PERSON>George Seifert</PERSON> is
having similar thoughts.;   (box) They failed to win a home game in five
tries. This season, the 49ers are 6-1 with a home game against <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> left on the schedule.;   (box) They didn't have <PERSON>Steve Young</PERSON> or
<PERSON>Steve Bono</PERSON>. Young was a junior at <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young University</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Bono</PERSON> was a
sophomore at UCLA.;   (box) They did have <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON>, who is the only player
left from that team on the current 49ers.; A LOOK AT THE STREAK; The 49ers
were trying to tie <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>' record of nine straight playoff appearances. A
season-by-season look at the 49ers during their playoff run:; Year   Rec.  How
they fared in playoffs; <DATE>1983</DATE>  10-6   Eliminated by <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> 24-21 in <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION>
title game; <DATE>1984</DATE>  15-1   Beat <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 38-16 in Super Bowl; <DATE>1985</DATE>  10-6  
Eliminated by <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION> 17-3 in first-round;             playoff; <DATE>1986</DATE> 
10-5-1 Eliminated by Giants 49-3 in divisional playoff; <DATE>1987</DATE>  13-2  
Eliminated by <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> 36-24 in divisional;             playoff; <DATE>1988</DATE>  10-6  
Beat <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 20-16 in Super Bowl; <DATE>1989</DATE>  14-2   Beat Denver 55-10 in Super
Bowl; <DATE>1990</DATE>  14-2   Eliminated by Giants 15-13 in <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> title game  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  -- Edmundo Macedo  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911217  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  283  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, December 17, 1991
00352222,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06011224 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06011224 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, chart; PHOTO: Associated Press; SEASON-WRECKER -- Anthony Carter, with
278 all-purpose yards, helped teach the 49ers a lesson they haven't forgotten.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-FRANCISCO; PROFESSIONAL; CLUB; GAME; HISTORY; CHART  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  In the spirit of The Catch and The Drive, it should be called The Loss.;   
Michael Carter's stomach turns when he thinks about it. Jerry Rice doesn't go
full-bore in postseason practices because of it. Ronnie Lott's off-day dreams
have been shaped by it. And even Randy Cross, two seasons after retirement, is
still disappointed with Coach Bill Walsh's strategy.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LOSS TURNED 49ERS' STOMACHS, HEADS
NEVER AGAIN, SAY VIKINGS' VICTIMS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Additional information attached to end of article  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     As a whole, the 49ers franchise has sworn never to underestimate an
opponent as the <ORGANIZATION>Niners</ORGANIZATION> did in their 36-24 loss to the <LOCATION>Minnesota Vikings</LOCATION> in the
divisional playoffs after the <DATE>1987</DATE> regular season. That's why they're taking
the <LOCATION>Washington Redskins</LOCATION>, their NFC divisional playoff opponent <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in
<LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION>, so seriously.;    "As far as a dark spot on our playoffs and
team greatness and all that stuff, we'll always remember that," said <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Niners</ORGANIZATION>' starting nose tackle then and now. "I was part of that, and when I
think about that game, it makes me sick. That was humiliating, embarrassing
and something I'll remember the rest of my life.";    There's one main reason
the <ORGANIZATION>Niners</ORGANIZATION> haven't forgotten the game, and it's not because the loss was
decisive or because it occurred early in the playoffs. After all, there was
the 49-3 divisional playoff loss to the <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION> in the same round in
the <DATE>1986</DATE> playoffs. It's an ice pick in the <ORGANIZATION>Niners</ORGANIZATION>' pride because . . . well,
let <PERSON>Lott</PERSON> explain:;    "That team, probably of all the teams, had the most
momentum going into any playoff situation that I've been a part of," <PERSON>Lott</PERSON>
said. ". . . I think everyone just has one of those  memories that you think
about, that you can't take any situation for granted, and that you have to be
mentally and  physically prepared for an all-out war. The days off, you have
to dream about it. You have to dream about making plays from this day on. A
lot of it is going to rely on skills, but a lot of playoff games are decided .
. . because you want it more than the other guy.";    To the <ORGANIZATION>Niners</ORGANIZATION>, that's
what hurts about the '87 loss. They had shown over the course of the season
that they were the league's best in virtually every aspect. They had posted a
league-best 13-2 record. They led the league in yards gained (5,987) and
fewest allowed (4,095). They scored the most points (459) and allowed the
fewest (253). They had the league's most proficient passer (<LOCATION>Joe Montana</LOCATION>, with
a 102.1 quarterback rating) and the league's top scorer (Rice with 123
points).;    "Everything seemed perfect," said center <PERSON>Jesse Sapolu</PERSON>, who in '87
became the starting left guard after Guy <PERSON>McIntyre</PERSON> suffered a foot injury in
the sixth game. "To get beat like that just shows you it doesn't mean one iota
what you do in the regular season.";    What they didn't have against
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Lott</PERSON> said, was the heart and desire that have been synonymous with
their subsequent 38-10 regular-season record, 6-0 playoff mark and two
consecutive Super Bowl titles.;    "I think the thing I remember most about
that game was that it seemed like everybody was moving in slow motion," <PERSON>Lott</PERSON>
said. "We didn't fight. We didn't fight like it was the last game of the year.
. . . In that situation, I don't think we even had that.";    And against a
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> team that had routed <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> 44-10 in the wild-card game, that's
exactly what they needed. Without it, the <ORGANIZATION>Vikings</ORGANIZATION>' <PERSON>Anthony Carter</PERSON> beat them
for 278 all-purpose yards and <PERSON>Wade Wilson</PERSON> completed 20 of 34 passes for 298
yards and two touchdowns.;    "I think we worked too hard and never completely
recovered during the extra week," former 49ers coach <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> said. "We thought
we needed to work on some things, but looking back, we should've eased up
rather than worked harder.";    The game still might have been salvaged had
<PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> made better halftime adjustments, <PERSON>Cross</PERSON> said.;    "That was one of the
few circumstances in which we were out-coached and out-prepared," <PERSON>Cross</PERSON> said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. "Things started to happen. They played our wide receivers
very physically and basically took our wide receivers out of the game. We
weren't going to different lengths to compensate for that.";    <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> could
not be reached <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> to respond to that comment, but Vikings
cornerback <PERSON>Carl Lee</PERSON> said he could tell the 49ers sensed early on that they
weren't prepared.;    "I think reality set in as the game went on that they
had not prepared," <PERSON>Lee</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday.</DATE>;    <PERSON>Rice</PERSON>, for one, has learned his
lesson.;    "Back then, I felt like a rookie," said <PERSON>Rice</PERSON>, who was in his third
<ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> season. "I didn't really know how to police myself. I would go out every
day and give it <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT>. But now I know how to police myself. If the
ball's not coming my way, I might come off the line of scrimmage hard for the
first 5 yards, and then I'm going to ease up and just try to save some of that
for the ballgame.";    If fatigue was the primary factor, <ORGANIZATION>Niners</ORGANIZATION> Coach <PERSON>George
Seifert</PERSON> has taken every precaution to make certain it isn't <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. One-day
vacations were handed out to practically anyone who wanted one last week. In
<PERSON>Rice</PERSON>'s case, he was given two days last week to spend in the sauna or on the
massage table.;    There is a difference, however, between relaxing physically
and relaxing mentally, which Lee believes the <ORGANIZATION>Niners</ORGANIZATION> might also have done in
the '87 playoffs.;    "They were like us and a lot of other teams, in that
when you're already being talked about as being in the Super Bowl, it's very
possible to be complacent. They knew they were the top team, and they knew no
one could beat them.";    That's what concerns Cross. This season's team, he
said, has talked -- or been asked -- about winning a third consecutive Super
Bowl since the end of last season.;    "You're looking at a team now that is
talking similar to the '87 team," <PERSON>Cross</PERSON> said. "They're talking about going to
the Super Bowl. That's usually something better left unsaid.";    There's also
the question of just how long The Loss can remain foremost in the 49ers'
minds.;    "They've never shown me in the last few years that they've
forgotten," <PERSON>Lee</PERSON> said. "But after you win so many games, it's possible to come
out flat."; <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> playoffs; at a glance; Second Round; SATURDAY; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> at
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <TIME>9:30 a.m.</TIME> CH3 CH4 CH8;    <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> at 49ers, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> CH5 CH10 CH46;
SUNDAY;    <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>New York Giants</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>9:30 a.m.</TIME> CH5 CH10 CH46;    <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>
at <ORGANIZATION>L.A. Raiders</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> CH3 CH4 CH8; Conference Finals; <LOCATION>SUNDAY</LOCATION>, <DATE>JAN. 20</DATE>;  <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION>
final, time TBA CH5 CH10 CH46;    AFC final, time TBA CH3 CH4 CH8; Super Bowl;
<LOCATION>SUNDAY</LOCATION>, <DATE>JAN. 27</DATE>; (At <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>); AFC champion vs. NFC champion, <TIME>3:18 p.m.</TIME>
CH7 CH11 CH13; (All times PST); BAD MEMORIES OF '87 PLAYOFFS; The 49ers' 36-24
loss to the <LOCATION>Minnesota Vikings</LOCATION> in the divisional playoff after the <DATE>1987</DATE> regular
season is still talked about by the players in funereal terms, reflecting how
deeply it affected them. Here are some of their comments.; (box) Nose tackle
<PERSON>Pete Kugler</PERSON>: "It was a dreary, rainy day, which was perfect for what happened.
It was just sickening. You just felt this emptiness inside."; (box) Former
center <PERSON>Randy Cross</PERSON>: "It was as bad as the guy who has played 10 years and has
the coach tap him on the shoulder at training camp and tell him he's gone.";
(box)  Tackle <PERSON>Steve Wallace</PERSON>: "The worst thing about it is, if we hadn't
screwed up, we would be talking about four-peat."; (box) Nose tackle <PERSON>Michael
Carter</PERSON>: "It makes me sick just to think about it."; -- <PERSON>Ric Bucher</PERSON>; 49ERS
REBOUND FROM TOUGH LOSS; In the three seasons since the 49ers' loss to the
<LOCATION>Minnesota Vikings</LOCATION> in the second round of the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> playoffs, they've had a
tremendous run of success. The impact of that loss might be seen by comparing
those three seasons with the <DATE>1985</DATE> through '87 seasons:; Category              
         1988-90   1985-87; Regular-season record          38-10   33-13-1;
Postseason record              6-0         0-3; 49ers-opponent playoff scoring
208-54  30-109;  -- <PERSON>Ric Bucher</PERSON>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RIC BUCHER, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910111  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,421  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, January 11, 1991
00011224,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121190-0050 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 320632 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 11, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 7; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1006 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PRO FOOTBALL; 
</P>
<P>
LOTT LEADS HIT PARADE, MAKING 200 POUNDS FEEL LIKE A TON 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BOB OATES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> lost to <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE>, the play that symbolized three 
combative hours in <LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION> was probably the hit of the year. 
</P>
<P>
It was the hit that <ORGANIZATION>Giant</ORGANIZATION> tight end <PERSON>Mark Bavaro</PERSON> absorbed from 49er free safety 
<PERSON>Ronnie Lott</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
It didn't save the game, a low-scoring affair that ended 7-3. The save came 
later -- when <PERSON>Lott</PERSON> made his other big play of a defensive night, a diving, 
one-handed deflection in the end zone. 
</P>
<P>
But it did raise a good question: How can this guy hit football players 
seemingly harder than anyone else does? 
</P>
<P>
He isn't the biggest 49er. Standing an even 6 feet, <PERSON>Lott</PERSON>, a former <ORGANIZATION>USC 
All-American</ORGANIZATION>, weighs an even 200 pounds. He is a lightweight next to the man he 
clobbered. 
</P>
<P>
A six-year <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> veteran from <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bavaro</PERSON> goes 6-4 and 245. 
</P>
<P>
Yet <PERSON>Lott</PERSON>, timing the hit perfectly, knocked him groggy. 
</P>
<P>
Lott's key is that he is a student of the mechanics of hitting. Muhammad Ali 
would be proud of him. So would any clean liver. 
</P>
<P>
Lott never goes for the knees. And unlike football's other heavy hitters, he 
doesn't attack shoulder-first. 
</P>
<P>
He is a body-to-body hitter. In a classic <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> moment, <ORGANIZATION>Giant</ORGANIZATION> quarterback <PERSON>Phil 
Simms</PERSON>, hurried by the 49er pass rush, had overthrown the target -- forcing 
<PERSON>Bavaro</PERSON> to stretch far out for the ball -- when <PERSON>Lott</PERSON> smashed him with the entire 
front of his body from the forehead down. 
</P>
<P>
It was an exotic piece of offensive defense. 
</P>
<P>
One unusual thing about pro football is that it seems to attract a good many 
casual fans. 
</P>
<P>
The TV crowd for any big <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> game obviously includes many thousands of passive, 
indifferent, or slightly interested fans -- those who doubt that football is a 
particularly great sport, though they will watch it, idly, on occasion. 
</P>
<P>
That is the only way to explain the audience-survey numbers. 
</P>
<P>
For the Giant-49er game <DATE>last week</DATE>, the <PERSON>Nielsen</PERSON> rating was 27. By comparison, 
the World Series last fall averaged 20.8. The <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> finals last <DATE>spring</DATE> averaged 
12.4. 
</P>
<P>
The strange truth is that the <PERSON>Neilsen</PERSON> rating for the Super Bowl's pregame show 
is larger than the numbers for championship games in other sports. 
</P>
<P>
In college basketball last <DATE>spring</DATE>, the title game hit 20. 
</P>
<P>
Leading into the Super Bowl <DATE>last winter</DATE>, the pregame show hit 21.6. 
</P>
<P>
The point is that many football spectators -- specifically, many of those who 
watched the 49ers and <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> last week -- are comparatively undiscerning fans. 
</P>
<P>
They are basketball fans or rock fans or, possibly, fast-car fans who, for a 
night, were drawn to an <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> event because it seemed to be the nation's biggest 
sports event since the Super Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
And that accounts for the dichotomy of the national reaction. 
</P>
<P>
Most football fans called it a good defensive game. 
</P>
<P>
Most casual fans called it boring. 
</P>
<P>
Casual fans criticized the 49er defensive team because it never sacked <PERSON>Simms</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Football fans realized that <PERSON>Lott</PERSON>'s big hit, for example, was set up by the 49er 
rush on <PERSON>Simms</PERSON>. They realized that for better or worse, football is offense and 
defense. 
</P>
<P>
In one of linebacker <PERSON>Lawrence Taylor</PERSON>'s big years, the Giant defense will get 
another chance against another brilliant offensive team <DATE>Saturday</DATE> when 
quarterback <PERSON>Jim Kelly</PERSON> arrives at the <LOCATION>Meadowlands</LOCATION> with the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills. 
</P>
<P>
Buffalo and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> are each 11-2, a tick behind the 49ers. And as the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s 
only 11-2 club, the Bills, in the opinion of many, are Super Bowl-bound. 
</P>
<P>
The Giants and other NFC clubs have won six consecutive Super Bowl games and 
eight of the last nine. Do the Bills really want to get there? 
</P>
<P>
Won't the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1990</DATE> champion become its seventh consecutive Super Bowl 
casualty? 
</P>
<P>
"It isn't the NFC that's been beating the AFC," <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> General Manager <PERSON>Bill 
Polian</PERSON> said. "As the regular-season results have told us for years, the 
conferences are about even. 
</P>
<P>
"What's important to understand is that the Super Bowl is a game of matchups. 
And it just happens that most of the teams that won <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> championships in the 
<DATE>1980s</DATE> didn't match up well with <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION> champions. 
</P>
<P>
"Secondly, the 49ers were a super Super Bowl team in the <DATE>'80s</DATE>. They've won four 
of the last nine. They'd have beaten anybody. The reason they win so often is 
that their big-play guys are more consistent than anyone else's." 
</P>
<P>
How would the Bills match up with the 49ers or Giants in Super Bowl XXV? 
</P>
<P>
"We have the defense and the quarterback," <PERSON>Polian</PERSON> said. "Defense gets you into 
the playoffs, and quarterbacking takes you the rest of the way." 
</P>
<P>
Of the <ORGANIZATION>AFC</ORGANIZATION> champions of recent years, only the <ORGANIZATION>Cincinnati Bengals</ORGANIZATION> have made a 
game of it against the <ORGANIZATION>NFC</ORGANIZATION>, losing Super Bowl XXIII to the 49ers in the last 
minute, <DATE>20-16</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
In a rematch <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the 49ers caught the Bengals again, <DATE>20-17</DATE>, in overtime. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> is the only AFC team that has matched up well with an (NFC 
champion) lately," the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> executive said. "As you saw again (<DATE>Sunday</DATE>), they 
have what it takes to battle <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> all the way -- a big offensive line, good 
play-action passing, an active defense and speed in the secondary. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> is an example of a team that could win AFC (titles) but didn't match up 
with NFC (champion). They're agile and well conditioned, but built to excel in 
<LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>'s rarefied air, and sometimes they've been too small." 
</P>
<P>
Will <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> beat the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>? 
</P>
<P>
"Our quarterback can do more things on his own than their quarterback," <PERSON>Polian</PERSON> 
said. "But everything depends on how we handle their power." 
</P>
<P>
Quote Department: 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> quarterback commenting on one aspect of the <PERSON>Browns</PERSON>' 
slump: "(Coach) <PERSON>Jim Shofner</PERSON> is the fifth play-caller I've had in six years." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Herb Adderley</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Green Bay</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame cornerback, on <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Famer Dick</ORGANIZATION> 
(Night Train) Lane, as quoted by <PERSON>Rick Korch</PERSON> in Pro Football Weekly: "Night 
Train was the best defensive back to ever play the game. I tried to pattern my 
game after him. I've never seen a defensive back hit the way he hit -- I mean, 
take them down, whether it be <PERSON>Jim Taylor</PERSON> or <PERSON>Jim Brown</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Chris Doleman</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> defensive lineman: "I don't like these bye weeks. I 
like getting right back in there and playing." 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890108-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-08-89 2012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PlayoffNewspage     01-08 0204</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Playoff Newspage,0210</SECOND>
<HEAD>San Francisco, Cincinnati Going to Super Bowl</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Cincinnati Bengals</ORGANIZATION> will meet the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 49ers in a
Super Bowl rematch for the <ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION> title in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>,
after winning decisive conference championships on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The Bengals, who lost the Super Bowl in <DATE>1982</DATE> to the 49ers,
defeated <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> 21-10 to win the <ORGANIZATION>American Football Conference</ORGANIZATION>. The
49ers beat the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> Bears 28-3 for the <ORGANIZATION>National Football
Conference</ORGANIZATION> title.
   In <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, playing in 30-mph winds and wind-chill factors of
almost 20 degrees below zero, quarterback <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON> and receiver
<PERSON>Jerry Rice</PERSON> combined for two touchdown passes and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> threw a
third to <PERSON>John Frank</PERSON> for the victory.
   It was the first road playoff victory for the 49ers since <DATE>1970</DATE>,
and it dispelled the notion that the Californians would be numbed in
the kind of weather that has been so good to the Bears in playoffs
past.
   In <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, with the Bengals' star rookie running back <PERSON>Ickey
Woods</PERSON> prancing into the end zone twice and running for 102 yards on
29 carries, the <LOCATION>Bengals</LOCATION> won their second AFC championship with the
victory over the Bills.
   The Super Bowl will be held on <DATE>Jan. 22</DATE> in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06350238 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06350238 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Chart; CHART: Kevin Boyd -- Mercury News; The Bay Area's Top 20  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPORT; CELEBRITY; AWARD; NAME; LIST; NEWSPAPER; SF-BAY-AREA; SERIES  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A look at the top 20 sports personalities in the Bay Area over the past 20
years, listing position and Bay Area affiliations:;   (box) NO. 1: Bill Walsh,
general manager and/or coach, Raiders, Stanford and 49ers: The 49ers lost 28
of 37 games before he arrived, three seasons later he had made them a Super
Bowl champion. He went on to guide the team to two other Super Bowl titles and
finished with a 102-63-1 record, including postseason games. Walsh, a Raiders
assistant in 1966, also led Stanford to two bowl appearances in two seasons, a
feat not matched at the school since he left after the 1978 season.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHY THEY'RE THE BEST  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Bay Area's Best of the Best  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     (box) NO. 2: <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON>, quarterback, 49ers: He was the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION>'s most
valuable player in <DATE>1989</DATE> and <DATE>1990</DATE>, the Sports Illustrated Sportsman of the year
in <DATE>1990</DATE>, a three-time Super Bowl MVP and the quarterback on all four of the
49ers Super Bowl champions.;   (box) NO. 3: <PERSON>Reggie Jackson</PERSON>, right fielder,
A's: He hit 563 home runs in a 21 season career, eight of which were spent
with the A's in Oakland.;   (box) NO. 4: <PERSON>O.J. SIMPSON</PERSON>, running back, <ORGANIZATION>City
College</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and 49ers: In <DATE>1973</DATE>, with the <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> Bills, he became
the first <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> player to rush for 2,000 yards in a season. He spent his last
season with the 49ers.;   (box) NO. 5: <PERSON>Rickey Henderson</PERSON>, A's left fielder: In
his second stint with the A's, he set the career record for stolen bases in a
career, breaking <PERSON>Lou Brock</PERSON>'s mark of 938 on <DATE>May 1</DATE> of this year.;   (box) NO.
6: <PERSON>Jim Plunkett</PERSON>, quarterback, Lick High, <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION>, 49ers and Raiders: To cap
his Heisman Trophy-winning season, he led <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> to an upset of unbeaten
<ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION> in the Rose Bowl in <DATE>January 1971</DATE>. He was named most valuable player
in the <DATE>1981</DATE> Super Bowl and was the quarterback on the <ORGANIZATION>Raiders Super Bowl</ORGANIZATION>
championship team during the <DATE>1983</DATE> season.;   (box) NO. 7: <PERSON>John Madden</PERSON>, coach,
Raiders: He was 103-32-7 over 10 seasons, guiding the <ORGANIZATION>Raiders</ORGANIZATION> to their first
Super Bowl title during the <DATE>1976</DATE> season.;   (box) NO. 8: <PERSON>Rick Barry</PERSON>, forward,
Warriors: An eight-time NBA All-Star, he led the Warriors to their only Bay
Area <ORGANIZATION>NBA</ORGANIZATION> title, averaging 30.6 points per game to finish second in the league
in scoring.;   (box) NO. 9: <PERSON>Bruce Jenner</PERSON>, track and field, former <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>
resident: He won the decathlon gold medal at the <DATE>1976</DATE> Summer Olympics in
Montreal.;   (box) NO. 10: <PERSON>Billie Jean King</PERSON>, tennis, former <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> resident:
She won 22 Wimbledon titles and was ranked No. 1 in singles on the women's
tour for five years.;   (box) NO. 11: <PERSON>Willie McCovey</PERSON>, first baseman, <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION>
and A's: He hit 521 home runs and holds the major league record for most grand
slams in a career at 18.;   (box) NO. 12: <PERSON>Mark Spitz</PERSON>, swimmer, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara
