<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06170043 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06170043 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3), map; Associated Press; PHOTO: ESCAPE -- Refugees from the city of
Angeles in the volcano region cross a river carrying what they can, above;
PHOTO: one fleeing resident carries a turkey on his shoulder, right.; PHOTO:
Associated Press; Janet Santiago cradles her baby Monday at a Manila refugee
center.; ...; MAP: Knight-Ridder News Service; Source: National Geographic,
World Almanac, news reports; Research by Wendy Govier; Mount Pinatubo's range
of destruction; Ash reach as far as Cambodia as eruptions of Mount Pinatubo
intensified over the weekend. The United States will evacuate 200,000 civilian
workers and dependents from Subic Bay Naval Station over the next few days.; 1
Subic Bay: Hail of inch-long pebbles damages 100 buildings; airfields closed;
2 U.S. Navy ships evacuate 5,900 Sunday and Monday; 3 Olongapo: One-third of
homes damaged; hospital roof collapses, eight killed; 4 Angeles: No
electricity; food, fuel shortages in city of 300,000; residents looting
stores; 5 Manila: Heavy ash fall closes airports; 6 Mount Taal: Second volcano
showing abnormal activity; 51 quakes since Sunday  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PHILIPPINES; VOLCANO; DISASTER; DEATH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  BEBY TOLENTINO said Monday that she had crossed herself and frantically
brought her hands together in prayer as the mudslide began to carry away the
neighborhood church.;    "People think that maybe God was trying to punish
us," said Tolentino, her hands and face coated with the talc-like volcanic ash
that has saturated the air since Mount Pinatubo began erupting last week. "I
hope it was not God."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THOUSANDS OF FILIPINOS LEFT DESTITUTE, BUT
ALIVE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Mercury News wire services contributed to this report.
See related stories page 2A of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Her neighborhood was leveled. The Tolentinos and 100 other poor families
along the <LOCATION>Albacan River</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, a once-bustling city of 280,000 people in
the shadow of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, lost their homes <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in mudslides and
floods brought on by the volcano's powerful eruption.;    One resident, an
elderly man, drowned in the torrent of thick volcanic ash and rainwater.;   
Because of impassable roads and downed telephone lines, it was still
impossible <DATE>Monday</DATE> to determine the extent of the damage.;    The death toll
from the eruptions of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, combined with a series of earthquakes
and torrential rains, increased to more than 200, according to Philippine
television. The <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> said at least 101 people had been
killed.;    The government estimated damage to property and crops at about
<MONEY>$200 million.</MONEY>;    Most of the deaths occurred when houses and other buildings
collapsed under the weight of as much as eight inches of ash and sand spewed
from the rumbling crater.;    Hundreds of people across the island of <LOCATION>Luzon</LOCATION>
were reported missing, while hundreds of thousands of others have been left
homeless.;    As many as 150,000 people fleeing the volcano were said to be
crowding into evacuation centers <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, the capital, about 50
miles south of the volcano.;    Volcano scientists continued to express a
careful optimism. <PERSON>Raymondo Punongbayan</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute
of Volcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology, said in an interview that while the volcano
remained a threat, the eruptions were "simmering down" and "significant,
critical eruptions are probably over.";    <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>'s domestic and international
airports were scheduled to reopen <DATE>today</DATE>, three days after they were closed
because of concern that ash from the volcano would damage jet engines.;   
Despite the optimism from scientists, however, the exodus of families fleeing
the volcano area continued late <DATE>Monday</DATE> as buses and trucks caked with gray ash
jammed roads leading into <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>. The government has set up more than 100
makeshift shelters in churches, schools, army camps and gymnasiums in the
capital.;    In the wake of the eruptions, Filipinos are facing monumental
tasks. Food and clean drinking water were running low in the central and
southwestern portions of the main <LOCATION>Luzon island</LOCATION>, which bore the brunt of the
volcano's week of fury.;    <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION> was without electricity <DATE>Monday</DATE> and so many
stores and gasoline stations were closed that it was difficult to find food
and fuel.;    Dozens of angry residents stormed a row of food shops in the
city's market, forced open the doors with crowbars and carted away canned
goods and other items, police and witnesses said.;    "We will die of hunger
if we don't do this," one of the looters said.;    Fifteen people were
arrested after more than 100 pigs were stolen from a farm near <LOCATION>Angeles.</LOCATION>;   
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> military officials said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that they were stepping up the
evacuation of 20,000 Americans, including the dependents of all employees at
the two huge U.S.-operated military bases, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Subic Bay.</LOCATION>;    <ORGANIZATION>Seven Navy</ORGANIZATION>
ships sailed <DATE>Monday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION>, 50 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, with 6,200
dependents.;    "It's about time we left," said <PERSON>Lisa Hedland</PERSON>, wife of an <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> sergeant, as she prepared to board the cruiser <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> with her
15-month-old daughter. "It's been horrible this past week.";    The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> said
a battle group led by the aircraft carrier <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON> was on the way to
<LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> to pick up 5,000 more Americans.;    For most Filipinos fleeing the
volcano, the journey to safety was less orderly and far more difficult.;   
"We have nothing except the clothes we are wearing," said <PERSON>Solidad Santiago</PERSON>, a
41-year-old laundry worker from <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, who fled to a <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> evacuation
center <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with most but not all of her family.;    "Our house collapsed
because of the volcano," said <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, a widow, whose face showed signs of
the wrenching fear of the past week. "My oldest son stayed behind to try to
guard our possessions.;    "He should be here by now," she said. "I have gone
on the public address system here and called his name, but there is never any
response. I am very concerned. I pray he is safe.";    <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> and her family
were among nearly 5,000 refugees who crowded <DATE>Monday</DATE> into the shaded bleachers
of a <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> sports stadium that is being used as an evacuation center.;    The
evacuees were provided with food -- mostly sausages, rice and crackers donated
by local businesses.;    "We have lost everything, but still I am happy, happy
to be here," said <PERSON>Romayo Garcia</PERSON>, a 29-year-old mason, whose house near the
now-evacuated <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, about 10 miles east of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, had
collapsed from the weight of volcanic ash.;    "The rocks were as big as
this," he said, bringing together his thumbs and index fingers to make a
circle five inches wide. "It was impossible to walk. People panicked. We had
to find a way to get out.";    <PERSON>Garcia</PERSON> said he and several members of his
family trudged nearly 20 miles through ankle-deep ash until they found a truck
driver willing to take them to <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PHILIP SHENON, New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Angeles, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910618  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,104  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday June 18, 1991
00170043,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06170206 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06170206 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3), map; Associated Press; PHOTO: ESCAPE -- Refugees from the city of
Angeles in the volcano region cross a river carrying what they can, above;
PHOTO: one fleeing resident carries a turkey on his shoulder, right.; PHOTO:
Associated Press; Janet Santiago cradles her baby Monday at a Manila refugee
center.; ...; MAP: Knight-Ridder News Service; Source: National Geographic,
World Almanac, news reports; Research by Wendy Govier; Mount Pinatubo's range
of destruction; Ash reach as far as Cambodia as eruptions of Mount Pinatubo
intensified over the weekend. The United States will evacuate 200,000 civilian
workers and dependents from Subic Bay Naval Station over the next few days.; 1
Subic Bay: Hail of inch-long pebbles damages 100 buildings; airfields closed;
2 U.S. Navy ships evacuate 5,900 Sunday and Monday; 3 Olongapo: One-third of
homes damaged; hospital roof collapses, eight killed; 4 Angeles: No
electricity; food, fuel shortages in city of 300,000; residents looting
stores; 5 Manila: Heavy ash fall closes airports; 6 Mount Taal: Second volcano
showing abnormal activity; 51 quakes since Sunday  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PHILIPPINES; VOLCANO; DISASTER; DEATH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  BEBY TOLENTINO said Monday that she had crossed herself and frantically
brought her hands together in prayer as the mudslide began to carry away the
neighborhood church.;    "People think that maybe God was trying to punish
us," said Tolentino, her hands and face coated with the talc-like volcanic ash
that has saturated the air since Mount Pinatubo began erupting last week. "I
hope it was not God."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THOUSANDS OF FILIPINOS LEFT DESTITUTE, BUT
ALIVE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Mercury News wire services contributed to this report.
See related stories page 2A of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Her neighborhood was leveled. The Tolentinos and 100 other poor families
along the <LOCATION>Albacan River</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, a once-bustling city of 280,000 people in
the shadow of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, lost their homes <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in mudslides and
floods brought on by the volcano's powerful eruption.;    One resident, an
elderly man, drowned in the torrent of thick volcanic ash and rainwater.;   
Because of impassable roads and downed telephone lines, it was still
impossible <DATE>Monday</DATE> to determine the extent of the damage.;    The death toll
from the eruptions of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, combined with a series of earthquakes
and torrential rains, increased to more than 200, according to Philippine
television. The <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> said at least 101 people had been
killed.;    The government estimated damage to property and crops at about
<MONEY>$200 million.</MONEY>;    Most of the deaths occurred when houses and other buildings
collapsed under the weight of as much as eight inches of ash and sand spewed
from the rumbling crater.;    Hundreds of people across the island of <LOCATION>Luzon</LOCATION>
were reported missing, while hundreds of thousands of others have been left
homeless.;    As many as 150,000 people fleeing the volcano were said to be
crowding into evacuation centers <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, the capital, about 50
miles south of the volcano.;    Volcano scientists continued to express a
careful optimism. <PERSON>Raymondo Punongbayan</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute
of Volcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology, said in an interview that while the volcano
remained a threat, the eruptions were "simmering down" and "significant,
critical eruptions are probably over.";    <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>'s domestic and international
airports were scheduled to reopen <DATE>today</DATE>, three days after they were closed
because of concern that ash from the volcano would damage jet engines.;   
Despite the optimism from scientists, however, the exodus of families fleeing
the volcano area continued late <DATE>Monday</DATE> as buses and trucks caked with gray ash
jammed roads leading into <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>. The government has set up more than 100
makeshift shelters in churches, schools, army camps and gymnasiums in the
capital.;    In the wake of the eruptions, Filipinos are facing monumental
tasks. Food and clean drinking water were running low in the central and
southwestern portions of the main <LOCATION>Luzon island</LOCATION>, which bore the brunt of the
volcano's week of fury.;    <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION> was without electricity <DATE>Monday</DATE> and so many
stores and gasoline stations were closed that it was difficult to find food
and fuel.;    Dozens of angry residents stormed a row of food shops in the
city's market, forced open the doors with crowbars and carted away canned
goods and other items, police and witnesses said.;    "We will die of hunger
if we don't do this," one of the looters said.;    Fifteen people were
arrested after more than 100 pigs were stolen from a farm near <LOCATION>Angeles.</LOCATION>;   
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> military officials said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that they were stepping up the
evacuation of 20,000 Americans, including the dependents of all employees at
the two huge U.S.-operated military bases, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Subic Bay.</LOCATION>;    <ORGANIZATION>Seven Navy</ORGANIZATION>
ships sailed <DATE>Monday</DATE> from <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION>, 50 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, with 6,200
dependents.;    "It's about time we left," said <PERSON>Lisa Hedland</PERSON>, wife of an <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> sergeant, as she prepared to board the cruiser <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> with her
15-month-old daughter. "It's been horrible this past week.";    The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> said
a battle group led by the aircraft carrier <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON> was on the way to
<LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> to pick up 5,000 more Americans.;    For most Filipinos fleeing the
volcano, the journey to safety was less orderly and far more difficult.;   
"We have nothing except the clothes we are wearing," said <PERSON>Solidad Santiago</PERSON>, a
41-year-old laundry worker from <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, who fled to a <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> evacuation
center <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with most but not all of her family.;    "Our house collapsed
because of the volcano," said <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, a widow, whose face showed signs of
the wrenching fear of the past week. "My oldest son stayed behind to try to
guard our possessions.;    "He should be here by now," she said. "I have gone
on the public address system here and called his name, but there is never any
response. I am very concerned. I pray he is safe.";    <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> and her family
were among nearly 5,000 refugees who crowded <DATE>Monday</DATE> into the shaded bleachers
of a <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> sports stadium that is being used as an evacuation center.;    The
evacuees were provided with food -- mostly sausages, rice and crackers donated
by local businesses.;    "We have lost everything, but still I am happy, happy
to be here," said <PERSON>Romayo Garcia</PERSON>, a 29-year-old mason, whose house near the
now-evacuated <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, about 10 miles east of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, had
collapsed from the weight of volcanic ash.;    "The rocks were as big as
this," he said, bringing together his thumbs and index fingers to make a
circle five inches wide. "It was impossible to walk. People panicked. We had
to find a way to get out.";    <PERSON>Garcia</PERSON> said he and several members of his
family trudged nearly 20 miles through ankle-deep ash until they found a truck
driver willing to take them to <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PHILIP SHENON, New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Angeles, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910618  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,104  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday June 18, 1991
00170206,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06170249 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06170249 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3), map; PHOTO: Associated Press; CRY FOR MAMA -- An infant cries
after being left alone at a refugee camp while her mother seeks food, above.
At right, one fleeing resident carries a turkey on his shoulder. (Photo ran in
PM edition only); Associated Press; PHOTO: one fleeing resident carries a
turkey on his shoulder, right.; PHOTO: Associated Press; Janet Santiago
cradles her baby Monday at a Manila refugee center.; ...; MAP: Knight-Ridder
News Service; Source: National Geographic, World Almanac, news reports;
Research by Wendy Govier; Mount Pinatubo's range of destruction; Ash reach as
far as Cambodia as eruptions of Mount Pinatubo intensified over the weekend.
The United States will evacuate 200,000 civilian workers and dependents from
Subic Bay Naval Station over the next few days.; 1 Subic Bay: Hail of
inch-long pebbles damages 100 buildings; airfields closed; 2 U.S. Navy ships
evacuate 5,900 Sunday and Monday; 3 Olongapo: One-third of homes damaged;
hospital roof collapses, eight killed; 4 Angeles: No electricity; food, fuel
shortages in city of 300,000; residents looting stores; 5 Manila: Heavy ash
fall closes airports; 6 Mount Taal: Second volcano showing abnormal activity;
51 quakes since Sunday  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PHILIPPINES; VOLCANO; DISASTER; DEATH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  BEBY TOLENTINO said Monday that she had crossed herself and frantically
brought her hands together in prayer as the mudslide began to carry away the
neighborhood church.;    "People think that maybe God was trying to punish
us," said Tolentino, her hands and face coated with the talc-like volcanic ash
that has saturated the air since Mount Pinatubo began erupting last week. "I
hope it was not God."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THOUSANDS OF FILIPINOS LEFT DESTITUTE, BUT
ALIVE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related article on page 2A of this section.
Mercury News wire services contributed to this report.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Her neighborhood was leveled. The Tolentinos and 100 other poor families
along the <LOCATION>Albacan River</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, a once-bustling city of 280,000 people in
the shadow of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, lost their homes <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in mudslides and
floods brought on by the volcano's powerful eruption.;    One resident, an
elderly man, drowned in the torrent of thick volcanic ash and rainwater.;   
Because of impassable roads and downed telephone lines, it was still
impossible <DATE>Monday</DATE> to determine the extent of the damage.;    The death toll
from the eruptions of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, combined with a series of earthquakes
and torrential rains, increased to more than 200, according to Philippine
television. The <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> said at least 101 people had been
killed.;    The government estimated damage to property and crops at about
<MONEY>$200 million.</MONEY>;    Most of the deaths occurred when houses and other buildings
collapsed under the weight of as much as eight inches of ash and sand spewed
from the rumbling crater.;    Hundreds of people across the island of <LOCATION>Luzon</LOCATION>
were reported missing, while hundreds of thousands of others have been left
homeless.;    As many as 150,000 people fleeing the volcano were said to be
crowding into evacuation centers <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, the capital, about 50
miles south of the volcano.;    Volcano scientists continued to express a
careful optimism. <PERSON>Raymondo Punongbayan</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute
of Volcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology, said in an interview that while the volcano
remained a threat, the eruptions were "simmering down" and "significant,
critical eruptions are probably over.";    <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>'s domestic and international
airports were scheduled to reopen <DATE>today</DATE>, three days after they were closed
because of concern that ash from the volcano would damage jet engines.;   
Despite the optimism from scientists, however, the exodus of families fleeing
the volcano area continued late <DATE>Monday</DATE> as buses and trucks caked with gray ash
jammed roads leading into <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>. The government has set up more than 100
makeshift shelters in churches, schools, army camps and gymnasiums in the
capital.;    In the wake of the eruptions, Filipinos are facing monumental
tasks. Food and clean drinking water were running low in the central and
southwestern portions of the main <LOCATION>Luzon island</LOCATION>, which bore the brunt of the
volcano's week of fury.;    <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION> was without electricity <DATE>Monday</DATE> and so many
stores and gasoline stations were closed that it was difficult to find food
and fuel.;    Dozens of angry residents stormed a row of food shops in the
city's market, forced open the doors with crowbars and carted away canned
goods and other items, police and witnesses said.;    "We will die of hunger
if we don't do this," one of the looters said.;    Fifteen people were
arrested after more than 100 pigs were stolen from a farm near Angeles.;
Another <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Navy</ORGANIZATION> flotilla steamed toward <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> today to help speed the
American exodus, and Filipinos complained that their government failed to
prepare them for the devastating fury of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo.</LOCATION>;    "We were really
caught flat-footed. They had not expected anything of this magnitude," said
Gov. <PERSON>Bren Guiao</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pampanga</LOCATION> province, where about 120,000 refugees were
seeking help.; "It's about time we left," said <PERSON>Lisa Hedland</PERSON>, wife of an <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> sergeant, as she prepared to board the cruiser <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> with her
15-month-old daughter. "It's been horrible this past week.";    For most
Filipinos fleeing the volcano, the journey to safety was less orderly and far
more difficult.;    "We have nothing except the clothes we are wearing," said
<PERSON>Solidad Santiago</PERSON>, a 41-year-old laundry worker from <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, who fled to a
<LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> evacuation center <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with most but not all of her family.;    "Our
house collapsed because of the volcano," said <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, a widow, whose face
showed signs of the wrenching fear of the past week. "My oldest son stayed
behind to try to guard our possessions.;    "He should be here by now," she
said. "I have gone on the public address system here and called his name, but
there is never any response. I am very concerned. I pray he is safe.";   
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> and her family were among nearly 5,000 refugees who crowded <DATE>Monday</DATE>
into the shaded bleachers of a <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> sports stadium that is being used as an
evacuation center.;    The evacuees were provided with food -- mostly
sausages, rice and crackers donated by local businesses.;    "We have lost
everything, but still I am happy, happy to be here," said <PERSON>Romayo Garcia</PERSON>, a
29-year-old mason, whose house near the now-evacuated <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, about 10
miles east of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, had collapsed from the weight of volcanic ash.; 
  "The rocks were as big as this," he said, bringing together his thumbs and
index fingers to make a circle five inches wide. "It was impossible to walk.
People panicked. We had to find a way to get out.";    <PERSON>Garcia</PERSON> said he and
several members of his family trudged nearly 20 miles through ankle-deep ash
until they found a truck driver willing to take them to <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PHILIP SHENON, New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Angeles, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910618  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,110  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday June 18, 1991
00170249,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06166274 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06166274 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; A young girl covers her face from volcano dust
at refugee camp today  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; PHILIPPINES; WEATHER; CHANGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mount Pinatubo shot a cloud of ash and steam nearly 19 miles high today in the
biggest eruption since it came to life this week. An approaching typhoon
threatened to trigger mudflows down the volcano.;    After sunset the volcano
erupted again, lighting up the night sky. Two streams of orange, glowing
material flowed from the crater.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NEW THREAT: TYPHOON
IT MAY TRIGGER MUDFLOWS AS PHILIPPINE VOLCANO
ERUPTS AGAIN  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Scientists initially thought it was the first flow of lava in a week of
eruptions. But <PERSON>Raymundo Punongbayan</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute of
Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology, said the glow was actually an "incandescent
pyroclastic flow," hot gases, stones and ash that travel at high speeds and
are an even greater threat than lava.;    As if the volcano were not enough,
the <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> weather bureau reported <DATE>today</DATE> that a typhoon was headed for the
eastern coast of <LOCATION>Luzon</LOCATION> island with maximum winds of 110 miles per hour.;   
Typhoon <PERSON>Yunya</PERSON> was expected to come ashore late <DATE>Saturday</DATE> or <DATE>Sunday</DATE> near <LOCATION>Baler</LOCATION>,
90 miles northeast of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>. Heavy rain began falling today in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>
and central Luzon.;    If the typhoon brings more rain, scientists fear it
will unleash mudflows -- giant rivers of earth, boulders and debris fused
together with sticky volcanic ash.;    <PERSON>Kelvin Rodolfo</PERSON>, a Filipino-American
geology professor from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Illinois-Chicago</ORGANIZATION>, said mudflows
represented one of the most serious dangers from <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION> because they
could bury towns and settlements quickly under tons of debris.;    At least
four people died; four were missing and 24 injured since <ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION> began
erupting <DATE>Sunday</DATE> after being dormant for 600 years, officials said. About
79,000 people, including 15,000 Americans, have been evacuated.;    The
thunderous explosions today spewed ash over a wide area, including the
evacuated <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION> 10 miles east of the volcano and <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> naval base
25 miles to the southwest, where the <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> personnel are being temporarily
housed.;    At <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, the remaining 1,500 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> service members guarding the
installation donned goggles and surgical masks.;    The mayor of <LOCATION>Olongapo</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Richard Gordon</PERSON>, urged residents to stay indoors because ash was falling like a
hailstorm and had accumulated up to three inches deep. Subic Bay naval base is
located next to Olongapo.;    The volcano's fallout made the town look "like
nighttime" in midafternoon, correspondent <PERSON>Louella Vizcocho</PERSON> said by telephone.;
   <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION> had been calm more than 24 hours after a major eruption
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> that shot ash more than 15 miles high, but scientists had
said pressure was intensifying within the 4,795-foot volcano.;    Then at
least four blasts within 2 1/2 hours of each other occurred today, sending ash
nearly 19 miles high.;    The <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute of Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and
<PERSON>Seismology</PERSON> said the fourth blast was the largest of 10 eruptions since
Sunday.;    During the evening eruption, seismologist <PERSON>Julio Sabit</PERSON> said the sky
darkened and then dramatically lit up.;    "The fireworks of Pinatubo began,"
the excited <PERSON>Sabit</PERSON> said by radio.;    Radio reporters at the scene said the
spectacle cast a gentle, orange glow over the summit of the volcano. "It's
very beautiful," reporter <PERSON>Vic Lima</PERSON> said. "There's a stream of orange flow on
the two sides of the volcano.";    About 64,000 people have been evacuated,
most of them since major eruptions began on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Food was reported
running low at refugee camps.;    Police said 12 people have been arrested for
allegedly looting parts of <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, which nearly 15,000 Americans and
their families evacuated <DATE>last Monday.</DATE>;    Many of the Americans expressed
concern for the safety of their belongings, but <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> officials assured
them that the 1,500 security guards would be sufficient to protect homes and
barracks.;    <ORGANIZATION>The Office of Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> said that at least four people have
been killed in eruptions this week. Unofficial reports by local officials and
survivors put the death toll at 10.;    Rescue agencies said they were still
trying to confirm the unofficial reports and some or all of these may be added
to official counts later.;    At least 24 people were injured and four were
missing, the civil defense agency said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Street  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910614  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  682  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday June 14, 1991
00166274,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06167046 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06167046 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PHILIPPINES; VOLCANO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mount Pinatubo rumbled today with explosions that hurled ash and gas more than
12 miles high, and a typhoon brought heavy rain that could unleash tons of
debris from the jagged slopes.;    Seven explosions were recorded from the
4,800-foot tropical volcano today, and scientists said more were expected.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NEW EXPLOSIONS ROCK PHILIPPINES' MOUNT PINATUBO  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Los Angeles Times contributed to this report.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Typhoon Yunya, packing 80 mph winds, slammed into the eastern coast of
<LOCATION>Luzon island</LOCATION>, which includes Mount Pinatubo, early in the day. But it quickly
weakened to a tropical storm with 60 mph winds by the time it was centered
about 70 miles east of the volcano.;    Still, heavy rains churned up by the
typhoon drenched <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> and the provinces near the volcano, raising fears of
mudflows that could bury whole towns up to 25 miles away.;    Meanwhile,
President <PERSON>Corazon Aquino</PERSON> dismissed a British newspaper report that Americans
had warned her of possible radioactive contamination if the volcano damages
nuclear storage sites at <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, abandoned <DATE>Monday</DATE> by nearly 15,000
Americans.;    The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military began flying home hundreds of the 28,000
Americans who crowded onto <LOCATION>Subic Bay Naval Base</LOCATION> as a bizarre tropical blizzard
of thick volcanic ash caused power failures across the base <DATE>Friday</DATE> during a
third day of increasingly violent eruptions of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo.</LOCATION>;    Showers of
'mud drops';  "It looks like it's snowing outside," said military spokeswoman
Capt. <PERSON>Kim Urie</PERSON>. Headlights and street lamps were turned on at midafternoon as
a "dark, black cloud" passed over the giant <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> base and dropped a gritty
rain of "mud drops," she said.;    At least four people have died, 24 have
been hurt and four have been listed as missing since <ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION> began erupting
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>, after lying dormant for six centuries, officials said. About 84,000
people, including Americans, have been evacuated.;    Police said 12 people
had been arrested for looting at Clark.;    Five explosions shook the mountain
<DATE>early today</DATE>, showering ash over a wide area and providing a spectacular
pre-dawn display of nature's fireworks against a backdrop of lightning and
rain.;    <DATE>Friday</DATE>, eight thunderous explosions shot a cloud of ash and steam
nearly 19 miles high.;    <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s eruptions hurled ash over <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, 10 miles
east of the volcano, and <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>, 25 miles southwest, where the <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> personnel
had been temporarily housed. Gray ash also fell in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, 60 miles south.;   
At <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>, base spokesman <PERSON>Robert Coble</PERSON> said generators had to be shut down from
time to time to clean out volcanic ash, plunging the base into darkness.;   
River temperatures rising;  Temperatures in local rivers were rising because
of the volcanic debris, officials said.;    After sunset, the volcano spewed
two streams of orange, glowing material from its crater in what scientists
thought was the first appearance of lava during the weeklong eruptions.;   
<PERSON>Raymundo Punongbayan</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute of Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and
Seismology, said <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s blasts were part of a single eruption, the largest
since <ORGANIZATION>Mount Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION> awoke <DATE>Sunday</DATE> from its 600-year slumber.;    A British
newspaper, the Guardian, reported <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that the Americans declared a
nuclear alert at <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> late <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and informed governments in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> that "a nuclear accident in the region was possible." But <PERSON>Aquino</PERSON>
told reporters the story was "baseless and purely fabricated.";    The <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> refuses to confirm or deny that it stores nuclear weapons in the
<LOCATION>Philippines.</LOCATION>;    Foreign Secretary <PERSON>Raul Manglapus</PERSON> also said the eruption
should have no effect on talks on the future of <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>, where leases
expire <DATE>Sept. 16</DATE>. The talks are deadlocked over compensation and the duration
of a new agreement.;    <PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION> could remain active
for years if it follows the pattern of similar Philippine volcanoes. That
would leave <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> unusable.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  MANILA, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910615  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  615  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday June 15, 1991
00167046,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06173235 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06173235 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; Children push a vegetable cart Thursday
through ash-clogged streets of Olongapo, Philippines.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; CLOSING; MILITARY; FACILITY; PHILIPPINES; VOLCANO; DISASTER  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Thousands of U.S. Air Force personnel were given orders to leave today and the
last group of military dependents began the journey home as an expert
predicted possible new eruptions on Mount Pinatubo.;    Fears of new eruptions
and landslides again drove Filipinos from their homes today.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LAST U.S. DEPENDENTS LEAVING PHILIPPINES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     About 3,000 Americans sailed from <LOCATION>Subic Bay Naval Base</LOCATION> aboard the aircraft
carrier <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON> bound for <ORGANIZATION>Cebu</ORGANIZATION>, where they will catch flights to the
<LOCATION>United States.</LOCATION>;    "I can't wait to get out of here," <PERSON>Tess Machinsky</PERSON>, 44, of
<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, said as she prepared to board the <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>. "This place is a
mess.";    The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> said all 20,000 military family members have now
left <ORGANIZATION>Subic</ORGANIZATION>. The naval base's population swelled by nearly 15,000 when the <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> evacuated troops and dependents from <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>June 10</DATE> after the
nearby volcano began erupting for the first time in more than 600 years.;   
An <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> spokesman, Maj. <PERSON>Wayne Crist</PERSON>, also announced that 4,500 air
personnel would begin loading later today aboard the carrier Midway in a move
that would reduce <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> troops by more than 60 percent.;    At <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, 10
miles east of the volcano, people who toured the base <DATE>today</DATE> said flows of hot
rocks, gas and other volcanic debris had reached within 300 feet of <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s
<LOCATION>Mactan</LOCATION> housing area. The flow was still smoking today.;    <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION> was
quiet after seven small ash eruptions <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, but a government expert said
tremors suggest eruptions could occur.;    "We are recognizing some long
tremor periods and earthquakes, and this means that some magma is again moving
to the surface," said <PERSON>Raymundo Punongbayan</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine
Institute of Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology.;    He said it was impossible to
predict when new eruptions could begin.;    Many Filipinos who had returned to
their homes after the volcano quieted down began leaving again today, worried
by the eruption prediction and fearing heavy rains may unleash tons of debris
from the volcano's slopes.;    Two weeks of eruptions on the 4,795-foot
volcano, about 60 miles north of <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, has claimed at least 268 lives.;   
<ORGANIZATION>Rivers</ORGANIZATION> in central <LOCATION>Luzon</LOCATION> were reported rising today as volcanic ash washed into
the streams after two days of steady rains. In Capas, near the volcano, police
said three refugee children were swept away by floodwaters <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and feared
dead.;    <PERSON>Roy David</PERSON>, mayor of <LOCATION>Porac</LOCATION> west of <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, said he had urged
residents who fled to evacuation centers not to return home because of the
rising <LOCATION>Porac River</LOCATION>. He estimates about <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the town's 68,000
residents have fled since <DATE>June 9</DATE> when eruptions began.;    "Mudflows have
already cascaded down the slopes of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>, and the silt in the <LOCATION>Porac
River</LOCATION> is steadily rising," he said.;    <PERSON>Jose Pangilinan</PERSON>, a resident of <LOCATION>Angeles
City</LOCATION> adjacent to <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, said he was returning his wife and two children to his
relatives' home in nearby Apalit town.;    "I can't take chances; it could be
real bad," <PERSON>Pangilinan</PERSON> said. He said he returned to his home in <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION> <DATE>last
Wednesday</DATE> to inspect damage from a huge mudflow that roared through city
streets before dawn last Sunday.;    <PERSON>Richard Gordon</PERSON>, major of <LOCATION>Olongapo</LOCATION>, said a
landslide along a major highway leading to the city near <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION> was preventing
supplies from reaching the more than 300,000 residents.;    "If we cannot pass
through that landslide, we cannot supply goods to Olongapo (and other towns),"
<PERSON>Gordon</PERSON> said.;    About 1,500 air personnel will remain to guard <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, and
1,000 others will stay at the <LOCATION>Subic Bay Naval Base</LOCATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman Lt.
Cmdr. <PERSON>Kevin Mukri</PERSON>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910621  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  17A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  611  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday June 21, 1991
00173235,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06162192 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06162192 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, map; PHOTO: Associated Press; GETTING OUT -- Aeta aborigines in Sapang
Bato, Philippines, load their dog on a truck as they evacuate Sunday near
Clark Air Base following the eruption of Mount Pinatubo.; MAP: Associated
Press; Subic Bay Naval Base  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; MILITARY; FACILITY; SAFETY; PHILIPPINES; VOLCANO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  About 15,000 U.S. service members, dependents and civilians were ordered early
today to evacuate Clark Air Base, one of the largest U.S. bases overseas,
after a Philippine volcano dormant for six centuries began exploding with
searing gases, thick ash and deadly debris.;    Lt. Col. Ron Rand, a spokesman
at Clark, announced at 5 a.m. that all non-essential personnel should begin
evacuating the sprawling base as dawn skies over central Luzon were filled
with gray ash and steam from eruptions of Mount Pinatubo, about 10 miles away
in central Luzon.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  U.S. AIR BASE CLEARING OUT AS VOLCANO ERUPTS
IN PHILIPPINES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Rand said that Americans who live on or near the base would drive or be
bused to the U.S-operated <ORGANIZATION>Subic Bay Naval Base</ORGANIZATION>, about an hour's drive to the
southwest. The evacuation was to take four hours, he said.;    There was no
indication how long the Americans would stay, but they were ordered to take
along important papers and three days worth of food, water and clothing.;   
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> officials earlier had ordered the evacuation of more than 11,000
people from about 20 villages near the volcano, about 60 miles northwest of
<LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, after a series of small eruptions began <DATE>Friday</DATE>. No injuries were
reported over the weekend.;    <PERSON>Raymundo Punongbayan</PERSON>, director of the
moderate eruptions shortly before <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> appeared to signal a larger
explosion.;    "We're expecting a major eruption," he said in a telephone
interview early today. "We're just at the beginning stage of eruptions. We're
expecting many, many more.";    <PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON> said that the 4,795-foot-high
volcano was spewing gases up to 1,800 degrees, thick black ash, boulders and
rock fragments in two fast-moving streams from two vents on the western side
of the lower summit.;    "It's very dangerous," he said. "Anything along its
path will be destroyed.";    Clouds and ashes;  <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s eruptions sent a
dense cloud of steam and ash billowing thousands of feet above rice paddies
that are lush green from an impending harvest. Heavy black clouds shrouded the
mountain, and a blanket of gray ash covered nearby fields. Debris reportedly
was sprayed as far as the <LOCATION>South China Sea</LOCATION>, 20 miles to the west.;    Villagers
from a 12-mile radius of the mountain fled the area on foot and water buffalo,
and aboard crowded trucks and jitneys. The <ORGANIZATION>Philippines Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> said 11,024
people, including local Aeta aborigines, were evacuated to 18 disaster relief
centers set up at area schools, but officials said that many villagers stayed
behind to protect their animals and farms from looters.;    <PERSON>Rand</PERSON> said the
evacuation of <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> was ordered "due to a slight increase of volcanic
activity" overnight. All <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION> planes had moved from the base to <ORGANIZATION>Cubi
Point Naval Air Station</ORGANIZATION> near <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, and infants in the base's
neo-natal hospital and other patients had been flown out.;    Evacuation
rehearsal;  All military personnel at <LOCATION>Clark</LOCATION>, home of the <ORGANIZATION>13th Air Force</ORGANIZATION>, were
recalled to the base <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials ordered local
Americans to pack bags and rehearse evacuation procedures.;    "People are
pretty calm," said one American woman who lives on the base. "People are
prepared.";    <ORGANIZATION>Rand</ORGANIZATION> said that a minimal number of troops would remain at <ORGANIZATION>Clark</ORGANIZATION>
to guard the facility and maintain essential services. Marines from <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION> as
well as <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military police were deployed along the road to
provide security.;    The volcano began showing signs of activity in <DATE>April</DATE> for
the first time in 600 years, and last week it began belching small amounts of
steam and smoke. Seismologists reported a marked increase in volcanic tremors
last week, with intense seismic quakes on the mountain Friday.;     Last
eruption;  Mount Pinatubo last erupted in <DATE>1380</DATE>, 141 years before <PERSON>Ferdinand
Magellan</PERSON>, a Portuguese explorer flying the flag of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, first reached the
islands in search of spices.;    There are about 21 active and 200 dormant
volcanoes in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, which sits on the "Ring of Fire" that circles
the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>. Scientists said there was no connection, however, to the
eruption last <DATE>Monday</DATE> of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Mount Unzen</LOCATION>, which killed at least 37 people
on <LOCATION>Kyushu Island</LOCATION>. A fresh flow of lava, gas and debris erupted there <DATE>Saturday</DATE>,
setting 73 homes on fire.;    Nearly 10,000 people have left their homes at
the foot of <LOCATION>Mount Unzen</LOCATION>, and two naval ships stood by to take residents
farther away in case a new eruption sent lava, hot rocks and ash over a yet
wider area.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910610  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  783  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday June 10, 1991
00162192,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06162032 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06162032 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, map; PHOTO: Associated Press; Carloads of American service members and
their families roll out of Clark Air Base in the Philippines today (Color)
(Ran only in the Street edition); MAP: Associated Press. Mount Pinatubo.
(Color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; PHILIPPINES  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Thousands of Americans piled into cars and buses with dogs, cats and duffel
bags and left Clark Air Base today after scientists warned that the eruption
of a nearby volcano could turn catastrophic.;    The decision to evacuate one
of the largest overseas U.S. military bases was made early today after searing
gases, ash and rock shot out of 4,795-foot Mount Pinatubo on Sunday at speeds
of up to 60 mph.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ANOTHER VOLCANO ERUPTS
AMERICANS FLEE BASE IN PHILIPPINES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The volcano, about 10 miles west of the air base, came to life last week
after six centuries of dormancy. No casualties have been reported, but experts
are concerned that a major eruption could occur soon.;    Gases, ash and
molten rock continued to pour out of the mountain today, enshrouding it in
thick, gray clouds of ash and steam that rose 12,000 feet.;    The <ORGANIZATION>Philippine
Institute of Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Seismology</PERSON> said it detected rhythmic ground
movements today that indicated molten material was rising to the surface of
the craters.;    Institute Director <PERSON>Raymundo Punongbayan</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Mount Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION>
was in the "early eruptive stage" and "after that we will have bigger ones."; 
  He said most of the ash and molten rocks had been flowing westward away from
<PERSON>Clark</PERSON>. But he said geological studies showed that in the previous eruption 600
years ago, the main flow cut across what is now the western portion of Clark.;
   <ORGANIZATION>Rains</ORGANIZATION> fell across the area <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, and officials warned residents in
the lush, green lowlands west of the mountain to move to higher ground to
escape mud flows.;    <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> spokesman Lt. Col. <PERSON>Ron Rand</PERSON> announced the
evacuation in a <TIME>5 a.m.</TIME> broadcast over the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military's <LOCATION>Far East Network</LOCATION>. An
hour later, the first vehicles began rolling out of <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> for the <LOCATION>U.S.-run
Subic Bay</LOCATION> naval base, where the 14,500 troops, dependents and civilian
employees will be housed until the danger passes. Another 1,500 troops
remained at <LOCATION>Clark</LOCATION> to provide security.;    The <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> command center operated
with a skeletal crew, but the base's operations were suspended. The base is a
major terminal for the worldwide network of flights operated by the <ORGANIZATION>Military
Airlift Command.</ORGANIZATION>;    The miles-long convoy jammed the two-lane roads leading
to <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>, about 50 miles southwest of <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>. <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Marines</ORGANIZATION> patrolled the
highways, which pass through areas where Communist guerrillas operate, and
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> helicopters hovered overhead.;    By <TIME>late afternoon</TIME>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said
all the evacuees had reached Subic.;    "If it's going to blow, I hope it does
it fast so I can go home before the cockroaches take my house," said Staff
Sgt. <PERSON>Mike Huffman.</PERSON>;    <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION> is in <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, a city of more than
300,000 people about 50 miles north of <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>. In <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, residents reported
no ash fell <DATE>today</DATE> but said the air smelled of sulfur.;    In southern <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>
today, <ORGANIZATION>Mount Unzen</ORGANIZATION> continued to shake and spew hot ash and rocks, and heavy
rain was falling on the tons of ash and rock it disgorged over the past week,
raising fears of deadly mudslides.;    Areas around the 4,452-foot volcano
covered by evacuation warnings were expanded to protect people against
possible slides of volcanic debris that could be triggered by the rain, police
said.;    An explosion of superheated gas, ashes and rocks from the mountain
one week ago claimed 38 lives, and a larger flow over the weekend razed dozens
more homes. In all, about 9,800 people have been evacuated from communities at
the foot of the mountain, said police in <LOCATION>Nagasaki</LOCATION>, 30 miles away.;    <LOCATION>Mount
Unzen</LOCATION> and Mount Pinatubo belong to the "Ring of Fire" that circles the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>
where shifting plates of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s crust push against each other, triggering
periodic volcanic eruptions and earthquakes.;    In the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, officials
have evacuated more than 12,000 people in three provinces since <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>
began erupting last week. About 3,100 of them are primitive Aeta tribes people
who lived on <ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION>'s slopes.;    Many of them walked or traveled by ox cart
to flee the volcano. But reporters found that some evacuees are returning to
their homes each morning to tend to livestock and crops and heading back to
evacuation centers at sundown.;    <PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON> said he flew to the area and
warned people there would be no time to escape once a major eruption begins.; 
  There was no indication how long the Americans evacuated from <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> would
stay at <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>, but they were ordered to take along important papers and food,
water and clothing for three days.;    <ORGANIZATION>Subic</ORGANIZATION> base spokesman <PERSON>Bob Coble</PERSON> said
families at the naval installation had been asked to take in evacuees and that
others would double up in bachelor officer and enlisted quarters.;    <LOCATION>Mount
Pinatubo</LOCATION>, which last had a major eruption in <DATE>1380</DATE>, began to show signs of
activity in <DATE>April</DATE>. Last week, it belched small amounts of steam and ash.;   
There are about 21 active and 200 dormant volcanoes in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. The
last major eruption occurred in <DATE>1965</DATE>, when the Taal volcano, about 50 miles
south of <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, exploded. About 200 people were killed.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910610  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  868  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday June 10, 1991
00162032,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06164210 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06164210 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, diagram; PHOTO: Associated Press; U.S. troops on guard at Clark Air
Base as huge plume rises from Mount Pinatubo eruption. (Color); DIAGRAM: Jeff
Fulaski--Knight0Ridder News Service. How volcanoes are formed.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; PHILIPPINES  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mount Pinatubo erupted with six thundering explosions today, shooting a giant
plume of ash 15 miles high. Molten rock and hot gas poured from the volcano,
and nearby residents fled in panic.;    A Filipino serving with the U.S. Navy
became the first reported fatality related to the eruption when his car
collided with a bus on an ash-slicked road north of the Subic Bay naval base.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THERE WAS PANIC EVERYWHERE
VOLCANO ON A RAMPAGE
ASH FILLS THE SKY; LAVA, GAS GUSH  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Residents of nearby Angeles panicked when a huge, gray-greenish mushroom
cloud burst from the volcano and turned day to night. Thousands of fleeing
people packed roads.;    "Stones as big as my head were falling down from the
mountains," said <PERSON>Rolly Soria</PERSON>, 18.;    "There was panic everywhere," said
<PERSON>Manuel Romualdo</PERSON>. "Children were crying. We had to grab whatever we could.";   
Scientists warned of more, possibly larger eruptions from the 4,795-foot
volcano, which was dormant for six centuries until it began spewing steam in
April.;    "This could be only the beginning," said <PERSON>Raymundo Punongbayan</PERSON>,
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute of Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology.;   
<LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, a city of 300,000, is adjacent to <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, but authorities had
not ordered a general evacuation there.;    Hundreds of Americans fled <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>,
home to 15,000 American military personnel and their families. Most of the
base's residents had been evacuated <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The base did not appear
immediately threatened by volcanic flow.;    Seismologists said searing gas,
ash and molten rock raced at great speed down the mountain's western and
northern slopes. They said most of the debris flowed into the <PERSON>Marella</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Maraunot</PERSON> and <PERSON>O'Donnell</PERSON> rivers and that there had been no reports that property
or homes had been damaged.;    About 3,000 Aeta tribesman, descendants of the
original inhabitants of the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, fled the slopes of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo.</LOCATION>;  
 At a refugee center in <LOCATION>Olongapo</LOCATION>, 35 miles southwest of the volcano, survivors
told of the sky growing dark, then of hearing a tremendous explosion followed
by a rain of ash.;    They said they scampered for safety with their
belongings and livestock over roads slippery with ashfall, many wearing
cardboard boxes to protect themselves from the ash.;    "They were stunned by
the eruption," television reporter <PERSON>Bert Basa</PERSON> said. "Their faces turned ashen,
and it looked like their hair was standing on end.";    Ash was so thick in
the air that at noon, motorists were driving with their headlights and
windshield wipers on.;    A photographer who circled the volcano in an
airplane said an aerial gunnery range at <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> was covered with ash, as were
mountains in the <LOCATION>Zambales</LOCATION> range, normally lush, green tropical peaks.;   
Today's first eruption began at <TIME>8:40 a.m.</TIME> with a tremendous blast that sent
forth a mushroom cloud. It was followed by a second explosion a few minutes
later and a third, smaller blast at <TIME>11:49 a.m.</TIME>;    The huge plume could be
seen in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, 60 miles to the south, and reporters at the scene said it
blocked out the sun. The cloud drifted westward into the <LOCATION>South China Sea.</LOCATION>;   
Two more thundering explosions rocked Mount Pinatubo late today.;    The
<ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute of Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Seismology</PERSON> said the explosions
occurred at <TIME>10:52 p.m. and 11:05 p.m</TIME>. The second explosion sent a plume of ash
and steam 80,000 feet into the sky.;    Shortly after <TIME>midnight</TIME>, a sixth
explosion was reported.;    Seismologists said the volcano had plenty of
built-up magma and even more severe eruptions could come later.;    "The
crisis has not ended yet," said <PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute of
Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology. "We have signs that the volcano is preparing for
another one.";    <PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON> warned people within a 15-mile radius of
Pinatubo to flee.;    "The smoke is very thick like a dark mushroom in the
sky," television reporter <PERSON>Gus Abelgas</PERSON> said in a broadcast from <LOCATION>Botolan</LOCATION>, near
the volcano's western slopes. He said strong tremors preceded the nighttime
eruptions and continued afterward.;    President <PERSON>Corazon Aquino</PERSON> visited
refugee centers near <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION> briefly before returning to <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> for
independence day celebrations.;    The Americans who fled <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> with a few
belongings <DATE>Monday</DATE> moved in with sailors and their families at <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> naval
base, 50 miles to the southwest.;    <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> is one of the biggest <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> bases
overseas. <PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that the site was in the path of the
volcanic flow from <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION> during its last major eruption, in 1380.;   
About 19,000 Filipinos earlier had been evacuated from three provinces near
the volcano's slopes and were housed in 25 makeshift evacuation centers
outside the projected danger zone.;    Officials said more were evacuated
after today's eruption.;    About 10 people in <LOCATION>Moraza</LOCATION>, a village on the
western slope of the mountain, were refusing to leave, relief officials said.
They told rescuers that they would not leave their livestock and if the
animals die, "we will die with them.";    On <DATE>April 2</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION> produced a
small hydrothermal explosion caused by underground water meeting hot rocks
deep inside. On <DATE>June 3</DATE>, the volcano spewed ash in a mild eruption.;    That
same day, 4,452-foot Mount Unzen in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> erupted with an explosion of
superheated gas, ashes and rocks that killed 38 people.;    Experts say there
is apparently no connection between <LOCATION>Unzen</LOCATION> and Pinatubo.;    There are about 21
active and 200 dormant volcanoes in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. The last major eruption
was the Taal volcano, about 50 miles south of <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1965</DATE>. That explosion
killed about 200 people.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910612  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DIAGRAM; PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  917  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday June 12, 1991
00164210,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06169132 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06169132 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; CAVE-INS -- Volcanic ash covers the roofs of a
dining room, foreground, and ballroom of a hotel in Subic, Philippines, on
Sunday after tons of ash caused them to collapse earlier.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; MILITARY; FACILITY; PHILIPPINES; VOLCANO; SAFETY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  U.S. officials Sunday launched an emergency evacuation to the United States of
about 20,000 military dependents and civilian workers from two strategic bases
after a deadly 36-hour string of eruptions at Mount Pinatubo.;    At least 76
people have been killed since the volcano began erupting June 9 for the first
time in 600 years, the Red Cross said.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  U.S. EXPANDS PHILIPPINE EVACUATION
20,000 CIVILIANS SLATED TO LEAVE; THREAT
OF VOLCANIC BLAST DIMINISHES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Mercury News wire services contributed to this report.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The first 900 of the evacuees boarded <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> warships <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Subic Bay
Naval Station</LOCATION> and departed for <ORGANIZATION>Cebu</ORGANIZATION>, a southern Philippine city about 350
miles from <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, where they were scheduled to board planes for the <ORGANIZATION>United
States.</ORGANIZATION>;    Even as the evacuation order was issued, Philippine volcano
scientists said that the worst of <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>'s eruptions may be over,
despite a prediction <DATE>Saturday</DATE> that the volcano was on the verge of a major
explosion.;    The scientists said that much of the pressure built up in the
volcano had dissipated this <DATE>weekend</DATE> in the emission of vast clouds of ash and
rock that turned day to night across the island of <LOCATION>Luzon</LOCATION>, and in a series of
earthquakes, including one that rocked skyscrapers in downtown <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> on
Sunday.;    The ash combined with rain from a tropical storm <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and left
a slippery glaze on buildings and roads as far away as <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, about 50 miles
south of the volcano.;    Panicked residents of villages close to the volcano
trudged on foot through knee-deep ash <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to escape the rumbling volcano.
Mudslides washed out bridges, clogged highways and caused hundreds of homes to
collapse.;    The international and domestic airports in the capital remained
closed <DATE>Sunday</DATE> out of concern that the ash would damage jet engines.;    Last
week, the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> announced that about 7,000 dependents of military and
civilian workers at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-run Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION> would be evacuated from the
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, one of the largest American military
bases outside the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, is 10 miles east of the volcano and has been
shut down since last Monday.;    <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s expanded evacuation order includes
all civilian workers at <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and at <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION>, as well as all dependents from
both installations.;    "The only ones left will be uniformed <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> or Marine personnel," said Lt. Cmdr. <PERSON>Kevin Mukri</PERSON>, a spokesman at <ORGANIZATION>Subic</ORGANIZATION>.
"You'll have to be in uniform to stay.";    Workers to remain at <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>;   
Military officials said that about 12,000 uniformed military workers were
stationed at the bases before the volcano erupted, and that most would remain
behind at <ORGANIZATION>Subic</ORGANIZATION> while their families and the civilian employees left the
<LOCATION>Philippines.</LOCATION>;    Virtually all of the 16,000 base workers at <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and their
family members were evacuated to <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> <DATE>last week.</DATE>;    The chief spokesman
at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Stanley Schrager</PERSON>, said the evacuation had been
ordered because "it's just untenable to have 30,000 people at <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>, double
the ordinary population, especially given the uncertainty over the volcano and
over the future of <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> as to when these people would be able to go home.";  
 On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> looked like a vast moonscape, with about six inches of
concrete-like volcanic ash covering roads, roofs and runways. Ragged scrubland
and manicured lawns had the same bleak blanket of hard gray crust.;    'A
wasteland';    "Everything looks like a wasteland," said Philippine Brig. Gen.
<PERSON>Leopoldo Acot Jr.</PERSON>, commander of about 150 Philippine troops guarding the
nearly deserted base.;    On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, volcanic ash and a hail of inch-long
pebbles emitted by <ORGANIZATION>Mount Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION> shut down operations at <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> and
damaged about 100 buildings, half of them seriously.;    Two people -- a
9-year-old American girl and a Filipino -- were reported killed late <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
when the roof of their shelter at <ORGANIZATION>Subic</ORGANIZATION> collapsed under the weight of the
ash.;    "We don't have snow here, and the roofs are not designed to hold
anything," <PERSON>Mukri</PERSON> said. "You get an event like this only about every 600 years.
It's not something you plan for.";    In the city of <LOCATION>Olongapo</LOCATION>, near the <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>
base, eight people were reported killed when the roof of a hospital collapsed
late <DATE>Saturday</DATE> because of ash deposits. Six people died when a church collapsed
in <LOCATION>Dau</LOCATION>, near Clark.;    Readiness unaffected;    <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said the
evacuation of base workers from <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and Subic would not affect military
readiness in the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>. All jet fighters had been withdrawn from <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> in
recent months as a result of a global redeployment of forces by the Pentagon.;
   But the volcano is expected to affect the final round of negotiations
between the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> over an extension of the joint
lease for the two bases, which expires in <DATE>September</DATE>. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials say <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>
may not be able to assume normal operations for months, if not years.;   
There appears to be no similar doubt about the future of <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>, which could
reopen fully within the next few weeks.;    Philippine scientists said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
it appeared that a section of the crater on <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION> had collapsed on
itself, releasing pressure that might otherwise have produced a cataclysmic
avalanche of molten rock.;    Forecast withdrawn;  On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine
Institute of Volcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology had predicted such an explosion after
obtaining satellite photos showing a nearly two-mile fissure along the
southern edge on the volcano. But <DATE>Sunday</DATE> it withdrew the ominous forecast.;   
The evacuation from <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION> began <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, when 900 Americans, mostly
wives and children from <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, boarded the cruiser <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> and two frigates,
the <PERSON>Rodney M. Davies</PERSON> and the <PERSON>Kurtz</PERSON>, bound for Cebu.;    Military officials
said the evacuees would probably be flown by chartered jets from the
international airport at <LOCATION>Cebu</LOCATION> to an American air base on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>, and, from
there, to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. Plans to evacuate the Americans by plane from the
<ORGANIZATION>Cubi Point</ORGANIZATION> naval air station, which adjoins <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION>, were foiled by the
ash.;    The aircraft carrier USS <PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON>, leading a battle group out
of <LOCATION>Okinawa</LOCATION> on the way to the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, is to assist in the evacuation,
which is expected to last a week to 10 days, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910617  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,052  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday June 17, 1991
00169132,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06172258 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06172258 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; CLEANUP -- Workers sweep volcanic ash from the
tarmac at Manila International Airport on Wednesday to prepare for partial
operation. The airport is closed to incoming flights.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; RESULT; US; MILITARY; TRIP  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The U.S. Air Force decided today to withdraw more than 60 percent of its
personnel from the Philippines because of damage to Clark Air Base from the
Mount Pinatubo volcano.;    The decision to withdraw the bulk of the Air Force
personnel suggests that damage to Clark, where they had been stationed, is
extensive and that it may take months before the facility can be used.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  VOLCANO CAUSES MORE TROOPS TO LEAVE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Until today, the evacuation of Americans from the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> affected
primarily military dependents.;    <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION> spewed more ash over <LOCATION>Clark</LOCATION>,
which is 10 miles away, and other areas during five eruptions today, and
regional officials raised the death toll from <DATE>last week</DATE>'s massive explosions
to 227.;    Also today, all flights in and out of <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>'s airport were
canceled for the day so workers could spread asphalt over tons of ash piled
along the runway shoulders.;    The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> evacuation announcement does not
affect <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Marine Corps</ORGANIZATION> personnel stationed at <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> naval base 25
miles southwest of the volcano.;    <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Stanley Schrager</PERSON>
said 4,500 <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> personnel will board ships <DATE>Friday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Subic</ORGANIZATION> and travel
south to <LOCATION>Cebu</LOCATION>, where they will board flights for the <ORGANIZATION>United States.</ORGANIZATION>;    That
will leave 2,500 airmen in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> -- 1,500 at <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and another 1,000
at Subic.;    The 1,500 airmen at <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> were left behind to guard the base
when the other 15,000 American soldiers and their families evacuated to <LOCATION>Subic</LOCATION>
on <DATE>June 10</DATE>, a day after Mount Pinatubo began erupting, ending 600 years of
dormancy.;    The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military announced on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> family
members would be evacuated to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and then later expanded the
withdrawal to include families of <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> and defense department civilians as
well.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910620  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  314  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday June 20, 1991
00172258,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06164150 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06164150 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, diagram; PHOTO: Associated Press; U.S. troops on guard at Clark Air
Base as huge plume rises from Mount Pinatubo eruption. (Color); DIAGRAM: Jeff
Fulaski--Knight-Ridder News Service. How volcanoes are formed.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; PHILIPPINES  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mount Pinatubo erupted with three thundering explosions today, shooting a
giant plume of ash more than 12 miles high and chasing nearby residents away
with an outpouring of molten rock and hot gas.;    A Filipino serving with the
U.S. Navy became the first reported fatality related to the eruption when his
car collided with a bus on an ash-slicked road north of the Subic Bay naval
base.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THERE WAS PANIC EVERYWHERE
VOLCANO ON A RAMPAGE
ASH FILLS THE SKY; LAVA, GAS GUSH  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Residents of nearby Angeles panicked at the roar of the initial blast, and
thousands of people packed roads after a huge gray-greenish mushroom cloud
burst from the volcano and turned day to night.;    At a refugee center in
<LOCATION>Olongapo</LOCATION>, 35 miles southwest of the volcano, survivors told of the sky growing
dark, then of hearing a tremendous explosion followed by a rain of ash.;   
"Stones as big as my head were falling down from the mountains," said <PERSON>Rolly
Soria</PERSON>, 18.;    "There was panic everywhere," said <PERSON>Manuel Romualdo</PERSON>, who fled
with his wife, five children, a cat and a dog. "Children were crying. We had
to grab whatever we could.";    Scientists warned of more, possibly larger
eruptions from the 4,795-foot volcano, which was dormant for six centuries
until it began spewing steam in <LOCATION>April.</LOCATION>;    "This could only be the beginning,"
and Seismology.;    Tens miles to the east, hundreds of Americans fled <ORGANIZATION>Clark
Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, home to 15,000 American military personnel and their families. Most
of the base's residents had been evacuated Monday.;    <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> did not appear
threatened by volcanic flow, and there were no immediate reports of
casualties.;    Seismologists said searing gas, ash and molten rock raced at
great speed down the mountain's western and northern slopes and into the
<PERSON>Marella</PERSON>, <PERSON>Maraunot</PERSON> and <PERSON>O'Donnell</PERSON> rivers.;    About 3,000 Aeta tribesman,
descendants of the original inhabitants of the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, fled the slopes of
<LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo.</LOCATION>;    People scampered for safety with their belongings and
livestock over roads slippery with ash fall. Refugees wore cardboard boxes to
protect themselves from the ash.;    "They were stunned by the eruption,"
reporter <PERSON>Bert Basa</PERSON> said by telephone from <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>. "Their faces turned ashen,
and it looked like their hair was standing on end.";    Ash was so thick in
the air that at noon, motorists were driving with their headlights on and
wipers operating to clear the windshields of volcanic debris. Bits of ash
wafted across the roads as if along a windy beach.;    A photographer who
circled the volcano in an airplane said an aerial gunnery range at <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> was
covered with ash, as were mountains in the <LOCATION>Zambales</LOCATION> range, normally lush,
green tropical peaks that now looked like the Alps in winter.;    <DATE>Today</DATE>'s
eruptions began at <TIME>8:40 a.m.</TIME> with a tremendous blast that sent forth a
mushroom cloud. It was followed by a second explosion a few minutes later and
a third, smaller blast at <TIME>11:49 a.m.</TIME>;    The huge plume 12 1/2 miles high
could be seen in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, 60 miles to the south, and reporters at the scene
said it blocked out the sun. The cloud drifted westward into the <LOCATION>South China
Sea.</LOCATION>;    Seismologists said the volcano had plenty of built-up magma and even
more severe eruptions could come later.;    "The crisis has not ended," said
<PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>Philippine Institute of Vulcanology</ORGANIZATION> and Seismology. "We
have signs that the volcano is preparing for another one.";    <PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON>
warned people within a 12-mile radius of Pinatubo to flee.;    "The smoke is
very thick like a dark mushroom in the sky," television reporter <PERSON>Gus Abelgas</PERSON>
said in a broadcast from <LOCATION>Botolan</LOCATION>, near the volcano's western slopes. "It's
just like what we saw in <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION>.";    President <PERSON>Corazon Aquino</PERSON> visited
refugee centers near <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION> briefly before returning to <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> for
independence day celebrations.;    Moments after the first explosion, sirens
wailed at <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air Base</ORGANIZATION>, and 600 of the 1,500 Americans remaining there fled
eastward to safety. <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> spokesman Lt. Col. <PERSON>Ron Rand</PERSON> said 900 Americans,
mostly security personnel, remained at the 130,000-acre base.;    <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> is one
of the biggest <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> bases overseas. <PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that the site was
in the path of the volcanic flow from <LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION> during its last major
eruption, in 1380.;    The <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>, which is trying to negotiate a new
contract with <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> for the base, said it can work around the temporary loss
of Clark.;    The Americans who fled <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> with a few belongings on <DATE>Monday</DATE>
moved in with sailors and their families at <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> naval base, 50 miles to
the southwest.;    Although the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> left <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, Philippine authorities
have not ordered a general evacuation of <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, a city of more than 300,000
people adjacent to the base.;    When Mount Pinatubo erupted today, church
bells pealed to sound the alarm and many people froze in their tracks with
fear. Many scampered for safety indoors.;    About 19,000 Filipinos had
earlier been evacuated from three provinces near the volcano's slopes and were
housed in about 25 makeshift evacuation centers outside the projected danger
zone.;    Officials said more were evacuated after <DATE>today</DATE>'s eruption but they
could provide no new figures.;    In the <PERSON>Sapang Bato</PERSON> area of <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, the city
district nearest the volcano, just 2,000 of 13,000 residents had been
evacuated as of <DATE>Monday</DATE>, officials said.;    Reporters visiting the village
today found it abandoned except for a few chickens and cattle. Houses were
padlocked, but the explosion had shattered some windows.;    Private jeep and
bus companies were ordered to the area today to pick up stragglers. About 10
people in <LOCATION>Moraza</LOCATION>, a village on the western slope, were refusing to leave,
relief officials said. They told rescuers that they would not leave their
livestock and if the animals die, "we will die with them.";    On <DATE>April 2</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION> produced a small hydrothermal explosion caused by underground water
meeting hot rocks deep inside.;    On <DATE>June 3</DATE>, the volcano spewed ash in a mild
eruption. That same day, 4,452-foot Mount Unzen in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> erupted with an
explosion of superheated gas, ashes and rocks that killed 38 people.;    A
larger flow days later razed dozens of houses.;    Experts say there is
apparently no connection between <LOCATION>Unzen</LOCATION> and Pinatubo.;    There are about 21
active and 200 dormant volcanoes in the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. The last major eruption
was the Taal volcano, about 50 miles south of <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1965</DATE>. That explosion
killed about 200 people.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Street  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910612  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DIAGRAM; PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,092  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday June 12, 1991
00164150,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06176049 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06176049 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; ASHEN -- People try to carry on business as
usual in Olongapo, Philippines, despite mounds of volcanic ash left over from
the eruption of Mount Pinatubo.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; DAMAGE; RESULT; US; MILITARY; FACILITY; PHILIPPINES  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Once the United States' largest overseas air base, this strategic military
installation may be crippled permanently, U.S. officials said Sunday as damage
reports continued to increase from last week's devastating eruption of Mount
Pinatubo.;    A six-hour tour of Clark showed that the eruption spewed a
deadly torrent of superheated gas, rocks and mud up to 20 feet high down a
river valley only a few hundred yards behind an officers' housing complex and
elementary school. It also sent waist-deep mud and swirling water across parts
of the base, damaging the hospital and washing cars and trucks away.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  VOLCANO DAMAGE RAISES DOUBTS U.S. CAN USE
AIR BASE AGAIN
ERUPTIONS COULD CONTINUE FOR 3 YEARS, SCIENTISTS
SAY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     At least 30 huge aircraft hangers, warehouses, a gymnasium and other
buildings were crushed from heavy gray ash that blankets runways, roads and
rooftops up to a foot deep in places. Falling trees damaged homes, a school
and other structures.;    With 10 new volcanic explosions <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, new ash
continues to rain down on <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, only 8.6 miles away. Worse, scientists say
<ORGANIZATION>Pinatubo</ORGANIZATION> may remain active and dangerous for up to three years, spewing
volcanic debris that endangers lives, threatens aircraft and fouls sensitive
communications equipment.;    "It'll take a long time to get <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> back and
operating, if ever," <PERSON>Stanley Schrager</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>,
said Sunday.;    Lt. Col. <PERSON>Ron Rand</PERSON>, a <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> spokesman, said it was not clear
whether the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> ever could use runways and fly so close to an erupting
volcano. The ash is much finer than the desert sand that pilots overcame
during the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> war.;    Moreover, the giant "pyroclastic flow" of
searing gas, steam and mud that roared at least 10 miles down the <LOCATION>Sacobia
River</LOCATION>, a short walk behind dozens of now ash-covered homes, broken trees and
the partially collapsed <ORGANIZATION>Grissom Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> in <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Mactan</LOCATION> housing
complex, indicates that the base is directly endangered by future eruptions.; 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> temporarily has transferred some of the base's essential
operations -- including training, airlift capability and special operations --
to other bases in the <LOCATION>Western Pacific</LOCATION>, particularly <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Okinawa</LOCATION>.
Officials say the transfers may become permanent if the base is deemed
inoperable.;    No precise figures are available, but damage and cleanup from
the <DATE>June 15</DATE> eruption is likely to cost <MONEY>hundreds of millions of dollars</MONEY> at
<PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and the equally stricken <LOCATION>Subic Bay Naval Base</LOCATION> and dockyard, where more
than 122 buildings were badly damaged or destroyed.;    <ORGANIZATION>Subic</ORGANIZATION>'s activities may
be temporarily relocated as well, officials said, but no decision has been
made yet. Subic is less likely to close permanently, however, since its ship
repair, refueling and resupply facilities are easier to maintain.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Clark Air Base, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910624  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  460  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday June 24, 1991
00176049,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06165191 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06165191 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; PHILIPPINES; PUBLIC; REACTION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mount Pinatubo spewed a deadly cloud of ash and gas more than 15 1/2 miles
high today after a turbulent night in which the volcano shook with the most
intense fury since it awoke from six centuries of sleep.;    "What we are
seeing now are phenomenal eruptions," said Raymundo Punongbayan, director of
Pinatubo is not quite over yet."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ASH AND GAS ARE SPEWED IN 'PHENOMENAL' ERUPTIONS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Two deaths reported;  Two deaths have been reported from the eruptions,
which began Sunday.;    A Filipino serving in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Navy</ORGANIZATION> was killed
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> when his car skidded on an ash-slickened road north of the <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION>
naval base, 30 miles southwest of the volcano, and crashed into a bus.;    A
member of the Aeta tribe that lives on the slopes of <LOCATION>Pinatubo</LOCATION>, said he saw his
uncle die in an eruption <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. There was no official confirmation, but
the man himself was badly burned.;    The latest eruption occurred at <TIME>8:41
a.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> and lasted for a half hour. It unleashed giant mudflows down the
jagged, ash-covered western slopes of the 4,795-foot mountain and into the
<LOCATION>Marella River.</LOCATION>;    The eruption sent a gray avalanche of deadly ash, gases and
molten rock down the slopes. The billowing ash cloud above turned day to
dusk.;    Debris from the eruption covered the roads, and huge boulders, some
the size of cars, littered gullies and riverbeds.;    Ash fell as far as
<LOCATION>Olongapo</LOCATION>, 25 miles to the southwest.;    Aviation authorities warned airline
pilots to avoid flying near the volcano after a <ORGANIZATION>Saudi Airlines</ORGANIZATION> 747 developed
engine trouble <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> when it passed near the ash cloud en route to <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>
from Dhahran.;    The plane landed safely and an inspection showed volcanic
ash in the engines, according to air controller <ORGANIZATION>Roserene Reyes.</ORGANIZATION>;    Today's
eruption followed a violent night in which the volcano exploded with a fury,
first at <TIME>10:52 p.m.</TIME>, then again a short time later and a third time at <TIME>12:04
a.m.</TIME> today.;    "This is already the big bang," <PERSON>Punongbayan</PERSON> said. "I can't see
any other eruption that will exceed this. What we are seeing now are
phenomenal eruptions.";    Another seismologist with the institute, <PERSON>Delfin
Garcia</PERSON>, said the volcano was entering "an episode of big eruptions" that would
continue indefinitely.;    <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s eruptions began at <TIME>8:40 a.m.</TIME> with a
tremendous blast that sent forth a mushroom cloud. It was followed by a second
explosion a few minutes later and a third, smaller blast at <TIME>11:49 a.m.</TIME>;   
After the nighttime eruptions, the troops that remained at nearby <ORGANIZATION>Clark Air
Base</ORGANIZATION>, from which most personnel were evacuated on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, prepared to
evacuate.;    About 100 vehicles lined up near the main gate and restless
troops milled about clutching their duffel bags, but no evacuation order was
issued.;    In the city of <LOCATION>Angeles</LOCATION>, which is adjacent to <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, the more than
300,000 residents spent an anguished night, fearful the volcano might force
them to flee. Many residents packed emergency kits with clothes and provisions
and stored them in their cars so they could leave at a moment's notice.;   
Thousands evacuated;  In all, more than 35,000 people have been evacuated from
areas near the volcano since it began showing signs of activity last week.
They include thousands of primitive Aeta tribesmen, who fled <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> on
buffaloes and ox-drawn carts after large rocks rained down on them.;    Aetas
who were evacuated to refugee centers in <LOCATION>Olongapo</LOCATION> appeared to have been upset
by the ordeal. Many spoke of the ground shaking furiously before the huge
volcanic clouds appeared.;    "It's very hard for us when the ground shakes,"
said <PERSON>Vilma David</PERSON>, 32. "Why doesn't it end so we can go home?"  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910613  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  22A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  609  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday June 13, 1991
00165191,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06166215 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06166215 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; FLEEING TO SAFETY -- A U.S. soldier at Clark
Air Base directs Filipinos escaping volcanic ash rising behind them.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PHILIPPINES; VOLCANO; PUBLIC; REACTION; UNUSUAL; WEATHER; CHANGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mount Pinatubo erupted today for a third straight day, shooting a cloud of gas
and steam more than 15 miles high, and an approaching typhoon threatened to
unleash tons of debris and boulders from the slopes of the rumbling volcano.; 
  Sirens blared at Clark Air Base, 10 miles east of Pinatubo, moments after
the volcano's latest eruption. Hundreds of U.S. troops milled about near the
gates, but no evacuation order was immediately issued.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  VOLCANO ERUPTS 3RD TIME
ONCOMING TYPHOON THREATENS MUDFLOWS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Geologists said <DATE>earlier today</DATE> that new activity was imminent because
pressure was building inside the 4,795-foot volcano 60 miles north of the
capital, <LOCATION>Manila.</LOCATION>;    As though the volcano were not enough trouble, the <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION>
weather bureau reported <DATE>today</DATE> that a typhoon was headed for the eastern coast
of <LOCATION>Luzon</LOCATION> island with maximum winds of 110 miles per hour. Typhoon Yunya is
expected to reach land late <DATE>Saturday</DATE> near <LOCATION>Baler</LOCATION>, about 90 miles northeast of
<LOCATION>Mount Pinatubo</LOCATION>. Rain already was falling today in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> and Luzon.;    If the
typhoon brings more rain, scientists fear that it will unleash mudflows --
giant rivers of earth, boulders and debris fused with sticky volcanic ash.;   
Meanwhile, administration officials in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that damage
from the volcano could cause the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration to reduce or pull back
its offers for the continued use of the strategic <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military bases in the
<LOCATION>Philippines.</LOCATION>;    "If <LOCATION>Clark Air Base</LOCATION> is unuseful to us, they (Philippine
officials) will pay the price for their decision (to balk at recent <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
offers)," said an administration official, who has closely followed the
negotiations.;    At the moment, he said, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> would not sign a
new agreement even if the Philippine government fully accepted the most recent
offer for the bases, the mainstay of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military power in <LOCATION>Southeast Asia.</LOCATION>;  
 Rather, this official said, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> wants to wait, at least
briefly, to see how much damage the volcano would cause to <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and the <LOCATION>Subic
Bay Naval Station</LOCATION>. The eruption "could, in the extreme, render (<ORGANIZATION>Clark Air
Base</ORGANIZATION>) inoperative for jet aircraft," the administration official said.;    The
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials spoke on condition that they not be identified.;    This
<DATE>spring</DATE>, after a year of negotiations, the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration and Philippine
officials had been moving toward an agreement that would permit continued <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
use of <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> for at least seven more years. The current base
leases expire <DATE>Sept. 16.</DATE>;    However, at the end of the last round of talks in
<DATE>May</DATE>, the two sides still remained deadlocked on several issues.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Wire Services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Manila, Philippines  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910614  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  437  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday June 14, 1991
00166215,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06197075 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06197075 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Armitage  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; MILITARY; FACILITY; PHILIPPINES  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The United States may give up volcano-damaged Clark Air Base, but it still
wants to keep a military presence in the Philippines, chief U.S. negotiator
Richard Armitage said today.;    As Armitage resumed talks on the future of
Clark Air Base and the Subic Bay Naval Base, his negotiating partner said that
the commander of U.S. forces in the Pacific recommended today that U.S. troops
quit Clark.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BASE TALKS RESUME; U.S. MAY QUIT CLARK  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The base has suffered extensive damage from the eruption of <LOCATION>Mount
