<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910628-0197
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910628-0197.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Letters to the Editor:
   We're Not Attacking Western Culture
</HL>
<DATE>
06/28/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A13
</SO>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   The Executive Council of the Modern Language Association
has noted with dismay the recent appearance of a number of
books and articles, including your May 3 and 23 editorials,
that decry "political correctness" on American campuses.
These texts charge that teachers of language and literature,
with the support of the MLA, are eliminating the classics of
Western civilization from the curriculum and making certain
attitudes toward race, class, gender, sexual orientation or
political affiliation the sole measure of a text's value.
Some teachers, it is said, intimidate colleagues who do not
comply with their own political agendas, and they subvert
reason, truth and artistic standards in order to impose crude
ideological dogmas on students. Normally, the MLA Executive
Council would not comment on the approaches members use in
their scholarly work or classrooms; however, recent
statements call for a response.
   The MLA, a century-old learned society, consists of almost
30,000 college and university scholars and teachers of the
modern languages and literature representing a wide spectrum
of histories, interests, scholarly methodologies and
approaches to teaching. In view of their great diversity, it
is unreasonable to suggest they are imposing a monolithic
ideology on the college curriculum. Over the past decade,
many have introduced new writers and raised new issues in
their courses, and there is a lively debate within the field
about the proper scope and focus of literary and language
studies. But this debate is scarcely unprecedented; it is an
extension of the legitimate process that has always made the
college curriculum in the U.S. responsive to the changing
interests of society and the changing shape of intellectual
disciplines.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   What is most disturbing in the attacks against the <ORGANIZATION>MLA</ORGANIZATION> and
individual members is the persistent resort to
misrepresentation and false labeling. While loudly invoking
rational debate, open discussion and responsible scholarship,
these attacks distort evidence and reduce complex issues to
slogans and name-calling. Further, they fail to acknowledge
the many differences in philosophical and other positions
represented among proponents for curricular change who,
whether or not one agrees with them, are raising important
questions about culture, language and society.
   Far from having discarded the established canon, most
teachers of literature and language continue to teach the
traditional works of Western culture, even as a growing
number introduce new or neglected works of Western and other
cultures. Instead of attacking traditional works on political
grounds, these teachers are re-enlivening the study of
literature and language by raising challenging questions from
new perspectives. Contrary to the charge that such questions
and perspectives debase standards, they have stimulated
students to think more critically, rigorously and creatively.
   Changes in what we teach our students have never been free
of controversy. In this context, it is useful to recall that
the <ORGANIZATION>Modern Language Association</ORGANIZATION> arose in <DATE>1883</DATE> precisely out
of such controversy -- the opposition to adding the teaching
of English and other modern languages and literatures to a
curriculum dominated by Greek and Latin. The teaching of
American literature, as distinct from English literature,
evolved after World War I out of a similar dispute, in which
many claimed that educational standards were being sacrificed
to popular taste. And 50 years ago there was strong
resistance to the introduction into literature classes of
writers such as <PERSON>Joyce</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Woolf</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kafka</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Garcia Lorca</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Faulkner</PERSON>.
   Literature has always been a theater of contention over
social, aesthetic and ethical values, and so has the study of
literature and language. Recent changes in our culture have
intensified these concerns in ways that need to be discussed
in a spirit of mutual respect. The <ORGANIZATION>Modern Language
Association</ORGANIZATION> will do everything it can to make the current
controversy -- at the moment so acrimonious -- fruitful and
genuinely educational.
   <ORGANIZATION>Mario J. Valdes
   President
   New York</ORGANIZATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880310-0255 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-10-88 1330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-AncientGreek Adv17   03-10 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ancient Greek, Adv 17,0765</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv17</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thu AMs, March 17 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Greek Students to Start Studying Ancient Greek Language</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HELENA SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In hopes of making Greeks more familiar
with their ancestors' ideas, the education minister has ordered
high school students to start taking daily classes in ancient Greek
in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   The decision by Education Minister <PERSON>Antonis Tritsis</PERSON> was reached
after months of public debate by scholars and educators, but some
teachers claim the language used by <ORGANIZATION>Homer</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Plato</PERSON> and the great
Greek dramatists might confuse young students and be too hard for
them to learn.
   ``Ancient Greek ideas should have a living medium in the world
today,'' <PERSON>Tritsis</PERSON> said in an interview, ``and I think that living
medium is the Greek people who continue to speak the same language
as the ancient Greeks.''
   He added that high school students 13 to 18 years old will be
the first to take compulsory ancient Greek, but that eventually
6-year-olds will start learning the language through word-games.
   ``We want every young Greek to be directly familiar with the
great wealth of his ancestors and those ancient Greek works that
have influenced the world,'' said <PERSON>Tritsis</PERSON>, an American-trained
architect.
   European literature began with <ORGANIZATION>Homer</ORGANIZATION>'s poems about the legendary
Greek heroes of the Trojan War, the ``Iliad'' and the ``Odyssey.''
   Plays by <ORGANIZATION>Aeschylus</ORGANIZATION>, Sophocles and Euripides in the <DATE>5th century</DATE>
B.C. are studied and performed in translation all over the world.
Plato's philosophic dialogues and Thucydides' histories contain
ideas that shaped Western thinking for centuries.
   Although Greek classical scholars and university professors say
they welcome Tritsis' project, schoolteachers protest that ancient
Greek is too difficult for all but the most talented linguists.
   While ancient Greek shares an alphabet and a wide range of
vocabulary with the present-day language, its grammar and structure
are much more complex.
   ``It is a fallacy that ancient Greek can be easily grasped by
every schoolchild,'' <PERSON>Christos Doukas</PERSON>, who heads the Athens-based
<ORGANIZATION>High School Teachers' Union</ORGANIZATION>, said in an interview.
   But <PERSON>Tritsis</PERSON> said Greek is a very conservative language. He
indicated it would be much less difficult for Greek students to
learn ancient Greek than it would be for American high school
students to learn Old English, which was spoken in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> from
around 400 to <DATE>1100</DATE> A.D., or even the English of Chaucer and
<ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The difference in language between <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s English and
modern English or Chaucer and modern English is greater than that
between Homer and <PERSON>Heroditus</PERSON> and the Greek spoken today,'' he said.
``Despite changes in forms ... the vast amount of words and
expressions are the very same language we use today.''
   Junior high students now study ancient Greek literature during
four 45-minute classes a week. But they read texts that have been
translated into modern Greek.
   Tritsis wants students to begin reading the texts in ancient
Greek.
   High school students take a two-year basic course in ancient
Greek and read some of the original literature. However, they are
not examined on the ancient Greek texts. Tritsis wants those
studies continued at a higher level entirely in the original Greek.
   The students will continue their usual studies of modern Greek
and their two classes a week of either French or English.
   The teachers, however, argue that language lessons should focus
on modern Greek, which a difficult language to master but still
easier than ancient Greek.
   ``Learning ancient Greek from original texts will only confuse
schoolchildren,'' said <PERSON>Doukas</PERSON> of the teachers union. ``Instead we
should all spend more time and energy concentrating on the Greek we
speak today, itself a rich and expressive language.''
   In a major reform of the Greek school system in <DATE>1976</DATE>, compulsory
ancient Greek was dropped from the state high school curriculum as
a ``dead'' language, irrelevant to modern educational needs.
   Now 15- and 16-year-old students intending to go to university
usually take a two-year basic course in ancient Greek, but scholars
say that isn't enough to keep the heritage alive.
   ``Ancient Greek has to be introduced at a much earlier stage in
a child's education, when it helps to develop his imagination,
judgment and memory,'' said <PERSON>Constantine Trypanis</PERSON>, a former culture
minister and retired <ORGANIZATION>Oxford University</ORGANIZATION> professor of Byzantine and
Modern Greek Studies.
   ``The study of ancient Greek language and literature in the
original is of cardinal importance if that tradition of culture is
to survive.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thu AMs, March 17</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880502-0101 </DOCNO>
<HL> 'Western Culture Must Go' </HL>
<AUTHOR> Bernard Lewis </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   This demand has been made of late by significant groups of students at <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> and elsewhere, with increasing support from professors, politicians and others. 
It is not always clear whether what must go is Western culture itself, or merely its teaching in the universities, but given the central role that <ORGANIZATION>Western</ORGANIZATION> culture assigns to universities in our life, the two may in the long run come to the same thing. 

   For those who wish to arrange its removal, it may be useful to attempt some definitions of what this Western culture means, and what its removal would involve. 
If Western culture does indeed go, a number of things would go with it and others would come in their place. 

   One consequence would be the restoration of slavery. 
The institution of slavery has existed in virtually all the societies known to human history, in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and pre-Columbian <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> as well as in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. 
The only thing that is peculiar about the institution of Western slavery is its abolition. 
The West alone, by its own choice and action -- sometimes, as in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, after bitter struggle -- abolished slavery in its own lands, and procured its abolition in those other parts of the world where the West exercised power or influence. 
In some of these countries the abolition of legal chattel slavery is very recent and could easily be reversed. 

   The restoration of slavery would also facilitate the introduction of another almost universal non-Western institution: the harem. 
The idea that marriage should take place only between one man and one woman at a time, both being free and adult, is peculiarly Western and has its roots deep in the Western past -- in <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> and Christianity. 
Other cultures have agreed in allowing a man, if he can afford it, to marry multiple wives, to enjoy the sexual use of female slaves and to castrate selected male slaves for the policing of his domestic establishment. 
In addition to polygamy and concubinage, other non-Western practices that might accompany this change could include child marriage and the burning of widows. 

   Changes of this magnitude would obviously arouse some opposition, even resistance. 
This, however, could easily be overcome by the removal of another of the peculiar and distinctive features of Western culture, namely political freedom. 
The idea that ordinary people have the right to share in the formation and conduct of government, and to criticize and seek to change the policies of those in power, is again peculiar to the Western cultural tradition and has Western roots going back to the American and French revolutions, the rise of the English Parliament, and the Greek city. 
The replacement of this outworn tradition by the natural and almost universal human combination of authority and submission would greatly ease the transition to a less parochially Western way of life. 

   Clearly, other cultures besides our own have art and music, philosophy and science, literature and life styles, the knowledge of which would benefit us and enrich our lives. 
But here we come to a dilemma. 

   Curiosity about other cultures, a willingness to learn their languages and study their ways, to appreciate and respect their achievements, all this again is peculiarly Western and relatively recent. 
The other great cultures of human history all have seen themselves as self-sufficient, and regarded the outsider -- or even the subculture insider -- with contempt, as barbarians, gentiles, untouchables, unbelievers, foreign devils, and the like. 
Only under the pressure of conquest and domination did they make the effort to learn the languages of other civilizations, and, in self-defense, to try to understand the ideas and ways of the current rulers of the world. 

   The West, in contrast, without constraint, developed an interest in other cultures, and made an effort to study them, to understand them and to enrich its own intellectual and cultural life in the process. 
This curiosity remains peculiar to <LOCATION>Western</LOCATION> and Westernized cultures and is still regarded with bafflement and anger by those who neither share nor understand it. 

   And here lies the difficulty. 
If Western culture goes, this kind of curiosity goes too, and with it our chance of learning about and learning from other cultures. 
How could we then get out of the vicious circle? 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Lewis</PERSON> is <ORGANIZATION>Dodge</ORGANIZATION> professor emeritus of <ORGANIZATION>Near Eastern</ORGANIZATION> studies at <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-35309 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes036_s_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-036 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  23 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Iran </F>
<H3> <TI>   Mirsalim Comments </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  LD2202122094 Tehran IRNA in English 1157 GMT 22 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> LD2202122094 </F>
<F P=104>  Tehran IRNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 22</DATE>, IRNA -- <PERSON>Mostafa Mirsalim</PERSON> who 
received a vote of confidence from the <LOCATION>Majlis</LOCATION> as the new 
his programs after President <PERSON>Akbar Hashemi-Rafsanjani</PERSON> introduced 
him to the deputies. 
  Mirsalim thanked the leader of the Islamic revolution 
<PERSON>Ayatollah 'Ali Khamene'i</PERSON> and President <PERSON>Rafsanjani</PERSON> for their 
confidence in him and disclosed the western conspiracies against 
the Islamic Republic. 
  He underlined the importance of the Islamic culture for the 
Iranian nation and said <DATE>today</DATE>'s world is faced with the 
domination-seeking tendencies of certain heinous states who 
insist to score cultural supremacy through dominating over other 
nations so as to pave the way for pocketing more interests. 
  Underlining the extensive dimension of the cultural assault, 
he said that only last year, 40 European and American research 
centers have published 214 books and 300 articles on <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and 
Islam while 16 counterrevolutionary and eight foreign radio 
stations broadcast programs in Persian. He added that 1,100 
counterrevolutionary t.v. stations also broadcast programs in 
<LOCATION>Persian</LOCATION> and 214 publishing centers of Iranians and non-Iranians 
abroad distributed 315 books in Persian in an effort to mock the 
Islamic values and to level accusations against <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>. 
  Giving more statistics, he also said that 310 cultural 
centers abroad were engaged in activities against the Persian 
and Islamic culture through publishing materials in 114 
periodicals in Persian while world's leading publications have 
published 110 articles on <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and Islam. 
  Moreover, he added, eight world conferences were held on 
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> 
during the period including the one on Iran-U.S. relations known 
as <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> conference. 
  The minister underlined that cultural growth is more 
important than economic and social growth. Mirsalim noted that 
language is the main medium for transfer of cultural concepts 
and that he plans to make efforts towards "preserving and 
strengthening the eloquent Persian language while at the same 
time to refine the language of alien words." He added that 
efforts will also be made to promote Persian in other regions 
particluarly in Persian speaking countries. 
  As another domain of his plans, he said that he will protect 
the rights of the writers and artists and systematize cultural 
and research centers. 
concerned, he said that facilities would be provided for 
cultural cooperation with the Central Asian states while such 
cooperation with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> would be strengthened 
and cultural ties with the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> littoral states would be 
continued. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091189-0060 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 105872 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 11, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 5; Column 2; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1082 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CHINA'S NEWSPAPERS HEADLINE COMMUNISTS' TOP 40 SLOGANS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVID HOLLEY, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
BEIJING 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
They aren't the catchiest slogans in the world, even in the original Chinese. 
But <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s leading newspapers gave top-of-page-one display <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to 40 of 
them -- some new, some old -- selected to be official slogans of the <DATE>40th 
anniversary Oct. 1</DATE> of the founding of the People's Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
It may be difficult even for the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> ideologues who compiled the 
list to envision enthusiastic repetition of such slogans as: "Enhance socialist 
democratic and legal construction and consolidate and develop the stable and 
unified political situation!" 
</P>
<P>
Virtually every person in <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> knows that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s top leadership, far from 
being stable or united, is rent by a fierce struggle over succession to 
85-year-old paramount leader <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON>. That, in fact, is why claims of 
unity are necessary. 
</P>
<P>
Almost no one, on the other hand, has any idea what "socialist democracy" 
means, if it means anything at all. "Legal construction" does at least have a 
meaning. It refers to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s attempt to gradually rely more on the rule of law 
and less on the whim of administrators and <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> bosses. Progress in 
this direction is spotty. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Neat Summary 
</P>
<P>
Despite their shortcomings, the slogans -- some simplistic, some bombastic, 
some contradictory -- give a neat summary of what preoccupies <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s leaders 
today. They form a kind of snapshot of <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> policies as the People's 
Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> nears its 40th birthday. 
</P>
<P>
The slogans reflect a recent shift toward more hard-line ideology, but most 
also address real problems. As in the case of references to stability and 
unity, however, the fact that a subject is embodied in a slogan usually means 
that it concerns an area where the government faces difficulties. 
</P>
<P>
Near the top of the list is praise for the <DATE>June</DATE> 3-4 martial-law crackdown 
hundreds, perhaps thousands, of students and ordinary <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> residents who 
poured into the streets in a vain attempt to block the army's advance. 
</P>
<P>
The people of <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, and of all <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, now are supposed to rally behind the 
slogan: "Warmly hail the successful quelling of the turmoil and 
counterrevolutionary rebellion!" Or: "Salute the People's <ORGANIZATION>Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION> men, 
police and armed police who have performed remarkable feats in the struggle to 
defend the People's Republic." 
</P>
<P>
In a rebuttal to Western condemnation of the brutal <DATE>June</DATE> crackdown, people are 
urged: "Maintain the sovereignty of the country and national dignity and firmly 
oppose any foreign interference in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s internal affairs!" 
</P>
<P>
Other slogans reflect the ideological and political tensions inherent in 
government policies that aim to open <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> to the world and introduce market 
forces, while at the same time trying to maintain a political dictatorship and 
elements of central planning. 
</P>
<P>
"Adhere to the reform and open policies and accomplish the tasks of improving 
the economic environment, straightening out economic order and deepening 
reform," proclaims one slogan, which strings together a series of familiar 
phrases. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Central Controls 
</P>
<P>
"Straightening out the economic order" is a reference to reassertion of some 
centralized controls to cope with problems such as corruption and inflation. 
The official line is that this will lay the groundwork for further 
market-oriented reforms, but <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s most enthusiastic reformists and many 
Western analysts view this "straightening out" as actually being an attack on 
the reforms by hard-line advocates of central planning. 
</P>
<P>
On the ideological front, the people of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> must "adhere to the Four Cardinal 
Principles" -- which require support for socialism and the dictatorship of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> -- and "firmly fight against bourgeois liberalization" -- a 
reference to the spread of <LOCATION>Western</LOCATION> concepts of democracy and civil liberties. 
</P>
<P>
At the same time, according to another slogan, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> will "carry out the policy 
This slogan was introduced by the late Chairman <PERSON>Mao Tse-tung</PERSON> to encourage a 
period of intellectual liberalization in <DATE>1956</DATE>, which was followed by the 
arrests of many critics. Since then, it has been repeatedly used during periods 
of relaxed political controls. 
</P>
<P>
Such periods, however, have always been followed by renewed crackdowns during 
which some of those who spoke their minds were punished. 
</P>
<P>
Some slogans stress the importance of education, science, culture and the role 
of intellectuals. 
</P>
<P>
But in a throwback to the Maoist rhetoric of the 1966-76 Cultural Revolution, 
one slogan declares: "Wholeheartedly rely on the working class and consolidate 
and develop the worker-peasant alliance." 
</P>
<P>
The people of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> also are to "enhance the construction of socialist ethics 
and be socialist citizens with ideals, morality, culture and discipline." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Number of Recent Moves 
</P>
<P>
This stress on "socialist ethics" is reflected in a number of recent policy 
moves, including a decision reported <DATE>Friday</DATE> by the official <ORGANIZATION>New China News 
Agency</ORGANIZATION> requiring all high schools and colleges in <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> to cooperate with 
factories "to have students perform regular manual labor." 
</P>
<P>
For many years, some schools have required students, as part of their 
ideological education, to spend time in workshops. Beijing authorities are now 
determined to expand the practice. Hard-line Communist Party leaders have 
repeatedly claimed that students who participated in this <DATE>spring</DATE>'s 
pro-democracy protests were divorced from <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s social realities. The 
performance of manual labor -- likely to be a few hours per week -- serves both 
as punishment and re-education. 
</P>
<P>
Rhetoric about tougher social and political discipline is also being paired 
with action. In the culmination of several years of preparation, a nationwide 
identity card system is to go into effect <DATE>Friday</DATE>, becoming a major new tool of 
authoritarian control. More than 570 million cards have been issued in the last 
few years, with more cards still due to be issued in some remote areas, 
according to Chinese press reports. Citizens over the age of 16 will be 
required to carry the cards at all times, the official <ORGANIZATION>China Daily</ORGANIZATION> reported 
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Other slogans list a variety of additional tasks, none of them easy: a battle 
against government corruption, protection of the legal rights of women and 
children, population control, protection of the environment and the 
reunification of Nationalist-ruled <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> with the Chinese mainland. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
NEWSPAPERS -- CHINA; COMMUNIST PARTY (CHINA); CHINA -- GOVERNMENT; SLOGANS; 
CHINA -- GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870514-0095 </DOCNO>
<HL> Beijing's Course:
The Chinese Economy
Appears to Be Firmly
On the Reform Path
---
But the Pace of Change Slows
After Resignation of Hu;
Political Reforms on Hold
---
Rock Discos and Irate Cabbies
---
By Barry Kramer
<DD> 05/14/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> FREST </IN>
<DATELINE> BEIJING  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Are reformers still in the driver's seat in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>? 
Or are Communist Party conservatives narrowing the country's eight-year-old economic and cultural opening to the outside world and putting a damper on free-market practices that have rejuvenated the centrally controlled economy? 

   The latest signs indicate that the pragmatists, led by <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s preeminent leader, are still firmly behind the wheel. 
But the leadership's consensus for far-reaching economic reforms is showing cracks. 
And political reforms, meant to introduce a modicum of Western-style democracy, have been on the back burner as leaders stress the inviolability of the Communist dictatorship. 

   Almost all of <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON>'s economic reforms, especially those allowing substantial foreign investment and imported technology, remain intact. 
Observers here can't identify any leaders who would return to the ultraconservative (in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, that means leftist) ways of <PERSON>Mao Tse-tung</PERSON>, under whom <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> languished in isolation for almost three decades. 

   But the breakdown of <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON>'s carefully crafted plans for his own succession has set off a power struggle. 
His protege <PERSON>Hu Yaobang</PERSON> was forced to resign as <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> boss in mid-January because he failed to quell party intellectuals and student demonstrators who had questioned communism and praised capitalism. 
As groups within the leadership vie for a say in who will replace the 82-year-old <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON>, the pace of economic reform has slowed. 

   That pace had been so fast that some party intellectuals had begun making speeches calling for a complete switchover to capitalism. 
Now all elements in the leadership, <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON> included, seem bent on proving that they are firmly committed to the "socialist road." 
One result: a "struggle" against so-called bourgeois liberalization. 

   The campaign frightened many Chinese and foreigners here when it began at the time of <PERSON>Mr. Hu</PERSON>'s ouster. 
It evoked visions of <PERSON>Mao</PERSON>'s much-reviled Cultural Revolution of the late <DATE>1960s</DATE> and early <DATE>1970s</DATE>. 
But Chinese and foreign observers are convinced, four months later, that the anti-Western, pro-party campaign is being strictly limited. 

   One recent clue came from <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Central Philharmonic Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>, which recently appeared on national TV wearing formal Western white ties and tails. 
In a country where the Mao jacket used to be de rigueur, comments an Asian diplomat here, "that's very symbolic." 

   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has sought to calm the fears through articles and reports in the official press and broadcast media and through a flood of public statements by <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Zhao Ziyang</PERSON> and other officials. 
"<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> can't afford any more upheavals and disturbances," says <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON>. 
"Without opening up {to the outside world} and reform {of the economy} there will be no hope for the success of our country's modernization program." 

   At the same time, <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON> tells any and all listeners that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> will remain a socialist country with the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> firmly in charge. 

   A year ago, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> watchers were convinced that <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON> was firmly in charge, and that even the most capitalist of the economic reforms then being bandied about would be carried out. 
But doubts about stability arose when small but well-publicized demonstrations in <DATE>December</DATE> by university students demanding more democracy had to be put down in several cities. 
Worries increased with the mid-January sacking of <PERSON>Mr. Hu</PERSON>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Hu</PERSON>'s forced retirement was accompanied by the start of the drive against bourgeois liberalization -- defined as Western ideas of democracy and anything else the party's conservatives find distasteful, even sexual allusions in fiction. 
It is also considered bourgeois liberalism to oppose the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>. 
Several intellectuals were thrown out of the party and transferred from their jobs for questioning the party's supremacy. 

   But things have eased considerably since those dark days in <DATE>December</DATE> and <DATE>January</DATE>. 
Party leaders quickly began assuring every foreign visitor, including Secretary of State <PERSON>George Shultz</PERSON>, who visited in <DATE>March</DATE>, that the struggle against bourgeois liberalization would be confined to the party. 
Prime Minister <PERSON>Zhao</PERSON>, who took on the additional duties of party boss after <PERSON>Mr. Hu</PERSON>'s ouster, has promised repeatedly that there will be no repetition of the extreme "leftist" practices of the Cultural Revolution. 
"There is no market for it," he told reporters. 
"All the {present} party and government leaders . . . were victims of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Cultural Revolution</ORGANIZATION>. 
Today, such a thing cannot get started anymore." 

   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s leaders also say that business relations with the outside world will be increased. 
And they pledge that economic reform within <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> will proceed after the experiences of the past eight years have been analyzed. 

   Economic reforms instituted in the past eight years, including the dismantling of Mao's farm collectives, have dramatically increased agricultural production and peasants' income. 
But grain and cotton production has slipped as farmers switched to more profitable crops, and irrigation systems have deteriorated as farmers spent their money on new homes, washing machines and color television sets. 

   The reforms in the cities, though major, have been less dramatic because they were introduced more recently. 
But dislocations occurred there, too, including a rush to build large capital projects and buy consumer goods, both of which ate into <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s foreign-exchange reserves. 
An inefficient bureaucracy displeased foreign investors, slowing the flow of foreign capital needed to expand the economy. 

   Today the government is acting to make life easier for foreign investors, and that seems to have calmed early worries among diplomats and businessmen from abroad. 
"The changes weren't as earth-shaking as they feared might take place," says a European diplomat. 

   In any case, the political changes take second place, in businessmen's eyes, to economic problems that they have been facing all along -- including the foreign-exchange shortage, which has caused the Chinese to cut back on foreign orders and has put many contract negotiations on hold. 
A few minor contracts have been canceled. 

   "Westerners weren't all that wound up about the investment climate here anyway," says a diplomat. 
"Some were already deciding that it wasn't a good place to invest. 
The events of <DATE>December</DATE> and <DATE>January</DATE> just added to that uncertainty." 

   The amount of direct foreign investment in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> last year fell by <PERCENT>48%</PERCENT> from a year earlier. 
That, and frequent complaints by foreigners here, led the government to introduce 22 regulations last fall designed to answer some of the complaints. 
"I don't mean to suggest that, suddenly, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> is an easy place to do business," says a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> trader, but since the 22 regulations were introduced, "it's easier." 
Still, he adds, "it's a tough year to make a direct sale." 
To make up foreign-exchange shortages, the Chinese have been holding imports down. 
The anti-Westernization drive also militates against imports that aren't used to increase production. 

   Other foreign observers here express concern that the new assertiveness of party conservatives will torpedo further implementation of some basic economic reforms that Western economists consider vital to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s economy. 
They most frequently mention price reform, which would let most prices float with supply and demand, and management reform, which would let skilled managers rather than <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> functionaries make factories' business and production decisions. 

   Under <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s present system, prices of most nonfarm commodities are set by the state, and this leads to inefficiencies. 
Factories waste raw materials and energy, for example, because their cost is kept artificially low by the state. 

   Price reform is a complicated problem for the Chinese, who have a distaste for the inflation that would probably result. 
But observers feel that price reform must be imposed if management reform is to succeed. 
"Prices are a signal," says a foreign banker here. 
"If prices are distorted, then signals to factories are distorted." 

   Although economic reform seems generally on track, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> watchers have been worried that political reform may be in trouble. 
"Economic reform isn't enough," says an Asian diplomat. 
"They have to raise the work ethic of the people." 
To do that, <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON> last year proposed daring plans to reform the political structure, including separation of the roles of the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> and the government and introduction of elements of grass-roots democracy. 

   Since the party hard-liners reasserted themselves in <DATE>January</DATE>, however, <PERSON>Mr. Deng</PERSON> and other leaders have been avoiding the subject. 
But just this week, in a move that diplomats interpreted as a sign of new confidence among the reformers, Prime Minister <PERSON>Zhao</PERSON> was quoted as saying that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> needed liberal reforms to expand "people's democracy." 

   The status of intellectuals in the party is still unclear. 
"There is a determined effort to persuade intellectuals that they shouldn't fear too much out of the bourgeois liberalization campaign," says a European diplomat, but intellectuals remain wary. 
"Thought control is under way," the diplomat says. 
"They won't stick their necks out." 

   There also has been a clampdown on newspapers and magazines. 
Hundreds of unauthorized publications appear to have been closed, not because they were particularly political but because they printed cheap fiction and scandal. 
Editors say they have been cautioned to steer clear of controversial topics like political reform. 
Students are being kept under control with reminders that any political transgressions could land them a post-graduation assignment to the deserts of <LOCATION>Xinjiang</LOCATION>. 

   Even so, intellectual caution appears to be easing. 
Some intellectuals who halted their Western contacts after <DATE>January</DATE> have resumed them. 
One American reporter was surprised recently when a Chinese journalist suddenly phoned to chat after not having been heard from for months. 

   The campaign against bourgeois liberalization seems to have affected ordinary Chinese not at all. 
Western-style dance halls, even discos with rock music, still thrive. 
Beijing residents recently could attend at least three Western theatrical productions with Chinese casts: "The Music Man," "The Fantasticks" and "Our Town." 
And <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> taxi drivers are as feisty as ever. 

   "The biggest problem with this country is the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>," said one taxi driver, complaining that many party functionaries were corrupt. 
"The Communist Party is like a big tree -- but the roots are rotten." 

   Outsiders are sometimes astonished to hear such talk. 
"The Chinese are surprisingly interested in talking about what's going on, and amazingly they speak their mind," says a Chinese-speaking American businessman here. 
"I can get in a taxi and get a pretty rip-roaring conversation going about the system. 
They say there are lots of problems, that the anti-bourgeois-liberalization campaign means nothing, that it's boring, and that the leaders are too old." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870430-0087 </DOCNO>
<HL> 3,000 Days of Ayatollah Khomeini
---
By Khosrow Fatemi</HL>
<DD> 04/30/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MDEST </IN>
<TEXT>
   The Islamic Republic of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> is 3,000 days old today. 
It was established on <DATE>Feb. 11, 1979</DATE>, a month after the shah left the country and two weeks after <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON> returned from 15 years in exile. 
These 3,000 days have brought much suffering to Iranians, suffering that can be calculated in human, economic and sociopolitical terms. 

   The principal feature of the ayatollah's regime has been <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s war with <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION>, which began in <DATE>September 1980</DATE> and nearly <DATE>seven years later</DATE> shows no sign of ending. 
Although the war was started by <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION>, it is Ayatollah <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>'s adamant opposition to a cease-fire or peace that has been the main cause of its prolongation. 
The ayatollah's approach to the war is to use antiquated military tactics such as human-wave attacks that result in a large number of casualties. 

   Most observers put the number of Iranian fatalities at 600,000 and the number of injuries at more than 1.5 million. 
In other words, for each of its inglorious days, the <LOCATION>Islamic Republic</LOCATION> has cost <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> 200 lives and 500 injuries. 
These numbers reflect only the Iranian side of the conflict and do not include Iraqi casualties, which are estimated to be one-half of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s. 
Their inclusion would increase the daily toll of the ayatollah's war by 100 deaths and 250 injuries. 

   The human suffering perpetuated by the ayatollah is not limited to that brought about by his war with <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION>. 
The Islamic Republic has also been implicated in several terrorist attacks on Western embassies and commercial centers around the world. 
Included in this category are 292 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Marines and tens of other Westerners killed by terrorists trained and financed by the ayatollah and his associates in diplomatic guise. 

   Estimates of the number of executions in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> for the ayatollah's 3,000 days range from a few thousand by <ORGANIZATION>Amnesty International</ORGANIZATION> (which footnotes all its figures by saying that its estimates are understated because of lack of reporting) to more than 100,000, which is the number given by Iranian opposition groups abroad. 
My own research indicates a figure of about 60,000, which would average out to 20 executions a day. 

   Finally, since the <DATE>1979</DATE> revolution, more than two million Iranians have been made homeless by the war and forced into internal migration to other parts of the country. 
In addition, another 2.5 million Iranians, resentful of the ayatollah's drive to return <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> to medieval morality and intolerant of his tactics, have been forced into exile, mostly in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Every day of the <LOCATION>Islamic Republic</LOCATION> has forced 667 Iranians out of their homes and another 833 out of their homeland. 

   The ayatollah's government claims that the cost of the war to the Iranian economy has been more than <MONEY>$300 billion</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> for each one of the <ORGANIZATION>Islamic Republic</ORGANIZATION>'s troubling days. 
This is for a country with a gross national product of about <MONEY>$183 million</MONEY> a day. 
In other words, every day, the Islamic Republic wastes more than half of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s total production in its war with <LOCATION>Iraq</LOCATION>. 

   The gravity of the situation becomes even more apparent when these figures are combined with other economic problems that the ayatollah's government has created for <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>. 
Among them is the continuing recession. 
The country's GNP reached <MONEY>$67 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1977</DATE> and has since remained at about that level in real terms, while the annual rate of inflation has averaged between <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT>. 
Another economic offshoot of the ayatollah's regime is unemployment, which was close to zero at the time of the Islamic revolution but is currently estimated at between <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of the total labor force. 
Underemployment is also a problem. 

   The ayatollah's only economic promise has been to reduce <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s dependence on imports and oil exports. 
Yet, according to the <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Fund</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s imports reached <MONEY>$15 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1984</DATE> (the latest year for which data are available), compared with <MONEY>$14 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1977</DATE>, the last peaceful year of the shah's reign. 
The country's non-oil exports, which were more than <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1977</DATE>, dwindled to less than <MONEY>$260 million</MONEY> out of a total of <MONEY>$13.2 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1985</DATE>, according to the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Another severe blow to the country's economic performance and development has been the emigration of more than 2.5 million Iranians since the start of the Islamic Republic. 
The impact of the shortage of human power is exemplified by the number of Iranian physicians at home and abroad. 
Before the Islamic revolution, there were 25,000 doctors in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> for a population of 35 million -- that is, one doctor for 1,400 people. (By comparison, there is about one doctor for every 500 people in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>) 
<DATE>Today</DATE>, there are 13,000 physicians for a population of 40 million, or one doctor for 3,077 people. 
Since the formation of the <LOCATION>Islamic Republic</LOCATION>, more than 15,000 doctors have emigrated, retired or died, and fewer than 3,000 new doctors have completed their studies because of the frequent closure of the universities. 

   Similar shortages exist in other professions, especially management and economics. 
There is also a shortage of university professors. 

   In sociopolitical terms, <PERSON>Ayatollah Khomeini</PERSON> has transformed the world's perception of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> into that of a nation of terrorists and barbarians. 
Under his guidance, the Islamic Republic has replaced <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s educational system with superstition and the teachings of the Middle Ages, converted Iranian women into second-class citizens, and brainwashed Iranian youths into martyring themselves in the ayatollah's "holy war" with <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION>. 
Moreover, the <ORGANIZATION>Islamic Republic</ORGANIZATION> has given a new meaning to political savagery and religious intolerance -- as Iranian Jews and Bahais can attest -- all in God's name. 

   While the ayatollah's regime may not have an overtly leftist orientation, through its alienation of the Iranian masses, it is paving the way for an eventual communization of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>. 
A likely scenario is not a popular communist uprising but rather a coup by a small group of military officers capitalizing on the regime's unpopularity, followed by an appeal for help to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> -- similar to what happened in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>. 
Moscow could use a <DATE>1921</DATE> treaty with <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> as a pretext to comply. 

   The West's naivete in such actions as the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration's secret dealings with the <ORGANIZATION>Islamic Republic</ORGANIZATION> lends credibility to the perception among many Iranians that the ayatollah is, in effect, kept in power by the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. 
These feelings are augmented by the Western world's willingness to support the ayatollah commercially. (<LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> provided <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of its total imports in <DATE>1985</DATE>.) 
All of this increases anti-Western sentiments not among the hooligans who are paid or brainwashed to shout "death to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>" in front of Western TV cameras, but in the educated middle class. 

   While Iranian culture is antipathetic to communism, the longer the ayatollah stays in power, the more likely this will change. 
According to an old Persian proverb, "a drowning man clutches onto anything, including a useless piece of wood." 
In the not-too-distant future, communism may become <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s useless piece of wood. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Fatemi</PERSON> is a professor of business at <ORGANIZATION>Laredo State University</ORGANIZATION> and editor of its International Trade Journal. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890715-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-89 0518EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-China 1stLd-Writethru a0427 07-15 0777</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0427,0795</SECOND>
<HEAD>Party Boss Calls For More Ideological Education</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with six grafs to UPDATE with foreign publications removed
from hotels, details. Picks up graf 3 pvs, `The military ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist Party chief <PERSON>Jiang Zemin</PERSON> called for more
ideological education to shield young people from the influences of
Western culture, official media reported today.
   Jiang, at a meeting <DATE>Friday</DATE> on higher education also attended by
Premier <PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON>, said educators must take a clear stand against
``bourgeois liberalization'' in the wake of the student-led movement
for democratic reform.
   Meanwhile, staff at the <ORGANIZATION>Jianguo Hotel</ORGANIZATION> and several other
well-known <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> hotels said officials from the <ORGANIZATION>China National
Publications Import and Export Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a state company, on <DATE>Friday</DATE>
removed all foreign magazines and newspapers from their stands.
   Several other hotels, including the <ORGANIZATION>Sheraton Great Wall</ORGANIZATION>, the
Holiday Inn and the Palace, also said foreign periodicals had been
confiscated. The hotels said the Chinese officials gave no reason
for confiscating the publications.
   Hotels are among the few places Chinese have access to foreign
news accounts of the crackdown on dissent in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, which have
differed greatly with the government's version. Satellite reception
of TV news from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, including CNN, were cut off at
several hotels earlier this month.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the official press reported the government was
planning a sweep on the nation's bookstores to removal publications
written by scholars wanted by police for participating in the
pro-democracy movement.
   The military crushed the movement in an attack on <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> on <DATE>June
3-4</DATE> after the government declared it had become a
``counterrevolutionary rebellion'' against the socialist system.
   Jiang, the party's general secretary, said the rebellion backed
up statements by senior leader <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON> that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s most
serious fault in recent years was neglecting ideological education.
   ``Quite a number of young people have been greatly influenced by
Western culture and ideology in recent years, yet we have slackened
correct ideological education among them. As a result, they are not
mentally prepared to face the hardships and complexities in the
socialist construction and the reform,'' the official <ORGANIZATION>Xinhua News
Agency</ORGANIZATION> quoted him as saying.
   University students already have been told they will have
additional mandatory classes in ideology this <DATE>fall</DATE>. The <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>
Daily reported this week that <DATE>summer</DATE> vacation programs have been
arranged for primary and middle school students to educate them in
loving the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>, socialism, the motherland and the
People's <ORGANIZATION>Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION>.
   It said military officers will give lectures to children on the
rebellion and children will visit martial law troops and the
families of soldiers killed by protesters resisting their advance
into the city.
   Jiang also gave backhanded praise to intellectuals, who had
expressed support for the democratic movement.
   He said they were the ``gem of the nation'' but that
``intellectuals have their shortcomings and we should help them to
have a better understanding through education and studies.''
   He said dissident <PERSON>Fang Lizhi</PERSON>, who has sought refuge in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Embassy</ORGANIZATION> and is wanted for purported counterrevolutionary crimes,
``and his like are scum of the Chinese intellectuals and very few in
number.''
   Jiang was appointed party chief on <DATE>June 24</DATE> when the party purged
<PERSON>Zhao Ziyang</PERSON>, who had sympathized with some of the students' demands.
Zhao, stripped of all his party posts, has not been seen since <DATE>May
19</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Li Ruihuan</PERSON>, a member of the powerful <ORGANIZATION>Politburo Standing
Committee</ORGANIZATION>, noted that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s two latest bouts of bourgeois
liberalization, or flirtation with Western culture, began with
student demonstrations. The government also launched a campaign
against bourgeois liberalization after student demonstrations in the
<DATE>winter of 1986-87</DATE>.
   ``This fact poses a problem for us and we should make a thorough
study on how to run the schools well,'' he said.
   Also <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> voted 81-10 to impose economic
sanctions on <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and to urge President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to take even harsher
measures.
Department</ORGANIZATION> appropriations bill, adopts several sanctions passed
earlier by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. It requires <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to suspend several trade
programs but gives him the flexibility to stop any program
suspension.
   The legislation includes six-month suspensions of trade insurance
by the <ORGANIZATION>Overseas Private Investment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and the use of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> funds
to support <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> trade.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> also adopted non-binding suggestions in which they
urged <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to take stiffer steps, including reviewing all trade
agreements between the countries.
   <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Marlin Fitzwater</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> with <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> for a
administration would consider the legislation but that the
president's current response to the crackdown has been appropriate.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910924-0104
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910924-0104.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   A Multicultural Reading List
   ----
   By Dinesh D'Souza
</HL>
<DATE>
09/24/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A18
</SO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
</IN>
<NS>
EDUCATION ISSUES (EDU)
</NS>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   The current drive to include multicultural and non-Western
books in the core curriculum of American universities is
justified in its goals, but misguided in its approach.
   If pursued as a complement to study of the West, learning
about the achievements and failings of other societies can
help us better understand our own. The great works of
non-Western civilization, like those of Greece and Rome, can
broaden the minds of young people and sharpen their thinking.
There are practical reasons, too, for Americans who come from
increasingly diverse backgrounds and who will have to compete
in a global economy to learn about the languages and cultures
of non-European lands.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Unfortunately, many institutions -- such as <LOCATION>Mount Holyoke</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Dartmouth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION> -- now
require students to take non-Western or ethnic studies but do
not require them to study the basic ingredients of Western
history, politics or literature. Meanwhile at universities
such as <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>, which boast of an inclusive curriculum,
multicultural education has degenerated into the uncritical
depreciation of Western classics as racist, sexist and
homophobic, combined with ethnic cheerleading and primitive
chic when the subject is minority or Third World cultures.
   The following "great books" could be required as part of a
non-Western curriculum. They could be taught alongside a
similar sequence in <LOCATION>Western</LOCATION> classics, or the two sets of
works could be integrated into a single core. Obviously, this
outline does not exhaust the list of important works produced
in other cultures; it is intended to suggest the approach
that should guide serious advocates of multiculturalism:
   -- The Upanishads. Written in Sanskrit between 800 and 400
<LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>, they represent sacred spiritual teaching for the
Hindus. The word "upanishad" means instruction at the foot of
a sage. There are more than a hundred upanishads, and of
them, the "Bhagavad-Gita" -- the lessons of life communicated
by <PERSON>Lord Krishna</PERSON> to the archer Arjun -- is undoubtedly the
most influential. The Upanishads teach that God is a sublime
force within us, enabling us to rise above our mortal
limitations. They have contributed to a widespread
conviction, across the Indian subcontinent, that it is a
waste of time to combat social injustice, as true liberation
comes from the inner soul's receptivity to the divine
calling.
   -- Confucius' "Analects." Compiled by his pupils soon
after the master's death in the 5th century <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>, Confucius'
teachings have become the foundation of Chinese thought. Like
<PERSON>Socrates</PERSON>, his rough contemporary, Confucius believed that men
should seek virtue for its own sake, rather than because it
promises a reward in this life or the next; he also shares
<PERSON>Socrates</PERSON>' view that the contemplative life is the highest
calling. Confucian life is dedicated to the relentless
pursuit of moral improvement, through refinement of such
character traits as courage and benevolence.
   Western students who study Confucius confront a worldview
that takes a fatalistic approach to reforming social
institutions, emphasizes unqualified obedience within the
family, and embraces rigid class structures and emperor
worship. A less pliant approach to political oppression may
be found in <LOCATION>Mencius</LOCATION>, whose doctrine of rulers existing for
the good of the people was ignored for most of Chinese
history.
   -- The Koran. The holy text of the Muslim religion,
accepted as the word of Allah communicated to the prophet
Mohammed in the <DATE>7th century</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION> has much in common
with the Judeo-Christian tradition out of which it sprang.
Like the <ORGANIZATION>Old Testament</ORGANIZATION>, it is a rich combination of
common-sense advice, history, moral instruction and divine
law. The Koran outlines a vision of human dignity,
self-discipline and charity that has greatly improved the
lives of many of its followers. While the cruel and heartless
will be punished, the Koran promises: "Those who have faith
and do good works will be rewarded by gardens watered by
running streams."
   At the same time, its teachings regarding male superiority
and authority over women, polygamy, and criminal deterrence
("As for the man or woman who is guilty of theft, cut off
their hands, for this is the punishment enjoined by Allah")
will be difficult for many Westerners to embrace. The Koran
does not distinguish between religious and political
activity: It calls for Muslim domination and limited rights
for others, and it urges a jihad, or holy war, against
non-Islamic states to bring them under the rule of Allah.
   -- Lady <PERSON>Shikibu Murasaki</PERSON>'s "Tale of Genji." Composed
during the <DATE>11th century</DATE>, this is a vivid and opulent account
of Japanese life at court. Murasaki, who served as an aide to
the <PERSON>Empress Akiko</PERSON>, camouflaged her learning in Chinese and
Japanese language, as well as history, because she knew that
such knowledge was considered inappropriate for a woman. But
this erudition, as well as a fluent style, are evident in
"Tale of Genji," in which Murasaki herself is a character --
the second wife of Prince Genji.
   The work was well known in court circles during her time,
and the emperor upon reading it was amazed at <ORGANIZATION>Murasaki</ORGANIZATION>'s
understanding of Japanese imperial history and convention.
"Tale of Genji" provides the patient student (it is a lengthy
novel of six parts) with a rare vista on the complex norms of
11th-century <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   -- <PERSON>Rabindranath Tagore</PERSON>'s "Gitanjali." Written in <LOCATION>Bengali</LOCATION>
in the <DATE>early 20th century</DATE>, this is a series of poetic
meditations on life and nature. <PERSON>William Butler Yeats</PERSON>, who
wrote the introduction to the English translation of the
"Gitanjali," said he discovered in Tagore a world that he had
always dreamed about, but never encountered, in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   "These verses," <PERSON>Yeats</PERSON> wrote, "will not lie in little
well-printed books upon ladies' tables, who turn the pages
with indolent hands that they may sigh over a life without
meaning . . . but, as the generations pass, travelers will
hum them on the highway, and men rowing upon the rivers.
Lovers, while they await one another, shall find this love of
God a magic gulf wherein their own more bitter passion may
bathe and renew its youth." Somehow <PERSON>Tagore</PERSON>'s spiritual ethos
managed to capture "a whole people, a whole civilization,"
and he did so grandly, nobly, without polemic.
   -- <PERSON>Chinua Achebe</PERSON>'s "Things Fall Apart." The conflict
between the old tribal ways of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and the new forces of
colonialism and Christianity are portrayed in this <DATE>1958</DATE>
novel. It dramatizes change through the life of a bellicose
tribesman of the Ibo tribe in <LOCATION>Nigeria</LOCATION>, who places such
emphasis on physical strength that he regards all men weaker
than himself as "women."
   <PERSON>Mr. Achebe</PERSON>'s novel recounts the destruction of
thousand-year-old indigenous traditions, including
internecine warfare among the tribes (the protagonist Okonkwo
drinks wine from the skulls of rival tribesmen he has
killed), wife-beating, the consultation of oracles leading to
bloodshed, and superstitious refusals to bury those who die
from disease. "Things Fall Apart" is written with such
economy, honesty and moral seriousness that it has been
compared to the classics of Greek tragedy.
   -- <PERSON>Naguib Mahfouz</PERSON>'s "The Thief and the Dogs." When <PERSON>Mr.
Mahfouz</PERSON> won the Nobel Prize in <DATE>1988</DATE> he was praised for being
realistic yet metaphorical, detailed yet evocative. In the
tradition of <ORGANIZATION>Flaubert</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Dickens</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mr. Mahfouz</PERSON> is a masterly
observer of the subtle interaction of foreign and indigenous
influences in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, and his novels reflect the rich social
texture of urban life: its distracting exotica; its
picaresque abandon; its social-climbing, kowtowing, and
disguised corruption. "The Thief and the Dogs," published in
<DATE>1961</DATE>, is a narrative thriller, following the roguish exploits
of the jewel robber <PERSON>Sai Mahran</PERSON>, his desperate attempts at
revenge and love, his moral disguise of revolutionary ideals
for his self-aggrandizing crimes, and ultimately his effort
to escape the police dogs without degrading himself to the
level of an animal. This novel raises the veil on an
often-concealed and often-misrepresented civilization.
   -- <PERSON>Octavio Paz</PERSON>'s "The Labyrinth of Solitude." Published in
<DATE>1985</DATE>, this collection consists of two long meditations -- the
famous title piece and "The Other Mexico" -- and other
shorter articles, all exploring the moral and psychological
identity of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, partly in relation with colonial <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>
and the <LOCATION>U.S</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Paz</PERSON>, who won the <DATE>1990</DATE> Nobel Prize for
literature, is a Mexican novelist, poet and social critic,
and this book employs flights of fancy, rhythm, and meter, as
well as trenchant analysis and commentary. <PERSON>Mr. Paz</PERSON> terms
himself a "disillusioned leftist," and his work resonates
with longing for a peasant utopia, punctuated by a keen
awareness of the follies that attend its implementation.
   Other classics that could be added to this list include
the "Tao Te Ching" of Lao-tse, <PERSON>Sun Tzu</PERSON>'s "Art of War," the
"<ORGANIZATION>Ramayana</ORGANIZATION>," <PERSON>Ibn Khaldun</PERSON>'s "Muqadimmah," the autobiography of
<PERSON>Al Ghazali</PERSON>, the Chinese drama "Three Kingdoms" by <PERSON>Lo
Kuan-Chung</PERSON>, and the "Rubaiyat of <PERSON>Omar Khayyam</PERSON>." Contemporary
works, such as <PERSON>Mario Vargas Llosa</PERSON>'s "Against Wind and Tide,"
<PERSON>V.S. Naipaul</PERSON>'s "A House for <PERSON>Mr. Biswas</PERSON>," the work of <PERSON>Jorge
Luis Borges</PERSON>, and the novels of <PERSON>Wole Soyinka</PERSON>, could be used as
well. Any multicultural curriculum should explore the
principles of Buddhism. There are also excellent collections
of folklore, historical surveys, and modern scholarly
analyses of the literature and philosophy of non-Western
cultures that merit study.
   Multiculturalism is bogus when it reduces scholarship to
ideology. Instead, universities should promote authentic
multiculturalism, which through a critical appraisal of both
Western and non-Western cultures promotes knowledge and
understanding among the peoples of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and of the world.
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. D'Souza</PERSON>, a research fellow at the <ORGANIZATION>American Enterprise
Institute</ORGANIZATION>, is the author of "Illiberal Education" (Free
Press/Macmillan).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880912-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-12-88 0105EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CulturalAmerica Bjt   09-12 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cultural America, Bjt,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Colleges Losing Interest in Humanities, But The Public's Not</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Colleges and universities are losing interest
in literature, language and history but Americans are showing a
``remarkable blossoming'' of interest in cultural events, spending
more money on them than on sports events, a government report says.
   The report by <PERSON>Lynne V. Cheney</PERSON>, chairwoman of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Endowment</ORGANIZATION> for the Humanities, says the high cost of education may
be causing more students to avoid liberal arts subjects in favor of
courses that will give them a money-making career.
   While the number of bachelor's degrees awarded increased <PERCENT>88
percent</PERCENT> in the past two decades, degrees in the humanities dropped
<PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT>, said her report released <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Foreign language
majors were down <PERCENT>29 percent</PERCENT>, English majors <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT>, philosophy
majors <PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> and history majors <PERCENT>43 percent</PERCENT>, it said.
   The 73-page report ordered by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> says too many colleges
are neglecting the achievements of Western culture while requiring
ethnic courses, treating literary masterpieces as political
documents, stressing publishing rather than teaching, and dealing
in topics so specialized that they have little meaning outside the
academic world.
   The report says museums, libraries, educational TV stations,
state humanities councils and private historical societies provide
so much education that they have become ``a kind of parallel
school,'' reaching millions of people outside college campuses.
   ``The remarkable blossoming of the humanities in the public
sphere is one of the least noted, though most important, cultural
developments of the last few decades,'' writes <PERSON>Mrs. Cheney</PERSON>.
   The <MONEY>$140 million</MONEY> endowment she has headed since <DATE>May 1986</DATE>
provides grants to scholars, colleges, museums, libraries and other
institutions to promote the humanities.
   Citing a variety of sources, the report gives several examples
of increased public interest in the humanities, including record
high book sales, a doubling of the number of historical
organizations in 20 years to nearly 10,000, and a <PERCENT>660 percent</PERCENT>
increase in visitors to the <ORGANIZATION>National Gallery of Art</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
since <DATE>1957</DATE>.
   Americans who spent twice as much on sports events as on
cultural endeavors 20 years ago are now spending more on culture _
<MONEY>$3.4 billion</MONEY> compared with <MONEY>$3.1 billion</MONEY> for sports in <DATE>1986</DATE>, said a
news release accompanying the report. It gave no details on how the
figures were obtained or what cultural events were included.
   The report says that while some have argued that television is
the enemy of books, people are actually both watching television
and reading, with book sales up <PERCENT>400 percent</PERCENT> since television was
rare 40 years ago.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Cheney</PERSON> credits television with increasing the sale of some
books which have been the basis for popular dramas or subjects of
discussion on educational television shows.
   In assessing the academic approach to the humanities, the report
says: ``Viewing humanities texts as though they were primarily
political documents is the most noticeable trend in academic study
of the humanities today. Truth and beauty and excellence are
regarded as irrelevant; questions of intellectual aesthetic
quality, dismissed.''
   The report says Western tradition is rich and creative, but many
colleges are abandoning courses that teach it.
   The report says a course in great Western literature is under
attack at <ORGANIZATION>Columbia University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, while <ORGANIZATION>Mount Holyoke
College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION> at Madison
require ethnic or Third World courses but have no Western
civilization requirements.
   ``The humanities are about more than politics, about more than
social power,'' the report says. ``What gives them their abiding
worth are truths that pass beyond time and circumstance; truths
that, transcending accidents of class, race, and gender, speak to
us all.''
   The report, ``Humanities in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>,'' resulted from several
meetings of advisory panels and regional groups formed by the
endowment. It follows a <DATE>1986</DATE> report, ``American Memory,'' which
detailed how little high school students know about Western
history, literature and culture.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880502-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-02-88 0211EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-BeijingUniversity Bjt   05-02 0933</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Beijing University, Bjt,0958</SECOND>
<HEAD>China's Most Prestigious University Celebrates 90th Year</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Beijing University</ORGANIZATION>, survivor of invasions,
repression and political warfare, commemorates on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> its
90th anniversary as <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s foremost center of learning.
   The celebrations have been pegged not to the college's founding
date in <DATE>1898</DATE> but to a famous uprising on <DATE>May 4, 1919</DATE>, that vaulted
<ORGANIZATION>Beijing University</ORGANIZATION> students into the vanguard of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s
revolutionary and nationalist movements.
   The university marks its birthday with symposiums on its great
thinkers, publication of books chronicling the university's role in
shaping modern <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, sports competition and disco and folk dancing.
   But as it enters its <DATE>10th decade</DATE>, <LOCATION>Beida</LOCATION>, as it is known in its
abbreviated Chinese form, faces yet another crisis, a lack of money
that educators claim could seriously erode its standards of
excellence.
   ``We have many problems,'' said <PERSON>Huang Huaicheng</PERSON>, director of the
president's office. ``Facilities are quite backward and need to be
renovated. Students live six to a room. There are not enough
classrooms and the library is inadequate. We can't even buy all the
books we need.''
   Huang said the school last year had to cut corners to make up a
<MONEY>$1.3 million</MONEY> gap between planned spending and funds of <MONEY>$8.1 million</MONEY>
from the government and other sources.
   He said there's no money left to boost pay for instructors, who
start out at less than <MONEY>$30</MONEY> a month, about the same as an unskilled
laborer, and seldom make more than <MONEY>$55</MONEY>.
   Most of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s 1,000 universities share the same financial
plight. The government, acknowledging that education has been
neglected in the past, is spending more, but must give priority to
lower education in a nation still <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> illiterate.
   The government now is encouraging teachers to help out colleges
and bolster their meager incomes by moonlighting. Universities are
being told to make money by selling basic services and technology.
   Beida students and faculty, living up to their activist
traditions, have been the first to question the wisdom of this
policy. Students with shoeshine kits appeared on <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>'s central
<LOCATION>Tiananmen Square</LOCATION> to show what they thought of sideline jobs.
   Open letters to members of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s parliament and big-character
posters on the campus recently spoke of the ``crisis'' engendered
by the government's investing in industrial development rather than
its human resources.
   ``Beida students have a tradition of being concerned about the
future of the country,'' <PERSON>Huang</PERSON> said.
   University President <PERSON>Ding Shisin</PERSON> defended the protestors and
complained to Chinese journalists that some department heads at the
university didn't even have their own offices.
   <ORGANIZATION>Beijing University</ORGANIZATION> began in <DATE>1898</DATE> as the <ORGANIZATION>Peking Imperial
University</ORGANIZATION>. It was founded during the Qing Dynasty's ``100-Day
Reform,'' a short-lived effort to introduce some Western ideas in
government and education.
   For its first two decades, the school's main role was to turn
out government functionaries, and among its less kind nicknames
were ``the gambling den'' and ``fountainhead of ribaldry and
bawdiness.''
   That changed in <DATE>1916</DATE> when <PERSON>Cai Yuanpei</PERSON>, a classical scholar who
had studied in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, became president. Cai introduced Western
scholarship and coed education and brought in educators such as
<PERSON>Chen Duxiu</PERSON>, one of the fathers of Chinese leftism, and <PERSON>Hu Shi</PERSON>, who
studied under American pragmatist <PERSON>John Dewey</PERSON> and led the movement
to use the vernacular language in Chinese literature.
   One of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s first Marxists, <PERSON>Li Dazhao</PERSON>, was librarian and then
professor at <LOCATION>Beida</LOCATION>. Among his library assistants was Mao Tse-tung.
   Beida and other <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> universities moved to the southwest
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> city of <LOCATION>Kunming</LOCATION> after Japanese troops invaded the capital in
<DATE>1937</DATE>, returning only in <DATE>1946</DATE> after World War II ended.
   Three years later Mao came to power in <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, bringing with
him strong anti-intellectual biases.
   In <DATE>1957</DATE>, when Mao encouraged critics to speak out with the
slogan, ``Let a hundred flowers bloom, let a hundred schools of
thought contend,'' Beida teachers declared that ``the masses want
to overthrow the Communist Party.'' They were among the first to be
purged in a subsequent crackdown.
   Ma Yinzhu, an American-educated economist, was replaced as
president in <DATE>1960</DATE> and disappeared shortly after knocking government
policies in a magazine article where he said, ``It is not enough to
destroy; one must build.''
   The first clashes of the disastrous Cultural Revolution began at
<LOCATION>Beida</LOCATION> in <DATE>1966</DATE> when <PERSON>Nie Yuanzi</PERSON>, a woman in the philosophy department
backed by <PERSON>Mao</PERSON>'s wife <PERSON>Jiang Qing</PERSON>, leveled attacks on university
President <PERSON>Lu Ping</PERSON>.
   In the next few years hundreds on the campus were detained,
driven to suicide or murdered in armed battles between rival
radical factions.
   For a decade almost all classes were suspended and no degrees
were given. ``The Cultural Revolution brought overall destruction
to the university,'' <PERSON>Huang</PERSON> said.
   He said entrance exams were revived in <DATE>1977</DATE>. The school now
accepts about one out of five examinees. It has offered degrees
since <DATE>1981</DATE>.
   The school now has 20,000 students, including post-graduates and
special students, with a freshman class of about 2,000. Since its
merger in <DATE>1952</DATE> with <ORGANIZATION>Yanjing University</ORGANIZATION>, a former American
missionary college, it has occupied 500 acres of wooded land in
<LOCATION>northwest Beijing</LOCATION>.
   Qing Dynasty-style buildings with red pillars and slanted, tiled
roofs and surrounded by bamboo groves and lakes are one throwback
to the Yanjing period.
   One fixture that will be missing at 90th anniversary
celebrations will be a giant statue of Mao, torn down late one
night in <DATE>April</DATE> by university workmen. Teachers who helped build the
monolith during the early days of the Cultural Revolution applauded
its removal, saying it was one reminder of the past they could live
without.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880622-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-22-88 0532EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-Students     06-22 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-Students,0458</SECOND>
<HEAD>Students To Be Taught To Support State Policies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist authorities are ordering <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s
rambunctious students to sit through special <DATE>summer</DATE> school classes
geared toward ridding them of yearnings for democracy and a better
life for intellectuals.
   Official reports today said the government ordered universities
to use <DATE>summer</DATE> school to teach students to support state policies
and to ``enhance students' consciousness'' about the difficulties
of implementing them.
   In <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, students every <DATE>summer</DATE> are sent for several weeks to
farms, factories and businesses to ``learn from the masses.''
   The People's Daily said this year's program would push the party
line.
   The order came down in a government directive, issued by the
<ORGANIZATION>Communist Party Propaganda Department</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>State Education Commission
and Communist Youth League</ORGANIZATION>. It appeared part of official efforts to
control <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s restive college students and lessen their
widespread alienation from the party line.
   The directive came two weeks after students at <ORGANIZATION>Beijing
University</ORGANIZATION> put up dozens of posters demanding democracy and
criticizing the government's ongoing political and economic reforms
as inadequate.
   ``The directive expressed the hope that the students will be led
to the frontline of the reforms to understand the great
achievements of the past 10 years of reform and increase their
confidence in it,'' the People's Daily said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Xinhua News Agency</ORGANIZATION>'s English service said the students
``should be educated to support reform programs drawn up by the
party and the government and take part in overcoming difficulties
in the reform.''
   Senior leader <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON> launched the reform program in <DATE>1978</DATE>
in an effort to develop <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s backward economy by replacing
central planning with elements of free-market economies.
   He also sought to make the sluggish bureaucracy more efficient.
   Many students believe the reforms do not go far enough and want
sweeping political changes, including introduction of Western-style
democracy.
   The posters that went up this month at <LOCATION>Beijing University</LOCATION> took
pokes at top leaders and demanded democracy, respect for human
rights, a freer press, more funds for education and better pay for
intellectuals.
   Police appeared in force to head off a march students had
planned to dramatize their demands. Authorities warned against
illegal protests and emphasized the need for stability if <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> is
to modernize.
   The official <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> Daily today quoted the head of the party
<ORGANIZATION>Propaganda Department</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Wang Renzhi</PERSON>, as telling a meeting of
ideological workers in <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> they must be careful in exposing
students to foreign ideas.
   Wang said <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> must introduce foreign ideas that are good for
its development, but should not embrace all Western culture and
ideology. He especially warned against teaching nihilist, egoist
and non-rationalist philosophies.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA050489-0078 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 52362 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 4, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 7; Column 1; Op-Ed Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
957 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IN THE MAY 4TH TRADITION, CHINESE STUDENTS SEEK A NEW TURNING POINT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MERLE GOLDMAN, Merle Goldman is a professor of Chinese history at Boston 
University and is completing a book on China's democratic elite. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The student demonstrations that erupted last month after the death of <PERSON>Hu 
Yaobang</PERSON>, who had become a symbol of democracy, are very much in the Chinese 
tradition. The first student demonstration in modern times occurred 70 years 
ago today. Then, as in <DATE>April</DATE>, <LOCATION>Beijing University</LOCATION> students marched from their 
campus to Tian An Men Square to demonstrate against the government and demand 
"democracy and science." <DATE>April</DATE>'s rally put less emphasis on science, which the 
government already supports, and more emphasis on demands for freedom of 
speech, rule of law, end of corruption and student-led, rather than party-led, 
organizations and publications. 
</P>
<P>
The <DATE>May 4th</DATE> Movement became a turning point in Chinese history, leading to the 
overthrow of the warlord government and rejection of Confucian ideology, which 
had dominated <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> for more than 2,000 years. Whereas the <DATE>May 4th</DATE> Movement 
challenged Confucianism, <DATE>1989</DATE>'s demonstration challenged Marxism-Leninism and 
the Communist Party that have dominated since <DATE>1949</DATE>. Like the <DATE>May 4th Movement</DATE>, 
the <DATE>April</DATE> demonstration was well-organized, starting in <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> and spreading 
to universities throughout <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. That the students were able to conduct their 
protests of more than 100,000, facing off against policemen and military men 
without any major incident, shows the degree of organizational skill that they 
must have learned from their party elders, the very people they have turned 
against. 
</P>
<P>
Like their <DATE>May 4th</DATE> predecessors, the students, following the demonstration, 
have boycotted classes and mobilized support to their cause from other groups 
-- the middle class, workers and peasants. In modern times, student movements 
have only been successful when they have gained wider social support. There is 
evidence that members of the emerging small-scale entrepreneurial class that 
has been spawned by <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON>'s economic reforms has helped the students 
morally and financially. Workers on fixed incomes who have been hurt by 
inflation, also caused by the reforms, have joined in the demonstrations, 
though their concerns are more economic than political. 
</P>
<P>
The <DATE>May 4th</DATE> Movement was able to take place and expand because the warlord 
government was relatively weak. By contrast, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s present government can act 
decisively if it wishes. It is ironic that one reason the party leaders purged 
Hu as the general secretary in <DATE>January, 1987</DATE>, was because he had refused to 
repress the student demonstrations for democracy in <DATE>December, 1986</DATE>. Yet the 
same leaders have showed restraint this time. 
</P>
<P>
In part, the leadership is divided and uncertain about what action to take. 
Accelerating inflation, blatant corruption of officials and their children and 
the people's general discontent have created a potentially explosive situation, 
which the leaders fear may erupt into chaos if they crack down. Moreover, the 
memory of repression and anarchy of the Cultural Revolution, in which these 
leaders were among the victims, also is a limiting factor. Perhaps most 
important, unlike the regimes of the warlords, <PERSON>Chiang Kai-shek</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mao 
Tse-tung</PERSON>, the Deng regime has been reluctant to use violent means to suppress 
political demonstrations. 
</P>
<P>
Another restraint is <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s concern with its image in the outside world. 
During the Cultural Revolution, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> did not care about its image abroad. But 
today it does because it wants foreign capital, technology and help with its 
modernization. It also cares about its image in the communist world, in which 
it sees itself in competition with the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> in developing the most 
effective model for reform. Although <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has stressed economic rather than 
political reform, it too has accepted the need for the latter. A bloody 
repression of students demanding democracy at the very time <PERSON>Mikhail S. 
Gorbachev</PERSON>'s visit is imminent could be very embarrassing. 
</P>
<P>
Both the <DATE>May 4, 1919</DATE>, and <DATE>April, 1989</DATE>, demonstrations occurred in a pluralistic 
intellectual atmosphere in which many ideas from abroad were vigorously and 
publicly debated. Many of the students' teachers and intellectual elders had 
written about and openly advocated the democratic rights for which the students 
demonstrated. In the two months preceding the <DATE>April</DATE> demonstration, nearly 100 
of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s most prominent intellectuals had success makes you feel pessimistic. 
It condemns you to loneliness and makes you feel apart from the world. Talking 
so much about my films sometimes makes me depressed. I think dwelling on your 
organized a petition to the government demanding the release of political 
prisoners and democratic rights. This was the first time since <DATE>1949</DATE> that 
intellectuals had organized publicly for political purposes. 
</P>
<P>
An important difference, however, between the two movements, is that they took 
place in different contexts. The <DATE>May 4th</DATE> occurred two years after the Russian 
Revolution, when it appeared that the Bolsheviks with their Marxist-Leninist 
ideology had found a way to modernize a backward country quickly. Its model and 
ideology became the inspiration for many of the participants of the <DATE>May 4th</DATE> 
Movement -- among them Mao -- who were to establish the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> 
and eventually lead it to power. 
</P>
<P>
The participants in the <DATE>April</DATE> demonstration specifically reject that model and 
ideology as a failure and as inappropriate. The models today are the Western 
democratic systems and the idea of human rights as evolved in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. 
However, just as the Chinese transformed Buddhism or Marxism-Leninism brought 
in from abroad, whatever they take from abroad today will be combined with 
aspects of their own tradition and society. 
</P>
<P>
This year is also the 40th anniversary of the Chinese Communist revolution. 
Will <DATE>1989</DATE> mark a comparable turning point in Chinese history? 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Drawing, The Great Wall of China, Kal 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Opinion 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910819-0115
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910819-0115.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Letters to the Editor:
   Multifaceted Replies on Multiculturalism
</HL>
<DATE>
08/19/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A9
</SO>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Irving Kristol has gone too far ("The Tragedy of
Multiculturalism," editorial page, July 31). Pillorying the
broad range of attempts to respond to our growing cultural
diversity by invoking such excesses as teaching that
"`Western civilization' was invented by black Egyptians and
feloniously appropriated by the Greeks" is about as useful,
and serves the same purpose, as the Bush presidential
campaign's use of Willie Horton: manipulation of public
opinion through fear of change, rather than providing the
facts.
   The fact is that, racially and ethnically, America's
school-age population is increasingly unlike its past
generations. According to the 1990 census, 15% of today's
preschoolers are black, 13% Hispanic, 3% Asian and Pacific
Islander, 1% American Indian and 6% "other." Compare that
with Mr. Kristol's contemporaries (people aged 70 to 74 in
1990): 8% black, 3.6% Hispanic, 1.5% Asian and Pacific
Islander, 0.4% American Indian and 1% "other."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Demographers have made much of the change from a majority
of families with children to a majority of families without
children. But that applies only to white families. Two-thirds
of black families have children under age 18, as do nearly
<PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of Hispanics and <PERCENT>63%</PERCENT> of "other" races. This ensures that
the school-age population will become even less a product of
"what we call `Western civilization'" in the future.
   It takes a high degree of obtuseness not to understand
that limiting the curriculum to "what we call `Western
civilization'" is a sure way to turn off a youth population
that is already largely alienated from school. A good example
of how their different backgrounds produce different
interests was provided by a study last year on awareness of
current news events. Most of the conclusions faulted the
younger generation for its ignorance of the Gorbachev-Bush
dialogue and the political changes in <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION> -- and
failed to note that its interest in the freeing of <PERSON>Nelson
Mandela</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> invasion of <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and the political
upheaval in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> was as great as that of older generations.
   <PERSON>Martha Farnsworth Riche
   Director</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Policy Studies
   Population Reference Bureau Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
   ---
   I found <PERSON>Mr. Kristol</PERSON>'s article very bold and accurate. I
recently graduated from one of the last bastions of a truly
classical liberal-arts education.
   But the "core curriculum," as it is known at my alma
mater, is under attack. This is not surprising, since most
schools across the country are also under fire. I am,
therefore, worried that if I have any children, they are
going to grow up without ever being exposed to (let alone
versed in) <LOCATION>Homer</LOCATION>, Aeschylus or Montaigne. Oh, by the way, I
am from <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> -- a real, greencard-carrying immigrant.
   There are thousands of Africans and other non-Americans
who would literally do anything for the privilege of being
"brainwashed" by studying Hobbes and <PERSON>Locke</PERSON>.
   Teodros Ashenafi
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
   ---
   First of all, multiculturalism is not an attempt to
address the social problems of African-Americans -- it is an
effort to correct the marginalization of significant
historical figures and events involving nonwhite people and
to portray history more accurately. Second, Latin Americans
and Asian-Americans have been equally involved in, and
concerned about, multicultural education. Third, <PERSON>Mr. Kristol</PERSON>
minimizes the impact of positive role models, contradicting
the declarations of social scientists concerning the
demonstrative impact of negative role models.
   Finally, schools are a microcosm of our society. As such,
they are an instrumental tool in the socialization of
American citizens. An inaccurate and biased education
contributes to the prejudices and misconceptions that others
have about African-Americans and that many African-Americans
have about themselves. To advocate the continuance of such an
educational injustice facilitates the miseducation of all and
further promotes many of the societal problems represented
daily in the media. This is the real tragedy.
   <PERSON>Marion O. Cunningham</PERSON>
   <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   ---
   Was <PERSON>Mr. Kristol</PERSON> trying to be funny? Saying that blacks
were "among the earliest arrivals" to this country must set a
record for most misguided euphemism. I suppose inmates on
<LOCATION>Alcatraz</LOCATION> were "island dwellers" and that <PERSON>Franco</PERSON>'s condition
has remained stable.
   Jordan Eth
   <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>
   ---
   Assimilation among earlier ethnic groups, though
difficult, happened because these people became Americans and
lost their ethnic identity, even if they maintained some
family traditions privately. That is much more difficult for
blacks to do, because no matter how well they adopt the local
culture, they are still black and still subject to all those
little racial insults, whether real or imagined. Small wonder
that some blacks decide to chuck trying, and develop a
culture they can live with. Wrong-headed as this might be,
calling it "psychobabble" isn't going to help much either.
   We need to show blacks that there really is a place for
them in mainstream American culture, and if teaching black
history helps boost their pride and bring them along, so much
the better. The alternative is a perpetuation of two separate
Americas, which helps no one.
   <ORGANIZATION>Timothy F. Merker
   Cedar Rapids</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>
   ---
   Grant it that black Americans have not become
"Americanized" to the degree of Hispanics or Orientals. But
the "arrival" of blacks on <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s shores for nearly two
centuries of slave trade meant being sold, starved, separated
from family, subjected to sexual and physical abuse, and
denied access to educational and economic opportunities
available to "other" groups by virtue of arriving as chattel,
subjected to a life of bondage. And, even after they were
finally emancipated, they were denied access to educational
and economic opportunities. Can we seriously blame certain
black Americans for not wanting to become "Americanized"? Can
we blame them for not wanting to be part of a "process"
rooted in an institution such as slavery? And can we fault
black Americans for seeing "multiculturalism" as an
alternative to the continued second-class status afforded
most blacks in our society? By the way, where do the American
Indians fit into <PERSON>Mr. Kristol</PERSON>'s analysis? Why don't we condemn
their failure to "Americanize"? After all, they were here
first]
   <PERSON>Robert Beeson
   Greenwich</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Conn</LOCATION>.
   ---
   When our nation was launched in the <DATE>late 18th century</DATE>, we
were primarily from <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, speaking English. The waves of
immigrants that came to our shores in the <DATE>19th century</DATE> were
assimilated into our culture by the third generation, and the
English language was the big unifier. When you could speak
English fluently, you were an American. And being an American
meant accepting the culture, social graces and form of
government that were primarily Anglo-Saxon.
   We have been fighting for the past half-century to bring
people together. Multiculturalism represents a major step
backward and is, on balance, far more destructive than
constructive. And why should minorities just include blacks,
Hispanics, Asians, etc.? How long will it be before other
"minorities" are clamoring for the same cultural purity?
   <PERSON>George J. Helwig
   Scarborough</PERSON>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   ---
   As anyone who follows this issue must be aware, the
principal justification for the multiculturalist movement is
that we are rapidly becoming a non-European country and our
culture and teaching of history must reflect that fact.
Multiculturalism, in short, is not simply a radical ideology;
it is a mainstream phenomenon, an historically predictable
outcome of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s revolutionary transformation into a
multiracial, white-minority society. In order to accommodate
itself to that transformation, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> is literally
reformulating itself, adopting group rights along with a
radically different "cultural story" to represent our
radically changed and heterogeneous population. This process
is pushed along by the expanding cultural and political power
of minorities and the collapse of morale among a majority
that sees itself rapidly diminishing.
   How strange and tragic it is that conservatives, who see
themselves as the embattled opponents of multiculturalism,
should continue to support the immigration policies that give
multiculturalism its most compelling rationale]
   <PERSON>Lawrence Auster</PERSON>
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
   ---
   That few individuals, mainly Afrocentrists, are aware of
the racial character of the ancient Egyptians as a black
people (by today's definitions), should come as no surprise.
   Egyptology was born on the crest of a great wave of racism
and anti-Semitism that swept <ORGANIZATION>Anglo</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Germanic Europe</LOCATION> in the
<DATE>early 19th century</DATE>. While Egyptology provided a pretext for
the mass transfer to European museums of the much coveted
wealth of the pyramids, it was also the hoped-for basis that
would legitimize the whitening of the ancient Egyptian
racial-ethnic character. With a Europeanized Egyptian type
that could never be confirmed as ancestor to those West
African peoples taken into <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION> slavery, it would prove
straightforward -- on moral grounds -- for <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> to justify
the colonization and enslavement of the dark-skinned races.
   Were the whole, unvarnished truth ever revealed in public
education, the white-supremacist impulse that has governed
the Western world for 500 years -- and which <PERSON>Mr. Kristol</PERSON> and
