<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900822-0042
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900822-0042.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Caesars World Raises
   Caesars New Jersey
   Bid to $22.25 a Share
</HL>
<DATE>
08/22/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A5
</SO>
<CO>
   CJN CAW
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- Caesars World Inc. said it agreed in
principle to increase by 25 cents a share, to $22.25 a share,
or $48.4 million, its tender offer for the 13.4% stake it
doesn't already hold in Caesars New Jersey Inc.
   The sweetened offer is part of a settlement of litigation
brought by certain shareholders of Caesars New Jersey. They
charged that, among other things, the company's original
$47.9 million offer was inadequate.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Caesars World, an owner and operator of hotels and
casinos, also extended its offer to <DATE>Sept. 7 from today</DATE>, and
said it might further extend the offer until final court
approval of the settlement, which isn't expected for at least
two months. <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> owns and operates <LOCATION>Caesars
Atlantic City</LOCATION>, a hotel and casino.
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> also agreed to amend its offer to pay
interest on <MONEY>$22</MONEY> a share if the offer is extended more than 30
days after the mailing of supplemental offer materials
describing the settlement and the amendment. The mailing is
expected this week.
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> also agreed that if it purchases at least
549,792 <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> shares, giving <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> at
least <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of the outstanding shares, it will merge <ORGANIZATION>Caesars
New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> with <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> or a <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary.
In the merger, shareholders would receive <MONEY>$22.25</MONEY> a share,
without interest. Of the 2,175,945 <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> shares
that <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> doesn't already own, about 1.5 million had
been tendered as of yesterday.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900918-0041
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900918-0041.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Business Brief -- Caesars World Inc.:
   Accord Met for Withdrawal
   Of Shareholder's Petition
</HL>
<DATE>
09/18/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   CJN CAW
</CO>
<IN>
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<LP>
   Caesars World Inc. said an agreement has been reached for
the withdrawal of a petition by a shareholder of Caesars New
Jersey Inc. with the New Jersey Casino Control Commission in
connection with Caesars World's pending tender offer for
Caesars New Jersey shares.
   The holder had alleged, among other things, that the $22 a
share Caesars World is offering for the 2.2 million shares of
Caesars New Jersey it doesn't already own was inadequate.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> said the withdrawal is provided for in an
amendment to its previously announced agreement in principle
connected with the settlement of certain shareholder lawsuits
related to the tender offer. Caesars World holds about <PERCENT>86.6%</PERCENT>
of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION>'s 16.3 million outstanding shares.
   As a result of the petition withdrawal, a <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey
Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION> hearing on the issue, previously
scheduled for <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, has been adjourned.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ901228-0037
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
901228-0037.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Business Brief -- Caesars World Inc.:
   Concern Completes Purchase
   Of Caesars New Jersey Unit
</HL>
<DATE>
12/28/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE 34
</SO>
<CO>
   CAW CJN
</CO>
<IN>
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
LODGING, HOTELS, MOTELS, LODGES, CAMPGROUNDS (LOD)
</IN>
<LP>
the 146,718 publicly held common shares of Caesars New Jersey
Inc. that it didn't already own, for about $3.3 million. As a
result, Caesars New Jersey became a wholly owned subsidiary
of Los Angeles-based Caesars World.
   Under the terms of the merger, former public shareholders
of Caesars New Jersey, which owns and operates Caesars
Atlantic City, are entitled to receive $22.25 a share in
cash, without interest.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The merger follows a recently completed tender offer by
<ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> for the common shares outstanding of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars
New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> that it did not already own. Under the tender
offer, which expired <DATE>Nov. 30</DATE>, some 2,029,227 shares were
tendered, and <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> increased its holdings to <PERCENT>99%</PERCENT> of
shares outstanding in <LOCATION>Caesars New Jersey</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION>'s shares on the <ORGANIZATION>American Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>
will be discontinued and registration of the shares under the
Securities Exchange Act of <DATE>1934</DATE> will be terminated. <ORGANIZATION>Caesars
World</ORGANIZATION> owns and operates hotels and casinos.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900720-0118
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900720-0118.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Caesars World Tender Offer
</HL>
<DATE>
07/20/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C9
</SO>
<CO>
   CJN CAW
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- Caesars World Inc. said it will make a
tender offer for the 13.4% stake it doesn't already hold in
Caesars New Jersey Inc. for $22 a share, or $48 million.
   Caesars World owns and operates hotels and casinos.
Caesars New Jersey owns and operates Caesars Atlantic City, a
hotel and casino.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> said it will make an offer next week for
about 2.2 million shares. It said it received a positive
fairness opinion for its financial adviser <ORGANIZATION>Wasserstein
Perella &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>.
   A spokesman said <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> was set up by <ORGANIZATION>Caesars
World</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1978</DATE> as a unit. Later that year the company offered
units and warrants in <LOCATION>Caesars New Jersey</LOCATION> to shareholders,
retaining about <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT>. In <DATE>1981</DATE>, the company bought back enough
shares to increase its stake to its current level of <PERCENT>86.6%</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900910-0046
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900910-0046.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Caesars World Inc.
   Again Extends Its Bid
   For New Jersey Unit
</HL>
<DATE>
09/10/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A7C
</SO>
<CO>
   CJN CAW
</CO>
<IN>
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
LODGING, HOTELS, MOTELS, LODGES, CAMPGROUNDS (LOD)
</IN>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- Caesars World Inc. again extended its
$22-a-share tender offer for the 2,175,945 shares of Caesars
New Jersey Inc. it doesn't already own to midnight Sept. 21
from last Friday.
   The hotel and casino operator holds about 86.6% of Caesars
New Jersey's 16,261,531 common shares outstanding. As of
Thursday, about 1,783,567 shares had been tendered.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> has agreed in principle to make an
additional payment of <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY> a share as part of a
settlement of lawsuits brought by some <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION>
shareholders. Final court approval isn't expected for at
least two months.
   Caesars also said the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION>
has scheduled a hearing <DATE>Sept. 19</DATE> to consider a petition filed
by a <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> holder alleging, among other things,
that the <MONEY>$22-a-share</MONEY> price is inadequate. The hearing is to
determine whether the petitioner has the standing to bring
the issue before the regulators.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112990-0196 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 315142 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 29, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 2; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
114 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BRIEFLY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Caesars Settlement Is Approved: <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> approved a 
settlement of lawsuits over <LOCATION>Caesars World</LOCATION>'s <MONEY>$22-per-share</MONEY> offer for the nearly 
2.2 million shares of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> that the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> company doesn't 
already own. 
</P>
<P>
Under the settlement, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> agreed to pay interest on the offering 
price for shares tendered and to make an additional 25-cent cash payment to 
shareholders whose stock is purchased under the offer, which is set to expire 
<DATE>Friday</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> also agreed to merge with <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> if it buys 
enough stock to give Caesars World a <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> stake in the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> company. 
<ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> owns <PERCENT>86.6%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SETTLEMENTS; SUITS; SECURITIES; CAESARS NEW JERSEY INC; CAESARS WORLD INC 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900726-0152
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900726-0152.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Caesars World Offer
</HL>
<DATE>
07/26/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A9
</SO>
<CO>
   CAW CJN
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- Caesars World Inc. began its previously
announced tender offer for the 13.4% stake it doesn't already
own in Caesars New Jersey Inc.
   The $22-a-share offer for 2.2 million shares is scheduled
to expire Aug. 21. Caesars World owns and operates hotels and
casinos. Caesars New Jersey owns and operates Caesars
Atlantic City, a hotel and casino.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Two shareholder suits seeking class-action status have
been filed against the <MONEY>$48 million</MONEY> offer, charging that it is
inadequate.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900924-0085
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900924-0085.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Caesars World Tender Offer
</HL>
<DATE>
09/24/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C10
</SO>
<CO>
   CJN CAW
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
</IN>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- Caesars World Inc. extended its $22-a-share
tender offer for the 2,175,945 shares of Caesars New Jersey
Inc. it doesn't already own to Oct. 17 from last Friday. The
offer was initially set to expire in August.
   Caesar's World, a hotel and casino operator, has agreed in
principle to make an additional payment to Caesars New Jersey
shareholders of 25 cents a share as part of a legal
settlement brought by some holders of the latter. Final court
approval isn't expected for at least two months.
</LP>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870908-0012 </DOCNO>
<HL> Caesars World
Drops Proposal
To Recapitalize
---
Casino Concern Starts Offer
To Buy 31% of Its Shares
For Up to $374 Million
---
By David B. Hilder
<DD> 09/08/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL)
BUYBACKS, REDEMPTIONS, SWAP OFFERS (BBK) </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> dropped its <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> recapitalization plan, which <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> gambling regulators refused to approve, and instead launched a tender offer to buy back <PERCENT>31%</PERCENT> of its shares at a cost of <MONEY>$325 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$374 million</MONEY>. 

   The operator of casino hotels began today a so-called Dutch auction tender offer for 11 million of its shares. 
Caesars said shares must be tendered at prices between <MONEY>$29.50</MONEY> and <MONEY>$34</MONEY> each. 
Under the Dutch auction procedures, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> will accept shares in the order of their specified prices, beginning with the lowest price, until the total reaches 11 million. 
The highest price required to reach the 11 million total will then be paid to all shares accepted. 

The offer will expire at <TIME>12:01 a.m. EDT</TIME> <DATE>Oct. 6</DATE> unless extended, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> said. 

   Caesars said it has been advised by its lawyers that the tender offer doesn't require approval by <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> gaming regulators. 
However, the company, which has casinos in both states, said if the regulators rule that their approval is required, Caesars reserves the right to cancel the offer. 

   Caesars also said the offer is conditioned on arranging the necessary financing of as much as <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY>, including expenses of the offer. 
Caesars said the offer would be financed with issuance of subordinated debt and bank borrowings. 
The company said its investment banker, <ORGANIZATION>Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, has advised that it is "highly confident" that the necessary debt securities can be sold. 

   <PERSON>Henry Gluck</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman and chief executive officer, said, "We believe that the purchase of shares through the offer constitutes an attractive investment for our company at this time because of recent market prices for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>'s shares, the company's reduced level of long-term debt and our business and financial prospects." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON> said the offer "should help to normalize the <LOCATION>Caesars World</LOCATION> shareholder base," which he said the company believes includes "a high percentage of short-term investors who purchased or held <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> stock in anticipation of receiving a dividend under the recapitalization plan." 

   The recapitalization plan, which was rejected <DATE>Aug. 12</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION>, would have paid a one-time cash dividend of <MONEY>$26.25</MONEY> to shareholders. 

   Caesars said yesterday it will withdraw its request that the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> commission reconsider its rejection of the recapitalization plan. 
A hearing on the request was scheduled for tomorrow. 

   In rejecting the plan, the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> commission said it "lacks any clear business" purpose and serves to "greatly enrich and permanently entrench" current management. 

   Caesars devised the recapitalization plan to fight off an unwanted takeover bid from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON>, who currently holds about <PERCENT>11%</PERCENT>, or 4.2 million shares, of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>. 

   A representative for <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said yesterday that <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> hadn't seen the offering papers and will withhold comment until he does. 

   In explaining its decision to abandon the recapitalization plan, in which the company would have issued <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> of new debt to pay the dividend, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> said it was advised by its lawyers that regulatory approval of the plan was unlikely. 
Caesars also cited "volatility of the financial markets and the effects of delay and uncertainty." 

   Caesars said neither the company nor its directors were expressing an opinion on whether shareholders should tender their shares under the company's offer. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON>, however, said in a statement that the offer "provides all shareholders with a means of liquidating a portion and possibly all of their <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> shares without the market disruption that might otherwise occur if they were sold in the open market." 

   A <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said all trades of post-dividend <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> shares, which were made on a when-issued basis, will be canceled because the dividend won't be paid. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900723-0021
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900723-0021.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Business Brief -- Caesars World Inc.:
   Holders File Suits Over Bid
   For Caesars New Jersey
</HL>
<DATE>
07/23/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   CAW CJN
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<LP>
   Two shareholder lawsuits seeking class action status have
been filed against Caesars World Inc. in the wake of its
announced intention to make a tender offer for the 13.4%
stake it doesn't already hold in Caesars New Jersey Inc.
   In a suit filed in U.S. District Court in Los Angeles, an
investor alleges that the company's $22-a-share, or $48
million, offer is inadequate and that it didn't seek
competing acquisition proposals. Another suit filed in state
court by four investors names 10 officers and directors of
the company as defendants and seeks an injunction blocking
the offer. Caesars World, based in Los Angeles, owns and
operates hotels and casinos.
</LP>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870324-0052 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sosnoff Discussed
Possible Joint Bid
for Caesars World
---
By Laurie P. Cohen
<DD> 03/24/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW PRAT SM
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON> said he had discussions with <ORGANIZATION>Pratt Hotel Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark Corp.</ORGANIZATION> about a possible joint venture to acquire <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The money manager and investor said that he, <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION> may jointly discuss with Caesars World a "friendly" transaction in which the three would "participate on an equal basis" in a joint venture. 

   The discussions among the three parties "are not currently being actively pursued," <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said in a news release. 
He added that it was uncertain whether talks would resume in the future. 
While <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> didn't say when the discussions had occurred, <LOCATION>Pratt</LOCATION> is understood to have initiated the talks about two weeks ago. 
<ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION>, which owns <PERCENT>36%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Pratt</LOCATION>, was brought in soon after. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> wasn't available to comment, but a source close to him said "these guys (<LOCATION>Pratt</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION>) approached him and he thought it could be a good deal." 

   Dallas-based Pratt is a hotel and casino owner. 
<ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION>, also based in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, has interests in real estate and financial services, and is a major hotel franchisee. 

   As previously reported, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s $28-a-share tender offer for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>, a Los Angeles-based gambling concern, was rejected as "inadequate" last week. 
He is <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>'s largest shareholder -- with a <PERCENT>13.6%</PERCENT> stake. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> spokesman declined comment on <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s statement. 

   Separately, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said he extended the expiration date of his offer for the <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> common stock he doesn't already own to 12:01 a.m. 
<DATE>May 16 EST</DATE>. 
The offer had been scheduled to expire on <DATE>April 3</DATE>. 
So far, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said, "only a negligible number of shares have been tendered" under the offer, which began earlier this month. 

   In <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>'s common closed at <MONEY>$28.75</MONEY>, down <MONEY>87.5 cents</MONEY>. 
Some Wall Street traders said that any <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION> and Pratt involvement with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> would make it less likely that a bidding war for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> would erupt. 

   Caesars World's financial adviser, <ORGANIZATION>Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, is understood to have contacted a number of companies to drum up interest in a friendly purchase of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION> was among the companies that <ORGANIZATION>Drexel</ORGANIZATION> contacted in the past two weeks, sources said. 

   <PERSON>William S. Friedman</PERSON>, vice chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION>, said that "a prime factor in our getting involved is that we're licensed (to operate casinos) in both <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>," where <LOCATION>Caesars World</LOCATION> has hotels. 

   <PERSON>Jack E. Pratt Sr.</PERSON>, <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> chairman, said <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION> will say today in a <ORGANIZATION>Securities and Exchange Commission</ORGANIZATION> filing that they are having talks with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> on a possible joint venture. 
He said the companies "plan to work with <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> on a friendly basis." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said that "several preliminary contacts" with <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> representatives haven't "resulted in any indication that (<LOCATION>Caesars World</LOCATION>) wishes to" negotiate with him, <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> or <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor's bid had been conditioned on his obtaining approval to control casinos from gaming authorities in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said yesterday that he hasn't been assured that "the necessary regulatory review would be completed on or prior to the original expiration date" of his tender offer. 
He said if the approval process is delayed, he may have to again extend the expiration date. 

   A source familiar with both <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> said that while <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> could raise the <MONEY>$725.2 million</MONEY> needed to complete his offer, the investor felt "he needed an experienced hotel operator to convince people he was serious about really" buying <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870316-0082 </DOCNO>
<HL> Caesars Rejects
Sosnoff's Bid
As 'Inadequate'
---
Gambling Concern Studies
Possible Restructuring,
Sale to a Friendly Suitor
---
By Laurie P. Cohen and Roy J. Harris Jr.
<DD> 03/16/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW ATL UAL GNG
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL)
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> is exploring restructuring or the sale of the company to a friendly suitor after rejecting <ORGANIZATION>Martin T. Sosnoff</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$28-a-share</MONEY> tender offer for the gambling concern as "inadequate." 

   A source familiar with <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> said that the primary options that the Los Angeles-based company and its financial advisers are studying are a management-sponsored leveraged buyout or a major stock buyback. 

   The suggestion that competing bidders might be sought spurred an increase in the price of Caesars shares. 
In <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> stock closed at <MONEY>$29.375</MONEY> a share, up <MONEY>$1.375</MONEY>, on heavy volume. 

   But <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>, which owns and operates the <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION> luxury hotel-casino in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, declined to say whether it had already begun talks with other parties about a competing offer. 

   In a <ORGANIZATION>Securities and Exchange Commission</ORGANIZATION> filing <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the company said that the mention of possible suitors "might jeopardize the continuation of any discussions or negotiations that the company may conduct." 

   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' largest shareholder, said he still seeks a "friendly acquisition" of the company despite its rejection of his offer. 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said he believes his offer is fair to all of the company's shareholders and represents a significant premium over recent and historic prices for the company's shares. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> is understood to be considering the possibility of increasing his bid for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>. 
"He feels he has access to the means to up the ante," said an individual familiar with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s bid for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>. 
"Whether he will is a matter of further study for him." 

   In rejecting <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s bid for the 25.9 million <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> common shares he doesn't already own, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> cited "uncertainties" in the offer, including the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> money manager's ability to finance the bid and to win <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> regulatory approval allowing him to become a casino operator. 

   Caesars said in the <ORGANIZATION>SEC</ORGANIZATION> filing that <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s bid "raises serious legal questions under the federal securities law," but didn't elaborate. 
The company said its financial adviser, <ORGANIZATION>Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, issued a written opinion concurring with its decision to spurn <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s bid. 

   Some stock analysts and Wall Street traders speculated that other possible buyers for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> might include <ORGANIZATION>UAL Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the Chicago-based parent of <ORGANIZATION>United Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> real estate developer <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>, investor <PERSON>Kirk Kerkorian</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Las Vegas-based Golden Nugget Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   But <PERSON>Mr. Kerkorian</PERSON> has denied that he is interested in <LOCATION>Caesars</LOCATION> and a source close to <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON> said the developer has "zero interest" in the company. 
<ORGANIZATION>UAL</ORGANIZATION> officials weren't available to comment, but a source familiar with the company said that while <ORGANIZATION>UAL</ORGANIZATION> "could be interested," it "would take a long time and be a big hassle (for <ORGANIZATION>UAL</ORGANIZATION>) to get licenses" to own and operate casinos in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>. 

   Golden Nugget, which is already licensed to own and operate casinos in both states, has plenty of available cash if it wishes to make an offer for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>. 
While officials of the hotel and casino concern weren't available to comment, sources familiar with <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> said that the company's management isn't likely to accept a Golden Nugget bid. 
"They'd rather have Sosnoff than Golden Nugget," said one of the sources, adding that Golden Nugget's chairman, <PERSON>Steve Wynn</PERSON>, "would probably fire everyone in a month," and that <PERSON>Caesars</PERSON>' chairman, <PERSON>Henry Gluck</PERSON>, "is smart enough to know that." 

   Neither <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON> nor any of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' advisers have had any conversations with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> or his representatives since <DATE>last Monday</DATE>, sources said. 
But <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON> may be reeling from his first contact with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> as a bidder for Caesars <DATE>March 8</DATE>. 

   According to one source, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> first notified <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON> in a phone call to <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION> that a tender offer was to be announced in a newspaper advertisement last <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>. 
When the investor reached <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON> by telling a receptionist that the call was urgent, the <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> chairman was on the dais at a televised celebration of the <DATE>20th anniversary of</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION>, which was about to begin. 

   The source said that the surprised <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON> is understood to have responded, "<PERSON>Marty</PERSON>, I always knew you'd come after me some time." 

   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' lawyers appeared in federal court in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE> to argue that a suit <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> filed against the company should be considered instead in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
As previously reported, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s complaint, filed last <DATE>Monday</DATE>, alleges that <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> and its directors breached their fiduciary duty to shareholders by approving anti-takeover measures last year. 
A decision on the matter is expected later this week. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870909-0058 </DOCNO>
<HL> Caesars World's Move to Abandon Plan
For Recapitalization Praised by Analysts
---
By David J. Jefferson
<DD> 09/09/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL)
BUYBACKS, REDEMPTIONS, SWAP OFFERS (BBK)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s decision to drop its <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> recapitalization plan in favor of a stock buy-back was praised by financial analysts, although the stock market reaction was less sanguine. 

   In <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> shares closed at <MONEY>$29.50</MONEY>, up <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY>, on volume of 749,600 shares. 

   Under the original recapitalization, devised to fend off an unwanted takeover bid from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> holders would have received a one-time dividend of <MONEY>$26.25</MONEY> a share and stock in the reconstituted company. 
The tender offer that replaced that plan will be at prices between <MONEY>$29.50</MONEY> and <MONEY>$34</MONEY> a share, or a total of between <MONEY>$325 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$374 million</MONEY> for 11 million of Caesars 35.2 million shares outstanding. 

   "This is probably what Caesars should have done in the beginning," said <PERSON>Harold Vogel</PERSON>, a securities analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
He said the new plan leaves the hotel-casino concern with far less debt and would be more acceptable to <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> gambling regulators, if regulators need to approve the buy-back at all. 

   The earlier recapitalization plan was rejected by <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> gambling regulators <DATE>Aug. 12</DATE> on the grounds that it loaded Caesars with debt while lacking a clear business purpose and serving to "greatly enrich and permanently entrench" current management. 

   Caesars, operator of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Caesars Atlantic City</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, needed both states' approval for the recapitalization. 
After announcing the tender offer, the company said it planned to withdraw an application for the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION> to rehear the recapitalization case. 
Caesars said it doesn't believe the stock buy-back requires state regulatory approval. 

   <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Walter N. Read</PERSON> said he wasn't sure whether the commission would need to approve the plan. 
He said <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> "has obviously gotten rid of some of the things we objected to in the recapitalization," but he declined to say whether he favors the buy-back. 

   Industry observers said that the buy-back leaves Caesars more vulnerable to a takeover attempt than it would have been under a recapitalization. 
The buy-back "provides less of a guarantee" against takeover attempts, said <PERSON>Mr. Vogel</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch</ORGANIZATION>. 
He added, however, that "I don't see anyone coming in after these gaming companies now anyhow because of the enormous licensing problems." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Vogel</PERSON>, however, didn't rule out the possibility of <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> making another pass at <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> holds 4.2 million Caesars shares, or about <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> of the total outstanding, and his stake would increase to <PERCENT>17.4%</PERCENT> if he didn't tender shares under the company's offer. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> hasn't been available for comment since <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> announced plans for the tender offer <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 

   But <PERSON>Marvin B. Roffman</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Philadelphia-based Janney Montgomery Scott Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, said he "can't see Sosnoff jumping in at all." 
<PERSON>Mr. Roffman</PERSON> said he believes <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> "saw the writing on the wall" when the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> commission rejected the Caesars plan, and thus wouldn't tempt the same fate by renewing his highly leveraged bid. 
<PERSON>Mr. Roffman</PERSON> said the state commission ruling delivered a message that "we don't want someone coming in here and leveraging up a company to take control of it." 

   Under the buy-back, which began yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> will purchase about <PERCENT>31%</PERCENT> of its shares outstanding through a so-called Dutch auction tender offer. 
Caesars will accept the shares in the order of the prices that holders have specified, within the stated range, until total shares tendered reach 11 million. 
The highest price required to reach the total will then be paid to holders of all the shares accepted. 
The offer ends at <TIME>12:01 a.m. EDT</TIME> <DATE>Oct. 6</DATE>, unless extended. 

   The stock market reaction to the new plan "shows that the arbitragers, who seem to be the dominant holders, are disappointed that <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> isn't pursuing another recapitalization," said <PERSON>Mark Manson</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>New York-based Donaldson Lufkin &amp; Jenrette</ORGANIZATION>. 
But he said the buy-back leaves Caesars a "fairly attractive" investment, with a much stronger balance sheet and healthier earnings potential than if the company had followed through with the recapitalization. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870813-0083 </DOCNO>
<HL> Caesars World Recapitalization Plan
Is Rejected by New Jersey Commission
---
By David J. Jefferson
<DD> 08/13/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW CJN
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION> rejected <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s proposed <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> recapitalization, saying it "lacks any clear business purpose." 

   Commission Chairman <PERSON>Walter N. Read</PERSON> said he had "very real doubt about the financial responsibility of the proposal," which <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> designed earlier this year to thwart a takeover attempt by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor <ORGANIZATION>Martin T. Sosnoff</ORGANIZATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> in <DATE>June</DATE> dropped a sweetened <MONEY>$35-a-share</MONEY> bid for the company and said he couldn't justify the cost of continuing the <MONEY>$1.11 billion</MONEY> takeover effort. 
He couldn't be reached yesterday to comment on the ruling. 

   The recapitalization plan, which calls for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' shareholders to receive a one-time cash dividend of <MONEY>$26.25</MONEY> a share and stock in the reconstituted company, was approved by shareholders last month. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Read</PERSON> said the plan will burden Caesars with "staggering debt." 
He added that <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' management "proposes to pile on this financial burden to pay shareholders a huge dividend to foster their approval of proposals, which will greatly enrich and permanently entrench present corporate officials." 

   Los Angeles-based Caesars, operator of the <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION> hotel-casino in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Caesars Atlantic City</LOCATION> hotel-casino in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, said it was "disappointed" with the commission's ruling, but declined to comment further. 
The company is awaiting an <DATE>Aug. 20</DATE> ruling from the <ORGANIZATION>Nevada Gaming Commission</ORGANIZATION> on the recapitalization plan. 

   The <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> commission, which has regulatory authority over the state's gambling operations and is empowered to issue and revoke gambling licenses, voted 4-1 against the plan. 
A favorable vote by at least four commissioners was required for approval of the Caesars plan. 

   Commissioner <PERSON>Valerie H. Armstrong</PERSON> cast the only vote in support of the plan, saying <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> had provided sufficient evidence that it wouldn't buckle under the strain of the <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> of new debt required to finance the recapitalization. 

   After the commission's action, one Wall Street executive suggested that <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> might sell its <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> operations, using proceeds to help recapitalize the company -- a move that would be similar to one by Los Angeles-based <ORGANIZATION>Hilton Hotels Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 
After <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE> denied <ORGANIZATION>Hilton</ORGANIZATION> a casino license for its <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION> hotel, it sold the property to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> real estate developer <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> had dropped his bid one week after receiving an unfavorable federal court ruling. 
In <DATE>June</DATE>, a federal judge in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> enjoined him from continuing his tender offer on the ground that it violated a <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> rule governing the financing of corporate takeovers. 

   Still, <PERSON>Mr. Read</PERSON> rejected <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' claim that it needed to proceed with the recapitalization even after <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> dropped his bid. 
"It is unclear why another takeover effort would be inevitable, considering the results of the last such effort and the regulatory hurdles involved," <PERSON>Mr. Read</PERSON> said. 
He also said it wasn't clear "why a takeover would necessarily be disadvantageous to the stockholders if the bidder received regulatory approvals." 

   In issuing its ruling, the commission attempted to distinguish the <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> plan from a similar <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY> recapitalization of <ORGANIZATION>Holiday Corp.</ORGANIZATION> approved by the commission in <DATE>April</DATE>. 
<LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, Tenn.-based Holiday, a hotel and gambling concern, proposed its plan last <DATE>November</DATE> when it was rumored to be a takeover target. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Read</PERSON> described the Holiday plan as essentially "an acceleration" of a long-term strategy to dispose of assets and move toward managing properties instead of owning them. 
But he said that <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> recapitalization plan would replace an existing policy of pursuing internal growth and expansion. 
He added that <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> proposes to "abandon a prudent, successful corporate strategy for an imprudent, risky one." 
The company's equity, he added, would become "a lowly foothill beneath its Alpine debt." 

   Securities analysts who follow the gambling industry were surprised by the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> commission's action. 
And one said he expects Caesars to appeal the ruling. 

   "It's palpably absurd, especially because this is the commission" that approved the <ORGANIZATION>Holiday Corp.</ORGANIZATION> plan, said <PERSON>Steven Eisenberg</PERSON>, an analyst with Bear, <ORGANIZATION>Stearns &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> "Caesars has adequately demonstrated that its cash flows are such that it won't have to sell one asset, and can still generate cash to service the debt. 
That suggests the company is very, very strong," <PERSON>Mr. Eisenberg</PERSON> said. 

   The <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> action came after the close of the stock market yesterday. 

   Caesars operates its <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION> hotel-casino through an <PERCENT>86.6%</PERCENT>-owned subsidiary, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870310-0003 </DOCNO>
<HL> Caesers World Stock Leaps as Investors
Anticipate Competing Bids for Concern
---
By Roy J. Harris Jr. and Laurie P. Cohen
<DD> 03/10/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW ATL GNG
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s stock price rose sharply yesterday, indicating that investors expect competing bids to follow <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor <ORGANIZATION>Martin T. Sosnoff</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$28-a-share</MONEY> offer for the Los Angeles-based gambling concern. 

   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Henry Gluck</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>, said the company's board will study the <ORGANIZATION>Sosnoff</ORGANIZATION> offer with legal and financial advisers before making a recommendation to holders. 
A spokesman declined to comment further on <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s offer, valued at <MONEY>$725.2 million</MONEY>, for the <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> shares he doesn't already own. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> holds a <PERCENT>13.6%</PERCENT> stake in <LOCATION>Caesars</LOCATION>, or about 4.1 million of the 30 million shares outstanding. 

   In <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> common closed at <MONEY>$27.75</MONEY> a share, up <MONEY>$3.25</MONEY>, on volume of 3.3 million shares. 

   Some securities analysts who follow the gambling industry suggested that higher bids are likely and that <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> might have positioned himself to turn a profit on his current Caesars stake. 

   "He hasn't ever bought and run a company, and he probably would accept a higher offer for his shares," <PERSON>Dennis Forst</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles-based Seidler Amdec Securities Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said. 
He said yesterday's trading, in which <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> shares rose as high as <MONEY>$28.50</MONEY> before easing slightly, suggests that Wall Street believes "this is the first salvo (in bidding for Caesars), but not the last." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Forst</PERSON> said he believes Caesars management "definitely prefers to remain independent and build the company along current lines." 

   <PERSON>Marvin B. Roffman</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Janney Montgomery Scott Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, said acquiring Caesars at <MONEY>$28</MONEY> a share would be "a steal." 
He said he believes <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s real goal is "to make money buying undervalued situations" rather than by operating casinos. 

   Among parties analysts mentioned as possible competing bidders are <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> investor <PERSON>Kirk Kerkorian</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Tracinda Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Nev.-based Golden Nugget Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, both of which have experience with the kind of luxury hotel-casino operations that <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> represents. 

   A spokesman for <PERSON>Mr. Kerkorian</PERSON>, however, said <ORGANIZATION>Tracinda</ORGANIZATION> isn't interested in bidding for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>, which operates the <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION> casino in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> among other properties and owns <PERCENT>86.6%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars New Jersey Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Golden Nugget officials couldn't be reached for comment. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>, who made his offer through newly formed <ORGANIZATION>MTS Acquisition Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, continued to insist yesterday that his offer is "for real" and dismissed speculation that it might be an attempt to put Caesars in play in the takeover field. 

   The investor also gave some details of his financing plans, which he said involve loan commitments valid for six months. 
In a letter to <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON>, he said <ORGANIZATION>Marine Midland Bank</ORGANIZATION> had agreed to lend <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> for the acquisition and to use its "best efforts" to syndicate an additional <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> in loans. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> also said in the letter that his financial adviser, <ORGANIZATION>PaineWebber Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, had said in writing that, "subject to market conditions," it is "highly confident" it can arrange commitments for as much as <MONEY>$475 million</MONEY> in financing. 
He said the offer "provides a fair and generous opportunity for all the company's shareholders to maximize the value of their investment." 

   He made the tender offer for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> without consulting the company or its board, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said, because his advisers had "repeatedly stressed" the Caesars management's "lack of responsiveness in the past." 

   Caesars World, which last year turned down <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s request for a seat on the board, retained <ORGANIZATION>Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ORGANIZATION> to help study the offer. 
Although <ORGANIZATION>Drexel</ORGANIZATION> traditionally has served as its investment banker, the firm also has represented <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> before. 
It managed the investor's initial public offering last year of <ORGANIZATION>Atalanta/Sosnoff Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, of which <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> is chairman. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> vigorously denied a report that he had tried to sell his <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> stake to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> real estate developer <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>. 
A source close to <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON> yesterday said he had been offered the <PERSON>Sosnoff</PERSON> stake "within the last month." 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said: "That's absolutely incorrect. 
I haven't talked to <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON> at all about Caesars." 
He said <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON>'s attorney called him about <DATE>two months ago</DATE>, but said, "I never returned the call." 

   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Moody's Investors Service Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Standard &amp; Poor's Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said they were considering downgrading <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> debt ratings because of the Sosnoff offer. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Moody's</ORGANIZATION> said it is reviewing its single-B-1 rating on about <MONEY>$215 million</MONEY> of subordinated debt of <LOCATION>Caesars World</LOCATION> and its <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Finance Corp.</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary. 
<ORGANIZATION>S&amp;P</ORGANIZATION> said it placed a total of about <MONEY>$231 million</MONEY> of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> and the finance unit's debt on its CreditWatch list with negative implications. 
Ratings under study by <ORGANIZATION>S&amp;P</ORGANIZATION> are double-B on <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> senior debt and single-B-plus on subordinated debt of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> and the unit. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870709-0042 </DOCNO>
<HL> Caesars World Holders
Clear Special Dividend,
Recapitalization Plan</HL>
<DD> 07/09/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said its shareholders approved the company's proposed <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> recapitalization plan and payment of a special dividend of <MONEY>$26.25</MONEY> a share. 

   The hotel and casino operator said 17.5 million shares were voted in favor of both the plan and dividend and 4.6 million were voted against. 
Among the shares voted in dissent were 4.2 million held by <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor and money manager, a <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said. 
Caesars had 30.5 million common shares outstanding as of <DATE>April 30</DATE>. 

   As previously reported, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> last month dropped his sweetened <MONEY>$35-a-share</MONEY> bid for the company, saying he could no longer justify the cost to himself and the company of continuing the <MONEY>$1.11 billion</MONEY> takeover effort. 
A week earlier, a federal judge in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> enjoined <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> from continuing his tender offer on the ground that it violated a <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> rule governing the financing of corporate takeovers. 

   Caesars said regulatory officials in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> have yet to approve the recapitalization and dividend, which the company designed to fend off <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s advances. 
The <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION> is scheduled to review the plan next week, although <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> said it doesn't expect the commission to reach a decision until the end of the month. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Nevada Gaming Commission</ORGANIZATION> is scheduled to consider next <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>Nevada Gaming Control Board</ORGANIZATION>'s recommendation that the plan be approved. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870422-0072 </DOCNO>
<HL> Caesars Holder
Seeks to Remove
4 Inside Directors
---
By Laurie P. Cohen
<DD> 04/22/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL)
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON>, whose sweetened <MONEY>$32-a-share</MONEY> tender offer for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> was rebuffed, said he is soliciting shareholder consent to remove the company's inside directors. 

   In a letter to <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> holders, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said he is seeking to remove four of the company's nine directors, "leaving in place a truly independent board that can review my amended offer and any other alternatives available to the company." 

   In the letter, the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor and money manager said that the company's inside directors "have demonstrated that they are not principally motivated by the sincere desire to assure that shareholders receive maximum value for their shares." 

   To succeed, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> needs votes of consent from a majority of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' 30.2 million shares outstanding. 
As the largest shareholder of the hotel and casino operator, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> already owns four million shares, or <PERCENT>13.3%</PERCENT> of the common shares outstanding. 
His latest tender offer expires <DATE>June 19</DATE>. 
In accordance with <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' bylaws, stock of record <DATE>March 27</DATE> is eligible to vote. 

   The directors <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> seeks to remove are <PERSON>Henry Gluck</PERSON>, chairman and chief executive officer; <PERSON>J. Terrence Lanni</PERSON>, president and chief operating officer; <PERSON>Philip Ball</PERSON>, senior vice president and general counsel; and <PERSON>M. Peter Schweitzer</PERSON>, vice chairman. 

   In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> had no immediate comment on <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s letter. 

   Earlier this week, in a petition filed with the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> unveiled plans to cut back some of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' operations if his takeover is successful. 

   Among the suggested cuts, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said he would close <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> corporate headquarters because it is "unnecessary in an industry where operational decision-making occurs on-site." 
He indicated, however, that he would encourage "substantially all of the existing management" to remain with the company. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> also said he possibly would discontinue the company's operations unrelated to its hotel and casino businesses, including investments in retailing and some limited food service operations. 
He said the cuts could save <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> between <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> and <MONEY>$7 million</MONEY> annually. 

   To counter <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s original <MONEY>$28-a-share</MONEY> takeover bid, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> proposed a recapitalization that included a one-time cash dividend of <MONEY>$25</MONEY> a share and the assumption of about <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> new debt. 

   In rejecting <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s sweetened <MONEY>$932.2 million</MONEY> tender offer bid earlier this month, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> said it might sweeten its recapitalization plan, which some Wall Street traders have valued at <MONEY>$30</MONEY> to <MONEY>$31.50</MONEY> a share. 

   Consent solicitations are used infrequently as alternatives to proxy battles. 
Only a few states permit such solicitations, including <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, where Caesars is incorporated. 
The consent process "is an unusual approach with inconsistent results," said <PERSON>John Gavin</PERSON>, executive vice president of <ORGANIZATION>D.F. King &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> proxy solicitation concern. 

   <PERSON>Asher Edelman</PERSON> used a consent solicitation in his successful bid to win control of <ORGANIZATION>Datapoint Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Joseph A. Frates</PERSON>, an <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> investor, failed in his attempt to get shareholder consent to take control of <ORGANIZATION>Kaiser Aluminum &amp; Chemical Corp.</ORGANIZATION> last year. 
And <PERSON>Irwin Jacobs</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> investor, also was unsuccessful in using a solicitation in his abortive bid for <ORGANIZATION>Pabst Brewing Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1982</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870528-0105 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sosnoff Misses
Date to Oust
Caesars's Board
---
By David J. Jefferson
<DD> 05/28/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said investor <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON> missed the deadline to present written consents from shareholders to remove the company's inside directors. 

   As previously reported, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>, who is making a <MONEY>$32-a-share</MONEY> hostile tender offer for the gambling concern, last month began soliciting shareholder consents to remove from <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' nine-member board <PERSON>Henry Gluck</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' chairman and chief executive officer; <PERSON>J. Terrence Lanni</PERSON>, president and chief operating officer; <PERSON>Philip Ball</PERSON>, senior vice president and general counsel; and <PERSON>M. Peter Schweitzer</PERSON>, vice chairman. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> also wanted to amend certain provisions of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' articles of incorporation and bylaws. 

   Under <PERSON>Caesars</PERSON>' bylaws, written consents must be presented by the 60th day following the solicitation. 
The record date for the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor and money manager's consent solicitation was <DATE>March 27</DATE>; the deadline was <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 

   Consent solicitations are used infrequently as alternatives to proxy battles, and just a handful of states permit them, including <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, where Caesars is incorporated. 

   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> said a number of meetings had been scheduled that will relate to the company's petition for approval of a nearly <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> recapitalization plan. 

   The plan, designed to thwart <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s takeover attempt, would require Caesars to incur <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> of new debt, and would give shareholders a one-time cash dividend of <MONEY>$26.25</MONEY> a share and stock in the reconstituted company. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION> tentatively scheduled a <DATE>June 16</DATE> special meeting to review the petition. 

   The gaming commission also will review <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s petition for approval of his tender offer. 

   In addition, the <ORGANIZATION>Nevada Gaming Control Board</ORGANIZATION> has tenatively scheduled a <DATE>June 10</DATE> special meeting to review <PERSON>Caesars</PERSON>' proposal to reincorporate in <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION> as part of the recapitalization plan, along with certain aspects of the proposed financing. 

   The board will then forward its recommendations to the <ORGANIZATION>Nevada Gaming Commission</ORGANIZATION>, which is set to review the plan at a <DATE>June 18</DATE> special meeting. 

   Caesars said <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> gaming authorities will review <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s offer concurrently with the company's plan. 

   Caesars cautioned that while it believes it will receive the necessary approvals from <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> gaming authorities, "There can be no assurance that such meetings will take place as scheduled, and the company is unable to predict with certainty when a determination will be made on these matters, or that such approvals will be forthcoming." 

   Caesars shareholders are to vote on the recapitalization plan at a special meeting <DATE>June 12</DATE> here. 
That meeting is unaffected by the scheduling of the meetings with gaming officials, a spokesman for the company said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870402-0131 </DOCNO>
<HL> Pratt, Southmark
Drop Plans to Join
Bid For Caesars</HL>
<DD> 04/02/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> PRAT SM CAW
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor and money manager, said <ORGANIZATION>Pratt Hotel Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark Corp.</ORGANIZATION> dropped their offer to join his <MONEY>$28-a-share</MONEY> bid to acquire <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said his tender offer for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> shares was still in effect. 

   In early March <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said he made a tender offer to buy the <PERCENT>86.4%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> common shares outstanding that he doesn't already own, in a transaction valued at <MONEY>$725.2 million</MONEY>. 
In mid-March, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>, the Los Angeles-based owner of casino hotels, rejected <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s bid as inadequate. 
<ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> also sued <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> in federal court in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to block the tender offer, saying the offer was "illusory" and merely designed to increase the price of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> shares so he can sell his shares at a profit. 

   Last week <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said he had held discussions with <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION>, who were interested in joining him in a friendly transaction. 
But in a statement yesterday, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION> furnished a notice terminating the talks. 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said that he hadn't held discussions with the two companies since <DATE>March 20</DATE>, but that under an agreement the Dallas-based companies said they wouldn't make a competing tender offer or bid for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> until they formally terminated their discussions with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>. 

   In <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jack E. Pratt Sr.</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Pratt Hotel</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION> ended joint-venture talks with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> because "both parties couldn't agree to move forward." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Pratt</PERSON> said he couldn't comment on whether <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION> might make an offer for Caesars themselves or propose another joint venture. 
"We want to expand and we're looking at a number of opportunties, but it would be premature to say what we plan to do," he said. 

   Pratt is a hotel and casino owner, and <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION>, which owns <PERCENT>36%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Pratt</LOCATION>, has interests in real estate and financial services. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said his tender offer expires <DATE>May 16</DATE> at <TIME>12:01 a.m. EDT</TIME>. 
In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> declined to comment. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881215-0251 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-15-88 0117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Caesars-Trump Bjt   12-15 0590</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Caesars-Trump, Bjt,0607</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trump May Try To Get Control Of Caesars World</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYCE A. VENEZIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The price of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> stock
rose just hours after the company announced that developer <PERSON>Donald
Trump</PERSON> had invested in the gaming company.
   At the close of the day <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> on Wall Street, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>
stock had jumped <MONEY>$4.12</MONEY>{ a share to <MONEY>$29.37</MONEY>{ in consolidated <ORGANIZATION>New York
Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> trading.
   The activity led at least one gaming analyst to credit <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> with
being a shrewd investor.
   ``I take my hat off to <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>,'' said <PERSON>Marvin Roffman</PERSON> of the
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> investment firm <ORGANIZATION>Janney Montgomery Scott Inc.</ORGANIZATION> ``It was a
wise investment to buy into <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>. ... We've always felt <PERSON>Caesars</PERSON>
was one of the best-managed companies in the industry, and we felt
it was worth up to <MONEY>$40</MONEY> a share.''
   Trump has asked the federal government for a ruling on whether
his investment would violate antitrust laws. He filed notice with
desire to possibly buy more than <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> common
stock.
   Although neither <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> nor <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> will say how much <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>
already owns, the filing was made under the Hart-Scott-Rodino Act,
which requires companies or individuals to seek such a ruling once
they have acquired at least <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY> worth of stock in a company.
   Caesars World officials refused comment on <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>'s notice, ``due
to the confusing content of this notice,'' according to a statement.
Trump also refused to comment <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``Such filings are very confidential and he's been advised not to
comment,'' said <PERSON>Susan Heilbron</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> owns three gaming halls: <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Hotel Casino</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Tahoe</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>.
   In the notice, <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> said he ``has the good-faith intention,
subject to price, availability and necessary approvals, if any, to
acquire such number of shares ... to hold in excess of <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of
the outstanding voting securities'' of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Roffman</PERSON> said, however, that <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> would not be successful in a
hostile takeover of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>. In a similar situation <DATE>last year</DATE>
involving investor <PERSON>Martin Sosnoff</PERSON>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> gaming regulators
blocked <ORGANIZATION>Sosnoff</ORGANIZATION>'s highly leveraged takeover proposal.
   In a similar situation involving <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey's Casino
Control Commission</ORGANIZATION> would probably also reject a highly leveraged
deal, <PERSON>Roffman</PERSON> suggested.
   ``<PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>'s style is not cash, it's to borrow,'' the analyst
said. ``He has (accumulated) a debt of <MONEY>$1.235 billion</MONEY> outstanding on
his three <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION> properties.''
   Under <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> law, <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> can own only three gaming halls in
the state. So far, he is licensed for two _ Trump Plaza and <ORGANIZATION>Trump
Castle</ORGANIZATION> casino hotels. A third, the massive <ORGANIZATION>Taj Mahal</ORGANIZATION>, is under
construction and expected to be completed in <DATE>1990</DATE>.
   ``I think he'll sell one anyway in the future, because it doesn't
make sense to market three in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Roffman</PERSON> said. ``But
the bottom line with this Caesars notice is that <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON> is
interested in making money, not owning another casino. He simply
bought into an undervalued situation and will come out with a
profit.''
   This is not the first time that <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> has invested in a rival
casino company.
   He made a <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> profit from investing in <ORGANIZATION>Holiday Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
stock and a <MONEY>$24 million</MONEY> profit on <ORGANIZATION>Bally Manufacturing Corp.</ORGANIZATION> stock.
He also bought a small amount of stock in <ORGANIZATION>Golden Nugget Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a
move that his competitor, Golden Nugget Chairman <PERSON>Steve Wynn</PERSON>, called
a ``publicity stunt.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870309-0011 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sosnoff Makes
Bid for Caesars
Of $28 a Share
---
By Laurie P.                                                  </HL>
<SO>  </SO>
<IN> CAW CJN
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL)
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor and money manager, disclosed a bid to acquire the shares of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> he doesn't own for <MONEY>$28</MONEY> each, or <MONEY>$725.2 million</MONEY>. 

   Under terms of the offer, which begins today, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> would acquire Los Angeles-based <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>, a profitable hotel-casino and real estate concern, through <ORGANIZATION>MTS Acquisition Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a company formed for the proposed purchase. 
The <MONEY>$28-a-share</MONEY> offer is set to expire at <TIME>12:01 a.m. EST</TIME> <DATE>April 4</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> is <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>'s largest holder with the equivalent of a <PERCENT>13.6%</PERCENT> stake, or about 4.1 million of the company's 30 million shares outstanding. 
The <MONEY>$28</MONEY> price values all of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> at <MONEY>$840 million</MONEY>. 

   The offer is conditioned on the approval of the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Nevada Gaming Commission</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>State Gaming Control Board of Nevada</ORGANIZATION>. 
Those agencies regulate casinos in those states. 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> also must have sufficient financing before the offer can be completed. 


   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said in an interview <TIME>last night</TIME> that financing of the offer would be managed by <ORGANIZATION>PaineWebber Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Marine Midland Banks Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> declined to elaborate on why he was bidding for the company, pending a news release, which he said would be issued "shortly." 
He said, however, that he believes that <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>'s management is "pretty good." 

   In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said the company hadn't been aware of the offer and that it would need time to study it before making a comment. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Atalanta/Sosnoff Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, has held a stake in <LOCATION>Caesars World</LOCATION> since <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
Last <DATE>September</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> filed for permission under federal antitrust laws to raise his stake in the company to as much as <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> has asked several times for a seat on the board of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>, a move that the company has rejected. 

   Some industry analysts suggested that <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>, by bidding for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>, may be hoping to attract the attention of other potential bidders. 

   "<PERSON>Marty</PERSON> has been trying to put the company in play for a long time," said <PERSON>Daniel Lee</PERSON>, analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ORGANIZATION> who follows the gaming industry. 
"I'm not sure he's serious." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Lee</PERSON> said that <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> had plenty of opportunities in the past to increase his <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> stake, and had offered to sell stock to <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> real estate developer, and others. 
"Why did he wait until the stock was hitting new highs to make a tender offer? 
It's a little puzzling." 
<PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON> couldn't be reached for comment. 

   A source close to <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said, however, that the offer was a "real" one. 
The source added that "commitments from the bank have been made and <ORGANIZATION>PaineWebber</ORGANIZATION> will do the subordinated financing." 
The source said that <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> first retained <ORGANIZATION>PaineWebber</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>December 1986</DATE> and that the decision to make a tender offer for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> is one "that he hasn't been planning out for a long time." 

   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> long has been known as a casino that appeals to high rollers, although it recently embarked on a program to attract middle-income and lower-income players, too. 
Its chairman and chief executive officer, <PERSON>Henry Gluck</PERSON>, is credited with having turned around the company. 

   When <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON> took the helm at <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE>, the company posted a loss of more than <MONEY>$21 million</MONEY>. 

   In the <DATE>second quarter ended Jan. 31</DATE>, the company reported net rose <PERCENT>6.8%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$12.6 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>41 cents</MONEY> a share, from the year-earlier quarter's <MONEY>$7.5 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY> a share. 
Revenue grew <PERCENT>16%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$190.4 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$163.8 million</MONEY>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> owns <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION>, its flagship hotel-casino in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev</LOCATION>. 
The company also owns a hotel-casino in <LOCATION>Lake Tahoe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, and another in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION> 
The company's holdings also include four honeymoon resorts in the <LOCATION>Poconos</LOCATION> and seven acres of undeveloped land along the <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION> boardwalk. 

   While industry analysts generally have praised <PERSON>Mr. Gluck</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>'s financial performance, some have said recently that the stock market long has undervalued the company's stock. 
<PERSON>Mr. Lee</PERSON> said that "<MONEY>$28</MONEY> (a share) is getting pretty close to what Caesars is worth." 

   Besides his <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> holding, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> also has bought large stakes for himself or his firm's clients in recent years in such companies as <ORGANIZATION>Triangle Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Loews Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>New York Times Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
In the past, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> always has been a passive investor, buying and selling for investment rather than takeover purposes. 

   Last year, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> sold a <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> stake in his investment management firm to the public through a <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> offering of about 1.8 million shares. 
He also sold <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> of convertible debentures. 
Atalanta/Sosnoff had said it wanted the money to expand and for acquisition of financial companies. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880226-0022 </DOCNO>
<HL> Caesars World Posts 25% Increase in Profit For Fiscal 2nd Period </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> CAW CHH FDS CJN </CO>
<IN> ERN CNO </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>fiscal second-quarter</DATE> profit rose <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$15.7 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>65 cents</MONEY> a share, primarily because of improved operating results at its <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> casino-hotels. 

   Net income for the year-earlier quarter was <MONEY>$12.6 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>41 cents</MONEY> a share. 
Revenue for the latest <DATE>second quarter</DATE>, ended <DATE>Jan. 31</DATE>, increased <PERCENT>5.4%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$198 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$187.8 million</MONEY> a year earlier. 


   Per-share earnings figures for the latest quarter and six months reflected the company's buy-back of 11 million common shares <DATE>last October</DATE>, which was offset by the conversion of its subordinated debentures into five million common shares. 


   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> said next month it will introduce its new line of fragrances in all of <ORGANIZATION>Carter Hawley Hale Stores Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s Broadway department stores in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Lazarus</PERSON> department stores in <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>. 
Lazarus is a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Cincinnati-based Federated Department Stores Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Caesars said it expects the fragrances, which had previously been availble at its resorts, to be marketed in about 500 retail outlets throughout the nation by the end of the year. 

   The company also said it signed agreements with <ORGANIZATION>Joan Hansen &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Equity Management Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Palatine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, both licensing agents, to represent the company in national licensing of apparel, home accessories and gift products under <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> brand labels. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870825-0081 </DOCNO>
<HL> Caesars World Inc.
Asks for Rehearing
On Recapitalization</HL>
<DD> 08/25/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW CJN
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL) </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said it filed a petition with the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Casino Control Commission</ORGANIZATION> for a rehearing on its proposed <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> recapitalization plan. 

   The commission rejected the hotel and gambling concern's recapitalization plan by a 4-1 vote <DATE>Aug. 12</DATE>. 
One commissioner argued that the plan, which would give <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' shareholders a one-time cash dividend of <MONEY>$26.25</MONEY> a share and stock in the reconstituted company, "lacks any clear business purpose" and is designed to "permanently entrench" current management while loading down the company with <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> of new debt. 

   Caesars, operator of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Caesars Atlantic City</LOCATION> hotel-casino in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, said that the timing of the rehearing, which might not be granted by the <ORGANIZATION>Casino Commission</ORGANIZATION>, is uncertain. 

   Caesars said it is asking permission to cross-examine one of the state's witnesses, <PERSON>H. Peter Gray</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Rutgers University</ORGANIZATION>, who testified before the commission that the proposed recapitalization would seriously weaken <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' capital structure. 
Caesars said it is also requesting permission to present testimony of additional independent financial experts. 

   The company added that it is continuing to explore a variety of alternatives to the proposed plan, but added that it hasn't determined which it would pursue should the plan be rejected. 
As previously reported, industry sources have suggested that the company might restructure its recapitalization plan to include less debt. 
Another action suggested by one Wall Street executive would be for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> to sell its <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION> property. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870911-0013 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sosnoff Won't Sell
Caesar's World Stake
To Firm in Buy-Back</HL>
<DD> 09/11/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW
BUYBACKS, REDEMPTIONS, SWAP OFFERS (BBK)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL)
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON>, who waged an unsuccessful takeover bid for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> earlier this year, said he won't sell his roughly <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> stake back to the company. 

   The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> financier hadn't previously responded to the Los Angeles-based casino operator's offer, launched this week, to buy <PERCENT>31%</PERCENT> of its shares for <MONEY>$29.50</MONEY> to <MONEY>$34</MONEY> each, or <MONEY>$325 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$374 million</MONEY>. 

   In <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> shares closed at <MONEY>$30</MONEY>, up <MONEY>37.5 cents</MONEY>. 

   In a statement, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> branded the buy-back offer a "pusillanimous" effort to "purge" all arbitragers and "other shortterm professional investors from the ranks of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' shareholders." 

   Officials of the hotel and gambling concern declined to comment on <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s announcement. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s response to <LOCATION>Caesars World</LOCATION>'s offer is the latest episode in one of the year's longest-running takeover sagas, which began in <DATE>March</DATE> with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s unsolicited <MONEY>$28-a-share</MONEY> bid for the company. 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> later raised his proposal to <MONEY>$35</MONEY> a share, or <MONEY>$1.11 billion</MONEY>, for the shares he didn't already own. 

   Caesars World's initial defense against <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> was a proposed <MONEY>$960 million</MONEY> recapitalization plan. 
After <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> regulators refused to approve that plan, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> replaced it with the buy-back offer. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881214-0276 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-14-88 1307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Caesars     12-14 0494</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Caesars,0511</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trump Indicates He May Seek Control Of Caesars</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Developer <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON> has notified
the federal government that he wants to buy <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> or more of
<ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> stock and that he may seek controlling interest,
the hotel and casino company says.
   In a statement issued <DATE>late Tuesday</DATE>, Caesars officials said they
were notified that <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> has asked the government for a ruling on
whether his investment in <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> would violate federal antitrust
laws.
   The disclosure sent <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' common stock sharply higher today.
a share to <MONEY>$29.25</MONEY>.
   But gaming analysts said <PERSON>Trump</PERSON>, who already owns two casinos in
<LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION> and is building a third, would face regulatory
obstacles to a move on <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> in both <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, where <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> is
based, and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, which prohibits single ownership of no more
than three casinos.
   The Los Angeles-based <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> owns the highly profitable <ORGANIZATION>Caesars
Hotel Casino</ORGANIZATION> here and the <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Palace</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Caesars Tahoe</ORGANIZATION> casino
hotels in <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>.
   Neither <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>'s filing nor <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' statement indicated how much
<ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> stock <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> may already own. <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s filing was made under
the Hart-Scott-Rodino Act, which requires companies or individuals
to seek such a ruling once they have acquired <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY> worth of
stock in a company.
   At <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s closing price of <MONEY>$25.25</MONEY> per share, that would
translate to about 590,000 shares, or about <PERCENT>2.4 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Caesar</ORGANIZATION>'s
24.5 million common shares outstanding.
   <PERSON>Susan Heilbron</PERSON>, executive vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>Turmp
Organization</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> had no comment on the filing other than to
confirm that it was made. She declined to say how much <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>'
stock, if any, <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> already owns.
   According to the <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>' statement, <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> indicated he ``has the
good faith intention, subject to price, availability and necessary
approvals, if any,'' to acquire <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Caesar</ORGANIZATION>'s stock.
   Trump's filing also said he ``may decide to seek control of
(<ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>) through the acquisition of <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> (or) more of the
outstanding voting securities.''
   ``Due to the confusing content of this notice, (<ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>) is
unable to ascertain <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON>'s plans at this time and has no
further comment,'' the company said in its release.
   One gaming analyst, <PERSON>Marvin Roffman</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Janney Montgomery Scott
Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, said he doubts that <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> is serious about
making a move to acquire <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION>, and said any such move would face
serious regulatory opposition in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>.
   ``The gaming board in <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> has come out and said it does not
particularly relish hostile takeovers, and I can tell you that this
would be a hostile takeover because the company will vigorously
defend its independence,'' he said.
   New Jersey gaming regulators have also strongly opposed hostile
takeovers of casino companies.
   Trump now owns <ORGANIZATION>Trump Plaza</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Trump Castle</ORGANIZATION> casino hotels in
<LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION> and is building the massive Taj Mahal casino hotel,
which should be complete in 15 months.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870413-0088 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sosnoff Sweetens
Offer for Caesars
To $32 a Share
---
A Wall Street Journal News Roundup</HL>
<DD> 04/13/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CAW
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
REAL ESTATE, REITS, LAND DEVELOPMENT (REL)
CASINOS AND GAMBLING (CNO) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Martin T. Sosnoff</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor and money manager, sweetened his hostile offer to acquire <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World Inc.</ORGANIZATION> to <MONEY>$32</MONEY> a share, or <MONEY>$931.2 million</MONEY>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>, who is <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>'s largest holder with a <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> stake on a fully diluted basis, last month launched a <MONEY>$28-as-hare</MONEY> tender offer for all of the shares outstanding in the Los Angeles-based owner of casino-hotels. 

   According to an advertisement in today's Wall Street Journal, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s amended offer will expire <DATE>June 19</DATE> at <TIME>5 p.m. EDT</TIME>, unless extended. 

   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said, "We think our offer is better than the company's because it doesn't put the shareholders at risk and it gives them all cash." 
He added that an attempt by <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> to increase its offer "raises questions about whether the remaining shares of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> would be worth very much after a recapitalization" because the company would be adding more debt. 
<PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> added that "we're still hopeful of getting a friendly deal" with <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>. 

   But <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION> is unlikely to be any more receptive to <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s second offer than it was to his first. 
The latest bid doesn't offer much of a premium to the company's own recapitalization plan announced about a week ago. 
Under that plan, <ORGANIZATION>Caesars</ORGANIZATION> would pay a one-time cash dividend of <MONEY>$25</MONEY> a share and incur about <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> of new debt. 

   Current shareholders also would retain common stock in a more highly leveraged Caesars. 
Last week, analysts generally valued the common stock after the recapitalization at about <MONEY>$6</MONEY> to <MONEY>$7</MONEY> a share, although some said the value could be as much as <MONEY>$10</MONEY> a share. 


   Some traders said <DATE>last week</DATE> that the price of the company's stock was bid up sharply after the company's announcement of its recapitalization plan on expectations that <ORGANIZATION>Southmark Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Pratt Hotel Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, both based in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, might make a joint bid for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>. 

   As previously reported, <ORGANIZATION>Southmark</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Pratt Hotel</ORGANIZATION> late last month held talks with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> about conducting a joint offer with the investor for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>. 
Those talks proved unsuccessful. 

   Terms of <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s latest offer for Caesars World call for purchasing <PERCENT>94%</PERCENT>, on a fully diluted basis, the shares that the investor doesn't already own. 
An individual familiar with <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON>'s latest offer said that the investor anticipates offering securities for the remaining 6.1 million shares with a value of <MONEY>$32</MONEY> a share. 

   The individual said that <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> received written commitments for <MONEY>$475 million</MONEY> from his investment banker, <ORGANIZATION>PaineWebber Inc</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> also has received <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> in commitments from a group of banks led by <ORGANIZATION>Marine Midland Banks Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, and expects an additional <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> in commitments from those banks. 

   As previously reported, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> had said he was contemplating a new offer for <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>. 
In a letter to <PERSON>Henry Gluck</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Caesars World</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Sosnoff</PERSON> said he was "prepared to offer a meaningful increase in price in the context of a friendly, negotiated transaction." 
