<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900111-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-90 1914EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Sylvester 1stLd-Writethru a0650 01-11 0555</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Sylvester, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0650,0565</SECOND>
<HEAD>Beneficiary of Babe Ruth's Legendary Home Run Dead at 74</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `Johnny reportedly...', to CORRECT father's
title to vice president sted president. Essex Fells is cq in 5th
graf. A version moving on sports wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LARRY McSHANE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When <PERSON>Johnny Sylvester</PERSON>'s father wanted a second
opinion about his sick boy, he consulted Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>. The baseball
legend's treatment was unorthodox _ a <DATE>1926</DATE> World Series home run.
   <PERSON>John Dale Sylvester</PERSON>, 74, died <DATE>Monday</DATE>. But <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s purported
promise and delivery of a home run lives on, memorialized in
newspapers, biographies and on film, though wildly distorted.
   ``So many things about Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> have become like Greek
mythology,'' baseball historian <PERSON>Don Honig</PERSON> said after hearing of
<ORGANIZATION>Sylvester</ORGANIZATION>'s death.
   Sylvester died at a hospital on <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>. No cause
of death was given.
   According to news reports from the time, <PERSON>Sylvester</PERSON> was kicked in
the head by a horse, suffering a life-threatening injury which left
the 11-year-old boy bedridden in <LOCATION>Essex Fells</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   Johnny reportedly told his father, <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> bank vice president
<PERSON>Horace Sylvester</PERSON>, ``Gee, I wish I could see Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> wallop a
homer before I die.''
   The elder Sylvester contacted <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s team, the <ORGANIZATION>New York Yankees</ORGANIZATION>,
in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> via telegram, recounting his son's request.
Autographed balls from the <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>St. Louis Cardinals</LOCATION> were
sent to the lad; <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> wrote on one ball, ``I'll hit a home run for
you in <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s game.''
   The Sultan of Swat then hit three homers in the <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION>' 10-5
fourth game victory over the <LOCATION>Cardinals</LOCATION>. Johnny's doctors reported
the boy had bounced back remarkably from his illness, and a legend
was born. Sylvester quickly became <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s most famous invalid.
   ``That and the called home run _ those two specific incidents
are probably the best known Ruth stories,'' said <PERSON>Robert Creamer</PERSON>,
author of the biography ``Babe.''
   ``The incident is sort of characteristic of Ruth. He had a great
sort of ingenious quality about him,'' said <PERSON>Creamer</PERSON>. ``He'd do
things like this, sometimes with great publicity, sometimes with no
publicity.''
   When <PERSON>William Bendix</PERSON> portrayed ``The Bambino'' on film, the story
had Ruth bedside with a dying boy when the home run was promised.
It was far from accurate, but as <PERSON>Creamer</PERSON> noted, ``That was a pretty
bad movie.''
   One week later, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> visited the lad. Johnny, well aware that
<PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> had been caught stealing for the final out in the Yankees
series loss, told the Babe, ``I'm sorry the Yanks lost.''
   Sylvester went on to attend <ORGANIZATION>Princeton University</ORGANIZATION>, serve in World
War II, and become president of packing machinery business. His
son, <PERSON>John Jr.</PERSON>, said his dad remained a <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION> fan until the end.
Slyvester is also survived by a sister and a brother.
   The whole <PERSON>Johnny Sylvester</PERSON> story apparently had little effect on
the Babe. According to <PERSON>Creamer</PERSON>'s biography, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> was sitting around
with a couple of baseball writers during <DATE>spring</DATE> training in <DATE>1927</DATE>
when <PERSON>Sylvester</PERSON>'s uncle approached the Babe and thanked him
profusely.
   ``How is Johnny?'' Ruth asked. The uncle assured the Babe that
<PERSON>Johnny</PERSON> was doing OK and walked away.
   Ruth, who was notoriously bad with names and referred to most
everyone as ``kid,'' turned to the reporters and asked, ``Now who
the hell is Johnny Sylvester?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA013190-0124 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 169624 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 31, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 7; Column 3; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
375 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COURT RULES RUTH NAME IS PRIVATE, IMAGE IS NOT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By HENRY WEINSTEIN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Book publishers and baseball memorabilia collectors have scored a major victory 
in a court case about who can publish photographs of <LOCATION>Babe Ruth</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> federal appeals court ruled <DATE>Monday</DATE> that, although the Babe's heirs own 
his name, they do not own his image. 
</P>
<P>
The ruling stemmed from a lawsuit filed against <ORGANIZATION>Macmillan Inc.</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s 
daughters, <PERSON>Dorothy Ruth Pirone</PERSON> and <PERSON>Julia Ruth Stevens</PERSON>, claiming that <PERSON>Macmillan</PERSON> 
had illegally used three photographs of <ORGANIZATION>Ruth</ORGANIZATION> in a <DATE>1988</DATE> baseball trivia 
calendar. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Judge Irving R. Kaufman</PERSON> wrote in his opinion: "Ruth was one of the most 
photographed men of his generation, a larger-than-life hero to millions and a 
historical figure in whom interest still runs high." 
</P>
<P>
While Ruth lived, the judge wrote, he was paid by various manufacturers for the 
use of his picture or name in promoting the sale of various products. After 
<PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s death in <DATE>1948</DATE>, his daughters registered the words <PERSON>Babe Ruth</PERSON> as a 
trademark for "paper articles, namely playing cards, writing paper and 
envelopes," <PERSON>Kaufman</PERSON> wrote. 
</P>
<P>
That trademark has been lucrative. <PERSON>Mark Roesler</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Curtis Management 
Group</ORGANIZATION>, the Babe's Indianapolis-based licensing agent, said last <DATE>December</DATE> that 
fees paid to the <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> family were estimated at <MONEY>$400,000</MONEY> for <DATE>1989</DATE> and were 
expected to grow to <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The photographs at issue in the case appeared in the <DATE>1988</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Macmillan Baseball 
Engagement Calendar</ORGANIZATION>. The words Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> are not on the calendar cover, the 
judge noted. 
</P>
<P>
The calendar cover has a photo of <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> helping a small boy with his batting 
grip. Inside the calendar, there is a photo of the Babe saluting Gen. <PERSON>John 
Pershing</PERSON> and a photo of a baseball autographed by <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Ruth's daughters objected to the use of <ORGANIZATION>Ruth</ORGANIZATION>'s likeness. Their suit alleged 
federal and common-law trademark infringement and unfair competition, 
infringement of the common law right of publicity and violation of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 
Civil Rights Law. The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> law forbids the use for advertising or trade 
purposes of any portrait or picture without the consent of the subject if the 
subject is living. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Judge Kaufman</PERSON> acknowledged that there is a valuable commodity in a public 
figure's image, but he said that <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s daughters had made much too broad a 
claim. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PRIVATE PROPERTY; TRADEMARKS; TRADE NAMES; PHOTOGRAPHS; ADVERTISING; NEW YORK 
(STATE) -- LAWS; CURTIS MANAGEMENT GROUP; RUTH, GEORGE HERMAN (BABE) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880507-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-07-88 0542EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RuthSuit     05-07 0297</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ruth Suit,0303</SECOND>
<HEAD>Daughters of The Babe Throw Brushback At Publisher</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY McSHANE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> wasn't just a legendary home run
hitter for the <ORGANIZATION>New York Yankees</ORGANIZATION> _ he's a registered federal
trademark, his two daughters have charged in a suit against
<ORGANIZATION>MacMillan Publishing</ORGANIZATION>.
   The suit filed <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Dorothy Ruth
Pirone</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Durham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Julia Ruth Stevens</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Conway</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>,
seeks to halt sales of a <DATE>1988</DATE> calendar published by <PERSON>MacMillan</PERSON> that
carries a picture of the late slugger on its cover.
   ``<PERSON>MacMillan</PERSON>'s unauthorized, unlicensed and unapproved use of
Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s image, likeness and name tends to cause confusion and
deceive the public,'' said attorney <PERSON>Martin A. Levitin</PERSON>, representing
the <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> family, in court papers.
   ``The <DATE>1988</DATE> MacMillan Baseball Engagement Calendar'' includes two
photos of the Babe that were used without permission of the family,
the suit charged.
   The suit, which also lists <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth League Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Curtis
Management Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION> as plaintiffs, said <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s daughters filed a
written request with <ORGANIZATION>MacMillan</ORGANIZATION> asking it to halt distribution of
the calendar. The publisher allegedly ignored the request.
   Ruth's daughters received a federal trademark last year for the
name ``Babe Ruth'' on paper articles, the suit said. Curtis handles
licensing of third parties seeking to use Ruth's name, it said.
   <PERSON>Sharon Dynak</PERSON>, a spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>MacMillan</ORGANIZATION>, said she had not yet
seen the suit and had no immediate comment on the suit, which
charges <ORGANIZATION>MacMillan</ORGANIZATION> with trademark infringement and unfair
competition.
   The plaintiffs asked <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Pierre Leval</PERSON> for a
permanent injunction blocking <ORGANIZATION>MacMillan</ORGANIZATION> from using additional
photos of Ruth; an award to the plaintiffs of all profits made from
calendar sales; additional monetary damages; and reimbursement for
all lawyers' fees.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900130-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-30-90 0419EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a PM-BRF--BabeRuthLawsuit     01-30 0174</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Babe Ruth Lawsuit,0177</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court: Ruth's Heirs Cannot Sue Publisher For Trademark
Infringement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s daughters struck out in federal
court when an appeals court ruled that a publisher did not infringe
on their trademark by using pictures of the <LOCATION>Bambino</LOCATION> in a calendar.
   Three judges of the <ORGANIZATION>2nd U.S. Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> upheld a
lower court ruling that dismissed a lawsuit by <PERSON>Julia Ruth Stevens</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Dorothy Ruth Pirone</PERSON>, who has since died, and against <ORGANIZATION>Macmillan
Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   After <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s death, the sisters registered the words ``Babe
Ruth'' as a trademark for playing cards and other uses.
   The court said the trademark did not apply to photographs of
<PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>.
   The calendar, ``The <DATE>1988</DATE> Macmillan Baseball Engagement
Calendar,'' contained three references to <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>. The cover was a
photograph of <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> helping a boy with his batting grip; a week in
<DATE>October</DATE> was illustrated with a picture of <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> saluting General
<PERSON>John Pershing</PERSON>; and a page in the <DATE>December</DATE> section had a photograph
of a baseball autographed by <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900111-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-90 0538EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Obit-Sylvester 1stLd-Writethru a0478 01-11 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Sylvester, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0478,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>``Johnny'' Sylvester, Babe Ruth's Most Famous Fan, Dead at 74</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf to fix typo in `wish'; INSERTS one graf after
8th, `The 1926 ...' to include Gehrig story; version moved on
sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MINEOLA, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>John Dale ``Johnny'' Sylvester</PERSON>, who became
the most famous little sick boy in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> after <LOCATION>Babe Ruth</LOCATION> promised
to smack a World Series homer for him _ and hit three _ has died 63
years later. He was 74.
   Sylvester died <DATE>Monday</DATE> at a <LOCATION>Mineola</LOCATION> hospital. No cause of death
was given.
   In <DATE>1926</DATE>, <PERSON>Sylvester</PERSON> was suffering from a serious infection of the
forehead caused by a kick from a horse when he told his father, ``I
wish I could see Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> wallop a homer before I die.''
   The family sent telegrams to the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Yankees while they
were playing in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. Back came an airmail package containing
two baseballs, one autographed by the <ORGANIZATION>St. Louis Cardinals</ORGANIZATION>, the
other signed by several <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION>, including <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>, who wrote, ``I'll
knock a homer for you on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.''
   Ruth hit three that day. In a follow-up note the day of Game 6,
<PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> said he would ``try to knock you another homer, maybe two
<DATE>today</DATE>,'' but went homerless. He hit one in Game 7 but it was not
enough to prevent the Yankees from losing the Series. In fact, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>
was caught stealing for the final out.
   Ruth visited the <LOCATION>Essex Fells</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, boy at his bedside after the
Series, a meeting at which Sylvester remarked, ``I'm sorry the
Yanks lost.''
   No miraculous recovery occurred, but the visit certainly did no
harm. It took Sylvester three years before he fully recovered.
Sylvester returned the gesture in <DATE>1948</DATE>, visiting Ruth four months
before the slugger died of cancer.
   The <DATE>1926</DATE> episode later was part of the movie ``The Babe <PERSON>Ruth
Story</PERSON>,'' but the screen version stretched the truth by having <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>
make his home run promise at <ORGANIZATION>Sylvester</ORGANIZATION>'s hospital bedside. The boy
apparently was never hospitalized.
   Earlier, in the <DATE>1942</DATE> movie ``The Pride of the Yankees,''
Hollywood had stretched the tale even further with a promise of two
home runs by <PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON>.
   Sylvester served in the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> in World War II and was later
president of <ORGANIZATION>Amscomatic Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a manufacturer of packing machinery.
   He is survived by his son, <PERSON>John Jr.</PERSON>, a sister, <PERSON>Ruth Elliott</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Barrington R.I.</LOCATION>, and a brother, <PERSON>Horace C. Sylvester Jr.</PERSON>, of
<LOCATION>Osterville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062290-0085 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 237151 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 22, 1990, Friday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 2; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
760 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LARRY KING GOES TO BAT FOR BABE RUTH MUSEUM 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN STEADMAN, BALTIMORE EVENING SUN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
All shapes and sizes of organizations have tried to recruit <PERSON>Larry King</PERSON>, one of 
the most distinctive voices in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, with the hope he might agree to stand 
up and offer an appeal for this or that cause. But it's not his game. He didn't 
want to be linked with fund-raising, or putting one charity ahead of another. 
So he declined, ever so politely. 
</P>
<P>
He has an imposing stature in the field of broadcasting and, in fact, has 
earned a presence for himself that rivals such luminaries of the past as <PERSON>Arthur 
Godfrey</PERSON>, <PERSON>Walter Winchell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ed Sullivan</PERSON>. There's an ethical awareness that 
prevents him from using his network platform to solicit contributions. 
</P>
<P>
But then along came the <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth Museum</ORGANIZATION>, located in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, and it asked 
King if he would become national chairman of its membership committee. His 
answer was a ringing acceptance and endorsement of a new campaign that will 
extend the facility's physical dimensions via an extensive expansion effort. 
</P>
<P>
King will be the point man, the personality who is out front selling the idea 
to individuals and corporations all across the nation. "The name Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> 
catches everyone's attention," he said. "The Babe was symbolic of baseball. He 
was and is baseball." 
</P>
<P>
A historian of a sport he enjoys and understands, <PERSON>King</PERSON> knows Ruth towers above 
all players, past and present, in talent and a sense of the dramatic. King 
never saw <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> play and wasn't old enough the one year, <DATE>1939</DATE>, when he served as 
a first-base coach for the <ORGANIZATION>Brooklyn Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> and took batting practice, which 
was a cheap grandstand ploy to sell tickets. 
</P>
<P>
"No, but I was in <LOCATION>Ebbets Field</LOCATION> and heard his farewell speech (<DATE>April 27, 1947</DATE>) 
when baseball celebrated Babe <PERSON>Ruth Day</PERSON> all over <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. The comments <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> made 
in <LOCATION>Yankee Stadium</LOCATION> about what baseball represented to the boys of our country 
and the other things he had to say, with a voice weakened by cancer, were 
pumped into <LOCATION>Ebbets Field</LOCATION> and to all other ballparks." 
</P>
<P>
What <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> had to say and how he struggled against the pain to speak in not much 
more than whisper so impressed King that he hasn't forgotten the tugging 
emotion of the moment. "No doubt, he was <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s greatest athlete, born and 
raised in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> and, in fact, as a child lived on the exact location where 
center field is going to be located in the new ballpark." 
</P>
<P>
On the subject of a stadium name, <PERSON>King</PERSON> reiterated his position. "It should be 
Babe <PERSON>Ruth Park</PERSON>," he emphasized. "To ignore Ruth's ties to <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> amid so 
much rich background would be some sort of craziness to me. Imagine the 
marketing value of the name. Without <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, plus the Orioles signing him, 
the world never would have heard of him." 
</P>
<P>
And if you want a little-known note about <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>, listen as <ORGANIZATION>King</ORGANIZATION> provides it. 
"With all of <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s hitting attainments, don't forget he won 94 games as a 
pitcher. And do you realize that in winning percentage against the <ORGANIZATION>New York 
Yankees</ORGANIZATION>, he stands second in percentage. When he was with the <ORGANIZATION>Boston Red Sox</ORGANIZATION>, 
he beat the Yanks 17 times and lost only five." 
</P>
<P>
King has long been a <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> booster. He was raised in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>, worked in 
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> and is now based in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. But if he has adopted a city by 
acclamation it would have to be <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>. That's because two of his broadcast 
friends, the late <PERSON>Bill O'Donnell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Joe Croghan</PERSON>, continually talked of its 
place in history and what it represented. 
</P>
<P>
So King was impressed. The Orioles draw his personal attention as no other team 
in sports. King is a student of the game, knows its <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame heroes as well 
as the utility journeymen and talks with in-depth knowledge of the character 
and nuances of baseball. 
</P>
<P>
He mentioned the unprecedented achievement of the Orioles winning seven 
straight pennants in the <ORGANIZATION>International League</ORGANIZATION>, a dynasty that stands alone in 
the record book. And then he pointed out that <PERSON>Al Kaline</PERSON>, a Baltimore-born <ORGANIZATION>Hall 
of Famer</ORGANIZATION>, lived only five minutes away from where <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> was born, the site of 
the museum at 216 <ORGANIZATION>Emory St.</ORGANIZATION> 
</P>
<P>
More than 28,000 men, women and children visited the "House of Ruth" last year 
and the total should continue to climb. It's the largest baseball museum in the 
country -- next to the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame in <LOCATION>Cooperstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> -- and features 
exhibits that pay tribute to <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>, to the Orioles and to other distinguished 
<LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> players. 
</P>
<P>
King wants to send out a message to stimulate more interest in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> among fans, with the enthusiastic expectation they will want 
to go to bat for <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>, in a manner of speaking and, in turn, enable the museum 
to enlarge. The Babe would've liked that. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880415-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-88 0411EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-BabeRuth-Medal     04-15 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Babe Ruth-Medal,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Medal Of Freedom Proposed For Babe Ruth</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CALLAHAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Sen. Lowell P. Weicker</PERSON> wants <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Famer
Babe Ruth</ORGANIZATION> to be honored with the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Medal of Freedom</ORGANIZATION>,
nearly 40 years after the baseball slugger's death.
   Ruth was a ``true American hero'' who ``epitomized the very best
of our national pastime,'' <PERSON>Weicker</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Conn.</LOCATION>, said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The medal, the nation's highest civilian award, is given by the
president for contributions to national security, world peace or
``significant private or public endeavors.'' Seventy-one Medals of
Freedom have been awarded by President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>.
   Weicker, in a letter to <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> nominating <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> for the award,
noted the athlete's off-the-field contributions.
   ``He had great compassion for the sick and dying,'' the senator
said. ``Against the advice of many, <LOCATION>Babe Ruth</LOCATION> visited those
afflicted with <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON>'s Disease in <LOCATION>Kalappapa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, and offered
those condemned to the `leper' colony his love and kindness.''
   Well known for his visits to sick children, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> also
established the <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth Foundation</ORGANIZATION> for underprivileged children
shortly before his death and left it a large part of his estate.
   Born in <DATE>1895</DATE> in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, <PERSON>George Herman Ruth</PERSON> hit 714 home runs
in 22 major league seasons with the <ORGANIZATION>Boston Red Sox</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>New York
Yankees</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Boston Braves</LOCATION>.
   A star pitcher early in his career, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s career home run total
stood as the major league record until <PERSON>Hank Aaron</PERSON> broke it in <DATE>1974</DATE>.
   Ruth died <DATE>Aug. 16, 1948</DATE>, at the age of 53.
   Other baseball players who have received the award include
former <ORGANIZATION>Yankee</ORGANIZATION> great <PERSON>Joe DiMaggio</PERSON> and the late <PERSON>Jackie Robinson</PERSON>, who
became the first black in the major leagues in the modern era when
he played for the <ORGANIZATION>Brooklyn Dodgers</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062090-0152 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 236431 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 20, 1990, Wednesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part P; Page 8; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
105 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SHORT TAKES; 
</P>
<P>
GO TO BAT FOR BABE, FANS ASKED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
BALTIMORE 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Talk show host <PERSON>Larry King</PERSON> is asking fans "to go to bat for the Babe" in a fund 
drive to expand the <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth Museum</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"These are exciting times for baseball fans. Starting today we're going to 
offer fans across the country membership to the Babe <PERSON>Ruth Museum</PERSON>," <PERSON>King</PERSON> said 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> behind the house where the Sultan of Swat was born 95 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
"We hope we can count on all of you to go to bat for the Babe." 
</P>
<P>
The museum hopes a broadened membership will pay for a 12,000-square-foot 
addition, including a 6,000-square-foot auditorium. 
</P>
<P>
The museum was built in <DATE>1974</DATE> around the birthplace of <PERSON>George Herman</PERSON> (Babe) 
<PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Larry King 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06280188 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06280188 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Stephen Lang plays Babe Ruth as a bigger-than-life hero and
hell-raiser; COVER PHOTO: WHAT A BABE; Stephen Lang plays Babe Ruth the way
Ruth played baseball, and life: 'as big as i can' (color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; BASEBALL; CELEBRITY; TELEVISION; MOVIE; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IF JOHN Goodman of "Roseanne" hadn't backed out of a deal to play baseball
immortal Babe Ruth in a new TV movie, Stephen Lang might still be toiling in
the minors.;   But Goodman did back out -- to make more money playing Ruth in
"The Babe," a movie coming to theaters early next year -- and Lang was called
in to take his place.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  TV Magazine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE TRUTH ABOUT THE BABE
PINCH HITTER MAKES LEGEND COME TO LIFE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cover Story; BABE RUTH; Tonight at 9 on; See also related article on page 7 of
this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The happy result is a big-league performance from the Broadway-trained <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>
in <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s "Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>," a stirring bio-film that premieres tonight at 9 as a
major event of baseball's World Series month.;   <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> is an incredibly
vain, headstrong hell-raiser who set as many records in the bedroom and at the
table as he did at the ballpark. Far from the bear-like buffoon <PERSON>William Bendix</PERSON>
played in the sanitized <DATE>1948</DATE> film "The Babe <PERSON>Ruth Story</PERSON>," <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> is a
hot-tempered giant who could look the commissioner of baseball in the eye and
call him a "white-haired old bastard," regardless of the fine and suspension
that guaranteed. He's a man who wanted it all, no matter who got hurt in the
process.;   Yet the new "Babe Ruth" isn't just a myth-busting movie that
rewrites the legend. Lang's <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> also takes us behind the bluster to see the
vulnerable man whose parents dumped him in a Catholic industrial school for
boys at an early age, then forgot about him.;   "I was too big and ugly for
anybody to come and see," the adult <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> tells a lonely boy when he returns to
the school many years later.;   More than anything, though, the new "Babe
Ruth" presents a formidable challenge to an actor. Lang not only had to beef
up for the role (gaining 35 pounds) and master Ruth's unorthodox batting
stance and unique base-trotting style, but also had to make a frequently
unpleasant man likable enough to command our attention for two hours.;   <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>
has the tools to meet such a challenge. Schooled at the famed Actors' Studio
and various regional theater companies, he appeared on Broadway with <PERSON>Dustin
Hoffman</PERSON> in "Death of A Salesman" and earned a Tony nomination last season for
"The Speed of Darkness." His films include "Last Exit to <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>" and
"Manhunter." In TV, he's best known for roles in "Crime Story" and the TV
version of <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON>'s "Salesman." Lang is known as an actor who gets deeply
involved with the characters he plays. He approached the role by locating what
he felt was the central metaphor for <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s life, which he found in a quote
from Ruth.;   "He said, 'I swing big; I hit big or I miss big; and that's the
way I live my life -- as big as I can,' " <PERSON>Lang</PERSON> explained.;   <PERSON>Lang</PERSON> decided he'd
take a "big bite" of the role and play it the way the real Ruth played ball.
But first the right-handed <PERSON>Lang</PERSON> had to get Ruth's left-handed swing down pat.;
  The producers arranged for him to work with another baseball star -- <PERSON>Hall of
Famer Rod Carew</PERSON>, who retired in <DATE>1986</DATE> with a lifetime batting average of .328
and seven <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> batting titles. After daily batting practice at
<ORGANIZATION>Carew</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> baseball school, <PERSON>Lang</PERSON> compared videotapes of
himself with films of Ruth until he could match them perfectly.;   "When the
hitting began to fall into place," said <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>, "then playing the role began to
fall into place.";   (<ORGANIZATION>Carew</ORGANIZATION> claims <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> had "terrible mechanics" as a hitter
and must have been incredibly strong to hit the ball as hard as he did from
his stance.);   The movie skips over <LOCATION>Ruth</LOCATION>'s days as a pitcher for the <ORGANIZATION>Boston
Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> and begins in <DATE>1920</DATE>, when the Babe was acquired by the <ORGANIZATION>New York
Yankees</ORGANIZATION>, primarily as a power hitter. In those days, the 6-foot-2 Ruth weighed
about 215 and was in trim shape. In the twilight of his career in the early
<DATE>1930s</DATE>, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> was much heavier, with a waistline of about 43 inches. Lang didn't
have time to gain that much weight, so makeup specialist <PERSON>Michael Westmore</PERSON>
fitted him with body padding and some special appliances to make his face and
neck appear fuller.;   For <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>, a lifelong baseball fan who grew up in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, the chance to play <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> was the proverbial dream come true. Lang lives
just three miles from the site in <LOCATION>Valhalla</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> is buried and has
regarded him as a hero since his earliest childhood.;   "The deeper I got into
him, the closer I felt to him," said <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>. "He was an extremely complex figure
-- and a very vulnerable figure with tremendous needs.";   In <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>'s mind,
Ruth altered baseball forever by changing it from "little ball," with the
emphasis on singles, doubles and sacrifices, to "big ball," where the crowd
came to see home run sluggers.;   In his last year with the <ORGANIZATION>Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> before
joining the <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> hit 29 homers, a then overwhelming feat that <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>
believes made baseball fans "long-ball hungry" for good. In <DATE>1927</DATE>, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> hit 60
home runs, more than any other team in the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION>. He ended his
career with 714 homers (not counting his 15 in World Series competition), a
record surpassed only by <PERSON>Hank Aaron</PERSON>, who broke <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s record 39 years later,
taking many more times at bat to do it.;   "People would rather see Ruth
strike out than see a lot of other fine players hit a single or double," said
Lang.;   <PERSON>Lang</PERSON>'s next acting assignment also is an extremely challenging one:
He'll play <LOCATION>Hamlet</LOCATION> on Broadway in <DATE>February</DATE>. But he's aware his portrayal of
<PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> may be a career-making one that people won't soon forget.;   "Maybe I'll
get a role as good as Babe," he said, "but I don't think I'll ever get one
better." (box)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RON MILLER, Mercury News Television Editor  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911006  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,030  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, October 6, 1991
00280188,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122289-0103 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 152252 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 22, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 2; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1627 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LEGACY OF EARNING POWER; 
</P>
<P>
BABE RUTH: DEAD 41 YEARS, HE LIVES ON IN ENDORSEMENTS THAT BRING HEIRS HUNDREDS 
OF THOUSANDS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By RICHARD SANDOMIR, SPECIAL TO THE TIMES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Imagine the potential Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> would have in today's 
every-athlete-has-a-sneaker-deal endorsement market. 
</P>
<P>
He could rival <PERSON>Bo Jackson</PERSON> -- "Babe knows baseball. . . . Babe knows hot dogs" 
-- hawk <ORGANIZATION>Hertz</ORGANIZATION> with <PERSON>Arnie</PERSON> and <PERSON>O. J.</PERSON>, look lumpy in his Hanes with <PERSON>Boomer 
Esiason</PERSON>, pitch Slimfast diets with <PERSON>Lasorda</PERSON> and take sides in the <PERSON>Miller Lite</PERSON> 
"Less filling! Tastes Great!" debate. 
</P>
<P>
As it is, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> is not doing shabbily. Forty-one years after his death, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s 
name and visage are licensed to more than 100 companies and products -- banks, 
car companies, retailers, trading card firms, teddy bears, and a maker of 
trapping knives -- avidly trying to profit from his powerful, mythic and 
mischievous appeal. 
</P>
<P>
The Bambino is earning wealth for his heirs that, given his own commercial 
bent, surely wouldn't have surprised the man who did not break stride when told 
his <MONEY>$80,000</MONEY> salary exceeded President <PERSON>Hoover</PERSON>'s. 
</P>
<P>
In an era in which celebrity worship is at its height, stars such as the Babe 
cannot commit the ultimate no-no of endorsement deals: getting in trouble. 
Though the Babe was known to imbibe, smoke and carouse, his conduct is now 
impeccable. Through the selective filter of hero worship, the Babe's image is 
as clean as <PERSON>Orel Hershiser</PERSON>'s. 
</P>
<P>
Add to that trend the expanding market for baseball memorabilia, and it's easy 
to see why the most popular player in the sport's history remains its most 
durable commercial symbol. 
</P>
<P>
So, whether he endorses <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> personal computers, sneakers, free checking for 
senior citizens at a <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> bank, <ORGANIZATION>Zenith</ORGANIZATION> power supplies or the 
<ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> sales force, <PERSON>Babe Ruth</PERSON> stands for whatever the paying company 
desires. 
</P>
<P>
"The legend of <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth</ORGANIZATION> is a very tangible thing," said <PERSON>Mark Roesler</PERSON>, 
president of <ORGANIZATION>Curtis Management Group</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Babe</ORGANIZATION>'s Indianapolis-based licensing 
agent. "Babe's image as the ultimate power hitter, the ultimate superstar isn't 
going to change. (<PERSON>Roger</PERSON>) <PERSON>Maris</PERSON> hit 61 homers, but the Babe's image will never 
change. He's achieved his place in history. Current players have not." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Roesler</PERSON> said that fees paid to the <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> family, including his surviving 
daughter, <PERSON>Julia Ruth Stevens</PERSON>, and his two daughters' children, and <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth 
Baseball Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, were estimated at <MONEY>$400,000</MONEY> for <DATE>1989</DATE> and are expected to grow to 
at least <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE>. <PERSON>Roesler</PERSON> said that before <PERSON>Curtis</PERSON> took control of 
the Ruth marketing from <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth Baseball</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>, annual fees amounted to 
less than <MONEY>$100</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
How would the Babe do if he returned in the pot-bellied flesh? 
</P>
<P>
Not badly, but he'd have more competition in a more active market. And he would 
risk being a disaster to those who would hire him as their spokesman if his 
personal excesses were as probed and criticized as those of today's stars. 
</P>
<P>
But if he controlled himself, he might outdo everybody. 
</P>
<P>
Said <PERSON>Daisy Sinclair</PERSON>, casting director for the <ORGANIZATION>Ogilvy &amp; Mather</ORGANIZATION> advertising 
agency: "I can't think of a category around that he wouldn't fit into, except 
Weight Watchers. He could do ads for vitamins because looking at him, you 
wonder how he could do what he did." 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> was the highest-paid player in baseball, the endorsement game was 
small. He got around more than any other star, endorsing a hat, a brand of 
cigar -- he puffed on them in the showroom window of the factory -- chewing 
tobacco, long johns, shoes, a watch and autographed balls given away by <ORGANIZATION>Texaco</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
He also backed the short-lived Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s Home Run Candy, which lost a legal 
fight with the makers of the <ORGANIZATION>Baby Ruth</ORGANIZATION> candy bar -- named not for the Babe, but 
for <PERSON>Grover Cleveland</PERSON>'s daughter, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> -- and a <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> haberdashery, <PERSON>Babe 
Ruth</PERSON>'s for Men, that shut its doors in six months. 
</P>
<P>
"Commercialization was so much less then," said <PERSON>Robert Creamer</PERSON>, author of 
"Babe: The Legend Comes to Life," the definitive <DATE>1974</DATE> biography of Ruth. 
</P>
<P>
"Now, it strikes me as something weird that a man dead 40 years can be a live 
property. But it's obvious that he's a recognizable personality and a 
plus-person -- that is, someone you'd like to see here now." 
</P>
<P>
Plenty of marketers evidently think the Babe is worth the price of seeing him, 
if not in person, in two dimensions. You want the Babe for a one-time ad in a 
newspaper? That will be <MONEY>$500</MONEY>. You want to put the Babe in a national print 
campaign? Pay <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY>, please. Now you want the <ORGANIZATION>Babe</ORGANIZATION> in a national multi-media 
campaign? Well, that will be <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
What do marketers want from <LOCATION>Babe Ruth</LOCATION>? 
</P>
<P>
 -- Power: For a <ORGANIZATION>Sears Business Centers</ORGANIZATION> campaign, the retailer paid about 
<MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> to feature Ruth in its "heavy hitters" advertising series to sell 
several makes of personal computers. The ads -- with retouched photos of the 
Babe holding or using PCs -- noted that the products were "marked down to 
prices in your ballpark. All heavy hitters . . . Not bad, huh, Babe?" 
</P>
<P>
 -- History: For the marketers at <ORGANIZATION>United Valley Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s 
image, teamed with that of teammate <PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON>, provided a touchstone for its 
target group: depositors 55 and older. 
</P>
<P>
"If you're old enough to remember them, you can forget about paying for 
checking," said the slogan, above a posed shot of <PERSON>Ruth and Gehrig</PERSON> before the 
<ORGANIZATION>Yankee Stadium</ORGANIZATION> backstop. 
</P>
<P>
 -- Inspiration: The <ORGANIZATION>Carlson Marketing Group</ORGANIZATION>'s motivation division used <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s 
image and his words -- "Baseball is a great teacher" -- on a poster to gussy up 
a baseball-oriented incentive program designed for computer sales forces. 
</P>
<P>
 -- Dependability: <ORGANIZATION>Owens-Corning Fiberglas Corp.</ORGANIZATION> featured a photo of <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s 
"called shot" in the <DATE>1932</DATE> World Series against <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Cub</ORGANIZATION> pitcher Charlie Root 
to illustrate reliability. 
</P>
<P>
"A promise made, a promise kept," read the ad. 
</P>
<P>
Chattanooga cutlery maker <PERSON>Jim Frost</PERSON> produces a series of commemorative trapping 
knives named for <ORGANIZATION>Ruth</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Gehrig</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ty Cobb</PERSON>. They are encased in walnut music 
boxes that play "Take Me Out to the Ball Game." 
</P>
<P>
Said Frost: "This is the era of name recognition, and we've gone this route to 
promote our merchandise. On the Ruth knife, we have an etching of him on the 
blade and an authorization slip that tells some of his history. We limit 
production to 3,000 pieces." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Curtis Management Group</ORGANIZATION> has carved a specialty out of marketing celebrities. 
Besides <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gehrig</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Cobb</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Curtis</PERSON>' sports clientele -- featuring 27 <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of 
Famers -- includes <PERSON>Honus Wagner</PERSON>, <PERSON>Roberto Clemente</PERSON>, <PERSON>Casey Stengel</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bob Feller</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Vince Lombardi</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jim Thorpe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jesse Owens</PERSON>. Its entertainment- and 
historical-figure roster features <PERSON>James Dean</PERSON>, <PERSON>Fred Astaire</PERSON>, <PERSON>Humphrey Bogart</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Mark Twain</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Amelia Earhart</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Hardly a baseball legend wanted by marketers is out of <PERSON>Curtis</PERSON>' realm. 
</P>
<P>
Said <PERSON>Jeff Stevens</PERSON>, merchandising director of the <ORGANIZATION>Baseball Hall</ORGANIZATION> of Fame: "If 
something we're doing is beyond the scope of the agreement the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Famers</ORGANIZATION> 
have directly with the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> for products we sell in our gift shop or through 
our catalogue, we go to <PERSON>Curtis</PERSON>. In fact, we're doing a series of <DATE>1991</DATE> calendars 
that use only Curtis clients." 
</P>
<P>
Curtis has been especially active in the last year, increasing its stable of 
baseball clients to about 30 former players. 
</P>
<P>
The year just past was the biggest yet for <PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON> licensing, because of the 
50th anniversary of his emotional retirement from baseball and <ORGANIZATION>Major League 
Baseball</ORGANIZATION>'s dedication of the season to the <ORGANIZATION>ALS Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, which raises funds 
to research a cure for amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, or <PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON>'s Disease. 
</P>
<P>
Eighty-seven companies are "Iron Horse" licensees, many for products tied to 
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Postal Service</ORGANIZATION>'s issue of a Gehrig stamp last <DATE>June</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Some estates restrict what the legends can sell. 
</P>
<P>
In <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s case, his daughters have barred liquor and tobacco ads. 
</P>
<P>
In <PERSON>Gehrig</PERSON>'s case, said <PERSON>Roesler</PERSON>: "We respect <PERSON>Eleanor Gehrig</PERSON>'s wish not to use 
<PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON> for fund-raising purposes. He's not licensed for any ALS research 
group except the one at <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Presbyterian Medical Center</ORGANIZATION> (the <PERSON>Eleanor</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON> ALS Center), though we allowed the ALS Foundation to do a few 
specific things this year." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Eleanor Gehrig</PERSON> left her estate and the rights to market her husband to the 
medical center, which derived a six-figure licensing income this year. 
</P>
<P>
Properties such as <PERSON>Ruth and Gehrig</PERSON>, valuable in life and death, are protected. 
Curtis has 18 infringement suits pending, including a protracted action against 
<ORGANIZATION>Macmillan Publishing Co.</ORGANIZATION> over an engagement calendar that <PERSON>Curtis</PERSON> alleges 
illegally used a photograph of Ruth; and two against card collector firms for 
alleged unauthorized use of the images of 10 of its players on card sets. 
</P>
<P>
Celebrity representatives are gaining more protection because of new state laws 
that grant the dead stars' exclusive licensing rights to their heirs for a 
specified number of years. For example, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1985</DATE> law grants the heirs 
licensing rights for 50 years after a celebrity's death; <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>'s term is 100 
years, <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>'s 50 and <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>'s 10. 
</P>
<P>
Even when the 50-year bell tolls on <LOCATION>Babe Ruth</LOCATION> in <DATE>1998</DATE>, there are other legal 
ways to protect his name and likeness. Curtis has secured trademark protection 
in categories such as paper goods, gifts, apparel and footwear that will 
protect the family's rights as long as their legacy's name and image stay in 
continual use. 
</P>
<P>
So as long as the Ruth legend remains a never-dying part of the magic and lore 
of baseball, it seems clear that marketers will turn to him when they want to 
ally their product or message with his ever-living mystique. 
</P>
<P>
"You look at today's players: most have professional credibility, but not the 
extra spark of charisma," said <PERSON>Marty Blackman</PERSON>, who advises corporations on the 
use of personalities in commercials. "But when you look for a spokesman, you 
want professional credibility, which <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> had with his hitting and home runs; 
and charisma, which he really had. He's one of those people who rose to the top 
and just stayed there." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Babe Ruth's name and visage have proved timeless as symbols used in 
endorsement game. Associated Press; Photo, Still EarningHome run champion Babe 
Ruth, above, has been dead for 41 years, but his heirs and others are still 
earning money from endorsements. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
RUTH, GEORGE HERMAN (BABE); ROYALTIES; PRODUCT ENDORSEMENTS; NAMES; CONTRACTS; 
PROFESSIONAL ATHLETES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06280107 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06280107 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Stephen Lang (Babe Ruth), far left, and Pete Rose, who plays Ty
Cobb, in a scene from 'Babe Ruth.'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; BASEBALL; PROFESSIONAL; TELEVISION; MOVIE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  CREATING almost as much stir as Stephen Lang's portrayal of "Babe Ruth" in
tonight's NBC movie is the man who plays baseball legend Ty Cobb in the film:
Pete Rose.;   A baseball immortal himself, Rose took on his first acting role
in the midst of the ongoing controversy over his disgrace in a betting scandal
that ended with his being banned from baseball for life in 1990.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  TV Magazine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PETE ROSE'S BIG (AND ONLY) SCENE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related article on page 6 of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     In the film, <ORGANIZATION>Rose</ORGANIZATION> has just one scene as <ORGANIZATION>Cobb</ORGANIZATION> with <ORGANIZATION>Lang</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Babe Ruth</LOCATION>. Ruth is
eager to become a baseball manager; so he meets with <PERSON>Cobb</PERSON>, then player-manager
of the <ORGANIZATION>Detroit Tigers</ORGANIZATION>, to see how he likes it.;   Ironically, <PERSON>Rose</PERSON>, years
later, also was a player-manager for his team, the <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> Reds. He also
was known as a "hustling" ballplayer like <PERSON>Cobb</PERSON> and, in fact, was the man who
broke <ORGANIZATION>Cobb</ORGANIZATION>'s record for total hits.;   "It just seemed to be a perfect
choice," said producer <PERSON>Frank Pace</PERSON>. "Rose named his son after <PERSON>Ty Cobb</PERSON> and knows
more about <ORGANIZATION>Cobb</ORGANIZATION> than possibly any person living.";   But there were limits to
how Rose could be used in the film. Organized baseball refused to permit Rose
to appear in a major league uniform and wouldn't allow him to be photographed
at a ballpark. One ballpark scene where Cobb disputes an umpire's call on <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>
was canceled. Rose appears in street clothes in a hotel room for his only
scene as Cobb.;   How does Rose perform as an actor? This critic thinks he's
fine in a very small part, but Executive Producer <PERSON>Lawrence Lyttle</PERSON>, the man who
signed <PERSON>Rose</PERSON>'s paycheck, offers a professional opinion:;   "He has a natural
cadence about his acting, and he was absolutely charming. I think everybody's
going to be surprised at just how natural he is as a performer." (box)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RON MILLER, Mercury News Television Editor  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911006  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  331  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, October 6, 1991
00280107,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA070789-0105 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 79242 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 7, 1989, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 1; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1035 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ALL-STAR GAME: A LOOK BACK; 
</P>
<P>
YOU LIKE ALL STARS? NOW BACK IN '24 . . .; 
</P>
<P>
ANAHEIM CLASSIC STIRS MEMORIES OF 1967 GAME AND BABE RUTH-WALTER JOHNSON 
CONFRONTATION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARK LANDSBAUM, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Remember way back when the All-Star game was first played in <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>? 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Dave Sommers</PERSON> remembers. He was one of 46,309 fans nestled comfortably in their 
seats at the nearly new <LOCATION>Anaheim Stadium</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 11, 1967</DATE>, when the Big A 
marquee stood right behind the outfield fence and when there was no permanent 
seating behind center field. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Chris Clair</PERSON> remembers. He was there too. He even has a memento of the game, a 
program that sold for <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> at the gate. This year's All-Star program costs 
<MONEY>$5</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
And 89-year-old <PERSON>Ernie Johnson</PERSON> remembers. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> wasn't at <LOCATION>Anaheim Stadium</LOCATION> in <DATE>1967</DATE> when the <ORGANIZATION>National League 
All-Stars</ORGANIZATION> clipped the <ORGANIZATION>American League All-Stars</ORGANIZATION> 2-1 in 15 innings. 
</P>
<P>
Johnson recalls an <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> all-star baseball game a few years earlier -- 
<DATE>1924</DATE> to be exact. That was when a barnstorming team headed by <ORGANIZATION>New York Yankee</ORGANIZATION> 
immortal Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> played in <LOCATION>Brea</LOCATION> against another touring team captained by 
favorite son <PERSON>Walter Johnson</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Senators, who, like <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>, ended 
up in the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"The only thing I can lay claim to is that I was there when Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Walter Johnson</PERSON> played," said <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Brea Canyon Oil Co.</ORGANIZATION> and no 
relation to the illustrious pitcher. "I was quite a follower of <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth</ORGANIZATION> and 
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>. They put on quite a show." 
</P>
<P>
Johnson the oil man said that <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> the pitcher grew up in <LOCATION>Olinda</LOCATION>, which is 
known today as Yorba Linda. 
</P>
<P>
"He persuaded Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> to come," <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
On that <DATE>November day nearly 65 years ago</DATE>, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> hit a home run off a Johnson 
pitch but another time he went down swinging. "He could throw that ball hard," 
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said of the pitcher. Nevertheless, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s team won 12-1. 
</P>
<P>
"When Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> struck at that ball and he missed it, he turned clear around," 
recalled <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>, one of 5,000 to 16,000 Orange County residents on hand that 
day, depending on which yellowing newspaper account you believe. 
</P>
<P>
"Baseball's quite a thing," <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> concluded. "It attracts a lot of people." 
</P>
<P>
One of those who will resist the attraction of this year's All-Star game is 
Orange County Supervisor <PERSON>Thomas F. Riley</PERSON>. Like <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> (<PERSON>Walter</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Ernie</PERSON>, that is), <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> played baseball as a young man and has remained a fan. 
But <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> will miss the midsummer classic in <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> just as he did in <DATE>1967</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"Just <TIME>this morning</TIME>, I had a call from a friend who invited me to sit in their 
box," <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> said. "I have tickets, but I'm going to give them to a member of 
the staff. 
</P>
<P>
"I am pretty much of a baseball fan . . . but <PERSON>Emma Jane</PERSON> (his wife) is not such 
an enthusiastic fan. We sort of compromised and will forgo this one." 
</P>
<P>
Had <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> an opportunity to attend the <DATE>1967</DATE> game, however, he would have leaped 
at the chance, he said. At that time he was recently retired from the <ORGANIZATION>Marine 
Corps</ORGANIZATION> and vice president of a <ORGANIZATION>Newport Beach</ORGANIZATION> manufacturing company. 
</P>
<P>
Riley does not recall the hoopla that led up to the <DATE>1967</DATE> game. But he clearly 
has noted the changes in <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> that have taken place since. 
</P>
<P>
"Some of us are still having difficulty with that feeling that we are really 
big boys now," <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> said. "We are really an urban county, second or third 
largest in the state, depending on which day you count." 
</P>
<P>
"We've developed that tremendous stadium. We've really developed a whole lot." 
</P>
<P>
"Don't you think it was kind of a remarkable thing that we had 63,000 people?" 
<PERSON>Riley</PERSON> said of the <DATE>Fourth of July</DATE> crowd at the stadium for the <ORGANIZATION>California 
Angels</ORGANIZATION>' game and fireworks display. 
</P>
<P>
Like <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Anaheim Stadium</LOCATION> has grown in the past 22 years. The <DATE>1989</DATE> 
All-Star game is a sellout, but there will be about 17,000 more seats occupied 
this year than at the <DATE>1967</DATE> sellout, a dozen years before the addition of two 
tiers of seating beyond the outfield fences. 
</P>
<P>
Another difference this year is that <PERSON>Genevieve Linhoff</PERSON> plans to see the entire 
game from her seat -- and a choice location it is too, right down in the front 
row, smack behind the <ORGANIZATION>American League</ORGANIZATION> third-base dugout. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1967</DATE>, Linhoff missed about three innings of the game when unexpected 
last-minute emergencies required her to help out in the stadium ticket office 
where she was employed as secretary to the ticket manager. This year she is 
assistant ticket manager. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm going to be sitting in the seats this time. I'm going to see the whole 
game," <PERSON>Linhoff</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"I think <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> has changed" since <DATE>1967</DATE>, <PERSON>Linhoff</PERSON> said. "We were more intimate 
. . . now we're big. Particularly at the stadium. You knew so many of the 
customers. We had fewer people." 
</P>
<P>
Like so many baseball fans, Linhoff is a traditionalist. She wasn't even real 
fond of expanding stadium seating and moving the distinctive Big A from behind 
center field to exile in the parking lot. 
</P>
<P>
"I didn't like that too well, but it's progress, more capacity," she said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Ernie Johnson</PERSON> recalled how progress altered forever another Orange County 
baseball tradition. 
</P>
<P>
In the early <DATE>1920s</DATE> a large crowd used to gather outside an <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> coffeehouse, 
where the proprietor kept the baseball-hungry throng posted on play-by-play 
developments of the World Series by relaying telegraph bulletins from the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
On a large board erected outside the eating establishment, the restaurateur had 
denoted bases, the outfield and the players. 
</P>
<P>
"We stood on the opposite side of the street and watched it and sat on the 
curb," <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> recalled. "He got the reports by telegraph, and he played the 
game out." 
</P>
<P>
"He had . . . lights and he'd ring a bell when there was a hit and he'd tell 
who the batter was. He yelled it out through that window." 
</P>
<P>
Alas, progress intervened and in later years radios became commonplace. There 
soon was always someone who would have more up-to-the-minute news than could be 
provided by the quaint coffee-shop scoreboard, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"That began to kind of spoil the thing a little bit," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Back to the future. Johnson intends to attend <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s All-Star game. Like 
Supervisor <PERSON>Riley</PERSON>, he missed the one in <DATE>1967</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Even if his wife were enthusiastic about attending, <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> has decided that 
considering "the traffic and all involved, I think I'd feel better if I watched 
it at home" on television. 
</P>
<P>
Times staff writer <PERSON>Jean Davidson</PERSON> contributed to this story. 
</P>
<P>
RELATED STORIES: Life, Calendar and Sports 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Chris Clair shows off his program from the 1967 All-Star game; top left, 
Walter Johnson on the mound in 1924 in Brea against a team led by Babe Ruth. 
RICK PERRY / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ANAHEIM STADIUM; ALL STAR GAMES; MAJOR LEAGUE BASEBALL (ORGANIZATION); BASEBALL 
PLAYERS; ORANGE COUNTY -- ATHLETICS; PROFESSIONAL ATHLETES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881006-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-06-88 0036EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-APArts:BaseballMovies-List     10-06 0216</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Baseball Movies-List,0240</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hollywood Baseball Movies</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-AP Arts: Baseball Movies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of the more notable films about baseball over the
years:
   ``Casey at the Bat'' <DATE>1899</DATE>.
   ``Casey at the Bat,'' (<ORGANIZATION>Wallace Beery</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``College'' (<PERSON>Buster Keaton</PERSON>), <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``Babe Comes Home'' (Babe Ruth), <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``Speedy'' (<PERSON>Harold Lloyd</PERSON>), <DATE>1928</DATE>.
   ``Elmer the Great'' (<PERSON>Joe E. Brown</PERSON>), <DATE>1933</DATE>.
   ``Alibi Ike'' (<PERSON>Joe E. Brown</PERSON>), <DATE>1935</DATE>.
   ``The Pride of the Yankees'' (<PERSON>Gary Cooper</PERSON>), <DATE>1942</DATE>.
   ``The Babe Ruth Story'' (<PERSON>William Bendix</PERSON>), <DATE>1948</DATE>.
   ``The Stratton Story'' (<PERSON>James Stewart</PERSON>), <DATE>1949</DATE>.
   ``Take Me out to the Ballgame'' (<PERSON>Gene Kelly</PERSON>, <PERSON>Esther Williams</PERSON>),
<DATE>1949</DATE>.
   ``It Happens Every Spring'' (<PERSON>Ray Milland</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jean Peters</PERSON>), <DATE>1949</DATE>.
   ``Kill the Umpire'' (<PERSON>William Bendix</PERSON>), <DATE>1950</DATE>.
   ``The <PERSON>Jackie Robinson</PERSON> Story'' (<PERSON>Jackie Robinson</PERSON>), <DATE>1950</DATE>.
   ``Angels in Outfield'' (<PERSON>Paul Douglas</PERSON>), <DATE>1951</DATE>.
   ``Rhubarb'' (<PERSON>Ray Milland</PERSON>), <DATE>1951</DATE>.
   ``The Winning Team'' (<PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>), <DATE>1952</DATE>.
   ``The Pride of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>'' (<PERSON>Dan Dailey Jr.</PERSON>), <DATE>1952</DATE>.
   ``The Big Leaguer'' (<PERSON>Edward G. Robinson</PERSON>), <DATE>1953</DATE>.
   ``Fear Strikes Out'' (<PERSON>Anthony Perkins</PERSON>), <DATE>1957</DATE>.
   ``Damn Yankees'' (Tab Hunter), <DATE>1958</DATE>.
   ``Safe at Home'' (<PERSON>Mickey Mantle</PERSON>, <PERSON>Roger Maris</PERSON>), <DATE>1961</DATE>.
   ``Bang the Drum Slowly'' (<PERSON>Michael Moriarity</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Robert de Niro</ORGANIZATION>),
<DATE>1973</DATE>.
   ``The Bad News Bears'' (<ORGANIZATION>Tatum O'Neal</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Walter Matthau</PERSON>), <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   ``The Bingo Long Traveling All-Stars and Motor Kings'' (<PERSON>James
Earl Jones</PERSON>, <PERSON>Billy Dee Williams</PERSON>), <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   ``The Natural'' (<PERSON>Robert Redford</PERSON>), <DATE>1984</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880930-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-30-88 1328EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e AM-APArts:BaseballMovies-List ADV06   09-30 0224</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AP Arts: Baseball Movies-List, ADV 06,0249</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv06</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thurs AMs, Oct 6 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Hollywood Baseball Movies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of the more notable films about baseball over the
years:
   ``Casey at the Bat'' <DATE>1899</DATE>.
   ``Casey at the Bat,'' (<ORGANIZATION>Wallace Beery</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``College'' (<PERSON>Buster Keaton</PERSON>), <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``Babe Comes Home'' (Babe Ruth), <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``Speedy'' (<PERSON>Harold Lloyd</PERSON>), <DATE>1928</DATE>.
   ``Elmer the Great'' (<PERSON>Joe E. Brown</PERSON>), <DATE>1933</DATE>.
   ``Alibi Ike'' (<PERSON>Joe E. Brown</PERSON>), <DATE>1935</DATE>.
   ``The Pride of the Yankees'' (<PERSON>Gary Cooper</PERSON>), <DATE>1942</DATE>.
   ``The Babe Ruth Story'' (<PERSON>William Bendix</PERSON>), <DATE>1948</DATE>.
   ``The Stratton Story'' (<PERSON>James Stewart</PERSON>), <DATE>1949</DATE>.
   ``Take Me out to the Ballgame'' (<PERSON>Gene Kelly</PERSON>, <PERSON>Esther Williams</PERSON>),
<DATE>1949</DATE>.
   ``It Happens Every Spring'' (<PERSON>Ray Milland</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jean Peters</PERSON>), <DATE>1949</DATE>.
   ``Kill the Umpire'' (<PERSON>William Bendix</PERSON>), <DATE>1950</DATE>.
   ``The <PERSON>Jackie Robinson</PERSON> Story'' (<PERSON>Jackie Robinson</PERSON>), <DATE>1950</DATE>.
   ``Angels in Outfield'' (<PERSON>Paul Douglas</PERSON>), <DATE>1951</DATE>.
   ``Rhubarb'' (<PERSON>Ray Milland</PERSON>), <DATE>1951</DATE>.
   ``The Winning Team'' (<PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>), <DATE>1952</DATE>.
   ``The Pride of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>'' (<PERSON>Dan Dailey Jr.</PERSON>), <DATE>1952</DATE>.
   ``The Big Leaguer'' (<PERSON>Edward G. Robinson</PERSON>), <DATE>1953</DATE>.
   ``Fear Strikes Out'' (<PERSON>Anthony Perkins</PERSON>), <DATE>1957</DATE>.
   ``Damn Yankees'' (Tab Hunter), <DATE>1958</DATE>.
   ``Safe at Home'' (<PERSON>Mickey Mantle</PERSON>, <PERSON>Roger Maris</PERSON>), <DATE>1961</DATE>.
   ``Bang the Drum Slowly'' (<PERSON>Michael Moriarity</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Robert de Niro</ORGANIZATION>),
<DATE>1973</DATE>.
   ``The Bad News Bears'' (<ORGANIZATION>Tatum O'Neal</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Walter Matthau</PERSON>), <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   ``The Bingo Long Traveling All-Stars and Motor Kings'' (<PERSON>James
Earl Jones</PERSON>, <PERSON>Billy Dee Williams</PERSON>), <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   ``The Natural'' (<PERSON>Robert Redford</PERSON>), <DATE>1984</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of the more notable films about baseball over the
years:
   ``Casey at the Bat'' <DATE>1899</DATE>.
   ``Casey at the Bat,'' (<ORGANIZATION>Wallace Beery</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``College'' (<PERSON>Buster Keaton</PERSON>), <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``Babe Comes Home'' (Babe Ruth), <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``Speedy'' (<PERSON>Harold Lloyd</PERSON>), <DATE>1928</DATE>.
   ``Elmer the Great'' (<PERSON>Joe E. Brown</PERSON>), <DATE>1933</DATE>.
   ``Alibi Ike'' (<PERSON>Joe E. Brown</PERSON>), <DATE>1935</DATE>.
   ``The Pride of the Yankees'' (<PERSON>Gary Cooper</PERSON>), <DATE>1942</DATE>.
   ``The Babe Ruth Story'' (<PERSON>William Bendix</PERSON>), <DATE>1948</DATE>.
   ``The Stratton Story'' (<PERSON>James Stewart</PERSON>), <DATE>1949</DATE>.
   ``Take Me out to the Ballgame'' (<PERSON>Gene Kelly</PERSON>, <PERSON>Esther Williams</PERSON>),
<DATE>1949</DATE>.
   ``It Happens Every Spring'' (<PERSON>Ray Milland</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jean Peters</PERSON>), <DATE>1949</DATE>.
   ``Kill the Umpire'' (<PERSON>William Bendix</PERSON>), <DATE>1950</DATE>.
   ``The <PERSON>Jackie Robinson</PERSON> Story'' (<PERSON>Jackie Robinson</PERSON>), <DATE>1950</DATE>.
   ``Angels in Outfield'' (<PERSON>Paul Douglas</PERSON>), <DATE>1951</DATE>.
   ``Rhubarb'' (<PERSON>Ray Milland</PERSON>), <DATE>1951</DATE>.
   ``The Winning Team'' (<PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>), <DATE>1952</DATE>.
   ``The Pride of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>'' (<PERSON>Dan Dailey Jr.</PERSON>), <DATE>1952</DATE>.
   ``The Big Leaguer'' (<PERSON>Edward G. Robinson</PERSON>), <DATE>1953</DATE>.
   ``Fear Strikes Out'' (<PERSON>Anthony Perkins</PERSON>), <DATE>1957</DATE>.
   ``Damn Yankees'' (Tab Hunter), <DATE>1958</DATE>.
   ``Safe at Home'' (<PERSON>Mickey Mantle</PERSON>, <PERSON>Roger Maris</PERSON>), <DATE>1961</DATE>.
   ``Bang the Drum Slowly'' (<PERSON>Michael Moriarity</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Robert de Niro</ORGANIZATION>),
<DATE>1973</DATE>.
   ``The Bad News Bears'' (<ORGANIZATION>Tatum O'Neal</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Walter Matthau</PERSON>), <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   ``The Bingo Long Traveling All-Stars and Motor Kings'' (<PERSON>James
Earl Jones</PERSON>, <PERSON>Billy Dee Williams</PERSON>), <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   ``The Natural'' (<PERSON>Robert Redford</PERSON>), <DATE>1984</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870408-0166 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf:
Baseball Stories: Martin, Maris and the Yanks
---
By Joe Mysak</HL>
<DD> 04/08/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   Old-timers know that baseball today is not what it was even 30 years ago. 
<PERSON>Billy Martin</PERSON>, who has been building winning ball clubs (and then getting fired from them) over much of this period, tells why. 

   In "BillyBall" (<ORGANIZATION>Doubleday</ORGANIZATION>, 276 pages, <MONEY>$16.95</MONEY>), <PERSON>Mr. Martin</PERSON>, with the help of <ORGANIZATION>New York Daily News</ORGANIZATION> sport columnist <PERSON>Phil Pepe</PERSON>, relates what he's done since the publication of his autobiography, "Number 1," seven years ago. 
Along the way he writes about managers and managing, why infielders often make the best managers, sketches <PERSON>George Steinbrenner</PERSON> and <PERSON>Reggie Jackson</PERSON>, tells how to put together a lineup, and discusses free agents, some old friends and, of course, the old days. 

   At age 60, he is not particularly old as far as managers go, but the game he played as second baseman for the <ORGANIZATION>New York Yankees</ORGANIZATION> during the <DATE>1950s</DATE> had more in common with the game played by <PERSON>John McGraw</PERSON> at the turn of the century than it does with the one played today. 

   Today's player, in <PERSON>Mr. Martin</PERSON>'s opinion, does not spend enough time in the minor leagues learning his trade. 
When he does make the big club, he rooms alone, and does not get the opportunity to talk baseball with a roomie. 
He feels little team loyalty. 
Long-term contracts sap his incentive to perform. 
And if he gets a powerful enough agent, he may be able to get his manager fired or otherwise dictate club policy. 

   Finally, there are the malcontents, who, despite fancy contracts, say they no longer want to play for their team because it is "not fun" anymore, which usually means that they don't like the skipper because he believes in platooning. 
<PERSON>Mr. Martin</PERSON>'s advice: "I wish baseball would just release them. 
Nobody sign the SOBs. 
You don't want to play here? 
You don't like it here? 
Released. 
Go home. 
Go to work. 
You get no more salary, no more having your contract renegotiated, no more calling your agent or the Players' Association for every little thing." 

   The solution, he says, is more one-year contracts for marginal players whose value has been inflated, and a less competitive free-agent market. 
The owners, who can take great responsibility for starting the whole mess, seem to be coming around to these ideas, which is why several familiar faces were not in a uniform on opening day. 

   In contrast with this tale of the preposterous debasement of the national pastime is "Sixty-One" (<ORGANIZATION>Macmillan</ORGANIZATION>, 269 pages, <MONEY>$19.95</MONEY>), by <PERSON>Tony Kubek</PERSON> and <PERSON>Terry Pluto</PERSON>, a history of the sublime <DATE>1961</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION>, "the most selfless team I've ever managed" in the words of <PERSON>Ralph Houk</PERSON>. 
It is a story of redemption, pursuit and triumph, built around one of the most magnificent feats in baseball. 

   The story belongs to <PERSON>Roger Maris</PERSON> and his pursuit of <PERSON>Babe Ruth</PERSON>'s record 60 home runs in one season. 
Fans tend to root for records to be broken -- but in <DATE>1961</DATE>, they wanted <PERSON>Mickey Mantle</PERSON>, <PERSON>Maris</PERSON>'s teammate, to do it, and in 154 games, the same number of games it had taken <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>, not the 162 games of the expanded schedule. 
<ORGANIZATION>Ford Frick</ORGANIZATION>, then commissioner of baseball, called attention to the difference between the two records, and rightly so. 
But it does not detract from its heroic quality. 
As <PERSON>Mantle</PERSON> says, "It was something. . . . 
All I know is that no one did it before or since, and I know how damn hard it is to do it, because I tried it and never made it." 

   At the time, however, <PERSON>Maris</PERSON> was subject to abuse from fans, tears from Ruth's widow, attacks from old-timers who contended <PERSON>Maris</PERSON> was unworthy because he was not as colorful as the <LOCATION>Bambino</LOCATION> and was not a .300 hitter, and from newspaper sportswriters who took joy in orchestrating the attack. 
<PERSON>Maris</PERSON> hit his 61, but paid the price, and from all accounts was not the same man afterward. 

   But the story goes beyond <LOCATION>Mickey</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Roger</PERSON> and ace pitcher <PERSON>Whitey Ford</PERSON> (who won 25 games and lost only four that season) and Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s ghost. 
The fabric of consistent, winning teams is of a finer weave. 
This is a story of great and small, and <PERSON>Mr. Kubek</PERSON>, with the help of sportswriter <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>, makes sure to tell the small. 
It is the story of a team that came back after the heartbreaking loss of the World Series in seven games in <DATE>1960</DATE> to win 109 games in <DATE>1961</DATE>, and to win the series that year in five. 

   It is the story of <PERSON>Ralph Houk</PERSON>, who replaced the legendary <PERSON>Casey Stengel</PERSON> at the helm. 
And it is the story of, among others, the acrobatic third baseman <PERSON>Clete Boyer</PERSON>; utility man <PERSON>Johnny Blanchard</PERSON>, who hit 21 homers, many of them game-winners, in only 243 at bats; and <PERSON>Luis Arroyo</PERSON>, the chubby relief pitcher who went 15-5 with 29 saves and a 2.19 earned run average. 

   It is also the story of <PERSON>Mr. Kubek</PERSON>, who was the shortstop for that team and who is now a commentator for <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s "Game of the Week." 
He tells his story, and his teammates' stories, usually in their own words. 
There are some pretty good ones. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Mysak</PERSON> is assistant managing editor of The Daily Bond Buyer. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030290-0057 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 183561 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 2, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 22; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
483 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HOME TECH / WHAT'S NEW: BASEBALL VIDEOS HERE -- EVEN IF SEASON ISN'T; 
</P>
<P>
THIS WEEK'S MOVIES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TERRY ATKINSON 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
There may not be baseball this <DATE>spring</DATE> -- thanks to the ongoing dispute between 
owners and players -- but there will be baseball videos to watch. 
</P>
<P>
"The Pride of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>" and "The Babe Ruth Story" (both from <ORGANIZATION>CBS/Fox</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$19.98</MONEY> 
each) aren't exactly up to "Bull Durham" in quality, but at least these two 
filmographies from 40 years ago will fill in a few hours with the sound of 
balls hitting bats and fists hitting gloves to comfort TV-game-less addicts. 
</P>
<P>
"The Pride of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>" is the better of the two. The <DATE>1952</DATE> film tells the 
story of one of the game's most colorful characters, pitcher (and later <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> 
announcer) Dizzy Dean. <PERSON>Dan Dailey</PERSON> plays Diz in a movie that doesn't quite 
convince but does entertain. 
</P>
<P>
Even less believable is "The Babe <PERSON>Ruth Story</PERSON>," a flat, whitewashed <DATE>1948</DATE> 
biography of the man who's generally considered the best in the game's history. 
<PERSON>William Bendix</PERSON> is suitably irrepressible as the Babe, but otherwise baseball 
fans will be disappointed. 
</P>
<P>
CBS/Fox is also re-releasing "The Pride of the Yankees" (also <MONEY>$19.98</MONEY>), 
previously available from Key Video. A far better film than the other two, this 
<DATE>1942</DATE> drama starred <PERSON>Gary Cooper</PERSON> as <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s most notable teammate, the great 
slugger <PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
And coming next week: "Field of Dreams" (<DATE>March 8</DATE>). 
</P>
<P>
Old baseball films aren't the only vintage videos <ORGANIZATION>CBS/Fox</ORGANIZATION> is offering this 
week. Under the banner of "Classic Romances," these four new releases are 
<MONEY>$39.98</MONEY> each: 
</P>
<P>
"Desk Set" (<DATE>1957</DATE>). <PERSON>Spencer Tracy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Katharine Hepburn</PERSON> in a lightweight but 
enjoyable comedy about the introduction of a computer to the research 
department of a business, much to the researchers' dismay. 
</P>
<P>
"Heaven Can Wait" (<DATE>1943</DATE>). Not to be confused with the <PERSON>Warren Beatty</PERSON> movie of 
the same name, this <ORGANIZATION>Ernst Lubitsch</ORGANIZATION> film is an ironic, sophisticated 
comedy/fantasy about a man (<PERSON>Don Ameche</PERSON>) who tells his life story to the devil 
in an attempt to figure out if he's been put in the right place. 
</P>
<P>
"The Ghost and <PERSON>Mrs. Muir</PERSON>" (<DATE>1947</DATE>). More sophisticated comedy -- this time from 
<PERSON>Joseph L. Mankiewicz</PERSON> -- about a young widow (<ORGANIZATION>Gene Tierney</ORGANIZATION>) and the ghost of a 
sea captain (<PERSON>Rex Harrison</PERSON>) who inhabits the house she moves into. 
</P>
<P>
"An Affair to Remember" (<DATE>1957</DATE>). <PERSON>Leo McCarey</PERSON> directed this OK but flawed remake 
of his superior <DATE>1939</DATE> film "Love Affair." <PERSON>Cary Grant</PERSON> and <PERSON>Deborah Kerr</PERSON> help make 
this shipboard comedy palatable. 
</P>
<P>
One other notable oldie, from <ORGANIZATION>Warner</ORGANIZATION> (<MONEY>$59.95</MONEY>), is "Goodby, My Lady" -- not a 
great film, but a touching and well-made one about a boy (the reliable <PERSON>Brandon 
de Wilde</PERSON>) and his dog. <PERSON>Walter Brennan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Phil Harris</PERSON> and a young <PERSON>Sidney Poitier</PERSON> 
also enliven the sentimental picture. 
</P>
<P>
The newer movies making their way to video this week are considerably less 
interesting, including the silly, unfunny Australian comedy "Young Einstein" 
(<ORGANIZATION>Warner</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$89.95</MONEY>, PG) and the putrid horror sequel "Halloween 5: The Revenge of 
<PERSON>Michael Myers</PERSON>" (<ORGANIZATION>CBS/Fox</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$89.98</MONEY>, R). <PERSON>TERRY ATKINSON</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Recording Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072890-0097 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 253731 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 28, 1990, Saturday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 14; Column 2 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
58 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AREA BABE RUTH TEAM REACHES STATE FINAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Van <PERSON>Nuys-Sherman Oaks Babe Ruth</PERSON> team defeated <LOCATION>El Segundo</LOCATION>, 21-3, <DATE>Friday</DATE> 
<TIME>night</TIME> in <LOCATION>Culver City</LOCATION> to advance to the final of the <ORGANIZATION>Babe Ruth</ORGANIZATION> state baseball 
tournament. 
</P>
<P>
Van Nuys-Sherman Oaks will face <LOCATION>Culver City</LOCATION> at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> at <LOCATION>Culver City 
Park</LOCATION>. Van Nuys-Sherman Oaks must defeat <LOCATION>Culver City</LOCATION> twice to win the 
double-elimination tournament. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890518-0209 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-18-89 2236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Ruth'sDaughter     05-18 0226</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Ruth's Daughter,0234</SECOND>
<HEAD>Babe Ruth's Daughter Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DURHAM, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Dorothy Ruth Pirone</PERSON>, the daughter of
baseball great <PERSON>Babe Ruth</PERSON>, died at home <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. She was 68 years
old.
   Pirone lived in <LOCATION>Durham</LOCATION> for more than a dozen years, where she
raised Arabian horses.
   For most of her life, <PERSON>Pirone</PERSON> was led to believe that her mother
was <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s first wife, <PERSON>Helen</PERSON>, despite rumors to the contrary in the
press.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, however, she learned that her real mother was a woman
she had grown up knowing and loving as a close family friend.
<PERSON>Pirone</PERSON> said last year she held no bitterness toward her father for
not revealing her true mother's identity.
   Last year, <PERSON>Pirone</PERSON> wrote a book about her famous father, ``My
Dad, the Babe.'' It was co-authored by <PERSON>Chris Martens</PERSON> and published
on the 40th anniversary of her father's death, <DATE>Aug. 16, 1988</DATE>.
   ``I think I did it more for myself and to show my father was not
the kind of person he was portrayed. I was very defensive of my
father and I can't help it,'' she said in an interview last year.
   Pirone died of natural causes, the family said through a
spokesman at the <ORGANIZATION>B.C. Bailey Funeral Home Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>Wallingford</LOCATION>.
   Pirone, wife of the late <PERSON>Dominick L. Pirone</PERSON>, is survived by four
daughters, one son and 12 grandchildren.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890707-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-07-89 1643EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush-LittleLeague     07-07 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Little League,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Honors Little League, Little Leaguers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>, former baseball coach, took time
out <DATE>Friday</DATE> from preparing for his trip to communist <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> to talk
baseball with 4,000 Little Leaguers.
   ``In Little League all that matters is the size of your heart and
of your dreams,'' he said to the kids.
   They were gathered on the <LOCATION>South Lawn</LOCATION>, decked out in uniforms
identifying them as <LOCATION>Indians</LOCATION>, Mets, <LOCATION>Springfield</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Rocco</PERSON>'s Rockettes,
and <ORGANIZATION>Parkland Blue Jays</ORGANIZATION>.
   The purpose was to mark the founding of Little League 50 years
ago in <LOCATION>Williamsport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa</LOCATION>. Adding luster to the ceremony were such
baseball greats as <PERSON>Stan Musial</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mike Schmidt</PERSON>, <PERSON>Brooks Robinson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gary
Carter</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ted Sizemore</PERSON>, <PERSON>Joe Morgan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jim Palmer</PERSON>.
   The president confessed his baseball hero was <PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON>. And he
recalled that when <PERSON>Babe Ruth</PERSON> presented his papers to <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>, the Yalie
who accepted them was none other than <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>.
   To the young players, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> repeated a line that Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>
delivered to a crowd in <LOCATION>Yankee Stadium</LOCATION> when he was dying of cancer:
   ``You know, the only real game in the world, I think, is
baseball. You've got to start from way down when you are 6 or 7
years old and if you try hard enough you're bound to come out on
top.''
   With those words, said the president, <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON> ``defined why Little
League baseball has become an American, indeed, an international
institution.
   ``My four boys played it, I coached it, and <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON> _ not many
non baseball players could properly score a baseball games, but
<PERSON>Barbara</PERSON> did that, inning after inning,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said.
   ``Like you, I know what makes Little League so special. It's a
feeling of sportsmanship, generosity, teamwork, a feeling of family,
fathers and daughters, mothers and sons.''
   He said in the 50 years, 20 million youngsters had played Little
League _ more than 2.5 million in 33 nations this year alone.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told the crowd that when he is in <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> next week, he will
have the pleasure of helping import Little League. And he said he
will tell about <PERSON>Musial</PERSON> and <PERSON>Carl Yastrzemski</PERSON>, both baseball greats of
Polish extraction.
   ``In Little League all that matters is the size of your heart and
of your dreams and ask these kids about it,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said. ``Dreams
are the essence of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and of baseball and Little League can
propel those dreams.
   ``In the end what matters is how we conduct ourselves on as well
as off the field. That's where Little league really connects, by
building courage and character. It belts a grandslam home run by
doing those two things.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900721-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-21-90 1917EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CelebrityAuction     07-21 0267</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Celebrity Auction,0273</SECOND>
<HEAD>George Washington's Hair, Hitler Letter, Babe Ruth Baseball
Auctioned Off</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A lock of <LOCATION>George Washington</LOCATION>'s hair fetched <MONEY>$2,750</MONEY>
at an auction of celebrity memorabilia <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, which also
featured a package of letters written by mass murderers and <PERSON>Adolf
Hitler</PERSON>.
   The lock from the nation's first president went to a bidder,
who, like the other buyers and the sellers, requested anonymity
from the DuMouchelles auction house in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, said auctioneer <PERSON>Joe
DuMouchelle</PERSON>.
   The collection of letters from <PERSON>John Wayne Gacy</PERSON>, <PERSON>David Berkowitz</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Charles Manson</PERSON> and Hitler brought <MONEY>$700</MONEY>.
   Fecthing the highest price was Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s 700th home-run
baseball, sold for <MONEY>$9,300</MONEY> by a <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> buyer, said DuMouchelle,
whose family owns the auction house.
   An autographed photograph of <PERSON>Marilyn Monroe</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>1962</DATE>,
brought <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>, the robe worn by <PERSON>Sylvester Stallone</PERSON> in ``Rocky
III'' sold for <MONEY>$2,400</MONEY>, and a pair of silk boxer shorts once owned
by actor <PERSON>Jack Nicholson</PERSON> went for <MONEY>$700</MONEY>.
   Two art deco etchings by <PERSON>Louis Icart</PERSON> sold for <MONEY>$7,000</MONEY> and <MONEY>$6,500</MONEY>
each, the auctioneer said.
   The items were auctioned off in estate sales and the
standing-room only crowd of bidders came from across the nation,
DuMouchelle said.
   Manson is serving a life prison term for the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> murders
of starlet <ORGANIZATION>Sharon Tate</ORGANIZATION> and six others by members of his cult
``family'' in <DATE>1969</DATE>; <PERSON>Gacy</PERSON> was convicted in <DATE>1980</DATE> of the sex-related
killings of 33 young men in suburban <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, more murders than
anyone in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history; ``Son of Sam'' killer <PERSON>Berkowitz</PERSON> murdered
six people in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> and wounded seven others in <DATE>1976</DATE> and
<DATE>1977</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06215047 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06215047 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  BASEBALL; VIDEO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  PERHAPS because of baseball's longevity, or maybe because of its association
with childhood summers, the sport thrives on nostalgia. It's a game many of us
can regard with soul-warming affection, even if we didn't play it well. By
definition, then, a videocassette called "Baseball's Greatest Moments" (60
minutes, $19.95) is destined to find a receptive audience.;    The tape also
happens to be a production of Major League Baseball Home Video, giving it that
"official" cachet. The viewer can rest assured the best available game footage
was used.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE BOYS OF SUMMER AND THEIR GREATEST HITS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  VIDEO  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> focus;    The tape limits itself to 20 "greatest moments," which
fill an hour nicely but also will spark disappointment among partisans who
have their own ideas of greatness. The relative merits of specific plays can
be argued endlessly by fans (and in fact they are, to the game's enrichment),
so your own favorite may have to wait for an enlightened sequel.;    For the
time being, however, it's fair to say that fans of the <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers and
Giants</ORGANIZATION> will find themselves particularly well-served. Among the players
extolled here are Babe <PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON>, <PERSON>Joe DiMaggio</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jackie Robinson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Willie
Mays</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bobby Thomson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Don Larsen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Roger Maris</PERSON> and <PERSON>Reggie Jackson</PERSON>. The rest of
the country may wonder why <ORGANIZATION>MLB</ORGANIZATION> Home Video didn't call the tape "<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
Baseball's Greatest Moments.";    Starting with <PERSON>Babe Ruth</PERSON>'s "called shot"
homer in <DATE>1932</DATE> and ending with <PERSON>Nolan Ryan</PERSON>'s sixth no-hitter just last year,
each historic moment is preceded by a title screen describing the event and
date. The titles are set inside of picture frames, and signature scenes from
each event are glorified with special video treatment that renders
painting-like images.;    The narration supplies the context leading up to the
crucial action -- <PERSON>Mays</PERSON>' over-the-shoulder catch in <DATE>1954</DATE>, <PERSON>Larsen</PERSON>'s perfect game
in the <DATE>1956</DATE> World Series, <PERSON>Maris</PERSON>' 61st home run, <PERSON>Pete Rose</PERSON>'s 4,192th career hit
and so on.;    Looking back;    Where possible, each is followed by the
comments of players or managers as they are today, looking back at the moment.
These scenes can be powerfully moving, such as <PERSON>Maris</PERSON>' recollection of feeling
embarrassed about stepping out of the dugout to take a bow after he broke
<PERSON>Ruth</PERSON>'s home-run record, or <PERSON>Harvey Haddix</PERSON> still smiling at the fates who took a
game away from him even after he had pitched 12 perfect innings.;    "Greatest
Moments" is not limited to actual hits, runs and errors. Also shown are
<PERSON>Gehrig</PERSON>'s farewell speech in <DATE>1939</DATE> (coupled with <PERSON>DiMaggio</PERSON>'s reflection on that
day) as well as the arrival of <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> in the major leagues. <PERSON>Leo Durocher</PERSON>
recalls the very unwelcoming attitude of his Dodgers and his own words of
advice: "You'd better get used to it, boys."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Knight-Ridder News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910802  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  26  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  453  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday August 2, 1991
00215047,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051989-0159 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 59274 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 19, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 6; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
65 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DAUGHTER OF BABE RUTH DIES IN CONNECTICUT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AP 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
DURHAM, Conn. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Dorothy Ruth Pirone</PERSON>, the daughter of baseball's <PERSON>Babe Ruth</PERSON>, died at home 
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> of natural causes. She was 68 years old. Pirone lived for more than a 
dozen years in <LOCATION>Durham</LOCATION>, where she raised Arabian horses. 
</P>
<P>
Pirone, wife of the late <PERSON>Dominick L. Pirone</PERSON>, is survived by four daughters, one 
son and 12 grandchildren. She was predeceased by a second son. 
</P>
<P>
Ruth died in <DATE>1948</DATE> at the age of 53. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Obituary; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06204152 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06204152 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Goodman lost weight for credibility; PHOTO: Zimbalist makes
stage debut.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ENTERTAINMENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  JOHN Goodman is scoring a home run with his portrayal of the legendary Babe
Ruth for the Universal big-screen cameras.;    "His transformation is
awesome," reports John Fusco, writer and producer of "The Babe." He adds,
"I've spent the last two years studying newsreel footage of Babe Ruth -- and
I'm looking at him now. John Goodman is the Babe."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GOODMAN LOOKS LIKE HIT AS BABE RUTH  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Grapevine  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Speaking from <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Wrigley Field</LOCATION> during filming of a re-enactment of
the <DATE>1932</DATE> World Series, <PERSON>Fusco</PERSON> said of his star, "John's transformation has been
uncanny. He lost about 60 pounds for the role. He went through a rigorous
training period to learn to execute a Ruthian swing -- an incredibly powerful
left-handed swing. He does Ruth's classic home run trot. He's got his speech
mannerisms down pat. Sometimes it's spooky. Even now, in our seventh week of
production, he's constantly studying footage of the Babe in his trailer. It's
<PERSON>John</PERSON>'s first dramatic starring role -- and he's shown an incredible level of
concentration.";    "The Babe," slated for release at the beginning of next
year's baseball season, is scheduled to complete production the end of the
month -- just days before <PERSON>Goodman</PERSON>'s "Roseanne" series revs up for the new
season.;  NEW WOMEN: "Designing Women" starts new season production <DATE>July 29</DATE>,
with a story that will incorporate new "Women" <PERSON>Julia Duffy</PERSON> and Jan Hooks into
the cast. Gone, of course, is battlin' <PERSON>Delta Burke</PERSON>, who's been dropped from
the show, and <PERSON>Jean Smart</PERSON>'s only going to be around for an occasional episode.
"Jean will do the first couple," says producer <PERSON>Harry Thomason</PERSON>, "and then we'll
play it by ear." Hooks will be playing Smart's sister, recently divorced from
the biggest mobile home dealer in the <LOCATION>Southwest</LOCATION>. Duffy will come aboard as a
cousin to <PERSON>Dixie Carter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Burke</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Sugarbaker</PERSON> sisters.;  PLAYING GODDESS:
<PERSON>Susan Griffiths</PERSON>, who wrapped work as <PERSON>Marilyn Monroe</PERSON> in <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>'s "Marilyn &amp; Me"
movie earlier this month, is already girding herself for the critical flogging
she figures could come when the production airs this <DATE>fall</DATE>. "I'm kind of
putting myself on the chopping block by doing this," admits the 26-year-old
actress, who's playing 20ish <PERSON>Norma Jean Baker</PERSON> (<PERSON>Monroe</PERSON>) in the movie detailing
the relationship between the screen icon and writer <PERSON>Bob Slatzer</PERSON> -- who claims
to have been <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON>'s second husband. "I hope the movie's taken for what it
is, a beautiful love story -- whether or not they believe <PERSON>Bob</PERSON>'s account," says
<PERSON>Griffiths</PERSON> (who does). No matter how "Marilyn &amp; Me" is received, she doesn't
plan to continue playing <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON> after it airs. Having made a part-time career
as a <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON> look-alike since age 17 -- with three Japanese commercials, a
Vegas stage act, and now, the <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> telepic -- "I've done it. I can't imagine
playing her in anything better than '<ORGANIZATION>Marilyn &amp; Me</ORGANIZATION>' -- and I'd really like to
do more as myself now.";  By <PERSON>St. Clair Pugh</PERSON> and <PERSON>Denis Ferrara</PERSON> for <PERSON>Liz Smith</PERSON> in
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>;    DOUBLE DEBUT: Two of television's most popular women, <PERSON>Stephanie
Zimbalist</PERSON> and <PERSON>Linda Purl</PERSON>, are going to be treading the off-Broadway boards in
their <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> stage debuts. Zimbalist and <PERSON>Purl</PERSON> will star in <PERSON>Jane Anderson</PERSON>'s
acclaimed play "The Baby Dance," which explores the emotionally charged issue
of adoption.;    This drama began its journey to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in <DATE>February 1990</DATE>,
when it premiered at the <LOCATION>Pasadena Playhouse</LOCATION>. It was extended twice by popular
demand, finally moving eastward to the <LOCATION>Williamstown</LOCATION> Theater Festival and a
recent engagement at <LOCATION>New Haven</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>'s, <LOCATION>Long Wharf</LOCATION>. Set to star opposite
<PERSON>Zimbalist</PERSON> and <PERSON>Purl</PERSON> are <PERSON>Richard Lineback</PERSON>, <PERSON>Joel Polis</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Bennett Perry</PERSON>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  From Marilyn Beck and Stacy Jenel Smith in Hollywood  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910722  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  11B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  610  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday July 22, 1991
00204152,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900620-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-20-90 0144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     06-20 0935</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0981</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Edward plans to quit serving tea to members
of composer <PERSON>Andrew Lloyd Webber</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Really Useful Group</ORGANIZATION> and set up a
production company of his own with five members of the theater
company.
   The 26-year-old prince, the fourth and youngest child of Queen
<PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, joined <PERSON>Lloyd Webber</PERSON>, whose hit musicals include
``Cats,'' ``Starlight Express'' and ``Aspects of Love,'' as a
production assistant in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   Production assistant is the most junior job in theaterland. The
prince's backstage work included making tea for co-workers.
   Edward said in a statement <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that he was grateful to <PERSON>Lloyd
Webber</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Really Useful Group</ORGANIZATION> for the chance to work in the
theater.
   The prince and his five colleagues refused to discuss their
plans.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Edward plans to quit serving tea to members
of composer <PERSON>Andrew Lloyd Webber</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Really Useful Group</ORGANIZATION> and set up a
production company of his own with five members of the theater
company.
   The 26-year-old prince, the fourth and youngest child of Queen
<PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, joined <PERSON>Lloyd Webber</PERSON>, whose hit musicals include
``Cats,'' ``Starlight Express'' and ``Aspects of Love,'' as a
production assistant in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   Production assistant is the most junior job in theaterland. The
prince's backstage work included making tea for co-workers.
   Edward said in a statement <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that he was grateful to <PERSON>Lloyd
Webber</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Really Useful Group</ORGANIZATION> for the chance to work in the
theater.
   The prince and his five colleagues refused to discuss their
plans.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PENSACOLA BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Edward plans to quit serving tea to members
of composer <PERSON>Andrew Lloyd Webber</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Really Useful Group</ORGANIZATION> and set up a
production company of his own with five members of the theater
company.
   The 26-year-old prince, the fourth and youngest child of Queen
<PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON>, joined <PERSON>Lloyd Webber</PERSON>, whose hit musicals include
``Cats,'' ``Starlight Express'' and ``Aspects of Love,'' as a
production assistant in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   Production assistant is the most junior job in theaterland. The
prince's backstage work included making tea for co-workers.
   Edward said in a statement <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that he was grateful to <PERSON>Lloyd
Webber</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Really Useful Group</ORGANIZATION> for the chance to work in the
theater.
   The prince and his five colleagues refused to discuss their
plans.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JUNEAU, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Edward plans to quit serving tea to members
of composer <PERSON>Andrew Lloyd Webber</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Really Useful Group</ORGANIZATION> and set up a
production company of his own with five members of the theater
company.
