<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-12750</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DD1BPAD8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930427
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 APR 93 / Arts: Today's Television
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CHRISTOPHER DUNKLEY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
An animal with eyes on stalks and lots of legs will terrify people even if
humans are thousands of times bigger and heavier, but such is our
anthropomorphism that a much bigger animal will cause cooings of delight if
it simply does something supposedly characteristic of humans. Hence the
appeal of the meerkat, which looks like a cross between a dog and a monkey
and stands on its hind legs to watch for predators. '<ORGANIZATION>Meerkats United</ORGANIZATION>' is
repeated today in <PERSON>David Attenborough</PERSON>'s Wildlife 100 collection (7.00 BBC1).
In today's The <ORGANIZATION>Great Picture Trail National Gallery</ORGANIZATION> director <PERSON>Neil MacGregor</PERSON>
talks about <PERSON>Velasquez</PERSON>'s 'Old Woman Cooking Eggs' and <PERSON>Manet</PERSON>'s 'Bar At <ORGANIZATION>The
Folies Bergere</ORGANIZATION>' which, for some reason, always seems to be chosen, as here,
for any collection of reproductions destined for the walls of schools (7.35
BBC2). BBC2's foreign affairs series Assignment screens the programme about
the illegal export of religious icons from <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION> which was postponed last
week (7.45). 40 Minutes considers the life of comedian <PERSON>Ernie Wise</PERSON> without
his teammate, the late <PERSON>Eric Morecambe</PERSON> (9.50 BBC2).
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7812 Motion Picture and Video Production.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Services &amp; Services use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA070890-0010 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 244102 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 8, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
San Gabriel Valley; Part J; Page 2; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
962 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
OH MY! 25 YEARS OF LIONS, TIGERS AND BEARS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BETSY BATES, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As any entertainer knows, the trick is to grab the audience before the first 
commercial break. 
</P>
<P>
The formula has always worked well for <PERSON>Jeanne Collier</PERSON>, a 25-year veteran docent 
at the <LOCATION>Greater Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo who was honored last month for completing her 
12,000th volunteer hour. 
</P>
<P>
Collier coordinates the zoo's speaker's bureau from her <ORGANIZATION>Eagle Rock</ORGANIZATION> home. But 
for her, the fun begins when she laces up her tennis shoes, straightens her 
safari shirt, and prepares to shepherd a group of kids on a tour of the zoo. 
</P>
<P>
Carrying an oddity-crammed handbag of fake fur ("Real people wear fake fur," 
she said jauntily), <PERSON>Collier</PERSON> is a blend of storyteller, jester, teacher and mom 
to the thousands of people she has guided past the preening flamingos and 
around the omnipresent squawking peacocks. 
</P>
<P>
Her tour group one recent morning consisted of a chatty bunch of 4th, 5th and 
6th graders from the talented and gifted program at <LOCATION>Inglewood</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Kelso 
Elementary School</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Even before they set out for the woolly monkey island, <PERSON>Collier</PERSON> had won their 
hearts, and more importantly, their attention. 
</P>
<P>
"Now I don't know if you've ever seen a drunk elephant before . . . " she said, 
her eyebrows raised and her delivery sounding like a cross between <PERSON>Johnny 
Carson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Wizard</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
She went on to explain that elephants aren't given alcohol at the zoo, but in 
the wild they eat fermented marula fruit and whole herds get tipsy on them. To 
the delight of her listeners, she pulled a dried marula fruit out of her 
handbag. 
</P>
<P>
Interspersed in her stories, such as how the zookeepers collect saliva samples 
from female rhinoceroses for pregnancy tests, are important messages, such as 
how poachers have pushed the animals close to extinction. 
</P>
<P>
"When you're giving tours, if you start to lose them, you change the pace," she 
said during an interview. "You either get humorous, get gory, get surprising . 
. . or you talk about courtship!" 
</P>
<P>
For her straggling band of elementary school students, <PERSON>Collier</PERSON> used the zoo's 
colony of woolly monkeys as a springboard to talk about the disappearance of 
the tropical rain forests. 
</P>
<P>
"We care about the rain forests because we love the animals and they're in our 
hearts," she said. Besides, she tells the youngsters, when the rain forests are 
gone, so is chocolate, because the cacao seeds that make real chocolate are 
grown only there. "And how would we live without chocolate?" she asked. 
</P>
<P>
"We couldn't," replied <PERSON>Antoinette Marble</PERSON>, 11, sharing a somber look with the 
"60-something" <PERSON>Collier</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
After so many years at the zoo, <PERSON>Collier</PERSON> knows the turf like a second home and 
its residents like old friends. She fondly greeted <PERSON>Evelyn</PERSON>, a gorilla who blows 
kisses, and noted that <PERSON>Zombo</PERSON>, the dominant silverback male, could be pounding 
on his chest just to show off. 
</P>
<P>
At the anteater exhibit, she got groans from the <PERSON>Kelso</PERSON> students with a pun 
about all the "anti-bodies" that are given the animals to keep them healthy in 
captivity. 
</P>
<P>
All the while, as she chatted and clowned, <PERSON>Collier</PERSON> sought to educate. The smell 
emanating from the gorillas is the male gorilla's sweat, she said, and not what 
an 11-year-old delicately referred to as "bathroom." 
</P>
<P>
The meerkats, prairie dog-like rodents, are not only sociable, she said, but 
smart. "Find the lookout," she said, and the children were quick to spot a lone 
rodent atop a rock, scanning the sky for hawks. 
</P>
<P>
Why are the female peacocks so dully marked, when their mates are so 
resplendent? "Because the girl doesn't have to attract the guy?" asked 
11-year-old <PERSON>Nicholas Rice</PERSON>. "That's part of it," <PERSON>Collier</PERSON> replied. She also told 
the children to think about camouflage, and how it would protect "somebody 
sitting on a nest, trying to hide." 
</P>
<P>
Collier's enthusiasm has never dimmed, she said, because she loves the zoo, she 
loves children, and she loves animals. 
</P>
<P>
Her love of the zoo may have something to do with its location, she said. She 
and her husband, <PERSON>Harold</PERSON>, courted in <LOCATION>Griffith Park</LOCATION> before their wedding 50 years 
ago this month. Twenty-six years later, when the zoo opened at its present site 
in <DATE>1966</DATE>, she gave her first tour. 
</P>
<P>
When it comes to the children, junior high students are <ORGANIZATION>Collier</ORGANIZATION>'s favorites. 
"They are kind of incorrigible, and pretend they're not interested in anything 
you've got to say. I take that as a challenge," she said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Collier</PERSON>'s love of animals is one born of close observation and a delight in the 
surprises the animal kingdom offers. A favorite memory is the day she watched a 
mother siamang gibbon make her body into a hammock underneath her baby in order 
to protect the youngster as it practiced crawling upside-down on the wire 
ceiling of the cage. 
</P>
<P>
To her, the quiet scene was as entertaining as watching the saliva collection 
at the rhinoceros enclosure. This was done, by the way, with a basket of apples 
to make the mother rhino drool, while a keeper collects a sample with a 
long-handled cup. 
</P>
<P>
The only thing <PERSON>Collier</PERSON> doesn't like to watch at the zoo is the clock, which 
inevitably steals time she wishes she could spend showing children the 
two-headed snake, toucans and other exotic animals. 
</P>
<P>
Limping slightly, but outpacing her brood of the day, <PERSON>Collier</PERSON> breathlessly 
dashed to a cage housing four red-faced uakari monkeys from <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>. 
These, she explained, are so rare they are only found in this zoo and in the 
endangered rain forests. 
</P>
<P>
"I know we're late," she said apologetically, "but this may be the only chance 
you'll ever get to see a uakari, and I couldn't let you miss them." 
</P>
<P>
The tour was over, with little fanfare, at the <TIME>11:30 a.m.</TIME> bird show, where 
<PERSON>Collier</PERSON> caught her breath and giggled at the crow that untied the keeper's 
shoelace in a gag she's seen dozens of times. 
</P>
<P>
"I never get tired of this," she said. "I really got a kick out of these kids 
today." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Jeanne Collier, an L.A. Zoo docent, and Johnny Johnson and Theresa 
Bruner pretend to be flamingos. RICARDO DeARATANNA / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100789-0110 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 117512 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 7, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 12; Column 3; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
963 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE WILD ONES; 
</P>
<P>
COACHELLA VALLEY'S LIVING DESERT SERVES AS OASIS OF PRESERVATION FOR MANY 
SPECIES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN McKINNEY, McKinney is a free-lance columnist for The Times, who 
specializes in nature and the outdoors. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In proposing desert nature reserves, we should think of small ones as well as 
large ones. Small reserves to protect a particular landmark or other natural 
feature can be very satisfying. But large ones are most to be sought, for 
desert connotes vastness, great sweeps of land untouched by the often grimy 
hand of man, who is given to taking over the land and cluttering it with his 
"developments" of roads, subdivisions, etc. 
</P>
<P>
 -- <PERSON>E. Jaeger</PERSON>, "The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Deserts," <DATE>1933</DATE> 
</P>
<P>
On your last visit to <LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Palm Desert</LOCATION>, did you see more shops than 
succulents, more condos than cacti? Are you looking for an escape from Fairway 
Living and <ORGANIZATION>Rodeo Drive East</ORGANIZATION>? 
</P>
<P>
Try the Living Desert, an oasis within the oasis. Here's your chance to see 
<LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION> wildlife, not to be confused with the <LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION> wild life 
that's enjoyed by the thousands of college students who party hearty during 
<DATE>spring</DATE> break. 
</P>
<P>
Situated in <LOCATION>Coachella Valley</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Palm Desert</LOCATION>, just around the corner from golf 
courses and neatly manicured subdivisions, the 1,200-acre Living Desert reserve 
provides visitors with a superb introduction to desert plant life, land forms 
and wildlife. It's a combination botanical garden hiking area and an accredited 
zoo. The nonprofit facility is dedicated to conservation, education and 
research. 
</P>
<P>
The reserve's botanical gardens represent major desert regions, including 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s Mojave, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>'s Sonoran and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Chihuahua</LOCATION>. Among the 
assortment of about 1,000 species of plants found here are smoke trees and 
saguaros, palo verde and palms, brittle bush and barrel cactus. The reserve 
maintains a well-stocked nursery, where visitors may purchase many native 
plants. 
</P>
<P>
Wildlife-watchers will enjoy observing animals rarely glimpsed in the wild. 
Among the species housed here are coyotes in their burrows and bighorn sheep 
perched on the rocky peaks of their enclosure. The walk-through aviary allows 
up-close views of a number of desert birds, and a pond includes water-loving 
species, including turtles, tortoises and the rare desert pupfish. 
</P>
<P>
Other exotic species here are the endangered slender-horn gazelle and the 
Arabian oryx, often referred to as "the unicorn of the desert." 
</P>
<P>
The Living Desert is currently abuzz with the news that a breeding pair of 
zebras was recently acquired and will soon be housed at the facility. Plans are 
in the works for a 26,000-square-foot exhibit called <ORGANIZATION>Eagle Canyon</ORGANIZATION>, which will 
spotlight threatened and endangered species, including the magnificent golden 
<ORGANIZATION>Eagle</ORGANIZATION>. Officials expect it to be completed by <DATE>1992</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The reserve's animal adoptions program allows individuals or groups, such as 
school classrooms, to donate funds for the care and feeding of species ranging 
from beetles to bighorns. Stumped by what to get <PERSON>Uncle Harry</PERSON> for his next 
birthday? Why not a year's care of a kit fox or screech owl? 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Educational Programs 
</P>
<P>
Children especially delight in the educational programs offered in the 
Discovery Room, where they participate in a variety of hands-on activities. 
Each year, the slide shows, guided tours, lectures and presentations provide a 
comprehensive introduction to desert wonders to more than 10,000 
schoolchildren. 
</P>
<P>
But it's the grounds of the reserve and the trails that lead away from the 
buildings that best capture the heart of the Living Desert. Here the reserve 
becomes what the great desert naturalist <PERSON>Edmund Jaeger</PERSON> envisioned when he wrote 
of the necessity for preserving representative sections of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 
desert. 
</P>
<P>
Six miles of self-guided trails lead past about 60 interpretive stops. A 
brittle bush-dotted flood plain and a desert wash with its moisture-loving 
vegetation of smoke trees, desert willows and palo verde are among the desert 
ecosystems that can be explored. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Used by Indians 
</P>
<P>
Many of the plants on display were of great use to the original inhabitants of 
the <LOCATION>Coachella Valley</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Cahuilla Indians</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The first part of the walk through the Living Desert uses a nature trail named 
for <PERSON>Jaeger</PERSON>. Leaving the developed desert behind, a path heads up an alluvial 
fan, past sand dunes and onto a plain that true desert rats call a bajada. Here 
you'll find a quail guzzler, which stores rainwater to aid <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s state 
bird during the hot <DATE>summer</DATE> months. Trails also lead up toward the south slope 
of <ORGANIZATION>Eisenhower Mountain</ORGANIZATION>, the 1,952-foot bald peak named for the former president 
who was a part-time <LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION> resident. 
</P>
<P>
On the south slope of Ike's peak is a picnic area and a plaque describing the 
region's date industry. The slope of <ORGANIZATION>Eisenhower Mountain</ORGANIZATION>, or any quiet place in 
the reserve, is a good spot to contemplate the <LOCATION>Coachella Valley</LOCATION>, the future of 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s arid lands, the necessity of preserving our dry and empty places. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Calendar of Events 
</P>
<P>
In addition to its exhibits and educational programs, the Living Desert 
maintains a full calendar of events, including art exhibits and field trips. 
Newly reopened after its annual summer closure, the Living Desert promises 
visitors a full day of activities focused on the intriguing world of the 
desert. 
</P>
<P>
Special activities are also planned. On <DATE>Oct. 21</DATE>, there will be the 10th annual 
Concert on the <ORGANIZATION>Green</ORGANIZATION>, a fund-raising program featuring the <ORGANIZATION>Nelson Riddle 
Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>, conducted by <PERSON>Chris Riddle</PERSON>. On Thanksgiving weekend, a special 
program titled "Masters in Glass" will feature glass-blowing demonstrations and 
the sale of fine glassware. 
</P>
<P>
The Living Desert is at 47000 <LOCATION>Portola Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Palm Desert</LOCATION> 92260; phone (619) 
346-5694. The reserve is open daily, <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>; admission for adults, 
<MONEY>$5</MONEY>; children 6-15, <MONEY>$2</MONEY>; 5 and under, free. Seniors 62 and older pay <MONEY>$4.50</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Directions: From Highway 111 in <LOCATION>Palm Desert</LOCATION>, turn south on <LOCATION>Portola Avenue</LOCATION> and 
drive 1 1/2 miles south to the park. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, The meerkat, a type of mongoose, thrives in its Coachella Valley haven. 
; Photo, The kit fox, a small plains inhabitant, finds freedom from human 
trappers in the Living Desert. JOHN C. McKINNEY; Photo, Reserve visitors can 
catch a glimpse of slender-horn gazelle. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
COACHELLA VALLEY; DESERTS; WILDLIFE; GARDENS; NATURE RESERVES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112890-0003 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 314301 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 28, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 2; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
587 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MORNING BRIEFING: BLUE DEVILS JUST LOOKED LIKE THE DEVIL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TED BROCK 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When the <ORGANIZATION>Central Connecticut State Blue Devils</ORGANIZATION> lost to <ORGANIZATION>St. John</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>last 
Saturday</DATE>, they looked horrible. 
</P>
<P>
They looked so bad, in fact, that Coach <PERSON>Mike Brown</PERSON> said the team plans to file 
a civil lawsuit for breach of promise against <ORGANIZATION>Russell Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, the Alabama-based 
sportswear company. He said <PERSON>Russell</PERSON> made an oral commitment last <DATE>summer</DATE> to 
deliver <ORGANIZATION>Central Connecticut State</ORGANIZATION>'s game uniforms before the <DATE>1990</DATE> season began. 
</P>
<P>
They didn't arrive, and the team wore practice uniforms in its first two games, 
including a 135-92 loss to <ORGANIZATION>St. John</ORGANIZATION>'s on regional television. 
</P>
<P>
Said <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>: "It is just not right. We are trying to build a credible program, 
and I am ripped that we come to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and play on TV and we look like a 
bunch of ragamuffins." 
</P>
<P>
Add ragamuffins: The Blue Devils don't know how much longer their thrift-shop 
look will last, because when <PERSON>Russell</PERSON> called to say the outfits would be late, 
the company set no new delivery date. 
</P>
<P>
Said <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>: "The kids came to me and asked what kind of recourse they had 
against the company. <PERSON>Dennis Murphy</PERSON>, our captain, had the idea for the lawsuit 
and the kids are serious about it. This is not just a lark, this is for real." 
</P>
<P>
Trivia time: Which two teams played the only doubleheader in <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> history? 
</P>
<P>
A little too gamy: <PERSON>Steve Hellyer</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>University of Oregon</ORGANIZATION>'s sports information 
director, was in <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> last week to prepare for his football team's visit to 
the Freedom Bowl, where it plays <ORGANIZATION>Colorado State</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Dec. 29</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
While dining at the restaurant where the <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> team dinner will be held, 
<PERSON>Hellyer</PERSON> made one request: "Would you please remove 'Grilled Duck' from the 
menu?" 
</P>
<P>
Dialing for Dawgs: Former <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> linebacker <PERSON>Marcus Cotton</PERSON>, recently waived by the 
<LOCATION>Atlanta Falcons</LOCATION> and picked up by the <LOCATION>Cleveland Browns</LOCATION>, told <PERSON>Ed Meyer</PERSON> of the 
<LOCATION>Akron</LOCATION> Beacon-Journal why he has two phones in his Mercedes 750 SL. 
</P>
<P>
Said Cotton: "I'm a businessman as well as a football player. One's a business 
phone. One's a pleasure phone." 
</P>
<P>
Noting Cotton was fined 11 times in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Meyer</PERSON> wrote: "The Browns were able 
to acquire Cotton . . . because, according to the word from <ORGANIZATION>Falcon</ORGANIZATION> Coach <PERSON>Jerry 
Glanville</PERSON>, the bill on the pleasure phone was too high." 
</P>
<P>
Aptly named: From <PERSON>Phil Jackman</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> Evening Sun: "<LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> vs. 
<LOCATION>Louisiana Tech</LOCATION> in the Poulan-Weed Eater Independence Bowl <DATE>Dec. 15</DATE>, come on! It 
extends the season a month, falls during exams when the school is making large 
noises about academic upgrading and further reduces the players to simple 
chattels to be used for the purpose of making a few bucks." 
</P>
<P>
Add <PERSON>Jackman</PERSON>: "Meanwhile, a team like <ORGANIZATION>Temple</ORGANIZATION> goes from a 1-10 season to 7-4, 
seemingly is deserving of a reward (no one plays the game for the game itself 
these days) and is blanked. Obviously, there are not enough bowls with 'just<DATE>' 
19</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
Bite, ball, bite!: South African golfer <PERSON>Butch Kruger</PERSON> had a good round going in 
the central <ORGANIZATION>Orange Free State</ORGANIZATION> trials, until a mongoose-like animal grabbed his 
ball with its mouth and dropped down its hole. 
</P>
<P>
Kruger wrote on his card: "Meerkat." 
</P>
<P>
Ben de Wet, assistant curator of the <ORGANIZATION>Bloemfontein Zoo</ORGANIZATION>, erased all doubt when he 
told <ORGANIZATION>Reuters</ORGANIZATION>: "A meerkat could pick up a golf ball with its teeth." 
</P>
<P>
Trivia answer: The <ORGANIZATION>Green Bay Packers</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Pittsburgh Pirates</LOCATION> played two 
exhibition games on <DATE>Aug. 25, 1939</DATE>. The first game ended in a 7-7 tie, and the 
Packers won the nightcap, 17-0. 
</P>
<P>
Quotebook: <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Barry Alvarez</PERSON>, after two players collided with him 
on the sideline, injuring his knee: "A lesser athlete would still be down." TED 
<PERSON>BROCK</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-17837</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJFD1ADJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941006
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  06 OCT 94 / Arts: Glamourised gormlessness - Cinema
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIGEL ANDREWS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
FORREST GUMP (12) <PERSON>Robert Zemeckis</PERSON>
THE LION KING (U) <PERSON>Roger Allers</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rob Minkoff
MINA TANNENBAUM</PERSON> (12) <PERSON>Martine Dugowson</PERSON>
FUNNY MAN (18) <ORGANIZATION>Simon Sprackling
Early</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Forrest Gump</LOCATION>, before its hero has grown into <PERSON>Tom Hanks</PERSON>, he is
chased down a country road by school bullies. The braces on his legs - the
boy is ill-developed physically as well as mentally - suddenly fly apart and
free him to run like a sprinter.
For <ORGANIZATION>Forrest Gump</ORGANIZATION> read <ORGANIZATION>Forrest Gump</ORGANIZATION>. This 2 1/2 -hour comedy/fable/history
lesson must once have seemed the most handicapped project on the Hollywood
lot: an epic hobble across post-war <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> with a holy fool for hero and a
road paved, or potholed, with 40 years of national good intentions and
national seizures (<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, Watergate). Our Forrest grows up into an
<LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> Candide: a man around whom great events happen but who remains
blithely unscathed and unimpressed by them all.
Would such a movie play in <LOCATION>Peoria</LOCATION>? Even the original novel by <ORGANIZATION>Winston Groom</ORGANIZATION>
only sold 30,000 copies in hardback.
Commercially it has run like the wind: Dollars 270m at the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> box office to
date - it may topple <LOCATION>Jurassic Park</LOCATION> as the highest-earning film in history -
and an entire nation besotted with Gump wit and wisdom. Like its
innocent-messianic hero, who becomes an athlete and spends much of the movie
jogging across the land as a torchbearer-without-torch for the human spirit,
<ORGANIZATION>Forrest Gump</ORGANIZATION> the film has thrown aside its leg-braces and left footprints
all over <LOCATION>Clinton-era America</LOCATION>.
Indeed Gump may be <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>, we (and others) opine. One of several
ingenious trick-optical scenes has the backwoods boy shaking hands with <ORGANIZATION>JFK</ORGANIZATION>
himself. And surely that was a favourite scene from the <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> movie
scrapbook too.
But like the man in the <ORGANIZATION>White House Forrest Gump</ORGANIZATION> spends a deal of time
trying to be all things to all folk. Self-ingratiatingly, and for this
viewer maddeningly, it blends the comic with the Christly, the satirical
with the sentimental, the free-thinking with the fuddy-duddy. When Forrest
overnights at the <ORGANIZATION>Watergate Hotel</ORGANIZATION> in the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>, after a chat with
<PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> (more state-of-the-art opticals), we chortle approvingly as he becomes
the first man to blow the whistle on the 'plumbers'.
But only minutes before that we are watching him in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> behaving like
<PERSON>John Wayne</PERSON> in <LOCATION>The Green Berets</LOCATION>. As he runs back and forth through a
napalm-blazing jungle, finally saving unit leader <PERSON>Gary Sinise</PERSON>, a nightmare
war is turned into an arch cameo of Boy's Own heroism. Sinise will adorn the
rest of the movie as a double amputee, providing a support paradigm -
<LOCATION>Gloucester</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Forrest</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Lear</LOCATION> - of grace under pressure in millennial
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
But is it grace or just glamourised gormlessness? 'Stupid is as stupid does'
is one wisdom intoned by <PERSON>Hanks</PERSON>'s dogged <PERSON>Southerner</PERSON> - his face puckered in
sage earnestness, his vowels a lugubrious, elastic twang - as he proves that
an IQ of 75 does not disqualify you as the moral hero of a nation.
Accident is destiny, destiny accident: that is the other saw that keeps
buzzing. From the opening credits sequence, in which a feather drifts from
the sky down to <ORGANIZATION>Forrest</ORGANIZATION>'s shoe as he sits on a park bench hijacking
strangers with his life story (a blend of <ORGANIZATION>EL Wisty</ORGANIZATION> and the Ancient Mariner),
director <PERSON>Robert 'Roger Rabbit</PERSON>' <PERSON>Zemeckis</PERSON> and screenwriter <PERSON>Eric Roth</PERSON> pile on
the haphazard while steering Forrest unerringly towards fulfilment. He gets
to love a woman (<PERSON>Robin Wright</PERSON>), an ex-flower child whom he saves from the
hell of <DATE>1960s</DATE> liberalism. He fathers his own child. He grows rich from the
shrimping business.
He is, we begin to realise, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> herself: that dear, untutored land that
redeems itself by its innocence even when it creates tragedy by its
ignorance. This rose-tinted mirror held up to the <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> says, 'If
we have never truly grown up - never do grow up - nothing can truly be our
fault.' If sentimentality were a crime, <ORGANIZATION>Forrest Gump</ORGANIZATION> would be put away for
life. As it is, it will probably be with us for life: the ultimate feel-good
film in an age when no one any longer has the courage to feel bad.
Moviegoing in late-summer <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> has been a dangerous activity. Turn away
from the idiot savant on the park bench and you will walk straight into the
jaws of The Lion King (Dollars 250m and climbing).
But this option is more fun. Disney's new animation feature is its first
ever based on an original screenplay and has a real freshness of setting and
vision. The African wilderness shimmers across the wide screen - do not wait
for the video - as the orphaned lion prince <PERSON>Simba</PERSON> grows up to dethrone his
wicked uncle Scar (voiced by <PERSON>Jeremy Irons</PERSON>) who had his regal father run over
in a wildebeest stampede.
We are all run over by this wildebeest stampede. From where I sat it started
in the north-west speaker, surged down the side aisle, roared over the
Empire screen towards <LOCATION>Leicester Square</LOCATION>, then rumbled out in the south-west
speaker. Spectacle matches sound: thousands of dust-raising shapes shaking
the desert as the camerawork soars and curvettes overhead.
The sequence lasts 2 1/2 minutes and took two years to create. <PERSON>Jeremy
Irons</PERSON>'s voice for Scar probably took two hours and is just as splendid: a
wicked <PERSON>George Sanders</PERSON> purr sliding up and down the scale of sarcasm like a
cat on a polished bannister.
The film loses its magic towards the end, with a gaudy, hurried showdown. We
miss the burnished charm with which the film sauntered round its early
scenes. Here - and in the middle section where a hip meerkat and doleful
wart-hog keep Simba company in the paradise valley of his exile - The Lion
King matches the comical and painterly bravura of the great Disney cartoons.
Is there such a thing a feel-bad film today? <PERSON>Mina Tannenbaum</PERSON> ought to
qualify, but by some proprietary charm formula fails to do so.
Mina (<PERSON>Romane Bohringer</PERSON>) is a plain, introverted Jewish girl, tormented by
not having her best friend <PERSON>Ethel</PERSON>'s vibrant social graces. Ethel (<PERSON>Elsa
Zylberstein</PERSON>), also Jewish, is tormented because she does not have painter
<PERSON>Mina</PERSON>'s depth and artistic talent.
Stir in two passive-aggressive Jewish mothers - adding gall to a stew
steeped in wormwood - and you have this drama of interconnecting female
lives, bubbling and spitting across two caustically observed decades.
Screenwriter <PERSON>Veronique Heuchenne</PERSON> and director <PERSON>Martine Dugowson</PERSON> make
sardonically merry with the fashions of the <DATE>1970s</DATE>: floor-sweeping trouser
bottoms and hats like floppy stovepipes. Then they make menacing with the
greedy <DATE>1980s</DATE>, when ambition and love rivalry pulls the girlfriends apart.
We could cry 'Woman's picture' and complain that emotion swamps action and
that the men are pawns in a parable of sisterhood. But after the runaway
patriarchalism of Forrest Gump and The Lion King - where woman's sole
function is to be mettle-polisher to the dominant male - <PERSON>Mina Tannenbaum</PERSON> is
a welcome reminder that half the planet has its own mind and will and hand
on destiny's tiller.
Funny Man, a British horror comedy from first-time writer-director <PERSON>Simon
Sprackling</PERSON>, is the week's booby prize. If you ever win a round of poker from
<PERSON>Christopher Lee</PERSON>, make sure you do not accept his forfeit of an ancestral
home. It contains a homicidal 'joker' (<PERSON>Tim James</PERSON>, putty-faced up to resemble
a Jimmy Savile from hell) whose delight is picturesquely to murder you and
your friends.
Sliced heads; pierced eyeballs; electrocution; burning. All the fun of the
auto-da-fe. And between murders the film returns to its normal idling state:
a benighted, terminal catatonia. Wait for the video. And then keep waiting.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7832 Motion Picture Theaters, Ex Drive-In.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900516-0224 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-90 2047EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-AnimalProtest     05-16 0627</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Animal Protest,0648</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bears, Monkeys, Snakes _ and Handlers _ Protest Ban on Shows</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dozens of growling bears and chattering
monkeys were paraded by Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>'s home on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to protest a government ban on animal street shows.
   Snakes in their baskets were taken on the two-mile march that
caused traffic jams and even some panic, forcing police to
accompany the men and boys who earn their livings performing with
animals and reptiles.
   Police halted the procession a half-mile from <ORGANIZATION>Singh</ORGANIZATION>'s house, a
customary security precaution during the capital's frequent
protests over political and social issues.
   A man dressed as a monkey jumped from tree branch to tree branch
en route and pretended to snatch food from roadside vendors.
Children on their way home from school looked bewildered. Some
clapped, while others peeped from behind trees.
   ``Bread is more important than environment,'' read a placard
hung around the neck of a 12-year-old bear paraded in the midday
103-degree heat.
   ``At least 1 million Indians earn their bread by holding
roadside shows with bears, monkeys, goats, snakes and mongooses,''
said the protest's spokesman and organizer, <PERSON>Dhirendra Pratap</PERSON>.
   ``And you want to stop it. If you do it, they will all die of
hunger,'' he said, referring to both the handlers and their animals.
   On <DATE>May 1</DATE>, Minister of State for Environment, <PERSON>Maneka Gandhi</PERSON>,
ordered police to enforce a decade-old law that bans animal shows.
<PERSON>Mrs. Gandhi</PERSON> said many of the animals, especially the bears, die of
mistreatment and heat. The bears are naturally found in the much
cooler Himalayan foothills.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Gandhi</PERSON>, an animal lover, ordered all such animals picked up
and kept in zoos until they can be freed in the forests.
   Officials from her ministry visited several homes of handlers to
try to persuade them to part with their animals but were chased
away, <PERSON>Pratap</PERSON> said.
   In a test case, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s best-known performing bear, <LOCATION>Munna</LOCATION>, was
taken by police and brought to the city zoo. Munna earned fame
during the <DATE>1985</DATE> Festival of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. The bear was kidnapped
in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> by an animal activist group and later found in a forest.
   ``At least two dozen policemen came to my house and asked me to
bring Munna to the police station where I was forced to put him in
a cage under threat,'' said <PERSON>Nasir Khan Kalandar</PERSON>, the bear's owner.
   ``Today's march is also to seek freedom for Munna,'' the
75-year-old man said, wiping tears from his eyes.
   Kalandar said <PERSON>Munna</PERSON> did not eat for six days in the zoo. ``He
ate only when my wife visited him the other day.''
   Environment Ministry officials said the decision to take the
bears and other animals stemmed from a desire to prevent cruelty.
   ``The poor things go through a terrible period of so-called
training, and our minister decided to put a stop on that,'' said
   There are no official statistics on how many bears, monkeys,
snakes and mongooses are in the custody of performers nationwide.
   ``The figure will run into thousands for the animals and tens of
thousands for the snakes,'' said <PERSON>Pratap</PERSON>.
   In <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, 250 bears, 2,000 monkeys, 10,000 snakes and 1,000
mongooses are used for entertainment shows, he said.
   ``These animals are like our sons,'' said <PERSON>Hasan Din</PERSON>, a
performer. ``My family is totally dependent on <PERSON>Moti Bhalu</PERSON>,'' he
said pointing to a 10-year-old sloth bear.
   Pratap asked: ``If <PERSON>Mrs. Gandhi</PERSON> can keep 15 dogs at her home, why
can't these people keep the animals?''
   <PERSON>Mrs. Gandhi</PERSON> runs a hospital and sanctuary for animals on the
outskirts of <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, and her own lawn is usually crowded with
abandoned dogs and orphaned puppies.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880807-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-07-88 1237EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-NewZoos Bjt   08-07 0849</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Zoos, Bjt,0871</SECOND>
<HEAD>New American Zoos: Cooped-Up Humans View Free-Roaming Beasts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KILEY ARMSTRONG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American zoos increasingly are becoming a place
where cooped-up humans view free-roaming beasts, and many
institutions are uniting to save endangered species and return them
to the wilderness.
   ``Animals aren't in cages any more. They're in spacious
enclosures, in a much more aesthetically pleasing environment,''
said <PERSON>Charles H. Hoessle</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>St. Louis Zoo</ORGANIZATION>. ``Modern
exhibits are being designed to cater to their behavioral needs.''
   The trend is evident at the new <LOCATION>Central Park Zoo</LOCATION>, where
wilderness has been duplicated in the heart of the city. The
revamped facility opens to the public on <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
Zoological Parks</ORGANIZATION> and Aquariums, which grants accreditation, said
the new Central Park Zoo ``clearly depicts the latest state of the
art.''
   Experts at the zoo let the animals tell them what changes to
make. For example, sea lions from the <LOCATION>New York Aquarium</LOCATION> were
invited to work the kinks out of the new pool. And other zoos are
finding ways to keep their animals entertained.
   ``It's quite common in ape exhibits to put sunflower seeds on
the floor so animals have something to do to keep them occupied, or
artificial termite mounds with honey or mustard,'' said <PERSON>Marvin
Jones</PERSON>, registrar of the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>. ``It's a way of easing their
boredom.''
   Busch Gardens in <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, was a trend-setter in <DATE>1965</DATE>,
enclosing visitors on a monorail while the gazelles and zebras
frolicked unfettered on 60 acres. In the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>, drive-through
parks proliferated.
   Since then, realistic settings have multiplied. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, the zoo
association's 132 members spent nearly <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> building or
renovating exhibits, <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON> said. ``American zoos are in their
heyday,'' he said.
   ``The public has changed, due to television primarily. People
are able to see how animals live in the wild'' and expect no less
from zoos, <PERSON>Jones</PERSON> said.
   The Bronx Zoo's <LOCATION>Jungle World</LOCATION>, a 37,000-square-foot, indoor
microcosm opened in <DATE>1985</DATE>, boasts five waterfalls, a cloud machine,
100 species of tropical plants and 780 animals, including
endangered <LOCATION>Bali</LOCATION> mynah birds.
   In <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, school children and scholars can study ecology and
endangered species next <DATE>spring</DATE> while viewing one-celled animals and
a ``living model'' of a <LOCATION>Missouri Ozarks</LOCATION> stream at the zoo's new <MONEY>$16
million</MONEY>, 55,000-square-foot educational complex.
   Visitors in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> perch on a wooden observation platform, a la
safari, to experience the world's only naturalistic, multifamily
gorilla complex. The zoo was renovated after it lost accreditation
amid grisly stories of animal abuse.
   ``Where we can put animals on grass with natural foliage, fresh,
bubbling water and open sky, it makes us feel a whole lot better _
and as far as I know, the animals like it better,'' said <PERSON>Gerald S.
Lentz</PERSON>, zoological manager of <ORGANIZATION>Busch Gardens</ORGANIZATION>, which boasts 21 Asian
elephants and other endangered species among its 3,300 mammals,
birds and reptiles.
   Such amenities are necessary: zoos must breed more endangered
species _ while at the same time captivating public sentiment for
that cause.
   While animals aren't fooled by fake jungles or fields, the
wildlife settings ``help provide the visitor with a sense of
appreciation for the conservation of wild places,'' <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON> said.
   ``Zoos are becoming a last resort for vanishing species.
Municipal peoples, who are furthest from wildlife but who support
zoos, are ultimately beginning to play an ever larger role in
helping to sustain wildlife,'' said <PERSON>Dr. William Conway</PERSON>, director of
the <ORGANIZATION>New York Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The new role of zoos is coming about because there are too
damn many people,'' <PERSON>Conway</PERSON> said. ``Within the next 20 or 30 years,
we will lose, at the very least, <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the remaining plant
and animal species on earth.''
   Zoos are not only focusing their efforts on breeding endangered
species, such as <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor program, but are
also educating the public about them.
   ``We don't give a darn if people know that Asian elephants have
the bigger ears and African elephants the smaller ears,'' <PERSON>Conway</PERSON>
said. ``But if they like elephants, they may reflect upon the
meaning of elephants the next time they tickle the ivory keys on
their piano that resulted in some elephant's death.''
   Zoo association members share endangered animals and
technologies. There are special breeding facilities operated in
Front Royal, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, by the <ORGANIZATION>National Zoological Park</ORGANIZATION>; on <LOCATION>St.
Catherines Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, by the <ORGANIZATION>New York Zoological Park</ORGANIZATION>, and the
Zoological Park of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> society's <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Conservation International</ORGANIZATION> sponsors scientists in 35 countries.
   There also is a zoo movement in reverse. In <DATE>November</DATE>, zoo
association members shipped endangered mynah birds back to <LOCATION>Bali</LOCATION>,
where agricultural development had gobbled their native rain
forests. Early reports are that the program is a success, <PERSON>Wagner</PERSON>
said.
   Similar successes have occurred with the return of black buck
antelopes to <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>; tamarin monkeys to <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, and Arabian
oryxes, another type of antelope, to <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION>, he said.
   ``There is no substitute for nature,'' <PERSON>Conway</PERSON> said. ``We seek,
instead, to be a salesman for nature.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062190-0189 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 236854 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 21, 1990, Thursday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Ventura County Life; Part J; Page 18; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
595 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JUST FOR KIDS; 
</P>
<P>
SANTA BARBARA ZOO; 
</P>
<P>
A TALL STORY; 
</P>
<P>
A DEFORMITY IN A GIRAFFE'S NECK HAS BECOME A LEADING ATTRACTION AT THE SANTA 
BARBARA ZOO. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JANE HULSE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
You've heard the one about the giraffe with a sore throat? Try the one about 
the giraffe with a kink in her neck. 
</P>
<P>
It's no joke to the people at the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara Zoo</LOCATION>. They're baffled by the 
very noticeable zigzag halfway up the neck of the 4-year-old female giraffe. 
</P>
<P>
It's so striking that the gangly animal has become one of the newer attractions 
at the zoo. A sign at the giraffe enclosure even points out the bizarre 
deformity and assures observers the animal is in no pain and that zoo 
veterinarians are monitoring her. 
</P>
<P>
"Our veterinarian contacted other giraffe keepers and no one had heard of 
anything like it," said <PERSON>Nancy Hollenbeck</PERSON>, assistant director of the zoo. 
</P>
<P>
To find out conclusively what is wrong would require that the giraffe be 
anesthetized and X-rayed, she said. That poses a <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> risk of death, and 
zoo officials decided against it. 
</P>
<P>
"She walks normally, she eats normally, and she shows no sign of pain," said 
<PERSON>Hollenbeck</PERSON>. The current theory is that it's a muscle contraction that grew 
progressively worse until last <DATE>summer</DATE> and now seems to have stabilized. 
</P>
<P>
The giraffe's crooked neck isn't the only new oddity for visitors at the zoo. A 
pair of tapirs recently arrived from <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> to take up residence at 
the zoo. The giant hog-like animals with their long flexible snouts wallow in 
muddy water. 
</P>
<P>
They're far from cute, but the male and female are starting to show an interest 
in each other, and that's good news to zoo officials. The tapirs, relatives of 
the rhinoceros, are an endangered species. 
</P>
<P>
There's always something new to see at the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara Zoo</LOCATION> no matter how many 
times you've been there. Because it's a small, compact zoo, it's an easy place 
to take children. The entire 81-acre grounds can be covered in an afternoon. 
</P>
<P>
Located on a hilltop overlooking the ocean, the <LOCATION>Santa Ynez Mountains</LOCATION> and the 
<ORGANIZATION>Clark Bird Refuge</ORGANIZATION>, it's more than a zoo. The garden-like grounds make it a 
horticultural paradise, especially with the addition of a new cactus garden. 
</P>
<P>
Although it's small, the zoo is home to more than 150 kinds of animals -- rare 
animals like the lesser panda, the black and white ruffed lemur, and the golden 
lion tamarin. 
</P>
<P>
It has the usual sampling of elephants, lions, sea lions, monkeys, snakes, and 
a large collection of birds including the rare <LOCATION>Bali</LOCATION> mynah and a flock of 
flamingos. 
</P>
<P>
One of the newest exhibits is the nocturnal hall, a dark setting for the 
animals of the night who sleep during the day. Special lighting reverses night 
and day for the animals and makes it possible to see the night monkey and 
<PERSON>Geoffroy</PERSON>'s cat as they skitter around glassed-in enclosures that look like 
their natural habitats. 
</P>
<P>
The spookiest exhibit in the nocturnal hall is the re-creation of an old mine 
shaft that is home to a swarm of bats that cling to the beams and flutter 
around as the sounds of the night are piped in. 
</P>
<P>
For children, there's a lot to do at the zoo. A miniature train takes riders on 
a one-mile spin around the zoo grounds. A playground comes in handy when the 
kids need a break from the animals. Or, the children can buy crackers in the 
gift shop and feed the goats in the farmyard exhibit. 
</P>
<P>
WHERE AND WHEN: The <LOCATION>Santa Barbara Zoo</LOCATION> is open daily from <TIME>10 a.m. to 5 p.m.</TIME>, and 
from <DATE>June 11 through Sept. 3</DATE> (Labor Day) from <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>6 p.m</TIME>. The elephant 
training demonstrations are usually at <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> and the sea lions are generally 
fed at <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> Admission is <MONEY>$4</MONEY> for adults, <MONEY>$2</MONEY> for senior citizens and children 2 
to 12 years, and free for those under 2 years. For more information call 
962-5339. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Children visiting the Santa Barbara Zoo focus their attention on a sea 
lion. Zoo includes a playground area. SCOTT HARRISON / For The Times; Photo, 
COLOR, (COVER) ON THE COVER: Taking care of the elephants at the Santa Barbara 
Zoo: It's a big job, but somebody has to do it. SCOTT HARRISON / For The Times. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA092090-0206 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 279094 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 20, 1990, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
OC Live; Page 4; OC Live 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
456 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
KID STUFF: ANIMAL COOKIES; 
</P>
<P>
SANTA ANA ZOO MOUNTS A SWEET SAFARI 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CORINNE FLOCKEN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Cookies and critters are among children's favorite things, and on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, 
<DATE>Sept. 22</DATE>, little ones can get a bellyful of both at the <LOCATION>Santa Ana Zoo</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Cookie 
Safari</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Upon arrival, young adventurers will be given a "passport" to visit the 13 
"cookie stations" scattered throughout the zoo grounds. At each, children can 
sample goodies from cookie giants such as <ORGANIZATION>Pepperidge Farms</ORGANIZATION>, Sunshine and 
<ORGANIZATION>Nabisco</ORGANIZATION>. After adding a stamp to their passports, they will wind past some of 
the zoo's 350 exhibited animals to the next outpost. With a full passport (and 
a fuller tummy), children will return to the zoo gift shop and receive a prize. 
</P>
<P>
According to <PERSON>Jacqueline Beurskens</PERSON>, program director of the Friends of the <LOCATION>Santa 
Ana Zoo</LOCATION>, the facility's support group, this fourth annual event serves as both 
a fund-raiser and a "friend-raiser." 
</P>
<P>
"The zoo is 38 years old, yet a lot of people in this area don't know we're 
here," <PERSON>Beurskens</PERSON> said. "So we came up with a family event that would be fun for 
everyone and help raise community awareness." Last year's <ORGANIZATION>Cookie Safari</ORGANIZATION> 
attracted about 3,000 visitors and raised <MONEY>$19,000</MONEY> for the zoo's general fund, 
she added. 
</P>
<P>
Currently, only one-third of the zoo's 20-acre site is dedicated to animal 
exhibits, but plans are in the works for a large-scale expansion and 
improvements. One of the items on the drawing board is <LOCATION>Monkey Island</LOCATION>, an 
open-air display featuring colobus monkeys and tiny duiker antelope. The zoo's 
collection now features 16 species of monkeys, as well as mountain lions, 
birds, reptiles and a small children's area with barnyard animals. Larger, more 
exotic animals will be added when space and funding allows. 
</P>
<P>
In the coming years, organizers also plan to do away with the outdated 
enclosures which house many of the animals. "Whenever possible, we're trying to 
get our animals out of cages and into more natural settings" similar to those 
at the much-larger <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Beurskens</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
At the <DATE>Sept. 22</DATE> event, a handful of furry and feathered folk will be brought 
out of their cages for a little kid-to-critter contact. Zoo personnel will 
answer questions and supervise handling of the animals. Also scheduled are 
animal shows, face painting, a kiddie train and carousel and entertainment by 
clowns and jugglers. The zoo's playground will also be open throughout the day. 
Food and drink will be sold, and <PERSON>Rico Garcia</PERSON> and the Local Boys will play Latin 
jazz from <TIME>11 a.m. to 3 p.m.</TIME> 
</P>
<P>
What 
</P>
<P>
The Cookie Safari. 
</P>
<P>
When 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 22</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Where 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Ana Zoo</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1801</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>E. Chestnut St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Whereabouts 
</P>
<P>
From 1st Street, turn south on Elk Lane then east on <ORGANIZATION>Chestnut</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Wherewithal 
</P>
<P>
<MONEY>$8</MONEY> for adults, <MONEY>$4</MONEY> for children ages 3 to 12. Under 3 admitted free. 
</P>
<P>
Where to call 
</P>
<P>
(714) 953-8555. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Kid-to-critter contact. Los Angeles Times; Photo, monkey 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SANTA ANA ZOO 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112290-0228 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 313253 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 22, 1990, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 2; Column 5; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
420 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CLIPBOARD; 
</P>
<P>
HOW TO ADOPT AN ANIMAL AT THE SANTA ANA ZOO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KATHIE BOZANICH 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Always wanted a swamp wallaby? Would you love to have a white-handed gibbon to 
call your very own? You can, through the Something Wild animal adoption program 
sponsored by the Friends of the <LOCATION>Santa Ana Zoo</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The 3-year-old program allows people to choose an animal on exhibit at the zoo 
to adopt. Even the animals that roam the grounds, such as peafowls, and the 
pond animals -- Japanese koi and western pond turtles -- are available for 
adoption. 
</P>
<P>
There are about 75 animals at the zoo, according to <PERSON>Pat Taylor</PERSON>, executive 
director of the Friends of the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Ana Zoo</ORGANIZATION> (a nonprofit agency that creates 
awareness of and raises funds for the zoo). 
</P>
<P>
The animals are divided into native land categories, as well as aviary, 
barnyard and education animals. They range from the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> king snake to 
the Toco toucan, from the red-backed squirrel monkey to the African-crested 
porcupine. 
</P>
<P>
The adoptions are tax deductible, <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said, adding that many people choose 
to give the adoption as a gift. 
</P>
<P>
The following lists the six types of adoption and what you receive. 
</P>
<P>
The <MONEY>$50</MONEY> Walkabout 
</P>
<P>
Your name on the in-park signs in front of your adopted animal for one year 
</P>
<P>
A Certificate of Adoption (suitable for framing) 
</P>
<P>
A Something Wild car window sticker 
</P>
<P>
An invitation to the annual Something Wild picnic 
</P>
<P>
A one-year subscription to Animal Tales, the zoo's bimonthly newsletter and 
calendar 
</P>
<P>
The <MONEY>$100</MONEY> Wildlife Protector 
</P>
<P>
All of the above, plus . . . 
</P>
<P>
Your name displayed in gold letters on a recognition sign indicating your 
concern for endangered and threatened wildlife. 
</P>
<P>
The <MONEY>$250</MONEY> Outback Explorer 
</P>
<P>
All of the above, plus . . . 
</P>
<P>
An invitation to the special Something Wild cocktail party, where you will meet 
other zoo "parents" and learn more about wild animals from a noted expert. 
</P>
<P>
The <MONEY>$500</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Savanna Club</ORGANIZATION> 
</P>
<P>
All of the above, plus . . . 
</P>
<P>
The zookeepers will design a personalized "zoo experience" just for you. (must 
be scheduled in advance and vary according to keeper activity). 
</P>
<P>
The <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> King of the Jungle 
</P>
<P>
All of the above, plus . . . 
</P>
<P>
A tour of three special exhibits at another zoo in the area. 
</P>
<P>
The <MONEY>$25</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Bush Buddy</ORGANIZATION> (restricted to children under 18. May not be given as a 
gift.) 
</P>
<P>
A Certificate of Adoption (suitable for framing) 
</P>
<P>
A one-year subscription to Animal Tales, the zoo's bimonthly newsletter and 
calendar 
</P>
<P>
For more information, contact the Friends of the <LOCATION>Santa Ana Zoo</LOCATION> at (714) 
953-8555. The zoo is at <LOCATION>Prentice Park</LOCATION>, <DATE>1801</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>E. Chestnut Ave.</ORGANIZATION> 
</P>
<P>
Source: Friends of the <LOCATION>Santa Ana Zoo KATHIE BOZANICH</LOCATION> 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, A white-handed gibbon is one of the many adoptable animals. Los Angeles 
Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SANTA ANA ZOO; ANIMALS; ADOPTIONS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072289-0117 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 85512 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 22, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 12; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1736 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WILDLIFE -- UP CLOSE 'N' PERSONAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ANNE Z. COOKE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Once upon a time, oh best beloved, there was a summer school for all the wild 
animals of the field and forest, veldt and savanna, water hole and river 
bottom. 
</P>
<P>
The school was at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> east of <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>, where 250 
animal species, 47 of them endangered, roam over 700 spacious acres in the dry, 
sunny <LOCATION>San Pasqual Valley</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <DATE>summer</DATE> school was for the birds -- and for the tigers, gorillas, 
wildebeests, rhinos and, yes, even for weak and puny man cubs. And for their 
parents, too. But at this school, the animals were the teachers and the 
students were the humans. 
</P>
<P>
The school was such a success and the humans learned so quickly that the 
animals got together and voted to continue the program. (Let the record show 
that the giraffes had to be bribed with carrots and that <PERSON>Gainda</PERSON>, the Indian 
rhinoceros, demanded more quality petting time.) 
</P>
<P>
So once again this <DATE>summer</DATE>, from now through <DATE>August</DATE>, the Wild Animal Park is 
offering one-, two-, three- and five-morning classes for youngsters from Grade 
1 through high school. The emphasis is on hands-on learning. Students join 
teachers, staff biologists and keepers to pet, feed, count, look at, listen to 
and -- most important -- learn about the creatures whose world we share. 
</P>
<P>
And for adults? They haven't been forgotten. From now through <DATE>September</DATE>, animal 
admirers and wildlife photographers ages 12 and up can sign up for special 
family and photo caravan safaris into the huge exhibits themselves. 
</P>
<P>
These open-air, bumpy expeditions, with 10 guests and two guides standing in 
the back of a truck, spend a couple of hours driving on the dirt roads through 
four of the park's five major habitats, the East and South African, and the 
<LOCATION>Asian Plains</LOCATION> and Asian Waterhole, about 320 acres in all. The guides stop the 
truck at various places to talk about the different animals and hand out 
carrots and apples. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
A Taste of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
"The caravans are a little taste of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>," says <PERSON>Larry Killmar</PERSON>, curator of 
mammals. "They're not so rugged or stressful as a safari in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, but they 
get the people down close." 
</P>
<P>
Right! One minute you're adjusting your sunglasses, the next you're looking up 
to see three tons of beady-eyed rhino barreling up to the truck. Then he -- or 
she -- stops and thrusts that huge wrinkled face and rubbery lips right next to 
yours. 
</P>
<P>
You may want to shriek or faint. Yech -- kissed by a rhino! Instead, hand over 
an apple and grab your camera. This is a rare chance to shoot wildlife photos 
from a distance of six inches. 
</P>
<P>
Bring your telephoto lens too, to snap candids of this year's crop of shy 
babies. Says <PERSON>Killmar</PERSON>, who has been with the park since it opened in <DATE>1972</DATE>: 
"<DATE>April</DATE> to <DATE>August</DATE> is the heavy calving season. We can have as many as eight 
births in a day -- they happen right out there in the exhibits." 
</P>
<P>
If feeding fruit to rhinos seems unnatural when the park's goal is to create an 
authentic living setting for the animals, you are right. And when excessive 
contact with humans does interfere with the animals' social group behavior, 
park biologists eschew it. 
</P>
<P>
But, <PERSON>Killmar</PERSON> says, offering treats to unpredictable and easily spooked Indian 
rhinos is the safest way to manage these 6,000-pound creatures. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Familiarity Breeds Friendship 
</P>
<P>
"From day one we get the rhino calves used to touching by the keepers," <PERSON>Killmar</PERSON> 
says. "If you give them apples and carrots and goodies, they'll do anything for 
you. This allows us to move them around -- even crate them -- without using any 
tranquilizers." 
</P>
<P>
Each caravan has its own surprises. On a recent outing, Wild Animal Park 
spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON> spotted a newly laid ostrich egg lying on the muddy river 
bank. The eggs are a favorite target for hawks, so he stopped to collect it. 
</P>
<P>
The visitors handed it around and agreed it felt large, heavy and very hard. 
Just the right size for an omelet, someone commented. "Do you know how to cook 
an ostrich egg?" Hanscom asked. "You put the egg and a rock in a pot of boiling 
water. When the rock's done, so is the egg." 
</P>
<P>
Youngsters coming to the park from the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> area usually are dropped off 
by their parents or ride the bus from <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>, but residents of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 
probably will find that the park is too far for a daily drive. 
</P>
<P>
A solution is to enroll the child in a one-day class (held each <DATE>Thursday</DATE> 
<TIME>morning</TIME>) and combine it with an all-day family visit to the park. Human cubs, 
grades one through six, join a "Wild Walkabout," visiting koalas and kangaroos 
and all the other strange fauna and flora from the Down Under continent, while 
students in grades seven to 12 enroll in the class called "Close Enough to 
Touch," similar to the photo caravans. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
For Budding Zoologists 
</P>
<P>
The older students actually accompany the keepers into the exhibits, through 
double-chain-link gates to help feed and count the zebras and gazelles and feel 
the giraffe's warm breath when it bends down for a carrot. 
</P>
<P>
If a budding zoologist begs for a three-day class, consider a mini-vacation for 
the family at one of the golf and leisure resorts east of <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION> or motel 
accommodations in that area. 
</P>
<P>
Start a day at the Wild Animal Park with a ride on the <PERSON>Wgasa Bush</PERSON> Line 
monorail. The monorail runs around the hills above the major habitats and 
provides an overview of the 2,500 animals that live behind special fencing 
called "inrigging." 
</P>
<P>
The fencing isn't all that tall, but it has a tremendous overhang at the top. 
As our monorail tour guide <PERSON>Becky Boomer</PERSON> announced: "The animals get up next to 
the fence and look up. When they see something over their heads, they think 
they can't jump out." 
</P>
<P>
On the ride, keep an eye out for a family of wild golden eagles circling 
overhead. The eagles are a few of the wild birds that have taken up residence 
in the surrounding hilltops and are getting fat on the gophers and mice that 
help themselves to animal feed. 
</P>
<P>
"We call them locals," <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> says, explaining that the Wild Animal Park 
spends between <MONEY>$41,000</MONEY> and <MONEY>$46,000</MONEY> monthly on animal food. The grocery bill 
would be higher, but the park actually grows some of its own browse food, such 
as eucalyptus, on the park's 1,800 acres. 
</P>
<P>
After the ride, visitors walk around the 1 1/4-mile <ORGANIZATION>Kilimanjaro Trail</ORGANIZATION> for a 
closer look into the special, smaller exhibits: the <LOCATION>Sumatran</LOCATION> tiger's woody 
hollow, the elephant enclosure, the lowland gorilla's lair and the cheetah's 
grassy plain. The animals are fascinating to watch, but their presence points 
to the Wild Animal Park's real purpose. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Protective Coloration 
</P>
<P>
The park's protective coloration -- the <LOCATION>Nairobi Village</LOCATION>'s thatched snack bar, 
outdoor cafe, T-shirt shop, souvenir store, live animal shows, the petting 
kraal -- is designed like a theme park to attract humans. But, <ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> says, 
the park's real purpose is 'to breed endangered species, and to study breeding 
problems of animals in captivity." 
</P>
<P>
For instance, he says, researchers discovered that flamingos wouldn't lay 
fertilized eggs unless there were at least 100 birds in the flock. "It's the 
number that seems to click the hormones and make them go," he says. 
</P>
<P>
"And the Southern White Rhino . . . for years, the two in the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo 
just ignored each other. Then they brought 20 females out here to the animal 
park and moved the male out here to retire, but all he needed was space and a 
harem. In 11 years, he sired 65 calves." 
</P>
<P>
However, numbers aren't always a determining factor. There are cheetahs in the 
wilds, but genetic studies reveal that they're very inbred, probably because 
they live in isolated family groups. As a result, many females are sterile or 
there's a high infant mortality. So the park is breeding cheetahs with better 
genes, then making them available to other zoos. 
</P>
<P>
The park's <DATE>summer</DATE> programs are scheduled almost every day of the week. Photo 
caravans run on <DATE>Wednesday, Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE> afternoons from <DATE>May 
through September</DATE>. Groups of 10 booking together can go any day. Each caravan 
is 1 3/4 hours long; tickets are <MONEY>$50</MONEY> for adults 16 and older and <MONEY>$35</MONEY> for 
children 12-15 with an adult. Children under 12 are not permitted on this 
caravan. The East African and the Asian Plains caravan leaves at <TIME>2:30 p.m</TIME>. The 
caravan to the South African habitat and the Asian Waterhole leaves at <TIME>4:30 
p.m.</TIME> 
</P>
<P>
You can take both tours for a full 3 1/2-hour safari; <MONEY>$75</MONEY> for adults and <MONEY>$50</MONEY> 
for children. Because <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> members get a big discount 
on all special tours, it may be possible to save money by joining the zoo at 
the time you enroll. The photo caravans always are sold out and must be booked 
in advance. 
</P>
<P>
The Family Caravans are similar to photo caravans but emphasize learning about 
and visiting family groups of animals rather than photography. They run <DATE>Monday</DATE> 
evenings from 5:30 to <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> Tickets are <MONEY>$55</MONEY> for one adult with one child, and 
<MONEY>$80</MONEY> for one adult with two children. Children must be 8 or older and be with an 
adult. 
</P>
<P>
The five-day <DATE>summer</DATE> school runs <DATE>Monday</DATE> through <DATE>Friday</DATE> from 9 to <TIME>11:30 a.m.</TIME>, 
with a separate class for each grade level from 1 to 9. The three-day 
summer-school program runs <DATE>Monday, Tuesday</DATE> and <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> from <TIME>8:30 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>1 
p.m</TIME>. The fee is <MONEY>$50</MONEY> and five different classes serve different grade levels. 
</P>
<P>
The one-day program runs each <DATE>Thursday</DATE> from <TIME>8:30 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> and costs <MONEY>$22</MONEY> 
to <MONEY>$35</MONEY>. Different classes are designed for three age groups. 
</P>
<P>
The "Keeper Connection" is a two-session career exploration class for 
10th-to-12th graders who are considering animal-related careers. The fee is 
<MONEY>$50</MONEY>; the first session in <DATE>August</DATE> is on the 11th, and participants have a choice 
for the second second sesssion of any day between <DATE>Aug. 14</DATE> and 18. 
</P>
<P>
You can enroll by telephone and pay by credit card. Call the <ORGANIZATION>Summer School 
Hotline</ORGANIZATION> at (619) 740-9383, or the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> at (619) 236-0163. You also can 
write to the <ORGANIZATION>Summer School</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 551, <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. 
92112-0551, but expect a several-week processing delay. 
</P>
<P>
Wild Animal Park hours are <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> through <DATE>Sept. 4</DATE> (Labor Day), and <TIME>9 
a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> after. The park is 30 miles north of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> on Interstate 15, 
then east on Highway 78. From <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> take Interstate 5 south to <LOCATION>Oceanside</LOCATION>, 
then <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 78 east to the park. A ticket package (entrance, monorail ride, 
animal shows and exhibits) is <MONEY>$12.95</MONEY> for adults, <MONEY>$6.20</MONEY> for ages 3-15, ages 2 
and under free. Stroller and wheelchair rentals are available. No pets, please; 
the wild animals frown on it. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Rubbernecking giraffe at Wild Animal Park. ; Photo, Top, wild animals 
greet visitors on photo safari who have traveled through San Diego Animal Park 
on a pickup truck. Above, Sunny Verghese gets chummy with heavyweight rhino 
named Gainda. ; Photo, Giraffe investigates the hand of friendship at animal 
park. ANNE Z. COOKE; PAUL COOKE 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SAN DIEGO WILD ANIMAL PARK; WILDLIFE REFUGES; ZOOS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900924-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-24-90 2347EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FifthAvenuePhyllis     09-24 0489</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fifth Avenue Phyllis,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Very Social Animal is Missing - or Worse</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICK HAMPSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fifth <PERSON>Avenue Phyllis</PERSON>, known as Fifth Avenue <PERSON>Phil</PERSON>
until the birth of her three babies, is the only groundhog ever to
move voluntarily into the Central Park Zoo. But now this very
social animal is missing - or worse.
   The outgoing woodchuck, who scampers up to people outside her
hole under the Children's Zoo and begs for Italian ice, hot dogs
and pretzels, has been gone almost two months. Some of her friends
are sure she was killed by a car.
   ``We're still holding out hope,'' zookeeper <PERSON>Herb Clement</PERSON> said
<DATE>Monday</DATE>. ``She's been gone before. She's not your everyday
groundhog.''
   The plump brown beast first made the pages of <ORGANIZATION>The New York Times</ORGANIZATION>
in <DATE>1985</DATE>, when she dug a hole near a driveway at the Children's Zoo
and set up housekeeping.
   Clement called it ``a case of reverse adoption,'' and, ignorant
of the groundhog's sex, dubbed her Fifth Avenue <PERSON>Phil</PERSON>.
   The groundhog may have been attracted by a crab apple tree that
dropped its fruit on the driveway, and by the grass and weeds in
front of the zoo entrance. But far better eating, the beast soon
realized, was hers for the asking.
   ``Groundhogs can get used to people after awhile, but she really
stepped forward,'' <PERSON>Clement</PERSON> recalled. ``She'd walk out among the
crowds and literally join them for lunch.''
   But it wasn't just the food; this groundhog was truly
gregarious.
   ``She would walk right up to you, rise up on her hind legs, and
rest her paws on your leg,'' said <PERSON>Virginia Ferguson</PERSON>, a neighborhood
resident.
   ``She was a New Yorker first,'' <PERSON>Clement</PERSON> agreed, ``and a
groundhog second. She wasn't even afraid of dogs.''
   A woman known to zoo regulars as the Groundhog Lady taught
<PERSON>Phyllis</PERSON> to come out of her burrow on cue and perform tricks. She
would sit on the woman's lap and hold a banana as the woman peeled
it; she would beg on her hind legs for bits of cookie.
   Phyllis delighted her admirers with a litter of three pups, then
chilled them by the ruthlessness with which all groundhogs root
their brood out of the hole.
   Phyllis again made the <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1987</DATE>, when <PERSON>Clement</PERSON> wrote a
letter to the editor citing ``the remarkable groundhog <PERSON>Phyllis</PERSON>'' as
an example of ``<LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s native wildlife.''
   The woodchuck, he explained, had gone far beyond her species'
traditional claim to fame - the prediction of winter's length - and
became ``the only groundhog to have voluntarily taken up residence
in a zoo.''
   Phyllis became a bigger attraction than most of the animals who
joined the zoo involuntarily. ``People come by to look for her, and
if she isn't around, they want to know why,'' <PERSON>Clement</PERSON> said.
``They're quite insistent.''
   Whenever there was a parade on Fifth Avenue, <PERSON>Phyllis</PERSON> would walk
along the wall between the avenue and the park, looking for
leftovers.
   But the groundhog disappeared at the end of <DATE>July</DATE>, and on <DATE>Aug. 16</DATE>
<PERSON>Virginia Ferguson</PERSON>'s husband, <PERSON>Donald</PERSON>, was jogging in the park when
he saw the body of a groundhog in the road. It had been run over;
it was, he believed, <PERSON>Phyllis</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Ferguson</PERSON> wrote this announcement and posted it near the
gate:
   ``To those watching for her
   She is gone
   She was killed by a car
   We all miss her.''
   <PERSON>Mrs. Ferguson</PERSON> also spent <MONEY>$75</MONEY> on a 5-by-7-foot black and silver
plaque that will be placed this week on a wall near the groundhog's
old hole.
   It reads: ``In affectionate tribute to a remarkably friendly and
tame groundhog. The original Fifth Avenue <PERSON>Phyllis</PERSON>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880525-0309 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-25-88 0757EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-LondonZooFun Adv02   05-25 0633</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-London Zoo Fun, Adv 02,0654</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv02</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thurs AMs, June 2, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>London Zoo Official Wants Animals to Have Fun, Too</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAGGIE JACKSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>David Shepherdson</PERSON>'s job is to take the boredom out
of life for the animals at the <LOCATION>London Zoo</LOCATION>, putting something more
into their day than sleeping, eating and watching humans.
   He has piped gibbon music into the the gibbon cage.
   For the mongooses, he has provided pieces of hollow wood filled
with crickets for the animals to try to catch. ``Cricket
dispensers,'' he calls them.
   He plans a light-and-sound show for the orangutans.
   The lanky 28-year-old Englishman, whose doctoral thesis had him
tracking wild badgers by radio at night, became behavioral
enrichment officer six months ago at the <LOCATION>London Zoo</LOCATION>, the first
British zoo to have one.
   Believing a little work for the animals is healthy, too,
<PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> is making some species work for their dinners.
   ``Zoos should show the animal as it behaves in the wild,'' he
said. ``For example, in the wild, most species spend more than <PERCENT>50
percent</PERCENT> of their time foraging for food. ... In the zoo, they get
fed once a day.
   ``You have a choice _ either change the environment, or you
don't keep the animals properly.''
   <PERSON>Trevor Paul</PERSON>, director of research at the <ORGANIZATION>Universities Federation
for Animal Welfare</ORGANIZATION>, the independent body co-sponsoring
<PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON>'s post, says the project also works well for people who
visit the zoo.
   ``There isn't a great deal of point in them seeing an animal
sitting in a corner behind bars,'' he said.
   He and <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> say that while zoos in many countries are
making cages more natural, few have spent much time studying animal
behavior in relation to their habitats.
   The 161-year-old <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> Zoo's gibbon monkeys never did much
loafing in their tree-lined outdoor enclosure, but with the change
in their zoo habitat they've become much more feisty.
   Gibbons usually have one mate for life and assert their
territory by singing. <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> Zoo's pair weren't as musical as they
should have been until <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> hung stereo speakers near their
cage and played taped gibbon duets twice a day.
   Thinking they have neighbors, the gibbons now sing, too.
   Shepherdson is also working on a computer keyboard to produce
sounds, food or even slide shows when orangutans operate it.
   <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> said an electronic organ failed to excite the apes, ``so
we'll try to get a keyboard which does more things than produce
sound.''
   Simple toys, often involving food, are best for most animals,
<PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> said.
   He had praise for <PERSON>Hal Markowitz</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> behavioral enrichment
pioneer who installed a machine to toss meatballs into a serval's
cage, but added that he believes more naturalistic tools should be
explored.
   Recently <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> equipped the ring-tailed lemurs' cage with
poles that sway like the trees in the primates' native <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> said one of the best ways to simulate natural behavior ``is
to make an animal work for its food (and) spend normal amounts of
time foraging.''
   In the kinkajous' cage, carrots, bananas and apples hang from
the ceiling, some tantalizingly out of reach for the weasel-like
creatures.
   Before getting the snacks, the female paced for hours _ one of
the first signs of boredom, said <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON>, watching as she
pursued a banana just beyond nose-reach.
   ``Even tortoises pace, I'm told,'' <PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON> added. ``It's not
a lack of space, it's what you have in that space that's
important.''
   After a cage is outfitted, zoo workers watch the animals for
hours to see how they respond.
   ``In every case so far, there's been a beneficial effect,'' said
<PERSON>Shepherdson</PERSON>. ``If every zoo in the country did these things, it
would be a great step forward in animal welfare.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thurs AMs, June 2</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880531-0252 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-31-88 1403EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--ExoticAnimals Adv12-2Takes   05-31 1082</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Exotic Animals, Adv 12-2 Takes,1114</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv12</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, June 12</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w
photo.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ Want to buy a lion? A zebra. A rhea bird? A trio
of bear cubs. No problem. Demand for wilder wildlife is sizeable
and the suppliers ever ready. That pleases animal dealers and
customers who, for benign and not so benign reasons, go for exotic
animals, even on a dinner plate. The trend bothers the increasingly
active animal rights groups and others who are disposed to raise
moral as well as ecological issues.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ Want to buy a lion? A zebra. A rhea bird? A trio
of bear cubs. No problem. Demand for wilder wildlife is sizeable
and the suppliers ever ready. That pleases animal dealers and
customers who, for benign and not so benign reasons, go for exotic
animals, even on a dinner plate. The trend bothers the increasingly
active animal rights groups and others who are disposed to raise
moral as well as ecological issues.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By TARA BRADLEY-STECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ Want to buy a lion? A zebra. A rhea bird? A trio
of bear cubs. No problem. Demand for wilder wildlife is sizeable
and the suppliers ever ready. That pleases animal dealers and
customers who, for benign and not so benign reasons, go for exotic
animals, even on a dinner plate. The trend bothers the increasingly
active animal rights groups and others who are disposed to raise
moral as well as ecological issues.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100290-0170 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 286554 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 2, 1990, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 3; Column 3; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
557 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BEASTS ARE BLESSED WITH A BENEFIT DINNER; 
</P>
<P>
A FRIENDS OF THE SANTA ANA ZOO EVENT RAISED FUNDS FOR A MONKEY HABITAT TO BE 
CONSTRUCTED NEXT YEAR. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PAMELA MARIN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Zoo News 
</P>
<P>
Friends of the <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> Zoo tossed a party last week in the courtyard outside 
Prego restaurant in <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>, drawing about 100 guests at <MONEY>$40</MONEY> each for no-host 
cocktails and a buffet of Italian specialties. The benefit raised <MONEY>$5,500</MONEY> toward 
the construction of <LOCATION>Monkey Island</LOCATION> -- an 18,000-square-foot, cageless habitat to 
be built next year. 
</P>
<P>
The exhibit is to be the first of 50 major projects planned for the zoo, said 
<LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Daniel H. Young</PERSON>, who sipped red wine and pressed the flesh of 
his constituents. Young said the zoo board has a master plan that calls for 
approximately <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> in construction and renovations at the city-owned 
facility. 
</P>
<P>
"We anticipate private funding for <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of that," said <PERSON>Young</PERSON>, "so we're probably 
talking about a 10-year plan." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Monkey Business 
</P>
<P>
H Iko</ORGANIZATION> -- a 5-year-old squirrel monkey on a leash. The handlers (from <LOCATION>Pacific 
Animal Productions</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>) gave each guest a sunflower seed to feed shy 
Iko, who reached into strangers' hands for the treat, then scampered back up to 
perch on familiar shoulders. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Animal Attractions 
</P>
<P>
Also there were Cleo the constrictor, <PERSON>Marcy</PERSON> the opossum, Pedro the parrot, Iggy 
the iguana, Barney the barn owl and a pygmy hedgehog named Spot. "These animals 
are really used to all the attention," said zoo volunteer <PERSON>Elta Chapman</PERSON>, who, 
with staffer <PERSON>Karen Cress Cribbs</PERSON>, brought the animals out of their cages one at 
a time and held them. "This is like our little movable petting zoo." 
</P>
<P>
Zoo board members <PERSON>Judy Fluor-Runels</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bradd Linn</PERSON> stroked <PERSON>Marcy</PERSON>'s shaggy fur 
as Fluor-Runels asked about possum diet, sleep habits and behavior. "So will 
she have babies or no?" Fluor-Runels asked in conclusion. (No, <PERSON>Chapman</PERSON> said.) 
</P>
<P>
Checking out Barney the owl, <PERSON>Karen Amies</PERSON> joked about the thick feathers in the 
center of his face. "How would you like to get up in the morning and brush your 
nose?" she asked her husband, <LOCATION>Grif</LOCATION>. (Not much, he said.) 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Marilyn Sion</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Sharon Ballidis</ORGANIZATION> reached out and touched Cleo the constrictor, 
and <ORGANIZATION>Sion</ORGANIZATION> talked about her two grown daughters' having done volunteer work at 
the zoo when they were teens. "They were always very animal-oriented," <PERSON>Sion</PERSON> 
said. "It was a great experience for them. They learned how important the 
hands-on part of the job was -- and they loved taking the animals out of their 
cages and communicating with them." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Buffet 
</P>
<P>
Iko settled for sunflower seeds, but the guests dug into a spread that included 
radicchio salad, prosciutto pizza, garlic rosemary bread, grilled shrimp with 
feta in a vinaigrette sauce, grilled eggplant and pasta in vodka cream sauce. 
For dessert: espresso-soaked ladyfingers, Mascarpone cheese, rum and cocoa. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Also Seen 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Trudy Thomas</PERSON>, Friends of the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Ana Zoo</ORGANIZATION> board member and chairwoman of the 
party. <PERSON>Allen Doby</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Ana</ORGANIZATION> director of parks and recreation, with his wife, 
<PERSON>LaFaye</PERSON>. <PERSON>Ron Izumita</PERSON> of the architectural firm Pod/Sasaki, which is to build 
<ORGANIZATION>Monkey Island</ORGANIZATION>. Also there were <PERSON>Ron Rus</PERSON>, <PERSON>Wanita Thomas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Donna Ayotte</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mary</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Ron Green</PERSON>, <PERSON>Yvonne</PERSON> and <PERSON>Eric Rasmussen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kathy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Randy Smith</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Quote 
</P>
<P>
I'm a friend of a Friend of the <LOCATION>Santa Ana Zoo</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Diane Triantis</PERSON>. "I 
bartended at one of their charity functions." 
</P>
<P>
"And I drank the booze," said <PERSON>Triantis</PERSON>' escort, <PERSON>Mike Gubbins</PERSON>, "So I guess I'm a 
friend of a friend of a Friend of the zoo." PAMELA <LOCATION>MARIN</LOCATION> 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Santa Ana Mayor Daniel H. Young, left, recoils at sight of the king 
snake held by Trudy Thomas, chairwoman of the event. At right is Ron Izumita of 
Pod/Sasaki architects, which will build the monkey enclosure. Young said 50 
major projects are planned for the zoo. KARI RENE HALL / Los Angeles Times; 
Photo, Iko the squirrel monkey, another of the several animal visitors, takes a 
sunflower seed from Donna Ayotte as Wanita Thomas looks on. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910719-0183
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910719-0183.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- The Mobile Guide:
   London Zoo Is Closing Down?
   ----
   By Paul Levy
</HL>
<DATE>
07/19/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A9
</SO>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   London -- When the British find that they have no further
use for one of their institutions, their first thought is
often to send it to America, as they did with the Queen Mary.
In the case of London Zoo, however, this solution does not
appear to be available. The Central Park Zoo, for example,
has problems of its own, as do many zoos that are dependent
on municipal funding.
   Still, London Zoo is special. In the first place, there is
its literary celebrity, as in Hilaire Belloc's "Jim, Who Ran
Away From His Nurse, &amp; Was Eaten by a Lion" (moral: "always
keep a-hold of Nurse/For fear of finding something worse"),
which is set at London Zoo, as is the late Sir Angus Wilson's
"The Old Men at the Zoo," in which the animals in Regent's
Park even survive a nuclear war. And there is "A Man in the
Zoo" by Bloomsbury Group member David ("Bunny") Garnett, in
which a spurned lover offers himself to the zoo, and is
accepted, for exhibition as a specimen of Homo sapiens.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In the second place, <LOCATION>London Zoo</LOCATION> is architecturally
significant. It is chock full of protected, "listed"
buildings. When I visited the zoo recently, the koala bears
who now inhabit <ORGANIZATION>Bertold Lubertkin</ORGANIZATION>'s listed <ORGANIZATION>Gorilla House</ORGANIZATION>
(<DATE>1933</DATE>) were as somnolent as ever, and the penguins in the
same architect's listed abstract sculptural Penguin Pool
(<DATE>1934</DATE>) seemed to be suffering as much as the visitors from
the unseasonable <DATE>June</DATE> chill. The birds in <PERSON>Lord Snowdon</PERSON>'s
as-yet-unlisted aviary were almost grounded by the cold, and
the elephants were huddled for warmth in Sir <PERSON>Hugh Casson</PERSON>'s
modern and still-unlisted <ORGANIZATION>Elephant House</ORGANIZATION>. I couldn't see what
was going on in <PERSON>Decimus Burton</PERSON>'s listed Giraffe and <ORGANIZATION>Hippo
House</ORGANIZATION> (1836), and the monkeys and apes were sheltering from
the weather in their houses opposite his listed II Clock
Tower (1830).
   Finally, some of the animals in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> Zoo are unusual.
When I visited, <LOCATION>Chia Chia</LOCATION> the giant panda was in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>,
where it was hoped he could be persuaded to father a new
entry in the international giant panda stud book, which is
overseen by <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> Zoo's <PERSON>Jo Gipps</PERSON>. He also looks after the
breeding records of the golden lion tamarin (a small South
American squirrel monkey) and those of Sumatran tigers. His
two pairs of young Asian lions are particularly important, in
view of the recent discovery that the captive population of
Asian lions in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is made up not of purebreds, but of
animals that have at some point acquired an admixture of
African-lion bloodlines.
   Not counting insects, there are 8,000 animals at the
"mother of zoos" (it opened in <DATE>1826</DATE>) that will have to be
rehoused or disposed of if it closes, as is now threatened,
in <DATE>September 1992</DATE>. There is obviously an element of
brinkmanship in the posture of the new director general,
<PERSON>David Jones</PERSON>, and the zoo's treasurer, <LOCATION>Lord Peyton</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Yeovil</LOCATION>.
The zoo is losing approximately <MONEY>$2.5 million</MONEY> a year, has cash
reserves of only <MONEY>$8.25 million</MONEY>, and doesn't seem able to
attract the 1.4 million visitors it needs every year to stay
in the black. In <DATE>1988</DATE> the government gave it a
once-and-for-all grant of <MONEY>$16.5 million</MONEY>, and <PERSON>Michael
Heseltine</PERSON>, the minister for the environment, and his junior
minister, <PERSON>David Trippier</PERSON>, are standing pat.
   In this zoo poker game <PERSON>Mr. Trippier</PERSON> is now claiming that
his ministry is reflecting the most up-to-date thinking about
zoos -- that such urban institutions are unsuitable, even
immoral, from a conservation point of view. His critics say
it is hypocritical of the government to latch onto the
prejudices of animal-rights activists. Lord <PERSON>Peyton</PERSON>,
meanwhile, has called the ministry's bluff by hinting that it
will be the Department of the Environment's fault if the
animals have to be put down.
   The British, as is well-known, are wacko about animals.
Old ladies really do leave their fortunes to cat and dog
homes. The government has to call a general election within
the next year, and as the Tory newspaper the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Telegraph</ORGANIZATION>
said in a recent editorial, "The zoo's directors know that no
government facing an election in the next few months could
face doing so against a background of mass executions of
animals taking place a few miles north of Westminster."
Perhaps it is malicious to suggest that this was the reason
that the deadline for closing the zoo was just moved ahead to
<DATE>1992</DATE>.
   Of course, the zoo may not close at all, if sufficient
funds can be raised. But it is perhaps not too early to think
about what the worst case would entail. <PERSON>Auberon Waugh</PERSON>, in his
column in the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Telegraph</ORGANIZATION> (the Conservatives are much
more exercised about the issue than is the <ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION>), has
made two modest proposals. As nobody would actually want to
buy a bunch of gorillas, kangaroos and alligators, why not
make the zoo into a temporary game park? Encourage Japanese
and American businessmen to stalk and shoot whatever animals
they choose, photograph them with their trophies, then take
the game away and "give it to the poor to eat." The rarest
species, "strange birds, as well as flying foxes, koalas and
centipedes," should be kept for a great <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> gastronomic
festival, "where Britons can taste delicacies from all over
the world, which they might otherwise miss from their life's
experience."
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Levy</PERSON> is a staff journalist for the Observer in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-6621</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CHYBZADVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920822
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 AUG 92 / Travel: Life and death in an ocean of emptiness - With the
lions of Ngorongoro, in Tanzania
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MICHAEL J. WOODS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
ON tip-toe, and with a smiling frown on her broad fawn face, the lioness
danced playfully away from the white-tailed mongoose. This valiant animal,
little bigger than a cat and with a white plume of a tail, repeatedly leaped
at the lioness's chin, snickering with anger as he did so.
The lioness stepped aside. As the mongoose made to run off, his tail like a
beacon in the flat grey light of morning, she flicked out a dinner-plate paw
and swept his feet from under him. The mongoose lay winded for a moment.
As he got up, a second lioness came to tease him further. Like domestic cats
with a shrew, they had no intention of eating their captive, merely of
having a good time.
But this was a terminal mongoose. His chattering so excited one lioness that
she playfully picked him up and tossed him a few feet through the air. He
was dead before he hit the ground.
These were just three of the 100 or so lions which are packed into the
Ngorongoro Crater in <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION>, for they live there at the very high density
of about one to the square mile. As a result, they are remarkably easy to
see but, like lions everywhere, they spend most of their time doing very
little.
To watch interesting lion activity you have to be out early or stay late,
which was possible when I was there (late <DATE>March</DATE>), when camping on the crater
floor was officially forbidden. That white-tailed mongoose met his end at
6.30am only 500 yards from our camp just a few days before the ban was
announced. From now on, you will have to rise very much earlier in order to
tackle the tortuous and hour-long descent to the crater floor to be in time
to catch some of this action.
By way of compensation, the Tanzanian government has allowed the
construction of a fourth lodge on the crater rim and a fifth is to follow,
offering between 200 and 400 more bed spaces. To avoid saturation of the
crater floor, access will be rationed by permit with the intention of
encouraging more people to explore the rest of the 3,200-square-mile
Ngorongoro conservation area which lies between the crater and <LOCATION>Serengeti</LOCATION>
national park.
It is an ocean of short grass plains, apparently endless, gently rolling - a
daunting space. Occasionally there is an island, a rounded granite hillock
exfoliating like an old, tired onion with a growth of whistling thorns and
characteristic umbrella acacias to give shade. These are havens for
predators which occasionally sally forth like pirates to make a raid on
passing prey.
In contrast to the crater, which has permanent water and a mosaic of
habitats and thus contains remarkable concentrations of mammals and birds,
the conservation area appears to be empty. But this is a trick of the
landscape, for its vastness, stretching in every direction, is deceptive,
giving the illusion of a much reduced quantity of game.
In fact, these plains were full of life during my visit, which took place
when the rains were imminent. The herbivores had given birth and the place
was bouncing with wildebeest calves, young <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>'s gazelles, zebra colts
and a host of other species.
Then strings of wildebeest set off to follow the rain. Files of animals
perhaps two or three miles in length came over the far horizon as a tiny
cloud of dust and after 20 minutes or so were barely distinguishable with
binoculars. At that distance they looked almost like North American plains
bison in a western.
Shortly, though, they were passing close at hand, walking, trotting,
cantering, walking again - cow, calf, cow, calf, making that strange
bleating sound and carving yet another groove across the plain. Crossing
these paths is like driving over the lines in a railway marshalling yard.
Gibbs Farm Safaris is run by <PERSON>Nigel Perks</PERSON>, a tall, broad Kiwi fed a love for
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> on a childhood diet of <PERSON>David Attenborough</PERSON>'s Zoo Quest programmes.
From our camp moored against a large rock (you have to link your camp to
something out there - simply to plonk a tent down on the open plain would be
terrifying), we set out every day without coming across another vehicle.
<PERSON>Nigel</PERSON> had an uncanny knack of foretelling what we would see and, with an
excellent eye for wildlife, ensured that the list included both serval and
African wild cat.
On the last day we were to have the privilege of joining a group visiting
Olduvai gorge, which also lies within the richly-endowed conservation area,
in the company of <PERSON>Mary Leakey</PERSON>. Looking round a kopje on the way we found a
dozing cheetah. With time to spare we sat and watched.
The cat lay warming on the rocks and gradually came to life. Cheetahs hunt
by sight, generally in the mornings, so we waited a little longer. Soon it
bounded nonchalantly from the rocks and strode casually on to the grass.
Here it stood for a while and then sat like a large china spotted cat. In
the distance were a group of gambolling, grazing <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>'s gazelles, too
far to stalk.
The cheetah flopped on the grass and stared glassily towards the horizon. A
faint hint of grey dust suggested approaching wildebeest.
The tension in the Land Rover was palpable. Wildebeest after wildebeest went
by. Perhaps we had mistaken the cheetah's intentions. But suddenly it was
flying; there was dust, panic, confusion, running hooves, a walking cheetah
 -it had missed.
Like cars on a packed motorway, wildebeest on the move speed up, slow down,
run, walk, trot, stop, canter, all for no apparent reason. The ones towards
the back had no idea why those further up were making haste and no inkling
that the cheetah was back in doormat mode.
This time there were no mistakes. We saw a spotted buff explosion, a pall of
dust and the waving chestnut legs of a wildebeest calf as the life was
suffocated out of it. We never did get to Olduvai.
<PERSON>Michael Woods</PERSON>' safari to the Ngorongoro conservation area in <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> with
<PERSON>Gibb</PERSON>'s Farm Safaris was arranged by <ORGANIZATION>Art Of Travel of 268 Lavender Hill</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> SW11 1LJ, tel: 071-738-2038. <ORGANIZATION>Gibb's Farm Safaris</ORGANIZATION> is based at <ORGANIZATION>Gibb</ORGANIZATION>'s
Farm, a lodge between <LOCATION>Lake Manyara</LOCATION> national park and the crater which is
linked to <ORGANIZATION>Ndutu</ORGANIZATION>, a second lodge on the edge of the short grass plains.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page VIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890430-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-30-89 1405EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     04-30 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HUNTINGTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A local detective took on a case of a
different sort when he was called in on a bird hunt for a
foul-tempered parrot who flew the coop.
   Armed only with a variety of bird calls, police Detective <PERSON>C.D.
Morrison</PERSON> winged it in his search for Charlie, a <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>South
American Macaw</ORGANIZATION> parrot who ventured from his perch.
   Charlie's owners, <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> and <PERSON>Chris Mort</PERSON>, notified police after
they discovered the bird was missing <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>.
   ``We let her out on the front porch, she's sort of the
neighborhood watch dog,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Mort</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Morrison</PERSON> said he tried to attract the bird by making parrot
calls, but there was no response.
   The Morts on <DATE>Friday</DATE> asked meter readers, mail carriers, police
and school children to aid in the search for Charlie.
   <PERSON>Morrison</PERSON> returned with a bird in his hand <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> after
a neighbor became a stool pigeon and turned Charlie in.
   ``She was about a block away in a big tall tree and a lady over
there spotted her,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Mort</PERSON> said. ``She's okay, just a little
wet.''
   The Morts were concerned not only about the parrot's
disappearance but about her mood swings. Charlie, who likes fried
chicken and coffee, can become very foul tempered for no reason,
they say.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SPOKANE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A local detective took on a case of a
different sort when he was called in on a bird hunt for a
foul-tempered parrot who flew the coop.
   Armed only with a variety of bird calls, police Detective <PERSON>C.D.
Morrison</PERSON> winged it in his search for Charlie, a <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>South
American Macaw</ORGANIZATION> parrot who ventured from his perch.
   Charlie's owners, <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> and <PERSON>Chris Mort</PERSON>, notified police after
they discovered the bird was missing <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>.
