<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890818-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-18-89 2056EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Voyager-Neptune     08-18 0651</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Neptune,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magnetic Field Around Neptune Discovered By Voyager 2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Voyager 2 space probe discovered that
a magnetic field surrounds <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, suggesting the planet is
enveloped by orbiting radiation belts and has an aurora like <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s
northern lights, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Further study of the magnetic field should allow scientists to
determine the exact length of a day on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, believed to be 17 to
18 Earth hours, and to gain better understanding of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s
internal structure, said <PERSON>Mary Beth Murrill</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s
Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   Just as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s magnetic field traps the Van <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> radiation
belts, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s magnetic field also may help create radiation belts
around that planet. Scientists don't yet know if that poses a hazard
to Voyager 2's electronic components, <PERSON>Murrill</PERSON> said.
   Voyager was 2.74 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and 5.92 million miles
from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, speeding toward the giant gas planet at
42,236 mph.
   The spacecraft was launched in <DATE>1977</DATE> and explored <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Voyager 2 will make its closest
approach to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> at <TIME>8:59 p.m. PDT</TIME> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when it flies about
3,000 miles over the cloudtops of the solar system's fourth-largest
planet.
   Voyager already has discovered four Neptunian moons in addition
to the two discovered from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, two partial rings, or ring arcs,
of debris orbiting the planet; and atmospheric patterns similar to
jet streams and giant cyclones on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Discovery of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s magnetic field was confirmed <DATE>Friday</DATE> by
intense, pulse-like radio emissions coming from the planet's
vicinity. Radio waves are generated when high-speed electrically
charged particles spiral into a planet's atmosphere along magnetic
field lines.
   ``Mercury, <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus have magnetic
fields, while <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and Mars do not,'' the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and
Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> said in a news release. ``Whether <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION> has one
or not is unknown.
   ``A planetary magnetic field is a girdle of magnetic field lines
that surround a planet,'' the agency said. ``Such fields are thought
to be generated by fluid motion in a planet's core. (<ORGANIZATION>Molten</ORGANIZATION> iron in
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s core, for example).''
   Certain electrically charged particles in space spiral along
magnetic field lines toward <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s poles, creating the northern and
southern lights. A magnetic field at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> means that planet also
may have auroras, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Scientists hope the magnetic field will allow them to understand
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s internal structure. Voyager project scientist <ORGANIZATION>Edward Stone</ORGANIZATION>
has said he believes that <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s hydrogen-helium outer atmosphere
gradually gives way to a superhot slurry of hot water and rock
closer to the planet's center. That would mean that <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> _ like
neighboring Uranus _ probably lacks a distinct sky-sea boundary.
   Some scientists believe radiation trapped by Uranus' magnetic
field bombards frozen natural gas on that planet's moons and rings
to turn them dark in color. Neptune's magnetic field may cause
similar radiation darkening of the Neptunian moons and ring arcs,
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The nature of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s radio signal allowed scientists to
determine the emissions came from a magnetic field, not from
discharges of lightning in the atmosphere, said <PERSON>James Warwick</PERSON>, head
of Voyager's radio science team.
   ``The radio emissions are very intense, very impulsive and occur
in a limited range of frequency,'' <PERSON>Warwick</PERSON>, a scientist at <LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Colo.-based Radiophysics Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, said in the release.
   Once <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> confirmed the existence of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s magnetic field
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, scientists found evidence for the telltale radio signals in
data collected by Voyager as early as <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``Early analysis indicates <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s magnetic field is of an
intensity similar to the fields of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and Uranus,'' <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <PERSON>Murrill</PERSON> said scientists don't yet know how <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s magnetic
field is aligned. Voyager found the axis of Uranus' magnetic field
was tilted about 60 degrees from the axis around which that planet
spins.
   Earth's north magnetic pole is tilted about 14 degrees from the
planet's north rotational axis.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890819-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-89 0506EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Voyager-Neptune 1stLd-Writethru a0439 08-19 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Voyager-Neptune, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0439,0625</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radiation Threat To Voyager Unlikely Despite Neptune's Magnetism</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 15th graf, `Some scientists ...' to CLARIFY process of
turning planet's moons and rings dark, and 16th graf, `NASA also ...' to
CLARIFY time element.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Discovery of a magnetic field around
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> suggests the planet is enveloped by radiation belts, but
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> hopes they won't damage the Voyager 2 spacecraft as it flies
past the planet.
   ``Right now I don't think anyone is terribly alarmed,'' said <PERSON>Norm
Haynes</PERSON>, Voyager project manager at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and
Space Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   Similar radiation belts at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> disrupted <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION>'s internal
clock, causing some of its instruments to make measurements at the
wrong time.
   Today, Voyager was 2.74 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and 5.01 million
miles from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, speeding toward the giant gas planet at 42,251
mph.
   The ship will make its closest approach to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> at <TIME>8:59 p.m.
PDT</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when it zooms about 3,000 miles over the cloudtops of
the solar system's fourth-largest planet. The spacecraft was
launched in <DATE>1977</DATE>, and explored <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and
Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Friday</DATE> that Voyager 2 detected intense, pulselike
radio signals coming from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> _ strong evidence the planet has a
magnetic field. Radio waves are generated when high-speed
electrically charged particles spiral into a planet's atmosphere
along magnetic field lines.
   Mercury, <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus have magnetic fields.
Venus and Mars do not. Whether <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION> has one is unknown, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Magnetic fields are thought to be generated by fluid motion in a
planet's core. Molten iron in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s core, for example, creates a
magnetic field that traps charged particles in the Van <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> belts.
   Although dissimilar from the ionizing radiation found in a
nuclear reactor, such fields of radiation can damage spacecraft
electronics.
   So far at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, ``there's nothing to indicate it (the
radiation) is anything worse than we expected,'' said <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON>. ``But
time will tell.''
   Existence of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s magnetic field suggests the planet has an
aurora like <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s northern and southern lights, created when
charged particles spiral along magnetic field lines toward a
planet's poles.
   Further study of the magnetic field also should let scientists
determine the exact length of a day on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> _ now believed to be
between 17 and 18 Earth hours _ and gain better understanding of
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s internal structure, said <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>
spokeswoman <PERSON>Mary Beth Murrill</PERSON>.
   Voyager project scientist <ORGANIZATION>Edward Stone</ORGANIZATION> has said he believes
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s hydrogen-helium outer atmosphere gradually gives way to a
superhot slurry of hot water and rock closer to the planet's center.
   That would mean that <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, like neighboring Uranus, probably
lacks a distinct boundary between the sky and sea.
   Some scientists believe radiation trapped by Uranus' magnetic
field bombards that planet's moons and rings to turn them dark in
color. Neptune's magnetic field may cause similar radiation
darkening of the Neptunian moons and ring arcs, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> also released new photographs taken by Voyager.
Blurry black-and-white images show markings on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s
largest moon, but ``it is still too early to tell if the features
are clouds or features on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s surface,'' <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   A color photo of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> shows complex, frequently changing
weather patterns in its atmosphere, including high-altitude wispy
clouds, a small cloud dubbed ``the scooter'' because it rotates
quickly, and other clouds that appear as long streaks.
   In recent weeks, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> also has discovered four Neptunian moons
besides two observed from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>; two partial rings, or ring arcs, of
debris orbiting the planet; and atmospheric patterns similar to jet
streams on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900717-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-17-90 1420EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-Venus-Glance Adv24   07-17 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Venus-Glance, Adv24,0452</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Tues AMs, July 24, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Magellan-Venus, b0442</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Planet Venus at a Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft goes into
orbit around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>, it will use radar to map the surface
of the cloud-covered planet. Here is some of what scientists
already know about the second planet from the sun:
   DIAMETER: About 7,520 miles, or <PERCENT>95 percent</PERCENT> as wide as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>;
sixth largest of the solar system's nine known planets.
   MASS: Venus weighs about <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> as much as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ATMOSPHERE: About <PERCENT>97 percent</PERCENT> carbon dioxide, with trace amounts
of nitrogen, sulfur dioxide, water vapor, argon, oxygen, carbon
monoxide, neon, and hydrochloric and hydrofluoric acids. The
planet's clouds contain sulfuric acid droplets. The atmosphere
traps heat in a runaway ``greenhouse effect'' that scientists
believe evaporated liquid water long ago, if there ever was any on
the planet. Large fluctuations in sulfur dioxide levels may
indicate that active volcanoes pump the gas into <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' atmosphere.
   SURFACE CONDITIONS: Temperature about 900 degrees Fahrenheit,
hot enough to melt lead, zinc or tin. Crushing atmospheric pressure
90 times that on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s surface, or equivalent to the pressure
2,700 feet beneath the surface of an ocean on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   THE CALENDAR: A day on Venus lasts longer than a year. A
Venusian year _ the time it takes for the planet to orbit the sun _
lasts 225 Earth days. A Venusian day _ the time the planet takes to
spin once on its axis _ lasts 243 Earth days. Venus also has
retrograde rotation, so the sun rises in the west and sets in the
east.
   DISTANCE FROM THE SUN: Venus is the second planet from the sun,
orbiting at a distance of 67.2 million miles. It is closer to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
than any other planet. Other than the sun and moon, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is the
brightest object in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s skies.
   MOONS: None.
   GEOLOGY: Earth-based and spacecraft radar revealed hundreds of
thousands of volcanoes on the Venusian lowlands, although
scientists don't yet know if any are active. Venus also has
meteorite impact craters and continent-like highlands with towering
peaks that dwarf Earth's tallest mountains. Scientists suspect
giant plates of rock may move in <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' crust in a process vaguely
like continental drift on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Venus' surface is about <PERCENT>65 percent</PERCENT>
rolling plains, <PERCENT>27 percent</PERCENT> flat lowlands and <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT> highlands
that may be similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s continents.
   GRAVITY: About <PERCENT>89 percent</PERCENT> as strong as on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   MAGNETIC FIELD: None detected so far, suggesting <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> now lacks
a liquid core, which is needed to generate a magnetic field.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tues AMs, July 24</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890419-0222 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-19-89 1331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-ReturntothePlanets Adv23-1stAdd   04-19 0911</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Return to the Planets, Adv 23 - 1st Add,0920</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, April 23, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>CAPE CANAVERAL: rise significantly.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The latest discoveries come from a far-off realm, Uranus,
relayed by Voyager 2, a marvelous machine launched along with
Voyager 1 in <DATE>1977</DATE> to probe <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>. Voyager 2 was
working so well after exploring <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> that <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> reprogrammed it to
sail past Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE> and <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> next <DATE>August</DATE>.
   Uranus is considered the oddball of the solar system because,
unlike the other planets, it lies tipped on its side with its north
and south poles alternately facing the sun. Voyager 2 found that
Uranus' magnetic field does not follow the usual north-south axis
and instead is tilted 60 degrees and offset at the center.
Astronomers believe it might have been knocked off course by an
ancient collision with another celestial object.
   Voyager 2 found that winds on Uranus whip up to 450 mph and blow
from the west instead of the east as previously suspected. About
5,000 miles below the planet's cloudtops, the spacecraft detected
evidence of a boiling ocean of water and dissolved ammonia some
6,000 miles deep. Beneath this ocean, it is believed there is an
Earth-size molten core of heavier materials.
   The spacecraft discovered 10 new moons orbiting Uranus, ranging
from 24 to 102 miles in diameter, much smaller than the planet's
previously recorded five satellites. Uranus was thought to have
nine rings; Voyager found 11. In contrast to <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s rings, which
are composed of bright grain-sized particles, Uranus' rings are
made up of dark boulder-sized chunks.
   The Voyagers also discovered a ring around <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the largest
planet in the solar system and a valuable astronomical laboratory
because of the diversity of its system of at least 16 moons.
   During the flyby encounters, the Voyagers and the earlier
Pioneers 10 and 11, found <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> to be a whirling ball of liquid
hydrogen, topped by a uniquely colorful atmosphere which is mostly
hydrogen and helium. They learned the Great Red Spot, observed for
centuries through Earth-based telescopes, is a tremendous
atmospheric storm similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s hurricanes.
   The space probes detected lightning in <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s upper
atmosphere and observed auroral emissions like <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s northern
lights in the Jovian polar regions. Jupiter spins at a dizzying
pace _ once every 9 hours, 55 minutes, 30 seconds _ but it takes
the massive planet almost 12 Earth years to complete a journey
around the sun.
   Before Pioneer 11 and the Voyagers passed by <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>, astronomers
knew the planet only as a fuzzy yellow sphere surrounded by six
rings. The startling images relayed back quickly identified several
thousand rings made up of small ice particles orbiting the planet
at various speeds.
   The spacecraft discovered five new Saturnian moons, raising the
total to 17. Titan, the largest, received the most attention
because it is the only moon in the solar system believed to have an
atmosphere. Although it is inconceivable that life could exist in
the oceans of liquid nitrogen and freezing hydrocarbons believed to
form <ORGANIZATION>Titan</ORGANIZATION>'s surface, scientists are intrigued by the possibility
that the giant moon may hold clues about the formation of organic
molecules in the atmosphere of the primeval <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> between three and
four billion years ago.
   The Voyagers also found <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere of hydrogen and
helium alive with monster storms, with winds of 1,100 mph.
   Venus, our sister planet and closest neighbor, more nearly
resembles Earth in size, physical composition and density than any
of the other planets. However, <ORGANIZATION>Mariner</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Pioneer</ORGANIZATION> probes found
that <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is a blistering hot world where the 900-degree heat is
trapped in a thick atmosphere of carbon dioxide.
   Radar peering through <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' thick cloud cover found evidence of
two major active volcano areas. The concentration of lightning over
these areas suggests frequent eruptions. A valley may have been
created by tension in the planet's crust pulling the surface apart
like similar processes on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Photographs taken of <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Mariner</ORGANIZATION> 10 in <DATE>1974</DATE> and <DATE>1975</DATE>
revealed an ancient, heavily cratered surface, closely resembling
our own moon. The pictures also showed huge cliffs crisscrossing
the planet.
   Instruments aboard <ORGANIZATION>Mariner</ORGANIZATION> 10 found that <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> has a weak
magnetic field and a trace of an atmosphere - a trillionth the
density of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s and composed chiefly of argon, neon and
helium. The spacecraft reported temperatures ranging from 950
degrees Fahrenheit on the sunlight side to 346 degrees below zero
on the shadowed side.
   Of all the planets, Mars has long been considered the solar
system's prime candidate for harboring extraterrestrial life. But
the results obtained by the Viking 1 and 2 landers in <DATE>1976</DATE> and <DATE>1977</DATE>
were teasingly inconclusive. Small samples of Martian soil were
scooped up and specially treated in three different experiments
designed to detect biological processes. While some of the tests
indicated biological processes were occuring, the same results
could be explained by the planet's chemistry. There was no evidence
of organic molecules in the small areas surveyed by the Vikings.
   The Vikings and earlier <ORGANIZATION>Mariners</ORGANIZATION> found that dust covers the
Martian surface under a sparse atmosphere that allows the wind to
stir up fierce <DATE>summer</DATE> storms. Massive active volcanoes dot the
landscape, and dry sinuous channels, perhaps carved long ago by
flowing water, stretch for hundreds of miles. Many scientists
believe water still lies below the surface, giving rise to
speculation that some form of life might yet be found there.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sun, April 23</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890629-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-29-89 1246EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Voyager-Neptune Adv03   06-29 1164</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Voyager-Neptune, Adv 03,1195</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, July 3, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Voyager 2 Approaches Neptune for Grand Finale of Solar System Trek</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto, LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twelve years, three planets and 4.4
billion miles after leaving <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 is converging on
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, a swirling, blue-green planet with a backward moon, for the
last stop on an extraordinary tour.
   ``The solar system is our neighborhood, and we're getting to the
end of the neighborhood,'' said <PERSON>Norm Haynes</PERSON>, Voyager project manager
at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space Admnistration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion
Laboratory.
   Voyager 2 already has detected a dark spot on <ORGANIZATION>Nep</ORGANIZATION>
a giant storm like <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot. As it nears the planet,
the probe will search for undiscovered moons and partial rings. And
at <TIME>9 p.m. PDT</TIME> on <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will swoop within 3,000 miles oftune
that may be
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north pole cloudtops _ the closest of its close encounters
and the first spacecraft to visit the planet.
   It will be 2.75 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> after traveling 4.43
billion miles along its curving path. The information it sends back
at the speed of light will take four hours and six minutes to arrive.
   Five hours after the closest encounter, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will fly within
25,000 miles of the backwards-orbiting moon, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>. The other known
moon is Nereid.
lion through the <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>
encounter, the Voyagers ``returned more new knowledge about the
outer planets ... than existed in all of the preceding history of
astronomy,'' according to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, discovered in <DATE>1846</DATE>, is 30,700 miles in diameter _ six
times <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s size and the fourth largest planet after <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus. A Neptunian year lasts 165 Earth years, and a day
lasts 17 to 18 Earth hours _ a detail Voyager may pinpoint. Neptune
usually is the eighth planet, but because of <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>'s elongated orbit
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> will be the ninth and outermost until <DATE>2007</DATE>.
   Scientists expect Voyager to discover at least 10 small moons,
said deputy project scientist <PERSON>Ellis Miner</PERSON>.
   Some moons may confine or shepherd the 5- to 12-mile-wide
incomplete rings, called ``ring arcs,'' orbiting <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, said
physicist Ed Stone, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Voyager project scientist and a vice
president at <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   Voyager also may discover dust bands and 50 to 100 partial rings
in addition to the three to six arcs scientists believe they
detected from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Stone added. The partial rings, possibly made
of dust and pebbles, most likely are debris from the collision of a
comet and an ancient moon, he said.
   Voyager should be some 33,400 miles above <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s clouds when
it crosses the ring region, so it is unlikely to be destroyed by an
unseen arc, he said.
   The probe also will study <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s weather. Scientists believe
the 6,200-mile-wide dark spot it found probably is similar to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s hurricanes or <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot. The source of the
internal heat driving <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s storms is a mystery; Earth's comes
decaying radioactive material in rocks.
   Neptune is pale blue-green because methane, or natural gas, in
its mostly hydrogen-helium atmosphere absorbs red light. Scientists
suspect that a third of the way toward the planet's center the
atmosphere becomes a superhot slurry of hot water and rock, so
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> _ like neighboring Uranus _ probably lacks a distinct
sky-sea boundary, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Despite any internal heat, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> receives 900 times less
sunlight than <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, so the temperature at the top of its atmosphere
is 350 degrees below zero Fahrenheit, about the same as on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Scientists believe <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> _ 1,400 to 2,240 miles wide, roughly
the size of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s moon _ will be the most fascinating part of
Voyager's flyby.
   When a planet and its moons form from a spinning disk of gas and
solid material, the moons should orbit in the direction the planet
rotates. <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s reverse orbit suggests it once orbited the sun
like a comet or a planet but collided with a moon to form a new
backwards-moving satellite, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> probably is cold and geologically inactive, with an icy
mantle over a rocky core. But it once may have had a molten interior
that created ridges, valleys, cliffs, canyons and volcanoes that
Voyager might photograph.
   Observations from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> indicate <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere contains
methane and nitrogen. Sunlight likely converts methane into complex
hydrocarbons, creating a transparent reddish-orange photochemical
haze, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said. The hydrocarbons may form heavier particles,
coating the surface with frozen sludge.
   Could the organic chemicals have allowed life to develop on
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>?
   ``The temperature is very, very cold, so I think it's unlikely,''
he said.
   Scientists believe <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has extreme seasons because its orbit
around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is highly inclined: One pole faces the sun for 82
years and the other remains in darkness. This may mean <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s
atmosphere gets thinner and thicker as methane-nitrogen icecaps
cover one pole, then the other.
   Researchers discarded the theory that <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has liquid nitrogen
oceans, but puddles or lakes are possible, along with fields of
nitrogen ice crystals, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Nereid, about 190 to 620 miles wide, has a very elongated
elliptical orbit. Caltech astrophysicist <PERSON>Peter Goldreich</PERSON> speculates
Nereid once had a circular orbit that was disturbed by gravity from
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> or a large passing object.
   If Voyager confirms that <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> has a magnetic field, the planet
also may have an aurora like <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s, and a mysterious ultraviolet
``electroglow.'' A magnetic field should trap a radiation belt
around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s Van <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> belts. <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s
radiation belts damaged some of Voyager's equipment; <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON> doubts
similar problems at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   Voyager 2 has worked 12 years with only relatively minor
failures, although it contains electronics equal to 10,000
television sets, he said.
   Commands sent to <LOCATION>Voyager</LOCATION>, and photos and information it sends to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, travel at the speed of light. But the one-way trip still take
four hours, six minutes. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is using 38 dish-shaped radio antennas
in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to capture the
radio signal, which is like trying to see a 20-watt light bulb
burning 2.75 billion miles away.
   ``Both Voyagers are expected to return valuable data well into
the 21st century'' before their power supplies run out in about
<DATE>2020</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   After <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 will join Voyager 1 and Pioneers 10 and
11 in seeking the true edge of the solar system, where solar wind
gives way to interstellar wind billions of miles beyond the planets.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for July 3</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890702-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-02-89 2351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-EXP--Voyager-Neptune     07-02 1152</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-EXP--Voyager-Neptune,1181</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voyager 2 Approaches Neptune for Grand Finale of Solar System Trek</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twelve years, three planets and 4.4
billion miles after leaving <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 is converging on
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, a swirling, blue-green planet with a backward moon, for the
last stop on an extraordinary tour.
   ``The solar system is our neighborhood, and we're getting to the
end of the neighborhood,'' said <PERSON>Norm Haynes</PERSON>, Voyager project manager
at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space Admnistration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion
Laboratory.
   Voyager 2 already has detected a dark spot on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> that may be
a giant storm like <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot. As it nears the planet,
the probe will search for undiscovered moons and partial rings. And
at <TIME>9 p.m. PDT</TIME> on <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will swoop within 3,000 miles of
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north pole cloudtops _ the closest of its close encounters
and the first spacecraft to visit the planet.
   It will be 2.75 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> after traveling 4.43
billion miles along its curving path. The information it sends back
at the speed of light will take four hours and six minutes to arrive.
   Five hours after the closest encounter, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will fly within
25,000 miles of the backwards-orbiting moon, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>. The other known
moon is Nereid.
   Voyager 1 and 2, laden with TV cameras and an array of sensors,
were launched from <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE>. They visited <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1979</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1981</DATE>, respectively. Voyager 2 reached
Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Voyager 1 now is heading toward interstellar space.
   Voyager 1 and 2 returned 65,000 photographs of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>
and their moons and rings. Voyager 2 sent back 8,000 pictures of
Uranus and its moons, and will take another 8,000 of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   At a cost <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON> pegged at <MONEY>$865 million</MONEY> through the <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>
encounter, the Voyagers ``returned more new knowledge about the
outer planets ... than existed in all of the preceding history of
astronomy,'' according to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, discovered in <DATE>1846</DATE>, is 30,700 miles in diameter _ six
times <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s size and the fourth largest planet after <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus. A Neptunian year lasts 165 Earth years, and a day
lasts 17 to 18 Earth hours _ a detail Voyager may pinpoint. Neptune
usually is the eighth planet, but because of <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>'s elongated orbit
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> will be the ninth and outermost until <DATE>2007</DATE>.
   Scientists expect Voyager to discover at least 10 small moons,
said deputy project scientist <PERSON>Ellis Miner</PERSON>.
   Some moons may confine or shepherd the 5- to 12-mile-wide
incomplete rings, called ``ring arcs,'' orbiting <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, said
physicist Ed Stone, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Voyager project scientist and a vice
president at <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   Voyager also may discover dust bands and 50 to 100 partial rings
in addition to the three to six arcs scientists believe they
detected from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Stone added. The partial rings, possibly made
of dust and pebbles, most likely are debris from the collision of a
comet and an ancient moon, he said.
   Voyager should be some 33,400 miles above <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s clouds when
it crosses the ring region, so it is unlikely to be destroyed by an
unseen arc, he said.
   The probe also will study <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s weather. Scientists believe
the 6,200-mile-wide dark spot it found probably is similar to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s hurricanes or <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot. The source of the
internal heat driving <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s storms is a mystery; Earth's comes
decaying radioactive material in rocks.
   Neptune is pale blue-green because methane, or natural gas, in
its mostly hydrogen-helium atmosphere absorbs red light. Scientists
suspect that a third of the way toward the planet's center the
atmosphere becomes a superhot slurry of hot water and rock, so
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> _ like neighboring Uranus _ probably lacks a distinct
sky-sea boundary, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Despite any internal heat, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> receives 900 times less
sunlight than <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, so the temperature at the top of its atmosphere
is 350 degrees below zero Fahrenheit, about the same as on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Scientists believe <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> _ 1,400 to 2,240 miles wide, roughly
the size of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s moon _ will be the most fascinating part of
Voyager's flyby.
   When a planet and its moons form from a spinning disk of gas and
solid material, the moons should orbit in the direction the planet
rotates. <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s reverse orbit suggests it once orbited the sun
like a comet or a planet but collided with a moon to form a new
backwards-moving satellite, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> probably is cold and geologically inactive, with an icy
mantle over a rocky core. But it once may have had a molten interior
that created ridges, valleys, cliffs, canyons and volcanoes that
Voyager might photograph.
   Observations from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> indicate <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere contains
methane and nitrogen. Sunlight likely converts methane into complex
hydrocarbons, creating a transparent reddish-orange photochemical
haze, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said. The hydrocarbons may form heavier particles,
coating the surface with frozen sludge.
   Could the organic chemicals have allowed life to develop on
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>?
   ``The temperature is very, very cold, so I think it's unlikely,''
he said.
   Scientists believe <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has extreme seasons because its orbit
around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is highly inclined: One pole faces the sun for 82
years and the other remains in darkness. This may mean <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s
atmosphere gets thinner and thicker as methane-nitrogen icecaps
cover one pole, then the other.
   Researchers discarded the theory that <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has liquid nitrogen
oceans, but puddles or lakes are possible, along with fields of
nitrogen ice crystals, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Nereid, about 190 to 620 miles wide, has a very elongated
elliptical orbit. Caltech astrophysicist <PERSON>Peter Goldreich</PERSON> speculates
Nereid once had a circular orbit that was disturbed by gravity from
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> or a large passing object.
   If Voyager confirms that <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> has a magnetic field, the planet
also may have an aurora like <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s, and a mysterious ultraviolet
``electroglow.'' A magnetic field should trap a radiation belt
around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s Van <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> belts. <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s
radiation belts damaged some of Voyager's equipment; <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON> doubts
similar problems at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   Voyager 2 has worked 12 years with only relatively minor
failures, although it contains electronics equal to 10,000
television sets, he said.
   Commands sent to <LOCATION>Voyager</LOCATION>, and photos and information it sends to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, travel at the speed of light. But the one-way trip still take
four hours, six minutes. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is using 38 dish-shaped radio antennas
in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to capture the
radio signal, which is like trying to see a 20-watt light bulb
burning 2.75 billion miles away.
   ``Both Voyagers are expected to return valuable data well into
the 21st century'' before their power supplies run out in about
<DATE>2020</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   After <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 will join Voyager 1 and Pioneers 10 and
11 in seeking the true edge of the solar system, where solar wind
gives way to interstellar wind billions of miles beyond the planets.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890830-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-89 0151EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Voyager-Neptune Bjt   08-30 0866</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Voyager-Neptune, Bjt,0891</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voyagers Bequeath a Legacy of Wonders</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ``Not fare well, But fare forward, voyagers.'' _ <ORGANIZATION>T.S. Eliot</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Not fare well, But fare forward, voyagers.'' _ <ORGANIZATION>T.S. Eliot</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   ``Not fare well, But fare forward, voyagers.'' _ <ORGANIZATION>T.S. Eliot</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900811-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-11-90 1618EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Magellan-Earth'sTwin Bjt   08-11 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Earth's Twin, Bjt,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magellan's Venus Exploration May Provide Clues to the Early Earth</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Geologists may get a glimpse of what
<ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s surface was like a few billion years ago when the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
spacecraft's radar pierces the clouds of Venus to reveal secrets of
an alien terrain.
   ``Venus is the last of the inner planets we are exploring in
detail, and probably is the most important from the point of view
of understanding the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Jim Head</PERSON>, a member of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> science team and a geology professor at <ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> fired its braking rocket and slipped into orbit around
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> after a 15-month, 948-million-mile voyage from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Engineers at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory monitored the
spacecraft's health <DATE>Saturday</DATE> so it will be ready by <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE> to use
its radar to peer through thick Venusian clouds and make the most
detailed pictures and maps yet of the planet's landscape.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> entered orbit so smoothly that it used very little
thruster fuel to point it properly while the rocket fired. So
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> weighs more and moves faster than expected, making the low
point in its orbit 183 miles above Venus instead of 171 miles as
planned, said navigation chief <PERSON>John McNamee</PERSON>.
   The orbit is so good that an adjustment maneuver planned for
<DATE>Aug. 28</DATE> will not be needed, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project manager <PERSON>Tony Spear</PERSON>
said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is designed to study the geology and geography of
<LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, heated to 900 degrees Fahrenheit by a ``greenhouse effect''
gone berserk.
   Venus' high temperature and crushing atmospheric pressure might
make rock in the planet's crust much thinner and more flexible than
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s, <PERSON>Head</PERSON> said.
   So Venus may resemble Earth before our home planet's crust
cooled off and broke into colossal plates. Those plates now drift
across the face of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, moving whole continents and colliding
to uplift mountain ranges and trigger volcanic eruptions and
earthquakes.
   Most of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s original surface was destroyed long ago by
erosion and plate movements, so ``we have grave difficulty
answering fundamental questions about the early history of the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' Head said.
   While <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is hot, dry and lifeless, ``it is very similar in
size and density and also is the closest planet to the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' he
said. ``That means it probably had the most similar conditions when
the planets formed (4.6 billion years ago). So if we want to study
another planet to learn something about the early <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is a
good candidate.''
   Learning how <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' crust moves and is deformed ``will tell us a
lot more about the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s chief
scientist for <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> may settle debate over competing theories that seek to
explain the creation of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' continent-like highlands, which
include Africa-sized <ORGANIZATION>Aphrodite Terra</ORGANIZATION>, Australia-sized Ishtar Terra
and Hawaii-like Beta Regio.
   Saunders believes ``hot spots'' of rising molten rock created
the highlands, just as hot spots created <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ``If you could look at a time-lapse movie over billions of
years, it might look like a big pot of thick porridge simmering,'
<PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said, adding <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' crust may feature ``a bunch of big
Hawaiis all over the place.''
   Some other scientists think <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' highlands are big pieces of
crust that solidified first as the planet's initial molten surface
cooled off.
   But Head believes plate movements formed the highlands.
Aphrodite Terra resembles <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s midocean ridges, the undersea
mountain ranges where molten rock emerges to add new material to
the drifting plates of crust.
   Ishtar Terra ``has many of the features that you would expect
where blocks of crust are colliding,'' including volcanoes such as
those along the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> coasts of <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> and
folded mountain belts such as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s Himalayas, which were created
because <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is smashing into <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>.
   Even if the Venusian crust hasn't yet broken into plates, ``we
probably will find faults like the <LOCATION>San Andreas</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,'' a
pretty sure sign that ``Venusquakes'' shake the second planet from
the sun, <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890829-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-89 1659EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Voyager-Neptune 1stLd-Writethru a0582 08-29 0945</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Neptune, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0582,0961</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Worlds Behind, Voyager Heads For The Stars</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 7-9 bgng `At Neptune ...' with 7 grafs to UPDATE
with details from final news conference.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 2 cruised away from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and
toward the stars <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, completing an <MONEY>$865 million</MONEY> trek past 60
worlds, a triumphant exploration that might help humans prevent
destruction of their own planet.
   ``If you want to understand Earth, go look at other worlds,''
said <ORGANIZATION>Cornell University</ORGANIZATION> astronomer <PERSON>Carl Sagan</PERSON>, a member of the team
that analyzed about 81,000 photographs taken by Voyager 2 and its
twin, Voyager 1.
   ``Our passion to explore, our deep need to understand our
origins, and the very urgent and practical matter of safeguarding
our planet are all enormously enhanced by studying other planets.''
   As scientists held a final news conference at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet
Propulsion Laboratory to summarize Voyager 2's discoveries, the
one-ton spacecraft was 2.76 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and 4.2 million
miles beyond <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, the solar system's fourth-largest and
currently most-distant planet.
   Voyager also was nearly 4.5 billion miles along a curving path
that took it from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE>, past <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>, and now past <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> in search of the edge
of the solar system. Voyager 1 explored <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>
in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   For <MONEY>$865 million _ 20 cents</MONEY> per year per American since the
project started _ the twin Voyagers visited four planets with at
least 56 moons, discovering at least 23 of the satellites and
examining worlds of wonder, like <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s moon Io, with its
sulfur-spewing volcanoes.
   ``As exciting as the discoveries at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> have been, this
encounter has really just been the fourth and final planet that
<PERSON>Voyager</PERSON> has revealed in an unprecedented decade of discovery in its
journey through the outer solar system,'' said Voyager project
scientist <ORGANIZATION>Edward Stone</ORGANIZATION>. ``For those of us fortunate enough to be
involved, this has been the journey of a lifetime.''
   At <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 discovered six moons in addition to <LOCATION>Nereid</LOCATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, which were first detected from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. It discovered
three thin rings of debris and two broad rings orbiting the planet.
It found at least six moonlets hidden in one of the rings.
   The spacecraft detected in <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s bluish atmosphere an
Earth-sized swirling storm called the Great Dark Spot, 720 mph
winds, photochemical smog, invisible ultraviolet auroras and cirrus
clouds of natural gas casting shadows on clouds far below.
   Voyager revealed two bizarre types of ice volcanoes on icy,
pinkish <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>. The first kind are calderas _ 1,000-foot-deep
craters measuring hundreds of miles across _ that produced
ocean-size floods of ice flowing like lava, probably no more
recently than <DATE>a half billion years ago</DATE>, said <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>
geologist <PERSON>Laurence Soderblom</PERSON>.
   The second type can erupt explosively, ejecting nitrogen ice and
gas 25 miles high at speeds of 560 mph _ higher and faster than
initially estimated, he said. He said he suspects the nitrogen
volcanoes are active today or were active within the past 300 years.
   Soderblom drew gasps of amazement when he showed a Voyager
photograph of one of the calderas, computer enhanced to make it look
as it would to someone standing on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s surface and seeing the
crater in three dimensions.
   Scientists also presented new findings <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> showing <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s
weak, tilted magnetic field doesn't go through the center of planet
but is offset about four-tenths of the way toward the surface. That,
plus new evidence that matter is distributed unevenly inside the
planet, suggests the liquid that generates the magnetic field may
exist in a shallow spherical shell, not in a deep central core as
inside the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ``These observations are just as arcane as the discoveries of
Captain Cook or even the posthumous accounts of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>,'' said
<ORGANIZATION>Planetary Society</ORGANIZATION> vice president <PERSON>Bruce Murray</PERSON>, former director of
<ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>. ``The discoveries challenge our
imagination and seem just like science fiction. But they may be very
important and very relevant to our grandchildren and their
grandchildren.''
   The knowledge gathered by the Voyagers may help alert their human
masters to the vulnerability of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, a tiny garden threatened by
nuclear warfare, the greenhouse effect and destruction of the ozone
shield.
   ``If you look who discovered these dangers ... you find a
remarkable preponderance of present and past planetary scientists,''
<PERSON>Sagan</PERSON> said.
   He said <PERSON>Sherwood Rowland</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mario Molina</PERSON> first warned of
depletion of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s ozone layer using chemical formulas devised to
help <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> understand the atmosphere of Venus. Molina now works at
<ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>.
   Sagan and other planetary scientists developed the theory that
smoke from nuclear war could plunge <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> into a dark, cold nuclear
winter and cause mass starvation of those who survived the exchange
of warheads.
   ``The idea ultimately evolved from our attempt to understand the
great Martian dust storm of 1971-72,'' which was detected by Mariner
9 and chilled Mars' already cold surface, <PERSON>Sagan</PERSON> said.
   From <ORGANIZATION>Mariner</ORGANIZATION> and the space probe Pioneer, scientists studied the
runaway ``greenhouse effect'' on <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, where thick clouds trap
solar heat, warming the planet to 900 degrees.
   <PERSON>Sagan</PERSON> said <PERSON>Voyager</PERSON> also helps satisfy human wanderlust and seeks
to answer that most fundamental question _ ``where we come from, how
we fit into the grand cosmological scheme.''
   Voyager 2 keeps looking back at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> until <DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>. Then, like
Voyager 1, it will spend the next 20 or 30 years collecting
information about particles and magnetic fields in space and
searching for the edge of the solar system. Scientists figure the
probes can continue transmitting data until <DATE>2020</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890827-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-27-89 2030EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Voyager-Neptune 3rdLd-Writethru a0713 08-27 0893</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Neptune, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0713,0915</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voyager Finds Apparently Active Nitrogen Ice Volcanoes On Triton</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, `While more...,' to CORRECT quote to say `whole
process,' sted `whole practice...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos LA2,1C</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 2's close-up photos of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s
moon <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> reveal what look like active ice volcanoes that erupt
explosively, spewing nitrogen ice particles and gas nearly 20 miles
high, scientists said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   ``I believe they are active,'' or erupted at least within the
past 100 years, said <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> geologist <PERSON>Larry
Soderblom</PERSON>, a member of the Voyager photographic imaging team at
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory. ``There's 10 or 20 or 30 _ lots.''
   ``This is a crazy idea ... but it's the best we have at the
current time'' to explain the pockmarked terrain, he added.
   While more evidence is needed to prove the volcanoes are active,
``the whole process makes physical sense,'' said <PERSON>Bradford Smith</PERSON>,
leader of the Voyager 2 imaging team. ``That is a perfectly sensible
explanation.''
   If <PERSON>Soderblom</PERSON> and <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> are right, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> is only the third object
in the solar system known to have active volcanism. Earth and
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s moon Io are the others.
   Soderblom compared the new type of ice volcanoes with
sulfur-spewing volcanoes on Io. But he said the volcanoes on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>
are produced when liquid nitrogen rises in underground pools rises
to the surface, where reduced pressure means ``it's got to explode
and will shower ice particles and gas.''
   Based on dark-colored, plume-shaped deposits that stretch up to
50 miles downwind from the volcanoes, <PERSON>Soderblom</PERSON> estimated the
eruptions eject debris at scores of mile per hour, perhaps faster,
sending it 12 to 19 miles skyward.
   ``The stuff comes shooting up like gas out of a gun barrel,''
said <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Arizona</ORGANIZATION> planetary scientist. The
deposits apparently contain radiation-darkened ices that fell to the
surface after being carried skyward by the blast, he added.
   Voyager 2 made its closest approach to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>
when it skimmed about 3,000 miles over the planet's north pole cloud
tops. Early <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, the spacecraft zoomed about 24,000 miles
past <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, taking the photos that have revealed at least three
kinds of icy volcanism on the moon.
   Voyager earlier discovered icy flows that oozed up from the
floors of long valleys, a process likened to toothpaste coming out
of a tube slit with a razor blade.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, scientists announced that Voyager had discovered a
different type of ice volcanoes, which appeared inactive and
possibly extinct. They are huge flat craters, called calderas,
similar to the one in which <ORGANIZATION>Yellowstone National Park</ORGANIZATION> rests.
   Some calderas, such as the crater atop <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kilauea</LOCATION> volcano,
fill with lava lakes. <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s calderas, measuring up to hundreds of
miles wide, fill with flows of viscous ice, possibly water ice, that
gushes up from below, <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said.
   New evidence released <DATE>Sunday</DATE> shows <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s ice-lava lakes ``can
come up and overflow. You see that happen in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> all the time''
when molten rock lava overflows crater walls, <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said.
   So eruptions from <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s calderas once produced ``a sea of
ice-like lava in repeated eruptions,'' resulting in ``massive,
oceanic-scale flooding,'' <PERSON>Soderblom</PERSON> said during a <DATE>Sunday</DATE> news
conference. He said at least four such calderas have been spotted on
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Soderblom</PERSON> said he believes the newly discovered nitrogen ice
volcanoes either are currently active or erupted within the past
century because they are located on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s huge south polar ice
cap.
   A year on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> lasts about 165 Earth years. So if
the ice cap had gone through a <DATE>summer</DATE>, evidence of volcanic deposits
would have been erased as the ice cap receded, he added.
   So far, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> has discovered six moons orbiting <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, in
addition to <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Nereid</LOCATION>, which were discovered from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. It
also has found five rings of debris orbiting the planet, including
two that are broad bands of dust.
   The latest ring photo released by <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> shows one of those
bands is even broader than thought, forming a beautiful, circular
sheet of dust that extends throughout the plane of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s rings
and extends inward toward the planet.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s latest results from <LOCATION>Voyager</LOCATION>'s close encounters with
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> found that:
   _Winds up to more than 700 mph have been measured in <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s
atmosphere.
   _A day on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> lasts 16 hours and three minutes, give or take
four minutes.
   _<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s south pole and equator, while incredibly cold, are
much hotter than the planet's middle latitudes.
   _The planet's magnetic poles are tilted an extreme 50 degrees
away from from the poles around which the planet rotates, a much
greater tilt than the minimum of 30 degrees scientists initially
estimated. That means <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s magnetic north pole is closer to its
equator than to its rotational north pole.
   It also means <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is much more similar to Uranus, which has a
magnetic field tilt of 58 degrees. Earth's magnetic poles are tilted
12 degrees from its true, or rotational poles.
   By <TIME>9 a.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will be 2.76 billion miles from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and 3.19 million miles behind <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, speeding away from the
planet at 37,621 mph.
   The probe on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> was looking for lightning and auroras on
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>. It also sent back its best picture of heart-shaped moon
1989N1, which has usurped Nereid as <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s second-largest moon.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890826-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-89 2018EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Voyager-Neptune 1stLd-Writethru a0561 08-26 0862</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Neptune, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0561,0879</SECOND>
<HEAD>Spacecraft Finds Three More Rings And Many Tiny Moonlets Around Neptune</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS lead and 6th graf, pvs, `However Smith ...' to UPDATE with
Smith now saying three new rings, for total of five, sted up to five. SUBS
grafs 12-13 pvs, bgn `Smith said...,' with 1 graf to conform. Picks up
14th graf pvs, `Researchers said...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos XJPL1, XJPL2; LaserColor XJPL3C</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 2 discovered at least six tiny
``moonlets'' hidden in one of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s two brightest rings, and
also found three more rings orbiting the planet, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Voyager's scientists also reported the solar system's
fourth-largest planet is surrounded by a radiation belt and has a
tilted magnetic field, and may have an aurora like <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s northern
and southern lights.
   The researchers said nitrogen _ the gas that makes up <PERCENT>78 percent</PERCENT>
of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere _ is the main component in the skies of
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, the frosty Neptunian moon sculpted with faults, cliffs, pink
snow, meteorite craters and inactive volcanoes that once oozed
viscous ice instead of molten rock. Methane, or natural gas, is
present as well, they said.
   By <TIME>9 a.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, Voyager will be 2.29 million miles from
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, speeding away from the planet at 37,689 mph. The probe will
be 2.75 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Voyager traveled a curving
4.43-billion-mile path to achieve <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s close encounter
with <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>'s flight past <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We have five rings at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>,'' including the two bright ones
found earlier by the spacecraft and three new ones, said <PERSON>Bradford
Smith</PERSON>, leader of the Voyager photographic imaging team at the space
agency's Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said later the boundaries between the five rings aren't
well defined, so there could be as few as three rings or as many as
five. He reversed himself later <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, deciding the rings are
distinct enough to count the total as five.
   A bright ring discovered <DATE>Aug. 11</DATE> initially appeared to be a
partial ring, called a ring arc, but proved to be a complete ring.
Six to eight icy objects _ the largest no bigger than 6 miles to 12
miles wide _ are embedded in that ring, <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said.
   ``You could refer to them as moonlets,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said the gravity of the moonlets may explain why the ring
has a clumpy appearance, with some segments wider than others.
   So far, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> has discovered six objects orbiting <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> that
are large enough to be called moons. That brings the total to eight
moons, including <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> and Nereid, which were discovered from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The ring containing the moonlets remains <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s outermost
ring. Next toward the planet is a narrow newly discovered ring,
followed by another previously unknown ring that is a broad, diffuse
band of dust. Then comes the other ring discovered earlier. Closest
to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is the third newly discovered ring, a broad, diffuse band
of dust <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said was 1,550 miles wide.
   The initial confusion over the number of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s rings is
reminiscent of what happened at Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Ten thin rings were
apparent as Voyager neared Uranus. But after the spacecraft passed
that planet, a wide sheet of rings and dust bands became visible
when backlit by the sun. As a result, scientists still are arguing
how many distinct rings orbit Uranus.
   Researchers said <DATE>Saturday</DATE> that Voyager also found:
   _<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s magnetic poles are tilted at least 30 degrees away
from the poles around which the planet rotates. Earth's magnetic
axis is angled 12 degrees away from its rotational axis, putting one
magnetic pole in northern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> about 1,000 miles from the true, or
rotational, north pole.
   _The planet is surrounded by a radiation belt much weaker than
the <ORGANIZATION>Van Allen</ORGANIZATION> belts encircling <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. The radiation belt's location
near the orbit of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> may explain the pinkish hue of some of the
moon's surface. Radiation bombardment can turn frozen natural gas
that color.
   Deputy Voyager project scientist <PERSON>Ellis Miner</PERSON> said there is
evidence from an ultraviolet light sensor that, at 30 degrees south
latitude, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> has an aurora similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s northern and
southern lights. Other scientists <DATE>Saturday</DATE> refused to discuss the
evidence, saying it was too preliminary.
   If the aurora proves real, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s tilted magnetic field would
explain why the glowing lights are relatively close to the planet's
equator rather than the rotational poles.
   Auroras are caused when electrically charged particles in solar
wind spiral in toward a planet along magnetic field lines. On Earth,
they surround the polar regions because the magnetic and rotational
poles are relatively close.
   Voyager continued <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to send back recorded photographs
taken during its Neptune-Triton flyby, including its most detailed
photos of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>.
   The spaceship also looked over its shoulder to make a global
temperature map of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, search for auroras and more rings, and
study the weight of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>.
   Voyager 2 was launched in <DATE>1977</DATE> and explored <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Until <DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>, Voyager 2 will look
back at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>. Then it will head toward interstellar space,
looking for the edge of the solar system.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890428-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-28-89 1301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u n AM-Shuttle-Venus Bjt   04-28 0887</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shuttle-Venus, Bjt,880</SECOND>
<HEAD>Maybe a Nice Place to Visit, But You Couldn't Live There</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Backgrounder, should stand even if there is a launch delay.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A runaway ``greenhouse effect'' has
eliminated any trace of water. Volcanoes number not in the hundreds
or thousands, but the hundreds of thousands. Its crushing
atmospheric pressure, suffice it to say, could never support
anything resembling human life.
   Venus is not exactly <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>.
   For eight months beginning in <DATE>August 1990</DATE>, the space probe
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will circle the second planet from the Sun, using
computer-enhanced radar images to study a planet so inhospitable
that its 900-degree surface temperature would melt lead.
   Yet, for all its alien qualities, scientists think the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
mission will yield valuable information about the formation of
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ``The most likely scenario is that we'll find something that
will completely astound and baffle us,'' said <PERSON>Steve Saunders</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>. The craft was being ferried into space aboard the shuttle
Atlantis, to be launched from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit on its 15-month
trajectory to <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>.
   Pictures from <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> should help scientists deduce ``the
probability you're going to find Earth-like planets _ and life _
somewhere else,'' said geologist <PERSON>Laurence Soderblom</PERSON>, a scientist
working on the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project.
   Peering through acid-laden clouds, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> should give
scientists their best look yet at a planet so outwardly different
from the garden of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> yet apparently shaped by the same geologic
processes.
   ``Of all the planets in the solar system, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is most like our
own Earth in size, mass and distance from the sun,'' <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> says.
   Among the common forces, scientists say, are volcanic eruptions,
meteorite impacts and, perhaps, continental drift, the evolutionary
movement of huge land masses. <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will also look for evidence
of wind and water erosion and test the bounds of Venus' gravity.
   The image of Venus formed by pictures taken from earlier <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
and Soviet space probes is of a planet where molten rock lies so
close to the solid crust surface that impacting meteorites might
produce volcanic eruptions, where hundreds of thousands of
volcanoes stretch for thousands of miles across lowland plains,
where continent-sized highlands sprout mountains dwarfing <ORGANIZATION>Everest</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, once it begins orbiting Venus on <DATE>Aug. 10, 1990</DATE>, will
look for ancient stream channels, shorelines and other evidence the
planet once may have had oceans. Scientists believe an unchecked
``greenhouse effect'' _ in which the carbon dioxide atmosphere
acted like greenhouse glass and trapped solar heat _ raised the
temperature until water disappeared.
   It's a <MONEY>$550-million</MONEY> project with the scientific world watching.
   ``Part of the answer is knowing whether Earth is a fluke or just
one of the natural consequences of the evolution of a generic solar
system,'' said <PERSON>Soderblom</PERSON>, who works for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Flagstaff</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>.
   Scientists will probe the gravity forces of Venus by plotting
the path of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> as it swoops to within 155 miles of the
planet's surface and then sweeps out to a high orbit point of 4,977
miles.
   In looking for similarities between <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, scientists
begin by noting that they are roughly the same size, weight and
distance from the Sun, and are both bigger than <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s moon,
<ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> and Mars.
   Heavenly bodies ``are a lot like potatoes. The big ones stay hot
for a long time, and the little ones cool off quickly,'' said
<PERSON>Saunders</PERSON>, himself a geologist.
   The moon, <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> and Mars have cold surfaces free of
continental drift. Because a planet's internal heat ``drives the
geological machinery,'' however, scientists believe <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and Earth
both give off heat through volcanic activity and movements of
gargantuan pieces of rock along the planetary crust, <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
   Magellan should help scientists learn if any of the Venusian
volcanoes are still erupting and how crustal rock movements differs
from that on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Rock in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s crust is created and recycled in a conveyor-belt
manner. Hot crustal rock is born along midocean ridges _ undersea
mountain chains thousands of miles long. New crust is pushed away
from these ridges as more rock emerges. The crust eventually
collides with lighter continental rock, such as at the ``subduction
zone'' where Pacific seafloor rock sinks beneath <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>.
   Heat is released as sinking rock melts, creating volcanoes.
   Earth releases most of its heat at midocean ridges and
subduction zones. Saunders and <PERSON>Gerald Schaber</PERSON>, another <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION>
geologist, believe <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> loses its internal heat mostly through
``hot spot'' volcanoes.
   On <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, such volcanoes form where molten rock rises through
thin parts of the crust, such as in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. But there's evidence
that <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> has crustal movement similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and that the
volcanic ranges may be the Venusian equivalent of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s midocean
ridges.
   No one yet has found conclusive evidence of subduction zones on
Venus. In places, however, folded mountains and valleys are
squeezed up against <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' continent-like highlands, Aphrodite and
Ishtar, the latter of which has mountains taller than <ORGANIZATION>Everest</ORGANIZATION>.
   These regions look something like <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Himalayas</LOCATION>, mountains
formed when <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> smashed into <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. So crustal movements on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>
may be ``thin-skinned,'' forming folded mountains without large
chunks of crustal rock diving deep into the planet, <PERSON>Schaber</PERSON> said.
   If large plates of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' crustal rock are in motion, ``you can
bet there's Venusquakes,'' he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890505-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-05-89 1026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Shuttle-Venus 1stLd-Writethru a0440 05-05 0753</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shuttle-Venus, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0440,0768</SECOND>
<HEAD>Venus, Earth's Ugly Sister, May Hold Secrets To Planetary Evolution</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4-5th grafs, `Lennard Fisk...', with 2 grafs to add distance
from sun of the two planets. Lennard is cq. Picks up 6th graf, `It has...'.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Space Shuttle, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Venus may be ``a terrible place to
live,'' but scientists believe the planet's torrid temperatures,
incredible pressures and sulfuric acid rain may be a great place to
learn about the solar system's evolution.
   A robot craft called <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, the first American space probe in
11 years, is on its way to survey <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> for clues to the forces
that molded all the inner planets orbiting the sun.
   The <MONEY>$550 million</MONEY> craft will use a powerful radar imaging system
to map <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface, where scientists believe the geologic
history of the planet is imprinted. By studying that history,
scientists hope to learn what's contained in the ``the missing
chapters'' of solar system evolution.
   <PERSON>Lennard Fisk</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist, said <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is known as the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s sister planet because it is about the same size as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
and close to the same distance from the sun, in astronomical terms.
Venus, the second planet from the sun, is 67 million miles away,
while <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, the third planet, is 93 million miles out.
   Despite the similarities, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> ``has evolved into ... a
substantially different object,'' <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said.
   ``It has an atmosphere that is 90 times that of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. It
has a runaway greenhouse effect. It has a surface temperature of
900 degrees. And it rains sulfuric acid,'' <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said. ``It would be
a terrible place to live.''
   The <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, along with <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> and Mars, are known as
the ``inner planets'' because of their grouping nearer to the sun
than the ``outer'' planets, such as <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus.
   The family of inner planets are all thought to have accreted, or
formed, 4.5 billion years ago. In the beginning, it's believed,
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> were near-twins in size and character.
   But while the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> went on to become a lovely, gentle world
thriving with life, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> became a hellhole _ so hot that lead
melts on its surface.
   ``You've got to ask yourself why?'' <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said. ``You've got to
ask yourself if our own environment is that fragile? With only
small changes, could Earth evolve into a different place?''
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> may help answer some of those questions.
   The spacecraft is scheduled to slip into <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' orbit in <DATE>August
1990</DATE>, and spend the following 243 days mapping the planet's surface
with the most sophisticated radar ever sent to deep space.
   Radar signals are able to penetrate the dense cloud cover that
conceals Venus from telescopes on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Radar views from <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
will be enhanced by <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> computers to give clear pictures of
powerful geologic forces at work on Venus.
   All the data could help experts ponder a fundamental question:
Is the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, like <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, fated to one day become a barren,
lifeless world backing in superheat and bathed by acids?
   Scientists expect to find thousands of volcanoes rising from the
baked Venusian plains. Venus also has vast mountain ranges with
peaks towering higher than the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Mount Everest</LOCATION>.
   Most scientists believe the runaway greenhouse effect on <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>,
caused by its thick atmosphere of carbon dioxide, long ago caused
all water on the planet to boil away.
   The experts also will look for indications of continental drift,
the force that causes rock plates to inch about the globe over
millions of years.
   If there is evidence of volcanism and crustal drift on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, it
will prove that the planet retains enough internal heat to melt
rock. The internal heat machine is what creates the lava for
volcanoes and drives the movement of continents.
   Meteors crashing into the shallow surface crust of the planet
are expected to have left craters in every sector of Venus. <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON>
said these scars will be of particular interest to experts. The age
of a solid planet or moon, he said, can be calculated by the number
and distribution of craters.
   ``Knowing whether Earth is a fluke or just one of the natural
consequences of the evolution of a generic solar system'' will help
answer such questions, said <PERSON>Laurence Soderblom</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Flagstaff</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>.
   He said <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> also may help scientists deduce ``the
probability you're going to find Earth-like planets _ and life _
somewhere else'' in the universe.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900717-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-17-90 1359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-Magellan-Venus Adv24   07-17 1011</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Venus, Adv24,1036</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Tues AMs, July 24, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Spacecraft Will Use Radar To Peer Through the Clouds of Venus</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bedeviled, beleaguered <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is hoping
the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft's rendezvous with <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> next month will
provide our best look yet at <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s hellishly hot neighbor.
   If all goes according to plan, the <MONEY>$413 million</MONEY> unmanned device,
centerpiece of a <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY> mission, will orbit the
cloud-shrouded planet on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> after a 15-month journey from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. And <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> desperately wants everything to go according to
plan.
   ``This thing must succeed because of the Hubble Space Telescope
effect and the generally bad impression we've all been getting of
how <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has been conducting its affairs lately,'' said <PERSON>Steve
Saunders</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project's chief scientist.
   But those setbacks _ the crippling of the <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> Hubble
observatory due to mirror imperfections; the temporary grounding of
the space shuttles due to hydrogen fuel leaks _ have not dimmed the
agency's enthusiasm for <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We've dreamed about the sights we would see. Now it's about to
happen,'' said <PERSON>Phil Allin</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project official at the
Laboratory.
   Named for 16th century explorer <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, the craft's
radar will penetrate acid-laden Venusian clouds to make pictures
and maps 10 times more detailed than the best previous images.
   That will help geologists understand forces that sculpted Venus
to create flat lowlands, hilly plains and continent-like highlands
capped by peaks such as 35,400-foot <PERSON>Mount Maxwell</PERSON>, which is a mile
taller than <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Mount Everest</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> says <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s radar will reveal unprecedented details of
the planet's terrain, a landscape shaped by meteorite craters, tens
of thousands of volcanoes, and perhaps movements of gargantuan
blocks of the planet's crust _ a process that may be similar to
continental drift on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The 3.7-ton spacecraft also will look for ancient shorelines and
channels to learn if Venus once had oceans and rivers, before its
carbon dioxide atmosphere trapped the sun's heat in a runaway
``greenhouse effect.''
   Such global warming makes modern Venus a bone-dry, 900-degree
Fahrenheit oven with an atmospheric pressure 90 times greater than
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s mission ``is the capstone of the exploration of the
inner planets,'' said <PERSON>Jim Head</PERSON>, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> science
team and a geologist at <ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>
   ``We've seen the surfaces of the moon, Mars, the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION>, but <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> always has been obscured by the clouds and we've
never gotten a good global view of it.''
   The 21-foot-long <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was released from the cargo bay of
space shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>May 4, 1989</DATE>, then launched on its
roundabout, 806 million-mile voyage by an inertial upper-stage
rocket.
   At <TIME>9:31 a.m. PDT</TIME> on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will fire its solid-fueled
Star rocket to slow down and go into a elliptical, nearly polar
orbit that ranges from 171 miles to almost 5,000 miles above <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>.
   After a few weeks of tests, the spacecraft will bounce radar
waves off Venus to make pictures and topographic maps of <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT>
to <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of the surface. Meanwhile, the planet will rotate
once on its axis during a single Venusian day, which equals 243
Earth days.
   ``It's going to give us a map of Venus that in many ways is
better than anything we have for the whole Earth,'' where most of
the ocean floor hasn't been mapped in detail, <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
   If scientists are lucky, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> may tell them if Venusian
volcanoes are active, if movements of the planet's crust produce
``Venus quakes,'' and if those movements are more like Earth's
drifting continents or like the upward boiling of molten rock that
created <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>.
   Venus is the planet most like <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in terms of size, density
and mass, and also is <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s nearest neighbor, other than the
moon. Yet its clouds prevent the surface from being seen by
telescopes or optical cameras aboard orbiting spaceships.
   About 20 spacecraft have visited <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> since the early <DATE>1960s</DATE>,
some deploying landers that photographed small parts of the
surface. Pictures also were made by transmitting radar waves from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, and from <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Pioneer Venus orbiter in <DATE>1978</DATE> and the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION>'s Venera 15 and 16 orbiters in <DATE>1983</DATE>.
   But the best radar pictures until now could distinguish only
those landscape features wider than about 1\ miles. <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s pictures will be roughly 10 times better, capturing
features as small as 260 yards, about the length of 2{ football
fields.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will take 3 hours and 11 minutes to orbit Venus once.
During each orbit, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will spend 37 minutes as it moves from
north to south bouncing radar off a swath of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' surface about
10,000 miles long but only 16 miles wide. The information will be
stored on two tape recorders.
   During the rest of each orbit, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will radio the
information back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, where it will be received by
230-foot-wide, dish-shaped antennas at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Deep Space Network</ORGANIZATION>
stations in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   Computers at <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> will assemble the data
into pictures and topographic maps of each swath. The swaths _
nicknamed ``noodles'' because they are so long and narrow _ then
will be assembled into pictures covering larger areas of the planet.
   ``Mapping a whole new planet will return an enormous amount of
data that will keep geologists busy for a long time,'' <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON>
said. ``If you printed it in books, it would fill a shelf about 10
miles long. It's very humbling.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s main 243-day mapping mission will miss the south
polar regions. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is expected to approve more 243-day mapping
cycles. A total of three are needed to map the entire planet.
   Cost of the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> mission through the first 243-day mapping
cycle is <MONEY>$744 million</MONEY>, including the cost of launching the
spacecraft from the shuttle, said <PERSON>Bill Dimmer</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s
comptroller's office in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. The spacecraft and its
instruments account for <MONEY>$413 million</MONEY> of that total, he said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tues AMs, July 24</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890826-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-89 1253EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Voyager-Neptune 3rdLd-Writethru a0432 08-26 1042</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Voyager-Neptune, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0432,a0481,a0490,1066</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA: Photos Show Southern Lights On Neptune, Nitrogen In Triton
Atmosphere</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with evidence of broad dust bands
around planet. Picks up 6th grafs pvs, `Evidence for...'.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 2, discovered broad, flat bands
of dust orbiting <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and found evidence the planet has
``southern lights,'' <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   The probe also detected nitrogen in the atmosphere of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, the
moon whose pink snow and ice volcanoes were described by excited
scientists as unique in the solar system, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``There's dust bands _ they're broad,'' said <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> astronomer <PERSON>Rich
Terrile</PERSON>, describing the findings from latest photorgraphs. The bands
orbit <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s equator, as do its narrow rings that were discovered
by Voyager earlier.
   Although Voyager has passed its closest encounters with <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, it continued today to back recorded photographs taken
during the time of closest approach. And scientists and engineers
celebrated the spacecraft's successful flyby.
   ``My understanding was most of the engineers and science team had
one hell of a party <TIME>last night</TIME>,'' <PERSON>Mike Urban</PERSON>, a Voyager engineer,
said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   The one-ton space probe capped its historic 4.43-billion-mile,
12-year tour of four planets when it skimmed 3,048 miles over
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north pole <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, then dove past <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, the
planet's largest moon. It made its closest approach about 23,900
miles above the moon's surface at <TIME>2:10 a.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   During its approach to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, Voyager discovered six moons
besides <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> and Nereid, which were first observed from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. It
also discovered one complete ring of debris around the planet and a
partial ring, or ring arc, scientists believe will also prove to be
a complete ring.
   While only the narrow rings were visible as Voyager flew toward
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, the broad dust bands became visible when they were backlit
by sunlight after the space probe passed the planet, <PERSON>Terrile</PERSON> said.
That makes them look like <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s broad rings, but only when viewed
from behind <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   The same thing happened when Voyager passed Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>. That
planet had 10 narrow rings when seen by the approaching spacecraft,
which then found extensive bands of dust after passing Uranus.
<PERSON>Terrile</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s dust bands are not as extensive.
   Evidence for the glowing lights, known as an aurora, was found at
30 degrees south latitude on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> as <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION>'s ultraviolet light
sensor made a north-to-south scan of the planet, deputy project
scientist <PERSON>Ellis Miner</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   Because the scan didn't cover different longitudes, scientists
don't know the aurora's full extent, or whether it circles <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>
east to west, as do <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s auroras, <PERSON>Miner</PERSON> said.
   Miner said <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> also found nitrogen in <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere.
Nitrogen makes up <PERCENT>78 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere.
   On Earth, the northern and southern lights encircle the poles,
but can get pushed closer to the equator when the sun generates
magnetic storms. However, it would be very unusual for an aurora on
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> to get as close to the equator as 30 degrees latitude.
   Auroras are caused when electrically charged particles in the
solar wind spiral in toward a planet along magnetivc field lines. On
Earth they glow in visible light. Neptune's lights glow ultraviolet
because of hydrogen in its atmosphere.
   Engineers spent the night unloading Voyager's eight-track tape
recorder _ playing back pictures and scientific data recorded during
the <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> rendezvous _ and also loaded new instructions
telling the probe how to point its cameras and sensors, <ORGANIZATION>Urban</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Voyager today started sending back its most detailed images of
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, which is four-fifth's the size of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s moon. But pictures
returned <DATE>Friday</DATE> were more than enough to stun scientists.
   ``The range of geological forms is dazzling,'' astronomer-author
<PERSON>Carl Sagan</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE>. ``We are almost certainly in a regime of
volcanism involving ices, maybe exotic ices'' such as water ice
mixed with frozen nitrogen or methane (natural gas).
   The photographs show a cracked, frozen <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> scarred by
thousand-foot-high ridges, fault lines, bowl-shaped craters,
mysterious domes and dark spots ringed with white halos that so far
defy explanation.
   ``The images returned this morning revealed a world unlike any
we've ever seen,'' Voyager project scientist <PERSON>Edward Stone</PERSON> said
Propulsion Laboratory.
   Icy volcanic flows have been seen on Uranus' moon <PERSON>Ariel</PERSON> and some
other moons, but <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> is the first place scientists have actually
seen ice volcanoes, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said. Photographs showed at least three
inactive volcanoes.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> geologist <PERSON>Joseph Boyce</PERSON> said one of the ice volcanoes _ which
look like dry lakebeds filled with smooth material _ measures
several hundred miles across. Some were encircled with cliffs 1,000
to 2,000 feet high.
   The properties of exotic ices of water, methane and nitrogen
``are very different from ordinary ice,'' said <PERSON>Sagan</PERSON>, a member of
the Voyager imaging team. ``That may explain the exoticness of the
landforms.''
   Parts of the moon are frozen methane discolored by a bombardment
of radiation that produced chemical changes, <PERSON>Sagan</PERSON> said. ``We've got
pink snow. Think about how exotic that is.''
   Preliminary measurements of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s magnetic field suggest that
it does not have a north pole and a south pole like <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s magnetic
field, but rather multiple poles, researchers said.
   <PERSON>Robert Strom</PERSON> of the Voyager imaging team said the relative
scarcity of craters on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> tends to confirm speculation that
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> originated outside the solar system and became captured by
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s gravity, perhaps after colliding with one of its moons.
   Voyager also revealed that <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has an atmosphere and is
covered with a haze of what could be photochemical smog.
   On the moon's sunlit southern hemisphere, frozen methane or other
volatile material is boiling off the surface, causing haze, and
condensing on the moon's cooler regions, scientists said.
   Voyager 2 was launched in <DATE>1977</DATE> and explored <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Until <DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>, Voyager 2 will look
back at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>. Then it will head toward interstellar space.
   Weary <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientists, many of whom spent all night at the
laboratory analyzing data returning from the spacecraft, gushed over
the spectacular images being received.
   <PERSON>Laurence Soderblom</PERSON> of the Voyager imaging team said: ``Wow! What
a way to leave the solar system.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081989-0069 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 96661 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 19, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 25; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
632 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TANTALIZING TASTE OF THINGS TO COME; 
</P>
<P>
VOYAGER DISCOVERS MAGNETIC FIELD ON NEPTUNE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEE DYE, Times Science Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
For the first time, the spacecraft Voyager has detected intense radio signals 
coming from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, revealing that the planet has a magnetic field and 
indicating that next week's close encounter will be as intriguing as scientists 
had hoped. 
</P>
<P>
The discovery suggests that the spacecraft will find a wide range of 
interesting phenomena as it passes close to the distant planet <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, 
including the kind of auroral activity that produces the northern and southern 
lights on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The signals were first detected last <DATE>Monday</DATE>, but scientists at the Jet 
Propulsion Laboratory were not sure they were coming from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, according to 
<PERSON>James Warwick</PERSON>, principal investigator on the planetary radio astronomy 
experiment. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Not What Was Expected 
</P>
<P>
"Their character was different than what we were expecting," <PERSON>Warwick</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"The radio emissions are very intense," <PERSON>Warwick</PERSON> said, adding that they came in 
short, powerful bursts over a limited frequency range. Scientists had expected 
radio signals from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, but they were looking for something less intense 
and less limited in frequencies. 
</P>
<P>
Warwick and fellow scientists working on the project decided to announce the 
discovery <DATE>Friday</DATE> after they grew more confident of what they were seeing. 
</P>
<P>
The discovery means <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> has a strong magnetic field because radio waves are 
generated by charged particles that become trapped in the magnetic field and 
spiral into the planet's atmosphere. 
</P>
<P>
It is the same process that produces the northern lights on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Charged 
particles from space flow along the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s magnetic field lines and into the 
atmosphere at either the North or <LOCATION>South Pole</LOCATION>, producing the celestial fireworks 
over the higher latitudes. Now, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> is expected to see the same thing at 
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Within 3,000 Miles 
</P>
<P>
The Voyager spacecraft, which will make its fourth and final planetary flyby 
next week when it passes within about 3,000 miles of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s cloud tops, used 
a radio receiver and a giant pair of "rabbit ears" to detect the radio 
emissions -- just as it did at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus. Each 33-foot-long 
ear scans a series of frequencies and, since they work separately, the 
"polarization," or vibration, of the signals can be determined, thus 
distinguishing between radio signals generated by lightning and those created 
by a magnetic field. 
</P>
<P>
