<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880926-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-26-88 0139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BrailleGreetings     09-26 0732</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Braille Greetings,0750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greeting Card Designer Wants To Bridge Gap Between Blind And
Sighted</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LISA PERLMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KALAMAZOO, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With something as simple as a greeting
card, <PERSON>Truesillia Ruth Shank</PERSON> hopes to help bridge the gap between
the worlds of the sighted and the blind.
   ``It seems so unfair that a blind person should miss out on the
simple, little pleasures of life,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON>, sitting in the
living room of her modest home that doubles as the office for her
7-month-old card company, Sucurre Greetings. Sucurre is an Old
French word meaning ``to assist.''
   ``Can you imagine being 30, 40 or 50 years old and having to
wait for someone to read a stack of Christmas cards to you? Or not
being able to go into a store and pick out an anniversary card for
your wife or a birthday card for your child?'' she asked.
   The inspiration for Sucurre Greetings, which <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> owns
with her husband, came while she was working on an advertising
project with a blind businessman.
   ``He was doing things I couldn't do even with my sight,'' she
said. ``It just didn't seem right that he needed someone to go to a
store with him just to pick out a card.''
   Because of the limited market, Braille greeting cards have not
been manufactured by established card companies, said <PERSON>Adam Ash</PERSON>,
publisher of the Gift Reporter, a trade publication for the gift
industry. Some rehabilitation agencies have been known to sell some
Braille cards at <LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION>, and others translate greeting cards to
<ORGANIZATION>Braille</ORGANIZATION> when requested.
   ``At best, what you've been able to get up until now is a card
for a sighted person that's been Brailled. These cards are designed
specifically for a visually impaired person, but are still
appealing to a sighted person as well,'' said <PERSON>Paul Ponchillia</PERSON>, a
professor in the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Blind Rehabilitation at Western
Michigan University</ORGANIZATION>.
   Ponchillia, who is blind, helped the <PERSON>Shanks</PERSON> design the cards.
   The <PERSON>Shanks</PERSON>, also co-owners of a year-old advertising and
printing company, hope the pastel colors and simple but elegant
designs embossed on the front of the cards will appeal to a wide
audience. Underneath the design is a description of the object in
<LOCATION>Braille</LOCATION>. Inside, <ORGANIZATION>Braille</ORGANIZATION> appears under the message, typically a
short phrase with slightly raised letters.
   One lavender card has an embossed bird in flight on the cover.
Inside, the message is ``My heart's all a-flutter.''
   In addition to her basic line of 25 cards, <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> said she
also has a line of Christmas cards.
   ``We want the person to get the full impact of the card _ a card
that everyone can enjoy,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON>, a bubbly, 32-year-old
mother of three.
   She does the embossing by hand. Her husband, <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>, art
director at a television station, does much of the designing and
printing. Most of the Brailling is done by blind volunteers.
   Distribution of the cards is mostly limited to local card shops,
but <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> says she fills mail orders and is trying to line up
distributors for the cards in other parts of the country. The cards
sell for <MONEY>$2</MONEY> and <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> locally.
   If the cards catch on, the <PERSON>Shanks</PERSON> would like to provide jobs for
blind rehabilitation and training groups.
   And it looks as if the cards may be catching on. <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Field</ORGANIZATION>
has expressed interest in buying the line for their chain of
department stores, as well as an alphabet book <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> designed
for use by both sighted and blind children.
   ``Before getting involved in this, I never really knew a blind
person and I don't think I ever remember seeing a book that's shown
me what Braille's like,'' she said.
   ``We planned the book to get rid of the gap between sighted and
blind children. We want a sighted child to know what Braille feels
like and a blind child to be able to feel the letters that we're
seeing. Maybe that way we can get rid of some of the prejudice.''
   Prejudice is a subject <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> knows well.
   ``Because I'm black, some people might ask why I'm not doing
something for a black cause. Well, blindness knows no color. When
people stop being prejudiced against blind people or handicapped
people, maybe they'll stop being prejudiced about black people,''
she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880920-0262 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-20-88 1340EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-BrailleGreetings Adv26   09-20 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Braille Greetings, Adv 26,0762</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv 26</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday Sept. 26 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Greeting Card Designer Wants To Bridge Gap Between Blind And
Sighted</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA PERLMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KALAMAZOO, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With something as simple as a greeting
card, <PERSON>Truesillia Ruth Shank</PERSON> hopes to help bridge the gap between
the separate worlds of the sighted and the blind.
   ``It seems so unfair that a blind person should miss out on the
simple, little pleasures of life,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON>, sitting in the
living room of her modest home that doubles as the office for her
7-month-old card company, Sucurre Greetings. Sucurre means ``to
assist'' in French.
   ``Can you imagine being 30, 40 or 50 years old and having to
wait for someone to read a stack of Christmas cards to you? Or not
being able to go into a store and pick out an anniversary card for
your wife or a birthday card for your child?'' she asked.
   The inspiration for Sucurre Greetings, which <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> owns
with her husband, came while she was working on an advertising
project with a blind businessman.
   ``He was doing things I couldn't do even with my sight,'' she
said. ``It just didn't seem right that he needed someone to go to a
store with him just to pick out a card.''
   Because of the limited market, Braille greeting cards have not
been manufactured by established card companies, said <PERSON>Adam Ash</PERSON>,
publisher of the Gift Reporter, a trade publication for the gift
industry. Some rehabilitation agencies have been known to sell some
Braille cards at <LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION>, and others translate greeting cards to
<ORGANIZATION>Braille</ORGANIZATION> when requested.
   ``At best, what you've been able to get up until now is a card
for a sighted person that's been Brailled. These cards are designed
specifically for a visually impaired person, but are still
appealing to a sighted person as well,'' said <PERSON>Paul Ponchillia</PERSON>, a
professor in the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Blind Rehabilitation at Western
Michigan University</ORGANIZATION>. Ponchillia, who is blind, helped the <PERSON>Shanks</PERSON>
design the cards.
   The <PERSON>Shanks</PERSON>, also co-owners of a year-old advertising and
printing company, hope the pastel colors and simple but elegant
designs embossed on the front of the cards will appeal to a wide
audience. Underneath the design is a description of the object in
<LOCATION>Braille</LOCATION>. Inside, <ORGANIZATION>Braille</ORGANIZATION> appears under the message, typically a
short phrase with slightly raised letters.
   One lavender card has an embossed bird in flight on the cover.
Inside, the message is ``My heart's all a-flutter.''
   In addition to her basic line of 25 cards, <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> said she
also has a line of Christmas cards for the holidays.
   ``We want the person to get the full impact of the card _ a card
that everyone can enjoy,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON>, a bubbly, 32-year-old
mother of three.
   She does the embossing by hand. Her husband, <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>, art
director at an area television station, does much of the designing
and printing. Most of the Brailling is done by blind volunteers.
   Distribution of the cards is mostly limited to local card shops,
but <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> says she fills mail orders and is trying to line up
distributors for the cards in other parts of the country. The cards
sell for <MONEY>$2</MONEY> and <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> locally.
   If the cards catch on, the <PERSON>Shanks</PERSON> would like to provide jobs for
blind rehabilitation and training groups.
   And it looks like the cards may be catching on. <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Fields</ORGANIZATION>
has expressed interest in buying the line for their chain of
department stores, as well as an alphabet book <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> designed
for use by both sighted and blind children.
   ``Before getting involved in this, I never really knew a blind
person and I don't think I ever remember seeing a book that's shown
me what Braille's like,'' she said. ``We planned the book to get
rid of the gap between sighted and blind children. We want a
sighted child to know what Braille feels like and a blind child to
be able to feel the letters that we're seeing. Maybe that way we
can get rid of some of the prejudice.''
   Prejudice is a subject <PERSON>Mrs. Shank</PERSON> knows well.
   ``Because I'm black, some people might ask why I'm not doing
something for a black cause. Well, blindness knows no color. When
people stop being prejudiced against blind people or handicapped
people, maybe they'll stop being prejudiced about black people,''
she said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Monday Sept. 26</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870922-0119 </DOCNO>
<HL> Net at American
Greetings Dropped
82% in 2nd Period
---
By Gregory Stricharchuk
<DD> 09/22/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> AGREA
EARNINGS (ERN) </IN>
<DATELINE> CLEVELAND  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, hurt by competitive pricing as it seeks to snare market share from other greeting card makers, reported that profit in the <DATE>fiscal second quarter</DATE> plunged <PERCENT>82%</PERCENT>. 

Revenue rose to <MONEY>$250.2 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$226.8 million</MONEY>. 

   "Without question, our earnings decline was greater than we had expected," said <PERSON>Morry Weiss</PERSON>, president. 
He also said it is "doubtful" that profit in the year ending <DATE>Feb. 28</DATE> will exceed year-earlier net income of <MONEY>$63.4 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$1.97</MONEY> a share, as predicted by the company earlier this year. 
Fiscal <DATE>1987</DATE> revenue was <MONEY>$1.13 billion</MONEY>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> didn't make a specific earnings forecast. 

   For the past several quarters, American Greetings -- the country's largest publicly traded greeting card maker -- has been embroiled in an intense fight for market share with major competitors, such as Cincinnati-based <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Greetings Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mo.-based Hallmark Cards Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which is closely held. 
According to an analyst report from <ORGANIZATION>Neuberger &amp; Berman</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, Hallmark holds about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of the greeting card market, followed by American Greetings with <PERCENT>35%</PERCENT> and <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Greetings</ORGANIZATION> with <PERCENT>9%</PERCENT>. 

   An American Greetings spokesman noted that the company recently won a national drugstore account away from <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> but that overall the market share battle has resulted in a draw. 

   Nonetheless, <ORGANIZATION>E. Gray Glass III</ORGANIZATION>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Prudential-Bache Securities Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, predicts "the competitive battle among the big three will continue." 
Most retail outlets, he said, already sell greeting cards, and therefore the "only way to grow is to take away market share" from competitors. 
Ultimately, smaller card makers probably will be forced to close, he predicted. 

   American Greetings signaled it might favor a cease-fire in the pricing war, saying that relationships between retailers and suppliers are being hurt along with profits. 
"The futility of continued profitdraining competitive activity should now be apparent," <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said. 

   Ward <PERSON>A. Cavanaugh</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gibson Greetings</PERSON>' chief financial officer, said the company has been getting "mixed signals" on whether pressure on pricing is easing. 
"We hope it abates," he said. 
<PERSON>Mr. Cavanaugh</PERSON> said the company doesn't comment on accounts won or lost. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said profit in the <DATE>fiscal second quarter</DATE> was pinched by higher-than-expected returns of seasonal merchandise, weaker-than-anticipated sales of such non-greeting card product lines as gift wrap, and increased interest expense on higher borrowing levels. 

   American Greetings said sales of everyday greeting cards have improved, "perhaps signaling an upturn in the poor retail environment" that has been hurting profit. 
Beginning with this year's Christmas program, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> said it will reduce seasonal shipments, among other things. 

   The company said it will review options "for dealing with underperforming noncard business" and also said it has reduced costs by eliminating 127 positions last month, mostly at corporate headquarters. 
A company spokesman said further staff reductions aren't planned. 

   In national over-the-counter trading, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> stock closed yesterday at <MONEY>$24.875</MONEY> a share, down <MONEY>$1.50</MONEY>. 

   In the fiscal first half, the company earned <MONEY>$14.4 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>45 cents</MONEY> a share, down <PERCENT>33%</PERCENT> from the year-earlier <MONEY>$21.7 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>67 cents</MONEY> a share. 
Revenue rose about <PERCENT>9%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$513.5 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$470.6 million</MONEY>. 

   (Revised WSJ <DATE>Sept. 23, 1987</DATE>)
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910329-0134
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910329-0134.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   American Greetings Says Estimates
   Of 4th-Quarter Earnings Are on Target
   ----
   By Joan E. Rigdon
</HL>
<DATE>
03/29/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B3E
</SO>
<CO>
   AGREA
</CO>
<IN>
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
DOW JONES INTERVIEW (CEO)
</IN>
<LP>
   CLEVELAND -- American Greetings Corp. officials said they
are comfortable with analysts' estimates that net income for
its fourth quarter, ended Feb. 28, will be about $22 million,
share, for the year-earlier period.
   "I have no problem with that estimate," said Henry
Lowenthal, chief financial officer for American Greetings,
the No. 2 greeting card maker behind closely held Hallmark
Inc.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   That would bring earnings for the year to <MONEY>$94 million</MONEY>, or
<MONEY>$2.60</MONEY> a share, compared with net of <MONEY>$72.2 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$2.25</MONEY> a
share, last year. Revenue this year will be in excess of <MONEY>$1.4
billion</MONEY>, <PERSON>Mr. Lowenthal</PERSON> said in an interview, compared with
year-earlier revenue of <MONEY>$1.31 billion</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Lowenthal</PERSON> said he is confident that American Greetings
can maintain the <PERCENT>9%</PERCENT> revenue growth achieved in the <DATE>first nine
months of fiscal 1991</DATE>. He cited the company's strong position
in the growing mass retail market and its limited exposure to
the specialty market, which is shrinking.
   For <DATE>fiscal 1992</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Lowenthal</PERSON> said he is comfortable with
the lower end of analysts' earnings estimates, which range
from <MONEY>$2.90</MONEY> to <MONEY>$3</MONEY> a share.
Weiss</PERSON>, said this year's earnings were boosted by the
recession-typically a good climate for the industry because
consumers who can't afford gifts send cards instead.
   Demand was so strong that American Greetings has
successfully increased prices by an average of <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT> over
last year, <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said. "It's taking place because the
consumer is opting for it," he said, explaining: "During a
recession, higher-priced cards sell better because they often
do not accompany a gift."
   Surprisingly robust <ORGANIZATION>Valentine</ORGANIZATION>'s Day sales also helped
increase earnings, he said. "As good as Christmas was,
<ORGANIZATION>Valentine</ORGANIZATION>'s Day was outstanding." The war may have helped
out. "During a war people are much more sentimental," he
said.
   The company's "Treasured Original" <MONEY>$100</MONEY> Valentine's Day
cards -- framed oil paintings done by hand -- inspired
consumers to buy more <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> and <MONEY>$5</MONEY> cards, <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said. All
2,000 of the Treasured Originals were sold to retailers, who
can't return them. However, any unsold cards can still be
marketed because the cards' verse is also appropriate for
Mother's Day and love in general, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> declined to say how much of the increased
earnings were due to price increases vs. sales volume. But he
said sales "outperformed" the company's expectations.
   The <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> war brought other good news for <ORGANIZATION>American
Greetings</ORGANIZATION>. In an attempt to promote its brand name, the
company produced two new lines: "America Misses You" cards to
be sent to the <ORGANIZATION>Gulf</ORGANIZATION> and "Greetings from the Gulf" to be sent
home. Unlike most of the company's new card lines, which
require production time of 12 to 15 months, the war cards
were produced in three weeks, <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said.
   In light of that accomplishment, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> will
try to cut its time to market so it can respond quickly to
trends. "We're looking for a <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> reduction," by 12 to 18
months from now, <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said the company will continue to expand its
best-selling "anytime" greeting cards, such as its Couples
lines, targeted at people in love relationships. This year,
two more "anytime" card lines will be introduced, this time
targeted around family relationships and friendships, <PERSON>Mr.
Weiss</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>National Wildlife Cards</ORGANIZATION> -- nature theme cards with
traditional greetings printed on recycled paper -- were
shipped to retailers two weeks ago. It's too early to tell
how well they're selling, <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> is pleased with its 1.5 million share,
or <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> stake in Artistic Greetings, which markets cards by
catalog, <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said. American Greetings bought the stake
at <MONEY>$4.30</MONEY> a share in <DATE>April 1990</DATE>. Since then the value of the
shares has shot up. Revenue for the equity stake will total
about <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> for fiscal <DATE>1991</DATE> and will be reflected in
year-end earnings, <PERSON>Mr. Lowenthal</PERSON> said.
   American Greetings has the option to buy all of Artistic
through <DATE>March 1992</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said he expects to decide in
the next "12 to 18 months," explaining that he can extend the
<DATE>March</DATE> deadline.
   American Greetings' biggest challenge will be to create
greeting card shops within mass retailer stores, where
consumers shop "as a matter of choice, not just convenience,"
<PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880407-0077 </DOCNO>
<HL> American Greetings Profit Plunged 95% In Fiscal 4th Period Due to Competition </HL>
<AUTHOR> Ralph E. Winter (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> AGREA </CO>
<IN> ERN </IN>
<DATELINE> CLEVELAND  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION> reported that profit for the <DATE>fourth quarter ended Feb. 29</DATE> dropped <PERCENT>95%</PERCENT> to a scant <MONEY>$748,000</MONEY>, or <MONEY>two cents</MONEY> a share, mainly because of extremely tough competition in the greeting card industry. 

   <PERSON>Morry Weiss</PERSON>, president and chief executive officer, said at a news conference that there are indications in the past few months that the three major greeting card makers are becoming a little less aggressive in trying to win retailers away from one another, but that it is too early to forecast a significant profit upturn. 
<ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>; American Greetings; and <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, together produce about <PERCENT>85%</PERCENT> of the greeting cards sold in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said. 

   In <DATE>year-earlier quarter</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> earned <MONEY>$15.4 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>48 cents</MONEY> a share. 
Sales for the latest quarter rose <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$314.5 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$291.2 million</MONEY> a year earlier, mainly because sales of newly consolidated subsidiaries were included in the <DATE>1988</DATE> period. 

Sales rose <PERCENT>6.5%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$1.20 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$1.13 billion</MONEY>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said he is "cautiously optimistic" about the profit outlook. 
However, he said he was "more optimistic than the record would suggest I should have been" <DATE>a year ago</DATE>, and declined to make an earnings forecast. 
A year ago, officials said profit would rise in <DATE>fiscal 1988</DATE>. 

   For both the quarter and the year, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> had higher than normal returns of seasonal merchandise and a decline in profit from its toy division and foreign subsidiaries, <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said. 
He said the company is considering dropping out of toy production and distribution, but hasn't put its <ORGANIZATION>AmToy Inc.</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary on the block. 
Even if the company halted toy production, it would continue to license other companies to produce American Greetings-designed toys, he said. 

   Analysts said they weren't surprised by the poor showing in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE> because management signaled in <DATE>January</DATE> that competition was eating away gross profit margins. 
Several analysts said they expect a profit increase in <DATE>fiscal 1989</DATE>, but they don't expect net to recover to the levels of the 1984-87 period when net ranged from <MONEY>$1.91</MONEY> a share to <MONEY>$2.35</MONEY> a share. 

   "We're still going to see the major players battle to maintain market share, and gross margins will continue at about the current depressed levels," said <PERSON>Charles E. Cerankosky</PERSON>, who follows <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings for Prescott, Ball &amp; Turben</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>. 
Major retailers have become very good at playing competing manufacturers against one another to obtain free display fixtures, cooperative advertising, extended payment terms and other concessions, as well as price discounts, he said. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Cerankosky</PERSON> estimates that the company will earn <MONEY>$1.20</MONEY> a share in the current year. 
Some other analysts said they estimate current year net at <MONEY>$1.50</MONEY> a share. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> defended its market share last year, "but at a very dear price." 
He said the company will continue to "maintain our market share as a critical element of our strategy." 
The company expects to use its position in retail stores to sell other items besides greeting cards, he said. 
Already the company is selling picture frames, he said. 

   American Greetings reduced shipments of seasonal cards in recent months, which it expects will also cut the number of cards returned by retailers, <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said. 
However, for the latest quarter and year, sales were reduced both by the lower shipments and the higher returns, which are subtracted to produce a net sales figure. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871224-0051 </DOCNO>
<HL> Card Makers' Tough Tactics Belie
Sweet Verse as Competition Rises
---
By Gregory Stricharchuk
<DD> 12/24/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> AGREA GIBG
RETAILING (RET) </IN>
<TEXT>
   Their verses may be perky and sweet, but behind the lines, the nation's three major greeting-card makers are waging a nasty, and costly, battle. 

   "It's like a military situation," says <PERSON>Benjamin J. Sottile</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Naval Academy</ORGANIZATION> graduate who has been on the attack since joining <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Greetings Inc.</ORGANIZATION> as president a year ago. 
"Cards are a mature industry, and the only way you can grow is at the expense of competitors." 

   Although Americans buy seven billion cards annually -- nearly 30 apiece -- growth in the <MONEY>$4 billion-a-year</MONEY> industry has stagnated. 
And the industry -- after introducing cards for everything from grandparents' day to <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON>'s birthday in recent years -- has practically exhausted occasions to celebrate. 

   So far, the three largest card makers have battled to a stalemate. 
<LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mo.-based Hallmark Cards Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, with <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of the market, is still the industry leader. 
<ORGANIZATION>American Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> is No. 2, with a <PERCENT>35%</PERCENT> market share, and Cincinnati-based <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> is third with <PERCENT>11%</PERCENT>. 
About 300 small card companies account for the rest. 

   As the Big Three try to carve into each other's market share, their tactics have gotten brutal and their profit margins have plunged. 
They raid each other's major retail accounts and forage into each other's product niches. 
Smaller card companies accuse the giants of pillaging their best ideas. 

   To woo major accounts, the card makers are forking over more and more of their profits to retailers -- and accounts shuffle back and forth, often to the highest bidder. 
"We pay the chains to keep our cards there," says <PERSON>Morty Wyman</PERSON>, vice chairman of the directors' executive committee at <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Although American Greetings and other card makers refuse to say how much they pay to win the loyalty of retailers, a lawsuit filed by <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> against a national drugstore chain provides some insight into the rivalry. 
In the suit, filed in <DATE>August</DATE> in <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>'s county court, <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> claims <ORGANIZATION>Revco D.S. Inc.</ORGANIZATION> repudiated its agreement with the card maker after <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> made special concessions to the retailer. 
The suit says <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> made the concessions this year to win back half of the 2,000-store account it had lost to <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON>. 
American Greetings wasn't accused of any wrongdoing. 

   <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> says it spent more than <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> installing new racks in about 500 <ORGANIZATION>Revco</ORGANIZATION> drugstores, with the understanding that it would supply 1,000 Revco stores for five years. 
<PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> contends that <ORGANIZATION>Revco</ORGANIZATION>, after asking <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> to make a proposal to supply all the chain's stores, suddenly picked American Greetings as its sole supplier. 
In the suit, <ORGANIZATION>Gibson</ORGANIZATION> is seeking <MONEY>$27.5 million</MONEY> for, among other things, damages and reimbursement for the money it spent on the racks. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Revco</ORGANIZATION> denies the allegations. 
"It is not uncommon, as a result of normal competitive processes, to find these or other greeting-card manufacturers displacing one another in various retail outlets throughout the nation," the company says. 

   The card makers also are waging an expensive battle for the accounts of specialty-card stores and gift shops -- one of the market's few bright spots. 
Such stores, previously Hallmark's bastion, continue to grow in number, while card makers believe they have saturated the mass-merchandiser market. 

   Such stores account for at least a third of all card sales, says <PERSON>Morry Weiss</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> chief executive. 
Although <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> has mainly supplied drugstores, discount stores and other chain outlets, it now is making a big push to expand into specialty stores. 
"I can't walk away from that market," he adds. 

   The card makers' biggest battlefield, however, is in the market for so-called alternative cards -- known for their satirical or inspirational messages and usually not pegged to a particular holiday or event. 
Alternative cards -- now the industry's hottest sellers and still growing -- represent between <PERCENT>17%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>22%</PERCENT> of all cards sold. 

   The Big Three are making their gains in the alternative card market largely at the expense of tiny competitors, who were successful early on in offering such lines. 
The major card companies didn't get into the market until last year. 

   The alternative cards appeal largely to baby boomers; the companies say many young adults enjoy sending humorous cards to friends for no particular occasion or holiday, but just to stay in touch. 
Many of the alternative lines also are geared toward women, who buy <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of all cards. 
<PERSON>Gibson</PERSON>, for example, offers a line called Women's Writes. 

   Of the major companies, Hallmark generated the most controversy with its alternative-card entry. 
In the largest rollout of new cards in the company's history, it brought out the "Shoebox" line, aimed mainly at women, and "Personal Touch," a line of sentimental cards. 

   Soon after the unveiling, suits were filed accusing the industry leader of buying up competitors' cards and then restocking shelves with Hallmark cards that closely resembled those that were pulled. 

   In a suit seeking damages of <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Blue Mountain Arts Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION>, Colo.-based company known for its watercolor designs and sentimental verse, accused Hallmark of copying its cards, among other things. 
In <DATE>November 1986</DATE> in federal court in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Judge Jim R. Carrigan</PERSON> issued a preliminary injunction against Hallmark, halting distribution of 83 cards that the court determined had been copied from <LOCATION>Blue Mountain</LOCATION>. 

   Hallmark denies the allegations and has appealed the preliminary injunction. 
A trial date hasn't been set for the suit. 

   In <DATE>July</DATE>, in amending the suit, <ORGANIZATION>Blue Mountain</ORGANIZATION> claimed Hallmark "pressured" greeting-card dealers to pull <ORGANIZATION>Blue Mountain</ORGANIZATION> cards from their shelves "as a condition of being allowed to continue a beneficial business relationship with Hallmark." 
Blue Mountain also alleged that Hallmark leases shopping-center stores only to dealers who pledge they won't sell Blue Mountain cards, and that Hallmark bought up and destroyed the smaller company's cards at various stores. 

   Hallmark denies the allegations in the amended suit as well, a company spokeswoman says. 
She says the company does have a program of giving dealers credit for "obsolete" cards made by Hallmark or any other company, but that dealers aren't obligated to accept the credit. 
She says "a large percentage" of Hallmark trade-name stores and independent dealers carry competing brands, including Blue Mountain at some stores. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910114-0071
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910114-0071.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   How Do I Love Thee? Just Let Me
   Count the Bucks Spent for a Card
   ----
   By Joan E. Rigdon
</HL>
<DATE>
01/14/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<CO>
   AGREA
</CO>
<IN>
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<LP>
   Diamonds are keen. Roses are, too. But $100 valentines are
the best way to woo.
   So says American Greetings Corp.'s upscale Carlton Cards
unit. Defying recessionary reports of penny-pinching, the
greeting-card company is offering Treasured Originals --
framed, 17-inch by 21-inch oil paintings of pink and red
roses, which open to one of four assorted love verses fresh
from the company's data base of romantic rhymes.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "What better way to say `I love you' than with the world's
most exclusive greeting card?" Carlton bubbles in a news
release.
   Having planned the new line before the invasion of <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION>,
the Cleveland-based company says the cards can sell well
despite economic turbulence prompted by war fears.
   "Love doesn't seem to be daunted by those things," says
<PERSON>Mary Ann Corrigan-Davis</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Carlton</ORGANIZATION> vice president.
   Research shows that shoppers are willing to dish out more
for <ORGANIZATION>Valentine</ORGANIZATION>'s Day cards than for cards on other occasions,
she says. American Greetings' ordinary valentines cost <MONEY>$1.75</MONEY>
to <MONEY>$2</MONEY>, while greeting cards for other occasions average
<MONEY>$1.40</MONEY>.
   As for the leap from <MONEY>$2</MONEY> to triple digits, <PERSON>Ms.
Corrigan-Davis</PERSON> says, "It's not unusual to spend over <MONEY>$100</MONEY> on
dinner and flowers. And a <ORGANIZATION>Treasured Original</ORGANIZATION> is a lasting
gift."
   The company ordered 4,000 cards from its painters in the
<LOCATION>Orient</LOCATION> and says it's already shipped some to distributors.
The profit margins on Treasured Originals are considerably
lower than on high-volume paper cards, <PERSON>Ms. Corrigan-Davis</PERSON>
says, but <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> will recoup its investment.
   Some analysts say the costly cards may help establish
American Greetings as a trend setter. Others, however, are
dubious. "It's an extreme extravagance," says <PERSON>Sheldon Grodsky</PERSON>
of <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Jerome &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Florham Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION> "I thought
that went out with the '80s." He predicts American Greetings,
the No. 2 card maker behind <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Co.</ORGANIZATION>, "won't tap the mass
market with this one."
   What do women think? <PERSON>Sally L. Schaadt</PERSON>, an analyst at
<ORGANIZATION>Fourteen Research Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, an equity research firm in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,
says she doesn't care what she gets on <DATE>Valentine's Day</DATE>, "as
long as I get something." But she says she'd probably rather
be wined and dined by candlelight than handed a <ORGANIZATION>Treasured
Original</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121790-0107 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 323671 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 17, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 4; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
533 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HOLIDAY CARDS PUT EXTRA EMPHASIS ON PEACE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PATRICIA ZENGERLE, REUTERS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
PITTSBURGH 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
With thousands of soldiers encamped in the deserts of the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION>, peace on 
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> may be too much to wish for this holiday season, but there's good reason 
to expect peace in your mailbox. 
</P>
<P>
Greeting card industry officials and analysts say holiday cards bearing peace 
wishes will sell briskly this holiday season, reflecting consumer concerns 
about the state of the world and events in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> in particular. 
</P>
<P>
And although the sputtering economy is expected to bring a not-so-merry 
Christmas for the nation's big retailers, sales of greeting cards should buck 
that trend, industry analysts said. 
</P>
<P>
"When times are tough, people cut back on buying expensive gifts and buy more 
expensive cards," said analyst <PERSON>Kendrick Noble</PERSON> at <ORGANIZATION>Paine Webber Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Greeting Card Assn.</ORGANIZATION>, an industry group based in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, estimates that 
2.3 billion cards will be purchased this holiday season, up from 2.2 billion in 
<DATE>1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
But for the full year, consumers will spend <MONEY>$4.6 billion</MONEY> on 7.3 billion 
greeting cards, up nearly <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> from <MONEY>$4.2 billion</MONEY> last year, the association 
projects. 
</P>
<P>
"It's going to be a pretty tough Christmas," said <PERSON>Kevin Moore</PERSON> at <ORGANIZATION>Ohio Co.</ORGANIZATION> "But 
on the other hand, greeting cards are a lower-priced kind of purchase and 
generally more of an impulse purchase." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Nancy Riviere</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for the trade group, said card sales overall have 
grown steadily for years. They totaled <MONEY>$2.1 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1980</DATE>, she noted. 
</P>
<P>
Christmas is by far the leading card-sending holiday, said Riviere. Valentine's 
Day and Easter are second and third, respectively, followed by Mother's Day. 
</P>
<P>
In addition to peace theme cards, the environment is another theme likely to 
dominate this season and throughout the <DATE>1990s</DATE>, the experts said. 
</P>
<P>
"There is a consumer preference for peace-themed items, such as doves, a 
reflection of people's concern over the world situation," said <PERSON>Steve Doyle</PERSON> of 
<ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, the nation's largest greeting card 
producer. 
</P>
<P>
Riviere said many manufacturers are jumping on the environmental bandwagon by 
planning cards made of recycled paper or linking their products to 
environmentally friendly organizations. 
</P>
<P>
"Retailers are being pushed by consumers to have a green ideology in all their 
products," said <PERSON>Jody Roberts</PERSON>, marketing coordinator at Cleveland-based <ORGANIZATION>American 
Greetings Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the No. 2 manufacturer. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Roberts</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> plans a complete environmental line of boxed 
cards for <DATE>Christmas, 1991</DATE>, and will introduce a line linked to the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Wildlife Federation</ORGANIZATION> before <DATE>Father's Day next June</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Other growing categories in the industry are cards that reflect changing social 
realities -- "Merry Christmas, Stepfather" is one example -- and cards, 
particularly those with humorous messages, designed to appeal to younger 
buyers. 
</P>
<P>
The average family sends a total of 44 Christmas cards, according to the group, 
37 of them from boxed sets and seven that are purchased individually. 
</P>
<P>
Nearly 1,000 companies make greeting cards in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. But the three 
largest generate <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the sales, the association estimates. <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Greetings 
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, is third behind Hallmark and American Greetings. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
HOLIDAYS; GREETING CARDS; PEACE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900918-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-18-90 1651EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-AmongFriends Adv24   09-18 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Among Friends, Adv 24,0671</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Monday, Sept. 24, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Alternative Card Company Sets Lofty Goals</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JERRY NACHTIGAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMDENTON, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the fiercely competitive greeting card
industry, <ORGANIZATION>Among Friends</ORGANIZATION> is a grain of sand on a beach dominated by
giants like <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Gibson
Greetings</PERSON>.
   But the alternative card company, which was formed two years ago
by three women in this Lake of the Ozarks community in <LOCATION>central
Missouri</LOCATION>, has set some lofty goals.
   ``People say, `Oh, is your goal to have Hallmark buy you out?' I
say, `no, our goal is to buy Hallmark,' '' <PERSON>Claudia Parrish</PERSON>, one of
the company's founders, said with a poker face.
   She quickly breaks into a smile and laughs at the thought of the
tiny, anonymous firm gobbling up Hallmark, the industry leader,
which reportedly notched <MONEY>$1.25 billion</MONEY> in greeting card sales last
year.
   But <PERSON>Parrish</PERSON> and her partners, <PERSON>Roxie Kelly</PERSON> and <PERSON>Shelly
Reeves-Smith</PERSON>, are serious about carving their own niche in a market
ruled by huge corporations.
   In just a couple of years, <ORGANIZATION>Among Friends</ORGANIZATION> has expanded from
selling a few cards in local shops to marketing a line of 36
all-occasion cards, gift tags, decorative bags and a
card-organizing notebook in 48 states, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. The
company is working to expand that line.
   Parrish, the company's business manager, says <ORGANIZATION>Among Friends</ORGANIZATION>
tripled its sales in the past year and now has about 1,300
accounts. She refused to disclose any figures.
   ``We don't even want them to know we exist,'' added
Reeves-Smith.
   <PERSON>Rudolf Hokanson</PERSON>, who tracks the greeting card industry for <ORGANIZATION>Blunt
Ellis &amp; Loewy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>, said the company has one advantage:
alternative cards are the fastest growing segment of the industry.
   ``It's impossible to say whether (Among Friends) will survive,''
<PERSON>Hokanson</PERSON> said. ``It's a competitive field, and there are a lot of
quality players. Like with any business, if they have a good
management team and marketing people . . . I think they've got a
chance.''
   The women say they are somewhat surprised at the company's
limited success considering the mistakes they made in the early
going.
   ``We knew nothing about the greeting card industry,'' <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>
recalled. ``We made some of the worst mistakes you can imagine. But
the cards sold anyway. It was amazing how much people liked them.''
   The women say the company name was a natural because of their
long friendships.
   <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>, 35, a former physical education teacher, used to own a
popular restaurant and a combination gourmet bakery-gift shop at
the lake. She handles marketing duties and maintains contact with
about 35 sales representatives.
   <PERSON>Parrish</PERSON>, 49, was a hostess at the restaurant and a business
partner in a cookbook <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> wrote and sold. She keeps a close eye
on the finances.
   The artist, Reeves-Smith, 24, was a student of <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>'s and later
worked in her restaurant and bakery. A longtime friend of the
<PERSON>Parrish</PERSON> family, Reeves-Smith also designed the cover of her
friends' cookbook.
   Kelly and <PERSON>Parrish</PERSON> credit Reeves-Smith, a <DATE>1988</DATE> art graduate, for
much of Among Friends' success.
   Reeves-Smith works with colored pencils and ink to design
``subjects that conjure up soothing, pleasant feelings, like a hat
box, an old clock, a <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> house - that's the style I feel
most comfortable with.''
   The result is detailed, intimate cards featuring a soft,
water-color appearance.
   The message inside is often inspirational, featuring classic
poems or a verse the women came up with themselves. Some contain a
favorite recipe, like <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>'s blueberry-peach-cinnamon muffins.
   The women say that even though they work so closely together
they've managed to stay good friends.
   ``We don't always agree, but we respect each other for our
individual talents and opinions,'' <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> said. ``We were friends
before we were partners and we want it to stay that way.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Monday Sept. 24</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   In the fiercely competitive greeting card
industry, <ORGANIZATION>Among Friends</ORGANIZATION> is a grain of sand on a beach dominated by
giants like <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Gibson
Greetings</PERSON>.
   But the alternative card company, which was formed two years ago
by three women in this Lake of the Ozarks community in <LOCATION>central
Missouri</LOCATION>, has set some lofty goals.
   ``People say, `Oh, is your goal to have Hallmark buy you out?' I
say, `no, our goal is to buy Hallmark,' '' <PERSON>Claudia Parrish</PERSON>, one of
the company's founders, said with a poker face.
   She quickly breaks into a smile and laughs at the thought of the
tiny, anonymous firm gobbling up Hallmark, the industry leader,
which reportedly notched <MONEY>$1.25 billion</MONEY> in greeting card sales last
year.
   But <PERSON>Parrish</PERSON> and her partners, <PERSON>Roxie Kelly</PERSON> and <PERSON>Shelly
Reeves-Smith</PERSON>, are serious about carving their own niche in a market
ruled by huge corporations.
   In just a couple of years, <ORGANIZATION>Among Friends</ORGANIZATION> has expanded from
selling a few cards in local shops to marketing a line of 36
all-occasion cards, gift tags, decorative bags and a
card-organizing notebook in 48 states, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. The
company is working to expand that line.
   Parrish, the company's business manager, says <ORGANIZATION>Among Friends</ORGANIZATION>
tripled its sales in the past year and now has about 1,300
accounts. She refused to disclose any figures.
   ``We don't even want them to know we exist,'' added
Reeves-Smith.
   <PERSON>Rudolf Hokanson</PERSON>, who tracks the greeting card industry for <ORGANIZATION>Blunt
Ellis &amp; Loewy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>, said the company has one advantage:
alternative cards are the fastest growing segment of the industry.
   ``It's impossible to say whether (Among Friends) will survive,''
<PERSON>Hokanson</PERSON> said. ``It's a competitive field, and there are a lot of
quality players. Like with any business, if they have a good
management team and marketing people . . . I think they've got a
chance.''
   The women say they are somewhat surprised at the company's
limited success considering the mistakes they made in the early
going.
   ``We knew nothing about the greeting card industry,'' <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>
recalled. ``We made some of the worst mistakes you can imagine. But
the cards sold anyway. It was amazing how much people liked them.''
   The women say the company name was a natural because of their
long friendships.
   <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>, 35, a former physical education teacher, used to own a
popular restaurant and a combination gourmet bakery-gift shop at
the lake. She handles marketing duties and maintains contact with
about 35 sales representatives.
   <PERSON>Parrish</PERSON>, 49, was a hostess at the restaurant and a business
partner in a cookbook <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> wrote and sold. She keeps a close eye
on the finances.
   The artist, Reeves-Smith, 24, was a student of <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>'s and later
worked in her restaurant and bakery. A longtime friend of the
<PERSON>Parrish</PERSON> family, Reeves-Smith also designed the cover of her
friends' cookbook.
   Kelly and <PERSON>Parrish</PERSON> credit Reeves-Smith, a <DATE>1988</DATE> art graduate, for
much of Among Friends' success.
   Reeves-Smith works with colored pencils and ink to design
``subjects that conjure up soothing, pleasant feelings, like a hat
box, an old clock, a <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> house - that's the style I feel
most comfortable with.''
   The result is detailed, intimate cards featuring a soft,
water-color appearance.
   The message inside is often inspirational, featuring classic
poems or a verse the women came up with themselves. Some contain a
favorite recipe, like <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>'s blueberry-peach-cinnamon muffins.
   The women say that even though they work so closely together
they've managed to stay good friends.
   ``We don't always agree, but we respect each other for our
individual talents and opinions,'' <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> said. ``We were friends
before we were partners and we want it to stay that way.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122189-0150 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 151782 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 21, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 2; Column 3; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
351 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IT'S ALREADY 1992 FOR CARD COMPANIES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ALISA SAMUELS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As the <LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION> season -- the greeting card industry's biggest moneymaker -- 
approaches its climax, major retail card makers are busily planning for 
<DATE>Valentine's Day, 1991</DATE>, and <DATE>Christmas, 1992</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"We normally work about 18 months to two years in advance of the holiday 
lines," said <PERSON>Barbara Miller</PERSON>, products spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Kansas 
City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo</LOCATION>. She said planners are researching and planning <DATE>1991 Valentine's Day</DATE> 
cards, which are second to Christmas cards in total sales and volume. 
</P>
<P>
Each year, 900 million sweetheart cards and 2.2 billion Christmas cards are 
exchanged in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Nancy Riviere</PERSON>, director of communications 
for the <ORGANIZATION>Greeting Card Assn.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. She added that the card industry 
makes <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY> in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales annually. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>American Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, has already begun creative 
development for <DATE>Christmas, 1992</DATE>, said <PERSON>John A. Hernandis</PERSON>, director of corporate 
communications. 
</P>
<P>
"The activity doesn't parallel the event," <PERSON>Hernandis</PERSON> said. "Our work for this 
<DATE>Christmas</DATE> season ended many, many months ago." 
</P>
<P>
It takes months for the card makers to design, produce, write and finally 
distribute the cards. After assignments are given to artists, writers and 
editors, their proposals are checked by a review committee. Finally, after 
being printed, boxed and packaged, the cards are shipped to warehouses and 
retailers. 
</P>
<P>
Hallmark, the nation's largest card maker with about <PERCENT>44%</PERCENT> of the market, will 
design about 2,000 different <ORGANIZATION>Valentine</ORGANIZATION>'s Day cards for <DATE>1991</DATE>, <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Doug Westen</PERSON>, manager of the Card Factory at the <ORGANIZATION>Beverly Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Beverly 
Hills</LOCATION>, said his store will not have to put away any unsold Christmas items to 
make room for the next major holiday, because this year's Christmas sales have 
been "wonderful. We have nothing left." 
</P>
<P>
Westen plans to display <ORGANIZATION>Valentine</ORGANIZATION>'s Day cards beginning in <DATE>mid-January</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Easter and Mother's Day are the third- and fourth-largest card-selling 
holidays, with <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales of 185 million and 145 million cards, respectively, 
<PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Holiday cards usually remain available for sale for four to six weeks. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Christmas Cards 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CHRISTMAS; GREETING CARDS; HALLMARK CARDS; HOLIDAYS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890615-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-15-89 1318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-GreetingCardGlut Adv18   06-15 0952</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Greeting Card Glut, Adv 18,0983</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv18</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, June 18</HEAD>
<HEAD>No One Need Fumble For Words</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also on financial wire</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserGraphic planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARYBETH NIBLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Father's Day card browsers faced a seemingly
endless choice of saccharin-sweet love messages and bad-taste
zingers this year, tailored to senders ranging from first-born
children to adoptees.
   The card glut reflects an effort by makers to capitalize on the
time-strapped consumer's quest for convenience. They're turning out
more types of cards and cramming them into store space approaching
saturation.
   If you looked past the Father's Day racks, the categories go far
beyond run-of-the-mill anniversaries, birthdays, baptisms and bar
mitvahs.
   The holiday lineup has lengthened into a string spanning more
days of the calendar. Christmas, <ORGANIZATION>Valentine's Day</ORGANIZATION>, Mother's Day,
<LOCATION>Easter</LOCATION>, Father's Day, <PERSON>Halloween</PERSON> and Thanksgiving are the leaders.
But <ORGANIZATION>Sweetest Day</ORGANIZATION>, Mothers-in-law Day and Boss's Day are getting
space too.
   No occasion is too obscure or private. Safe-sex friendship cards
warn about the dangers of AIDS. Conventional get-well messages now
include versions for the terminally ill.
   One company recently unveiled a faxable greeting card, betting
that use of facsimile machines will get trendier than it already is.
   In their zeal to satisfy every taste and circumstance, card
companies seem determined to make sure no one ever fumbles for words.
   Card sending may be a widely held habit partly because many
people simply don't know how to express their thoughts in writing,
officials of the <MONEY>$3 billion-a-year</MONEY> card industry say.
   Nonetheless, they're not taking any chances on missing a market
of literate card senders. Many supply artwork-adorned versions with
empty space for customers who have the time and inclination to write
their own.
   Most buyers probably jot down a thought or two anyway,
supplementing the generic sentiments, but even so some may feel
guilty as they span the racks for something to send.
   Commentator <PERSON>Andy Rooney</PERSON> has put his feelings about greeting cards
this way: ``Why are we buying someone else's words to convey
supposedly intimate sentiments? Doesn't anyone just sit down with a
blank piece of paper anymore and write a simple note to someone on a
special occasion?''
   More often than not, the answer is no.
   Industry analyst <ORGANIZATION>E. Gray Glass III of Prudential-Bache Securities
Inc.</ORGANIZATION> says consumers seem to be clamoring for alternative cards that
are becoming more plentiful.
   These non-occasion cards, appropriate any day, are part of the
industry push to develop new card-sending opportunities.
   ``That's going to have the effect of expanding the per capita
sending of cards,'' says Glass. ``Cards are also impulse purchases
so the idea is that you should have as many types of cards available
on the market as possible.''
   <PERSON>Marianne McDermott</PERSON>, executive vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>Greeting Card
Association</ORGANIZATION>, says consumers have become more demanding in choosing
cards and makers have reacted nimbly to social change, creating a
card-choice explosion.
   ``People aren't happy to pick up just any card, it has to say
just the right thing,'' <PERSON>McDermott</PERSON> says.
   The challenge is that cards are proliferating but the growth in
retail distributors has slowed to a crawl.
   Space-wise, one of the few remaining card-selling opportunities
is in mass merchandizing outlets and supermarkets.
   ``Food stores are the last to fill up,'' says <PERSON>McDermott</PERSON>.
``There's still some room for expansion there.''
   <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, Ohio-based company that
ranks second to industry leader <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, always has
maintained a strong mass market presence. Its cards are carried in
giant retailers such as <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Roebuck and Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>K mart Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, big
discounters and drug chains.
   Spokesman <PERSON>John Hernandis</PERSON> says <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> is trying to
enhance its good position within the mass volume retailing business.
Responding to retailer needs, it's making shelf space more
productive.
   Redesigned cabinets increase density, accommodating more cards.
High-visibility locator signs make it easier for shoppers to find
what they want.
   Helping shoppers locate desired cards has grown in importance
partly because women, who buy about <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of the 7 billion
greetings cards sold annually in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, have less time
to look. Many work full-time.
   American Greetings also is emphasizing a concept called seasonal
program marketing. They did it first this past Easter by grouping
all Easter merchandise _ cards, party items, giftwrapping and plush
toys _ around a central theme. Bloomer Bunny was the pitch rabbit
for the stuff.
   Hernandis says the company intends to use this approach every
holiday. Placing related merchandise readily at hand makes people
more apt to buy.
   ``You end up spending more, buying more than you would
normally,'' says <PERSON>Hernandis</PERSON>. ``You may have your paper cups and paper
plates, but you may not be even thinking about streamers.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Greetings Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, has found ways
to increase card and related merchandise sales in supermarkets,
which now account for about <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of annual sales industrywide
vs. about <PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT> in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Greg Ionna</PERSON>, vice president of marketing, says <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> has
identified several natural tie-ins between foods and cards.
Valentine's Day cards have been placed in candy aisles, puppy and
kitten calendars have crept into pet food shelves and cards are
appearing alongside flowers in grocery-store floral departments.
   ``There's lots of opportunities, we believe, to cross merchandise
with other products,'' <PERSON>Ionna</PERSON> says.
   Hallmark, of <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, dominates what it calls the social
expression business, with an estimated <PERCENT>42 percent</PERCENT> of the market,
followed by <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> with about <PERCENT>32 percent</PERCENT> and
third-ranked <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> with about <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>. Possibly as many as 1,000
other companies share the rest.
   The rankings are only analysts' best guesses because Hallmark is
a private company and doesn't disclose many financial details.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, June 18</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0271 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1633EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-GreetingCards Bjt   12-22 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greeting Cards, Bjt,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baby Boomers Like Humor For Christmas Cards But Tradition Prevails</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DWIGHT WOODWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   'Tis the season to be traditional, but silly
Santas, laughing reindeer and teddy bears are arriving in mailboxes
nationwide this year as Christmas card makers appeal to a trend in
card buying that transcends race, religion and sex _ humor.
   Those who like the offbeat can send a card showing cow udders
singing a Christmas carol or <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> kicking a football through the
antlers of a laughing reindeer.
   While the majority of the 2.3 billion Christmas cards sent this
year will reflect more customary symbols of the holiday, humor is
where the growth is, said <PERSON>Terry Carney</PERSON>, spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>American
Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, the largest publicly owned greeting card company
with <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> in annual sales.
   ``But it's not usually the kind of humor that is nasty, rude or
sarcastic,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Carney</PERSON>.
   About 500 members of the creative staff at <ORGANIZATION>American</ORGANIZATION>, based in
suburban <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, produce about 2,300 designs a year of which
about one-third are Christmas cards, <PERSON>Ms. Carney</PERSON> said.
   In addition to laughs, specialty cards with a regional flavor _
cactus for the <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>, for instance _ or messages aimed at
particular occupations are popular.
   As with most consumer tastes, the explanation is demographic.
   ``The bulk of the cards purchased are by people between 35 and
59,'' said E. Gray Glass III, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> stock market analyst with
<ORGANIZATION>Prudential-Bache Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Glass. ``These are people that move around a
lot and they want to keep in contact with their friends.''
   <PERSON>Barbara Miller</PERSON>, spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, agreed that
humor is in this year, but she said tradition dies hard.
   ``Wreaths, holly trees, bells, fireplace and sleigh scenes _
these are the symbols people see as <DATE>Christmas</DATE>,'' she said.
   That doesn't mean the giant Hallmark hasn't cultivated a Yuppie
sense of humor. One Hallmark offering shows a dazed cat with a
stocking cap swinging on an ornament attached to <LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION> tree
lights. Inside, the caption reads, ``In the air there's a feline of
Christmas.''
   Among the specialty cards designed to suit distinctive tastes
are ones ``for the barber, the teacher, bus driver or the
mailman,'' <PERSON>Ms. Miller</PERSON> said.
   With annual sales of more than <MONEY>$3.5 billion</MONEY>, the privately held
<ORGANIZATION>Hallmark</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, has the biggest single share
of the greeting card market, producing 2,700 card designs for
over-the-counter sales and another 400 different boxed sets of
multiple cards, <PERSON>Ms. Miller</PERSON> said.
   Glass said <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark</ORGANIZATION> produces about <PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Christmas
cards, followed by American with <PERCENT>32 percent</PERCENT> and <ORGANIZATION>Cincinnati-based
Gibson Greetings Inc.</ORGANIZATION> about <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   Another 700 to 800 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> companies produce the remainder of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Christmas cards with a negligible portion coming from foreign
manufacturers, Glass said.
   Among the strangest, if not funniest, cards to emerge are
pet-to-pet missives.
   ``From our cat to your cat, from our dog to your dog _ people
consider their pets part of the family,'' <PERSON>Ms. Miller</PERSON> said. ``They
are cute cards, not drippy or sentimental.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880406-0279 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-06-88 2052EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-AmericanGreetings     04-06 0333</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-American Greetings,0345</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greeting Card Company Reports Earnings Decline</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By M.R. KROPKO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Greetings, the nation's second largest
greeting card company, reported <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that its earnings
declined by <PERCENT>95.1 percent</PERCENT> in its <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>, which included
Christmas sales.
   The quarter contributed to a <PERCENT>47.3 percent</PERCENT> earnings decline in
American Greetings' fiscal <DATE>1988</DATE>, completed <DATE>Feb. 29</DATE>.
news conference that stiff competition, combined with unexpected
returns of seasonal merchandise, contributed heavily to the
earnings drop.
   The company's AmToy subsidiary also had a disappointing quarter
and year, <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> said.
   The company earned <MONEY>$748,000</MONEY>, or <MONEY>2 cents</MONEY> a share, in the <DATE>fourth
quarter</DATE>, although revenue amounted to <MONEY>$314.5 million</MONEY>. In the <DATE>final
quarter of 1987</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> earned <MONEY>$15.3 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>48
cents</MONEY> a share, on revenue of <MONEY>$291.2 million</MONEY>.
   For the full fiscal year, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> earned <MONEY>$33.4
million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$1.04</MONEY> a share, on revenue of nearly <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY>. In
the prior year, earnings came to <MONEY>$63.6 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$1.97</MONEY> a share,
on revenue exceeding <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY>.
   Earnings dropped for a third consecutive year. The per-share
earnings of <MONEY>$1.04</MONEY> was the lowest since fiscal <DATE>1981</DATE>, when earnings
were <MONEY>97 cents</MONEY> per share.
   ``While results for fiscal <DATE>1988</DATE> are a major disappointment, the
good news is that they reflect, in part, a number of corrective
measures taken which should be positive for our future prospects,''
<PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> said.
   He said the company has begun or is considering consolidation of
its manufacturing and distribution operations of the domestic
greeting card business, personnel reductions, revisions in seasonal
merchandise shipping and a scaling back of the toy business.
   He also said the company needs a spurt of creativity to increase
sales, adding that there has been good initial reaction to its new
<ORGANIZATION>Nosy Bears</ORGANIZATION> and Special Blessings products.
   The Cleveland-based company employs about 20,000. Some layoffs
occurred last year, although the company-wide figure has not been
made public, said <PERSON>John Hernandis</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> spokesman.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880620-0159 </DOCNO>
<HL> Profit at American Greetings Climbed 14% in 1st Period </HL>
<AUTHOR> Gregory Stricharchuk (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> AGREA </CO>
<IN> ERN </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION> posted a <PERCENT>14%</PERCENT> profit rise in the <DATE>fiscal first quarter</DATE>, signaling a turnaround for the greeting card maker after a costly two-year battle for market share. 


   In the latest quarter, a reduction in the effective tax rate to <PERCENT>39%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>43%</PERCENT> added as much as <MONEY>three cents</MONEY> to per-share figures, the company said. 
However, that increase was partly offset by a "nominal loss" the company had as a result of the previously reported sale of two businesses. 

   Revenue rose about <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$303.2 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$263.3 million</MONEY>. 

   The profit rise, the first improvement in eight consecutive quarters, was slightly better than analysts expected. 
They also viewed <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION>' robust results as a barometer for the entire industry. 

   "I believe it's a pivotal quarter. 
We expect further good news as we go through the year," <PERSON>Henry Lowenthal</PERSON>, senior vice president and chief financial officer, said in an interview. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Lowenthal</PERSON> described the mood at the company's <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> headquarters "as definitely upbeat." 
Officials said greeting cards, especially everyday and non-occasion, "showed particularly strong sales increases, both domestically and internationally." 

   In an effort to snare market share, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mo.-based Hallmark Cards Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and Cincinnati-based <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION> began slashing prices. 
<PERSON>Mr. Lowenthal</PERSON> said the intensity of the battle has abated, although there are occasionally flare-ups in parts of the country. 

   However, the big three's market shares have remained almost unchanged, <PERSON>Mr. Lowenthal</PERSON> said. 
He didn't quibble with analysts' estimates that <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> has slightly more than <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of the market. 

   Hallmark is the leader with about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT>, and <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> has about <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>. 
About 800 companies, many of them producers of off-beat "alternative cards," make up the industry. 

   E. Gray Glass III, an analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Prudential Bache Securities</ORGANIZATION>, said the quarter's results make him feel more comfortable with his estimate that American Greetings for the full year will earn <MONEY>$1.65</MONEY> a share. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Glass</PERSON> said he had been recommending the stock, but that its price recently has reflected upgraded analysts' estimates. 

   In national over-the-counter composite trading <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>$19.125</MONEY>, up <MONEY>75 cents</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06265132 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06265132 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  TELEVISION; COMPANY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  In its largest diversification effort to date, Hallmark Cards Inc. has agreed
to invest about $1 billion in Cencom Cable Association, which has, directly
and indirectly, about 550,000 cable television subscribers. The deal will
instantly make Hallmark one of the nation's largest cable operators.;   The
investment will be made through a Hallmark subsidiary, Crown Media, which
already has a stake in cable systems in Wisconsin that serve 150,000
subscribers.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HALLMARK LEAPS INTO CABLE TV  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Hallmark, a privately held company based in <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, with sales of
<MONEY>$2.7 billion</MONEY> last year, began diversifying into cable only in the <DATE>last two
years.</DATE>;   "We are in the communications business, and the greeting card is the
most prominent manifestation of that," <PERSON>Irvine Hockaday Jr.</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark</ORGANIZATION>'s
president and chief executive, said in a telephone interview <DATE>Friday</DATE>. "We see
in cable an attractive investment on its own with long-term possibilities for
cross-marketing.";   <ORGANIZATION>Cencom</ORGANIZATION>, a privately held company based in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, has
about 150,000 subscribers in the <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> area. In addition there are 400,000
subscribers in systems that are owned by partnerships affiliated with <ORGANIZATION>Cencom</ORGANIZATION>
and managed by Cencom.;   Hallmark began moving beyond its core greeting card
business in <DATE>1984</DATE>, when it bought <ORGANIZATION>Binney &amp; Smith</ORGANIZATION>, the manufacturer of Crayola
crayons, for <MONEY>$204 million.</MONEY>;   <DATE>Three years later</DATE> it began expanding into
broadcasting with the purchase of the <ORGANIZATION>Spanish International Communication
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a group of nine television stations that carry Spanish-language
programming. The group included WXTV-TV, Channel 41 in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, and KMEX-TV
in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. That purchase price was <MONEY>$286 million.</MONEY>;   In <DATE>1988</DATE>, it bought
million.</MONEY>;   Hallmark remains the largest maker of greeting cards, ahead of
<ORGANIZATION>American Greetings</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Greetings</ORGANIZATION>. Hockaday estimated that <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark</ORGANIZATION> had
<PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT> of the market and that about half of the company's revenues came
from cards.;   He said <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark</ORGANIZATION> looks at expansion from two angles. On the one
hand, the purchase of <ORGANIZATION>Binney &amp; Smith</ORGANIZATION> was "a form of reinvestment in our core
business." Many of <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark</ORGANIZATION>'s card sales come from a franchised chain of card
shops, which the company thought would also be good sites for selling Crayola
products.;   "People use the word diversification loosely," <PERSON>Hockaday</PERSON> said. "I
prefer to think of new channels of distribution.";   By contrast, he said, the
more recent acquisitions, of Spanish-language television and cable, were an
example of diversification as most people use the term.;   "We saw a market
that is growing four to five times faster than the Anglo market," he said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910921  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  16F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  422  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, September 21, 1991
00265132,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-4003</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BDVB1ACIFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910422
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 APR 91 / The Queen's Awards For Export and Technology 1991 (Company
Profiles): Happy occasion for greetings card maker - Second Nature
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ANDREW JACK
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Mr Rod Schrager</PERSON>'s business maxim is 'focus at the top end of the market'. In
10 years he has turned a chance holiday encounter into a successful
greetings cards company using just that principle.
'A <ORGANIZATION>Queen</ORGANIZATION>'s Award puts the seal on our success in building up a British
presence in an international industry', he says. His company <ORGANIZATION>Second Nature</ORGANIZATION>,
a publisher of quality cards and Christmas decorations, has a projected
turnover of Pounds 7m this year, and expects to sell more than 1m cards a
month - <DATE>one quarter</DATE> of which will be outside the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>.
By contrast, most greetings card manufacturers do not export very much, he
says. The reason is that they focus on the bottom end of the market.
Low-priced cards can easily be produced locally, and some designs -
including those with a particular country's humour - often do not easily
translate to overseas markets.
He points to three segments in the greetings card industry: those bought for
associates; for family and close friends; and 'the one or two beautiful,
more expensive cards for those you are closest to'. Second Nature focuses on
the latter two categories, with a series of elaborate cards at higher
prices.
The company was launched in <DATE>1981</DATE> after Zimbabwean-born <PERSON>Mr Schrager</PERSON>, who was
then working as an accountant for Peat Marwick in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, went on holiday to
the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>. He met a Californian designer who asked him to try to sell some of
his greetings cards with floral patterns in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. Keeping up the theme,
he also suggested a name: <ORGANIZATION>Second Nature</ORGANIZATION>.
Schrager was surprised to find British retailers greatly interested, and on
an investment of Pounds 3,000 of his own money, he started to produce the
cards himself, with designs under license from the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.
His big break came four years ago, when he began to sell pop-up cards. The
pop-up was originally invented by the Victorians and then faded out in card
designs, although a number of books using the same principle were beginning
to emerge in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
'I just brought the idea back up to date,' he says. 'We wanted an unusual
design, but one we could produce commercially. It was quite a bold move
then.' Second Nature began selling cards at Pounds 2.50, at a time when the
average card price was about 65p. 'But there was a definite need for a
contemporary card with a higher price.'
Now the company has a total portfolio of some 800 cards. Half a dozen of the
designs have even been patented, and many use sophisticated paper
engineering techniques.
The cards are still entirely made in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, using labour-intensive hand
assembly that can take up to three minutes for each card. The company
searched overseas to see if they could be produced more cheaply, but the
difference in costs was negligible.
None of the company's 65 staff are involved directly in production, however.
'I don't believe it's good to vertically integrate,' says <PERSON>Schrager</PERSON>. 'By
contracting out all our assembly work, we can stay on top of innovation and
creativity.'
The focus on higher-end cards also means that the company's business is less
seasonal than for many manufacturers. Nevertheless, <ORGANIZATION>Second Nature</ORGANIZATION> has
launched high quality Christmas decorations using similar sophisticated
designs.
In two weeks' time, representatives from the company will be anxiously
sitting in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Waldorf Astoria</LOCATION> hotel. They have 11 nominations for
the 'Louie awards' - named after <PERSON>Louis Prang</PERSON>, inventor of <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> greetings
cards. But it will be hard to improve on <DATE>last year</DATE>, when they were the first
company outside <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> to win 'Card of the Year'.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18 Photograph Ream realm, Rod Shrager displays Second Nature's
elaborate pop-ups (Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880525-0340 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-25-88 1145EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f BC-BlueMountain-Hallmark     05-25 0540</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Blue Mountain-Hallmark,0557</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Upholds Ruling Against Hallmark Cards</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATTY REINERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal appeals court has upheld a ruling
temporarily forbidding <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards Inc.</ORGANIZATION> from making greeting
card designs resembling those of a small competitor, clearing the
way for a full trial of the company's <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> damage suit
against Hallmark.
   ``Blue Mountain Arts has pushed the bullies back to the alley.
We've been waiting and waiting on the ruling and it's entirely in
our favor,'' said <PERSON>Bob Gall</PERSON>, general manager of the <LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION>,
Colo.-based company, which won the injunction. ``We are absolutely
ecstatic.''
   Blue Mountain brought suit against Hallmark, based in <LOCATION>Kansas
City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>July 1986</DATE>, alleging that <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Personal
Touch'' line of greeting cards is deceptively similar to <ORGANIZATION>Blue
Mountain</ORGANIZATION>'s ``AireBrush Feelings'' and ``WaterColor Feelings'' lines.
   Blue Mountain alleged that Hallmark was guilty of unfair
competition and copyright infringement.
   A federal court ruled in <DATE>November 1986</DATE> that Blue Mountain's two
card lines have ``an inherently distinctive and highly uniform
overall appearance that is recognizable and attributable to Blue
Mountain.''
   It ordered Hallmark to stop producing and marketing 83 specific
greeting card designs.
   The Blue Mountain cards are characterized by backgrounds of soft
colors done with air brush blends or light watercolor strokes.
   In <DATE>April</DATE>, Hallmark appealed the injunction order, arguing that a
single greeting card company should not have ``perpetual rights to
a style of art, a style of text and a concept of their combined
use.''
   In <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s decision, the 10th <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION>
affirmed the injunction, saying the lower court was correct in
determining that the combination of features comprising the trade
dress, or the overall appearance, of Blue Mountain's cards can be
protected.
   A date for a full trial is expected to be scheduled now that the
appeal has been decided. Blue Mountain is seeking <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> in
damages from Hallmark and will fight what they consider Hallmarks's
other ``copycat'' card designs.
   ``It's not only a victory for <PERSON>Stephen</PERSON> and me and for <ORGANIZATION>Blue
Mountain</ORGANIZATION>, but it's also a victory for the arts and for all creative
people,'' said <PERSON>Susan Polis Schutz</PERSON>, a poet who co-founded Blue
Mountain with her husband <PERSON>Stephen Schutz</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Polis Schutz</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Blue Mountain</ORGANIZATION>'s main complaint was the look of
the cards, which she said confused everyone, ``including myself.''
   ``This decision means you can create something and not have to
worry about it being stolen,'' she said. ``One of the things that
<PERSON>Stephen</PERSON> and I learned is that it is possible to stand up for your
rights no matter how small you are or how big your opponent is.''
   <PERSON>Charles W. Hucker</PERSON>, a spokesman for the greeting card giant, said
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> that Hallmark was disappointed but not surprised by
the decision.
   ``We will consider making a further appeal. It is important to
understand that this is a preliminary decision based on a limited
airing of the issues,'' <PERSON>Hucker</PERSON> said. ``We will have the opportunity
to present our case in full for the first time at the trial.''
   Hucker noted that the <ORGANIZATION>Blue Mountain</ORGANIZATION> suit contended Hallmark
copied the smaller company's look.
   ``It is absolutely not true, and they know it's not true, that
we copied specific designs,'' he said.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871222-0027 </DOCNO>
<HL> American Greetings
Reports 31% Decline
In 3rd-Quarter Net</HL>
<DD> 12/22/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> AGREA
EARNINGS (ERN) </IN>
<DATELINE> CLEVELAND  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>American Greetings Corp.</ORGANIZATION> reported a <PERCENT>31%</PERCENT> decline in fiscal <DATE>third-quarter</DATE> net income and said it expects a drop for the year as well. 

   For the <DATE>third quarter ended Nov. 30</DATE>, the company earned <MONEY>$18.2 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>57 cents</MONEY> a share, down from the year-earlier <MONEY>$26.3 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>82 cents</MONEY> a share. 
Revenue rose <PERCENT>2%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$370.9 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$364.3 million</MONEY>. 

   The maker of greeting cards, gifts, wrappings and stationery said it expects to post net income of between <MONEY>$1</MONEY> and <MONEY>$1.10</MONEY> a share for fiscal <DATE>1988</DATE>. 
For <DATE>fiscal 1987</DATE>, earnings were <MONEY>$1.97</MONEY> a share. 

He also said if certain accounting changes are made, as expected, profits could climb to the <MONEY>$1.40</MONEY> to <MONEY>$1.50</MONEY> range. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> said the falloff in <DATE>third-quarter</DATE> profits was due to a variety of factors, including returns of seasonal merchandise that exceeded expectations; a dismal year for the toy industry and, thus, the company's AmToy unit; smaller than expected sales increases, particularly on non-greeting card items; and requirements for higher levels of working capital that resulted in increased borrowing and higher interest expense. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Weiss</PERSON> also cited keen competition and said pressure on earnings should continue through the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-8072</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKQCRAEUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931117
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  17 NOV 93 / UK Company News: Brownsword in cards merger with Hallmark
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BLACKWELL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
CONGRATULATIONS to <PERSON>Andrew Brownsword</PERSON>, thought to be one of the highest paid
men in the UK, who is moving house.
<PERSON>Mr Brownsword</PERSON>, who started designing and publishing greetings cards from his
kitchen table more than 20 years ago, has agreed to merge his group of
companies with the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> - <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> operations of <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards</ORGANIZATION>, the world's
largest greetings card publisher with annual sales of more than Dollars 3bn
(Pounds 2bn).
In its last published accounts for the 13 months to <DATE>January 1991</DATE> the
<PERSON>Brownsword</PERSON> company, which owns the quintessentially English <PERSON>Gordon Fraser</PERSON>
and Forever Friends, reported turnover of nearly Pounds 45m and pre-tax
profits of Pounds 19.7<ORGANIZATION>m.
Hallmark Cards</ORGANIZATION> is one of the biggest privately owned companies in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>. It
is based in <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, where founder <PERSON>Joyce Hall</PERSON> started selling
postcards in <DATE>1910</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mr Hall</PERSON>, who was named after a bishop and constantly received mail addressed
to <PERSON>Miss Hall</PERSON>, died aged 91 in <DATE>1982</DATE>, handing the business on to his son,
<PERSON>Donald J Hall</PERSON>.
The company employs 700 artists and offers cards for every occasion - from
birth to death, taking in all stages of modern American courtship, including
a request for information on a partner's HIV status.
In the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark</ORGANIZATION> has 140 retail outlets known as <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Cards</ORGANIZATION>, where it
offers its collection of brands including the Snoopy range. <PERSON>Mr Brownsword</PERSON>,
46, will assume overall responsibility for the combined group's operations
in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>.
Neither <PERSON>Mr Brownsword</PERSON> or <PERSON>Mr Don Read</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark UK/Ireland</ORGANIZATION>'s group managing
director, were available for comment yesterday.
But <PERSON>Mr Read</PERSON> said in a press statement that the merger 'brings together two
of the leading names in the greetings cards business and offers exciting
growth prospects for the industry as a whole.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Andrew Brownsword Collection.
    Hallmark Cards.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
    IEZ  Ireland, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2771 Greeting Cards.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 28
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920225-0040
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920225-0040.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Who's News:
   American Greetings
   Names Fruchtenbaum
   Company President
</HL>
<DATE>
02/25/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B10
</SO>
<CO>
   AGREA WNEWS
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
PUBLISHING, INFORMATION SERVICES COMPANIES (PUB)
</IN>
<NS>
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
</NS>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
OHIO (OH)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   CLEVELAND -- American Greetings Corp. said Edward
Fruchtenbaum, who has been credited with leading the
company's turnaround in core greeting card operations, has
   Mr. Fruchtenbaum, 43 years old, succeeds Morry Weiss, who
was named chairman. Mr. Weiss, 51, will remain chief
executive officer, a post he has held since 1987. He had been
Stone assumes the new title of founder-chairman and retains
his post as chairman of the board's executive committee.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Since <DATE>January 1990</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Fruchtenbaum</PERSON> had been director and
president of <ORGANIZATION>American Greeting</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Greeting Card Division</ORGANIZATION>,
which accounts for roughly <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of the company. Under his
leadership, the company rebounded from an earning's low of
<MONEY>$1.04</MONEY> a share in <DATE>1988</DATE> to a high of <MONEY>$2.61</MONEY> in fiscal <DATE>1991</DATE>. The
company's fiscal year <DATE>1992</DATE> ends <DATE>Saturday</DATE>; analysts expect
earnings to hit <MONEY>$2.80</MONEY> a share for fiscal <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   All domestic and international operating units will now
report to <PERSON>Mr. Fruchtenbaum</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA052689-0171 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 62433 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 26, 1989, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Orange County Life; Part 9; Page 6; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
929 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SINGLE LIFE: GREETING CARDS PUT NEW STAMP ON DATING RITUAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SUSAN CHRISTIAN, Susan Christian is a regular contributor to Orange County 
Life. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Situation One: You were under the impression that your blind date had as much 
fun as you did. But 2 weeks have passed and you haven't heard a peep out of 
him. What's a woman to do? 
</P>
<P>
Solution: Send him a card, perhaps the one that says, "1,387 hours, 22 seconds. 
Average length of time a woman waits for a man to call. . . . <ORGANIZATION>Time</ORGANIZATION>'s up." 
(<ORGANIZATION>Carolyn Bean Cards</ORGANIZATION>.) 
</P>
<P>
Situation Two: You and your best friend recently had a no-good-men 
conversation, which she immediately followed up with an appropriate card. So 
now you owe her one. How can you outdo her? 
</P>
<P>
Solution: Go to a Hallmark shop, and find the card that says, "We shouldn't 
worry about finding a man. There are lots of men out there. They're married, 
lunatics and losers, sure, but they're out there." 
</P>
<P>
And so on, ad infinitum. 
</P>
<P>
In the past few years, there has been a proliferation of such greeting cards 
aimed at the singles market. Commonly found in the "Fun and Love" section at 
gift shops, the humorous cards address every aspect of single life -- for 
better or worse. 
</P>
<P>
There are post-date cards, love-hate cards, losing-weight cards. There are 
congratulations-on-your-divorce cards and sorry-your-dumb-boyfriend-dumped-you 
cards. There are cards too sweet for words and cards too dirty for mention. 
</P>
<P>
"We have cards for all the different stages of dating -- first date, casual 
flirtation, longstanding relationships," Hallmark spokeswoman <PERSON>Barbara Miller</PERSON> 
said. "They are one of our fastest-growing areas." 
</P>
<P>
Paper Moon Graphics, the Los Angeles-based manufacturer that rocketed into 
orbit 12 years ago, sells as many "Fun and Love" cards as it does birthday 
cards. "In the past 3 years, our relationship cards have had phenomenal 
success," said <PERSON>Vivian Lipman</PERSON>, national sales manager for Paper Moon. 
</P>
<P>
Lipman attributed the genre's upward mobility to relationship-confused yuppies. 
"So many men have the <PERSON>Peter</PERSON> Pan syndrome (i.e., fear of commitment) that it has 
become women's little joke," she said. 
</P>
<P>
Male-bashing is definitely hot in card land. "Quick: What's the difference?" 
asks a Hallmark witticism displaying a rock vs. a man on its cover. Answer: 
"Right, the rock is slightly more sensitive (also a better listener)." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Larry Templeman</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Southern California-based Scott Cards</ORGANIZATION> 
(distributed by Recycled Paper Products), gave two reasons for the popularity 
of male-bashing. 
</P>
<P>
First, women buy <PERCENT>85%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of all greeting cards. "It's a female-dominated 
market," <PERSON>Templeman</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Furthermore, <PERSON>Templeman</PERSON> added, "all those male-bashing books of the past 10 
years" have fanned the fire. 
</P>
<P>
"There's a double standard," he said. "Some of the things you can get away with 
saying about men would be viewed as sexist if said about women. 
</P>
<P>
"But it's all in fun; I don't think men take this stuff too seriously." 
</P>
<P>
Relationship themes have been "revolutionary rather than evolutionary," said 
<PERSON>Dennis Chupa</PERSON>, executive director of everyday products for <ORGANIZATION>American Greeting</ORGANIZATION>. 
"They emerge almost spontaneously -- seemingly overnight," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Divorce cards did not fare well for <ORGANIZATION>American Greeting</ORGANIZATION> until they recently 
gained a sense of humor: "Let's face it: Your prince turned out to be a frog." 
</P>
<P>
"Still, divorce cards are tricky, no matter how they're approached," <PERSON>Chupa</PERSON> 
said. "You have to know how the person is handling their divorce before you can 
send them a joke about it." 
</P>
<P>
San Francisco-based <ORGANIZATION>Carolyn Bean Cards</ORGANIZATION> offers this consolation: "Your spouse 
was a louse. Be sure you get the house." 
</P>
<P>
A lot of "Fun and Love" cards actually deal with love -- or, at least, like. 
Many do so in a risque manner: 
</P>
<P>
* "The moment our eyes met, the rest of me wanted to get acquainted." 
(<LOCATION>Carlton</LOCATION>.) 
</P>
<P>
* "I've had it with you. And boy was it great." (Paper Moon.) 
</P>
<P>
* "Wanna cuddle? Or whatever." (<ORGANIZATION>Scott Cards</ORGANIZATION>.) 
</P>
<P>
* "You make me feel like a kid again. Wanna sleep over?" (Hallmark.) 
</P>
<P>
That last one is about as suggestive as Hallmark gets, but other manufacturers 
push the limits. "Some of the most conservative-looking people come in here and 
buy cards with four-letter words," said <PERSON>Sandra Small</PERSON>, manager of <PERSON>Mr. G</PERSON>'s 
Expressions card shop in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Although Hallmark's 3-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Shoebox Cards</ORGANIZATION> division sprinkles 
double-entendres throughout its line of cards, the company still steers clear 
of strong language. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a hard call," spokeswoman <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> admitted. "Our overriding concern is 
that customers consider our cards in good taste. Yet we don't want to seem 
old-fashioned; we want to be timely and to reflect contemporary society." 
</P>
<P>
Many "Fun and Love" cards reflect the issues singles are facing in contemporary 
society. 
</P>
<P>
Relationship befuddlement: "If loving you is wrong, I don't want to be right. 
But if loving you is right, I don't want to be wrong, either. I'm so confused." 
(Hallmark.) 
</P>
<P>
Safe sex: "So it's our first date. How does dinner, a movie and a blood test 
sound?" (Paper Moon.) 
</P>
<P>
Birth control: One dog to another -- "Jowles, I hate to spoil the romantic 
mood, but have you been fixed?" (Paper Moon.) 
</P>
<P>
Fear of scaring off a love interest: "Please don't take this as a sign of 
weakness, but I miss you." (<ORGANIZATION>Scott Cards</ORGANIZATION>.) 
</P>
<P>
Noncommittal communication: "I want to tell you how I really feel. I really 
feel fine, thanks." (Recycled Paper.) 
</P>
<P>
Unrequited love: "I'm so miserable without you.. . . . It's almost like having 
you here." And, "Thinking of you. . . . Wish you would change." (Paper Moon.) 
</P>
<P>
But most "Fun and Love" cards are on the lighter side. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mitch Zack</PERSON>, manager of Krazy Kards store in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>, summed them up this way: 
"They get the message across without saying, 'I want to have your children.' " 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891018-0268 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-89 1416EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-CrayonCompany Adv23   10-18 0738</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Crayon Company, Adv 23,0760</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday Oct. 23</HEAD>
<HEAD>Not Just For the Kiddies Anymore</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALLY STREFF BUZBEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WINFIELD, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's a child's delight _ rows of bright
red, yellow and green crayons that pop out of molding machines,
roll along conveyor belts and slip into little boxes that have
become a fixture in any toy store.
   But <ORGANIZATION>Binney &amp; Smith</ORGANIZATION> is making more than Crayola crayons at its
plant in this small <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> town south of <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION>. The 85-year-old
company has branched into art products designed to appeal to
everyone from toddlers to professionals, as part of a larger
diversification plan by parent company <ORGANIZATION>Hallmark Cards Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Kansas City-based cardmaker bought <ORGANIZATION>Binney &amp; Smith</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$200
million</MONEY> <DATE>five years ago</DATE>, shortly after <PERSON>Irvine O. Hockaday Jr.</PERSON> became
since steered Hallmark into markets ranging from real estate to
Spanish-language television, but he still thinks his first buy was
a good one.
   ``It's hard to match the criteria we set,'' <PERSON>Hockaday</PERSON> said. ``But
<ORGANIZATION>Binney &amp; Smith</ORGANIZATION> is incomparable as far as people recognizing the
Crayola name and having good feelings about it. We thought that
