<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890718-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-18-89 0148EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mozambique     07-18 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mozambique,0392</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Calls For Peace Negotiations With Guerrillas</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MAPUTO, Mozambique (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE>
his country is weary of war and said he authorized church leaders to
present government peace proposals to guerrillas.
   Chisano said the church officials and a government delegation
were in <LOCATION>Nairobi</LOCATION> for talks with guerrilla leaders on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. In
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, a rebel spokesman said the guerrilla delegation would
consider the government proposals.
   It was not immediately clear what the government proposals would
include.
   An estimated 100,000 people have died in the 12-year-old civil
war that broke out after <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> gained independence from
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>. About 1.6 million Mozambicans are refugees, and half the
country's 14.7 million people depend, at least partially, on food
aid.
   Chissano, who in the past has rejected negotiations with the
<ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION> guerrillas, said <DATE>Monday</DATE> he decided to
negotiate because of ``the sentiments of the population vis a vis
the war.''
   He said that although the Mozambican people repudiated the
guerrillas' ``acts of violence'' they also had ``a great desire for
the end of the war.''
   <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said he asked <PERSON>Catholic</PERSON> and Protestant members of the
19-church <ORGANIZATION>Mozambican Christian Council</ORGANIZATION> to meet with a guerrilla
delegation in <LOCATION>Nairobi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> to find out ``what they want,'' the
government news agency, AIM, reported.
   AIM quoted <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> as saying the government will not inist that
the guerrillas lay down their arms, but that they ``end all acts of
terrorism and banditry.''
   <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said a Mozambican government delegation consisting of
provincial leaders was also in <LOCATION>Nairobi</LOCATION> to clarify the government's
position for the Kenyan government or the church delegation.
   RENAMO began its guerrilla war against the Marxist government in
<DATE>1977</DATE>, with Rhodesian help, and was then aided by <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> from
1980-84, until <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> signed a non-aggression pact with
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
   The Mozambican government continued to accuse <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> of
violating the agreement, but relations have improved recently and
the Mozambican government now says support for the guerrillas still
comes from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, but it does not say who is behind it.
   RENAMO, which has been accused of mutilating peasants, enslaving
children, burning villages and crops and attacking food relief
convoys, is not openly supported by any government, but it maintains
offices in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110490-0017 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 302591 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 4, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 36; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
748 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MOZAMBIQUE SEEKS PEACE AMID FAMINE; 
</P>
<P>
AFRICA: TALKS WITH REBEL FORCES BROKE DOWN IN SEPTEMBER, CURTAILING OPTIMISM. 
MALNUTRITION IS WIDESPREAD AND PLEDGES OF AID HAVE FALLEN OFF SHARPLY. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By IAN MacKENZIE, REUTERS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MAPUTO, Mozambique 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Peace is proving an elusive commodity in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, where a population of 15 
million is teetering on the edge of famine. 
</P>
<P>
"Every issue you discuss always comes back to the same point -- the need for 
peace," said a senior European diplomat. 
</P>
<P>
Several diplomats in the region said right-wing opponents of South African 
President <PERSON>Frederik W. de Klerk</PERSON>'s efforts to end his country's racial separation 
policy of apartheid are also backing the <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> guerrillas fighting the 
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> government. 
</P>
<P>
"The people trying to stop the internal revolution in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> are the same 
people destabilizing <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>," the European diplomat said. "If you believe 
the revolution in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> is irreversible, you must believe peace will 
come back to <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>. War doesn't make sense anymore." 
</P>
<P>
The head of the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> development program in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Peter Simkin</PERSON>, warned 
that the country faces mass famine. Diplomats estimate two-thirds of the 
population already live in absolute poverty and malnutrition is endemic. 
</P>
<P>
Nations</ORGANIZATION> estimated there were 900,000 war-related deaths in eight years 
beginning with <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> is living on a knife edge that could easily become a disaster area 
of major proportions . . . it could translate into famine later this year or 
early next year and we have no resources to fall back on," <PERSON>Simkin</PERSON> said in an 
interview. "We are not in a position to prevent disaster or to mount a massive 
relief campaign." 
</P>
<P>
Diplomats said pledges of aid dropped sharply this year due in part to the 
<LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> crisis, reconstruction demands for <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION> and "donor 
weariness." 
</P>
<P>
Government and church leaders in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> were optimistic in early <DATE>September</DATE> 
that a peace agreement with <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> was possible after two rounds of talks in 
<LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>. President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON>, who has promised the country's first-ever 
about peace by <DATE>Christmas</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
But <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>'s refusal to attend a third round of talks in <DATE>September</DATE> has deadened 
optimism, with <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> throwing the blame squarely on the rebels. 
</P>
<P>
Diplomats note the ruling <ORGANIZATION>Frelimo Party</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION> has basically preempted all 
<ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> demands by ditching its socialist ideology and agreeing to a market 
economy, political pluralism and a free press. 
</P>
<P>
"You know if you have an open multi-party system, <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> has no hope of gaining 
power," one diplomat said. 
</P>
<P>
The shadowy rebel movement demanded withdrawal of <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> troops from 
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and an end to attacks on <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> base areas as a prerequisite for 
further talks. 
</P>
<P>
Diplomats estimate <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> has 6,000 troops in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, primarily to 
protect the so-called <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> corridor rail link from <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Indian 
Ocean</LOCATION> port of <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
" . . . The achievement of peace would mean a quick withdrawal of all <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> 
troops," President <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> told journalists at the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 
recently. "All those interested in seeing the country free of foreign troops 
should cooperate so that we can achieve peace as soon as possible -- tomorrow 
if possible." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique Resistance Movement</ORGANIZATION>, originally was set up by the white 
minority government of <PERSON>Ian Smith</PERSON> in what was then <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION> as a destabilizing 
force after <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> achieved independence from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> in <DATE>June, 1975</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Diplomats in southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> said the Rhodesians recruited <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> guerrillas 
from among black members of <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s former colonial forces. They were used 
primarily against black nationalists operating out of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> against 
<LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
When <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION> became <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> with independence in <DATE>1980</DATE>, the former white 
security forces handed <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> over to <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, which continued to use it 
against <LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Pretoria and <ORGANIZATION>Maputo</ORGANIZATION> signed the <LOCATION>Nkomati</LOCATION> Accord of nonaggression and 
good-neighborliness in <DATE>1984</DATE> and the South African government subsequently cut 
all official links with <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Chissano himself has said he trusted <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>'s good faith. 
</P>
<P>
Diplomats also believe <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> severed ties with <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>, cutting it off 
from weapons and communications supplies. 
</P>
<P>
But they said it appears right-wing groups in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, including 
Portuguese emigres hoping to recover property they left behind in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, 
continued to support the rebels. 
</P>
<P>
They believe other support came from groups within <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> -- <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>'s 
official headquarters are in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> -- and also <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890816-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-16-89 1011EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Mozambique     08-16 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mozambique,0539</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mozambique Rebels Announce Peace Plan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mozambican rebel forces have issued a peace
plan saying they would rather participate in elections than carry on
their 12-year-old battle to oust the government by force.
   Their 16-point plan, released in <LOCATION>Nairobi</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, represented an
answer to an earlier proposal by the Mozambican government of
President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON>.
   The rebel plan said neither the rebels nor the government would
gain from continued fighting.
   ``It is not <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>'s intention to change the existing order in
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> through armed force,'' said the two-page document,
referring to the Portuguese acronym for the rebel <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique
National Resistance</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The armed struggle is just a last recourse in the defense of
the people against the negation of their rights,'' the two-page
document said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> has been fighting the Marxist-oriented government since
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> gained independence from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE>. The war has
killed an estimated 600,000 people.
   The rebel proposal followed a week of discussions that began <DATE>Aug.
8</DATE> in <LOCATION>Nairobi</LOCATION> between <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> and a delegation of Mozambican Roman
Catholic and protestant church leaders.
   During the talks, the church officials presented a 12-point peace
plan from the Mozambican government.
   Renamo leader <PERSON>Afonso Dhlakama</PERSON> said the rebel proposal was a
response to <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>'s offer, which was never made public.
   In its proposal, <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> called for the withdrawal of foreign
troops from the southeast African nation and urged ``genuine'' peace
negotiations be held.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and many other Western countries have been
providing non-military aid to the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> government, which
continues to get the bulk of its arms from Soviet bloc. Some Western
countries, including <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, provide some security
assistance. <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> has large number of troops in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>
helping the government fight the war.
   <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said recently he has accepted <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s word that
it no longer aids the rebels. However, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> still believes the
rebels receive help from non-governmental groups in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>'s statement said the rebels want negotiations toward ``a
national reconciliation without winners or losers'' that would
``finally end in peace.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>'s other proposals included a call for its own recognition
``as a political force,'' an end to verbal attacks by <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>'s
government and general elections. The guerrilla proposal also stated
<ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>'s opposition to human rights abuses.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> is a guerrilla force whose survival depends only on the
people, therefore it is by nature against any atrocity that risks
the lives of the people, its reason for being,'' said the document.
   The rebels have been accused of committing atrocities against
civilians while seeking food or new recruits.
   In an English-language news release accompanying the proposal,
<PERSON>Dhlakama</PERSON> said the church leaders and rebels addressed the withdrawal
of foreign troops and possible ways of ending the conflict.
   The closed-door meetings between church leaders and rebels were
held under Kenyan government auspices.
   The <LOCATION>Nairobi</LOCATION> talks followed <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>'s request to Presidents
<PERSON>Daniel arap Moi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Robert Mugabe</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> to mediate an
end to conflict in the former Portuguese colony.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> is one of the world's poorest countries. An estimated
6 million of its 15 million people receive food aid.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900101-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-01-90 1616EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mozambique     01-01 0231</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mozambique,0237</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conditions Becoming Ripe for Direct Talks With Rebels</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MAPUTO, Mozambique (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   African leaders trying to mediate
peace talks between the Mozambican government and guerrillas say
conditions are becoming ripe for direct talks, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s foreign
minister said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Foreign Minister <PERSON>Pascoal Mocumbi</PERSON> said on <ORGANIZATION>Radio Maputo</ORGANIZATION> that
President <PERSON>Daniel arap Moi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Robert Mugabe</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>
had made progress in their efforts, and the Mozambican government
is prepared to talk to members of the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambican National
Resistance</ORGANIZATION>.
   Pascoal said the mediators told the Mozambican government ``that
the conditions are becoming ripe for a direct dialogue'' between
the Mozambican government and <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>, the guerrilla group.
   The Kenyan and Zimbabwean leaders have been facilitating talks
between Mozambican churchmen and guerrilla representatives.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Mozambican National Resistance</ORGANIZATION> began fighting the government
forces in <DATE>1977</DATE>. White-run <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION> first supported them, then <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>.
   The South African government has said it no longer supports the
guerrillas, but <PERSON>Mocumbi</PERSON> said ``within <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, some forces,
even if they are not supported by the government, continue to seek
to use the <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> bandits as an instrument.'' He said there had
been a reduction in the amount of aid reaching the guerrillas from
across the border, but some assistance continued.
   The war has claimed an estimated 600,000 lives, displaced more
than 1 million people and left about half the population in need of
food aid.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900313-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-13-90 1615EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Mozambique     03-13 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Mozambique,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Urges End to Mozambique Civil War</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> saluted <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s
march toward democracy and economic reform, urging President
<PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON> to begin talks ``at the earliest opportunity'' to
end the 10-year-old civil war.
   Chissano assured <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> that his government was already taking
steps ``to enter into a direct dialogue'' with the <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> rebels as
soon as possible.
   Chissano, whose African country has abandoned Marxism and
shifted its sights toward the West, congratulated <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
efforts ``to promote peace and democracy in southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>,''
especially <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, at a departure ceremony after talks in the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> and
over lunch, offered a strong endorsement of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s reforms,
which he said had also ``buoyed the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> peace process.''
   ``For that, <PERSON>Mr. President</PERSON>, I salute you. Yet we look forward to
even further reforms,'' said <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, who expressed concern about the
millions of Mozambicans suffering from both the war and drought.
   ``We urge all parties to talk at the earliest opportunity so as
to avoid further suffering,'' he said.
   Chissano, who became president in <DATE>1986</DATE> after <PERSON>Samora Machel</PERSON> died
in a plane crash, said his government had put forward a draft
constitution that would provide for universal sufferage, including
direct election of the president and the <ORGANIZATION>People's Assembly</ORGANIZATION>.
   Chissano called his reception at the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> ``another giant
step forward'' for <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>. It came five years after a
path-breaking visit by <PERSON>Machel</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> during the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
administration.
   Chissano, speaking English, said he told <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> ``of the decision
of my government to enter into a direct dialogue with <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> as
soon as possible, and about the measures already taken to bring
this decision into effect.''
   Chissano expressed appreciation ``for the stand the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> has taken on the war in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and for the positive role
it has been playing in the peace process.''
   RENAMO, an organization vilified by human rights groups for its
brutality in the civil war, has been demanding that the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>
government abandon Marxism-Leninism and establish a multiparty
system.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, which gained independence from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> in <DATE>1975</DATE>,
formally abandoned Marxism last <DATE>summer</DATE>. As a reward for embracing
private enterprise and a free-market economy, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> recently struck
the country from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> list of Marxist states, opening the way
for lending and trade concessions.
   Attempts at getting the two sides to stop their war began last
year, with the presidents of <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> mediating.
   Chissano expressed the hope the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> would ``spare no
effort until peace, stability and economic prosperity are achieved
in the region of southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.''
   An estimated 3.2 million Mozambicans have been driven from their
homes, either to internal or external exile during the civil war.
The international community has had to give Mozambique <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY>
to buy food every year.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, on the southeast coast of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, has a population
of 15 million.
   RENAMO was created originally by the white South African
government to counter the Mozambican government's support for the
<ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION>. However, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s new president,
<ORGANIZATION>President F.W. de Klerk</ORGANIZATION>, has cut off assistance to <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> and
recognized the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Zimbabwe-War     12-20 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zimbabwe-War,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mozambique Rebel Offensives a Dilemma for Mugabe</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN EDLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MUTARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ten years ago, guerrilla chieftain
<PERSON>Robert Mugabe</PERSON> put pen to paper in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> to end a bloody seven-year
war for control of his homeland, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s last colonial outpost in
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> known as <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION>.
   That all-party peace pact signed on <DATE>Dec. 21, 1979</DATE>, silenced the
guns and led to the birth of black-governed <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> <DATE>four months
later</DATE>.
   A decade later, as president of <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> is on the
receiving end of offensives across the eastern border by rebels
based in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
   While <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> was able to lead <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION> to peace as <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>
through talks, he is opposed to similar direct negotiations with
the insurgents, who have threatened to bring their war into
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Alfonso Dhlakama</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION> seeks to
undermine <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON>'s socialist
government.
   The 12-year-old war has left an estimated 500,000 to 700,000
dead and created about 1 million Mozambican refugees. Almost half
of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s 15 million people require some food aid.
   The guerrillas also sabotage roads and railways vital to
landlocked <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s economy, and <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> has stationed 12,000
troops in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> at a crippling cost of <MONEY>$450,000</MONEY> a day.
   Dhlakama's rebels now routinely cross the scrub-studded plains
and pine-carpeted mountains into <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> to raid tea and coffee
plantations, native villages and state schools.
   Hundreds of Zimbabweans have been slain or abducted in these
forays, and tens of thousands have been herded into state-guarded
villages, upsetting life all along the 800-mile frontier.
   ``The Rhodesians forced many people into so-called protected
villages when they were fighting <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON>'s guerrillas,'' said a
Roman Catholic missionary, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
``So there are villagers today who are suspicious that they're
being placed in similar settlements by the government they
support.''
   But missionaries back the government's contention that
Zimbabweans are better off behind wire and under guard because of
the rebels.
   The guerrillas, known also by their Portuguese acronym <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>,
have been accused of widespread atrocities, including the killing
of children, mutilating of victims, rape, and destruction of entire
communities.
   The rebels were founded in <DATE>1977</DATE> by former Rhodesian Prime
Minister <PERSON>Ian D. Smith</PERSON> to hound <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON>'s guerrillas in their
Mozambican bases.
   Mugabe ended aid for <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> when he came to power and no
government currently acknowledges assistance.
   Mugabe and Kenyan President <PERSON>Daniel arap Moi</PERSON> have been acting as
intermediaries in indirect talks in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> between the rebels and
the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> government. There have been no breakthroughs since
the talks began in <DATE>July</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> has long said he opposes direct formal peace talks for
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, insisting <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> disavow violence and lay down its arms
first.
   <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>, in turn, demands <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> withdraw its troops from
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> before face-to-face negotiations can be considered.
   <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> also demands that <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s government allow it to
take part in elections as a legal party.
   The Mozambican government says it will not accept a second party
but is considering a proposal that would allow people who are not
in the ruling party to run for <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880917-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-17-88 0935EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Pope 2ndLd-Writethru a0485 09-17 0627</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pope, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0485,0643</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Talks of Peace in War-torn Mozambique</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 5 grafs to CORRECT that civil war 13 years old,
UPDATE with rebel battle report for the last month. Pickup 5th graf
pvs, ``Some Mozambican...'' Edits 10th graf pvs, ``The
conflict...'' to conform.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS REDMONT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRA, Mozambique (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> <DATE>today</DATE> preached peace
and reconciliation in <LOCATION>northern Mozambique</LOCATION>, where a 13-year civil
conflict has forced 1 million to flee and left 6 million at the
edge of famine.
   The Roman Catholic leader traveled from <LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION>, the capital, to
this <LOCATION>Indian Ocean</LOCATION> port city in the devastated north, where he
celebrated Mass before thousands of people, including many refugees.
   The pope lamented ``the prevailing situation of insecurity due
to violence which ... generates violence, anxiety and distress,
leaving limited space for freedom.''
   <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION>, which has port and rail facilities that reach into
landlocked African nations, has been a frequent target of attacks
by rebels of the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION>, known by their
Portuguese acronyn as <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>.
   The rebels in a statement today from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> claimed their
troops killed 46 soldiers from <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> in the <DATE>last
30 days</DATE>, including one near <LOCATION>Vila de Mungari</LOCATION>, southwest of <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION>.
Rebel leader <PERSON>Alfonso Dhlakama</PERSON> also said he hoped the papal visit
would contribute to peace in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
   Some Mozambican bishops have been urging President <PERSON>Joaquim
Chissano</PERSON>'s Marxist government to start talks with the rebels. <PERSON>John
Paul</PERSON> told <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> that ``the efforts of my brother
bishops in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> have always received my backing.''
   The Marxist government, however, has refused to negotiate and
has criticized the bishops for advocating talk with ``armed
bandits.''
   ``The weapons we are still obliged to carry are used exclusively
to defend our country's freedom and our nation,'' <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> told the
pope.
   The Mozambican army, assisted by Zimbabwean forces, has been
able to keep the rail lines running for the past year.
   Renamo guerrillas also have been extremely active in <LOCATION>Nampula
province</LOCATION>, where the pope will stop <TIME>this afternoon</TIME> for a meeting
with local Roman Catholic clergy.
   The conflict that started in <DATE>1975</DATE> between the government and the
guerrillas has forced about 1 million Mozambicans to flee into
neighboring countries and left an estimated 6 million of
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s 14.5 million people in need of food aid, according to
relief organizations.
   The anti-Marxist guerrillas, believed to number between
12,000-22,000, are able to roam the countryside almost at will.
   No government acknowledges assisting the rebels, who have caused
tremendous economic damage and have been accused of widespread
civilian atrocities. <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> denies the charges.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. State Department</ORGANIZATION>, in a report released in <DATE>April</DATE>,
estimated the rebels had killed 100,000 civilians in the past two
to three years.
   Earlier this week, <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> announced a unilateral cease-fire
during the pope's visit and wished the pontiff a good stay.
Nonetheless, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> announced extensive security measures for
the pope and the pilgrims traveling to see him.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> is the final stop on the pope's 10-day tour of
southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. He has visited <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Lesotho</LOCATION> and made a brief, unscheduled stop in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> after
his plane was diverted in bad weather.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, which also has been ravaged by drought in recent
years, receives most of its military assistance from the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION>, but increasingly has been making overtures to Western
nations.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is the largest donor of food aid to
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> has been providing military training.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> also has been working to improve relations with
neighboring <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, which has backed <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> in the past.
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> says it stopped supporting the guerrillas under terms
of a <DATE>1984</DATE> mutual non-aggression pact, but <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> has continued
to charge <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> with providing assistance.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890714-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-14-89 0633EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Mozambique-US     07-14 0679</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mozambique-US,0698</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Official: Mozambique Approves Peace Plan with Rebels</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MFUWE LODGE, Zambia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Mozambican government has approved
a peace plan involving negotiations with the guerrillas to end the
country's 12-year civil war, the top <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> official on African policy
said.
made the announcement <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the Zambian president's safari
lodge after meeting with <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON>.
   Cohen, ending a week-long tour of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, headed today to
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s former colonial ruler.
   Briefing <PERSON>Kenneth Kaunda</PERSON> at the president's lodge in eastern
<LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Cohen</PERSON> said <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> had received the approval of the <ORGANIZATION>Central
Committee</ORGANIZATION> of the ruling party to engage in ``a full-fledged peace
process through negotiations over the conflict in his country.
   ``He has asked the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to be helpful and we have agreed
to do whatever he thinks we should do to contribute to this
process,'' <PERSON>Cohen</PERSON> said.
   Earlier at <LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION> airport, <PERSON>Cohen</PERSON> said <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> indicated he might
ask the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to meet with the guerrillas, and that such a
request would be seriously considered.
   <PERSON>Kaunda</PERSON> said he would be willing to meet ``in confidence'' with
<PERSON>F.W. de Klerk</PERSON>, the leader of the ruling <ORGANIZATION>National Party</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION> and designated to be the country's next president, before or
after the South African parliamentary elections in <DATE>September</DATE>. De
Klerk would not become president until <DATE>September</DATE>, when he is
virtually certain to succeed <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Kaunda</PERSON> has previously said he would be willing to meet de Klerk
after <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> granted independence to <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, whose elections
are not scheduled until <DATE>November</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Kaunda</PERSON> did not give a reason for offering to move up a proposed
meeting with de Klerk, but he welcomed the meeting last week between
<PERSON>Botha</PERSON> and <PERSON>Nelson Mandela</PERSON>, the imprisoned leader of the <ORGANIZATION>African
National Congress</ORGANIZATION>, which has its exile headquarters in <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Kaunda</PERSON> said he would also encourage the <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION>, which has been
waging intermittent guerrilla attacks in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> since <DATE>1961</DATE>, to
talk to the South African government.
   Cohen praised <PERSON>Kaunda</PERSON> for offering to meet de Klerk, whom <PERSON>Cohen</PERSON>
had talked to early this month. He said <PERSON>de Klerk</PERSON> was ``a man who is
willing to listen to ideas.
   ``I believe it is important the he listen not only to the ideas
of Prime Minister (<PERSON>Margaret</PERSON>) <PERSON>Thatcher</PERSON> and (West German Chancellor)
<PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>, but that he also talks to African leaders, because he
is an African and has to find African solutions to the problems of
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Cohen</PERSON> said.
   ``I am persuaded that the president truly seeks to resolve the
conflict through a political settlement,'' he said.
   ``It is now important for <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> (the Portuguese acronym for the
guerrilla organization) to reciprocate by accepting the principle
that no group in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> should seek to impose its will on the
people or government through use of force or violence,'' <PERSON>Cohen</PERSON> said.
   Chissano ``indicated that the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> could play a role in
facilitating the peace process. We agree to play a role and will
continue discussions to decide how this can best be carried out,''
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> official added.
   The national news agency AIM said <PERSON>Cohen</PERSON> made it clear that the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>' role would be on the side of the Mozambican
government and ``not as a mediator.''
   He said <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> ``indicated that he might ask us to meet <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>
some time. If he does this, we will consider it seriously.''
   RENAMO began its guerrilla war against the Marxist government in
<DATE>1977</DATE>, with Rhodesian help, and was then aided by <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> from
1980-84, until <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> signed a non-agression pact with
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>. The Mozambican government continued to accuse <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION> of violating the agreement, but relations have improved
recently and the Mozambican government now says support for the
guerrillas still comes from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, but it does not say who is
behind it.
   RENAMO, which has been accused of mutilating peasants, enslaving
children, burning villages and crops and attacking food relief
convoys, is not openly supported by any government, but it maintains
offices in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900612-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-12-90 1042EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Mozambique     06-12 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mozambique,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebel Leader, Government Delegation Arrive for Peace Talks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MAPUTO, Mozambique (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government and rebel leaders traveled
to neighboring <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE> for their first direct peace talks
aimed at ending a 13-year-old civil war, the national news agency
reported.
   <PERSON>Afonso Dhlakama</PERSON>, commander of the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION>
known by its Portuguese acronym <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>, arrived in <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>'s capital
<LOCATION>Blantyre</LOCATION>, the AIM news agency said.
   The delegation of the leftist government included Transport
Minister <PERSON>Armando Guebaza</PERSON> and Foreign Minister <PERSON>Pascoal Mocumbi</PERSON>, both
members of the <ORGANIZATION>Political Bureau</ORGANIZATION> of the ruling <ORGANIZATION>FRELIMO Party</ORGANIZATION>, AIM
said.
   ``By midday, all the actors in the drama were present in
<LOCATION>Blantyre</LOCATION>, although the talks had not yet begun,'' AIM said.
   Also in <LOCATION>Blantyre</LOCATION> to mediate the talks were government officials
from <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>.
   Kenyan President <PERSON>Daniel Arap Moi</PERSON> and President <PERSON>Robert Mugabe</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> arranged several indirect, low-level meetings last year
aimed at bringing the two sides to the negotiating table.
   Earlier today, a spokesman for the guerrillas in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, denied that <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> would hold talks in <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>.
   ``We are prepared to meet anytime, anywhere, except <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>,''
<PERSON>Manuel Frank</PERSON> told the independent TSF radio station in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>.
   RENAMO had said it would prefer talks in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>,
which ruled <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> until <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   The war has claimed an estimated 600,000 lives and turned the
southeast African nation into one of the poorest countries in the
world. Almost half of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s 15 million people require food
assistance and the annual per capita income is less than <MONEY>$200</MONEY>.
   The rebels are active throughout <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, waging hit-and-run
attacks on both military and civilian targets. They have been
   No government acknowledges supporting the rebels, although <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION> openly backed them in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, and the
white-minority government of <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION> helped them until it became
black-ruled <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>.
   The rebels have demanded recognition by the government and free
elections in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, but their political aims have never been
clear.
   Chissano's government officially dropped its Marxist label last
year and has moved away from its socialist-oriented economy toward
a more market-oriented system in recent years.
   The government has proposed a new constitution to allow
elections in which independents could challenge candidates from
<PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>'s ruling party, the Front for the Liberation of
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>. However, the government has refused to allow opposition
parties.
   The government receives most of its military aid from the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION>, but it also has developed good relations with the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in
recent years. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is the leading donor of food aid in
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861209-0141 </DOCNO>
<HL> 

By Roger Thurow
<DD> 12/09/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> AFRIC
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON) </IN>
<TEXT>
   From <ORGANIZATION>Casa Banana</ORGANIZATION>, his headquarters deep in the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> bush, guerrilla leader <PERSON>Afonso Dhlakama</PERSON> has become one of the key players in the international sanctions war against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Dhlakama</PERSON>, the 33-year-old leader of the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION>, or <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>, is a chubby, bespectacled man who gave up his accounting studies for guerrilla warfare more than a decade ago. 
He and his 22,000 rebels are fighting to overthrow <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s tottering Marxist government, which has been further weakened by the recent death of its first president, <ORGANIZATION>Samora Machel</ORGANIZATION>. 

   But <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> also is engaged in a broader struggle against all of black southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> that is interfering with international sanctions meant to seal off <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. 

   Claiming that it is a black nationalist movement that has no sympathy for the white minority government in <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> denies that it receives military aid from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. 
But the fact that <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>'s actions play into <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>'s hands, as well as a history of South African contacts with the guerrillas, have much of the world believing otherwise. 

   Renamo controls most of the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> countryside, and has been able almost at will to attack the oil pipeline, railway, roads and Indian Ocean port that make up the <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> Corridor. 
Were it free from guerrilla attack, the <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> Corridor could provide black southern African countries with an alternative to the present practice of moving the bulk of their trade through <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. 
So important is this route in isolating <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> that the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and several European countries have considered coupling their own sanctions against <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION> with an aid package to upgrade the carrying capacity of the corridor and keep <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> open. 

   A stable and upgraded <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> Corridor would enable the so-called frontline states, <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, to reduce their dependence on <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and impose economic sanctions on <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>. 
But if <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> continues to blow up the pipeline and railway and hijack trucks, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> will retain its intimidating position. 

   "Renamo can render the <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> Corridor so insecure that it won't function," says <PERSON>Andre Thomashausen</PERSON>, a law professor and <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> analyst at the <ORGANIZATION>University of South Africa</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION>. 

   And without a functioning <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> Corridor, the black states of southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> are trapped. 
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, which has been making the loudest noises about imposing sanctions against <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION> and would be the hardest hit by any countersanctions, has recently been forced to turn to <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> for tons of fuel because of supply disruptions in the <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> Corridor. 
About <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s foreign trade passes through <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>; it is about <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> for <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>. 

   Despite the advantages for <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> of continued <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> successes, <LOCATION>Pretoria</LOCATION> stridently denies that it aids the rebels. 
Indeed, it says it wants to improve economic ties with the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> government, now headed by <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON>. 
Besides, says a Foreign Ministry official, "<ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> isn't hard up for financial help. 
It has a hard time using up what it has." 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION> initially was nurtured by security forces in neighboring white-ruled <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION>. 
But when black rule came to <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION> (now <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>), <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> became the main supplier of arms and training, Western diplomats say. 
On occasion, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s deputy foreign minister flew to the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> bush to meet with the rebels. 

   In early <DATE>1984</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>South Africa</ORGANIZATION> signed an accord with <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> promising to halt its support to the rebels. 
While <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> offices in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> were closed, the suspicion of continued aid to the rebels hasn't diminished. 
President <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> last week accused <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> of airdropping supplies to <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Today, diplomats and analysts of the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> war say, <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> is so strong, compared with the ragged government troops, that it could continue its fight without outside aid. 
In recent months, the rebels have captured several cities in the north and made occasional forays into <LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION>, the capital. 
Last year one siege of <LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION> was so tight that President <PERSON>Machel</PERSON> slept at night on a yacht several miles offshore, according to press reports. 

   Because of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s economic crisis, government soldiers are poorly clothed and fed and, despite the assistance of Soviet bloc advisers, badly trained. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> guerrillas are also badly clothed, but they feed off the land, which they control, and they claim to have captured big reserves of Soviet-made arms from government troops. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Dhlakama</PERSON>, who was educated in a Roman Catholic missionary school, says he wants free elections in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and respect for human rights. 
But, despite such talk, and the stories about <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> soldiers carrying Bibles, the rebels have a reputation for banditry. 
The government says <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>'s tactics include random attacks on civilian buses, kidnapping and cutting off the noses and ears of peasants who cooperate with the government or resist joining the rebels. 

   Renamo charges the government with religious persecution and with imprisoning opponents in "reeducation camps." 
One way <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> built up its support initially was by running a radio service that informed people about government prisoners. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Dhlakama</PERSON>, the son of a tribal chief, talks about victory within two years. 
"Militarily, <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> could win the war. 
It could storm the presidential palace," says <PERSON>Mr. Thomashausen</PERSON>. 
"But it won't unless it has a strategy for the day after." 

   So far, such a strategy hasn't emerged. 
<PERSON>Mr. Dhlakama</PERSON> is said to be interested in pushing for a reconciliation with the government because he realizes there isn't enough expertise within <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> to run a government by itself. 
And without a reconciliation, the government troops might take to the bush and continue the war. 

   Sources say <PERSON>Mr. Dhlakama</PERSON> also realizes that governing the country would be nearly impossible without international support, which has so far been denied because of his group's ties to <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and because the international community recognizes the government. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Dhlakama</PERSON> is said to be jealous of <PERSON>Jonas Savimbi</PERSON>, the high-profile leader of the anti-communist guerrillas in <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> who is received by leaders around the world. 
As a result, <PERSON>Mr. Dhlakama</PERSON> is trying to spruce up his image: his eyeglasses, worn to make him look older, are said to be only window glass, and he is studying English and listening to the <ORGANIZATION>Voice of America</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>British Broadcasting Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890729-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-29-89 0513EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Zimbabwe-Mozambique     07-29 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Zimbabwe-Mozambique,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zimbabwe Leader Says Peace Talks With Mozambique Rebels On Track</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANGUS SHAW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Robert Mugabe</PERSON> says he will
consult with President <PERSON>Daniel arap Moi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> in the next few
days to prepare the way for peace talks between warring sides in
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
   The African leaders are negotiating to end a 12-year war that
has cost hundreds of thousands of lives and made half of
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s 14.7 million people wholly or partly dependent on food
aid.
   <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> said he expects to contact Moi ``in the next few days''
to arrange preliminary talks with officials of the rebel <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique
National Resistance</ORGANIZATION>, also known by the Portuguese acronym <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>.
   The peace initiative, headed by <PERSON>Moi</PERSON>, aims at bringing the
guerrillas to a conference table with representatives of President
<PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON>'s Marxist-oriented government, <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> said.
   ``We are looking forward to cooperation by <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>, as much
cooperation as possible,'' he told reporters <DATE>Friday</DATE>, a day after
his return from an <ORGANIZATION>Organization of African Unity</ORGANIZATION> summit in <LOCATION>Addis
Ababa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>.
   ``We hope eventually there will be direct contact between the
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> government and <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>. It is these two parties that must
negotiate a settlement to their problems,'' he said.
   Mozambican rebels have been fighting for 12 years to oust the
<LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION> government and are accused of widespread atrocities. They
are considered right-wing because they used to be armed by <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>, but their political goals are unclear.
   <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> said <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> asked him on <DATE>July 10</DATE> to join <PERSON>Moi</PERSON> as a
mediator to end the fighting that, coupled with mismanagement and a
weak infrastructure inherited from Portuguese colonizers, has
placed <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> among the world's poorest nations.
   Mugabe met with Moi at the African summit and the two agreed to
``draft parameters on the way we hope to operate'' and compare
notes soon afterward, <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> said.
   He said a meeting with Mozambican rebel officials will follow,
but gave no details.
   Landlocked <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> has 12,000 troops fighting alongside
Mozambican government forces and guarding transport links and an
oil pipeline through <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> to the Indian Ocean.
   The proposed rapprochement follows a U.S.-brokered peace accord
for southern African involving independence for <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION> and the
withdrawal of South African and Cuban troops in <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>.
   Until the <DATE>June 22</DATE> cease-fire between <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>'s government and
<PERSON>Jonas Savimbi</PERSON>'s U.S.-backed rebels, <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> opposed similar
negotiations in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
   At first, the Mozambican rebels rejected <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> as too partisan
to mediate. But earlier this month they accepted his role in the
peace initiative.
   Chissano's government is debating negotiations with the rebels
at the annual congress of its ruling Front for the Liberation of
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, the country's sole legal political party.
   The congress <DATE>Friday</DATE> presented a new policy document that drops
all references to Marxism, Leninism and Western imperialism. But it
says the party remains committed to socialism.
   The alterations coincide with a new government drive to end
central control of the economy and reflects <ORGANIZATION>Maptuo</ORGANIZATION>'s improving
and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880916-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-16-88 1633EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pope 1stLd-Writethru   09-16 0710</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0686,0727</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Calls For Peace And Reconciliation In War-Torn Mozambique</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 3rd graf, ``The efforts...' to ADD proportion of
Catholics.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NBN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS REDMONT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MAPUTO, Mozambique (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> urged the Marxist
government <DATE>Friday</DATE> to make peace with guerrillas and offered to let
the church mediate in this war-torn country, where 6 million people
live on the edge of famine.
   ``In the face of this lamentable situation, when the opportunity
arose, I have never ceased to repeat, `No to violence and yes to
peace,''' the pontiff told President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON> after
arriving from neighboring <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION>.
   ``The efforts of my brother bishops in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> have always
received my backing,'' <PERSON>John Paul told Chissano</PERSON>, who was baptized a
Roman Catholic but now is non-practicing. About one-eighth of
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s 11.7 million people are Catholic.
   The bishops have been urging <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>'s government to start
negotiations with anti-Marxist rebels of the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National
Resistance</ORGANIZATION>, known by their Portuguese acronym, <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>. The
government has refused to negotiate and has criticized the bishops
for advocating talk with ``armed bandits.''
   ``The weapons we are still obliged to carry are used exclusively
to defend our country's freedom and our nation,'' <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> told the
pope at the <ORGANIZATION>Ponte Vermelha</ORGANIZATION> (Red Point) palace, built by the
Portuguese colonialists before <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> became independent in
<DATE>1975</DATE>.
   ``Your holiness proclaims the path of peace and denounces the
paths of hatred, the trade of war, the murder of innocents and the
inadmissable methods of terrorism,'' <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said.
   The 11-year-old civil war in this southeast African country has
forced about 1 million Mozambicans to flee into neighboring
countries. Nearly half <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s 14.5 million people are in need
of food aid, according to relief organizations.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> is the final stop on the pope's 10-day tour of
southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. In addition to <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION>, he also has visited
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Lesotho</LOCATION> and made a brief unscheduled stop in
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> after his plane was diverted in bad
weather.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> guerrillas, believed to number between 12,000 and
22,000, roam the countryside almost at will and have caused
tremendous econonic damage.
   No government acknowledges assisting the rebels, who have been
accused of widespread civilian atrocities. <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> denies the
charges.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. State Department</ORGANIZATION>, in a report released in <DATE>April</DATE>,
estimated the rebels killed 100,000 civilians in the past two to
three years.
   <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> this week announced a cease-fire during the pope's visit
and wished the pontiff a good stay. Still, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> announced
extensive security measures for the pope and the pilgrims traveling
to see him at stops in <LOCATION>Nampula</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION>, the capital.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> receives most of its military assistance from the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> but increasingly has been making overtures to Western
nations. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is the largest donor of food aid in
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> has been providing military training.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> also has been working to improve relations with
neighboring <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, which has backed <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> in the past.
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> says it stopped supporting the guerrillas under terms
of a <DATE>1984</DATE> mutual non-aggression pact, but <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> has continued
to accuse <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> of providing assistance.
   Mozambique regularly refers to <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> as the ``racist
regime,'' but on <DATE>Monday</DATE> Chissano hosted South African President
<PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON> on his first summit meeting in a black-ruled African
nation.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> has tried to prod the peace process in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> by
sending one of <PERSON>John Paul</PERSON>'s top cardinal aides to meet separately
with <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> and <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> in <DATE>July</DATE>. Also, some Mozambican bishops
reportedly have maintained contacts with <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>.
   Chissano met the pope in <DATE>May</DATE> in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, but the Vactican appears
incentive to move the peace process ahead.
   In <LOCATION>Mbabane</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION>, earlier <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the pope preached about
the virtues of monogamy at a Mass attended by <LOCATION>Swaziland</LOCATION>'s
20-year-old king and his four wives.
   King <PERSON>Mswati III</PERSON>, the world's youngest monarch, sat
expressionless as the pope told a crowd of 10,000 at the capital's
national stadium that God intended each husband to have one wife.
   The pope, who arrived at the stadium in his popemobile escorted
by spear-carrying warriors, spoke from an altar topped by a turret
manned by a soldier with a rifle and binoculars.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47888 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drafr087_d_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-AFR-94-087 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  5 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SOUTHERN AFRICA </F>
<F P=101> Mozambique </F>
<H3> <TI>   Chissano Announces Suspension of Demobilization </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Chissano Announces Suspension of Demobilization </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   MB0505111294 Maputo Radio Mozambique Network in Portuguese 
1030 GMT 5 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> MB0505111294 </F>
<F P=104>  Maputo Radio Mozambique Network </F>
<F P=105>  Portuguese </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Speaking in <LOCATION>Tete Province</LOCATION> yesterday, President of 
the Republic <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON> announced that the government has 
decided to temporarily suspend its troop demobilization process. 
As a reason for such a decision, the Mozambican head of state 
said that the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION>'s [<ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>] troop 
demobilization process had not been balanced. He also noted the 
need for making technical corrections to the figures and lists 
that <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> has been supplying to the <ORGANIZATION>UN Operations</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> Technical Unit. 
  NOTICIAS reports that President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON> made that 
announcement after visiting the troop assembly area in <LOCATION>Ulongwe</LOCATION>, 
the capital of <ORGANIZATION>Tete Province</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Angonia District</ORGANIZATION>. NOTICIAS also 
reports that the Mozambican head of state warned the soldiers of 
the need for them to remain in the area for a while longer. He 
explained that it is an area that continues to deserve special 
attention. NOTICIAS says President <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> was indirectly 
referring to the fact that <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> soldiers continue to be 
powerfully armed and terrorizing the civilian population in many 
parts of <ORGANIZATION>Tete Province</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The president of the <ORGANIZATION>Republic</ORGANIZATION> traveled 260 km on the road 
between the city of <ORGANIZATION>Tete</ORGANIZATION>, the provincial capital, and <ORGANIZATION>Angonia 
District</ORGANIZATION>. He passed many areas where <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> continues to 
prevent the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambican Government</ORGANIZATION> from implementing the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Reconstruction Program</ORGANIZATION> and other political organizations from 
doing their political work. 
  NOTICIAS also reports today that a South African citizen was 
distributing photographs of <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> leader <PERSON>Afonso Dhlakama</PERSON> in one 
of the areas visited by the Mozambican head on his way to 
<ORGANIZATION>Angonia District</ORGANIZATION>. That South African citizen had not been 
allowed to come into the country from <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>, but was 
subsequently seen in Mozambican territory. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900315-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-15-90 1245EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Mozambique     03-15 0463</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Mozambique,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Says He's Ready for Talks with Rebels</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON> said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> his government is willing to start talks within several
weeks with the <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> rebels on ending the country's 10-year civil
war.
   <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said he was awaiting an answer from the rebels through
mediators who have been trying to bring the sides together. He
praised the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> for a seven-point proposal it presented
both sides last year to help them overcome their reluctance to
negotiate.
   ``We feel we can now go into talks,'' <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> told reporters at
a news conference summing up three days of talks with President
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, top officials of his administration and congressional leaders.
   ``If <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> gives us a quick answer, we are ready to start,'' he
added. Negotiations could begin as soon as Chissano returns from
next week's ceremonies marking the independence of neighboring
<LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, he said.
   RENAMO had been reluctant to accept one of the points that deals
with recognition of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s government and its constitution,
<PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said. But now, the rebels appear willing to recognize the
government and recognition of the constitution can be worked out
during the actual peace talks, he said.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, which in recent years has renounced its Marxist
doctrine and shifted to a market-oriented economy, is drafting a
constitution that would allow independent candidates to run in
elections, he said. Individuals from <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> would be eligible to
participate, <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said.
   The people of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> will also vote this <DATE>summer</DATE> on a
proposal to allow more than one political party. If that happens,
<ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> could compete in elections, he said.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> has been devastated by the fighting with <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>,
founded in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> by white <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION> to counter the
government's support for the guerrillas of the <ORGANIZATION>African National
Congress</ORGANIZATION>. The group has been accused by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials and human
rights monitors of savage attacks on innocent civilians.
   <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said he was satisfied that the South African government
of <ORGANIZATION>F.W. de Klerk</ORGANIZATION> had stopped all assistance to <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>. He said
South African authorities were cooperating with his government to
stop aid for the rebels from inidividuals in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. The
organization also has wealthy right-wing backers in <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   While praising de Klerk for progress he has made toward starting
talks with his country's black majority about the future of
apartheid, <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> also urged the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to maintain its
economic sanctions against <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> ``until everyone is sure
the process is irreversible.''
   <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said he had asked <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> for additional financial help to
rehabilitate his country and help an estimated 5.6 million refugees
and handicapped people. <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> receives more than <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>
annually from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, making it the largest aid
recipient in <LOCATION>sub-Saharan Africa</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880307-0220 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-88 1419EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-MozambiqueWar-Zimbabwe Adv13   03-07 0969</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Mozambique War-Zimbabwe, Adv 13,0997</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv13</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, March 13, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Zimbabwe's Troops Help Mozambique in Guerrilla War</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds, separate editor's note is b0570 and companion story is
BC-Mozambique War-Malawi, b0571</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN EDLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MUTARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A decade ago, thousands of guerrillas
flooded across the border from <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> to mount a final assault
against the white-minority government in what then was call
<LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION>.
   Today, eight years after <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION> became black-governed
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, battalions of troops, including guerrilla veterans of
that independence war, are strung along the same border _ this time
to block a new wave of incursions by guerrillas fighting to
overthrow <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s government.
   The outcome of the guerrillas' strikes in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and inside
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> will have a major impact on the fragile economies of the
troubled region in southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.
   Several black-ruled states are striving to divert their trade
traffic from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Indian Ocean</LOCATION> ports in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, a
former Portuguese colony, in a bid to loosen their economic
dependency on the <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION>.
   The rebels, in turn, vow to continue sabotaging <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s
supply lines that also serve <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zaire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>.
   So far, the 12,000 to 20,000 guerrillas of the anti-government
<ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION> seem unharried by the conventional
forces ranged against them in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> _ some 30,000
Mozambican regulars, more than 12,000 Zimbabweans, 2,000 Tanzanians
and a few hundred Malawians.
   The guerrillas, who call themselves nationalists opposing a
Marxist-based government, roam <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s 10 provinces and mount
frequent raids into <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> with virtual impunity.
   ``It's very strange being on the other side,'' said a young
Zimbabwean corporal who fought the Rhodesians under the name
<ORGANIZATION>Comrade Hammer</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We know from our experience it's hard to beat guerrillas. But
these people are just bandits and at least we know exactly how they
think and what they might do next.''
   The guerrillas, known by the Portuguese acronym <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>,
originally were formed by the Rhodesian intelligence service in
<DATE>1977</DATE>, two years after <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s independence from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, to
harass nationalist guerrillas directed by <PERSON>Robert Mugabe</PERSON> from inside
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> during <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s 1973-79 independence war.
   Mugabe became <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s prime minister at independence from
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>April 1980</DATE> and cut support to the Mozambican rebels. But
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> took over the reins until <DATE>1984</DATE> when it signed a
non-aggression pact with <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>. Since then, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> claims
South African support has continued, a charge denied by the South
African government.
   The Mozambican rebels declared war on <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> after
<PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> vowed that a quarter of his forces stationed in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>
would fight to keep its government in power.
   Since then they have stepped up raids along the 750-mile
frontier of forested mountains and scrub-dotted plains.
   Rebels have killed scores of villagers and some security-force
militias. They have abducted hundreds of civilians, including
children, and marched them at gunpoint into <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, apparently
as dragooned recruits.
   They also have destroyed government schools, clinics and
development projects; robbed country stores and remote homesteads
of food, drink and clothing; ambushed buses and looted passengers;
ordered workers to leave forestry estates, coffee plantations and
orchards; rustled cattle, sheep and goats.
   <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> has exhorted his troops ``to erect an impassable defense
along our border'' to prevent fresh incursions.
   He also urged them to renew military efforts inside <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>
``to completely deny the enemy any ... chance to sabotage our
arteries to the sea.''
   Lt. Col. <PERSON>Solomon Mujuru</PERSON>, a wartime guerrilla chieftain and now
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s army commander, called on civilians living along the
frontier to report people they suspect might have links to the
guerrillas.
   But <PERSON>Mujuru</PERSON> said Zimbabwean troops had gained the upper hand in
counterinsurgency operations since the first major incursions eight
months ago.
   Before <DATE>June</DATE>, <PERSON>Mujuru</PERSON>'s soldiers and the rebels clashed only in
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
   Since then, troops of <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s new 5,000-member 6th Brigade
have reinforced border defenses, militias are guarding farms,
villages, schools and clinics and cross-border movement has been
banned except at established immigration posts.
   Anti-personnel mines have been sown where guerrillas are thought
to cross into <PERSON>Zimbabwqe</PERSON> and the identification papers of some
65,000 Mozambican refugees in three camps are being screened by
local authorities and the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations High Commission</ORGANIZATION> for
Refugees.
   In addition, courts have cracked down on local peasants
suspected of links to the insurgents. Early in <DATE>February</DATE>, a <LOCATION>Mutare</LOCATION>
judge sent a woman to prison for six years and a man for five years
for failing to report the presence of bandits to officials.
   At stake in the conflict is not only the survival of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>,
its economy already in ruins as a result of fighting and famine.
   Also at issue is the fate of the so-called <LOCATION>Beira Corridor</LOCATION>, a
186-mile trade route that meanders through mountains, fertile
valleys and swamps from the Zimbabwean border city to the <LOCATION>Indian
Ocean</LOCATION> port of <LOCATION>Beira</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
   A fifth of the overseas trade of the black-ruled neighbor states
flows along the corridor's railroads and highways. Landlocked
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> receives most of its fuel suppliers from a corridor
pipeline despite repeated sabotage by the guerrillas. Most of that
trade and oil previously went through <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
rejected suggestions that they hold peace talks with the
guerrillas, arguing that the rebels are puppets of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s
government and have no support from either the East or the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   Mugabe, at the graduation ceremony for the 6th Brigade in
<DATE>September</DATE>, said he was forced to form the unit because of what he
called South African destabilization in the region.
   ``<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s subversion of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s ... sovereignity had
the potential to completely deny us any routes to the sea,'' <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON>
said.
   ``The survival of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> is our survival,'' <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON> said.
``The fall of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> certainly also will be our <DATE>fall</DATE>.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, March 13</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900614-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-14-90 1221EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Mozambique     06-14 0321</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mozambique,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mozambique, Rebels Postpone Direct Peace Talks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BLANTYRE, Malawi (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first direct peace talks between
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s government and right-wing rebels have been postponed.
   A communique <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by officials of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s leftist
government and mediating countries said the talks did not begin as
scheduled <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>, which borders the troubled southeast
African nation.
   The discussions were to include Mozambican Cabinet ministers and
<PERSON>Alfonso Dhlakama</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION>
guerrilla army, known by its Portuguese acronym <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION>.
   The communique said without elaboration that the talks were
postponed because of ``difficulties experienced by the <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> delegations.''
   ``Efforts are continuing to set a new date in the near future
for the process to begin in <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION>,'' said the statement, published
by the official <ORGANIZATION>Malawi News Agency</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Mana</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> has been fighting for control of the territory for 13
years and opposes the one-party rule of President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON>.
The war has left hundreds of thousands of people dead, mostly
civilians.
   The <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> national news agency, AIM, had reported from
<LOCATION>Blantyre</LOCATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that Mozambican Cabinet ministers and the
leader of the guerrillas had gathered in the city for the talks.
But <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> did not sign <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s communique. The host government
for several days declined to grant visas for Western correspondents
seeking to report on the meeting.
   <ORGANIZATION>Renamo</ORGANIZATION> has opposed <LOCATION>Malawi</LOCATION> as a venue, favoring either <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> or
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s former colonial ruler that granted
independence in <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   Malawian officials, contacted by telephone from the Zimbabwean
capital, <LOCATION>Harare</LOCATION>, said they were not authorized to discuss the
aborted meeting beyond what was published in the communique.
   The <LOCATION>Blantyre</LOCATION> talks were expected to focus on President
<PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>'s proposals for a new constitution to allow independents
elections.
   But <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> has rejected demands for the creation of opposition
parties.
   <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> have for several months brokered low-level
peace talks.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900313-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-13-90 1454EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Mozambique 3rdLd-Writethru a0574 03-13 0682</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Mozambique, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0574,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Calls for Early Negotiations to End Mozambique's Civil War</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Combines pvs</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, trying his hand at African
peacemaking, called today for early negotiations to end
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s 10-year civil war.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> issued the plea after talks with <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON>, the
president of the former Marxist state.
   At a departure ceremony after talks in the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> and over
lunch, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>'s government has taken ``significant
steps to heal divisions which threaten your nation. And we urge all
parties to talk at the earliest opportunity so as to avoid further
suffering.''
   He praised <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> for strengthing ties with the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
and adopting reforms on voting, property rights and religious
freedoms, but said more needs to be done.
   ``We look forward to even further reforms,'' the president said.
``So we talked today of common concerns like refugee issues and
<LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s humanitarian concerns _ the crisis in humanitarian
concerns, I might add.''
   <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said he assured <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> that his government was ready to
enter into direct talks with rebel forces as soon as possible. He
also said he expressed appreciation ``for the stand the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> has taken on the war in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and for the positive role
it has been playing in the peace process.''
   Chissano appeared taken aback by the crush of television cameras
on hand to witness the start of his <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> visit.
   As the crews pushed their long boom microphones toward his face,
<PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> asked, ``What do you do with all these photos? It's too
many.''
   The media people were ushered out as <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>, seated
in wingback chairs by the fireplace, began their talks in private.
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> official who briefed reporters about today's visit said
the government of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> rebels were nearing
agreement on starting peace talks.
   ``I believe they're in a pre-negotiating stage right now to
determine the framework for their talks. And we're hoping that they
will take the final step to get together,'' said the official, who
spoke <DATE>Monday</DATE> on condition of anonymity.
   RENAMO, an organization vilified by human rights groups for its
brutality in the civil war, has been demanding that the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>
government abandon Marxism-Leninism and establish a multiparty
system.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, which gained independence from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> in <DATE>1975</DATE>, has
dropped its Marxist ideology and turned to private enterprise and a
free-market economy in recent years. As a reward, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> recently
struck the country from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> list of Marxist states, opening
the way for lending and trade concessions.
   ``It is our belief that because so many of <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>'s demands have
been met already, it should not be too difficult to enter into a
negotiated settlement in the near future,'' said the official.
   Attempts at getting the two sides to stop their war began last
year, with the presidents of <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> mediating.
Assistant Secretary of State <PERSON>Herman Cohen</PERSON> and other <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials
also have been trying to help.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> reportedly has a seven-point plan that would
meet both sides' preconditions for talks.
   ``We have been acting as a facilitator. And we will be wanting
to consult with President <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> at this time to see what more we
can do to help the start of direct negotiations,'' said the
official.
   The war has been a costly one. An estimated 3.2 million
Mozambicans have been driven from their homes, either to internal
or external exile. The international community has had to give
Mozambique <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> to buy food every year.
   Created originally by the white South African government to
counter the Mozambican government's support for the <ORGANIZATION>African
National Congress</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> has in recent months lost much of its
ideological and financial support.
   When President <ORGANIZATION>F.W. de Klerk</ORGANIZATION> came to power in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> <DATE>last
year</DATE>, he stopped assistance to <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>. He since has dropped the ban
on <ORGANIZATION>ANC</ORGANIZATION> and has made overtures to its leadership designed to lead to
talks about the future of the apartheid racial discrimination
system.
   RENAMO still gets money from sympathizers in <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881122-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-22-88 1336EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mozambique     11-22 0487</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mozambique,0504</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report Mozambique Allowing Churchmen to Talk to Rebels</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN EDLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marxist <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> has decided for the
first time to allow talks with right-wing rebels in a bid to bring
peace to the former Portuguese colony, a church leader said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The Rev. <PERSON>Filipe Sigue Banze</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique United Methodist
Church</ORGANIZATION> told reporters that a mediation committee of church leaders
has been set up with the blessing of the <LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION> government to
contact the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION>.
   The resistance group, also known by its Portuguese acronym
<ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>, has been blamed for widespread atrocities, making hundreds
of thousands of people homeless and forcing tens of thousands more
into exile.
   Guerrillas who have been fighting for control of the southeast
African territory for a decade, control most of the countryside and
make it dangerous for civilians to venture out of the capital,
<LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION>.
   ``The government believes that since the churches represent many
of the people it is for the churches to establish dialogue with the
destabilizers of the region,'' <PERSON>Banze</PERSON> told a news conference.
   There was no immediate comment from the <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> government.
Until now, President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON>'s government had refused to
allow any dialogue with the rebels, arguing they are terrorists on
the payroll of neighboring <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   In recent talks with <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>, South African President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON>
pledged that all support for the rebels had stopped.
   Banze said the Peace and <ORGANIZATION>Reconciliation Committee</ORGANIZATION> was established
by the 17-member <ORGANIZATION>General Christian Council of Mozambique</ORGANIZATION> under the
leadership of Anglican Bishop <PERSON>Denis Sengulane</PERSON>.
   Committee members first met Chissano in <DATE>August</DATE> and got specific
instructions to seek direct talks with the rebels, he said.
   ``We the leaders of the church believe we can carry out that
role,'' <PERSON>Banze</PERSON> said. The first problem is finding the leaders, who
are scattered throughout <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, he said.
   Banze said the committee hoped to report progress in peace
efforts at a meeting with <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> next month.
   ``We do not know what the atmosphere will be like,'' the cleric
said. ``If it is favorable on the one side we will then speak to the
other side. We have to take it as it comes.''
   Ultimately, <PERSON>Banze</PERSON> said, the committee hoped to get the government
and the guerrillas to talk to each other.
   Banze was among 150 church leaders and human rights activists at
a five-day <ORGANIZATION>World Council of Churches</ORGANIZATION> conference in <LOCATION>Harare</LOCATION> on South
African destabilization in the region.
   The guerrrila group was created by the intelligence services of
the Rhodesian government in <DATE>1977</DATE> to harass black nationalist
guerrillas who used <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> as a launching pad for offensives
into <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>General Christian Council of Mozambique</ORGANIZATION> does not include the
<ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>, the largest Christian denomination in the
country with about 2 million adherents out of the 15 million people.
Half of Mozambicans adhere to traditional animist beliefs and about
<PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> are Moslem.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900711-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-11-90 1023EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Mozambique 1stLd-Writethru   07-11 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mozambique, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0516,0674</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mozambique and Its Rebels Hold First Direct Peace Talks</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to CORRECT that government leftist, sted Marxist,
and UPDATE with background on the insurgency's goal and cost in
lives. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By FRANCES D'EMILIO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Negotiators for <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s leftist government and
the nation's rebels held their first direct peace talks this week
and said <DATE>today</DATE> they would try to end the 13-year-old insurgency.
   The talks, involving the rebels' No. 2 leader and a government
minister, could lead to a cease-fire by the end of the year, said
<PERSON>Mario Raffaelli</PERSON>, a parliamentary deputy who monitored the talks for
the Italian government.
   Both sides met <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <DATE>Monday</DATE> and <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>
headquarters of <ORGANIZATION>San Egidio Community</ORGANIZATION>, a religious organization that
aids poor immigrants in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, and which also observed the talks.
   The negotiations were not announced ahead of time and were held
privately.
   An estimated 600,000 people, mostly civilians, have died in the
war in the southeast African nation. The rebels have been accused
of widespread civilian atrocities by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. State Department</ORGANIZATION> and
others.
   The war has left <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> one of the poorest countries in the
world. Annual per capita income is about <MONEY>$200</MONEY> and almost half the
15 million people require some level of food aid.
   Leading the Mozambican government delegation in the talks was
<PERSON>Armando Gebuza</PERSON>, minister of transport and communication. Raul
Domingos, No. 2 official for <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>, as the rebels are known,
headed the other delegation.
   ``We could be optimistic'' about the possibility for a
cease-fire, <PERSON>Raffaelli</PERSON> said. ``I think it's realistic that there
could be one by the end of this year, maybe in time for
Christmas,'' said <PERSON>Raffaelli</PERSON>, a Socialist who formerly was the
<ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>'s undersecretary for <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Raffaelli</PERSON> said both sides would meet again in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> ``as soon as
possible,'' probably within several weeks.
   RENAMO, the Portuguese acronym for the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambican National
Resistance</ORGANIZATION>, has been fighting a war against the government of the
country, which gained independence from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> in <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   ``Keeping in mind the greater interests of the Mozambican
nation, both sides have agreed on the necessity to put aside that
which divides them, and to concentrate, with priority, their
attention on that which unites them, toward creating a common
working base to realize, in a spirit of mutual comprehension, a
dialogue within which they can debate their different points of
view,'' said a communique signed by the two sides and released
<DATE>today</DATE>.
   Both sides said they were ready to commit themselves toward
``the search for a working platform to end the war and to create
political, economic and social conditions that will allow a lasting
peace and the normalization of life of all Mozambican citizens.''
   Before the peace talks this week, efforts by <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>
had failed to get both sides to the negotiation table.
   <PERSON>Raffaelli</PERSON> said both sides agreed a month ago to have the talks
held in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> was informed about the peace efforts but
was not directly involved, officials at the news conference said.
   Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> visited <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> in <DATE>September 1988</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> says its wants recognition as a political party and free
elections, but its political program has never been clear. No
government publicly supports the rebels, although <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>
openly backed them until it signed a mutual non-aggression pact
with <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s ruling <ORGANIZATION>Frelimo Party</ORGANIZATION> dropped its Marxist label last
year and has been liberalizing the economy and politics. The
government of President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON> is working toward a more
market-oriented economy and is considering a constitution that
would allow independents to run for parliament. however, it has not
come out in favor of allowing opposition parties.
   The Mozambican government still receives most of its weapons
from the Soviets, but it has developed increasingly close ties with
Western countries.
   Britain helps train government troops and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is
the leading food donor to <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900801-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-01-90 0717EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Mozambique     08-01 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mozambique,0451</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government To Allow Competing Parties</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MAPUTO, Mozambique (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Joaquim Chissano</PERSON> has
announced that, for the first time in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s history,
opposition parties will be allowed to compete for power.
   The move, reported <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by the national news agency AIM, was
considered a major concession that could help end the nation's
13-year-old civil war.
   The conflict has claimed about 100,000 lives, most of them
civilians.
   ``For those who want to form parties, as long as they obey the
law, as long as they behave peacefully, we have no right to prevent
them from doing so,'' AIM quoted <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> quoted as saying.
   <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> said the political bureau of the ruling <ORGANIZATION>FRELIMO</ORGANIZATION> party
had voted unanimously to adopt a multiparty system and that it
next year.
   FRELIMO has ruled <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> as the sole legal political party
since independence from <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> in <DATE>1975</DATE>. The party was Marxist,
but has undergone reforms in recent years and officially dropped
its Marxist label last year.
   Rebels of the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION> began their
insurgency in <DATE>1977</DATE>, and the war has made this southeast African
nation one of the poorest countries in the world.
   Almost half of <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s 15 million people require food aid.
capita income is under <MONEY>$200</MONEY>.
   The rebels, known by their Portuguese acronym, <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION>, demand a
multiparty system and free elections.
   The government and rebels held their first direct talks three
weeks ago in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>. No major breakthroughs emerged, but more talks
are considered likely.
   Asked if <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> could become a legal political party, <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>
said, ``I don't imagine that <ORGANIZATION>RENAMO</ORGANIZATION> will have any difficulty in
fulfilling the criteria.
   ``RENAMO knows the country, they have people in all the
provinces and districts. They have the possibility of creating a
base, though how big it would be, I don't know.''
   The rebels have no clear political program. They have devastated
the country with hit-and-run attacks and have been accused of
widespread civilian atrocities by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. State Department</ORGANIZATION> and
others.
   The government controls the major cities, but the rebels are
active throughout the country in rural areas.
   No government acknowledges supporting the rebels, although <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION> openly backed them before signing a <DATE>1984</DATE> mutual
non-aggression pact with <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> still receives most of its military help from the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>. But the government has developed close ties with the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and other Western countries in recent years.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> helps train the army and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is the
leading donor of food aid.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880427-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-27-88 0737EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Mozambique     04-27 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mozambique,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mozambique Blames Its Civil War On South Africa</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MAPUTO, Mozambique (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Joachim Chissano</PERSON> blamed
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> for <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s devastating civil war but sent an
emissary on a goodwill mission to the white-ruled nation, raising
the possibility of a summit meeting.
   Chissano spoke harshly of <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> at the opening of a
conference convened <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by his Marxist-oriented government and
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> to address <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s emergency relief needs
for the coming year.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> says 6 million of its 14.5 million people need
emergency food aid. It has appealed for 900 million tons of donated
food, as well as other assistance, with a total cost of <MONEY>$380
million</MONEY>.
   <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> attributes most of its problems to the insurgency
waged since <DATE>1977</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>Mozambique National Resistance</ORGANIZATION>, which it
says is backed by <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> in violation of a <DATE>1984</DATE>
non-aggression treaty.
   But as the conference began, <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON> dispatched Cooperation
Minister <PERSON>Jacinto Veloso</PERSON> with a conciliatory message for South
African President <PERSON>P.W. Botha</PERSON>. <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> said
<PERSON>Veloso</PERSON> met with <PERSON>Botha</PERSON>, conveyed <PERSON>Chissano</PERSON>'s interest in improving
relations and discussed a possible summit meeting between the two
leaders.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Foriegn Ministry</ORGANIZATION> quoted <PERSON>Botha</PERSON> as offering to promote
regional development and saying the two countries should stop
accusing each other of breaching the <DATE>1984</DATE> non-aggression accord.
   In the treaty, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> pledged to halt
assistance to insurgents fighting the other country's government.
   There is widespread international support for <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s claim
that South African security forces continue to provide logistical
aid to the Mozambican rebels despite the treaty.
   The conference in <LOCATION>Maputo</LOCATION> was attended by about 200 delegates
from <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> agencies, relief organizations and foreign governments.
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> delegate, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State <PERSON>Roy Stacey</PERSON>,
accused the Mozambican rebels of ``one of the most brutal
holocausts against ordinary human beings since World War II.''
   <PERSON>Stacey</PERSON> said the rebels' supporters, ``wherever they may be,
