<DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880601-0108 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Prism Entertainment Corp. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> PRZ WNEWS </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, said it signed a definitive merger agreement with closely held <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Entertainment Group</ORGANIZATION> that will give shareholders of <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> a <PERCENT>77%</PERCENT> stake in the combined companies. 

   Under the agreement, stockholders of <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> will receive 7.5 million shares of Prism common, or about <PERCENT>77%</PERCENT> of the then-outstanding stock of the merged companies. 
Prism will then effect a 1-for-2 reverse split of its common stock and pay a dividend of one share of Prism Class B common stock for each post-split common share outstanding. 
The Class B shares will have 10 votes each. 


   <PERSON>Thomas J. Coleman</PERSON>, chairman of <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, a motion picture distribution and television concern, will become chairman and chief executive officer of the merged company. 
<PERSON>Barry Collier</PERSON>, president and founder of Prism, a videocassette distributor, will become vice chairman and chief operating officer of the combined companies. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880715-0092 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Prism Entertainment Corp. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> PRZ </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<TEXT>
   A group including <ORGANIZATION>KuwAm Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, investment firm, and several of its directors said it acquired a <PERCENT>5.9%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s common shares outstanding. 


   According to the filing, the group acquired its stock in the Los Angeles-based videocassette distributor for investment purposes and may buy or sell shares in the future, depending on market conditions and other factors. 

   Prism said it viewed KuwAm's purchase as friendly and for investment purposes. 
In <DATE>May</DATE>, Prism signed a definitive merger agreement with <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Entertainment Group</ORGANIZATION>, a closely held <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> company, and the company said it doesn't believe the KuwAm stock acquisition was made to compete with that pact. 

   A lawyer for <ORGANIZATION>KuwAm Corp.</ORGANIZATION> didn't return a telephone call seeking comment. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880517-0048 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Prism Entertainment Corp. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> PRZ </CO>
<IN> TNM ERN </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it agreed in principle to be acquired by closely held <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Entertainment Group</ORGANIZATION>, in a stock transaction in which Prism will be the surviving company. 

   Terms weren't disclosed. 
Prism said the merged entity will remain public, but most of its shares will be owned by the current shareholders of <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, a movie company whose films include "<PERSON>Teen Wolf</PERSON>," "Extremities" and "Stormy <DATE>Monday</DATE>." 

   Prism, a Los Angeles-based videocassette distributor, also reported financial results for the year ended <DATE>Jan. 31</DATE>. 

   Prism said the merger agreement is subject to the arrangement of additional financing. 
The merger is also subject to approval of a definitive pact by the directors of Prism and <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, and to shareholder approval. 


</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880906-0033 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Prism Entertainment Corp. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> PRZ </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> said it terminated a proposed merger agreement with closely held <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Entertainment Group</ORGANIZATION> because <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> imposed "new conditions to the merger relating to financing." 

   Atlantic had asked Prism to approve additional financing, which it intended to use prior to completion of the transaction, Prism said. 
The financing was to have been partly secured by Prism, which "could have put us at risk if the transaction fell through," said a spokesman for Prism, a videocassette distributor. 

   <PERSON>Thomas J. Coleman</PERSON>, chairman and chief executive officer of <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> motion picture distribution and television concern, said the problem was that "the transaction was taking too long to close . . . and we had to restructure the deal." 
He said <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> secured the financing anyway, totaling more than <MONEY>$12.5 million</MONEY>, and that it is starting its own video distribution without Prism. 
Under the terminated agreement, <PERSON>Mr. Coleman</PERSON> was to have become chairman and chief executive of the merged companies. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880914-0139 </DOCNO>
<HL> Prism Entertainment Investor Group Lifts Common Stake to 8.4% </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> PRZ </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group including <ORGANIZATION>KuwAm Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, investment firm, and several of its directors, said it raised its stake in <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to <PERCENT>8.4%</PERCENT> of the common shares outstanding. 


   A spokesman for KuwAm said the stake is for investment purposes. 

   Prism Entertainment's president and chief executive officer, <PERSON>Barry Collier</PERSON>, said the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> videocassette company considers KuwAm to be a friendly holder of its stock. 

   In composite trading yesterday on the <ORGANIZATION>American Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, Prism shares closed at <MONEY>$3.25</MONEY>, up <MONEY>12.5 cents</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891004-0022 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891004 </DD>
<AN> 891004-0022. </AN>
<HL> Business Brief -- Prism Entertainment Corp.:
@  Special Situation Investment
@  Increases Its Stake to 11.9% </HL>
<DD> 10/04/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> PRZ </CO>
<IN> TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<TEXT>
   A group including <ORGANIZATION>Special Situation Investment Holdings Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, investment firm, said it raised its stake in <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to <PERCENT>11.9%</PERCENT> of the common shares outstanding. 


   No reason was given in the filing for the increase in the group's Prism holdings. 

   <ORGANIZATION>KuwAm Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, also of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, is the general partner of <ORGANIZATION>Special Situation Investment</ORGANIZATION>. 

   In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, Prism said Special Situation's investment is "strictly passive." 
Special Situation has been an investor in Prism for about two years, said <PERSON>Earl Rosenstein</PERSON>, Prism's senior vice president and chief financial officer. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880916-0050 </DOCNO>
<HL> Prism Entertainment Net Income Fell 92% In Fiscal 2nd Period </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> PRZ </CO>
<IN> ERN </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> reported a <PERCENT>92%</PERCENT> plunge in profit for the fiscal-second quarter ended <DATE>July 31</DATE>, citing a drop in videocassette sales to rental and retail outlets. 

   The entertainment concern said net income in the latest quarter totaled <MONEY>$36,000</MONEY>, or <MONEY>two cents</MONEY> a share, compared with <MONEY>$457,000</MONEY>, or <MONEY>21 cents</MONEY> a share a year earlier. 
The latest period results include <MONEY>$24,000</MONEY> of tax credits, compared with <MONEY>$94,000</MONEY> in the previous year. 
Sales slid <PERCENT>3.4%</PERCENT>, to <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$5.2 million</MONEY>. 

   Prism said video retailers continue to seek hit films from major studios, leaving fewer funds for the purchase of the "B" movies that Prism licenses. 

   <PERSON>Barry Collier</PERSON>, president and chief executive officer, cited cost reductions initiated last year, which he said enabled the company to report a slim profit despite lower sales and more than <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> in expenses related to a now-terminated merger agreement with <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Entertainment Group</ORGANIZATION>. 

   For the six months, net fell <PERCENT>56%</PERCENT>, to <MONEY>$438,000</MONEY>, or <MONEY>20 cents</MONEY> a share, from <MONEY>$988,000</MONEY>, or <MONEY>45 cents</MONEY> a share. 
The latest period included tax credits of <MONEY>$96,000</MONEY> compared with <MONEY>$106,000</MONEY> a year earlier. 
Revenue in the latest period dropped <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT>, to <MONEY>$10.1 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$11.5 million</MONEY>. 

   For the six-month period, <PERSON>Prism</PERSON> said sales of its <ORGANIZATION>Fox/Lorber Associates Inc.</ORGANIZATION> television-syndication unit rose more than <PERCENT>54%</PERCENT> but that the climb failed to offset a <PERCENT>29%</PERCENT> plunge in the company's basic business -- the sale of videocassettes to rental and "sell through" retail markets. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870420-0037 </DOCNO>
<HL> Prism Unit Set to Launch
Financial News TV Show</HL>
<DD> 04/20/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> PRZ FNNI DIS BITC
TELECOMMUNICATIONS, BROADCASTING, TELEPHONE, TELEGRAPH (TEL) </IN>
<DATELINE> LOS ANGELES  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s television distribution unit said it plans next <DATE>Monday</DATE> to launch a daily half-hour financial news program called "<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s Business." 

   Fox/Lorber <ORGANIZATION>Associates</ORGANIZATION>, the Prism unit, said it expects the syndicated show to fill a gap left by the cancellation this month of <ORGANIZATION>Walt Disney Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s "Today's Business." 
While <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> attributed its move to a soft advertising market, <PERSON>David M. Fox</PERSON>, chief executive officer of Fox/Lorber, said he believes the new program, which he hopes will be carried by about 80 stations, will succeed because of production costs "dramatically lower" than <ORGANIZATION>Disney's</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The Prism programming will be produced by a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Financial News Network</ORGANIZATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Fox</PERSON> said the programs will draw on the network's film footage and use production facilities and a staff already in place. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Financial News Network</ORGANIZATION> is a division of <ORGANIZATION>New York-based Biotech Capital Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Prism, in addition to its television distribution activities, makes and licenses videocassettes. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900914-0059
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900914-0059.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Who's News:
   Prism Entertainment Corp.
</HL>
<DATE>
09/14/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   WNEWS PRZ
</CO>
<IN>
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<LP>
   PRISM ENTERTAINMENT Corp. (Los Angeles) -- Barry Collier,
chairman, succeeding Paul Levinson, 48, who didn't stand for
reelection as a director. The company markets videocassettes
of theatrical and television films and other programs in the
U.S. and Canada.
</LP>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900206-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-06-90 0359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-People-DreamsSuit     02-06 0251</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-People-Dreams Suit,0258</SECOND>
<HEAD>Actor Kevin Costner, Universal File Suit Against Video Company</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Kevin Costner</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Universal Pictures
Inc.</ORGANIZATION> are suing a video company, saying it is trying to profit from
the hit movie ``Field of Dreams'' by marketing a film in which
<ORGANIZATION>Costner</ORGANIZATION> played a minor role.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> lawsuit says <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
has distributed a <DATE>1985</DATE> film, ``Chasing Dreams,'' in which <PERSON>Costner</PERSON>
played an ``extremely minor role.''
   The videocassette cover prominently displays <PERSON>Costner</PERSON>'s picture
and name, according to the lawsuit filed <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The lawsuit seeks an injunction barring ``misrepresentations''
in the marketing of ``Chasing Dreams,'' Prism's profits from the
videocassette, and unspecified punitive damages.
   ```Chasing Dreams' was neither critically acclaimed nor
financially successful,'' wrote plaintiffs' attorney <PERSON>Frank Rothman</PERSON>.
``It was shown only in approximately 40 movie theaters in the
midwestern <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.''
   Prism President <PERSON>Barry Collier</PERSON> declined comment, saying he had
not seen the lawsuit.
   In the hit ``Field of Dreams,'' <PERSON>Costner</PERSON> plays a farmer who
builds a baseball diamond in his corn field where ghost players,
including ``Shoeless'' <PERSON>Joe Jackson</PERSON> and other members of the <DATE>1919</DATE>
Chicago ``Black Sox'' come to play.
   Costner is shown on the cover of ``Chasing Dreams'' wearing a
baseball uniform but does not play a baseball player in the film,
according to the lawsuit.
   ``Field of Dreams'' has grossed <MONEY>$63 million</MONEY> since its release
<DATE>last year</DATE> but has yet to be released on videocassette, the lawsuit
says. Universal owns <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> distribution rights to the film.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920211-0058
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920211-0058.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Marketing Brief:
</HL>
<DATE>
02/11/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   PRZ TWX WNEWS
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
FILM, TELEVISION &amp; MUSIC INDUSTRIES (MOV)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY (REC)
</IN>
<NS>
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   LOW-BUDGET PICTURES: Barbara Javitz was named president of
Prism Pictures Corp., a new unit of Prism Entertainment Corp.
set up to develop, finance and co-produce up to 12 low-budget
pictures annually. Ms. Javitz, 38, was vice president at
Prism Entertainment, in charge of acquisitions. Prism, a home
video concern, plans to finance the pictures through existing
cash flow, bank lines of credit and outside companies, among
other sources.
                                                                                                       

</LP>
<TEXT>
   WHO'S NEWS: <PERSON>Dan Meyerson</PERSON>, 39, was named a vice president
of <ORGANIZATION>Time Life Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the book, music and video marketing unit
of <ORGANIZATION>Time Warner Inc</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Meyerson</PERSON>, whose appointment increases
the number of <ORGANIZATION>Time Life</ORGANIZATION> vice presidents to 11, will continue
to serve as president of <ORGANIZATION>Time-Life Libraries</ORGANIZATION>, the
telemarketing arm of <ORGANIZATION>Time Life Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021290-0074 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 175323 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 12, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 2; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
98 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IN COURT: A SUMMARY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA-RELATED BUSINESS LITIGATION 
DEVELOPMENTS DURING THE PAST WEEK. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From United Press International 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Costner Sues Video Firm: Actor <PERSON>Kevin Costner</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Universal Pictures Inc.</ORGANIZATION> filed 
suit in <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> charging a video firm with 
trying to profit from "Field of Dreams," a hit movie in which <PERSON>Costner</PERSON> starred. 
</P>
<P>
The suit said <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is distributing videocassettes of a 
<DATE>1985</DATE> film, "Chasing Dreams" in which <PERSON>Costner</PERSON> played a minor role, by linking it 
with "Field of Dreams." Costner and <ORGANIZATION>Universal</ORGANIZATION> seek to alter the marketing plan 
and collect profits from the sale of Prism's videocassette. (Filed <DATE>Feb. 5, 
1990</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Case No</ORGANIZATION>. CV 900580 WMB) 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Column; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
COSTNER, KEVIN; SUITS; UNIVERSAL PICTURES; FIELD OF DREAMS (MOTION PICTURE); 
PRISM ENTERTAINMENT CORP; MARKETING; VIDEO RECORDINGS; MOTION PICTURES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900410-0084
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900410-0084.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Savin Expecting
   To Post a Profit
   For 1st Quarter
   ----
   By Robert Daniels
</HL>
<DATE>
04/10/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A18
</SO>
<CO>
   SVB CLRX
</CO>
<LP>
   STAMFORD, Conn. -- Savin Corp. expects to report a profit
for the first quarter, compared with a year-earlier loss, as
it began to benefit from placements of its Prism I color
copier, said E.P. van den Boogaard, the copier marketer's new
chairman.
   Savin also announced a long-term supply accord with
Colorocs Corp., which designs the Prism I. And the company
also is still accepting and counting votes from holders of
common shares on four proposals. Savin had asked its
shareholders to, among other things, give the company more
flexibility when paying dividends and to let the company
award certain options.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   For the <DATE>first quarter</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Savin</ORGANIZATION> estimates pretax earnings of
<MONEY>$400,000</MONEY>, compared with a year-ago loss of <MONEY>$1.1 million</MONEY>.
Savin declined to disclose the after-tax number, but <PERSON>Mr.</PERSON> van
den <ORGANIZATION>Boogaard</ORGANIZATION> said it would be printed in black ink. A
year-earlier, <ORGANIZATION>Savin</ORGANIZATION> had a loss of <MONEY>$930,000</MONEY>, or <MONEY>three cents</MONEY> a
share.
   Savin estimated that revenue advanced <PERCENT>3.3%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$92 million</MONEY>
from <MONEY>$89 million</MONEY>. The first quarter is usually <ORGANIZATION>Savin</ORGANIZATION>'s
weakest, said <PERSON>Mr. van den Boogaard</PERSON>, who took the top post
late last month.
   Mr. van den <ORGANIZATION>Boogaard</ORGANIZATION>, 46 years old, also is president and
chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>HCS Technology N.V.</ORGANIZATION>, an <LOCATION>Amsterdam</LOCATION>
distributor of facsimile machines, copiers, and computer
hardware and software. <ORGANIZATION>HCS</ORGANIZATION> recently boosted its voting stake
in <LOCATION>Savin</LOCATION> to <PERCENT>55%</PERCENT> by buying the <ORGANIZATION>Savin</ORGANIZATION> holding of <ORGANIZATION>Colorocs Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
Mr. van den <ORGANIZATION>Boogaard</ORGANIZATION> took the chairman's post from <PERSON>Charles
Muench</PERSON>, president and chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Colorocs</ORGANIZATION>.
   At a special meeting last month, <ORGANIZATION>Savin</ORGANIZATION> presented eight
proposals to shareholders. Holders agreed to cut the par
value on the common and four classes of preferred stock; to
let <ORGANIZATION>Savin</ORGANIZATION> pay dividends on Series-A preferred in common
stock; to increase authorized Series-C shares; and to make
some changes in a stock-option plan.
   The special meeting was postponed to <DATE>March 29</DATE> and then to
<DATE>April 20</DATE> to allow common-share holders to continue to vote on
proposals to let <ORGANIZATION>Savin</ORGANIZATION> pay Series-C dividends with more
Series-C; to grant certain stock options; to grant an option
on three million Series-C shares to <ORGANIZATION>HCS</ORGANIZATION>; and if this third
proposal fails, to grant to <ORGANIZATION>HCS</ORGANIZATION> as much as <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> of
common or Series-C stock.
   If <ORGANIZATION>HCS</ORGANIZATION> receives and exercises the option on the three
million Series-C shares, it would invest as much as <MONEY>$21
million</MONEY> in <LOCATION>Savin</LOCATION>, increasing its voting stake to <PERCENT>63%</PERCENT>.
   The votes that are coming in still largely favor the
proposals, <PERSON>Savin</PERSON> said, declining to provide specific numbers.
The company has said that the initial failure of the four
ballot measures, which require approval from two-thirds of
the common shares, stemmed from the difficulty of getting its
many holders to vote.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900327-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-27-90 0805EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Britain-BAT     03-27 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Britain-BAT,0252</SECOND>
<HEAD>BAT To Sell Breuner Stores for $92.5 Million</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>BAT Industries PLC</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> it would sell its
18 <ORGANIZATION>John Breuner Co.</ORGANIZATION> furniture stores to <ORGANIZATION>Prism Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a
merchant bank in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, for <MONEY>$92.5 million</MONEY> in cash.
   The deal is to be completed in about two months through <ORGANIZATION>BATUS
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> subsidiary of BAT, the conglomerate said.
   Breuners, which is based in <LOCATION>San Ramon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, was bought by
BAT in <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   The sale is one step in BAT's strategy of focusing on its
tobacco and financial services businesses to fight off a 13.4
billion-pound, or <MONEY>$22 billion</MONEY>, hostile takeover offer from <ORGANIZATION>Hoylake
Investments Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, an investor group led by Anglo-French financier
Sir <PERSON>James Goldsmith</PERSON>.
   Part of this restructuring includes the sale of all BAT's retail
operations in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The others to be sold include Saks Fifth Avenue, <ORGANIZATION>Marshall
Field</ORGANIZATION>'s, <PERSON>Ivey</PERSON>'s and Breuners' furniture rental business. The
conglomerate said it hopes to have all the sales completed by the
middle of this year.
   Prism was founded last year by <PERSON>Dennis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Steven Wong</PERSON>, who have
backgrounds in merchant banking, venture capital and real estate,
BAT said.
   Prism also owns a controlling interest in <ORGANIZATION>Barker Bros</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a
chain of 11 high-quality furniture stores in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>,
BAT said.
   Prism intends to operate the two retailers independently, it
said.
   The combined annual revenue of Breuners and <PERSON>Barker</PERSON> exceed <MONEY>$200
million</MONEY>, BAT said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900206-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-06-90 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     02-06 0651</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0676</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLOTTE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The cameras are rolling on actor <PERSON>Kevin
Spacey</PERSON> as fallen <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> evangelist <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bernadette Peters</PERSON> as
his wife, <PERSON>Tammy Faye</PERSON>.
   ``Fall From Grace,'' which ends with the couple's ouster from
the television ministry in <DATE>1987</DATE>, is in its first full week of
production in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, The Charlotte Observer reported <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> movie, suggested by the Bakkers, should be broadcast
sometime in <DATE>May</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> bought rights from the couple, but won't say
how much was paid.
   <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> publicist <PERSON>Catherine Boxberger</PERSON> would say only that the
agreement stipulated the couple would not have script approval.
   Actress <PERSON>Annie Rubanoff</PERSON> will play former church secretary <PERSON>Jessica
Hahn</PERSON>, whose revelations of a sexual encounter with <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> started
an investigation into his ministry.
   Bakker is serving 45 years in a federal prison in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>
after being convicted last fall in federal court in <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> of
fraud and conspirary charges.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: A version moved on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The cameras are rolling on actor <PERSON>Kevin
Spacey</PERSON> as fallen <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> evangelist <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bernadette Peters</PERSON> as
his wife, <PERSON>Tammy Faye</PERSON>.
   ``Fall From Grace,'' which ends with the couple's ouster from
the television ministry in <DATE>1987</DATE>, is in its first full week of
production in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, The Charlotte Observer reported <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> movie, suggested by the Bakkers, should be broadcast
sometime in <DATE>May</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> bought rights from the couple, but won't say
how much was paid.
   <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> publicist <PERSON>Catherine Boxberger</PERSON> would say only that the
agreement stipulated the couple would not have script approval.
   Actress <PERSON>Annie Rubanoff</PERSON> will play former church secretary <PERSON>Jessica
Hahn</PERSON>, whose revelations of a sexual encounter with <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> started
an investigation into his ministry.
   Bakker is serving 45 years in a federal prison in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>
after being convicted last fall in federal court in <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> of
fraud and conspirary charges.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The cameras are rolling on actor <PERSON>Kevin
Spacey</PERSON> as fallen <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> evangelist <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bernadette Peters</PERSON> as
his wife, <PERSON>Tammy Faye</PERSON>.
   ``Fall From Grace,'' which ends with the couple's ouster from
the television ministry in <DATE>1987</DATE>, is in its first full week of
production in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, The Charlotte Observer reported <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> movie, suggested by the Bakkers, should be broadcast
sometime in <DATE>May</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> bought rights from the couple, but won't say
how much was paid.
   <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> publicist <PERSON>Catherine Boxberger</PERSON> would say only that the
agreement stipulated the couple would not have script approval.
   Actress <PERSON>Annie Rubanoff</PERSON> will play former church secretary <PERSON>Jessica
Hahn</PERSON>, whose revelations of a sexual encounter with <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> started
an investigation into his ministry.
   Bakker is serving 45 years in a federal prison in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>
after being convicted last fall in federal court in <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> of
fraud and conspirary charges.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BILLINGS, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The cameras are rolling on actor <PERSON>Kevin
Spacey</PERSON> as fallen <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> evangelist <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bernadette Peters</PERSON> as
his wife, <PERSON>Tammy Faye</PERSON>.
   ``Fall From Grace,'' which ends with the couple's ouster from
the television ministry in <DATE>1987</DATE>, is in its first full week of
production in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, The Charlotte Observer reported <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> movie, suggested by the Bakkers, should be broadcast
sometime in <DATE>May</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> bought rights from the couple, but won't say
how much was paid.
   <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> publicist <PERSON>Catherine Boxberger</PERSON> would say only that the
agreement stipulated the couple would not have script approval.
   Actress <PERSON>Annie Rubanoff</PERSON> will play former church secretary <PERSON>Jessica
Hahn</PERSON>, whose revelations of a sexual encounter with <PERSON>Bakker</PERSON> started
an investigation into his ministry.
   Bakker is serving 45 years in a federal prison in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>
after being convicted last fall in federal court in <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> of
fraud and conspirary charges.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-3829</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CIJB4ACTFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920910
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 SEP 92 / Technology: Designers check out the chip library - A quick
way to produce 'mixed signals'
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LOUISE KEHOE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
In the electronics industry, <DATE>last year</DATE>'s product is already a dinosaur. The
market lifetime of many types of electronic products is shrinking rapidly,
forcing manufacturers to accelerate design and development cycles.
One bottleneck has been the development of custom semiconductor chips;
devices that are designed to meet the specifications for a particular
product.
In the digital world of computers, several short-cut 'semi-custom'
approaches to chip design are well established. But bridging the digital and
'real world' of analogue signals is more difficult. Demand for such 'mixed
signal' chips is rising with the use of increasingly sophisticated
electronics in, for example, cars, household appliances and industrial
control applications.
The automatic breaking systems found on some cars and the control devices
used in washing machines require both digital and analogue circuits. Home
automation, lighting control and any type of motor control also span the
digital to analogue divide.
Producing such combinations of digital, analogue, power and memory circuits
on a single chip, to provide lower cost, smaller and more reliable devices,
is one of the most challenging tasks facing the semiconductor industry.
Doing so fast enough to keep pace with accelerating product life cycles is
even more demanding.
Taking a new approach to the problem, <ORGANIZATION>Texas Instruments</ORGANIZATION>, the leading US chip
maker, has devised a new design method it calls Prism based upon 'reusable
engineering'.
In concept, Prism methodology can be likened to a library that has
integrated circuit elements on its shelves instead of books. When a customer
outlines a need for a new semiconductor, the TI design team does not have to
create it from scratch.
Instead, the engineers can go to the 'library', find predefined modules and
re-use them to meet the customers' needs.
The techniques make it easier to customise semiconductors, meaning designers
can add unique capabilities to their products more quickly than their
competitors, providing a critical time-to-market advantage. The chip design
time can be cut from a year to as little as three months, and full
production can be achieved in just six months, TI claims.
Prism also permits a new level of integration - combining multiple
semiconductors with different functions on a single chip - thus decreasing
the component count in new electronic systems by as much as 50 per cent.
'Prism methodology addresses a number of our customers' most important
concerns,' said <PERSON>Tom Engibous</PERSON>, senior vice-president of <ORGANIZATION>TI</ORGANIZATION>'s semiconductor
group.
'It shortens time-to-market, reduces development cost, lowers component
count and makes it easier to design the end products. Current customers in
automotive electronics have been pleased with the results enabled by Prism
methodology, and we are expanding its use into other areas.'
Another important element of the Prism approach is that it permits reuse of
test programs and qualification data, meaning new test procedures do not
have to be redefined for each product. This represents a significant step
forward in reducing the time required to get a new chip to market.
The Prism concept also extends to the manufacturing process, which is
segmented into modules so that only the steps that are needed to produce a
specific chip are used.
An important advance achieved by <ORGANIZATION>TI</ORGANIZATION> has been to squeeze power transistors,
used in high-voltage applications, into the same miniature geometries that
are standard for digital circuitry.
For the end user, faster development of more highly-integrated chips
promises lower prices and more features. In the automotive market, for
example, automatic breaking, cruise control and other features found mostly
on top-of-the-line expensive cars can be expected on lower cost models.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 14
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-14197</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EGODBAFHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940715
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 JUL 94 / UK Company News: Prism Leisure ahead 38% but warns on first
quarter
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By GARY EVANS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Prism Leisure Corporation, the USM-quoted computer games and music group,
yesterday reported a 38 per cent profits rise, but a warning that trading in
the <DATE>first quarter</DATE> of the current year had been 'somewhat disappointing'
pushed the shares down 5p at 167p.
<PERSON>Mr Geoff Young</PERSON>, chairman, said the <DATE>Christmas quarter</DATE> remained the company's
most significant trading period.
Pre-tax profits for the 53 weeks to <DATE>April 2</DATE> rose to Pounds 1.85m (Pounds
1.33m) on turnover 24 per cent higher at Pounds 19.4m. Earnings per share
increased to 14.2p (10.4p) and a recommended final dividend of 3.03p makes a
total for the year of 4.18p (3.27p).
<PERSON>Mr Young</PERSON> said the computer games division, and in particular the
merchandising operation, once more performed strongly. The audio and video
side however, had a difficult year, with turnover reduced.
The German subsidiary had a good year, with both turnover and profits up,
while Prism's pub quiz offshoot made a marginally lower contribution than in
previous years, but still 'performed creditably', said <PERSON>Mr Young</PERSON>.
In its first full year within the group, <PERSON>Paul Lamond</PERSON> - mainly trading in
board games - performed in line with expectations and contributed 'a useful
profit'.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Prism Leisure Corp.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7372 Prepackaged Software.
    P5092 Toys and Hobby Goods and Supplies.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>FIN  Annual report.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06277081 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06277081 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  RECREATION; EQUIPMENT; GUIDELINE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  MODERN BINOCULARS offer so much that choosing the right one can become
confusing.;   There are hundreds of models available, ranging from $10 sport
glasses to autofocus binoculars utilizing the latest in microchip technology
and priced at $700 or more.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Venture  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ARE YOU SETTING YOUR SIGHTS ON A PAIR OF
BINOCULARS?  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Venture -- Celebrating the Active Life; See also related story on P. 7G of
this section; Gearing Up  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Before you shop, do some homework.;   (check) Are your binoculars going to
be primarily for viewing wildlife, sports, stars or a combination? Will you
use them in normal light, or in the shadows of late evening or deep forest?
Will they be routinely exposed to elements or relatively protected? Is
durability a factor?;   (check) How much are you willing to spend is the final
determination. If you are only going to use the binoculars once or twice and
leave them stored the rest of the time, you can probably get away with a
lower-priced model.;   Don't just settle on the cheapest pair. You will regret
it later. Generally, the higher the price the better the optical quality and
the more durable the housing -- to a point. Beyond <MONEY>$250</MONEY> to <MONEY>$300</MONEY> you probably
won't notice the difference.;   Here are some basic specifications:;   Power
or magnification determines how much an object is enlarged. A 7x35 binocular
magnifies seven times, or makes an object appear seven times closer. You will
find some binoculars with a 10x magnification, but unless you plan on using a
tripod stay away from these models. Any gain in magnification is lost by the
corresponding magnification of movement.;   Objective size refers to the
diameter of the front or objective lenses. A 7x35 binocular's objective lens
measures 35 millimeters across. Larger objective lenses allow more light
through and are better in low light situations.;   The "exit pupil" of a
binocular is determined by dividing the larger number by the smaller number.
For example, a 7x35 binocular has an exit pupil of 5mm (35 divided by 7). The
larger the exit pupil number, the more light is being transmitted to your
eyes. A 3mm to 5mm exit pupil is generally adequate for normal viewing. An
exit pupil of 7mm is best for low-light use.;   "Field of view" is the width
or amount of area that you are able to see through binoculars at 1,000 yards.
The field of view for a 7x binocular is normally seven degrees, or 369 feet.
This information is always printed on the instruction sheet if not on the
binocular body. Any binocular with a nine degree field of view or over is
considered a wide-field model. A wider field of view is helpful for wildlife
viewing.;   Prisms bend the light entering the binoculars, allowing you to see
an upright image with increased magnification and brightness.;   <PERSON>Porro</PERSON> prism
binoculars are bulkier and heavier, but offer an accurate sense of depth of
field. Roof prisms are more expensive, but offer a lighter and more compact
alternative with virtually the same features as a porro prism model. Depth of
field is not as good, however.;   Focusing is either fixed, center or
individual. Fixed is convenient, but loses in overall image quality and
versatility. Center focusing adjusts both eye-pieces at once and is usually
the preferred option. Individual focusing is a pain!;   Finally, opt for
waterproof housing -- which won't handle prolonged underwater submersions well
-- when the anticipated use is in dusty or moist environments.;   Here are
some tips on binoculars:;   (check) Never touch binocular lenses with your
fingers. Instead, remove grit and grime with a few puffs of a blower brush,
which can be found in most photo stores, and then brush away any remaining
particles. Remove haze and fingerprints by gently wiping with a lens tissue
dampened with a drop of lens cleaner.;   (check) Don't leave your binoc's in
the hot sun, the trunk of your car or anywhere heat may warp the casing.;  
(check) Keep your binoculars stored in a padded nylon or leather case. Add a
packet of silica gel to help absorb any moisture.;   (check) Only clean the
exterior of your binoculars with a lint-free cotton cloth or a silicon
impregnated cloth that some manufacturers supply with your purchase.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Michael Hodgson column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911003  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7G  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  694  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, October 3, 1991
00277081,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910501-0060
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910501-0060.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Marketing &amp; Media:
   Cable Operator Cries Technical Foul
   On 76ers' Drive From Broadcast TV
   ----
</HL>
<DATE>
05/01/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B8
</SO>
<CO>
   CCPI GE
</CO>
<MS>
CONGLOMERATES (CGL)
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
CONGLOMERATES (CGL)
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<RE>
CONNECTICUT (CT)
PENNSYLVANIA (PA)
</RE>
<LP>
   With mounting concern over the loss of free sporting
events on broadcast television, one of the country's biggest
cable operators is taking the unusual step of opposing a
professional team's plan to air its games exclusively on
cable.
   Comcast Corp., owner of the Philadelphia cable system, is
mounting a campaign to pressure the Philadelphia 76ers
basketball team to reconsider its plan to take the games off
broadcast television and sell them to the cable networks
PRISM and SportsChannel America for a higher fee.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Comcast</ORGANIZATION> is stirring up support among local politicians,
and got a boost from the chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House
Telecommunications Subcommittee</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Edward Markey</PERSON>, who put out a
news release urging the 76ers to reconsider the deal.
   PRISM and the 76ers, who haven't yet closed the deal,
declined to comment. "We aren't going to debate our business
in the newspapers," says <PERSON>Donald Heller</PERSON>, vice president and
general manager of PRISM.
   <ORGANIZATION>Comcast</ORGANIZATION> says that while getting the basketball games
exclusively on its system via PRISM might enhance its local
cable service and even help lure new subscribers, the <PERCENT>55%</PERCENT> of
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> residents who don't subscribe to cable would be
deprived of the games. <PERSON>Brian Roberts</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Comcast</ORGANIZATION>,
says that is likely to alienate consumers and add to the
perception that cable is siphoning programming from broadcast
TV. Moreover, he says, it will increase his company's own
programming costs -- a bill that <ORGANIZATION>Comcast</ORGANIZATION> will ultimately have
to pass along to subscribers.
   Even if <ORGANIZATION>Comcast</ORGANIZATION>'s campaign against the cable deal isn't
successful, it is still a shrewd public relations move. <PERSON>Mr.
Roberts</PERSON> held a news conference with local media on <DATE>Monday</DATE>,
and has been in contact with both the mayor's office and
local congressmen on the issue. Rep. <PERSON>Markey</PERSON>'s statement,
which <ORGANIZATION>Comcast</ORGANIZATION> also made available, commended <PERSON>Mr. Roberts</PERSON> and
<ORGANIZATION>Comcast</ORGANIZATION> "for putting the interests of the fan above profits,"
and said that depriving <LOCATION>Philly</LOCATION> sports fans of 76er games
would be "unconscionable."
   Cable operators are becoming increasingly sensitive to
charges that they may speed the demise of free sports on
television. Last year, <ORGANIZATION>Comcast</ORGANIZATION> and others called for a
moratorium on new sports programming for cable TV, worried
that cable's foes would use the issue as part of an effort to
reregulate the industry. Many national events, such as
prizefights, are already exclusive to cable or available only
to a handful of cable subscribers that have pay-per-view
technology. A plan by <ORGANIZATION>General Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National
Broadcasting Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Cablevision Industries Inc.</ORGANIZATION> to show some
of the <DATE>1992</DATE> Olympics on pay-per-view has also stirred
controversy.
   But the issue is particularly volatile on the local level.
At present, only one other major basketball team -- the <LOCATION>New
York Knicks</LOCATION> -- is exclusive to cable. Most local sports teams
currently split their games between cable networks like
<ORGANIZATION>SportsChannel</ORGANIZATION> and broadcast TV. However, with soaring
players' salaries and team owners eager to up the ante on
television rights fees, <PERSON>Mr. Roberts</PERSON> warns that the 76ers deal
may be just the beginning of a trend.
   "This issue is symptomatic of what is going on in
professional sports," says <PERSON>Mr. Roberts</PERSON>. "If this trend
ultimately ends up with no sports on broadcast television, I
believe it is bad business and bad policy."
   Other cable operators and industry experts agree that the
trend is worrisome, both for the cable industry and for
sports teams. <PERSON>Paul Bortz</PERSON>, whose <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Bortz &amp; Coddington</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> consults with cable companies and sports teams over
rights issues, says he recommends against such exclusive
deals. "For a team to retain broad popularity in a community,
it needs to keep a minimum of ten or fifteen games on
broadcast TV," he says.
   Although terms of the 76ers deal under discussion with the
cable network weren't made public, the cable network is said
to be offering a premium of about <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> more than the amount
the team was offered by the local broadcaster which had been
airing the games. <PERSON>Mr. Bortz</PERSON> notes, however, that higher fees
don't translate into retained loyalty from fans. Unlike a
national sporting event, such as a boxing match, "circulation
at the local level is just crucial" for teams such as the
76ers, he says. "A franchise's popularity is a very fragile
thing."
   PRISM and <ORGANIZATION>SportsChannel</ORGANIZATION> are both owned by the cable joint
venture of <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Cablevision</ORGANIZATION>. PRISM is a premium channel
for which subscribers must pay extra, while <ORGANIZATION>SportsChannel</ORGANIZATION> is
offered as part of the basic cable package. Under the
contract for the just-completed 76ers season, PRISM carried
all the team's home games while local broadcast station
WPHL-TV aired away games. Under the proposed new deal, the
games would be split between PRISM and <ORGANIZATION>SportsChannel</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Comcast</ORGANIZATION> carries both services on its cable system.
   ---
   <ORGANIZATION>Corrections &amp; Amplifications
                                                                                                       

   SPORTSCHANNEL</ORGANIZATION> <LOCATION>AMERICA</LOCATION>, a joint venture of <ORGANIZATION>Cablevision
Systems Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>General Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National
Broadcasting Co.</ORGANIZATION> unit, was misidentified in <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s
edition as a party negotiating to purchase cable rights to
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> 76ers basketball games. Those talks are being
conducted by its local affiliate, <ORGANIZATION>SportsChannel</ORGANIZATION> <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>.
   (WSJ <DATE>May 6, 1991</DATE>)
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA052490-0158 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 223652 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 24, 1990, Thursday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 16; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
156 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BANK OF CHINA OPENS IN HONG KONG SKYSCRAPER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From United Press International 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HONG KONG 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Beijing-owned Bank of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has opened for business in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> in a 
70-story prism-shaped skyscraper that dominates the city's skyline and that has 
sparked superstitious worries among residents. 
</P>
<P>
The 1,289-foot-tall skyscraper was designed by Chinese-American architect <PERSON>I. M. 
Pei</PERSON> and is the tallest building in the British colony, which is due to be 
handed back to the communist mainland in <DATE>1997</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
But the building's four right-angled triangular prisms, placed together to form 
a long, thin square column topped by twin antennas, have been condemned by many 
of the territory's superstitious residents. 
</P>
<P>
Scholars of <ORGANIZATION>Fung Shui</ORGANIZATION> -- the study of wind and water -- have said the 
building's prism design is a sure sign of bad luck. 
</P>
<P>
The sharp edges on the interlocking triangles that make up the sides of the 
building have been likened to daggers. The twin antennas that top the tower 
have been compared to empty chopsticks. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060190-0162 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 227532 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 1, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 5; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
156 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BANK OF CHINA OPENS IN HONG KONG SKYSCRAPER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From United Press International 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HONG KONG 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Beijing-owned Bank of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has opened for business in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> in a 
70-story prism-shaped skyscraper that dominates the city's skyline and that has 
sparked superstitious worries among residents. 
</P>
<P>
The 1,289-foot-tall skyscraper was designed by Chinese-American architect <PERSON>I.M. 
Pei</PERSON> and is the tallest building in the British colony, which is due to be 
handed back to the communist mainland in <DATE>1997</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
But the building's four right-angled triangular prisms, placed together to form 
a long, thin square column topped by twin antennas, have been condemned by many 
of the territory's superstitious residents. 
</P>
<P>
Scholars of <ORGANIZATION>Fung Shui</ORGANIZATION> -- the study of wind and water -- have said the 
building's prism design is a sure sign of bad luck. 
</P>
<P>
The sharp edges on the interlocking triangles that make up the sides of the 
building have been likened to daggers. The twin antennas that top the tower 
have been compared to empty chopsticks. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SUPERSTITIONS; HONG KONG -- CULTURE; DESIGN; ARCHITECTURE; CHINA -- FOREIGN 
RELATIONS -- HONG KONG; BUILDINGS; CHINA -- FOREIGN INVESTMENTS -- HONG KONG; 
BANKS; BANKING INDUSTRY -- CHINA 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-11373</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CA4AUAF2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920131
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  31 JAN 92 / UK Company News: Prism Leisure beats targets
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Prism Leisure, whose core business covers the wholesale and distribution of
pre-recorded music and computer games, raised pre-tax profit from Pounds
303,000 to Pounds 374,000 in the six months to <DATE>September 30</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mr Geoff Young</PERSON>, chairman, said the plan was for moderate growth.
Sales of the USM-quoted group rose to Pounds 5.83m (Pounds 5.24m). The core
business performed well, <PERSON>Mr Young</PERSON> said.
He reiterated his confidence that full year figures would show a solid
advance. Pre-tax profit for last year was Pounds 761,000.
Earnings per share came to 6p (4.6p) and the interim dividend is again 1.5p.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 23
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-12729</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EA1CHAEZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940128
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  28 JAN 94 / UK Company News: Prism 35% ahead at Pounds 0.65m
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Prism Leisure, the USM-quoted computer games and music group, lifted interim
pre-tax profits by 35 per cent and forecast a 'significant advance' in the
full-year result. The shares rose 5p to 183p.
Profit for the 27 weeks to <DATE>October 2</DATE> amounted to Pounds 649,000 compared
with Pounds 478,000 last time and Pounds 1.33m for the previous full year.
Turnover was 26 per cent higher at Pounds 7.65m.
Earnings per share showed a <MONEY>29 per cent</MONEY> rise from 3.8p to 4.9p; the interim
dividend is lifted by 28 per cent from 0.9p to 1.15p.
Directors said a principal area of growth was increased turnover in the
wholesale distribution and merchandising of computer games. Sales on the
audio and video side showed a slight decline.
They reported that trade was good in the <DATE>Christmas quarter</DATE>, particularly for
computer games. <PERSON>Paul Lamond Games</PERSON>, the board game division, showed
encouraging initial trading and was expected to make a positive contribution
to full-year results.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Prism Leisure Corp.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P5735 Record and Prerecorded Tape Stores.
    P5092 Toys and Hobby Goods and Supplies.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>FIN  Interim results.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-12380</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DA3AKAAKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930129
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  29 JAN 93 / UK Company News: Prism shares rise on profits surge
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Shares of <ORGANIZATION>Prism Leisure Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, the USM-quoted music and games group,
rose 12p to 75p yesterday on news of a <MONEY>28 per cent</MONEY> rise in pre-tax profits
to Pounds 478,000 for the 26 weeks ended <DATE>September 27</DATE>.
Turnover improved from Pounds 5.83m to Pounds 6.07m. Earnings rose 0.8p to
3.8p and the interim dividend is being lifted from an adjusted 0.75p to
0.9p.
At period end cash reserves were in excess of Pounds 1m.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Prism Leisure.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6719  Holding Companies, NEC.
    P5099  Durable Goods, NEC.
    P573  Radio, Television, and Computer Stores.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>FIN  Interim results.
    COSTS  Equity prices.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870710-0138 </DOCNO>
<HL> Who's News:
Prism Entertainment Corp.</HL>
<DD> 07/10/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> PRZ WNEWS </IN>
<DATELINE> PRISM ENTERTAINMENT CORP. (Los Angeles)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
    <PERSON>Richard Lorber</PERSON>
was elected a director of this videocassette distributor. He
succeeds <PERSON>David Fox</PERSON>, who didn't stand for reelection. <PERSON>Mr.
Lorber</PERSON> is president of <ORGANIZATION>Fox/Lorber Associates Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a wholly
owned subsidiary of the company.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032890-0074 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 195942 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 28, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 2; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
83 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BRIEFLY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Buyer Found for <ORGANIZATION>John Breuner Co.</ORGANIZATION>: <ORGANIZATION>BAT Industries</ORGANIZATION> said it reached an agreement 
to sell its furniture store chain, <ORGANIZATION>John Breuner Co.</ORGANIZATION>, to <ORGANIZATION>Prism Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of 
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for <MONEY>$92.5 million</MONEY>. It involves the 18 Breuners stores in <LOCATION>Northern 
California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> but not the company's 44 rental centers, which 
still are up for sale. Prism already owns a controlling interesting <ORGANIZATION>Barker 
Bros.</ORGANIZATION>, an 11-store <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> furniture chain, but plans to keep the 
retail operations separate. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ACQUISITIONS; JOHN BREUNER CO; BAT INDUSTRIES PLC; PRISM CAPITAL CORP 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-14189</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DGOCUAE2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930715
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 JUL 93 / UK Company News: Games side boost for Prism
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
A STRONG performance from its computer games division helped Prism Leisure
report record profits for the 12 months to <DATE>March 28</DATE>.
Shares of the USM-quoted group rose 10p to 150p after the announcement of
pre-tax profits of Pounds 1.33m, up 37 per cent on the comparable Pounds
975,000. Turnover improved to Pounds 15.5m (Pounds 13.5m).
<PERSON>Mr Geoff Young</PERSON>, chairman, said the computer games side had exceeded
expectations: 'The customer profile has continued to improve and now covers
many major retailers,' he said.
The audio and video operation maintained profits in difficult trading, but
the German subsidiary, which began trading last <DATE>July</DATE>, produced an
'encouraging' profit, <PERSON>Mr Young</PERSON> said.
Cash balances at the year-end amounted to Pounds 1.5m.
A proposed final dividend of 2.37p brings the total to 3.27p - a 20 per cent
rise - covered over three times by earnings of 10.4p (8.4p) per share.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Prism Leisure Corp.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3571 Electronic Computers.
    P3944 Games, Toys, and Children's Vehicles.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>FIN  Annual report.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-47300 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpust012___94054" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-UST-94-012 </AU>
JPRS 
Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Central Eurasia </ABS>
<DATE1>   8 June 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Principles of Designing Technical Sighting System for </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Principles of Designing Technical Sighting System for </PHRASE></F></HT>


<TEXT>
Prevention   of <ORGANIZATION>Railroad Train Collisions 

<FP=102> 947J0028C St. Peterburg OPTICHESKIY ZHURNAL</ORGANIZATION> in Russian No. 
2, Feb 94 (manuscript received 2 Feb 93) pp 58-62 </F>

<FP=103> 947J0028C </F>
<FP=104>  St. Peterburg OPTICHESKIY <ORGANIZATION>ZHURNAL </F>
<FP=105>  Russian </F>
CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FP=106> [Article by <ORGANIZATION>I.A. Machtovoy</ORGANIZATION>, candidate of technical sciences, </F>
and <ORGANIZATION>A.S. Mikheyev</ORGANIZATION>, candidate of technical sciences, <ORGANIZATION>All-Russian 
Science Center at State Institute of Optics</ORGANIZATION> imeni <LOCATION>S.I. Vavilov</LOCATION>; 
<ORGANIZATION>UDC</ORGANIZATION> 681.327.12.001] 
  [Abstract] A technical sighting system for prevention of 
railroad train collisions is being designed, a major role being 
assigned to semaphores. Its three basic tasks are to detect 
objects (obstacles), to identify them, and to decode their 
encoded position. A telephoto camera with an optoelectronic 
receiver of semaphore lights feeds images to a detector (image 
converter). The latter sends signals to: 1. an object identifier 
followed by a semaphore lights color analyzer, 2. a 
stereorangefinder, 3. a path analyzer. A generator of brake 
activation signals, upon receiving signals from these three 
sources, transmits an output signal to the brake servomechanism. 
The stereorangefinder and the tracking device are interfaced, 
the latter sending signals to a light source for the road. In 
the stereorangefinder a right prism with mirror faces is placed 
symmetrically between two terminal reflectors of incident light. 
This prism combines the light coming from both reflectors into a 
single beam and sends that beam through an intensity regulator 
into an objective followed successively by a focus magnifier and 
a beam splitter. Two hoods, one around each reflector, prevent 
entry of sunlight or the headlight beam of a train into the 
system. The spectral sensitivity band of the system is 0.45-0.90 
?m, which covers both visible and near infrared light so that 
the system can respond to semaphore lights of all three colors: 
green (0.51-0.55 ?m) - yellow (0.57-0.59 ?m) - red 
(0.62-0.78 ?m) semaphore lights. Object-obstacle 
identification is based on geometrical characteristics. The 
color of a semaphore light is identified by spectral 
discrimination. The path analyzer has an autointerrogator with 
an exclusive-NOR gate, and a decoder followed successively by a 
comparator, a memory, and an autoresponder. Figures 4; 
references 3. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-13180</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CGOA1ACHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920715
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 JUL 92 / UK Company News: Prism returns record Pounds 975,000
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Prism Leisure Corporation, the music and computer games group traded on the
<ORGANIZATION>USM</ORGANIZATION>, returned record profits of Pounds 975,000 pre-tax for the 52 weeks
ended <DATE>March 29</DATE>.
The 28 per cent improvement over the previous year's Pounds 761,000 was
achieved on the back of an <MONEY>8 per cent</MONEY> rise in turnover to Pounds 13.5m.
Earnings rose by 5p to 16.8p and an increased final dividend of 3.95p makes
a 5.45p (4.95p) total. Year-end cash balances totalled Pounds 800,000.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 28
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121089-0038 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 146224 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 10, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 26; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
949 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WOMEN'S ROLE IN MILITARY TO BE REFLECTED IN GLASS-BEDECKED MONUMENT; 
</P>
<P>
ARCHITECTURE: PRISMS 39 FEET HIGH TO ARE TO BE THE CENTERPIECE OF A MEMORIAL. 
THE DESIGNER WANTED TO "SHED LIGHT" ON UNRECOGNIZED WORK. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By NORA FRENKIEL, THE BALTIMORE SUN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ARLINGTON, Va. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Marion Gail Weiss</PERSON> held up her slender hands, palms facing inward, in front of 
her to make the point. "I had this image," the architect says, "of women's 
hands, all those women's hands and the unrecognized work those women did." 
</P>
<P>
Soon that image will be transformed into a centerpiece -- of 10 triangular 
prisms of glass -- in a monument to the women of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> who have 
served in the military. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Weiss</PERSON>, a 31-year-old assistant professor of architecture at the <ORGANIZATION>University of 
Maryland</ORGANIZATION> for the last year, and <PERSON>Michael Manfredi</PERSON>, 36, an architect in <LOCATION>New York 
City</LOCATION>, were announced recently as the winners of the competition to design the 
memorial, which was authorized by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>. It will cost <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> -- 
to be raised by private funds -- and is scheduled to be completed by <DATE>1992</DATE>. The 
site, which is at the Memorial Gate Area at <LOCATION>Arlington National Cemetery</LOCATION> -- 
where millions of Americans pay their respects to the country's war dead -- is 
directly across from the <LOCATION>Lincoln Memorial</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"The challenge was the sensitivity of the site and the sensitivity of the 
subject -- the role of women in the military. For too long, they have been 
unseen," <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"This sheds light on their unrecognized achievements," added <PERSON>Manfredi</PERSON>, her 
design partner. "We didn't want this to be garish or upstage any of the other 
sites. We wanted this to be part of the family of monuments." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wilma L. Vaught</PERSON>, the retired <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> brigadier general who is president of 
the nonprofit Women in <ORGANIZATION>Military Service</ORGANIZATION> for <ORGANIZATION>America Memorial Foundation</ORGANIZATION> that 
oversaw the selection process, praised the design, which will feature 39-foot 
prisms and incorporate the main features -- the wrought iron gates, the curved 
wall known as the "Hemicycle" and wide plaza -- already on the site. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a beautiful monument and representation of women's contribution to the 
military," she said. "It is also very uplifting." The announcement of the 
winning design had been made to coincide with <ORGANIZATION>Veteran</ORGANIZATION>'s Day, she said, and to 
celebrate the commemoration of <ORGANIZATION>National Women</ORGANIZATION>'s Veterans Recognition Week. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> explained the symbolism of the design, selected from among 137 entries in 
the competition. In addition to the 10 prisms -- "hands by day, illuminated 
candles by night" -- there will be four staircases leading from the ground 
level to a terrace. "They symbolize the slow passage for women, their struggle 
and ascent in the military," <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
In her chosen field of architecture, <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> said she wished there were fewer 
barriers for women as well. "I wish I could say it was easier," she admitted, 
"but it is difficult for women to get ahead. But I'm optimistic that there are 
more and more role models for women." 
</P>
<P>
This professional pairing began in <DATE>1984</DATE> when <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> -- a <DATE>1983</DATE> graduate of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Yale School of Architecture</ORGANIZATION> -- joined the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> architectural firm of 
<ORGANIZATION>Mitchell Giurgola</ORGANIZATION>. There she met <PERSON>Manfredi</PERSON>, who had graduated from <ORGANIZATION>Cornell</ORGANIZATION> with 
a master's degree in architecture in <DATE>1979</DATE>. The two joined forces for such 
clients as <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Volvo</ORGANIZATION>. They also became friends, the kind of friends who are 
apt to finish each other's sentences. They even look somewhat alike: they are 
slight, dark-haired and partial to black clothing. 
</P>
<P>
When they chose to branch out on their own <DATE>two years ago</DATE>, they decided to open 
offices in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Manfredi</PERSON>, a graduate of <ORGANIZATION>Winston 
Churchill High School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Potomac</LOCATION>, had family. 
</P>
<P>
So far, their combined work has been included in an exhibit organized by the 
Architectural League of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> called "Vacant Lots" for their design for 
low-income housing in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON>, who divides her time between <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, is also at work on an apartment project on upper Fifth 
Avenue in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Yet nothing prepared them for this professional breakthrough. "We're really 
still starting out," she said. "This is an amazing feeling for us. We're very 
thrilled to have won. It is an amazing opportunity for us." 
</P>
<P>
Although they were paid <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> as one of four finalists in <DATE>June</DATE> to go into the 
second phase -- completion of a scaled-down model -- and will be paid <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> 
for their continued work on the project, not large sums by architectural 
project standards, they agreed it was not a labor for money. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Weiss</PERSON>, who grew up near <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, recalled that her father had served in 
the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> in the late <DATE>1940s</DATE>. And <PERSON>Manfredi</PERSON>'s mother, <PERSON>Dorothy</PERSON>, served as a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. 
Army</ORGANIZATION> nurse for 11 years, beginning in the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> during World War II. It was 
<PERSON>Dorothy Manfredi</PERSON> who first showed her son the clipping about the competition 
and urged the duo to enter. 
</P>
<P>
When the monument opens, women will be able to place their hands at the base of 
the prisms where women's memories of their military experiences will be 
inscribed. They will be able to stand inside the monument and walk the curved 
time line, which will explain women's role in the military since the 
Revolutionary War. They will also be able to enter the heart of the monument 
and use computers to read the register of names of women who have served their 
country. (For <MONEY>$25</MONEY>, any woman who has served in the military can register to be 
included in the computer files; it is part of the ongoing effort to raise money 
to complete the memorial.) 
</P>
<P>
"I'm really excited about the idea of people coming to this memorial," <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> 
said. "Women who've served in the military will bring their grandchildren and 
tell their stories and later their children will come telling the stories. The 
thing that's unique is that it doesn't commemorate dead people, but it 
commemorates all those who served. It's also a living memorial and will be 
there to tell a story and to inspire all those women who will serve in the 
future." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032790-0157 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 196081 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 27, 1990, Tuesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part P; Page 3; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
179 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
P.M. BRIEFING; 
</P>
<P>
JOHN BREUNER STORES TO BE SOLD 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
LONDON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>BAT Industries PLC</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE> it will sell its 18 <ORGANIZATION>John Breuner Co.</ORGANIZATION> furniture 
stores to <ORGANIZATION>Prism Capital Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a merchant bank in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, for <MONEY>$92.5 million</MONEY> 
in cash. 
</P>
<P>
The deal is to be completed in about two months through <ORGANIZATION>BATUS Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
subsidiary of BAT, the conglomerate said. 
</P>
<P>
Breuners, which is based in <LOCATION>San Ramon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, was bought by BAT in <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The sale is one step in BAT's strategy of focusing on its tobacco and financial 
services businesses to fight off a 13.4-billion, or <MONEY>$22-billion</MONEY>, hostile 
takeover offer from <ORGANIZATION>Hoylake Investments Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, an investor group led by 
Anglo-French financier Sir <PERSON>James Goldsmith</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Part of this restructuring includes the sale of all BAT's retail operations in 
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The others to be sold include Saks Fifth Avenue, <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Field</ORGANIZATION>'s, <PERSON>Ivey</PERSON>'s and 
Breuners' furniture rental business. The conglomerate said it hopes to have all 
the sales completed by the middle of this year. 
</P>
<P>
Prism also owns a controlling interest in <ORGANIZATION>Barker Bros</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a chain of 11 
high-quality furniture stores in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-40229 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpcst002___94023" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-CST-94-002 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  China </ABS>
<DATE1>    25 February 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> Lasers, Sensors, Optics </F>
<H3> <TI>   Optical Omega Network With Four-Function Optical Exchange-Switch for Digital Optical Switching Network </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  94P60110A Shanghai GUANGXUE XUEBAO [ACTA OPTICA SINICA] in 
Chinese Vol 13 No 12, Dec 93 pp 1105-1109 </F>

<F P=103> 94P60110A </F>
<F P=104>  Shanghai GUANGXUE XUEBAO [ACTA OPTICA SINICA] </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FP=105> Chinese </F>
Article Type:<ORGANIZATION>CSO</ORGANIZATION> 

<FP=106> [Article by <PERSON>Cao Mingcui</PERSON> [2580 2494 5050], Luo Fengguang </F>
[5012 7364 0342], et al. of the <ORGANIZATION>National Laboratory of Laser 
Technology</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Huazhong</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Central China) University of Science &amp; 
Technology</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Wuhan</LOCATION> 430074: ``Four-Function Exchange-Switch 
<ORGANIZATION>Optical Omega Network for Digital Optical Switching Network</ORGANIZATION>,'' 
supported by grants from NDSTIC's Science Fund and <ORGANIZATION>NSFC</ORGANIZATION>; MS 
received 13 <DATE>Oct 92</DATE>, revised 25 Jan 93] 
  [Abstract] An optical <ORGANIZATION>Omega</ORGANIZATION> network with a four-function 
optical exchange-switch for a digital optical switching network 
is presented. The principle of the optical implementation of the 
four-function exchange-switch and <ORGANIZATION>Omega</ORGANIZATION> network via an 8-pixel 
liquid-crystal spatial light modulator (LCSLM) and special 
polarizing prisms is discussed in detail. The optical system and 
experimental results with twisted-nematic liquid crystal plates 
are given. 
  Figures 1, 3, 4, and 6, reproduced below, show an <ORGANIZATION>Omega</ORGANIZATION> 
interconnection network (<LOCATION>P.S.</LOCATION> = perfect shuffle, <ORGANIZATION>A-L</ORGANIZATION> are the 
twelve 2 x 2 switches), a schematic diagram of the optical <ORGANIZATION>Omega</ORGANIZATION> 
network with four-function optical exchange-switch (I and II are 
polarizing optical prisms, lines AB and CD indicate polarizing 
films, C[.sup]0[/] and C[.sub]4[/] are two of the eight 
pixels in the LCSLM, and PB[.sup]1[/] and PB[.sub]2[/] are 
prism blocks), the four states of the exchange-switch 
corresponding to the different states of the liquid-crystal 
pixels, and a schematic diagram of the optical <ORGANIZATION>Omega</ORGANIZATION> 
interconnection network with four-function optical 
exchange-switch arrays, respectively. Figures 2, 5, and <DATE>7</DATE>, not 
reproduced, show a simple schematic of a four-function exchange 
switch, five photographs (input light-beam permutation, left 
<LOCATION>P.S.</LOCATION> connection, right <LOCATION>P.S.</LOCATION> connection, down-spread connection, 
and up-spread connection) of the experimental results for the 
four-function optical exchange-switch, and five photographs of 
the experimental results for the optical <ORGANIZATION>Omega</ORGANIZATION> network with 
four-function optical exchange-switch, respectively. There are 
no tables. 

<FIGID=JPRS-CST-002C-29A>           Figure 1. The <ORGANIZATION>Omega Interconnection Network</ORGANIZATION> (N = 8) </FIG>


<FIGID=JPRS-CST-002C-29B>           Figure 3. Schematic Diagram of <ORGANIZATION>Optical Omega Network With Four-Function Optical Exchange-Switch</ORGANIZATION> </FIG>


<FIGID=JPRS-CST-002C-29C>           Figure 4. The Four States of the Exchange-Switch </FIG>


<FIGID=JPRS-CST-002C-29D>           Figure 6. The <ORGANIZATION>Optical Omega Interconnection Network </FIG>


References 
  1</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>J. Jahns</PERSON>, <PERSON>M. J. Murdocca</PERSON>, ``Crossover Networks and Their 
Optical Implementation,'' APPL. OPT., <DATE>1988</DATE>, 27(15): 3155-3160. 
  2. Cao Mingcui, <PERSON>Li Hongpu</PERSON>, <PERSON>Liu Xiaan</PERSON>, et al., ``Optical 
Hardware for the Perfect Shuffle Interconnection,'' OPTICAL 
COMPUTING AND PROCESSING, <DATE>1991</DATE>, 1(1): 23-27. 
  3. Cao Mingcui, <LOCATION>Luo Fengguang</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Li Hongpu</PERSON>, et al., ``Optical 
Perfect Shuffle-Exchange Interconnect Network Using Liquid 
Crystal Light Switch,'' APPL. OPT., <DATE>1992</DATE>, 31: 6817-6819. 
  4. Cao Mingcui, <PERSON>Li Hongpu</PERSON>, <PERSON>Luo Fengguang</PERSON>, et al., ``Optical 
Implementation of Perfect Shuffle/Exchange <ORGANIZATION>Omega</ORGANIZATION> Interconnection 
Network'' [in Chinese], GUANGXUE XUEBAO [ACTA OPTICA SINICA], 
<DATE>1992</DATE>, 12(12): 1129-1133 [translated in full in JPRS-CST-93-010, 
27 <DATE>May 93</DATE> pp 19-22]. 
  5. <PERSON>K. H. Bremer</PERSON>, <PERSON>A. Huang</PERSON>, ``Optical Implementation of 
Perfect-Shuffle Interconnection,'' APPL. OPT., <DATE>1988</DATE>, 27(1): 
135-137. 
  6. M. <PERSON>J. Murdocca</PERSON>, <PERSON>A. Huang</PERSON>, <PERSON>J. Jahns</PERSON>, et al., ``Optical 
Design of Programmable Logic Arrays,'' APPL. OPT., <DATE>1988</DATE>, 27(9): 
1650-1660. 
  7. M. Murdocca, <PERSON>T. J. Cloonan</PERSON>, ``Optical Design of a Digital 
Switch,'' APPL. OPT., <DATE>1989</DATE>, 28(13): 2505-2517. 
  8. <PERSON>G. Eichmann</PERSON>, <PERSON>Yao Li</PERSON>, ``Compact Optical Generalized 
Perfect 
Shuffle,'' APPL. OPT., <DATE>1987</DATE>, 26(7): 1167-1169. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06105078 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06105078 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COMPUTER; PROGRAM  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Shareware programs are available from computer bulletin boards, computer clubs
and from this column. Users try them, then pay a fee to register them if they
decide to use them regularly.;    PRISM -- Want to trace your ancestors and
build a family tree? Prism is a genealogical data base that will help you
plant, nurture and harvest your family tree. A series of menus, help screens
and the use of function keys on an International Business Machines Corp. or
compatible computer will have you entering everything you know about your
family quickly.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Computing  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HOW TO TRACE FAMILY TREE, LOCATE LOST OR
HIDDEN FILES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Shareware
Trial copies of these programs are available for $4 each. Send a check to
Shareware, P.O. Box 4101, Lakewood, Calif. 90711. Please indicate 5 1/4- or 3
1/2-inch disk.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Once you've entered enough data, you can view or print your family tree,
culled from the thousands of names you input. Then, when you want to find
about more about <PERSON>Uncle Max</PERSON>, who homesteaded near <LOCATION>Devils Lake</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.D.</LOCATION>, back at
the turn of the century, you simply search for Max.;    You'll need a hard
disk and 640 kilobytes of random-access memory to run Prism. A free version
can be found on computer bulletin boards. It's limited to 50 people but will
give you a good idea how the program works. The full-blown version costs <MONEY>$44</MONEY>
and can be ordered from <PERSON>Gary R. Austin</PERSON>, <DATE>1459</DATE> Tenth St., <LOCATION>Grand Rapids</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>
49504. Austin also will send you the limited bulletin board version for <MONEY>$5</MONEY>, to
cover shipping.;    PROFESSIONAL MASTER KEY -- If accidentally formatting your
hard disk is a recurring nightmare, get yourself a backup program, such as
Backup, and use a utility such as <ORGANIZATION>PMK</ORGANIZATION> that will bring back those files. Aside
from its unformat features, <ORGANIZATION>PMK</ORGANIZATION> also will show you a directory of any kind of
hard or floppy disk, unerase files, find files using wild cards, sort files,
delete files, rename them and even let you edit text files with a text editor
called Tiny Edit. If security is a concern, <ORGANIZATION>PMK</ORGANIZATION> will erase all data from a
hard or floppy disk or erase all data from a particular file.;    If <ORGANIZATION>PMK</ORGANIZATION>
sounds like it's a cross between Xtree and the <ORGANIZATION>Norton Utilities</ORGANIZATION>, two
commercial utilities, it is similar, but, as with most shareware programs, it
costs a lot less. If you're downloading <ORGANIZATION>PMK</ORGANIZATION> from a bulletin board, look for
Version 3.2. To register, send <MONEY>$35</MONEY> to <ORGANIZATION>Public Brand Software</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 51315,
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION> 46251.;    HOME INSURANCE -- There are a lot of good
reasons for taking inventory of your worldly possessions, not the least of
which are the possibilities of theft or fire. This shareware program takes you
by the hand on a tour through your home. As you catalog your possessions,
you'll be prompted for serial numbers, descriptions and replacement costs,
among other details.;    The folks at Homecraft Software recommend that you
take a day for this task. It's a day well spent because insurance companies
like to have the cold, hard facts when you're faced with a loss. This program
also lets you figure out how much insurance you need, and it lets you group
special items that may require additional insurance. Then you can print
reports and make some intelligent decisions about how much insurance you
need.;    To register for Home Insurance, send <MONEY>$62.95</MONEY> to <PERSON>Steve Hudgik</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Homecraft Computer Products</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 974, <LOCATION>Tualatin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 97062.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  NOAH MATTHEWS, Knight-Ridder News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910414  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  563  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 14, 1991
00105078,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861229-0030 </DOCNO>
<HL> ServiceMaster Units
Scheduled to Begin
Trading on Big Board</HL>
<DD> 12/29/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SMAS EQM PSMN AZB FAL GUN CPST DEAL HSPA LLSL LEIX MMSB
STOCK MARKET, OFFERINGS (STK)
SECURITIES INDUSTRY (SCR) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>ServiceMaster Limited Partnership</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Downers Grove</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, will begin trading units <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> on the <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> under the symbol SVM. 

   The provider of health care and cleaning services, recently converted to a limited partnership, formerly traded over the counter as <ORGANIZATION>ServiceMaster Industries Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Equitable Real Estate Shopping Centers Limited Partnership</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, began trading last week on the <ORGANIZATION>Big Board</ORGANIZATION> under the symbol EQM. 
It was formed to acquire two regional shopping malls in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> from <ORGANIZATION>Equitable Life Assurance Society</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Shearson Lehman Brothers Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, an <ORGANIZATION>American Express Co.</ORGANIZATION> unit, is the general partner. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Universal Health Realty Income Trust</ORGANIZATION> began trading shares of beneficial interest last week on the <ORGANIZATION>Big Board</ORGANIZATION> under the symbol UHT. 
The King of <LOCATION>Prussia</LOCATION>, Pa.-based concern is a real estate investment trust. 

   On the <ORGANIZATION>American Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Prism Entertainment Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, will begin trading tomorrow under the symbol PRZ. 
The home-video and television-syndication company previously traded over the counter. 

   Three previously unreported issues began trading on the Amex last week. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Arizona Commerce Bank</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, began trading under the symbol AZB. 
The state-chartered bank previously traded over the counter. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Falcon Cable Systems Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a limited partnership, began trading shares of beneficial ownership under the symbol FAL. 
The <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>, Calif.-based concern owns and operates cable television systems in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Gundel Environmental Systems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, began trading under the symbol GUN. 
The company makes and installs polyethylene lining systems to control hazardous wastes. 

   Six new listings began trading over the counter recently. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Plastics Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Litchfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, began trading under the symbol CPST. 
The company designs, makes and markets plastic containers, primarily for dairy products. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Dial Reit Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, an <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>, Neb.-based real estate investment trust, began trading under the symbol DEAL. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Home Savings Association of Penna.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Tamaqua</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, began trading under the symbol HSPA. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Lakeland Savings &amp; Loan Association</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Succasunna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, began trading under the symbol LLSL. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Lowrance Electronics Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Tulsa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>, began trading under the symbol LEIX. 
The company designs, makes and markets sonar equipment and accessories for use in fishing and boating. 

   Mid <ORGANIZATION>Maine Savings Bank</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Auburn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, began trading under the symbol MMSB. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-2296</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFTD4AERFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940620
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 JUN 94 / International Company News: Life company farms out
derivatives management
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By TRACY CORRIGAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Confederation Life, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s fourth biggest life company, has passed on the
management of its derivatives portfolio to <ORGANIZATION>Sumitomo Bank Capital Markets</ORGANIZATION>.
Many companies have become increasingly nervous about using derivatives,
following losses in recent months by <ORGANIZATION>Metallgesellschaft</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Procter &amp; Gamble</ORGANIZATION>,
and others.
While it is highly unusual for a company to farm out all its derivatives
management to an outside specialist, the growing need for sophisticated
operational controls and computer systems when using derivatives has made it
increasingly difficult for companies to manage risk effectively in-house.
SBCM will take over the risk management activities of <ORGANIZATION>Confederation Treasury
Services</ORGANIZATION> under guidelines and policies set by the company. 'We will manage
their books, but some transactions will require authorisation,' said SBCM.
It will use its Prism front-to-back office system, developed in-house, to
perform services such as daily valuation, risk analysis, trade
confirmations, payments and rate resets.
Prism supports <ORGANIZATION>SBCM</ORGANIZATION>'s current portfolio of over 10,000 swap transactions in
17 currencies. SBCM's <ORGANIZATION>Derivatives Products Group</ORGANIZATION> has 170 employees in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>, having poached teams from <ORGANIZATION>Pru-Bache</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Security
Pacific</ORGANIZATION> in the late <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Confederation Life Insurance.
    Sumitomo Bank Capital Markets.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6221 Commodity Contracts Brokers, Dealers.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>MGMT  Management &amp; Marketing.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA052190-0062 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 222054 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 21, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 3; Column 3; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
199 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PACIFIC NOTES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Beijing-owned Bank of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> opened for business in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE> in a 
70-story, prism-shaped skyscraper that dominates the city's skyline and has 
sparked superstitious worries among residents. 
</P>
<P>
The 1,289-foot-tall skyscraper, designed by Chinese-American architect <PERSON>I.M. 
Pei</PERSON>, is the tallest building in the British colony, which is to be handed back 
to the Communist mainland in <DATE>1997</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
But the building's four right-angled triangular prisms, placed together to form 
a long, thin square column topped by twin antennas, have been condemned by many 
of the territory's superstitious residents. 
</P>
<P>
Scholars of fung shui -- literally the study of wind and water -- say the 
building's design is a sure sign of bad luck. The sharp edges on the 
interlocking triangles that make up the sides of the building are said to be 
like daggers, the twin antennas that top off the tower like empty chopsticks. 
Both symbols are bad omens, according to fung shui. 
</P>
<P>
Many of the more superstitious residents living near the building have hung 
small mirrors outside their windows to reflect the tower's bad luck. 
</P>
<P>
The project ran eight months behind schedule and <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> over 
budget. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CHINA -- FOREIGN INVESTMENTS -- HONG KONG; CHINA -- FOREIGN RELATIONS -- HONG 
KONG; BANK OF CHINA; OFFICE BUILDINGS; SUPERSTITIONS; ARCHITECTURE; DESIGN; 
PEI, IEOH MING 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900806-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-06-90 0250EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-ExtravagantAirForce     08-06 0510</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Extravagant Air Force,525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Air Force Has Champagne Taste</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> has spent hundreds of <MONEY>millions
of dollars</MONEY> on gold-plated chandeliers, golf course projects and
other luxuries to boost morale, internal <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> documents show.
   Back in <DATE>1985</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> decided to refurbish its officers'
club at the <LOCATION>Mildenhall</LOCATION> base in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> at a cost of <MONEY>$75,000</MONEY>. The
service's champagne taste, however, hardly matched the appropriated
amount.
   Gold-plated chandeliers valued at <MONEY>$145,000</MONEY> were installed, solid
oak paneling lined the walls and fireplaces with marble fixtures
completed the decor. The final tally was more than <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> with
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> taxpayers picking up the tab.
   The internal <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> audits, conducted in <DATE>April</DATE> and <DATE>May of
this year</DATE>, reveal widespread waste and abuse in the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
management of its Morale, Welfare and <ORGANIZATION>Recreation Activities</ORGANIZATION>.
   Golf course projects at <ORGANIZATION>Myrtle Beach Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> cost nearly
<MONEY>$600,000</MONEY>, while parties for a departing officer at <ORGANIZATION>Ramstein Air
Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> totaled <MONEY>$26,000</MONEY>.
   In a letter to <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Dick Cheney</PERSON>, Rep. <PERSON>Barbara
Boxer</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Calif.</LOCATION>, called for leadership from the highest levels of
the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> to crack down on these abuses.
   The documents reveal ``a mindset among some senior <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
officials that the bases they command are their own personal
fiefdoms, with appropriated funds to be used at their discretion
regardless of law and regulation,'' <PERSON>Boxer</PERSON> said in the letter.
   According to the documents, strict restrictions on excessive
spending on renovation projects have been either ignored or
circumvented. Projects valued at more than <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> must be
reported to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. In some instances, however, major projects
were split into smaller projects to avoid seeking congressional
approval.
   Even the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> auditors expressed dismay at the renovation
projects.
   In the documents, <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> management at the base in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>
argued that the chandeliers couldn't be standard-issue.
   ``Low quality chandeliers could not act as the main
architectural highlight of a room as the existing chandeliers do.
The crystal used would not have the capability to break apart the
available light in a room into its primary colors (prism effect),''
the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> said.
   In response, the auditors said ``spending an additional <MONEY>$15,900</MONEY>
in appropriated funds to purchase chandeliers that have the correct
`prism effect' is not appropriate.''
   Other instances of abuse include relocation of a skeet shooting
club at <ORGANIZATION>Tinker Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>. The estimated cost of
the project was <MONEY>$722,000</MONEY> and it was included in the cost of a
construction project for basing of the B-2 stealth bomber.
   But when it was discovered that the project was <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> over
budget, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> proposed eliminating the work stations at the
facility rather than the <ORGANIZATION>Skeet Club</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I find it appalling that the weaknesses in the management and
oversight of Morale, Welfare and Recreation operations have been
repeatedly documented by <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> auditors,
whistleblowers and <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, that <MONEY>hundreds of millions of dollars</MONEY>
are being illegally spent on parties, golf courses and officers
clubs, yet internal recommendations to remedy the problems have
been ignored,'' <PERSON>Boxer</PERSON> said in the letter.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890612-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-12-89 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Women'sMemorial     06-12 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Women's Memorial,380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Design Finalists Selected</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A grove of bronze trees, a cluster of
illuminated glass prisms and a platform overlooking <ORGANIZATION>Arlington
National Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> were among features of surviving designs <DATE>Monday</DATE> in
the first phase of competition to select a memorial to women in
military service.
   The ultimate winner from the finalists will be selected in
<DATE>November</DATE> by five judges.
   Retired <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> Brig. Gen. <PERSON>Wilma L. Vaught</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Women
in Military Service</ORGANIZATION> for <ORGANIZATION>America Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, said <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> prizes were
awarded to three teams.
   They were <PERSON>Teresa Norton</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Tybee Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, and associates
<PERSON>Cleve Harp</PERSON>, <PERSON>David Overholt</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sergio Chavarria</PERSON>, <PERSON>Peter S. Christman</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Martha Enzmann</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ming T. Shaing</PERSON>; <PERSON>Gregory A. Galford</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maria L.
Antonis</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>; and <PERSON>Michael A. Manfredi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and
associates <PERSON>Marion G. Weiss</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ellen D. Sands</PERSON> and <PERSON>Thomas Schumacher</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   The memorial is to be built with private funds with ground
breaking by <DATE>1991</DATE>, in accordance with legislation passed by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
in <DATE>1986</DATE>. It is to be located at, and is designed to complete, the
memorial gate of <LOCATION>Arlington Cemetery</LOCATION>. The gate was left unfinished
during the Depression.
   Harp said the grove of 49 trees in the <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> team's design was
designed to symbolize a guard of sentries. He said an underground
hall would be lit from above through a glass floor allowing the
shadows of the trees to fall into the hall. The plan also calls for
a waterfall in connection with the pool that is a feature of the
memorial gate.
   <PERSON>Galford</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> team's design would include a
spiraling ramp recessed into the four-acre site in front of the
gate. He said it also would include rooms dedicated to women's role
in each of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s wars, and a platform overlooking the cemetery
and the grave of <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Manfredi</PERSON> said the New York-Washington entry would involve 10
clear glass prisms, illuminating exhibits telling the story of women
in the military. The spires would be about 18 feet high, he said.
The 10 niches of the existing structure would be pierced by stairs
and become gateways to the cemetery.
   Gen. <PERSON>Vaught</PERSON> said judges recommended making a fourth entry,
submitted by <PERSON>Stephen D. Siegle</PERSON> and <PERSON>Margaret Derwent</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, an
alternate in case one of the other three dropped out. Instead, she
said, the foundation chose to makle the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> entry an additional
finalist, although its designers did not share in the prize money.
   Unlike the other entries, the Siegle-Derwent design calls for
building an educational-cultural center.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-40547 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpjst007__l94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-JST-94-007L </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Science &amp; Technology 

</HEADER>

<ABS>  Japan </ABS>
<DATE1>   17 February 1994 </DATE1>
<F P=100> Aerospace </F>
<H3> <TI>   Guidance Alignment Building for H-2 Launch Site Detailed </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  94P60095A Tokyo NASDA NEWS in Japanese Oct 93 pp 8-9 -- FOR 
OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> 94P60095A </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo NASDA NEWS </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FP=105> Japanese </F>
Article Type:CSO 
