<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06010225 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06010225 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  NEW-YORK; PUBLIC; LIBRARY; BOOK  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IN 1857, Elisha G. Otis invented the passenger elevator. Fifteen years later,
William LeBaron Jenny designed the first skyscraper, a 10-story structure.;   
Naturally, someone had to invent the elevator before someone could build a
skyscraper, but the same year that gave us the skyscraper gave us the
commercial electric fan. Cool.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHADDYA WANT TO KNOW? IT'S HERE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Books  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     If these seemingly disparate historical tidbits attract you, then leaf
through "The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Public Library Desk Reference," a book full of
surprises. It is based on the more than 5 million questions the library and
its 82 branches answer each year.;    <PERSON>Vartan Gregorian</PERSON>, former president and
chief executive officer of the library, writes in his preface, ". . . unlike
annuals and almanacs that need revising and updating each year, the <ORGANIZATION>Desk
Reference</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Stonesong Press</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$34.95</MONEY>) holds a considerable amount of true
reference information, unchanging basic facts and background.;    "We also
hope that our book will be easy to read and fun to browse through.";    It
is.;    For instance, if you know <PERSON>Thomas Alva Edison</PERSON> invented the phonograph
in <DATE>1878</DATE>, you will be pleased to know <PERSON>L.O. Colvin</PERSON>  invented the milking machine
the same year, and <PERSON>James J. Ritty</PERSON>  invented the cash register the year after
that.;    These were heady times, a veritable cascade of brainstorms. But
every year was like that.;    For instance, last year was the 110th birthday
of the hearing aid, and the 120th for linoleum and the snap button. It also
was the 100th anniversary of motion pictures and the electric subway. It was
the 90th anniversary of the paper clip.;    This year is the 100th birthday of
the flashlight (by <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Bristol Electric Lamp Co.</ORGANIZATION>), the aluminum boat (by
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Escher Wyss &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>) and the zipper (by <PERSON>Whitcombe L. Judson</PERSON>).;   
The Desk Reference has less esoteric fare. It tells you how to write your
member of congress and how to call toll-free for rental cars and hotels. There
are 15 pages of visa requirements to travel anywhere from <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> to
Zimbabwe.;    There is an illustrated section on the human anatomy and one on
how to play board games from backgammon to Scrabble or cards  from blackjack
to solitaire.;    There is simply no way to list all of the tidy bits of
information from dietary tables to musical terms and symbols,  from extinct
animals to semaphore, from etiquette to legal forms, from animal first aid to
a directory of poison control centers.;    It's also a settler of arguments.
Take religion: The book says there are 648 million Hindus, 18 million Jews,
840 million Muslims, 158 million Orthodox Catholics, 307 million Buddhists and
5.6 million followers of Confucius.;    In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, there are 31
million Baptists, 2.7 million Episcopalians, 13.5 million Methodists, 2.8
million Mormons, 8 million Lutherans and 700,000 Jehovah's Witnesses. But
worldwide, there are 900 million Roman Catholics, the largest <ORGANIZATION>Christian Church</ORGANIZATION>
in the world. It takes 6 1/2 pages to list all the popes.;    One thing that
strikes the reader is how long ago some of the inventions sprang from the
human mind. And what in the world did mankind do before they came along?;   
We were blessed with the screwdriver and wrench about 1550 by unknown
gunsmiths.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JOHN BARBOUR, Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910110  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  530  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, January 10, 1991
00010225,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891009-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-09-89 1219EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--PaperClip     10-09 0113</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Paper Clip,0115</SECOND>
<HEAD>Try Making a Chain Out of These</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OSLO, Norway (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 22{-foot-tall paper clip was unveiled
outside a business college <DATE>Monday</DATE> to honor the Norwegian who
invented the office helper 90 years ago.
   The paper clip, weighing a desk-crushing 1,320 pounds, is a
faithful copy of Norwegian <PERSON>Johan Vaaler</PERSON>'s <DATE>1899</DATE> invention, said Per
Langaker of the <ORGANIZATION>Norwegian School of Management</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The paper clip is <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT> accurate and fully functional if
anyone has big enough paper,'' said <PERSON>Langanker</PERSON>, 23, of the school's
student committee.
   The paper clip was made from steel tubing and is mounted on a
6-ton concrete base outside the institute in <LOCATION>Baerum</LOCATION>, an <LOCATION>Oslo</LOCATION> suburb.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901231-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-31-90 1349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-APN--LibraryTrivia ADV13   12-31 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Library Trivia, ADV 13,0900</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv13</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Jan. 13</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1
graphic.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - There is a fascination for some, usually the
doers of crossword puzzles and fans of Trivial Pursuit, in trifling
information. Here is a book of facts great and small, distilled
from millions of questions asked of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION> by
people who can't take ``don't know'' for an answer.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - There is a fascination for some, usually the
doers of crossword puzzles and fans of Trivial Pursuit, in trifling
information. Here is a book of facts great and small, distilled
from millions of questions asked of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION> by
people who can't take ``don't know'' for an answer.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By JOHN BARBOUR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - There is a fascination for some, usually the
doers of crossword puzzles and fans of Trivial Pursuit, in trifling
information. Here is a book of facts great and small, distilled
from millions of questions asked of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION> by
people who can't take ``don't know'' for an answer.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV Sunday Jan. 13</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - There is a fascination for some, usually the
doers of crossword puzzles and fans of Trivial Pursuit, in trifling
information. Here is a book of facts great and small, distilled
from millions of questions asked of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION> by
people who can't take ``don't know'' for an answer.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051389-0137 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 57364 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 13, 1989, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 21; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
664 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THEY READ IT IN THE PAPER CLIPPINGS; 
</P>
<P>
IN HER FAMILY, A PUBLIC MEDIUM RELAYS MEMBERS' PRIVATE MESSAGES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARILYN GARDNER, The Christian Science Monitor 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Most days, mail call at our house is a ho-hum event. Only an occasional letter 
breaks the monotony of all those catalogues, credit-card applications, 
sweepstakes entries, and <LOCATION>Cape Cod</LOCATION> time-share lures that burden our mail carrier 
and quickly fill our wastebaskets. 
</P>
<P>
But several times a month an oversize envelope bearing a <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> postmark and 
the familiar handwriting of one of my parents appears in the mailbox. Instantly 
my spirits rise: another batch of clippings! 
</P>
<P>
For more years than I can remember, my parents and I have been trading 
clippings the way boys trade baseball cards. In the beginning, we simply 
enclosed an article or two in the same envelope with a letter. But gradually, 
as we spent more time talking on the telephone and less time writing letters, 
the clippings assumed a life of their own. Now bulky <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> envelopes regularly 
wing their way between our respective ZIP codes, carrying everything from 
editorials, political cartoons and interviews to columns, book reviews, and 
recipes. 
</P>
<P>
The best packets of clippings are, in fact, like a balanced meal, offering 
something nutritious -- a well-argued op-ed piece, perhaps -- topped off with 
something light and sweet such as a cartoon or comic strip. 
</P>
<P>
Armed with scissors and a ballpoint, veteran clippers approach each day's 
newspaper with enthusiasm. We read. We clip. We underline. We write relevant, 
and sometimes funny, comments in the margins. We also attach yellow Post-It 
notes explaining our choices or amplifying points. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Network Expands 
</P>
<P>
Over the years, my network of newsprint pen pals has expanded. In a typical 
week, I might save an article about a major auction for an aunt and uncle in 
<LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION> who collect antiques. For my sister, a high school Spanish teacher in 
<LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, I may clip a travel story about museums in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. A New 
Yorker cartoon about cats and a story on <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION>'s controversial new video will 
be tucked into the next letter to our daughter at college. And the latest 
position paper on the <ORGANIZATION>Great Books</ORGANIZATION> controversy will find its way into an 
envelope for a self-improvement enthusiast in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Even the most dedicated clipper knows better than to think that borrowed words 
on folded newsprint can ever take the place of a real letter containing 
personal news and private opinions. But for those of us whose busy schedules 
allow little time for proper correspondence -- and who have the phone bills to 
prove it -- these patchwork collections, custom-tailored to the recipient, can 
serve as love notes on the run. 
</P>
<P>
Not everyone agrees, of course. There are those who disdain the smudgy 
practice, harrumphing all the way to the post office that only a handwritten 
letter in the 18th-Century manner constitutes a proper communication with 
friends and relatives. 
</P>
<P>
But as a veteran collector of mailable tidbits, I disagree. I like to think of 
a clipping as a compliment, a shorthand way of saying, "You're in my thoughts." 
</P>
<P>
Over time, a collection of clippings forms a mosaic, creating a portrait of the 
sender. In our choice of articles and jokes and photos, we give ourselves away, 
revealing our senses of humor, our politics, our serious and not-so-serious 
interests. Indirectly we are saying, "This is who I am." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Coded Messages 
</P>
<P>
At the same time, as we choose subjects of interest to the recipient, we are 
saying, "This is who I think you are; send me a clipping if you think I'm 
wrong." 
</P>
<P>
On sensitive subjects, clippings can serve as diplomatically coded messages. My 
mother, for instance, might send a page from a catalogue with the notation, "I 
think these curtains could look very nice in your family room." An article on 
overwork, passed along without comment, is her oblique way of expressing 
maternal concern. 
</P>
<P>
As a daughter, I love this particular form of conversation with my mother. So 
charmed am I by her mastery of the game that one Mother's Day I sent her a 
sterling silver paper clipper -- the perfect gift from one clipper to another. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
NEWSPAPERS; COMMUNICATIONS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-3871</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BDWB7AB5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910423
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  23 APR 91 / Technology: At the sharp end of a supply chain - Dave Madden
explains how United Stationers has turned the distribution of its goods into
a fine art
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVE MADDEN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Distribution is one of the duller business ghettos - dusty warehouses,
broken pallets and diesel oil. But the image, and the reality, are beginning
to change.
As <ORGANIZATION>Fiat</ORGANIZATION> shows off its robot-controlled inventory stacks in glossy
advertisements and <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> switches off the lights in its automated warehouse in
<LOCATION>Greenock</LOCATION>, it is clear that this <LOCATION>Cinderella</LOCATION> operation has a new set of
high-tech glad rags.
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s high street retailer Marks and <PERSON>Spencer</PERSON> has long appreciated that
sophisticated distribution processes are an important part of supply chain
management. They influence customer loyalty, product differentiation and
profit margins. According to <PERSON>Lee Iacocca</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION>: 'The company
with the best distribution systems and service level will win all the
marbles.'
In short, advanced logistics is no longer a luxury. One consequence of this
shift is the emergence of a new type of wholesale service company where
distribution is just as important as the product that is shipped.
Take paper clips. If you are an office products wholesaler, how do you get
retailers to buy such a simple, undifferentiated item from you, rather than
from any number of your competitors?
The answer, in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> at least, is 'value-added' distribution. <ORGANIZATION>United
Stationers</ORGANIZATION>, the country's biggest office products distributor, can sell and
ship a single pencil or one box of paper clips and still make a profit.
The same is true on all 25,000 items in its catalogue, from pens to filing
cabinets. And if a customer places an order by 6.00 pm it will be delivered
by 9.00 am the next morning to any location in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.
Not surprisingly, this demands an extensive physical operation. <ORGANIZATION>United
Stationers</ORGANIZATION>, based near <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, sells products from around 400 manufacturers
to some 10,000 retailers across the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, via 14 regional distribution
centres.
This physical network is entirely dependent on a complex computing and
telecommunications infrastructure: <ORGANIZATION>Amdahl</ORGANIZATION> 5995 and <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> 3090 mainframes
supported by robotic storage devices from <ORGANIZATION>Storage Technology</ORGANIZATION> as well as
telephone and satellite communications networks. In all an incremental
investment of some Dollars 200m (Pounds 115m).
United's customers obtain information on the company's inventory via a
computer network which connects their machines to <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION>'s system of 1,400
PCs. This automates the ordering process and allows clients to see whether
<ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> has a particular product in stock.
'Our customers enter upwards of 70 per cent of our orders for us,' says
<PERSON>Patrick Murray</PERSON>, IT vice president. 'We do it in lots of different ways. We
talk to everybody's computer. We do it in batch mode, we do it online -
however a customer requires it.'
Ultimately, <PERSON>Murray</PERSON> expects <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION>'s terminals to be on the desks of his
customers' customers too, and he intends to apply the same technology to
links with his own suppliers.
Ordering is only part of the value-added process. The sooner the retailer
knows that <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> has shipped goods, the sooner he can bill his customer and
collect his money, says <PERSON>Murray</PERSON>. Similarly <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> uses the system to get the
latest manufacturers' pricing information to these retailers, so that they
can manage their prices too.
Giving retailers such access to and control over the ordering and inventory
process, and the imperative to turn orders around in hours, has had serious
implications for <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION>'s warehousing operation.
Items are not stored in pre-defined areas. Rather, they are put in the next
available bin, as dictated by <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION>'s disparate product range: boxes of
pencils and desks do not take up the same shaped space. The warehouse map is
computer-controlled and the system tracks every individual batch of items.
Surprisingly, this random binning is not completely arbitrary. The system is
able to analyse the inventory and track 'hot' products - high moving items -
and guide them to where they are most accessible.
When a piece of inventory is manually put into store, staff use radio
frequency data entry terminals, complete with bar-coded reading guns, to
update the control system directly on line.
The logical extension of all this, says <PERSON>Murray</PERSON>, is to use similar tools and
driver can verify that the right carton has been dropped at the right door,
and give proof of delivery. United hopes to introduce such an innovation
this year.
The same integrated technology feeds <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION>'s sales and marketing effort.
Its primary marketing tool is a catalogue of products, and <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> publishes
and distributes some 4m copies a year.
But because the catalogue becomes out of date almost immediately after it is
issued (with products being added or dropped), <PERSON>Murray</PERSON> has to provide regular
updates. He is hoping in the near future, however, to produce an electronic
catalogue, with colour pictures, dimension data and moving price
information.
At the hub of <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION>'s operation is a central IT development and operations
staff. Typically this is pared to the bone - <DATE>40</DATE> people to manage data and
voice communications, systems operations and a help desk (there is no
computer expertise in the regional centres). In addition, <PERSON>Murray</PERSON> has 100
staff in applications development and product introduction.
The effect of this technological commitment is two fold, <PERSON>Murray</PERSON> says. First,
<ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> has grown significantly - it is now a Dollars 1bn company, and one of
just four national office products distributors in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>. Second, its
technology culture has enabled <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> to set pioneering service levels.
For example, <PERSON>Murray</PERSON> explains: 'We are doing lots of small orders. About 80
per cent of what we sell is not in the same packaging that it came to us in.
We don't sell a whole carton of paper - we'll sell one ream. Now the service
we provide for our reseller says you go out to each of your customers and
you take the orders the way they want them.
'You send the orders to us and we'll package them in such a way that they
can be delivered directly to the end user and you don't have to add labour.
When we put the label on the box the label says it came from you not from
us. Our dealer doesn't have to handle the merchandise at all. The most
profitable dealer is the guy who never sees the merchandise, absolutely
never sees it at all.'
The downside is that higher expectations become institutionalised. Because
<ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> delivers anywhere in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> by the following day, and guarantees to
be in stock on all of its inventory, that has become the service norm.
Similarly United cannot afford to let up on its technical innovation. Murray
claims that the company currently has a lead of six to 12 months, but 'the
competition is pretty good at copying - so we better have the next thing
coming up to keep the gap open. To get the order we've got to be the easiest
company to do business with,' he says.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 12 Illustration (Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890302-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-02-89 0827EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-JailSmokes     03-02 0270</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Jail Smokes,0279</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ban On Jailhouse Smoking Has Inmates Fuming</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GRANTS PASS, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One year after smoking was outlawed in
the <LOCATION>Josephine County Jail</LOCATION>, the inmates are fuming, but the jailers
are smiling.
   Jail Commander <PERSON>Mark Dickson</PERSON> said inmates are fighting less and
are much healthier since cigarettes _ jailhouse currency for
generations _ were taken away.
   ``In fact, I have had far more inmates come up to me since this
was issued and thank us for the policy, because it forced them to
quit smoking,'' <PERSON>Dickson</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Inmate <PERSON>Ron Wise</PERSON> wasn't one of them.
   ``It's unconstitutional deprivation, in my way of thinking,'' he
said. ``The sheriff has taken it upon himself to decide what's good
for us.''
   <PERSON>Dickson</PERSON> said the jail was the first in <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> to outlaw tobacco,
but others have followed suit. He estimated <PERCENT>95 percent</PERCENT> of the
inmates smoked when they entered jail.
   Inmates found smuggling in tobacco aren't punished; the goods are
merely confiscated, <PERSON>Dickson</PERSON> said.
   Blackened electrical outlets are evidence that some cigarettes
are getting in. Inmates who can find something to smoke but don't
have matches put a paper clip in the outlet, then draw a spark with
another paper clip, <PERSON>Dickson</PERSON> said.
   One inmate was so desparate for a smoke he rolled herbal tea in
toilet paper and lit up, the commander said.
   With cigarettes out of the way, the jail is cutting back on
caffeine. Coffee with caffeine is no longer available at lunch and
will soon be gone from the dinner table.
   ``I think we have an obligation to maintain the healthiest
environment possible,'' <PERSON>Dickson</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042289-0014 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 47252 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 22, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 21; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
229 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NORTH JURORS DELIBERATE FOR 5 1/2 HOURS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From a Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A jury of nine women and three men deliberated for 5 1/2 hours <DATE>Friday</DATE> without 
reaching a verdict in the case against former <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> aide <PERSON>Oliver L. North</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Gerhard A. Gesell</PERSON> excused the jurors for the day and 
instructed them to return to the courthouse this morning to resume 
deliberations. 
</P>
<P>
If they fail to reach a verdict <DATE>today</DATE>, they will take <DATE>Sunday</DATE> off before 
deliberating again on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, court officials said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Asks for <ORGANIZATION>Paper Clips 
</P>
<P>
Jury</ORGANIZATION> foreman <PERSON>Denise Anderson</PERSON> sent <PERSON>Gesell</PERSON> a note <DATE>Friday</DATE> asking for additional 
note pads, pencils and paper clips -- and requesting lunch at the same time 
each day -- indicating that deliberations on the 12 criminal counts against 
North in the Iran-Contra case may take several days. Jurors are being 
sequestered at night in a downtown hotel. 
</P>
<P>
Anderson added that "everyone would like a copy of the instructions" that 
<PERSON>Gesell</PERSON> read to the jury <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. <PERSON>Gesell</PERSON> agreed to furnish duplicates of the 
approximately 40-page text. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, an alternate juror who was present for all eight weeks of testimony 
said she would have voted to convict North on at least some of the charges 
against him. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Horasina McKie</PERSON>, one of five alternates dismissed when the case went to the 
regular jury on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, said that, in accordance with the judge's 
instructions, she had not discussed the evidence with other jurors. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
GUERRILLAS -- NICARAGUA; NORTH, OLIVER L; UNITED STATES -- MILITARY AID -- 
NICARAGUA; UNITED STATES -- ARMS SALES -- IRAN; LYING 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA040790-0039 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 200843 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 7, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part F; Page 20; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
451 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SHAKING YOUR FAMILY TREE: KEEPSAKES MUST BE KEPT SAFELY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MYRA VANDERPOOL GORMLEY 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Among the keepsakes of genealogists are photographs of ancestors and paper 
certificates, documents and newspaper clippings. However, if they are 
improperly stored, they will not last long enough to be a treasure of 
generations to come. 
</P>
<P>
Attics and basements are the worst places to store keepsakes. Valuable photos 
should be kept where temperature, humidity and light levels are low. Color 
prints are best stored below 75 degrees Fahrenheit and <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> humidity, and in the 
dark. Avoid using plastic storage containers that may contain polyvinyl 
chloride. 
</P>
<P>
Acid-neutral boxes and envelopes are available. If you use envelopes and 
sleeves to hold your photos and slides, be sure they are made of acid-neutral 
paper, or polyester, archival polyethylene, or triacetate plastic film. 
</P>
<P>
Use photo albums with acid-neutral pages and avoid waxed pages. Adhesive tape, 
white glue, rubber cement, paper clips and mothballs or crystals can damage 
your photos. To label photos on the backside before storing or displaying -- 
and all your photographs should be identified with names, dates and places -- 
use a soft No. 1 pencil and press lightly. 
</P>
<P>
Copy old photos first, then store the negatives in a dark place. 
Black-and-white negatives will last a long time if well cared for. However, 
color slides may last only 10 to 50 years, depending on care. 
</P>
<P>
Use acid-free materials when mounting newspaper clippings and other paper 
items. Pastes made from flour and water, wheat or rice are less acidic and less 
damaging than most other pastes. However, they are subject to mildew and 
household pest damage, and may bubble or ripple the item. Linen tape can be 
used for mounting. Find an art supply store for these supplies. Before using 
anything on a valuable item, test each product for any initial staining or 
damage. 
</P>
<P>
Photocopies of clippings can be mounted in scrapbooks, but the originals should 
be placed in a dark storage container. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>American Assn. for State</ORGANIZATION> and Local History (AASLH), 708 <LOCATION>Berry Road</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION> 37204, publishes books and technical leaflets on the 
collection, care and preservation of many items. 
</P>
<P>
If you want to know specifically what your antiques, collectibles or keepsakes 
are worth and to document their value, you will need the services of a personal 
property appraiser. Appraisers of antique and collectible keepsakes should be 
specialists. Spend as much time finding a qualified appraiser as you would 
looking for a professional in any field. 
</P>
<P>
Once you have obtained an appraisal, it should be dated, signed by the 
appraiser, along with the purpose of the appraisal and the qualities and 
disinterest of the appraiser noted. Keep the appraisal in your safety deposit 
box. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920203-0091
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920203-0091.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   REVIEW &amp; OUTLOOK (Editorial) -- Asides:
   Operation Paper Clip II
</HL>
<DATE>
02/03/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<CO>
   LABOR
</CO>
<MS>
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
AEROSPACE (ARO)
NUCLEAR POWER, FUEL (NUK)
</IN>
<NS>
LABOR, UNIONS, STRIKES, WAGES, RECRUITMENT (LAB)
NUCLEAR POWER, ENERGY (NUK)
</NS>
<RE>
EASTERN EUROPE (EEU)
EUROPE (EU)
FAR EAST (FE)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
COMMONWEALTH OF INDEPENDENT STATES (UR)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Boris Yeltsin, who first proposed a joint SDI program with
the U.S., is looking for a solution to another nuclear threat
on his -- and our -- hands. What to do with the Russian
nuclear engineers and scientists who reportedly are getting
lucrative offers to relocate to Third World capitals? Russian
academic Evygeny Belikov says that while top scientists
aren't hopping on planes just yet, the country's nuclear
brain trust of some 3,000 people has a network of unsavory
contacts. It was the Russians, for example, who worked on
fusion for Moammar Gadhafi. Russians can use the threat of
rogue scientists as a sales pitch for Western financial aid,
but we have a better idea: Operation Paper Clip. After the
Second World War, Britain and the U.S. cooperated in this
program to buy off, de-Nazify and relocate Hitler's
rocket-builders, including Wernher von Braun. Let's do it
again, for Russians. The cost could be low considering that
Moscow pays even its best nuclear scientists about $100 a
month at the ruble's current depressed rate. Ignoring the
opportunity could mean facing the results of Ivan Rocket
Scientist's work from Baghdad or Tripoli.
</LP>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031290-0028 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 188343 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 12, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 1; Column 2; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
504 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FOOTNOTES: SINGING THE BLUE CROSS BLUES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Blue Cross of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> has the blues because it thinks that the press is 
ignoring it, but the health insurer isn't suffering in silence. In a recent 
letter to the editor of the trade paper <ORGANIZATION>Managed HealthCare</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Blue Cross</ORGANIZATION> Chief 
Executive <PERSON>Leonard D. Schaeffer</PERSON> complimented the editors for a recent article on 
the <ORGANIZATION>Blue Cross/Blue Shield</ORGANIZATION> system. 
</P>
<P>
However, he added, "as usual, the Chicago-based Blue Cross and <ORGANIZATION>Blue Shield 
Assn.</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> Plan were interviewed for the article. We were not 
contacted, even though <ORGANIZATION>Blue Cross of California</ORGANIZATION> has more members in managed 
care than any other 'Blue' Plan." 
</P>
<P>
Lately, <ORGANIZATION>Blue Cross</ORGANIZATION>'s public relations agency has been sending letters to 
editors offering interviews with the chairman, who is described as "the 
architect of a stunning two-year turnaround of the once-failing health 
insurance giant." 
</P>
<P>
A Royal Pain for Imperial 
</P>
<P>
Things are tough enough in the banking and thrift business without having 
people confuse you with a troubled operation. 
</P>
<P>
The woes at <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Savings &amp; Loan</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> are causing headaches for 
at least two unrelated <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> institutions, <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Thrift &amp; 
Loan</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Burbank</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Imperial, the bank, is making sure people know that it has no ties to Imperial, 
the savings and loan. Its ads now include a paragraph in large letters: 
"Imperial Bank is not -- nor has it ever been -- affiliated with <ORGANIZATION>Imperial 
Savings &amp; Loan</ORGANIZATION> or its parent, <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
And Trouble at <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln Too 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln Bancorp</ORGANIZATION> suffers from a similar problem. <PERSON>John J. Keating</PERSON>, 
chief executive of the <LOCATION>Encino</LOCATION> holding company for <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln National Bank</ORGANIZATION>, says, 
"I've got the double whammy." Customers and others muddle his bank's name with 
that of <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln Savings &amp; Loan</ORGANIZATION>, and they confuse him with <PERSON>Charles H. 
Keating Jr.</PERSON>, the controversial chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>S&amp;L</ORGANIZATION>'s parent company. The 
two are not related. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Lincoln Bancorp</ORGANIZATION>'s board wants to change the institution's name. There's an 
employee contest to rename the bank, but no one has yet won the prize, a 
Hawaiian vacation. Several suggestions were turned down. So was a consultant 
who offered to come up with a new name for <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Bear <PERSON>Stearns</PERSON>' Miserly Ways 
</P>
<P>
In the current severe slump of the securities industry, the Wall Street firm 
<ORGANIZATION>Bear Stearns Cos.</ORGANIZATION> is one of the relatively few prospering brokerages. This is 
in part because of the notorious penny-pinching ways of the firm's chairman and 
chief executive, <ORGANIZATION>Alan C.</ORGANIZATION> (Ace) <PERSON>Greenberg</PERSON>. Staffers complain that paper clips, 
pencils and rubber bands are in short supply. Employees are told to save paper 
clips from incoming mail. Now <PERSON>Greenberg</PERSON> has carried the campaign a step 
further: Employees recently received notification that they will have to turn 
their frequent-flyer miles from business trips back to the company to be used 
to pay for other business trips. But one staff member said it probably won't 
make much difference to most employees. "People never have time to even take 
vacations," the executive said. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, John J. Keating ; Photo, Charles H. Keating Jr. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AnonymousElmer     08-26 0803</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Anonymous Elmer,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Who's That Crouching Next to the Pianist? Hey, It's Elmer Booze!</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Elmer Booze strides onto the concert stage for
another virtuoso performance, but nobody applauds. He shares the
spotlight but never takes a bow. His name doesn't even appear in
the program.
   So what? The guy spends most of the evening staring at the sheet
music and wetting his thumb and forefinger. Big deal.
   Any pianist, though, will say that <PERSON>Elmer Booze</PERSON> really is a big
deal. He is a professional page turner, one of the most
indispensable _ and most anonymous _ figures in the musical world.
   Booze, 57, a small, soft-spoken man who wears gold-rimmed
glasses, has turned the pages of musical scores for <PERSON>Aaron Copland</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Rudolf Serkin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Andre Watts</PERSON>, <PERSON>Leon Fleisher</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bella Davidovich</PERSON> and
hundreds of other musicians for nearly a quarter-century.
   He turned pages for opera singer <ORGANIZATION>Leontyne Price</ORGANIZATION>'s accompanist at
a <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> recital for President <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>. He's been a consultant
and resident page turner for the annual summer <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>) Music
Festival for the past 14 years.
   He's a regular at concert series at the <ORGANIZATION>National Gallery of Art</ORGANIZATION>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian Embassy</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Center</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Library of
Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. He has flown to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> to sit
at the elbow of concert pianists who insisted that only Elmer Booze
would do.
   An accomplished pianist himself, with music degrees from two
universities, Booze is content to labor in the shadows of the
keyboard giants.
   A colleague at the <ORGANIZATION>Library of Congress</ORGANIZATION>, where Booze works during
the day as a senior reference librarian in the music division,
proudly calls him ``a world-renowned page turner.'' Booze modestly
dismisses such extravagant praise.
   ``For me, it's a job that anybody can do,'' he said. ``But
apparently that's not entirely true. I've talked to pianists who
say they can't turn pages. It makes them very nervous.''
   By contrast, Booze sits on the edge of his chair with
unflappable ease as the pianist struggles through stormy
fortissimos and crashing arpeggios.
   ``Pianists want someone with them in their greatest moment of
need, when they've gotten to the last note on the page,'' he said.
   That's the moment when Booze shifts into a low crouch and, with
a lightning thrust of the arm, flips to the next page and returns
to his seat. His movements are so unobtrusive that one pianist
calls him ``the ghost.''
   A good page turner must be skilled in reading a musical score,
Booze says, and a rehearsal is helpful to become familiar with the
pianist's eccentricities.
   Does he memorize the score? (Chamber music is rarely played from
memory, Booze says.) Are the pianist's jerks and nods a signal to
turn the page, or is he simply getting carried away with the music?
Are the pages old and brittle? Do they stick together?
   Onstage, he says, a page turner should keep his eyes on the
music and maintain ``a certain decorum'' to put the pianist at ease.
   ``If there's panic in your eyes, you can believe the pianist
will panic, too,'' he said. ``The last thing he needs is a spastic
page turner.''
   Despite the page turner's best efforts, disasters do happen.
Booze recalls the nightmarish evening of the missing paper clip.
   His pianist had promised in the dressing room of the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy
Center Concert Hall</ORGANIZATION> to insert a paper clip in the score of a
devilishly complex work by <PERSON>Franz Liszt</PERSON> for two pianos. At the point
when Booze was supposed to turn back 20 pages for a repeat in the
second movement, the paper clip wasn't there.
   ``It was something to behold,'' he said. ``He was going like a
bat out of hell. His arms were in my way and mine were in his,
trying to find the exact page. Both pianists stopped playing, and
the whole thing came to a screeching halt. It was not a good show.''
   Booze has left his tuxedo jacket unbuttoned during concerts ever
since he rose from his chair to turn a page for <PERSON>Aaron Copland</PERSON> and a
button popped onto the keyboard while the composer was performing
at the <ORGANIZATION>Library of Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   Booze turned another anxious moment into a tour de force that
garnered the first and only ovation he has ever received from an
audience.
   When he and a pianist took their seats at the <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION> festival,
they discovered that the piano's music rack had been removed and
was nowhere to be found. So Booze became a human music rack,
holding up photocopies of each page of the score.
   When the piece was finished, the festival president leaped to
her feet. ``Let's all clap for Elmer,'' she shouted, and the page
turner shyly emerged from the shadows to accept his acclaim.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900429-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-29-90 1617EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BaseballArtist     04-29 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baseball Artist,0451</SECOND>
<HEAD>Artist Paints Tiny Portraits on Baseballs, Rice</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALTON, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Dave Stevens</PERSON> has an acute eye for art.
   He also has great acuity of vision _ <DATE>20-17</DATE> to be exact _ which
enables him to paint tiny portraits on grains of rice, watch faces
and the heads of pins.
   His miniature portrait of <ORGANIZATION>St. Louis Cardinal</ORGANIZATION> shortstop <PERSON>Ozzie
Smith</PERSON> on a grain of rice is enshrined in the <LOCATION>St. Louis Baseball
Hall</LOCATION> of Fame.
   Now his attention has turned to bigger things: portraits of
Cardinals manager <PERSON>Whitey Herzog</PERSON> on baseballs.
   ``<PERSON>Herzog</PERSON> has a banquet coming up at the end of <DATE>May</DATE>. I have to do
seven dozen portraits in seven weeks,'' he said, dipping a tiny
brush into a palette.
   The Alton artist painted 100 baseballs with <PERSON>Herzog</PERSON>'s likeness
for the manager last year. Herzog auctioned them off to benefit the
<ORGANIZATION>YMCA</ORGANIZATION>.
   A baseball card serves as <PERSON>Stevens</PERSON>' inspiration and he creates
his art on a TV tray in his living room. It takes <PERSON>Stevens</PERSON> about one
hour to paint <PERSON>Herzog</PERSON>'s portrait on the back of a regulation
baseball.
   ``I do it over and over so they're not identical, but I want
them as close as possible,'' he says.
   Stevens collects <MONEY>$25</MONEY> per portrait, not including the cost of the
ball.
   He doesn't limit his subjects to baseball players or baseballs.
His favorite effort: a grinning <PERSON>Mickey Mouse</PERSON> on the head of a
straight pin.
   ``I've done portraits on old lockets and inside pocket watch
covers,'' he said. ``Once I took the crystal out and painted a
player in the batting stance on the face of a watch. I made the bat
on the big hand and the ball with all the stitchings on the end of
the small hand,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Steven</PERSON>'s smallest painting is a skull and crossbones on the tip
of a paper clip for a motorcycle rider.
   ``I read the smallest painting in the world is on the head of a
pin, so I used the paper clip. The wire tip is as small as a shaft
of the pin,'' the artist said.
   Most of his ideas come from customers who want, for example, a
portrait of an anniversary couple on rice or a color drawing of a
favorite car encased on a belt buckle, <PERSON>Stevens</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Stevens</PERSON> began creating miniature art six years ago out of
boredom.
   ``It was one of those weekends in <DATE>August</DATE> when nothing was on TV
and I had been asleep on the couch,'' he said. ``I painted a scene
on a stone the size of a quarter and it snowballed after that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091290-0180 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 275841 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 12, 1990, Wednesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<P>
LUCY CORDOVA 
</P>
<SECTION>
<P>
Special Section; Part S; Page 10; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
816 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FASHION: FALL ISSUE; 
</P>
<P>
INNOVATIVE EARRING MAKER FINDS GOLD IN MOTHER LOBE OF JUNK; 
</P>
<P>
JEWELRY: ALMOST ANY COMMON OBJECT -- EVEN BICYCLE TIRES -- IS FAIR GAME FOR THE 
FOUNDER OF THE JUNQUE LINE. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KATHRYN BOLD, Kathryn Bold writes about fashion for the View section. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HUNTINGTON BEACH 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Where others see trash, <PERSON>Lucy Cordova</PERSON> sees a pair of earrings. 
</P>
<P>
Bicycle tires, old records, paper clips -- no common object is too lowly for 
her lobes. 
</P>
<P>
"I make earrings out of things you wouldn't normally think they're made of," 
says the 27-year-old woman. "People don't recognize the materials. They touch 
them and say, 'Oh, they're bicycle tires!' " 
</P>
<P>
Once she has finished applying paint, glitter, pearls and rhinestones to her 
designs, few people recognize the earrings for what they are: junk. Only on 
closer inspection does one see the tread of a tire, the grooves from an old 
record. 
</P>
<P>
"I just get things around the house," she says. "I broke a glass in the kitchen 
one day and when I saw the pieces I said, 'Hey, I can use these as earrings!' " 
</P>
<P>
Her glitzy, gaudy designs are strictly for fun. One pair features three roving 
eyeballs, the plastic kind found on small stuffed toys. She sells her earrings 
on torn pieces of cardboard under the name Junque for <MONEY>$5</MONEY> to <MONEY>$10</MONEY> a pair. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't mean it to be trashy," she says. That's why she gave "junk" a faux 
French spelling. 
</P>
<P>
Cordova's fetish for earrings led her to create the Junque line. 
</P>
<P>
"I love earrings. I have 80 pairs, and I didn't get my ears pierced until I was 
19," she says. 
</P>
<P>
Two years ago, she bought a pair of earrings made from warped record fragments 
in a department store. She lost one of the earrings and couldn't find a pair to 
replace them. That's when she decided to make the earrings herself. 
</P>
<P>
"I made a couple pairs and wore them to work at a nightclub," she says. "My 
co-workers saw them and said, 'Make some for us.' I started selling them that 
way." Since then, she has expanded her line to include all kinds of everyday 
objects. 
</P>
<P>
Her method for transforming records into earrings is not terribly 
sophisticated. 
</P>
<P>
She holds a disposable lighter underneath the record to soften the vinyl, then 
cuts it with a scissors into the shape she wants. Then she melts the piece 
again to create funky waves and folds. Often, one can still see the grooves in 
the vinyl on the finished product. 
</P>
<P>
"I want people to see they are records, so the lines show," <PERSON>Cordova</PERSON> explains. 
</P>
<P>
Old records have proven the perfect medium for her big earrings, which can 
measure several inches in length and diameter. Not only is the vinyl material 
malleable, it's light enough not to weight down one's lobes. 
</P>
<P>
She buys the record albums for about <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> each at swap meets. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't even know who these people are," she says. "But I think I melted 
<PERSON>Rickie Lee Jones</PERSON> once." 
</P>
<P>
After she has worked the vinyl into the desired shape, she decorates it with 
paint, rhinestones, sequins, glitter, and even small screws and bolts. 
</P>
<P>
Cordova adorned one pair with white lace and seed pearls. Only the black vinyl 
kept them from looking like something out of a bridal magazine. 
</P>
<P>
She has painted some with old fingernail polish and coated others with 
"webbing," a spray paint that gives a lacy effect. 
</P>
<P>
Once she found an old chain in her father's garage, cut it up and attached the 
links to her earrings. She wraps geometric-shaped pieces of vinyl with scraps 
of suede donated by a friend, then sprinkles rhinestones and beads onto the 
fabric. 
</P>
<P>
As a finishing touch, she often substitutes a paper clip for the conventional 
earring hook. 
</P>
<P>
Cordova cuts up bicycle tires and decorates them in similar fashion. 
</P>
<P>
"I buy the tires new," she says. "I couldn't use old ones -- they'd be flat and 
dirty." 
</P>
<P>
While shopping at a home supply store, she bought a vinyl floor tile and turned 
it into earrings too. 
</P>
<P>
She also makes earrings out of paper. She moistens heavy, watercolor paper, 
bends it into wavy abstract shapes and lets it dry. Then she paints the 
hardened paper and douses it with glitter. One pair of pink and purple squares 
has a raised cross and iridescent sparkles. 
</P>
<P>
"I look at things and think, 'Gosh, what can I do with this?' " she says, 
holding up a plastic bottle that she has cut up for future earrings. 
</P>
<P>
All of <ORGANIZATION>Cordova</ORGANIZATION>'s designs are big, gaudy and fun. 
</P>
<P>
"I like big earrings." 
</P>
<P>
One pair features fragments of an old 33 rpm folded and painted with silver 
webbing. A triangle-shaped pair comes in teal-colored suede littered with a 
small rhinestone, beads and a narrow strip of iridescent film. 
</P>
<P>
"The earrings are good conversation pieces," <PERSON>Cordova</PERSON> says. "A girl looked at me 
the other day and said, 'You put a paper clip through your ear?' 
</P>
<P>
"That's why I like them." 
</P>
<P>
She's also started making bolo ties out of records. The vinyl's warped shapes 
suit bolos perfectly and appeal to men who want a different look when they're 
trolling the nightclubs. 
</P>
<P>
Junque sells at <ORGANIZATION>Total Effect 'n' Fashion</ORGANIZATION> at <DATE>1142</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>N. Brookhurst St.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Cordova concedes that her disposable earrings are not for everyone. They're for 
people who, like her, prefer clothes and costume jewelry that are "trendy and 
fun." 
</P>
<P>
"It takes a certain kind of person," she notes. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, One of her models are earrings made from old records, which she softens 
with a lighter and cuts the design with scissors. PETER ROSS / Los Angeles 
Times; Photo, Lucy Cordova fashions her Junque earrings from this and that in 
her apartment. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FASHION DESIGNERS; JEWELRY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06339097 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06339097 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; EDUCATION; SCIENCE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  LAST WEEK I mentioned that no one, no scientist or teacher, knows precisely
why the Earth behaves like a giant magnet. But we have learned a lot about
magnets in general, ever since our ancestors thousands of years ago unearthed
some strange black rocks that seemed to hold an invisible and mysterious power
over any particles or pieces of iron.;   The Greek philosopher Thales
(THAY-leez) was one of the first to study the properties of this mineral, and
since he obtained his samples from an area called Magnesia, he called the
mineral "magnes," from which we get our word "magnet" as well as the modern
name for this iron oxide, "magnetite."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  East Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DRAW CURIOSITY TO MAGNETS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Also ran in EX1/3, EX4/4, WL4; Education; Family Learning  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     In more recent centuries this material was known as "lodestone," which
meant a "leading stone," because when it was allowed to move freely, it would
point in a northerly direction, and so could "lead" ships on their proper
course.;   Having a compass and a bar magnet or two around the house is a
great way to tap your children's innate curiosity about the physical world,
and to encourage them to investigate and experiment with "hands-on" science as
well. It also provides parents a way to practice a set of behaviors that will
encourage children to learn for themselves.;   Amazing phenomenon the first
time;   The first time that children see a magnet pick up a thumbtack off a
table from an inch or two away, they will be amazed, but they will not have an
uncontrollable need to know the scientific explanation for this phenomenon.;  
Parents who launch right into a discussion of "lines of force" and "magnetic
poles" will miss the opportunity to have their children experience for
themselves the effect that this magnet has on a variety of materials. But if,
instead, you try the magnet on objects -- a wooden match, a paper clip,
various coins, some staples, toothpicks, safety pins, stamps, whatever is at
hand -- and preface each trial with a question like "What do you think will
happen if we try . . . ?" then your children will get a feeling for what
magnetism is. And, you will get a feeling for asking encouraging, open-ended
questions.;   We all have to make a conscious effort at developing this
questioning skill, precisely because it is so easy to lean in the other
direction and "tell" rather than "ask." Sometimes we phrase our questions so
that we are really "telling" instead of "asking" at all: "Isn't it true that .
. . ?" "Don't you think that . . . ?" or "Wouldn't it be better if . . . ?";  
Ask questions that lead to thinking;   These questions don't lead the child to
do any thinking at all, but questions that call for a prediction, and
questions like "What do you think is happening here?" certainly do. Let your
children feel the tug between two bar magnets, then turn one magnet around and
have them experience for themselves what the words "repel" and "repulsion"
feel like and mean. (How about repulsive?);   Hang a chain of paper clips or
tacks from the ends of your magnet. Can you make the same length chain closer
to the middle? How many will hang from the exact middle? "What do you think
will happen if . . . ?";   Have them see whether the magnet's power to move
tacks or clips will extend through various substances such as glass, plastic,
water and wood. "What materials do you think might block the magnet's power?";
  There are many books in the 538 section of the juvenile collection of your
library that will describe other experiments you and your children can do with
magnets and with a compass. There are no books, however, that will tell you
what questions to ask in each instance, but with a little practice, you won't
need them, either.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  William Russell column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911204  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  652  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, December 4, 1991
00339097,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880616-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-16-88 1611EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Reagan-DefenseProbe     06-16 0605</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan-Defense Probe,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Termed `Very Concerned' About Pentagon Probe</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Defense Probe Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MERRILL HARTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taking a rare active role in an ongoing
federal investigation, President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> told top law enforcement
officials <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to move ``as rapidly as possible'' to get the
facts in a burgeoning <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> fraud investigation.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, who told <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> two years ago that he did not want
lawmakers ``scrutinizing every paper clip, bolt and bullet'' in the
defense budget, was described by spokesman <PERSON>Marlim Fitzwater</PERSON> as
``very concerned'' about allegations of bribe-paying and kickbacks.
   ``I think we're all aware of the wide scope of this
investigation,'' <PERSON>Fitzwater</PERSON> said, ``and it certainly poses an
internal security problem and an abuse problem of dimensions that
have to be dealt with forthrightly.''
   ``I'm just not at liberty to expand on any of the details,'' he
said when asked to elaborate.
   Federal investigators armed with evidence from two years' worth
of wiretaps and this week's coast-to-coast raids are preparing to
approach witnesses who now may be forced to cooperate in the probe.
   The investigation has turned up ``rampant bribery in the
government'' and includes allegations of cash payments, purchase of
cars and payments of bills for government employees, <PERSON>Sen. John
Warner</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, the ranking Republican member of the <ORGANIZATION>Armed
Services Committee</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Fitzwater</PERSON> said <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> believes this is a matter ``that deserves
his attention, and that everyone involved should know of his
feelings, the intensity which he feels about dealing with any kinds
of crimes that have been committed here.''
   Government sources familiar with the probe said searches of
offices of 15 defense contractors on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> stemmed from wiretaps
on the offices of two top <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> officials. The bugs have been in
place for much of the two-year investigation.
   Reagan in <DATE>1985</DATE> created a commission to study ways to streamline
<ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> operations. The panel, headed by industrialist and former
<ORGANIZATION>Deputy Defense</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>David Packard</PERSON>, recommended a stronger hand
for the chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Joint Chiefs of Staff</ORGANIZATION> and a new civilian
office to oversee <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> purchasing.
   The commission also recommended that there be less
``micromanagement'' of the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> _ and <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> said
he agreed with that.
   ``Instead of scrutinizing every paper clip, bolt and bullet,
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> should give more thought to our overall defense needs and
strategy,'' he said.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> met with Attorney General <PERSON>Edwin Meese III</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>William Sessions</PERSON> and top <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION>
prosecutors. He had met <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Frank C.
Carlucci</PERSON>.
   Reagan seldom has involved himself directly in investigations of
alleged wrongdoing, although he was interviewed by a commission
that probed the Iran-Contra affair.
   <PERSON>Fitzwater</PERSON> said the president had not been told about the
<ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> investigation at its outset, but was not disturbed by that.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> starts hundreds of investigations that are carried out
over a long period of time. The <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> is not aware of most,
if not all of, those investigations,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Fitzwater</PERSON> said ``there always comes a time when any
investigation, when it's presented to the <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> for
criminal action or whether it's presented to a grand jury for
possible indictment, it becomes known to the civilian authority,
whether it's the president or the head of the agency or the bureau
or whatever.
   ``I'm sure that in this case, it was simply their judgment that
this was the right time to make it known to the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION>
and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Fitzwater</PERSON> said the president was ``satisfied that the bureau has
acted with the <ORGANIZATION>Naval Investigative Service</ORGANIZATION> quickly and effectively
and pursued this investigation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891002-0184 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891002 </DD>
<AN> 891002-0184. </AN>
<HL> Pepper...and Salt </HL>
<DD> 10/02/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<TEXT>






   ---







   ---



   --<PERSON>Marvin Alisky</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900213-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-13-90 0821EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MailBombs     02-13 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mail Bombs,0611</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper: FBI Seized Bomb Materials</HEAD>
<DATELINE>REX, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> agents seized items that could be used to
make a pipe bomb such as those that killed a federal judge and
civil rights lawyer during a search of property owned by a man
convicted 18 years ago of possessing a similar bomb, a newspaper
reported.
   The <LOCATION>Atlanta Constitution</LOCATION> quoted federal sources it did not
identify in today's editions as saying laboratory tests are pending
to establish whether the items found on the property of <PERSON>Walter
Leroy Moody Jr.</PERSON> match the two bombs that exploded in <DATE>December</DATE>.
   Moody denied any connection with the bombs, his lawyer said.
   The bombs sent through the mail killed <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Circuit Court <PERSON>Judge
Robert Vance</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and lawyer <PERSON>Robert Robinson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Savannah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga</LOCATION>.
Two other bombs were safely intercepted.
   Investigators confiscated 2{-inch pipe, six-penny nails, rubber
bands, alarm wire, flashlight bulbs, bolts, paper clips,
gunpowder-packed bullets and welding machinery _ all similar to
items used to make the mail bombs, the newspaper said.
   Also seized were adhesives, brown paper, labels, tape and
``old'' string, the paper reported. Similar materials _
particularly a unique string that has not been manufactured for
about seven years _ were used on the packages in which the four
bombs were mailed.
   The Constitution, in a story also copyrighted by <ORGANIZATION>The Atlanta
Journal</ORGANIZATION>, reported that agents seized the following:
   _Seventeen 25-cent ``flag over Yosemite'' postage stamps in the
pocketbook of <PERSON>Susan McBride</PERSON>, who lives with <ORGANIZATION>Moody</ORGANIZATION>. That stamp was
used on all four package bombs.
   _A desktop copier. Photocopied, typewritten letters from a
purported group calling itself ``Americans for a Competent Federal
Judicial System'' were sent after the bombings.
   _Highlighted newspaper clippings about the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION>'s investigation
of <PERSON>Robert Wayne O'Ferrell</PERSON>, an <LOCATION>Enterprise</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, junk-store owner
whose home and business were searched <DATE>last month</DATE> and who has been
questioned repeatedly. O'Ferrell denies any knowledge of the bomb
attacks.
   _Two typewriters that were examined on the scene and determined
not to match the ones used by ``Americans for a <ORGANIZATION>Competent Federal
Judicial System</ORGANIZATION>.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Moody</ORGANIZATION>, reached at his <LOCATION>Clayton County</LOCATION> home, referred inquiries to
his attorney, <PERSON>Michael C. Ford</PERSON>.
   ``I don't see anything there that I see as significant,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>
said of the seized items. ``They found brown paper. Well, I hope
they don't search my office. I probably have some of that, too.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> said two motions were filed in federal court <DATE>Monday</DATE> seeking
the return of <ORGANIZATION>Moody</ORGANIZATION>'s property and attacking the searches as
faulty. He said <ORGANIZATION>Moody</ORGANIZATION> has no connection to the bomb attacks.
   <ORGANIZATION>Moody</ORGANIZATION>, 55, a self-employed literary consultant, was convicted in
<DATE>1972</DATE> of possessing a pipe bomb that the newspaper's sources said is
very similar to the <DATE>December</DATE> package bombs. He was acquitted on a
charge of building the bomb, which injured his then-wife, <PERSON>Hazel</PERSON>, in
their <LOCATION>Macon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, home.
   In his appeals in that case, court records show <ORGANIZATION>Moody</ORGANIZATION> was
extremely critical of the attorney, judges and government agents
associated with his case.
   During an interview <DATE>Friday</DATE> with WSB-TV, <ORGANIZATION>Moody</ORGANIZATION> said,
``Criticizing the court is not an unhealthy practice, I don't
think. I think it's unhealthy when you say, `If you don't rule my
way, then I'm going to send you a bomb.' That's ridiculous.''
   Moody served nearly three years in the <LOCATION>Atlanta Federal
Penitentiary</LOCATION> on the bomb possession conviction but maintains his
innocence. He is representing himself in asking the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme
Court</ORGANIZATION> to throw out his conviction after an 11th <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Circuit Court
of Appeals</ORGANIZATION> panel denied his third appeal in <DATE>June</DATE>. <PERSON>Vance</PERSON> was not on
that panel.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-9039</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CBNB3AA6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920214
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 FEB 92 / Technology (Worth Watching): Top prizes in the invention
stakes
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DELLA BRADSHAW
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
A MEDICAL system which could enable doctors to test for illnesses in their
surgery - without sending blood or urine samples off to the laboratory - won
a team of scientists at the <PERSON>Wolfson</PERSON> research laboratories at <ORGANIZATION>Birmingham
University</ORGANIZATION> the top prize in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION> year of invention competition.
The printed liquidic circuit system - resembling a large electronic circuit
 -uses standard chemistry tests, but carries them out automatically in a
single device - unlike previous more complicated methods.
The device consists of a single layer of filter paper on to which a pattern
of wax tracks is printed, defining the channels through which the body fluid
flows. The device contains a layer of antibodies to which the antigens in
the blood or urine, if present, bind. At the end of the test a colourmetric
device shows whether antigens are present.
A FIFTEEN-year-old schoolboy won the schools category of the awards with an
energy-saving device which could cut the electricity bills of schools and
factories.
After noticing that the lights at a local school were often left switched on
at <TIME>night</TIME>, <PERSON>Richard Mead</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>Cheltenham College</ORGANIZATION>, set about designing a series
of clips which can be attached over the lighting circuits in the fuse boxes.
Attached on top of the wiring insulation the clips detect the magnetic field
when power passes through the wiring. The clips in turn are wired to a
central electronic box with a series of red lights on the top. When the
lights are left on, corresponding ones on the box light up too.
A HAND-HELD instrument which helps owners of oil rigs or power stations to
cut their repair bills won two divers the individual award category.
The device, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Instrument and Inspection Services</ORGANIZATION>, of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, is used
by repair workers carrying out remedial grinding on huge metal joints - a
process in which the sharp edges of the cracked surface are smoothed away to
help prevent further deterioration. The gauge accurately calculates the
thickness of the metal left by subtracting the depth of the grinding from
the metal remaining.
THE small business category of the <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION> awards was won by <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
architect <PERSON>Brian Perry</PERSON> for developing a fire escape system using
non-incandescent light. Intended for use in public places, the continuous
luminescent beams can be used to identify escape routes and can be activated
automatically by fire or smoke detectors.
The non-incandescent light becomes highly visible when the minute particles
present in smoke and dust from the fire act as a diffuser.
Contacts: <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION>: <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, 03 3457 4511. <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION> year of invention hotline:
UK, 081 691 9191. <ORGANIZATION>Wolfson Research Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>: UK, 021 472 1311.
Cheltenham College: <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, 0242 513540. Instrument and Inspection Services: UK,
071 499 7484. Perry Architects: UK, 071 485 4142.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10 Illustration (Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890411-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-11-89 0828EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Southwest-Report     04-11 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Southwest-Report,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Southwest Airlines Report Features Punch-Out Fun</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In addition to the facts and figures formally
found in a firm's annual report, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Airlines Co.</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>1988</DATE>
features fun, in the form of a paper airplane.
   ``This was one of those wonderful years when we made a lot of
money and it seemed to be we made a lot of money by getting back to
the basics. ... and we translated that to what we thought was the
most basic of all airplanes, the paper airplane,'' said <PERSON>Tim
McClure</PERSON>, executive creative director of <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION> advertising agency
<ORGANIZATION>GSD&amp;M</ORGANIZATION>, which designed the report.
   The booklet, besides reporting on <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s record <MONEY>$57.95
million</MONEY> in profit, traces the construction of a paper airplane from
the first folding of the paper to the final painting to resemble
<ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s ``flying whale'' jet rolled out <DATE>last year</DATE>
during the airline's promotion of <ORGANIZATION>Sea World</ORGANIZATION> theme parks in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   ``You think every pre-schooler and first grader in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> will
want one?'' asked <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <ORGANIZATION>Charlotte Goddard</ORGANIZATION>. ``Or all
the CEOs?''
   Besides a picture of Chairman <PERSON>Herb Kelleher</PERSON> throwing a paper
airplane, the middle of the report features a four-page foldout
picture of <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>.
   On the back page, there's the punch-out version of the unusually
painted plane, with assembly instructions and this ``helpful hint:''
   ``Herb attaches a paper clip to the nose for longer flights
(<ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>'s, not his).''
   Even though <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> previously has taken a light approach to
its reports, <PERSON>McClure</PERSON> said it was a little difficult this year to
sell the idea of a punch-out airplane because, ``once someone
punches it out, you have an annual report with holes in the back.''
   He said he persuaded <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> that the unusual idea would
become enticing. ``Everybody's going to pick it up ... and call up
for one.''
   ``I think it's a delightful brochure and something that really
shows the personality that <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> is,'' <PERSON>McClure</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>, a regional airline that employs almost 6,500 people,
is based at <LOCATION>Love Field</LOCATION> near downtown <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> and operates a
distinctive fleet of gold, rust and orange jets.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890411-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-11-89 1450EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     04-11 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The annual report of <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Airlines Co.</ORGANIZATION>
contains something that could raise a flap, or at least a couple
wings _ a paper airplane.
   ``This was one of those wonderful years when we made a lot of
money and it seemed to be we made a lot of money by getting back to
the basics, said <PERSON>Tim McClure</PERSON>, executive creative director of <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>
advertising agency <ORGANIZATION>GSD&amp;M</ORGANIZATION>, which designed the <DATE>1988</DATE> report.
   ``And we translated that to what we thought was the most basic
of all airplanes, the paper airplane.''
   The booklet, besides reporting on the regional airline's record
<MONEY>$57.95 million</MONEY> in profit, traces the construction of a paper
airplane from the first folding of the paper to the final painting
to resemble <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s ``flying whale'' jet rolled out
<DATE>last year</DATE> during the airline's promotion of <ORGANIZATION>Sea World</ORGANIZATION> theme parks
in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   ``You think every pre-schooler and first grader in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> will
want one?'' asked <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <ORGANIZATION>Charlotte Goddard</ORGANIZATION>. ``Or all
the CEOs?''
   Besides a picture of Chairman <PERSON>Herb Kelleher</PERSON> throwing a paper
airplane, the middle of the report features a four-page foldout
picture of <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>.
   On the back page, there's a punch-out version of the plane, with
assembly instructions and this ``helpful hint'':
   ``Herb attaches a paper clip to the nose for longer flights
(<ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>'s, not his).''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The annual report of <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Airlines Co.</ORGANIZATION>
contains something that could raise a flap, or at least a couple
wings _ a paper airplane.
   ``This was one of those wonderful years when we made a lot of
money and it seemed to be we made a lot of money by getting back to
the basics, said <PERSON>Tim McClure</PERSON>, executive creative director of <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>
advertising agency <ORGANIZATION>GSD&amp;M</ORGANIZATION>, which designed the <DATE>1988</DATE> report.
   ``And we translated that to what we thought was the most basic
of all airplanes, the paper airplane.''
   The booklet, besides reporting on the regional airline's record
<MONEY>$57.95 million</MONEY> in profit, traces the construction of a paper
airplane from the first folding of the paper to the final painting
to resemble <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>'s ``flying whale'' jet rolled out
<DATE>last year</DATE> during the airline's promotion of <ORGANIZATION>Sea World</ORGANIZATION> theme parks
in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   ``You think every pre-schooler and first grader in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> will
want one?'' asked <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <ORGANIZATION>Charlotte Goddard</ORGANIZATION>. ``Or all
the CEOs?''
   Besides a picture of Chairman <PERSON>Herb Kelleher</PERSON> throwing a paper
airplane, the middle of the report features a four-page foldout
picture of <ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>.
   On the back page, there's a punch-out version of the plane, with
assembly instructions and this ``helpful hint'':
   ``Herb attaches a paper clip to the nose for longer flights
(<ORGANIZATION>Shamu One</ORGANIZATION>'s, not his).''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890312-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-12-89 1814EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WarTrialPapers     03-12 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-War Trial Papers,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Papers Of Japanese War Crimes Trials Donated To University</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPOKANE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of just two known sets of the records
of one of the last chapters of World War II is slowly falling apart.
   The brittle, yellowing records include copies of the briefs filed
_ a panel of judges from 11 countries who tried <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s military and
civilian leaders for war crimes.
   Printed on inexpensive paper and bound by string or paper clips,
they sit in two file cabinets in the rare book room of <ORGANIZATION>Gonzaga
University</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Crosby Library</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The quality of the paper and the printing is such that they
will decay over time,'' said <PERSON>Bob Burr</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Gonzaga</ORGANIZATION>'s library director.
   Burr, convinced the documents have great historical value, said
he is seeking grants to help preserve them. The documents include
the indictments and verdicts against 28 Japanese leaders and a
129-page list of atrocities committed against prisoners.
   They were apparently reproduced on a type of mimeograph machine,
using whatever paper was available in war-torn <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> between <DATE>1946</DATE>
and <DATE>1948</DATE>.
   The only other known copy of the tribunal records is in the
<ORGANIZATION>National Archives</ORGANIZATION>, unindexed and reproduced on the same cheap paper.
   The documents were donated to the university last year by <PERSON>Daniel
Mahoney</PERSON>, a retired <LOCATION>Spokane</LOCATION> attorney whose late father, <PERSON>Willis
Mahoney</PERSON>, was acting chief prosecutor at the trials' conclusion.
   The tribunal was the Japanese counterpart of the Nuremburg trials
of the <ORGANIZATION>Nazi</ORGANIZATION> high command. It convicted 25 Japanese leaders,
including War Minister <PERSON>Hideki Tojo</PERSON>, who was ordered executed along
with six others.
   Others were sentenced to prison for life or given long sentences.
   Although complete records of the <DATE>1946</DATE> Nuremburg trials have been
published, the records of the Far East tribunal have not, <PERSON>Burr</PERSON> said.
   ``It's an asset that's priceless,'' <PERSON>Mahoney</PERSON> said. ``I don't want
anything to happen to it.''
   His father, a lawyer, went to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in <DATE>1946</DATE> to assist chief
prosecutor <PERSON>Joseph Keenan</PERSON>, and became acting chief prosecutor when
<PERSON>Keenan</PERSON> fell ill.
   When the trials concluded, the elder <PERSON>Mahoney</PERSON> sent one set of
records to the <ORGANIZATION>National Archives</ORGANIZATION> and brought another set home to
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore</LOCATION>. He later gave the set to his son, with instructions
they eventually be donated to <LOCATION>Gonzaga</LOCATION>, where both Mahoneys attended
law school.
   ``I've read very little, but the little I've read is
fascinating,'' <PERSON>Mahoney</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Burr</PERSON> said he may seek grants to place the documents on microfilm,
a project that is tentatively estimated to cost as much as <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06314152 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06314152 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Reliable Home Office; Home-office designers say personal
objects such as photographs and favorite works of art can transform a work
space from a sterile to a warm environment (color); PHOTO: A drop-leaf
wall-mounted desk can double as a mini-bar. (color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BUSINESS; ALTERNATIVE; HOUSING; OFFICE; TREND  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IT'S A sign of our comfort-seeking times: Since the '80s, the trend has been
to furnish work spaces with residential and personal touches. But a good third
of the nation's workforce, 35 million Americans, have decided to bring
business home.;   For parents, the option of full-, flex- or part-time work at
home is welcome. Early retirement has created another home-office workforce.
The personal computer boom has generated a wave of home-office wannabes, and
the advent of modems and faxes has further expanded the home-office network.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Home  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HOMEWORK
RESIDENTIAL OFFICES TAKE CARE OF BUSINESS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cover Story; Elaine Markoutsas is Midwest editor of Metropolitan Life
magazine.; See also related articles on this page.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Corporations such as <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> are helping employees move their offices to
attics, basements or spare bedrooms. Some people are even forsaking their tax
deduction (the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> requires a separate room for a legal deduction) and are
setting up offices in portions of living and dining rooms, master bedrooms and
master baths.;   <DATE>Just five years ago</DATE>, if you needed furniture to set up shop
at home, your choices were greatly limited. The focus was more on the
utilitarian -- a no-frills clerical look rather than executive.;   <DATE>Today</DATE>,
you'll find a range of pieces designed for home-office spaces. There are
drop-leaf, wall-mounted desks that can be installed in a kitchen corner and
can moonlight as mini-bars, as well as basic black laminate office systems
tucked into converted bedrooms. There are lateral file cabinets in a rainbow
of colors, even in marbleized and granite-look finishes. You'll also see
elegant mahogany desks and nail-studded leather chairs.;   You can create an
instant office by shopping in department stores; specialty stores, such as
<ORGANIZATION>Crate &amp; Barrel</ORGANIZATION>; or even in catalogs. Spiegel's fall and winter catalog
features 12 pages of office furnishings. <ORGANIZATION>J.C. Penney</ORGANIZATION> has a 16-page pullout.
And the 5-year-old Chicago-based <ORGANIZATION>Reliable Home Office</ORGANIZATION>, whose catalog reaches
10 million consumers, mixes standard commodities such as fax machines and
electronic Rolodexes with arts and crafts-inspired desks that double as dining
tables, glass-topped desks with Greco-Roman stonelike pedestal bases, chairs,
lamps, and snazzy supplies such as marbleized file folders, lavender legal
pads, neon orange paper clips and hot-pink staplers.;   Whatever space you've
designated as your home office demands the same design courtesy as any other
room -- especially if it's in a high-traffic, high-visibility spot.;   Of
course, the electronic age has brought challenges. Hiding the computer,
peripheral equipment and cables has become as much of a design challenge as
stashing away the television set.;   Much of the furniture designed specially
for computers has been, until recently, largely uninspired. Most of it fell in
the category of ready-to-assemble.;   "Some of these are so chintzy-looking
and badly designed that people wouldn't even put them in their basements,"
said one furniture executive. "They're looking for the same detailing and
hand-worked finishes they have in their other furnishings.";   However, things
are looking up. The down-sizing of computers and components is prompting
manufacturers to modify proportions and deliver more style.;   With its <DATE>spring</DATE>
catalog, <ORGANIZATION>J.C. Penney</ORGANIZATION> discovered that consumers are hungry for style -- desks,
chairs and cabinets whose design, finish and details wouldn't seem awkward or
inferior. A group of traditional executive-style furniture in cherry finish
with brass-finished hardwood was featured at <MONEY>$499.</MONEY>;   "The response surprised
us," said <PERSON>Patricia Treiber Shaw</PERSON>, home-furnishings consultant for the catalog.
"The group has done very, very well. There obviously is a need for people who
are working at home. They don't want to have ugly stuff sitting in a corner.
They want their furnishings to go with the rest of the home.";   Even the
styling of the basic desk chair has gone beyond the swivel. A recent model by
<ORGANIZATION>Girsberger Industries</ORGANIZATION>, for example, has a rounded silhouette and vivid red
upholstery. But it has more than streamlined form: A triple-jointed mechanism
allows the chair to move freely (it also can be locked into position), and it
has pneumatically adjustable height (a gas cylinder makes the adjustment at
the touch of a lever), all designed in an elastic material with a thinner
profile. It retails for <MONEY>$800</MONEY> to <MONEY>$1,300</MONEY>, depending on materials and whether the
chair has arms.;   Still, some consumers say furniture designed for the office
is too hard-edged for the home and that residential furniture can't quite get
down to business, so they opt to customize their home offices.;   The results
can be smashing. <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> interior designer Vassa started with an old-fashioned
banker's desk in an office she planned for a family in a contemporary suburban
home. But she gave it an non-traditional look with modern materials -- a
metallic laminate that matches the bookshelves that line two walls; the top is
inlaid with leather.;   Actually, a fabric was the starting point for the
design.;   "The geometric-pattern, with its metallic gray, bronze and zippy
blue, gave us an Old World flavor as well as a contemporary feeling," said
<PERSON>Vassa</PERSON>, who coined the term "hoffice" to describe this kind of space that she's
designed for eight years.;   <ORGANIZATION>Vassa</ORGANIZATION> makes sure there is adequate lighting,
always on dimmers. Both residential and contract office furnishings
manufacturers sell lighting. Task lighting in the form of a desk lamp is
essential.;   Halogens (those tiny low-voltage lights that are popular not
only for their sexy looks but because people like their white light), come in
a variety of architectural or sculptural styles with high-tech looks. Some
offer dimmers. There are classic banker's lamps, in brass or black, some
updated for halogens.;   Stylish home offices demand equally fashionable
accessories. That means everything from desk blotters to tape dispensers to
paper-clip holders, even the phone itself.;   "We've taken the approach of the
humanized home office," said <PERSON>Bette Frank Rosenberg</PERSON>, home fashion director for
<ORGANIZATION>Spiegel Inc.</ORGANIZATION> "It's important to bring a little personality into the home
office. Nobody likes to work in a sterile environment. Pretty picture frames,
fun executive toys (electronics, gadgets), small-screen TVs and, yes, even art
-- are very important. We want to offer a functional environment that's
organized, uncluttered and convenient, yet expresses someone's personality."; 
 So if you shop wisely, you'll soon be sitting pretty in your home office,
probably thinking, "There's no place like hoffice."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Elaine Markoutsas  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911109  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,101  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, November 9, 1991
00314152,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060790-0062 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 230032 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 7, 1990, Thursday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
396 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VENTURA COUNTY NEWS ROUNDUP: VENTURA; 
</P>
<P>
STUDENTS SEE HOW IDEAS FLY IN CONTEST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KIRSTEN LEE SWARTZ 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The children chose bold names for their airplanes: Supersonic Spyplane, 391 
Speedbird and Jetski III. Although these planes were made of flimsy white 
paper, their young pilots took them as seriously as the shuttles they hope to 
ride into outer space someday. 
</P>
<P>
"I want to be an astronaut," said <PERSON>Jesus Sanchez</PERSON>, 8. "I want to explore." 
</P>
<P>
Sanchez and about 14 other members of the Young Astronaut Program flew the 
paper planes in a contest <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in the yard of the <ORGANIZATION>E.P. Foster Elementary 
School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ventura</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
science, mathematics and space-related subjects. The effort is intended to help 
reverse the low proficiency levels of American students in these subjects, 
compared with children in other industrialized countries. 
</P>
<P>
The students' creations were judged by the school's principal and two reading 
specialists on the planes' distance, speed and fancy acrobatics. Using scissors 
and thin white paper, the students designed the planes, adding ridges and folds 
that enabled the aircraft to dip and glide in strange patterns. Paper clips 
mounted to the folds increased the planes' speed. 
</P>
<P>
Sanchez's F-14 Tomcat, an intricately folded plane, earned him the title of 
overall winner and first place in the distance category and second place in 
acrobatics. 
</P>
<P>
Sanchez's peers also expressed an avid interest in aviation. <PERSON>Mario Pena</PERSON>, who 
placed third in distance, said he too wanted to go into space. "I'd like to see 
the planets," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Winning planes flew 20 to 30 feet, and some remained in the air for more than 
two minutes. 
</P>
<P>
Teacher <PERSON>Catharine Byl</PERSON> began a chapter of the <ORGANIZATION>Young Astronauts Program</ORGANIZATION> at the 
school in <DATE>February</DATE> and has helped about 20 second- and third-grade students 
build model space shuttles, understand gravity and weightlessness and 
experiment with team-related projects. 
</P>
<P>
"There's a real need for kids today to improve in those areas," she said, 
adding that aerospace and aviation will be among the major fields in the future 
as the technological revolution continues. 
</P>
<P>
Byl has been active in the <ORGANIZATION>Eagle</ORGANIZATION> Flight Program, an organization that trains 
classroom teachers to instruct other teachers on methods to teach aerospace in 
the classroom. 
</P>
<P>
Foster Principal <PERSON>Greg Kampf</PERSON> said he has never disciplined a student for flying 
paper airplanes in the classroom. KIRSTEN LEE SWARTZ 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Students at E.P. Foster School in Ventura, top, send their planes 
skyward as Principal Gregory Kampf, above, dodges an entry. Right, Mario Pena, 
10, prepares a launch. ALAN HAGMAN / Los Angeles Times; Photo, AIRBORNE: Making 
and flying paper planes is usually prohibited during school classes. But 
members of the Young Astronaut Program flew paper planes during in a in the 
yard of the E.P. Foster Elementary School in Ventura. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-477</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DC3CGACVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930330
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 MAR 93 / Management (The Growing Business): Getting the green light -
A look at three companies which have become environmentally aware
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By HESTER THOMAS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Coming from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> to manage <PERSON>Berger Aus Berg</PERSON>, manufacturers of metal
drum closures in <LOCATION>Peterlee</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Co Durham</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Richard Swart</PERSON> arrived with fresh eyes.
He was immediately aware of the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>'s different seasons and dark winter
afternoons, plus the toll they take on energy consumption - not least of all
in his factory.
At the same time, <PERSON>Swart</PERSON> discovered that while environmental issues are not
as high on the South African agenda, in the UK his company was operating in
the packaging industry - which is acutely environmentally conscious. Linking
the need to tackle <PERSON>Berger Aus Berg</PERSON>'s energy consumption with a need to learn
more about environmental issues, he decided it was time to review the
company's environmental practices.
Increasingly, companies are paying more attention to their environmental
performance. While many do it to ensure they are meeting UK and <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> legal
requirements, others are interested in quantifying their environmental
impact and using the information to maintain good relations with their local
community, customers, suppliers or even investors. Companies which have
their sights set on achieving BS <DATE>7750</DATE> - a recently published British
standard for <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Management Systems</ORGANIZATION> - or other similar schemes,
know they must first set their house in order.
Ironically, when <ORGANIZATION>Hedda Bird formed Conservation Papers</ORGANIZATION> in Reading in <DATE>1988</DATE>
the last thing she thought about was 'making the company greener than
green'. This was despite the fact that it was operating in an
environmentally conscious area, marketing recycled paper to the business
community. Yet within six months her attitude changed. 'Everyone - including
us - rapidly became much more sophisticated and knowledgeable about
environmental issues,' she recalls.
Three years later, <PERSON>Dorothy Mackenzie</PERSON> formed the London-based marketing
consultancy <ORGANIZATION>Dragon International</ORGANIZATION>, which is run on environmentally friendly
lines. 'We provide environmental consultancy,' explains <PERSON>Mackenzie</PERSON>, 'and to
have credibility with clients we needed to practice what we preached.'
Although all three companies have analysed their environmental practices,
only <PERSON>Berger Aus Berg</PERSON> has paid for an independent environmental review. Last
<DATE>summer</DATE> it commissioned <ORGANIZATION>Groundwork Foundation's Environmental Review Service</ORGANIZATION>
to see what environmental improvements could be made. The review took three
days with <PERSON>Groundwork</PERSON> - which is supported by the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Environment</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>BP</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Countryside Commission</ORGANIZATION> - looking at energy use, waste management,
legal compliance, recycling and potential cost savings.
<PERSON>Swart</PERSON> has already implemented several of Groundwork's recommendations. For
example, it advised the company to reduce its energy consumption by altering
the factory's lighting. The factory had previously had to have all its
lights on when only half were needed. Swart expects future electricity bills
for lighting to be 50 per cent less and will recoup his investment within
eight months.
Groundwork also advised the company to take pallets and bags it receives
from suppliers and re-use them when sending products to its customers. This
it has done with impressive results. In the past, most transport packaging
costs were passed on to customers. By re-using packaging the costs have been
significantly reduced. Customers have been informed about this reduction in
charges.
At <ORGANIZATION>Conservation Papers</ORGANIZATION>, staff had been running the company along
environmental lines to the best of their abilities. However, in <DATE>1992</DATE> they
adopted a more formal approach and joined an <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Business
Challenge</ORGANIZATION>, launched by <ORGANIZATION>Reading Borough Council</ORGANIZATION>, to help companies develop
and implement an environmental policy. 'It gave us a structure to work
with,' says Bird, 'and most of the changes we've made have been as a result
of it.' In an attempt to reduce its energy consumption by up to 15 per cent,
<ORGANIZATION>Conservation Papers</ORGANIZATION> has taken some simple steps, turning down thermostats
and switching off heating at weekends.
'At <ORGANIZATION>Dragon International</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mackenzie</PERSON> and her colleagues assessed the
environmental impact of all they did from the first day. Setting the company
up, they purchased second-hand 'recycled' furniture - furniture which does
not contain tropical hardwoods, bought a photocopier for double-sided copies
and decided against supplying company cars. Staff are encouraged to use
bicycles or public transport.
The company buys recycled non-chlorine bleached paper, re-uses scrap paper,
re-cycles its paper and laser printer toner cartridges, fits long-life light
bulbs, uses environmentally sensitive cleaning equipment and supplies china
rather than disposable cups.
Being environmentally sensitive brings costs with it. <PERSON>Berger Aus Berg</PERSON> has
spent Pounds 600 on an electrician's bill and Pounds 150 on <ORGANIZATION>Groundwork</ORGANIZATION>'s
fees. Conservation Papers spent Pounds 70 on automatic door closures. <ORGANIZATION>Dragon
International</ORGANIZATION>'s main expenditure will be on better insulation and a more
efficient boiler for its offices costing several hundred pounds.
Although all the companies have spent several hours discussing environmental
practices with staff, none has found the process disruptive. 'Everyone
starts thinking along the same lines,' explains <PERSON>Mackenzie</PERSON>. <PERSON>Swart</PERSON> has seen
his employees change their attitudes. 'At first they were curious about the
review,' he says. 'Now they tell me what we can do to make further
environmental improvements.'
There are other benefits too. All the companies have reduced their overheads
by implementing energy saving measures and all expect to recoup the
investment within two years in lower energy bills.
Perhaps what is surprising is how many benefits have been gained through
relatively few changes. To a large extent these companies have simply made
sure their housekeeping is in good order - albeit under an environmental
umbrella.
Although none has gone out of its way to promote the changes, all the
companies expect that one day they will have to justify their environmental
practices. To that end they are continuing their environmental programmes.
EASY STEPS TO IMPROVING A COMPANY'S ENVIRONMENTAL PRACTICES
Review energy efficiency. Reduce consumption by turning down the thermostats
and turn off un-needed lights and equipment.
Encourage employees to re-use as much equipment as possible - paper-clips,
scrap paper, elastic bands, bull-dog clips etc.
See whether there are ways to reduce waste or generate a further income by
selling your waste as scrap.
Reduce vehicle use. Encourage staff to use public transport or walk. If
employees live locally, set up a company bike scheme.
Review purchasing policy. For example could you save money or improve your
public image by consider purchasing recycled paper. Only buy ozone-friendly
products and cleaning materials which are free of phosphates and are readily
biodegradable.
Reduce paper usage. Encourage staff to write on both sides of any paper and
use double-sided photocopies when sending long memos.
Recycle paper, glass, plastics and cans.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8742 Management Consulting Services.
    P99   Nonclassifiable Establishments.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Energy use.
    MGMT  Management.
    RES  Pollution.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 16
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910104-0008
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910104-0008.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Heard on the Street:
   Investors Go on a Shopping Spree for Stocks
   Of No-Frills Retailers, but Caveat Emptor
   ----
   By Linda Sandler
</HL>
<DATE>
01/04/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C2
</SO>
<CO>
   PCLB WBN ODEP SPLS COST HD
</CO>
<IN>
STOCK MARKET, OFFERINGS (STK)
HEARD ON THE STREET (HRD)
SPECIALTY RETAILERS (OTS)
</IN>
<LP>
   Warehouse clubs are a hot concept, but even they have
winners and losers. Remember all the look-alike hamburger
joints in the 1970s? Most have disappeared.
   Investors looking for winners in no-frills retailing now
have to pick and choose carefully among companies such as
Price Co., Staples Inc., Home Depot and their many imitators.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   With so many shoppers feeling poorer these days, the
