<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06099209 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06099209 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Diagrams (2); DIAGRAM: Karl Tate--Associated Press.; NASA's new orbital
observatory. (Ran in the Morning Final Edition).; DIAGRAM: Associated Press.;
Repair in space. Astronauts inside the shuttle lift the 17-ton observatory in
the shuttle's payload bay using the robot arm. Robot arm. After the
communications antenna and solar-cell arrays extend properly, the satellite
was to be released. Gamma ray observatory. But the antenna did not unfold
until astronauts, during a walk in space, shook the balky antenna and freed
it. Repaired antenna. Solar cells. The repair job made it possible to release
the observatory at 3:37 p.m. PDT, Sunday.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SPACE; AVIATION; PROGRAM  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Two space-walking astronauts rode carts along a rail in Atlantis' open cargo
bay today, testing techniques that will be needed to build a space station.;  
 It was the second day in open space for Jerry Ross and Jay Apt, who took an
emergency "walk" Sunday to fix a stuck antenna on a $617 million observatory.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ASTRONAUTS RIDE THE RAILS IN SPACE
CONSTRUCTION CARTS UNDERGO TEST  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "Very nice braking. This thing moves very, very easily," <PERSON>Ross</PERSON> said as he
zipped up and down the nearly 47 feet of track on a manually operated cart.
"This is the way to travel around the world.";    Said Apt, who joined <PERSON>Ross</PERSON>
aboard the cart to test its capacity: "Boy, this thing glides slick. It really
does.";    They were less impressed with a mechanical cart that they operated
by pumping a handle back and forth. They said the brakes were bad. An electric
cart also was being tested.;    Today's spacewalk into the open bay, which had
been on the agenda all along, was to be more leisurely than the unscheduled
one Sunday.;    The two crew members had to go into space when the 17-ton
<ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION>'s antenna couldn't be extended by electronic signals
from the ground. They shook the antenna loose, then got an early start on
today's space-walking activities.;    Flight director <PERSON>Phil Engelauf</PERSON> said
<DATE>today</DATE>'s space walk would go as planned for about six hours unless the
astronauts become tired and want to go back in early. Only those tests
performed <DATE>Sunday</DATE> were dropped from the schedule.;    "But they were pretty
pumped up after yesterday's walk. I expect they'll want to go for six hours,"
<PERSON>Engelauf</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE>. "It's the astronauts' call.";    A battery on a backup
spacesuit was installed <DATE>today</DATE> in <PERSON>Ross</PERSON>' outfit after his battery failed to
recharge properly during the night. There were no problems with Apt's suit.;  
 <PERSON>Ross</PERSON> and Apt went into the shuttle's cargo bay <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to extend the
observatory's antenna from its 16 1/2-foot boom, and within minutes <PERSON>Ross</PERSON> had
shaken it loose.;    "It's free, it's free! I can see it move, it's free!" he
shouted.;    "Far out; good work," said Apt.;    It was the first spacewalk by
Americans in more than five years.;    <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> was quick to point out that the
observatory could not have been fixed on the spot if it had been carried aloft
by an unmanned rocket.;    "You saw today the value of manned space flight,"
said <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> flight director <PERSON>Chuck Shaw</PERSON>. "We did a lot of work from the ground,
and we needed the folks on the scene to finish up the job.";    Because <PERSON>Ross</PERSON>
and Apt already were in the cargo bay, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> decided to have them start early
on some of today's spacewalk tasks.;    They did small tests to measure how
much effort building a space station would take. In one test, <PERSON>Ross</PERSON> lifted Apt
up and down several times and from side to side, while the platform he stood
on measured the force applied.;    The astronauts also cavorted about, doing
cartwheels and head stands.;    "Talk about a view," Apt exulted during the 4
1/2-hour spacewalk.;    "Feel like you're walking on top of the world? Look
what's coming, <PERSON>Jay</PERSON>. <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Ross</PERSON> said.;    The space station, if approved by
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, will be assembled in space and require considerable hands-on efforts
by astronauts.;    <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s effort was the second unscheduled walk in <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
history. Astronauts went outside Discovery in <DATE>April 1985</DATE> to try to switch on
the electrical power to a communications satellite launched from the shuttle,
but they couldn't fix it. A crew trained to do the repairs went up <DATE>four months
later</DATE> and fixed it.;    <PERSON>Ross</PERSON> and Apt were ordered outside the cabin after six
efforts from the ground failed to extend the antenna. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said a locking pin
on the antenna had properly retracted, and only a shake was required to work
the antenna loose.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Cape Canaveral, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910408  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DIAGRAM  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  742  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 8, 1991
00099209,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06099220 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06099220 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, diagram; PHOTO: Associated Press; WALK IN SPACE -- Jerry Ross, left,
and Jay Apt experiment with a rope outside the shuttle Atlantis.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SPACE; VEHICLE; EQUIPMENT; HUMAN; REPAIR; RESULT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Two astronauts made America's first successful emergency spacewalk Sunday from
the shuttle Atlantis, saving a $617 million astronomy observatory by freeing a
stuck antenna.;    The 4 1/2-hour orbital ballet took place 280 miles above
Earth at 17,000 mph, beginning at about 11:40 a.m. PDT Sunday. It was the
first U.S. spacewalk since December 1985 and the second "unplanned" outing
prompted by a crisis.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EMERGENCY SPACEWALK IS A SUCCESS
IN A FIRST FOR NASA, ATLANTIS CREW FREES
OBSERVATORY'S BALKY ANTENNA  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Lt. Col. <PERSON>Jerry Ross</PERSON>, 43, performed the equivalent of kicking a
tire when he gave a shake to the stuck boom of the high-gain communications
antenna, freeing it to swing out as planned from one end of the massive <ORGANIZATION>Gamma
Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION> (GRO).;    The "<PERSON>Jay</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jerry Show</PERSON>," as <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION> billed
it, resulted from remote cameras aboard the shuttle that provided stunning
live television images of the drama, which at times turned into a happy romp.;
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> officials have long argued that this is the advantage of having a
piloted shuttle and that it balances the risks and costs: Humans can cope with
the unexpected in a way that robots cannot. For this reason, they say, the
shuttle is the safest launcher for top-priority payloads of increasing
complexity.;    <PERSON>Ross</PERSON> broke the boom free 19 minutes after he had floated out
of the Atlantis air lock to begin what <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> refers to as EVA (extravehicular
activity). He was assisted during the outing by mission specialist <PERSON>Jay Apt</PERSON>,
41, a physicist.;    <ORGANIZATION>Cheers</ORGANIZATION> and applause erupted in the two <ORGANIZATION>National
Aeronautics and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> control rooms in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Greenbelt</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, from relieved engineers and scientists. Shouts of "Far out!" and
"Fantastic!" rang between the astronauts and mission control at <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Houston.</LOCATION>;    "I'm just thankful there was a man in the loop here,"
said <ORGANIZATION>Goddard Space Flight Center</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>John Hrastar</PERSON>, GRO project manager. GRO's
controllers at <ORGANIZATION>Goddard</ORGANIZATION> had tried and failed six times to free the balky
high-gain antenna by remote control.;    Unplanned walk;  The astronauts had
not planned to go spacewalking until today, when they are to test a mini-rail
system scheduled for use in constructing the proposed orbital space station in
the <DATE>late 1990s</DATE>. Much of that exercise is still on the schedule, but once the
antenna problem was solved, the astronauts performed some of today's
assignments <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, trying out hand tools and a rope transport system.;   
<PERSON>Ross</PERSON> was on the team that made the last <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> spacewalk, in <DATE>December 1985</DATE>. The
following month, the Challenger accident grounded the shuttle fleet for more
than two years.;    The only other emergency spacewalk occurred in <DATE>April 1985</DATE>,
when shuttle astronauts tried unsuccessfully to flip a switch on a <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>
communications satellite using a jury-rigged "fly swatter" and the robot arm.
The satellite was later retrieved for repairs.;    GRO is designed to
investigate gamma rays, the most energetic and least studied radiation in the
cosmos, with instruments 10 to 50 times more sensitive than their
predecessors.;    Complex maneuvers;  The crew was in the midst of a complex
sequence of maneuvers leading to <ORGANIZATION>GRO</ORGANIZATION>'s deployment in orbit when the antenna
problem was discovered.;    Earlier in the day, mission specialist <PERSON>Linda
Godwin</PERSON> had used the shuttle's robot arm to lift <ORGANIZATION>GRO</ORGANIZATION> straight up and out of the
payload bay and into position to unfurl its solar panels, accordion fashion,
to a wingspan of 70 feet. At 17 tons, it is the heaviest science satellite the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has launched.;    When controllers had no luck extending the
antenna, the astronauts tried moving the orbiter, then tried flexing the robot
arm to shake it loose. Still no luck. The antenna boom was stuck in the cradle
on <ORGANIZATION>GRO</ORGANIZATION>'s underside, where it is stored during launch.;    Data receptor;  The
antenna -- a dish at the end of a 16 1/2-foot boom -- is to transmit and
receive data through a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> communications satellite, which is to relay it to
<LOCATION>Goddard</LOCATION> through a station in <LOCATION>White Sands</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION> Although it passed release
tests on the ground, "in space, it takes much less torque to hang you up,"
<PERSON>Hrastar</PERSON> said.;    At <TIME>11:40 a.m.</TIME>, as Atlantis passed above the southern tip of
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, live TV images from a remote camera mounted in the cargo bay showed
<PERSON>Ross</PERSON> pushing his way out of the air lock like a baby chick hatching.;    As he
floated back along the side of the cargo bay at the end of a tether, <PERSON>Godwin</PERSON>
used the robot arm to move the GRO down where he could reach it.;    <PERSON>Hrastar</PERSON>
said engineers believe a small piece of the boom's insulation had snagged on a
bolt or other protrusion -- "not a super major grab" -- and came loose easily
when <PERSON>Ross</PERSON> shook it.;     DIAGRAM: <PERSON>Karl Tate</PERSON> -- Associated Press; <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s new
orbital observatory; The Gamma Ray Observatory (GRO) is the second in a
planned series of four major Earth-orbiting telescopes and astronomy
satellites. GRO's mission is to study gamma-ray-emitting objects in our galaxy
and beyond. The first observatory, the <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>, detects
ultraviolet and visible light. Two others are planned; the Advanced X-Ray
Observatory (<ORGANIZATION>AXAF</ORGANIZATION>) and the Space infrared Telescope Facility (SIRTF); ...;
<ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION> (drawing); Cost: <MONEY>$557 million</MONEY>; Length: 25 ft.; Weight:
35,000 lbs.; Altitude: 279 miles; OSSE: Oriented Scintillation Spectrometer
Experiment; designed to detect low-energy gamma rays; Thrusters (underneath);
Antenna; COMPTEL: Imaging telescope designed to produce a detailed map of the
sky in moderate-energy gamma rays; EGRET: Telescope designed to map the sky in
high-energy gamma rays, and monitor gamma-ray emissions from pulsars;
Astronaut to scale; Solar panels; ...; Gamma rays are form of light that
cannot penetrate the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere or be seen by human eyes. The rays
have the highest energies of any type of light radiation, and are emitted by
some of the most exotic structures in the universe: supernovae, neutron stars,
black holes and quasars.; ...; ELECTROMAGNETIC SPECTRUM; Gamma Rays: Very
short wavelength, highest frequency radiation; X-Rays; Visible Light (Violet
to Red); Infrared; <LOCATION>Microwaves</LOCATION>; Radio: Very long wavelength; Source: <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>; The
New Atlas of the Universe by <PERSON>Patrick Moore</PERSON>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Washington Post  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910408  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DIAGRAM; PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,030  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 8, 1991
00099220,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06098048 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06098048 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; SPACE TALK -- Space shuttle pilot Kenneth
Cameron uses an amateur radio hookup to talk to students at the Johnson Space
Center. NASA called Saturday's radio experiment a success.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPACE; TRAVEL  </DESCRIPT>
for two days of intense activity, including the first spacewalk in more than
five years, and took a few minutes off to talk with schoolchildren about the
adventures of space flight.;    Today, physicist Linda M. Godwin, 38, will use
the shuttle's robotic arm to lift a $617 million observatory out of Atlantis'
cargo bay. The 35,000-pound observatory will dangle on the end of the arm for
several hours until all its systems have been checked, and then Godwin will
set the instrument free to study the universe in ways that it has never been
studied before.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ATLANTIS ASTRONAUTS PREPARE FOR FIRST SPACEWALK
IN 5 YEARS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION> has been designed to spend two years examining
objects that emit gamma rays, the most powerful form of radiation in the
electromagnetic spectrum. However, scientists expect it to operate for much
longer than its design life -- possibly as long as eight years. Gamma rays can
only be studied from space.;    Atmospheric pressure in the interior of
<LOCATION>Atlantis</LOCATION> was lowered <DATE>Saturday</DATE> from 14.7 pounds per square inch, which is
sea-level pressure, to 10.2 psi to pave the way for a spacewalk if anything
goes wrong during the deployment of the observatory.;    It is necessary to
reduce the pressure inside the vehicle to prevent the astronauts from going
through the bends, similar to what happens to deep-sea divers when they
surface too quickly, after they re-enter the shuttle.;    Even if they do not
have to leave the shuttle today, astronauts <PERSON>Jerry L. Ross</PERSON>, 43, and <PERSON>Jay Apt</PERSON>,
41, will go out <DATE>Monday</DATE> to test equipment that could be used later this decade
in the construction of the planned space station Freedom.;    Atlantis has
been enjoying a near-perfect mission since its launch Friday.;    "This has
been a really clean flight," said flight director <PERSON>Chuck Shaw.</PERSON>;    The
astronauts took time to chat with schoolchildren by way of amateur radio
linkups, and they got at least one question that showed that even the very
young can wonder about the meaning of it all.;    "Do you tend to re-evaluate
your life when you look at the Earth?" a young boy asked the shuttle's pilot,
<PERSON>Kenneth Cameron</PERSON>, 41.;    "When you float up here above the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in a little
spacecraft and look down at the big spacecraft that we all fly on, it makes us
all think about what our priorities are," <PERSON>Cameron answered.</PERSON>;    The flight is
scheduled to end at <TIME>6:34 a.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with a landing at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air
Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Southern California.</LOCATION>;    Atlantis is commanded by <PERSON>Steven R.
Nagel</PERSON>, 44.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Kennedy Space Center, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910407  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  466  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 7, 1991
00098048,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06100008 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06100008 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SPACE; TRAVEL; VEHICLE; GOVERNMENT; PROGRAM; RESEARCH; FACILITY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The Atlantis astronauts' spacewalking adventures will provide the first hard
data from orbit about building a space station, NASA managers say.;    Jerry
Ross and Jay Apt went on a six-hour spacewalk Monday to test tools and compare
ways of moving astronauts and loads around.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NASA 'EXTREMELY PLEASED' WITH SPACEWALK MISSION  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "We're extremely pleased," said <PERSON>Ed Whitsett</PERSON>, a manager in <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s automatic
and robotics division.;    Mission commander <PERSON>Steven Nagel</PERSON> today began
maneuvering the spaceship to within nine miles of the <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION> to
practice using the shuttle's navigation system.;    Also <TIME>this morning</TIME>, the
astronauts saw the Soviet space station Mir as Atlantis flew within 130 miles
of the craft over <LOCATION>Australia.</LOCATION>;    The shuttle is scheduled to land <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
<TIME>morning</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Space Center, Houston  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Home  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910409  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  119  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday April 9, 1991
00100008,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06158043 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06158043 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SPACE; VEHICLE; REPAIR; US  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  NASA told Columbia's astronauts today that they may have to perform an
emergency spacewalk to fix or remove a loose seal that could prevent proper
closing of the space shuttle's cargo bay doors.;    "We're trying to determine
by analysis if we'll be able to close the door safely with the environmental
seal where it is currently," Mission Control's Jan Davis told the crew. "We
have a lot of good folks working on that, and we're hopeful we can clear it by
analysis."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SPACEWALK POSSIBLE TO REPAIR LOOSE SEAL
BAY DOOR CLOSING INHIBITED BY FLAW  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "If we can't, there's a possibility that we'll do" a spacewalk, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> said.
She said a spacewalk would not be made before <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. The flight is
scheduled to last nine days.;    The cargo bay doors must be closed tightly
for the shuttle to safely make the fiery re-entry through the atmosphere. Two
of the astronauts -- <PERSON>Tamara Jernigan</PERSON> and <PERSON>James Bagian</PERSON> -- are trained in
spacewalking in case the doors must be closed manually.;    Loose insulation; 
Television pictures beamed to the ground <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> showed that several white
blankets of insulation had come loose in the payload bay. And some
weatherstripping, a long sealing belt, also came loose along the edge of one
of the doors that covers the bay during launch and landing.;    Engineers
still were assessing the situation to see if the doors can be shut tightly by
themselves at the end of the mission.;    <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s astronauts began their
second day of experiments inside <LOCATION>Spacelab</LOCATION> <TIME>this morning</TIME>, drawing more blood
from one another as part of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s most in-depth biomedical research mission.;
   Four of the seven astronauts didn't have far to go when they woke up. They
slept inside the pressurized laboratory module in the shuttle's cargo bay.;   
"They all thought it was a great place to sleep," shuttle commander <PERSON>Bryan
O'Connor</PERSON> said.;    Television images beamed down from space showed cell
biologist <PERSON>Millie Hughes-Fulford</PERSON> calmly taking blood from <PERSON>F. Andrew Gaffney</PERSON>, a
cardiologist. He offered his left arm casually.;    Less than an hour later,
<PERSON>Bagian</PERSON>, a physician, took more blood from <PERSON>Gaffney</PERSON>. Again, he did not flinch.; 
  <PERSON>M. Rhea Seddon</PERSON>, another physician, told <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION> today it was taking
a little longer than anticipated to collect the blood samples.;    "It's still
running a little ragged because everything takes longer and people are
scattered and veins are not cooperating. But I think we're getting it all
done," <PERSON>Seddon</PERSON> said.;    Smiling rat;  She also said that the rats aboard the
flight looked good, joking that two of them she checked "looked happy. One was
smiling at us, and the other one was sleeping. They looked real clean and real
nice." In all, there are 29 white rats and 2,478 tiny jellyfish on board for
the biomedical research.;    The four men and three women, delayed twice in
two weeks because of faulty equipment, rode into orbit <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> after waiting
85 minutes for the weather to improve at <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>;    <LOCATION>Spacelab</LOCATION>, a
pressurized laboratory module in the cargo bay, quickly was powered up, and
the four medical specialists on board began taking the first of daily blood
and urine samples and blood pressure readings planned during the nine-day
mission.;    <PERSON>Bill Huffstetler</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Space Flight
Center</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that television views of the laboratory showed it was
"as clean as a pin" and suffered no damage during the launch.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Space Center, Houston  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910606  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  555  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday June 6, 1991
00158043,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06159146 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06159146 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SPACE; VEHICLE; TRIP  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A loose seal on a cargo bay door presented an unexpected chore today for NASA
engineers on the ground, as well as the prospect of a spacewalk for two
Columbia astronauts.;    A long piece of weatherstripping came loose along the
edge of a door covering the bay during launch and landing.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NASA CONSIDERS SPACEWALK TO FIX LOOSE SEAL
ON SHUTTLE DOOR  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The 60-foot-long doors must close tightly for the fiery re-entry into the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere or the shuttle could burn up. If the doors close properly,
but the loose seal causes a gap, the shuttle could be damaged.;    Engineers
have studied the problem since it was discovered shortly after <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s
launch and are considering sending two of the seven astronauts on board out to
duplicate the problem today on the shuttle Discovery at <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>;    "There are no real concerns that we couldn't
today, right now if we needed to, crush that seal and latch the doors down,"
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> flight director <PERSON>Randy Stone</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. "But it's always the better
part of valor to analyze things in their entirety.";    Several white blankets
of insulation also came loose in the payload bay, probably at the same time
the seal was loosened, in a rush of trapped cargo bay air into the vacuum of
space.;    If the crew can close the doors tight enough, a spacewalk may not
be necessary. But if need be, astronauts <PERSON>James Bagian</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tamara Jernigan</PERSON>
could take a spacewalk as early as <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said. They would either snap
the seal back in place or snip it off. It should take about 1 1/2 hours.;   
<PERSON>Bagian</PERSON> is part of the four-member research team conducting comprehensive
medical tests in <LOCATION>Spacelab</LOCATION>, a compartment the size of a small bus stored in the
bay and connected by a tunnel to the shuttle's crew compartment.;    The
astronauts worked in the lab for the third day in a row <DATE>today</DATE>, collecting
blood samples from each other and monitoring other bodily functions to
determine the effects of weightlessness on humans. They also moved urine
samples from a Spacelab refrigerator back into a mid-deck refrigerator that
got too warm <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and had to be emptied.;    The mid-deck
refrigerator was back in order <TIME>this morning</TIME>, but <PERSON>Bagian</PERSON> said when he opened
the door he was greeted by "a real stench that permeates the whole vehicle."
He said that may be caused by drops of loose urine on the outside of the
sample containers.;    All the urine samples were in good condition despite
the refrigerator problem, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Space Center, Houston  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910607  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  14A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  434  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday June 7, 1991
00159146,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06100068 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06100068 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; Astronauts Jerry L. Ross and Jay Apt put away
a cart they used Monday to move themselves through the cargo bay of Atlantis.
They were testing equipment for possible use by space station builders.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPACE; TRAVEL; VEHICLE; RESEARCH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Grunting, puffing and giggling as they glided up and down the shuttle's cargo
bay, two astronauts tested several different vehicles Monday to determine
which would be the most helpful to workers who are to assemble the space
station later this decade.;    What they may have proved during their marathon
venture outside the Atlantis is that less may be best.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ASTRONAUTS TEST NASA VEHICLES
DEVICES MADE FOR BUILDING SPACE STATION  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Astronauts <PERSON>Jerry L. Ross</PERSON>, 43, and <PERSON>Jay Apt</PERSON>, 41, seemed to prefer the
simplest of the three vehicles they tested along a 47-foot-long track they
installed on the side of the cargo bay.;    <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> wants to know; <ORGANIZATION>The National
Aeronautics and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> would like to know which vehicle would
best serve astronauts who would be required to make many trips along the
station's main truss, which will be longer than a football field. Sometimes
they will have to carry loads so heavy they could not budge them on the
ground.;    One day after their unscheduled spacewalk, during which they fixed
a stuck antenna that threatened the <MONEY>$617 million</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION>,
<DATE>Monday</DATE>'s "extra-vehicular activity," as <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> calls it, was sort of a joy
ride.;    Hand over hand over <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>;  "What a great way to travel," <PERSON>Ross</PERSON> said
as he glided along the rail. The Atlantis was passing 280 miles above <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>,
traveling at 17,300 miles an hour, as the two astronauts moved back and forth
on their makeshift railroad at about the speed of a brisk walk.;    One of the
three vehicles was a platform that the astronaut hooked his feet in and then
pulled himself manually -- hand over hand -- along the rail. The second looked
a little like a railway push car; the astronaut powered it by pushing a handle
back and forth, cranking a mechanical ratchet drive. The third was powered by
a motor with electricity generated by cranks turned by the astronaut.;    Both
men seemed to prefer the hand-over-hand, manually propelled platform, and
their conclusions largely will determine what system is eventually used, said
former astronaut <PERSON>Robert Overmyer</PERSON>, who is in charge of astronaut systems for
one of the station's prime contractors, <ORGANIZATION>McDonnell Douglas.</ORGANIZATION>;    The Atlantis,
commanded by <PERSON>Steven R. Nagel</PERSON>, 44, is scheduled to land <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at <TIME>7:34 a.m.
PDT</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>. The other crew members
are <PERSON>Kenneth D. Cameron</PERSON>, 41, the pilot, and <PERSON>Linda M. Godwin</PERSON>, 38.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Cape Canaveral, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910409  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  431  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday April 9, 1991
00100068,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06102039 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06102039 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Map; MAP: Associated Press; Shuttle landing  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SPACE; VEHICLE; TRIP; END; CALIFORNIA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Space shuttle Atlantis landed with five astronauts today after a triumphant
spacewalking mission that lasted a day longer than planned because of strong
desert wind.;    Atlantis glided through the sky and touched down at 6:55 a.m.
PDT, shortly after sunrise. The arrival was heralded by twin sonic booms that
shook the ground.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ATLANTIS LANDS IN TRIUMPH: 'YOU MADE IT LOOK
EASY'  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Mission Control's <PERSON>Brian Duffy</PERSON> told Cmdr. <PERSON>Steven Nagel</PERSON>, "<PERSON>Steve</PERSON>, you and your
crew did it all and you made it look easy. Congratulations on a great job.";  
 About 1,100 spectators cheered as Atlantis landed smoothly on the dry lake
bed and rolled to a stop.;    Atlantis circled the world almost 93 times
during the six days in space. It traveled 2,480,016 miles.;    <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION>
issued the go-ahead for a landing in the <LOCATION>Mojave Desert</LOCATION> after the winds calmed
down <TIME>this morning</TIME>. Powerful gusts prevented Atlantis from landing there as
planned <DATE>Wednesday.</DATE>;    Flight directors passed up an earlier landing
opportunity at <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION> because of fog and clouds. The weather in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> later cleared, but <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> opted for the spacious lake bed at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> Base.;    The crew of four men and one woman could have stayed up until
Saturday.;    <ORGANIZATION>Atlantis</ORGANIZATION>' astronauts accomplished their primary task on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>,
releasing the 17-ton <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION>. It will circle the Earth for more
than two years in search of gamma rays, the most intense radiation in the
universe.;    The crew also undertook the first American spacewalks in five
years -- one an emergency mission to fix a stuck antenna on the <MONEY>$617 million</MONEY>
observatory, the other to lay groundwork for a <MONEY>$30 billion</MONEY> space station <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
hopes to start building in <DATE>1995.</DATE>;    <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said the crew gathered a wealth of
engineering information from the spacewalks, during which they tested tools
and construction methods for the orbiting laboratory.;    <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION>
awoke crew members today shortly after <TIME>midnight</TIME> -- about 1 1/2 hours early --
to prepare them for a possible <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> landing.;    They were greeted with
music from the TV series "Magnum, <LOCATION>P.I.</LOCATION>" and a taped message from its star, <PERSON>Tom
Selleck</PERSON>. Astronaut <PERSON>Linda Godwin</PERSON> is a big <PERSON>Selleck</PERSON> fan, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.;    "Good
morning, and a special wake-up to <PERSON>Linda</PERSON>," the message said. "This is <PERSON>Tom
Selleck</PERSON> and I hope you had a nice night's sleep, but it's time to get up and
go to work.";    On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, after <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION> waved off the shuttle,
the crew members pulled their ham radio back out and chatted with radio
operators. They also got in some more sightseeing as they orbited Earth at
17,400 mph.;    "It is incredible. Some of the views are amazing," said
astronaut Jay Apt. "You wouldn't believe it. This spacecraft has great
windows.";    The mission, the first of <DATE>1991</DATE>, began with liftoff Friday.;   
Discovery was supposed to go up first, but cracked door hinges forced <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> to
postpone its military flight in <DATE>March to late April</DATE>. Atlantis also has hinge
cracks, but <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said they were much smaller and posed no danger.;    The
doors, on the orbiter's belly, must close tightly to prevent the craft from
being destroyed by the heat of re-entering the atmosphere.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Edwards Air Force Base  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Street  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910411  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  524  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday April 11, 1991
00102039,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06102069 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06102069 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; Atlantis glides down at Edwards Air Force Base
today after 6-day mission  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SPACE; VEHICLE; TRIP; END  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Space shuttle Atlantis landed with five astronauts today after a triumphant
spacewalking mission that lasted a day longer than planned because of strong
desert wind.;    Atlantis glided through the sky and touched down at 6:55 a.m.
PDT, shortly after sunrise. The arrival was heralded by twin sonic booms that
shook the ground.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE SHUTTLE RETURNS IN TRIUMPH  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Mission Control's <PERSON>Brian Duffy</PERSON> told Cmdr. <PERSON>Steven Nagel</PERSON>, "<PERSON>Steve</PERSON>, you and your
crew did it all and you made it look easy. Congratulations on a great job.";  
 About 1,300 spectators cheered as Atlantis landed smoothly on the dry lake
bed and rolled to a stop.;    Atlantis circled the world almost 93 times
during the six days in space. It traveled 2,480,016 miles.; The orbiter and
its crew appeared in excellent condition after landing, with the shuttle's new
carbon brakes looking good and only minimal damage to its heat-shielding
tiles, <PERSON>P.J. Weitz</PERSON>, deputy director of <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>, said at a news
conference in <LOCATION>California.</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION> issued the go-ahead for a landing
in the <LOCATION>Mojave Desert</LOCATION> after the winds calmed down <TIME>this morning</TIME>. Powerful gusts
prevented Atlantis from landing there as planned <DATE>Wednesday.</DATE>;    Flight
directors passed up an earlier landing opportunity at <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION>
because of fog and clouds. The weather in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> later cleared, but <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
opted for the spacious lake bed at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Base.;    The crew of
four men and one woman could have stayed in space until Saturday.;   
<ORGANIZATION>Atlantis</ORGANIZATION>' astronauts accomplished their primary task on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, releasing the
17-ton <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION>. It will circle the Earth for more than two years
in search of gamma rays, the most intense radiation in the universe.;    The
crew also undertook the first American spacewalks in five years -- one an
emergency mission to fix a stuck antenna on the <MONEY>$617 million</MONEY> observatory, the
other to lay groundwork for a <MONEY>$30 billion</MONEY> space station <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> hopes to start
building in <DATE>1995.</DATE>;    <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said the crew gathered a wealth of engineering
information from the spacewalks, during which they tested tools and
construction methods for the orbiting laboratory.;    <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION> awoke
crew members today shortly after <TIME>midnight</TIME> -- about 1 1/2 hours early -- to
prepare them for a possible <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> landing.;    They were greeted with music
from the TV series "Magnum, <LOCATION>P.I.</LOCATION>" and a taped message from its star, <PERSON>Tom
Selleck</PERSON>. Astronaut <PERSON>Linda Godwin</PERSON> is a big <PERSON>Selleck</PERSON> fan, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.;    "Good
morning, and a special wake-up to <PERSON>Linda</PERSON>," the message said. "This is <PERSON>Tom
Selleck</PERSON>, and I hope you had a nice night's sleep, but it's time to get up and
go to work.";    On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, after <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION> waved off the shuttle,
the crew members pulled their ham radio back out and chatted with radio
operators. They also got in some more sightseeing as they orbited Earth at
17,400 mph.;    "It is incredible. Some of the views are amazing," said
astronaut Jay Apt. "You wouldn't believe it. This spacecraft has great
windows.";    The mission, the first of <DATE>1991</DATE>, began with liftoff Friday.;   
Discovery was supposed to go up first, but cracked door hinges forced <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> to
postpone its military flight in <DATE>March to late April</DATE>. Atlantis also has hinge
cracks, but <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said they were much smaller and posed no danger.;    The
doors, on the orbiter's belly, must close tightly to prevent the craft from
being destroyed by the heat of re-entering the atmosphere.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Edwards Air Force Base  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910411  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  12A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  579  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday April 11, 1991
00102069,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900721-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-21-90 0358EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SpaceStation     07-21 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Space Station,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Concludes Space Station May Require Up To 10 Space Walks A
Week</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Up to 10 spacewalks a week will be needed to
maintain outside components of the proposed Space Station Freedom
unless there are major design changes, a study says.
   The study, by astronaut <PERSON>Bill Fisher</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>
engineer <PERSON>Charles Price</PERSON> and released <DATE>Friday</DATE>, showed that in peak
maintenance years with the present space station design, two
astronauts working together would have to spend up to 6,462 hours a
year in space suits repairing and replacing parts.
   Other years, the maintenance would require fewer space walks,
the study said, but over the 35-year lifetime of the station the
time spent on repair space walks would average about 3,276
astronaut-hours a year. This would amount to 273 two-person space
walks a year, or 5.3 a week.
   Each space walk takes about six hours.
   Fisher and <ORGANIZATION>Price</ORGANIZATION> said that the number space walks could be
reduced by up to half if more work can be done by robots that could
be controlled from inside the space station or from the ground.
   Simplifying repair tasks and making all parts replaceable by
robots could drop the total annual space walk hours to 507, a
number that <PERSON>Fisher</PERSON> said would be manageable.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has been criticized by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for designing a space
station that would require so much maintenance, so much so that
much of the time of at least two astronauts on board would be spent
on repairs and parts replacement.
   The current plan calls for eight-member crews.
   <PERSON>Richard Kohrs</PERSON>, director of the space station program, said that
design of the station is now undergoing a major review and that
each of the recommendations in the <ORGANIZATION>Fisher-Price</ORGANIZATION> study will be
evaluated.
   He said changes are being made that will cut down on the weight,
power use and maintenance of the station.
   Reducing the number of space walks, he said, is a major goal.
   ``We're going to build the space station for science research,''
<PERSON>Kohrs</PERSON> said at a news conference <DATE>Friday</DATE>. ``If you are spending a
major part of your time on EVA (extra vehicular activity or space
walks), then you are taking that away from science.''
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> executives had ordered the space walk study to coincide
with the space station design review. <PERSON>Kohrs</PERSON> said the purpose of the
study was to spot problems so that corrections can be made before
construction of station parts begins.
   Assembly of the space station is expected to begin in about
three years and it is expected to be permanently occupied by <DATE>1996</DATE>.
   The station is expected to cost about <MONEY>$30 billion</MONEY> and last about
35 years. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has said the station is critical to the agency's
future plans to explore the moon and to voyage to Mars.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Fisher-Price</ORGANIZATION> report said that a major problem to overcome is
the number of hours of space walking required to maintain the
station while it is being assembled. The station will be put
together with a series of 18 flights by the space shuttle, and
parts of the station will spend months in orbit before it is
permanently occupied by astronauts.
   During that 30-month assembly period, the report said, there
will be a need for 6,267 hours of maintenance by spacewalking
astronauts. This equals about four two-man spacewalks a week.
   ``All of these would have to be done from the space shuttle,''
said <PERSON>Fisher</PERSON>.
   Another study, started after the <ORGANIZATION>Fisher-Price</ORGANIZATION> team made a
preliminary report in the <DATE>spring</DATE>, concluded with estimates close to
those of <PERSON>Fisher</PERSON> and Price. The study, led by <PERSON>William Simon</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>, said, however, that with changes in design,
the spacewalks required to maintain the station could be reduced to
about 485 man-hours a year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871102-0111 </DOCNO>
<HL> The Latest Fashion
For U.S. Spacemen
Is Still Up in the Air
---
The Shuttle Suit Is Old Hat;
Two Engineers at NASA
Vie to Create a Successor
---
By Laurie McGinley
<DD> 11/02/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> GOVMT
AEROSPACE (ARO) </IN>
<DATELINE> HOUSTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A new space race is on -- not to Mars, but to determine what the well-dressed astronaut will wear on strolls outside <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s future space station. 

   The competition is between two spacesuits: One is the daring and exotic all-aluminum AX-5, which has what is known in space circles as the Tin Man. 
The other is the Zero Pre-breathe Mark 3, fashioned from the latest blend of metal and cloth. 
The Mark 3 is more in the traditional spacesuit image. 

   A restyled suit is necessary because changing space needs make the garb used on the space-shuttle flights as outdated as a Nehru jacket. 
"Something more like a blue-collar work suit. 
A suit that you just put on and go out and do a job." 

   Spacesuits, which generally are used only for activities outside a spacecraft -- the suits worn inside the craft are called flight suits -- have run into problems in the past. 
When <ORGANIZATION>Edward White</ORGANIZATION> walked in space in <DATE>1965</DATE>, his suit's cooling system malfunctioned, causing his visor to fog up. 
The beverage sack in <PERSON>Charles Duke</PERSON>'s moon suit leaked in <DATE>1972</DATE>, sending drops of orange drink floating around inside his helmet. 
Apollo crew members complained later that year of being unable to scratch their noses while they walked on the moon. 
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> solved all these problems, the last by putting a strip of Velcro inside the astronauts' helmets so that they could relieve nose itches by simply moving their heads. 

   The goal now is to find the best attire for the space station scheduled to be launched around <DATE>1994</DATE>. 
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> plans to spend <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> on the new suits, which will probably weigh 50 to 100 pounds more than the current, 100-pound shuttle suits. 

   Vying to become the <PERSON>Pierre Cardin</PERSON> of orbital haute couture are two <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers: <PERSON>Mr. Vykukal</PERSON> of the agency's <ORGANIZATION>Ames Research Center</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Moffett Field</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, whose AX-5 is a drastic departure from the mostly soft suits that <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has used before; and <PERSON>Joseph Kosmo</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION> here, whose Mark 3 has evolved from the agency's shuttle suits. 

   "The one who gets there first gets his name in the history books. 
There is no second place," says <PERSON>James Clougherty</PERSON>, a manager at <ORGANIZATION>ILC Dover Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION> spacesuit manufacturer that is helping produce the Mark 3 suit. 

   The winner will be decided partly by a swim-off designed to simulate walking in outer space. 
In coming months, at least three astronauts here will take turns donning the AX-5 and being lowered by crane into a pool 25 feet deep. 
While underwater cameras record their movements, they will touch their toes, work in a mock-up of the shuttle's cargo bay and do underwater construction work. 
Early next year, they will do the same thing with the Mark 3. 
The water tests will measure the suits' flexibility and comfort. 

   Both camps agree that <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> needs a new Extravehicular Mobility Unit, known by most earthlings as a spacesuit, for use in Extravehicular Activities, or spacewalks. 
Space-station astronauts will be working in the vacuum of space three or four times a week for a total of 1,000 hours a year. 
"They'll be fixing solar sails, putting out scientific experiments and servicing satellites," says astronaut <ORGANIZATION>Sherwood Spring</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The new suit should provide greater protection against such potentially deadly hazards as radiation, micrometeoroids and man-made debris. 
"There's a lot of junk out there," notes <PERSON>Mr. Vykukal</PERSON>. 
The new suit also should be easier to maintain than the shuttle suit, which must be overhauled by ground technicians after being used three or four times. 

   Regardless of which suit is developed, certain features probably will be incorporated. 
Any suit, for example, is likely to have a "heads-up display" that would be activated by voice and provide the astronaut with important information, such as the suit's internal temperature, on a one-inch-square TV screen inside the helmet. 
And the suit probably will catch up with the Russians by having a rear hatch for easier donning and doffing. 

   The astronauts will have a big say in deciding which of the newly proposed suits will fly. 
So far, neither suit suits them, and for the same reason. 
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>, at least for now, is insisting that both suits be designed to work at a pressure of about eight pounds per square inch, twice the pressure used in the current shuttle suits. 
But the astronauts worry that a higher-pressure suit could be as inflexible as an overinflated beach ball. 

   The big advantage of a high-pressure suit is that it would eliminate a time-consuming, cumbersome procedure known as pre-breathing. 
On the shuttle, to avoid getting the "bends," astronauts must either pre-breathe <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> oxygen for 3 1/2 hours before going outside, or lower the pressure of the shuttle for several hours and then breathe oxygen for 40 minutes. 
Either way, "it's rather boring," says <PERSON>James</PERSON> "Ox" van <PERSON>Hoften</PERSON>, a former astronaut who now is the manager of space programs at <ORGANIZATION>Bechtel National Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The astronauts' worries about a higher-pressure suit center on the gloves, which they fear could swell up stiff as a frozen flounder, even stiffer than the unpopular shuttle gloves. 

   "Hand fatigue could be a real problem," warns astronaut <PERSON>Jerry Ross</PERSON>. 
"Everything in space is hand work. 
The only time you use your feet is to put them in foot restraints to prevent yourself from floating away." 
He and astronaut <ORGANIZATION>Spring</ORGANIZATION>, in a <DATE>1985</DATE> spacewalk that demonstrated techniques for space-station construction, ended up with sore and tired hands. 
"I felt like I'd been squeezing a rubber racketball," <PERSON>Mr. Ross</PERSON> recalls. 

   The designers admit they are having a hard time coming up with gloves that will work properly. 
Here at the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Kosmo</PERSON> pulls on a newly designed glove, thrusts it into a small vacuum chamber, and repeatedly opens and closes his hands. 
"We're progressing," he says with a sigh. 
"But it doesn't happen overnight." 

   The future of the space station still isn't certain, and astronauts could find themselves all dressed up with no place to go. 
Nevertheless, the spacesuit race is moving ahead. 
About half of the <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> center's Mark 3 suit will be made of metal, but the shoulder and knee joints will be fabric. 
That, the suit's creators say, will make their outfit much more comfortable than the Ames center's all-hard suit. 
"Would you rather bump into the inside of a trash can or a balloon?" says <ORGANIZATION>ILC</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Richard Ellis</PERSON>. 

   But <PERSON>Mr. Vykukal</PERSON>, who has been working on hard suits at <LOCATION>Ames</LOCATION> for two decades but has never had one fly, says he will use padding to make the inside of his AX-5 more user-friendly. 
Astronaut <PERSON>James Buchli</PERSON>, who has tried it on, says he is pleased by the suit's comfort and mobility. 
Moreover, <PERSON>Mr. Vykukal</PERSON> says a hard suit would be more durable, easier to manufacture and less sensitive to the high pressure than a soft suit. 

   Yet for all the debate about weighty design questions, some decisions come down to a simple question of appearance. 
"You can have something that works perfectly," says <PERSON>Mr. Vykukal</PERSON>, who has given his suit a sleeker, sci-fi look. 
"But if it doesn't look good, nobody will buy it." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06101282 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06101282 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  WEATHER; RESULT; US; SPACE; AVIATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Blustery winds prevented NASA from landing the space shuttle Atlantis in
California today, and the astronauts were ordered to remain in space an extra
day.;    Mission Control first delayed the landing by 1 1/2 hours in hopes the
winds would subside. But they didn't, and flight directors decreed a Thursday
morning touchdown at Edwards Air Force Base in the Mojave Desert.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WINDS PREVENT SHUTTLE FROM LANDING  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "I hope you don't mind if we ask you to stay up another day but we're going
to give up on today," Mission Control's <PERSON>Brian Duffy</PERSON> told the crew.;    "We
understand, and I think that's a good decision <PERSON>Brian</PERSON>. Thanks a lot," replied
<PERSON>Steve Nagel</PERSON>, mission commander.;    The astronauts have enough supplies on
board to stay up at least through <DATE>Friday</DATE>. High winds were expected again
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Edwards</LOCATION>, and the weather did not look favorable at the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy
Space Center</ORGANIZATION> backup site in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. Kennedy had not been considered for
today.;    Crosswinds had exceeded <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s limit of 17.3 mph by nearly double
most of the morning in <LOCATION>California.</LOCATION>;    <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> previously has had to delay a
shuttle landing for weather reasons, and a wave-off has almost become
routine.;    <TIME>This morning</TIME>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> re-established contact with a satellite used
to communicate with the shuttle. The space agency lost touch with the
satellite late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and had to switch to ground stations.;    Atlantis'
five astronauts accomplished their primary task on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, releasing the
17-ton <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION>. It will circle the Earth for more than two years
in search of gamma rays, the most intense radiation in the universe.;    The
crew also undertook the first American spacewalks in five years -- one an
emergency mission to fix a stuck antenna on the <MONEY>$617 million</MONEY> observatory, the
other to lay groundwork for a <MONEY>$30 billion</MONEY> space station <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> hopes to start
building in <DATE>1995.</DATE>;    On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, Mission commander <PERSON>Steven Nagel</PERSON> guided
Atlantis to within nine miles of the observatory, after a chase that started
from 95 miles away. After closing in on its quarry, the shuttle zig-zagged
behind it for several hours.;    <PERSON>Nagel</PERSON> used star trackers instead of the more
accurate and sophisticated radar to follow the observatory 280 miles above
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. The star-tracking technique would be vital in case radar failed.;   
The satellite trouble today involved a satellite that covers <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Eastern
Hemisphere</LOCATION>. It relays video and voice signals and other data to the shuttle
and made ground stations obsolete. It was those ground stations that <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
activated.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Cape Canaveral, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910410  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  410  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday April 10, 1991
00101282,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900424-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-24-90 1238EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Shuttle-Thumbnails     04-24 1272</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shuttle-Thumbnails,1327</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Crew of Shuttle Discovery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPACE CENTER, Houston (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are brief sketches of the five
Discovery crew members:
   <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Loren J. Shriver</PERSON> is making his second trip into
space as commander of Discovery on its mission to deploy the <MONEY>$1.5
billion</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>.
   Shriver heads a crew of space veterans on the flight. The last
of shuttle veterans was on the first post-Challenger flight, in the
<DATE>fall of 1988</DATE>.
   As commander, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> is responsible for guiding the shuttle
back to the telescope should a problem occur after it is put in
orbit. Other crew members then would spacewalk to fix the telescope.
   The 45-year-old astronaut first flew into space as pilot of
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s first secret shuttle mission for the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>. That <DATE>January
1985</DATE> flight lasted three days.
   The excitement surrounding the long-awaited mission continued to
mount as the launch day neared, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> said in a recent interview
at the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This is a major milestone,'' he said.
   ``I think they're (scientists using Hubble) going to make some
discoveries and answer some questions we've got now and probably
raise a lot more than we know about right now.''
   Shriver was born in <LOCATION>Jefferson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, and grew up in <LOCATION>Paton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
where his parents still live. He graduated from <ORGANIZATION>Paton Consolidated
High School</ORGANIZATION>.
   He graduated from the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Academy</ORGANIZATION> with a bachelor's degree
in aeronautical engineering. He earned a master's degree in
astronautical engineering from <ORGANIZATION>Purdue University</ORGANIZATION>.
   He attended the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> test pilot school at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force
Base</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and worked on development test and evaluation of the
F-15 fighter aircraft. In <DATE>1978</DATE>, he was selected for astronaut
training.
   He and his wife, <PERSON>Susan</PERSON>, have four children.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are brief sketches of the five
Discovery crew members:
   <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Loren J. Shriver</PERSON> is making his second trip into
space as commander of Discovery on its mission to deploy the <MONEY>$1.5
billion</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>.
   Shriver heads a crew of space veterans on the flight. The last
of shuttle veterans was on the first post-Challenger flight, in the
<DATE>fall of 1988</DATE>.
   As commander, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> is responsible for guiding the shuttle
back to the telescope should a problem occur after it is put in
orbit. Other crew members then would spacewalk to fix the telescope.
   The 45-year-old astronaut first flew into space as pilot of
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s first secret shuttle mission for the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>. That <DATE>January
1985</DATE> flight lasted three days.
   The excitement surrounding the long-awaited mission continued to
mount as the launch day neared, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> said in a recent interview
at the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This is a major milestone,'' he said.
   ``I think they're (scientists using Hubble) going to make some
discoveries and answer some questions we've got now and probably
raise a lot more than we know about right now.''
   Shriver was born in <LOCATION>Jefferson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, and grew up in <LOCATION>Paton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
where his parents still live. He graduated from <ORGANIZATION>Paton Consolidated
High School</ORGANIZATION>.
   He graduated from the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Academy</ORGANIZATION> with a bachelor's degree
in aeronautical engineering. He earned a master's degree in
astronautical engineering from <ORGANIZATION>Purdue University</ORGANIZATION>.
   He attended the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> test pilot school at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force
Base</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and worked on development test and evaluation of the
F-15 fighter aircraft. In <DATE>1978</DATE>, he was selected for astronaut
training.
   He and his wife, <PERSON>Susan</PERSON>, have four children.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are brief sketches of the five
Discovery crew members:
   <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Loren J. Shriver</PERSON> is making his second trip into
space as commander of Discovery on its mission to deploy the <MONEY>$1.5
billion</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>.
   Shriver heads a crew of space veterans on the flight. The last
of shuttle veterans was on the first post-Challenger flight, in the
<DATE>fall of 1988</DATE>.
   As commander, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> is responsible for guiding the shuttle
back to the telescope should a problem occur after it is put in
orbit. Other crew members then would spacewalk to fix the telescope.
   The 45-year-old astronaut first flew into space as pilot of
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s first secret shuttle mission for the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>. That <DATE>January
1985</DATE> flight lasted three days.
   The excitement surrounding the long-awaited mission continued to
mount as the launch day neared, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> said in a recent interview
at the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This is a major milestone,'' he said.
   ``I think they're (scientists using Hubble) going to make some
discoveries and answer some questions we've got now and probably
raise a lot more than we know about right now.''
   Shriver was born in <LOCATION>Jefferson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, and grew up in <LOCATION>Paton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
where his parents still live. He graduated from <ORGANIZATION>Paton Consolidated
High School</ORGANIZATION>.
   He graduated from the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Academy</ORGANIZATION> with a bachelor's degree
in aeronautical engineering. He earned a master's degree in
astronautical engineering from <ORGANIZATION>Purdue University</ORGANIZATION>.
   He attended the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> test pilot school at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force
Base</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and worked on development test and evaluation of the
F-15 fighter aircraft. In <DATE>1978</DATE>, he was selected for astronaut
training.
   He and his wife, <PERSON>Susan</PERSON>, have four children.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are brief sketches of the five
Discovery crew members:
   <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Loren J. Shriver</PERSON> is making his second trip into
space as commander of Discovery on its mission to deploy the <MONEY>$1.5
billion</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>.
   Shriver heads a crew of space veterans on the flight. The last
of shuttle veterans was on the first post-Challenger flight, in the
<DATE>fall of 1988</DATE>.
   As commander, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> is responsible for guiding the shuttle
back to the telescope should a problem occur after it is put in
orbit. Other crew members then would spacewalk to fix the telescope.
   The 45-year-old astronaut first flew into space as pilot of
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s first secret shuttle mission for the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>. That <DATE>January
1985</DATE> flight lasted three days.
   The excitement surrounding the long-awaited mission continued to
mount as the launch day neared, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> said in a recent interview
at the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This is a major milestone,'' he said.
   ``I think they're (scientists using Hubble) going to make some
discoveries and answer some questions we've got now and probably
raise a lot more than we know about right now.''
   Shriver was born in <LOCATION>Jefferson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, and grew up in <LOCATION>Paton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
where his parents still live. He graduated from <ORGANIZATION>Paton Consolidated
High School</ORGANIZATION>.
   He graduated from the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Academy</ORGANIZATION> with a bachelor's degree
in aeronautical engineering. He earned a master's degree in
astronautical engineering from <ORGANIZATION>Purdue University</ORGANIZATION>.
   He attended the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> test pilot school at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force
Base</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and worked on development test and evaluation of the
F-15 fighter aircraft. In <DATE>1978</DATE>, he was selected for astronaut
training.
   He and his wife, <PERSON>Susan</PERSON>, have four children.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are brief sketches of the five
Discovery crew members:
   <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Loren J. Shriver</PERSON> is making his second trip into
space as commander of Discovery on its mission to deploy the <MONEY>$1.5
billion</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>.
   Shriver heads a crew of space veterans on the flight. The last
of shuttle veterans was on the first post-Challenger flight, in the
<DATE>fall of 1988</DATE>.
   As commander, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> is responsible for guiding the shuttle
back to the telescope should a problem occur after it is put in
orbit. Other crew members then would spacewalk to fix the telescope.
   The 45-year-old astronaut first flew into space as pilot of
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s first secret shuttle mission for the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>. That <DATE>January
1985</DATE> flight lasted three days.
   The excitement surrounding the long-awaited mission continued to
mount as the launch day neared, <PERSON>Shriver</PERSON> said in a recent interview
at the <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This is a major milestone,'' he said.
   ``I think they're (scientists using Hubble) going to make some
discoveries and answer some questions we've got now and probably
raise a lot more than we know about right now.''
   Shriver was born in <LOCATION>Jefferson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, and grew up in <LOCATION>Paton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
where his parents still live. He graduated from <ORGANIZATION>Paton Consolidated
High School</ORGANIZATION>.
   He graduated from the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Academy</ORGANIZATION> with a bachelor's degree
in aeronautical engineering. He earned a master's degree in
astronautical engineering from <ORGANIZATION>Purdue University</ORGANIZATION>.
   He attended the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> test pilot school at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force
Base</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and worked on development test and evaluation of the
F-15 fighter aircraft. In <DATE>1978</DATE>, he was selected for astronaut
training.
   He and his wife, <PERSON>Susan</PERSON>, have four children.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06096046 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06096046 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; Shuttle crew heads out to launch pad today at
Kennedy Space Center, Cape Canaveral, Fla. Atlantis astronauts are pilot
Kenneth Cameron, front left, Cmdr. Steve Nagel; mission specialists Jerry
Ross, back left, Jay Apt and Linda Godwin.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPACE; RESEARCH; TRAVEL; VEHICLE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Atlantis thundered into orbit today with five astronauts and an immense
observatory that will stalk the hottest, most powerful rays in the heavens.;  
 Spewing flame from twin booster rockets, the shuttle roared from its seaside
launch pad at 6:23 a.m. PST. It cleared the tower and headed out over the
Atlantic Ocean.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ATLANTIS ROARS INTO ORBIT WITH 5 ASTRONAUTS
MINOR THRUSTER GLITCH NOT EXPECTED TO AFFECT
FLIGHT  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The sky was cloudy after a morning of rain. The weather made the launch
five minutes late.;    The rockets burned for two minutes and dropped empty
into the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> about 130 miles downrange, where ships were waiting to pick
them up. The 100-ton shuttle reached orbit 6 1/2 minutes later on the thrust
of its three main engines.;    Except for the failure of one of several
thrusters during ascent, a minor problem that was not expected to affect the
flight, "all systems aboard Atlantis appear to be performing exceptionally
well," said <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Jeff Carr.</PERSON>;    It was the 39th launch of a
shuttle and the first of <DATE>1991</DATE>, after a hiatus of four months. Gone were
worries over tiny cracks in a door-opening mechanism of Atlantis that had
grounded another shuttle. The two doors on the belly of the orbiter shut
tightly after the fuel tank dropped off, <PERSON>Carr</PERSON> said.;    The main event of the
flight, which will last five days, is the release of the <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray
Observatory</ORGANIZATION>. Mission Cmdr. <PERSON>Steve Nagel</PERSON> and his crew of four will place the
spacecraft in a 279-mile-high orbit on Sunday.;    On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, astronauts <PERSON>Jerry
Ross</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jay</PERSON> Apt are scheduled to take the first space walk by Americans in
more than five years. They are to spend six hours in the open cargo bay
testing equipment that would be needed to build a space station.;    Also
during the mission, pilot <PERSON>Kenneth Cameron</PERSON> and other astronauts will use a ham
radio to contact schoolchildren and other amateur radio operators around the
world. They also hope to reach cosmonauts aboard the Soviet space station
Mir.;    The 17-ton <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION>, the heaviest science satellite ever
lifted by a shuttle, will circle the Earth for at least two years in its quest
for gamma rays.;    "The study of gamma rays opens a new window not only to
the universe but to a whole new realm of physical activities," said <PERSON>Charles
Pellerin</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s astrophysics division.;    "You have the real
possibility of seeing phenomena that have not been observed before and perhaps
have not been imagined before," <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> chief scientist <PERSON>Lennard Fisk</PERSON> said.;   
The Gamma <PERSON>Ray Observatory</PERSON>, known as <ORGANIZATION>GRO</ORGANIZATION>, is the second in <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s series of
<LOCATION>Great Observatories</LOCATION>. The first is the <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>, which was placed
in orbit <DATE>last April</DATE> to examine visible light from objects billions of years
old.;    While the Hubble does its work in the relatively narrow bands of the
visible spectrum, gathering light that originated billions of years ago, the
<ORGANIZATION>GRO</ORGANIZATION> operates at the extreme far end -- beyond ultraviolet and X-rays.;    In
that range, it monitors energies ranging from 20,000 to more than 30 billion
electron volts. Gamma rays are born often in cataclysms that flourish in black
holes, quasars, pulsars and supernova explosions.;    The rays do not
penetrate <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere. If they did, the sky would be a flashing,
violent sight.;    Unlike Hubble, the <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION> has no mirrors. A
shuttle mission is scheduled in <DATE>1993</DATE> to fix a flaw in <LOCATION>Hubble</LOCATION>'s mirror, which
was not discovered until the telescope was in orbit.;    The <MONEY>$617 million</MONEY>
gamma ray probe consists of four scientific instruments, three of them
Volkswagen-sized. Massive devices are needed to collect the rare, sporadically
occurring gamma rays.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MARCIA DUNN, Associated Press; Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Cape Canaveral, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Street  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910405  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  644  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday April 5, 1991
00096046,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900711-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-11-90 1706EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-SpaceStation     07-11 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Station,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Finds More Time Needed for Station Maintenance</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An internal <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> study concludes that
astronauts will have to spend <PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> more time spacewalking to
maintain the space station than previously thought, a congressman
said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``It's going in the wrong direction, not the right direction,''
Rep. <PERSON>Bill Green</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-N.Y.</LOCATION>, said in a telephone interview.
   Green, the ranking minority member of the appropriations
subcommittee that oversees <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> spending, said his staff had seen
some of the same gloomy forecasts as <ORGANIZATION>The New York Times</ORGANIZATION>, which
published the results in its <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> editions.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has said it will make the document public next week, along
with plans to reduce the number of space walks through design
changes and other means. The agency declined requests to make the
study public immediately.
   The space station's top official, <PERSON>William B. Lenoir</PERSON>, has
maintained that the estimates would be high but that the number
could be cut sharply.
   Green said the maintenance requirements were only one issue. The
other, he said, is the limited amount of electrical power that
appears to be available for microgravity experiments on the station.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> plans initially to have 75 kilowatts of power, of which 45
kilowatts will be needed for housekeeping.
   Green said that if <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> can't bring maintenance under control or
provide enough power to be useful, it might be time to change
designs.
   ``One has to look at the possibility that if the situation
continues to deteriorate in terms of safety and the capacity of the
station, there comes a point where we say, `Hey, this design is not
working' and maybe go back to the design this country had,
<ORGANIZATION>Skylab</ORGANIZATION>,'' Green said.
   The Skylab program in <DATE>1973</DATE> and <DATE>1974</DATE> involved sets of three
astronauts working inside the orbiting laboratory for periods of
28, 56 and 84 days.
   The space station, whose cost has more than tripled from the <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY> estimate when President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> proposed it in <DATE>1984</DATE>, is in
the preliminary design phase. A review late this year will lead to
the start of detailed designs.
   A preliminary report in <DATE>March</DATE> by a 12-member team headed by <PERSON>Dr.
William J. Fisher</PERSON>, an astronaut, and <PERSON>Charles R. Price</PERSON>, a robotics
engineer, found the station would need more than 2,200 hours of
maintenance each year, far more than the 130 hours that had been
budgeted.
   The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> said the final report expects that more than
3,800 hours of spacewalking time would be needed. To date,
astronauts have logged 400 hours of space walks, each a risky
exercise.
   ``You can't do it as currently designed,'' the newspaper quoted
an unnamed engineer. ``You have to build a different station.''
   Green said the space station would be useful for two major
tasks: learning what happens when humans spend extended time in
space and processing materials in a near-zero gravity environment.
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is considering a request of <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY> for the
station in the next fiscal year. The first elements of the station
are expected to be put into orbit early in <DATE>1995</DATE>, with completion
some 28 flights later in <DATE>1999</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06096254 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06096254 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; Shuttle crew heads out to launch pad today at
Kennedy Space Center, Cape Canaveral, Fla. Atlantis astronauts are pilot
Kenneth Cameron, front left, Cmdr. Steve Nagel; mission specialists Jerry
Ross, back left, Jay Apt and Linda Godwin.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPACE; RESEARCH; VEHICLE; TRAVEL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Atlantis thundered into orbit today with five astronauts and an immense
observatory that will stalk the hottest, most powerful rays in the heavens.;  
 Spewing flame from twin booster rockets, the shuttle roared from its seaside
launch pad at 6:23 a.m. PST. It cleared the tower and headed out over the
Atlantic Ocean.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ATLANTIS ROARS INTO ORBIT WITH 5 ASTRONAUTS
MINOR THRUSTER GLITCH NOT EXPECTED TO AFFECT
FLIGHT  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The sky was cloudy after a morning of rain. The weather made the launch
five minutes late.;    "No drama," <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> launch director <PERSON>Bob Sieck</PERSON> said of the
countdown. "We had a safe and successful launch.";    The rockets burned for
two minutes and dropped empty into the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> about 130 miles down-range,
where ships were waiting to pick them up. The 100-ton shuttle reached orbit 6
1/2 minutes later on the thrust of its three main engines.;    Except for the
failure of one of several thrusters during ascent, a minor problem that is not
expected to affect the flight, "all systems aboard Atlantis appear to be
performing exceptionally well," said <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Jeff Carr.</PERSON>;    It was
the 39th launch of a shuttle and the first of <DATE>1991</DATE>, after a hiatus of four
months. Gone were worries over tiny cracks in a door-opening mechanism of
Atlantis that had grounded another shuttle. The two doors on the belly of the
orbiter shut tightly after the fuel tank dropped off, <PERSON>Carr</PERSON> said.;    "We were
confident that was going to work," <PERSON>Sieck</PERSON> said.;    The main event of the
flight, which will last five days, is the release of the <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray
Observatory</ORGANIZATION>. Mission Cmdr. <PERSON>Steve Nagel</PERSON> and his crew of four will place the
spacecraft in a 279-mile-high orbit on Sunday.;    On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, astronauts <PERSON>Jerry
Ross</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jay</PERSON> Apt are scheduled to take the first space walk by Americans in
more than five years. They are to spend six hours in the open cargo bay
testing equipment that would be needed to build a space station.;    Also
during the mission, pilot <PERSON>Kenneth Cameron</PERSON>, astronaut <PERSON>Linda Godwin</PERSON> and the
others will use a ham radio to contact schoolchildren and other amateur radio
operators around the world. They also hope to reach cosmonauts aboard the
Soviet space station Mir.;    The 17-ton <ORGANIZATION>Gamma Ray Observatory</ORGANIZATION>, the heaviest
science satellite ever lifted by a shuttle, will circle the Earth for at least
two years in its quest for gamma rays.;    "The study of gamma rays opens a
new window not only to the universe but to a whole new realm of physical
activities," said <PERSON>Charles Pellerin</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s astrophysics division.;
   "You have the real possibility of seeing phenomena that have not been
observed before and perhaps have not been imagined before," <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> chief
scientist <PERSON>Lennard Fisk</PERSON> said.;    The Gamma <PERSON>Ray Observatory</PERSON>, known as <ORGANIZATION>GRO</ORGANIZATION>, is
the second in <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s series of <LOCATION>Great Observatories</LOCATION>. The first is the <ORGANIZATION>Hubble
Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>, which was placed in orbit <DATE>last April</DATE> to examine visible light
from objects billions of years old.;    While the Hubble does its work in the
relatively narrow bands of the visible spectrum, gathering light that
originated billions of years ago, the <ORGANIZATION>GRO</ORGANIZATION> operates at the extreme far end --
beyond ultraviolet and X-rays.;    In that range, it monitors energies ranging
from 20,000 to more than 30 billion electron volts. Gamma rays are born often
in cataclysms that flourish in black holes, quasars, pulsars and supernova
explosions.;    The rays do not penetrate <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere. If they did, the
sky would be a flashing, violent sight.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MARCIA DUNN, Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Cape Canaveral, Fla.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910405  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  615  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday April 5, 1991
00096254,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06166236 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06166236 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SPACE; VEHICLE; TRIP; END; CALIFORNIA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Space shuttle Columbia glided through a clear sky and returned home with seven
astronauts today after a nine-day mission that provided new insight into how
humans adapt to space.;    Columbia landed on the desert base's concrete
runway at 8:39 a.m. returning to Earth without problems despite a loose cargo
bay door seal that had raised concern during the flight. The spaceship's
arrival was heralded by the customary twin sonic booms.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COLUMBIA ENDS 'SUPER FLIGHT' WITH LANDING
AT EDWARDS AFB  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "Congratulations on a super flight," Mission Control's <PERSON>Steve Oswald</PERSON> told
shuttle commander <PERSON>Bryan O'Connor</PERSON> after the orbiter rolled to a stop.;   
<ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> circled the world 146 times and logged 3,779,940 miles during the
journey, which began <DATE>June 5</DATE>. In addition to the four men and three women, the
shuttle carried a Spacelab research module, 29 rats and 2,478 tiny jellyfish.;
   More than 7,500 people gathered at <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> for the landing.;    As the
astronauts prepared for landing earlier today, the shuttle's cargo bay doors
closed normally despite loose weatherstripping. The crew successfully latched
the left, then right, door as ground controllers anxiously monitored the
events.;    An emergency spacewalk would have been required if the damaged
seal had prevented the left door from shutting tightly.;    Astronaut <PERSON>James
Bagian</PERSON> watched the closing of the left door from a medical laboratory in the
payload bay. It was vital that the 60-foot doors close tightly; otherwise, the
shuttle could burn up during the fiery re-entry into the atmosphere.;   
Although data was beamed to the ground on whether the problem door closed
properly, <PERSON>Bagian</PERSON> provided extra information by watching from about 25 feet
away. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said all the latches on the left door snapped properly. The loose
seal did move into part of one latch as expected, but caused no trouble, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
said.;    <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> had been prepared, if necessary, to delay <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s landing
until Saturday.;    The astronauts' biggest problem during the flight, aside
from the loose seal, was two overheating refrigerator-freezer units. The crew
had to shuffle precious blood and urine samples from one laboratory freezer to
the other, depending on which worked at the time.;    Both freezers seemed to
be working well today, said <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION> commentator <PERSON>James Hartsfield.</PERSON>;   
The astronauts wrapped up their research <DATE>Thursday</DATE> with more blood collection,
and heart and lung tests. During the mission, the astronauts poked and prodded
each other in a series of experiments to learn more about how weightlessness
affects humans.;    Four astronauts will remain at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards</ORGANIZATION> a week after
landing for further medical tests. The rats and jellyfish also will be studied
after their return.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Edwards Air Force Base  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910614  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  422  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday June 14, 1991
00166236,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900331-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-31-90 1736EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpaceShuttle     03-31 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle,0490</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Moves Up Launch Date for Space Telescope</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>, in a rare move, advanced the
launch date <DATE>Saturday</DATE> for the shuttle Discovery and its prestigious
payload, the <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>.
   Discovery now is due to lift off <DATE>April 10</DATE>, two days earlier than
planned.
   ``The shuttle team is ready to fly. Hubble is one of the most
exciting payloads ever launched aboard the shuttle, and we're
looking forward to the mission,'' said <PERSON>William Lenoir</PERSON>, associate
administrator for space flight for the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and
Space Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   The space agency's <ORGANIZATION>Flight Readiness Review Board</ORGANIZATION> decided to move
up the mission after meeting for two days at <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>last week</DATE> technicians needed little of the contingency
time built into <ORGANIZATION>Discovery</ORGANIZATION>'s prelaunch schedule.
   Once deployed by <ORGANIZATION>Discovery</ORGANIZATION>'s astronauts, the Hubble will orbit
380 miles above <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> for 15 years. The telescope will be capable
of looking seven times more deeply into space with greater clarity
and detecting objects 50 times fainter than the best ground-based
observatory.
   Astronomers expect to use it to study stars and galaxies so
distant that their light has been traveling toward <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> for 14
billion years.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> occasionally has shifted shuttle launch dates because of
scheduling changes in the months prior to liftoff. But it is the
first time liftoff has been accelerated during orbiter processing.
   In <DATE>February</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Discovery</ORGANIZATION>'s launch date was changed from <DATE>April 18
to April 12</DATE> after the lower right segment of the shuttle's solid
rocket booster was replaced more quickly than anticipated.
   The telescope's installation into the orbiter was delayed <DATE>last
week</DATE>, however, after small mosquito-like insects called midges
invaded a payload preparation room at the launch pad. Engineers
feared the bugs might damage the sensitive instrument, the most
expensive unmanned spacecraft ever built.
   Forty midges were trapped, and technicians loaded the
25,000-pound telescope into the shuttle's payload bay <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, two
days later than planned.
   Mission specialist <PERSON>Bruce McCandless II</PERSON>, one of Discovery's five
astronauts, helped link electrical connections between Discovery
and Hubble on <DATE>Friday</DATE>. He also checked the telescope for sharp edges
that might snag spacesuits in the event of a spacewalk.
   McCandless and mission specialist <PERSON>Kathryn Sullivan</PERSON> are prepared
to step into space should the telescope need to be adjusted or
repaired following deployment. It would be the first American
spacewalk since <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   Technicians planned to test the telescope's systems and
scientific instruments <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. They want to ensure remote
communications with the <ORGANIZATION>Space Telescope Operations Control Center</ORGANIZATION>
facilities.
   The telescope is named for the late American astronomer <PERSON>Edwin P.
Hubble</PERSON>, who discovered in the <DATE>1920s</DATE> the universe is constantly
expanding, a finding that is the basis for the current Big Bang
theory of the formation of the universe.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-37169 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drsov031_b_94015" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-SOV-94-031 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> RUSSIA NATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<F P=101> Energy &amp; Space Issues </F>
<H3> <TI>   Shuttle Program Ends in `Failure' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PM1402162394 Moscow IZVESTIYA in Russian 12 Feb 94 p 2 </F>
<F P=103> PM1402162394 </F>
<F P=104>  Moscow IZVESTIYA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FP=105> Russian </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Sergey Leskov</PERSON>: "<PERSON>Krikalev</PERSON>'s Debut on `Discovery' </F>
Was Successful, But the Satellite's Debut was Not"] 
  [Text] The landing of the "Discovery" space shuttle at the 
Canaveral space center at <DATE>2050</DATE> on 11 <DATE>February</DATE> marks the end of 
the first ever flight when <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> astronauts and a Russian 
cosmonaut have been members of the same crew. Unfortunately, 
the attempts to place the "Wake Shield" satellite in orbit ended 
in failure. <PERSON>Sergey Krikalev</PERSON> was going to work with the 
satellite, which had been carried in the cargo bay. 
  The satellite was to have moved to a distance of 75 km from 
the space shuttle. At that distance, with no microgravitation 
at all and no effect from the station's exhaust gases, there 
would have been an experiment to grow extremely pure 
semiconductor films for new-generation computers. But the 
guidance system of the manipulator, which would have been used 
to move the satellite, turned out to be faulty. 
  This failure is very regrettable, since this faulty 
manipulator will be used to assemble the components of the 
"Alfa" international station when it is created. After many 
attempts the astronauts did manage to obtain seven laminated 
electronic components of reasonable quality in the satellite 
factory, but they were not as fine as had been expected. 
  According to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> specialists, <PERSON>Sergey Krikalev</PERSON> performed 
very well, despite the relative failure of the main experiment. 
Any aberrations in the operation of the vehicle were instantly 
eliminated by our engineer. 
  In a year's time a second Russian cosmonaut -- Colonel 
<PERSON>Vladimir Titov</PERSON> -- will fly in the shuttle. During this flight 
the shuttle will approach our "Mir" station for the first time 
and <ORGANIZATION>Titov</ORGANIZATION> will perform a spacewalk. A docking between "Mir" and 
the shuttle is planned for <DATE>spring 1995</DATE>. Incidentally, this week 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> astronauts <PERSON>Norman Thagard</PERSON>, 51, and <PERSON>Bonnie Dunbar</PERSON>, 45 (wife 
of astronaut <PERSON>Ronald Sega</PERSON>, who was on the "Discovery" flight), 
started training sessions at the <ORGANIZATION>Cosmonaut Training Center</ORGANIZATION> near 
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>. The long flight by a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> astronaut on the Russian 
"Mir" station is to begin on 1 <DATE>March 1995</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
