<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880714-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-14-88 1228EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-BoyAviator Bjt   07-14 0721</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boy Aviator, Bjt,0740</SECOND>
<HEAD>11-Year-Old Completes Flight Over Atlantic</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 11-year-old Californian, the youngest pilot to
fly the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, stepped from the cockpit <DATE>Thursday</DATE> with a huge
grin on his freckled face. He was greeted by champagne toasts and a
proud but worried mother.
   ``We're finally here. We made it,'' said <PERSON>Christopher Lee
Marshall</PERSON>, weary but beaming, as he stood on the wing of his
single-engine <PERSON>Mooney</PERSON> 252 aircraft at <LOCATION>Le Bourget</LOCATION>, the same airfield
where <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON> completed the first solo transatlantic
flight in <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   ``Mommy missed you so much. Give me a kiss,'' said his mother,
<PERSON>Gail Marshall</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Oceana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, who waved an American flag and
handed Christopher a new stuffed bear.
   His old stuffed bear <PERSON>Charles Lindbeargh</PERSON>, cuddly and blue with
aviator's helmet and goggles, accompanied him on the long flight.
   ``<PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON> was one of my heroes,'' the young aviator
told reporters. ``So we decided on this trip, then next year
hopefully around the world.''
   He still wore his bright blue flight suit, with a baseball cap
reading ``<PERSON>Chris Marshall</PERSON> Tour'' covering his straw-colored hair, as
he sipped cola at a champagne and soft-drink reception inside an
airport hangar.
   Unlike <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON>, <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> made several stops between <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> _ in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> _ and
had company and emergency help from retired <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot <PERSON>Randy
Cunningham</PERSON>, 46. Their trip started in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 7</DATE>.
   ``I didn't want to take an 11-year-old boy and make him fly for
20 hours straight,'' <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> said. ``I had a hard enough time
having him fly eight hours a day and keeping him awake. You know an
11-year-old boy wants to go to sleep when he gets tired.''
   Christopher's mother and friends who helped plan the trip said
they did not know who the previous youngest pilot to fly the
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> might have been, but they were confident no one younger
had done it.
   <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> said the youngster, who will enter fifth grade this
<DATE>fall</DATE>, is ``a very talented pilot. He flies better than some of the
adults I've flown with.''
   He first went into a cockpit when he was 4 years old _ with his
father, an airline pilot _ and began flying with an instructor when
he was 7.
   Last year he became the youngest pilot to fly across the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>, but the record already has been broken. <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> said he
was glad even younger kids have followed his example.
   ``I'm an ambassador to the youth of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, and I'm showing all
kids across <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> that they can go out and accomplish their
dreams,'' he said.
   The scariest moment of the flight came <DATE>early Wednesday</DATE>, when the
plane's oil pressure fell and its engine began overheating in bad
weather between <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Reykjavik</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>.
   Cunningham took the controls for the return to the southeast
coast of <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> and had to pick his way through mountains to a
small airfield at <LOCATION>Kulusuk</LOCATION>, where clouds were just 100 feet off the
ground.
   ``Only one of a million pilots could have made that landing and
he did,'' <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> said. ``We came so close to dying.''
   ``I didn't think we'd make it through. We had to fly at 50 feet
off the ground, because there were mountains and it was
quarter-mile visibility and all the ocean was iced up. It was
neat.''
   The former <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot said <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> was not exaggerating the
danger they had faced.
   ``I went back in the clouds and came back down and then went
back around the mountains for about 20 minutes, trying to find the
runway desperately,'' he said. ``I didn't think I was going to
live.''
   Because <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> only flew the plane while it was
backtracking, he and <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> both consider the youngster to
have been the pilot for a complete transatlantic crossing.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Marshall</PERSON> said she worried throughout the voyage, while
waiting at a <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> hotel room, but didn't realize until later how
frightening the experience could be for her son.
   ``If I knew, I don't think I would have let him go,'' she said.
   After engine repairs in <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> took the controls
again for the flight to <LOCATION>Reykjavik</LOCATION>, then on to <LOCATION>Glasgow</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>,
where they stayed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> before the final leg to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880713-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-13-88 2223EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BoyAviator 1stLd-Writethru a0878 07-13 0367</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boy Aviator, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0878,0374</SECOND>
<HEAD>California Boy Flyer Arrives In Scotland; Next Stop: Paris</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to Clarify that boy and Cunningham don't
regard feat accomplished until they arrive in Paris, as per
Lindbergh's route. PICKS up 4th graf pvs bgng, Earlier Wednesday,
...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>GLASGOW, Scotland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 11-year-old <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> boy bidding
to fly the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> in a single-engine plane arrived in this
western Scottish port city <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> from <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Christopher Lee Marshall</PERSON> said he plans to leave for <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> to complete his journey and become the youngest
pilot to cross the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   The boy, from <LOCATION>Oceano</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, started his flight in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, <DATE>July 7</DATE>. He said he hoped to reach Le Bourget airport
outside <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> (<TIME>5 a.m. EDT</TIME>). Le Bourget is where <PERSON>Charles
Lindbergh</PERSON> completed his historic solo crossing in <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   Christopher and <PERSON>Randy Cunningham</PERSON>, a 46-year-old retired <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot who is accompanying the boy, don't regard the feat
accomplished until they reach <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, following <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON>'s
tradition. The two stayed overnight at a <LOCATION>Glasgow</LOCATION> hotel.
   Earlier <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> landed his <PERSON>Mooney</PERSON> 252 aircraft at
<LOCATION>Reykjavik</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>'s capital, after flying about 450 miles from
<LOCATION>Kulusuk</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>'s southeast coast in 2 hours, 15 minutes.
   On arrival at <LOCATION>Reykjavik</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> said the flight was
pleasant but he was frightened <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> over <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> when he was
forced to return to Kulusuk because of problems with low oil
pressure and an overheated engine.
   He said he flew the plane all the time but needed <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON>'s
expert skills and knowledge to advise him on landing in <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>.
   Asked why he was doing it, the boy said: ``I want to get kids
all over the world to accomplish their dreams.''
   Christopher has his teddy bear in the plane's back seat.
   ``He (the bear) doesn't like to sit in the back but I throw him
farther back if he starts complaining,'' he said.
   Cunningham limits <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON>'s daily flying time to eight
hours. He stopped in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> before flying
to <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>.
   Last year <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> became the youngest pilot to cross the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, a record that has since been broken by 9-year-old
<PERSON>Tony Aliengena</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06279017 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06279017 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Bruno Hauptmann; PHOTO: Anna Hauptmann  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; HISTORY; KIDNAPPING; AIR; AVIATION; CELEBRITY; CHILD  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The 92-year-old widow of a man executed in 1936 for killing the kidnapped son
of aviator Charles Lindbergh returned to the scene of her husband's
sensational trial Friday as part of her campaign to clear his name.;   Anna
Hauptmann visited this small town for the first time since the trial to again
urge Gov. Jim Florio to declare that Bruno Richard Hauptmann was unfairly
convicted 56 years ago.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WIDOW SEEKS TO REOPEN LINDBERGH CASE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Florio</PERSON> said state Attorney General <PERSON>Robert Del Tufo</PERSON> believes there is no
reason to reopen what was then dubbed "the trial of the century." But he said
he would look at material sent to him.;   In her second public plea to <PERSON>Florio</PERSON>
in 16 months, <PERSON>Anna Hauptmann</PERSON> said she wants a chance to convince him that her
husband did not kidnap and murder 20-month-old <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh Jr.</PERSON> in <DATE>1932.</DATE>;
  "My husband was never, never near the <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> home," <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> told a news
conference at the <ORGANIZATION>Union Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, where reporters and jurors stayed during the
trial. "They killed an innocent man.";   She said she was with her husband the
night of the kidnapping.;   "We didn't even know there was a kidnapping until
the next day," she said.;   <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> went to the electric chair <DATE>April 3,
1936</DATE>, about four years after the boy was abducted from the <LOCATION>Lindbergh</LOCATION> home near
<ORGANIZATION>Hopewell</ORGANIZATION>. The child's body was discovered in a shallow grave near the home.
<PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON>, a German immigrant, maintained his innocence to the end.;   "The
trial of the century was probably the greatest fraud in the history of this
country," said <PERSON>Robert Bryan</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> attorney who represents <PERSON>Anna
Hauptmann.</PERSON>;   <PERSON>Bryan</PERSON> said hundreds of thousands of pages of documents and lost
trial evidence prove that the trial was filled with misrepresentations and
fraud, that evidence was suppressed, that witnesses lied and that testimony
was changed.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Flemington, N.J.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911005  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  313  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, October 5, 1991
00279017,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880712-0144 </DOCNO>
<HL> Young Pilot Delays Trans-Atlantic Flight Because of Problems </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> MONTREAL (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 11-year old who is trying to become the world's youngest trans-Atlantic pilot had to postpone his dream <DATE>Sunday</DATE> when a voltage regulator on his plane started acting up. 

   <PERSON>Christopher Lee Marshall</PERSON>, who wants to emulate <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>'s <DATE>1927</DATE> flight to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, arrived in <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> aboard his <PERSON>Mooney</PERSON> 252 two-seater. 

   The young aviator from <LOCATION>Oceana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, was scheduled to fly to <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, then stop in <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> before arriving in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
He began his trip <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. 

   But <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>' co-pilot, <PERSON>Randy</PERSON> (Duke) <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON>, flew the plane to <LOCATION>Danbury</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to have the voltage meter repaired. 
The two hoped to resume the flight yesterday. 

   <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>, who will be a fifth grader this <DATE>fall</DATE>, first took the controls of a plane at age four and began flying with an instructor at seven. 
He is the son of a commercial pilot. 
Last year, he became the youngest pilot to cross the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   <PERSON>Mr. Cunningham</PERSON>, 46, a retired commander at <LOCATION>Miramar Naval Air Station</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and a <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> war pilot, sits in the pilot's seat. 
But he says <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> has done all the flying. 
He limits the boy's flying time to less than eight hours at a stretch. 

   Chris has said this trip will make him the world's youngest trans-Atlantic pilot. 
His next goal is to become the youngest pilot to fly around the world. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Lindbergh</PERSON> flew from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, then to <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> before completing his 33 1/2-hour, non-stop solo flight across the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>1927</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880710-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-88 2258EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Boy-Aviator     07-10 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boy-Aviator,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Young Pilot's Transatlantic Flight Held Up By Electrical Problem</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONTREAL (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 11-year-old who is trying become the world's
youngest transatlantic pilot had to postpone his dream <DATE>Sunday</DATE> when
a voltage regulator on his plane started acting up.
   <PERSON>Christopher Lee Marshall</PERSON>, who wants to emulate <PERSON>Charles
Lindbergh</PERSON>'s <DATE>1927</DATE> flight to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, arrived in <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> aboard his <ORGANIZATION>Mooney</ORGANIZATION> 252 two-seater.
   The young aviator from <LOCATION>Oceana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, was scheduled to fly to
<LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, then stop in <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> before arriving in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. He began his trip <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>.
   But <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>' co-pilot, <PERSON>Randy</PERSON> (Duke) <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON>, flew the plane to
<LOCATION>Danbury</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to have the voltage meter repaired. The two
hope to resume the flight <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>, who will be a fifth grader this <DATE>fall</DATE>, first took the
controls of a plane at age 4 and began flying with an instructor at
7. He is the son of a commercial pilot.
   Last year, <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> became the youngest pilot to cross the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Tony Aliengena</PERSON>, a 9-year-old from <LOCATION>San Juan Capistrano</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, broke the record in <DATE>April</DATE> by making a
California-to-Massachusetts round trip.
   <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON>, 46, a retired commander at <LOCATION>Miramar Naval Air
Station</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and a <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> war pilot, sits in the pilot's seat.
But he says <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> has done all the flying.
   Cunningham limits the boy's flying time to less than eight hours
at a stretch.
   Chris has said this trip will make him the world's youngest
transatlantic pilot. His next goal is to become the youngest pilot
to fly around the world.
   Lindbergh flew from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, then to <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION> before completing his 33{-hour, non-stop solo flight across
the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>1927</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880709-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-09-88 0556EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BoyFlier     07-09 0470</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boy Flier,0485</SECOND>
<HEAD>11-Year-Old Pilot Arrives In New York Prior To Paris Trip</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: May be led.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 11-year-old aviator who plans to emulate
<PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>'s flight to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> arrived in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> with a bit
of a scare.
   <PERSON>Christopher Lee Marshall</PERSON> was piloting his <PERSON>Mooney</PERSON> 252 two-seater
toward busy <LOCATION>La Guardia Airport</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> when the plane's
electrical power _ and radio _ went dead.
   ``I thought we might get in trouble if we can't call the
tower,'' <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> said later.
   But the power outage lasted only about 10 seconds and he landed
safely.
   ``I thought it was neat to land at a big airport,'' the <LOCATION>Oceano</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, boy said.
   <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>, who is accompanied by a former <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot, hopped across
the country from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Kerrville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, then to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Today _ if the plane's electrical problems are sorted out _ he
and his companion planned to head toward <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. His flight plan
calls for stops in <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>.
   ``I want to show all other kids across <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> that if I can do
this trip, they can do this trip,'' <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Lambert
Airport</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> before taking off for <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>, the son of a commercial pilot, first took the controls of
a plane at age 4, and began flying with an instructor at 7.
   Lindbergh flew from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, then to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
before completing his 33{-hour, non-stop solo flight across the
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   Last year, <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> became the youngest flier to cross the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Tony Aliengena</PERSON>, a 9-year-old from <LOCATION>San Juan Capistrano</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, broke the record in <DATE>April</DATE> by making a
California-to-Massachusetts round trip.
   <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>, who will be a fifth-grader this <DATE>fall</DATE>, said this trip
would make him the world's youngest trans-Atlantic pilot. He is
accompanied by <PERSON>Randy</PERSON> ``Duke'' <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON>, 46, a retired commander
at <LOCATION>Miramar Naval Air Station</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War pilot.
   Cunningham sits in the pilot's seat in the two-seat craft.
<PERSON>Chris</PERSON>' seat is boosted to window-level by a foam cushion. But <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>
has done all of the flying, <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> said.
   The two flew to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> in a borrowed plane, then traded it for a
new aircraft that was built for the trans-Atlantic journey.
   Because <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> is limiting the boy's flying time to less
than eight hours at a time, the flight will be stretched out over
five days.
   ``He's doing good; he's a tiger,'' <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> said. ``He was
sick on the flight from <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, but he flew right through it. He's
got around 270 hours of flying time in and he's very responsive.
Tell him to do something and he does it.''
   <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>' mother, <PERSON>Gail Marshall</PERSON>, founded a company that raised
money to pay for the flight.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880707-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-07-88 1331EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BoyFlier 1stLd-Writethru a0587 07-07 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boy Flier, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0587,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>11-Year-Old Starts Lindbergh Flight Re-creation</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS Kernville to Kerrville in 2nd graf, `Christopher Lee
....'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SHARON L. JONES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 11-year-old boy accompanied by a retired
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot ace today flew off on his quest to retrace <PERSON>Charles A.
Lindbergh</PERSON>'s historic flight to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, a 7,000-mile journey.
   <PERSON>Christopher Lee Marshall</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Oceano</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Randy
Cunningham</PERSON>, 46, departed from <ORGANIZATION>Montgomery Field</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>8:32 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>
on the first leg of their trip to <LOCATION>Kerrville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   The two, flying the first leg in a borrowed plane, will trade it
for a new Mooney 252 aircraft built for the trans-Atlantic journey.
Takeoff was originally scheduled for <DATE>Monday</DATE>, but was delayed by
storms in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1927</DATE>, <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> flew from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, then
flight across the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Because <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> is limiting the boy's flying time to less
than eight hours at a time, the trip will stretch out over five
days and include stops in <LOCATION>Kernville</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>; Sondestrom, <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Reykjavik</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>.
   According to <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>, the flight to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> would make him the
world's youngest trans-Atlantic pilot.
   ``I'm very happy,'' he said shortly before takeoff. ``I am an
ambassador to the youth of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, and I want to show all the
youth that if I can do my dreams, anyone can.''
   He said ``trying to stay awake'' would probably be the most
difficult part, ``but I will.''
   ``I'm not going to touch the controls unless there's an
emergency. <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>' aviation skills are phenomenal,'' <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON>
said. The youngster has logged 200 hours, compared to <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON>'s
more than 7,000 miles.
   <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>, the son of a commercial air pilot, gained fame last
<DATE>August</DATE> when at age 10 he became the youngest aviator to fly across
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>April</DATE>, however, a 9-year-old from <LOCATION>San Juan Capistrano</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Tony Aliengena</PERSON>, broke the record by making a
California-Massachusetts round trip.
   <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> and his mother, <PERSON>Gail Marshall</PERSON>, who live about 15 miles
south of <LOCATION>San Luis Obispo</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>central California</LOCATION>, recruited
<PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> for this trip after meeting him at an air show last year.
   Cunningham, a retired <LOCATION>Miramar Naval Air Station</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>,
commander, was the only <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot ace in the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War and is
the most-decorated <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot, a <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880709-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-09-88 2343EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BoyFlier 1stLd-Writethru a0625 07-09 0414</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boy Flier, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0625,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>11-Year-Old Pilot Begins First Hop On Flight To Paris</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf with 2 grafs to UPDATE with comment from boy
after he arrived in Montreal, picking up 3rd graf pvs, `He
arrived...'.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eleven-year-old pilot <PERSON>Chris Marshall</PERSON> took off
from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> on a trip to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, just like his hero,
<PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON> _ but with a few stops and a grown-up co-pilot.
   Bad weather and a thorough mechanical inspection of his <PERSON>Mooney</PERSON>
252 two-seater delayed the takeoff from <LOCATION>La Guardia Airport</LOCATION> until <TIME>5
p.m.</TIME>
   ``I want to show all the kids in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> that if I can do
this trip, then they can achieve their dreams too,'' <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> said
after arriving at his first stop along the way, <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>.
   He arrived in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> after a disconcerting
moment when the electrical system shut down for 10 seconds during
his approach.
   Chris landed safely, though, and all systems were go <DATE>Saturday</DATE> _
onboard video cameras were suspected of having drained the
batteries on <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Chris, of <LOCATION>Oceano</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, has flown from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. He plans stops in <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> on his way to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Though space was at a premium because of emergency gear required
for flights over the <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> made room for his
stuffed bear, outfitted with goggles, named ``<PERSON>Charles Lindbeargh</PERSON>.''
   The fifth-grader, the son of a commercial pilot, is also
accompanied by <PERSON>Randy</PERSON> ``Duke'' <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON>, 46, a retired <LOCATION>Miramar
Naval Air Station</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, commander and pilot in the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   Cunningham sits in the pilot's seat in the two-seat craft.
<PERSON>Chris</PERSON>' seat is boosted to window-level by a foam cushion. But <PERSON>Chris</PERSON>
has done all of the flying, <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> said. The boy's flight time
is limited to less than eight hours at a stretch.
   Chris first took the controls of a plane at age 4, and began
flying with an instructor at age 7.
   Last year, he became the youngest flier to cross the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Tony Aliengena</PERSON>, a 9-year-old from <LOCATION>San Juan Capistrano</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, broke the record in <DATE>April</DATE> by making a
California-Massachusetts round trip.
   <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> said this trip would make him the world's youngest
transatlantic pilot.
   Lindbergh flew from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, then to <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION> before completing his history-making solo flight across the
<LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>1927</DATE>. The non-stop flight took 33{ hours.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880714-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-14-88 0558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-BoyAviator     07-14 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boy Aviator,0524</SECOND>
<HEAD>California Boy, 11, Becomes Youngest Pilot To Cross Atlantic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LE BOURGET, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 11-year-old <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> boy today
became the youngest pilot to cross the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, landing at the
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> airport where <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON> completed a historic solo
crossing in <DATE>1927</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Christopher Lee Marshall</PERSON> touched down his single-engine plane at
Le Bourget airport on a flight from <LOCATION>Glasgow</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>, where he
spent the night.
   The boy aviator was greeted by his mother as he stepped from the
plane wearing a bright blue flight suit and a baseball cap with a
sign reading ``<PERSON>Chris Marshall</PERSON> Tour.''
   ``We're finally here. We made it,'' he said, grinning ear-to-ear
but looking tired.
   ``Mommy missed you so much. Give me a kiss,'' said his mother,
<PERSON>Gail Marshall</PERSON>, who waved an American flag and clutched a stuffed
bear intended as a present for her son.
   The young aviator from <LOCATION>Oceano</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, then kissed his mother.
   Christopher started his flight in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 7</DATE>. He was
accompanied by retired <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot <PERSON>Randy Cunningham</PERSON>, 46, who limited
<PERSON>Marshall</PERSON>'s flying time to eight-hour stretches.
   A champagne and cola reception was held in the hangar of the
airport, north of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Despite the trans-Atlantic venture, which included stops in <LOCATION>St.
Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> revealed his youth.
   On stepping from the plane, his first words to his mother were:
``I have to go to the toilet.'' He disappeared briefly then
returned to pose for photographers.
   At one point, <PERSON>Christopher</PERSON> re-entered the aircraft to produce his
old stuffed bear, from which he has said he is inseparable.
Photographers snapped pictures of Christopher with the cuddly
animal in its goggles and helmet and bearing a sign with its name
``<PERSON>Charles Lindbeargh</PERSON>.''
   Christopher arrived in <LOCATION>Glasgow</LOCATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> after an 840-mile
flight from <LOCATION>Reykjavik</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> in his single-engine <PERSON>Mooney</PERSON> 252
aircraft.
   He arrived in <LOCATION>Reykjavik</LOCATION> early <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> after flying about 450
miles from <LOCATION>Kulusuk</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>'s southeast coast in 2 hours 15
minutes.
   The arrival in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> was delayed by one day due to engine
troubles <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that forced the plane back to <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> said he took over the controls to fly the plane 50
miles back to <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> after engine trouble and bad weather with
low visibility made the situation critical.
   He said it was the only time during the flight that he took
control of the aircraft.
   <PERSON>Cunningham</PERSON> said he had trouble finding the air field at <LOCATION>Kukusuk</LOCATION>,
an island of <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>'s southeast coast: ``We would have had to
ditch at sea. I didn't think I was going to live.''
   The oil filter cap had rattled loose so the oil pressure
plummeted and the engine overheated.
   Christopher's mother said her son began flying with his father
at the age of 4 and began training with an instructor at age 7.
   She said she was worried by the problems <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``If I knew, I don't think I would have let him go,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880706-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-06-88 0016EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LindberghRuling     07-06 0271</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lindbergh Ruling,0278</SECOND>
<HEAD>Appeals Court Affirms Lower Court Ruling That Rejects Hauptmann
Lawsuit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal appeals court <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> rejected
efforts by the wife of <PERSON>Bruno Richard Hauptmann</PERSON> to clear his name in
the <DATE>1932</DATE> kidnapping-murder of the son of aviator <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>
   In a one-sentence statement, the 3rd <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Circuit Court of
Appeals</ORGANIZATION> here affirmed a <DATE>September 1987</DATE> ruling by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District
<PERSON>Judge Garrett E. Brown Jr.</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Trenton</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Robert R. Bryan</PERSON>, the attorney of <PERSON>Anna Hauptmann</PERSON>, vowed to take
his appeal to the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We are undaunted,'' he said in a telephone interview from his
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> office. ``Our goal remains the same: to clear her
husband's name during her life.''
   <PERSON>Mrs. Hauptmann</PERSON>, 89, lives in <LOCATION>Yeadon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa</LOCATION>.
   Her husband was convicted in the <DATE>March 1, 1932</DATE>, kidnapping and
murder of the 20-month-old son of <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> and his wife, <PERSON>Anne
Spencer Morrow Lindbergh</PERSON>, from their <LOCATION>East Amwell Township</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>,
estate.
   <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> was convicted following a sensational trial in
<LOCATION>Flemington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION> that earned international attention, and was
executed <DATE>April 3, 1936</DATE>, at <ORGANIZATION>Trenton State Prison</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Hauptmann</PERSON> charged in a federal lawsuit that the case
against her husband should be reopened. The legal action was based
on new evidence <PERSON>Bryan</PERSON> said he uncovered, including more than 22,000
pages of documents and lost trial evidence found three years ago in
the garage of the late <PERSON>Harold G. Hoffman</PERSON>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>'s governor at
the time of the trial and execution.
   The lawsuit claimed that the trial was riddled with
mispresentations and fraud, evidence was suppressed, witnesses were
coerced or lied on the state and testimony was changed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06065120 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06065120 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  NEWS; WRITING; PROFESSIONAL; DEATH; OBITUARY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Leo Katcher, who interviewed the kidnapper of Charles Lindbergh's baby, wrote
novels and was a political organizer for a president, has died. He was 79.;   
Mr. Katcher died Wednesday of a heart attack, his brother, Eddie Katcher, said
by telephone from New York. Mr. Katcher became ill after appearing on a local
television show Tuesday night, his brother said.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LEO KATCHER, REPORTER, NOVELIST, POLITICAL
ACTIVIST  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Obituaries  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Mr. Katcher</PERSON> began his newspaper career at age 10 in <LOCATION>Bayonne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, when the
<ORGANIZATION>Bayonne Evening News</ORGANIZATION> offered him a job as an office boy in exchange for his
promise to quit playing handball off the side of the newspaper office.;    His
longtime friend, <PERSON>Tim Mayer</PERSON>, said <PERSON>Mr. Katcher</PERSON>'s stories included an exclusive
interview with <PERSON>Bruno Hauptmann</PERSON>, who was executed in <DATE>1936</DATE> for the fatal
kidnapping of pioneer aviator <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>'s infant son.;    <PERSON>Mr. Katcher</PERSON>
turned to politics in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>, working as a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> organizer for <PERSON>John F.
Kennedy</PERSON>'s successful <DATE>1960</DATE> presidential campaign against <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Oceanside  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910305  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  156  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday March 5, 1991
00065120,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880706-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-06-88 1559EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Wilentz     07-06 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Wilentz,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wilentz, Father Of Chief Justice And Lindbergh Prosecutor, Dead At
93</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONG BRANCH, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>David T. Wilentz</PERSON>, who gained worldwide
attention in <DATE>1935</DATE> when he prosecuted <PERSON>Bruno Richard Hauptmann</PERSON> for
the kidnap and murder of the <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> baby, has died at age 93.
   <PERSON>Wilentz</PERSON>, the father of state <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> Chief Justice <PERSON>Robert
N. Wilentz</PERSON>, died ``peacefully in his sleep'' <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night at his
<DATE>summer</DATE> home in <LOCATION>Long Branch</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Anne Riegle</PERSON>, a family spokeswoman.
   Gov. <PERSON>Thomas H. Kean</PERSON> said <PERSON>Wilentz</PERSON>'s death ``marks the passing of
a figure and personality of near legendary proportions.''
   His death came hours after a federal appeals court in
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> rejected the most recent effort of <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON>'s widow,
<PERSON>Anna</PERSON>, to clear her husband's name.
   Born in <LOCATION>Dwinsk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Latvia</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Dec. 21, 1894</DATE>, <PERSON>Wilentz</PERSON> came to the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> at age 6 and became a naturalized citizen in <DATE>1900</DATE>.
   As a young state attorney general, he handled his first criminal
case when he prosecuted <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> in what became known as ``the
trial of the century.''
   <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> was convicted of kidnapping the 20-month-old son of
aviator <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON> from his <LOCATION>East Amwell</LOCATION> estate and then
murdering the child. He was executed <DATE>April 3, 1936</DATE>, at <ORGANIZATION>Trenton
State Prison</ORGANIZATION>.
   The trial was followed worldwide and journalist <PERSON>H.L. Mencken</PERSON>
called it ``the biggest event since the Resurrection.'' <PERSON>Wilentz</PERSON>,
who personally opposed the death penalty, was noted during the
trial for his eloquence.
   Some students of the case and <PERSON>Mrs. Hauptmann</PERSON> continue to claim
<PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> was innocent and was railroaded during the trial.
   After a decade as attorney general, <PERSON>Wilentz</PERSON>, whose main home was
in <LOCATION>Perth Amboy</LOCATION>, served as chairman of the state <ORGANIZATION>Democratic
Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   Although he considered running for governor, he later told
friends he decided that <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> at that time would not elect a
Jewish governor.
   Wilentz went on to found one of the most prominent and powerful
law firms in the state. He also was the former director of the
board of <ORGANIZATION>Amerada Hess Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   Despite his advancing age, <PERSON>Wilentz</PERSON> continued to report for work
frequently at the family's <PERSON>Woodbridge</PERSON> law firm, and he had spent
some time working at the firm <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``He was active from the time he was admitted to practice law in
<DATE>1919</DATE> right to the present,'' <PERSON>Ms. Riegle</PERSON> said.
   She said funeral arrangements were pending.
   Wilentz is survived by his wife, <PERSON>Lena</PERSON>; sons <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> and <PERSON>Warren</PERSON>;
and his daughter <PERSON>Norma Hess</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890106-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-06-89 0132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Deaths 1stLd-Writethru a0827 01-06 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0827,0584</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS Lawe; No separates moved for the AMs cycle.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Dexter Masters</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Dexter W. Masters</PERSON>, a writer and former executive
director of <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> which publishes Consumer Reports
magazine, died <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of bronchial pneumonia. He was 80.
   Masters began his writing career with <ORGANIZATION>Time</ORGANIZATION> and Fortune magazines.
He was named editor of Tide, a journal of advertising and marketing.
Masters joined the staff at <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> soon after the
organization's founding in <DATE>1936</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1958</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION>, was named executive director of <ORGANIZATION>Consumers
Union</ORGANIZATION>, a post which he held until <DATE>1963</DATE> when he resigned to pursue
his own writing projects.
   In <DATE>1955</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> published a novel, ``The Accident,'' about the
<LOCATION>Los Alamos</LOCATION> weapons laboratory. He also wrote a book about consumer
issues in <DATE>1965</DATE>, entitled ``The Intelligent Buyer and the Telltale
Seller.'' In <DATE>1971</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> published ``The Cloud Chamber,'' a novel
dealing with nuclear issues.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Hans Kloppenburg</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSON TOWNSHIP, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Dexter W. Masters</PERSON>, a writer and former executive
director of <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> which publishes Consumer Reports
magazine, died <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of bronchial pneumonia. He was 80.
   Masters began his writing career with <ORGANIZATION>Time</ORGANIZATION> and Fortune magazines.
He was named editor of Tide, a journal of advertising and marketing.
Masters joined the staff at <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> soon after the
organization's founding in <DATE>1936</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1958</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION>, was named executive director of <ORGANIZATION>Consumers
Union</ORGANIZATION>, a post which he held until <DATE>1963</DATE> when he resigned to pursue
his own writing projects.
   In <DATE>1955</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> published a novel, ``The Accident,'' about the
<LOCATION>Los Alamos</LOCATION> weapons laboratory. He also wrote a book about consumer
issues in <DATE>1965</DATE>, entitled ``The Intelligent Buyer and the Telltale
Seller.'' In <DATE>1971</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> published ``The Cloud Chamber,'' a novel
dealing with nuclear issues.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Thomas Holmes</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Dexter W. Masters</PERSON>, a writer and former executive
director of <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> which publishes Consumer Reports
magazine, died <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of bronchial pneumonia. He was 80.
   Masters began his writing career with <ORGANIZATION>Time</ORGANIZATION> and Fortune magazines.
He was named editor of Tide, a journal of advertising and marketing.
Masters joined the staff at <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> soon after the
organization's founding in <DATE>1936</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1958</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION>, was named executive director of <ORGANIZATION>Consumers
Union</ORGANIZATION>, a post which he held until <DATE>1963</DATE> when he resigned to pursue
his own writing projects.
   In <DATE>1955</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> published a novel, ``The Accident,'' about the
<LOCATION>Los Alamos</LOCATION> weapons laboratory. He also wrote a book about consumer
issues in <DATE>1965</DATE>, entitled ``The Intelligent Buyer and the Telltale
Seller.'' In <DATE>1971</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> published ``The Cloud Chamber,'' a novel
dealing with nuclear issues.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>John Lawe</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Dexter W. Masters</PERSON>, a writer and former executive
director of <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> which publishes Consumer Reports
magazine, died <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of bronchial pneumonia. He was 80.
   Masters began his writing career with <ORGANIZATION>Time</ORGANIZATION> and Fortune magazines.
He was named editor of Tide, a journal of advertising and marketing.
Masters joined the staff at <ORGANIZATION>Consumers Union</ORGANIZATION> soon after the
organization's founding in <DATE>1936</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1958</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION>, was named executive director of <ORGANIZATION>Consumers
Union</ORGANIZATION>, a post which he held until <DATE>1963</DATE> when he resigned to pursue
his own writing projects.
   In <DATE>1955</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> published a novel, ``The Accident,'' about the
<LOCATION>Los Alamos</LOCATION> weapons laboratory. He also wrote a book about consumer
issues in <DATE>1965</DATE>, entitled ``The Intelligent Buyer and the Telltale
Seller.'' In <DATE>1971</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> published ``The Cloud Chamber,'' a novel
dealing with nuclear issues.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900405-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-05-90 2129EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LindberghBio     04-05 0245</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lindbergh Bio,0251</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lucky Lindy's Widow Authorizes Biography</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Author <PERSON>A. Scott Berg</PERSON> will write a biography of
<PERSON>Charles A. Lindbergh</PERSON>, authorized by the pioneering aviator's widow,
the <ORGANIZATION>Putnam Berkley Group</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``Impressed by the thoroughness, objectivity and compassion of
his previous works, <PERSON>Anne Morrow Lindbergh</PERSON> has granted <PERSON>A. Scott Berg</PERSON>
complete access to the heretofore restricted <PERSON>Charles A. Lindbergh</PERSON>
collections at <ORGANIZATION>Yale University</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> Historical
Society,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Lindbergh</PERSON>'s attorney, <PERSON>James W. Lloyd</PERSON>.
   The 83-year-old widow of the man who first flew solo from the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> also granted <PERSON>Berg</PERSON> access to her personal
papers.
   The permission is valid until the year <DATE>2000</DATE>. Access to the
Lindbergh collections by other researchers will be restricted while
<PERSON>Berg</PERSON> completes his biography, the publisher said.
   ``<PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON> has been idolized and demonized ... and the
truth remains to be revealed,'' said <PERSON>Berg</PERSON>. ``In the end, I feel a
great life story will emerge _ one whose values are not only timely
but also timeless.''
   <PERSON>G.P. Putnam</PERSON>'s Sons will publish the <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> book in hardcover
in the <DATE>fall of 1997</DATE>. A paperback edition will be issued by Berkley
Books the following year.
   Berg graduated from <ORGANIZATION>Princeton University</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1971</DATE> and spent the
next seven years expanding his senior thesis on <PERSON>Maxwell Perkins</PERSON>
into the biography, ``<PERSON>Max Perkins</PERSON>: Editor of Genius,'' which won
the American Book Award.
   His most recent book was the bestseller ``Goldwyn: A
Biography,'' published last year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06216099 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06216099 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  AIR; AVIATION; HISTORY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Before becoming famous for his non-stop, trans-Atlantic flight, Charles
Lindbergh flew solo for the first time at an airfield here. Now officials plan
to erect a monument in his honor.;    "From here he flew . . . into aviation
history," said Henry King Stanford, who has raised $75,000 for the monument.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LINDBERGH'S SOLO COMMEMORATED  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Lindbergh bought a World War I biplane, and, after only a few hours of
lessons, took off on his own. Four years later he flew the "Spirit of <LOCATION>St.
Louis</LOCATION>" to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Americus, Ga.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910803  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  85  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday August 3, 1991
00216099,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890630-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-30-89 1830EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-VeteranEngineer     06-30 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Veteran Engineer,0568</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oldest Navy Employee Retires at 89</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By IKE FLORES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s oldest civilian engineer retired
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, after a career that spanned two world wars and included a
stint helping <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON> design the pontooned planes he flew
to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Rudy Ries</PERSON>, 89, was honored during ceremonies at the <ORGANIZATION>Naval
Training Systems Center</ORGANIZATION> for his achievement of being the oldest
full-time civilian employee in the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``You've been an inspiration to us all,'' said Capt. <PERSON>C.D. Rowley</PERSON>,
commanding officer of the <ORGANIZATION>Naval Training Systems Center</ORGANIZATION>, as he
presented <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> with a number of certificates, letters of
commendation and a plaque. ``We are all proud you were one of us.''
   In a letter read to <PERSON>Ries</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>H. Lawrence Garrett III</PERSON>
thanked him for his 26 years of dedicated service.
   When the German-born <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> joined the <ORGANIZATION>German Air Force</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1916</DATE>,
World War I had ended before he could become a fighter pilot. In
<DATE>1928</DATE>, he saw the onset of Naziism in his country and came to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>
as a mechanical engineer.
   Ries began his latest career in <DATE>1963</DATE> and might have continued in
his job, he said in an interview, if his wife, <PERSON>Julia</PERSON>, hadn't died
last year and if the nature of his engineering work hadn't changed.
   He's a hands-on engineer and much of today's engineering is just
paperwork, <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> said. In effect, he said, they've taken away his
drafting board.
   ``I enjoy engineering. I think engineering is designing things,
creating things,'' he said. ``But one thing we've turned to now is
just writing specifications ... for somebody else to build
something. I don't like this.''
   He described the reams of specifications turned out by today's
engineers as ``letters to <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION>.''
   In earlier years, <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> worked with <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> and Adm. <PERSON>Richard
Byrd</PERSON> in designing pontoons for the planes they flew to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>South Pole</LOCATION>.
   He worked first for <ORGANIZATION>Fairchild Aviation</ORGANIZATION> and then <ORGANIZATION>Merganthaler
Linotype Co.</ORGANIZATION> before joining EDO Aircraft on <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION> in <DATE>1930</DATE>. He
became an American citizen in that year.
   It was at EDO that he worked with <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> and <PERSON>Byrd</PERSON>.
   ``<PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> and his wife were flying to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and he wanted
special floats outfitted to the bottom of the plane, with a motor in
between, in case he landed in the water,'' <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> said.
   The <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON>'s returned to <ORGANIZATION>EDO</ORGANIZATION> aircraft after their flight to
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and had lunch with <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> and other company officials. ``I
loaned him my pocketknife to cut his onions with, and I've still got
that knife,'' <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> said.
   He helped design one of the world's first high-altitude metal
planes, was a consultant in the <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION> to Soviet builders of the
American-designed PBY flying boat and worked for the <ORGANIZATION>Fokker Aircraft
Co.</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> before the Germans invaded <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>,
precipitating World War II.
   In recent years, he has designed training simulators to explode
<DATE>Tomahwak</DATE> and Harm missiles when they fail to detonate in combat and
maneuvers. He is also responsible for the design of a training aid
for the military's newest torpedo, the Mark 50.
   He said he intends to keep active when he returns to his native
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> to live with his son and family in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>. His son, <PERSON>Eric Ries</PERSON>,
is a civil engineer with the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> there.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890701-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-89 1311EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-VeteranEngineer     07-01 0532</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Veteran Engineer,0546</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aircraft Engineer Retires as Navy Employee at 89</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By IKE FLORES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s oldest civilian employee, an
89-year-old engineer, has retired and is going back to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>,
where he launched a career in aviation that spanned six decades.
   <PERSON>Rudy Ries</PERSON> came to this country in <DATE>1928</DATE> and worked for 35 years
for companies that pioneered in aviation: Fairchild, <ORGANIZATION>Convair</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Martin</PERSON>, EDO Aircraft and for <ORGANIZATION>Fokker</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>. He helped
design pontoons for the planes flown by <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON> to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>
and by Adm. <PERSON>Richard Byrd</PERSON> to the <LOCATION>South Pole</LOCATION>.
   ``I've enjoyed my work, all of it,'' he said sadly at a
retirement ceremony at the <ORGANIZATION>Naval Training Systems Center</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
``I will miss it.''
   He said he would fly to <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, this weekend to live
with his son, a civil engineer posted with the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. State Department</ORGANIZATION>
there.
   The diminutive, soft-spoken <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> worked ``only'' 26 years for the
<ORGANIZATION>Navy Department</ORGANIZATION>, starting in <DATE>1963</DATE>.
   Born in <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>, he joined the German air force during World
War I, but he hadn't completed pilot training when it ended. In
<DATE>1928</DATE>, he saw the onset of Nazism in his country and came to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
   He became a citizen in <DATE>1930</DATE>, the year he joined EDO on <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s
<LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>.
   ``<PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> and his wife were flying to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and he wanted
special floats outfitted to the bottom of the plane, with a motor in
between, in case he landed in the water,'' <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> said.
   The Lindberghs returned to <ORGANIZATION>EDO</ORGANIZATION> after their flight to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and
had lunch with <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> and other company officials.
   ``I loaned him my pocket knife to cut his onions with, and I've
still got that knife,'' <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> said.
   Another highlight of his two stints at <ORGANIZATION>EDO</ORGANIZATION> was the design of an
all-metal airplane designed to operate at 30,000 feet, a two-seater
named the Model-R in his honor. The Depression caused the company to
cut back work on it and the Model-R was never flown.
   In <DATE>1936</DATE>, <PERSON>Ries</PERSON> went to work for <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Aircraft</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, which later became Convair.
   From there, he and 20 other engineers and assistants were sent to
the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> to help in setting up an assembly plant. After
spending more than a year in the <LOCATION>Ukraine</LOCATION>, he got a job at <ORGANIZATION>Fokker
Aircraft Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Amsterdam</LOCATION>. But <PERSON>Ries</PERSON>' European stay was cut short
with the approach of World War II, and he returned to this country.
   A hands-on mechanical engineer, he admitted frustration with his
profession's increasing reliance on paperwork, which he called
``letters to <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION>.''
   ``I enjoy engineering. I think engineering is designing things,
creating things,'' he said. ``But one thing we've turned to now is
just writing specifications ... for somebody else to build
something. I don't like this.''
   In recent years, he has designed training simulators for the
controllers who explode Tomahawk and Harm missiles when they fail to
detonate or go off course. He also is responsible for the design of
a training aid for the military's newest torpedo, the Mark 50, which
can be dropped from an airplane or fired from land or ships at sea.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880711-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-11-88 2122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BoyAviator     07-11 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boy Aviator,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Young Pilot Resumes Flight To Paris After Stop For Plane Repairs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONTREAL (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 11-year-old pilot left <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE> on the
next part of his <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> journey after his plane was
grounded for a day by mechanical trouble.
   <PERSON>Christopher Lee Marshall</PERSON> left <LOCATION>Dorval</LOCATION> airport at <TIME>2:42 p.m. EDT</TIME>
headed for <LOCATION>Wabush</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Labrador</LOCATION>, in a single-engine <PERSON>Mooney</PERSON> 252
two-seater, said <PERSON>Doug McGurk</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Transport Canada</ORGANIZATION> spokesman.
   The boy from <LOCATION>Oceano</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, has said the trip will make him the
world's youngest transatlantic pilot and he wants to make the trip
to emulate <PERSON>Charles Lindberg</PERSON>'s <DATE>1927</DATE> flight to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. One of his
other goals is to become the youngest pilot to fly around the world.
   The fifth-grade student and son of a commercial pilot is
accompanied by <PERSON>Randy Cunningham</PERSON>, 40, a retired pilot who served in
the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> war. Cunningham limits the boy's flying time to less
than eight hours at a stretch.
   They are scheduled to fly to <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> before
arriving in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. The trip began in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> <DATE>last Thursday</DATE>.
   They had been scheduled to leave <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> but were unable
to take off because a voltage regulator aboard the plane had to be
repaired.
   <PERSON>McGurk</PERSON> said the flight from <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Wabush</LOCATION>, at 21,000 feet,
would take nearly four hours.
   Lindbergh flew from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, then to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
before completing his 33{-hour non-stop solo flight across the
<LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Christopher first took the controls of a plane at age four and
began flying with an instructor three years later.
   Last year he became the youngest pilot to cross the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Tony Aliengena</PERSON>, a 9-year-old from <LOCATION>San Juan Capistrano</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, broke the record in <DATE>April</DATE> by making a
California-to-Massachusetts round trip.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880716-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-16-88 1154EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CorriganAnniversary Bjt   07-16 0741</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Corrigan Anniversary, Bjt,0760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Douglas `Wrong-Way' Corrigan Heads For The Irish Coast Again</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SAN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD DE ATLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Imagine a brash astronaut thumbing his nose
at the space agency and taking an old <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft all the
way to the moon, then claiming it was a mistake, and you get a
glimmer of <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON> ``Wrong Way'' <PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON>'s feat 50 years ago.
   ``My compass froze. I guess I flew the wrong way,'' <PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON>
claimed on <DATE>July 18, 1938</DATE>, after making a forbidden New
York-to-Dublin flight in a used Curtiss-Robin monoplane on which
he'd spent <MONEY>$900</MONEY>. Plus <MONEY>$90</MONEY> for gas and oil.
   He has steadfastly maintained he thought he was returning to his
home base of <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, after federal aviation authorities
denied him permission to fly to <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>.
   But <PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON>, now 81 and living in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, hinted in
a telephone interview last week that his wrong-way explanation may
change after he flies again to <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, this time as an
honored guest for three days of ceremonies commemorating his flight.
   ``Maybe this time over in <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>, I'll tell them another story.
We'll see,'' he said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Corrigan's ``wrong-way'' explanation sounded like pure blarney
at the time _he was made a lifetime member of the <ORGANIZATION>Liars Club</ORGANIZATION> _ but
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> loved it.
   He was the overnight guest of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ambassadors in <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. After he returned to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> by ship, with his plane in a
crate, he was given a ticker-tape parade. There was even a meeting
with President <PERSON>Franklin Roosevelt</PERSON>.
   A movie was turned out by RKO Studios,``The Flying Irishman,''
starring <PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON> as himself, and there were magazine articles and
an autobiography, ``That's My Story.'' He estimated he grossed
<MONEY>$85,000</MONEY> from tours and speeches.
   As punishment for his journey, the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Air Commerce</ORGANIZATION>,
forerunner of the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Aviation Administration</ORGANIZATION>, suspended
<PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON> from flying for five days. Those five days were served
while he was still aboard ship on the way home.
   Whatever the true story, <PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON> had joined the ranks of his
hero, <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>, and <ORGANIZATION>Wiley Post</ORGANIZATION> by making a solo, nonstop,
single-engine crossing of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   He also dispelled the notion that air feats were only for
millionaires and well-financed aviators.
   When <PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON> was 20, he was a woodworker at <ORGANIZATION>Ryan Aircraft</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> and helped build <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON>'s Spirit of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> for the
<DATE>1927</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>New York-to-Paris</ORGANIZATION> solo trans-Atlantic flight.
   Corrigan got his pilot's license the next year. He bought a
leather flight jacket just like <PERSON>Lindy</PERSON>'s, scraped his money together
and studied navigation.
   He bought his monoplane for <MONEY>$310</MONEY> in <DATE>1931</DATE>, and spent an
additional <MONEY>$590</MONEY> modifying it into a long-distance machine. Before
the flight to <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, he flew from <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> nonstop
in 27 hours on <DATE>July 7-8</DATE>.
   Then the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Air Commerce</ORGANIZATION> refused to grant permission for
a trans-Atlantic flight, on grounds his plane, loaded with 330
gallons of gasoline and five gallons of oil, was <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT> too
heavy for a safe flight.
   Corrigan took off from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Floyd Bennett</PERSON> Field on <DATE>July
17</DATE>, saying he was headed for <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>. He landed at <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> 28
hours and <TIME>13 minutes later</TIME>, 3,150 miles from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   ``There had been a haze near the ground and when I was 500 feet
high, there was fog below the plane,'' <PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON> once said of his
flight. ``When I started to turn west I noticed the top compass was
not working right, due to the liquid having leaked out. ... There
was another compass down on the floor that I had set to fly a
westerly course, so now I turned the plane until the parallel lines
matched, and flew over the fog.''
   The wrong way.
   He had no radio and his <MONEY>$1</MONEY> wristwatch stopped. ``The only modern
instrument I had was a turn-and-bank indicator,'' said <PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON>,
who subsisted on fig and chocolate bars and some water during his
flight.
   ``I knew I wasn't in <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> when I dropped out of the
overcast over <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>,'' he said. ``The place was greener and some
of the houses had hay roofs.''
   Corrigan will be the guest of <ORGANIZATION>Aer Lingus</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> when the
Irish airline takes him to <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> aboard a <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 747.
   ``We offered him a first-class seat, but he said he would prefer
to fly economy,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Aer Lingus</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Bill Maxwell</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0224 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1548EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-EthanolPlane 1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ethanol Plane, 1st Ld-Writethru,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Atlantic Crossing Made By Ethanol Plane</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS spelling of pilot to Shauck, sted Schauck, in grafs
8, 9, 12, 16 and 18.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It wasn't quite <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON>, but a <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> university
professor earned his footnote in aviation history <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> when he
completed the first trans-Atlantic flight in an ethanol-fueled
airplane.
   <PERSON>Max Shauck</PERSON>, a mathematics instructor at <ORGANIZATION>Baylor University</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Waco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, landed at the small Toussus-le-Noble airport southwest
of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> after a one-hour flight from Tours.
   He set out with Italian co-pilot <PERSON>Grazia Zanin</PERSON> from <LOCATION>Waco</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sept.
15</DATE> in a light experimental aircraft that carried them through often
rough weather to <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Azores</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and finally
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   ``We feel we have proved that ethanol is a very reliable fuel,''
<PERSON>Shauck</PERSON> said. ``You can't get across the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> on an unreliable
fuel.''
   Proving the merits of the relatively cheap, non-polluting
ethanol compared to standard fuel drove <PERSON>Shauck</PERSON> make the journey,
which he funded himself at more cost ``than I care to think about.''
   Ethanol is essentially an alcohol fuel made from vegetable
matter, usually corn in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and sugar beets in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Shauck</PERSON>, who also does air pollution research at <LOCATION>Baylor</LOCATION>,
says ethanol retails for about <MONEY>$1.20</MONEY> per gallon in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> compared to <MONEY>$1.80</MONEY> for high-octane aviation fuel.
   ``It produces more power, it burns cooler and there's a lot less
pollution,'' he said. ``But we had to go out of our way sometimes
to find it.''
   Indeed, <PERSON>Shauck</PERSON> and <PERSON>Zanin</PERSON>'s flight log includes a hodgepodge of
small stopovers in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> chosen chiefly because ethanol
could be delivered there.
   These included <LOCATION>Paducah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Hazelton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>; and
<LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y</LOCATION>. The plane also stopped at <PERSON>Shauck</PERSON>'s hometown of
<LOCATION>Mansfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, they stopped at <LOCATION>Moncton</LOCATION> and St. Pierre-et-Miquelon
before lifting off from <ORGANIZATION>St. John's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Newfoundland</LOCATION> on <DATE>Oct. 20</DATE> for
Flores in the <LOCATION>Azore Islands</LOCATION>, a 2,000-mile crossing made terrifying
by rain and thunderstorms.
   ``It's a long way over a lot of water when you're flying a
little plane looking for little islands,'' he said. ``We didn't
have sophisticated navigation equipment.''
   They waited in the <LOCATION>Azores</LOCATION> for nearly three weeks for a shipment
of ethanol to arrive before flying to <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> <DATE>Nov. 10</DATE>. <PERSON>Shauck</PERSON>, 54,
and <PERSON>Ms. Zanin</PERSON>, 33, made stops in <LOCATION>Bilbao</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION>,
Rochet-Sur-Yon and Tours in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   Technically, they became the first people to cross the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>
in an ethanol-fueled plane the minute they touched down in
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, but the original plan they filed with American
authorities was from <LOCATION>Suffolk County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, airport to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   The fiberglass aircraft, a sort of flying wing built by the
<ORGANIZATION>Velocity Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Sebastian</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, featured elevators, normally
found on the tail, at the front of the airplane and a propellor
mounted on the back.
   The whole contraption weighs about 2,100 pounds and can reach a
top speed of 200 mph.
   Shauck resists comparison with American aviator <PERSON>Charles
Lindbergh</PERSON>, first man to cross the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> in a flight from <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> to Le Bourget airport in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <DATE>May 31, 1927</DATE>.
   ``He is a hero,'' <PERSON>Shauck</PERSON> said. ``Everything now is different
than it was in his day. I avoided going to Le Bourget because I
didn't want to be compared to him.''
   <PERSON>Shauck</PERSON> said he would take a commercial flight back to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, but
that the aircraft will make one more trip _ to <PERSON>Ms. Zanin</PERSON>'s
hometown, <LOCATION>Trieste</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900620-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-20-90 2130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Mandela-Parades 1stLd-Writethru a0620 06-20 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela-Parades, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0620,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela's Path Beaten by Fliers and Athletes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 10th graf to ADD parade by Apollo 11
astronauts; picks up 11th graf, `Astronaut Gordon ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Mandela, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ticker tape parade <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for <ORGANIZATION>Nelson
Mandela</ORGANIZATION> is the fifth in the last 10 years through <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s
``Canyon of Heroes'' on lower Broadway.
   There have been about twoscore such parades since <PERSON>Charles
Lindbergh</PERSON> was lionized here in <DATE>1927</DATE>. Aviators, athletes and
warriors predominate.
   Among the notable parades:
   <DATE>1986</DATE> _ <LOCATION>New York Mets</LOCATION>, after beating the <ORGANIZATION>Boston Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> in the
World Series.
   <DATE>1985</DATE> _ 25,000 <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans, led by Gen. <PERSON>William Westmoreland</PERSON>
and 26 Medal of Honor winners, in a 10-years-later welcome-home
tribute.
   <DATE>1984</DATE> _ 221 athletes of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Olympic team are cheered, but
101 spectators are injured when a construction scaffold on the
parade route gives way.
   <DATE>1981</DATE> _ Welcome home for the Americans hostages freed from <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>1979</DATE> _ Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON>.
   1978 _ <ORGANIZATION>New York Yankees</ORGANIZATION> world champion team.
   1969 _ ``Miracle'' Mets world champion team.
   <DATE>1969</DATE> _ Astronauts <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> and <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON>, the first men
to land on the moon, and fellow Apollo 11 astronaut <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>.
   <DATE>1963</DATE> _ Astronaut <PERSON>Gordon Cooper</PERSON>.
   1962 _ Astronaut <PERSON>John Glenn</PERSON>, the first American in orbit.
   1958 _ <PERSON>Van Cliburn</PERSON>, the only classical musician ever to get the
ticker-tape treatment, after winning piano competition in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
   1951 _ Gen. <PERSON>Douglas MacArthur</PERSON>, after his recall from <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> by
President <PERSON>Truman</PERSON>.
   1938 _ <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON> ``Wrong-Way'' <PERSON>Corrigan</PERSON>, for his air flight to
<LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> while claiming his destination was <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   1938 _ <PERSON>Howard Hughes</PERSON> and his plane crew, for breaking <ORGANIZATION>Wiley
Post</ORGANIZATION>'s round-the-world flight record.
   1936 _ <PERSON>Beryl Markham</PERSON>, for the first westward trans-Atlantic solo
flight, described later in her memoir ``West With the Night.''
   1928 _ <PERSON>Amelia Earhart</PERSON>, first woman to fly the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, as
navigator, before making her own solo flight some years later.
   1927 _ <LOCATION>Lindbergh</LOCATION>, after returning from solo flight to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Several of the parades were larger in scope than the traditional
route from <ORGANIZATION>Bowling Green to City Hall</ORGANIZATION>, a canyon about 16 blocks
long formed by the office towers along Broadway in the financial
district.
   Glenn's parade, which wended through midtown as well as lower
<LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, produced the greatest fallout of paper in any ticker
tape parade, 3,474 tons, according to <ORGANIZATION>Sanitation Department</ORGANIZATION> records.
   The most paper generated by a canyon-only parade was 1,262 for
the <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> hostage parade.
   Official estimates of spectator numbers have been extravagant.
The Mets<DATE>' 1986</DATE> parade was reported as drawing 2.2 million people.
That works out to 137,000 people per block, or enough to fill Shea
Stadium 2{ times.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900628-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-28-90 1500EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AircraftAuction     06-28 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Aircraft Auction,0360</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: retransmits a0616 to CORRECT cycle</NOTE>
<HEAD>Auction of Corporate Aircraft An Industry First</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By J.L. SCHMIDT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LINCOLN, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bit of aviation history was made in this
city where <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON> learned to fly.
   Twenty corporate aircraft, half of them the popular Learjets,
were put on the auction block <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in a first-of-its-kind
event for the aircraft industry.
   ``This has never been done before in aviation, save for an
occasional bankruptcy sale and sales of smaller or antique
planes,'' said <PERSON>J. Robert Duncan</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Duncan Aviation</ORGANIZATION>.
   The sale was also a first for <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, the international
auction house that specializes in fine art and antiques. <PERSON>John L.
Marion</PERSON>, the head of <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s North American operations, wielded
the gavel.
   Within an hour, <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> crews wheeled the aircraft, one-by-one,
through a clean aircraft hangar. There, <PERSON>Marion</PERSON> bellowed the
auctioneer's mantra: ``I have <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> to start, I have 2
million.''
   When it was over, five airplanes had been sold for a total of
<MONEY>$7,927,750</MONEY>. Two others, including the most expensive one offered,
were snapped up before the sale, bringing the total to more than
<MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>, <PERSON>Marion</PERSON> said.
   Duncan, who heads the 30-year-old business aviation sales and
service with 550 employees in 14 cities, said he was pleased with
the sale, but had greater expectations.
   ``We'll analyze the results and evaluate whether or not we want
to make this an annual event. I think we might have another sale,''
he said.
   Prices paid ranged from <MONEY>$309,750</MONEY> for a <DATE>1980</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Piper Cheyenne</ORGANIZATION> I to
``about <MONEY>$14 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY>'' for a <DATE>1988</DATE> Canadair Challenger
_ one of the two sold before the auction, <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Gary Conklin</PERSON>, a representative of <ORGANIZATION>Great Planes Sales Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of
<LOCATION>Tulsa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>, picked up a <LOCATION>Westwind</LOCATION> 1124 for <MONEY>$2.1 million</MONEY>. He said
his company buys planes, renovates them and then looks for a buyer.
   The names of other buyers were not made public.
   Lindbergh studied flying at the old <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln School of Aviation</ORGANIZATION>
in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>. He made his solo flight of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> in <DATE>May 1927</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880815-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-15-88 2359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DoubleEagleAnniversary     08-15 1018</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Double Eagle Anniversary,1055</SECOND>
<HEAD>Balloonist Recounts Historic Flight On 10th Anniversary</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ARNOLD STAPLETON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a cramped gondola dangling beneath
an 11-story helium balloon, with clouds obstructing any view below,
the disembodied voice of the radar operator seemed scarcely to be
believed.
   ``You have crossed the coast of <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>,'' the voice told three
American balloonists on that still-dark early morning 10 years ago.
<PERSON>Larry Newman</PERSON> asked if the message was indeed that which had eluded
others for 105 years.
   Silence.
   Then, crisply, ``Sir, my radar is never wrong.''
   Newman, along with <PERSON>Ben Abruzzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON>, whooped with
joy. Sunburned and weary after five days aloft, the
businessmen-adventurers had made the first trans-Atlantic crossing
in a balloon.
   The three landed their black-and-silver Double Eagle II later
that day, <DATE>Aug. 17, 1978</DATE>, in a wheat field west of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Today, <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> is the only one of the three still alive.
   <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> was killed in <DATE>1983</DATE> at age 48 when his balloon crashed
in a West German forest during a race. Abruzzo, then 53, died in
<DATE>1985</DATE> when his twin-engine airplane crashed shortly after takeoff in
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>, now 40 and a commercial airline pilot in <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>,
said he has no specific plans to celebrate <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s anniversary.
   But he said his thoughts often drifted back to that <DATE>summer 10
years ago</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> recalled that after the initial jubilation, <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> went
to sleep while he and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> looked down through the clearing
clouds on the lights of <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>.
   The silent 112-foot balloon 15,000 feet up caught sounds that
drifted skyward. <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> could hear dogs barking and
trains rumbling along tracks nearly 3 miles below.
   ``Tears came to my eyes,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``I put my arm around
<PERSON>Ben</PERSON> _ he'd always been somewhat like a father to me. I hadn't felt
that close to another human being for as long as I can remember.''
   The men began the flight six days earlier when the <ORGANIZATION>Double Eagle
II</ORGANIZATION> lifted up from <LOCATION>Presque Isle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, and headed toward <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
more than 3,000 miles away.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> says the flight was not without problems, including a
clash of personalities.
   ``<PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON> later stated that he wished he could have flown
the flight by himself,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``I don't know what <PERSON>Ben</PERSON>'s
feelings were, but I wanted someone to share this with. I didn't
want to be <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>.''
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said conflicts arose when <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> both began
making key decisions.
   ``Any aircraft can only have one captain, and we had two: <PERSON>Ben
Abruzzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON>,'' he said.
   But <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said conflicts were overshadowed by the hardships of
the flight in the 12-by-6-foot living space crowded with TV cameras
and navigational equipment. Newman's hang glider dangled beneath
the gondola and 5,500 pounds of sand and lead for ballast hung over
the sides in bags.
   ``There were many times the flight was in question,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>
recalled. ``But how close it came to failure at each moment was
interpreted different by each of us.''
   They lost altitude rapidly at one point when ice chunks crusted
the top of the balloon. They jettisoned valuable ballast. When they
dropped to 4,000 feet the ice melted.
   Later in the flight they dumped more ballast, including an
expensive navigation system that had failed on the second day. They
tossed oxygen bottles, anything they could.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said that at one point, a bit delirious from the
altitude, he chucked a <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> radio _ and only later noticed a jar
of peanut butter that weighed as much.
   Plans were for <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> to fly the glider down once they made it
to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   But 400 miles from <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, it came down to a choice of dropping
the glider, their last oxygen and food, or a propane tank for a
heater to battle <ORGANIZATION>Abruzzo</ORGANIZATION>'s frostbite. The glider went.
   Radios also failed during the flight, and the men had to
communicate by ham radio.
   ``The first guy I talked to wouldn't talk because I didn't have
a license,'' said <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>. ``And he didn't believe I was in a
balloon over the middle of the ocean.''
   Finally, <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> reached an old man confined to a wheelchair in a
home for the elderly somewhere in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   ``His call sign was `G4JY.' I don't think I'll ever forget
that,'' he said. ``He talked to me until the <DATE>last day</DATE> of the
flight. He was like the Good Shepherd.''
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said the rough times were offset by the excitement.
   A high point, he said, came over <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> when a jumbo jet
relayed a message from the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution</ORGANIZATION>. The museum had
asked to display the gondola and balloon in the <ORGANIZATION>National Air</ORGANIZATION> and
Space Museum that houses the Apollo 11 moonship, <ORGANIZATION>Lindbergh's Spirit
of St. Louis</ORGANIZATION> and the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers' plane.
   In the final few hours the men believed they would make it to
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> had landed 51 years before after the first
solo trans-Atlantic airplane flight. But over <LOCATION>Evreux</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, they
realized they could not go on.
   The last of the ballast was gone, save for a bottle of
champagne. They were 60 miles west of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, 3,107 miles and 137
hours from <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> where the helium-packed balloon had taken off.
   The swiftly draining balloon envelope carcass and its gondola
settled gently to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as cheering spectators abandoned their cars
along a nearby highway and rushed to the balloon.
   Hundreds tried to take a piece of history.
   ``It's hard to chew rubberized cloth,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``People
were trying to tear little shreds off, but I think they were
probably losing their teeth more than damaging the balloon.''
   The French press dubbed them the ``new Lindberghs.''
   But <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> says the only time he thought about <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> was
when the adventurers drew straws that evening to see which would
sleep in <LOCATION>Lindbergh</LOCATION>'s bed at the American ambassador's residence in
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> and his wife won.
   ``And I ended up on the floor after 30 minutes because I
couldn't sleep,'' he said. ``The bed was like a banana. The springs
were shot.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880812-0245 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-88 0707EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-DoubleEagleAnniversary Adv16   08-12 1032</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Double Eagle Anniversary, Adv 16,1068</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv16</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Tue AMs, Aug. 16, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Balloonist Recounts Historic Flight on 10th Anniversary</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ARNOLD STAPLETON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a cramped gondola dangling beneath
an 11-story helium balloon, with clouds obstructing any view below,
the disembodied voice of the radar operator seemed scarcely to be
believed.
   ``You have crossed the coast of <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>,'' the voice told three
American balloonists on that still-dark early morning 10 years ago.
<PERSON>Larry Newman</PERSON> asked if the message was indeed that which had eluded
others for 105 years.
   Silence.
   Then, crisply, ``Sir, my radar is never wrong.''
   Newman, along with <PERSON>Ben Abruzzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON>, whooped with
joy. Sunburned and weary after five days aloft, the
businessmen-adventurers had made the first trans-Atlantic crossing
in a balloon.
   The three landed their black-and-silver Double Eagle II later
that day, <DATE>Aug. 17, 1978</DATE>, in a wheat field west of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Today, <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> is the only one of the three still alive.
   <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> was killed in <DATE>1983</DATE> at age 48 when his balloon crashed
in a West German forest during a race. Abruzzo, then 53, died in
<DATE>1985</DATE> when his twin-engine airplane crashed shortly after takeoff in
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>, now 40 and a commercial airline pilot in <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>,
said he has no specific plans to celebrate <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s anniversary.
   But he said his thoughts often drifted back to that <DATE>summer 10
years ago</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> recalled that after the initial jubilation, <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> went
to sleep while he and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> looked down through the clearing
clouds on the lights of <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>.
   The silent 112-foot balloon 15,000 feet up caught sounds that
drifted skyward. <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> could hear dogs barking and
trains rumbling along tracks nearly 3 miles below.
   ``Tears came to my eyes,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``I put my arm around
<PERSON>Ben</PERSON> _ he'd always been somewhat like a father to me. I hadn't felt
that close to another human being for as long as I can remember.''
   The men began the flight six days earlier when the <ORGANIZATION>Double Eagle
II</ORGANIZATION> lifted up from <LOCATION>Presque Isle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, and headed toward <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
more than 3,000 miles away.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> says the flight was not without problems, including a
clash of personalities.
   ``<PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON> later stated that he wished he could have flown
the flight by himself,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``I don't know what <PERSON>Ben</PERSON>'s
feelings were, but I wanted someone to share this with. I didn't
want to be <PERSON>Charles Lindbergh</PERSON>.''
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said conflicts arose when <PERSON>Anderson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Abruzzo</PERSON> both began
making key decisions.
   ``Any aircraft can only have one captain, and we had two: <PERSON>Ben
Abruzzo</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maxie Anderson</PERSON>,'' he said.
   But <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said conflicts were overshadowed by the hardships of
the flight in the 12-by-6-foot living space crowded with TV cameras
and navigational equipment. Newman's hang glider dangled beneath
the gondola and 5,500 pounds of sand and lead for ballast hung over
the sides in bags.
   ``There were many times the flight was in question,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>
recalled. ``But how close it came to failure at each moment was
interpreted different by each of us.''
   They lost altitude rapidly at one point when ice chunks crusted
the top of the balloon. They jettisoned valuable ballast. When they
dropped to 4,000 feet the ice melted.
   Later in the flight they dumped more ballast, including an
expensive navigation system that had failed on the second day. They
tossed oxygen bottles, anything they could.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said that at one point, a bit delirious from the
altitude, he chucked a <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> radio _ and only later noticed a jar
of peanut butter that weighed as much.
   Plans were for <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> to fly the glider down once they made it
to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   But 400 miles from <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, it came down to a choice of dropping
the glider, their last oxygen and food, or a propane tank for a
heater to battle <ORGANIZATION>Abruzzo</ORGANIZATION>'s frostbite. The glider went.
   Radios also failed during the flight, and the men had to
communicate by ham radio.
   ``The first guy I talked to wouldn't talk because I didn't have
a license,'' said <PERSON>Newman</PERSON>. ``And he didn't believe I was in a
balloon over the middle of the ocean.''
   Finally, <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> reached an old man confined to a wheelchair in a
home for the elderly somewhere in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   ``His call sign was `G4JY.' I don't think I'll ever forget
that,'' he said. ``He talked to me until the <DATE>last day</DATE> of the
flight. He was like the Good Shepherd.''
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said the rough times were offset by the excitement.
   A high point, he said, came over <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> when a jumbo jet
relayed a message from the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian Institution</ORGANIZATION>. The museum had
asked to display the gondola and balloon in the <ORGANIZATION>National Air</ORGANIZATION> and
Space Museum that houses the Apollo 11 moonship, <ORGANIZATION>Lindbergh's Spirit
of St. Louis</ORGANIZATION> and the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers' plane.
   In the final few hours the men believed they would make it to
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> had landed 51 years before after the first
solo trans-Atlantic airplane flight. But over <LOCATION>Evreux</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, they
realized they could not go on.
   The last of the ballast was gone, save for a bottle of
champagne. They were 60 miles west of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, 3,107 miles and 137
hours from <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> where the helium-packed balloon had taken off.
   The swiftly draining balloon envelope carcass and its gondola
settled gently to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as cheering spectators abandoned their cars
along a nearby highway and rushed to the balloon.
   Hundreds tried to take a piece of history.
   ``It's hard to chew rubberized cloth,'' <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> said. ``People
were trying to tear little shreds off, but I think they were
probably losing their teeth more than damaging the balloon.''
   The French press dubbed them the ``new Lindberghs.''
   But <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> says the only time he thought about <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> was
when the adventurers drew straws that evening to see which would
sleep in <LOCATION>Lindbergh</LOCATION>'s bed at the American ambassador's residence in
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Newman</PERSON> and his wife won.
   ``And I ended up on the floor after 30 minutes because I
couldn't sleep,'' he said. ``The bed was like a banana. The springs
were shot.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tue AMs, Aug. 16</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920320-0008
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920320-0008.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Chicago Star to Shine in East
   ----
   By Joel Henning
</HL>
<DATE>
03/20/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A10
</SO>
<LP>
   Chicago -- Within the next month, Denis O'Hare, a slightly
built, well-spoken young man of 30 years, should know whether
he has a future as a word processing temp.
   Word processing is Mr. O'Hare's day job at KPMG Peat
Marwick &amp; Associates here. Until recently, his night job was
playing the title role in the Victory Gardens Theater
production of "Hauptmann" by John Logan. The show played to
rapt audiences and was held over for several months. Mr.
O'Hare's uncertain employment future stems from the transfer
of that production to the Cherry Lane Theatre in New York,
where it is scheduled to begin previews on April 9 prior to
an April 16 opening. Mr. O'Hare, who will go into rehearsals
for the show before the end of the month, is hoping to do
well enough in the Big Apple to give up his days at the
computer keyboard forever.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   I have not seen <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON> process words, but his
portrayal of <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> was electrifying. Nor was I
the only critic to gush. <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> provoked
singular praise among local critics. His work was described
as "the performance of the year" by the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Tribune</ORGANIZATION>. The
<ORGANIZATION>Sun-Times</ORGANIZATION> wrote that <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON> had accomplished "A tour de
force that could hold its own on any stage in the world."
   "Hauptmann" recounts the sensational prosecution of the
German immigrant <PERSON>Bruno Richard Hauptmann</PERSON> for the kidnapping
of the legendary <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> baby, infant son of the aviation
pioneer <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> ("Lucky Lindy") <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> and the writer <PERSON>Anne
Morrow Lindbergh</PERSON>. <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON> portrays the unsavory but not
necessarily guilty <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> with sardonic petulance. As the
play opens, we hear the judge pronounce his guilt and
sentence him to death. What follows is a two-hour impression
of the events surrounding his capture, incarceration and
trial from <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON>'s point of view, a view profoundly
affected by his imminent execution.
   <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> is no innocent martyred on the
altar of American hero worship. He lies to his captors about
circumstantial evidence linking him to the Lindbergh ransom,
he lies to his wife, and we are never sure when he is lying
to us, the audience. In a transcendent scene, <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON>
chillingly recounts a version of the baby's kidnapping and
death. The story he tells recapitulates how the kidnapper may
have gained entry to the second-story Lindbergh nursery in
<ORGANIZATION>Hopewell</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, snatched the infant, and then accidentally
killed him during the getaway down the ladder.
   <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON>'s subtly etched portrayal serves as the frame
within which we view the <PERSON>Lindbergh</PERSON> kidnapping, a classic
American carnival of media excess and unfair, overwrought
legal process. Everybody from President <PERSON>Hoover</PERSON> to <PERSON>Al Capone</PERSON>
pledged to help bring the baby's kidnapper to hard justice.
Everybody was outraged when <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON> was apprehended but
failed to confess. We leave the theater without answers
concerning <PERSON>Hauptmann</PERSON>'s guilt or innocence but moved by an
affecting portrayal of a man caught in the vortex of inflamed
national passions.
   Hauptmann is not <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON>'s first major role or villain.
He portrayed <PERSON>Nathan Leopold Jr.</PERSON>, an admitted child kidnapper
and killer, in another play by <PERSON>Mr. Logan</PERSON>, "Never the Sinner."
He won an Emmy for his performance as a character based on
<PERSON>Richard Speck</PERSON>, the mass murderer of eight nurses, in the TV
special "Moment of Rage."
   <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON> studied acting at <ORGANIZATION>Northwestern University's
School of Speech</ORGANIZATION>. "My acting classes taught me to wear black
turtlenecks and smoke," he recalls. "Acting classes can only
teach you how to perform. Don't get me wrong. I love
performers. <PERSON>Victor Borge</PERSON> does the same thing every time he
performs, and it's terrific. . . . I learned how to be an
actor in my non-acting classes studying literature, music,
poetry and architecture."
   Local success in his craft hasn't spoiled <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON>.
O'Hare is a household word, but only as the name of the
city's main airport, and <LOCATION>O'Hare</LOCATION> the actor still has to round
out his income at the computer keyboard. When "Hauptmann"
opened, <PERSON>Mr. O'Hare</PERSON>, as the lead performer, received the
<ORGANIZATION>Actors Equity</ORGANIZATION> minimum rate of <MONEY>$335</MONEY> a week, or an annualized
salary of less than <MONEY>$17,500</MONEY>. When the play was held over, his
